<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par14" class="p">Long-term analyses of fixed moorings, ARGO floats and ship-based CTD data
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">21</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">22</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" class="xref">35</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" class="xref">36</xref>
 </sup> suggested that there are important intermediate T and S peaks in both areas (Levantine, Cretan). In particular
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" class="xref">36</xref>
 </sup>, analyzed the long-term variability of the water column properties in the Cretan Sea (1986–2014) based on historical CTDs and found that after S peaks in 1993 and 1999, between 2008 and 2011 the S of CIW has increased by 0.2–0.25. According to refs 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">21</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" class="xref">35</xref> this is a manifestation of the salinity preconditioning of the Cretan Sea (due to mechanisms such as NIG reversals or the thermohaline pump mentioned before), i.e. a recurrent phenomenon. But what is not considered in these studies is that there is also a tendency of the peaks (in the Levantine and in the Cretan Sea, as appears from the datasets published by refs 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">21</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" class="xref">35</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" class="xref">36</xref>) to reach greater values, whose causes cannot be found in the local hydrographic and atmospheric conditions. Instead they occur “upstream” reflecting the increasingly strong water mass transformation that AW and LSW experience while on their path towards the formation regions of LIW/CIW. The same tendency is observed in the SC where from our time series we estimated a trend in the T and S peaks by fitting a linear regression model to the annual maximum T and S values: in both cases a significant (p-values ≪ 0.01) increasing trend of 0.036 °C yr
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup> and 0.0046 yr
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>, for T peaks (R
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> = 0.84) and S peaks (R
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> = 0.75) respectively, was found.
</p>
