<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par89" class="p">People have used migration as an adaptation strategy for centuries; they move away from stress and towards places that help sustain their wellbeing. People use migration to deal with a permanent loss of livelihood options in their home areas. Short-term migration can also help overcome temporary livelihood insecurities, due to climatic stress and other disturbances (Black et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">2011a</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">2013</xref>; Kniveton et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" class="xref">2012</xref>). Migration can be an effective way to bounce back from environmental shocks. When people, for example, already have a social network in place elsewhere, such as Bhola Slum, the adaptation strategy is more likely to be successful. National government and NGOs can in such instances economically support people who consider migration as an adaptive solution. Assisted migration programs have a greater chance of success than inflexible resettlement programs. By contrast, forced displacement can also be an indication that the previous adaptation strategies have failed (Black et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">2011a</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">2013</xref>; Adger et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" class="xref">2003</xref>). Seasonal, temporary and permanent migration is common in all seven study sites:
 <disp-quote class="disp-quote">
  <p id="Par90" class="p">I went to Sylhet to cut wood in a saw factory. I go there every year for 2–3 months./…/My daughter also went to Dhaka to work in the garment factories. Now she is earning 7000–8000 taka a month [Male (1963), Gabtola, 2014.05.27].
   <xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn23" class="xref">23</xref>
  </p>
 </disp-quote>
 <disp-quote class="disp-quote">
  <p id="Par92" class="p">I usually go to Dhaka when there is no work to do here. After [Bengali month] Magh the crops are harvested so there is no work for us. That is why we go to Dhaka in [Bengali month] Falgun and spend the whole month there. After 1 month we return to the village for about 15 days and then we go back to Dhaka. We go to Dhaka to work as day labors [Male (1982), Jamalpur, 2014.06.09].
   <xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn24" class="xref">24</xref>
  </p>
 </disp-quote>
 <disp-quote class="disp-quote">
  <p id="Par94" class="p">I went there because we did not have any money left in our family to survive. So I was almost forced to go and work for a living [Female (1984), Singpur, 2014.06.02].
   <xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn25" class="xref">25</xref>
  </p>
 </disp-quote>
 <disp-quote class="disp-quote">
  <p id="Par96" class="p">In 1995 we all came to Dhaka. I could not continue living there [Bhola Island] after my parents passed away. We had already lost most of our land to riverbank erosion and our house was located very close to the river. We had no other option than to come here. That is why we moved to Dhaka [Male (1952), Bhola Slum, 2014.06.12].
   <xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn26" class="xref">26</xref>
  </p>
 </disp-quote>
</p>
