<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par102" class="p">Seasonal migration can be a successful adaptation strategy that enhances livelihood security. However, it often comes at a cost; working conditions tend to be challenging and dangerous. Migrants are often injured or even killed in work-related accidents (McNamara et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" class="xref">2015</xref>). Loss of ability to work means income loss and reduced livelihood resilience. When people get sick or injured, they usually need medicine or immediate hospital attendance. Migration can serve as a solution to escape environmental stress, but it also exposes people to new hazards and risks:
 <disp-quote class="disp-quote">
  <p id="Par103" class="p">My husband can not work properly as he had an accident. While cutting mud on a hill he was struck by a sudden landslide. There was a pipe inside the hill and it broke creating a landslide and he fell down in a hole got buried. The other workers removed the mud and managed to save him. They took my husband to the hospital. Now when trying to work he faces a lot of problems. He has pain coming from two sides of his belly and sometimes when he coughs, blood comes out of his mouth [Female (1975), Bhola Slum, 2014.06.15].
   <xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn28" class="xref">28</xref>
  </p>
 </disp-quote>
 <disp-quote class="disp-quote">
  <p id="Par105" class="p">Carrying bricks is not the nicest job. It is hard and it breaks you down. I know that you must think that I am older than 35, but I am not. I am quite young. It is the effect of the hard work [Female (1981), Singpur, 2014.06.01].
   <xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn29" class="xref">29</xref>
  </p>
 </disp-quote>
 <disp-quote class="disp-quote">
  <p id="Par107" class="p">Many people from this village went to Alliganj after losing everything [previous crop failure]. They went to Alliganj because anybody can get work there. Your whole family can work there which is impossible here. Though they have to work hard in Alliganj, which makes them forget about their [additional] family back here [Male (1990), Singpur, 2014.06.01].
   <xref ref-type="fn" rid="Fn30" class="xref">30</xref>
  </p>
 </disp-quote>
</p>
