<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The future scenario of +2 °C hypothesized for Europe is realistic
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b23" href="#b23">23</a> and could change several plant-pathogen interactions in the whole continent
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b24" href="#b24">24</a>. In particular, due to climate change, aflatoxin contamination of maize kernels will be an important concern for food and feed safety and security. A reduction of safe maize production is predicted by this study, and was also recently observed
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b14" href="#b14">14</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b15" href="#b15">15</a>. This would reduce availability of maize for both food and particularly feed uses. Contaminated crops will have a reduced economic value, as they need to be diverted to other uses such as biofuel generation. This could lead to an end of maize production in current areas as being uneconomical. In addition, the enlargement of aflatoxin risk zones could increase human and animal population chronic exposures to these mycotoxins.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Occurrence of aflatoxins in food and feed is therefore a “hot issue” in Europe for policy makers. The first regulation of the European Commission was adopted in 2001 setting the maximum limits for foodstuffs (Commission Regulation 2001/466/EC) and in 1974 for animal feeding stuffs (Council Directive 74/63/EEC of 17 December 1973) and several amendments followed. In general, official control measures contribute to the global effort to reduce risks for human and animals from exposure to aflatoxins by food and feed intake. However, specific action plans also need to be directed to the production chain.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We consider aflatoxin contamination as a main emerging issue related to maize grown in Europe. We suggest the modelling approach as a supporting tool to reinforce aflatoxin management in maize, to prevent human and animal exposure and related health risks
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b25" href="#b25">25</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Indeed, new strategies supported by predictions should be adopted
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b25" href="#b25">25</a>, such as biological control using atoxigenic 
  <span class="italic">A. flavus</span> strains, able to displace the toxigenic populations of the fungus, as largely applied in risk areas in the USA and Africa
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b26" href="#b26">26</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b27" href="#b27">27</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From a risk assessment perspective, the aflatoxin risk maps produced in this study could be used as a communication tool for stakeholders, especially for farmers and stockbreeders. Moreover, the maps could also be used as a management tool to highlight aflatoxin contamination risk areas in order to prioritize aflatoxin control and intervention strategies.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The approach followed in this study is transferable to a global level and can significantly support strategic decisions especially in high risk areas, frequently placed in emerging countries with limited resources, to contribute in reducing local population exposure to aflatoxins and therefore in improving public and animal health.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A similar approach could be applied to other crop-mycotoxin combinations. In the perspective of a dramatic switch of the toxigenic fungal population profiles, as recorded by several scientists over a wide range of geographical areas and in various types of crops, such a modelling approach could become a powerful tool for a more efficient management of mycotoxin contamination worldwide.</p>
</sec>
