<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2a" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(a)</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to represent the population dynamics of 19 Atlantic cod stocks, we collected time series of comparable spawner biomass (SB) (i.e. biomass of mature fish in tonnes) and fishing mortality estimates derived from stock assessments. Data were provided by the International Council for the Exploration of the Sea (ICES), the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration of the USA (NOAA), the Northwest Atlantic Fisheries Organization (NAFO) and the Department of Fisheries and Ocean in Canada (DFO) (electronic supplementary material, tables S1 and S2). A few recent stock assessments (i.e. the Kattegat, the western Baltic and the Norwegian coastal cod) comprised only reduced assessment periods. Where possible, we extended the SB and fishing mortality time series by combining them with comparable estimates from previous assessments after performing consistency checks (electronic supplementary material, figure S5).</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To represent changes in environmental conditions experienced by each stock, we collected time series of SST (in °C). Although SST does not fully reflect the thermal habitat of cod, a predominately demersal (bottom-dwelling) species, SST has previously been shown to be a strong predictor influencing cod stock dynamics, including reproduction and growth [
  <a rid="RSPB20182877C50" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182877C50">50</a>,
  <a rid="RSPB20182877C51" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182877C51">51</a>]. SST data were collated from the NOAA Extended Reconstructed Sea Surface Temperature dataset (ERSST, 
  <span xlink:href="www.ncdc.noaa.gov" class="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.ncdc.noaa.gov</span>) v. 4. The dataset represents a reconstruction of SST from 1854 to the present and represents monthly anomalies computed with respect to the period 1971–2000, resolved in a 2° × 2° grid of spatial coverage. For every stock, we calculated the mean annual SST values averaged over the management area (electronic supplementary material, table S2). As the eastern Baltic cod stock is not strongly influenced by temperature but rather affected by oxygen, the annual extents of anoxic areas (in km
  <span class="sup">2</span>) [
  <a rid="RSPB20182877C52" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20182877C52">52</a>] were used as environmental covariate for this particular stock.
 </p>
</sec>
