<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par35">While the review highlights some important findings, the limited number of papers located suggests that the country has some way to go to fulfilling its potential leadership role on the continent, and indeed globally. One area that health practitioners in South Africa could lead on is the promotion of a ‘meat tax’, given their pioneering work on the ‘sugar tax’ [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">95</xref>]. Curbing the intake of ruminant meat is a key climate change mitigation strategy and would lower cancer risks, among other health benefits [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96">96</xref>]. This is important in South Africa, where an estimated total of 875,000 tons of beef are consumed annually [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97">97</xref>], producing 648 gigagrams of methane [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98">98</xref>]. The principal arguments for a sugar tax – and indeed for tobacco and alcohol taxes – hold for ruminant meat: harm to self and others, and the considerable cost burdens on broader society [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99">99</xref>]. In this case, the harms are mediated through environmental destruction, a change in climate and cancer, amongst others [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95">95</xref>]. Such policies are, however, likely to be vigorously opposed by the meat industry in South Africa, and public health and environmental and social justice experts in the country will need to rally together [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Bringing together the complementary skills of these experts has the potential for powerful synergies and for drawing additional researchers into the climate change and health arena. Similarly, broadening the scope of climate change adaptation to encompass existing programmes that have an indirect impact on climate change adaptation would also increase the number of climate adaption workers. This would also assist in mainstreaming climate change into existing health programmes, and highlight additional ways that the health sector has successfully responded to the problem. Increased attention to these successes might demonstrate the extent to which the sector is leading the field and its potential contribution to overall adaptation efforts in the country.
</p>
