<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Aircraft measurements</div>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Aircraft measurements of CO
  <sub>2</sub> and CH
  <sub>4</sub> over the Athabasca OS region of northern Alberta were performed from August 13 to September 7, 2013 as part of an intensive field campaign. Details of the study objectives, aircraft implementation, and other technical aspects have been described previously
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
  </span>. During the study, 22 flights totaling 84 h were conducted over individual facilities of the OS and downwind of the facilities at distances up to 120 km. The flight patterns have been shown previously
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
  </span>, 13 of which were used to quantify primary emissions from individual OS facilities, and 4 conducted to quantify their transformation downwind. Emission quantification flights were conducted by flying a 4- or 5-sided polygon, at multiple altitudes, resulting in 21 separate virtual boxes encompassing 7 OS facilities. Results from 17 flights were used in the current analysis, while the others were excluded because of highly variable wind speeds and direction and/or the presence of confounding pollutant interferences from adjacent OS facilities. The specific facilities studied and their corresponding flight numbers are given in Supplementary Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>. Three of the flights (F7, F19, and F20) examined the photo-chemical transformation of pollutants downwind of the OS facilities
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
  </span> and are used here to quantify total emissions from all OS surface mining facilities (for comparison to the sum of individual emission flights), as they encompass the majority of emissions from the region. These transformation flights were designed as Lagrangian, such that the same air parcel in the OS plumes was sampled successively, 1 h apart, in virtual screens constructed from level flight tracks at multiple altitudes (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">3</a>, Supplementary Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>). There were no industrial emissions between the screens of each flight.
 </p>
 <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Gas, particle, meteorological, and aircraft state measurements were made during flights, with a detailed description provided elsewhere
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
  </span>. The current work makes use of a subset of these measurements specifically for the quantitation of CO
  <sub>2</sub> and SO
  <sub>2</sub> gases. CO
  <sub>2</sub> was measured using a Picarro model G2401-
  <span class="italic">m</span> instrument (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.picarro.com/products_solutions/gas_analyzers/flight_co_co2_ch4_h2o" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.picarro.com/products_solutions/gas_analyzers/flight_co_co2_ch4_h2o</span>) with a time resolution of 2 s
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>. The instrument sampled ambient air through a 6.35-mm (1/4 inch) diameter perfluoroalkoxy, backwards facing sampling line with a residence time of ~2 s. Calibrations were performed before, during, and after the field campaign using a range of mixing ratios from NIST certified standard cylinders (350–450 ppm). The precision of the CO
  <sub>2</sub> measurements in flight were estimated to be &lt;100 ppb. SO
  <sub>2</sub> was measured using a Thermo Scientific 43iTLE analyzer with a time resolution of 1 s. The SO
  <sub>2</sub> instrument was calibrated with NIST certified standard cylinders over a range of 0–400 ppb. The standard deviation of the calibration slopes was 0.9% and the average standard deviation of the 1-s data during calibrations was 1.99 ppb
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span>. The time delay for the SO
  <sub>2</sub> measurement, due to the gas traversing the length of the inlet, was ≈6 s and was corrected for in the data. NO and NO
  <sub>2</sub> measurements were made using two Thermo Scientific 42iTLE analyzers at 1 Hz (NO
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">X</span>
  </sub> averaged to 2 s) with a sample residence time of ≈3–4 s. Each instrument was calibrated with NIST standard cylinders of NO. High frequency wind data were averaged to 1 or 2 s for subsequent analysis in the emission rate algorithm.
 </p>
</sec>
