<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The objective of limiting the increase in global temperature to &lt;1.5 °C this century is dependent upon reducing anthropogenic greenhouse gas (GHG) emissions to net zero
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span>. Identifying mitigation potentials to achieve this goal and assessing GHG reductions relies upon accurate emission estimates of anthropogenic sources, which inform national and international climate policies. Consequently, participating countries in the United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change (UNFCCC) are required to submit sector-based emissions data in an annual national GHG inventory report (NIR)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span>. Such anthropogenic GHG emission data ultimately underpin carbon pricing and trading policies.
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The global energy industry alone accounts for ≈35% of anthropogenic GHG emissions (using a 100-year global warming potential (GWP))
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span>, a significant portion of which are attributed to the global upstream oil and gas (O&amp;G) sector. It is estimated that the global O&amp;G sector (which is included in NIRs) contributes ~10% of anthropogenic GHG emissions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span>, using GHG emission estimates that are derived primarily through complex calculations based upon UNFCCC inventory guidelines
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span>. The estimation of anthropogenic GHG emissions in NIRs from stationary sources in the energy sector (including the O&amp;G sector) is primarily a bottom–up exercise, where GHG emissions from individual sources within a given facility are added together, as outlined in UNFCCC protocols
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span>. These estimates have varying degrees of accuracy (i.e., Tier 1–3)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span> but fundamentally rely on emission factors and associated activity data (e.g., production and consumption intensity), which in some cases may be outdated or assumed to be homogeneous across the world. In general, Tier 3 approaches are considered to use the best available data specific to the industry and should provide improved emissions estimates relative to Tier 1 and Tier 2 methods.
 </p>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The large contribution of the O&amp;G sector to global GHG emissions underscores the need for accurate sectoral GHG emissions in national inventories. This is particularly relevant since studies have indicated discrepancies between top–down and bottom–up estimates of O&amp;G methane (CH
  <sub>4</sub>)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>, many of which having shown that official inventories or industrial reports underestimate emissions. However, few atmospheric measurement-based evaluations have been performed for O&amp;G carbon dioxide (CO
  <sub>2</sub>) emission inventories, despite CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions being significantly larger than CH
  <sub>4</sub>. This may be in part because uncertainties in emission factors and activity data used in bottom–up CO
  <sub>2</sub> estimates for this sector are considered small (&lt;10%)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span> compared to CH
  <sub>4</sub> (50–150%)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span>. Nonetheless, small uncertainties in CO
  <sub>2</sub> emission estimates have the potential to result in large unaccounted for CO
  <sub>2</sub> based upon the magnitude of the CO
  <sub>2</sub> emitted compared to CH
  <sub>4</sub>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Evaluating GHG emissions reported to inventories for the O&amp;G sector is especially important now, with global fossil fuel production and demand at an all-time high
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>
  </span>. Such evaluations are highly important for countries with resource-based economies such as Canada, where O&amp;G activities account for ≈26% of national GHG emissions and oil sands (OS) production in particular ≈10%
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span>. In general, CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions from the O&amp;G sector (including the Canadian OS sector) are derived for inventories using an Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) Tier 3 approach
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span> and following the UNFCCC protocols
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span>. However, estimates of the emission intensity (kg CO
  <sub>2</sub>e per barrel of oil) of OS operations and of their absolute GHG emissions are not derived from direct measurements of CO
  <sub>2</sub>. Aircraft measurements over large-scale O&amp;G emission sources can provide a top–down assessment of these bottom–up reported GHG estimates.
 </p>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here the utility of a top–down measurement approach is demonstrated below for the Canadian OS surface mining operations (one of the largest single O&amp;G sources of GHGs in Canada). The results indicate that overall, OS GHG emissions may be underestimated and suggests that reporting that follows this Tier 3 approach (or less accurate Tier 1 and Tier 2 approaches) may universally underestimate CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions. This highlights the potential need for updated IPCC inventory guidelines that include atmospheric measurement-based evaluations of CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions, for an improved assessment of the O&amp;G contribution to the global anthropogenic GHG burden.
 </p>
</sec>
