<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Top–down emission rate retrieval algorithm analysis</div>
 <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">CO
  <sub>2</sub> emission rates for each OS surface mining facility and for the entire OS region were derived using an algorithm designed to estimate pollutant transfer rates through the virtual boxes/screens of aircraft measurements. The algorithm is based on the Divergence Theorem to resolve mass balance (TERRA)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span> and has been used extensively for determining emission rates of volatile organic compounds (VOCs), black carbon, CH
  <sub>4</sub>, secondary organic aerosol (SOA), organic/inorganic acids, and SO
  <sub>2</sub>
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
  </span> Emissions are derived with the TERRA algorithm by combining box-like aircraft flight patterns with pollutant concentration measurements at high time resolution and wind speed and direction data. The algorithm applies simple kriging
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span> to the data to produce virtual walls of gridded 20 × 40 m
  <span class="sup">2</span> mesh on the virtual box, resolves the air mass balance within the virtual box, and determines the mass transfer rates across the walls (including the top of the box) to derive a net emission rate for a pollutant. In the case of virtual screens (rather than boxes), TERRA quantifies the mass transfer rate of a pollutant (kg h
  <span class="sup">−1</span>) through the virtual screens, in the same manner as it does for a single wall of a virtual box flight
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The use of the standard TERRA to estimate emissions accounts for incoming and outgoing air mass advective and turbulent fluxes within a volume, including the top of the virtual box, and is ideal for species that have little background contribution to the measured concentration. However, in the case of CO
  <sub>2</sub> that has a large background concentration, this approach can introduce large uncertainties if even a small portion of the measured CO
  <sub>2</sub> is calculated to leave through the top of the box. To address this uncertainty, a background CO
  <sub>2</sub> is subtracted prior to the use of TERRA, such that the transfer rate through any one outgoing side of a box (or single screen) represents the facility emission rate. This approach has been used successfully for CH
  <sub>4</sub>
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>, VOCs
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
  </span>, and SOAs
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
  </span> and is similar to other single screen approaches
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>
  </span>. Background CO
  <sub>2</sub> was determined using upwind measurements for box flights and screen flights (where available). For screen flights where upwind measurements were not conducted, the levels at the edges of the screen were used as background. The background between upwind data was linearly interpolated and box-car smoothed within a 20–40-min moving window to derive a variable baseline CO
  <sub>2</sub> for the entire 2–3 h flight. Examples of the derived CO
  <sub>2</sub> baseline are shown in Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">3</a>. The uncertainty added to the final emission rate for each flight contributed by the baseline estimation method was examined by varying the derived CO
  <sub>2</sub> baseline by the standard deviation of the upwind data (±0.5–3 ppm CO
  <sub>2</sub>), followed by input into TERRA. This baseline CO
  <sub>2</sub> sensitivity analysis resulted in CO
  <sub>2</sub> emission rates that varied by 1–33% (
  <span class="italic">δ</span>
  <sub>B</sub>; Supplementary Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>). This relatively small variation in emission rates caused by the background CO
  <sub>2</sub> is due to the short duration of the flights, which were flown during an established planetary boundary layer and because there was significant enhancement of plume CO
  <sub>2</sub> of up to &gt;80 ppm above background. In general, a changing boundary layer depth could in principle introduce additional uncertainty in the emission results from TERRA. However, the flights were intentionally conducted during mid-afternoon hours, when the boundary layer was constant. This was assessed through vertical profiles performed before and after the emission estimation portions of the flights. Under conditions where boundary layer depth was stable, real-time vertical profile data (pollutants, water vapor, temperature) from the flights were used to ensure that the highest flight track was always above the top of the boundary layer, hence ensuring that the entire plume from the various facilities was contained within the specific flight box or within the flight screen.
 </p>
 <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It has been demonstrated previously that extrapolation of pollutant concentrations from the lowest flight level to the ground is the main source of uncertainty in TERRA, with an overall uncertainty in the derived emission rates of approximately 20%
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span>. This was determined previously
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span> through a sensitivity analysis in a series of closed-loop numerical experiments. In such experiments, a simulated Gaussian plume driven by a known emission flux was created and sampled with the TERRA algorithm, while also using various forms of extrapolation to the ground (i.e., linear to the ground, exponential, constant, linear to zero). A similar analysis was performed in the current study, with the differences in extrapolations also resulting in a &lt;20% difference in final estimated emissions. For pollutant sources that are entirely above the lowest flight level, extrapolation to the ground is not relevant and the associated uncertainty in the TERRA-derived emissions has been demonstrated to be ≈ 4%
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span>. This was determined by comparing the TERRA-derived emissions of SO
  <sub>2</sub> with continuous emissions monitoring system (CEMS) data for the same facility stack (CNRL) and for the exact hour of the flight. We note that CEMS data are regularly audited and mandated to be accurate to within 10%. Further comparisons of TERRA-derived SO
  <sub>2</sub> stack emission rates with those concurrently measured with CEMS indicate that this uncertainty may be even smaller (&lt;1%) as shown in Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">4a</a>. However, the larger 4% uncertainty for elevated stack emissions is used in this analysis. The excellent agreement between TERRA emissions and the audited CEMS data provide confidence that uncertainties associated with possible under sampling are negligible. The uncertainties for stack and ground-based emissions (i.e., 4% and 20%) are applied separately in cases where low level and elevated stack sources are clearly spatially differentiated, which are further propagated with the uncertainties associated with the background CO
  <sub>2</sub> determination described above. The overall propagated uncertainty associated with the hourly emission rates derived for individual facilities ranged from 8% to 28% 
  <div id="IEq33" class="inline-formula">
   <div class="alternatives">
    <span id="M65" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$(\Delta E_{{\mathrm{CO}}_2})$$\end{document}</span>
    <div id="M66" class="math">
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mo">(</span>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mi">Δ</span>
       <div class="msub">
        <div class="mrow">
         <span class="mi">E</span>
        </div>
        <div class="mrow">
         <div class="msub">
          <div class="mrow">
           <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">CO</span>
          </div>
          <div class="mrow">
           <span class="mn">2</span>
          </div>
         </div>
        </div>
       </div>
      </div>
      <span class="mo">)</span>
     </div>
    </div>
    <span xlink:href="41467_2019_9714_Article_IEq33.gif" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </div> for facility flights and from 24% to 38% for downwind transformation flights as shown in Supplementary Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>. In contrast to the emission box flights, the largest uncertainty in the transfer rates through the downwind screens arises from the background subtraction of CO
  <sub>2</sub> (
  <span class="italic">δ</span>
  <sub>B</sub> in Eq. 
  <a rid="Equ9" ref-type="" href="#Equ9">9</a> below) due to the higher variability in background CO
  <sub>2</sub> over a typically longer flight time. Such uncertainties are included in the emission results from TERRA and reported separately in Supplementary Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>.
 </p>
</sec>
