<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par6" class="p">Low δ
 <sup class="sup">234</sup>U values are observed during the Younger Dryas (12,300–11,700 cal yr BP) and at around 8,100 and 4,000 cal yr BP. On the other hand, δ
 <sup class="sup">234</sup>U displays high values during the Early Holocene (11,700–8,200 cal yr BP), Mid Holocene (4,200–7,800 cal yr BP) and Late Holocene (2,500 cal yr BP – present). This pattern co-varies with climate variability in the Eastern Mediterranean Region over the past 12,300 yr. Several archives show overall higher temperatures and humidity during the Holocene compared to the Late Glacial period, but with short-lived cool/dry events at 8,200 and 4,200 cal yr BP
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">24</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>
 </sup>. This is consistent with variations in CaCO
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> concentrations in Lake Dojran sediments
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">23</xref>
 </sup>, used as a proxy for primary productivity (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1e</xref>). High calcium carbonate concentrations during the Early- to Mid Holocene between 11,700 and 2,500 cal yr BP indicate warm spring and summer temperatures, whereas low calcite concentrations during the Younger Dryas (13,000 and 11,700 cal yr BP) are consistent with a low primary productivity and low spring and summer temperatures. The low calcite concentrations during the Late Holocene (2,500 cal yr BP and present) are mainly a result of dilution with clastic matter, most likely caused by an increase in clastic sediment flux from the catchment. Two excursions towards low calcite concentration centred at 8,200 and 4,000 cal yr BP imply that the lake productivity decreased abruptly over a period of several hundred years. These two cold phases are commonly referred to as the 
 <italic class="italic">8</italic>.
 <italic class="italic">2</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">4</italic>.
 <italic class="italic">2 ka events</italic>, which lasted for approximately 400 years
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" class="xref">27</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>
 </sup>, and are associated with dry conditions at Lake Dojran
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">23</xref>
 </sup>, although not captured by the local pollen record
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">30</xref>
 </sup>. Independent climate data confirm the presence of these two cool and arid phases in the Mediterranean region: tree pollen data obtained from northern Greece show an abrupt decline around 8,200 cal yr BP (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1d</xref>)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>
 </sup>. Flowstones from western Italy show a positive excursion of δ
 <sup class="sup">13</sup>C and Mg:Ca ratios at 4,000 cal yr BP (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1d</xref>), which is indicative of drier conditions
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" class="xref">27</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
