<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Tropical Precipitation Extremes</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As compared to the extratropics, the intermodel range in the sensitivity of precipitation extremes is much larger in the tropics (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>), with close to zero sensitivity in some models and greater than 30 % K
  <span class="sup">−1</span> in others. Additional reasons to doubt the response of tropical precipitation extremes in these global climate models include the large differences between tropical precipitation extremes in the twentieth-century simulations in different models [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>], the inability of the models to represent mesoscale convective organization [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72" href="#CR72">72</a>] or to simulate the interannual variability in tropical precipitation extremes when compared to observations [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>], and the disproportionate increases in precipitation extremes compared to other parts of the precipitation distribution that is found in some models—an “extreme mode” in the tropical response to climate change that relates to gridpoint storms [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">66</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" href="#CR67">67</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Observations can be used to better constrain the large uncertainty in the response of tropical precipitation extremes to warming. The sensitivity of tropical precipitation extremes for climate change in different climate models is correlated with their sensitivity for shorter term variability within a climate (variability that is primarily related to El Niño-Southern Oscillation) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>]. For example, models with a relatively high sensitivity of tropical precipitation extremes for climate change also have a relatively high sensitivity of tropical precipitation extremes for variability in historical simulations, although the sensitivities for climate change and variability are generally different in value. The robust relationship between the sensitivities for climate change and variability has been used together with observed variability to constrain the sensitivity of tropical precipitation extremes to climate change [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>]. The black line in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a> shows a similar observationally constrained estimate of the sensitivity of the 99.9th percentile of daily precipitation for climate change, but instead of considering the sensitivity for climate change aggregated over the whole tropics as in [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>], the analysis is applied separately to the sensitivity for climate change in 10° latitude bands in both the tropics and extratropics.
  <a ref-type="fn" rid="Fn3" href="#Fn3">3</a> This observationally constrained estimate is similar to the multimodel median in the extratropics but higher than the multimodel median in the tropics. It peaks near the equator and is higher for the tropics (11 % K
  <span class="sup">−1</span>, 90 % confidence interval 7–15 % K
  <span class="sup">−1</span>) than the extratropics (6 % K
  <span class="sup">−1</span>, 90 % confidence interval 6–7 % K
  <span class="sup">−1</span>). Interestingly, a higher sensitivity in the tropics compared to the extratropics was also found using historical rain-gauge data (“
  <a rid="Sec2" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec2">Observed Changes in Precipitation Extremes</a>”). For the tropics, there still remains considerable uncertainty in both the estimate from rain-gauge data and the observationally constrained estimate discussed in this section, and better constraining the sensitivity of tropical precipitation extremes is an important research challenge.
 </p>
</sec>
