<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">When Reluctant Geoengineering invokes visions of conflict and cooperation, it tends to stay within this neo–neo framework. It emphasizes primarily the perspective of rational, self-interested states in terms of both conflict and possible cooperation. The key problem is assumed to be the potential divergence and coordination of interests among putative climate engineering nations, as well as between such nations and other affected states. In the absence of clear international rules or procedures to establish and enforce such rules, climate engineering becomes a case of potential ‘cooperation under anarchy’ between rational states, and the challenge is to design the right institutions that secure stability or incentivize cooperation. Rational states try to pass on costs to each other, but the leading solar climate engineering methods are not thought to have the burden-sharing problems that mitigation and infrastructure-intensive CDR methods tend to have (
 <xref rid="bibr30-0967010617704142" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Crutzen, 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bibr54-0967010617704142" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Keith, 2013</xref>: xxi; 
 <xref rid="bibr100-0967010617704142" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Snyder-Beattie, 2015</xref>). Some early estimates of the cost of stratospheric aerosol injection range from only $1 billion to $8 billion per year to offset global warming (
 <xref rid="bibr6-0967010617704142" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Barrett, 2008</xref>). The low price and technical ease of deploying aerosols that is often quoted (see, for example, 
 <xref rid="bibr54-0967010617704142" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Keith, 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bibr104-0967010617704142" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Victor, 2008</xref>) is contested, and is based on estimates from a non-peer-reviewed report by a private aerospace consultancy with a potential interest in delivering such a technology (
 <xref rid="bibr65-0967010617704142" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">McClellan et al., 2010</xref>). But even so, cost is widely assumed not to be a big problem for the international politics of stratospheric aerosols because economic burden-sharing directly concerned with the technology would be manageable. However, problems might still arise from distribution of harms, benefits, and compensations linked to solar geoengineering programs, the magnitude of which could be substantial.
</p>
