<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">As the aim of our study was to investigate the possibility of indirect, biotic effects of climate changes, we collected soil samples when no treatments were actively being applied; this precludes analysis of seasonal changes in microbial communities but ensured comparable soil temperature and soil water content among treatments (Fridley et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32700-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). We found evidence of links between plant traits and soil microbial communities despite the breadth of microbial functional groups included in our community fingerprints; the seemingly small effect sizes in our study are unsurprising, given the high microbial diversity and the potential influence of numerous soil physical and chemical properties. Soil pH in particular has an overriding effect on soil bacteria (Fierer, Bradford, &amp; Jackson, 
 <xref rid="ece32700-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>; Griffiths et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32700-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>), and it is conceivable that some of the observed differences in bacterial community structure are a result of lower soil pH in the drought plots and deep microsites (Fridley et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32700-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>) or a direct effect of differences in soil depth. Nevertheless, plant C:N ratios explained a greater proportion of the variation in soil bacteria compared to microsite characteristics (soil depth and pH) and the carbon construction costs of plant material explained an equivalent amount of variation in both bacterial and fungal community structures. In addition, the effect of microsite was weaker or entirely absent when dominant microbial taxa were excluded, whereas the effect of drought and the relationship with plant functional traits remained (Figure 
 <xref rid="ece32700-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3</xref>). This suggests that subordinate taxa may be more sensitive to changes in resource quality than soil depth or pH. Hence, we suggest that the concordance between plant species composition and microbial community structure in our study provides evidence for plant‐mediated effects of climate change on soil microbial communities and the links to specific plant traits suggest that decomposition processes may play an important role in concerted above‐ and belowground responses to long‐term climate change (McGuire &amp; Treseder, 
 <xref rid="ece32700-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>).
</p>
