<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par14" class="p">Using three regression based optimal fingerprint methods, two observed datasets, and two temporal-averaging choices we are able to robustly attribute TAS changes over India between 1956–2005 and 1906–2005 to anthropogenic forcing. The contributions of natural forcings to the observed trend during 1956–2005 period is minimal with a comparatively larger contribution during 1906–1955. We also find that the observed increases in TAS over WCIND, IPIND, ECIND, and WHIND cannot be explained by natural forcings or internal climate variability alone. The largest warming rates are seen in the Western Himalayas - a mountainous region that is likely experiencing elevation enhanced warming
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">22</xref>
 </sup>. This has implications for the health of glaciers in this region with continued anthropogenic forcing leaving them more prone to mass loss and resulting downstream effects
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">23</xref>
 </sup>. The influence of anthropogenic forcing is also detected in NEIND, NCIND, and NWIND, but only with the CRU dataset. However, the two observational datasets are different in the number of observing stations they include and this influences results to some extent. Using a three-signal analysis, we find that GHG forcing is the dominant contributor to the positive trends over India with OA forcings exerting a cooling influence. Over the individual sub-regions however, we were not able to consistently detect the influence of GHG and OA. The influence of aerosols
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">24</xref>
 </sup> and land use (that are the main constituents of OA) cannot be separated using these methods which assume that signals can be decomposed as a simple linear addition of forcings. The impact of observational uncertainty (to the extent evident in the two datasets used) is clearly seen in our results for individual regions. Concerted efforts to quantify observational uncertainty at these smaller spatial scales are necessary to have better confidence in D&amp;A results and also to enable climate model improvements
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" class="xref">25</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
