<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Overexploitation of marine resources is also a major human pressure in marine ecosystems, especially coastal environments since these areas are highly productive and serve as nursery grounds for a wide diversity of species. Catches from fisheries peaked in late 1980s and have been relatively stable since then, at values around 90 million tons per year [
 <xref rid="B10-ijerph-16-02737" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. As a consequence of an increasing fishing pressure, marine fisheries resources have been declining worldwide. The percentage of marine resources’ stocks within biologically sustainable levels decreased from 90%, in the 1970s, down to 67%, in 2015, and the percentage of underfished stocks also decreased from 40%, in the 1970s, to less than 10%, in 2015 [
 <xref rid="B10-ijerph-16-02737" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Coastal fisheries, that are mainly small-scale, represent more than 50% of global marine fisheries, while its area of operation corresponds to about 3% of the global ocean [
 <xref rid="B11-ijerph-16-02737" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Besides the direct impact on the populations of harvested species (e.g., reduction in number of individuals, reduction of individuals mean length, earlier maturation and at smaller sizes; [
 <xref rid="B12-ijerph-16-02737" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-ijerph-16-02737" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-ijerph-16-02737" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-ijerph-16-02737" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-ijerph-16-02737" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]), fisheries have several other effects such as bycatches and discards, ghost fishing, decrease in trophic level, bottom destruction, among others (e.g., [
 <xref rid="B12-ijerph-16-02737" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-ijerph-16-02737" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]). Projections regarding fisheries trends and impacts often take into account foreseen climate changes. According to several authors, projected fisheries catches for 2050 may vary less than 10% [
 <xref rid="B18-ijerph-16-02737" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-ijerph-16-02737" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>], but a high spatial variation may occur, with a stronger decline expected for tropical areas [
 <xref rid="B18-ijerph-16-02737" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].
</p>
