<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Since modern times (after 1911) in China, the distribution of animals was surveyed based on scientific field investigations. We obtained distribution data with accurate year and coordinate information (
 <italic>n</italic> = 2,325, covering the period of 1913 to 2006) for 10 mammal species (except rhinos) from the China Species Information Service (CSIS) by Xie et al. (
 <xref rid="r46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>) as supplementary data to the compendium compiled by Wen (
 <xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). The occurrence time and sites of these mammals compiled in the CSIS database were collected from a large amount of scientific literature (
 <xref rid="r46" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>). To reconfirm the presence or absence of the 11 mammal species after 2006, we used the current International Union for Conservation of Nature (IUCN) distribution information (updated in 2014) about these mammal species from METADATA (Digital Distribution Maps on The IUCN Red List of Threatened Species, version 4) to determine the time of extinction in local grids of 0.5° × 0.5° (
 <xref rid="r47" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>). For example, if a species was last recorded in a grid in 1990 (last observation time) in our database but the occurrence of the species in that grid was not reported in the 2014 IUCN distribution map, then the year 1991 and the years after were defined as years of absence (i.e., extinction), and the years before 1991 were defined as years of presence (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig04">Fig. 4</xref>). Using the IUCN data, the definition of the local extinction time based on the last observation time is more conservative because it usually takes over 20 y to conclude that a species is extinct. The presence and absence data of mammals during 1700 to 2000 are supplied in 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1818019116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <italic>SI Appendix</italic>
 </ext-link>.
</p>
