<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The United Nations Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005705.ref069" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">69</xref>] defines future climate change scenarios in terms of representative concentration pathways (RCPs). The RCPs consider mitigation scenarios that assume policy actions will be taken to achieve certain greenhouse gases (GHG) emission targets [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005705.ref069" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">69</xref>] consistent with a wide range of possible changes in future anthropogenic GHG emissions [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005705.ref001" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>]
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Representative_Concentration_Pathways#cite_note-collins_rcp_ghg_emissions-3" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Representative_Concentration_Pathways#cite_note-collins_rcp_ghg_emissions-3</ext-link>. Radiative forcing and mitigation policies are different for each RCP scenario. In the highest GHG emission scenario, RCP8.5, radiative forcing increases throughout the 21
 <sup class="sup">st</sup> century before reaching a level of about 8.5 W m−2 at the end of the century. In the two intermediate scenarios, RCP4.5 and RCP6.0, radiative forcing stabilizes without overshoot at a level of 4.5 Wm-2 after 2100, while in the peak-and-decay scenario, RCP2.6, radiative forcing reaches a maximum near the middle of the 21
 <sup class="sup">st</sup> century before decreasing to an eventual nominal level of 2.6 W m−2 [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005705.ref069" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">69</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pntd.0005705.ref070" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">70</xref>]. Global average temperatures show a similar increase of approximately 0.3–0.7°C for the period of 2016–2035 in all four scenarios. After this period, the magnitude of the projected climate change is substantially affected by the choice of the scenario, with the highest global temperature increase estimated under RCP8.5 [
 <xref rid="pntd.0005705.ref071" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">71</xref>].
</p>
