<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract class="abstract">
 <p class="p">Future climate change can impact ozone concentrations by changing regional meteorological factors related to ozone (O
  <sub class="sub">3</sub>) pollution. To better understand the variations of meteorological factors and their effects on O
  <sub class="sub">3</sub> formation processes under future climate conditions, we model the present and the future meteorology and air quality in summer over the Yangtze River Delta (YRD) region by using the Weather Research and Forecasting Model with Chemistry module (WRF/Chem), which is driven by the outputs of Community Climate System Model version 4 (CCSM4). The simulations predict that solar radiation, 2-m air temperature, and wind speed increase in the daytime over most of the YRD region. Absolute humidity and precipitation increase in the north and decrease in the south, while the planetary boundary layer height (PBLH) has an opposite change pattern displaying a decrease in the north and an increase in the south. The southerly wind will be strengthened in the daytime. At night, the change patterns of the meteorological factors are similar to the daytime but with small variations. Meanwhile, O
  <sub class="sub">3</sub> and its precursors all increase in the north and decrease in the south. The increases of NO
  <sub class="sub">x</sub>, volatile organic compounds (VOC), and CO are related with the decreases of PBLH and the input effect of stronger southerly wind, while the decreases are attributed to the output effect of the stronger southerly wind. During the daytime, the increase of surface O
  <sub class="sub">3</sub> in the north is dominated by the chemical processes related with the increases of solar radiation, air temperature, and O
  <sub class="sub">3</sub> precursors. The decrease of surface O
  <sub class="sub">3</sub> in the south is mainly caused by the transport process changing with the strengthened southerly wind. At night, the surface O
  <sub class="sub">3</sub> changing the amplitude is less than the daytime. The less O
  <sub class="sub">3</sub> variations at night can be attributed to an O
  <sub class="sub">3</sub> titration reaction with NO, the changes in NO
  <sub class="sub">x</sub> concentrations, and the increases of nocturnal PBLH. With the aid of H
  <sub class="sub">2</sub>O
  <sub class="sub">2</sub>/HNO
  <sub class="sub">3</sub>, O
  <sub class="sub">3</sub> formation in the YRD region is found to be easily affected by NO
  <sub class="sub">x</sub> in the future. The findings can help to understand the changing trend of O
  <sub class="sub">3</sub> in the YRD region and can propose reasonable pollution control policies.
 </p>
</abstract>
