<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We sampled loggerhead turtles captured in commercial fishing gear (pound nets and long haul seines) in Core and Pamlico Sounds, North Carolina, USA (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0160911.g001" class="xref">Fig 1</xref>) from 1998–2002 [
 <xref rid="pone.0160911.ref034" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>] and from 2003–2007 (this study). Pound nets are a stationary gear that passively capture targeted fish by directing them into an enclosure (pound) by means of the lead [
 <xref rid="pone.0160911.ref035" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>]. Long-haul seines are 1 km x 2 m nets pulled between two boats for up to 8 km before the catch is encircled and concentrated by pulling the net around a stake [
 <xref rid="pone.0160911.ref036" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>]. When sea turtles are also incidentally captured, they are accessible for sampling purposes. We analyzed turtles sampled only during the summer months (June–August) to increase the likelihood of sampling the resident population and to avoid any seasonal bias in testosterone concentration [
 <xref rid="pone.0160911.ref034" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>]. Using a sterile syringe with a 3.81 cm, 20 gauge needle, we collected 5 ml of blood from the dorsocervical sinus of the turtle [
 <xref rid="pone.0160911.ref037" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>]. Blood samples were immediately transferred to a sterile lithium heparin or sodium heparin tube and stored on ice for a maximum of 5 h (i.e., for the rest of the field day). We applied Inconel metal alloy size 681 self-piercing tags (National Brand and Tag Company, Newport, Kentucky, USA) to both rear flippers and injected Passive Integrated Transponder (PIT) tags (Destron-Fearing Corp., South St. Paul, Minnesota, USA, 125 kHz) in the triceps superficialis muscle of the left front flipper to recognize recaptures. We measured standard straight-line carapace length (SCL) from the nuchal notch to the posterior tip to the nearest 0.1 cm using calipers, and excluded turtles with a carapace length greater than 76 cm [
 <xref rid="pone.0160911.ref030" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>] from the analysis to prevent use of adults in this study (and avoid bias associated with various sex-specific behaviors of the adult population) [
 <xref rid="pone.0160911.ref030" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0160911.ref031" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>]. We recorded surface water temperature to the nearest 0.5°C using calibrated thermometers. If we encountered previously sampled turtles (from prior years), we included them, as they also were members of that year’s resident population. After returning from the field, we centrifuged blood samples for 6–10 min, then pipetted 2 ml samples of plasma into cryogenic vials, and stored them in an ultra-cold (–80°C) freezer.
</p>
