<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="Abs1" class="abstract">
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Background</title>
  <p class="p">The aim of the present study was to analyse the effect of climate change on phytochemicals, total phenolic content (TPC) and antioxidant potential of methanolic extracts of 
   <italic class="italic">Aloe vera</italic> collected from different climatic zones of the India.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Methods</title>
  <p class="p">Crude methanolic extracts of 
   <italic class="italic">A. vera</italic> from the different states of India were screened for presence of various phytochemicals, total phenolic content and in vitro antioxidant activity. Total phenolic content was tested by Folin–Ciocalteau reagent based assay whilst DPPH free radical scavenging assay, metal chelating assay, hydrogen peroxide scavenging assay, reducing power assay and β carotene-linoleic assay were used to assess the antioxidant potential of 
   <italic class="italic">A. vera</italic> methanolic leaf extracts.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Results</title>
  <p class="p">Alkaloids, phenols, flavonoids, saponins, and terpenes were the main phytochemicals presents in all accessions. A significant positive correlation was found between TPC and antioxidant activity of different accessions. Extracts of highland and semi-arid zones possessed maximum antioxidant potential. Accessions from tropical zones showed the least antioxidant activity in all assays.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Conclusions</title>
  <p class="p">It could be concluded that different agro-climatic conditions have effects on the phytochemicals, total phenolic content (TPC) and antioxidant potential of the 
   <italic class="italic">A. vera</italic> plant. The results reveal that 
   <italic class="italic">A. vera</italic> can be a potential source of novel natural antioxidant compounds.
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
