<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec003" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Modelling the present distribution of climate suitability</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We use climate variables affecting pipit and chiffchaff abundance to predict the distribution of the most suitable wintering grounds. To do this, we use the spatial distribution of winter ring records provided by the European Union for Bird Ringing (Euring; 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.euring.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.euring.org/</span>) to explore the distribution of species. As these recoveries are widely distributed throughout the study area (
  <a rid="pone.0146958.g002" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0146958.g002">Fig 2</a>) they can be used to explore the environmental preferences of birds. The models will be constructed with Maxent, a popular machine-learning technique designed to predict the occurrence probabilities of species by combining species presences (latitude and longitude) with the geographical distribution of climate variables [
  <a rid="pone.0146958.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146958.ref030">30</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146958.ref031" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146958.ref031">31</a>]. The ability of these maps to identify sectors of different climatic suitability will be tested with the distribution of pipits and chiffchaffs in the study localities (
  <a rid="pone.0146958.g002" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0146958.g002">Fig 2</a>). If the actual occupancy and abundance [
  <a rid="pone.0146958.ref032" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146958.ref032">32</a>] of birds agree with the occurrence probability maps, we will use the models to forecast the changes in the extent and suitability of wintering areas according to predictions of climate change. This approach assumes a "space-for-time" design, which attempts to predict temporal changes from present spatial correlates between species distribution and climate variables [
  <a rid="pone.0146958.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146958.ref033">33</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
