<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Cassava (
 <italic class="italic">M. esculenta</italic>) is the crop with the highest total production in Africa, with 118 million tonnes of productions across the continent in 2010, contributing significant energy input to the population with an average 196 kcal/capita/day in 2008 (FAO 
 <xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>; Smit and Skinner 
 <xref rid="CIT0051" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2002</xref>). Cassava is a major staple for more than 500 million people in Africa, and is renowned for its drought tolerance and hardiness in stressful environments (El-Sharkawy 
 <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2004</xref>). From the few studies which have quantified the impacts or responses of cassava to climate change, Jarvis et al. (
 <xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>) found out that cassava is the least affected crop when compared with other major staples such as maize, sorghum and millets. Liu et al. (
 <xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2008</xref>) used the Geographical Information Systems (GIS)-based Environmental Policy Integrated Climate (GEPIC) model to evaluate impacts on cassava production across sub-Saharan Africa, finding a change in production to 2030 of -2% to +1% depending on the Special Report on Emission Scenarios (SRES). The results were in agreement with those by Lobell et al. (2008) who found cassava to moderately benefit from climate change by 2030 with an average increase of 1.1% in production from 2000 through the use of statistical models. Jarvis et al. (
 <xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>) carried out a research on the impacts of climate change on cassava and compared it with other important African staples such as maize, sorghum, millets, potato, common bean and banana and found that cassava is not affected by soil type and changes in weather patterns. Jarvis et al. (
 <xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>) also found that very few studies have focused on cassava when predicting impacts of climate change on crop production, partly because process-based crop models are not accurate or not available at all (Boote et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>; Challinor &amp; Wheeler 
 <xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2008</xref>; Fermont et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>), and partly because most research on climate change impact assessment has focused on better documented staples such as maize, wheat and rice (Bakker et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2008</xref>).
</p>
