<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par4" class="p">Restriction or blockage of tidal flows dramatically alters wetlands as habitat for flora and fauna
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">8</xref>
 </sup>, and further causes major changes in microbial and chemical processes in wetland soil and water
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">11</xref>
 </sup>. Here we emphasize that those changes can also alter the direction and magnitude of greenhouse gas (GHG) exchange between the wetland and the atmosphere. The fate of soil C in wetlands, and emissions of CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> and CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>, largely depend on water salinity and water table elevation relative to the soil surface, with temperature and plant productivity also having important influence. Under flooded or impounded conditions, soil becomes anaerobic, effectively to the soil surface. Under those conditions, if blockage of tidal flows has caused water salinity to decrease from &gt;18 psu (~50% seawater) to &lt;18, then a substantial increase in CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> emission is expected to occur
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">9</xref>
 </sup>. Salinity is a critical driver because seawater contains abundant sulfate ion, and where sulfate is abundant, sulfate reduction tends to outcompete methanogenesis as a metabolic pathway for microbial decomposition of organic matter. Additionally, sulfate can serve as the terminal electron acceptor in the oxidation of methane to carbon dioxide
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">12</xref>
 </sup>, further reducing CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> emissions under saline conditions. Though measurements are uncommon, CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> emissions in inundated, low salinity portions of tidally-restricted wetlands are elevated
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">13</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">14</xref>
 </sup>, and similar to the average of published rates for tidal wetlands at salinity &lt;18 psu
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">3</xref>
 </sup>. Drainage of both tidal and non-tidal wetlands, on the other hand, drains water from soil pore-spaces and exposes soil organic matter to air and associated oxygen, thereby promoting aerobic microbial respiration of C stocks that have accumulated over centuries to millennia, with CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> as the primary product. Drainage-associated soil CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> emissions are intense per unit area, and drained tidal wetlands
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">15</xref>
 </sup> and terrestrial peatlands
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>
 </sup> are significant drivers of climate change. Drainage and restoration of terrestrial (non-tidal, freshwater) peatlands are not the focus of the present study, except as an informative comparison to GHG consequences of tidal restriction and restoration of tidal wetlands, since rewetting (re-flooding through restoration of natural hydrology) of terrestrial peatlands, to protect soil C stocks from ongoing respiration and loss as CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> emissions, is considered to have great potential as a landuse-based climate intervention
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">17</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
