<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par16" class="p">These results provide insight and nuance into earlier classifications of precipitation frequency changes by intensity categories for California
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" class="xref">41</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" class="xref">43</xref>
 </sup>. Generally speaking, the probability density function of daily precipitation is projected to favor heavy and extreme events due to reinforced AR activity in a warmer climate, while the frequency of medium-low-intensity precipitation dwindles as the wintertime circulation over the north-eastern Pacific generally becomes more anticyclonic
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" class="xref">44</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" class="xref">45</xref>
 </sup>, the storm track migrates poleward
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" class="xref">46</xref>
 </sup>, and mid-latitude cyclones respond by generally diminishing in frequency
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" class="xref">44</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" class="xref">46</xref>
 </sup>. Other results indicate a strengthening and SE-ward extension of the NE Pacific jet stream in the historical jet exit region west of California
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" class="xref">46</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" class="xref">47</xref>
 </sup>. This is consistent with a stronger and more SE-ward extensive Aleutian Low, which, in combination with a more poleward-extensive Subtropical High, promotes stronger vapor transport into California
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>
 </sup> bolstering AR activity there but displacing cold-frontal convection northward. While examination of these somewhat competing dynamical mechanisms in the Real-5 GCMs is beyond the scope of the current work, we reiterate that the largest decrease in precipitation frequency occurs in the shoulder seasons
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">21</xref>
 </sup>, while the largest increase in extreme precipitation should occur at the peak of the AR season (Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S4</xref>), which in California is winter.
</p>
