<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par18" class="p">The same mechanisms operate over a larger west-coastal domain (Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S8</xref>), but they do not exert as much impact on precipitation volatility in the Northwest (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3</xref>). Precipitation is much more frequent there and major topography is not oriented ideally to enhance AR-related precipitation intensity (Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S5</xref>, i.e. NNE-SSW-oriented Cascades compared to NNW-SSE-oriented Sierra Nevada). This results in little change in annual total precipitation (Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S7</xref>) as well as its interannual variability over the Pacific Northwest (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3</xref>). As nature does not respect political boundaries, Northern Baja California’s border region displays anthropogenic signals similar to those of Southern California, but projections indicate drying further to the south (Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S7</xref>), where precipitation frequency decreases more decisively (Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S6</xref>) but precipitation intensity does not follow suit (Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S5</xref>). In the rain-shadow of the Sierra Nevada, the Great Basin is projected to receive more total precipitation (Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S7c</xref>), stemming from more frequent precipitation (Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S6c</xref>) and greater intensity (Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S5</xref>), although these changes may be less related to AR activity (Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S6f</xref>) than they are to changes in the Southwest monsoon
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" class="xref">49</xref>
 </sup>, which is beyond the scope of the present work.
</p>
