<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The findings of this analysis regarding forest biomass and composition have both similarities and differences compared to other analyses evaluating the impacts of N deposition and climate change, but direct comparisons are difficult due to differences in objectives, models, and the drivers included. For example, Aber and Driscoll (
 <xref rid="ecm1345-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1997</xref>) evaluated the impacts of climate, N deposition, and land‐use and disturbance history on N dynamics and total C storage by forest ecosystems. They found that increasing background N deposition to current levels increased net ecosystem productivity in all the forests by 24–47 g C·m
 <sup class="sup">−2</sup>·yr
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>; similar differences in net productivity were also found in their comparison of average (1980–1994) vs. real climate conditions. Townsend et al. (
 <xref rid="ecm1345-bib-0081" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1996</xref>), modeled the influence of anthropogenic N deposition on global C accumulation from 1845 to 1990, and estimated that in 1990 C storage was 0.44–0.74 Pg C/yr with the rate varying due to different in N deposition level, vegetation type and land‐use. Other studies have focused specifically on forests and the influences of climate change on biomass and composition. For example, Thompson et al. (
 <xref rid="ecm1345-bib-0080" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>) modeled changes in Massachusetts forest biomass and composition in response to changes in land use and climate. Similar to our study, they found that changes in climate increased total biomass, but they found little impact of climate and land use changes on overall forest composition. Scheller and Mladenoff (
 <xref rid="ecm1345-bib-0074" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2005</xref>) also found that Wisconsin forest biomass would increase in response to future climate scenarios. Live biomass was predicted to be 5–29% higher by 2190 if the influence of other disturbances (wind and harvesting) were not accounted for. However, their study also predicted changes in forest composition and varying effects on biomass due to the combined effects of tree species extirpation (poor seed dispersal and migration), harvesting, windthrow, and climate change. In contrast, Duveneck et al. (
 <xref rid="ecm1345-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>) in their evaluation of the impacts of future climate scenarios, harvest, wind, and fire on northern Great Lakes forests reported lower total forest biomass under the climate associated with the highest emissions scenario. However, they also found that forest productivity and diversity responses and relationships varied with soils, landscape, and regional climate under a high emissions scenario.
</p>
