<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par20" class="p">We used the VIC model to simulate streamflow in the observed and projected future climate. The VIC model
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" class="xref">53</xref>
 </sup> is a semi-distributed and physically based hydrological model that solves both water and energy balance for each grid-cell. The VIC model uses the infiltration mechanism utilized in the Xinanjiang model
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" class="xref">54</xref>
 </sup> to generate runoff from precipitation higher than the available infiltration capacity. Baseflow in the VIC model is computed using Arno model conceptualization
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" class="xref">55</xref>
 </sup>. Snow model
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" class="xref">56</xref>
 </sup> and frozen soil algorithm
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">18</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" class="xref">57</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" class="xref">58</xref>
 </sup> in the VIC model are used to calculate cold season processes (snow storage and melt). In the snow model, a two-layer snowpack is represented, which accounts for refreezing of meltwater, the role of vegetation, and snow age-dependent albedo
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" class="xref">56</xref>
 </sup>. We did not explicitly represent glaciers in the VIC model. However, we followed the approach of Schaner 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">11</xref>
 </sup> to account for the snow and glaciers on hydrological processes. We used a 57 year (1951–2007) spin up period for the VIC model to initialize the soil water storage and to create snow reservoirs (similar to glaciers) in the high elevation areas. For each 0.25° grid, we used ten snow bands to consider elevation variation within the grid cell. More information on the snow model and glacier simulations can be obtained from Cherkauer 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">18</xref>
 </sup> and Schaner 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">11</xref>
 </sup>, respectively.
</p>
