<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We investigated the phenotypic divergence of personality traits among plateau pika populations along an altitudinal gradient. Previous work on plateau pika populations indicates that the life-histories of high-altitude populations are slow. In support of the POLS hypothesis, we observed that higher-altitude populations also possessed personality traits that have been characterized as slow, i.e., less active and more docile, compared with the lower-altitude populations.</p>
 <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The differences in activity and docility among plateau pika altitude-associated populations can be attributed to the differing life history strategies that have evolved in response to different climates and environments (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>). Low-altitude pikas from GN show high reproductive output, which may be correlated with behaviour associated with increased energy intake [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>]. Activity in the open field is associated with activity levels, which are required for foraging, mating and predator escape [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>]. Docility is often used as a measure of risky behaviour in response to predator cues [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>]. The thorough activity and low docility of pikas from GN (lowest altitude) may facilitate them to obtain sufficient energy to satisfy greater energy requirements for reproduction.
 </p>
 <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our findings indicate that differences in environmental conditions resulted in specific associations between behavioural traits of plateau pikas. These results indicate that behavioural syndromes could be adaptive, such that associations between behaviour may vary substantially in accordance with prevailing environmental conditions. Activity and docility were negatively associated in pikas from high- and medium-altitude sites. Correlations between these traits may corroborate the POLS hypothesis [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>]. In the Tibetan Plateau, an increase in altitude is associated with a decrease in temperature and food resources [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>]. Environmental or animal status may affect relationships between behavioural and physiological traits [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>]. Negative feedback mechanisms (e.g. asset protection hypotheses) may predominate at low resource levels and decouple such correlations. By contrast, positive feedback mechanisms between animal states and different behaviour (e.g. starvation avoidance or state-dependent safety hypotheses) at intermediate levels of resource availability can produce behavioural syndromes [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>]. Our study implied that the directions of such relationships could be affected by altitude. In high-altitude populations, negative associations between activity and docility may be adaptive and enable pikas to obtain additional food resources and evade predation. Pikas from lowest sites occupy higher vegetation cover and food availability, which can weaken or eliminate the correlations between activity and docility in pika populations [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We analysed behavioural differences among populations at the phenotypic level. As a result, we cannot rule out whether phenotypic differences reflect genetic differences or developmental plasticity [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>]. Regardless of the cause of differences among populations, our results suggest that the divergence in behaviour traits across the altitudinal gradient may enable pikas to cope with different local environments [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>]. Reciprocal translocation or common-garden experiments would help to determine if personality differences reflect genetic differences or developmental plasticity [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">59</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We were unable to conclusively identify the precise divergences in the personality of pika populations distributed at higher altitudes, given that we focused on the traits of pika populations distributed within a limited altitude range. Nevertheless, our data reveal that the personality of pikas differs across altitudinal sites. Our study also provides valuable information regarding the effects of ecological conditions on the behavioural traits of animals at the population levels [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>]. Although numerous studies have documented variation in life-history traits and phenotypes in response to global climate change [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>], only a few have shown adaptations of animal personality to global warming [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">60</a>]. Increases in altitude are associated with decreases in temperature, and changes in environments may reflect how animals will respond to future climate change [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>]. Further studies illuminating the mechanisms underlying the personality differences among populations are necessary to improve our understanding of animal responses to future climate change [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">61</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">63</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
