<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study system</div>
 <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The plateau pika is a small, diurnal lagomorph that is widely distributed throughout the alpine meadows of the Tibetan Plateau. Populations can live between altitudes of 3,200 and 5,300 m [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>]. Pikas live communally forming territorial, mixed-sex groups that use a distinct burrow system with multiple entries [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>]. Previous studies have shown population divergence in life history traits at different altitudes [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>]. For example, low-altitude populations (e.g. Guinan, 3,200 m) produce 3–5 litters per year with 4.5 ± 0.1 pups in each litter [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>], whereas those from high-altitude (e.g. Guoluo, 4,000 m) produce 1–2 litters per year with 3.2 ± 0.1 pups in each litter [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We investigated three plateau pika populations at three different altitudes: Maqin (MQ), Zeku (ZK) and Guinan (GN), in the eastern Tibetan Plateau, Qinghai, China (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). The distances between sites ranged from 180 km to 285 km, and the normal dispersal distance of plateau pika is about 40 m [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>]; therefore, gene flow among the three populations is limited. At all sites, the climate is dry and cool, typical of a plateau continental climate [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>]. Precipitation occurs mostly from May to September, and heavy winter snowfalls are rare. Daily temperatures vary considerably (up to 25 °C). The climate is harsher at higher altitudes with decreasing annual temperatures, whereas annual precipitation increases. As a result, productivity and vegetation height decreases, and the growing season becomes shorter at higher altitudes (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>).
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Map showing the locations of the study sites indicated by abbreviations corresponding to Table 
     <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="12983_2019_329_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Vegetation at the three sites is typical of Tibetan alpine meadows. The dominant plant species include 
  <span class="italic">Kobresia humilis</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Elymus nutans</span> Griseb. and 
  <span class="italic">Leontopodium alpinum</span>. To evaluate vegetation at each site, we quantified plant cover and height using the approach developed by Huenneke et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>]. At each site, 10 quadrats (50 cm × 50 cm) were randomly selected. We estimated plant biomass within each quadrat using non-destructive measurements of plant species cover and height and total vegetation cover by counting the portions of squares occupied by plants. Vegetation height was presented as the mean height of each species. With the increase in altitude, vegetation cover and height were significantly higher at GN than at GL and ZK (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">At all sites, grass is grazed all year round by livestock (i.e. yak, sheep and horse). Other small herbivores, such as woolly hares (
  <span class="italic">Lepus oiostolus</span>), Himalayan marmots (
  <span class="italic">Marmota himalayana</span>) and plateau zokors (
  <span class="italic">Myospalax baileyi</span>), were absent at the sites. Common predators include red fox (
  <span class="italic">Vulpes vulpes</span>), Tibetan fox (
  <span class="italic">V. ferrilata</span>), upland buzzard (
  <span class="italic">Buteo hemilasius</span>) and saker falcon (
  <span class="italic">Falco cherrug</span>).
 </p>
</sec>
