<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Identifying trends in the population, used to be a long and drawn out process utilizing surveys and polls and then collating the data to determine what is currently most popular with the population [
  <a rid="pone.0138996.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138996.ref001">1</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0138996.ref002" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138996.ref002">2</a>]. This is true for everything that was of merit to the political organizations present, regarding any issue of political or public interest.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Recently, the use of the two terms ‘Climate Change’ and ‘Global Warming’ have become very visible to the public and their understanding of what is happening with respect to the climate [
  <a rid="pone.0138996.ref003" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138996.ref003">3</a>]. The public response to all of the news and publicity about climate has been a search for understanding and comprehension, leading to support or disbelief. The two terms while having similarity in meaning are used in slightly different semantic contexts. The press in order to expand their news readership/viewer lists has chosen to use this ambiguity to their favor in providing news to the public [
  <a rid="pone.0138996.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138996.ref004">4</a>]. Within the news releases, the expression ‘due to climate change’ has been used to explain phenomological causality.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">These two terms “global warming–(GW)” and “climate change–(CC)” both play a role in how the public at large views the natural world and the changes occurring in it. They are used interactively by the news agencies, without a thought towards their actual meaning [
  <a rid="pone.0138996.ref003" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138996.ref003">3</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0138996.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138996.ref004">4</a>]. Therefore, the public in trying to identify changes in the news and their understanding of those changes looks for the meaning of those terms online. The extent of their knowledge can be examined by assessing the use of the terms in online search queries. Information searches using the internet are increasing, and therefore can indicate public or individual interest.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Internet search queries can be tracked using a variety of analytic engines that are independent of, or embedded into, the respective search engines (google trend, naver analytics) and are used to determine the popularity of a topic in terms of internet searches [
  <a rid="pone.0138996.ref005" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138996.ref005">5</a>]. The trend engines will look for selected keywords from searches, keywords chosen for their relevance to the field or the query being performed.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The process of using social media to obtain information on public opinion is a practice that has been utilized with increasing frequency in modern research for subjects ranging from politics [
  <a rid="pone.0138996.ref006" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138996.ref006">6</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0138996.ref007" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138996.ref007">7</a>] to linguistics [
  <a rid="pone.0138996.ref008" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138996.ref008">8</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0138996.ref010" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138996.ref010">10</a>] complex systems [
  <a rid="pone.0138996.ref011" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138996.ref011">11</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0138996.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138996.ref012">12</a>] to environment [
  <a rid="pone.0138996.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138996.ref013">13</a>]. This variety of research belies the flexibility of the approach, the large availability of data availability for mining in order to formulate a response to public opinion regarding the subject being assessed. In modern society understanding how the public responds regarding complex issues of societal importance [
  <a rid="pone.0138996.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138996.ref012">12</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While the two causally connected terms GW and CC are used interchangeably, they describe entirely different physical phenomena [
  <a rid="pone.0138996.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138996.ref014">14</a>]. These two terms therefore can be used to determine how people understand the parallel concepts, especially if they are used as internet search query terms in trend analysis. However, searching the internet falls into two patterns, searches for work or for personal interest, neither of which can be determined from the trend engines. The By following the searches, it is possible to determine the range of public interest in the two terms, based on the respective volumes of the search queries. Previously in order to mine public opinion on a subject, government agencies had to revert to polling and surveys, which while being effective did not cover a very large component of the population [
  <a rid="pone.0138996.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138996.ref015">15</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0138996.ref017" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138996.ref017">17</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Google trend data is one method of measuring popularity of a subject within the population. Individuals searching for a topic use search keywords to obtain the desired information [
  <a rid="pone.0138996.ref005" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138996.ref005">5</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0138996.ref018" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138996.ref018">18</a>]. These keywords are topic sensitive, and therefore indicate the level of knowledge regarding the searched topic. The two primary word phrases here “climate change” and “global warming” are unilateral terms that indicate a level of awareness about the issue which is indicative of the individuals interest in that subject [
  <a rid="pone.0138996.ref005" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138996.ref005">5</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0138996.ref019" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138996.ref019">19</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0138996.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138996.ref020">20</a>]. Google trend data relates how often a term is searched, that is the frequency of a search term can be identified from the results of the Google® trend analysis. While frequency is not a direct measure of popularity, it does indicate if a search term is common or uncommon and the value of that term to the public at large. The relationship between frequency and popularity lies in the volume of searches by a large number of individuals over specific time duration. Therefore, by identifying the number of searches during a specific period, it is possible to come to a proximate understanding of how popular or common a term is for the general population [
  <a rid="pone.0138996.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138996.ref021">21</a>]. However, the use of trend data is more appropriately used to identify awareness of an issue rather than its popularity.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This brings us to sentiment analysis. Part of the connection between the search and the populations’ awareness of an issue can be measured using how they refer to the subject in question. This sentiment, is found in different forms of social media, or social networking sites sites i.e. twitter®, Facebook®, linked in® and personal blogs [
  <a rid="pone.0138996.ref007" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138996.ref007">7</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0138996.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138996.ref022">22</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0138996.ref024" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138996.ref024">24</a>]. Thus, the original information, which was found on the internet, becomes influenced by personal attitudes and opinions [
  <a rid="pone.0138996.ref025" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138996.ref025">25</a>]and then redistributed throughout the internet, accessible to anyone who has an internet connection and the desire to search. This behavior affects the information that now provides the opportunity to assess public sentiment regarding the prevailing attitudes regarding environmental issues [
  <a rid="pone.0138996.ref026" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138996.ref026">26</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0138996.ref027" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138996.ref027">27</a>]. To assess this we used Google® and Twitter® data to understand public concerns related to climate change and global warming. Google trend was used to trace changes in interest between the two phenomena. Tweets (comments made on Twitter®) were analyzed to identify negative or positive emotional responses.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Comparatively, twitter data is more indicative of how people refer to topics of interest [
  <a rid="pone.0138996.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138996.ref028">28</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0138996.ref031" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138996.ref031">31</a>], in a manner that is very linguistically restricted. As well, twitter is used as a platform for verbal expression of emotional responses. Due to the restrictions on tweet size (each tweet can only be 140 characters in length), it is necessary to be more direct in dealing with topics of interest to the tweeter. Therefore, the tweets are linguistically more emotionally charged and can be used to define a level of emotional response by the tweeter.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The choice of target words for the tweets and for the Google trend searches were the specific topic phrases [
  <a rid="pone.0138996.ref032" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138996.ref032">32</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0138996.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138996.ref033">33</a>]. These were chosen because of the descriptive nature of the phrases. Scientific literature is very specific in its use and therefore has very definitive meanings. The appropriation of these words by the population as a method for describing their response to the variation in the environment provides the basis for the choice as target words for the study. The classification of the words as being positive versus negative lies in the direction provided by Frank Lutz. This politicization of a scientific word as a means of directing public awareness, means the prescription of one phrase (climate change) as being more positive than the other (global warming).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Global warming is defined as the long-term trend of increasing average global temperatures; alternatively, climate change is defined as a change in global or regional climate patterns, in particular a change apparent from the mid to late 20
  <span class="sup">th</span> century onwards and attributed to the increased levels of atmospheric carbon dioxide arising from the use of fossil fuels. Therefore, the search keywords were chosen based on their scientific value and their public visibility. What is important about the choice of these search terms is that due to their scientific use, they describe a distinctly identifiable state. The more specific these words are, the less risk of the algorithm misinterpreting the keyword and thus having the results misinterpreted [
  <a rid="pone.0138996.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138996.ref034">34</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0138996.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138996.ref036">36</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The purpose of the following study was to identify trends within search parameters for two specific sets of trend queries. The second purpose of the study was to identify how the public responds emotionally to those same queries. Finally, the purpose of the study was to determine if the two had any connections.</p>
</sec>
