<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ack class="ack">
 <title class="title">Acknowledgments</title>
 <p class="p">We would like to thank D. Wake, K. Zamudio, and the Clemson Writing Group for their comments on this manuscript. 
  <bold class="bold">Funding:</bold> We would like to thank the Highlands Biological Station in Highlands, NC for the opportunity to collect these data through their Grant-in-Aid Program. Funding for the experiments was provided by the NSF Doctoral Dissertation Improvement Grant Program (#1601485) and the Clemson Creative Inquiry program. We thank the Clemson Creative Inquiry program, the Open Access Publishing Fund through the Clemson Library, and the Department of Biological Sciences at Clemson University for funding to cover publication costs. 
  <bold class="bold">Author contributions:</bold> E.A.R. conceptualized, designed, implemented the experiments, conducted the analyses, developed the mechanistic SDM, and wrote the manuscript. J.P.O. and J.D.D. assisted with the experiments. M.W.S. conceptualized and designed the project, as well as provided helpful comments to the manuscript. 
  <bold class="bold">Competing interests:</bold> The authors declare that they have no competing interests. 
  <bold class="bold">Data and materials availability:</bold> Data are available on the Open Science Framework (
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://osf.io/e4sp6/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://osf.io/e4sp6/</ext-link>), and Python Script with supporting materials is available on GitHub (
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/ecophysiology/salamander_simulation" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://github.com/ecophysiology/salamander_simulation</ext-link>). All data needed to evaluate the conclusions in the paper are present in the paper and/or the Supplementary Materials. Additional data related to this paper may be requested from the authors.
 </p>
</ack>
