<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par8" class="p">One reason for this ambiguity about the role of low temperature could be that bud formation is confused with dormancy. For example, in proleptic hybrid aspen, para-dormant and dormant axillary buds (AXBs) are structurally similar, but shoot decapitation can only activate para-dormant AXBs [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>]. TBs can also form temporarily under stress without establishing dormancy [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">12</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" class="xref">19</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">30</xref>]. Even tropical trees show this behaviour during episodic growth, in response to drought, or during the alternation of elongation growth and branching [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" class="xref">19</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" class="xref">31</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" class="xref">32</xref>]. Thus, conclusive assessment of whether buds are dormant, i.e. intrinsically arrested, requires tests in which buds are freed from apical dominance and correlative inhibition. Presently, tests should also include analyses of key marker genes of dormancy [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" class="xref">33</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" class="xref">34</xref>]. The claim that low temperature in the chilling range can induce dormancy or contribute to its establishment is puzzling, because it is a universal cause of dormancy release [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" class="xref">35</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" class="xref">37</xref>], and there is no explanation of how low temperature could both induce and antagonize the same state. The manner in which temperature intersects with the photoperiodic pathway during bud initiation and dormancy therefore requires further investigation.
</p>
