<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par9" class="p">The photoperiodic response that results in TB formation is well documented. For example, 
 <italic class="italic">Betula</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Populus</italic> monitor the declining photoperiod by means of light-sensitive phytochromes in the leaves [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" class="xref">25</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">38</xref>]. These pigments provide input to a circadian clock that transcriptionally regulates expression of the floral promoter 
 <italic class="italic">CONSTANS</italic> (
 <italic class="italic">CO</italic>) and the key integrator gene 
 <italic class="italic">FLOWERING LOCUS T</italic> (
 <italic class="italic">FT</italic>) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" class="xref">25</xref>]. 
 <italic class="italic">Populus</italic> possesses two functionally distinct paralogs, 
 <italic class="italic">FT2</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">FT1</italic>, which promote vegetative growth and flowering, respectively [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" class="xref">34</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" class="xref">39</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" class="xref">40</xref>]. Exposure to short photoperiod downregulates 
 <italic class="italic">FT2</italic> in the leaves, and transiently upregulates the gene 
 <italic class="italic">CENTRORADIALIS-</italic>like1 (
 <italic class="italic">CENL1</italic>) at the rib meristem to support TB formation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" class="xref">34</xref>]. Thereby, the apex switches to the developmental program of AXBs, both structurally and molecularly. When TBs and the young AXBs complete their development and establish dormancy, 
 <italic class="italic">CENL1</italic> expression ceases. In contrast, para-dormant AXBs that develop under long photoperiod maintain a high level of 
 <italic class="italic">CENL1</italic> expression and are poised for vegetative growth, only requiring removal of apical dominance [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>]. During chilling-induced dormancy release, 
 <italic class="italic">FT1</italic> transcription is hyperinduced, but 
 <italic class="italic">CENL1</italic> is not [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" class="xref">40</xref>]. As these genes are central in the regulation of vernalization and floral transition [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" class="xref">39</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" class="xref">41</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" class="xref">42</xref>], this suggests that low temperature not only releases dormancy, but may also promote vernalization of dormant buds. To clarify the role of temperature in dormancy establishment, it is important to assess how exposure to low temperature during the bud development phase (hereafter referred to as pre-dormancy) interferes with the transcriptional patterns of key dormancy-cycling and vernalization genes.
</p>
