<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="pmed.1002688.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pmed.1002688.g004</object-id>
 <label class="label">Fig 4</label>
 <caption class="caption">
  <title class="title">Schematic of rainfall and flood pulse influences on surface water quality and diarrheal disease outbreaks in a flood pulse river system.</title>
  <p class="p">In these systems, the flood pulse uniquely links aquatic and terrestrial habitats and microbial communities including potential pathogens. During the wet season (panel 1), rainfall moves fecal 
   <italic class="italic">E</italic>. 
   <italic class="italic">coli</italic> (a marker for fecal bacteria) overland from riparian areas into the river channel. As in-river 
   <italic class="italic">E</italic>. 
   <italic class="italic">coli</italic> increases, the number of diarrheal disease case reports increases in the population using municipal water that was obtained from the river (wet season outbreak). During this same period, seasonal pans are filled with rainfall, and water-dependent animals (wildlife and, to a lesser extent, livestock) move out of the riparian area into the interior to utilize forage and water resources. Floodwaters (panel 2) rise and inundate floodplains, incorporating fecal microbial communities on previously dry land areas. With progression of the dry season and no rainfall, water pans in the interior dry up, and water-dependent animals move back to the river’s edge, concentrating fecal material along river floodplains while utilizing the only permanent surface water in the system. Floodwaters begin to recede from the inundated land areas (panel 3), and TSS levels increase, as does the number of diarrheal case reports (dry season outbreak). In the rare event of rainfall in the dry season, 
   <italic class="italic">E</italic>. 
   <italic class="italic">coli</italic> levels in the water channel increase and are positively associated with diarrheal case reports (not shown). TSS, total suspended solids.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="pmed.1002688.g004" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
