<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Given the broad scale at which our analysis was conducted, a variety of indirect and nonclimatic factors (for example, fire regimes, invasive species, forest management, conservation efforts, and land use change) could also have influenced the directional trends observed. The fact that the observed abundance change is positively correlated with the densification of forests, which is often attributed to diminishing fire frequency and severity (
 <xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">26</italic>
 </xref>), confirms that nonclimatic factors are also responsible for the observed spatial shift of species abundance. Heavy infestations of invasive insects, plants, and pathogens could contribute to species shifts in other directions (
 <xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">41</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">42</italic>
 </xref>). In addition, forest conservation and plantation efforts in the study area such as those by the U.S. Department of Agriculture (USDA) Conservation Reserve Program could also influence the observed spatial shift. Nevertheless, we observed clear broad-scale evidence of the impact of climate change on forest tree spatial dynamics, where changes in mean annual precipitation alone explained about 19% of the variability in species abundance change and spatial shift. It could be beneficial for future studies to investigate the impacts of inter- and intra-annual variability of moisture availability at finer spatial and temporal resolutions (for example, for droughts and floods) on vegetation dynamics, given the high likelihood of more variable precipitation patterns in the future (
 <xref rid="R43" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">43</italic>
 </xref>). In addition, because more repeated plot-level measures are becoming available across the regional scale, we can better study the degree to which climate change induces new community assemblages owing to the varying mortality and recruitment and/or competitive release of different trait- and phylogenetic-specific groups. These repeated measures may eventually enable the analysis of more tree species in the eastern U.S. forests, rather than the selected ones in this study, allowing the detection of phylogenetic- and trait-specific patterns that might be undetected in the current analysis.
</p>
