<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">There is a growing body of evidence showing that climate change may affect the incidence and prevalence of certain vector-borne diseases such as malaria, dengue, West Nile fever, and LD. Unlike weather, which defines a condition of the atmosphere over a short period of time, climate represents atmospheric “behavior” over a relatively long period of time [
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>]. Climate change, therefore, refers to changes in long-term averages of daily weather including temperature, humidity, air pressure, and precipitation. The incidence of tick-born zoonoses such as LD is particularly likely to be affected by climate change because ticks spend the majority of their life cycle outside the host in an environment where temperature and humidity directly affect their development, activity, survival, and host-seeking behavior [
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. The number of annually reported cases of LD in the United States has sharply increased over the last three decades, from about 10,000 in 1991 to about 28,000 annually in recent years [
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. Not only did the incidence of the disease increase, but also its geographical distribution. While climate change might significantly contribute to the emergence of new infections, it is interesting to contrast this change in the incidence of tick-borne diseases in the United States with the changes happening in Europe. There, during the 9 years prior to 2015, the growth of the cases of louse-born relapsing fever (due to 
 <italic class="italic">B. recurrentis</italic>) has been associated to the increase in refugees [
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>–
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. Furthermore, in the last few decades, newly recognized tick-borne rickettsioses have been shown to be present. 
 <italic class="italic">R. conorii</italic> sub sp. 
 <italic class="italic">Israelensis</italic> has been detected in human cases in Sicily and Sardinia in Italy and in different regions of Portugal [
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>].
</p>
