<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">To predict the distribution of leishmaniases under recent past and future land use and climate change scenarios, each BRT-submodel (from the abiotic-only suite of predictors) was applied to the prediction layers for a given land use and climate combination using the predict.gbm function of the gbm package [
 <xref rid="pone.0183583.ref057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>] in R. The predicted relative probability of presence was averaged across sub-models to produce an ensemble relative probability of presence (and standard deviation). External validation of recent past models was achieved by correlating the average case rate per municipality (2007–2011, see above) with the average predicted relative probability of presence across pixels in that municipality for each disease form. For each BRT model, the threshold relative probability of presence that maximises discrimination between presence/background for the hold-out dataset was calculated by gbm.step and averaged across folds (cross-validation threshold). Occurrence patterns were compared between the recent past and the future predicted distributions by converting the recent past and future predicted distributions to binary presence-absence maps per sub-model using the mean cross-validation threshold relative probability of presence for each recent past sub-model. The predicted extent of occurrence in terms of number of study grid squares or pixels was calculated for the recent past and each future land use and climate combination. The geographical extent of predictions was limited to the region for which the environmental predictors were available (the most restrictive of these being the land-cover metric) and of necessity omitted some adjacent areas of autochthonous leishmaniasis transmission such as Argentina. As per the matrix in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0183583.g002" class="xref">Fig 2</xref>, six different combinations of scenarios were considered i.e. 2 RCPs x 3 SSPs x 1 circulation model (HadGEM2-ES).
</p>
