<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fn-group class="fn-group">
 <fn id="Fn1" class="fn">
  <label class="label">1</label>
  <p class="p">The Government of India has categorized the so-called lower castes of India under three main categories. According to the 2011 Census of India, in Uttarakhand, Scheduled Castes constitute 18 % of population, while Scheduled Tribes and Other Backward Classes constitute 3 % of population. Forward castes (middle and high castes) constitute more than 50 % of the population in this region (Source: Census of India 2011).</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="Fn2" class="fn">
  <label class="label">2</label>
  <p class="p">In Bihar, Scheduled Castes constitute 15 % of population, Scheduled Tribes 1.3 % of population and Other Backward Classes 51 % of population. An Extremely Backward Class also exists and is a unique categorization to the state of Bihar. Forward classes (middle and upper castes) constitute 15 % of population in Bihar (Source: Census of India 2011).</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="Fn3" class="fn">
  <label class="label">3</label>
  <p class="p">Indian States are administratively composed of districts. The smallest administrative subdivision of districts is known as blocks, i.e. group of villages, which only exist in rural areas.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="Fn4" class="fn">
  <label class="label">4</label>
  <p class="p">The US National Academy of Sciences has identified Horse gram (
   <italic class="italic">Macrotyloma uniflorum</italic>) as a potential food source for the future, thanks to its exceptional nutrition profile, drought resistance and general hardiness (Bhardwaj and Yadav 
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">2015</xref>).
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="Fn5" class="fn">
  <label class="label">5</label>
  <p class="p">Results from our survey confirm that around a 70 % of sampled women in each village declared to be involved in collective activities of fertility management, harvesting and fodder cutting, while men are little or not involved.</p>
 </fn>
</fn-group>
