<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="wcc591-sec-0007" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">THE MULTIDECADAL DROUGHT OF THE 20TH CENTURY</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the course of the 20th century, variability in seasonal rainfall totals was large and spatially coherent over much of the Sahel (Figure 
  <a rid="wcc591-fig-0006" ref-type="fig" href="#wcc591-fig-0006">6</a>). The first part of the 20th century shows a predominance of anomalously wet years and decades, followed by a decline in seasonal rainfall totals during the later half of the record, with overall low rainfall decades punctuated by devastating short‐term droughts such as those of 1972 and 1983–1984 (Figure 
  <a rid="wcc591-fig-0006" ref-type="fig" href="#wcc591-fig-0006">6</a>a). The map of the multidecadal rainfall trend (brown colors in Figure 
  <a rid="wcc591-fig-0006" ref-type="fig" href="#wcc591-fig-0006">6</a>b) highlights the continental scale of long‐term climate change in the Sahel.
 </p>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="wcc591-fig-0006" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 6</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>(a) Summer‐mean (July to September) standardized anomalies in rainfall totals (black solid line) and number of rainy days (red dashed line) averaged over the region 10°N–20°N and 20°W–30°E (from the University of East Anglia Climate Research Unit gridded data set, TS4.1). (b) Linear trend in summer‐mean African rainfall between 1940 and 1985 (brown and green hues) and in annual‐mean sea surface temperatures over the same period (blue and orange hues) (Reprinted with permission from Biasutti (
    <a rid="wcc591-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0010">2011</a>). Copyright 2011 Nature)
   </p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-13" xlink:href="WCC-10-na-g006" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The cause of the 20th century droughts has been amply discussed in the literature. In the early 70s—even while meteorologists had started to recognize the possible role of the global atmospheric circulation “teleconnecting” remote regions—the dominant view of the Sahel drought (Charney, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0024">1975</a>) posited that local human activity was driving local climate in a positive feedback loop between poor land use practices, land denudation, and weakening monsoon rainfall. Two scientific developments led to a paradigm shift (Herrmann &amp; Hutchinson, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0061">2005</a>). On one hand, accumulating satellite observation of vegetation distribution were showing that, at the continental scale, vegetation was quick to expand in response to increased rainfall, overcoming the supposed fragility of the natural dryland ecosystem (Herrmann, Anyamba, &amp; Tucker, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0060" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0060">2005</a>). Since then, land use by local populations has been linked, more subtly, to both land degradation (Brandt et al., 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0020">2017</a>) and land stewardship (Stith et al., 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0130" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0130">2015</a>), and no unequivocal indication has emerged, either in observations or models, that changes in land use were ever large‐scale and homogeneous enough to affect the regional climate (see Box 
  <a rid="wcc591-fea-0001" ref-type="boxed-text" href="#wcc591-fea-0001">1</a>). On the other hand, progressively sophisticated computer models of the general circulation of the atmosphere (GCMs) first simulated a decrease in Sahel rainfall when forced with the pattern of the global ocean temperature anomalies of the 70s and 80s (Folland et al., 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0043">1986</a>) and, later, were able to reproduce the sequence of pluvial and droughts by including the historical evolution of sea surface temperature (SST), without any forcing from changes in land use (Giannini, Saravanan, &amp; Chang, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0049">2003</a>). It is now accepted that the main source of coherent interannual to interdecadal variability in 20th century Sahel rainfall (the pacing, although not necessarily the full magnitude) has been the variability of SST, while the potential role of natural soil and vegetation processes has been to amplify the remotely driven anomalies (Giannini et al., 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0049">2003</a>; Kucharski, Zeng, &amp; Kalnay, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0078" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0078">2012</a>; Zeng, Neelin, Lau, &amp; Tucker, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0155" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0155">1999</a>).
 </p>
 <div position="float" content-type="BOX" id="wcc591-fea-0001" orientation="portrait" class="boxed-text" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">BOX 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">DROUGHT, DESERTIFICATION, AND RESILIENCE</div>
  </div>
  <sec id="wcc591-sec-0008" class="sec" xmlns="">
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On the heels of the “Great Drought” of 1968–1973, the United Nations General Assembly called for international cooperation to combat desertification (which it formally defined in 1994 as “land degradation in arid, semi‐arid and dry sub‐humid areas resulting from various factors, including climatic variations and human activities”). The view at the time was that drylands, with their poor climate and soils, were especially fragile and vulnerable to human land use. This, coupled with the assumption that desertification might itself force drought (Charney, 
    <a rid="wcc591-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0024">1975</a>), had led to a forecast of spiraling degradation. This view has since been challenged by both the natural and the social sciences (Herrmann &amp; Hutchinson, 
    <a rid="wcc591-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0061">2005</a>). Ecological studies have emphasized how drylands are highly variable ecosystems, for which a dynamic nonequilibrium is to be expected. Their health is better monitored by slow‐varying variables such as soil fertility, rather than by variables such as vegetation cover or crop yields that respond fast to the vagaries of precipitation, pest outbreaks, and the like (Reynolds et al., 
    <a rid="wcc591-bib-0112" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0112">2007</a>). Indeed, as rainfall totals have increased since the mid‐1980s, vegetation has expanded in what has been known as a re‐greening (Dardel et al., 
    <a rid="wcc591-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0034">2014</a>). Similarly, socioeconomic studies have highlighted how rural populations employ risk‐spreading (e.g., economic diversification) and coping strategies (e.g., labor‐intensive conservation practices) to reduce stress on both their livelihoods and the environment (Mortimore, 
    <a rid="wcc591-bib-0096" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0096">2010</a>; Reynolds et al., 
    <a rid="wcc591-bib-0112" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0112">2007</a>). Still, soil erosion, loss of soil fertility, and loss of biodiversity remain widespread problems. As the climate changes outside the realm of modern experience, an alliance of local and science‐based knowledge is needed to build resilient human and environmental systems in the Sahel (Maestre et al., 
    <a rid="wcc591-bib-0089" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0089">2016</a>).
   </p>
  </sec>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The pattern of SST anomalies associated with decade‐long droughts in the Sahel (Figure 
  <a rid="wcc591-fig-0006" ref-type="fig" href="#wcc591-fig-0006">6</a>b) has lent itself to different descriptions. Assuming the point of view linking Sahel rainfall to the planetary ITCZ (Figure 
  <a rid="wcc591-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#wcc591-fig-0002">2</a>) leads to an emphasis on interhemispheric gradients, with early work (Folland et al., 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0043">1986</a>) emphasizing the SST gradient and recent literature (Hwang et al., 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0066" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0066">2013</a>; Schneider et al., 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0122" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0122">2014</a>) emphasizing the gradient in atmospheric energy input. Other studies have attempted to provide a more mechanistic explanation and to connect the SST anomalies in individual basins to specific processes that affect moisture supply and vertical stability. For example, localized warm anomalies in the Indian Ocean generate planetary waves that may lead to more stable profiles in the Atlantic sector and to reduced Sahel rainfall (e.g., Bader &amp; Latif, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0004">2003</a>; Hagos &amp; Cook, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0055">2008</a>). More generally, warmer tropical SSTs induce a more stable atmosphere and thus might induce drought, if not counteracted (see Figure 
  <a rid="wcc591-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#wcc591-fig-0003">3</a>). Giannini et al. (
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0048" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0048">2013</a>) have suggested that the nearby Atlantic can provide the needed counteraction. Positive rainfall anomalies in the Sahel ensue when warm temperatures in the subtropical north Atlantic make the low‐level monsoon flow sufficiently moist as to overcome the background stability. In their view, then, the tropics as a whole control stability (and control rainfall accumulation through its frequency) and the subtropical north Atlantic controls moisture supply (and controls rainfall accumulation through its intensity).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Whether the subtropical north Atlantic is the key region for moisture supply remains unproven. Lagrangian calculations of moisture sources for West Africa are at odds with this interpretation, as they indicate that Sahel rainfall originates from the South Atlantic and the African continent itself (Keys, Barnes, van der Ent, &amp; Gordon, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0075" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0075">2014</a>).
  <a ref-type="fn" rid="wcc591-note-0003" href="#wcc591-note-0003">2</a> It seems more likely, therefore, that warm anomalies in the subtropical north Atlantic affect Sahel rainfall through their effect on the temperature, humidity, and circulation over the Sahara, in the same fashion as has been suggested for warm anomalies in the extra‐tropical north Atlantic (Liu &amp; Chiang, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0087" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0087">2012</a>; Park, Bader, &amp; Matei, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0106" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0106">2015</a>) or the Mediterranean (Park, Bader, &amp; Matei, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0107" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0107">2016</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The mechanisms by which a northerly flow of anomalous warm and moist air coming across the Sahara can affect Sahel rainfall are multiple. In general, altering the moisture profile above the boundary layer modulates convective inhibition (the effect of a stable or dry layer of air that caps vertical motion close to the ground) as well as the effect of entrainment on convective plumes (as dry air mixing in during ascent dilutes the energy available for convection). These processes would seem to be quite fundamental, in view of the strong association between total column water vapor and daily rainfall that is a hallmark of tropical rainfall (Bretherton, Peters, &amp; Back, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0021">2004</a>). Nevertheless, in the Sahel variations in the temperature profile dominate over humidity in modulating the seasonal‐scale variations of the level of free convection and of the occurrence and intensity of deep convection (Kollias, Miller, Johnson, Jensen, &amp; Troyan, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0077" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0077">2009</a>). It remains to be seen if temperature remains the dominant factor for decadal‐scale Sahel drought.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Furthermore, temperature and humidity trends within the Sahara might have affected Sahel rainfall indirectly, by changing the large‐scale circulation. One hypothesis is that the advected warm (cold) temperature anomalies or the radiative effect of the positive (negative) moisture anomaly would cause the SHL to shift to the north (south). This would result in a shift of the mid‐level divergence and would allow more/less rainfall at the latitude of the Sahel (Evan, Flamant, Lavaysse, Kocha, &amp; Saci, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0037">2015</a>; Shekhar &amp; Boos, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0126" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0126">2017</a>; Zhai &amp; Boos, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0156" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0156">2017</a>). Observations of long‐term trends in the Sahara (whether they be of moisture, temperature, or surface pressure) are unfortunately not available, preventing the testing of these mechanisms for the 20th century drought. Yet, one indirect piece of evidence might be found in simulations of the direct effect of greenhouse gases, that is, the effect that results in atmosphere‐only GCMs from increasing atmospheric long‐wave absorption while keeping SST unaltered. In these simulations (Gaetani et al., 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0044" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0044">2016</a>), the Sahara warms, the heat low shifts north, and rainfall in the Sahel is enhanced throughout the rainy season. We can surmise that the Sahel response would be the same if the Sahara warming were due to advection of SST‐forced anomalies, instead of being forced locally by radiative fluxes.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">No matter the details of the mechanisms, theory, modeling, and observations, all indicate that the Sahel drought was driven by processes that were global in scale. Yet, processes that are local to the Sahel—biogeochemical and biophysical vegetation and soil processes that affect the surface fluxes of matter and energy—are known to be important as amplifiers of the anomalies (Kucharski et al., 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0078" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0078">2012</a>; Zeng, Neelin, &amp; Chou, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0154" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0154">2000</a>). At the timescales of paleoclimatic changes, feedbacks involving land cover types and dust sources are believed to be key to the establishment of climatic anomalies (Kutzbach, Bonan, Foley, &amp; Harrison, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0079" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0079">1996</a>; Mohtadi, Prange, &amp; Steinke, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0095" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0095">2016</a>; Pausata, Messori, &amp; Zhang, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0109" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0109">2016</a>; Timm, Köhler, Timmermann, &amp; Menviel, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0140" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0140">2010</a>). At the shorter time scales of interest here, it is sufficient to consider moisture and energy feedbacks involving plant function and soil properties.
  <a ref-type="fn" rid="wcc591-note-0004" href="#wcc591-note-0004">3</a>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">According to recent work (Taylor et al., 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0137" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0137">2011</a>; Taylor, de Jeu, Guichard, Harris, &amp; Dorigo, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0136" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0136">2012</a>), a negative feedback between soil moisture, surface convergence, and rainfall depresses rainfall initiation over wet patches. Yet, this mechanism influences mesoscale variability without carrying over to regional rainfall (Guillod, Orlowsky, Miralles, Teuling, &amp; Seneviratne, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0052">2015</a>; Seneviratne et al., 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0123" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0123">2010</a>). At the regional scale of the Sahel, the traditional view of a positive feedback due to moisture recycling still holds: a wet surface can provide more water vapor to fuel more convection and rainfall (Brubaker, Entekhabi, &amp; Eagleson, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0022">1993</a>). Nevertheless, it is unclear if a positive land‐surface feedback is a persistent characteristic of Sahel rainfall. Berg, Lintner, Findell, and Giannini (
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0006">2017</a>) have shown that the positive feedback of moisture recycling interacts with the effect that moisture gradients have on surface temperature and the regional circulation (the shallow meridional circulation that penetrates north into the Sahara, and the strength and position of the AEJ), leading to divergent feedbacks in these models. Berg, Lintner, et al. (
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0006">2017</a>) were analyzing global warming simulations, but shortcomings in the representation of the full land‐surface feedbacks might also explain the inability of most GCMs to reproduce the amplitude of observed 20th century trends (Biasutti, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0011">2013</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The multidecadal swings in seasonal rainfall totals just discussed can be explained in terms of variability in the number of wet days (see Figure 
  <a rid="wcc591-fig-0006" ref-type="fig" href="#wcc591-fig-0006">6</a>a). In the most recent period, though, the relationship between rainfall frequency and rainfall accumulation weakened somewhat, suggesting that variations in rainfall intensity are nonnegligible even at the regional and seasonal scale. These trends are discussed in the next section.
 </p>
</sec>
