<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="wcc591-sec-0001" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">INTRODUCTION</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The name Sahel refers to the semi‐arid region stretching longitudinally from Senegal in West Africa to Sudan and Ethiopia in East Africa and latitudinally from just north of the tropical forests to just south of the Sahara desert (roughly between 10° and 20°N). Across this vast expanse, seasonal rainfall varies sharply in the meridional direction but much less in the zonal direction (Figure 
  <a rid="wcc591-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#wcc591-fig-0001">1</a>a). The climatology is well described by the meridional movement of a zonal rain band whose summertime northward progression produces a single rainy season: ramping up around May, winding down by October, and with the bulk of the annual rainfall falling between June and September (Figure 
  <a rid="wcc591-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#wcc591-fig-0001">1</a>b). Annual mean rainfall decreases from more than 800 mm in the south to less than 200 mm in the north and determines the progression of natural land cover from shrublands to grasslands and savanna, and the prevalence of sedentary agriculture or nomadic pastoralism. Across the region, abundance or scarcity of rainfall—as well as its distribution over the rainy season and the associated maximum temperature extremes—determines the success or failure of smallholder farming systems, which are often rain‐fed. At the same time, extreme rainfall events cause urban floods, impair drinking water distribution systems, and erode top‐soil from the land. There is, therefore, a strong need for monitoring and predicting rainfall changes throughout a large range of spatial and temporal scales, from local weather to continental climate change.
 </p>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="wcc591-fig-0001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>The main features of the rainfall climatology in West Africa. (a) Mean May–October rainfall (color shading); location of the African Easterly Jet (AEJ, magenta contour) as indicated by the 9 m/s contour of the easterly wind at 600 hPa; maximum African Easterly Waves (AEW, orange color; contour retraced from Figure 5a in Thorncroft &amp; Hodges, 
    <a rid="wcc591-bib-0139" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0139">2001</a>) as indicated by the a track density scaled to number density per unit area (10
    <span class="sup">6</span> km
    <span class="sup">2</span>) per season (MJJASO) greater than 6; and near surface (925 hPa) wind (streamlines; ERA40, Uppala et al., 
    <a rid="wcc591-bib-0143" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0143">2006</a>). All fields are for the 1979–1998 period, for consistency with Thorncroft and Hodges (
    <a rid="wcc591-bib-0139" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0139">2001</a>). (b) The seasonal cycle of sector mean (20°W‐30°E) surface air temperature (warm shaded colors; CPC Monthly Global Surface Air Temperature, Fan &amp; van den Dool, 
    <a rid="wcc591-bib-0038" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0038">2008</a>), precipitation (contours, same colors as in (a); GPCP Huffman et al., 
    <a rid="wcc591-bib-0065" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0065">1997</a>), and the intertropical discontinuity (ITD, indicated in blue by the zero contour of the 925 hPa meridional wind from ERA40 reanalysis). Note how the advance of the ITD is connected with the warming of the Sahara and how the rain band stays to the south of the ITD
   </p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-3" xlink:href="WCC-10-na-g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the remote (Shanahan et al., 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0125" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0125">2009</a>) and recent (Nicholson, Fink, &amp; Funk, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0101" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0101">2018</a>) past, rainfall in the Sahel has undergone profound changes and more changes of the same magnitude are expected for the near future (Chadwick, Good, Martin, &amp; Rowell, 
  <a rid="wcc591-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" href="#wcc591-bib-0023">2016</a>). This review aims to assess how well we understand the causes of past variability and how confident we are in our ability to predict the future. Confidence in model projections cannot rely on past model performance alone. Instead, it requires that our predictive models represent all relevant mechanisms for Sahel rainfall: those that controlled its variability in the past, and those that will control its trends in a future fundamentally altered by anthropogenic emissions. Thus, we determine our reasons for confidence—or lack thereof—by reviewing past and projected changes in Sahel rainfall through the lenses of climate dynamics. This means that (a) we focus on the mechanisms of rainfall variations at different scales, (b) we assess models on their ability to reproduce those mechanisms, and (c) we assess climate projections on the likelihood that the same mechanisms will be relevant in future decades.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We limit our review to the regional and continental trends in seasonal accumulation, the timing of the rainy season, and the mean intensity of daily rainfall. Changes in other aspects of Sahelian hydro‐climate can be just as important for their impact on natural and human systems: consider, for example, the hydrological impacts of subdaily rainfall intensity, or the hazard posed by extreme dry or wet spells for agriculture and land degradation. Yet, this review skirts the investigation of these hydro‐climatic variables. Our choice is motivated by the desire to assess trends in quantities that are reasonably well observed and for which current‐generation climate models are most reliable. Efforts to quantitatively predict higher‐order aspects of the precipitation statistics over Africa are coming online but are still in their infancy. This is due to the inability of global coupled models to resolve the relevant dynamics, to the relative few attempts at climate projections using convection‐permitting models, and to the scarcity of long‐term observations that could constrain statistical models.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This review is organized as follows. In Section 
  <a rid="wcc591-sec-0001" ref-type="sec" href="#wcc591-sec-0001">1</a> we survey the drivers of rainfall variability that are relevant for the Sahel. In Section 
  <a rid="wcc591-sec-0002" ref-type="sec" href="#wcc591-sec-0002">2</a> we summarize observations of rainfall variability in the 20th century. We focus on the drought decades (the 1970s and 1980s) and on the dominant influence of SST on seasonal mean anomalies. In Section 
  <a rid="wcc591-sec-0007" ref-type="sec" href="#wcc591-sec-0007">3</a> we zoom in on the most recent decades and review trends in the rainfall distribution across the rainy season. We relate such trends to the dynamics of intense rainfall events and to the influences of external drivers on storm environments. In Section 
  <a rid="wcc591-sec-0009" ref-type="sec" href="#wcc591-sec-0009">4</a> we connect past and current trends to changing anthropogenic forcings: emissions of aerosols and greenhouse gases (GHGs) and land‐use changes. In Section 
  <a rid="wcc591-sec-0010" ref-type="sec" href="#wcc591-sec-0010">5</a> we suggest how our understanding of mechanisms of Sahel rainfall variability can inform our assessment of future projections. We appraise the reliability of consensus projections in view of systematic model biases and simplifications; we emphasize remaining uncertainty; and suggest how knowledge of mechanisms of regional variability can help paint plausible regional scenarios for decision making. Section 
  <a rid="wcc591-sec-0011" ref-type="sec" href="#wcc591-sec-0011">6</a> concludes by providing an outlook on the creation and use of climate information for the Sahel.
 </p>
</sec>
