<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Observed and modeled SST and VWS</div>
  <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The observed sea surface temperature used in this study is taken from the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA) Extended Reconstructed SST version 3b (ERSST v3b) monthly data
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
   </span> and the model SST data are directly taken from the CMIP5 and CESM-LE monthly outputs. The vertical wind shear used in this study is computed from the difference in vector wind at 200 hPa minus that at 850 hPa for both observations and climate model outputs. For observations, VWS is computed as in Kossin
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
   </span>, that uses the daily-mean vector winds from the National Center for Environmental Prediction/National Center for Atmospheric Research (NCEP/NCAR) reanalysis data
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
   </span> from 1948 to 2015. The daily vertical wind shear was computed first and then averaged to get the monthly and seasonal mean VWS used in the analysis. For the CMIP5 models and the CESM-LE, VWS was computed from the monthly mean vector winds from the model output for each model ensemble member. The resulting monthly mean VWS are found to be relatively insensitive to whether one uses daily or monthly vector winds for the vertical shear calculation. The multi-model or multi-ensemble mean and spread are then obtained from the 27 CMIP5 simulations (see Supplementary Table 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S1</a>) and the 42-member CESM-LE, respectively.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec11" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hurricane potential intensity</div>
  <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The hurricane potential intensity used in this study is as computed in Ting 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>.
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
   </span> and using the definition developed by Bister and Emanuel in a series of papers
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>–
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
   </span>. The PI is defined as
   <div id="Equ1" class="disp-formula">
    <span class="label">1</span>
    <div class="alternatives">
     <span id="M1" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$PI=\frac{{C}_{k}}{{C}_{d}}\frac{{T}_{s}}{{T}_{0}}(CAP{E}^{\ast }-CAP{E}^{b})$$\end{document}</span>
     <div id="M2" display="block" class="math">
      <span class="mi">P</span>
      <span class="mi">I</span>
      <span class="mo">=</span>
      <div class="mfrac">
       <div class="mrow">
        <div class="msub">
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mi">C</span>
         </div>
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mi">k</span>
         </div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <div class="mrow">
        <div class="msub">
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mi">C</span>
         </div>
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mi">d</span>
         </div>
        </div>
       </div>
      </div>
      <div class="mfrac">
       <div class="mrow">
        <div class="msub">
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mi">T</span>
         </div>
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mi">s</span>
         </div>
        </div>
       </div>
       <div class="mrow">
        <div class="msub">
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mi">T</span>
         </div>
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mn">0</span>
         </div>
        </div>
       </div>
      </div>
      <span stretchy="false" class="mo">(</span>
      <span class="mi">C</span>
      <span class="mi">A</span>
      <span class="mi">P</span>
      <div class="msup">
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mi">E</span>
       </div>
       <span class="mo">⁎</span>
      </div>
      <span class="mo">−</span>
      <span class="mi">C</span>
      <span class="mi">A</span>
      <span class="mi">P</span>
      <div class="msup">
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mi">E</span>
       </div>
       <span class="mi">b</span>
      </div>
      <span stretchy="false" class="mo">)</span>
     </div>
     <div xlink:href="41598_2019_44252_Article_Equ1.gif" position="anchor" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    </div>
   </div>where C
   <sub>k</sub> is the surface exchange coefficient for enthalpy and C
   <sub>d</sub> the drag coefficient, T
   <sub>s</sub> is the SST and T
   <sub>0</sub> the air temperature at the outflow level. The convective available potential energy (CAPE) is the vertical integral of parcel buoyancy as a function of temperature, pressure, and specific humidity, as well as the vertical profile of virtual temperature. CAPE* is the value of CAPE for an air parcel lifted from a saturated state at the sea surface temperature while CAPE
   <span class="sup">b</span> is the value of CAPE calculated from the actual humidity value, both at the radius of maximum wind. The environmental variables used to calculate PI include the SST, sea level pressure, and vertical profiles of temperature and specific humidity.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec12" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Signal-to-noise maximizing empirical orthogonal function analysis (S/N EOF)</div>
  <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to separate the radiatively forced and naturally occurring multidecadal variations in VWS and SST, we apply the S/N maximizing EOF analysis
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>–
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>
   </span> to the global SST from multi-model CMIP5 or CESM-LE outputs. The S/N EOF method first applies a spatial pre-whitening transformation to the model SST aimed at removing the spatially coherent structure due to the internally-generated climate variability, which is defined by the modes of variability contained in the control simulations of the same set of models with pre-industrial radiative forcing. Thus the spatial and temporal variations in the ensemble average SST are purely caused by external radiative forcing after the pre-whitening. An EOF analysis is then applied to the pre-whitened multi-model ensemble average global SST and the first mode usually contains over 80% of the total forced variance. The first principal component (PC1) is then taken as representing the radiatively forced SST changes. The S/N EOF analysis here is applied to the ASO seasonal mean SST to extract the forced signal for the peak hurricane season. The North Atlantic SST in observations or each ensemble member at each grid point can then be separated into two components as follows:
   <div id="Equ2" class="disp-formula">
    <span class="label">2</span>
    <div class="alternatives">
     <span id="M3" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$${{\rm{SST}}}_{{\rm{i}},{\rm{j}}}({\rm{t}})={{\rm{a}}}_{{\rm{i}},{\rm{j}}}\,{\rm{PC}}1({\rm{t}})+{{\rm{\varepsilon }}}_{{\rm{i}},{\rm{j}}}({\rm{t}})$$\end{document}</span>
     <div id="M4" display="block" class="math">
      <div class="msub">
       <div class="mrow">
        <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">SST</span>
       </div>
       <div class="mrow">
        <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">i</span>
        <span class="mo">,</span>
        <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">j</span>
       </div>
      </div>
      <span stretchy="false" class="mo">(</span>
      <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">t</span>
      <span stretchy="false" class="mo">)</span>
      <span class="mo">=</span>
      <div class="msub">
       <div class="mrow">
        <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">a</span>
       </div>
       <div class="mrow">
        <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">i</span>
        <span class="mo">,</span>
        <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">j</span>
       </div>
      </div>
      <span width=".25em" class="mspace"/>
      <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">PC</span>
      <span class="mn">1</span>
      <span stretchy="false" class="mo">(</span>
      <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">t</span>
      <span stretchy="false" class="mo">)</span>
      <span class="mo">+</span>
      <div class="msub">
       <div class="mrow">
        <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">ε</span>
       </div>
       <div class="mrow">
        <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">i</span>
        <span class="mo">,</span>
        <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">j</span>
       </div>
      </div>
      <span stretchy="false" class="mo">(</span>
      <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">t</span>
      <span stretchy="false" class="mo">)</span>
     </div>
     <div xlink:href="41598_2019_44252_Article_Equ2.gif" position="anchor" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    </div>
   </div>where SST
   <sub>i,j</sub>(t) is the observed or modeled ASO seasonal mean SST at time t and grid point (i, j), α
   <sub>i,j</sub> is the regression coefficient between SST at that grid point and PC1, and ε
   <sub>i,j</sub>(t) is the residual SST variation that is not explained by PC1. The North Atlantic domain averaged SST from the first term on the right side of Eq. (
   <a rid="Equ2" ref-type="" href="#Equ2">2</a>) forms the forced SST index and the second term the internally varying SST index. We apply a 10-year Butterworth filter to the SST data prior to the S/N EOF analysis, thus the internal variability component only contains those with time scale longer than 10-years, and is called Atlantic Multidecadal Variability, or AMV component, as shown in Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S1</a> for observed SST. These decompositions can be done for each model and each ensemble member. The spatial patterns of VWS, SST or hurricane PI can be obtained by regressing these fields onto the forced and AMV component of the corresponding observations or model ensembles.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
