<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">VWS forced by future anthropogenic radiative forcing</div>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The VWS has not been substantially influenced by the anthropogenic radiative forcing in the past few decades (see top left panel in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). However, as GHG forcing increases, the VWS associated with anthropogenic forcing may also increase in amplitude. To explore future changes in VWS and its relative role as compared to the AMV, Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a> shows the CMIP5 multi-model mean (MMM) changes in VWS as the difference between two time periods, between 1971–2005 and 1871–1905 for the historical period, and between 2070–2099 and 1971–2000 for the two future scenarios (rcp4.5 and rcp8.5). As a comparison, we also average the periods identified as positive and negative AMV (defined as one standard deviation above or below the AMV index), and take the difference between the positive and negative phases to illustrate the VWS pattern associated with AMV. It is clear that the VWS patterns simulated by the model associated with AMV (right panels of Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>) have a similar dipole structure to observations (lower left panel in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>), with enhanced VWS along the U.S. coast and suppressed VWS in the tropical Atlantic MDR for positive AMV. The radiatively forced VWS change, however, paints a very different picture. Along the U.S. East Coast, the VWS shows an opposite sign to that corresponding to positive AMV, with suppressed VWS along the coastal region. In the tropical North Atlantic extending from the Caribbean to the Gulf of Mexico, the VWS is enhanced. However, the enhanced VWS in the tropical Atlantic is only limited to the western part of the MDR, with the exception of the historical period, when the intensified VWS extends to the central tropical Atlantic including most of the MDR region. The differences between historical and future scenarios may be linked to aerosol forcing, which is relatively strong during the historical period
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>
  </span>. The forced patterns with enhanced VWS in the Caribbean region are somewhat similar to those shown in CMIP3 models
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>
  </span> and a subset of the CMIP5 models
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>
  </span>. But the strong suppressed shear along the U.S. East Coast, although present in the CMIP3 models, is much stronger in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>, particularly for the rcp8.5 future scenario. The implication of the anthropogenically forced future VWS suppression along the U.S. East Coast is that future hurricanes may go through stronger intensification and cause more powerful destructions when moving into the coastal region.
  <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Vertical wind shear from left panels: CMIP5 multi-model mean representing the radiatively forced changes between two different time periods for historical (top, 1971–2005 minus 1871–1905), rcp4.5 (middle, 2070–2099 minus 1971–2000) and rcp8.5 (bottom, 2070–2099 minus 1971–2000) and right panels: composite based on positive AMV years minus negative AMV years for the historical, rcp4.5 and rcp8.5 integrations. Units are in m/s and the stippling indicates 75% of the models or ensemble members having the same sign changes.</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_44252_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e448" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
