<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec011" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The recreational reconstructed catch in Algeria reached 6,000 tonnes in 2015, which is higher comparing to previous estimates of annual recreational catches ranged between 380 t [
  <a rid="pone.0201602.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0201602.ref023">23</a>], and 1,000 t [
  <a rid="pone.0201602.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0201602.ref009">9</a>], The case of Boumerdes shows that, potentially, only 1% (7.5 t reported from 599 t estimated) of the total recreational catch is ever reported. This may be due to the fact that remote landing beaches and other improvised landing places, amounting a total of 32 along the Algerian coastline [
  <a rid="pone.0201602.ref024" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0201602.ref024">24</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0201602.ref025" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0201602.ref025">25</a>], are not accounted for in official statistics. However, given that our estimate is based on all licensed vessels, we believe that by extrapolating an average observed CPUE on the total authorized fleet, all authorized vessels are captured in our estimate. Sumaila [
  <a rid="pone.0201602.ref026" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0201602.ref026">26</a>] Classified three forms of subsidies; “Beneficial subsidies” or “good”, they enhance the growth of fish stocks through conservation, and the monitoring of catch rates through control and surveillance measures, “Capacity-enhancing subsidies” or “bad” which are all forms of capital inputs that reduce cost or enhance revenue,”Ambiguous subsidies” or “ugly” are defined as programs whose impacts are undetermined. We highlight, herein, that in addition to the catch under-reporting, both the regulation status and the reporting system are questionable. Overall, the fishery generates over 45 million USD in revenue that remains part of the informal economy, “given our findings, recreational fishers enjoy a discounted price for licences while they compete on the same market and for the same stocks of fish than artisanal fishers. Given the lack of oversight on the fishery, which translates into unreported catches and important losses to the government, we argue that the discount offered is a form of capacity enhancing subsidy, which is one of the bad forms of subsidies” which have, in addition to potential negative impacts on the environment, far reaching socio-economic impacts, when ill-managed [
  <a rid="pone.0201602.ref026" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0201602.ref026">26</a>]
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Algerian law clearly states that sports and recreational fishing products cannot be sold or exchanged, and are only intended for self-consumption or release. “
  <span class="italic">Recreational fishing practiced with recreational vessels is subject to an authorization delivered by the administration responsible for the fishing</span>” [
  <a rid="pone.0201602.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0201602.ref015">15</a>]. Respective of the conditions above, the difference in licensing fees amounting at a total of over $1, 607 580 US (1170 USD annually per fisher) as assessed in this study serves as an incentive for many artisanal fishers to convert to a recreational activity because of the lack of control in the latter, and lower post-harvest costs, overall. In fact, whereas the previous law precisely defined the conditions for the practice of recreational fishing (distance, gear and period restrictions) [
  <a rid="pone.0201602.ref027" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0201602.ref027">27</a>], the new regulations adopted as of 2011 do not provide any specificities with regards to potential infractions, limiting only the purpose of the catch that has to be for self-consumption and not for sale [
  <a rid="pone.0201602.ref010" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0201602.ref010">10</a>], In 2015, this law was modified and supplemented, and a fine is imposed to anyone who practice recreational fishing in contravention of the provisions of this law [
  <a rid="pone.0201602.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0201602.ref028">28</a>]. Without any further precisions, that means that the commercialization of catch remains the only infraction.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Thanks to this legal loophole, many recreational vessels operate commercially [
  <a rid="pone.0201602.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0201602.ref020">20</a>] and outcompete artisanal fishers. Indeed, the number of recreational licenses is 1.8 times higher than the number of artisanal (commercial) licenses, for the same vessel length range, and lower restrictions on the recreational sector [
  <a rid="pone.0201602.ref011" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0201602.ref011">11</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0201602.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0201602.ref029">29</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0201602.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0201602.ref030">30</a>]. The highest difference in number of licenses between the two sectors is observed in Tipaza, Chlef, Mostaganem and Oran, where controls and monitoring by the coast guards are severely lacking.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another difference that highlights a lack of monitoring capacity occurs between the number of authorizations as reported by local departments of fisheries (2,067 recreational vessels licensed in 2013), and those reported by the Central Ministry of Fisheries (25,042 for the same year) [
  <a rid="pone.0201602.ref031" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0201602.ref031">31</a>], denoting of a major discrepancy between the central and regional governments.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although spearfishing is closely regulated [
  <a rid="pone.0201602.ref010" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0201602.ref010">10</a>], restrictions on diver’s age, fishing times, and distance from shore are often infringed upon. In addition to authorized spearfishers not abiding by the law, a high number of unauthorized are operating along the coast, which means that the catch estimates and values presented herein are likely conservative.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This paper sheds some light on the far-reaching negative social and economic implications of the so-called recreational fisheries of Algeria, whose impacts on the government are often assumed positive when compared to commercial sectors. Indisputably, far from being for sports and recreational purposes, the economic value that these fisheries generate, while escaping local controls, and providing a tax shelter for fishers outcompeting traditional small-scale fishers facing declining fish stocks [
  <a rid="pone.0201602.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0201602.ref009">9</a>], still contribute somehow to social peace in the country through supplying human nutrition and food security [
  <a rid="pone.0201602.ref032" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0201602.ref032">32</a>]. The dynamics of this sector remain unique in the sense that there is a general attitude of 
  <span class="italic">laissez faire</span> within the government management system–which would have to face yet again social frustration by the Youth—, Hence, these issues need to be urgently addressed given that catches are drastically declining across sectors [
  <a rid="pone.0201602.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0201602.ref009">9</a>]. The issue of competition between artisanal (traditional) and recreational sectors is reflected through other examples globally, yet it remains largely understudied. Indeed, Canadian Pacific fisheries whose management is based on a output controls generated an important dispute over access between the recreational fishing lobby and the traditional indigenous fishing communities when 12% of the overall fishing quota was reallocated to the recreational sector. This issue was exacerbated by the fact that the recreational sector's catch in Canada’s Pacific, when monitored, appears to exceed quota [
  <a rid="pone.0201602.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0201602.ref033">33</a>]. This allocations has alienated small-scale and indigenous fishing communities at various occasions and remain an ongoing issue, mainly driven by access priorities, and the lack of knowledge on the impacts of recreational fisheries [
  <a rid="pone.0201602.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0201602.ref033">33</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0201602.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0201602.ref034">34</a>]. Similarly, the lack of knowledge on recreational fisheries in the Bahamas [
  <a rid="pone.0201602.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0201602.ref035">35</a>] creates a tremendous burden on the ecosystem,
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This problem is also observed in Caribbean marine protected areas, in which fees of scuba diving collected, which could contribute to resources conservation cost, do not reflect the real number of divers neither the real ecological impact [
  <a rid="pone.0201602.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0201602.ref036">36</a>]. On a global scale, universal code of conduct for the practice and management of recreational fisheries is required [
  <a rid="pone.0201602.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0201602.ref037">37</a>]. In fact, even where recreational fishing sector is controlled, obeys to the leisure principle, and where fishes are released, there is an ecological impact and contribution on global fish stock decline [
  <a rid="pone.0201602.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0201602.ref038">38</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0201602.ref041" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0201602.ref041">41</a>]. This unsuspected additional pressure, on the marine resource in Algeria suggests a higher ecological impact. The imprecise regulation of recreational sector allows a "legitimate" confusion with commercial sector and the lack of control is "trivializing" a non conformity. These two points are the mains issues highlighted in this paper. Managing recreational fisheries, within the fragile social environment of Algeria, where subsidizing recreational fisheries is perceived as a levy to reduce social pressures [
  <a rid="pone.0201602.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0201602.ref042">42</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0201602.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0201602.ref044">44</a>] is a difficult but necessary task. Herein, we argue that as the footprint of recreational fisheries is higher than that shown in official figure, the losses both on stocks, commercial fishers, and the government are important, there is an urgent need for better monitoring of the fishery.
 </p>
</sec>
