<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec005" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fishers’ income from recreational fisheries and government lost revenue</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Algerian government collects taxes from all commercial sectors, and given the prohibition of trade of recreationally caught fish, the Government does not collect any taxes from recreational fishers, assuming fishers abide by the law. Herein, we calculated the potential economic loss to the Government that is attributable to this unregulated fishery as the difference between the revenue that the license fees and other fees like social security, crew role, … etc would have brought in if considered artisanal (1,200 USD per vessel) and the license fees that they bring as they are considered recreational (30 USD) [
  <a rid="pone.0201602.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0201602.ref020">20</a>], knowing that most recreational catch is sold in local markets (pers. observation.). The difference represents a nontaxable income to local recreational fishers.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hence, the total revenue earned by recreational fishers is calculated as the discount on the cost of the license and other fees, i.e. the difference between the cost of a full commercial license (1,200USD)–noting that vessel size is similar, and geographic fishing range, and fishing capacity are similar–and that of a recreational license (30 USD), plus the revenue from the catch itself (or landed value).</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The operating costs (fuel and lubricant) are deduced from the total revenue, on the basis of an average number of trips of 73 days per year multiplied by a cost estimated at 2,300 DA by trip, according to small scale fishers with whom we conversed.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hence, the total operating cost is estimated as the cost per day, multiplied by the number of trips (fishing days), multiplied by the number of licenses (which reflects the number of boats, as one boat gets one license). Therefore, profits from the recreational sector gained by fishers, are estimated as the total revenue i.e. average ex-cessel price multiplied by the catch per year, plus the value they would otherwise pay if they were considered professional (i.e. lost to government), minus the operating costs.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ex-vessel price is estimated at 675 AD (Algerian Dinar) in 2015 ($1 US = 100 AD) as extracted from the Algerian National Fisheries Database (Government of Algeria, unpub. data).</p>
</sec>
