<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Earlier studies used the rules provided by MaxEnt (percent contribution, permutation importance, and jackknife test) to determine the variable importance(Fand et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35129-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; Liu et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35129-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2018</xref>; Saatchi et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35129-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>; Smart et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35129-bib-0067" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>; Yao et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35129-bib-0078" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). Given interactions among variables were unavoidable, variable importance should be interpreted with caution when using these traditional methods (Parisien &amp; Moritz, 
 <xref rid="ece35129-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>). However, the global sensitivity analysis can reveal the importance of the main and total effects of different variables with considering interactions among variables (Haaker &amp; Verheijen, 
 <xref rid="ece35129-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2004</xref>; Liu et al.,
 <xref rid="ece35129-bib-0100" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2019</xref>). Our research demonstrated that Bio02 and Elevation were the most important variables in controlling the distribution of 
 <italic class="italic">S. alterniflora</italic> on the northern coast, whether main or total effects. The finding was consistent with previous studies (Kirwan et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35129-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>; Liu, 
 <xref rid="ece35129-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2018</xref>; Priest, 
 <xref rid="ece35129-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>). However, Elevation is by far the most important variable on the southern coast due to the width of tidal flat was narrow and the altitude has a relatively high limitation for the expansion of 
 <italic class="italic">S. alterniflora </italic>(Gao et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35129-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). Bio02 and Elevation showed strong interactions among variables. An explanation for this might be that altitude can directly affect climatic factors such as temperature and precipitation and in turn climatic factors affect species distribution at different altitudes (Crosby et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35129-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>; Idaszkin &amp; Bortolus, 
 <xref rid="ece35129-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>; Marangoni &amp; Costa, 
 <xref rid="ece35129-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>; Zhao et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35129-bib-0082" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). There were obvious interactions among variables influence the distribution of 
 <italic class="italic">S. alterniflora</italic> on the Chinese coast, and interactions of the northern coast were much greater than that of the southern coast. Interactions reduced the importance of Tece and Drainage, while enhanced the importance of Tph on the northern Chinese coast. On the southern Chinese coast, interactions were low and it still enhanced the importance of Bio02, making the importance of Bio14, Bio19, Tgravel, Tph, Tsand, and Tclass change from zero to non‐zero.
</p>
