<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Although ecological niche modeling (MaxEnt) is a superior technology for modeling the potential distribution of species, it has several limitations including its uncertainty and transferability (Phillips et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35129-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>; Swanson et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35129-bib-0068" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). Given the model's uncertainty, our research was built on 10‐fold cross‐validation and multiple threshold rules, together with its high accuracy, and all of them supported the reliability of the results obtained (Elith &amp; Yates, 
 <xref rid="ece35129-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Radosavljevic et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35129-bib-0058" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). MaxEnt assumes that species will not exhibit phenotypic adaptation to new environmental conditions (Hernandez et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35129-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>). Our model did not account for species dispersal, while the seeds of 
 <italic class="italic">S. alterniflora</italic> can spread over long distances by wind and waves. Thus, further work is needed to combine the dispersal of 
 <italic class="italic">S. alterniflora</italic> to better predict its actual distribution. Furthermore, we only assumed that the average sea level will rise by 1 meter without considering the spatial heterogeneity of sea level rise. Abiotic environmental factors such as interspecies competition and ecosystem dynamics could also influence 
 <italic class="italic">S. alterniflora</italic>'s survival and colonization success (Woolfolk, Wasson, 
 <xref rid="ece35129-bib-0084" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Garner et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35129-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). Therefore, further studies require considering the effects of biological factors such as species dispersal, competition, the spatial patterns of sea level rise in different regions.
</p>
