<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Both CEM and BRT models project that 15%–40% of current rainfed rice locations may be at risk from climate change by 2050, based on the consensus across multiple GCMs. These declines in suitability were most pronounced in eastern India, in the States of Odisha, Assam and Chhattisgarh. These States predominantly use rainfed cultivation methods and contribute more than a quarter of India's annual rice production. The farming communities in these States are dominated by small-landholders (usually owning &lt; 2 ha; 
 <xref rid="bb0120" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Joshi, 2015</xref>), with little opportunity to produce surplus grain for consumption or for generating income. In addition, small-holders often have limited access to financial markets or crop insurance (
 <xref rid="bb0260" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Thapa and Gaiha, 2011</xref>), and so these projected climate-driven declines in rainfed rice cultivation would be expected to be detrimental to local livelihoods. Our model outputs agree with other studies projecting declines in rainfed rice yields in future, based on outputs of process-based crop models (
 <xref rid="bb0215" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Rao et al., 2016</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0255" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Soora et al., 2013</xref>) and statistical crop models (
 <xref rid="bb0015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Auffhammer et al., 2012</xref>). Rainfed areas already have a large yield gap compared with irrigated areas (
 <xref rid="bb0180" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Mueller et al., 2012</xref>) and further reductions in the extent of climatically-suitable areas could widen these yield gaps with negative consequences for regional food security (
 <xref rid="bb0005" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Aggarwal et al., 2008</xref>). Both CEMs and BRTs identified similar areas at risk in the states of Chhattisgarh and Odisha, although they differ in the projected severity of risk in these locations (i.e. they differ in the number of cells projected to become less suitable or unsuitable in future). The major difference between the projections for the two approaches across the GCM ensemble is that CEMs project more cells becoming less suitable but with high confidence, whereas BRTs project more cells to be unsuitable but with only medium confidence. This difference in model outputs could be due to differences in the climate variables deemed as the most influential by the two approaches (see below).
</p>
