<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Reduced DMS emissions in the AZ of the SO during glacials</div>
 <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sulphate aerosol observations at EDC and coastal Antarctic sites display a clear seasonal pattern with a maximum in austral summer
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
  </span>. High surface DMS concentrations and emission fluxes over the modern SO in austral summer have also been reported
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
  </span>. The dominant source of biogenic sulphate in the Antarctic interior is thus most likely DMS emitted from the SO. The flux of marine biogenic sulphate deposited in the Antarctic interior would then be controlled by DMS emissions in the source regions, the location of these source regions (i.e., distance to Antarctic interior sites), DMS oxidation chemistry, and depositional processes. As glacial/interglacial changes in oxidation chemistry and deposition are likely to be small, the decreased biogenic sulphate flux during glacials would be caused by reduced DMS emissions and/or longer transport distances
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>
  </span> (
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">Supplementary Discussion</a>). Transport distances depend strongly on the summer sea ice extent around Antarctica
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>
  </span> (
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">Supplementary Discussion</a>), but only limited information is available for glacials. In the Indian Ocean sector, the summer sea ice extent at the LGM was only slightly greater than the present day
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
  </span>, whereas in the Atlantic Ocean sector, the sporadic occurrence of summer sea ice considerably farther north is indicated
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
  </span> (
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">Supplementary Discussion</a>). Although data from other oceanic sectors are very sparse, Gersonde et al.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
  </span> speculate that the summer sea ice field around Antarctica changed from 4 × 10
  <span class="sup">6</span> km
  <span class="sup">2</span> (present day) to 5–6 × 10
  <span class="sup">6</span> km
  <span class="sup">2</span> (LGM).
 </p>
 <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">DF and EDC display similar residual nssSO
  <sub>4</sub>
  <span class="sup">2−</span> fluxes with glacial/interglacial ratios of 1/3 to 1/4 (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>). The LGM/Holocene ratios (~1/3) at DF, EDC, and EDML are consistent with the MSA flux at Siple Dome (West Antarctica, Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>) where MSA can be used as a proxy for marine biogenic sulphur deposition because its post-depositional loss is minimal
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>
  </span>. In other words, the four sites facing different sectors of the SO, which includes the Indian sector where summer sea ice extent increased only slightly at the LGM, display similar glacial/interglacial ratios of biogenic sulphur species. The similar ratios would be mainly associated with glacial-interglacial changes in DMS emissions in the SO, and specifically the AZ because it is a major DMS source region for biogenic sulphate in the present-day Antarctic interior
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>
  </span> (
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">Supplementary Discussion</a>). The reduced biogenic sulphate fluxes at the LGM could be partly due to the increased transport distances. However, the LGM increase in the summer sea ice extent around Antarctica by 1.25 to 1.50 times
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
  </span> would only slightly increase the transport distances to the Antarctic interior sites, which are affected by a mixture of air masses from different oceanic sectors
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>
  </span> (
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">Supplementary Discussion</a> and Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">7</a>). Thus, lower biogenic nssSO
  <sub>4</sub>
  <span class="sup">2−</span> fluxes during glacials indicate reduced DMS emissions in the AZ, suggesting that primary production, as well as export production, decreases during glacials, which is consistent with marine sediment records
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
</sec>
