<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>What is needed is the urgency of the space race aimed, not at the Moon or Mars, but rather toward harnessing the promise of exascale supercomputing to reliably simulate Earth’s regional climate (and associated extremes) globally. This will only be possible if the broader climate science community begins to articulate its dissatisfaction with business as usual—not just among themselves but externally to those who seek to use the models for business, policy, or humanitarian reasons. Failing to do so becomes an ethical issue in that it saddles us with the status quo: a strategy that hopes, against all evidence, to surmount the abyss between scientific capability and societal needs on the back of 2 less-than-overwhelming ideas: 1) that post processing (i.e., empirically correcting or selectively sampling model output) can largely eliminate the model systematic biases that would otherwise make the models unfit for purpose (
 <xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>) and 2) that incremental changes in model resolution or parametrization can overcome structural deficiencies that otherwise plague the present generation of models (
 <xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>). Empirical bias corrections can work well for systems that behave linearly, but a large part of the reason for developing comprehensive models is to account for, or help anticipate, the climate system’s nonlinearities (
 <xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>). Were this not reason enough (
 <xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>) to be dissatisfied with a disproportionate emphasis on idea 1, then surely lessons from numerical weather prediction—where an increase in skill has gone hand in hand with a reduction in systematic error—are (
 <xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>). As for idea 2, after 6 generations of model development spanning roughly 30 y, it seems safe to conclude that the task that we set for ourselves was, if not impossible, then too difficult to be achieved by incremental improvements alone. Even the most optimistic assessment of model development efforts cannot avoid concluding that progress has been far too slow to justify continuing to prioritize the present path.
</p>
