<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="jeb13389-sec-0015" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.2</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Considerations for cross‐species studies of signal honesty</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sex‐specific trends in quantitative honesty found for 
  <span class="italic">Z. filipendulae</span> (Briolat, Burdfield‐Steel, et al., 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0010">2018</a>; Briolat, Zagrobelny, et al., 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0011">2018</a>) and 
  <span class="italic">Z. ephialtes</span> suggest that differences between sexes should be considered in studies of signal honesty. The costs and benefits of aposematic signalling may vary between males and females of warningly coloured species, due to size dimorphism, trade‐offs related to sexual signalling, and variation in habitat use and behaviour, modulating their exposure to predators. In sexually dimorphic seven‐spot ladybirds (
  <span class="italic">Coccinella septempunctata</span>), an honest relationship between elytra carotenoids and coccinelline levels was only found in females, a result attributed to greater resource limitation or greater benefits of aposematic signalling in the larger sex (Blount et al., 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0008">2012</a>). Burnet moths are similarly sexually dimorphic, with larger females (Naumann, Tarmann, &amp; Tremewan, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0070" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0070">1999</a>), but other factors may also affect the economics of aposematic signalling: although both sexes are highly visible at rest, males are generally more active (Naumann et al., 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0070" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0070">1999</a>), and there is some limited evidence that visual signals could play a role in sexual signalling, at close range (Friedrich &amp; Friedrich‐Polo, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0040">2005</a>; Koshio, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0060" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0060">2003</a>; Zagatti &amp; Renou, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0128" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0128">1984</a>), and at certain times of day (Hofmann &amp; Kia‐Hofmann, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0053">2010</a>). Across species, trends were broadly similar between sexes in this study, but the significance of these relationships varied, suggesting that ignoring differences between sexes could mask interesting results. This is an important consideration, as existing studies of quantitative honesty across aposematic species and populations do not analyse males and females separately, even in taxa in which males and females are known to differ (e.g. in ladybirds; Arenas et al., 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0003">2015</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our study also revealed considerable variation, in both coloration and toxicity, between individuals collected in two different years. These differences are unlikely to be caused by inconsistencies in our experimental procedures. While caterpillars were raised under natural conditions during collection trips, subsequent rearing conditions were kept as consistent as possible between specimens collected in 2015 and 2016. Moreover, differences in colour between years were found even among 
  <span class="italic">Z. trifolii</span> specimens, collected as pupae from the same location and placed in an incubator with the same settings until eclosion, suggesting that conditions prior to euthanasia were not responsible for this variation. Preliminary experiments verified that the time that specimens were kept in the −80°C freezer between termination and photography did not impact coloration. Methods and equipment used for image capture did not vary between years, and all images from both seasons were processed and analysed together. Finally, we verified that differences in toxin levels were not caused by variations in the sensitivity of the LC‐MS machine and column used, by re‐running a subset of samples from both years together. While existing studies of signal honesty in aposematic species do not consider temporal variation in signal and defence traits, our study suggests that seasonal variation may have an impact on these traits.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">With only 2 years of data, it is difficult to explain the observed patterns of between‐year variation, but environmental conditions, linked to variation in weather across years (see Supporting Information Data 
  <a rid="jeb13389-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#jeb13389-sup-0001">S7</a>), are likely to impact investment in coloration and chemical defences in burnet moths. Variation in coloration in tiger moths (Erebidae) has been linked to fluctuations in local ecological conditions (Galarza, Nokelainen, Ashrafi, Hegna, &amp; Mappes, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0042">2014</a>), and in particular temperature (Goulson &amp; Owen, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0045" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0045">1997</a>; Lindstedt, Lindström, &amp; Mappes, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0064" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0064">2009</a>). Climate may also indirectly affect resource allocation to signals and defences in aposematic species, via effects on their host plants. Cyanogenic plants possess highly variable levels of defensive chemicals, strongly affected by environmental conditions (Gleadow &amp; Woodrow, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0044" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0044">2002</a>). The effects of temperature have been well documented in both 
  <span class="italic">Trifolium repens</span> (white clover; Daday, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0014">1954a</a>,
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0015">b</a>, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0016">1958</a>; De Aráujo, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0021">1976</a>; Stochmal &amp; Oleszek, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0114" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0114">1997</a>; Richards &amp; Fletcher, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0090" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0090">2002</a>) and 
  <span class="italic">Lotus corniculatus</span> (bird's foot trefoil), a key host plant of several Zygaenidae (Ellis, Keymer, &amp; Jones, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0029">1977</a>; Jones, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0056" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0056">1977</a>; Salgado, Suchan, Pellissier, Rasmann, &amp; Ducrest, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0093" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0093">2016</a>). For the species relying completely on de novo synthesis of cyanogenic glucosides, plant productivity may still be important. For example, nitrogen limitation will lead to reduced investment in cyanogenic glucosides in burnet moths, due to trade‐offs with other products, as suggested by the hypothesized breakdown of cyanogenic glucosides during pupation to fuel chitin synthesis (Zagrobelny et al., 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0131" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0131">2007</a>). Interestingly, all the species in which cyanogenic glucoside levels decreased between years in males (
  <span class="italic">A. infausta</span>,
  <span class="italic"> R. pruni</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Z. sarpedon</span>) feed on acyanogenic host plants, suggesting that resource allocation trade‐offs may broadly differ between species able to sequester cyanogenic glucosides from their host plants and those who cannot. Comparing host plant levels of cyanogenic glucosides and other nutritional resources to moth toxin levels and coloration across years would help elucidate the relationship between environmental conditions, host properties and aposematic phenotypes. This type of longitudinal study could be a valuable means of testing for quantitative honesty in aposematic signalling, providing the opportunity to study how resources are allocated to signals and defences in response to environmental conditions, and as the communities of predators and prey co‐evolve.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In conclusion, the present work deepens our understanding of the relationship between signals and defences across species, by contributing to the small number of studies testing signal honesty across closely related aposematic species, with sophisticated methods for quantifying chemical defences, phylogenetic controls and measures of coloration accounting for predator vision. We find no clear evidence of quantitative signal honesty across the sampled species of Zygaenidae, especially not with regard to those aspects of appearance most likely to be salient to predators, a result likely attributable to varying costs of signal and defence production across species. Our study also highlights the importance of considering differences between sexes and temporal variation in analyses of signal honesty moving forward.</p>
</sec>
