<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="jeb13389-sec-0005" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Image analysis</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All image analysis was performed in ImageJ (Schneider, Rasband, &amp; Eliceiri, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0097" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0097">2012</a>) using open access custom‐made plugins in the Image Calibration and Analysis Toolbox (Troscianko &amp; Stevens, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0122" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0122">2015</a>). Methods used for processing images and extracting colour metrics are summarized below; full details are provided in Supporting Information Data 
  <a rid="jeb13389-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#jeb13389-sup-0001">S3</a>. To allow for objective colour measurements, images were linearized and normalized (Stevens, Párraga, Cuthill, Partridge, &amp; Troscianko, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0112" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0112">2007</a>), and then scaled to 100 pixels/mm. Photographs taken with the two types of filter were combined using an automatic alignment tool, and the resulting multispectral images were mapped to avian vision, as previous observations show that birds are likely to be the most relevant visual predators of burnet moths (Tremewan, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0121" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0121">2006</a>). Each image was converted to the visual system of 
  <span class="italic">C. caeruleus</span>, the model species for the ultraviolet‐sensitive (UVS) avian visual system (Hart, Partridge, Cuthill, &amp; Bennett, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0050" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0050">2000</a>) using a highly accurate polynomial mapping technique (Pike, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0086" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0086">2011</a>; Stevens &amp; Cuthill, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0111" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0111">2006</a>; Stevens et al., 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0112" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0112">2007</a>; Troscianko &amp; Stevens, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0122" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0122">2015</a>) to produce a set of image layers corresponding to the predicted cone catch values for each of the five avian cone types: long wavelength (LW)‐, medium wavelength (MW)‐, short wavelength (SW)‐ and ultraviolet (UV)‐sensitive photoreceptors, and double cones. Relevant wing areas were selected using the freehand tool in ImageJ. Most species display red forewing markings, but for 
  <span class="italic">Rhagades pruni</span> (Denis &amp; Schiffermüller, 1775), the iridescent blue patch at the base of the wing was selected as the markings, whereas for 
  <span class="italic">Theresimima ampellophaga</span> (Bayle‐Barelle, 1808), the whole uniform wing was measured as a single patch. Cone catch values for every photoreceptor type were obtained from each selected patch and then averaged to obtain a single measure of colour per individual, for both the wing markings and wing background area.
 </p>
</sec>
