<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="jeb13389-sec-0001" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">INTRODUCTION</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Aposematic animals use conspicuous colours and patterns to warn potential predators of their unprofitability, linked to physical or chemical defences (Ruxton, Sherratt, &amp; Speed, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0092" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0092">2004</a>; Stevens &amp; Ruxton, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0113" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0113">2012</a>). This strategy, first proposed by Alfred Russell Wallace to explain the colourful appearance of caterpillars (Wallace, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0124" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0124">1867</a>), is now recognized to occur in a wide range of taxa, from a host of invertebrates [e.g. Hemiptera (Exnerová et al., 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0033">2003</a>), Lepidoptera (Rothschild, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0091" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0091">1985</a>)] and amphibians (e.g. poison frogs; Summers &amp; Clough, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0116" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0116">2001</a>) to mammals (Stankowich, Caro, &amp; Cox, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0107" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0107">2011</a>) and birds (Dumbacher, Deiner, Thompson, &amp; Fleischer, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0024">2008</a>). Predators who encounter distasteful warningly coloured prey should learn to associate the prey signal with their unpleasant experience and avoid attacking similar prey in the future. Bright and colourful patterns facilitate this process in a number of ways, enhancing the “efficacy” of aposematic signals by increasing their detectability, memorability and discriminability (Guilford &amp; Dawkins, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0048" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0048">1991</a>; Ruxton et al., 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0092" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0092">2004</a>). Moreover, traditional theory rooted in Fritz Müller's insights into mutually beneficial mimicry between defended species (Müller, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0068" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0068">1879</a>) holds that warning signals should converge onto a limited number of common forms, to further speed up predator avoidance learning. Yet, there is extensive variation in warning coloration across aposematic taxa, which can be perceptible to their predators (Arenas &amp; Stevens, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0001">2017</a>; Briolat, Burdfield‐Steel, et al., 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0010">2018</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A key line of enquiry into this seemingly paradoxical variation explores the relationship between the strength of visual signals and levels of defences, which also vary greatly both between (e.g. Arenas, Walter, &amp; Stevens, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0003">2015</a>) and within species (e.g. Brower, Ryerson, Coppinger, &amp; Glazier, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0012">1968</a>). As conspicuous coloration incurs the cost of heightened detection by predators, it should often be too costly for undefended species, which would be captured and consumed (with the exception of Batesian mimics of aposematic species; Bates, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0007">1862</a>). Aposematic signals are therefore generally considered to be qualitatively honest, reliably indicating the presence of a defence (Ruxton et al., 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0092" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0092">2004</a>; Sherratt, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0098" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0098">2002</a>). Whether they should also be expected to be quantitatively honest, with the strength of visual signals reflecting the potency of the defences they advertise, is more controversial.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Despite the cost of increased visibility to predators, early interpretations of aposematism as an honest handicap signal (Grafen, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0046" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0046">1990</a>) have been criticized for the lack of a physiological link between visual features and defensive chemistry (Guilford &amp; Dawkins, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0049">1993</a>). This could be provided by competition between traits for resources, leading to positive correlations between signals and defences when these resources are limited (Blount, Speed, Ruxton, &amp; Stephens, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0009">2009</a>; Blount et al., 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0008">2012</a>). Yet, some theoretical models predict a disjunction between signals and defences, suggesting that prey should prioritize investment in either signals, to which predators respond (Leimar, Enquist, &amp; Sillen‐Tullberg, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0062">1986</a>), or defences, which do not incur detection costs (Speed &amp; Ruxton, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0104" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0104">2007</a>). Overall, considering the relative costs of signals and defences, quantitative honesty may be expected to occur under certain conditions, depending on the economics of colour and toxin production (Speed &amp; Ruxton, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0104" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0104">2007</a>), predator behaviour (Guilford, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0047">1994</a>; Speed, Ruxton, Blount, &amp; Stephens, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0105" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0105">2010</a>) and prey resilience to attack (Sherratt, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0098" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0098">2002</a>). Although most theoretical work focuses on single species, several of these evolutionary mechanisms have been proposed to underpin signal honesty across closely related species too (Summers, Speed, Blount, &amp; Stuckert, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0117" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0117">2015</a>). Coevolutionary dynamics with mimics of defended prey (Franks, Ruxton, &amp; Sherratt, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0038" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0038">2009</a>), cautious or “go‐slow” behaviour on the part of predators (Guilford, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0047">1994</a>), exaptation through other functions of visual signals (Lee, Speed, &amp; Stephens, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0061">2011</a>), and resource allocation trade‐offs (Blount et al., 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0009">2009</a>), are all thought to have the capacity to lead to honest signalling between populations or species (Holen &amp; Svennungsen, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0055">2012</a>; Summers et al., 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0117" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0117">2015</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Most empirical studies of the relationship between signals and defences across clades of species have found positive correlations between measures of visual signal strength and measures of toxicity, suggesting quantitative honesty in signalling (Cortesi &amp; Cheney, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0013">2010</a>; Santos &amp; Cannatella, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0095" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0095">2011</a>; Summers &amp; Clough, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0116" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0116">2001</a>; but see Darst, Cummings, &amp; Cannatella, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0017">2006</a>; Winters et al., 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0126" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0126">2018</a>). Work on ladybird beetles (Coccinellidae), combining toxin bioassays and field predation experiments with ladybird models presented to birds, has explicitly linked more conspicuous coloration and higher defence levels to greater survival in the wild (Arenas et al., 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0003">2015</a>). However, these studies are restricted in taxonomic scope, primarily focusing on poison frogs (Dendrobatidae), ladybird beetles and to a lesser extent marine opisthobranchs (Cortesi &amp; Cheney, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0013">2010</a>; Winters et al., 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0126" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0126">2018</a>), so research in a wider range of taxa is needed before more general conclusions can be drawn (Stevens, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0110" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0110">2015</a>; Summers et al., 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0117" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0117">2015</a>). Existing studies can also be difficult to compare, as they employ a wide range of methods for quantifying defences, from bioassays (e.g. Arenas et al., 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0003">2015</a>; Darst et al., 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0017">2006</a>) to specific quantification of individual chemicals (e.g. alkaloids in the Dendrobatidae; Summers &amp; Clough, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0116" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0116">2001</a>), and vary in their approaches to measuring coloration. Animal visual systems differ from human perception and are highly variable between species, so it is essential to consider visual signals from the perspective of the relevant receivers, which in the case of aposematism are potential predators (Stevens, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0108" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0108">2007</a>, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0109" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0109">2011</a>). Although this is not always the case (e.g. Dumbacher, Spande, &amp; Daly, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0025">2000</a>; Dumbacher et al., 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0024">2008</a>; Summers &amp; Clough, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0116" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0116">2001</a>), studies of aposematism are increasingly considering predator perception [e.g. birds (Arenas et al., 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0003">2015</a>; Darst et al., 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0017">2006</a>) and fish (Cortesi &amp; Cheney, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0013">2010</a>; Winters et al., 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0126" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0126">2018</a>)], as our understanding of animal vision improves.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Aposematic burnet moths (Lepidoptera: Zygaenidae) are well suited to testing the relationship between signals and defences across closely related species. In the Western Palearctic, the Zygaenidae are represented by three subfamilies: the Zygaeninae, Procridinae and Chalcosiinae. Of the 1036 species of Zygaenidae recognized worldwide (van Nieukerken et al., 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0075" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0075">2011</a>), all 45 tested so far, including members of all three relevant subfamilies (38 Zygaeninae, including 35 
  <span class="italic">Zygaena</span> spp., two Procridinae and five Chalcosiinae), possess potent chemical defences, in the form of cyanogenic glucosides (Davis &amp; Nahrstedt, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0018">1982</a>, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0019">1985</a>; Zagrobelny et al., 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0132" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0132">2004</a>). The Zygaenidae synthesize the cyanogenic glucosides linamarin and lotaustralin de novo, from the amino acids valine and isoleucine, respectively (Wray, Davis, &amp; Nahrstedt, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0127" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0127">1983</a>), but species in the Zygaeninae further have the apparently unique ability to simultaneously sequester the same compounds from their host plants (Zagrobelny et al., 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0133" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0133">2014</a>). Cyanogenic glucosides, occurring in plants and several arthropod lineages (Zagrobelny, Bak, &amp; Møller, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0130" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0130">2008</a>), are bitter‐tasting compounds, distasteful to avian predators, so are likely to facilitate taste rejection during an attack (Skelhorn &amp; Rowe, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0100" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0100">2009</a>). They are also toxic, releasing hydrogen cyanide upon enzymatic breakdown, due to enzymes either in the gut of predators or present in the prey themselves (Zagrobelny et al., 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0130" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0130">2008</a>). In terms of coloration, there are dramatic differences in wing patterns between subfamilies of Zygaenidae, and more subtle variation within. Burnet moths in the genus 
  <span class="italic">Zygaena</span> are characterized by classically conspicuous aposematic markings, with a typical pattern of black forewings with red spots, and red hindwings. Both within and between species, there can be extensive variation on this theme, with respect to the colour, size, shape and number of markings (Hofmann &amp; Tremewan, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0054">2017</a>). By contrast, temperate species of Procridinae, or forester moths, are iridescent green or dull brown in colour (Drouet, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0023">2016</a>) and are generally considered cryptic (Efetov &amp; Tarmann, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0028">1999</a>). The single representative of the Chalcosiinae in Western Europe, 
  <span class="italic">Aglaope infausta</span> (L.), has brown forewings with discreet red markings, and red hindwings.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To test for evidence of quantitative signal honesty across the Zygaenidae, we measured signal and defence properties in 14 species, collected in 2015 and 2016 from a range of locations in Denmark, France and the UK. As the defences of the Zygaenidae have been extensively studied, we were able to accurately quantify the levels of cyanogenic glucosides in our samples, using a liquid chromatography–mass spectrometry (LC‐MS) protocol specifically refined to identify linamarin and lotaustralin. In terms of signal receivers, birds are the most likely visually driven predators of adult Zygaenidae. Experiments with captive birds, including 
  <span class="italic">Cyanistes caeruleus</span> (blue tits) and 
  <span class="italic">Parus major</span> (great tits) (Wiklund &amp; Järvi, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0125" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0125">1982</a>) as well as 
  <span class="italic">Sturnus vulgaris</span> (starlings; Rammert, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0089" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0089">1992</a>), suggest that they generally find burnet moths distasteful, yet observations in the wild reveal that several species, such as 
  <span class="italic">Alauda arvensis</span> (skylarks), 
  <span class="italic">Anthus pratensis</span> (meadow pipits) and even 
  <span class="italic">S. vulgaris,</span> will nevertheless attack and in some cases partly or entirely consume these moths (Tremewan, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0121" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0121">2006</a>). Using visual modelling techniques, we measured multiple characteristics of zygaenid wing patterns, from the perspective of a potential avian predator, with a visual system modelled on the blue tit, 
  <span class="italic">C. caeruleus</span>. In addition, molecular data and recent phylogenies of the Zygaenidae and the genus 
  <span class="italic">Zygaena</span> are available (Niehuis, Hofmann, Naumann, &amp; Misof, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0071" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0071">2007</a>; Niehuis, Naumann, &amp; Misof, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0072" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0072">2006a</a>,
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0073" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0073">b</a>,
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0074" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0074">c</a>), enabling evolutionary relationships to be accounted for when analysing variation across species. This study is the first detailed exploration of the chemical defences and coloration of multiple species in this family of aposematic Lepidoptera. We test the idea of quantitative signal honesty in a new study system, using relevant and meaningful measures of signals and defences, to contribute to the debate over signal honesty across aposematic species.
 </p>
</sec>
