<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="jeb13389-sec-0008" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.6</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Phylogenetic reconstruction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The phylogenetic tree was reconstructed using previously published mitochondrial and nuclear sequences, following existing studies of the evolutionary history of the Zygaenidae (Niehuis et al., 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0072" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0072">2006a</a>, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0071" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0071">2007</a>): complete sequences of the mitochondrial genes for NADH dehydrogenase subunit 1 (ND1), tRNA‐leucine (tRNA‐Leu), the large subunit ribosomal RNA (16S rRNA), tRNA‐valine (tRNA‐Val) and a large fragment of the sequence for the mitochondrial small subunit of rRNA (12S rRNA), as well as two nuclear DNA fragments, an almost complete sequence of the small subunit rRNA (18S rRNA) and the 5′ end of the large subunit rRNA (28S rRNA). A new phylogenetic tree was built from these sequences, as previously published phylogenies using all available sequences (Niehuis et al., 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0072" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0072">2006a</a>, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0071" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0071">2007</a>) did not include all our species of interest. 
  <span class="italic">Sesia bembeciformis</span> (Lepidoptera: Sesiidae) was used as an outgroup to root the tree (Niehuis et al., 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0072" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0072">2006a</a>,
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0073" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0073">b</a>,
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0074" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0074">c</a>). Sequences for each species photographed and the outgroup were downloaded from GenBank (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/</span>; see Supporting Information Data 
  <a rid="jeb13389-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#jeb13389-sup-0001">S4</a>) and aligned using MUSCLE (Edgar, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0027">2004</a>), as implemented by the “ape” package (Paradis, Claude, &amp; Strimmer, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0083" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0083">2004</a>) in R 3.3.1 (R Development Core Team, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0088" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0088">2015</a>). The alignments for each sequence were then concatenated to produce a single final alignment [5697 base pairs (bp) long] for phylogenetic reconstruction.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Phylogenetic relationships were assessed with maximum likelihood (ML), using the “phangorn” package (Schliep, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0096" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0096">2011</a>) in R. The most appropriate model of evolution was identified as a GTR+G+I model, allowing for variation in mutation rates between sites and the presence of invariant sites, according to ML estimates calculated with the modelTest function in “phangorn”. Tree topology was then optimized by nearest‐neighbour interchange (NNI), using the optim.pml function. Finally, partitions allowing different rates of evolution for nuclear and mitochondrial sequences or for every different gene were tested with the pmlPart function. Based on Akaike information criterion (AIC) scores, a partitioned model considering each gene separately was selected (AIC
  <sub>no partition</sub> = 40049.83, AIC
  <sub>nuclear/mitochondrial partition</sub> = 39575.70, AIC
  <sub>partition by gene</sub> = 39405.41). The final rooted tree (Fig. 
  <a rid="jeb13389-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#jeb13389-fig-0001">1</a>) was bootstrapped with 1,000 replicates, and nodes with &lt;70% support were collapsed into polytomies.
 </p>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="jeb13389-fig-0001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Phylogenetic tree of the Zygaenidae used in this study. Branch labels represent bootstrap values for 1000 replicates; the scale bar corresponds to genetic distances between sequences, along branch lengths. Image credits: 
    <span class="italic">T. amphellophaga,</span> adapted from 
    <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.lepinet.fr/especes/nation/lep/index.php?id=02140" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.lepinet.fr/especes/nation/lep/index.php?id=02140</span>, ©Daniel Morel; all other images authors’ own
   </p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-1" xlink:href="JEB-32-31-g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
