<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="jeb13389-sec-0007" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.5</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Quantification of chemical defences</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">After photography, each specimen, complete with its forewings, was preserved in 1 ml 80% methanol in preparation for analysis of their cyanogenic glucoside content. Quantification of linamarin and lotaustralin in our samples was performed by liquid chromatography–mass spectrometry (LC‐MS), following a protocol specifically refined to identify these compounds, and used in previous work on the chemistry of the Zygaenidae (Fürstenberg‐Hägg et al., 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0041">2014</a>; Pentzold et al., 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0084" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0084">2015</a>, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0085" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0085">2016</a>; Zagrobelny, Simonsen, Olsen, Bak, &amp; Møller, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0135" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0135">2015</a>; Zagrobelny et al., 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0132" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0132">2004</a>, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0129" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0129">2007</a>, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0131" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0131">2007</a>, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0133" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0133">2014</a>). Samples were prepared by grinding up the specimens in 1 ml ice‐cold 55% MeOH with 0.1% formic acid and then passing them through an Anopore 0.45‐μm filter (Whatman). The analytical LC‐MS was performed with an Agilent 1100 Series LC (Agilent Technologies, Waldbronn, Germany), and Bruker HCT‐Ultra ion trap mass spectrometer (Bruker Daltonics, Bremen, Germany), run in positive electrospray mode, with an oven temperature of 35°C. A Zorbax SB‐C18 column (Agilent; 1.8 μM, 2.1 × 50 mm) was used for chromatographic separation, running with a flow rate of 0.2 ml/min, increased to 0.3 ml/min from 11.2 to 13.5 min. The mobile phases A and B were composed, respectively, of H
  <sub>2</sub>O with 0.1% (v/v) HCOOH, 50 μM NaCl and MeCN with 0.1% (v/v) HCOOH, with a gradient as follows: 0–0.5 min, isocratic 2% B; 0.5–7.5 min, linear gradient 2%–40% B; 7.5–8.5 min, linear gradient 40%–90% B; 8.5–11.5 isocratic 90% B; 11.6–17 min, isocratic 2% B. Sodium adducts of linamarin [retention time (RT) 2.6 min, (M + Na)
  <span class="sup">+</span> at 
  <span class="italic">m/z</span> 270] and lotaustralin [RT 5.5 min, (M + Na)
  <span class="sup">+</span> at 
  <span class="italic">m/z</span> 284] were detected and compared to authentic standards (Møller, Olsen, &amp; Motawia, 
  <a rid="jeb13389-bib-0067" ref-type="ref" href="#jeb13389-bib-0067">2016</a>) using native analysis software. The total amount of each compound was estimated according to its extracted ion chromatogram (EIC) peak areas and quantified using calibration curves for the linamarin, lotaustralin and amygdalin standards. Finally, the concentration of cyanogenic glucosides in each sample was determined by dividing the total amount of compounds in each sample by the specimen mass, recorded at the time of preservation. Samples of larval host plants were analysed similarly. To rule out the possibility that differences between samples from 2015 and 2016 were caused by the LC‐MS machine, a subset of 20 samples (5 
  <span class="italic">A. infausta</span> and 5 
  <span class="italic">Z. trifolii</span> from each year, both males and females) were run together a second time in 2017. Analysing the results with a mixed effects model including specimen ID as a random effect, we found no significant effect of the interaction between collection year and machine run (original, in 2015 or 2016, vs. second run in 2017) on the concentration of cyanogenic glucosides for either 
  <span class="italic">A. infausta</span> (
  <div id="nlm-math-2" class="math">
   <div class="msubsup">
    <span class="mi">χ</span>
    <div class="mrow">
     <span class="mn">1</span>
    </div>
    <span class="mn">2</span>
   </div>
  </div> = 1.73, 
  <span class="italic">df</span> = 1, 
  <span class="italic">p</span> = 0.19) or 
  <span class="italic">Z. trifolii</span> (
  <div id="nlm-math-3" class="math">
   <div class="msubsup">
    <span class="mi">χ</span>
    <div class="mrow">
     <span class="mn">1</span>
    </div>
    <span class="mn">2</span>
   </div>
  </div> = 0.64, 
  <span class="italic">p </span>= 0.43), suggesting that differences between years were not due to variation in the sensitivity of the LC‐MS machine in 2015 and 2016.
 </p>
</sec>
