<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We investigated how the timing of arrival, breeding, and the duration of the arrival‐breeding interval have changed during the study period. All regression models used a normal response distribution and included: yearly trend (continuous) and female age (first‐year breeder or experienced) as explanatory variables, with female identity included as a random intercept to account for individuals who were sampled in &gt;1 year (Appendix 
 <xref rid="ece35716-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref>a). For changes in the arrival‐breeding interval, we modeled this in terms of the year effect during the study period (as above), as well as a second model that also accounted for the arrival date (interval ~ intercept [ID] + year + age + arrival + arrival × year). These two ways of modeling the interval provided us with subtly different interpretations for its change over time. The first gives information as to the absolute magnitude of change in the interval and reflects relative changes in arrival versus breeding date across the years of the study. Thus, if the interval is declining over time, this suggests something may be constraining arrival relative to the timing of breeding; if the interval is increasing, then breeding may be constrained relative to arrival. However, this only looks at the relationship between arrival and breeding, and it does not account for shifts in the overall timing of the breeding season. The second modeling approach examines the change in the interval for birds when the arrival date has been accounted for. A declining interval over time here would show whether birds have been able to reduce their interval relative to the absolute date and the factors linked to that, rather than simply relative to arrival. Models were implemented in a Bayesian framework (JAGS; Plummer, 
 <xref rid="ece35716-bib-0046" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>), with the probability and magnitude of change directly calculated from the posterior distributions of derived variables (Appendix 
 <xref rid="ece35716-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref>a,b). We also modeled the variance in egg‐laying dates relative to arrival to examine whether early‐arriving birds have more flexibility in their arrival‐breeding interval compared to late‐arriving birds (e.g., Teplitsky et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35716-bib-0054" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>); here, we included a regression model on sigma [sigma ~ intercept + arrival + arrival
 <sup>2</sup>] in addition to the model on the mean [mean ~ intercept + age + year] (Appendix 
 <xref rid="ece35716-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref>c).
</p>
