<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The CEM and BRT models were very good at mapping rainfed rice at a regional (~ 18 km cell) scale using only monsoon climate variables, confirming the dependency of rainfed rice cultivation on climate. Of the four climate variables included in our models, 
 <italic class="italic">PER</italic> was the most important for mapping the occurrence of rainfed rice using CEMs, but all four variables were important for projecting extent of rainfed rice cultivation using BRTs, although there was some indication that rainfall variables were slightly more important. Previous studies have shown that monsoon rainfall affects important decisions such as planting dates (
 <xref rid="bb0320" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Zhao et al., 2016</xref>) and choice of rice cultivar (
 <xref rid="bb0310" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Xiong et al., 2014</xref>), and that rainfall is also important for other rainfed crops such as wheat (
 <xref rid="bb0160" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Mavromatis, 2016</xref>), sunflowers (
 <xref rid="bb0280" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Valverde et al., 2015</xref>), and sorghum (
 <xref rid="bb0010" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Alemaw and Simalenga, 2015</xref>). It is most likely that planting decisions by farmers are based on monsoon conditions in the initial growing periods (
 <italic class="italic">PER</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">max</italic>
 </sub>) as opposed to variables during the final growing periods (
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">min</italic>
 </sub> and 
 <italic class="italic">Rain</italic>), which may explain why 
 <italic class="italic">PER</italic> was the most important predictor in CEMs, and why there was more spatial consensus in outputs from CEMs than from BRTs. 
 <italic class="italic">PER</italic> is a ratio of rainfall and potential evapotranspiration, both of which are expected to increase in the future, although projections for rainfall are less certain (
 <xref rid="bb0110" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Jayasankar et al., 2015</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0245" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Sharmila et al., 2015</xref>) than those for temperature (
 <xref rid="bb0030" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Chaturvedi et al., 2012</xref>). However, increased temperatures will increase potential evapotranspiration and hence reduce water available to plants, showing that both rainfall and temperature changes are important. Nonetheless, since GCMs have less agreement on future rainfall patterns compared with temperature, any model that relies predominantly on rainfall, rather than 
 <italic class="italic">PER</italic> which combines rainfall and temperature, might be expected to show more spatial heterogeneity across different GCMs. This explanation could be why there was less consensus for BRTs (i.e. fewer high confidence cells) compared with CEMs.
</p>
