<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We obtained projections of daily sea ice concentration from archives of CMIP5 GCM outputs (see Supporting Information Table 
 <xref rid="ece34637-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S3</xref> for a list of models). For each model, we extracted data from 2 to 6 grid cells (depending on the spatial resolution of the model output) that fell within the core wintering area, and took the average sea ice cover from all cells. Because our data requirements were specific (daily sea ice concentrations from 1950 to 2100), our ensemble was limited by data availability to eight models. Historical data were necessary to compare modeled simulations of sea ice concentrations to observed conditions dating back to 1950. For projected sea ice concentrations, we used model outputs based on two emissions scenarios: Representative Concentration Pathway (RCP) 4.5 and RCP 8.5, in which radiative forcing above preindustrial levels stabilizes near 4.5 W/m
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> by 2100 under RCP 4.5, and reaches 8.5 W/m
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> on an increasing trajectory by 2100 under RCP 8.5. From the GCM daily sea ice concentration outputs, we tallied the number of extreme ice days (days with &gt;95% cover) and number of minimal sea ice days (days with &lt;15% ice cover) at the Spectacled Eider wintering area from November through April each year. We chose the 95% cutoff to represent days with contiguous ice cover, which limits access by eiders to benthic foraging grounds (Lovvorn et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34637-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). We chose the 15% cutoff to represent the opposite scenario, where sea ice is largely absent (Wang &amp; Overland, 
 <xref rid="ece34637-bib-0065" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). A weighted mean across models was calculated based on comparisons to observations using methods developed by Knutti et al. (
 <xref rid="ece34637-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>). Briefly, this weighting scheme is based on model performance and interdependence, and is calculated as follows:
 <disp-formula id="ece34637-disp-0002" class="disp-formula">
  <math id="nlm-math-2" class="math">
   <mrow class="mrow">
    <msub class="msub">
     <mi class="mi">w</mi>
     <mi class="mi">i</mi>
    </msub>
    <mo class="mo">=</mo>
    <mfrac class="mfrac">
     <msup class="msup">
      <mi class="mi">e</mi>
      <mrow class="mrow">
       <mo class="mo">−</mo>
       <mfrac class="mfrac">
        <msubsup class="msubsup">
         <mi class="mi">D</mi>
         <mrow class="mrow">
          <mi class="mi">i</mi>
         </mrow>
         <mn class="mn">2</mn>
        </msubsup>
        <msubsup class="msubsup">
         <mi class="mi">σ</mi>
         <mrow class="mrow">
          <mi class="mi">D</mi>
         </mrow>
         <mn class="mn">2</mn>
        </msubsup>
       </mfrac>
      </mrow>
     </msup>
     <mfenced close=")" open="(" separators="" class="mfenced">
      <mrow class="mrow">
       <mn class="mn">1</mn>
       <mo class="mo">+</mo>
       <msubsup class="msubsup">
        <mo class="mo">∑</mo>
        <mrow class="mrow">
         <mrow class="mrow">
          <mi class="mi">j</mi>
          <mo class="mo">≠</mo>
          <mi class="mi">i</mi>
         </mrow>
        </mrow>
        <mi class="mi">M</mi>
       </msubsup>
       <msup class="msup">
        <mi class="mi">e</mi>
        <mrow class="mrow">
         <mo class="mo">−</mo>
         <msubsup class="msubsup">
          <mi class="mi">S</mi>
          <mrow class="mrow">
           <mrow class="mrow">
            <mi mathvariant="italic" class="mi">ij</mi>
           </mrow>
          </mrow>
          <mn class="mn">2</mn>
         </msubsup>
        </mrow>
       </msup>
       <mo stretchy="false" class="mo">/</mo>
       <msubsup class="msubsup">
        <mi class="mi">σ</mi>
        <mrow class="mrow">
         <mi class="mi">s</mi>
        </mrow>
        <mn class="mn">2</mn>
       </msubsup>
      </mrow>
     </mfenced>
    </mfrac>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </disp-formula>
</p>
