<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Based on changes in physical activity (Δ min/person/week) (see results of the Transport Modelling Tool, (1) in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-15-00880-f001" class="xref">Figure 1</xref>) we can estimate the related changes in mortality (by the Health Model, 3). In the case of physical activity we do not need to calculate all three scenarios, since the scenario Zero Emissions (ZE) only replaces the combustion-engine-driven mobility in the Green Exercise (GE) scenario by electric vehicles, which does not alter the level of physical activity. The health impacts of increased physical activity are quantified by modelling the relationship between these factors and mortality, based on existing meta-analytical estimates. The functional relationship between Metabolic Equivalent of Task (MET) hours per week and the relative risk for all-cause mortality was estimated based on available meta-analyses [
 <xref rid="B31-ijerph-15-00880" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-ijerph-15-00880" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="B33-ijerph-15-00880" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-ijerph-15-00880" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>] (MET is an equivalent of physical activity. It is in units of basic metabolic rate [
 <xref rid="B35-ijerph-15-00880" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>]). Accordingly, a more physically active person’s relative risk of death (RR; defined as the ratio between the risk of an exposed person to the risk of another person not or less exposed) is lower than that of another person with lower activity levels. RR and Hazard Risks (HR) are similar indicators, albeit with small conceptual differences related to time. Hazard ratio provides instantaneous risk at a particular time and relative risk pertains to cumulative risk over a span of time [
 <xref rid="B36-ijerph-15-00880" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>]. Based on individual HR we calculated HR for atraumatic mortality for the affected group for each city, considering the actual changes in activity levels introduced by the scenarios. The atraumatic mortality includes all mortality causes except injuries (code: A00-R99; World Health Organisation International Classification of Diseases, ICD-10 [
 <xref rid="B37-ijerph-15-00880" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>]).
</p>
