<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusions</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on this review, methodological guidelines specific to the economics of health and climate changes are needed to stimulate more economic research and provide standardization of approaches. More recently, the WHO Regional Office for Europe developed detailed methods on how to assess impacts and adaptation costs, which hopefully will be helpful to further shape this agenda.
  <a rid="b13-ehi-8-2014-043" ref-type="bibr" href="#b13-ehi-8-2014-043">13</a> Further, more information and data are necessary on the health impacts of climate change, potential future developments, adaptation options, and the monetary requirements in the health sector and beyond. At the moment, the few studies available indicate simply that more resources need to be allocated in countries with the highest health impacts and with the least resilience to withstand climate change. Despite the evidence gaps, investing in health protection measures will pay economic dividends in terms of saved treatment costs, gained workforce productivity, as well as the very large social and welfare value associated with saved lives. Current approaches focus mainly on a near-term perspective with a lower risk “no regrets” policies, rather than a longer term perspective. A monitoring and surveillance system targeted to detect the health effects of climate change would help to identify emerging health risks so that timely action can be taken, as well as would generate data to be used in assessments and economic analysis.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Evidence plays a more important role than it currently does in guiding health and policies that cut across different sectors. This fact is generally recognized across EU member states, for example, where health systems regulate what health interventions are applied through strict Health Technology Assessment procedures and other evidence-to-policy initiatives.
  <a rid="b58-ehi-8-2014-043" ref-type="bibr" href="#b58-ehi-8-2014-043">58</a> However, preventive policies – environmental health policies more specifically – have a significantly weaker evidence-base than curative and drug-related procedures in the health community. More evidence is required to show the health-protecting effect of safe environments (eg, urban areas, homes, workplaces) as well as the intangible health and non-health impacts. To support the generation of this evidence, methodological guidelines specific to the economics of health and climate change are needed to stimulate more economic research and provide standardization of approach. The first step has been done by the recent economic tool developed by the WHO Regional Office for Europe to guide health damage and adaptation studies.
  <a rid="b13-ehi-8-2014-043" ref-type="bibr" href="#b13-ehi-8-2014-043">13</a> This will help to stimulate health and scientific authorities to consider approaches to utilizing existing health economic studies based on recalculating results from common methods using local input values, and adjusting to current prices. Access to the underlying data and tools remains a challenge, in particular when health effects estimations are not available or detailed health service utilization costs are required.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Significant health gains can be achieved through interventions that are not primarily under the control of the health sector, but are embedded in action at, for example, the urban or regional level. Health gains from investments in other sectors are an opportunity rather than a threat. Economic analyses in areas such as air pollution, nutrition, and transport policy generally show the importance of health outcomes. The new Health 2020 aims at promoting health in all policies.
  <a rid="b59-ehi-8-2014-043" ref-type="bibr" href="#b59-ehi-8-2014-043">59</a>–
  <a rid="b61-ehi-8-2014-043" ref-type="bibr" href="#b61-ehi-8-2014-043">61</a> Collaboration with other ministries and public agencies, in order to ensure that health is not overlooked in any policy that can potentially harm or benefit health, is embedded in the Expo Convention and the strategic impact assessment, however not always carried out. Economics can be used as a common language to make the case for intervention and hence bring others on board. To achieve this, a standardized approach, increased transparency of methods and interests, and a more common presentation from economic studies are needed.
 </p>
</sec>
