<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">For meteorological data, we used daily measurements of maximum and minimum temperature as well as total precipitation from NOAA, publicly available at 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncdc.noaa.gov/cdo-web/datasets" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://.ncdc.noaa.gov/cdo-web/datasets</ext-link>. This dataset provides detailed weather measurements at over 20,000 weather stations across the country. Daily average temperature was calculated as the arithmetic average of daily maximum and minimum temperatures, in degree Celsius (°C). Annual average temperature for the period 2000–2016 was obtained by averaging all daily observations throughout the year. For counties with no weather stations, we imputed annual average temperature by computing a weighted average of that variable from the counties within 50 miles of the original county centroid using inverse distance weights. With measures of annual county-level average temperatures in hand, indicator variables for bins of annual average temperature were generated straightforwardly. Each indicator variable takes the value one if the annual average temperature for a county is in the prespecified range, and zero otherwise. We created indicators for the following ranges: below 5, 5–7, 7–9, 9–11, 11–13, 13–15, and above 15°C. The shares of observations in each bin are reported in 
 <xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref>. Annual total precipitation for the period 2000–2016 was obtained by summing all daily precipitation for a county, in centimeters (cm). Imputation for counties with no weather stations was done as described for temperature. Indicator variables for bins of annual total precipitation were generated in a fashion similar to temperature for the following ranges: below 70, 70–120, 120–170, 170–220, 220–270, and above 270 cm. Again, the shares of observations in each bin are reported in 
 <xref rid="tab1" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref>. The average annual total precipitation for the counties in our sample is approximately 174 cm. For reference, the average annual rainfall is 20 cm in Phoenix (Arizona), 87 cm in Madison (Wisconsin), 120 cm in Providence (Rhode Island), 157 cm in Miami (Florida), and 300 cm in Mt. Rainier (Washington).
</p>
