<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Catchments were selected on the basis that they (i) have good quality, long‐term observational data; (ii) are minimally impacted by human activity; (iii) constitute a representative sample of different catchment types; and (iv) have associated PCDs. In all, 35 catchments (Murphy et al., 
 <xref rid="wrcr23804-bib-0066" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Figure 
 <xref rid="wrcr23804-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref>) meet these criteria with flow data that variously cover the years 1973–2001. Daily flow series were obtained from the Office of Public Works (OPW; 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://waterlevel.ie/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://waterlevel.ie/</ext-link>) and Environmental Protection Agency (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.epa.ie/hydronet/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.epa.ie/hydronet/</ext-link>). The physical attributes of each catchment are obtained from the OPW's Flood Studies Update (FSU; 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://opw.hydronet.com" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://opw.hydronet.com</ext-link>; Mills et al., 
 <xref rid="wrcr23804-bib-0064" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). PCDs provide information about the climatological, soil and morphometric properties of each catchment (see Tables 
 <xref rid="wrcr23804-tbl-0001" ref-type="table" class="xref">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="wrcr23804-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S1</xref>, and 
 <xref rid="wrcr23804-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S2</xref>). Relative to a larger sample, the catchments used are representative of hydroclimatological conditions across the island, but with a recognized underinclusion of smaller upland catchments located along coastal margins. Urban extent is low overall. For the 215 catchment sample the majority (~95%) have &lt;6% urban extent, with only seven having coverage &gt;6%. The greatest urban coverage by a considerable margin (68%) is for the river Slang (ID: 9011). To calibrate hydrological models we use gridded (1 × 1 km) daily precipitation and temperature data (Walsh, 
 <xref rid="wrcr23804-bib-0099" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>) area averaged to provide a single representative baseline for each catchment. Daily potential evapotranspiration is estimated from air temperature and radiation following the method of Oudin et al. (
 <xref rid="wrcr23804-bib-0070" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2005</xref>). This is favored over less parsimonious but more physically based methods (e.g., Penman‐Monteith), which have greater data requirements (e.g., wind speed, humidity) not available for all study catchments (Kay et al., 
 <xref rid="wrcr23804-bib-0045" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>).
</p>
