<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Background</div>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The term “context” is derived from the Latin 
  <span class="italic">cum</span> (“with” or “together”) and 
  <span class="italic">texere</span> (“to weave”). Understanding what happens when an evidence-based practice, e.g. an intervention, programme, method or service, is “woven together” with a team, department or organization is important to better address implementation challenges in health care and other settings. Accounting for the influence of context is necessary to explain how or why certain implementation outcomes are achieved, and failure to do so may limit the generalizability of study findings to different settings or circumstances. Context is considered responsible for study-to-study variations in outcomes [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The relevance of the context in implementation science is reflected in the numerous theories, frameworks, models and taxonomies (referred in this paper to as frameworks) that are applied to analyse barriers and facilitators concerning various implementation outcomes [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>]. Frameworks such as Promoting Action on Research Implementation in Health Services (PARIHS) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>] and Theoretical Domains Framework (TDF) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>] explicitly refer to context as one of several determinants; other frameworks do not explicitly mention context. Instead, many other terms referring to the same or similar concept are in use, e.g. “environmental factors” [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>] and “inner setting” and “outer setting” [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>]. Terms such as “context”, “setting” and “environment” are often used interchangeably in implementation science and other research fields [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Regardless of which terms are used, it is not known whether these determinant frameworks conceptualize context in a similar way and describe the same context dimensions or to what extent they encompass different dimensions of the context. Lack of conceptual and terminological clarity and consistency makes it difficult for implementation researchers to identify the most relevant context dimensions for any given study. If neglected dimensions are causally significant for implementation outcomes, their omission may create problems in interpreting and applying the findings.</p>
 <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Some of these determinant frameworks are widely used in implementation science [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>], which means that context as understood in these frameworks may have considerable impact on how the concept is studied de facto. No previous study has investigated determinant frameworks in terms of how they define or describe context and what might be a core set of contextual determinants that most frameworks account for. Therefore, the aim of this scoping review was to identify and examine determinant frameworks used in implementation science to address four issues: how were the frameworks developed, what terms do they use to denote contextual determinants for implementation, how is the context conceptualized, and which context dimensions are applied across the frameworks. Greater conceptual and terminological clarity and consistency may enhance transparency, improve communication among researchers, and facilitate exchange of data and comparative evaluations.
 </p>
</sec>
