<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec11" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">How were the determinant frameworks developed?</div>
 <p id="Par35" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The frameworks were developed in three different ways, as described in the investigated publications. Eleven frameworks are based on literature reviews of empirical studies and of theories, models and frameworks used in implementation science to describe determinants of various implementation-relevant outcomes: Cabana et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>]; Fleuren et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>]; Greenhalgh et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>]; Cochrane et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>]; Nutley et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>]; Feldstein and Glasgow (PRISM) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>]; Damschroder et al. (CFIR) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>]; Gurses et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>]; and Flottorp et al. (TICD) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>]. Presumably the framework by Rainbird et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>] is also based on a literature review, although details about how this framework was developed are not actually provided. The basis of the framework developed by SURE [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>] is also somewhat unclear; it is simply stated that “published lists of barriers for implementing changes in health care often show a high degree of overlap” ([
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>], p. 6), implying that it was developed based on the existing literature. Fleuren et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>] combined the literature review with a Delphi process involving 44 implementation experts.
 </p>
 <p id="Par36" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Four of the frameworks are based on the authors’ own implementation experiences and/or empirical studies. PARIHS [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>] emerged from the observation that successful implementation in health care might be premised on three key determinants (characteristics of the evidence, context and facilitation), a proposition that was subsequently analysed in four empirical studies. PARIHS subsequently underwent substantial research and development work [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>]. The revised i-PARIHS was proposed by Harvey and Kitson ([
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>], p. 2) based on their own “ongoing application of the framework in implementation studies together with critiques and evaluations of the framework by other research teams”. Grol and Wensing ([
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>], p. 558) based their work on “analyses of the literature and research conducted at our research centre”. Similarly, the AIF [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>] combined the developers’ implementation experiences with literature reviews. Mäkelä and Thorsen [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>] referred to “previous work in the area” and data from various projects within a project called Concerted Action of the Changing Professional Practice ([
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>], p. 24).
 </p>
 <p id="Par37" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Two frameworks are derived from existing theory or theoretical assumptions rather than experience or empirical studies. The framework by Wensing et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>] was based on an analysis of the literature concerning theories on behaviour or organizational change in a variety of disciplines. It is not stated how many theories were identified, but the searches continued “until the overview of theories was ‘saturated’” ([
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>], p. 16). The TDF [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>] was constructed on the basis of a synthesis of 128 constructs related to behaviour change found in 33 established social-cognitive behaviour change theories.
 </p>
</sec>
