<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec15" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An alternative age model</div>
 <p id="Par32" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A different age model applied to the JY loess–paleosol sequence would generate a shift similar to the classic MPT from 41-kyr to 100-kyr cycles. In this case, the duration of the lower portion (below L
  <sub>15</sub>) needs be extended from 480 kyr (AGE1, 1.25–1.73 Ma) to 950 kyr (AGE2, 1.25-2.2 Ma) (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">5</a>). On the AGE1 model, the lower portion of the JY loess core is correlated to L
  <sub>15</sub>–S
  <sub>23</sub>, whereas on the AGE2 model, this portion is correlated to L
  <sub>15</sub>–S
  <sub>29</sub>. We prefer the first age model (AGE1) because of two reasons. First, the Olduvai subchron is not recorded in the Jingyuan loess sequence and thus the basal age should be &lt;1.77 Ma. Second, a remarkable shift of the sedimentation rate from 13.5 to 25 cm/kyr around L
  <sub>15</sub> based on the JY-AGE2 is significantly different from the relative stable sedimentation rates in several classic loess profiles since the Olduvai subchron (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">6</a>). Such a two-fold increase of the sedimentation rate at this single site cannot be explained by either tectonic or climatic factors.
 </p>
 <p id="Par33" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition, numerous geomorphologic and paleomagnetic investigations on the terrace sequences of the Yellow River indicate that the loess sequences (S
  <sub>0</sub>–S
  <sub>24</sub>) accumulated on the oldest terrace are &lt;1.8 Ma
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
  </span> Based on the new terrace classification of the Yellow River
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
  </span>, Jingyuan loess sequences (S
  <sub>0</sub>–S
  <sub>23</sub>) was accumulated on the ninth terrace, with a rough basal age of 1.7 Ma. While an alternative pedostratigraphic correlation of the lower portion below L
  <sub>15</sub> can generate a classical MPT shift from 41-kyr to 100-kyr cycles, the relatively old basal age (~2.2 Ma) and two-fold increase in the sedimentation rates around L
  <sub>15</sub> are apparently inconsistent with independent dating results and with age–depth relationships of other classic loess profiles on the CLP, respectively. Thus we think that our preferred AGE1 is more reasonable, as inferred from the paleomagnetic and burial dating results.
 </p>
</sec>
