<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sensitivity simulations</div>
 <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To estimate the monsoon sensitivity to various forcings, we use the set of 61 experiments with the climate model HadCM3
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>
  </span>, which were designed to sample the ensemble of glacial, CO
  <sub>2</sub>, and astronomical conditions experienced by the land–ocean–atmosphere system during the Pleistocene (Methods). A statistical model (called emulator) is used to interpolate the output of these experiments and to simulate the trajectory of the climate system throughout the Pleistocene. The model results are used to estimate the relative influences of different astronomical parameters (eccentricity, obliquity, and precession)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
  </span>, CO
  <sub>2</sub> concentrations (180–280 ppmv)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>
  </span>, and discrete levels of glaciation ranging from 1 (Holocene-like) to 11 (Last Glacial Maximum)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>
  </span> (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">8</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As the loess δ
  <span class="sup">13</span>C
  <sub>IC</sub> record is affected by changes in mean annual precipitation (MAP) and temperature (MAT), we focused on these two variables averaged over northern China (30–40°N, 104–120°E), where the precipitation change is more sensitive to summer monsoon intensity
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
  </span>. The sensitivity analysis was based on the emulator approach
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>
  </span>. The emulator is evaluated using a leave-one-out cross-validation approach, which consists of predicting the output of one experiment using the emulator calibrated on all the other experiments. Prediction errors for the MAT and MAP over northern China are well calibrated, and about 2/3 of the prediction errors are within one standard deviation (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">9</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The calibrated emulator is then used for two purposes. First, we estimated the evolution of these indices throughout the Pleistocene to reconstruct the MAP and MAT curves. The MAP and MAT values are the estimated equilibrium response of HadCM3 for forcing conditions spanning the last 1.7 Ma. The climate evolution estimated following this approach considers thus that MAT and MPT are in quasi-equilibrium with the forcing components, including astronomical solutions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>
  </span>, ice levels
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span>, and CO
  <sub>2</sub> concentrations
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>
  </span>. Next, we estimated the total variances of both MPT and MAT with the emulator, before and after the MPT. The expected variances of these variables caused by the variations of only one or two factors (eccentricity and longitude of perihelion, obliquity, ice, and CO
  <sub>2</sub>) were estimated by assuming that the other factors are fixed
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
</sec>
