<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Setting and sampling</div>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">CLP climate is characterized by seasonal changes in temperature and precipitation. Summer is the warm and humid season due to the influence of the summer monsoon, which transports heat and water vapor from the low-latitude oceans. The summer precipitation from May to September contributes to the annual precipitation by 60–75% and results in strong pedogenesis of the loess–paleosol sequences. In contrast, winter is the cold and dry season associated with strong winter monsoon wind, which is linked to the Siberian–Mongolian high-pressure system. The winter monsoon transports vast of dust particles from inland Asia to the downwind CLP. Therefore, Chinese loess, as a unique continental archive, can document multi-scale monsoon variability linked to past climate changes in both high- and low-latitude regions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Jingyuan loess sequence (JY, 36.35°N, 104.6°E, 2,210 m above sea level) is located at the depositional center of modern dust storms on the northwestern CLP (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). A 430-m core was retrieved from the highest terrace of the Yellow River near Jingyuan County. The JY core consists of a 427-m loess deposit underlain by a 3-m gravel layer. A 40-m outcrop was excavated nearby to collect parallel samples spanning the last interglacial–glacial cycle. Continuous U-channel and discrete cube samples were taken from the split cores for alternating-field and thermal demagnetization measurements, respectively (Methods). Three quartz samples were chosen from the underlying gravel layer for 
  <span class="sup">26</span>Al/
  <span class="sup">10</span>Be burial dating (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>). Powder samples were taken at 10-cm intervals for magnetic susceptibility, grain size, and δ
  <span class="sup">13</span>C
  <sub>IC</sub> analyses.
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Location of JY loess core and representative loess profiles on the Chinese Loess Plateau (CLP). Black dots denote four classic loess profiles, which have been investigated intensively as the Quaternary stratotype sections
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>–
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
     </span>. Red dot indicates the Jingyuan loess profile accumulated on the ninth terrace of the Yellow River in the northwestern CLP
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>,
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
     </span>
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2018_8257_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e619" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
