<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">UVI Development: Theory and Data Collection Method</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The major research question is in which way we can measure urban vulnerability in Beijing. Subquestions concern the role of floods, the role of heat waves and the role of droughts. 
  <a rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-14">Kropp et al. (2009)</a> developed heat wave indicator within the scope of a climate change vulnerability study for North Rhine Westphalia. However, this indicator does not cover the three components of exposure, sensitivity and adaptive capacity. In our research, we propose that vulnerability could be assessed by the dimensions of exposure, sensitivity and adaptive capacity. Exposure is determined solemnly by climatic threats or issues (e.g., heat wave, urban flooding, drought, etc.). The sensitivity is determined by characteristics of sectors, systems and group of people that are directly or indirectly influenced by climatic threats. The adaptive capacity of a system is determined by the system’s capacity to adjust to climatic threats including the ability to learn from experience or information and hence to reduce its sensitivity. Both exposure and sensitivity lead to more vulnerability, while increased adaptive capacity diminishes vulnerability. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1" href="#fig-1">Figure 1</a> shows the procedures we developed to guide the assessment of vulnerability. We separate the procedure to do the assessment from the methods used to come up with the necessary data.
 </p>
 <div id="fig-1" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.7717/peerj.7018/fig-1</span>
  <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Procedures for the assessment and methodology for data collection.</div>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="peerj-07-7018-g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate change has different meaning for different cities and different cities face different priority climate themes. In this study, Impact Oriented Monitoring (IOM), together with stakeholders’ participation is applied to identify key climatic threats or priority climate themes that Beijing is facing. IOM is based on historical data of direct economic loss of climatic events, in particular the data concerning the last 12 years in the Beijing Annual Natural Disaster Report. Following the identification of priority climate themes, a one day workshop was organized by the Beijing Climate Change Response Research and Education Centre, of the Beijing University of Civil engineering and Architecture for allowing expert judgment and stakeholders’ participation for identifying vulnerable sectors and groups. Title of this workshop was Vulnerable Sector and Groups: How Beijing Adapt to Climate Change and it took place on 14 April 2017. 30 participants attended the workshop. Among the 30 participants who are all senior experts, 24 (two from each sector) are from sectors like water supply and sewage, waste management, public health, energy supply, urban green and biodiversity, forest and ecosystem, tourism, nature conservation, information and communication, insurance, transportation and education and six are experts recommended by China National Expert Committee on Climate Change Adaptation (CECCCA). Participants were selected on criteria like (1) at least 5 years working experiences in natural disaster governance or climate adaptation, (2) good knowledge of indicator development and index processing, (3) have participated in development of its sectoral strategies and policies on climate change adaptation. Before making a judgment participants listened to a presentation of this research and were discussing vulnerability issues allowing an intensive exchange of ideas between stakeholders and experts.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A two-steps approach was applied for the preliminarily selection of individual indicators. The first step is to do a literature review selecting individual indicators for climatic threats related vulnerable systems/sectors and vulnerable groups/individuals. By the literature reviews, we have selected preliminary 26 individual indicators for assessing urban vulnerability to the threat of floods, 32 indicators for assessing urban vulnerability to the threat of heat waves and 29 individual indicators for assessing vulnerability to the threat of drought. All those preliminary selected 87 indicators, together with a brief description of each indicator were distributed to the participants before the workshop. The second step is to adopt an expert approach and achieve stakeholders’ participation as described above. The experts and stakeholders present their own understanding and comments and finally they make their own scoring for each of indicators, based on the criteria: (1) the indicators are closely related to the issue, (2) they are independent of one another, (3) relevant in the context of Beijing, (4) measurable and (5) the data are available. Based on the sum of the scores of each indicators, the final 23 indicators were selected for measuring urban vulnerability.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A frequently mentioned challenge in indicator programmes (
  <a rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-21">Van Dijk, 2014</a>) is how the index’s inputs should be weighted. In most of international indicator programmes, nominally all inputs into an index receive equal weight. No indicator gets more weight than any other. An environmental sustainability index programme implemented jointly by the World Economic Forum’s global Leaders for Tomorrow Environment Task Force, the Yale Center for Environmental Law and Policy, and the Columbia University Center for International Earth Science Information Network (CIESIN) has also addressed the issue of weighting indicators (
  <a rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-24">World Economic Forum, 2001</a>). However the result is not acceptable for two reasons. One is that weights identified by different experts from different countries are very likely to differ significantly. This is because the situation is different from one country to another. Another reason for getting poor results is probably that vulnerability is a complicated issue and may lead to confusion among different experts. The reason for opting for a weighting approach for the aggregation of the selected indicators are twofold. One to allow cross-urban comparisons. Most Chinese cities are quite similar in terms of climatic threats, economic growth, social progress, institutional capability and governance. Therefore a scientifically acceptable determination of the weights should be achieved. Secondly we used the Analytical Hierarchy Process (AHP) method, together with consultation of experts. One of the main advantages of the AHP is that it allows experts to compare two factors by using the same criteria and scoring rule. As the identification with the same criteria and scoring rule is quite simple, statistical results can easily be obtained at an acceptable level. As an example, 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2" href="#fig-2">Fig. 2</a> shows how AHP is applied to aggregate weighted indicators into urban sensibility index that is one component of urban vulnerability for the threat of floods.
 </p>
 <div id="fig-2" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.7717/peerj.7018/fig-2</span>
  <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">AHP framework for measuring urban sensibility for the threat of floods.</div>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="peerj-07-7018-g002" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2" href="#fig-2">Fig. 2</a>, the AHP objective (first hierarchy) is to measure urban sensibility for the threat of floods under three principles (second hierarchy) of (1) relevance, (2) scientifically sound and (3) applicable to users by using weighted individual indicators (third hierarchy) of annual rainstorm hours (indicator (1), percentage of paved area (indicator (2) and risk of secondary disasters caused by heavy precipitation (indicator (3). Relevance is explained as directly related to the issue, based on a known linkage between the indicator and sensibility and sensitive to changes in the conditions of interest. Scientifically sound is explained as unbiased and representative of the conditions of concern, scientifically credible, so that they cannot be easily challenged in terms of their reliability or validity, based on data of a known and acceptable quality and consistent and comparable over time and space. Applicable to users is explained as based on data which are available at an acceptable cost-benefit ratio, easily understood and applicable by potential users, acceptable to stakeholders and available soon after the event or period to which it relates (so that policy decisions are not delayed). Experts and stakeholders compare the three individual indicators against each of the three principles by using the AHP scoring rule in 
  <a rid="table-1" ref-type="table" href="#table-1">Table 1</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Likewise, the urban exposure index and the urban adaptive capacity index can be calculated by weighted indicators and the urban vulnerability index can be weighted by giving weight to urban sensibility, urban exposure and urban adaptive capacity.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The composite UVI combines numbers of individual indicators measured in different units into a single number between 0 and 1. 
  <a rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-14">Kropp et al. (2009)</a> uses fuzzy logic techniques for this combination in order to account for a quantification of uncertainties. Kropp notes that “these techniques allow for gradual instead of binary allocation of variable values to classes”. For example in a region where life expectancy of 25 years old is classified as low and life expectancy of 85 years old is classified as high. A practical value in between these two thresholds is then allocated to the class ‘life expectancy’ according to a linear function that could for example result in the number ‘0.5’ for the value 55 years old.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For applying fuzzy logic techniques, we developed the methodology for standardizing data aiming at generating the value of each of the indicators in a range from 0–1.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Standardized data is calculated by:</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I 
  <sub>i</sub> = (X 
  <sub>i</sub> − B 
  <sub>i</sub>)/(A 
  <sub>i</sub> − B 
  <sub>i</sub> ) (if I 
  <sub>i</sub> is a positive indicator. 
  <span class="italic">i</span> = 1, 2, 3, …, n)
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I 
  <sub>i</sub> = (B 
  <sub>i</sub> − X 
  <sub>i</sub> )/(B 
  <sub>i</sub> − A 
  <sub>i</sub>) (if I 
  <sub>i</sub> is a negative indicator, 
  <span class="italic">i</span> = 1, 2, 3, …, n).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Where:</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">I
  <sub>i</sub>: &amp; Standardized version of an indicator I 
  <sub>i</sub>. It varies from 0 to 1. X
  <sub>i</sub>: &amp; Real value of an indicator I
  <sub>i</sub>;
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A
  <sub>i</sub>: &amp; Theoretically max. value of a positive indicator I
  <sub>i</sub> and theoretically min. value of a negative indicator I 
  <sub>i</sub>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">B
  <sub>i</sub>: &amp; Theoretically min. value of a positive indicator I
  <sub>i</sub> and theoretically max. value of a negative indicator I
  <sub>i</sub>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Beijing has a population of 22 million and covers an area of 16,400 km
  <span class="sup">2</span>. The city of Beijing is divided into four areas with 16 districts. Forced by the availability of statistical data, collected mainly by the district statistical bureaus, the research unit is the district, as presented in 
  <a rid="table-2" ref-type="table" href="#table-2">Table 2</a>.
 </p>
 <div id="table-1" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.7717/peerj.7018/table-1</span>
  <span class="label">Table 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title"> Values of comparison between two factors.</div>
  </div>
  <div class="alternatives">
   <div xlink:href="peerj-07-7018-g008" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <colgroup span="1">
     <col span="1"/>
     <col span="1"/>
    </colgroup>
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Description</th>
      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Value of A/B</th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1. as important as B</td>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2. between 1 and 3</td>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3. slightly more important than B</td>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4. between 3 and 5</td>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5. really more important than B</td>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6. between 5 and 7</td>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7. much more important than B</td>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8. between 7 and 9</td>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9. very much more important than B</td>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
  </div>
 </div>
</sec>
