<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Here, we test whether the locomotor performance of adults in two closely related aquatic frog species from different latitudes, 
 <italic class="italic">Xenopus tropicalis</italic> (tropical, low latitude) and 
 <italic class="italic">X. laevis</italic> (temperate, high latitude), shows acclimation effects. Locomotor performance is temperature dependent (
 <xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Herrel and Bonneaud, 2012a</xref>) and relevant to study in the context of predator escape, prey capture, reproduction (mate finding) and dispersal (
 <xref rid="ref25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Husak, 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">James 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic> 2007
 </xref>). However, different locomotor traits are important in different contexts with burst performance, for example, being likely selected for in the context of predator escape and prey capture (
 <xref rid="ref57" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Vanhooydonck and Van Dame, 2003</xref>). In contrast, locomotor endurance or stamina is likely more important in the context of mate finding and dispersal. Trade-offs may exist in these locomotor traits due to their reliance of different underlying physiological traits (
 <xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Herrel and Bonneaud, 2012b</xref>). As such, the thermal optima and the acclimation effects may also differ between these types of performance traits (
 <xref rid="ref58" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Van Damme 
  <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 1991
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Herrel and Bonneaud, 2012a</xref>). Finally, we also tested for sex differences in acclimation as males and females have previously been shown to differ in locomotor performance in both species (
 <xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Herrel 
  <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 2012
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Louppe 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2017
 </xref>). Moreover, previous studies on other taxa have demonstrated sex-specific acclimation effects (
 <xref rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Rogers 
  <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 2007
 </xref>). In summary, the objectives of this study were (i) to evaluate the capacity of adults of 
 <italic class="italic">X. tropicalis</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">X. laevis</italic> to acclimate their burst locomotor performance (jumping) at low or high temperature; (ii) to explore the possible trade-offs between exertion and burst capacity in 
 <italic class="italic">X. tropicalis</italic>; and (iii) to examine whether sexes differ in their thermal acclimation response.
</p>
