<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Wheat breeding sites in North America experienced slightly different scenarios. Tmin during April-August increased from 1981–1990 to 2006–2015, while Tmax decreased during the same period. The exposure of spring wheat to heat in North America was therefore slightly reduced. The rainfall during April-August and during agricultural year (October-September) increased. The growing season precipitation, 1981 to 1990, was much below the long term mean while the growing season precipitation in 2010 to 2015 was above the long term mean. This increase in precipitation in would contribute to reduced Tmax. Overall, the climatic changes in North America were more favorable for spring wheat compared to Eurasia due to less exposure to high temperature and more rainfall. As in Eurasia, changes in the planting and harvesting dates were site specific, though there was an overall increase in crop cycle duration by 3–4 days due to later harvesting. For individual sites, the grain yield response to higher temperature, rainfall in spring-summer and growing cycle duration was very similar to Eurasian sites. The analysis of long-term data for Montana spring wheat resulted in similar conclusions [
 <xref rid="pone.0204932.ref022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>]. McCaig [
 <xref rid="pone.0204932.ref026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>] examined weather variables and durum wheat grain yield at Swift Current for 1946–1995 and reported the highest correlation between weather parameters and grain yield occurred around the end of June through early July, approximately the time of anthesis. The strategy to address the climate change in the Canadian prairies is seeding earlier and choosing cultivars with later maturity dates and longer growing period [
 <xref rid="pone.0204932.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. Furthermore, because winter temperatures are projected to increase and precipitation in April and May is projected to increase, which are both favorable for winter wheat, another strategy is to increase the planting of winter wheat.
</p>
