<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec16" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The patient perspective</div>
 <p id="Par60" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Patients expressed perceptions that did not directly influence the referral process but were relevant in understanding the perceptions of this process. These concerned their first visits to FPs and the profession they considered were best suited for conducting MINI assessments.</p>
 <sec id="Sec17" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Most patients accept meeting FPs first</div>
  <p id="Par61" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Many patients were satisfied with meeting FPs first and then being referred to therapists for assessment (Q25, Q26, Table 
   <a rid="Tab5" ref-type="table" href="#Tab5">5</a>). If they were dissatisfied, it most often was related to mistrust, of either the FPs or the therapists, rather than to the referral procedure. Some patients, though, found the FP visits to be unnecessary. They perceived that they already knew their problems and wanted psychological treatment immediately. They saw the FP visits as a formality without any clear benefit. Others wanted to shorten the time to treatment and suggested that the FP could conduct the MINI during the visit rather than referring the patient to a therapist.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec18" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Importance of personality and knowledge</div>
  <p id="Par62" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Even if a patient appreciated a referral to a therapist, it was not self-evident that the therapist was the most appropriate for conducting the MINI. The profession itself was not regarded as crucial. The personality, knowledge and experience of the person conducting the MINI interview played a more important role (Q27, Table 
   <a rid="Tab5" ref-type="table" href="#Tab5">5</a>). The interviewer should, for example, be familiar with any unwanted emotions during the MINI and know how to handle them. Some patients were confident that their FPs could conduct MINIs effectively. Others were indifferent and perceived that it did not matter whether an FP or a therapist conducted the MINI; they would accept both.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
