<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Capabilities, psychological</div>
 <sec id="FPar1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">FPs’ competence in terms of knowledge and skills</div>
  <p id="Par36" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Most FPs believed that they had sufficient competence in psychiatry, especially regarding depression, to make adequate clinical judgements without the MINI. However, they perceived that the MINI could offer extra help with complicated patients, which usually were referred to therapists (Q1, Table 
   <a rid="Tab5" ref-type="table" href="#Tab5">5</a>). Some FPs expressed that their diagnostic knowledge and skills were insufficient due to too little training or experience. These FPs referred patients more broadly, including those with less complicated situations.
  </p>
  <p id="Par37" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The patients often expressed that FPs had insufficient competence in psychiatry. Some of them anticipated that psychiatry was not a part of the FPs’ education. Therefore, according to them, psychiatry was not the business of the FP but for therapists with their education in psychology. Referral was thus seen as natural from the patients’ perspectives (Q2, Table 
   <a rid="Tab5" ref-type="table" href="#Tab5">5</a>).
  </p>
  <p id="Par38" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Furthermore, FPs’ communication of the purpose of the MINI was described as a skill that could influence the patients’ motivation to be referred. Both patients and therapists provided examples where lacking or unclear information from the FP had made the patient feel unsafe or disinterested in the referral (Q3, Table 
   <a rid="Tab5" ref-type="table" href="#Tab5">5</a>) For patients, the consultation style could be problematic. The FP took over the agenda and did not give the patients the opportunity to talk as they had wanted to (Q4, Table 
   <a rid="Tab5" ref-type="table" href="#Tab5">5</a>). Other patients felt that the FPs concentrated on somatic problems instead of trying to find out what was really distressing them. In addition, at PHCC1, the competence of the FP influenced the feedback of the MINI results from the therapist to the FP. The therapist felt that a discussion was especially important for inexperienced FPs.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
