<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results</div>
 <sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Adoption of the process and patient satisfaction with it</div>
  <p id="Par32" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">At PHCC1, nine out of the 15 FPs referred patients (average of seven patients, range one to 17 per FP) according to the study plan. After feedback of the results, the FPs made their diagnosis and initiated treatment. At PHCC2, a third diagnostic process had developed (See Table 
   <a rid="Tab3" ref-type="table" href="#Tab3">3</a>, column 3). The FPs had discontinued their previous use of the MINI.. Patients with complex problems were referred to the therapists for more comprehensive examinations including the MINI. The therapists then, made the final diagnosis and initiated psychological treatment. There was no further involvement from the FPs, except when the therapist judged that referral to psychiatry was warranted (Table 
   <a rid="Tab3" ref-type="table" href="#Tab3">3</a>, column 3).
  </p>
  <p id="Par33" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">According the answers to the question “How satisfied are you of being interviewed by a therapist as part of clarifying your problems?” the patients appreciated the referrals to therapists. The median satisfaction was 92 (ICR 75, 100; 
   <span class="italic">n</span> = 102 patients, no differences between PHCCs).
  </p>
  <p id="Par34" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Many patients had previous experiences from visiting health care facilities for psychiatric problems. In the interviews, they compared the visits and perceived that the diagnostic process including referral to a therapist was more thorough.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Enablers of and barriers to the process</div>
  <p id="Par35" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although the aims of the referrals differed between the PHCCs, many associated barriers and enablers were similar. The identified factors that could influence referrals and feedback discussions, respectively, are described in Table 
   <a rid="Tab4" ref-type="table" href="#Tab4">4</a>. Representative quotations for the findings are compiled in Table 
   <a rid="Tab5" ref-type="table" href="#Tab5">5</a> and referred to in the text. 
   <div id="Tab4" class="table-wrap">
    <span class="label">Table 4</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Factors influencing an inter-professional diagnostic process for depression and anxiety in primary care</p>
    </div>
    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
     <thead>
      <tr>
       <th>Component in COM-B [
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>]
       </th>
       <th>Factor influencing referral</th>
       <th>Factor influencing a feedback discussion</th>
       <th>Respondents</th>
      </tr>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <tr>
       <td>Capabilities, psychological</td>
       <td colspan="2">FPs’ competence in terms of knowledge and skills</td>
       <td>FPs, therapists, patients</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td rowspan="3">Opportunities, physical</td>
       <td colspan="2">The priorities of the management </td>
       <td>FPs, therapists, patients</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Limited time for FPs’ assessment</td>
       <td/>
       <td>FPs, therapists, patients</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Easy access to a therapist</td>
       <td/>
       <td>FPs</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td rowspan="2">Opportunities, social</td>
       <td>Patient characteristics</td>
       <td/>
       <td>FPs</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td colspan="2">Process facilitator or change agent available</td>
       <td>FPs, therapists,</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td rowspan="3">Motivation, reflective</td>
       <td>Beliefs that referral facilitates the work of the FP</td>
       <td/>
       <td>FPs, therapists, patients</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td colspan="2">Beliefs that collaboration on diagnosis can improve patient management</td>
       <td>FPs, therapists, patients</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td colspan="2">Beliefs about professional roles</td>
       <td>FPs, therapists</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td rowspan="2">Motivation, automatic</td>
       <td>Positive experiences facilitate a new habit</td>
       <td/>
       <td>FPs, therapists</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Easier to continue working as usual</td>
       <td/>
       <td>FPs</td>
      </tr>
     </tbody>
    </table>
    <div class="table-wrap-foot">
     <p>
      <span class="italic">FP</span> Family Practitioner
     </p>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div id="Tab5" class="table-wrap">
    <span class="label">Table 5</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Sample quotations for analysis of factors that influence the referral to a therapist for assessment with the MINI, with COM-B as framework</p>
    </div>
    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
     <thead>
      <tr>
       <th>Influencing factor</th>
       <th>Sub-category</th>
       <th>Sample quotation</th>
      </tr>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <tr>
       <td rowspan="4">FPs’ competence in terms of knowledge and skills</td>
       <td rowspan="2">Knowledge about mental disorders</td>
       <td>Q1. One has to consider whether there is a need for the MINI (and referral) or if my own assessment is sufficient (FP 8, PHCC 1)</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Q2. The doctor knows about injuries and the therapist about the soul (Patient 1).</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Communication skills</td>
       <td>Q3. I was not really prepared for the visit to the therapist. My FP had only told me that I […] needed to talk to a therapist, which I felt was a good idea. This meant that I did not know that I was about to have an interview and the MINI test. […] So, the therapist was a bit unprepared as well and had to explain what it all was about. However, then we talked about what I needed to discuss with her – before the interview. I felt that this was doing it backwards, we should have made the interview first and talked afterwards (Patient 16).</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Consultation skills</td>
       <td>Q4. Doctors are doctors after all, they kind of, how shall I express it, take over, I am not in charge anymore. (Patient 9).</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td rowspan="2">The priorities of the management</td>
       <td rowspan="2">Lack of supportive routines</td>
       <td>Q5. …and there are no fora (for discussions). If you need to contact someone, you have to go and knock on the door when that person is not occupied and you yourself is not occupied. This is very tricky. The alternative is the lunch room… which is well, so-so, you don’t want to do that for all your patients (therapist, PHCC2).</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>
        <p>Q6. The administrative extra tasks have to be taken into consideration e.g. to have</p>
        <p>a specific time for discussions with the therapist instead of the therapist coming to me in the staff room or in the corridor (FP, PHCC1).</p>
       </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td rowspan="2">Limited time for FPs’ assessment</td>
       <td rowspan="2"/>
       <td>Q7. I have had many new patients with short time slots. They present pain and symptoms in different places and you get the impression that depression, anxiety or something similar is behind it all. Then it is important to have this resource (the therapist) since you cannot do that assessment in 15 min (FP 3, PHCC1).</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Q8. Stressed doctors have difficulties to sense who you are and to give the adequate questions about your health (Patient 3).</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Easy access to a therapist</td>
       <td/>
       <td>Q9. I have reasoned that as the waiting time to the therapist is so short, I have referred them (the patients) before initiation of treatment… and then I have perceived that my depression diagnosis is more robust (FP 9 PHCC1).</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Patient characteristics</td>
       <td/>
       <td>Q10. You and the patient have to agree on what to do. Especially depressive and psychiatric diagnoses, they are extra sensitive. Had this been a project concerning diabetes, it goes without saying, you would refer the patient (FP 6, PHCC 1).</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td rowspan="2">Process facilitator or change agent available</td>
       <td rowspan="2"/>
       <td>Q11. The therapist chased us in order to catch us for the feedback. I guess it has been heavy for her (FP 9, PHCC1).</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Q12. Initially, it took time to fill the time slot (assigned for assessment by the MINI) so I sent out reminders in the patient record system in order to get it moving (therapist, PHCC1).</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td rowspan="3">Beliefs that referral facilitates the work of the FP</td>
       <td rowspan="2">Saving time and effort</td>
       <td>Q13. So, with the therapist assessment, the table was set when the patients came back. It is amazing! The patient was nearly fully examined. So, it saved time for me (FP 4, PHCC1).</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Q14. It is harder for the doctor to arrive at a diagnosis without cooperation with a therapist (patient 1).</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Gives additional information</td>
       <td>Q15. …a different climate is needed, kind of, in order for those questions to surface. If you have an hour at your disposal, in an undisturbed context and normal clothing (as is the case for the therapist), the conditions for the therapist are so much better than ours (FP 4, PHCC1).</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td rowspan="3">Beliefs that collaboration on diagnosis can improve patient management</td>
       <td rowspan="3"/>
       <td>Q16. It is a big advantage that there is someone with whom you can discuss the patient (FP 7, PHCC1).</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Q17. Patients often refer to conversations with the FP and want me to do something. This could be prevented if the FP and I talk and agree on a treatment plan (therapist, PHCC2).</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Q18. I think that you need to meet with a therapist as well as a doctor if you don’t feel well. That the diagnosis and examination are made from both a doctor- and a therapist perspective in order to capture all parts. That the doctor does not label you as being sick “OK take some vitamin-D because you seem to be a bit moody” without the input from someone who is more competent concerning such matters (Patient 18).</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td rowspan="2">Beliefs about professional roles</td>
       <td rowspan="2"/>
       <td>Q19. But it is something that you feel when you ask the questions (of the MINI) so it becomes an integrated assessment (FP 2, PHCC2).</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Q20. What I do NOT want to see, is that patients are sent to us for an assessment only. An assessment means to create an alliance (between the therapist and the patient) and start planning how patient and therapist can work together, during a treatment. (therapist, PHCC2).</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td rowspan="2">Positive experiences facilitate a new habit</td>
       <td rowspan="2"/>
       <td>Q21. I began to refer patients that did not fulfil the criteria of the MINI-study as well (FP 3, PHCC1).</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Q22. … and when I have done it once, the doctors understand that they can use me again. So, then they have referred more patients and I have done many more assessments than those included in the study (therapist, PHCC1).</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td rowspan="2">Easier to continue working as usual</td>
       <td rowspan="2"/>
       <td>Q23. …many that comes to us for help already have a diagnosis from somewhere else. Then it is easy to accept their diagnosis and continue with treatment. Then there is not much of a diagnostic process, although that does not mean that the original diagnosis is the correct one (FP 2, PHCC2).</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Q24. I don’t think that it is self-evident when you see the patient that this person should be referred (for the MINI in a diagnostic process) – it just keeps rolling (FP 8, PHCC1).</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td colspan="3">The patient perspective</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td rowspan="2">Most patients accept meeting FPs first</td>
       <td rowspan="2"/>
       <td>Q25. If I had the opportunity to choose I had visited the doctor first, after all. Because it feels as if the can place you right […], as I said before, I came for stomach problems and did not think at all that I suffered from depression and anxiety (Patient 11).</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Q26. But I can think that it would be good if the doctor could perform the test (MINI) as fast as possible. And if the doctor considers that you suffer from something like --- or if the test suggests that you suffer from something …then the doctor refers you to a therapist (Patient 19).</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Importance of personality and knowledge</td>
       <td/>
       <td>Q27. It is hard to say who should conduct the test because it depends on background and experience. Maybe the title does not matter much. But the one conducting the test must feel comfortable and understand it. It is not enough to just present the questions and then just fill in “yes” or “no”. Patients might get upset when certain questions are presented, and difficult emotions might come up. So, you have to know how to handle such reactions (Patient 23)</td>
      </tr>
     </tbody>
    </table>
   </div>
  </p>
  <sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Capabilities, psychological</div>
   <sec id="FPar1" class="sec">
    <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">FPs’ competence in terms of knowledge and skills</div>
    <p id="Par36" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Most FPs believed that they had sufficient competence in psychiatry, especially regarding depression, to make adequate clinical judgements without the MINI. However, they perceived that the MINI could offer extra help with complicated patients, which usually were referred to therapists (Q1, Table 
     <a rid="Tab5" ref-type="table" href="#Tab5">5</a>). Some FPs expressed that their diagnostic knowledge and skills were insufficient due to too little training or experience. These FPs referred patients more broadly, including those with less complicated situations.
    </p>
    <p id="Par37" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The patients often expressed that FPs had insufficient competence in psychiatry. Some of them anticipated that psychiatry was not a part of the FPs’ education. Therefore, according to them, psychiatry was not the business of the FP but for therapists with their education in psychology. Referral was thus seen as natural from the patients’ perspectives (Q2, Table 
     <a rid="Tab5" ref-type="table" href="#Tab5">5</a>).
    </p>
    <p id="Par38" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Furthermore, FPs’ communication of the purpose of the MINI was described as a skill that could influence the patients’ motivation to be referred. Both patients and therapists provided examples where lacking or unclear information from the FP had made the patient feel unsafe or disinterested in the referral (Q3, Table 
     <a rid="Tab5" ref-type="table" href="#Tab5">5</a>) For patients, the consultation style could be problematic. The FP took over the agenda and did not give the patients the opportunity to talk as they had wanted to (Q4, Table 
     <a rid="Tab5" ref-type="table" href="#Tab5">5</a>). Other patients felt that the FPs concentrated on somatic problems instead of trying to find out what was really distressing them. In addition, at PHCC1, the competence of the FP influenced the feedback of the MINI results from the therapist to the FP. The therapist felt that a discussion was especially important for inexperienced FPs.
    </p>
   </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec11" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Opportunities, physical</div>
   <sec id="FPar2" class="sec">
    <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The priorities of the management</div>
    <p id="Par39" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The priorities of the management of the two PHCCs differed and influenced the process. At PHCC1, the manager encouraged the study and the referral process. She/he was interested in the results and in whether these results would suggest a decision to change routines. The therapist was given time for the assessment, which resulted in easy access to the therapist. At PHCC2, the management at that time introduced a new patient record system, which was given high priority. The FPs got less time to assess complicated psychological symptomatology, which contributed to increased referrals.</p>
    <p id="Par40" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
     <div class="disp-quote">
      <p id="Par41">
       <span class="italic">‘Initially, I wanted to conduct the MINI myself and make my own judgements. Now, I have less time and closer to the therapists, so I feel that we could at least share the burden’</span> (FP 3, PHCC2).
      </p>
     </div>
    </p>
    <p id="Par42" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Feedback discussions of the MINI results were hampered by a lack of supportive routines as expressed by FPs and therapists. At PHCC1, the FPs had no time allocated for feedback discussions, which annoyed them. At PHCC2, no policies were in place concerning communication between FPs and therapists. Thus, discussions were few and ad hoc. For both PHCCs, communication tended to take place in the lunch room or during short breaks between patients, which was seen as not acceptable (Q5, Q6, Table 
     <a rid="Tab5" ref-type="table" href="#Tab5">5</a>).
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec id="d29e1256" class="sec">
    <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Limited time for FPs’ assessment</div>
    <p id="Par43" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All respondent groups perceived that the FPs’ consultation times were insufficient for dealing with undetermined psychological symptoms (Q7, Table 
     <a rid="Tab5" ref-type="table" href="#Tab5">5</a>). This was even more problematic when psychological symptoms were not the reasons given for a visit. As expressed by an FP:
     <div class="disp-quote">
      <p id="Par44">
       <span class="italic">‘I often experience that patients test us. They visit for something else, like acne, but you feel that they are not focused on the problem. They want to see if they can trust you and then, at the end of the consultation, they bring up that they have felt moody for a long time’</span> (FP 1, PHCC2).
      </p>
     </div>
    </p>
    <p id="Par45" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The patients experienced that short consultations led to frustrated FPs who already had the next patient in mind and thus did not listen to them thoroughly (Q8, Table 
     <a rid="Tab5" ref-type="table" href="#Tab5">5</a>).
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec id="FPar3" class="sec">
    <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Easy access to a therapist</div>
    <p id="Par46" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Short waiting times for a visit with a therapist supported referral at both PHCCs (Q9, Table 
     <a rid="Tab5" ref-type="table" href="#Tab5">5</a>). The FPs emphasised that short waiting times were essential for avoiding the delay of treatment.
    </p>
   </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec13" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Opportunities, social</div>
   <sec id="FPar4" class="sec">
    <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Patient characteristics can be a barrier</div>
    <p id="Par47" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The FPs perceived that some patients were not keen on being referred for a MINI assessment (Q10, Table 
     <a rid="Tab5" ref-type="table" href="#Tab5">5</a>) Some patients did not believe that they had a mental problem, others with longstanding problems did not want an extra visit to the PHCC. Such patients were not referred to the therapist at PHCC1, as the FPs did not want to persuade patients.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec id="FPar5" class="sec">
    <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Process facilitator or change agent available</div>
    <p id="Par48" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">At PHCC1, the therapist spontaneously assumed the responsibility of acting as a facilitator. Initially, the FPs forgot to refer patients, and the therapist sent reminders. The FPs appreciated this and increased their referrals. The therapist also took every opportunity to share the MINI results with the FP orally, as recommended in the guidance for the study (Q11, Q12, Table 
     <a rid="Tab5" ref-type="table" href="#Tab5">5</a>).
    </p>
   </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec14" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Motivation, reflective</div>
   <sec id="FPar6" class="sec">
    <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Referral facilitates the work of the FP</div>
    <p id="Par49" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">According to all respondent groups, the diagnostic process saved the FPs’ time and effort (Q13, Q14, Table 
     <a rid="Tab5" ref-type="table" href="#Tab5">5</a>) The FPs compared the process with referrals for somatic problems, e.g. spirometry, that specialised asthma nurses performed. FPs at PHCC1 expressed that psychiatric problems should be handled in the same way and appreciated the diagnostic process.
    </p>
    <p id="Par50" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another advantage was that the therapists could offer the patients a more comforting atmosphere and more time for reflection and building confidence than what was possible during an FP consultation, according to the respondent groups at PHCC1. As a result, the patient could provide more well-grounded information, which the FPs at PHCC1 saw as a benefit (Q15, Table 
     <a rid="Tab5" ref-type="table" href="#Tab5">5</a>).
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec id="FPar7" class="sec">
    <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Collaboration on diagnosis can improve patient management</div>
    <p id="Par51" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All respondent groups agreed that an inter-professional diagnostic process could provide benefits to the patient (Q16, Q17, Table 
     <a rid="Tab5" ref-type="table" href="#Tab5">5</a>). The patients expressed that a major benefit was that the assessment was made from both a medical and a psychological perspective (Q18, Table 
     <a rid="Tab5" ref-type="table" href="#Tab5">5</a>).
    </p>
    <p id="Par52" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">At PHCC1, such cooperation was established to a varying degree. The therapist presented the results, and often the FP and the therapist discussed how to proceed with the patient. This included treatment options as well as whether the patient needed referral to psychiatry. However, some FPs preferred to ponder the results and did not involve the therapist in the treatment choice.</p>
    <p id="Par53" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">At PHCC2, minimal collaboration took place between FPs and therapists, except for when a therapist judged that a patient needed referral to psychiatry. In these cases, the therapist prepared the referral documents. Often, the therapist said that the FP just signed them without further discussion. However, the therapists and the FPs noted that feedback on decisions could be valuable, e.g. in the form of a short meeting. According to them, patients could feel confused by the perceived different messages from the FP and the therapist. Some patients confirmed this as well.</p>
   </sec>
   <sec id="FPar8" class="sec">
    <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Beliefs about professional roles</div>
    <p id="Par54" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Beliefs about professional roles affected the motivation for referral and feedback discussions. At PHCC1, the inter-professional process did not interfere with existing roles. The FP maintained the patient responsibility, including decisions to refer patients for CBT. A discussion on results and actions to be taken was seen as rewarding among both FPs and therapist.</p>
    <p id="Par55" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The therapist perceived increased competence with the new task. Furthermore, becoming more familiar with the MINI, the therapist took her own initiatives, using the MINI for non-assessed patients where the referral form seemed vague and then communicating the results to the FP.</p>
    <p id="Par56" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">At PHCC2, neither the FPs nor the therapists appreciated the concept of referral for MINI assessment only, albeit for different reasons. The FPs trusted their own assessment skills and felt that they would miss important non-verbal information required for their own diagnostic work if a therapist made the assessment (Q19, Table 
     <a rid="Tab5" ref-type="table" href="#Tab5">5</a>). For the therapists, the diagnostic process was seen as part of creating an alliance and a treatment plan with the patient and thus as an important part of their work. Assisting FPs in their diagnoses was not seen as part of their duties, and furthermore, they did not trust the FPs’ ability to interpret the results from the MINI (Q20, Table 
     <a rid="Tab5" ref-type="table" href="#Tab5">5</a>).
    </p>
   </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec15" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Motivation, automatic</div>
   <sec id="FPar9" class="sec">
    <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Positive experiences facilitate a new habit</div>
    <p id="Par57" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Some FPs at PHCC1, as told by the FPs and the therapist, changed their habits. They had positive experiences with their first patients and increased their referrals, widening to patients who were outside the scope of this study, e.g. patients with suspected eating disorders (Q21, Q22, Table 
     <a rid="Tab5" ref-type="table" href="#Tab5">5</a>). However, others lost interest in the referral when some patients declined the offered assessment.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec id="FPar10" class="sec">
    <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Easier to continue working as usual</div>
    <p id="Par58" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The urge to continue working according to established routines was a strong factor against referral, according to the FPs (Q23, Q24, Table 
     <a rid="Tab5" ref-type="table" href="#Tab5">5</a>). It did not matter that they were aware that referrals were useful.
    </p>
    <p id="Par59" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The FPs also expressed that, for patients who already had been diagnosed elsewhere, it was easier to accept the diagnoses and initiate treatment, even though these diagnoses might not be the correct ones.</p>
   </sec>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec16" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The patient perspective</div>
  <p id="Par60" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Patients expressed perceptions that did not directly influence the referral process but were relevant in understanding the perceptions of this process. These concerned their first visits to FPs and the profession they considered were best suited for conducting MINI assessments.</p>
  <sec id="Sec17" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Most patients accept meeting FPs first</div>
   <p id="Par61" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Many patients were satisfied with meeting FPs first and then being referred to therapists for assessment (Q25, Q26, Table 
    <a rid="Tab5" ref-type="table" href="#Tab5">5</a>). If they were dissatisfied, it most often was related to mistrust, of either the FPs or the therapists, rather than to the referral procedure. Some patients, though, found the FP visits to be unnecessary. They perceived that they already knew their problems and wanted psychological treatment immediately. They saw the FP visits as a formality without any clear benefit. Others wanted to shorten the time to treatment and suggested that the FP could conduct the MINI during the visit rather than referring the patient to a therapist.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec18" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Importance of personality and knowledge</div>
   <p id="Par62" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Even if a patient appreciated a referral to a therapist, it was not self-evident that the therapist was the most appropriate for conducting the MINI. The profession itself was not regarded as crucial. The personality, knowledge and experience of the person conducting the MINI interview played a more important role (Q27, Table 
    <a rid="Tab5" ref-type="table" href="#Tab5">5</a>). The interviewer should, for example, be familiar with any unwanted emotions during the MINI and know how to handle them. Some patients were confident that their FPs could conduct MINIs effectively. Others were indifferent and perceived that it did not matter whether an FP or a therapist conducted the MINI; they would accept both.
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
</sec>
