<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName archivearticle3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Ecol Evol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Ecol Evol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.1002/(ISSN)2045-7758</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ECE3</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Ecology and Evolution</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-7758</issn><publisher><publisher-name>John Wiley and Sons Inc.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Hoboken</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5395435</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ece3.2892</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ECE32892</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Are whooping cranes destined for extinction? Climate change imperils recruitment and population growth</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="ece32892-cr-0001" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Butler</surname><given-names>Matthew J.</given-names></name><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9864-803X</contrib-id><address><email>matthew_butler@fws.gov</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="ece32892-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="ece32892-cr-0002" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Metzger</surname><given-names>Kristine L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="ece32892-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="ece32892-cr-0003" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>Grant M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="ece32892-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="ece32892-aff-0001"><label><sup>1</sup></label><named-content content-type="organisation-division">Division of Biological Services</named-content><institution>U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service</institution><named-content content-type="city">Albuquerque</named-content><named-content content-type="country-part">NM</named-content><country country="US">USA</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="correspondenceTo"><label>*</label><bold>Correspondence</bold><break/>
Matthew J. Butler, Division of Biological Services, U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service, Albuquerque, NM, USA.<break/>
Email: <email>matthew_butler@fws.gov</email><break/></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>21</day><month>3</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>4</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>8</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ece3.2017.7.issue-8</issue-id><fpage>2821</fpage><lpage>2834</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>21</day><month>9</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>26</day><month>1</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>1</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><!--<copyright-statement content-type="issue-copyright"> &#x000a9; 2017 Published by John Wiley & Sons Ltd. <copyright-statement>--><copyright-statement content-type="article-copyright">Published 2017. This article is a U.S. Government work and is in the public domain in the USA. <italic>Ecology and Evolution</italic> published by John Wiley &#x00026; Sons Ltd.</copyright-statement><license license-type="creativeCommonsBy"><license-p>This is an open access article under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution</ext-link> License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="file:ECE3-7-2821.pdf"/><abstract id="ece32892-abs-0001"><title>Summary</title><p>Identifying climatic drivers of an animal population's vital rates and locating where they operate steers conservation efforts to optimize species recovery. The population growth of endangered whooping cranes (<italic>Grus americana</italic>) hinges on juvenile recruitment. Therefore, we identify climatic drivers (solar activity [sunspots] and weather) of whooping crane recruitment throughout the species&#x02019; life cycle (breeding, migration, wintering). Our method uses a repeated cross&#x02010;validated absolute shrinkage and selection operator approach to identify drivers of recruitment. We model effects of climate change on those drivers to predict whooping crane population growth given alternative scenarios of climate change and solar activity. Years with fewer sunspots indicated greater recruitment. Increased precipitation during autumn migration signified less recruitment. On the breeding grounds, fewer days below freezing during winter and more precipitation during breeding suggested less recruitment. We predicted whooping crane recruitment and population growth may fall below long&#x02010;term averages during all solar cycles when atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> concentration increases, as expected, to 500&#x000a0;ppm by 2050. Species recovery during a typical solar cycle with 500&#x000a0;ppm may require eight times longer than conditions without climate change and the chance of population decline increases to 31%. Although this whooping crane population is growing and may appear secure, long&#x02010;term threats imposed by climate change and increased solar activity may jeopardize its persistence. Weather on the breeding grounds likely affects recruitment through hydrological processes and predation risk, whereas precipitation during autumn migration may influence juvenile mortality. Mitigating threats or abating climate change should occur within &#x02248;30&#x000a0;years or this wild population of whooping cranes may begin declining.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-generated"><kwd id="ece32892-kwd-0001">atmospheric <styled-content style="fixed-case">CO</styled-content><sub>2</sub></kwd><kwd id="ece32892-kwd-0002">boreal pond</kwd><kwd id="ece32892-kwd-0003">decadal cycle</kwd><kwd id="ece32892-kwd-0004">groundwater</kwd><kwd id="ece32892-kwd-0005"><styled-content style="fixed-case">LASSO</styled-content></kwd><kwd id="ece32892-kwd-0006">precipitation</kwd><kwd id="ece32892-kwd-0007">reproduction</kwd><kwd id="ece32892-kwd-0008">solar activity</kwd><kwd id="ece32892-kwd-0009">sunspots</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="6"/><table-count count="3"/><page-count count="16"/><word-count count="10080"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>source-schema-version-number</meta-name><meta-value>2.0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>component-id</meta-name><meta-value>ece32892</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>April 2017</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>details-of-publishers-convertor</meta-name><meta-value>Converter:WILEY_ML3GV2_TO_NLMPMC version:5.0.9 mode:remove_FC converted:18.04.2017</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><p content-type="self-citation">
<mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32892-cit-1001">
<string-name>
<surname>Butler</surname>
<given-names>MJ</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Metzger</surname>
<given-names>KL</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Harris</surname>
<given-names>GM</given-names>
</string-name>. <article-title>Are whooping cranes destined for extinction? Climate change imperils recruitment and population growth</article-title>. <source>Ecol Evol</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>2821</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2834</lpage>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1002/ece3.2892">https://doi.org/10.1002/ece3.2892</ext-link>
</mixed-citation>
</p></notes></front><body><sec id="ece32892-sec-0001"><label>1</label><title>Introduction</title><p>Identifying drivers of animal population demographics (i.e., associations between environmental conditions and vital rates) and locating where they operate is necessary for steering efforts to optimize wildlife species management and conservation (e.g., Caughley, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">1994</xref>; Mills, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0036" ref-type="ref">2007</xref>). Doing so establishes a foundation to evaluate how climate change may impact an animal's population growth and vulnerability (Brook et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0002" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>). This information is especially critical for recovering species endangered with extinction (Ak&#x000e7;akaya, Butchart, Watson, &#x00026; Pearson, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0001" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>). Herein, we focus on the population growth of endangered whooping cranes (<italic>Grus americana</italic>), which hinges on recruitment (Butler, Metzger, &#x00026; Harris, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>).</p><p>Our aims were to model associations between whooping crane recruitment and environmental conditions, examine how climate change affects those conditions, and translate those effects to population growth. Our work reveals the climatic threats on the species and where they operate, it predicts the prospects for species recovery, and helps develop hypotheses about how climate drivers act on whooping crane demographics and where management intervention would be most effective. We demonstrate that although the wild whooping crane population is growing and therefore may appear secure (Butler, Harris, &#x00026; Strobel, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>), long&#x02010;term threats imposed by climate change jeopardize this population's persistence (Carroll, Townshend, DiMiceli, Loboda, &#x00026; Sohlberg, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0008" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>; Chavez&#x02010;Ramirez &#x00026; Wehtje, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>; Smith, Sheng, MacDonald, &#x00026; Hinzman, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0048" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>).</p><p>In North America, whooping cranes breed in the boreal ecosystem of Canada (Canadian Wildlife Service [CWS] &#x00026; U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service [USFWS], <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">2007</xref>; Kuyt, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">1995</xref>). Here, one of the most studied biological phenomena is the approximate decadal cycles of snowshoe hare (<italic>Lepus americanus</italic>) and lynx (<italic>Lynx canadensis</italic>; Krebs, Boonstra, Boutin, &#x00026; Sinclair, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0022" ref-type="ref">2001</xref>). This decadal cycle is well documented in other species (Klvana, Berteaux, &#x00026; Cazelles, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0020" ref-type="ref">2004</xref>; Marques, Short, &#x00026; Creed, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0032" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>; Sel&#x000e5;s, Hogstad, Kobro, &#x00026; Rafoss, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0045" ref-type="ref">2004</xref>; Sinclair &#x00026; Gosline, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0047" ref-type="ref">1997</xref>), occurs in whooping crane demographics (Butler et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>), and appears in ground&#x02010; and surface water levels of the whooping crane breeding grounds (Gibson, Prowse, &#x00026; Peters, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">2006</xref>; McNaughton, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0033" ref-type="ref">1991</xref>; Timoney, Zoltai, &#x00026; Goldsborough, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0054" ref-type="ref">1997</xref>). Recent work confirms that the lynx cycle is inversely correlated with whooping crane fledging rate (Wilson, Gil&#x02010;Weir, Clark, Robertson, &#x00026; Bidwell, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0056" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>), while fledgling rate influences recruitment and ultimately whooping crane recovery. Correlation between solar irradiance (Krivova, Vieira, &#x00026; Solanki, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0023" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>), as measured by the number of sunspots, to mammal abundance is also apparent (Sinclair &#x00026; Gosline, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0047" ref-type="ref">1997</xref>). While the proximal regulator of population cycles in boreal species remains unclear, the relationship likely involves complex interactions among food supply, predator abundance, weather patterns and hydrology, which may be influenced by the solar cycle (Krebs &#x00026; Berteaux, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0021" ref-type="ref">2006</xref>; Krebs et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0022" ref-type="ref">2001</xref>; Rind, Lean, Lerner, Lonergan, &#x00026; Leboissetier, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0041" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>; Sinclair &#x00026; Gosline, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0047" ref-type="ref">1997</xref>).</p><p>Given that the approximate decadal population cycle observed in many boreal species appears mediated through climate processes (Scott &#x00026; Craine, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0044" ref-type="ref">1993</xref>; Yan, Stenseth, Krebs, &#x00026; Zhang, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0057" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>), we examined whether and how global climate change may influence whooping crane demographics. Climatic changes may affect whooping crane recruitment through direct (i.e., increases in predator densities) or complex indirect interactions. For example, whooping cranes build nests in shallow lakes and ponds of the taiga to deter predation (Kuyt, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">1995</xref>; Kuyt, Barry, &#x00026; Johns, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0026" ref-type="ref">1992</xref>; Timoney et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0054" ref-type="ref">1997</xref>). Climate change is reducing the amount of surface water and likely the depth and seasonal longevity of these ponds (Carroll et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0008" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>; Smith et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0048" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>). Fewer, shallower, and more ephemeral ponds failing to persist through the entire nesting period may increase nest predation, thereby reducing recruitment of juveniles (Timoney et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0054" ref-type="ref">1997</xref>).</p><p>Other factors outside of the breeding grounds may also affect whooping crane recruitment as it represents a combination of several demographic parameters (e.g., breeding propensity, clutch size, hatch and fledge rates, and juvenile survival during migration). Reproduction by adults can be supported using stored resources (known as capital breeding) or via the uptake of resources concomitant to a reproductive attempt (known as income breeding; Stephens, Boyd, McNamara, &#x00026; Houston, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0051" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>). If a capital breeding strategy is employed by whooping cranes, weather conditions prior to their departure to the breeding grounds may affect breeding propensity and nest success. Alternatively, juveniles may be influenced by conditions encountered during southern migration (e.g., inclement weather, food quality, and quantity) that could reduce their survival and subsequently affect their recruitment into the winter flock.</p><p>We examined environmental drivers of whooping crane recruitment by modeling it as a function of solar, weather, and hydrological factors spanning all portions of its life cycle (breeding, wintering, and migration). On the breeding grounds, these models examined associations of recruitment with the solar cycle and winter temperature and precipitation. For the wintering grounds, models included drought conditions and freshwater balance of estuaries, as these factors may limit food production (Butler et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>). During the spring and fall migrations, models evaluated temperature, precipitation and drought, as each affects food availability and production, and inclement weather may increase juvenile mortality during southern migration (Kuyt, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0024" ref-type="ref">1992</xref>).</p><p>We predicted the potential impact of climate change on whooping crane recruitment and population growth for future scenarios, by linking the primary drivers of recruitment with atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations (elevated concentrations are indicative of climate warming) and the solar cycle. Scenarios of atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> concentration consisted of the 2015 concentration (&#x02248;400&#x000a0;ppm) and the predicted 2050 concentration (&#x02248;500&#x000a0;ppm; Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change [IPCC], <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0016" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>). The solar cycle scenarios were the modern grand maximum (1954&#x02013;1964), the Dalton minimum (1811&#x02013;1821), and a typical cycle. This procedure reveals how climate change may affect the whooping crane population's dynamics through 2050, provides expectations for species recovery, and indicates where management intervention would likely be most effective.</p></sec><sec id="ece32892-sec-0002"><label>2</label><title>Material and Methods</title><sec id="ece32892-sec-0003"><label>2.1</label><title>Breeding grounds, wintering grounds, and migratory route</title><p>Only one wild, migratory population of whooping cranes exists. It breeds on and around Wood Buffalo National Park, Alberta, and Northwest Territories, Canada, and overwinters along the Gulf of Mexico centered on Aransas National Wildlife Refuge (NWR), Texas, USA (&#x02248;4,000&#x000a0;km migration, one way; CWS &#x00026; USFWS, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">2007</xref>; Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). This population is growing, yet small (&#x02248;340 birds), range restricted, and therefore considered endangered with extinction (Butler et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>; CWS &#x00026; USFWS, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">2007</xref>).</p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece32892-fig-0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Migratory route of whooping cranes in North America. The breeding grounds are on and around Wood Buffalo National Park, Canada, and the wintering grounds are on and around Aransas National Wildlife Refuge, Texas, USA</p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-3" xlink:href="ECE3-7-2821-g001"/></fig><p>Whooping cranes arrive on their wintering grounds surrounding Aransas NWR beginning in October and depart by late April. Their migratory route leads north through central Texas, Oklahoma, Kansas, and Nebraska into western South Dakota and North Dakota to the USA&#x02013;Canada border (Kuyt, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0024" ref-type="ref">1992</xref>). Their migratory route continues north&#x02010;northwest across Saskatchewan to Alberta and then north to Wood Buffalo National Park (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>; Kuyt, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0024" ref-type="ref">1992</xref>).</p><p>Whooping cranes begin arriving on their breeding grounds by late April, and their nests are initiated by mid&#x02010;May (Kuyt, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">1995</xref>). Whooping cranes build their nests in shallow boreal ponds or lakes by constructing a mound of mud and vegetation in open water or placing it among clumps of brush on natural islets (Kuyt, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">1995</xref>; Kuyt et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0026" ref-type="ref">1992</xref>; Timoney et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0054" ref-type="ref">1997</xref>). Whooping cranes, along with the young of the year, depart the breeding grounds starting in mid&#x02010;September and follow the same migratory route south to the Texas coast (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>; Kuyt, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0024" ref-type="ref">1992</xref>). During the autumn migration, central Saskatchewan appears to be a staging area in which whooping cranes congregate and forage on waste grain during late September to mid&#x02010;October (Johns, Woodsworth, &#x00026; Driver, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0018" ref-type="ref">1997</xref>). Once whooping cranes depart the staging grounds in central Saskatchewan, southern migration across the USA can be as short as 1&#x000a0;week with delays occurring due to low&#x02010;pressure weather systems (Kuyt, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0024" ref-type="ref">1992</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="ece32892-sec-0004"><label>2.2</label><title>Aerial surveys</title><p>Annual, repeated aerial surveys of whooping cranes have been conducted by USFWS personnel on the wintering grounds between October and May since 1950 (Butler, Strobel, &#x00026; Eichhorn, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>; Strobel &#x00026; Butler, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0052" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>). The survey has been primarily conducted from a fixed&#x02010;wing aircraft with transects spaced approximately 250&#x02013;800&#x000a0;m apart (Butler et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>). The number of surveys conducted each winter between December 1 and March 31 has ranged from 4 to 21 (Butler et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>). This survey produced counts of total winter abundance and number of juvenile birds recruited plus estimates of annual mortality (Butler et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="ece32892-sec-0005"><label>2.3</label><title>Possible predictors of recruitment</title><p>As indicators of weather conditions on the wintering grounds, we obtained monthly values of the Palmer drought indices for Texas Climatological Division 7 (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>; Palmer, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0038" ref-type="ref">1965</xref>; National Climatic Data Center [NCDC] <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0037" ref-type="ref">2007</xref>). For each of the Palmer indices, we averaged the months of November&#x02013;March of each year. We obtained monthly freshwater balance (i.e., balance&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;inflow&#x000a0;&#x02212;&#x000a0;evaporation&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;precipitation) for the Guadalupe and Mission&#x02010;Aransas estuaries (Guthrie &#x00026; Lu, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0014" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>; Schoenbaechler, Guthrie, &#x00026; Lu, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0043" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>). For both estuaries, we summed the months of November&#x02013;March of each year and scaled estimates to 1 million acre&#x02010;feet. The Aransas&#x02010;Wood Buffalo whooping crane population overwinters along both estuaries, so we also combined freshwater balance for them. As environmental conditions on the wintering grounds may affect whooping crane body condition and therefore reproduction once birds return to the breeding grounds (i.e., capital breeding; Stephens et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0051" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>), we lagged the wintering ground variables by 1&#x000a0;year (e.g., drought indices from November 1950&#x02013;March 1951 were paired with recruitment during winter 1951&#x02013;1952).</p><p>We divided the migratory route into two primary areas: northern U.S. Great Plains and southern Saskatchewan prairies. We obtained monthly values for the Palmer drought indices for Nebraska Climatological Divisions 2&#x02013;9, South Dakota Climatological Divisions 2&#x02013;3 and 6&#x02013;9, and North Dakota Climatological Divisions 1&#x02013;2, 4&#x02013;5, and 8&#x02013;9 (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>; Palmer, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0038" ref-type="ref">1965</xref>; NCDC <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0037" ref-type="ref">2007</xref>), as indicators of climatic conditions on the northern U.S. Great Plains. For each of the Palmer indices, we averaged data from the Climatological Divisions across months for the spring migration period (i.e., April) and autumn migration period (i.e., October&#x02013;November).</p><p>We used the proportion of days in which the maximum temperature remained below freezing (i.e., &#x02264;0&#x000b0;C), the proportion of days in which minimum temperature was below freezing, mean temperature, and the total precipitation obtained from three Global Historical Climatology Network (GHCN) stations (i.e., Regina University, CA004016640; Saskatoon Airport, CA004057120; and Muenster, CA004015440) located across the southern Saskatchewan prairies (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). All three of these stations had a complete record from 1950&#x02013;2010 and covered the southern and northern portions of the migratory route through the southern Saskatchewan prairies. Data were pooled across the three stations and months for the spring (i.e., April) and autumn migration periods (i.e., September&#x02013;October).</p><p>Few long&#x02010;term GHCN stations exist in the vicinity of Wood Buffalo National Park and the whooping crane's breeding grounds. We obtained weather data (same measures used for southern Saskatchewan prairies) from the GHCN station at Fort Smith, Northwest Territories, Canada (CA002202200), the station closest to the breeding grounds (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). For the breeding grounds, we also considered two periods as potentially important to recruitment: winter (November&#x02013;March) and breeding (April&#x02013;September). We considered the winter prior to arrival because surface water conditions in breeding ponds may be affected by winter weather (Yoshikawa &#x00026; Hinzman, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0058" ref-type="ref">2003</xref>).</p><p>The solar cycle has been implicated as a potential factor in the cyclic population dynamics of lynx, snowshoe hare, and other organisms (Klvana et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0020" ref-type="ref">2004</xref>; Krebs et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0022" ref-type="ref">2001</xref>; Marques, Short, et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0032" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>; Sel&#x000e5;s et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0045" ref-type="ref">2004</xref>). Sunspots are a long&#x02010;term indicator of total solar irradiance (Krivova et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0023" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>), so we obtained the annual sunspot number from the Royal Observatory of Belgium (SILSO World Data Center <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0046" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>). We used year as a predictor to investigate trends in recruitment.</p></sec><sec id="ece32892-sec-0006"><label>2.4</label><title>Addressing bias in recruitment estimates</title><p>We suspected recruitment estimates may have been biased high during years with fewer surveys (similar biases occurred with winter mortality estimates; Butler et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>). We examined recruitment estimates for this potential bias by regressing recruitment and the number of surveys conducted during a winter between December 1 and March 31 (logistic regression). If unbiased, recruitment estimates should not be associated with the number of surveys. However, if an inverse relationship between recruitment and the number surveys exists, it indicates some adults are missed when the number of surveys is small. For example, detection of a whooping crane group was estimated as 55.8% (Strobel &#x00026; Butler, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0052" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>) which means the cumulative detection probably does not exceed 99% until six surveys are completed. Therefore, estimates of recruitment are likely biased high during years in which the number of surveys conducted was less than six. We removed those potentially biased years and reexamined the association between recruitment and the number of surveys conducted.</p></sec><sec id="ece32892-sec-0007"><label>2.5</label><title>Modeling recruitment and survival with LASSO</title><p>We modeled recruitment (i.e., proportion of juvenile whooping cranes in the total population count for each winter) as a function of the predictor variables described above (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-tbl-0001" ref-type="table-wrap">1</xref>), many of which were collinear, using logistic regression. To select the model, we used the least absolute shrinkage and selection operator (LASSO), a statistical regularization technique (i.e., procedure for balancing model fit and complexity) appropriate for model selection when a relatively large set of possibly collinear predictor variables are used (Gerber, Kendall, Hooten, Dubovsky, &#x00026; Drewin, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>; Tibshirani, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0053" ref-type="ref">1996</xref>). Unlike other statistical regularization techniques (i.e., ridge regression), LASSO regression allows some effects to be exactly zero which results in a more easily interpretable model, because the number of predictors is reduced (Reineking &#x00026; Schr&#x000f6;der, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0040" ref-type="ref">2006</xref>; Tibshirani, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0053" ref-type="ref">1996</xref>). In LASSO regression, the balance between model fit and complexity is achieved through the parameter lambda.</p><table-wrap id="ece32892-tbl-0001" xml:lang="en" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Variables used to model recruitment of juvenile whooping cranes into the winter population</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><thead valign="top"><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable<xref ref-type="fn" rid="ece32892-note-0001">a</xref>
</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Global</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SSN</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Annual sunspot number</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TIME</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sequence of 1 to 61 indicating an annual time step</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SURVEYS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of aerial surveys conducted between 1 December and 31 March</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Wintering Grounds</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PDSI.ANWR.1103</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean Palmer drought severity index for November&#x02013;March on Texas Coast</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PHDI.ANWR.1103</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean Palmer hydrological drought index for November&#x02013;March on Texas Coast</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PMDI.ANWR.1103</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean modified Palmer drought severity index for November&#x02013;March on Texas Coast</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZNDX.ANWR.1103</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean Palmer Z index for November&#x02013;March on Texas Coast</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GEFB.ANWR.1103</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total Guadalupe Estuary freshwater balance for November&#x02013;March</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MAEFB.ANWR.1103</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total Mission&#x02010;Aransas Estuary freshwater balance for November&#x02013;March</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CoEFB.ANWR.1103</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total combined estuary freshwater balance for November&#x02013;March</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Spring migration</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PDSI.NEDA.04</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean Palmer drought severity index for April in northern U.S. Great Plains</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PHDI.NEDA.04</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean Palmer hydrological drought index for April in northern U.S. Great Plains</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PMDI.NEDA.04</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean modified Palmer drought severity index for April in northern U.S. Great Plains</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZNDX.NEDA.04</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean Palmer Z index for April in northern U.S. Great Plains</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TPCP.SASK.04</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total precipitation (cm) in southern Saskatchewan prairie during April</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DT32.SASK.04</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion of days during April in southern Saskatchewan prairie with minimum temperature &#x02264;0&#x000b0;C</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DX32.SASK.04</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion of days during April in southern Saskatchewan prairie with maximum temperature &#x02264;0&#x000b0;C</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MNTM.SASK.04</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean temperature (F&#x000b0;) during April in southern Saskatchewan prairie</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Breeding grounds</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TPCP.WBNP.1103</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total precipitation (cm) during November&#x02013;March in Wood Buffalo National Park</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DT32.WBNP.1103</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion of days during November&#x02013;March in Wood Buffalo National Park with minimum temperature &#x02264;0&#x000b0;C</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DX32.WBNP.1103</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion of days during November&#x02013;March in Wood Buffalo National Park with maximum temperature &#x02264;0&#x000b0;C</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MNTM.WBNP.1103</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean temperature (F&#x000b0;) during November&#x02013;March in Wood Buffalo National Park</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TPCP.WBNP.0409</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total precipitation (cm) during April&#x02013;September in Wood Buffalo National Park</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DT32.WBNP.0409</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion of days during April&#x02013;September in Wood Buffalo National Park with minimum temperature &#x02264;0&#x000b0;C</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DX32.WBNP.0409</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion of days during April&#x02013;September in Wood Buffalo National Park with maximum temperature &#x02264;0&#x000b0;C</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MNTM.WBNP.0409</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean temperature (F&#x000b0;) during April&#x02013;September in Wood Buffalo National Park</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">Autumn migration</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PDSI.NEDA.1011</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean Palmer drought severity index for October&#x02013;November in northern U.S. Great Plains</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PHDI.NEDA.1011</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean Palmer hydrological drought index for October&#x02013;November in northern U.S. Great Plains</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PMDI.NEDA.1011</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean modified Palmer drought severity index for October&#x02013;November in northern U.S. Great Plains</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZNDX.NEDA.1011</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean Palmer Z index for October&#x02013;November in northern U.S. Great Plains</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TPCP.SASK.0910</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total precipitation (cm) in southern Saskatchewan prairie during September&#x02013;October</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DT32.SASK.0910</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion of days during September&#x02013;October in southern Saskatchewan prairie with minimum temperature &#x02264;0&#x000b0;C</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DX32.SASK.0910</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion of days during September&#x02013;October in southern Saskatchewan prairie with maximum temperature &#x02264;0&#x000b0;C</td></tr><tr><td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">MNTM.SASK.0910</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean temperature (F&#x000b0;) in southern Saskatchewan prairie during September&#x02013;October</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="ece32892-note-0001"><label>a</label><p>The first four letters of each variable's name represent the weather index and follow the standard acronym used if available. The second four letters are acronyms for location (e.g., ANWR&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;Aransas National Wildlife Refuge, WBNP&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;Wood Buffalo National Park, SASK&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;Saskatchewan, NEDA&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;Nebraska and the Dakotas). The four numbers indicate the range of months the variable includes (e.g., 1103 represents November&#x02013;March).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap><p>We used the glmnet package (Friedman, Hastie, &#x00026; Tibshirani, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>; Hastie &#x00026; Qian, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0015" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>) in program R (R Core Team <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0039" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>) to conduct the analysis. We used the cv.glmnet function to preform tenfold cross&#x02010;validation to select the optimal lambda (i.e., most regularized model whereby the mean cross&#x02010;validated error is within one standard error of the minimum; Hastie &#x00026; Qian, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0015" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>). As the folds used in cross&#x02010;validation are selected randomly, we repeated the cross&#x02010;validation procedure 1,000 times to characterize the uncertainty in lambda and the model coefficients. We also calculated the proportion of repeats in which a predictor variable was selected.</p><p>We conducted the repeated cross&#x02010;validated LASSO procedure described above for survival as well. We estimated annual whooping crane survival (<mml:math id="nlm-math-1"><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math>) as <mml:math id="nlm-math-2"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">/</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math>, where <mml:math id="nlm-math-3"><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>N</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:math> was the total abundance during winter <italic>t</italic> and <mml:math id="nlm-math-4"><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>A</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math> was the number of after&#x02010;hatch&#x02010;year birds in the population during winter <italic>t</italic>&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;1 (Butler et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="ece32892-sec-0008"><label>2.6</label><title>Modeling weather variables</title><p>The repeated cross&#x02010;validated LASSO procedure identified the most important weather variables for predicting recruitment. We modeled those weather variables as functions of sunspot number and the natural log of mean annual atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> concentration (&#x003bc;mol of CO<sub>2</sub>/mol [ppm]; Keeling et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">2001</xref>). Simple linear or logistic regression was used depending on the distributional characteristics of each variable. We used data from 1958&#x02013;2014 for these analyses as measurement of the concentration of atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> began in March 1958 (Keeling et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">2001</xref>). By assuming a log&#x02010;linear relationship with CO<sub>2</sub> concentration, we obtain conservative estimates describing the potential magnitude of change.</p></sec><sec id="ece32892-sec-0009"><label>2.7</label><title>Relationships with nesting pond depth</title><p>Kuyt et&#x000a0;al. (<xref rid="ece32892-bib-0026" ref-type="ref">1992</xref>) measured the water depth of whooping crane nesting ponds during late May 1976&#x02013;1991 and reported the annual mean. As surface water conditions in boreal ponds are affected by winter temperature and snow depth (Yoshikawa &#x00026; Hinzman, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0058" ref-type="ref">2003</xref>), we examined these relationships on the whooping crane's breeding grounds. We used simple linear regression to relate mean pond depth to sunspot number and the proportion of freezing days and precipitation on the breeding grounds during November&#x02013;March. We also used logistic regression to examine the relationship between recruitment and pond water depth. This analysis helped explain associations between some of the weather variables and recruitment.</p></sec><sec id="ece32892-sec-0010"><label>2.8</label><title>Population growth, recruitment, survival, and environmental change</title><p>To predict the potential impact of climate change on whooping crane recruitment, we assessed the potential changes in climatic condition for various scenarios of atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> concentration and sunspot number. First, we developed three solar cycle scenarios: one based on the cycle that contained the modern grand maximum (1954&#x02013;1964; min&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;6.6, max&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;269.3), one based on the Dalton minimum (1811&#x02013;1821; min&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;2.3, max&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;76.3), and one based on a typical cycle. To characterize the typical solar cycle, we fit the sunspot number (1712&#x02013;2007) as a polynomial of the number of years since a cycle began. We examined two atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> concentration scenarios: the 2015 concentration of &#x02248;400&#x000a0;ppm and the predicted 2050 concentration of &#x02248;500&#x000a0;ppm (IPCC, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0016" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>). We converted predicted recruitment from a proportion to a ratio by proportion/(1&#x02013; proportion). We estimated predicted population growth (<mml:math id="nlm-math-5"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">&#x003bb;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math>) for each scenario as (<mml:math id="nlm-math-6"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math>) <mml:math id="nlm-math-7"><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math> where <mml:math id="nlm-math-8"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math> is the geometric mean of annual survival and <mml:math id="nlm-math-9"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math> is the predicted ratio of hatch&#x02010;year to after&#x02010;hatch&#x02010;year birds for each scenario (Butler et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>).</p><p>To characterize the uncertainty in predicted recruitment and population growth rate for the climate change scenarios, we implemented a nonparametric bootstrap procedure. Specifically, for each iteration of the repeated cross&#x02010;validated LASSO procedure, we bootstrapped the models for each of the important weather variables and predicted the weather condition for each scenario. We bootstrapped whooping crane annual survival for each iteration of the repeated cross&#x02010;validated LASSO procedure so predicted population growth would incorporate uncertainty and variability in survival and predicted recruitment.</p><p>If management options that directly manipulate recruitment are unavailable, management options may exist to manipulate annual survival. Therefore, we estimated the annual survival (<mml:math id="nlm-math-10"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math>) required to avoid population decline or avoid population growth from falling below average (i.e., <italic>&#x003bb;</italic>&#x000a0;&#x02265;&#x000a0;1.035) for each scenario where <mml:math id="nlm-math-11"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>S</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math> is <mml:math id="nlm-math-12"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo stretchy="false">/</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>R</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math> (Butler et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="ece32892-sec-0011"><label>3</label><title>Results</title><p>The whooping crane population has grown at approximately 3.5% annually (geometric mean, <italic>n&#x000a0;</italic>=<italic>&#x000a0;</italic>61, <italic>SD</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;10.7) since 1950 but varied from &#x02212;19.4% to 33.3%. Using all survey data, recruitment of juvenile birds (<mml:math id="nlm-math-13"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math>; ratio of hatch&#x02010;year to after&#x02010;hatch&#x02010;year birds) into the winter population of whooping cranes ranged from 0 to 0.4 (geometric mean&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.145, <italic>n&#x000a0;</italic>=<italic>&#x000a0;</italic>61, <italic>SD</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.090). Annual whooping crane survival (<mml:math id="nlm-math-14"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi>S</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math>) ranged from 0.645 to 1.0 (geometric mean&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.906, <italic>n&#x000a0;</italic>=<italic>&#x000a0;</italic>60, <italic>SD</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.060).</p><sec id="ece32892-sec-0012"><label>3.1</label><title>Addressing bias in recruitment estimates</title><p>We found that recruitment was biased high for years with few surveys. Specifically, it was inversely related to the number of surveys conducted such that an additional survey produced a 3.6% decline in recruitment (<mml:math id="nlm-math-15"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;0.036, <italic>SE</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.010, <italic>p&#x000a0;</italic>&#x0003c;<italic>&#x000a0;</italic>.001). This occurred because detection of a whooping crane group was 55.8% (Strobel &#x00026; Butler, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0052" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>) resulting in the cumulative detection probably not exceeding 99% until six surveys were completed. Therefore, we removed years in which the number of surveys conducted was fewer than six (<italic>n&#x000a0;</italic>=<italic>&#x000a0;</italic>6). Once years with &#x0003c;6 surveys were removed, recruitment was no longer associated with the number of surveys conducted (<mml:math id="nlm-math-16"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;0.016, <italic>SE</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.012, <italic>p&#x000a0;</italic>=<italic>&#x000a0;</italic>.119). Recruitment during years with &#x02265;6 surveys ranged from 0 to 0.31 (geometric mean&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.137, <italic>n&#x000a0;</italic>=<italic>&#x000a0;</italic>55, <italic>SD</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.074).</p></sec><sec id="ece32892-sec-0013"><label>3.2</label><title>Modeling recruitment and survival with LASSO</title><p>The repeated cross&#x02010;validated LASSO procedure suggested four variables were important to predicting recruitment (selected by &#x0003e;95% of iterations; Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-tbl-0002" ref-type="table-wrap">2</xref>). Sunspot number (<italic>n&#x000a0;</italic>=<italic>&#x000a0;</italic>55, mean&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;94.8, <italic>SD</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;69.1, min&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;4.2, max&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;225.1) was the most important predictor of recruitment and the model indicated that as sunspots increased, recruitment declined (SSN; Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-tbl-0002" ref-type="table-wrap">2</xref>). Precipitation during autumn migration in the northern U.S. Great Plains (ZNDX.NEDA.1011; <italic>n&#x000a0;</italic>=<italic>&#x000a0;</italic>55, mean&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.49, <italic>SD</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1.26, min&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;1.60, max&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3.74) was the second most important predictor (based on standardized <mml:math id="nlm-math-17"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math>; Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-tbl-0002" ref-type="table-wrap">2</xref>). As precipitation increased during autumn migration, recruitment declined. Conditions on the breeding grounds were also important. Recruitment increased as more days remained below freezing during winter (DX32.WBNP.1103; <italic>n&#x000a0;</italic>=<italic>&#x000a0;</italic>55, mean&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.91, <italic>SD</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.05, min&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.74, max&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.99), and it declined as precipitation increased during the breeding season (TPCP.WBNP.0409; <italic>n&#x000a0;</italic>=<italic>&#x000a0;</italic>55, mean&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;23.4, <italic>SD</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;5&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;.8, min&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;9.7, max&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;41.6; Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-tbl-0002" ref-type="table-wrap">2</xref>). Two other variables were of lesser certainty in their importance (selected by &#x02248;75% of iterations; Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-tbl-0002" ref-type="table-wrap">2</xref>). Greater precipitation on the wintering grounds prior to spring migration (ZNDX.ANWR.1103; <italic>n&#x000a0;</italic>=<italic>&#x000a0;</italic>55, mean&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.04, <italic>SD</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1.19, min&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;2.44, max&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3.57) was associated with increased recruitment (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-tbl-0002" ref-type="table-wrap">2</xref>). Increased precipitation on the breeding grounds during winter (TPCP.WBNP.1103; <italic>n&#x000a0;</italic>=<italic>&#x000a0;</italic>55, mean&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;8.7, <italic>SD</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;2.5, min&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;4.3, max&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;15.1) was associated with decreased recruitment (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-tbl-0002" ref-type="table-wrap">2</xref>). The repeated cross&#x02010;validated LASSO procedure suggested none of the variables were important to predicting annual survival.</p><table-wrap id="ece32892-tbl-0002" xml:lang="en" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Variables predicting recruitment of juvenile whooping cranes into the winter population</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><thead valign="top"><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Predictor variable</th><th align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion of models<xref ref-type="fn" rid="ece32892-note-0002">a</xref>
</th><th align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Standardized <mml:math id="nlm-math-18"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math>
</th><th align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<mml:math id="nlm-math-19"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math>
</th><th align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>SE</italic>
</th><th align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>p</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SSN</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.000</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.166</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.002</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DX32.WBNP.1103</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.999</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.053</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.068</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.313</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZNDX.NEDA.1011</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.984</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.072</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.057</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.021</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.005</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TPCP.WBNP.0409</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.960</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.042</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.007</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.003</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.022</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZNDX.ANWR.1103</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.769</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.009</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.254</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TPCP.WBNP.1103</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.740</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.028</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.011</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.011</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.324</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DX32.WBNP.0409</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.286</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.008</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.264</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.510</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.604</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TPCP.SASK.04</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.264</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.005</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.004</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.008</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.623</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DT32.SASK.0910</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.247</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.076</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.160</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.632</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TPCP.SASK.0910</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.184</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.692</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PDSI.NEDA.04</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.170</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.004</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.002</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.731</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZNDX.NEDA.04</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.117</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">.771</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="ece32892-note-0002"><label>a</label><p>Modeled recruitment (<italic>n&#x000a0;</italic>=<italic>&#x000a0;</italic>55) using LASSO regression and tenfold cross&#x02010;validation to select the optimal model. This procedure was repeated 1,000 times and proportion of times a variable was selected was recorded. Acronyms are defined in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-tbl-0001" ref-type="table-wrap">1</xref>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap></sec><sec id="ece32892-sec-0014"><label>3.3</label><title>Modeling weather variables</title><p>The proportion of days that remained below freezing during winter on the breeding grounds (DX32.WBNP.1103) decreased as the sunspot number and natural log of atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> concentration increased (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-tbl-0003" ref-type="table-wrap">3</xref>). If sunspot number was at the modern grand maximum (269.3) and CO<sub>2</sub> concentration was 500&#x000a0;ppm, this model predicts the proportion of days that remained below freezing (DX32.WBNP.1103) would likely be 0.765 (<italic>SE</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.042) which is within the range of values observed for this variable historically. On the northern U.S. Great Plains during October&#x02013;November, precipitation (ZNDX.NEDA.1011) increased log&#x02010;linearly with atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> concentration (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-tbl-0003" ref-type="table-wrap">3</xref>). If CO<sub>2</sub> concentration was 500&#x000a0;ppm, this model predicts precipitation during southern migration through the northern U.S. Great Plains (ZNDX.NEDA.1011) would likely be 2.71 (<italic>SE</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.88) which is also within the range of values observed for this variable historically. Neither atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> concentration nor sunspot number was associated with total precipitation on the breeding grounds during April&#x02013;September (TPCP.WBNP.0409; Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-tbl-0003" ref-type="table-wrap">3</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="ece32892-tbl-0003" xml:lang="en" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Weather variables that were associated with recruitment of juvenile whooping cranes into the winter population were modeled as functions of atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> concentration and/or sunspot number</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><thead valign="top"><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" rowspan="2" valign="top" colspan="1">Response<xref ref-type="fn" rid="ece32892-note-0003">a</xref>
</th><th valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="char" colspan="2" style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" valign="top" rowspan="1">Intercept</th><th align="char" colspan="2" style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" valign="top" rowspan="1">Sunspot no.</th><th align="char" colspan="2" style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000" valign="top" rowspan="1">log CO<sub>2</sub>
</th></tr><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>n</italic>
</th><th align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<mml:math id="nlm-math-20"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math>
</th><th align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>SE</italic>
</th><th align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<mml:math id="nlm-math-21"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math>
</th><th align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>SE</italic>
</th><th align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<mml:math id="nlm-math-22"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math>
</th><th align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>SE</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ZNDX.NEDA.1011</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">64</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;34.768</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.026</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.031</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.396</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DX32.WBNP.1103</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">65</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.151</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.209</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;0.002</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.001</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;1.986</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.545</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TPCP.WBNP.0409</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">65</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.327</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.693</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="ece32892-note-0003"><label>a</label><p>All weather variables were modeled with simple linear regression except DX32.WBNP.1103 which was modeled using logistic regression. Acronyms are defined in Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-tbl-0001" ref-type="table-wrap">1</xref>.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap></sec><sec id="ece32892-sec-0015"><label>3.4</label><title>Relationships with nesting pond depth</title><p>Mean water depth in nesting ponds ranged from 14.3 to 27.8&#x000a0;cm (mean&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;21.4&#x000a0;cm, <italic>SD</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;4.21). Mean water depth in nesting ponds exhibited a relationship with sunspot number (<mml:math id="nlm-math-23"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;0.038, <italic>SE</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.009, <italic>t&#x000a0;</italic>=&#x000a0;&#x02212;4.172, <italic>p&#x000a0;</italic>=<italic>&#x000a0;</italic>.001), proportion of days that remained below freezing on the breeding grounds during November&#x02013;March (<mml:math id="nlm-math-24"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;44.838, <italic>SE</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;15.078, <italic>t&#x000a0;</italic>=<italic>&#x000a0;</italic>2.974, <italic>p&#x000a0;</italic>=<italic>&#x000a0;</italic>.012), and total precipitation on the breeding grounds during November&#x02013;March (<mml:math id="nlm-math-25"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;0.555, <italic>SE</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.265, <italic>t&#x000a0;</italic>=&#x000a0;&#x02212;2.096, <italic>p&#x000a0;</italic>=<italic>&#x000a0;</italic>.058). Whooping crane recruitment increased as pond depth increased (odds ratio&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1.097, <mml:math id="nlm-math-26"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.093, <italic>SE</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.021, <italic>p&#x000a0;</italic>&#x0003c;<italic>&#x000a0;</italic>.001).</p></sec><sec id="ece32892-sec-0016"><label>3.5</label><title>Population growth, recruitment, survival, and environmental change</title><p>We used an 11&#x02010;year period for the typical sunspot cycle and estimated it as a sixth&#x02010;order polynomial of the number of years since a cycle began (model selected using AIC; min sunspot number&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;10.8, max sunspot number&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;156.6; Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). We used this typical cycle, the Dalton minimum cycle (1811&#x02013;1821; Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>), and the modern grand maximum cycle (1954&#x02013;1964; Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>) to predict future whooping crane recruitment and population growth for two atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> concentration scenarios (i.e., 400 and 500&#x000a0;ppm). Whooping crane population growth fluctuates inversely to the solar cycle, resulting in greater population growth during years of reduced solar activity (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). At the current atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> concentration (&#x02248;400&#x000a0;ppm), years with negative growth are likely rare during a typical solar cycle (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). However, our model predicts years with negative growth become more common in the future (500&#x000a0;ppm CO<sub>2</sub>), as 4&#x000a0;years of the typical solar cycle have negative population growth (i.e., &#x003bb;&#x000a0; &#x0003c; &#x000a0;1; Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Average recruitment is predicted to fall below the long&#x02010;term average (0.137) in all the scenarios, except one: a solar cycle similar to the Dalton minimum with 400&#x000a0;ppm CO<sub>2</sub> (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). Indeed, at 500&#x000a0;ppm CO<sub>2</sub> during a solar cycle similar to the modern grand maximum, mean recruitment lies below the amount required for population growth (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">4</xref>).</p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece32892-fig-0002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>The solar cycle as indicated by sunspot number has varied over the last three centuries (1712&#x02013;2007). The Dalton minimum occurred during 1811&#x02013;1821 and modern grand maximum occurred during 1954&#x02013;1964. We estimated the typical cycle as a sixth&#x02010;order polynomial of the number of years since a cycle began</p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-5" xlink:href="ECE3-7-2821-g002"/></fig><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece32892-fig-0003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Predicted whooping crane population growth for two atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> concentration scenarios during a typical solar cycle (horizontal line indicates 0% population growth, &#x003bb;&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1)</p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-7" xlink:href="ECE3-7-2821-g003"/></fig><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece32892-fig-0004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Predicted juvenile recruitment (ratio of hatch&#x02010;year [HY] to after&#x02010;hatch&#x02010;year [AHY] birds) of whooping cranes during an 11&#x02010;year solar cycle for two atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> concentration scenarios. Top dotted line represents long&#x02010;term mean recruitment (0.137) and bottom dotted line represents required recruitment (0.103) needed to maintain a stable population (&#x003bb;&#x000a0;&#x02265;&#x000a0;1) given the long&#x02010;term mean annual survival of 90.6%. Points represent mean predictions and vertical bars 95% confidence intervals</p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-9" xlink:href="ECE3-7-2821-g004"/></fig><p>Regardless of the solar scenario, our model predicts reduced whooping crane population growth if atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> concentration continues to increase (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-fig-0005" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). Whooping crane population growth likely falls below the long&#x02010;term average (3.5%) for all solar conditions examined with 500&#x000a0;ppm CO<sub>2</sub> (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-fig-0005" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). Further, the population will likely decline by &#x02212;0.44% (95% CI&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;2.98% to 1.57%) if a solar cycle similar to the modern grand maximum occurs in the future (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-fig-0005" ref-type="fig">5</xref>).</p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece32892-fig-0005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Predicted whooping crane population growth during an 11&#x02010;year solar cycle for two atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> concentration scenarios. Top dotted line represents long&#x02010;term mean population growth of 3.5%. Points represent mean predictions and vertical bars 95% confidence intervals. Only a solar cycle similar to the Dalton minimum with &#x02264;400&#x000a0;ppm CO<sub>2</sub> will likely maintain population growth at or above the long&#x02010;term mean of 3.5%</p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-11" xlink:href="ECE3-7-2821-g005"/></fig><p>We found the past survival rate of 90.6% was likely sufficient to maintain a stable population (&#x003bb;&#x000a0; &#x02265; &#x000a0;1) for all but one scenario: a solar cycle similar to the modern grand maximum with 500&#x000a0;ppm CO<sub>2</sub> (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-fig-0006" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). In this scenario, our model predicts annual survival would need to be increased to 91.0% (95% CI&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;89.3%&#x02013;93.4%; Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-fig-0006" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). If the past population growth rate of 3.5% is to be maintained, then all scenarios with 500&#x000a0;ppm CO<sub>2</sub> would require increasing annual survival above its long&#x02010;term mean (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-fig-0006" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). For example, during a typical solar cycle with 500&#x000a0;ppm CO<sub>2</sub>, our model predicts annual survival would need to be increased to 93.4% (95% CI&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;91.8%&#x02013;95.7%) to maintain 3.5% population growth (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-fig-0006" ref-type="fig">6</xref>).</p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece32892-fig-0006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Predicted whooping crane survival needed to maintain 0% population growth and 3.5% population growth (long&#x02010;term mean) during an 11&#x02010;year solar cycle for two atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> concentration scenarios. Dotted line represents long&#x02010;term mean annual survival of 90.6%. Points represent mean predictions and vertical bars 95% confidence intervals</p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-13" xlink:href="ECE3-7-2821-g006"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="ece32892-sec-0017"><label>4</label><title>Discussion</title><sec id="ece32892-sec-0018"><label>4.1</label><title>Environmental conditions and recruitment</title><p>Heightened solar activity increases the amount of radiation striking the Earth's surface (Krivova et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0023" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>). This raises atmospheric temperatures and alters weather patterns thereby influencing plant growth, surface hydrology, and faunal responses (Klvana et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0020" ref-type="ref">2004</xref>; Krebs et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0022" ref-type="ref">2001</xref>; Marques, Short, et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0032" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>; Stager, Ruzmaikin, Conway, Verburg, &#x00026; Mason, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0049" ref-type="ref">2007</xref>). Solar activity, as indexed by the sunspot number, had the greatest magnitude of effect on whooping crane recruitment (based on Standardized <mml:math id="nlm-math-27"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover></mml:math>; Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-tbl-0002" ref-type="table-wrap">2</xref>), having &#x02265;2.3 times more effect than any other variable. The mechanism(s) describing how sunspot activity affects whooping crane recruitment remains unknown. Unraveling similar correlations between sunspots and other cyclical biological phenomena within the boreal ecosystem, and identifying mechanism(s) that generate these observed relationships also remains elusive (Krebs et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0022" ref-type="ref">2001</xref>; Sinclair &#x00026; Gosline, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0047" ref-type="ref">1997</xref>).</p><p>The amount of precipitation in the northern U.S. Great Plains during the autumn migration was the second most important predictor. This variable had &#x02265;36% the influence of the remaining weather variables. Recruitment declined as the amount of precipitation increased during autumn migration. We hypothesize that juveniles are more vulnerable to mortality or abandonment during inclement weather. As juveniles have greater energy expenditure during migration than adults (Rotics et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0042" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>) and are inexperienced foragers, inclement weather may reduce foraging opportunities (Clark, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0100" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>), predisposing juveniles to greater morality risk. Further, inclement weather conditions can increase risk of collision for migrating birds with power lines or other infrastructure (Marques, Batalha, et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>) and juvenile cranes are more vulnerable to collisions than adults (Brown &#x00026; Drewien, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">1995</xref>; Chavez&#x02010;Ramirez &#x00026; Wehtje, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>; Ward &#x00026; Anderson, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0055" ref-type="ref">1992</xref>).</p><p>On the breeding grounds, recruitment increased with more days remaining below freezing during winter. We also observed that nesting pond depth decreased as the number of days remaining below freezing during winter decreased. The potential mechanism behind the association between recruitment and the number of freezing days during winter may be that fewer cold days (&#x0003c;0&#x000b0;C) reduces the amount of time the active groundwater layer remains frozen. Frozen earth retains pond water into the nesting period, with thinner layers more easily breached by the water trapped above (Yoshikawa &#x00026; Hinzman, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0058" ref-type="ref">2003</xref>). Thawing of the ground allows water to permeate the soil, resulting in reduced pond depth, size, and longevity. Presumably, adult whooping cranes nest within ponds to reduce predation on themselves, eggs and hatchlings (Kuyt et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0026" ref-type="ref">1992</xref>; Timoney et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0054" ref-type="ref">1997</xref>). If ponds dry too quickly, nests may become more vulnerable to terrestrial predators, thereby lowering hatchling survival resulting in reduced recruitment.</p><p>Precipitation on the breeding grounds during winter, though much less influential than other weather variables, reduced recruitment. Increased precipitation, likely in the form of snow, acts as an insulator maintaining soil warmth, reducing the thickness of frozen earth and thereby reducing water depth in nesting ponds (Yoshikawa &#x00026; Hinzman, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0058" ref-type="ref">2003</xref>). Corroborating this, we observed nesting pond depth declined as winter precipitation increased.</p><p>Increased precipitation during the breeding season on the breeding grounds was associated with reduced recruitment. We hypothesize that increased precipitation during incubation causes nest flooding and failure (Ivey &#x00026; Dugger, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0017" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>; Layne, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0027" ref-type="ref">1983</xref>). Furthermore, increased rainfall is more apt to soak nesters and hatchlings, thereby increasing their risk of illness or death (Chavez&#x02010;Ramirez &#x00026; Wehtje, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>; Layne, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0027" ref-type="ref">1983</xref>).</p><p>Variables associated with recruitment primarily operate on the breeding grounds or during southern migration across the northern U.S. Great Plains. The variables operating in other locations were much less influential. For example, precipitation on the wintering grounds prior to spring migration and breeding was associated with increased recruitment. This suggests that whooping cranes do not exhibit a complete income breeding strategy (Stephens et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0051" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>). Instead, breeding propensity or other reproductive parameters appear partially controlled by conditions prior to migration. However, precipitation on the wintering grounds was at least 69% less influential than the other weather variables already discussed (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-tbl-0002" ref-type="table-wrap">2</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="ece32892-sec-0019"><label>4.2</label><title>Potential impacts of climate change on recruitment and population growth</title><p>Elevated concentrations of atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> warm the Earth, reducing the proportion of days below freezing on the breeding grounds (i.e., increased temperature; Lemmen, Warren, Lacroix, &#x00026; Bush, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0028" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>) and increasing precipitation on the northern U.S. Great Plains during autumn (Melillo, Richmond, &#x00026; Yohe, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0034" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>). Given these relationships, we substituted the amount of atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> for these variables to evaluate the potential effects of CO<sub>2</sub> concentration on recruitment.</p><p>Our model predicts recruitment declines as the magnitude of the solar cycle moves from the Dalton minimum to the modern grand maximum, or as atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations increase from 400 to 500&#x000a0;ppm (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). The influence of sunspots and atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> on recruitment is comparable, although sunspots have a greater effect. For example, at 400&#x000a0;ppm CO<sub>2</sub> concentration, the difference in average population growth between the Dalton minimum (3.7% mean growth; Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-fig-0005" ref-type="fig">5</xref>) and the modern grand maximum (1.2% mean growth; Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-fig-0005" ref-type="fig">5</xref>) is 2.5% (95% CI mean difference&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1.3%&#x02013;3.8%). Hence, a solar cycle similar to the grand maximum would result in &#x02248;68% less population growth than a solar cycle similar to the Dalton minimum. Alternatively, during a typical solar cycle, the difference in average population growth between 400&#x000a0;ppm (2.2% mean growth; Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-fig-0005" ref-type="fig">5</xref>) and 500&#x000a0;ppm CO<sub>2</sub> concentration (0.4% mean growth; Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-fig-0005" ref-type="fig">5</xref>) is 1.8% (95% CI mean difference&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.3%&#x02013;3.6%). Hence, as atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> concentration increases to 500&#x000a0;ppm, population growth will likely be reduced by &#x02248;80% compared to the current CO<sub>2</sub> concentration.</p><p>Only one scenario, a solar cycle similar to the Dalton minimum with 400&#x000a0;ppm CO<sub>2</sub> concentration, results in population growth commensurate with the long&#x02010;term average (i.e., &#x0003e;3.5% growth; Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-fig-0005" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). This scenario results in no simulations indicating a population decline. All other scenarios portend a future with whooping crane population growth likely falling below the long&#x02010;term average (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-fig-0005" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). Population growth will likely be reduced by half during a solar cycle similar to the Dalton minimum with 500&#x000a0;ppm CO<sub>2</sub>, suggesting downlisting and recovery may take two times longer. The most likely future scenario, a typical solar cycle with 500&#x000a0;ppm CO<sub>2</sub>, suggests population growth will likely be minimal (0.4% mean growth which is an eighth of the long&#x02010;term average), with 31% of the simulations indicating a population decline. These results suggest downlisting and recovery may require eight times longer than conditions without climate change (Butler et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>). If the scenario of a solar cycle similar to the grand maximum with 500&#x000a0;ppm CO<sub>2</sub> concentration occurs, then 63% of the simulations indicate population declines, likely precluding downlisting and recovery in the foreseeable future.</p><p>The sunspot numbers that compose the scenarios described above were observed within the data used (min&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;4.2, max&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;225.1) to build our models, with the exception of the minimum sunspot number observed during the Dalton minimum (2.3) and the two maximum sunspot numbers observed during the modern grand maximum (261.7 and 269.3). Although the 500&#x000a0;ppm CO<sub>2</sub> concentration is beyond the range of the data upon which our models were built, the relationships we developed between weather variables (DX32.WBNP.1103, ZNDX.NEDA.1011) and CO<sub>2</sub> concentration assumed a log&#x02010;linear relationship which results in conservative estimates of the potential magnitude of change. Further, the predictions at 500&#x000a0;ppm CO<sub>2</sub> concentration and the modern grand maximum for these weather variables were within the range of values observed for the variables historically (see results). Hence, our predictions about potential impacts of climate change on recruitment and population growth are tempered and reasonable.</p></sec><sec id="ece32892-sec-0020"><label>4.3</label><title>Management intervention to improve recruitment</title><p>Recruitment should remain at or above 0.103 to maintain stable to increasing population growth (&#x003bb;&#x000a0;&#x02265;&#x000a0;1; Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). If the scenario of a solar cycle similar to the grand maximum with 500&#x000a0;ppm CO<sub>2</sub> occurs, recruitment may decline to 0.099 (95% CI&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.071&#x02013;0.120; Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">4</xref>) and management intervention on the breeding grounds would likely have to result, on average, in an additional 0.5 juveniles per 100 adults to avoid population decline. To maintain long&#x02010;term average population growth (3.5%), recruitment should remain at or above 0.137 (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). The only scenario predicted to achieve this is 400&#x000a0;ppm CO<sub>2</sub> concentration during a solar cycle similar to the Dalton minimum (Figures&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">4</xref> and <xref rid="ece32892-fig-0005" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). Other scenarios, such as a typical solar cycle or modern grand maximum with 500&#x000a0;ppm CO<sub>2</sub> concentration suggests average recruitment may decline to 0.108 (95% CI&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.081&#x02013;0.128) and 0.099 (95% CI&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.071&#x02013;0.120; Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">4</xref>), respectively. Thus, any management intervention on the breeding grounds would likely have to result, on average, in an additional 3 to 4 juveniles recruited per 100 adults to maintain the long&#x02010;term population growth.</p><p>These targets appear achievable. Potential management strategies include predator management (Littlefield, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0029" ref-type="ref">2003</xref>), the addition of nesting platforms or structures (Maggiulli &#x00026; Dugger, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>; Miller, Grand, Fondell, &#x00026; Anthony, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0035" ref-type="ref">2007</xref>), and manipulation of nesting pond depths. While it has been suggested that management intervention on Wood Buffalo National Park is infeasible given its remoteness and lack of infrastructure (Wilson et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0056" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>), these challenges would need to be overcome to recover whooping cranes. Without management intervention, the required amount of time to achieve population goals for downlisting and recovery likely becomes greatly extended or potentially impossible, given our model's predictions.</p><p>How climate change may manifest in the predator&#x02013;prey cycle remains unclear. Lynx declines have been linked to climate warming (Yan et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0057" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>), yet we do not know the ecological ramifications of this outcome, or climate effects on other predators. Other complex interactions associated with ponds drying and increased vulnerability to nest and fledgling predation could also decrease recruitment even if predator densities remained similar or declined. Furthermore, increased temperatures may result in predator populations becoming less cyclic and more generalized in prey selection (Scott &#x00026; Craine, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0044" ref-type="ref">1993</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="ece32892-sec-0021"><label>4.4</label><title>Management intervention to improve annual survival</title><p>If management intervention cannot improve recruitment, maintaining long&#x02010;term average population growth (3.5%) likely requires increases in annual adult survival in all but one of the scenarios (solar cycle similar to the Dalton minimum with 400&#x000a0;ppm CO<sub>2</sub>; Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-fig-0006" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). For instance, the scenario of a typical solar cycle with 500&#x000a0;ppm CO<sub>2</sub>, annual adult survival should be increased from 90.6% (long&#x02010;term geometric mean; <italic>SD</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.060) to 93.4% (95% CI&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;91.8%&#x02013;95.7%; Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-fig-0006" ref-type="fig">6</xref>) to maintain the long&#x02010;term average population growth. At the current population of &#x02248;340 whooping cranes, this is equivalent to, on average, 9 to 10 fewer adult mortalities per year. However, none of the variables we examined were important to predicting survival and many management actions are already underway to reduce adult mortality (e.g., signage to inform hunters, marking of power lines in strategic locations). Past mortality from power line collisions and incidental or illegal harvest is rare (&#x0003c;1 bird/year succumbs to these mortality causes; Stehn &#x00026; Haralson&#x02010;Strobel, <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0050" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>). Thus, little gains in annual survival can currently be expected from these management actions.</p><p>Long&#x02010;term annual adult survival is 90.6% and likely remains sufficient to maintain population stability (0% growth) across all solar cycle and CO<sub>2</sub> concentration scenarios except during a solar cycle similar to the grand maximum with 500&#x000a0;ppm CO<sub>2</sub> (Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-fig-0006" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). Given this scenario, annual survival needs to reach 91.0% (95% CI&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;89.3%&#x02013;93.4%; Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-fig-0006" ref-type="fig">6</xref>) to avoid a population decline. In a scenario where a typical solar cycle occurs with 500&#x000a0;ppm CO<sub>2</sub>, annual adult survival could decline to 90.2% (95% CI&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;88.7%&#x02013;92.5%; Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-fig-0006" ref-type="fig">6</xref>) and still avoid population decline. Hence, given a typical solar cycle with 500&#x000a0;ppm CO<sub>2</sub> and the current population of &#x02248;340 whooping cranes, on average, 1 to 2 additional mortalities per year could result in a declining population.</p></sec><sec id="ece32892-sec-0022"><label>4.5</label><title>Synthesis</title><p>This whooping crane population will likely continue experiencing periodic and predictable years of low recruitment and growth, as sunspots form the primary driver of their approximate decadal population cycle. Climate change likely threatens this population by 2050 when CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations are expected to reach 500&#x000a0;ppm, as our model predicts population growth can become negative during any solar cycle (unlike 400&#x000a0;ppm CO<sub>2</sub>; Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-fig-0005" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). Hence, science has roughly three decades to reveal the on&#x02010;the&#x02010;ground mechanisms relating solar activity and atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> with recruitment (i.e., proximate causes) and to design approaches for mitigating the adverse effects. Alternatively, other management actions could increase annual survival to avoid population declines. Optimistically, increasing recruitment and survival so the population continues growing requires only 1&#x02013;4 additional recruits or survivors per year. Survivorship is the tougher to address, as many of the actions are continental in scope and multifaceted (e.g., power line marking, wind turbine curtailment, hunter education and law enforcement, etc.).</p><p>Recruitment affects whooping crane population growth most (Butler et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>; Wilson et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0056" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>), and our model predictions show that climate change may imperil it. Hence, any perceptions that whooping cranes remain secure in Canada, and can remain free of active management, are false. If conserving whooping cranes in North America remains an important goal, then attention must center on understanding mechanisms limiting recruitment. There appears to be a connection between recruitment, breeding pond hydrology, and predation. Already, the numbers of boreal ponds and their temporal longevity during summer are declining (Carroll et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0008" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>; Smith et&#x000a0;al., <xref rid="ece32892-bib-0048" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>). Unless trends of increasing atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> are abated, science must determine how to mitigate the likely reduction in recruitment by 2050. Future monitoring and research should focus on relationships of depth and seasonal longevity of nesting ponds with nest success and causes of nest failure. Additionally, fledgling mortality and its causes on the breeding grounds and during southern migration should be investigated. The results of this work could steer conservation actions toward long&#x02010;term sustainability and protection of whooping cranes in North America. If such efforts prove unsuccessful, then the only wild population of this species must adapt or likely face extinction.</p></sec></sec><sec id="ece32892-sec-0024"><title>Conflict of Interest</title><p>None declared.</p></sec></body><back><ack id="ece32892-sec-0023"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>Findings and conclusions in this manuscript are those of the authors and do not necessarily represent the views of USFWS. Use of trade, firm, or product names is for descriptive purposes only and does not imply endorsement by the U.S. Government. We thank Leandra N. Taylor for helping design Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32892-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>.</p></ack><ref-list content-type="cited-references" id="ece32892-bibl-0001"><title>References</title><ref id="ece32892-bib-0001"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32892-cit-0001">
<string-name>
<surname>Ak&#x000e7;akaya</surname>, <given-names>H. R.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Butchart</surname>, <given-names>S. H. M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Watson</surname>, <given-names>J. E. M.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Pearson</surname>, <given-names>R. G.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Commentary: Preventing species extinctions resulting from climate change</article-title>. <source>Nature Climate Change</source>, <volume>4</volume>, <fpage>1048</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1049</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0002"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32892-cit-0002">
<string-name>
<surname>Brook</surname>, <given-names>B. W.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ak&#x000e7;akaya</surname>, <given-names>H. R.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Keith</surname>, <given-names>D. A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Mace</surname>, <given-names>G. M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Pearson</surname>, <given-names>R. G.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Ara&#x000fa;jo</surname>, <given-names>M. B.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Integrating bioclimate with population models to improve forecasts of species extinctions under climate change</article-title>. <source>Biology Letters</source>, <volume>5</volume>, <fpage>723</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>725</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19625300</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0003"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32892-cit-0003">
<string-name>
<surname>Brown</surname>, <given-names>W. M.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Drewien</surname>, <given-names>R. C.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Evaluation of two power line markers to reduce crane and waterfowl collision mortality</article-title>. <source>Wildlife Society Bulletin</source>, <volume>23</volume>, <fpage>217</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>227</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0004"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32892-cit-0004">
<string-name>
<surname>Butler</surname>, <given-names>M. J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Harris</surname>, <given-names>G.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Strobel</surname>, <given-names>B. N.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Influence of whooping crane population dynamics on its recovery and management</article-title>. <source>Biological Conservation</source>, <volume>162</volume>, <fpage>89</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>99</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0005"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32892-cit-0005">
<string-name>
<surname>Butler</surname>, <given-names>M. J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Metzger</surname>, <given-names>K. L.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Harris</surname>, <given-names>G.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Whooping crane demographic responses to winter drought focus conservation strategies</article-title>. <source>Biological Conservation</source>, <volume>179</volume>, <fpage>72</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>85</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0006"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="ece32892-cit-0006">
<string-name>
<surname>Butler</surname>, <given-names>M. J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Strobel</surname>, <given-names>B. N.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Eichhorn</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2016</year>). <source>Whooping crane winter abundance survey protocol: Aransas National Wildlife Refuge. Version 1.1. Survey identification number: FF02RTAR00&#x02010;002</source>. <publisher-loc>Austwell, TX, USA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service</publisher-name>. doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.7944/W3159J">https://doi.org/10.7944/W3159J</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0007"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="ece32892-cit-0007">
<collab collab-type="authors">Canadian Wildlife Service &#x00026; U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service</collab>
(<year>2007</year>). <source>International recovery plan for the whooping crane (Grus americana), third revision</source>. <publisher-loc>Albuquerque, NM, USA &#x00026; Ottawa, Canada</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Environment Canada and U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0008"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32892-cit-0008">
<string-name>
<surname>Carroll</surname>, <given-names>M. L.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Townshend</surname>, <given-names>J. R. G.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>DiMiceli</surname>, <given-names>C. M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Loboda</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Sohlberg</surname>, <given-names>R. A.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Shrinking lakes of the Arctic: Spatial relationships and trajectory of change</article-title>. <source>Geophysical Research Letters</source>, <volume>38</volume>, <fpage>L20406</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0009"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32892-cit-0009">
<string-name>
<surname>Caughley</surname>, <given-names>G.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Directions in conservation biology</article-title>. <source>Journal of Animal Ecology</source>, <volume>63</volume>, <fpage>215</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>244</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0100"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32892-cit-0100">
<string-name>
<surname>Clark</surname>, <given-names>J. A.</given-names>
</string-name>, (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Selective mortality of waders during severe weather</article-title>. <source>Bird Study</source>, <volume>56</volume>, <fpage>96</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>102</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0010"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32892-cit-0010">
<string-name>
<surname>Chavez&#x02010;Ramirez</surname>, <given-names>F.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Wehtje</surname>, <given-names>W.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Potential impact of climate change scenarios on whooping crane life history</article-title>. <source>Wetlands</source>, <volume>32</volume>, <fpage>11</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>20</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0011"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32892-cit-0011">
<string-name>
<surname>Friedman</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Hastie</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Tibshirani</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Regularization paths for generalized linear models via coordinate descent</article-title>. <source>Journal of Statistical Software</source>, <volume>33</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>22</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20808728</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0012"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32892-cit-0012">
<string-name>
<surname>Gerber</surname>, <given-names>B. D.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Kendall</surname>, <given-names>W. L.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Hooten</surname>, <given-names>M. B.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Dubovsky</surname>, <given-names>J. A.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Drewin</surname>, <given-names>R. C.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Optimal population prediction of sandhill crane recruitment based on climate&#x02010;mediated habitat limitations</article-title>. <source>Journal of Animal Ecology</source>, <volume>84</volume>, <fpage>1299</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1310</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25808951</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0013"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32892-cit-0013">
<string-name>
<surname>Gibson</surname>, <given-names>J. J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Prowse</surname>, <given-names>T. D.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Peters</surname>, <given-names>D. L.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Hydroclimatic controls on water balance and water level variability in Great Slave Lake</article-title>. <source>Hydrological Processes</source>, <volume>20</volume>, <fpage>4155</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4172</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0014"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="ece32892-cit-0014">
<string-name>
<surname>Guthrie</surname>, <given-names>C. G.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Lu</surname>, <given-names>Q.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2010</year>). <source>Coastal hydrology for the Guadalupe Estuary: Updated hydrology with emphasis on diversion and return flow data for 2000&#x02013;2009</source>. <publisher-loc>Austin</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Texas Water Development Board</publisher-name> Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.twdb.texas.gov/surfacewater/bays/major_estuaries/guadalupe/doc/TWDB_Hydrology_GuadalupeEstuary_201011.pdf">http://www.twdb.texas.gov/surfacewater/bays/major_estuaries/guadalupe/doc/TWDB_Hydrology_GuadalupeEstuary_201011.pdf</ext-link>. (accessed 2 September 2015)</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0015"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="ece32892-cit-0015">
<string-name>
<surname>Hastie</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Qian</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2015</year>). <source>Glmnet vignette</source>. <publisher-loc>Stanford, CA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Stanford University</publisher-name> Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://web.stanford.edu/~hastie/Papers/Glmnet_Vignette.pdf">http://web.stanford.edu/~hastie/Papers/Glmnet_Vignette.pdf</ext-link> (accessed 27 July 2015).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0016"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="ece32892-cit-0016">
<collab collab-type="authors">Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change</collab>
(<year>2014</year>). <source>Carbon dioxide: Projected emissions and concentrations</source>. <publisher-loc>Geneva, Switzerland</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Data Distribution Centre, Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change</publisher-name> Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ipcc-data.org/observ/ddc_co2.html">http://www.ipcc-data.org/observ/ddc_co2.html</ext-link>. (accessed 6 January 2015).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0017"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32892-cit-0017">
<string-name>
<surname>Ivey</surname>, <given-names>G. L.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Dugger</surname>, <given-names>B. D.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Factors influencing nest success of greater sandhill cranes at Malheur National Wildlife Refuge, Oregon</article-title>. <source>Waterbirds</source>, <volume>31</volume>, <fpage>52</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>61</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0018"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32892-cit-0018">
<string-name>
<surname>Johns</surname>, <given-names>B. W.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Woodsworth</surname>, <given-names>E. J.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Driver</surname>, <given-names>E. A.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Habitat use by migrant whooping cranes in Saskatchewan</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the North American Crane Workshop</source>, <volume>7</volume>, <fpage>123</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>131</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0019"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="ece32892-cit-0019">
<string-name>
<surname>Keeling</surname>, <given-names>C. D.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Piper</surname>, <given-names>S. C.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Bacastow</surname>, <given-names>R. B.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Wahlen</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Whorf</surname>, <given-names>T. P.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Heimann</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Meijer</surname>, <given-names>H. A.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2001</year>). <source>Exchanges of atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> and <sup>13</sup>CO<sub>2</sub> with the terrestrial biosphere and oceans from 1978 to 2000. I</source>. Global aspects, SIO Reference Series, No. 01&#x02010;06, <publisher-loc>San Diego, CA, USA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Scripps Institution of Oceanography</publisher-name> Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://scrippsco2.ucsd.edu/">http://scrippsco2.ucsd.edu/</ext-link>. (accessed 10 August 2015).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0020"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32892-cit-0020">
<string-name>
<surname>Klvana</surname>, <given-names>I.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Berteaux</surname>, <given-names>D.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Cazelles</surname>, <given-names>B.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Porcupine feeding scars and climatic data show ecosystem effects of the solar cycle</article-title>. <source>American Naturalist</source>, <volume>164</volume>, <fpage>283</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>297</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0021"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32892-cit-0021">
<string-name>
<surname>Krebs</surname>, <given-names>C. J.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Berteaux</surname>, <given-names>D.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Problems and pitfalls in relating climate variability to population dynamics</article-title>. <source>Climate Research</source>, <volume>32</volume>, <fpage>143</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>149</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0022"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32892-cit-0022">
<string-name>
<surname>Krebs</surname>, <given-names>C. J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Boonstra</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Boutin</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Sinclair</surname>, <given-names>A. R. E.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2001</year>). <article-title>What drives the 10&#x02010;year cycle of snowshoe hares?</article-title>
<source>BioScience</source>, <volume>51</volume>, <fpage>25</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>35</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0023"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32892-cit-0023">
<string-name>
<surname>Krivova</surname>, <given-names>N. A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Vieira</surname>, <given-names>L. E. A.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Solanki</surname>, <given-names>S. K.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Reconstruction of solar spectral irradiance since the Maunder minimum</article-title>. <source>Journal of Geophysical Research</source>, <volume>115</volume>(<issue>A12</issue>), <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0024"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="ece32892-cit-0024">
<string-name>
<surname>Kuyt</surname>, <given-names>E.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Aerial radio&#x02010;tracking of whooping cranes migrating between Wood Buffalo National Park and Aransas National Wildlife Refuge, 1981&#x02013;84</article-title>. Occasional Paper 74, <publisher-name>Canadian Wildlife Service</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Ottawa, Canada</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0025"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32892-cit-0025">
<string-name>
<surname>Kuyt</surname>, <given-names>E.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>The nest and eggs of the whooping crane, <italic>Grus americana</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Canadian Field&#x02010;Naturalist</source>, <volume>109</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0026"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32892-cit-0026">
<string-name>
<surname>Kuyt</surname>, <given-names>E.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Barry</surname>, <given-names>S. J.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Johns</surname>, <given-names>B. W.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Below average whooping crane production in Wood Buffalo National Park during drought years 1990 and 1991</article-title>. <source>Blue Jay</source>, <volume>50</volume>, <fpage>225</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>229</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0027"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32892-cit-0027">
<string-name>
<surname>Layne</surname>, <given-names>J. N.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1983</year>). <article-title>Productivity of sandhill cranes in south central Florida</article-title>. <source>Journal of Wildlife Management</source>, <volume>47</volume>, <fpage>178</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>185</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0028"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="ece32892-cit-0028">
<string-name>
<surname>Lemmen</surname>, <given-names>D. S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Warren</surname>, <given-names>F. J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Lacroix</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Bush</surname>, <given-names>E.</given-names>
</string-name> (Eds.) (<year>2008</year>). <source>From impacts to adaptation: Canada in a changing climate 2007</source> (<fpage>448</fpage> p). <publisher-loc>Ottawa, ON</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Government of Canada</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0029"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32892-cit-0029">
<string-name>
<surname>Littlefield</surname>, <given-names>C. D.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Sandhill crane nesting success and productivity in relation to predator removal in southeastern Oregon</article-title>. <source>Wilson Bulletin</source>, <volume>115</volume>, <fpage>263</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>269</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0030"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32892-cit-0030">
<string-name>
<surname>Maggiulli</surname>, <given-names>N. M.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Dugger</surname>, <given-names>B. D.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Factors associated with dusky Canada goose (<italic>Branta canadensis occidentalis</italic>) nesting and nest success on artificial nest islands of the western Copper River Delta</article-title>. <source>Waterbirds</source>, <volume>34</volume>, <fpage>269</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>279</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0031"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32892-cit-0031">
<string-name>
<surname>Marques</surname>, <given-names>A. T.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Batalha</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Rodriques</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Costa</surname>, <given-names>H.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Pereira</surname>, <given-names>M. J. R.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Fonseca</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x02026; <string-name>
<surname>Bernerdino</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Understanding bird collisions at wind farms: An updated review on the causes and possible mitigation strategies</article-title>. <source>Biological Conservation</source>, <volume>179</volume>, <fpage>40</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>52</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0032"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32892-cit-0032">
<string-name>
<surname>Marques</surname>, <given-names>L. V.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Short</surname>, <given-names>F. T.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Creed</surname>, <given-names>J. C.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Sunspots drive seagrasses</article-title>. <source>Biological Rhythm Research</source>, <volume>46</volume>, <fpage>63</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>68</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0033"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="ece32892-cit-0033">
<string-name>
<surname>McNaughton</surname>, <given-names>D.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1991</year>). <source>Final report on hydrological investigations Wood Buffalo National Park 1985 to 1990</source>. <publisher-loc>Fort Smith, Canada</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Wood Buffalo National Park</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0034"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="ece32892-cit-0034">
<string-name>
<surname>Melillo</surname>, <given-names>J. M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Richmond</surname>, <given-names>T. C.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Yohe</surname>, <given-names>G. W.</given-names>
</string-name> (Eds.) (<year>2014</year>). <source>Climate change impacts in the United States: The third national climate assessment</source> (<fpage>841</fpage> pp). <publisher-loc>Washington, D.C., USA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>U.S. Global Change Research Program</publisher-name>. doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.7930/J0Z31WJ2">10.7930/J0Z31WJ2</ext-link>
</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0035"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32892-cit-0035">
<string-name>
<surname>Miller</surname>, <given-names>D. A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Grand</surname>, <given-names>J. B.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Fondell</surname>, <given-names>T. F.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Anthony</surname>, <given-names>R. M.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Optimizing nest survival and female survival: Consequences of nest site selection for Canada geese</article-title>. <source>Condor</source>, <volume>109</volume>, <fpage>769</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>780</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0036"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="ece32892-cit-0036">
<string-name>
<surname>Mills</surname>, <given-names>L. S.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2007</year>). <source>Conservation of wildlife populations: Demography, genetics, and management</source>. <publisher-loc>Malden, MA, USA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Blackwell Publishing</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0037"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="ece32892-cit-0037">
<collab collab-type="authors">National Climatic Data Center</collab>
(<year>2007</year>). <source>Time bias corrected divisional temperature&#x02010;precipitation&#x02010;drought index, TD&#x02010;9640</source>. <publisher-loc>Asheville, NC, USA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>National Climatic Data Center</publisher-name> Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www1.ncdc.noaa.gov/pub/data/cirs/drd/divisional.README">http://www1.ncdc.noaa.gov/pub/data/cirs/drd/divisional.README</ext-link>. (accessed 2 September 2015).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0038"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="ece32892-cit-0038">
<string-name>
<surname>Palmer</surname>, <given-names>W. C.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1965</year>). <source>Meteorological drought</source>. Research Paper No. 45, <publisher-loc>Washington, DC, USA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>U.S. Weather Bureau</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0039"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="ece32892-cit-0039">
<collab collab-type="authors">R Core Team</collab>
(<year>2014</year>). <source>R: A language and environment for statistical computing</source>. Version 3.1.1. <publisher-loc>Vienna, Austria</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>R Foundation for Statistical Computing</publisher-name> Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.R-project.org">http://www.R-project.org</ext-link>. (accessed 9 October 2014).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0040"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32892-cit-0040">
<string-name>
<surname>Reineking</surname>, <given-names>B.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Schr&#x000f6;der</surname>, <given-names>B.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Constrain to preform: Regularization of habitat models</article-title>. <source>Ecological Modelling</source>, <volume>193</volume>, <fpage>675</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>690</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0041"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32892-cit-0041">
<string-name>
<surname>Rind</surname>, <given-names>D.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Lean</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Lerner</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Lonergan</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Leboissetier</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2008</year>). <article-title>Exploring the stratospheric/tropospheric response to solar forcing</article-title>. <source>Journal of Geophysical Research</source>, <volume>113</volume>, <fpage>D24103</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0042"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32892-cit-0042">
<string-name>
<surname>Rotics</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Kaatz</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Resheff</surname>, <given-names>Y. S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Feldman Turjeman</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Zurell</surname>, <given-names>D.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Sapier</surname>, <given-names>N.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x02026; <string-name>
<surname>Nathan</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names>
</string-name>, (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>The challenges of the first migration: Movement and behavior of juvenile versus adult white storks with insights regarding juvenile mortality</article-title>. <source>Journal of Animal Ecology</source>, <volume>85</volume>, <fpage>938</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>947</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27046512</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0043"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="ece32892-cit-0043">
<string-name>
<surname>Schoenbaechler</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Guthrie</surname>, <given-names>C. G.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Lu</surname>, <given-names>Q.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2011</year>). <source>Coastal hydrology for the Mission&#x02010;Aransas Esturary</source>. <publisher-loc>Austin</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Texas Water Development Board</publisher-name> Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.twdb.texas.gov/surfacewater/bays/major_estuaries/mission_aransas/doc/TWDB_Hydrology_MissionAransas_20110222.pdf">http://www.twdb.texas.gov/surfacewater/bays/major_estuaries/mission_aransas/doc/TWDB_Hydrology_MissionAransas_20110222.pdf</ext-link>. (accessed 2 September 2015).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0044"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32892-cit-0044">
<string-name>
<surname>Scott</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Craine</surname>, <given-names>I. T. M.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>The lynx cycle: A climatic perspective</article-title>. <source>Climate Research</source>, <volume>2</volume>, <fpage>235</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>240</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0045"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32892-cit-0045">
<string-name>
<surname>Sel&#x000e5;s</surname>, <given-names>V.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Hogstad</surname>, <given-names>O.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Kobro</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Rafoss</surname>, <given-names>T.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Can sunspot activity and ultraviolet&#x02010;B radiation explain cyclic outbreaks of forest moth pest species?</article-title>
<source>Proceedings of the Royal Society of London B</source>, <volume>271</volume>, <fpage>1897</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1901</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0046"><mixed-citation publication-type="miscellaneous" id="ece32892-cit-0046">
<collab collab-type="authors">SILSO World Data Center</collab>
(<year>2015</year>).<article-title>The international sunspot number</article-title>. Version 2.0. International Sunspot Number Monthly Bulletin and online catalogue, Royal Observatory of Belgium, Brussel. Retrieved from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sidc.be/silso/datafiles">http://www.sidc.be/silso/datafiles</ext-link>. (accessed 11 August 2015).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0047"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32892-cit-0047">
<string-name>
<surname>Sinclair</surname>, <given-names>A. R. E.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Gosline</surname>, <given-names>L. M.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Solar activity and mammal cycles in the Northern Hemisphere</article-title>. <source>American Naturalist</source>, <volume>149</volume>, <fpage>776</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>784</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0048"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32892-cit-0048">
<string-name>
<surname>Smith</surname>, <given-names>L. C.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Sheng</surname>, <given-names>Y.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>MacDonald</surname>, <given-names>G. M.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Hinzman</surname>, <given-names>L. D.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Disappearing arctic lakes</article-title>. <source>Science</source>, <volume>308</volume>, <fpage>1429</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15933192</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0049"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32892-cit-0049">
<string-name>
<surname>Stager</surname>, <given-names>J. C.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Ruzmaikin</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Conway</surname>, <given-names>D.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Verburg</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Mason</surname>, <given-names>P. J.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Sunspots, El Ni&#x000f1;o, and the levels of Lake Victoria, East Africa</article-title>. <source>Journal of Geophysical Research</source>, <volume>112</volume>, <fpage>D15106</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0050"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32892-cit-0050">
<string-name>
<surname>Stehn</surname>, <given-names>T. V.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Haralson&#x02010;Strobel</surname>, <given-names>C. L.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>An update on mortality of fledged whooping cranes in the Aransas/Wood Buffalo population</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the North American Crane Workshop</source>, <volume>12</volume>, <fpage>43</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>50</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0051"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32892-cit-0051">
<string-name>
<surname>Stephens</surname>, <given-names>P. A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Boyd</surname>, <given-names>I. L.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>McNamara</surname>, <given-names>J. M.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Houston</surname>, <given-names>A. I.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Capital breeding and income breeding: Their meaning, measurement, and worth</article-title>. <source>Ecology</source>, <volume>90</volume>, <fpage>2057</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2067</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19739368</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0052"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32892-cit-0052">
<string-name>
<surname>Strobel</surname>, <given-names>B. N.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Butler</surname>, <given-names>M. J.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Monitoring whooping crane abundance using aerial surveys: Influences on detectability</article-title>. <source>Wildlife Society Bulletin</source>, <volume>38</volume>, <fpage>188</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>195</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26388657</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0053"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32892-cit-0053">
<string-name>
<surname>Tibshirani</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1996</year>). <article-title>Regression shrinkage and selection via the Lasso</article-title>. <source>Journal of the Royal Statistical Society B</source>, <volume>58</volume>, <fpage>267</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>288</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0054"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32892-cit-0054">
<string-name>
<surname>Timoney</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Zoltai</surname>, <given-names>S. C.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Goldsborough</surname>, <given-names>L. G.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1997</year>). <article-title>Boreal diatom ponds: A rare wetland associated with nesting whooping cranes</article-title>. <source>Wetlands</source>, <volume>17</volume>, <fpage>539</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>551</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0055"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32892-cit-0055">
<string-name>
<surname>Ward</surname>, <given-names>J. P.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Anderson</surname>, <given-names>S. H.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>1992</year>). <article-title>Sandhill crane collisions with power lines in southcentral Nebraska</article-title>. <source>Proceedings of the North American Crane Workshop</source>, <volume>5</volume>, <fpage>189</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>196</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0056"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32892-cit-0056">
<string-name>
<surname>Wilson</surname>, <given-names>S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Gil&#x02010;Weir</surname>, <given-names>K. C.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Clark</surname>, <given-names>R. G.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Robertson</surname>, <given-names>G. J.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Bidwell</surname>, <given-names>M. T.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Integrated population modeling to assess demographic variation and contributions to population growth for endangered whooping cranes</article-title>. <source>Biological Conservation</source>, <volume>197</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0057"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32892-cit-0057">
<string-name>
<surname>Yan</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Stenseth</surname>, <given-names>N. C.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<surname>Krebs</surname>, <given-names>C. J.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Zhang</surname>, <given-names>Z.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Linking climate change to population cycles of hares and lynx</article-title>. <source>Global Change Biology</source>, <volume>19</volume>, <fpage>3263</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3271</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23846828</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32892-bib-0058"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32892-cit-0058">
<string-name>
<surname>Yoshikawa</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names>
</string-name>, &#x00026; <string-name>
<surname>Hinzman</surname>, <given-names>L. D.</given-names>
</string-name> (<year>2003</year>). <article-title>Shrinking thermokarst ponds and groundwater dynamics in discontinuous permafrost near Council, Alaska</article-title>. <source>Permafrost Periglacial Processes</source>, <volume>14</volume>, <fpage>151</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>160</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>