<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par26" class="p">The SSPs describe prototypical trajectories for societal development that may occur in the future. The range of SSPs is intended to span the uncertainty associated with societal development, although outcomes outside of this range cannot be ruled out. Various assumptions regarding the SSP pathways
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" class="xref">46</xref>
 </sup> and the IAM implementation of these pathways are described in earlier manuscripts
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" class="xref">51</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" class="xref">53</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" class="xref">55</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" class="xref">57</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" class="xref">61</xref>
 </sup> and a brief overview of these assumptions is included here. The SSP1-2.6 Sustainability scenario, contributed by the IMAGE model
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" class="xref">62</xref>
 </sup>, assumes sustainable growth in the future that focuses on human well-being and respect for environmental boundaries
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" class="xref">57</xref>
 </sup>. For the continental United States, cropland area and fertilizer usage are projected to increase slightly by the end-of-the-century, driven by an increase in energy crops. The SSP2-4.5 Middle of the Road scenario, contributed by the MESSAGE-GLOBIOM model
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" class="xref">63</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" class="xref">64</xref>
 </sup> assumes that future growth patterns will be similar to historical patterns, and is designed to cover the middle ground in terms of mitigation and adaptation challenges between more extreme SSPs
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" class="xref">61</xref>
 </sup>. For the continental United States, cropland area is projected to remain unchanged while fertilizer usage is projected to decrease slightly. The SSP3-7.0 Regional rivalry scenario, contributed by the AIM model
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" class="xref">65</xref>
 </sup>, represents a world with increased nationalism and regional rivalry and decreased globalization
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" class="xref">53</xref>
 </sup>. For the continental United States, this scenario leads to increased deforestation associated with an increase in cropland area and fertilizer usage. The SSP4 Inequality pathway represents a world with increasing inequality both within and across countries
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" class="xref">51</xref>
 </sup>. This pathway was combined with two climate outcomes, yielding the SSP4-3.4 and SSP4-6.0 scenarios, both based on the GCAM model
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" class="xref">66</xref>
 </sup>. These two scenarios are based a common set of high-level assumptions about societal growth, but with different climate outcomes representing different degrees of climate mitigation. For the continental United States, for both the SSP4-3.4 and SSP4-6.0 scenarios, cropland area and fertilizer usage is projected to increase in the future, as a result of an increase in bioenergy crops and an increase in domestic food production. The increase in bioenergy production for the SSP4-3.4, however, is much larger than for the SSP-6.0 (Supplementary Figure 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">5</xref>). The SSP5-8.5 Fossil-fueled development scenario, contributed by the REMIND-MAGPIE model
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" class="xref">67</xref>
 </sup>, represents a world with increased globalization and high economic growth
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" class="xref">54</xref>
 </sup>. For the continental United States, cropland area remains largely unchanged, developed land areas increase slightly, and fertilizer usage decreases due to an increase in productivity.
</p>
