<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par18" class="p">Before making climate projections, we analyze simulations by the MRCM constrained by boundary conditions from reanalysis data and evaluate its performance against observations. The rationale for carrying these experiments is to test the model skill in reproducing observed regional climate, as well as to study the impact of land use change on the historical climate of the region. As irrigation is widely practiced in NCP (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1b</xref>), it is essential that we evaluate the impact of irrigation on surface climate. In this regard, additional 30 years (1982–2011) numerical experiments consisting of control (CONT, without irrigation module) and irrigation (IRR, with irrigation module) simulations are performed using MRCM (Supplementary Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">3</xref>). The MRCM experiments adopt the same model configuration (e.g., domain coverage, spatiotemporal resolution, and physical parameters) as one used in the GCM downscaling, but are driven by the 1.5° × 1.5° 6-hourly ERA-Interim data
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" class="xref">41</xref>
 </sup> as lateral boundary conditions and the 1° × 1° weekly NOAA optimum interpolation sea surface temperatures for the ocean surfaces
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" class="xref">42</xref>
 </sup>. To evaluate the two simulations, we compare the simulated surface conditions to the Climate Research Unit (CRU)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" class="xref">43</xref>
 </sup> data, focusing on several key surface variables such as surface temperature (Supplementary Figs. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">5</xref> and 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">6</xref>), specific humidity (Supplementary Figs. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">7</xref> and 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">8</xref>), and TW (Supplementary Figs. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">9</xref> and 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">10</xref>). The finger print of irrigation can be seen clearly by comparing field observations of surface conditions to the results of the numerical model simulations. Without explicit representation of irrigation and its direct and indirect effects, models would consistently simulate a summer climate over the NCP that features warmer temperature, drier air, and cooler TW. These difference between simulations and observations are consistent with the finger print of irrigation. Indeed, inclusion of a reasonable representation of irrigation into the model improves the correspondence between the model results and observations in terms of surface temperature, atmospheric humidity, and surface TW, leading to statistically significant reductions of overall biases. In a recent coordinated set of numerical models’ simulations over Eastern China, a warm and dry bias in surface conditions was identified as a common deficiency in the ability of other regional climate models (without irrigation) to simulate the observed climate of this region
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" class="xref">44</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
