<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par21" class="p">The University of Maryland global vegetation classifications (UMD GLCF), available at 1 km spatial resolution
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" class="xref">59</xref>
 </sup> was used to develop vegetation parameters. Soil parameters were derived from the Food and Agriculture Organization
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" class="xref">60</xref>
 </sup> dataset available at 5-minute spatial resolution. The parameters used for the calibration of the VIC model include infiltration parameter (Binf), soil layers (second and third layer) thickness (D), maximum baseflow velocity (Dsmax), the fraction of maximum baseflow velocity (Ds), and the fraction of maximum soil moisture content (Ws). The simulated runoff and baseflow from each grid-cell were routed using a standalone routing model
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" class="xref">61</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" class="xref">62</xref>
 </sup>, which explicitly represents the routing of surface and subsurface runoff within a grid using a unit hydrograph that contributes to a channel network. The VIC model has been applied in the Indian sub-continent in several previous studies. For instance, daily streamflow simulations using the VIC model were used to examine the bias and uncertainty in satellite-based precipitation products over the Indian subcontinental river basins for the period of 2000–2013
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">3</xref>
 </sup>, while Shah and Mishra
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">9</xref>
 </sup> evaluated hydrologic changes in the Indian sub-continental river basins using the VIC model. In our simulations, the VIC model does not consider dynamic vegetation for the observed and future climate, sediment load in streamflow, explicit representation of glaciers, and human influence on the water cycle (e.g., groundwater abstraction, reservoir operation). These factors can affect streamflow and reservoir capacity. Despite these limitations, the streamflow changes in the natural water cycle are useful to evaluate the changes in the hydropower during the warming climate.
</p>
