<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">While the impact of climate change on crops has been extensively studied, both at the regional level [e.g., 
 <italic class="italic">Lobell et al.,</italic>
 <xref rid="eft2229-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>; 
 <italic class="italic">Auffhammer et al.,</italic>
 <xref rid="eft2229-bib-0005" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>; 
 <italic class="italic">Blanc,</italic>
 <xref rid="eft2229-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>; 
 <italic class="italic">Tao et al.,</italic>
 <xref rid="eft2229-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>] and at the global level [e.g., 
 <italic class="italic">Arnell et al.,</italic>
 <xref rid="eft2229-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; 
 <italic class="italic">Teixeira et al.,</italic>
 <xref rid="eft2229-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; 
 <italic class="italic">Deryng et al.,</italic>
 <xref rid="eft2229-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>], understanding the effect of climate change on irrigated crop yields is more challenging due to the complexity of the system to consider. Biophysical crop models are specifically designed to estimate crop yields under different climatic conditions, but they usually consider only two irrigation scenarios [
 <italic class="italic">Rosenzweig et al.,</italic>
 <xref rid="eft2229-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>]: no irrigation (rainfed yield) or perfect irrigation with no water stress experienced by the crops (optimal irrigated yield). Water resources system models account for competing water uses but are not capable of estimating the effect of the resulting potential water limitations on crop yields. In the most extensive assessment to date, 
 <italic class="italic">Elliott et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="eft2229-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>] assess the impact of future irrigation water availability on crop productivity at the global level using an ensemble of water supply and demand projections from 5 global climate models, 10 global hydrological models, and 6 global gridded crop models, thus accounting for the uncertainty in projections of climate change, hydrology, and crop modeling. This study, however, only considers a single GHG concentration scenario and does not simulate the possible benefits of abatement policies. Also, it considers water use and resources without spatial or temporal optimization of water allocation. The lack of optimization is a crude assumption that is not representative of current water management practices. Focusing on the U.S., 
 <italic class="italic">Hejazi et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="eft2229-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>] do include a river routing and reservoir operations models in an integrated assessment framework but do not account for any uncertainty in projections of climate change other than two GHG emissions scenarios.
</p>
