<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Tel Dan is a rectangular mound (circa 20 ha) located in the northeastern reaches of the Hula valley near the foothills of Mount Hermon (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" class="xref">Fig. 2</xref>). Terrestrial and freshwater biological indicators were extracted from a 675-cm continuous core (TD-1, 33°15′00.24″N, 35°39′13.18″E; +209 m mean sea level) drilled on the alluvial fan of the Nahal Sion (fig. S8), close to the eastern flank of Tel Dan, in an avocado orchard near the Middle Bronze Age mudbrick gate. The chronology of the core is based on nine accelerator mass spectrometry 
 <sup class="sup">14</sup>C dates (table S1). No botanical macro-remains or secure bulk fractions were found in the middle core, leaving a floating chronology between 250- and 150-cm depth. Dated samples were calibrated (1σ and 2σ calibrations, respectively, 68 and 95% of probability) using CALIB REV 7.1 with IntCal13 (
 <xref rid="R86" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">86</italic>
 </xref>). The average chronological resolution for the core stratigraphy is 4 years/cm
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup> (2.5 mm per year
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>). We recognize that this average is liable to mask both more intense weather events and closely sequenced series of more extreme years of drought or high precipitation. It would then also mask some of the temporal variability in the depositional patterns of alluvium and pollen. From the point of view of a single core, this would result in a heuristic exercise of interpolation, rather than as a chronologically reliable record of changing climate. Nevertheless, when the same patterns recur in different cores from different locations in the eastern Mediterranean and western Asia (
 <xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">12</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">19</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">20</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">41</italic>
 </xref>–
 <xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">44</italic>
 </xref>), we can consider these patterns as reflecting the temporal dimension with some degree of precision.
</p>
