<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par8" class="p">Within each article, the headline, section, column, and text were coded for content. A combination of frame analysis, drawing on Entman (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">1993</xref>), and conventional content analysis, drawing on Hsieh and Shannon (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">2005</xref>), were used. Content was coded descriptively and for context, in order to provide descriptive explanations (Hsieh and Shannon 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">2005</xref>). Frames were conceptualized as a way to “promote a particular problem definition, causal interpretation, moral evaluation, and/or treatment recommendation” across the entire article (Entman 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">1993</xref>, p. 52). Codes were developed inductively through familiarization and refined through three trial rounds of coding, with five to ten articles coded in each round. A set of codes was developed to describe characteristics for climatic impacts, responses, and agents (See 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">Supplementary Information</xref>). The coding scheme captured the stage, scale, and type of impacts and responses, severity of impacts and the type of knowledge used to identify them, and actor types and roles (e.g., victim, researcher). Additionally, thematic codes (e.g., colonialism, resiliency) were developed inductively to identify broader concepts. Finally, a questionnaire provided additional context on each article’s type, the author’s identity, and any major events linked to the article’s publication. Coding was conducted predominantly by one coder using Atlas.ti, with a second researcher coding a sub-sample of texts to ensure replicability and reduce the possibility of bias. Articles coded during trial rounds were re-coded toward the end of the process, and results were compared to verify replicability. Throughout the familiarization and coding processes, a research journal was kept to document potential research biases, trends, and other notes.
</p>
