<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="discussion" id="s3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In contrast to conventional wisdom and several recent review papers, our analysis of 952 species shows little to no support for a negative intraspecific temperature-mass relationship that is sufficiently strong or common to be considered a biogeographic rule. Three quarters of bird and mammal species show no significant change in mass across a temperature gradient and temperature explained less than 10% of intraspecific variation in mass for 87% of species (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig2" href="#fig2">Figure 2A</a>). This was true regardless of taxonomic group (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig2" href="#fig2">Figures 2</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig3" href="#fig3">3</a>), temporal lag in temperature (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig4" href="#fig4">Figure 4</a>), species' size, location, or sampling intensity or extent (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig5" href="#fig5">Figure 5</a>). These results are consistent with two previous studies that examined museum specimen size measurements across latitude. The first study showed that 22 out of 47 North American mammal species studied had no relationship between latitude and length, and 10 of the 25 significant relationships were opposite the expected direction (
  <a rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib59">McNab, 1971</a>). The second found a similar proportion of non-significant results (42/87), but a lower proportion of significant relationships that opposed the rule (9/45) for carnivorous mammals (
  <a rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib61">Meiri et al., 2004</a>). While more species had significant negative relationships than positive in both our study and these two museum-based studies, in all cases less than half of species had significant negative correlations (14–41%). In combination with these two smaller studies, our results suggest that there is little evidence for a strong or general Bergmann's rule when analyzing raw data instead of summarizing published results.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results are inconsistent with recent reviews, which have reported that the majority of species conform to Bergmann's rule (
  <a rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib3">Ashton, 2002</a>; 
  <a rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib62">Meiri and Dayan, 2003</a>; 
  <a rid="bib109" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib109">Watt et al., 2010</a>). While these reviews included results that were either non-significant or opposite of Bergmann's rule, the proportion of significant results in support of Bergmann's rule was higher and therefore resulted in conclusions that supported the generality of the temperature-mass relationship. Generalizing from results in the published literature involves the common challenges of publication bias and selective reporting (
  <a rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib54">Koricheva et al., 2013</a>). In addition, because the underlying Bergmann's rule studies typically report minimal statistical information, often providing only relationship significance or direction instead of p-values or correlation coefficients (
  <a rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib62">Meiri and Dayan, 2003</a>), proper meta-analyses and associated assessments of biological significance are not possible. While several reviews found no evidence for publication bias using limited analyses (
  <a rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib3">Ashton, 2002</a>; 
  <a rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib61">Meiri et al., 2004</a>), the notable differences between the conclusions of our data-intensive approach and those from reviews suggest that publication bias in literature examining Bergmann's rule warrants further investigation. These differences also demonstrate the value of data-intensive approaches in ecology for overcoming potential weaknesses and biases in the published literature. Directly analyzing large quantities of data from hundreds of species allows us to assess the generality of patterns originally reported in smaller studies while avoiding the risk of publication bias. This approach additionally makes it easier to integrate other factors that potentially influence size into future analyses. The new insight gained from this data-intensive approach demonstrates the value of investing in large compilations of ecologically-relevant data (
  <a rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib47">Hampton et al., 2013</a>) and the proper training required to work with these datasets (
  <a rid="bib46" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib46">Hampton et al., 2017</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our analyses and conclusions are limited to the intraspecific form of Bergmann’s rule. This is the most commonly studied and well-defined form of the relationship, and the one most amenable to analyses using large compilations of museum data. Difficulty in interpreting Bergmann’s original formulation has resulted in an array of different ideas and implementations of interspecific analyses (
  <a rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib9">Blackburn et al., 1999</a>; 
  <a rid="bib63" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib63">Meiri and Thomas, 2007</a>; 
  <a rid="bib109" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib109">Watt et al., 2010</a>; 
  <a rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib64">Meiri, 2011</a>). The most common forms of these interspecific analyses involve correlations between various species-level size metrics and environmental measures and are conducted at various taxonomic levels from genus to class (e.g., 
  <a rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib10">Blackburn and Gaston, 1996</a>; 
  <a rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib34">Diniz-Filho et al., 2007</a>; 
  <a rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib15">Boyer et al., 2009</a>; 
  <a rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib25">Clauss et al., 2013</a>). Efforts to apply data-intensive approaches to the interspecific form of this relationship will need to address the fact that occurrence records are not evenly distributed across the geographic range of species, and determine how the many interpretations of interspecific Bergmann’s rule are related to one another and the biological expectations for interspecific responses to temperature.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The original formulation of Bergmann's rule, and the scope of our conclusions, apply only to endotherms. However, negative temperature-mass relationships have also been documented in ectotherms, with the pattern referred to as the size-temperature rule (
  <a rid="bib78" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib78">Ray, 1960</a>; 
  <a rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib1">Angilletta and Dunham, 2003</a>). In contrast to the hypotheses for Bergmann's rule, which are based primarily on homeostasis (
  <a rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib43">Gardner et al., 2011</a>), the size-temperature rule in ectotherms is thought to result from differences between growth and development rates (
  <a rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib39">Forster et al., 2011</a>). The current version of VertNet contained ectotherm size data for only seven species, which is not sufficient to complete a comprehensive analysis of the ectotherm size-temperature rule. Future work exploring the ectotherm size-temperature rule in natural systems using data-intensive approaches is necessary for understanding the generality of this rule in ectotherms, and data may be sought for this effort in the literature or via a coordinated effort by museums to continue digitizing size measurements for specimens.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A number of mechanisms have been suggested to explain why higher temperatures should result in lower body sizes, including heat loss, starvation, resource availability, migratory ability, and phylogenetic constraints (
  <a rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib9">Blackburn et al., 1999</a>). Most of the proposed hypotheses have not been tested sufficiently to allow for strong conclusions to be drawn about their potential to produce Bergmann's rule (
  <a rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib9">Blackburn et al., 1999</a>; 
  <a rid="bib109" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib109">Watt et al., 2010</a>; 
  <a rid="bib92" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib92">Teplitsky and Millien, 2014</a>) and the widely studied heat loss hypothesis has been questioned for a variety of reasons (
  <a rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib51">James, 1970</a>; 
  <a rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib59">McNab, 1971</a>; 
  <a rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib9">Blackburn et al., 1999</a>; 
  <a rid="bib109" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib109">Watt et al., 2010</a>; 
  <a rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib60">McNamara et al., 2016</a>). While no existing hypotheses have been confirmed, it is possible that some processes are producing negative relationships between size and temperature. The lack of a strong relationship does not preclude processes that result in a negative temperature-mass relationship, but it does suggest that these processes have less influence relative to other factors that affect intraspecific size.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The relative importance of the many factors besides temperature that can influence size within a species is as yet unknown. Size is affected by abiotic factors such as humidity and resource availability (
  <a rid="bib92" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib92">Teplitsky and Millien, 2014</a>), characteristics of individuals like clutch size (
  <a rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib15">Boyer et al., 2009</a>), and community context, including possible gaps in size-related niches (
  <a rid="bib88" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib88">Smith et al., 2010</a>) and the trophic effects of primary productivity on consumer size (
  <a rid="bib86" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib86">Sheridan and Bickford, 2011</a>). Temperature itself can have indirect effects on size, such as via habitat changes in water flow or food availability, that result in size responses opposite of Bergmann's rule (
  <a rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib43">Gardner et al., 2011</a>). Anthropogenic influences have been shown to influence the effect of temperature on size (
  <a rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib38">Faurby and Araújo, 2016</a>), and similar impacts of dispersal, extinctions, and the varying scales of climate change have been proposed (
  <a rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib25">Clauss et al., 2013</a>). Because our data primarily came from North America, further analyses focused on species native to other continents could reveal differing temperature-mass relationships due to varying temperature regimes. While our work shows that more species have negative significant relationships between temperature and mass than positive, only 21% of species have statistically significant relationships and it consequently appears that some combination of other factors more strongly drives intraspecific size variation for most endothermic taxa.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The lack of evidence for temperature as a primary determinant of size variation in endothermic species calls into question the hypothesis that decreases in organism size may represent a third universal response to global warming. The potentially general decline in size with warming was addressed by assessments that evaluated dynamic body size responses to temperature using similar approaches to the Bergmann's rule reviews discussed above (
  <a rid="bib86" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib86">Sheridan and Bickford, 2011</a>; 
  <a rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib43">Gardner et al., 2011</a>; 
  <a rid="bib92" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib92">Teplitsky and Millien, 2014</a>). The results of these temporal reviews were similar to those for spatial relationships, but the conclusions of these studies clearly noted the variability in body size responses and the need for future data-intensive work (
  <a rid="bib86" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib86">Sheridan and Bickford, 2011</a>; 
  <a rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib43">Gardner et al., 2011</a>) using broader temperature ranges (
  <a rid="bib92" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib92">Teplitsky and Millien, 2014</a>) to fully assess the temperature-size relationship.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results in combination with those from other studies suggest that much of the observed variation in size is not explained simply by temperature. While there is still potential for the size of endotherms, and other aspects of organismal physiology and morphology, to respond to both geographic gradients in temperature and climate change, these responses may not be as easily explained solely by temperature as has been suggested (
  <a rid="bib86" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib86">Sheridan and Bickford, 2011</a>; 
  <a rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib43">Gardner et al., 2011</a>). Future attempts to explain variation in the size of individuals across space or time should use integrative approaches to include the influence of multiple factors, and their potential interactions, on organism size. This will be facilitated by analyzing spatiotemporal data similar to that used in this study, which has broad ranges of time, space, and environmental conditions for large numbers of species and individuals. This data-intensive approach provides a unique perspective on the general responses of bird and mammal species to temperature, and has potential to assist in further investigation of the complex combinations of factors that determine biogeographic patterns of endotherm size and how species respond to changes in climate.
 </p>
</sec>
