<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="s1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Bergmann's rule describes a negative relationship between body mass and temperature across space that is believed to be common in endothermic species (
  <a rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib6">Bergmann, 1847</a>; 
  <a rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib17">Brown and Lee, 1969</a>; 
  <a rid="bib52" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib52">Kendeigh, 1969</a>; 
  <a rid="bib40" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib40">Freckleton et al., 2003</a>; 
  <a rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib19">Carotenuto et al., 2015</a>). Many hypotheses have been proposed to explain this pattern (
  <a rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib9">Blackburn et al., 1999</a>; 
  <a rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib3">Ashton, 2002</a>; 
  <a rid="bib109" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib109">Watt et al., 2010</a>) including the heat loss hypothesis, which argues that the higher surface area to volume ratio of smaller individuals results in improved heat dissipation in hot environments (
  <a rid="bib6" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib6">Bergmann, 1847</a>). Though originally described for closely-related species (i.e., interspecific; 
  <a rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib9">Blackburn et al., 1999</a>), the majority of studies have focused on the intraspecific form of Bergmann's rule (
  <a rid="bib79" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib79">Rensch, 1938</a>; 
  <a rid="bib64" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib64">Meiri, 2011</a>) by assessing trends in individual size within a species (
  <a rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib58">Langvatn and Albon, 1986</a>; 
  <a rid="bib116" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib116">Yom-Tov and Geffen, 2006</a>; 
  <a rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib42">Gardner et al., 2009</a>). Bergmann's rule has been questioned both empirically and mechanistically (
  <a rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib59">McNab, 1971</a>; 
  <a rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib44">Geist, 1987</a>; 
  <a rid="bib50" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib50">Huston and Wolverton, 2011</a>; 
  <a rid="bib92" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib92">Teplitsky and Millien, 2014</a>) but the common consensus from recent reviews is that the pattern is general (
  <a rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib2">Ashton et al., 2000</a>; 
  <a rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib3">Ashton, 2002</a>; 
  <a rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib62">Meiri and Dayan, 2003</a>; 
  <a rid="bib110" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib110">Watt and Salewski, 2011</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It has recently been suggested that this negative relationship between mass and temperature could result in decreasing individual size across species in response to climate change (
  <a rid="bib86" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib86">Sheridan and Bickford, 2011</a>) and that this may be a ‘third universal response to warming’ (
  <a rid="bib43" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib43">Gardner et al., 2011</a>). The resulting shifts in size distributions could significantly alter ecological communities (
  <a rid="bib16" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib16">Brose et al., 2012</a>), especially if the rate of size decrease varies among species (
  <a rid="bib86" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib86">Sheridan and Bickford, 2011</a>). While there is limited empirical research on body size responses to changes in temperature through time (but see 
  <a rid="bib87" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib87">Smith et al., 1995</a>; 
  <a rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib20">Caruso et al., 2014</a>; 
  <a rid="bib92" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib92">Teplitsky and Millien, 2014</a>), the apparent generality of Bergmann's rule across space indicates the likelihood of a similar relationship in response to temperature change across time.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The generality of Bergmann's rule is based on many individual studies that analyze empirical data on body size across an environmental gradient (e.g., 
  <a rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib58">Langvatn and Albon, 1986</a>; 
  <a rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib4">Barnett, 1977</a>; 
  <a rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib41">Fuentes and Jaksic, 1979</a>; 
  <a rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib33">Dayan et al., 1989</a>; 
  <a rid="bib81" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib81">Sand et al., 1995</a>) and reviews that compile and evaluate the results from these studies (
  <a rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib3">Ashton, 2002</a>; 
  <a rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib62">Meiri and Dayan, 2003</a>; 
  <a rid="bib109" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib109">Watt et al., 2010</a>). Most individual studies of Bergmann's rule are limited by: (1) analyzing only one or a few species (e.g., 
  <a rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib58">Langvatn and Albon, 1986</a>); (2) using small numbers of observations (e.g., 
  <a rid="bib41" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib41">Fuentes and Jaksic, 1979</a>); (3) only including data at the small scales typical of ecological studies (e.g., 
  <a rid="bib81" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib81">Sand et al., 1995</a>); (4) using latitude instead of directly assessing temperature (e.g., 
  <a rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib4">Barnett, 1977</a>); and (5) focusing on statistical significance instead of the strength of the relationship (e.g., 
  <a rid="bib33" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib33">Dayan et al., 1989</a>). The reviews tabulate the results of these individual studies and assess patterns in the direction and significance of relationships across species. Such aggregation of published results allows for a more general understanding of the pattern but, in addition to limitations of the underlying studies, the conclusions may be influenced by publication bias and selective reporting due to studies or individual analyses that do not support Bergmann's rule being published less frequently (
  <a rid="bib54" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib54">Koricheva et al., 2013</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Previous analyses of publication bias in the context of Bergmann’s rule have found no evidence for selective publication, which supports the idea that it is a general rule (
  <a rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib3">Ashton, 2002</a>; 
  <a rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib61">Meiri et al., 2004</a>). However, two of the most extensive studies of Bergmann’s rule, which both used museum records to assess dozens of intraspecific Bergmann’s rule relationships simultaneously, found that the majority of species did not exhibit significant positive relationships between latitude and size (
  <a rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib59">McNab, 1971</a>; 
  <a rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib61">Meiri et al., 2004</a>). As a result, understanding the generality of this ecophysiological rule and its potential implications for global change requires more extensive analysis.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A data-intensive approach to analyzing Bergmann's rule, evaluating the pattern using large amounts of broad scale data, has the potential to overcome existing limitations in the literature and provide a new perspective on the generality of the intraspecific form of Bergmann's rule. Understanding the generality of the temperature-mass relationship has important implications for how size will respond to climate change. We use data from VertNet (
  <a rid="bib28" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib28">Constable et al., 2010</a>), a large compilation of digitized museum records that contains over 700,000 globally distributed individual-level size measures, to evaluate the intraspecific relationship between temperature and mass for 952 mammal and bird species. The usable data consist of 273,901 individuals with an average of 288 individuals per species, with individuals of each species spanning an average of 75 years and 34 latitudinal degrees. This approach reduces or removes many of the limitations to previous approaches and the results suggest that Bergmann's rule is not a strong or general pattern.
 </p>
</sec>
