<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Growth rates of individual germlings and total cover of CCA germlings showed a parabolic response to elevated pCO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>, with intermediate pCO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> enrichment favouring growth rates
 <sub class="sub">.</sub> This trend was clearer under low irradiance conditions (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0189122.g006" class="xref">Fig 6E</xref>). This suggests that different response variables of the early life stages of CCA respond differently to environmental stressors. On the other hand, our results suggest that moderate pCO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> enrichment may in fact favour the growth of early stages of the CCA 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">onkodes</italic>, as has been observed on some adult CCAs [
 <xref rid="pone.0189122.ref019" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0189122.ref068" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">68</xref>]. CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> is a substrate for photosynthesis, therefore elevated pCO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> can potentially alleviate CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> limitation leading to enhancement of algal growth [e.g. as discussed in [
 <xref rid="pone.0189122.ref069" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">69</xref>]]. This will depend on whether 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">onkodes</italic> uses CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> directly from the surrounding water via diffusion gradients, or whether it uses bicarbonate (HCO
 <sub class="sub">3</sub>
 <sup class="sup">-</sup>) as a source of carbon for photosynthesis [e.g. via carbon concentrating mechanisms (CCM)], as well as the ability to upregulate or down-regulate CCM activity [e.g. [
 <xref rid="pone.0189122.ref070" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">70</xref>]]. Although we demonstrated that intermediate pCO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> concentrations favour the growth of early life stages of CCA, this only occurred under low irradiance conditions. Photosynthesis from non-calcifying red algae in low irradiance environments that lack CCM increases when exposed to high CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> concentrations [
 <xref rid="pone.0189122.ref071" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">71</xref>]. In these algae, CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> is incorporated to the site of photosynthesis via direct diffusion gradients with little participation of CCM (e.g. [
 <xref rid="pone.0189122.ref071" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">71</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0189122.ref073" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">73</xref>]), and this may be a process by which CCA increase growth under moderate CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> enrichment. Our results contrast with those from Bradassi 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="pone.0189122.ref041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>] who found that the growth of early stages of temperate CCA were not altered by variations in pCO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>. Different methodologies were employed by Bradassi 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="pone.0189122.ref041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>]: they measured growth rates on two week old juveniles, while we recorded growth on 1–6 day old germlings making direct comparisons difficult. The decline in growth rates under elevated pCO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> is consistent with other studies that have shown declines in CCA recruitment with high pCO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> [
 <xref rid="pone.0189122.ref027" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0189122.ref030" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0189122.ref039" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0189122.ref059" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">59</xref>]
 <sub class="sub">.</sub> We can infer that the decline observed in CCA recruitment under high pCO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>/low pH in our experiment may be a direct result of the inability of the spores to commence cell division and germination disc formation and the decrease of germling growth rate.
</p>
