<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Our study also demonstrates a positive effect of elevated temperature on individual germling growth rates. Elevated temperature in itself may enhance metabolic processes leading to increased algal growth which has been suggested for CCA [
 <xref rid="pone.0189122.ref074" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">74</xref>] and other macroalgae [
 <xref rid="pone.0189122.ref075" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">75</xref>]. The effects of temperature on CCA growth depends on species, temperature levels and interactions with other factors. For example, rising temperature accelerated the growth of germlings of a temperate coralline alga in Japan [
 <xref rid="pone.0189122.ref051" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">51</xref>]. On the other hand, elevated temperature in combination with high pCO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> reduced CCA growth and calcification on tropical and temperate CCA, but temperature in itself did not have a significant effect on growth [
 <xref rid="pone.0189122.ref021" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0189122.ref022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>]. Contrary to this, no interactive effects of pCO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> and temperature were observed on a tropical CCA [
 <xref rid="pone.0189122.ref076" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">76</xref>]. Different results can also vary depending on the biological process being measured; for instance, diel net calcification in 
 <italic class="italic">Lithothamnion corallioides</italic> increased under elevated CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> with a progressive temperature increase from 10–19°C, while some photosynthetic pigments were reduced [
 <xref rid="pone.0189122.ref032" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>]. As discussed earlier, elevated temperature in our experiment did reduce germination (germination disc formation) but only under high pCO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>. From these results and the literature we conclude that the effect of rising temperature can be positive or negative, but in general when temperature interacts with high pCO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> it synergistically impairs CCA physiology.
</p>
