<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">A growing area of environmental social science research on consumption focuses instead on nations' militaries. For example, recent longitudinal analyses within sociology link higher levels of national‐level energy consumption and carbon emissions to the relative size (measured as military participation rate) and capital intensity (measured as military expenditures as % GDP and military expenditures per soldier) of nation's militaries, a finding which holds for both developed and developing nations (Bradford &amp; Stoner, 
 <xref rid="wcc554-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>; Clark, Jorgenson, &amp; Kentor, 
 <xref rid="wcc554-bib-0038" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>; Jorgenson, Clark, &amp; Kentor, 
 <xref rid="wcc554-bib-0129" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>). A network of military bases encompasses the globe, requiring the consumption of a vast amount of resources—including fossil fuels—to staff, operate, and transport equipment and personnel between destinations (Gould, 
 <xref rid="wcc554-bib-0084" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>; Hooks and Smith 
 <xref rid="wcc554-bib-0100" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2004</xref>, 
 <xref rid="wcc554-bib-0101" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2005</xref>, 
 <xref rid="wcc554-bib-0102" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). Common military equipment, such as planes, ships, helicopters, tanks, and vehicles requires the consumption of large amounts of energy. For example, 1 hr of operation of a nonnuclear aircraft carrier consumes 21,300 L (over 5,621 gal) of fossil fuel; large, high‐tech military helicopters burn five gallons of fuel for every mile that they travel; and fighter planes, such as the F‐15 and F‐16, consume between 1,500 and 1,700 gal of fuel per hour. If their afterburners are used, up to 14,400 gal are exhausted per hour (Clark &amp; Jorgenson, 
 <xref rid="wcc554-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). This body of research on the environmental impacts of nations' militaries is also relevant for approaches to international inequality and ecologically unequal exchange, which are discussed below.
</p>
