<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<list list-type="simple">
 <list-item>
  <p>The first open question is both the most trivial and the most difficult to answer, but still is the most important: we need to record global isopod diversity, in terms of species occurrence and exact distribution ranges at a habitat and a regional scale, but also in terms of population abundance. How can we evaluate distribution patterns without a solid knowledge of actual distributions? Research on isopod distribution, of course, should be coupled with advancements in isopod taxonomy and phylogenetic analysis, using also molecular data, so that we can get a good picture of genetic diversity and variation patterns, in addition to a more robust natural taxonomy of isopods.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>Global and regional latitudinal and altitudinal patterns of isopod diversity are still largely unknown. In addition, research on such gradients might also take into account possible trends in life-history parameters or other relevant features, such as body size etc. In addition, explorations of ‘species – area – habitat diversity’ relationships at different scales and in different systems (‘habitat islands’, oceanic versus continental islands etc.) could provide crucial information on processes that shape isopod communities.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>Isopod invasions and long-distance dispersal remain a terra incognita for isopods, with current knowledge based mainly on anecdotal evidence. We need to solidly document such processes, possibly also using molecular approaches. There are several closely related questions that we also need to address, such as: What constitutes a propagule for different isopod species? To what extent are isopods able to exhibit niche shifts in order to establish populations in new habitats?</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>We need to employ state-of-the-art tools in order to predict distribution changes, taking advantage of all evidence available, at least for those species that have been studied in detail for many years in the past. Such tools include modern Species Distribution Models that are not solely based on species presence and/or absence data, but are also able to incorporate information on life-history parameters, abundance etc. There is a wide array of relevant models that are continuously improved and applied to a vast variety of taxa. We still lack, though, any application on terrestrial isopods, despite the fact that the information needed to apply some of these models is available, at least for a few, mostly European, regions.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>We need detailed data on the life history (longevity, fecundity etc.) and other autecological parameters of as many species as possible. These data may also include tolerance to environmental factors, reaction norms of different phenotypes etc. Such data are crucial for evaluating population trends, niche shifts, for population viability analyses etc.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>We need further research on expected changes of soil processes that might affect isopod distribution. Soil dynamics are under intensive research for quite a long time. The complexity of the systems, though, has not allowed researchers to provide sufficient models of soil processes under supposed climate change variations. The rapidly evolving tools of ‘next generation sequencing’, especially those concerning microbiome analysis, might prove of prime importance towards an increased understanding of a variety of relevant processes, especially taking into account the role of micro-organisms as food for isopod species. The effects of temperature increase and changes in local precipitation regimes on soil processes must be studied in detail, because they might play a crucial role in determining isopod distribution, acting synergistically with other factors, such as physiological, behavioural etc.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>Functional diversity, including ‘ecomorphological strategies’, is tightly connected with species distribution dynamics. We urgently need a classification of isopod features, including aspects of morphology, physiology, behaviour, and several life-history parameters that will provide a meaningful description of functional diversity. Within this framework, it will be possible to make a finer analysis of isopod body plans, and to identify additional features that might be connected to these plans. The analysis of current functional diversity will offer lots of evidence for possible future trends under climate change.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>We still lack robust data on isopod intra- and interspecific interactions. Available data are both taxonomically and geographically restricted, so we need to study such interactions for more species, coming also from more biomes. Interspecific interactions, of course, should not be restricted to isopods, but should also include possible interactions with predators, parasites, hosts, competitors and/or other species that might interact with isopods, such as other detritivores like diplopods etc. The examples of myrmecophilous species with the role of relations with ants for their distribution described in this chapter are highly indicative for the importance of this line of research for evaluating distribution dynamics under environmental change.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>Research on evolutionary processes pertaining to isopod diversification is still lacking today, even though it is crucial in order to evaluate long-termed effects of current changes for isopod species. The role of environmental stresses as selective forces leading to speciation or extinction should be explored also within the framework of adaptive and non-adaptive radiations. The effects of population bottlenecks and population isolation due to habitat fragmentation should be closely studied in different species from a variety of isopod clades. We should also note here that evolutionary studies should particularly address the issue of regressive evolution, related to the path towards a life in caves or in deep soil, a path very commonly followed by isopods.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>Last, but not least, we have to take full advantage of the unique features of terrestrial isopods among animal taxa, features that make them exceptionally useful models for the study of a wide range of phenomena, including those related to climate change effects on distribution. Isopods provide a unique opportunity for comparative studies among clades that represent almost all stages of evolution from a life in the sea to a life in almost all terrestrial habitats.</p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item>
  <p>As a conclusion to this paper, we have to stress the need for an up to date, revised web-based isopod database, where all new data on species occurrences and, possibly also other data, will be regularly added in a format that will enable communication with GIS analytical tools etc.</p>
 </list-item>
</list>
