<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">As shown in Figure 
 <xref rid="ece32735-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3</xref>, tropical PFTs had opposite responses to temperature change between two models. Our other research showed that such distinctions were likely to result from the differences in seedling establishment scheme and photosynthesis parameterization (see Appendice S1). IAP‐DGVM explicitly considers the impact of soil moisture on the establishment rates of woody PFTs. When temperature decreased, lower evapotranspiration increased soil moisture, not only benefiting seedling establishment rates which increased tree population densities, but also improving the maximum rate of carboxylation (
 <italic class="italic">V</italic>
 <sub class="sub">max</sub>) and GPP
 <sub class="sub">eco</sub> (Figure 
 <xref rid="ece32735-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref>), leading to individual growth. As a result, the fractional coverage of tropical forests increased. However, if not considering the soil moisture influences on establishment rates in IAP‐DGVM (Equation S6; like the establishment parameterization in CLM4‐CNDV), similar results with CLM4‐CNDV were found, i.e., the tropical tree population densities would decrease in the case of cooling. Therefore, introducing the effects of soil moisture on establishment rates directly accounted for the different vegetation responses to climate change. As to the fall in GPP simulated by CLM4‐CNVD in the case of cooling, it was mainly because of complicated nitrogen limitation. In CLM4‐CNDV, 
 <italic class="italic">V</italic>
 <sub class="sub">max</sub> also varies with foliage nitrogen concentration and specific leaf area (SLA, assumed to increase linearly with cumulative LAI). Such complicated nitrogen influences exceeded the positive effects from moister soil on 
 <italic class="italic">V</italic>
 <sub class="sub">max</sub> and led to GPP
 <sub class="sub">eco</sub> decline when temperature decreased.
</p>
