<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="supplementary-material" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Additional files</div>
 <sec id="Sec19" class="sec">
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <div content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1" class="supplementary-material">
    <div xlink:href="12913_2019_4226_MOESM1_ESM.pdf" class="media" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
     <span class="label">Additional file 1:</span>
     <div class="caption">
      <p>The Supplemental File is composed of three elements. First, a screenshot of the performance feedback report is provided. Second, a Gantt chart is displayed to document the relative timing of the data included in the three iterations of the feedback report which had been distributed at the time of qualitative data collection. Due to unspecific documentation, date data for indicators sourced from Electronic Medical Records are not reported in the Gantt chart. It is suspected that EMR queries likely varied by practice base and were not standardized to a specific date. The “Admin Cost Data” row is each facet is meant to reflect only cost data obtained from administrative sources. In facets where this field is blank, the cost data are incorporated into the “Admin” field. Third, a table is presented summarizing the source, operationalized definition and the stated rationale for inclusion in the performance feedback report. Data and information summarized in the Gantt chart and the table were sourced from materials provided to the research team by AFHTO. (PDF 565 kb)</p>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2" class="supplementary-material">
    <div xlink:href="12913_2019_4226_MOESM2_ESM.pdf" class="media" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
     <span class="label">Additional file 2:</span>
     <div class="caption">
      <p>The Supplemental File contains a table summarizing the FHT practice characteristics as well as interview formats and participants for the present study. (PDF 102 kb)</p>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
