<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Background</div>
 <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Audit and Feedback (A&amp;F) is a popular quality improvement (QI) strategy and is synonymous with the terms clinical audit, practice feedback and performance dashboards. Defined as a summary of clinical performance to health care providers over a specified period of time, the popularity of A&amp;F is attributable to the sound rationale that measurement is necessary to improve quality of care [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>]. Audit and Feedback seeks to support QI through the systematic assessment of care against explicit criteria and the subsequent implementation of change [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is well understood that a feedback loop reflecting an iterative, self-regulating QI process serves as the mechanism of action for A&amp;F interventions [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>]. This feedback loop is composed of three distinct stages: 
  <span class="italic">audit</span>, 
  <span class="italic">feedback,</span> and 
  <span class="italic">response</span>. In the 
  <span class="italic">audit</span> stage, data are collected (manually or electronically) to capture recent performance for some measure (or series of measures). The audited data are contrasted against some comparator measure such as a consensus benchmark, a summary of peer performance, or historical data of the recipient. In the 
  <span class="italic">feedback</span> stage, information on the comparative level of performance is delivered to the intended audience. Modes of delivery may include some combination of post, electronic mail, in-person review, or electronic performance dashboard. To initiate the 
  <span class="italic">response</span> stage, the feedback recipient(s) must i) assess whether a quality of care gap exists, ii) consider whether it warrants a change in effort or in clinical processes or workflows, and then iii) carry out the necessary action(s) to achieve a higher score in the future. Feedback recipients can be expected to weigh their decision in the context of the available resources to act on the gap and on the perceived validity and relative importance of the gap [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>]. Following a pre-specified period, the feedback loop would be repeated. Iterations of this feedback loop aim to motivate ongoing efforts to close existing gaps or to identify emergent gaps requiring action. Over multiple iterations, behaviour and/or policy changes by health professionals and organization should address the gaps between ideal and expected care.
 </p>
 <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the purposes of this paper, it is important to distinguish between “external” and “internal” A&amp;F efforts. The former refers to initiatives organized, developed, and administered by an entity external to the setting which is the subject of the audit, such as a funder or regional organization. The latter refers to A&amp;F efforts initiated, managed, and maintained by the local healthcare professional recipients of the feedback [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While the mechanism of action for A&amp;F is straightforward in principle, the intervention has been described as an unreliable approach to QI [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>]. Most prominently, findings from the 2014 Cochrane review on A&amp;F reported a large interquartile range (0.5 to 16%) for improvements in processes of care across a range of clinical conditions and settings [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>]. In response, the field has advocated for a shift in inquiry to understand how and when this intervention works best [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>]. Efforts to optimize the impact of A&amp;F have emerged, including 15 suggestions by Brehaut et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>]. Such suggestions offer guidance to leverage the mechanism of action of A&amp;F by strengthening fidelity to all three stages of the feedback loop. Evaluations that help to identify whether, how, and why initiatives are able to implement fully all stages of the feedback loop may help to unearth additional opportunities to optimize the effectiveness of A&amp;F. For instance, a 2018 study explored the execution of the feedback and response stages in the mental health care context. Failure to execute the latter stage was attributed to unclear expectations and the absence of senior leaders at feedback report meetings [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>]. However, a gap persists with respect to evaluations exploring implementation in the context of the entire feedback loop.
 </p>
 <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The present study aimed to evaluate the implementation of a voluntary, external A&amp;F intervention in a team-based primary care practice context. Specific research questions included: i) To what extent did the implementation of the A&amp;F program reflect a complete feedback loop?; and ii) What were the barriers and facilitators to implementation at each stage of the feedback loop?</p>
</sec>
