<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data collection</div>
 <p id="Par33" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The interview sampling frame was drawn from FHTs that met two eligibility criteria: i) the FHT had agreed to participate in an AFHTO-led developmental evaluation of D2D, and ii) the FHT had participated in at least one iteration of the A&amp;F program. Following the release of the third iteration of the feedback report, Executive Directors (ED) from eligible FHTs were invited to participate in semi-structured interviews to discuss their experience with D2D. These leaders were targeted as informants as they were the intended recipients of the feedback report. In recognition of the role played by other team members, additional informants who were more familiar with D2D processes and procedures were invited at the discretion of the ED. Additional informants included Physician Leaders, QIDSS staff, and interdisciplinary health professionals.</p>
 <p id="Par34" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Criterion sampling was utilized to ensure variability across FHTs for practice setting, roster size, teaching status and the Standardized Adjusted Clinical Group Morbidity Index (SAMI). The SAMI is a measure indicative of the relative complexity of patients rostered to a FHT [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>]. Informants were recruited via email, with the first group of practices identified by AFHTO using an in-house composite measure of quality which is included in the D2D feedback report. All subsequent recruitment groups were selected by the lead investigator (DJW) by actively monitoring representation across the four above measures [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par35" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As previously described, the Consolidated Framework for Implementation Research (CFIR) was used as the conceptual framework for this study [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>]. Two key factors served as the rationale for the use of CFIR against some alternative. First, CFIR reflects a consolidation of theories across implementation science. Second, CFIR offers researchers flexibility in selecting constructs which are considered to be relevant to the study. Furthermore, having a standardized taxonomy of constructs allowed for some comparability of findings across studies [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>]. In the present study, it offered a means to evaluate whether, how, and why different types of FHTs may have engaged D2D to guide their QI activities.
 </p>
 <p id="Par36" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The interview guide for the present study was prepared from a template made available by CFIR’s developers. As described previously, the template guide was adapted to reflect the objectives of the present study [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>]. Further revisions to question structure and sequencing occurred prior to recruitment following piloting of the interview guide with a FHT leader who did not participate in the study.
 </p>
 <p id="Par37" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Interviews began by defining the study context and building rapport. Open-ended questions were then asked to explore how FHTs use D2D, their motivations for participation, and the resources required to participate. Probing questions were used to further explore areas of interest and specific points raised by informants. Next, participants were invited to complete a usability testing exercise of the online D2D feedback report. Informed by user-centred design methodology, usability testing is a technique to evaluate whether the intended users of a product or service can achieve desired tasks. In the context of the A&amp;F literature, usability of the feedback report is an issue which is addressed infrequently, despite the proliferation of electronic feedback [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>]. Participants were encouraged to “think out loud” as they attempted to complete two distinct tasks on the D2D website [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>]. In the first task, participants were asked to load their team specific results in the interactive feedback report on the D2D web-page. In the second task, participants were asked to review their results for the core D2D measures. This approach offered an opportunity to ask probing questions seeking confirming or disconfirming evidence from earlier in the interviews. For example, in the main interview, participants were asked about D2D support materials. Data collected could be validated in the usability exercise by asking the user where they would look for clarity about the data, among other items. The usability testing supported two distinct outputs. First, a summary was provided to AFHTO to support future enhancements to the D2D website design. Second, data were used to support the analysis for the present study as described in the procedures below.
 </p>
</sec>
