<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Intervention</div>
 <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In 2014, the Association of Family Health Teams of Ontario (AFHTO) launched Data-2-Decisions (D2D) as an A&amp;F program and strategy to support FHT efforts to measure and improve the quality of team-based primary care [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>]. As a not-for-profit advocacy association, AFHTO is mandated to promote the delivery of high-quality primary health care among its membership. AFHTO has engaged in a number of activities to evaluate and subsequently improve D2D as part of a fulsome change management strategy [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>]. While AFHTO facilitated recruitment and provided background information for this study, the funding, design, data collection, analysis, and dissemination of this evaluation were independently executed.
 </p>
 <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">D2D is a voluntary initiative, informed by the work of Barbara Starfield to include meaningful measures of quality in primary care [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>]. For the purposes of this study, D2D is classified as an external A&amp;F initiative since it was organized by AFHTO to provide targeted feedback to FHTs. The measures included in D2D are assessed and selected by an AFHTO sub-committee of relevant stakeholders including FHT staff, beyond Executive Directors, who would ultimately receive the D2D reports. Selected measures were intended to reflect patient centered care, access, and guideline concordant practice. Metrics included within the final category (cancer screening, childhood immunization rates and diabetes care) reflect areas of priority identified by Health Quality Ontario or AFHTO itself as well as Canadian practice guidelines [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>]. In other words, D2D deliberately consolidated indicators from multiple initiatives and sources believed, from the perspective of AFHTO members, to be of high-priority. An example of the feedback report, the measures of interest, source of data and rationale for inclusion are presented in Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>. At the time of this study, the audit included three sources of data: FHT electronic medical records, annual patient experience surveys, and administrative data. For measures relying on administrative data, values were acquired in their raw format from the agency responsible for housing it or in summarized format extracted from a primary care group practice report produced by Health Quality Ontario [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>]. Each participating FHT extracted their measures from the relevant source and then manually transcribed them into an online data-entry portal made available by AFHTO during the audit period. The timing of the inputs to the feedback report, relative to its release is presented in Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par31" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Several weeks after the audit process, AFHTO notified participants that their D2D feedback report was available on a password protected website. Notifications were distributed via email, and participants were invited to engage in an AFHTO-hosted webinar to understand the results. As presented in Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>, the D2D feedback report provides a summary of a FHT’s performance relative to a group of peers. Peer status is determined by four self-reported characteristics of each participating FHT: urban or rural setting; teaching status (none, academic, non-academic); access to hospital discharge data; and roster size of the practice.
 </p>
 <p id="Par32" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To facilitate D2D participation, AFHTO collaborates with Quality Improvement Decision Support Specialists (QIDSS). These individuals are funded by the Ontario MoHLTC and are a shared resource among a group of FHTs to support ongoing quality improvement activities. As QIDSS’ responsibilities are exclusive to QI, they are not involved in the daily operations of the FHT. The QIDSS role varies between FHTs to meet individual practice needs. AFHTO provides QIDSS staff with specific training so that they can support D2D. As the availability of the QIDSS resource is not linked to D2D participation, these individuals may engage in separate QI activities within each practice.</p>
</sec>
