<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="FPar5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Relative priority</div>
 <p id="Par51" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">FHTs had access to a wide array of A&amp;F initiatives and participation in these varied widely. All FHTs participated in mandatory quality improvement programs, which included the Quality Improvement Plan (QIP) and patient experience surveys, as outlined in provincial legislation [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>]. Participants had access to feedback reports covering a range of indicators from several existing provincial initiatives [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>]. The most common were Health Quality Ontario’s (HQO) Primary Care Group Practice Report; the Screening Activity Report (SAR) from Cancer Care Ontario (CCO); the Electronic Medical Record Administrative Data Linked Database (EMRALD); and the Canadian Primary Care Sentinel Surveillance Network (CPCSSN) from the College of Family Physicians of Canada [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>]. FHTs also conducted their own internal A&amp;F programs with varying degrees of sophistication. Often, D2D was viewed to be of lower priority relative to these other A&amp;F initiatives. Relative priority was a function of regulatory requirements, available capacity and maturity to support QI, and the perceived attributes of each A&amp;F effort. Specifically, FHTs which lacked internal reporting mechanisms, or which did not participate in external programs assigned greater priority to D2D. (Table 
  <a rid="Tab7" ref-type="table" href="#Tab7">7</a>).
  <div id="Tab7" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 7</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Supporting Quotations for “Relative Priority”</p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td colspan="2">• We rely on our patient surveys and our diabetes stats quite highly, because they are monthly, so they’re real time, and because with our diabetes stats we can then drill down into those stats and find out who the ones are that we’re missing. So that’s very concrete for us. Some of the HQO and the D2D stuff is more higher level. (ID = 015)</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td colspan="2">• Other problem is we have all of our information, which is second to none through CCPSN and UTOPIAN. We now have shared data. We’re housed with the hospital, where we can look at acute and primary and see how we’re going in that area. This is a bit of a make work project for us, but we participate because we thought we’d be very useful to be part of the bigger picture. (ID = 007)</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td colspan="2">• I think what I meant to let you know is that we try to speak to the quality committee this time for 3.0 prior to the board meeting, but it didn’t quite make it through the agenda. And so, the board got presented first, and hopefully we’ll have time to talk to the quality committee about it next time. But our priority was the QIP that’s due out on April 1st, and we had a lot of discussions around that as a priority as opposed to the dissemination of these results. (ID = 002)</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td colspan="2">• I think that we’ve spent quite a lot more time and got more value out of the Cancer Care Ontario SAR Report than anything else. (ID = 014)</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
