<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Setting and context</div>
 <p id="Par28" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Family Health Team (FHT) is a primary-care practice model in Ontario, Canada where a multi-disciplinary team of health care providers collaborate to provide patient-centred care [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>]. The FHT model emerged in parallel with the patient-centred medical home (PCMH) and is thought to meet similar standards and requirements [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>]. All FHT services are available at no cost to the patient and providers are remunerated by the Ontario Ministry of Health and Long Term Care (MoHLTC) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>]. Team members and roles vary between practices. The multi-disciplinary, non-physician, providers on the team are salaried and may include Nurse Practitioners, Social Workers, Dietitians and other regulated and/or unregulated health professionals. The group of physicians affiliated with a FHT may organize under a range of legal structures and are remunerated under a blended capitation model [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>]. It would be appropriate to characterize this setting as a partnership between physicians and the FHT (which represents the interdisciplinary health professionals), as the organizational structures granted to physicians are intended to preserve physician autonomy. The FHT is typically led by an Executive Director who serves as an organizational and administrative lead. Governance of the FHT may be one of three types: i) physician led, where the affiliated physician group makes up the full board; ii) mixed, where governance is shared between the FHT and affiliated physician group; or iii) community sponsored, where governance is led by the FHT and community representatives. At the time of this study there were 184 FHTs in Ontario, serving approximately 3.5 million patients (25.4% of the Ontario population) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
