<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="methods" id="cox065s2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Materials and methods</div>
 <sec id="cox065s2a" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study animal</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Arctic ground squirrels are distributed across northern Alaska, Canada, and eastern Siberia and are the northern most hibernator (
   <a rid="cox065C41" ref-type="bibr" href="#cox065C41">Naughton, 2012</a>). They live in generally well-drained sites in the tundra, the alpine and the meadows of the boreal forest. They are key prey for many predators, including golden eagles, hawks, owls, foxes, wolves, weasels, bears, wolverines and lynx. Their annual cycle includes a short 3–6 months of above-ground active season with spring breeding occurring immediately after females emerge from hibernation in mid to late April (
   <a rid="cox065C13" ref-type="bibr" href="#cox065C13">Buck and Barnes, 1999a</a>; 
   <a rid="cox065C57" ref-type="bibr" href="#cox065C57">Sheriff 
    <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2011a
   </a>). The breeding season lasts only 2 weeks, and females exhibit behavioral estrus on only 1 day (
   <a rid="cox065C31" ref-type="bibr" href="#cox065C31">Lacey 
    <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 1997
   </a>). Females produce a single litter ~25 days later in mid to late May, in underground burrows, and young appear above ground shortly before weaning in late June to early July (
   <a rid="cox065C30" ref-type="bibr" href="#cox065C30">Lacey, 1991</a>). Dispersal occurs 2–3 weeks thereafter, with nearly all males dispersing (~515 m) from their natal home range and most females remaining within their natal home range (~120 m from natal burrow; 
   <a rid="cox065C17" ref-type="bibr" href="#cox065C17">Byrom and Krebs, 1999</a>). Adult females enter hibernation as early as late July, juvenile females enter hibernation in mid to late September, and juvenile males enter in early October (
   <a rid="cox065C57" ref-type="bibr" href="#cox065C57">Sheriff 
    <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2011a
   </a>). Animals spend the remaining 6–9 months sequestered in their hibernacula alternating between long bouts (2–3 weeks) of torpor at core body temperatures as low as −2.9°C and short (&lt;1 day) periods of high body temperature (~36°C; 
   <a rid="cox065C25" ref-type="bibr" href="#cox065C25">Barnes, 1989</a>; 
   <a rid="cox065C15" ref-type="bibr" href="#cox065C15">Buck 
    <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2008
   </a>). During this long hibernation, females lose approximately 1 g of body mass per day and emerge from hibernation at their lowest body condition, having lost approximately 35% of their body mass including a 66% loss in body fat and a 21% loss in lean mass (
   <a rid="cox065C14" ref-type="bibr" href="#cox065C14">Buck and Barnes, 1999b</a>). Thus, at the most energetically expensive time (breeding) females are at their worst body condition.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="cox065s2b" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study area and AGS phenological-environmental relationship</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our study occurred in 2011 and 2012 at two sites with large contiguous AGS populations, Toolik Lake and Atigun River. These sites are separated by approximately 20 km along the Dalton Highway in northern Alaska (68°N, 149°W). The topography is similar at both sites, being relatively flat with gently rolling hills underlain by continuous permafrost with a seasonal thaw depth of 1–2 m (
   <a rid="cox065C14" ref-type="bibr" href="#cox065C14">Buck and Barnes, 1999b</a>). Entrances to burrows at the two sites do not differ in exposure to or shelter from solar radiation, shade or wind.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Arctic ground squirrels are generalist herbivores (
   <a rid="cox065C2" ref-type="bibr" href="#cox065C2">Batzli and Sobaski, 1980</a>; 
   <a rid="cox065C24" ref-type="bibr" href="#cox065C24">Hobbie 
    <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2017
   </a>) and, although there may be vegetation differences between the sites in terms of plant phenology and composition (albeit slight MJS pers. obs.; Toolik Environmental Data Center http://toolik.alaska.edu/edc/), the most pronounced difference between the sites is the marked food restriction in spring due to prolonged snow cover throughout AGS pregnancy at Toolik as compared to Atigun (
   <a rid="cox065C61" ref-type="bibr" href="#cox065C61">Sheriff 
    <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2015
   </a>). As snow melts at both sites it creates a mottled patchy environment, where most areas have snow-free and snow-covered patches. This patchy environment may present several challenges as AGS must traverse across snow patches to access snow-free areas, making squirrels more vulnerable to predation and increasing their cost of locomotion. Additionally, at Toolik 100% snow cover occurs from mid to late September, a critical time for offspring that are still fattening in preparation for hibernation (which begins late September—early October). At Atigun, 100% snow cover usually begins late September—early October after offspring have entered hibernation (
   <a rid="cox065C61" ref-type="bibr" href="#cox065C61">Sheriff 
    <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2015
   </a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The timing of snow cover has been recorded since 2007 using a camera (Campbell Scientific, CC640 Digital Camera) mounted on a tower facing across each study area that captures a daily image at solar noon. We assessed the percentage of area within each image covered with snow from April 15th (prior to first female emergence at either site) until October 10th (after offspring entrance into hibernation) for 2011 and 2012 from camera images.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="cox065s2c" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Animal handling and population estimates</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Arctic ground squirrels were captured using live-traps (Tomahawk Live Trap Co., Tomahawk, Wisconsin) baited with carrot. Adult females were captured 10–14 days after conception at mid-gestation (early to mid-May) which we term gestation, and at weaning (early to mid-July); juveniles were captured at weaning, and prior to entering hibernation (early to mid-September) which we term pre-hibernation. Adult females were not trapped prior to entering hibernation as this can occur as early as late July and continue into late August, making standardization of timing difficult at a population level. Phenological differences between the sites were accounted for and, thus, AGS at Toolik were captured 6–10 days after those at Atigun. At each time point, we estimated population density via mark-recapture methods on 6 ha grids with stations spaced 20 m apart in a 15 × 10 m array and traps at alternate stations. Traps were set at 0800–1000 h depending upon season, and checked every 2 h, with no more than 4 capture sessions per day per site, and a total of eight capture sessions per site over a 3-day period. Upon first capture, AGS were weighed with a Pesola spring scale (±5 g), assessed for sex and ID, measured for zygomatic arch width (± 0.5 mm; as an index of body size), and assessed for reproductive condition. Upon initial capture, new individuals were uniquely ear-tagged (Monel #1 and a unique 4-color combination). A fecal sample, for later determination of cortisol metabolite levels, was collected only from individuals captured in the first session of the day and who had not been captured within the previous 48 h. These grids were placed within the larger contiguous populations at both sites.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">‘Body condition’ was estimated from 86 adult females (31 from Toolik and 55 from Atigun) and 112 juveniles (41 from Toolik and 71 from Atigun) as the residuals of body mass (g) regressed on zygomatic arch width (a reliable estimate of skeletal size; 
   <a rid="cox065C54" ref-type="bibr" href="#cox065C54">Schulte-Hostedde 
    <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2005
   </a>) with simple linear regression using ordinary least squares. 
   <a rid="cox065C54" ref-type="bibr" href="#cox065C54">Schulte-Hostedde 
    <span class="italic">et al.</span> (2005)
   </a> assessed techniques for determining body condition and report that this method performs best. ‘Reproductive output’ was estimated as the number of offspring per adult female (calculated from the density of each when young first appeared above ground). ‘Recruitment’ was estimated as the density of young-of-the-year (juveniles) at pre-hibernation. All density estimates were calculated using the maximum likelihood spatial model within the program Density version 5.02 using all the default parameters (
   <a rid="cox065C22" ref-type="bibr" href="#cox065C22">Efford 
    <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2009
   </a>). This model has been used to estimate AGS population density previously (
   <a rid="cox065C64" ref-type="bibr" href="#cox065C64">Werner 
    <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2015
   </a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="cox065s2d" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Stress physiology</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used an enzyme immunoassay to measure fecal cortisol metabolite (FCM) concentrations (reflecting glucocorticoid levels) from 41 adult females (18 from Toolik and 23 from Atigun) and 61 juveniles (24 from Toolik and 37 from Atigun), validated specifically for use with AGS (see 
   <a rid="cox065C59" ref-type="bibr" href="#cox065C59">Sheriff 
    <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2012
   </a> for details). FCM values represent one of the least invasive measures of physiological stress and have been widely used in wild animals (
   <a rid="cox065C58" ref-type="bibr" href="#cox065C58">Sheriff 
    <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2011b
   </a>; 
   <a rid="cox065C20" ref-type="bibr" href="#cox065C20">Dantzer 
    <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2014
   </a>). FCM values reflect free (unbound to corticosteroid binding globulin) glucocorticoid levels found in the blood (
   <a rid="cox065C56" ref-type="bibr" href="#cox065C56">Sheriff 
    <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2010
   </a>; 
   <a rid="cox065C23" ref-type="bibr" href="#cox065C23">Fauteux 
    <span class="italic">et al.</span> 2017
   </a>) that an individual has experienced over a specific time period (
   <a rid="cox065C44" ref-type="bibr" href="#cox065C44">Palme 
    <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2005
   </a>), 4–12 h in AGS (
   <a rid="cox065C59" ref-type="bibr" href="#cox065C59">Sheriff 
    <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2012
   </a>). Thus, FCM values provide an integrated measure of circulation glucocorticoid levels, better reflecting the average physiological state of the individual as compared with blood samples, that provide a point-in-time sample (
   <a rid="cox065C58" ref-type="bibr" href="#cox065C58">Sheriff 
    <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2011b
   </a>). FCM values have been used to investigate the influence of both predictable (changes in season, reproductive status, etc.) and unpredictable stressors (predation risk, food limitations, competition) in a wide variety of free-living animals (reviewed in 
   <a rid="cox065C58" ref-type="bibr" href="#cox065C58">Sheriff 
    <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2011b
   </a>; 
   <a rid="cox065C20" ref-type="bibr" href="#cox065C20">Dantzer 
    <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2014
   </a>). Although it is often assumed that individuals with higher FCM levels have reduced fitness, it is important to appreciate that, as with any measure of physiological stress, the FCM—fitness relationship likely forms a bell shaped curve with greater levels potential increasing an individual’s ability to cope with a particular stressor to a certain threshold at which point greater levels reduce fitness (
   <a rid="cox065C53" ref-type="bibr" href="#cox065C53">Selye, 1936</a>). Thus, FCM levels are best suited to provide insights into how individuals cope with a particular stressor and should be paired with actual fitness measures (
   <span class="italic">sensu</span>
   <a rid="cox065C20" ref-type="bibr" href="#cox065C20">Dantzer 
    <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2014
   </a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this study fecal samples were obtained within 2 h of capture, thus the stress of capture would not have affected measured FCM levels (
   <a rid="cox065C59" ref-type="bibr" href="#cox065C59">Sheriff 
    <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2012
   </a>). Further, although human disturbance may increase FCM values, trapping and sampling procedures were similar between sites and this potential disturbance likely did not affect potential site differences in FCM levels. Further, AGS are highly re-trappable (even within the same session), indicating humans and traps are not perceived as much of a threat. Upon collection in the field, feces were immediately placed on wet ice, transported back to the Toolik Field Station, and frozen at −20°C within 7 h of collection. Samples were transported on dry ice to the University of Toronto where they were lyophilized (LabConco, Missouri, USA) and homogenized. Following extraction with 80% methanol (50 ± 3 mg feces with 1 ml), FCMs were measured as outlined by 
   <a rid="cox065C59" ref-type="bibr" href="#cox065C59">Sheriff 
    <span class="italic">et al.</span> (2012)
   </a> using the 11-oxoetiocholanolone-EIA developed by 
   <a rid="cox065C39" ref-type="bibr" href="#cox065C39">Möstl 
    <span class="italic">et al.</span> (2002)
   </a>. Intra-assay and inter-assay coefficient of variation (CV) were 15.3% and 14.6%, respectively (
   <span class="italic">n</span> = 22 plates).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="cox065s2e" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analyses</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All data are presented as mean ± SE, unless otherwise stated. All statistics were performed using the software package STATISTICA 10. Because individual ground squirrels could not be tracked throughout the entire study, individual ID was tested as a covariate. The latter was found to be non-significant and was dropped from the models. The assumption of normality was tested with Shapiro–Wilks test, and the assumption of homogeneity of variances was tested with Levene’s test. For data that met the assumptions we used a 3-way ANOVA (site × date × year). For data that did not meet the assumptions a Kruskal–Wallis non-parametric test was used; no interaction effects could be tested. Comparisons of the means were considered significant if 
   <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.05.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
