<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="cox065s4d" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Recruitment</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We found that pre-hibernation juvenile density was lower and that there was a 10% greater reduction in density from weaning to hibernation at Toolik compared with Atigun. This was particularly evident in 2012, when pre-hibernation density at Toolik was 0.19 juvniles/ha, only 25% of that at weaning, whereas at Atigun the pre-hibernation density was 1.89 juveniles/ha, almost 70% of that at weaning. At weaning in 2012, Toolik offspring were in significantly worse condition and had significantly higher FCM levels, which may have affected their propensity to disperse and their survival (although we do not know the exact fates of juveniles who disappeared off of our trapping grids). Juvenile dispersal in AGS occurs in the first few weeks of July and is sex-specific; studies in the Yukon have shown that females are highly philopatric and disperse approximately 120 m, and males disperse approximately 500 m from the natal area (
  <a rid="cox065C17" ref-type="bibr" href="#cox065C17">Byrom and Krebs, 1999</a>). During this time juveniles, regardless of sex, lose significant mass (
  <a rid="cox065C13" ref-type="bibr" href="#cox065C13">Buck and Barnes, 1999a</a>); however, little is known about how an individual’s stress physiology may influence dispersal. In other vertebrates, glucocorticoid levels have been shown to alter juvenile dispersal. For example, in willow tits (
  <span class="italic">Parus montanus</span>) experimental increases in glucocorticoids increased dispersal propensity (
  <a rid="cox065C30000" ref-type="bibr" href="#cox065C30000">Silverin, 1997</a>), and in the common lizard (
  <span class="italic">Lacerta vivipara</span>) experimental increases in both maternal and juvenile glucocorticoids alter juvenile dispersal (
  <a rid="cox065C36" ref-type="bibr" href="#cox065C36">Meylan 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2004
  </a>). This has been suggested as an adaptive mechanism increasing offspring movement out of poor habitats (
  <a rid="cox065C35" ref-type="bibr" href="#cox065C35">Meylan and Clobert, 2005</a>). Adult density is likely unrelated to the potential greater dispersal of Toolik offspring, given Atigun density is higher than Toolik (see 
  <span class="italic">Reproductive output</span> in Results).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The low recruitment and large reduction in Toolik offspring density in 2012 may also be driven by decreased offspring survival. In 2012, Toolik offspring were in poor body condition and may have needed to spend more time foraging, increasing their susceptibility to predation (AGS are primary prey for nearly all arctic mammal and avian predators). Additionally, their poor start may have been exacerbated by the poor environment at Toolik, where winter snow begins to accumulate and reduce food availability earlier in the active season. Clearly, the interaction AGS have with their environment likely plays an important role in recruitment of offspring, and as environments change in the spring (altering maternal condition) or in the autumn (altering the ability of offspring to prepare for hibernation) recruitment is likely to be greatly affected.</p>
</sec>
