<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="cox065s2a" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study animal</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Arctic ground squirrels are distributed across northern Alaska, Canada, and eastern Siberia and are the northern most hibernator (
  <a rid="cox065C41" ref-type="bibr" href="#cox065C41">Naughton, 2012</a>). They live in generally well-drained sites in the tundra, the alpine and the meadows of the boreal forest. They are key prey for many predators, including golden eagles, hawks, owls, foxes, wolves, weasels, bears, wolverines and lynx. Their annual cycle includes a short 3–6 months of above-ground active season with spring breeding occurring immediately after females emerge from hibernation in mid to late April (
  <a rid="cox065C13" ref-type="bibr" href="#cox065C13">Buck and Barnes, 1999a</a>; 
  <a rid="cox065C57" ref-type="bibr" href="#cox065C57">Sheriff 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2011a
  </a>). The breeding season lasts only 2 weeks, and females exhibit behavioral estrus on only 1 day (
  <a rid="cox065C31" ref-type="bibr" href="#cox065C31">Lacey 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 1997
  </a>). Females produce a single litter ~25 days later in mid to late May, in underground burrows, and young appear above ground shortly before weaning in late June to early July (
  <a rid="cox065C30" ref-type="bibr" href="#cox065C30">Lacey, 1991</a>). Dispersal occurs 2–3 weeks thereafter, with nearly all males dispersing (~515 m) from their natal home range and most females remaining within their natal home range (~120 m from natal burrow; 
  <a rid="cox065C17" ref-type="bibr" href="#cox065C17">Byrom and Krebs, 1999</a>). Adult females enter hibernation as early as late July, juvenile females enter hibernation in mid to late September, and juvenile males enter in early October (
  <a rid="cox065C57" ref-type="bibr" href="#cox065C57">Sheriff 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2011a
  </a>). Animals spend the remaining 6–9 months sequestered in their hibernacula alternating between long bouts (2–3 weeks) of torpor at core body temperatures as low as −2.9°C and short (&lt;1 day) periods of high body temperature (~36°C; 
  <a rid="cox065C25" ref-type="bibr" href="#cox065C25">Barnes, 1989</a>; 
  <a rid="cox065C15" ref-type="bibr" href="#cox065C15">Buck 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2008
  </a>). During this long hibernation, females lose approximately 1 g of body mass per day and emerge from hibernation at their lowest body condition, having lost approximately 35% of their body mass including a 66% loss in body fat and a 21% loss in lean mass (
  <a rid="cox065C14" ref-type="bibr" href="#cox065C14">Buck and Barnes, 1999b</a>). Thus, at the most energetically expensive time (breeding) females are at their worst body condition.
 </p>
</sec>
