<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par5" class="p">The ITCZ moves north and south across the equator following the seasonal cycle of solar insolation, and is intimately connected to seasonal monsoon circulations [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">6</xref>]. In the annual average, the ITCZ lies a few degrees north of the equator [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>]. Considerable research has focused on why the ITCZ lies north of the equator, and how this meridional location responds to past and future climate change [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">8</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">11</xref>]. An energetic theory has been developed over the past two decades to diagnose how processes in Earth’s climate—including radiation asymmetries between hemispheres, atmosphere-ocean coupling, and energy input to the tropical atmosphere—control the zonal-mean ITCZ location [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">21</xref>]. This theory has recently been extended to understand variations of the ITCZ location with longitude [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">22</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">23</xref>]. Four recent review articles have comprehensively synthesized this body of research on the ITCZ location [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">1</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">24</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" class="xref">26</xref>]. Here, we provide a broader perspective of the response of the ITCZ to climate change. We focus on two aspects of the ITCZ which have received relatively little attention: its width and strength. In contrast to the ITCZ location, which has not shifted substantially over the past three decades in the Pacific [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" class="xref">27</xref>] and which shows no robust response in simulations with elevated CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> concentrations [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" class="xref">26</xref>], the ITCZ width and tropical circulation strength have changed significantly over recent decades [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" class="xref">27</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>]. And, the ITCZ width and circulation strength are predicted to continue changing into the future [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">30</xref>]. In climate change simulations, the ITCZ narrows and strengthens in the core of the ascent region as climate warms, a pattern of change which has been termed the “deep-tropics squeeze” [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>]. These changes are expected to have important impacts on tropical regions. Our physical understanding of why the ITCZ width and strength change with warming is only beginning to develop [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">30</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">38</xref>] and represents a key challenge in climate dynamics. Limited understanding of ITCZ width and strength contrasts with our well-developed knowledge of the ITCZ location and the extent of the Hadley circulation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" class="xref">39</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" class="xref">42</xref>].
</p>
