<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="methods" id="s2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec id="s2a" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study species</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We tested the effect of temperature on the nectar production of two perennial Mediterranean species of the Lamiaceae family, 
   <span class="italic">Ballota acetabulosa</span> (L.) Benth. and 
   <span class="italic">Teucrium divaricatum</span> Sieber ex Heldr. Both species inhabit the same phryganic communities, but prefer to grow in different microhabitats. While 
   <span class="italic">B. acetabulosa</span> often grows near stony structures or walls (e.g. abandoned agricultural terraces) or in places partially shaded by taller vegetation (e.g. in dehesa type scrub) (
   <a rid="PLV111C34" ref-type="bibr" href="#PLV111C34">Petanidou 
    <span class="italic">et al</span>. 2000
   </a>; T. Petanidou, pers. obs.), 
   <span class="italic">T. divaricatum</span> clearly prefers well-sunlit open habitats. Both species flower at the same time of the year, from May to July (
   <a rid="PLV111C7" ref-type="bibr" href="#PLV111C7">Davis 1982</a>; 
   <a rid="PLV111C28" ref-type="bibr" href="#PLV111C28">Petanidou 1991</a>). They are visited by a wide range of medium- to large-sized wild bees of the families Megachilidae and Apidae and are also important food plants for bee-keeping (
   <a rid="PLV111C28" ref-type="bibr" href="#PLV111C28">Petanidou 1991</a>; 
   <a rid="PLV111C6" ref-type="bibr" href="#PLV111C6">Dauber 
    <span class="italic">et al</span>. 2010
   </a>; T. Petanidou 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span> unpubl. data).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2b" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Experiment design</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Plants of 
   <span class="italic">B. acetabulosa</span> used in the experiment were grown from seeds collected from the I. &amp; A. Diomedes Botanical Garden of Athens University in 2005. Seeds were sown in October 2013, potted as seedlings, and grown outdoors until flowering. As for 
   <span class="italic">T. divaricatum</span>, entire plants were collected from a natural population on Lesvos Island in October 2013, potted and grown outdoors until they were in bloom, ready to be used in the experiment.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The experiment was conducted at the University of the Aegean in Mytilene on Lesvos Island. Both study species were subjected to the same treatments simultaneously. For each species, two groups of plants were considered. One treatment group (15 plants per species) was tested under different temperature regimes in a climate chamber (Walk-in GRW-20 CMP 3/TBLIN, CDR Chryssagis™) and the second treatment group (six plants per species) was grown outdoors under naturally varying temperature and air humidity conditions. Comparing the two treatments allows us to estimate the effect of temperature separately from the effect of time and thus see, whether the trends are driven solely by temperature or whether they may be partially caused by the plants’ intrinsic limitations (e.g. exhausted nutrient reserves), which plants naturally incur during their flowering period. Some of the initial plants (one for 
   <span class="italic">B. acetabulosa</span> in the climate chamber, and 16 for 
   <span class="italic">T. divaricatum</span>, of which 11 in the climate chamber and 5 outdoors) were replaced with new ones during the experiment when they got close to the end of their flowering period, in order to have the same number of flowering plants at all tested temperatures. Altogether, including the replacement plants, 22 
   <span class="italic">B. acetabulosa</span> and 38 
   <span class="italic">T. divaricatum</span> plants were employed. Each plant was labelled with a unique number and considered as a separate entity in the subsequent analyses. The experiment for both species lasted from 24 May to 17 June 2014 in the climate chamber and in the outdoors from 24 May to 8 July 2014, following the plants through the flowering period both in the climate chamber and outdoors.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the climate chamber, a 14-h photoperiod was used for both species, corresponding to the natural day length at the time of the year. A mixture of plant growth fluorescent lamps (Gro-lux) and low-pressure sodium lamps were used, with a total light intensity of ∼800 μmol m
   <span class="sup">−2</span> s
   <span class="sup">−1</span> (∼43 000 lx) over the waveband 400–700 nm in the chamber. Light intensity in the chamber was somewhat lower than what the plants would experience in nature; however, the intensity was constant throughout the days, compensating for the lower intensity.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The climate chamber experiment for both species was started at the lowest temperatures, and the temperature was increased every 3 days by 3 °C increments. Tested 24 h average temperatures ranged from 17.5 to 38.5 °C (day temperatures 20–41 °C, night temperatures always 6 °C lower, corresponding to the approximate natural difference between day and night temperatures at the time of the year). Tested temperatures were chosen to cover a range around the long-term (1958–2001) June average temperature of ∼26 °C according to Elefsis weather station near Athens, Greece, but including also elevated temperatures at least up to the temperatures predicted by climate change scenarios (
   <a rid="PLV111C18" ref-type="bibr" href="#PLV111C18">IPCC 2013</a>) to test for the effect of future climate warming. Relative air humidity was kept constant at 60 ± 5% during the day and 80 ± 5% during the night, corresponding approximately to current natural conditions. Plants were watered on the first day of every temperature step to avoid water stress.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Plants in the outdoor group were placed in an open area in full sunlight and were covered with large and airy tulle cages to prevent pollinator visits. The light intensity inside the covered cages was higher than in the climate chamber (∼1400 μmol m
   <span class="sup">−2</span> s
   <span class="sup">−1</span> or ∼75 000 lx). Data on ambient temperatures outdoors were obtained from the nearby (&lt;300 m) climate station at the University of the Aegean in Mytilene (
   <span xlink:href="http://catastrophes.geo.aegean.gr/" class="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://catastrophes.geo.aegean.gr/</span>). The average temperature of the 3 days corresponding to each temperature step in the climate chamber was used in the analyses. The mean outdoor temperature during the test period ranged from 16.7 to 26.1 °C.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nectar measurements both in the climate chamber and in the outdoor group were taken between 1230 and 1700 h on Day 3 of each temperature step, to give the plants in the climate chamber time to adjust to the changed conditions before sampling. Flowers were sampled on the first day of anthesis following 
   <a rid="PLV111C31" ref-type="bibr" href="#PLV111C31">Petanidou and Smets (1996)</a>. To ensure that only first day flowers were sampled, all open flowers were removed on Day 2, 24 h before nectar collection. Nectar was extracted from flowers with Drummond microcaps
   <span class="sup">®</span> (2 and 1 μL for 
   <span class="italic">B. acetabulosa</span>; 0.5 μL for 
   <span class="italic">T. divaricatum</span>), using a single flower per sample. Three flowers per plant, selected randomly from among the flowers directly exposed to light, were sampled for nectar volume and sugar concentration per flower. Nectar sugar concentration of each of the sampled flowers was measured by using special hand refractometers for small nectar volumes (Bellingham &amp; Stanley LTD, Tunbridge Wells). After sampling, the same three flowers per plant that were sampled for nectar were dried at 50 °C for 12 h and their biomass per flower was weighed (calyx and corolla together). All flowers, which had opened during the previous 24 h were counted and removed after nectar sampling on Day 3 before proceeding to the next temperature set.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2c" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The sugar content per flower (micrograms) was calculated (volume per flower × concentration × density) with the density values taken from available sugar solution density tables (
   <a rid="PLV111C5" ref-type="bibr" href="#PLV111C5">Dafni 
    <span class="italic">et al</span>. 2005
   </a>). In the very few cases (18/840 flowers of 
   <span class="italic">B. acetabulosa</span> and 7/845 of 
   <span class="italic">T. divaricatum</span>) when the collected nectar volume was too small for the refractometer to measure sugar concentration, the average value of sugar concentration of the other two flowers from the same plant was used, in order to be able to calculate sugar content per flower. For data analysis, we used the average values of the three sampled flowers per plant. Sugar content per plant was calculated by multiplying the average sugar content per flower with the number of flowers per plant produced on Day 3. The proportion of empty flowers per plant (i.e. producing no nectar) was also calculated based on the three flowers sampled for nectar. Proportion of empty flowers per plant was used in models only in the case of 
   <span class="italic">B. acetabulosa</span>, because 
   <span class="italic">T. divaricatum</span> produced only few nectarless flowers. We calculated the coefficient of variation (CV) for each of the measured flower traits (nectar volume, concentration, sugar content and biomass per flower) to characterize trait variation within a plant. In the case of sugar concentration per flower, the CV was determined based on the original data, prior to calculating the sugar concentration for the measurements with too small nectar volumes for direct sugar concentration detection. If the mean trait value of a plant was zero, the CV of the corresponding trait was also defined to be zero for that plant. Nectar volume per flower, sugar content per flower, sugar content per plant, number of flowers per plant and biomass per flower data were log-transformed and nectar sugar concentration per flower was logit-transformed to deal with the constraints of percentage data.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We tested for the possible differences between the original and replacement plants of 
   <span class="italic">T. divaricatum</span> in their response to time, using linear mixed models (LMM) with interaction terms (‘time × replacement group’). There were no significant differences in the studied traits, except in sugar concentration per flower in the outdoor group (time
   <span class="sup">2</span>× replacement group interaction, 
   <span class="italic">t</span> = −2.013, 
   <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.049). Similarity of response indicates that the replacement plants had similar response patterns to the original plants and that the two plant groups can be analysed together in order to identify the general response patterns.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data analysis was carried out in three consecutive steps. First, we used LMM models to identify the effect of temperature on plant traits in the climate chamber, testing both linear and quadratic effect of temperature on the traits and using plant number (plant ID) as a random factor. Analysis of variance (ANOVA) was used to compare the fit of the linear and quadratic models, based on the AIC values. However, it is essential to note that in the climate chamber we could not truly separate the effect of temperature and time on plants, since the temperature was increased linearly with time.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Secondly, we used the outdoor data to discern the separate effect of temperature on plant traits independent of time, fitting LMM models with two crossed random factors (plant ID and time from the beginning of the experiment) on the outdoor data. Naturally, temperature outdoors increased with time throughout the study period from May to July (
   <span class="italic">r</span> = 0.65, 
   <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.009). However, this modelling approach enables us to separate the real effect of temperature on plant traits by taking into account the effect of time as a random factor.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As a third step, we identified the possible differences in response to time between the plants manipulated in the climate chamber and the plants grown outdoors. In these models we defined treatment group (climate chamber or outdoor) as an explanatory variable and used ‘trait × group’ interaction for identifying differences between the groups. No difference in trait response between the groups would therefore indicate that the trends in the climate chamber could be explained by the effect of time and that the effect of temperature was negligible or at least not significant. If the interaction terms in the models are significant, then the difference between the climate chamber and outdoor group can be attributed to the effect of elevated temperatures in the climate chamber. We did not perform the third set of models for the trait variation (CV) data because the effect of temperature on these traits was negligible in the first two sets of models.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to compare the response to time between the climate chamber and outdoor treatment groups, which had a different experiment duration, we used standardized time (mean = 0, SD = 1) in the models. Although having a different duration, the time span corresponds to the same ecological period for plants in both test groups, since the plants were examined from the beginning of full bloom until the end of the flowering period both in the climate chamber and outdoors.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All studied traits except the proportion of empty flowers per plant were modelled by following the description above. For modelling the proportion of empty flowers of 
   <span class="italic">B. acetabulosa</span>, we followed a similar protocol, but used generalized linear mixed models (GLMM) with a negative binomial error distribution to account for the different distribution in the data. We also tested for the need to use zero-inflated models, but models with no zero-inflation parameter had a better fit (lower AIC values).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The analyses were conducted in R 3.1.1 (
   <a rid="PLV111C36" ref-type="bibr" href="#PLV111C36">R Core Team 2014</a>). Linear mixed models were fitted using the function 
   <span class="italic">lmer</span> in the 
   <span class="italic">lme4</span> package (
   <a rid="PLV111C2" ref-type="bibr" href="#PLV111C2">Bates 
    <span class="italic">et al</span>. 2014
   </a>), the GLMM models were built using the function 
   <span class="italic">glmmadmb</span> in the package 
   <span class="italic">glmmADMB</span> (
   <a rid="PLV111C10" ref-type="bibr" href="#PLV111C10">Fournier 
    <span class="italic">et al</span>. 2012
   </a>; 
   <a rid="PLV111C42" ref-type="bibr" href="#PLV111C42">Skaug 
    <span class="italic">et al</span>. 2015
   </a>). Additional 
   <span class="italic">P</span>-values for the 
   <span class="italic">t</span>-values in LMM models were calculated using the package 
   <span class="italic">lmerTest</span> (
   <a rid="PLV111C21" ref-type="bibr" href="#PLV111C21">Kuznetsova 
    <span class="italic">et al</span>. 2014
   </a>) and the conditional and marginal coefficients of determination (
   <span class="italic">R</span>
   <span class="sup">2</span>c and 
   <span class="italic">R</span>
   <span class="sup">2</span>m) for the LMM models were calculated with the function 
   <span class="italic">r.squaredGLMM</span> in the package 
   <span class="italic">MuMIn</span> (
   <a rid="PLV111C1" ref-type="bibr" href="#PLV111C1">Barton 2015</a>). 
   <span class="italic">R</span>
   <span class="sup">2</span>c shows the model variance explained by both fixed and random factors, while 
   <span class="italic">R</span>
   <span class="sup">2</span>m represents the variance explained by fixed factors alone. Graphs were compiled using the function 
   <span class="italic">ggplot</span> in the 
   <span class="italic">ggplot2</span> package (
   <a rid="PLV111C48" ref-type="bibr" href="#PLV111C48">Wickham 2009</a>) using a smoothing function to plot the relationships.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
