<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Comparing the populations’ responses to climate (type B and type C traits) in the common garden revealed existing genetic variation for tolerance to freeze and drought. The positive influence of a warm autumn during the year preceding ring formation (CS
 <sub class="sub">BAI</sub>–Temp.Oct
 <sub class="sub">(
  <italic class="italic">t</italic>−1)
 </sub>) was stronger for populations from southernmost provenances and significantly increased with MAT
 <sub class="sub">p</sub> (Fig. 
 <xref rid="nph14968-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" class="xref">4</xref>a,b). Furthermore, the negative effect of early autumn freeze (CS
 <sub class="sub">BAI</sub>–Freeze.Oct
 <sub class="sub">(
  <italic class="italic">t</italic>−1)
 </sub>) and late spring freeze (CS
 <sub class="sub">BAI</sub>–Freeze.Jun
 <sub class="sub">(
  <italic class="italic">t</italic>)
 </sub>) was greater for warm provenances (Fig. 
 <xref rid="nph14968-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S6</xref>). The timing of bud set and bud flush are two important traits involved in the adaptation to local climate that are known to be under strong genetic control in forest trees (e.g. Billington &amp; Pelham, 
 <xref rid="nph14968-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1991</xref>; Savolainen 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="nph14968-bib-0070" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2004</xref>; Bennie 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="nph14968-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>; McKown 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="nph14968-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). Populations from colder provenances have probably evolved to set buds and enter dormancy earlier, thereby minimizing the risk of early autumn freeze injuries. Clinal variations in cold hardiness were also reported for 
 <italic class="italic">P. strobus</italic> (Lu 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="nph14968-bib-0050" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2003</xref>), thus supporting our findings that warmer provenances were more likely to be impacted by freeze injuries and to exhibit reduced growth. Genetic variation related to cold hardiness was further demonstrated by among‐provenance variations in the standardized residual growth of 2003 (BAI
 <sub class="sub">2003</sub>) following lower than average temperatures (e.g. −2°C) during autumn 2002 and spring 2003 (type B traits). The relative growth reduction following this event was significantly more pronounced for populations from warmer provenances (Fig. 
 <xref rid="nph14968-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3</xref>e), with the two southern group provenances exhibiting a very severe growth reduction.
</p>
