<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Saami People</div>
  <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The traditional settlement area is called 
   <span class="italic">Sápmi</span> (land of the Saami) in the North Saami language. The population of Saami people is estimated at 50,000–70,000 in Norway [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>], over 10,000 in Finland [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>], 20,000–35,000 in Sweden [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>••], and 2000 in Russia [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>]. Approximately half of the Saami speak Saami as their native language. All Saami languages are classified as endangered or highly endangered [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>]. Traditional Saami livelihoods include reindeer herding, fishing, hunting, handicrafts (duodji), and gathering. Reindeer herding is the most viable livelihood. Many of the Saami reindeer-herding families are also involved in Saami handicrafts, fishing, and gathering. In Sweden and Norway, practically only the Saami can practice reindeer herding. At present many Saami are occupied outside traditional livelihoods and many, especially youth, have migrated to urban regions outside Sápmi [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Framework and Theory</div>
  <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The main proposition is that the global change driven by the anthropogenic climate change is influencing entire cultures of the indigenous populations in the Artic (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). We conceptualized the complex causal web schematically in Figs. 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a> and 
   <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>. Figure 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>a is an extension of the framework of the Center for Environmental and Respiratory Health Research multidisciplinary research program established in 2009 [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>]. In the present form, “public health” appearing in the center was replaced with “culture, well-being, and health”. The arrows from Global change illustrate how the effects of global change are hypothesized to be mediated through climate, air, water, and soil pollution, housing, and life style. Figure 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>a explains the multi-dimensional, direct and indirect effects of climate change to culture, well-being, and health.
   <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Flowchart of the systematic literature search</p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="40572_2018_211_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
   <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>
      <span class="bold">a</span> Conceptual framework of the study. 
      <span class="bold">b</span> Main factors influencing the health and well-being of Saami individual in reindeer-herding community
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="40572_2018_211_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
   <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Local observations on the effects of climate change in Sápmi region based on the present systematic literature research and complementary fieldwork by Dr. Näkkäläjärvi</p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="40572_2018_211_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We apply the proposition of Butler and Harley to divide the health effects of climate change into the primary, secondary, and tertiary effects. The primary effects arise from the direct changes and impacts of the physical system. The secondary effects arise due to alternations in the ecology of vectors, parasites, and host animals, and effects mediated by the allergens and air pollutants are included in this category. The tertiary effects refer to wider scale of effects caused by intersection of climate, politics, and ecology, both human and non-human [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>••]. Our framework in the Saami context is expanded to cover cultural and social effects of climate change. Cultural and social effects are likely to influence health and well-being.
  </p>
  <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figure 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>a, b describes the different methodological approaches to understand the factors effecting Saami health and cultural well-being in a changing climate and the main forces driving the global change.
  </p>
  <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figure 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>a describes the central research disciplines and research methods that applied to study the holistic effects of climate change on Saami culture. Figure 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>b describes the ethno-ecological niche [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>] of Saami people and the changing framework of their culture. The niche includes the individual and the 
   <span class="italic">siida</span> that is kinship-based Saami communal structure that manages reindeer work in its own area. Each siida has its own pasture areas, but the siida system is very flexible [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>]. The cultural ecological framework of the niche consists of the 
   <span class="italic">eallu</span> (the reindeer) and biodiversity. Saami people and culture are not isolated but part of larger Saami community and national society with its legislation, practices, education system, and jurisprudence. Climate change has been identified as a new framework for Saami culture and livelihoods due to its far-reaching and holistic influences [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>••, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>•].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Literature Search and Complementary Evidence</div>
  <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We conducted a systematic literature review on peer-reviewed publications covering any articles on (1) Saami people; (2) Saami reindeer herding; and (3) climate change and its effects on the Saami and the Sápmi region. We focused only on studies providing empirical research data, either qualitative or quantitative. The inclusion criteria were that the article provided information on (1) Saami culture, health, well-being and/or livelihoods; and (2) the effects of climate change on the Sápmi and Saami livelihoods. Keywords were selected based on tests of different keywords in academic search engines. Articles published in 1990–2017 were included.</p>
  <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition to the systematic literature search, we included evidence from an ethnographic fieldwork conducted by Dr. Näkkäläjärvi, which included interviews of 30 reindeer herders from four Saami communities in Finland 2015–2017, during the conduct of this systematic review. These interviews provided important insight into the holistic effects of climate change perceived by reindeer herders and it influenced the development of the theoretical framework.</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
