<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The Stockholm paradigm, and theories of ecological fitting, suggest a glimmer hope for some parasites in the face of a changing climate [
 <xref rid="RSOS160535C72" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">72</xref>] (and casts doubt on the relative predictive power of coextinction models). In the evolutionary long term, climate change could drive diversification; some authors have argued the staggering diversity of parasites worldwide may have been facilitated by climate-driven periods of intense host switching [
 <xref rid="RSOS160535C73" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">73</xref>], and experimental [
 <xref rid="RSOS160535C74" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">74</xref>] and historical [
 <xref rid="RSOS160535C75" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">75</xref>] evidence further supports that these processes have dramatic effects on the persistence of parasites in unlikely environments. Moreover, as some parasites do poorly, their absence may trigger competitive release in others, enabling a once-excluded species to exhibit plasticity and dominate under novel conditions in a given host species [
 <xref rid="RSOS160535C76" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">76</xref>]. In the works of Hoberg and Brooks, the process of ecological fitting is interpreted as a driving factor not just in the production of a host–parasite coevolutionary geographical matrix, but also in the emergence of human and wildlife infectious diseases. But they similarly acknowledge that ecological fitting is not without constraints; long-term evolutionary recovery may still be matched by short-term decreases in diversity (i.e. many species are still likely to face some threat of extinction). We further note that the unprecedented velocity of current climatic change may make ecological fitting an ineffective silver bullet for mitigating short-term extinction risks in more species than usual, especially considering the limited success in keeping pace with climate change that most free-living species are already projected to have (see fig. 4 and 5 in [
 <xref rid="RSOS160535C77" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">77</xref>]). In the light of this evidence, coextinction estimates based on binary host–parasite association matrices could be perhaps replaced by more informed predictive approaches that anticipate host switching. Host switching and parasite diversification occur more often within definitive hosts of the same guild than among hosts of different guilds [
 <xref rid="RSOS160535C69" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">69</xref>], and are less likely if no closely related hosts occur in the parasite's geographical range or host genera are species-poor [
 <xref rid="RSOS160535C78" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">78</xref>]. Merging geographical and phylogenetic data may offer a better perspective on the extinction risk of different species in groups of conservation interest.
</p>
