<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec001" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1 Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ocean acidification, the process where increased atmospheric carbon dioxide (CO
  <sub>2</sub>) concentration reduces ocean pH and calcium carbonate saturation state [
  <a rid="pone.0203536.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0203536.ref001">1</a>], has already been implicated in negative impacts on the aquaculture industry on the US West Coast [
  <a rid="pone.0203536.ref002" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0203536.ref002">2</a>]. Laboratory studies for a number of other economically important marine species suggest ocean acidification has the potential to significantly impact fisheries landings and revenues regionally and around the world [
  <a rid="pone.0203536.ref003" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0203536.ref003">3</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0203536.ref006" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0203536.ref006">6</a>]. Marine mollusks appear to be particularly sensitive to ocean acidification due to the sensitivity of the calcification process to seawater chemistry during shell building [
  <a rid="pone.0203536.ref006" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0203536.ref006">6</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0203536.ref008" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0203536.ref008">8</a>]. Mollusks make up approximately 22 and 15% of the wild-caught fisheries yield globally and in the US, respectively [
  <a rid="pone.0203536.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0203536.ref009">9</a>]; therefore, understanding sensitivities of wild-caught fisheries to ocean acidification is an important step in the long-term sustainable management of these species.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Marine mollusks, specifically bivalves, are impacted in many ways by acidification. Their often complex, multi-stage life-cycle leads to potential bottlenecks where the chemical environment is particularly important, such as during metamorphoses from various larval stages prior to settlement [
  <a rid="pone.0203536.ref010" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0203536.ref010">10</a>]. Many species have shown increased larval mortality due to acidification, and larvae that survive often have deformed shell structures that suggest potential reductions in fitness during juvenile or adult stages [
  <a rid="pone.0203536.ref010" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0203536.ref010">10</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0203536.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0203536.ref012">12</a>]. Experimental manipulations of juvenile and adult bivalves suggest reduced growth and calcification rates under acidified conditions [
  <a rid="pone.0203536.ref007" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0203536.ref007">7</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0203536.ref008" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0203536.ref008">8</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0203536.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0203536.ref013">13</a>]. Further, shellfish predator-prey interactions are hypothesized to be influenced by acidification, due to decreased shell thickness and strength [
  <a rid="pone.0203536.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0203536.ref014">14</a>], reduced escape performance [
  <a rid="pone.0203536.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0203536.ref015">15</a>], and decreased behavioral responses to predators [
  <a rid="pone.0203536.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0203536.ref014">14</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The US Atlantic sea scallop (
  <span class="italic">Placopecten magellanicus</span>) is an ideal test species to apply integrated assessment modeling to project the impacts of global change on a wild-caught fishery. The 
  <span class="italic">P</span>. 
  <span class="italic">magellanicus</span> fishery is one of the most valuable wild-caught fisheries in the US, regularly worth roughly $500 million (USD) in ex-vessel revenue [
  <a rid="pone.0203536.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0203536.ref016">16</a>]. This fishery was severely overfished in the early to mid-1990s, but was rapidly rebuilt by the early 2000s using a combination of fishing effort reductions, gear restrictions, and rotational as well as long-term fishery closures [
  <a rid="pone.0203536.ref017" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0203536.ref017">17</a>]. Because the 
  <span class="italic">P</span>. 
  <span class="italic">magellanicus</span> fishery is currently sustainable, stakeholders and managers have the opportunity to consider the impacts of long-term environmental change on the fishery stock, yield, and economic benefits.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to maintain a sustainable fishery into the future, it is important that all stakeholders involved in both the management and exploitation of the fishery understand possible futures of the 
  <span class="italic">P</span>. 
  <span class="italic">magellanicus</span> fishery and the potential impacts of decision-making. In this work, we expand on the model described in Cooley et al. [
  <a rid="pone.0203536.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0203536.ref013">13</a>] by incorporating different future scenarios to inform planning for long-term change. Moreover, new elements have been added to the model to include the economic development associated with different growth and emissions scenarios (the RCP pathways); economic development was previously held constant in Cooley et al. [
  <a rid="pone.0203536.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0203536.ref013">13</a>]. We designed a decision-support framework that explores multiple combinations of potential future scenarios to provide an ensemble of model output varying major influences on the fishery as a whole. In this manuscript, we describe a subset of those scenarios to address the following questions: how might the future trajectory of the 
  <span class="italic">P</span>. 
  <span class="italic">magellanicus</span> fishery change under future climate warming and ocean acidification? How do differing management regimes influence the long-term outcomes of the 
  <span class="italic">P</span>. 
  <span class="italic">magellanicus</span> fishery? In this work, we designed future scenarios that incorporate potential acidification impacts, future climate scenarios that affect economic development, fisheries management, and changing fuel costs (described in more detail below).
 </p>
</sec>
