<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ecological impacts of environmental homogenization</div>
 <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Under climate change, our results show that the spatial and temporal autocorrelation of temperature are expected to increase at a potentially accelerating pace over time. This will promote the homogenization of the world, with equator-like conditions spreading geographically to higher latitudes and leading to concomitant changes in the composition of ecological communities
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
  </span>. This is expected to lead to greater spatial and temporal homogeneity (i.e., due to increased spatial and temporal autocorrelation in temperature).
 </p>
 <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ecological consequences of increased homogeneity in the environment have been documented in a number of studies. Increased spatial and temporal homogeneity in environmental variables has been linked to increased extinction risk in populations
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span>. Increased temporal autocorrelation has been shown to promote extinction risk in red-shifted, slow growing species that do not exhibit overcompensatory density-dependence or high sensitivity to environmental stochasticity
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>
  </span>. Indeed, under prolonged exposure to poor environmental conditions, these slow-growing and red-shifted species will see their numbers dwindle and will thus be unable to recover fast enough when conditions improve. Hence, increasing the extent of poor environmental conditions by increasing temporal autocorrelation will erode temporal refugia and prevent temporal rescue effects. Since most animal populations appear to be red-shifted
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
  </span>, extinction risk is likely to rise due to the increased temporal autocorrelation of temperature under climate change.
 </p>
 <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Additionally, greater spatial homogeneity in environmental variables such as temperature may disrupt spatial rescue effects by destroying the spatial heterogeneity needed in order for source-sink dynamics to occur
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
  </span>. Overall, the simultaneous erosion of temporal and spatial refugia under climate change has the potential to promote extinction risk. Mitigating the impacts of these trends in the spatiotemporal properties of temperature is thus critical in order ensure the persistence of complex and interconnected ecosystems in an increasingly homogeneous world.
 </p>
</sec>
