<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par2" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although classical studies have focused almost exclusively on determining the ecological impacts of shifting average environmental conditions, there is growing recognition that statistical properties beyond the mean can play an equally important role in shaping the structure and functioning of ecosystems under climate change
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span>. For instance, high variance in an environmental variable can destabilize populations by inducing greater fluctuations in their abundance over time and thus increase the risk of stochastic extinction
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span>. Even when environmental variance is too weak to promote extinction risk, it can have a more insidious effect on ecological systems due to nonlinear averaging. Specifically, if a population responds nonlinearly to environmental conditions, then changes in the temporal or spatial properties of the environment (e.g., temporal or spatial variance) can alter the mean ecological response even if the mean environmental conditions remain constant, and the strength of this effect will depend on the degree of nonlinearity in the functional response of the population
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
  </span>. This implies that the variance of an environmental variable has consequences for ecological systems that cannot be inferred from their average values alone
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span>. Indeed, studies have shown that variation in environmental variables impacts natural populations and consideration of variance can be required for successful model predictions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span>. Hence, in order to determine how climate change will impact ecological systems, it is at least as important to study variation in temperature and other critical environmental variables as it is to study their mean.
 </p>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition to variance, it is also crucial to consider the temporal structure or autocorrelation of environmental variables such as temperature, as the variation in environmental variables is predicted to change over time
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
  </span>. Studies of historical temperatures have shown an increase in their temporal autocorrelation from 1961 to 1990
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span>, and these trends are expected to increase under climate change
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
  </span>. Quantifying such changes in the temporal autocorrelation of environmental variables is critical in order to accurately predict the dynamics and persistence of ecological systems under climate change. Indeed, increased temporal autocorrelation in climate variables has been linked to lower persistence of model and natural populations
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>
  </span>. In general, theory predicts that a reddening of environmental time series (an increase in its temporal autocorrelation) can extend the duration of poor conditions and thus promote extinction risk by eroding temporal refugia or rescue effects
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The combination of increased temporal variance and autocorrelation in the environment could have even more dire consequences for ecological systems. For example, Dillon 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. showed that adding power to lower frequencies of temperature time series increased their temporal variance and autocorrelation, and thus the overall incidence and persistence of long-term heat waves and cold snaps
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span>. Such increased intensity (temporal variance) and duration (temporal autocorrelation) of harsh conditions can promote extinction risk. Hence, the destabilizing effect of increased temporal environmental variability can be amplified by an increase in its autocorrelation. Overall, this suggests that increased temporal variance and autocorrelation of environmental conditions may interact synergistically to destabilize ecological systems.
 </p>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The link between spatial autocorrelation of the environment and population dynamics has also been well established, with theoretical and empirical studies showing that spatiotemporally correlated or synchronized fluctuations in environmental conditions can give rise to synchronized fluctuations in ecological populations (i.e., the Moran effect
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>). For instance, increased spatial synchrony in air temperature due to changes in basin-scale climate forcing (North Atlantic Oscillation) gave rise to increased synchrony in Greenland animal populations
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span>. In general, increased spatial autocorrelation in the environment is expected to promote the scale and the magnitude of synchronized fluctuations in populations and thus reduce the spatial heterogeneity of ecological systems. In doing so, increased spatial environmental autocorrelation can thus promote extinction risk at local and regional scales by eliminating the potential for spatial rescue effects between interconnected but increasingly synchronized populations
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although the negative effects of spatial and temporal autocorrelation have been established independently in model and natural systems, little is known about how these two phenomena will interact under climate change. Overall, theory suggests that increased spatial and temporal autocorrelation of environmental factors like temperature are expected to interact synergistically to destabilize ecological communities by disrupting both temporal and spatial rescue effects
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span>. To determine the potential for such synergistic interactions, we characterized spatial and temporal autocorrelation in temperature from climate model projections. This was accomplished by analyzing temperature data from 1871 to 2099 using spectral analysis to measure temporal autocorrelation by calculating the spectral exponent and estimating spatial autocorrelation by determining the lag distance at which temperature becomes spatially uncorrelated (i.e., the spatial range).
 </p>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We found that temporal and spatial autocorrelation increased over time in individual climate models and the multimodel mean. However, there was considerable regional variation in temporal autocorrelation, with western North America, central South America, northwestern Eurasia and North Africa seeing significant increases in temporal autocorrelation, but West Africa and the Southern Ocean seeing significant decreases in temporal autocorrelation. Piecewise regression analyses showed consistent breakpoints in spatial trends in autocorrelation around the year 2030 globally, and spatial trends in autocorrelation were statistically significant after the breakpoint across time windows of different sizes. Our results suggest that climate change is likely to increase the spatial and temporal homogeneity of temperature, which may negatively impact connectivity between source and sink populations and thus reduce the persistence of ecological communities.</p>
</sec>
