<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Regional trends in temporal autocorrelation</div>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although the temporal autocorrelation in temperature increases at the global scale, there is significant geographical variation in both the sign and the strength of the trend (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>). Temporal autocorrelation in temperature increases most on land in northwestern North America, central South America, northwestern Eurasia, and North and central Africa (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2a,b</a>). Temporal autocorrelation also increases in the ocean, mostly in the central and southern Atlantic Ocean, the southern Indian Ocean, the Arctic Ocean and the Pacific Ocean. However, temporal autocorrelation decreases almost uniformly across the entire Southern Ocean and West Africa (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2a,b</a>). Overall, these temporal trends in autocorrelation lead to changes of up to 0.2 units in the spectral exponent from 1870 to 2099 (Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S1</a>).
  <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Maps of changes in the temporal autocorrelation of the multimodel mean temperature. Temporal autocorrelation was quantified via the spectral exponent, with more negative values indicating greater autocorrelation. (
     <span class="bold">a</span>) Map of the slope obtained by regressing the spectral exponent against time over 10-year periods between 1870 and 2090. Negative (positive) values depicted in red (blue) indicate an increase (decrease) in autocorrelation due to an increase (decrease) in the dominance of lower frequencies. (
     <span class="bold">b</span>) Grey contours indicate statistically significant slopes (
     <span class="italic">p</span>-value &lt; 0.05). Side plots represent the percentage of geographical locations at each latitude or longitude characterized by an increase in the dominance of lower (red) or higher (blue) frequencies. (
     <span class="bold">c</span>) Map of model agreement for the slope of the spectral exponent. Agreement is defined as the proportion of models predicting the same sign for the slope as the multimodel mean, with areas of high agreement being depicted in darker shades of purple. Side plots represent the percentage of geographical locations where model agreement exceed 50% at each latitude or longitude. (
     <span class="bold">d</span>) Map of model robustness for the slope of the spectral exponent. Robustness is defined as the proportion of models that agree with the multimodel mean on the sign and the statistical significance of the slope. Side plots represent the percentage of geographical locations where model robustness exceeds 50% at each latitude or longitude.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2018_33217_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e922" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There are no consistent differences in the percentage of geographical locations exhibiting increased vs. decreased temporal autocorrelation of temperature across longitudes. However, there are strong latitudinal patterns, with autocorrelation decreasing most between 70 S and 40 S due to the influence of the Southern Ocean. Autocorrelation increases most in temperate regions due to the effects of both land and sea. In general, model agreement is relatively high across most of the globe, with the notable exceptions of parts of Antarctica and the north Atlantic (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2c</a>). Model robustness is notably the highest in the Southern Ocean (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2d</a>). However, robustness is below 50% at other latitudes despite high agreement, which indicates that while individual GCMs are consistent in the trend, there is disagreement about the significance of the trend. Although there is no meaningful change in model agreement and robustness across longitudes, model agreement and robustness vary latitudinally reaching lower values around the South Pole, the equator and the North Pole.
 </p>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is important to note that these results are based on the linearly detrended data, which retain seasonal temperature cycles. To determine the robustness of our results to seasonality, we conducted the same analyses on seasonally detrended data (Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S2</a>). The results from the seasonally detrended data show an almost universal increase in temporal autocorrelation of temperature across the globe, particularly in the Pacific Ocean, the northern Atlantic Ocean, western North America, South America, western Africa and Australia (Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S2</a>). Overall, the predicted trends in the temporal autocorrelation of temperature are stronger and more spatially-uniform when seasonal temperature cycles are removed. This is because seasonal (annual) temperature fluctuations are characterized by high power and occur at relatively low frequencies when using multi-year time windows. Hence, when regressing (log) power against (log) frequency, annual fluctuations in temperature have high statistical leverage on the slope estimate used to quantify the spectral exponent. Removing seasonality, which remains relatively constant over time and has high leverage on the spectral exponent estimate, thus facilitates the detection of temporal trends in autocorrelation due to changes in temperature fluctuations occurring at non-annual frequencies. One can thus think of the trends obtained using the linearly detrended data as a conservative estimate of the expected changes in the temporal autocorrelation of temperature and those obtained using the seasonally detrended data as anti-conservative.
 </p>
</sec>
