<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec015" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion and Conclusions</div>
 <sec id="sec016" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Politics and education effects</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The most striking result here is the stability of public beliefs about anthropogenic climate change. That holds across different surveys (
   <a rid="pone.0138208.g001" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0138208.g001">Fig 1A</a>) and over a five-year time span (
   <a rid="pone.0138208.g002" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0138208.g002">Fig 2A</a>), although not across places (
   <a rid="pone.0138208.g001" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0138208.g001">Fig 1B</a>). General stability is anchored by wide, persistent political divisions (
   <a rid="pone.0138208.g002" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0138208.g002">Fig 2B</a>). Effects from individual age, gender, education and political party manifest as similar odds ratios on many different surveys (
   <a rid="pone.0138208.t002" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0138208.t002">Table 2</a>). Very similar 
   <span class="italic">education</span>×
   <span class="italic">party</span> interaction effects occur in most of these surveys as well. In social research, interaction effects in multivariate models frequently prove to be sample-specific, so the degree of replication seen in 
   <a rid="pone.0138208.g003" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0138208.g003">Fig 3</a> is extraordinary.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Political identity dominates other background characteristics in predicting individual climate-change beliefs. Politics moderate effects from education, the second-strongest predictor. Agreement with the scientific consensus increases with education among Democrats and Independents (or liberals and moderates), but stays level or declines with education among Republicans (or conservatives). Similar interactions were first tested with different climate variables in 2006 GSS data [
   <a rid="pone.0138208.ref027" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref027">27</a>] and subsequently replicated on other regional [
   <a rid="pone.0138208.ref024" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref024">24</a>][
   <a rid="pone.0138208.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref028">28</a>] and nationwide [
   <a rid="pone.0138208.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref009">9</a>][
   <a rid="pone.0138208.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref029">29</a>] surveys. Variations on this pattern include objectively-assessed science knowledge [
   <a rid="pone.0138208.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref030">30</a>], numeracy [
   <a rid="pone.0138208.ref031" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref031">31</a>] or self-assessed understanding [
   <a rid="pone.0138208.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref009">9</a>][
   <a rid="pone.0138208.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref028">28</a>] in place of education; and measures of ideology [
   <a rid="pone.0138208.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref009">9</a>][
   <a rid="pone.0138208.ref027" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref027">27</a>][
   <a rid="pone.0138208.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref028">28</a>] or culture [
   <a rid="pone.0138208.ref031" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref031">31</a>] in place of political party. Some other environment-related questions exhibit interactions of the same type [
   <a rid="pone.0138208.ref018" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref018">18</a>][
   <a rid="pone.0138208.ref019" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref019">19</a>][
   <a rid="pone.0138208.ref032" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref032">32</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Common explanations for the pattern invoke greater awareness among educated individuals about the views of politicians and media they follow—the 
   <span class="italic">elite cues</span> hypothesis [
   <a rid="pone.0138208.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref009">9</a>][
   <a rid="pone.0138208.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref033">33</a>][
   <a rid="pone.0138208.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref034">34</a>][
   <a rid="pone.0138208.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref035">35</a>]. More educated or information-rich individuals also could be more effective in seeking out and retaining information that accords with their prejudices—as described by 
   <span class="italic">biased assimilation</span> [
   <a rid="pone.0138208.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref009">9</a>][
   <a rid="pone.0138208.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref036">36</a>][
   <a rid="pone.0138208.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref037">37</a>], 
   <span class="italic">motivated skepticism</span> [
   <a rid="pone.0138208.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref038">38</a>] and related hypotheses [
   <a rid="pone.0138208.ref026" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref026">26</a>][
   <a rid="pone.0138208.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref039">39</a>][
   <a rid="pone.0138208.ref040" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref040">40</a>]. These explanations all hinge on the active, motivated acceptance/rejection of information, a major complication to the simpler 
   <span class="italic">information deficit</span> hypothesis that people express low concern about scientifically-identified problems because they lack information that scientists could provide [
   <a rid="pone.0138208.ref041" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref041">41</a>]. With regard to climate change many people assert that they are well informed, although their sense of understanding may come from politics rather than science [
   <a rid="pone.0138208.ref032" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref032">32</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec017" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Place and temporal effects</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Place-to-place variations can be substantial (
   <a rid="pone.0138208.g001" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0138208.g001">Fig 1B</a>). Other studies have found both systematic and idiosyncratic explanations for such place effects, reflecting characteristics of the local economy, history, environment and culture.[
   <a rid="pone.0138208.ref018" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref018">18</a>][
   <a rid="pone.0138208.ref019" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref019">19</a>][
   <a rid="pone.0138208.ref025" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref025">25</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Temporal variations over the years studied here have been smaller (
   <a rid="pone.0138208.g002" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0138208.g002">Fig 2A</a>), with only weak seasonal and daily temperature effects. The latter finding fits the mixed conclusions of previous research, in which some authors report effects from ambient conditions [
   <a rid="pone.0138208.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref042">42</a>][
   <a rid="pone.0138208.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref043">43</a>][
   <a rid="pone.0138208.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref044">44</a>], weather [
   <a rid="pone.0138208.ref045" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref045">45</a>][
   <a rid="pone.0138208.ref046" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref046">46</a>][
   <a rid="pone.0138208.ref047" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref047">47</a>][
   <a rid="pone.0138208.ref048" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref048">48</a>][
   <a rid="pone.0138208.ref049" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref049">49</a>][
   <a rid="pone.0138208.ref050" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref050">50</a>] or climate trends [
   <a rid="pone.0138208.ref024" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref024">24</a>][
   <a rid="pone.0138208.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref029">29</a>]. Other studies, however, find minor or nonexistent effects from weather or climate [
   <a rid="pone.0138208.ref051" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref051">51</a>][
   <a rid="pone.0138208.ref052" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref052">52</a>]. These inconsistent results suggests that weather or climate effects tend to be minor and contingent, in contrast to the strong, ubiquitous effects of political orientation.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The New Hampshire time series was initiated to monitor possible changes in public agreement with the scientific consensus on climate change. The relative 
   <span class="italic">lack</span> of change was an early, unexpected discovery. As the series lengthens, however, we see evidence of upward drift. Overall, New Hampshire public acceptance of anthropogenic climate change moved up about five points, from 53% in 2010 to 58% in 2015. This small but statistically significant (
   <a rid="pone.0138208.t002" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0138208.t002">Table 2</a>) drift roughly agrees with yearly nationwide results based on other survey questions [
   <a rid="pone.0138208.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref004">4</a>]. That agreement on trends incidentally provides further encouragement for viewing the New Hampshire series as a proxy. Despite upward movement, both New Hampshire and national public opinion falls far short of the 97% consensus among climate scientists.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec018" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Future research</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The basic climate-change question offers currency, simplicity and unambiguous interpretation—whether individuals personally agree with the central point of scientific consensus on this globally important issue. As the examples here show, the question adapts readily to diverse survey instruments, opening possibilities for temporal, geographic and social-group comparisons. One planned future application is the 2016 General Social Survey, which offers an impressive range of sociological covariates. We also expect further regional surveys along the lines of CERA and CAFOR, investigating local variations. Finally, the same climate question has proven useful at smaller scales, in the benchmark and evaluation stages of education activities that are in progress but not described here.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The quarterly resolution and increasingly long run of the New Hampshire time series provides a unique platform to detect and characterize future change. To date it has shown only minor fluctuations around a slow upward drift. Seemingly large external events including an election and nearby hurricane had no detectable effects, but the possibility remains that cumulative or more extreme political, economic or climate-related events could have greater impact. With or without dramatic impacts, the series provides a monitoring system for the 
   <span class="italic">shape</span> of any changes in public acceptance—whether abrupt or gradual, ephemeral or lasting.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
