<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec013" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Place-to-place variation</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The CERA/CAFOR surveys covered 35 different counties, and re-surveyed three of them on two different occasions (2011 and 2014), for a total of 38 county/occasions. Earlier work found substantial place-to-place variation [
  <a rid="pone.0138208.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref022">22</a>], motivating our inclusion of 37 intercept dummy variables in the regression model. As 
  <a rid="pone.0138208.t002" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0138208.t002">Table 2</a> notes these county/occasion indicators help to predict individual-level climate beliefs. An adjusted Wald test finds that the county indicators collectively have significant impacts.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Place-to-place variations can themselves be a focus of research. Studies using other dependent variables have found broad structural effects, as from unemployment or population growth rates, alongside other effects reflecting local circumstances such as the importance of coal mining in rural Kentucky or the experience of warming winters in northern New England [
  <a rid="pone.0138208.ref018" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref018">18</a>][
  <a rid="pone.0138208.ref019" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref019">19</a>][
  <a rid="pone.0138208.ref024" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref024">24</a>][
  <a rid="pone.0138208.ref025" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0138208.ref025">25</a>].Our focus here has been on individual-characteristic effects that prove stable across many different surveys. This includes the CERA/CAFOR surveys where, after adjusting for the significant place-to-place variation, we find substantially the same individual effects (from 
  <span class="italic">age</span>, 
  <span class="italic">gender</span>, 
  <span class="italic">education</span>, 
  <span class="italic">party</span> and 
  <span class="italic">education</span>×
  <span class="italic">party</span>) seen in other surveys.
 </p>
</sec>
