<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The effective ice down-wasting rate (
 <italic class="italic">A</italic>
 <sub class="sub">eff</sub>) in equation 
 <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq29" class="xref">(11)</xref> will change as a function of environmental forcing and the thickness of evolving supraglacial debris (
 <italic class="italic">h</italic>). As mass balance initially turns negative, incipient supraglacial debris (&lt;∼1 cm) is likely sparse and would only impact ablation dynamics through localized changes in albedo. Under this scenario, we set the effective ice down-wasting rate equal to the modelled mass balance for the clean ice case (which includes the mass flux of snowfall). Once the debris layer evolves to become a continuous sheet, it is no longer appropriate to include mass gains from snowfall (because snow that falls on top of the debris tends to sublimate and not add to the glacier mass balance), and we equate the effective ablation rate to the modelled ablation (
 <italic class="italic">A</italic>) (MB minus snowfall). For continuous supraglacial debris thicker than a few cm, the ablation rate becomes vapour-diffusion-limited
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b80" class="xref">80</xref> and the EBM model developed for clean ice is also not applicable. For such thick supraglacial debris conditions we abandon the EBM approach, for example, ref. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b81" class="xref">81</xref>, and instead follow Mackay and Marchant
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14" class="xref">14</xref> and model the ablation rate as an exponential function of the supraglacial debris thickness, for example, refs 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b82" class="xref">82</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b83" class="xref">83</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b84" class="xref">84</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b85" class="xref">85</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b86" class="xref">86</xref>, using coefficients fit to experimental data from Mullins Glacier
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10" class="xref">10</xref>. Thus, we arrive at a modelling scheme for the downwasting of ice that adapts to different debris thickness cases as follows: 
 <list id="l1" list-type="order" class="list">
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">For the case where ice is essentially bare, without debris cover, the downwasting rate is set equal to the EBM mass balance model results (which may include a positive ice growth contribution from precipitation).</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">For the special case where debris thickness=
    <italic class="italic">H</italic>
    <sub class="sub">p1</sub>≈1 cm, the downwasting rate is set to the bare-ice EBM mass balance results, except that accumulation from snowfall is ignored (that is, the EBM ablation rate, 
    <italic class="italic">A</italic>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">Finally, for ice covered with debris thickness ≥
    <italic class="italic">H</italic>
    <sub class="sub">p2</sub> ∼3 cm, the downwasting rate is determined by the (parameterized) vapour diffusion model.
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
