<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Central Indo-Pacific Rainfall Variations and ENSO</div>
 <p content-type="flushleft" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The most notable feature of the TK δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O record is the long-term increasing trend, which signifies decreasing rainfall in the NCIP over the past 2,700 y. This suborbital-scale rainfall decline is recognizable in paleohydrological records from numerous locations in the northern tropics, such as Southeast Asia (
  <a rid="r25" ref-type="bibr" href="#r25">25</a>), Mesoamerica (
  <a rid="r35" ref-type="bibr" href="#r35">35</a>, 
  <a rid="r36" ref-type="bibr" href="#r36">36</a>), and the Caribbean (
  <a rid="r15" ref-type="bibr" href="#r15">15</a>). An opposite increasing rainfall trend is documented in the southern tropics, including East Africa (
  <a rid="r37" ref-type="bibr" href="#r37">37</a>), the Western Pacific Warm Pool (
  <a rid="r38" ref-type="bibr" href="#r38">38</a>, 
  <a rid="r39" ref-type="bibr" href="#r39">39</a>), the eastern tropical Pacific (ETP) (
  <a rid="r40" ref-type="bibr" href="#r40">40</a>), and South America (
  <a rid="r41" ref-type="bibr" href="#r41">41</a>) (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1903167116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S12
  </span>). This tropical interhemispheric precipitation see-saw pattern on suborbital timescales is similar to observations during the last glacial period (
  <a rid="r42" ref-type="bibr" href="#r42">42</a>, 
  <a rid="r43" ref-type="bibr" href="#r43">43</a>) and is most likely driven, on a longer timescale, by precessional changes in summertime insolation in each respective hemisphere.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The centennial- to decadal-scale rainfall variation in the NCIP is highlighted in the detrended TK δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O record (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3
   <span class="italic">B</span>
  </a>). Comparison with other hydroclimate sequences in the southern central Indo-Pacific (SCIP) region during the last 2,000 y, including the hydrogen isotopic ratios of terrestrial higher plant leaf waxes (δD
  <sub>wax</sub>) in marine sediments from southwest Sulawesi in central Indonesia (
  <a rid="r39" ref-type="bibr" href="#r39">39</a>), and a synthesized stalagmite-based rainfall record from Liang Luar Cave in eastern Indonesia (
  <a rid="r3" ref-type="bibr" href="#r3">3</a>), are given in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3 
   <span class="italic">B</span>–
   <span class="italic">D</span>
  </a>. All records feature deceased rainfall during the 20th century [Current Warm Period (CWP)] and at periods of 950–1150 AD and 1200–1300 AD during the Medieval Warm Period (MWP). In contrast, both NCIP and SCIP experienced increased rainfall during the LIA and the Dark Ages Cold Period (DACP) (
  <a rid="r9" ref-type="bibr" href="#r9">9</a>). A dry MWP is also confirmed by the low accumulation rate of peat in Lake Pa Kho (&lt;0.1 mm/y) in northeastern Thailand (
  <a rid="r44" ref-type="bibr" href="#r44">44</a>). On the contrary, much higher accumulation rates were observed during the LIA (∼1 mm/y) and the DACP (∼1.3 mm/y) (
  <a rid="r44" ref-type="bibr" href="#r44">44</a>). The extremely wet late 14th century in our TK record coincides with the timing of extensive floods and destruction of the water management systems in Angkor, Cambodia, confirming the role of climate on the decline of the Khmer Empire (
  <a rid="r45" ref-type="bibr" href="#r45">45</a>).
 </p>
 <div id="fig03" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 3.</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Comparisons of the detrended TK stalagmite δ
    <span class="sup">18</span>O record with high-resolution rainfall records from SCIP region, and ENSO and volcanic activities during the last 2,000 y. (
    <span class="italic">A</span>) Northern Hemisphere temperature (NHT) (
    <a rid="r65" ref-type="bibr" href="#r65">65</a>). (
    <span class="italic">B</span>) TK δ
    <span class="sup">18</span>O record (gray line) from southern Thailand (this study). The blue line is the 20-y moving average. (
    <span class="italic">C</span>) Leaf waxes δD in marine sediments from southwest Sulawesi, central Indonesia (
    <a rid="r39" ref-type="bibr" href="#r39">39</a>). (
    <span class="italic">D</span>) Multiproxies synthesized stalagmite record (LLPC1) from Liang Luar Cave in eastern Indonesia (
    <a rid="r3" ref-type="bibr" href="#r3">3</a>). Records in 
    <span class="italic">B</span>−
    <span class="italic">D</span> are detrended to emphasize their centennial to decadal timescale variations. (
    <span class="italic">E</span>) Reconstructed SOI record (
    <a rid="r14" ref-type="bibr" href="#r14">14</a>). (
    <span class="italic">F</span>) El Niño activities recorded by percent of sand in lake sediments of El Junco, Galápagos; an increase in sand abundance represents more intense rainfall events associated with El Niño events (
    <a rid="r40" ref-type="bibr" href="#r40">40</a>). (
    <span class="italic">G</span>) Model simulated Niño3.4 sea surface temperatures variability (
    <a rid="r48" ref-type="bibr" href="#r48">48</a>). (
    <span class="italic">H</span>) Volcanic sulfate recorded in the Greenland Ice Sheet Project 2 (GISP2) ice core (
    <a rid="r66" ref-type="bibr" href="#r66">66</a>). Yellow bars denote dry conditions during the MWP and CWP, corresponding to enhanced El Niño activities. Gray bars mark the wet LIA and DACP, corresponding to enhanced La Niña activities.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div id="gra3" xlink:href="pnas.1903167116fig03" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The spatial patterns of centennial- to decadal-scale dry conditions in the CIP region during the MWP and CWP are similar to that during El Niño events today (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" href="#fig01">Fig. 1
   <span class="italic">C</span>
  </a>). Indeed, a 2,000-y reconstruction of Southern Oscillation Index (SOI) shows intensified El Niño activity during the MWP and CWP (
  <a rid="r14" ref-type="bibr" href="#r14">14</a>). A significant negative correlation (
  <span class="italic">r</span> = −0.28, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.01) was observed between TK δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O and the SOI record, with more positive TK δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O values (less rainfall) correlated to more negative SOI values (El Niño-dominated conditions), and vice versa (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3
   <span class="italic">E</span>
  </a>). In addition, increased sand abundance and red color intensity of lake sediments from ETP during the MWP (
  <a rid="r40" ref-type="bibr" href="#r40">40</a>, 
  <a rid="r46" ref-type="bibr" href="#r46">46</a>) reveal enhanced rainfall in this region, also suggesting El Niño-like conditions during the MWP (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3
   <span class="italic">F</span>
  </a>). On the other hand, relatively wet conditions during the LIA and DACP in the CIP correspond to La Niña-like conditions, as suggested by increased SOI values and decreased ETP rainfall (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3</a>). Modern observations and model results indicate that, since the mid-19th century, the warming of the tropical Pacific caused a weakening of the Walker circulation (
  <a rid="r47" ref-type="bibr" href="#r47">47</a>). Some model simulations also suggest La Niña-dominated conditions and enhanced Walker circulation during the LIA and El Niño-dominated conditions during the MWP and CWP (
  <a rid="r48" ref-type="bibr" href="#r48">48</a>) (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3
   <span class="italic">G</span>
  </a>). All lines of evidence suggest ENSO influence on CIP rainfall variability. ENSO can impact tropical rainfall through the east−west displacement of the ascending and descending branches of the Walker circulation (
  <a rid="r49" ref-type="bibr" href="#r49">49</a>). During El Niño (La Niña) conditions, the ascending branch of the Walker circulation moves eastward (westward), and the increased descent (ascent) is distributed over CIP, suppressing (enhancing) monsoon rainfall in this region.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results contrast with hydroclimate records from western United States (
  <a rid="r12" ref-type="bibr" href="#r12">12</a>) and sea surface temperature reconstructions from the tropical Pacific (
  <a rid="r10" ref-type="bibr" href="#r10">10</a>, 
  <a rid="r11" ref-type="bibr" href="#r11">11</a>) which suggest La Niña-like conditions during the MWP and El Niño-like conditions during the LIA. Conroy et al. (
  <a rid="r11" ref-type="bibr" href="#r11">11</a>) suggested the disparity of ENSO reconstructions might result from 1) the age model errors inherent in 
  <span class="sup">14</span>C-dated records, 2) North Atlantic temperature’s impact on the precipitation over the western United States, and 3) different spatial expressions of El Niño and La Niña events. Our rainfall reconstruction, showing dry MWP and wet LIA in the CIP, is robust, with superior chronological control. If a strengthened zonal sea surface temperature gradient across the tropical Pacific during the MWP, as suggested by marine proxies, is confirmed, the physical mechanism of ENSO, Walker circulation, and rainfall in the tropical Indo-Pacific needs to be reconsidered. Additional high-resolution, radiometrically dated climate records covering the past 1,000 to 2,000 y from different regions will contribute to a comprehensive understanding of past ENSO and Walker circulation variability, impacts, and their responses to global climate change.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The drought lasting many decades during 1220–1300 AD coincides with the largest volcanic eruption, in 1257 AD (
  <a rid="r50" ref-type="bibr" href="#r50">50</a>), over the past 2,000 y (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3
   <span class="italic">H</span>
  </a>). Decreased rainfall in the TK record is also observed during the 2 large eruptions of 1600 AD (
  <a rid="r51" ref-type="bibr" href="#r51">51</a>) and 1815 AD (
  <a rid="r52" ref-type="bibr" href="#r52">52</a>), suggesting a consistent response of tropical rainfall to volcanic eruptions (
  <a rid="r53" ref-type="bibr" href="#r53">53</a>). However, the annual-scale volcanic aerosol effect (
  <a rid="r53" ref-type="bibr" href="#r53">53</a>) could not have been the primary driving force of droughts in the tropics lasting decades. As shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3
   <span class="italic">H</span>
  </a>, the intensities of volcanic eruptions in the 20th century and during the MWP are smaller than those during the 13th century, but the droughts during the 2 periods apparently were much more severe. The timing and magnitude of the rainfall changes in the CIP imply that forcings in addition to volcanic aerosols, as well as natural climate variability, affect tropical rainfall.
 </p>
</sec>
