<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">ITCZ Shifts over the Past 2,000 y</div>
 <p content-type="flushleft" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition to zonal Walker circulation variability induced by ENSO, tropical rainfall is also influenced by meridional ITCZ shifts (
  <a rid="r1" ref-type="bibr" href="#r1">1</a>, 
  <a rid="r3" ref-type="bibr" href="#r3">3</a>, 
  <a rid="r15" ref-type="bibr" href="#r15">15</a>). Considering the synchronous, direct impact of ENSO on rainfall variations in the CIP of both hemispheres (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" href="#fig01">Fig. 1
   <span class="italic">C</span>
  </a>), the history of ITCZ shifts is revealed from antiphased rainfall differences between the NCIP and SCIP. Indeed, the observed annual mean cross-equatorial rainfall gradient between the 2 sectors (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1903167116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S13
  </span>) for the years 1983–2012 AD supports this argument (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1903167116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S12
  </span>). The time series of this gradient shows a significant positive correlation (
  <span class="italic">r</span> = 0.57, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.01) with the observed location of the ITCZ in boreal summer over this region (
  <a rid="r1" ref-type="bibr" href="#r1">1</a>) (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1903167116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S14
  </span>). Higher (lower) rainfall in the NCIP relative to the SCIP corresponds to a northward (southward) movement of the ITCZ.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The TK δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O record from Klang Cave in southern Thailand and the stalagmite δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O record (LL) from Liang Luar Cave (8°32′S, 120° 26′E) in eastern Indonesia (
  <a rid="r3" ref-type="bibr" href="#r3">3</a>) (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" href="#fig01">Fig. 1</a>) are negatively correlated with the regional rainfall amount in the NCIP and SCIP, respectively. Although other factors, including cave air temperature (related to regional sea surface temperatures), surface seawater δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O, and ENSO (
  <a rid="r3" ref-type="bibr" href="#r3">3</a>), might exert a relatively minor influence on the stalagmite δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O in both caves, their impacts are similar due to homogeneous environmental conditions in both regions. We thus construct a new ITCZ shift index (SI) sequence for the past 2,000 y (1−2004 AD) by subtracting the standardized LL record from the standardized TK record (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig04" href="#fig04">Fig. 4</a> and 
  <a ref-type="sec" rid="s3" href="#s3">
   <span class="italic">Materials and Methods</span>
  </a>). Negative (positive) ITCZ SI values represent higher (lower) rainfall in the NCIP as relative to the SCIP, and a northward (southward) shift of the CIP ITCZ.
 </p>
 <div id="fig04" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 4.</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Reconstruction of the ITCZ SI for CIP during the past 2,000 y (1−2004 AD). (
    <span class="italic">A</span>) Composite TK δ
    <span class="sup">18</span>O record. (
    <span class="italic">B</span>) Normalized annual TK δ
    <span class="sup">18</span>O record (TK
    <sub>n</sub>). (
    <span class="italic">C</span>) Original LR06-B1 δ
    <span class="sup">18</span>O record (LL) from eastern Indonesia (
    <a rid="r3" ref-type="bibr" href="#r3">3</a>). (
    <span class="italic">D</span>) Normalized annual LL δ
    <span class="sup">18</span>O record (LL
    <sub>n</sub>). Red lines in 
    <span class="italic">B</span> and 
    <span class="italic">D</span> are the 20-y moving averages of the normalized TK and LL records, respectively. (
    <span class="italic">E</span>) The ITCZ SI series (green line) results from subtracting the smoothed LL
    <sub>n</sub> dataset from the TK
    <sub>n</sub> record, and its comparison with the temperature gradient between the Northern Hemisphere (NH) and Southern Hemisphere (SH) extratropics (red line, ref. 
    <a rid="r56" ref-type="bibr" href="#r56">56</a>).
   </p>
  </div>
  <div id="gra4" xlink:href="pnas.1903167116fig04" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ITCZ SI sequence (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1903167116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Dataset S2</span>) shows a general trend of southward movement over the past 2 millennia (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig04" href="#fig04">Fig. 4
   <span class="italic">E</span>
  </a>). Superimposed on the long-term trend, it reveals a relatively northern mean ITCZ position during the first century, followed by a southward shift during the second century. From the third century AD onward, the CIP ITCZ began to move northward, and maintained its most northern position between the fourth and early seventh centuries. Thereafter, an abrupt 40-y-long southward movement was followed by multidecadal oscillations for the next 350 y, until another rapid southward shift occurred in the early 11th century. Since the late 11th century, a northward−southward−northward pattern of ITCZ movements is observed, with each phase lasting ∼200 y. The CIP ITCZ retracted southward since the 18th century, and reached its most southerly position in the 1980s (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig04" href="#fig04">Fig. 4
   <span class="italic">E</span>
  </a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The reconstruction reveals a southward mean ITCZ position during the early MWP and the CWP. Spectral analysis indicates significant ∼1,000-, ∼400-, 130- to 140-, and ∼60-y cycles in the ITCZ SI record (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1903167116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S15
  </span>). Further ensemble empirical mode decomposition analysis suggests that these cycles contribute 6%, 54%, 28%, and 8%, respectively, of ITCZ variance during the last 2,000 y (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1903167116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S16
  </span>). The 130- to 140- and ∼60-y cycles are significant throughout the entire ITCZ SI reconstruction (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1903167116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S17
  </span>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our ITCZ SI record is consistent with a discontinuous reconstruction of ITCZ rainfall changes in the ETP during some events (
  <a rid="r54" ref-type="bibr" href="#r54">54</a>) (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1903167116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S18
  </span>). The only discrepancy is observed in the seventh century, when the reconstructed ITCZ rainfall in the ETP shows an unusual southward shift (
  <a rid="r54" ref-type="bibr" href="#r54">54</a>). While our ITCZ SI also suggests a southward movement during this period, the amplitude was smaller (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1903167116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S18
  </span>). We also find a weak but significant negative correlation between our new ITCZ SI and a marine sediment Ti record (
  <span class="italic">r</span> = −0.17, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.01) from the Cariaco Basin (
  <a rid="r15" ref-type="bibr" href="#r15">15</a>), with relatively low ITCZ SI values (interpreted as northward ITCZ movement) corresponding to rainfall-induced high Ti content (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1903167116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S18
  </span>). Modern observations of rainfall over the CIP (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1903167116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S14
  </span>) and North Africa confirm a northward ITCZ shift since the 1990s (
  <a rid="r55" ref-type="bibr" href="#r55">55</a>), which is also recorded in our SI record (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig04" href="#fig04">Fig. 4
   <span class="italic">E</span>
  </a>). The correspondence between proxy records provides additional evidence for large-scale movements of the ITCZ over the past 2,000 y. Discrepancies between the records could be attributed to the complex relationship between the biomarker index/grain size variations in lake sediments and rainfall over the ETP, on one hand (
  <a rid="r54" ref-type="bibr" href="#r54">54</a>), and regional differences between ITCZ movements in the CIP and the ETP, on the other hand. The differences between our ITCZ SI time series and the Cariaco Basin Ti record most likely results from ENSO’s influence on rainfall in the tropical Atlantic, as well as a regionally different behavior of the ITCZ in the Atlantic versus the Pacific. Our record suggests that ITCZ migrations on millennial to multicentennial timescales are coherent with the temperature contrast between the northern and southern extratropics (
  <a rid="r56" ref-type="bibr" href="#r56">56</a>) (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig04" href="#fig04">Fig. 4
   <span class="italic">E</span>
  </a>). According to the atmospheric energy balance ITCZ mechanism (
  <a rid="r1" ref-type="bibr" href="#r1">1</a>), a warming of the northern relative to the southern extratropics differentially reduces meridional temperature gradients in the northern extratropics. This can reduce the energy export out of the tropics into the Northern Hemisphere, resulting in a northward ITCZ repositioning. In contrast, warming of the southern relative to the northern extratropics can lead to a southward ITCZ shift (
  <a rid="r1" ref-type="bibr" href="#r1">1</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The southward mean position of the ITCZ is concurrent with enhanced El Niño conditions during the early MWP and the CWP. This is coherent with observations of a southward shift of the ITCZ in the Indo-Pacific during strong El Niño events (such as in 1983 AD and 1998 AD) (
  <a rid="r57" ref-type="bibr" href="#r57">57</a>). Our highly resolved and accurately dated stalagmite record suggests that the drying trend in the northern tropics since the 20th century is similar to that during the historical warm period (950–1150 AD), which was caused by intensified El Niño activities and a southward ITCZ shift. Anthropogenically forced regional rainfall changes may, therefore, remain difficult to detect against the relatively large background of natural hydroclimate variability.
 </p>
</sec>
