<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Uncertainties related to our model should be kept in mind when interpreting the results of this study. One important uncertainty derives from the fact that non-climatic factors, such as soil conditions, could not be integrated into our modelling because of the lack of sufficient data so far. In addition, many other ecological and evolutionary processes, such as biological interactions and interactions between the functional traits of an organism and its habitat, will also affect the distribution of species (
 <xref rid="ref-66" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kearney &amp; Porter, 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Fordham et al., 2012</xref>). These constraints are being addressed by some mechanistic modelling approaches. Compared to the MaxEnt-style correlative/statistical model, which statistically links spatial data to species distribution records, mechanistic models incorporate mechanistic links between the functional traits of organisms and their environments (e.g., 
 <xref rid="ref-100" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Renton, Shackelford &amp; Standish, 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-109" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Tomlinson et al., 2017</xref>). These two types of models have both strengths and weaknesses (
 <xref rid="ref-66" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kearney &amp; Porter, 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-65" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kearney, Wintle &amp; Porter, 2010</xref>). For poorly studied taxa with a paucity of knowledge about the physiological constraints on their survival and reproduction, such as 
 <italic class="italic">P. amabilis</italic>, MaxEnt-style correlative/statistical models are a better choice. We will never be able to reconstruct the past and predict the future with accuracy, but we need a strategy for utilizing existing knowledge to reveal the likely effects of climate on species survival. Optimistically, we hold the opinion that as more data become available, ENMs will generate more realistic simulations and provide a solid basis on which to draw a more practical conservation strategy.
</p>
