<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In the southwestern United States, climate change could lead to particularly large increases in electricity demand via increased need for cooling
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1" class="xref">1</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2" class="xref">2</xref>. Increased cooling demands could strain the electricity supply, at the same time that generation and transmission capacity could be affected by decreases in water availability and increases in water and air temperatures
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3" class="xref">3</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4" class="xref">4</xref>. Los Angeles County (LAC) has 3.1% of the US national population
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5" class="xref">5</xref> and consumes 2% of the country's electricity
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6" class="xref">6</xref>. In addition, a relatively low proportion of homes in the county have air conditioning (40%; ref. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7" class="xref">7</xref>), so increased adoption of cooling technologies could substantially have an impact on residential electricity demand. The state of California predicts that the population of LAC will increase by 17% to 11.5 million inhabitants by 2060, creating new demands for housing and energy
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8" class="xref">8</xref>. In the state of California, Executive Order S-3-05 targets greenhouse gas emissions reductions of 80% below 1990 levels by 2050, and previous research suggests that increased electrification of space heating, water heating and transportation coupled with de-carbonization of the electricity supply will be fundamental to meeting this goal
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9" class="xref">9</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10" class="xref">10</xref>. Current trends also suggest that consumers are already fuel-switching from fossil fuels to electricity for residential space conditioning
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11" class="xref">11</xref>. While fuel-switching could help meet greenhouse gas mitigation targets, it will increase demand for electricity, and there is mounting evidence that these traditional power supplies could be constrained by drought and climate change impacts
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12" class="xref">12</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13" class="xref">13</xref>. Without proper planning, meeting these demands could come at high economic and environmental costs. Faced with this potentially constrained supply, forecasting demand changes under future climate change is critical for identifying cost-effective paths to meet or mitigate the demand.
</p>
