<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The effects of meteorological conditions (and climatic conditions in the long term) on the formation of each of the 
 <italic class="italic">Spartina</italic> hybrids may be related to alterations in the flowering dynamic of 
 <italic class="italic">S. maritima</italic> phenology. Air temperature is an important factor in the induction of flowering in grasses (
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Cooper and Calder, 1964</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Heide and Heide, 1994</xref>). Both 
 <italic class="italic">S. maritima</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">S. densiflora</italic> flowers during the end of spring and the beginning of summer when increasing temperatures and photoperiods co-occur and both cordgrasses are protogynous, with the pistil emerging earlier than the stamens starting from upper flowers in the inflorescences to their bottom (
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Davis et al., 2004</xref>). In mild years during May–July, as those frequently recorded in the first decades of the twentieth century, 
 <italic class="italic">S. maritima</italic> lengthened its flowering, starting in May and being prolonged until the end of July, and 
 <italic class="italic">S. densiflora</italic> started its flowering in July. In these meteorological conditions similar to those of 2018, 
 <italic class="italic">S. maritima</italic> finished its flowering exerting all its stamens, showing high pollen:ovule ratio. Thus, it would be expected that the hybrid of which 
 <italic class="italic">S. densiflora</italic> is the seed parent (
 <italic class="italic">S. densiflora × maritima</italic>) would be the most abundant, as recorded in our study. There would be a greater chance of matching the last stamens (pollen) of 
 <italic class="italic">S. maritima</italic> to the first pistils (stigma) of 
 <italic class="italic">S. densiflora</italic>, when its stamens have not yet been exerted, than 
 <italic class="italic">vice versa</italic>. In contrast, during warm flowering periods, as those recorded mainly at the end of the twentieth century and the beginning of the twenty-first century as 2017, the flowering of 
 <italic class="italic">S. maritima</italic> finished early and abruptly in July so that the stamens of some inflorescences did not get to be exerted while the pistils were already exerted, which was reflected in low pollen:ovules ratio for 
 <italic class="italic">S. maritima</italic>. Thus, the result of low pollen:ovule ratio of 
 <italic class="italic">S. maritima</italic> during warm flowering periods would result, as recorded in our study, in a higher formation of the hybrid 
 <italic class="italic">S. maritima × densiflora</italic>. On the other hand, the broad flowering period of 
 <italic class="italic">S. densiflora</italic> from June to December reported by 
 <xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Valdes et al. (1987)</xref> and 
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Castillo and Figueroa (2009a)</xref> in the Gulf of Cadiz and (
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bortolus, 2006</xref>) in different regions worldwide would be related to the high phenotypic plasticity of this cordgrass in response to contrasted environmental conditions (
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Nieva et al., 2001</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Castillo et al., 2014</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Grewell et al., 2016</xref>). 
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Seneca and Blum (1984)</xref> observed that air temperature was the main factor controlling the flowering of 
 <italic class="italic">Spartina alterniflora</italic> Loisel., blooming at 22–26°C, while 
 <italic class="italic">Spartina foliosa</italic> Trin. flowered in a wider temperature range being less dependent on this factor. This increase in the flowering of 
 <italic class="italic">S. alterniflora</italic> with temperature was mainly associated to high carbon assimilation, although photoperiod-temperature direct induction was not ruled out. Also, mild temperatures in spring and early summer are known to delay flowering of the allopolyploid 
 <italic class="italic">Spartina anglica</italic> C.E.Hubb. (
 <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ranwell, 1967</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gray et al., 1991</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Thompson, 1991</xref>). Another factor that would favor the formation of the hybrid 
 <italic class="italic">S. maritima × densiflora</italic> at low marshes is the fact that 
 <italic class="italic">S. densiflora</italic> in this stressful habitat flowers normally earlier than at middle marshes (
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Nieva et al., 2005</xref>), facilitating the pollination of 
 <italic class="italic">S. maritima</italic>.
</p>
