<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Climate change models predict increases in maximum temperatures and decreases in rainfall in the Mediterranean basin especially in summer (
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Giorgi and Lionello, 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Giannakopoulos et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kovats et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">IPCC, 2015</xref>), so we predict a reduction of the formation of the hybrid 
 <italic class="italic">S. densiflora × maritima</italic> in favor of 
 <italic class="italic">S. maritima × densiflora</italic>. In view of our results, the rise in just a few degrees in air maximum temperature during the flowering periods of 
 <italic class="italic">S. maritima</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">S. densiflora</italic> increases the probabilities of establishment of the hybrid 
 <italic class="italic">S. maritima × densiflora</italic> in relation to 
 <italic class="italic">S. densiflora × maritima</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">S. maritima × densiflora</italic> was formed mainly with mean maximum temperature in June higher than 29°C, whereas 
 <italic class="italic">S. densiflora × maritima</italic> with mean maximum temperature in June lower than 31°C. The predictions of maximum temperature increase with climate change in summer in Southern Iberian Peninsula range from +2.5°C in 2040 to +7.2°C in 2100 (
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Anaya-Romero et al., 2015</xref>), so a marked intensification in the maternal switch in the formation of 
 <italic class="italic">Spartina</italic> hybrids is expected. Specifically in Southwest Iberian Peninsula where this study was carried out, atmospheric temperatures and the duration and intensity of heat waves are increasing, and are predicted to continue to increase in the mid-term (2046–2065) and specially in the long-term (2081–2100) future due to climate change (
 <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Pereira et al., 2017</xref>). Thus, if the current trend continues, most summer days would present maximum daily temperatures higher than 30–35°C by the end of the XXI century (
 <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Pereira et al., 2017</xref>). Under these future conditions, our results suggest only the invasive hybrid 
 <italic class="italic">S. maritima × densiflora</italic> may establish and persist.
</p>
