<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We expected to find functionally more diverse seed pools in the flooded areas than in the drought areas, reflecting that hydrochory can introduce seeds from an upstream species pool in addition to seeds that may enter from the local species pool by wind and/or animal dispersal. Furthermore, earlier investigations have shown that seed deposition in flooded areas is highly dependent on flow patterns and microtopography within the areas and that the amount of seeds deposited coincides with the drift line in flooded areas (Nilsson &amp; Grelsson, 
 <xref rid="ece33973-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1990</xref>; Riis, Baattrup‐Pedersen, Poulsen, &amp; Kronvang, 
 <xref rid="ece33973-bib-0056" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). We therefore expected to find the highest diversity at intermediate distance from the streams. However, our study did not confirm this expectation as the functional diversity was unaffected by flooding. This finding indicates that species arriving by water may not be more functionally diverse than those arriving by other means of dispersal. This interpretation is supported by previous studies reporting that species dispersed by hydrochory are often those already locally abundant (Brederveld, Jähnig, Lorenz, Brunzel, &amp; Soons, 
 <xref rid="ece33973-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>; Soomers et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33973-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>) and that flooding in itself may not be sufficient to increase species richness in grassland vegetation upon restoration of more natural flooding conditions (Baattrup‐Pedersen, Riis, &amp; Larsen, 
 <xref rid="ece33973-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Baattrup‐Pedersen, Dalkvist, et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33973-bib-0005" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Bissels, Holzel, Donath, &amp; Otte, 
 <xref rid="ece33973-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2004</xref>).
</p>
