<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece35087-sec-0004" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Characterizing MHC</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For each of the 128 birds sampled, we used polymerase chain reaction (PCR) to amplify the hypervariable second exon of class II MHC. We used primers 
  <span class="italic">SospMHCint1f </span>(Slade et al., 
  <a rid="ece35087-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0061">2016</a>) and 
  <span class="italic">Int2r.1</span> (Edwards, Gasper, &amp; March, 
  <a rid="ece35087-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0017">1998</a>), which should bind within introns 1 and 2 respectively, to amplify exon 2. In addition to the priming sequence, each primer included a unique “barcode” sequence of eight base pairs; four “wobble” bases; and an adaptor sequence for the Illumina MiSeq platform. PCRs were conducted in a total volume of 30 μl, including 12.5 μl of GoTaq® Hot Start Master Mix (Promega), 0.2 μM of each primer, and 25–60 ng of template DNA. Cycling conditions were 3 min at 94°C; 28 cycles of 30 s at 94°C, 30 s at 62°C, and 45 s at 72°C; and a final extension step of 10 min at 72°C. We confirmed amplification by running a portion of each PCR product on a 2% agarose gel. We then pooled together all samples for a given field season (2014, 2015) to form a library. Each season's library was run on a separate Illumina MiSeq flow cell at the London Regional Genomics Center.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used a pipeline (Gloor et al., 
  <a rid="ece35087-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0021">2010</a>) together with individually unique combinations of barcode sequences to assign MHC reads to individuals. We identified and removed chimeric sequences using UCHIME (Edgar, Haas, Clemente, Quince, &amp; Knight, 
  <a rid="ece35087-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0016">2011</a>). We also filtered out any sequence occurring in fewer than 1% of an individual's total reads, as these rare sequences might represent errors in PCR or sequencing. This 1% threshold was established as described in Slade, Sarquis‐Adamson, et al. (
  <a rid="ece35087-bib-0060" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0060">2017</a>); briefly, we used bacterial cloning (Promega pGEM‐T Easy Vector System) to generate colonies that each contained a single allele. We included these colonies on the flow cell run and used the frequency of secondary reads to establish the error rate associated with PCR and sequencing. After filtering, we aligned the remaining sequences in MEGA 7.0 (Kumar, Stecher, &amp; Tamura, 
  <a rid="ece35087-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0035">2016</a>). We trimmed each to a length of 216–219 base pairs (72‐73 codons; this variation in length reflects the presence of a 3‐bp indel), corresponding to codons 8‐80 of exon 2 of MHC class II (total length 90 codons; Minias et al., 
  <a rid="ece35087-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0043">2018</a>) in order to restrict our analysis to the region of highest read quality and to maintain consistency with previous studies (Slade, Sarquis‐Adamson, et al., 
  <a rid="ece35087-bib-0060" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0060">2017</a>; Slade et al., 
  <a rid="ece35087-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0061">2016</a>; Slade, Watson, &amp; MacDougall‐Shackleton, 
  <a rid="ece35087-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0062">2017</a>). Hereafter, references to specific codon numbers (e.g., codon 2, codon 6) refer to positions within the trimmed region that we analyzed, not within the full exon 2. We confirmed similarity to other passerine sequences by querying the Basic Local Alignment Search tool (BLAST; Altschul, Gish, Miller, Myers, &amp; Lipman, 
  <a rid="ece35087-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0001">1990</a>) implemented in GenBank.
 </p>
</sec>
