<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="discussion" id="ece35087-sec-0009" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">DISCUSSION</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The diversifying effects of disassortative mating, that is, increasing genetic diversity of individuals and maintaining multiple alleles within populations, are similar to those of heterozygote advantage and negative frequency‐dependent selection. The general prevalence of balancing selection at MHC (Hedrick, 
  <a rid="ece35087-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0022">1998</a>; Piertney &amp; Oliver, 
  <a rid="ece35087-bib-0051" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0051">2006</a>), combined with the discovery that these loci affect not just disease resistance but also odor, thus providing a plausible mechanism for nonrandom mating (Yamazaki et al., 
  <a rid="ece35087-bib-0073" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0073">1979</a>), led to the reasonable initial expectation that when mating is nonrandom with respect to MHC, it should be disassortative such that mate choice operates in concert with the diversifying effects of balancing selection mediated by pathogens.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As predicted, we found evidence of historical balancing selection at MHC class II in our study population of song sparrows, presumably reflecting long‐standing evolutionary interactions with pathogens. Several codons showed an excess of nonsynonymous relative to synonymous variation, indicating positive Darwinian selection consistent with balancing selection. Likewise, many of the alleles characterized in song sparrows were more similar to alleles found in other species (including some from different avian families) than to other song sparrow sequences: This pattern implies long‐term balancing selection at MHC class II, which should promote the maintenance of multiple alleles at these loci and thus be associated with high levels of individual genetic diversity. In contrast, however, free‐living song sparrows paired assortatively rather than disassortatively at these loci, a pattern which should reduce individual genetic diversity of the resultant offspring. Indeed, nestling song sparrows in this population are less diverse at MHC class II than are adults (Watson, 
  <a rid="ece35087-bib-0067" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0067">2017</a>), a pattern which might result from assortative mating. Collectively, our findings show that even when balancing selection is operating at MHC, nonrandom mating does not necessarily reinforce these diversifying effects.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Song sparrows in the study population showed several signals of past balancing selection. Although most codons appear to have been primarily subject to purifying selection, as is typical for functional coding loci (Yang &amp; Swanson, 
  <a rid="ece35087-bib-0076" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0076">2002</a>), six codons were consistently identified across multiple tests for sequence evolution as being likely to have experienced positive selection. Two of these, based on alignment to human MHC sequence, correspond to antigen‐binding positions that are likely to experience particularly intense selection (Hughes &amp; Hughes, 
  <a rid="ece35087-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0025">1995</a>). Moreover, four of the six codons identified correspond to the consensus of positively selected sites across passerines (Minias et al., 
  <a rid="ece35087-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0043">2018</a>). The remaining positively selected codon (site 24) did not correspond to an antigen‐binding position based on sequence alignment with human MHC, nor was it reported to be positively selected site across passerines in general (Minias et al., 
  <a rid="ece35087-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0043">2018</a>). Positive selection at MHC is widespread: In a recent review of the literature (25 publications on 25 vertebrate species), positive selection within the peptide‐binding region of MHC was reported in every study (Slade, 
  <a rid="ece35087-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0059">2018</a>). Although both balancing and directional selection can generate positive selection (Hedrick, 
  <a rid="ece35087-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0023">2007</a>), positive selection at MHC is generally considered to result from balancing selection (i.e., new alleles entering a population through mutation or immigration tend to increase in frequency). Still, we do not conclusively rule out the possibility that the observed positive selection could reflect a transient excess of nonsynonymous variants resulting from directional rather than balancing selection.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Further support for the importance of balancing selection in shaping variation at the song sparrow MHC class II comes from comparing sequences in song sparrows to their homologues in other songbird species. While we did not observe trans‐species polymorphisms as strictly defined, several alleles found in song sparrows were more similar to heterospecific alleles than to other conspecific alleles. For example, song sparrow sequences SOSP‐DAB*18, *19, and *21 were more similar to sequences from Thraupidae, Icteridae, and Emberizinae than to other alleles from song sparrows (family Passerellidae), despite the long‐standing divergence between Passerellidae and these other avian families (16.3–32.6 MY; Selvatti, Gonzaga, &amp; de Moraes Russo, 
  <a rid="ece35087-bib-0056" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0056">2015</a>). Although we cannot conclusively exclude the possibility of convergent sequence evolution, we think it probable that long‐standing balancing selection has maintained these allelic lineages since before the divergence of Passerellidae.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The expectation that sexual selection should favor MHC‐disassortative mating stems from the premise that offspring fitness (specifically, resistance to infectious disease) increases with increasing diversity at MHC. Clearly, offspring resulting from more MHC‐dissimilar pairings should be more diverse at MHC, and presumably capable of responding to a wider diversity of antigens (Klein, 
  <a rid="ece35087-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0031">1986</a>). However, whether this translates into enhanced lifetime reproductive success, or even into superior disease resistance, is less clear. First, trade‐offs between nonadditive (compatible gene) effects, such as heterozygote advantage, and additive (good gene) effects may generate stabilizing selection on MHC diversity. Thus, given a finite level of gene product, excessive diversity at MHC may dilute the protective effects of locally good alleles (de Boer &amp; Perelson, 
  <a rid="ece35087-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0014">1993</a>; Kubinak, Nelson, Ruff, &amp; Potts, 
  <a rid="ece35087-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0033">2012</a>; Wegner et al., 
  <a rid="ece35087-bib-0069" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0069">2003</a>). Second, the risk of parasitic infection associated with insufficient diversity at MHC may trade off with the risk of autoimmune disorders associated with excessive diversity (Apanius, Penn, Slev, Ruff, &amp; Potts, 
  <a rid="ece35087-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0002">1997</a>; Bottazzo, Todd, Mirakian, Belfiore, &amp; Pujol‐Borrell, 
  <a rid="ece35087-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0008">1986</a>; Wegner et al., 
  <a rid="ece35087-bib-0069" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0069">2003</a>). Finally, pairings that are maximally dissimilar at MHC may generate outbreeding depression in offspring by disrupting coadapted gene complexes at MHC or other linked loci (Tregenza &amp; Wedell, 
  <a rid="ece35087-bib-0065" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0065">2000</a>). This risk may be magnified in hybrid zones, or when two or more locally adapted populations come into contact (Neff, 
  <a rid="ece35087-bib-0046" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0046">2004</a>). We suggest that systems in which MHC is highly polygenic and polymorphic, such as song sparrows, are also likely to experience stabilizing rather than directional selection on MHC diversity. Optimal mate choice thus requires resolving trade‐offs between the benefits and the costs of high MHC diversity, which promote disassortative and assortative mating, respectively.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our study did not address directly whether pathogen‐mediated balancing selection is currently operating in this population, for example, by comparing disease resistance of more versus less diverse genotypes. However, a cross‐sectional analysis in the study population showed that adults were more diverse than nestlings (more alleles per individual) at MHC class II (Watson, 
  <a rid="ece35087-bib-0067" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0067">2017</a>). One interpretation of this pattern is that MHC‐diverse individuals are more likely to survive to adulthood than their less diverse counterparts. However, this pattern was observed in just one of two years of study, and MHC diversity did not predict overwinter return rates (interpreted as survivorship; Watson, 
  <a rid="ece35087-bib-0067" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0067">2017</a>). Thus, if MHC diversity confers a survival advantage in this population, it does not do so consistently every year (Watson, 
  <a rid="ece35087-bib-0067" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0067">2017</a>). Moreover, as noted above, assortative mating at MHC could also explain the difference in diversity between age cohorts. Song repertoire size, a sexually selected trait associated with early‐life condition, is also highest in males with intermediate rather than maximal MHC class II diversity in this population (Slade, Watson, et al., 
  <a rid="ece35087-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0062">2017</a>). Thus, the relationship between MHC class II diversity and fitness in our study population does not appear to be uniformly positive, perhaps because of high standing levels of genetic variation.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We interpret the observed pattern of MHC‐assortative pairing as reflecting preferences, actively expressed by one or both sexes, for MHC‐similar social mates. In theory, assortative mating could also be explained through passive mechanisms, that is, by highly restricted natal dispersal such that close relatives are more likely to interact than nonrelatives. However, song sparrows are highly mobile, with natal dispersal distances on the order of 6 km (Zink &amp; Dittmann, 
  <a rid="ece35087-bib-0078" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0078">1993</a>) and individuals in our study population routinely migrating hundreds of kilometers between breeding and wintering grounds (Kelly et al., 
  <a rid="ece35087-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0029">2016</a>). Thus, we do not think it likely that mobility constrains social mate choice at the geographic scale we investigated (&lt;1 km
  <span class="sup">2</span>). Moreover, based on band‐recapture analysis, natal philopatry is low (5%–15% of new recruits each year were banded as nestlings; Stewart &amp; MacDougall‐Shackleton, 
  <a rid="ece35087-bib-0064" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0064">2008</a>) and strongly male‐biased, further reducing the likelihood of close relatives encountering one another as potential mates. Similarly, we cannot exclude the possibility that the observed mating patterns reflect active inbreeding, such that individuals preferentially mate with close relatives, which would also result in mated pairs being relatively similar at MHC. However, we think this unlikely as song sparrows do not appear to either prefer or avoid close relatives as social mates (Keller &amp; Arcese, 
  <a rid="ece35087-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0028">1998</a>). Behavioral tests under controlled conditions, for example, testing preferences for preen oil odor from MHC‐similar versus MHC‐dissimilar individuals (Leclaire et al., 
  <a rid="ece35087-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0036">2017</a>), represent a critical next step to confirm (a) whether assortative pairing observed in the field reflects preferences expressed in the laboratory, and (b) whether chemical cues provide a mechanism for assessing MHC similarity in songbirds, as they do in other vertebrates (Brennan &amp; Zufall, 
  <a rid="ece35087-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0010">2006</a>; Leclaire et al., 
  <a rid="ece35087-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0036">2017</a>; Milinski et al., 
  <a rid="ece35087-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0041">2005</a>). Comparing the pairing behavior of free‐living animals to preferences expressed under standardized conditions will also shed light on potential trade‐offs between direct and indirect benefits associated with social and genetic mating decisions, and whether MHC‐related preferences are similar in both sexes.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Regardless of whether assortative mating stems from expressed mating preferences or from some other mechanism, its effects on individual genetic diversity (i.e., increasing homozygosity) oppose those of balancing selection (i.e., increasing divergence). In systems where strong and long‐standing balancing selection, presumably mediated by past arms races with pathogens, has generated high variation at immune loci, the ability of mate choice to “balance” balancing selection (i.e., to avoid producing offspring with an excessive number of different alleles) may be advantageous. Whether the assortative mating we observed in this population at the hypervariable class II MHC also occurs at the less variable class I MHC remains an open, and important, question. In particular, whereas song repertoire size does not increase monotonically with class II diversity in this population (Slade, Watson, et al., 
  <a rid="ece35087-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0062">2017</a>), resistance to hematozoan infection does increase monotonically with class I diversity (Slade, Sarquis‐Adamson, et al., 
  <a rid="ece35087-bib-0060" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0060">2017</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Assortative mating does not necessarily reduce genetic diversity at the population level, at least under monogamous mating systems where the ability to attract a mate does not differ appreciably between genotypes. Assortative mating at MHC may thus balance the costs and benefits of genetic diversity within individuals, without constraining the evolutionary potential of populations to adapt to future changes in pathogen regime.</p>
</sec>
