<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="materials-and-methods" id="ece35087-sec-0002" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">MATERIALS AND METHODS</div>
 <sec id="ece35087-sec-0003" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study animals and field methods</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fieldwork focused on a long‐term study population of migratory song sparrows breeding near Newboro, Ontario, Canada (44.6338°N, 76.3308°W). During spring 2014 (April 14‐June 2) and 2015 (April 13‐June 6), corresponding to nesting, egg‐laying, incubating, and provisioning offspring in the study population, we captured adult song sparrows; collected blood samples for genetic analysis; and identified socially mated pairs, using trapping records and behavioral observations as detailed below.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We captured song sparrows in two‐celled, seed‐baited Potter traps, which we checked once per hour, three times a day, between 07:00 and 11:00. We captured 69 birds in 2014 (44 males, 25 females) and 87 in 2015 (49 males, 38 females). These figures include 28 birds that were captured in both study years (25 males, three females); thus, our sample comprises 128 individuals (68 males, 60 females).</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From each bird, we collected ~25 μl of whole blood via brachial venipuncture the first time it was captured each year. We blotted blood onto high wet‐strength filter paper saturated with 0.5 M Na‐EDTA (pH 8.0), allowed the blot to air‐dry, then stored it at room temperature awaiting DNA extraction. We identified sex based on the presence (male) or absence (female) of a cloacal protuberance, supplemented by unflattened wing length (measured with dial calipers to the nearest 0.1 mm). If not already banded, we outfitted the bird with a numbered aluminum leg band (Environment and Climate Change Canada Scientific Banding Permit 10691B), and a unique combination of three colored plastic leg bands to permit individual identification in the field. We recorded any other song sparrows in the trap (i.e., trapped in the other cell at the same time) and released birds at their site of capture. In almost all cases, birds were later resighted and/or recaptured, implying that they were resident breeders. Animal procedures were approved by the Animal Use Subcommittee at the University of Western Ontario (protocols 2008‐054 and 2015‐047 to EAM‐S) and conducted under the required federal permits.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Song sparrows are socially monogamous, and extrapair mating is rare in the study population: Fewer than 20% of nests contain extrapair offspring (Potvin &amp; MacDougall‐Shackleton, 
   <a rid="ece35087-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0052">2009</a>). For these reasons, and because high rates of nest failure make it challenging to collect blood from nestlings for genetic parentage analysis, we focused on social rather than genetic mate choice. We identified socially mated pairs through opportunistic behavioral observations on color‐banded individuals (e.g., copulations or copulation solicitations; female and male observed foraging together; female and male observed provisioning the same nest) combined with trapping records. We identified pairs based on trapping records if one or both of the following conditions were met: (a) Two individuals of opposite sex were trapped together at the same time (8.7% of all trapping records), or (b) two individuals of opposite sex were captured in the same trap within 48 hr of one another, and no other song sparrows were trapped at that location during the entire field season (8.8% of all trapping records). Based on these criteria, we identified 18 socially mated pairs in 2014 and 22 in 2015. These figures include one pair that remained the same over both field seasons; to avoid pseudoreplication, we included this pairing in the 2014 mate choice analysis only. These figures also include three individuals (one male, two females) that were each identified as part of a mated pair in 2014, but had a different mate in 2015: These were included in both years’ mate choice analyses.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece35087-sec-0004" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Characterizing MHC</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For each of the 128 birds sampled, we used polymerase chain reaction (PCR) to amplify the hypervariable second exon of class II MHC. We used primers 
   <span class="italic">SospMHCint1f </span>(Slade et al., 
   <a rid="ece35087-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0061">2016</a>) and 
   <span class="italic">Int2r.1</span> (Edwards, Gasper, &amp; March, 
   <a rid="ece35087-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0017">1998</a>), which should bind within introns 1 and 2 respectively, to amplify exon 2. In addition to the priming sequence, each primer included a unique “barcode” sequence of eight base pairs; four “wobble” bases; and an adaptor sequence for the Illumina MiSeq platform. PCRs were conducted in a total volume of 30 μl, including 12.5 μl of GoTaq® Hot Start Master Mix (Promega), 0.2 μM of each primer, and 25–60 ng of template DNA. Cycling conditions were 3 min at 94°C; 28 cycles of 30 s at 94°C, 30 s at 62°C, and 45 s at 72°C; and a final extension step of 10 min at 72°C. We confirmed amplification by running a portion of each PCR product on a 2% agarose gel. We then pooled together all samples for a given field season (2014, 2015) to form a library. Each season's library was run on a separate Illumina MiSeq flow cell at the London Regional Genomics Center.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used a pipeline (Gloor et al., 
   <a rid="ece35087-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0021">2010</a>) together with individually unique combinations of barcode sequences to assign MHC reads to individuals. We identified and removed chimeric sequences using UCHIME (Edgar, Haas, Clemente, Quince, &amp; Knight, 
   <a rid="ece35087-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0016">2011</a>). We also filtered out any sequence occurring in fewer than 1% of an individual's total reads, as these rare sequences might represent errors in PCR or sequencing. This 1% threshold was established as described in Slade, Sarquis‐Adamson, et al. (
   <a rid="ece35087-bib-0060" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0060">2017</a>); briefly, we used bacterial cloning (Promega pGEM‐T Easy Vector System) to generate colonies that each contained a single allele. We included these colonies on the flow cell run and used the frequency of secondary reads to establish the error rate associated with PCR and sequencing. After filtering, we aligned the remaining sequences in MEGA 7.0 (Kumar, Stecher, &amp; Tamura, 
   <a rid="ece35087-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0035">2016</a>). We trimmed each to a length of 216–219 base pairs (72‐73 codons; this variation in length reflects the presence of a 3‐bp indel), corresponding to codons 8‐80 of exon 2 of MHC class II (total length 90 codons; Minias et al., 
   <a rid="ece35087-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0043">2018</a>) in order to restrict our analysis to the region of highest read quality and to maintain consistency with previous studies (Slade, Sarquis‐Adamson, et al., 
   <a rid="ece35087-bib-0060" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0060">2017</a>; Slade et al., 
   <a rid="ece35087-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0061">2016</a>; Slade, Watson, &amp; MacDougall‐Shackleton, 
   <a rid="ece35087-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0062">2017</a>). Hereafter, references to specific codon numbers (e.g., codon 2, codon 6) refer to positions within the trimmed region that we analyzed, not within the full exon 2. We confirmed similarity to other passerine sequences by querying the Basic Local Alignment Search tool (BLAST; Altschul, Gish, Miller, Myers, &amp; Lipman, 
   <a rid="ece35087-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0001">1990</a>) implemented in GenBank.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece35087-sec-0005" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mate choice analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To test whether song sparrows pair nonrandomly at MHC class II, we compared genetic distances between socially mated pairs to the randomized set of possible opposite‐sex combinations based on adults captured at the site during the corresponding field season. Because some allelic pairs are more similar in sequence than others, rather than simply quantify allele sharing, we used UniFrac (Lozupone &amp; Knight, 
   <a rid="ece35087-bib-0038" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0038">2005</a>) to take into account phylogenetic distances between alleles. Based on a phylogeny of all alleles detected, the algorithm calculates the distance between two individuals’ translated MHC repertoires, such that two individuals with the identical set of alleles would have a UniFrac distance of zero and two individuals with alleles derived from completely different clades in the reference tree would have a UniFrac distance of one (Lozupone &amp; Knight, 
   <a rid="ece35087-bib-0038" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0038">2005</a>). We first constructed a maximum‐likelihood phylogeny of all alleles recovered, over both field seasons, using Whelan and Goldman (
   <a rid="ece35087-bib-0071" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0071">2001</a>) substitution with five discrete gamma categories. Based on this phylogeny, we calculated pairwise amino acid UniFrac distances for observed pairings (i.e., between socially mated pairs). Because genotype data were binary (i.e., presence or absence of an allele within an individual's genotype) rather than continuous, we calculated unweighted (qualitative) rather than weighted (quantitative) UniFrac. UniFrac distances were calculated using the package GUniFrac (Chen et al., 
   <a rid="ece35087-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0013">2012</a>), implemented in R 3.4.0 (R Core Team, 
   <a rid="ece35087-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0053">2017</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used a Monte Carlo simulation (Manly, 
   <a rid="ece35087-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0039">1997</a>) implemented in a custom Microsoft Excel macro (Neff, Garner, Heath, &amp; Heath, 
   <a rid="ece35087-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0047">2008</a>) to generate 10,000 randomized male–female adult pairings. Genotypes from which randomized pairings were drawn were sorted by year, such that, for example, an adult female captured at the field site in 2014 was assumed to have had the potential to pair with any of the adult males present in that year. We then calculated pairwise genetic distance for each randomized pairing using unweighted UniFrac as described above. Finally, we calculated the average genetic distance over the 40 observed social pairings and compared this to the expected distribution of genetic distances based on random mating.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece35087-sec-0006" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.4</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sequence evolution</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We tested for signatures of positive selection using all available genotypes from the study population in 2014 and 2015 (128 breeding adults). After filtering out chimeras and very low‐frequency reads as described above, we tested for positive selection across our sequenced portion of exon 2, using PAMLx 1.3.1 (Xu &amp; Yang, 
   <a rid="ece35087-bib-0072" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0072">2013</a>). Statistical significance was assessed by a 
   <span class="italic">Z</span>‐test, bootstrapped at 500 replicates, and conducted in MEGA 7.0 (Kumar et al., 
   <a rid="ece35087-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0035">2016</a>). To ensure we confidently identified positively selected sites, we tested for positive selection at each codon site separately using multiple complementary approaches implemented in 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.datamonkey.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">datamonkey.org</span> (Weaver et al., 
   <a rid="ece35087-bib-0068" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0068">2018</a>) in addition to PAMLx 1.3.1. Specifically, we tested for positive selection using a mixed‐effects model of evolution (MEME; Murrell et al., 
   <a rid="ece35087-bib-0045" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0045">2012</a>), fixed‐effects likelihood (FEL; Kosakovsky Pond &amp; Frost, 
   <a rid="ece35087-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0032">2005</a>), single‐likelihood ancestor counting (SLAC; Kosakovsky Pond &amp; Frost, 
   <a rid="ece35087-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0032">2005</a>), and fast, unconstrained Bayesian approximation (FUBAR; Murrell et al., 
   <a rid="ece35087-bib-0044" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0044">2013</a>). Finally, because positive selection is expected to be strongest at peptide‐binding codons, we compared the set of codons our analyses identified as having experienced past positive selection to the set of codons identified as peptide‐binding in humans (Brown et al. 
   <a rid="ece35087-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0011">1993</a>), as well as to those codons recently identified as positively selected in passerines in general (Minias et al., 
   <a rid="ece35087-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0043">2018</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In PAMLx 1.3.1, we used the 
   <span class="italic">codeml</span> command (Yang, 
   <a rid="ece35087-bib-0075" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0075">2007</a>) to calculate ω, defined as the ratio of nonsynonymous substitutions per nonsynonymous site (dN) to synonymous substitutions per synonymous site (dS). Codons (sites) at which ω is less than, equal to, or greater than one is interpreted as having undergone purifying (negative) selection (ω
   <sub>0</sub>,) neutral evolution (ω
   <sub>1</sub>), and positive selection (ω
   <sub>2</sub>), respectively. 
   <span class="italic">Codeml</span> does not make a priori assumptions as to which codons are likely to experience each type of selection (Yang &amp; Swanson, 
   <a rid="ece35087-bib-0076" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0076">2002</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To evaluate which model(s) of sequence evolution best explained the observed variation in MHC class II exon 2 sequence in 
   <span class="italic">codeml</span>, we used an information theoretic approach (Burnham &amp; Anderson, 
   <a rid="ece35087-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0012">2002</a>), ranking candidate models generated by PAML based on Akaike's information criterion (AIC). Candidate models were M1a (nearly neutral; ω
   <sub>0</sub> &lt; 1, ω
   <sub>1</sub> = 1), M2a (positive selection; ω
   <sub>2</sub> &gt; 1), M8 (positive selection with β distribution; 0 &lt; ω &lt; 1, ω &gt; 1), and M7 (null model counterpart to M8). Models M1a and M2a use the ω distribution to model parameters, and models M7 and M8 use the β distribution, constrained to range between 0 and 1 (Yang, 
   <a rid="ece35087-bib-0074" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0074">2000</a>). We were particularly interested in the explanatory power of M2a relative to M1a, and of M8 relative to M7, because models M2a and M8 permit some codons to experience positive selection, whereas the null models M1a and M7 assume that codons experience neutral evolution, but also test for purifying selection. We identified positively selected codons using the Bayes empirical Bayes approach (Yang, Wong, &amp; Nielsen, 
   <a rid="ece35087-bib-0077" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0077">2005</a>) implemented in PAMLx 1.3.1 (Xu &amp; Yang, 
   <a rid="ece35087-bib-0072" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0072">2013</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece35087-sec-0007" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.5</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Trans‐species polymorphisms</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Trans‐species polymorphisms involve two or more alleles, each occurring in two or more species. We conducted a nonexhaustive survey for such polymorphisms, including variants that while not identical across species, are more similar to their heterospecific counterpart than to one or more conspecific alleles. We identified the ten most common alleles in the study population of song sparrows and queried them against BLAST in GenBank (Altschul et al., 
   <a rid="ece35087-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0001">1990</a>). For each allele, we identified any heterospecific sequences with at least 94% DNA sequence similarity. In all, we retrieved 25 such sequences from other songbirds.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We constructed a maximum‐likelihood phylogeny of the ten most common song sparrow alleles and the 25 heterospecific sequences, using a Jukes–Cantor model. Interdigitation of song sparrow alleles with those of other species would suggest that allelic diversification occurred prior speciation events and that balancing selection is of ancient origin. Conversely, if the ten song sparrow alleles comprised a monophyletic clade, this would suggest that allelic diversification has occurred more recently than speciation events and that balancing selection is of relatively recent origin.</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
