<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece35087-sec-0003" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study animals and field methods</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fieldwork focused on a long‐term study population of migratory song sparrows breeding near Newboro, Ontario, Canada (44.6338°N, 76.3308°W). During spring 2014 (April 14‐June 2) and 2015 (April 13‐June 6), corresponding to nesting, egg‐laying, incubating, and provisioning offspring in the study population, we captured adult song sparrows; collected blood samples for genetic analysis; and identified socially mated pairs, using trapping records and behavioral observations as detailed below.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We captured song sparrows in two‐celled, seed‐baited Potter traps, which we checked once per hour, three times a day, between 07:00 and 11:00. We captured 69 birds in 2014 (44 males, 25 females) and 87 in 2015 (49 males, 38 females). These figures include 28 birds that were captured in both study years (25 males, three females); thus, our sample comprises 128 individuals (68 males, 60 females).</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From each bird, we collected ~25 μl of whole blood via brachial venipuncture the first time it was captured each year. We blotted blood onto high wet‐strength filter paper saturated with 0.5 M Na‐EDTA (pH 8.0), allowed the blot to air‐dry, then stored it at room temperature awaiting DNA extraction. We identified sex based on the presence (male) or absence (female) of a cloacal protuberance, supplemented by unflattened wing length (measured with dial calipers to the nearest 0.1 mm). If not already banded, we outfitted the bird with a numbered aluminum leg band (Environment and Climate Change Canada Scientific Banding Permit 10691B), and a unique combination of three colored plastic leg bands to permit individual identification in the field. We recorded any other song sparrows in the trap (i.e., trapped in the other cell at the same time) and released birds at their site of capture. In almost all cases, birds were later resighted and/or recaptured, implying that they were resident breeders. Animal procedures were approved by the Animal Use Subcommittee at the University of Western Ontario (protocols 2008‐054 and 2015‐047 to EAM‐S) and conducted under the required federal permits.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Song sparrows are socially monogamous, and extrapair mating is rare in the study population: Fewer than 20% of nests contain extrapair offspring (Potvin &amp; MacDougall‐Shackleton, 
  <a rid="ece35087-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35087-bib-0052">2009</a>). For these reasons, and because high rates of nest failure make it challenging to collect blood from nestlings for genetic parentage analysis, we focused on social rather than genetic mate choice. We identified socially mated pairs through opportunistic behavioral observations on color‐banded individuals (e.g., copulations or copulation solicitations; female and male observed foraging together; female and male observed provisioning the same nest) combined with trapping records. We identified pairs based on trapping records if one or both of the following conditions were met: (a) Two individuals of opposite sex were trapped together at the same time (8.7% of all trapping records), or (b) two individuals of opposite sex were captured in the same trap within 48 hr of one another, and no other song sparrows were trapped at that location during the entire field season (8.8% of all trapping records). Based on these criteria, we identified 18 socially mated pairs in 2014 and 22 in 2015. These figures include one pair that remained the same over both field seasons; to avoid pseudoreplication, we included this pairing in the 2014 mate choice analysis only. These figures also include three individuals (one male, two females) that were each identified as part of a mated pair in 2014, but had a different mate in 2015: These were included in both years’ mate choice analyses.
 </p>
</sec>
