<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par10" class="p">In previous GHG mitigation policy analyses with CAPRI, technological (i.e. technical and management-based) mitigation options were not implemented endogenously. This paper draws on the first study to endogenize the choice among the following selected technological mitigation options (each of them can voluntarily be applied by farmers) within the CAPRI model (see Van Doorslaer et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" class="xref">2015</xref>): (1) farm scale anaerobic digestion, (2) community anaerobic digestion, (3) nitrification inhibitors, (4) improved timing of fertilization, (5) precision farming and (6) changes in the composition of animals’ feed. The model allows the simultaneous use of different options, for example, nitrification inhibitors, the timing of fertilization and precision farming can be combined to reduce N
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O emissions due to fertilizer applications. Implementation costs and mitigation potential of the modelled technological mitigation options are taken from the Greenhouse Gas and Air Pollution Interactions and Synergies (GAINS) database (GAINS 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">2013</xref>; Höglund-Isaksson et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">2013</xref>). The level of production activities and the use of mitigation technologies are constrained by various factors, including land availability, fertilization requirements of the cropping systems versus organic nutrient availability, feed requirements in terms of dry matter, net energy, protein and fibre for each animal. Production activities and decision-making are also influenced by agricultural and environmental policy restrictions (Britz and Witzke 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" class="xref">2014</xref>; CAPRI 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">2016</xref>). The next section provides more details on how mitigation options have been implemented into the CAPRI model.
</p>
