<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="Introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Birds are among the most suitable groups of organisms for assessing species vulnerability to climate change (
  <a rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41">Pacifi et al. 2015</a>). There is scientific evidence of the impact of climate change on bird communities (
  <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">Crick 2004</a>, 
  <a rid="B42" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42">Pearce-Higgins and Green 2014</a>, 
  <a rid="B43" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43">Pearce-Higgins et al. 2015</a>). Most studies supporting such impacts are based on long-term datasets (e.g. 
  <a rid="B33" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33">Gregory et al. 2009</a>). Long-term datasets have been recognized as a key component for monitoring biodiversity (
  <a rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38">Magurran et al. 2010</a>), and are considered one of the major requirements to identify changes in phenology (
  <a rid="B49" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49">Sanz 2002</a>). However, long-term monitoring programs are often difficult to develop. In this sense, reviewing old studies can help to integrate short-term studies into long-term datasets, providing a potential source of data to assess changes in ecological communities (
  <a rid="B49" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49">Sanz 2002</a>, 
  <a rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39">M체ller et al. 2010</a>). This is relevant for the Mediterranean region, where more bird studies as well as available long-term datasets (
  <a rid="B49" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49">Sanz 2002</a>) are needed, especially considering that predicted levels in species richness have shown a sharp decrease in the southern regions of Europe (
  <a rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4">Barbet-Massin et al. 2012</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this paper, a dataset of passerine bird communities is described from Sierra Nevada, a Mediterranean high mountain region in southern Spain. The dataset comes from Sierra Nevada Global Change Observatory (
  <div xlink:title="Sierra Nevada Global-Change Observatory" class="abbrev" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">OBSNEV</div>), a monitoring programme designed to evaluate the potential impacts of global change in this mountain area. Monitoring methodologies of the 
  <div xlink:title="Sierra Nevada Global-Change Observatory" class="abbrev" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">OBSNEV</div> include revisiting old plots to assess long-term population trends, changes in phenology, and shifts in community composition, among other parameters.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Studies of bird communities in the Sierra Nevada mountain region go back to the 1850s, with the first published records of field observations recorded by ornithologists (
  <a rid="B47" ref-type="bibr" href="#B47">Pleguezuelos 1991</a>, 
  <a rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30">Garz처n 2012</a>). A recent review of the birds in the Sierra Nevada was made by 
  <a rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31">Garz처n and Henares (2012)</a>. All these works include passerines, but specific studies focusing specifically on passerine bird communities on this mountain region were conducted during the 1980s (
  <a rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" href="#B54">Zamora and Camacho 1984</a>, 
  <a rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" href="#B55">Zamora 1987a</a>, 
  <a rid="B56" ref-type="bibr" href="#B56">1987b</a>, 
  <a rid="B57" ref-type="bibr" href="#B57">1988a</a>, 
  <a rid="B58" ref-type="bibr" href="#B58">1988b</a>, 
  <a rid="B59" ref-type="bibr" href="#B59">1990</a>). The dataset presented here contributes knowledge about the passerines in this area, enabling assessments of population trends (e.g. 
  <a rid="B61" ref-type="bibr" href="#B61">Zamora and Barea-Azc처n 2015</a>).
 </p>
 <!--PageBreak-->
</sec>
