<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">So what does drive the sometimes large (−26 to 17 Sv) changes in ACC transport in some models if not changes in surface wind stress? This is presently an open question, although some clues exist. In both CMIP3 and CMIP5, there is a strong correlation between the change in ACC transport and change in the area of the ACC itself, with narrowing ACCs tending to have weaker transport [
 <xref rid="RSTA20130296C32" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSTA20130296C46" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>]. In CMIP5, the northern boundary of the ACC is universally moved polewards by the expanding subtropical gyres, themselves forced by increases in wind stress curl. However, the degree of poleward shift is not correlated with the change in ACC transport. Instead, it is the change in subpolar gyre area that correlates (
 <italic class="italic">r</italic>=0.67 in RCP4.5) with the change in transport, with weakening ACCs being associated with equatorward expanding subpolar gyres. Those gyres that increase in size also increase in strength [
 <xref rid="RSTA20130296C47" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>]. Although the changes in area can be significant, there is no clear pattern to the changes in the subpolar gyres, with the Ross and Weddell Gyres appearing to behave independently both within and across models [
 <xref rid="RSTA20130296C32" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>]. The Ross Gyre tends to exhibit the largest degree of variability and qualitative influence on the ACC position, perhaps as a result of weaker topographic constraints in the Pacific sector. As in CMIP3, changes in wind stress curl are not correlated with the gyre strength [
 <xref rid="RSTA20130296C48" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>], despite high-resolution model studies suggesting that wind stress curl is a significant factor in setting gyre strength [
 <xref rid="RSTA20130296C49" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>]. Ekman pumping, ACC eddy interaction and surface freshwater fluxes have all been suggested as possible factors controlling the subpolar gyres [
 <xref rid="RSTA20130296C47" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSTA20130296C48" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>], but no clear cause has yet been identified. A further complicating factor may be the presence of physically unrealistic open water convection occurring in the Weddell and Ross Gyres in CMIP5 [
 <xref rid="RSTA20130296C50" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>] that will certainly impact the gyre transport and density structure, although the extent of this has not yet been investigated.
</p>
