<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Variables and effect sizes</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The experiments were scored for variables that related to the behaviour and life-history traits of each study species by collating data from original publications or other literature (i.e., bird handbooks, internet; see Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM3">3</a> for more details). Each species was assigned to one of the six established bird types (corvids, passerines other than corvids, birds of prey, seabirds, wetland birds, others; see Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM3">3</a> for details on the categories). Behavioural variables included migratory status (migratory/year-round resident), food caching (caching/non-caching) and propensity to accept a new type of food (generalist diet/specialist diet), while life-history traits measured maximal clutch size, broodedness (one/more than one clutch per year) and body mass. All experiments were also scored for variables related to the experimental setup, such as timing of food supplementation (before and/or during egg-laying only/other timings, i.e., from hatching to fledging or throughout the breeding season), the level of accessibility to the feed for the target species (low/intermediate/high), environmental conditions, such as latitude and elevation (m a.s.l.) of the study site, and the relative background level of food resources (higher/lower than average) (see Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM3">3</a>). The background level of resources was assigned for all studies that estimated the abundance of the most common food item or prey for the target species or reported clear differences in environmental quality (i.e., due to drastic changes in weather conditions) between study years. Food accessibility was considered low when food was substantially exploited by dominants, immigrants and/or non-target species. Accessibility was deemed high when supplemented food was delivered to the nest or nest box, or to the adults directly, and when direct observations indicated that most or all of the food was consumed by the target species. Accessibility was considered intermediate when food was only occasionally exploited by dominants, immigrants and/or non-target species, and not provided directly to the nest or nest box, or to the adults.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The reproductive responses considered in our analyses included laying date, clutch size, egg size, hatching success, brood size, chick body mass and breeding success. Hatching success was defined as the number of hatchlings divided by the total number of eggs laid. Several estimates of breeding success were used, i.e. the number of fledglings per nest, the number of fledglings divided by the total number of hatchlings or by the number of pairs that initiated reproduction or successfully fledged young, if the number of hatchlings was not reported.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Frequently, ecologists are interested in the actual difference in mean performance or the proportional change in performance in response to a treatment. This is why Hedges’
  <span class="italic">d</span> and the log response ratio (ln 
  <span class="italic">R</span>) have been so commonly used as effect sizes in ecological meta-analyses. Since this study is interested in the factors causing variation in life-history traits of bird species, we need to incorporate a measure of variance in the calculation of the effect size, so that a change in any reproductive parameter can be interpreted as the fitness benefit to that species. For example, clutch size might be very constrained in one species and thus a 10% change in response to food supplementation (e.g., change from 1 ± 0.5 SD to 1.1 ± 0.5 SD) is to be valued more than a 10% change when clutch size is less constrained (e.g., change from 1 ± 1 SD to 1.1 ± 1 SD).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used the unbiased standardized mean difference Hedges’
  <span class="italic">d</span> (hereafter 
  <span class="italic">d</span>) as a measure of effect size in our meta-analyses. This effect size can be interpreted as the difference between the reproductive responses of supplemented birds versus non-supplemented birds, measured in units of standard deviations. Thus, large differences and low variability generate the largest effect sizes [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" href="#CR69">69</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" href="#CR70">70</a>]. Positive 
  <span class="italic">d</span> values indicate that food supplementation has a positive effect on the reproduction of a study species, while negative values indicate greater values in controls compared to the experimental group. By convention, a large effect is indicated by |
  <span class="italic">d|</span> &gt; 0.8, a moderate effect by |
  <span class="italic">d|</span> = 0.2-0.8, and a small effect by |
  <span class="italic">d|</span> = 0-0.2 [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71" href="#CR71">71</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72" href="#CR72">72</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
