<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ancestral state reconstruction in honeyeaters and allies</div>
 <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The command ‘phylomorphospace’ in the R package phytools
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>
  </span> was used to generate the plot shown in the results, which contains phylogenetic information as well as nest shape information from the PCO. Three methods of ancestral state reconstruction of discrete characters available in phytools
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>
  </span> were used to explore the ancestral state of different traits in Supplementary Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S2</a>. To do this I run each method in a sample of 1000 trees from the posterior distribution of trees of the most recent phylogenetic analysis for Meliphagoidea
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
  </span>, and I report 95% HPD intervals for the probability of each state. The command 
  <span class="italic">fitER</span> was used to explore the evolution under a model that assumes equal transition rates between states. I also used the command 
  <span class="italic">fitARD</span> to fit a model where backward and forward rates can change. To complement this analysis I also used the command 
  <span class="italic">AncThresh</span> in phytools, which uses Bayesian MCMC to estimate ancestral states, and builds a threshold model that detects thresholds of change between states
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>
  </span>. For nest height (log
  <sub>10</sub> height + 0.1), a continuous character, I used the 
  <span class="italic">fastAnc</span> command in phytools
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>
  </span>, which uses maximum likelihood to calculate ancestral states. I report the 95% HPD interval of the ancestral nest height across 1000 trees in the most ancestral node. The phylogenetic signal (Pagel’s λ) is also reported for specific traits using the 
  <span class="italic">phylosig</span> command in phytools
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>
  </span> for continuous characters and 
  <span class="italic">fitDiscrete</span> in Geiger
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>
  </span> for discrete traits. Larger values of λ (closer to one) indicate that the phylogenetic signal is high, and closely related species are more likely to share similar trait values than unrelated species
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
</sec>
