<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Evolution of nest traits in honeyeaters and allies</div>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ordination within Meliphagoidea showed four clear clusters of nest types (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>). The first axis (x) separates nests that have an entrance on the top or on the side of the nest. This separation is equivalent to the broad categorization of ‘open’ and ‘domed’ nests, but is also related to the type of materials used in the nest, with nests on the left employing a broader set of materials (e.g. feathers) than nests on the right. The second axis (y) mainly separates nests that are either supported (that are attached to a surface) or suspended (those that hang from the rims of branches). This division is also related to the elongation of the nest, with nests that are supported being usually less deep (lower length/width ratio) than nests that are suspended.
  <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Nest phylomorphospace in Australian honeyeaters and allies. Principal coordinate analysis (PCO) of nest architecture across Superfamily Meliphagoidea using eight nest traits shown in Supplementary Table 
     <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S1</a> and the MCC tree. See animation of phylomorphospace in supplementary material.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_41948_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e662" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The GLMM models showed that temperature or radiation could not predict the characteristics of the nest. The second dimension of the nest ordination (whether a nest is suspended or supported, and the elongation of the nest) was related to the size of the species and the height of the nest (Table 
  <a rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" href="#Tab2">2</a>, Supplementary Material Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S4</a>). Nests that are elongated and suspended (Y-axis) are built by smaller species and are built higher up (Table 
  <a rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" href="#Tab2">2</a>, Supplementary material Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S4</a>). This last result is possibly driven by the fact that nests built in bushes (lower) are usually supported and not suspended. In general, larger species tend to build nests that are higher up from the ground (Supplementary Material Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S5</a>). However, this association was not statistically significant after phylogenetic control, probably because most large species in this dataset belong to the same family (Meliphagidae, Slope β = 0.176 to 0.223, P = 0.117 to 0.217).
  <div id="Tab2" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Results of GLMM models showing which variables can predict specific morphological nest traits of honeyeaters and allies (N = 191 species).</p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th>Model/Predictor</th>
      <th>Estimate</th>
      <th>Lower limit</th>
      <th>Upper limit</th>
      <th>P-mcmc</th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td colspan="5">
       <span class="bold">
        <span class="italic">log X axis ~ log (weight)</span>
       </span>
       <span class="bold"> + </span>
       <span class="bold">
        <span class="italic">log (height)</span>
       </span>
       <span class="bold"> + </span>
       <span class="bold">
        <span class="italic">PC1 environment</span>
       </span>
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>log (weight)</td>
      <td>0.02</td>
      <td>−0.002</td>
      <td>0.04</td>
      <td>0.07</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>log (height)</td>
      <td>0.006</td>
      <td>−0.006</td>
      <td>0.02</td>
      <td>0.31</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>PC1 environment</td>
      <td>0.001</td>
      <td>−0.002</td>
      <td>0.003</td>
      <td>0.50</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td colspan="5">
       <span class="bold">
        <span class="italic">Y axis ~ log (weight)</span>
       </span>
       <span class="bold"> + </span>
       <span class="bold">
        <span class="italic">log (height)</span>
       </span>
       <span class="bold"> + </span>
       <span class="bold">
        <span class="italic">PC1 environment</span>
       </span>
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>log (weight)</td>
      <td>−0.14</td>
      <td>−0.22</td>
      <td>−0.08</td>
      <td> &lt; 0.0001</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>log (height)</td>
      <td>0.05</td>
      <td>0.02</td>
      <td>0.09</td>
      <td>0.004</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>PC1 environment</td>
      <td>0.007</td>
      <td>−0.001</td>
      <td>0.02</td>
      <td>0.1</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
   <div class="table-wrap-foot">
    <p>Larger values of PCO 1 (X axis) are associated with open nests built with fewer materials. Larger values of PCO 2 (Y axis) are associated with suspended and elongated nests.</p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ancestral reconstruction of traits was qualitatively similar for the three methods employed, and revealed that the ancestral nest type for the Meliphagoidea was a domed nest, supported on a surface rather than suspended, likely to be of a globular shape, built with twigs, other plant material and feathers and between 0.87 and 0.95 m from the ground (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>, Supplementary Material Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S5</a>). However, the variable rates method (ARD) showed inconclusive results for the analysis of nest shape and nest material, so these results should be taken with caution. The analysis of phylogenetic signal shows that having supported vs. suspended nests and general nest structure (cup or domed) have a relatively high phylogenetic signal (λ = 0.93–0.97 and 0.92–0.95, respectively), compared to traits like nest height (λ = 0.82–0.87) or having shallow, globular or deep nests (λ = 0.76–0.86), which are more labile. The use of different materials had a highly variable phylogenetic signal depending on the tree (λ = 0.19–0.96, MCC tree λ = 0.88).
  <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Ancestral state reconstruction (using equal rates) of four nest traits in the superfamily Meliphagoidea. The ancestral nest type of the honeyeaters and allies was likely to be a supported nest (
     <span class="bold">a</span>), with a side entrance (
     <span class="bold">b</span>), with globular shape (
     <span class="bold">c</span>) and around 1 m above the ground (
     <span class="bold">d</span>). Circle around (
     <span class="bold">a</span>) represents families: Maluridae (blue), Pardalotidae and Dasyornithidae (purple), Acanthizidae (yellow), Meliphagidae (black).
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_41948_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e880" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
