<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Evolution of nest traits in honeyeaters and allies</div>
 <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To explore how particular traits of nest shape evolve in Australasian passerines from the superfamily Meliphagoidea, detailed information on nest variables for 191 species was extracted. This analysis included the families Meliphagidae, Maluridae, Acanthizidae, Dayornitidae and Pardalotidae, five of the 12 families with domed nests in Australia and 106 of the 277 species present in the previous analysis. This clade was chosen because it comprises more than 45% of the passerine avifauna in Australia
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
  </span>, it exhibits high variability in nesting habits, and because there is available information for a large percentage of species (68%). For this analysis I did not exclude cavity nesters such as pardalotes, because I was able to specify whether they built domed or open nests inside the cavities. I used the ‘Handbook of Birds of the World online’
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span> to extract information on the average nest height in metres (middle value from range reported or average value reported), and a set of parameters that describe the general structure of the nest (Supplementary Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S2</a>), such as general shape (elongated vertically or horizontally), number of materials used (e.g. only twigs vs. twigs and feathers), and type of attachment (suspended or supported). I performed a Principal Coordinate Analysis (PCO)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>
  </span> using the variables described in Supplementary Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S2</a>, since this is an ideal method to summarize continuous, ordinal and categorical variables. To do this, I first constructed a dissimilarity matrix of all variables with the daisy function in the 
  <span class="italic">cluster</span> R package, using the ‘Gower’ method of variable standardization
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
  </span>. Then, I used the matrix constructed with the function 
  <span class="italic">cmdscale</span> to obtain a set of coordinates for two dimensions, which describe the nest structure for each species in the data set. These two coordinates were used in posterior analyses (see statistical analyses).
 </p>
 <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To extract environmental variables from species in the Meliphagoidea I used the rgbif package
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>
  </span> to download 1000 records, and I extracted six bioclimatic variables for each location using the Worldclim database in the raster package
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>
  </span> (annual temperature, mean temperature of wettest quarter, mean temperature of warmest quarter, annual precipitation, precipitation of wettest quarter, precipitation of warmest quarter). I used a different methodology from the one described earlier for all Australian passerines because the Atlas of Living Australia does not have information for species outside Australia (and several species of the Meliphagoidea are found outside Australia). After extracting the six climatic variables, I generated an environmental PC that summarised 62% of the variation in climate.
 </p>
</sec>
