<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div id="F3" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
 <div class="caption">
  <p>
   <span class="bold">Principal component analysis of geographic barriers identified by the topographic ring model. A</span>: Density of all candidate barriers on the planet, with numbers corresponding to reference barriers known to promote ring speciation processes: (1) 
   <span class="italic">Ensatina</span>: Central Valley, California, USA; (2) 
   <span class="italic">Acacia</span>: Drakensberg Massif, South Africa; (3) 
   <span class="italic">Larus</span>: Makarov Basin, Arctic Ocean; (4) 
   <span class="italic">Phylloscopus</span>: Tibetan Plateau, Central Asia; (5) 
   <span class="italic">Phylloscopus</span>: Takla Maka and Gobi Deserts, Central Asia; (6) 
   <span class="italic">Larus</span>: Amundsen and Nansen Basins, Arctic Ocean; (7) 
   <span class="italic">Larus</span>: Canada Basin, Arctic Ocean. Darker red tones correspond to higher barrier density; whitespace identifies areas where barriers are undefined (that is, non-existent). 
   <span class="bold">B</span>: Vertical zoom on numbers 1 to 7 in A, showing in red the 100 closest cohesive candidate barriers (Euclidean distance) to the 
   <span class="italic">Ensatina </span>and 
   <span class="italic">Acacia </span>reference barriers (1 and 2), and the 1,380 cohesive candidate barriers identified for the bird taxa 
   <span class="italic">Larus </span>and 
   <span class="italic">Phylloscopus </span>and used to evaluate candidate composite barriers. Green points show the distribution of barriers where permeability as measured by fragmentation was less than the maximum possible. Lowercase letters show the locations of barriers evaluated in the discussion (b = Baja, c = Costa Rica, i = Iberian Peninsula, m = Madagascar, n = New Guinea). Black contours identify (from left to right) tiers of increasing density.
  </p>
 </div>
 <div xlink:href="1741-7007-10-20-3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</div>
