<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Implication for the long-term LW cloud feedback</div>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Obviously, the long-term cloud feedback cannot be observed now. However, there are some possibilities for the long-term cloud feedback mechanism associated to climate warming to be linked to the short-term feedback associated to present-day climate variations
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
  </span>. Under the assumption there is a relationship between simulated present day and transient scale variabilities, observed relationships between clouds and their controlling factors can be used to constrain long-term feedbacks from models. Given that the length of the CALIPSO record has a limited number of years, and relying on a recent study
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
  </span> which suggests that there maybe a relationship for some climate feedbacks between feedback strength at monthly and transient timescales, we estimated the short-term feedback from monthly mean data.
 </p>
 <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figure 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a> shows that the simulated long-term LW cloud feedback has the same sign as the simulated short-term feedback but with smaller amplitudes. It is consistent with the study of Zhou 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>
  </span>. The simulated short-term and long-term LW cloud feedbacks are both positive, and mainly due to the change in opaque cloud altitude, although partially compensated by the change in opaque cloud cover. The thin cloud properties do not play a significant role.
 </p>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The similarities between short-term and long-term simulated LW cloud feedbacks suggest there is a link between the two in the model world. Supposing such a link also exists in the real world, then comparison of the simulated and observed short-term LW cloud feedbacks can provide a constraint on the long-term LW cloud feedback. Results shown in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a> suggest that the long-term positive LW cloud altitude feedback mechanism —robustly reproduced by all climate models for nearly five decades— is not the dominant term, at least over the oceans. Uncertainty in amplitude of the positive LW cloud altitude feedback simulated by model is large
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span> and the basic cloud-rise mechanism may be complicated by factors such a possible decrease in tropical anvil coverage which tends to accompany the cloud rise according to a “stability-iris” mechanism
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When considering the total cloud feedback (LW + SW), the opaque cloud cover change feedback (which dominates the negative LW feedback over oceans) has likely less impact because its effect on longwave radiation partially compensates its positive feedback effect on the shortwave radiation.</p>
</sec>
