<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The habitat is characterized by high productivity owing to its upwelling system [
 <xref rid="pone.0220433.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Alongshore wind stress brings cool, nutrient-rich water to the surface [
 <xref rid="pone.0220433.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. In such upwelling systems, small pelagic reproduction has been found to depend mainly on two factors: retention of larvae and primary productivity. Both are influenced by wind conditions [
 <xref rid="pone.0220433.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0220433.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0220433.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. On the one hand, according to Thiaw et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0220433.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], the lagged spring and autumn upwelling indexes have a significant positive effect on 
 <italic>Sardinella aurita</italic> abundance, because they spur primary productivity. On the other hand, wind stress can influence retention negatively, because larvae drift off to areas where they cannot survive [
 <xref rid="pone.0220433.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0220433.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>]. Owing to the broad continental shelf in the main spawning area, retention is high in general [
 <xref rid="pone.0220433.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. We use the ERA Interim Reanalysis product, available from the European Centre for Medium-Range Weather Forecasts [
 <xref rid="pone.0220433.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>], to calculate a seasonal coastal upwelling index (CUI) from wind stress using standard procedures [
 <xref rid="pone.0220433.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>] (see Section B of the 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0220433.s001">S1 File</xref>). We average over the area between 13.5–16°N and 17.25–18°W. Our index shows the typical regional pattern: upwelling is strongest in winter, and subsides between June and October.
</p>
