<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par11" class="p">Our results emphasize the potential threat that hurricanes may become more intense in the future as they move toward the East Coast of the United States. This is mainly caused by a reduction of future vertical wind shear along the U.S. East Coast, which favors the intensification of hurricanes by less dispersion of latent heat energy, compared to the case of strong VWS. The weak vertical wind shear environment would help hurricanes reach their potential intensity, the maximum possible intensity given the environmental conditions, which has already increased in magnitude due to warmer sea surface temperatures. Furthermore, the modulation due to natural multidecadal climate variability in the North Atlantic, the AMV, may become less effective in the future as GHG forced changes become more dominant. In the recent past, AMV modulation dominated the VWS pattern, which favors a dipole structure with one node in the MDR region and another along the US East Coast with opposite sign anomalies. When VWS is weak in the MDR region, which favors more hurricane activity in the tropical North Atlantic, the VWS along the US East Coast is suppressed. This dipole pattern provides a natural barrier to strong hurricane occurrence and intensification along the East Coast. As shown in Kossin
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">17</xref>
 </sup>, the decades since the early 90s have seen suppressed hurricane intensification along the U.S. East Coast even when hurricane activity is heightened in the tropical Atlantic. Our results indicate that natural multidecadal variability, through the dipole mode modulating the vertical wind shear and the hurricane intensification rate, is largely responsible for the protective barrier of the recent East Coast hurricane activity. In the future, the role of the AMV modulation may diminish in comparison to the ever stronger anthropogenic GHG forcing. Thus the protective barrier of the AMV to the East Coast hurricane intensification may be largely eroded by the GHG effect. Coupled with the robust warming of the ocean surface temperature in the future, it is likely that the US East Coast will experience unprecedented hurricane intensification in the future, causing even greater threats to the coastal community. For the Gulf Coast, the future projected increase in VWS may make the region slightly less vulnerable to strong landfalling hurricanes, although the increase in potential intensity there may outweigh the VWS effect.
</p>
