<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Enhancing Potato Productivity Through Improved Photosynthetic Yield Potential</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Since the mid-1950s the increased application of pesticides, fertilizers and irrigation water as well as genetic improvement have mainly contributed to the enhanced yield of major food crops (
  <a rid="B93" ref-type="bibr" href="#B93">Murchie et al., 2009</a>). The slower yield increase of principal food crops since the last decade suggests that the yield enhancement due to increased use of agricultural inputs and improved cultivation practices has reached a maximum theoretical limit (
  <a rid="B144" ref-type="bibr" href="#B144">Zhu et al., 2008</a>, 
  <a rid="B145" ref-type="bibr" href="#B145">2010</a>). Consequently, the additional increase in the yield of major crops can only be expected through improving genetic yield potential that is, the crop yield that a plant can achieve per unit ground area under optimum growth conditions in the absence of biotic and abiotic stresses (
  <a rid="B145" ref-type="bibr" href="#B145">Zhu et al., 2010</a>; 
  <a rid="B99" ref-type="bibr" href="#B99">Ort et al., 2014</a>). The genetic gain in potato, particularly yield, has been low and is in need for improvement (
  <a rid="B66" ref-type="bibr" href="#B66">Jansky, 2009</a>; 
  <a rid="B56" ref-type="bibr" href="#B56">Hirsch et al., 2013</a>). The maximum potential yield is determined by a number of yield components associated with photosynthesis. They are (i) amount of incident solar radiation (ii) light interception efficiency, by which photosynthetic pigments intercept photosynthetically active radiation (PAR, 400–700 nm) (iii) photosynthetic efficiency, through which the intercepted light energy is converted to biomass (iv) partitioning efficiency, by which the biomass energy is partitioned into seeds/tubers also known as harvest index (
  <a rid="B84" ref-type="bibr" href="#B84">Long et al., 2006</a>; 
  <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">Amthor, 2007</a>; 
  <a rid="B144" ref-type="bibr" href="#B144">Zhu et al., 2008</a>, 
  <a rid="B145" ref-type="bibr" href="#B145">2010</a>). After 1960’s green revolution, the light interception efficiency and the energy partitioning efficiency have approached the plateau due to release of new cultivars and intensive use of agricultural inputs. Thus, further enhancement in yield potential can only be obtained by improving photosynthetic light conversion efficiency (
  <a rid="B99" ref-type="bibr" href="#B99">Ort et al., 2014</a>). This notion has been supported by recent studies, which revealed that improving photosynthetic efficiency significantly increases wheat and rye grain yield (
  <a rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27">Dahal et al., 2014b</a>), tobacco biomass (
  <a rid="B72" ref-type="bibr" href="#B72">Kromdijk et al., 2016</a>) and tobacco seed yield (
  <a rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25">Dahal and Vanlerberghe, 2018b</a>). Although photosynthesis is central to convert solar incident energy into biomass and crop yield, improving photosynthetic efficiency has received little research priority in enhancing crop yield (
  <a rid="B84" ref-type="bibr" href="#B84">Long et al., 2006</a>; 
  <a rid="B145" ref-type="bibr" href="#B145">Zhu et al., 2010</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The processes of solar incident energy conversion to plant biomass through C
  <sub>3</sub> photosynthesis and associated energy losses are illustrated in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">Figure 2</a>. Since about 51.3% of the total solar energy striking leaf surface is outside of the 400–700 nm range of PAR, photosynthetic pigments intercept only remaining 48.7% of the total solar incident energy. However, photosynthetic organisms reflect or transmit about 4.9% of total solar incident energy as they weakly absorb in the green region of visible spectrum. This leaves only 43.8% of the total solar energy available for absorption by chlorophylls in the leaf. Leaf chlorophylls absorb maximally in the blue and red regions of PAR with 400 and 700 nm wavelengths, respectively. The reaction centers in the Photosystem I (PSI) and PSII drive photochemistry with the energy level of red photons only. Consequently, the energy absorbed at blue photon needs to be converted to the lower energy level of red photons resulting in heat dissipation of 6.6% of the intercepted solar energy, leaving only about 37.2% of the initial solar energy (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">Figure 2</a>). The assimilation of one CO
  <sub>2</sub> molecule into carbohydrate by Calvin cycle requires 2NADPH and 3ATP molecules (
  <a rid="B144" ref-type="bibr" href="#B144">Zhu et al., 2008</a>). The absorption of four moles of photons by chlorophyll molecules will generate one molecule of NADPH through linear electron transport chain, which is coupled to translocation of six protons into the thylakoid lumen. The synthesis of 1ATP molecule require 4 protons. Thus, absorption of 8 moles of photons are required to generate 2NADPH and 3ATP molecules to assimilate one CO
  <sub>2</sub> molecule into carbohydrate. The eight moles of red photons contain 1388 kJ energy whereas one-sixth of a glucose molecule (1C carbohydrate unit), contains only 477 kJ energy (
  <a rid="B144" ref-type="bibr" href="#B144">Zhu et al., 2008</a>). Thus, the minimum energy loss between photons absorbed by reaction centers and photosynthetic linear electron transport chain to carbohydrate assimilation is, 1 – (477/1388), which represents a loss of 24.6% of the total incident solar energy, leaving about 12.6% of the total energy (
  <a rid="B144" ref-type="bibr" href="#B144">Zhu et al., 2008</a>). In C
  <sub>3</sub> plants, photorespiration and respiration result in the loss of fixed carbon causing 6.1 and 1.9% expense of total energy. Thus, it is estimated that out of the total incident solar energy striking the leaf surface only about 4.6% is conserved to plant biomass, suggesting a maximum theoretical energy conversion efficiency of 0.046 in C
  <sub>3</sub> plants (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">Figure 2</a>). This estimate, however, does not include energy consumed in N and S reduction which needs to be taken in to account as they also consume photosynthetically generated electrons (
  <a rid="B47" ref-type="bibr" href="#B47">Foyer and Noctor, 2002</a>).
 </p>
 <div id="F2" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">FIGURE 2</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>A simplified model for the processes involved in the conversion of solar incident energy to final plant biomass and associated energy losses. Out of 100% solar incident energy the C
    <sub>3</sub> photosynthetic organisms are capable of converting only 4.6% to final plant biomass, suggesting a maximum theoretical energy conversion efficiency of 0.046. Most portion of solar energy is lost resulting in considerable decrease in energy conversion efficiency between the solar energy and final plant biomass. Redrawn from 
    <a rid="B144" ref-type="bibr" href="#B144">Zhu et al. (2008</a>, 
    <a rid="B145" ref-type="bibr" href="#B145">2010</a>); and modified based on 
    <a rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26">Dahal et al. (2014a</a>,
    <a rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27">b</a>).
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="fpls-10-00563-g002" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Potato tuber is chiefly composed of photoassimilates mainly starch. Hence, an enhancement in tuber yield can be obtained through stimulation of photosynthetic carbon fixation and its translocation to underground stem. 
  <a rid="B121" ref-type="bibr" href="#B121">Slattery and Ort (2015)</a> have suggested an energy conversion efficiency between 0.028 and 0.041 for eight different C3 plants, with potato as the best with an energy conversion efficiency of 0.041. Since current energy conversion efficiency of potato is less than the maximal theoretical limit expected for C
  <sub>3</sub> plants (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">Figure 2</a>), there is a great potential to enhance potato tuber yield through improved photosynthetic efficiency. Potato cultivars exhibit a considerable difference in rates of photosynthesis, which can be used effectively in breeding new cultivars with a higher photosynthetic yield potential (
  <a rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19">Cieply, 1976</a>). These differences in rates of photosynthesis can be used as a physiological marker for screening potato germplasms for higher tuber yield potential. It should be, however, considered that the canopy level net CO
  <sub>2</sub> assimilation, duration of photosynthetic activity and transport of photoassimilates determines tuber size (
  <a rid="B48" ref-type="bibr" href="#B48">Frier, 1975</a>). Several studies suggest that increase in atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub> will stimulate photosynthetic yield potential. However, one should also note that the CO
  <sub>2</sub>-stimulation of rate of photosynthesis is substantially offset by higher than optimal temperature, drought and soil salinity. Thus, future breeding programs should focus on screening potato cultivars that have potential to maintain higher CO
  <sub>2</sub> assimilation rates under abiotic stress associated with global warming and climate change. Following section will discuss how elevated CO
  <sub>2</sub>, high temperature, drought and soil salinity impact on maximum potential yield with particular focus on potato and photosynthetic efficiency.
 </p>
</sec>
