<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">High Temperature</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As a cool weather crop potato grows well under moderate temperature in temperate regions. Temperature above the optimal is likely to inhibit plant growth and survival and hence causes reductions in tuber yield and productivity (
  <a rid="B80" ref-type="bibr" href="#B80">Levy and Veilleux, 2007</a>; 
  <a rid="B124" ref-type="bibr" href="#B124">Tang et al., 2018</a>). The susceptibility of potato crops to high temperature, however, largely depends on cultivars (
  <a rid="B124" ref-type="bibr" href="#B124">Tang et al., 2018</a>), growth stage and stress duration (
  <a rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2">Ahn et al., 2004</a>). The optimal temperature requirements for above ground plant growth and below ground tuber growth are different, the former perform well in the range of 20–25°C and the later in the range of 15–20°C (
  <a rid="B132" ref-type="bibr" href="#B132">Van Dam et al., 1996</a>). 
  <a rid="B112" ref-type="bibr" href="#B112">Rykaczewska (2015)</a> tested six potato cultivars to determine whether the temperature sensitivity of potato plant is growth stage dependent and revealed that the earlier high temperature stress occurs, the more negatively it impacts the plant growth and tuber yield. Temperature above 25°C has been found to delay tuberization. It has been predicted that potato yield will decline substantially by 2055 as a consequence of global warming and drought (
  <a rid="B58" ref-type="bibr" href="#B58">Holden et al., 2003</a>). In another study 
  <a rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" href="#B55">Hijmans (2003)</a> anticipates that world potato production will decline by 18–32% in the projected period of 2040–2069.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">High temperature negatively impacts tuber yield and quality through inhibition of carbon synthesis and its subsequent translocation to stolon (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Figure 1</a> and 
  <a rid="T1" ref-type="table" href="#T1">Table 1</a>). It has been suggested that the optimum temperature for photosynthesis and biomass accumulation in potato is about 20°C and an increment of every 5°C above the optimum may decrease photosynthetic rate by 25% (
  <a rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15">Burton, 1981</a>; 
  <a rid="B128" ref-type="bibr" href="#B128">Timlin et al., 2006</a>). In another study Burton reported that temperatures higher than 30°C cause a complete inhibition of the net photosynthesis in potato (
  <a rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14">Burton, 1972</a>). However, the response of potato plants to temperature varies across the cultivars, for instance, the commercial cultivar Russet Burbank exhibited maximum rates of photosynthesis at 24 to 30°C with photosynthetic reduction observed only at or above 35°C (
  <a rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35">Dwelle et al., 1981</a>). Similarly, although growth at 30/20°C day/night temperature reduced tuber yield, the high temperature stimulated the rates of photosynthesis (
  <a rid="B51" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51">Hancock et al., 2014</a>). High temperature-induced inhibition of rates of photosynthesis is associated with a reduction in RuBisCO activation state, irreversible photosystem II damage and increased rates of photorespiration in many plant species including wheat, rye and canola (
  <a rid="B83" ref-type="bibr" href="#B83">Long et al., 2004</a>; 
  <a rid="B114" ref-type="bibr" href="#B114">Salvucci and Crafts-Brandner, 2004</a>; 
  <a rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4">Ainsworth and Rogers, 2007</a>; 
  <a rid="B73" ref-type="bibr" href="#B73">Kumar et al., 2009</a>; 
  <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">Dahal et al., 2012</a>). In potato, although few studies suggest that high temperature inhibits PSII activity (
  <a rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" href="#B54">Havaux, 1993</a>), its effect on RuBisCO activity and photorespiration is still not known. Additionally, heat stress has been suggested to inhibit tuberization and tuber yield through change in assimilate partitioning and impaired sucrose translocation to tubers (
  <a rid="T1" ref-type="table" href="#T1">Table 1</a>). The delayed tuberization is associated with high temperature-induced inhibition of tuberization signal (
  <a rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38">Ewing, 1981</a>), which is thought to be an ortholog of the Arabidopsis protein FLOWERING LOCUS T (FT) known as StSP6A (
  <a rid="B94" ref-type="bibr" href="#B94">Navarro et al., 2011</a>). High temperature decreases harvest index and thus, tuber weight by inhibiting the carbon export to the sink organs (tubers) from the source leaf. The assimilated carbon is accumulated to source leaves or diverted to other leaves as indicated by increased leaf dry matter (
  <a rid="B51" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51">Hancock et al., 2014</a>). It has been reported that the accumulation of carbon in the source leaves has multiple consequences including feedback limitation of photosynthesis.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">High temperature negatively impacts tuber quality such as, hollow heart, tuber cracking, secondary growth, malformations. Heat stress stimulates conversion of starch to reducing sugars that triggers dark French fries (
  <a rid="B90" ref-type="bibr" href="#B90">Minhas, 2012</a>; 
  <a rid="B137" ref-type="bibr" href="#B137">Wang-Pruski and Schofield, 2012</a>). High temperature induces heat necrosis in the tuber flesh deteriorating fresh market and processing quality. Moreover, high temperature triggers skin russeting (
  <a rid="B137" ref-type="bibr" href="#B137">Wang-Pruski and Schofield, 2012</a>) chain and misshapen tubers, field sprouting and decreased dry matter content in response to high soil temperature.
 </p>
</sec>
