<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Global climate change poses a major challenge to sustainable crop production. Global climate change has affected weather patterns resulting in extremes of heat, drought, frequent frost and snow fall in high altitudes (
  <a rid="B62" ref-type="bibr" href="#B62">IPCC, 2014</a>). The sub-optimal growth conditions associated with global warming and climate change negatively impact plant growth, survival and crop yield (
  <a rid="B77" ref-type="bibr" href="#B77">Lesk et al., 2016</a>). Such negative impact on plant performance and crop yield is likely to be aggravated in future because continued greenhouse gas emissions will intensify crop plant’s exposure to abiotic and biotic stresses (
  <a rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31">DeLucia et al., 2012</a>; 
  <a rid="B62" ref-type="bibr" href="#B62">IPCC, 2014</a>). Climate scientists have projected that the current ambient CO
  <sub>2</sub> concentration of 380 ppm will double to ca. 700 ppm by the end of the 21st century (
  <a rid="B61" ref-type="bibr" href="#B61">IPCC, 2007</a>), which is likely to be coupled with a rise in the global air temperature by 0.3 to 4.8°C (
  <a rid="B62" ref-type="bibr" href="#B62">IPCC, 2014</a>). The predicted increase in the atmospheric temperature may increase the evapo-transpiration water loss causing soil water limitation and agricultural drought (
  <a rid="B53" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53">Hatfield et al., 2011</a>; 
  <a rid="B133" ref-type="bibr" href="#B133">Vandegeer et al., 2012</a>). Climate change is also predicted to increase soil salinity particularly in the coastal regions through sea level rise and salt water intrusion (
  <a rid="B108" ref-type="bibr" href="#B108">Rahmstorf, 2007</a>; 
  <a rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29">Dasgupta et al., 2009</a>). Recent study suggests that the geographical distributions of pest and pathogens, and their interactions with plant hosts, including changes in host susceptibility, will be affected by changing climate (
  <a rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36">Elad and Pertot, 2014</a>). Thus, while the anticipated increase in the atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub> level may enhance yield potential in certain crop species (
  <a rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32">Deryng et al., 2016</a>) the yield losses due to high temperature and water deficit may surpass the benefit achieved by any increase in CO
  <sub>2</sub> (
  <a rid="B82" ref-type="bibr" href="#B82">Lobell and Gourdji, 2012</a>). Moreover, the sub-optimal growth conditions are occurring at a time of predicted 30% increase in the world population by 2050 (
  <a rid="B131" ref-type="bibr" href="#B131">United Nations Department of Economic and Social Affairs, 2011</a>). This has created a global challenge concerning food security, which urges that the yield of major food crops needs to be increased two-fold over the next 50 years to fulfill the nutritional requirements of the increasing population (
  <a rid="B93" ref-type="bibr" href="#B93">Murchie et al., 2009</a>). The projected increase in food demand is further complicated by decrease in the total area of agricultural land due to desertification and urbanization, and increase in the food grain demand for animal nutrition and biofuel generation (
  <a rid="B93" ref-type="bibr" href="#B93">Murchie et al., 2009</a>; 
  <a rid="B145" ref-type="bibr" href="#B145">Zhu et al., 2010</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The global potato production is estimated to be 382 million tons in 2014 ranking first highest produced non-cereal food crop and the fourth highest produced crop worldwide after wheat, corn and rice (
  <a rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39">FAOSTAT, 2017</a>). Potato is cultivated in over 100 countries feeding over a billion people worldwide. It is a rich source of carbohydrates and provides other essential nutrients, such as dietary fiber, vitamins, minerals, protein and antioxidants (
  <a rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10">Bach et al., 2012</a>). Hence, enhancing potato crop productivity can contribute to fulfill the nutritional requirements of the rising population (
  <a rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12">Birch et al., 2012</a>). Potato is mainly grown for its tubers. Synthesis of carbohydrates through photosynthesis in the source leaves, translocation of photosynthetic end product, sucrose, to the stolon and conversion of sucrose to starch in the stolon are key physiological process for potato tuber initiation and growth (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Figure 1</a>). The effective coordination among these processes determines tuber productivity and quality. During photosynthesis, photosynthetic electron transport chain generates ATP and NADPH, which are then consumed by Calvin cycle to assimilate CO
  <sub>2</sub> to carbohydrates (
  <a rid="B122" ref-type="bibr" href="#B122">Stitt et al., 2010</a>; 
  <a rid="B109" ref-type="bibr" href="#B109">Rochaix, 2011</a>; 
  <a rid="B46" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46">Foyer et al., 2012</a>). The photosynthetic end product, sucrose, is then translocated into the underground stem via phloem loading and converted into starch (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Figure 1</a>). Any stresses that have negative effects on these processes may substantially inhibit tuberization and tuber growth resulting in lower tuber yield and quality. Since the potato tuber is chiefly composed of photoassimilates, mainly starch, an increase in tuber yield can be expected through stimulation of photosynthetic CO
  <sub>2</sub> assimilation and translocation of the photosynthetic end product to the underground stem. Major abiotic stresses namely, high temperature, drought, soil salinity and nutrient stresses adversely affect these processes and substantially curtail plant growth, tuberization, tuber bulking, and hence tuber yield and quality (
  <a rid="B90" ref-type="bibr" href="#B90">Minhas, 2012</a>; 
  <a rid="B137" ref-type="bibr" href="#B137">Wang-Pruski and Schofield, 2012</a>). The magnitude of yield loss due to these stresses, however, depends on the duration, severity and plant growth stage (
  <a rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37">Evers et al., 2010</a>). Early stress is most detrimental to tuberization, bulking and tuber yield as a result of reduced rates of carbon assimilation and decreased partitioning of assimilates to tubers (
  <a rid="B96" ref-type="bibr" href="#B96">Obidiegwu et al., 2015</a>). It has been predicted that potato yield will decline substantially by 2055 due to global warming and drought (
  <a rid="B58" ref-type="bibr" href="#B58">Holden et al., 2003</a>). In another study 
  <a rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" href="#B55">Hijmans (2003)</a> anticipates that world potato production will decline by 18–32% in the projected period of 2040–2069 as a consequence of biotic and abiotic stresses associated with climate change. Thus, in order to improve potato yield, we need to identify best production practices and develop new potato cultivars that best fit in the predicted climate change. Yet the lack of data on the precise mechanisms of plant resistance to abiotic stress and the subsequent ability to predict future outcomes constitute a major knowledge gap. This review paper first describes processes of enhancing crop yield through improved energy conversion efficiency into biomass and crop yield followed by some important abiotic stresses impacting this efficiency. The main focus will be on how these abiotic factors impact potato growth, development and yield, and possible adaptation strategies to combat these stresses.
 </p>
 <div id="F1" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">FIGURE 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>A schematic diagram illustrating the photosynthetic carbon assimilation and its export to the potato tuber sink. In the chloroplast, light harvesting complexes absorb sunlight and generate ATP and NADPH through photosynthetic electron transport chain. The ATP and NADPH are then consumed by Calvin cycle to assimilate carbon to simple carbohydrate, triose phosphates (triose-P). Triose-P is either used to synthesize starch in the chloroplast or exported to cytosol in exchange for Pi through triose-P/P
    <sub>i</sub> translocator. In the cytosol, the triose-P is then converted to sucrose via hexose phosphates using key sucrose biosynthetic enzymes, cFBpase and SPS. Sucrose is then transported to the sink (tuber), where it is converted to starch by AGPase. The synthesis of sucrose in the cytosol generates P
    <sub>i</sub> which is exported to the chloroplast in the exchange for triose-P. Any stress that inhibit sucrose synthesis and its transport to sink (tuber) results in the feedback inhibition of photosynthesis due to P
    <sub>i</sub> regeneration limitation. The broken arrows indicate the stress sensitive processes. RuBisCO, ribulose-1,5-bisphosphate carboxylase/oxygenase; RuBP, ribulose-1,5-bisphosphate; TPT, triose phosphate translocator; cFBPase, cytosolic fructose bisphosphatase; SPS, sucrose phosphate synthase, AGPase: ADP glucose pyrophosphorylase. Modified from 
    <a rid="B59" ref-type="bibr" href="#B59">Hüner et al. (2016)</a>.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="fpls-10-00563-g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
