<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-ijerph-16-02398" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1. Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Creating and sustaining wildfire smoke-resilient communities is an urgent public health priority, and one that is of high concern for Washington state agencies involved in wildfire smoke risk reduction.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the past several years, the western part of the United States has experienced extensive and damaging wildfire seasons [
  <a rid="B1-ijerph-16-02398" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-ijerph-16-02398">1</a>]. Instances of wildfires burning in locations previously thought of as low-risk, and significant smoke permeating dense urban areas, have been a wakeup call to communities with little or no experience dealing with wildfires and/or extended exposure to wildfire smoke. In Washington state, the past two summers have been particularly impactful on urban residents not used to summertime burns. In 2017, fires in Western Washington resulted in moderate to unhealthy air quality for over 2 weeks, while Eastern Washington experienced 15 days with a range of poor air from “unhealthy for sensitive groups” up to “very unhealthy for all” [
  <a rid="B2-ijerph-16-02398" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-ijerph-16-02398">2</a>]. At the same time, the state experienced higher than average summertime temperatures. The combination of smoke and high heat presented a unique challenge for densely populated urban areas in Western Washington, where air conditioning is limited in many residential and commercial buildings. In 2018, smoke returned to dominate the normally enjoyable August weather, impacting summertime activities and ushering in news coverage like “Air quality around the Seattle region varied from unhealthy to very unhealthy on Wednesday, with index readings far worse than those at the same time in Bejing [sic], China, infamous for its polluted skies” [
  <a rid="B3-ijerph-16-02398" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3-ijerph-16-02398">3</a>]. By the end of the summer, Washington state residents had experienced 42 days where at least 1 federal air monitor had measured PM2.5 in the 
  <span class="italic">unhealthy for sensitive groups</span> or worse air quality categories [
  <a rid="B2-ijerph-16-02398" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-ijerph-16-02398">2</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There is growing evidence suggesting that wildfire smoke poses a serious public health threat. Wildfire smoke has been shown to be associated with respiratory morbidity and all-cause mortality [
  <a rid="B4-ijerph-16-02398" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-ijerph-16-02398">4</a>,
  <a rid="B5-ijerph-16-02398" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-ijerph-16-02398">5</a>,
  <a rid="B6-ijerph-16-02398" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6-ijerph-16-02398">6</a>]. Mixed evidence has pointed to a possible association with cardiovascular health impacts [
  <a rid="B4-ijerph-16-02398" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-ijerph-16-02398">4</a>,
  <a rid="B5-ijerph-16-02398" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-ijerph-16-02398">5</a>,
  <a rid="B6-ijerph-16-02398" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6-ijerph-16-02398">6</a>]. Yet, uncertainties remain. For instance, the need for research in wider geographical areas over longer periods of time to further understand adverse health outcome risks and sensitive groups, as well as identify social and contextual determinants of the exposure–health outcome relationship, has been discussed [
  <a rid="B6-ijerph-16-02398" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6-ijerph-16-02398">6</a>]. Amidst widespread exposure, public health practitioners and others serving impacted communities are grappling with assessing, communicating, and managing risk with insufficient evidence.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The risks of wildfire smoke are compounded by strong evidence that climate change is bringing more and bigger wildfires to Washington state and the greater western United States (e.g., [
  <a rid="B7-ijerph-16-02398" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-ijerph-16-02398">7</a>,
  <a rid="B8-ijerph-16-02398" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8-ijerph-16-02398">8</a>,
  <a rid="B9-ijerph-16-02398" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9-ijerph-16-02398">9</a>,
  <a rid="B10-ijerph-16-02398" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10-ijerph-16-02398">10</a>]). Human-caused climate change is estimated to have led to an additional 4.2 million hectares of area burned between 1984–2015 across the western U.S.; this is nearly double the area burned expected in the absence of human-caused climate change [
  <a rid="B7-ijerph-16-02398" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-ijerph-16-02398">7</a>]. Climate change is also leading to increased frequency, duration, and intensity of wildfires [
  <a rid="B11-ijerph-16-02398" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-ijerph-16-02398">11</a>,
  <a rid="B12-ijerph-16-02398" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12-ijerph-16-02398">12</a>,
  <a rid="B13-ijerph-16-02398" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13-ijerph-16-02398">13</a>,
  <a rid="B14-ijerph-16-02398" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14-ijerph-16-02398">14</a>], and longer regional fire seasons [
  <a rid="B8-ijerph-16-02398" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8-ijerph-16-02398">8</a>,
  <a rid="B10-ijerph-16-02398" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10-ijerph-16-02398">10</a>,
  <a rid="B11-ijerph-16-02398" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-ijerph-16-02398">11</a>]. Further, future projections of wildfire in the Northwest suggest that the area burned by wildfires by the 2080s could more than double relative to 1916–2006 (under a medium emissions scenario) [
  <a rid="B9-ijerph-16-02398" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9-ijerph-16-02398">9</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As climate change alters the pattern of wildfires across the Northwest, the implications for the extent and presence of wildfire smoke remain an active area of research for public health and climate researchers alike. Following two summers of intense wildfire smoke across Washington state, it is clear that there is the need for more research on wildfire smoke risk, future wildfire smoke extent and duration, and the human health implications of wildfire smoke. There is also a need for greater coordination between researcher and practitioner communities in order to develop and deploy adaptations, solutions, and preventative actions that minimize the risks associated with wildfire and wildfire smoke in a changing climate.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In an effort to respond to these needs and to engage regional stakeholders in dialogue around the risks and responses to wildfire smoke, the Wildfire Smoke Risk Communication Stakeholder Synthesis Symposium was held in Seattle, Washington on 30 October 2018. The goals of the symposium were to identify and prioritize practice-based information gaps necessary to: Promote effective wildfire smoke risk communication and risk reduction across Washington state; foster collaboration among practitioners and academics to address information gaps using research; and provide regional stakeholders with access to the best available climate science about current and future wildfire risks.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here, we present the information gaps and research priorities identified during this interactive workshop in order to guide the development of a practitioner-relevant research agenda, with the ultimate goal of helping Washington state communities, agencies, researchers, and practitioners reduce community-wide risks from exposure to wildfire smoke.</p>
</sec>
