<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We used daily precipitation and temperature data from randomly selected years from 1981 to 2010, from the Parameter‐elevation Relationships on Independent Slopes Model (PRISM; PRISM Climate Group, Oregon State University 
 <xref rid="eap1979-bib-0047" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>) to run model spin‐up. Future climate projections were based on four global circulation models (GCMs) that were selected based on their correlation with historical climate data and their representation of climate extremes in the future. To do this, we calculated correlation coefficients of monthly PRISM vs. modeled historical (1981–2005) data from each GCM using four climate variables that previous studies have found to be important to ponderosa pine growth and recruitment (Feddema et al. 
 <xref rid="eap1979-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>, Kolb et al. 
 <xref rid="eap1979-bib-0029" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>, Petrie et al. 
 <xref rid="eap1979-bib-0044" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>, 
 <xref rid="eap1979-bib-0045" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>): winter precipitation, summer average temperature, spring average temperature, and summer relative humidity. Using those same four climate variables plus annual precipitation, we also calculated the difference between the averages from 1981 to 1999 and 2081 to 2099. We then choose four GCMs based on those that were highly correlated with the historical period and fell into each of these categories: below and above average increases in modeled temperature and below and above average changes in modeled precipitation. Chosen GCMs were INMCM4 (warm/dry), BCC‐CSM1‐1 (warmer/wetter), IPSL CM5A LR (hot/drier), MIROC ESM CHEM (hotter/wet) and were obtained from Multivariate Adaptive Constructed Analogs data sets (Appendix 
 <xref rid="eap1979-sup-0004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref>: Figs. S1, S2; Abatzoglou and Brown 
 <xref rid="eap1979-bib-0001" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>). RCP 8.5 models were used in all cases. Monthly precipitation (mm), maximum temperature (°C), minimum temperature (°C), and the standard deviation of each of those variables were input into the NECN succession extension. Daily precipitation (mm), average temperature (°C), wind speed (km/h), wind direction (degrees), and relative humidity (%) were used to calculate a fire weather index, fine fuel moisture code, and build‐up index for use in the Dynamic Fire extension. Wind speed and wind direction were not expected to change with future climate change (Eichelberger et al. 
 <xref rid="eap1979-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>), so historical daily wind direction and wind speed (Western Regional Climate Center 
 <xref rid="eap1979-bib-0068" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>) were randomized and used for future climates. Future fire weather was input as different files for each decade so that fire weather would change into the future by decade.
</p>
