<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Climate change, through the combined effects of temperature and sea level rise, is expected to affect contaminant removal in the STA in the Northeastern United States. Sea level rise will reduce the volume of unsaturated soil available for wastewater treatment in coastal areas. The sea level in the Northeastern U.S. is projected to rise 90–120 cm by 2100 [
 <xref rid="pone.0162104.ref009" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>], resulting in higher water tables in coastal regions as denser saltwater displaces lighter freshwater. The effect of sea level rise on water table elevation will diminish with distance from the coast, affect areas with shallow water tables, and depend on the hydrology of the region. A USGS study of Cape Cod found median water table elevation to increase 19–63 cm for modeled sea level elevations between 60 and 180 cm, with 30 cm or greater elevations occurring within approximately 10 km of the coast [
 <xref rid="pone.0162104.ref010" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. Furthermore, precipitation events are expected to increase in number and severity over the same time period [
 <xref rid="pone.0162104.ref009" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. The effects of greater evapotranspiration experienced during warmer temperature [
 <xref rid="pone.0162104.ref011" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>] is likely to mitigate and often exceed increased precipitation rates on an annual basis, however, at shorter temporal and smaller spatial scales, precipitation may be very large when there is little evapotranspiration. Higher groundwater tables will result in a wetter conditions that enhance the survival and transport of bacterial and viral pathogens [
 <xref rid="pone.0162104.ref012" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0162104.ref013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. Wetter soils may also result in microbial metal reduction, leading to lower P removal capacity and increased mobilization of P retained on soil particles [
 <xref rid="pone.0162104.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. In contrast, removal of N by microbial reduction to N
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> may be enhanced by diminished O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> diffusion in wetter soils [
 <xref rid="pone.0162104.ref015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>]. Finally, decomposition of organic carbon may be hindered or enhanced by increased soil moisture [
 <xref rid="pone.0162104.ref016" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>], which will affect BOD
 <sub class="sub">5</sub> removal. Because 40% of the U.S. population resides in coastal communities [
 <xref rid="pone.0162104.ref017" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>], sea level rise will likely impact coastal communities that rely on OWTS for wastewater renovation.
</p>
