<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par13" class="p">Modern forest composition was quantified using the Québec government’s forest inventories since 1980. These inventories are based on 400 m
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> circular plots distributed across different types of productive forest through stratified random sampling (Supplementary Figure 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">1</xref>). Only plots that were located within a maximum distance of 3 km from historical observations were retained, resulting in a total of 59,359 plots. The vast majority of plots have been continuously forested during the last century, with &lt;1% of plots having developed on abandoned farmlands. Within these plots, all stems &gt;9 cm diameter at breast height of each species were measured and inventoried and were used to compute species basal area per plot. Surveyors of the nineteenth century did not systematically distinguish all phylogenetically close species and thus several species had to be grouped at the genus level to match the taxa that were recorded by historical surveyors (
 <italic class="italic">Picea</italic> spp., 
 <italic class="italic">Pinus</italic> spp., 
 <italic class="italic">Acer</italic> spp., 
 <italic class="italic">Populus</italic> spp.). Because the nineteenth-century surveyors only specified the most abundant taxa in their observations, we also controlled the number of taxa per modern plot in order to obtain more comparable datasets. Taxa that represented &lt;5% of the total basal area of a modern plot were removed; this threshold was chosen to obtain roughly the same number of taxa per observation in both historical and modern datasets (Supplementary Figure 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">1</xref>). Modern taxa frequencies were finally aggregated to the 25 km
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> grid by calculating number of plots where a taxon is present divided by the number of plots in the corresponding grid cell (Supplementary Figure 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">2</xref>).
</p>
