<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The regulation of life cycles of temperate insects is typically due to plasticity in relation to seasonal cues such as photoperiod and temperature (Tauber et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" class="xref">1986</xref>; Nylin and Gotthard 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" class="xref">1998</xref>). Given the patterns shown here, it seems likely that the part of the life cycle determining adult emergence of 
 <italic class="italic">A. cardamines</italic> in the spring is highly dependent on temperature. As this species spends the overwinter period in the pupal stage, it is the post-diapause pupal development in spring that will determine when the adults hatch. Hence, variation in adult emergence is likely to be strongly affected by the thermal reaction norms of pupal development. The advancement of spring phenology during the last decades as well as the latitudinal variation is likely to be largely a consequence of plasticity in response to variation in temperature (Gienapp et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">2008</xref>; Merilä and Hendry 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">2014</xref>). However, thermal reaction norms have a genetic basis and may evolve in response to environmental changes. Indeed, recent experimental studies demonstrate that thermal reaction norms of post-diapause development in 
 <italic class="italic">A. cardamines</italic> varies among populations from different latitudes suggesting that a part of the spatial variation in phenology seen here is due to local adaptation in these thermal reaction norms (Posledovich et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">2014</xref>; Ståhandske et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" class="xref">2014</xref>). This also indicates that natural selection due to consistent directional change in climatic conditions over time will alter adaptations that are central for the evolution of phenology. From a climate change perspective, such evidence of local adaptation in thermal reaction norms suggests that responses to similar changes in temperatures will differ between regions along latitudinal gradients.
</p>
