<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">While our survey captured valuable information that can be used by public health practitioners in NYC and beyond, several limitations should be noted, some of which also applied to the 2011 survey [
 <xref rid="B14-ijerph-15-01433" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. While every effort was made to achieve a high response rate in this study, including using a highly trained survey interview staff, callbacks on different days and at different hours, and attempted refusal conversions of soft refusals by trained refusal conversion specialists, we achieved a response rate of 22%. It should be noted that this is well above the current standard of approximately 9% in RDD telephone studies and there is no indication of nonresponse bias [
 <xref rid="B37-ijerph-15-01433" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>]. We used closed-ended survey questions, which may miss responses not included as options or overly simplify complex reasons for behaviors. Additionally, interpretation of questions may have varied by respondents. Due to funding constraints that limited the number of survey questions, we were unable to ask about residential building conditions that could affect participants’ ability to stay cool (other than AC ownership). It is now a necessity to use a dual-frame survey of landline and cell phone numbers for telephone surveys [
 <xref rid="B38-ijerph-15-01433" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>]; however, a 30% cell sample may underrepresent some segments of the population. Finally, although our survey sample size was sufficiently large to estimate prevalence, it may have been too small to test for statistical differences between subgroups in some cases. In particular, the size of the sample which chose to complete the survey in Spanish was small and we note that conducting a survey in only two languages in NYC may have limited participation. Future research should explore the relationship between language and heat vulnerability in more detail, as well as among more subsets of race and ethnicity categories.
</p>
