<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec13" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Global sea-level projections</div>
 <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To project future sea-level rise, we apply a component-based global sea-level model
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span>, which includes an updated parameterization of the Antarctic ice sheet response based on refs. 
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>,]
  </span>. For thermal expansion, glaciers and the Greenland surface mass balance, the model combines the long-term sensitivity
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span> of each component to global-mean temperature warming with the individual recent observations. Future evolution is thus constrained to both long-term sensitivity and past observations. For the three components, we use a pursuit curve approach, in which the difference between long-term sensitivity 
  <span class="italic">S</span>
  <sub>eq</sub>(
  <span class="italic">T</span>,
  <span class="italic">α</span>) and the time-dependent contribution 
  <span class="italic">S</span>(
  <span class="italic">t</span>) drives the rate of sea-level rise for each component:
  <div id="Equ1" class="disp-formula">
   <span class="label">1</span>
   <div class="alternatives">
    <span id="M1" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$\frac{{{\rm d}S}}{{{\rm d}t}} = \frac{{S_{{\rm eq}}\left( {T\left( t \right),\alpha } \right) - S\left( t \right)}}{\tau }.$$\end{document}</span>
    <div id="M2" display="block" class="math">
     <div class="mfrac">
      <div class="mrow">
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">d</span>
       <span class="mi">S</span>
      </div>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">d</span>
       <span class="mi">t</span>
      </div>
     </div>
     <span class="mo">=</span>
     <div class="mfrac">
      <div class="mrow">
       <div class="msub">
        <div class="mrow">
         <span class="mi">S</span>
        </div>
        <div class="mrow">
         <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">e</span>
         <span class="mi">q</span>
        </div>
       </div>
       <div close=")" open="(" separators="" class="mfenced">
        <div class="mrow">
         <span class="mi">T</span>
         <div close=")" open="(" separators="" class="mfenced">
          <div class="mrow">
           <span class="mi">t</span>
          </div>
         </div>
         <span class="mo">,</span>
         <span class="mi">α</span>
        </div>
       </div>
       <span class="mo">-</span>
       <span class="mi">S</span>
       <div close=")" open="(" separators="" class="mfenced">
        <div class="mrow">
         <span class="mi">t</span>
        </div>
       </div>
      </div>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mi">τ</span>
      </div>
     </div>
     <span class="mo">.</span>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="41467_2018_2985_Article_Equ1.gif" position="anchor" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </div>The sensitivity parameter α is determined from equilibrium simulations for each component, with uncertainty in the long-term sensitivity covered by variation of the parameter. 
  <span class="italic">S</span>
  <sub>eq</sub>(
  <span class="italic">T</span>,
  <span class="italic">α</span>) has different functional forms for the different components. The response time 
  <span class="italic">τ</span> is calibrated to observations for each component, with the range of 
  <span class="italic">τ</span> reflecting the uncertainty in observations.
 </p>
 <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We use a response-function approach
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>
  </span> for the Greenland solid ice discharge due to missing long-term sensitivity estimates or past trends in observations. This assumes that frontal stress release
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
  </span> and runoff lubrication
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>
  </span> can be approximated as linearly depending on the global-mean temperature anomaly (ref. 
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span>, equation 4). Both Greenland surface mass balance and solid ice loss are calibrated to new observations
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>
  </span>. To cover the recently proposed increased sensitivity of the Antarctic ice sheet to global warming
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
  </span>, we update our method to capture the corresponding Antarctic sea-level contribution. We utilize a parametrization that combines a slow and gradual response to global warming with a fast discharge term that mimics ice instability
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>
  </span>. The parametrization has four free parameters that include a threshold temperature and a rate for fast discharge. Fast discharge contributes to sea-level rise once the threshold temperature is passed. We create a 29-member ensemble of the four-parameter set by calibrating our parametrization to the response of each ensemble member available from ref. 
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
  </span> for the RCP2.6, RCP4.5, and RCP8.5 scenarios simultaneously.
 </p>
 <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The long response times of ice sheets, glaciers and ocean make it probable that a fraction of their contribution originates from their ongoing adaptation to past climate change, i.e., the little or the last ice age
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>
  </span>. Only for glaciers we are able to explicitly incorporate such a natural fraction, which is declining and below 30% at present
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>
  </span>. We do not include changes in land water storage as climate mainly influences its decadal variability
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>
  </span> and not its long-term trend. Direct human influence on land water storage through groundwater pumping
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>
  </span> and dam building
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span> cannot be linked to global climate change and would thus unnecessarily blur our analysis.
 </p>
 <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our aggregate uncertainty estimates are based on Monte-Carlo sampling: for each sea-level contribution, we draw from the calibrated sets of sea-level functions, which incorporate the different observational datasets and long-term estimates, and from the 29 calibrated parameter sets of the Antarctic component. We drive the selected sea-level functions with a global-mean temperature pathway, randomly drawn from the 600 member global-mean temperature ensemble for a specific scenario. The sampling is repeated 10000 times.</p>
</sec>
