<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece34829-sec-0005" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data resampling and environmental covariates</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We nested the 377 1‐km transects, considering them as spatial observations replicated within the site, which are necessary for estimating detection probability. Sites are defined as grid cells that together cover the whole study area. This composition of sites along with environmental covariates is useful for estimating site‐level occupancy (Sadoti et al., 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0048" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0048">2013</a>). Since the resolution of the cells (sampling unit of the site) might vary depending on the spatial scale and species being studied, two potential aggregation schemes were chosen, with different grid cell sizes, an aggregation scheme with a grid size of 60 × 60 and 90 × 90 s, (AS2x2 and AS3x3, respectively). Based on the species of bird community (most of them passerines with small home ranges; Rechetelo, Grice, Reside, Hardesty, &amp; Moloney, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0045" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0045">2016</a>), both sizes of grid cell may be suitable for evaluating the effects of environmental covariates on bird species occupancy at regional scale (Kéry et al., 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0025">2013</a>; Lipsey et al., 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0031">2017</a>). The aggregation scheme AS2x2 grouped from 1 to 5 transects per site, giving a total of 246 cell sites with observations (Figure 
  <a rid="ece34829-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#ece34829-fig-0002">2</a>a,c). The aggregation scheme AS3x3 grouped from 1 to 7 transects per site, giving a total of 185 cell sites with data in the region of Murcia (Figure 
  <a rid="ece34829-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#ece34829-fig-0002">2</a>b,d).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The percentage of forest cover (FOREST) was estimated from the CORINE Land Cover 1990 map (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://centrodedescargas.cnig.es" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://centrodedescargas.cnig.es</span>), using data from 0% to 100% (mean = 28.51%). Climate variables were the annual mean temperature (TEMP) and the annual precipitation (PREC) obtained from the average monthly climate data of temperature and precipitation for the period 1960–1990, which were downloaded from the global dataset WorldClim version 1.4 (Hijmans, Cameron, Parra, Jones, &amp; Jarvis, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0020">2005</a>; 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.worldclim.org/version1" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.worldclim.org/version1</span>). The annual mean temperature ranged from 10.9°C to 18.3°C and from 10.72°C to 18.13°C for AS2x2 and AS3x3, respectively. The annual precipitation ranged from 275 to 580 mm and from 274.1 to 596.0 mm for AS2x2 and AS3x3, respectively. GIS analyses were carried out with the 
  <span class="italic">raster</span> package (Hijmans, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0019">2016</a>) in R 3.3.2 (R Core Team, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0044" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0044">2016</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
