<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece34829-sec-0009" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">DISCUSSION</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study offers a new look at the use of historical data by means of considering them as spatial replicates that are nested within a site, and develops community occupancy models. This approach can be extrapolated to other species and areas, where valuable data from historical bird surveys can be used (Tingley &amp; Beissinger, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0053">2009</a>). Classical bird surveys were designed previously to the development of hierarchical occupancy models (MacKenzie et al., 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0034">2006</a>), so we grouped these transects into larger cells to serve as spatial replicates for a site defined in this way. This framework allows community occupancy models to be fitted, providing individual estimates for occupancy and species richness and accounting for imperfect detection in classical monitoring programs. Moreover, the effects of habitat covariates on the estimated parameters must be considered to study the environmental response of bird communities (Tingley &amp; Beissinger, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0053">2009</a>; Zipkin et al., 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0058" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0058">2009</a>). To the best of our knowledge, this is the first study that specifically was able to make use of historical data by means of spatial replicates to make inference about a large community of birds and their habitat associations. Future studies will hopefully “rediscover” historical occurrence data and elucidate on how communities, populations, and species have shifted over temporal scales (Tingley &amp; Beissinger, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0053">2009</a>). It is also important to consider that the ecological system must be combined with a good understanding of the statistical principles behind sampling in order to improve the value of monitoring programs (Karanth et al., 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0022">2011</a>). Furthermore, the effectiveness of related management actions is especially relevant in the context of ecology and conservation, fields where resources are often fairly limited, and can be increased by applying spatial replicates in sample fields involved in monitoring species at large landscape scales (Martínez‐Martí et al., 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0036">2016</a>; Srivathsa et al., 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0050" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0050">2018</a>). It is also important to highlight that in order to compare the range shift from historical data and compare occupancy and detectability among years, we should consider the field design established, so future surveys will be conducted following similar protocol of the first (Yackulic &amp; Ginsberg, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0055">2016</a>). Moreover, in order to establish probabilities of extinction and colonization without bias, it would be necessary to use the same size of aggregation scheme by including surveys in the same cell sites for the following period (Peach, Cohen, &amp; Frair, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0042">2017</a>; Sadoti et al., 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0048" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0048">2013</a>). Moreover, the mixture of spatial and temporal replicates to estimate detection may also induce bias, so this bias can be removed by choosing sampling locations with replacement, or if the species is highly mobile over a short period of time (Kendall &amp; White, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0024">2009</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">During the development of this new design, the question emerged concerning the potential size of grid for aggregating spatial transects in a cell site. As we stated in the introduction section, the finest cell site resolution may be of 30 × 30 s (i.e., 0.86 km
  <span class="sup">2</span>), so we generate two potential aggregation schemes of 60 × 60 and 90 × 90 s (AS2x2 and AS3x3). The results for models using the aggregation schemes AS2x2 and AS3x3 showed that estimates of occupancy and detectability were highly correlated between both aggregation schemes. Therefore, we consider that both aggregation schemes are equally useful to develop this hierarchical framework in the future bird surveys. In other words, and following our previous hypothesis, our results show relative independence between the two sizes of cell sites proposed. Therefore, ecological reasons and cost‐effective sampling designs should be considered to select the more suitable aggregation scheme in the future studies. Nevertheless, models with data augmentation could be more precise for estimating community size (Zipkin et al., 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0058" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0058">2009</a>), although this was not the aim of this study. Our study design will allow us to implement a dynamic framework, by comparing past bird surveys with modern surveys designed for the same conditions and also estimating parameters that govern change in species presence/absence, for example, probabilities of extinction and colonization (Dorazio, Kéry, Royle, &amp; Plattner, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0009">2010</a>; MacKenzie, Nichols, Hines, Knutson, &amp; Franklin, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0032">2003</a>). This application is relevant for Breeding Bird Atlas Projects (Peach et al., 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0042">2017</a>). Another recent extension developed for community occupancy models is the extension of hierarchical models to multi‐scale habitat selection (Lipsey et al., 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0031">2017</a>) and across multiple regions of interest (e.g., reserves or biomes; Sutherland, Brambilla, Pedrini, &amp; Tenan, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0051" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0051">2016</a>), allowing the estimation of region‐specific community size.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another relevant property of community occupancy models is that they allow occupancy probability to be obtained in relation to environmental covariates and to analyze climate change effects (Clement et al., 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0008">2016</a>). Our results show that a higher percentage of forest cover reduces slightly the mean occupancy of bird communities. Moreover, when environmental covariates (annual mean temperature and annual precipitation) increase, the mean occupancy of bird species is reduced drastically for both aggregation schemes. This result does not agree with a previous study of Tayleur et al. (
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0052">2015</a>), where Swedish birds are tracking by temperature but not by rainfall. It is probably due to the different climate conditions between both avian communities. These aspects need to be borne in mind in light of the changing meteorological conditions in SE Spain at nowadays, since it is an ideal area to study climate change effects and bird distribution in semiarid ecosystems (Esteve et al., 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0015">2015</a>). Therefore, this study could be considered as a pilot study before evaluating climate change effects in southeastern Spain through the development of modern bird surveys. This application of community occupancy models to evaluate climate change effects has been explored recently (Tingley &amp; Beissinger, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0054">2013</a>), although spatial replicates have only been used in one mammal study (Moritz et al., 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0040">2008</a>). Studies about community‐level responses to environmental variations have been developed along with new statistical tools (Kéry &amp; Royle, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0028">2016</a>) which allow the estimate of nondetected species through data augmentation (Dorazio et al., 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0011">2006</a>), estimates of abundance (Yamaura et al., 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0057" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0057">2016</a>), the development of community dynamic models (Dorazio et al., 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0009">2010</a>), and even the combination of trait data with phylogenetic data (taxonomy identity; Ovaskainen et al., 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0041">2017</a>). In this line, future research should focus on developing these mechanistic tools for the study of community species, optimizing sampling effort, and allowing managers to obtain valuable ecological information on wildlife species.
 </p>
</sec>
