<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece34829-sec-0001" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">INTRODUCTION</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Historical occurrence data represent a common, but underused and valuable source of data that can provide novel insights into how the natural world has changed over human life spans (Tingley &amp; Beissinger, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0053">2009</a>). One of the most relevant uses to which these sources can be put is to forecast species distribution by comparison with past climate conditions (Millar &amp; Woolfenden, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0038" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0038">1999</a>). However, due to the complex and variable nature of past occurrence data (museum collections, field notes, etc.), a flexible framework for analysis is needed. Indeed, direct comparison of old, historic, and present‐day data may be complicated or even impossible if the survey methodology has changed or if any other factor that may influence detection probability differently affects old and the new data (Tingley &amp; Beissinger, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0053">2009</a>). Some of the methodological issues involved in using historical data (e.g., limited historic sampling or the inability to control for changes in detectability between sampling periods) can now be explicitly accounted for through occupancy modeling and related quantitative techniques (Kéry &amp; Royle, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0028">2016</a>; Moritz et al., 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0040">2008</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Occupancy models provide estimates of occurrence probability for species that are corrected for imperfect detection (Bailey, MacKenzie, &amp; Nichols, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0002">2014</a>; MacKenzie et al., 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0034">2006</a>). These models enable us to rigorously evaluate the effects of environmental variables on occupancy probability, mapping species range dynamics (Kéry, Guillera‐Arroita, &amp; Lahoz‐Monfort, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0025">2013</a>; Santika, McAlpine, Lunney, Wilson, &amp; Rhodes, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0049">2014</a>), study the interactions between species (Michel, Jiménez‐Franco, Naef‐Daenzer, &amp; Grüebler, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0037">2016</a>; Yackulic et al., 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0056" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0056">2014</a>) and evaluate the effects of climate change (Clement, Hines, Nichols, Pardieck, &amp; Ziolkowski, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0008">2016</a>). Multispecies occupancy models are a more complex framework, aimed at estimating total community richness (Dorazio &amp; Royle, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0010">2005</a>; Dorazio, Royle, Söderström, &amp; Glimskär, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0011">2006</a>; Kéry &amp; Royle, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0026">2008</a>) and few studies have evaluated the effects of different habitats (Zipkin, DeWan, &amp; Royle, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0058" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0058">2009</a>) and range shift over two different periods (Moritz et al., 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0040">2008</a>; Tingley &amp; Beissinger, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0054">2013</a>). The fundamental idea behind the multispecies modeling approach is that collective community data can inform the occurrence probabilities for all observed species, even those that are rare or elusive, and allow for occurrence estimation of species that were never observed in the sample plots (Zipkin et al., 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0058" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0058">2009</a>). Thus, a multispecies approach can provide more precise estimates of species richness, while accounting for variation in occurrence and detection among species, which is a useful tool to inform which species respond in a comparable manner to habitat changes (Russell et al., 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0047">2009</a>). Moreover, in order to separately estimate occupancy and detection probability, it is typically necessary to have replicated observations from at least some of the sites considered in a study (MacKenzie et al., 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0033">2002</a>, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0034">2006</a>). There are several ways to collect information about species detectability: temporal replicates, records collected by multiple independent observers, multiple independent detection methods or by spatial subsampling of a site (MacKenzie &amp; Royle, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0035">2005</a>). Most studies so far have used temporal replicates at a site, that is, multiple visits (MacKenzie &amp; Royle, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0035">2005</a>), for example, within one breeding season (León‐Ortega, Jiménez‐Franco, Martínez, &amp; Calvo, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0030" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0030">2017</a>). However, spatial replicates at a given site may be a more efficient protocol for large areas (Karanth et al., 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0022">2011</a>), or when there are budget constraints (Martínez‐Martí, Jiménez‐Franco, Royle, Palazón, &amp; Calvo, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0036">2016</a>). Spatial replicates are defined as surveyed points or transects that are nested in what is considered a site, such as a grid cell. Such nested subsamples have great potential for mapping species distributions using occupancy modeling over large areas (Srivathsa, Puri, Kumar, Jathanna, &amp; Karanth, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0050" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0050">2018</a>). The use of spatial replication in occupancy modeling assumes that the species of interest have a nonzero probability of occurring in each spatial replicate, given that they occur somewhere in the larger grid cell, that is, spatial closure, and uniform availability of the species for detection (Charbonnel et al., 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0007">2014</a>; Hines et al., 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0021">2010</a>; Kendall &amp; White, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0024">2009</a>). This typically means that individuals may move widely within the latter or that there is suitable habitat for each within the area of every spatial replicate. The topic of spatial subsampling has recently received growing attention, so studies have analyzed and compared spatial versus temporal replicates (Charbonnel et al., 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0007">2014</a>), as well as the comparison among different data sources in the same system (Srivathsa et al., 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0050" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0050">2018</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Documenting range shifts is an integral part of understanding how species and communities have responded to past environmental change, and occupancy models require the same sampling design in the old and the new period if valuable comparisons are to be made. Few studies have used historical data in occupancy models (Eaton, Hughes, Hines, &amp; Nichols, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0012">2014</a>; Moritz et al., 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0040">2008</a>; Tingley &amp; Beissinger, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0054">2013</a>), probably due to the lack of temporal replicates in the historical surveys, which precludes the estimation of detectability. When there are no temporal replicates, it is useful to consider spatial subsampling of a site to obtain information about detection probability at a scale larger than the fundamental survey unit. For example, the North American Breeding Bird Survey (Robbins, Bystrack, &amp; Geissler, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0046" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0046">1986</a>) consists of roadside surveys, each composed of 50‐point counts spaced at 800‐m intervals. Such surveys could be used to evaluate occupancy by partitioning each site (survey route) into spatial subunits (detection/nondetection of species at single stops or pooled across groups of stops; Kendall &amp; White, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0024">2009</a>). Sadoti, Zuckerberg, Jarzyna, and Porter (
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0048" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0048">2013</a>) aggregated basic atlas survey quadrats into "sites" containing two to four contiguous quadrats, each quadrat serving as a spatial replicate for the analysis of occupancy and detection at site level.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this study, we use a historical data set from an avian community composed of 1‐km transects surveyed in 1991 and 1992. These transects are grouped as spatial replicates nested within a site so that it is possible to fit occupancy models to correct our inferences on species distributions for imperfect detection. An important aspect for aggregating the original survey units (such us points or transects) is the definition of the site. Although a patch of homogeneous habitat could be considered the most appropriate way of defining a site, grouping spatial replicates in a grid cell is quite useful, since environmental data are typically available in grid cells covering entire geographical areas, for example, from GIS databases (MacKenzie &amp; Royle, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0035">2005</a>), which allows mapping the distribution of every species in the community (Budic, Didenko, &amp; Dormann, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0005" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0005">2016</a>). Another important aspect is the selection of the size of a site, which varies in occupancy studies in relation to home range sizes (Efford &amp; Dawson, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0013">2012</a>), and has implication in species distribution models (Yackulic &amp; Ginsberg, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0055">2016</a>). The concept of plot size for the design of occupancy studies in continuous habitat is itself somewhat complex (Efford &amp; Dawson, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0013">2012</a>). The properties of the variable occupancy differ greatly when plots are very large or very small relative to home range size. On the one hand, MacKenzie and Royle (
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0035">2005</a>) stated that “For a species with relatively large home ranges compared with the size of the sampling units, the proportion of area used over a longer timeframe may be close to 100% even though population size is very small.” On the other hand, plots smaller than a home range would violate the assumption of closure (i.e., constant occupancy) between replicate samples. According to Charbonnel et al. (
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0007">2014</a>), spatial scale of the sampling sites must be the same as the home range of the species (or as close to it as possible). Therefore, special attention should be paid in community models, where different species may have different sizes of home ranges. Nevertheless, plot size is usually seen as a design variable under the control of the investigator (Efford &amp; Dawson, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0013">2012</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Environmental data from the WorldClim database have small spatial resolution (30‐s latitude/longitude, i.e., 0.93 × 0.93 = 0.86 km
  <span class="sup">2</span> at the equator), so it is possible to resample for different sizes, depending on the study species, the dimensions of the study area, and the specific aspects of the spatial subsampling of a site; for example, length or distribution of transects in a study area (Lipsey, Naugle, Nowak, &amp; Lukacs, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0031">2017</a>). Based on our sample dataset of 1‐km transects, the spatial resolution of 30 s is too small to grouping these spatial replicates, so the double and triple of this spatial resolution of 30 s may be aggregation schemes with the finest potential spatial scales for the size of the site (hereafter, aggregation schemes AS2x2 and AS3x3).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To make an informed choice for the design of a modern‐day bird survey, we fit community occupancy models to our historical data considering 1‐km transects as spatial replicates that are nested within of larger sites defined as grid cells. The aims are as follows: (a) to fit a community occupancy model to a classical bird survey; (b) to compare the relative independency of estimates of species detectability and occupancy between two aggregation schemes corresponding to two different cell site resolutions of potential use in our study area (AS2x2 and AS3x3); (c) to evaluate the influence of environmental variables (forest cover, temperature, and precipitation) on the occurrence of each member in the avian community. We hypothesized that a higher percentage of forest cover may have a positive influence on occupancy probability for the bird community (Gil‐Tena, Saura, &amp; Brotons, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0017">2007</a>; Zipkin, Royle, Dawson, &amp; Bates, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0059">2010</a>). Regarding weather conditions, sites with a higher average temperature and a lower average precipitation could decrease bird occupancy due to climate constrains in Mediterranean semiarid areas (Garrido, Palenzuela, Bañón, &amp; García, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0016">2015</a>; Zuckerberg et al., 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0060" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0060">2011</a>). This study emphasizes the importance of grouping historical field surveys data within a site, in order to use methods that properly account for imperfect species detection. Moreover, we focus on evaluating the effects of environmental and climatic variables on occupancy of bird species in a Mediterranean region of varying climate sensitivity (Garrido et al., 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0016">2015</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
