<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece34829-sec-0003" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study area and species</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study was developed in the region of Murcia (SE Spain) with an area of 11,317 km
  <span class="sup">2</span> and a semiarid Mediterranean climate, where during the last five decades (1961–2014), the annual temperature has been 16.7°C, with a tendency to increase by 0.135°C per decade (Garrido et al., 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0016">2015</a>). The annual precipitation for this period was 310 mm/year on average, with a wide degree of variation. A clear tendency related to climate change is the decrease in the number of days with snow in the coldest part of the study area (NW), falling from 20 (at the end of the 1960s) to 10 days (in the 2010s; Garrido et al., 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0016">2015</a>). The wide climatic gradient in the study area means that it harbors several types of ecosystem that conform to an ecotone between the Mediterranean and arid subtropical: semi‐desert areas, Mediterranean scrub, and coniferous forest (Esteve et al., 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0015">2015</a>). In compliance with the European Birds and Habitats Directives, 22 Special Protection Areas for birds have been designated in the region (Abellán, Martínez, Palazón, Esteve, &amp; Calvo, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0001">2011</a>). As a result of the climatic gradient and the different ecosystems, the bird community is diverse, with a total of 339 bird species cataloged from 24 orders and 69 families (Calvo et al., 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0006">2017</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study focuses on bird species inhabiting Mediterranean forest ecosystems in the region of Murcia (Figure 
  <a rid="ece34829-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#ece34829-fig-0001">1</a>). These forest areas are dominated by one tree species, the Aleppo pine (
  <span class="italic">Pinus halepensis</span>), a conifer that may reach up to 22 m in Mediterranean areas (Mitsopoulos &amp; Dimitrakopoulos, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0039">2014</a>), having opened areas comprised of Mediterranean scrubs. A total of 73 avian species were recorded (Supporting Information Table 
  <a rid="ece34829-sup-0002" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#ece34829-sup-0002">S1</a>), being most of them passerines, and the most representative families Sylviidae, Turdidae, Fringillidae, and Paridae. These four families encompass more than a third of the forest bird community (31 species), being indicative of different status of forest maturity and including representatives of relevant trophic and functional guilds (granivores, frugivores, seed dispersers, etc.), as well as of different zoogeographical origins, for example, boreal versus Mediterranean species (Blondel, Aronson, Bodiou, &amp; Boeuf, 
  <a rid="ece34829-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34829-bib-0003">2010</a>).
 </p>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece34829-fig-0001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Nine representative bird species of the study area. From left to right, and top to bottom: 
    <span class="italic">Carduelis carduelis</span>, 
    <span class="italic">Sylvia undata</span>, 
    <span class="italic">Parus major</span>, 
    <span class="italic">Turdus viscivorus</span>, 
    <span class="italic">Sylvia melanocephala</span>, 
    <span class="italic">Emberiza cia</span>, 
    <span class="italic">Lophophanes cristatus</span>, 
    <span class="italic">Aegithalos caudatus,</span> and 
    <span class="italic">Loxia curvirostra</span>. Photograph credit: Carlos González Revelles
   </p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-3" xlink:href="ECE3-9-825-g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
