<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Population growth rates of species with similar life histories (e.g. clutch sizes or survival rates) have the potential to be highly synchronized [
 <xref rid="RSTB20160144C24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSTB20160144C25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>], while differences in life history can desynchronize dynamics across species [
 <xref rid="RSTB20160144C24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSTB20160144C25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. Thus, we contrast the timing of extreme responses of birds and Lepidoptera, with the expectation that we will observe similar temporal responses within, but not between, these two taxonomic groups. We then go on to identify consensus years where an unusually large proportion of species experiences extreme population changes, and assess whether these consensus years tend to coincide with extreme climate conditions in the same and/or previous year. Although the importance of ECEs to population dynamics is widely discussed in the ecological and climate change literatures [
 <xref rid="RSTB20160144C6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>], the extent to which these events do or do not predict long-term population trends has not been assessed robustly. There is no necessary link between the two, although there is certainly the potential for ECEs to cause long-term population changes (e.g. [
 <xref rid="RSTB20160144C26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>]). There may be no link because extreme events, by definition, are rare, and an extreme change in one year may have very little impact on the average rate of population growth or decline over a longer period. Alternatively, it is possible that the cessation of some kinds of ECEs (which previously either constrained populations, or generated periodic increases in reproduction) may be as important to long-term population changes as an increased frequency of previously rare or wholly novel conditions. The influence of such events may only be seen in population time series of long duration. Therefore, we consider empirically whether the long-term population trends of species (over four decades) are linked to the extreme population responses that they exhibit over the entire period.
</p>
