<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Despite these observed rapid changes in migratory behavior in response to changing environmental conditions, it is widely acknowledged that migratory species in general seem to suffer more from population declines than species that do not migrate, with climate change as one of its four drivers (Wilcove &amp; Wikelski, 
 <xref rid="ece33357-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>). It is predicted that communities of migratory bird species in Europe will be altered through changes in migratory behavior under current projected climatic changes, rather than through reassembly of bird communities, the latter of which would lead to lower proportions of migratory species (Schaefer, Jetz, &amp; Böhning‐Gaese, 
 <xref rid="ece33357-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>). Interestingly, partially migratory populations have been observed to suffer less population declines than fully residential or fully migratory populations from changing climatic conditions (Gilroy, Gill, Butchart, Jones, &amp; Franco, 
 <xref rid="ece33357-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>), suggesting the migratory diversity facilitates adequate responses such changes. Our results suggest that for species of which migration decisions are controlled by the genetic threshold model, environmental changes could be met with across generational changes in the frequency of migratory phenotypes. Current findings that partially migratory populations seem to better deal with changing can be in line with our suggestion. We would then expect that fully residential and fully migratory populations are able to adapt as well. Current local lack of genetic diversity for different threshold values might delay the necessary changes and population declines could be the result ongoing selection against threshold values that are deleterious under the new conditions. Particularly in populations bordering the zone of partially migratory populations, selection against 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>‐values coding for the adverse migratory phenotype is strong (Cobben &amp; Van Noordwijk, 
 <xref rid="ece33357-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). In this study, populations are well connected and the full environmental gradient is inhabited, allowing the build‐up and movement of genetic diversity for 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>‐values, which is not necessarily or even most likely not the case in the empirical examples investigated. All in all, from our study, we conclude that under the assumption of the genetic threshold value for migratory behavior, the phenomenon of (passerine) migration will not be lost provided species can inhabit places where resident survival is smaller than migratory survival, although reaching such a new equilibrium situation may take multiple generations.
</p>
