<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">To further characterize the differences in the thermal responses, we used the Kaplan–Meier product limit method (Kaplan &amp; Meier, 
 <xref rid="ece35045-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1958</xref>) and the log‐rank test (Mantel, 
 <xref rid="ece35045-bib-0044" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1966</xref>), which are commonly used in exposure‐dose survival assays across different scientific disciplines as a method for constructing and statistically comparing time to event data curves (De Clercq, 
 <xref rid="ece35045-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>; Dickel, Münch, Amdam, Mappes, &amp; Freitak, 
 <xref rid="ece35045-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2018</xref>; Govaert et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35045-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). In the analysis, we focused on the probability of each species of not suffering necrosis through time when exposed to different temperature treatments, which allowed us to determine the upper thermal limits of each species (defined here as the first temperature at which a given species presents a significantly lower probability of remaining healthy (without necrosis) throughout the experiment compared to the control conditions). We could then classify them according to these thermal limits into three different groups: highly resistant (thermal limit ≥28°C), intermediately resistant (thermal limit = 27°C), and minimally resistant or sensitive (thermal limit = 26°C). Furthermore, when significant differences between the control and any of the treatments were obtained, pairwise log‐rank comparison tests were performed to further explore the differences between the treatments (Supporting information Table 
 <xref rid="ece35045-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S3</xref>). Then, the same procedure was repeated to explore the differences between the different species and phyla exposed to the same temperature treatments. In this case, only the 10 and 8 day periods were considered when comparing the species or phyla at 28 and 29°C, as this was the duration of the experiment for the species tested in 2012 at these two temperatures. Statistical analyses were not performed regarding the growth form given the low number of species in each group. All the statistical analyses and graphics were produced using R version 3.1.2 (R Core Developer Team, 2014).
</p>
