<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The growth rate trends at the uppermost part of the elevational gradients across all four treeline species were positive, but significant for larch at Bosco/Gurin and Zermatt only, and nearly significant for Swiss stone pine at Zermatt. Spruce and mountain pine did not yield significant trends in growth rates over time. Following the general hypothesis of temperature being the most important factor limiting tree growth at the treeline (e.g., Körner, 
 <xref rid="ece33290-bib-0058" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>), as well as our findings regarding the relationship of temperature and growth (Figure 
 <xref rid="ece33290-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3</xref>) in conjunction with rising temperatures in months that affect tree growth (Figure 
 <xref rid="ece33290-fig-0005" ref-type="fig" class="xref">5</xref>), these trends are likely induced by improved growth conditions due to recent climate change. Although some studies suggest elevated atmospheric CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> levels or increased nitrogen deposition to account for positive trends in tree growth rates of some species (e.g., Dawes et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33290-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>), the timing of the growth increase at our study sites favors temperature as the key factor since the start of the positive trend (ca. 1950) does not coincide with a pronounced increase of CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> (Bigler, 
 <xref rid="ece33290-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). Furthermore, the study sites are located in areas that experienced relatively small amounts of nitrogen deposition (Thimonier et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33290-bib-0089" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>). Thus, our findings confirm the results of studies on the impact of climate change on tree growth in the Alps, attributing accelerated growth of Swiss stone pine (Motta &amp; Nola, 
 <xref rid="ece33290-bib-0073" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2001</xref>; Vittoz, Rulence, Largey, &amp; Freléchoux, 
 <xref rid="ece33290-bib-0093" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>) and larch (Motta &amp; Nola, 
 <xref rid="ece33290-bib-0073" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2001</xref>) to a rise in temperature.
</p>
