<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Fieldwork was conducted in a wetland network in southwestern Spain encompassing ca. 6,000 km
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0192702.g001" class="xref">Fig 1</xref>). This network included permanent and temporary waterbodies in a salinity gradient ranging from fresh water ponds to brackish marshes to salt pans, in the provinces of Huelva, Seville and Cadiz. The climate is Mediterranean sub-humid with rainy winters and dry summers. The study area includes the Doñana wetland complex, a large and shallow floodplain at the estuary of the Guadalquivir River. This complex is considered the Western Europe’s largest sanctuary for migratory birds and holds a number of national and international recognitions (National Park, biosphere reserve, Ramsar site) [
 <xref rid="pone.0192702.ref041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>]. We carried out fortnightly surveys (1718 point-counts) at 80 different fixed selected localities (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0192702.g001" class="xref">Fig 1</xref>) throughout the 2008–2009 annual cycle (from January 2008 to February 2009). With an annual accumulated precipitation of 476 mm and an average daily mean temperature of 17.2°C, this annual cycle fell well within the average range for the study area (541 mm and 17.3°C for the long term 1994–2016 average; 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0192702.g002" class="xref">Fig 2</xref>). Waterbird species occurrences (presence/absence) were recorded during a 20-minute interval at each site scanning a 180° field-of-view in front of the observer. The direction of observation at the locality was selected to cover the wetland habitat with homogeneous characteristics. Concurrently, the observer recorded environmental information and relevant predictors in the observed area likely driving both the detectability and the presence of waterbirds (
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0192702.t001" class="xref">Table 1</xref>).
</p>
