<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s20009" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Systems thinking application to highlight factors impeding effective food production</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Causal loop modelling was used to produce an ST model to highlight the interconnections and interdependencies among the various components within Igbide, Uzere and Olomoro communities (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F0003" href="#F0003">Figure 3</a>). Each variable can either progress in parallel or opposite directions. If an increase in one variable leads to a decrease in another variable, it is denoted by ‘-’ close to the arrow head. Conversely, if an increase in one variable results in an increase in another variable, it is denoted by ‘+’ close to the arrow head. The ST model, as argued by Kunsch et al. (
  <a rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0024">2007</a>) and Flood (
  <a rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0016">2010</a>), is analysed through feedback loops. Feedback loops are either balancing or reinforcing. Balancing loops seek to stabilise a system or return it back to normal. Reinforcing loops, on the other hand, usually represent increasing or decreasing actions (Nguyen &amp; Bosch 
  <a rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0034">2013</a>). 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F0003" href="#F0003">Figure 3</a> identified eight reinforcing (R) loops and three balancing (B) loops. For reasons of brevity, we have deliberated on issues that could eventually result in making food production overwhelmingly difficult within the shortest timeframe if decisive measures are not taken by development practitioners.
 </p>
 <div id="F0003" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">FIGURE 3</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Systems model of factors undermining effective food production in the study areas. Dashed lines have no influence on the loop they pass through.</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="JAMBA-11-597-g003" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F0003" href="#F0003">Figure 3</a>, a glaring issue that is impacting negatively food production is the abuse of the drug 
  <span class="italic">tramadol</span>. It was argued that this has constituted a menace in these communities including the depletion of household workforce, thereby compromising the ability of affected households to produce more food. Some participants explained that while the sale of drug is illegal, some pharmaceuticals still make this drug readily available for those in need of the substance. It was alleged that one reason the drug is highly sought-after is that it ‘enhances stamina during sexual intercourse’. The adverse implications associated with a 
  <span class="italic">tramadol</span> overdose by husbands or partners, which often results in some of them collapsing, are twofold: firstly, wives or partners are left with no alternative but to seek medical assistance for their husbands or partners. Even after their husbands or partners have been stabilised by a medical practitioner, the women still have to cater to their needs for some days as they need to be closely monitored at home. This ultimately results in disruption of food production and shortage of household labour in circumstances where the men assist their wives to produce food. This can have severe implications for households’ food security in circumstances where the households have not harvested all their cassava tubers on the low-lying farmlands before the seasonal inundation occurs (
  <span class="italic">elelame</span>), and are unable to return within the next 2 days to harvest the inundated tubers in order to prevent them from rotting away. Secondly, and overdose of 
  <span class="italic">tramadol</span> by husbands or partners may cause emotional abuse in women (B_3) through shaming and mockery by community members because the affected women will likely be perceived as sexually insatiable by their husbands’ or partners’ natural energy levels. This has the potential to impede the affected women from producing food efficiently because emotional well-being is crucial for maximum productivity (Donald et al. 
  <a rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0010">2005</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F0003" href="#F0003">Figure 3</a> also reveals that the participants have, for decades, relied and continue to rely on IKS not limited to the observation of the flowering of specific trees, croaking of frogs and cloud observation (see Ebhuoma &amp; Simatele 
  <a rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0013">2017b</a>). For example, a participant explained:
 </p>
 <div class="disp-quote" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <p>‘The use of IKS [indigenous knowledge systems] by farmers in this community to determine when to start growing our food is hinged on tradition. Although it has not been 100% accurate at all times, it has, for decades, proved extremely beneficial to those who respect tradition. When farmers obey instructions from nature, they get rewarded bountifully.’ (Male farmer from Olomoro, in his sixties)</p>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The participants, however, pointed out that IKS has not been reliable as it used to be in previous decades. While 3% of the participants suggested that only God can determine the cause regarding the inconsistences of their IKS, 18% argued that this is the resultant effect of oil exploration activities. In narrating how oil exploration activities have affected IKS, it was argued that gas flaring has negatively impacted the rubber trees and cassava leaves, which they rely upon to predict the weather. This is because, occasionally, the rubber trees and cassava leaves do not flower at the time ‘they are naturally supposed to’. When this happens, the tendency for their predictions to be inaccurate becomes relatively high. Thus, oil exploration activities, from the participants’ perspective, have undermined their traditional way of life.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From a political perspective, political instability has, in part, emanated from the federal governments’ introduction of a policy in 2016 that allowed the currency to trade freely in a move to control the currency crisis. This resulted in a significant devaluation of the naira, with the naira exchanging in December 2016 at 305 naira (₦305.00) to 1 US dollar, as against 155 naira in November 2014 (₦155.00) (Nigerian Bulletin 
  <a rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0036">2016</a>; Tijani 
  <a rid="CIT0055" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0055">2015</a>). This adversely reduced the purchasing power of most end-users (B_1), which, in turn, reduces farmers’ financial capital. This is because Nigeria depends largely on foreign products (Vanguard 
  <a rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0057">2015</a>). Thus, the soaring of the US dollars heightened the prices of most goods in the country, thereby creating a ripple effect by affecting other sectors of the country. Also, the government’s inability to pay workers’ salaries regularly at the end of each month – in some instances, workers are owed over 6 months salaries (Vanguard 
  <a rid="CIT0058" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0058">2018</a>) – has significantly reduced the purchasing power for most consumers, with severe implications for the financial capital of the farmers (R_8). The lack of financial capital impedes farmers’ ability to purchase seedlings, fertilisers and other basic items necessary to produce food efficiently.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the context of population growth, it was argued that it has facilitated the conversion of farmlands into housing units. Further, the increase in population, which also triggered deforestation, catalysed the inability for farmers to leave their farmlands to undergo bush fallowing as they usually did between the 1960s and the 1980s in order to produce ‘enough’ food to meet their livelihood objectives. Thus, the increase in population has made yearly food production in the limited available farmlands the norm. This has also contributed to the low quality of food produced because of a significant reduction in the soil quality (R_3). In the context of soil quality, the participants (89%) echoed that oil exploration activities remain the causal factor for the reduced soil quality (R_2); an elderly participant from Uzere, in his 80s, provided a mind-boggling insight. Not refuting the claim that oil exploration activities have compromised the soil quality, he argued that the annual seasonal flooding which occurs on the low-lying farmlands brings along with it alluvial soil. This, as he further pointed out, helps to replenish the soils’ lost nutrients. He, however, concluded that oil exploration activities have expedited the loss of soil nutrients at a pace faster than the rate at which alluvial soil replenishes the lost nutrients.</p>
</sec>
