<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Causes of variation in the timing of breeding</div>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mean spring temperature, altitude, distance from the coast, population density, overall mean territory occupancy rate, overall mean territory success rate, and overall mean territory clutch, brood size were included in a linear mixed model framework in order to explain the variation in hatching date using an explorative approach. Because we were interested in potential interactions with mean spring temperature and population density, we compared models with the additional two-way interactions between them and the other variables. We used model averaging to rank models with the Bayesian Information Criterion, BIC, with the random intercepts year, territory identity and female identity. The top model had considerably higher BIC weight (BIC
  <sub>w</sub> = 0.71) than the lower ranked models (three models, ΔBIC &gt; 4.0, BIC
  <sub>w</sub> ≤ 0.09; Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>). The top model included spring temperature, altitude, distance from the coast, population density, overall mean territory success rate and overall mean territory brood size, in addition to the interactions between density and distance, density and overall mean territory success rate, and density and overall mean territory brood size, respectively, (Table 
  <a rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" href="#Tab2">2</a>), and it explained 78% of the variation in hatching date (conditional R
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.78, marginal R
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.61; random effects: year SD = 3.4, territory id SD = 2.7, female id SD = 2.9, residual SD = 5.9). Hatching date advanced with increasing spring temperature, and with decreasing altitudes (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2a</a>). Hatching date advanced with increasing population density at coastal territories, while it was delayed with increasing population densities inland (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2b</a>). At low population density, hatching date at seldom occupied territories was earlier, while at high population density, often occupied territories hatched earlier (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2c</a>). In contrast hatching was earlier at territories with large overall mean territory brood size during low population density years, while at high population density hatching occurred at the same time at all territories (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2d</a>). Spring temperature (25.0%), the interaction between density and overall mean territory brood size (21.4%), altitude (13.7%) and density (12.0%) explained most of the variation, while overall mean territory brood size (7.8%), year (5.7%), female identity (4.1%), overall mean territory occupancy rate (2.6%), distance from the coast (1.8%), the interaction between density and distance from the coast (1.3%), and overall mean territory occupancy rate (1.1%) explained a smaller part of the variation in breeding time.
  <div id="Tab1" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>The top ten models given by a model selection process where timing of breeding were explained by spring temperature (temp), altitude (alt), distance from the coast (dist), population density (dens), the territory quality variables overall mean territory occupancy rate (tocc), brood size (tbrood), and success rate (tsuccess), in addition to all interactions with spring temperatures, and all interactions with population density, in the white-throated dipper population in Lyngdalselva 1978–2011.</p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th>Models</th>
      <th>df</th>
      <th>BIC</th>
      <th>ΔBIC
       <sub>c</sub>
      </th>
      <th>BIC
       <sub>w</sub>
      </th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td>dist + tocc + dens + alt + temp + tbrood + dist × dens + tocc × dens + tbrood × dens</td>
      <td>14</td>
      <td>6789.2</td>
      <td>0.0</td>
      <td>0.71</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>dist + tocc + dens + alt + temp + tbrood + dist × dens + tocc × dens + tbrood × dens + alt × temp</td>
      <td>15</td>
      <td>6793.3</td>
      <td>4.1</td>
      <td>0.09</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>dist + tocc + dens + alt + temp + tbrood + tocc × dens + alt × dens + tbrood × dens + alt × temp</td>
      <td>15</td>
      <td>6793.6</td>
      <td>4.4</td>
      <td>0.08</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>dist + tocc + dens + alt + temp + tbrood + dist × temp + tocc × dens + tbrood × dens + alt × temp</td>
      <td>15</td>
      <td>6793.9</td>
      <td>4.7</td>
      <td>0.07</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>dist + tocc + dens + alt + temp + tbrood + dist × temp + tocc × dens + alt × dens + tbrood × dens + alt × temp</td>
      <td>16</td>
      <td>6796.9</td>
      <td>7.7</td>
      <td>0.02</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>dist + tocc + dens + alt + temp + tbrood + dist × dens + dist × temp + tocc × dens + tbrood × dens + alt × temp</td>
      <td>16</td>
      <td>6798.4</td>
      <td>9.2</td>
      <td>0.01</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>dist + tocc + dens + alt + temp + tbrood + dist × dens + tsuccess + tocc × dens + tbrood × dens + alt × temp</td>
      <td>16</td>
      <td>6798.8</td>
      <td>9.6</td>
      <td>0.01</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>dist + tocc + dens + alt + temp + tbrood + dist × temp + alt × dens + alt × dens + tbrood × dens + alt × temp</td>
      <td>16</td>
      <td>6798.9</td>
      <td>9.7</td>
      <td>0.01</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>dist + tocc + dens + alt + temp + tbrood + dist × dens + tocc × dens + tbrood × dens + alt × temp + tbrood × temp</td>
      <td>16</td>
      <td>6799.0</td>
      <td>9.8</td>
      <td>0.01</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>dist + tocc + dens + alt + temp + tbrood + dist × dens + tocc × dens + tbrood × dens + temp × dens + tbrood × dens + alt × temp</td>
      <td>16</td>
      <td>6799.0</td>
      <td>9.8</td>
      <td>0.01</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
  </div>
  <div id="Tab2" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Timing of breeding explained by the model with the lowest BIC, consisting of spring temperature (temp), altitude (alt), distance from the coast (dist), population density (dens), the territory quality variables overall mean occupancy rate (tocc) and brood size (tbrood) in the white-throated dipper in Lyngdalselva 1978–2011.</p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th>Fixed effects</th>
      <th>Estimate</th>
      <th>t</th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td>intercept</td>
      <td>152.00</td>
      <td>24.1</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>temp</td>
      <td>−4.76</td>
      <td>−9.6</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>alt</td>
      <td>0.03</td>
      <td>8.4</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>dist</td>
      <td>0.0001</td>
      <td>1.9</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>dens</td>
      <td>−0.18</td>
      <td>−2.5</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>tocc</td>
      <td>0.07</td>
      <td>1.8</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>tbrood</td>
      <td>−6.76</td>
      <td>−4.5</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>dist x dens</td>
      <td>0.000001</td>
      <td>1.7</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>tocc x dens</td>
      <td>−0.0010</td>
      <td>−2.4</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>tbrood x dens</td>
      <td>0.06</td>
      <td>3.3</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
  </div>
  <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>The causes of variation in the timing of breeding modelled in a linear mixed-effects model in the white-throated dipper in Lyngdalsvassdraget 1978–2011. Effects are shown for the following fixed effects, using model predictions and a restricted data set: (
     <span class="bold">a</span>) altitude (m above sea level), (
     <span class="bold">b</span>) the interaction between distance from the coast (m) and population density, where population density is ordered from low to high with decreasingly light grey tones, (
     <span class="bold">c</span>) the interaction between overall mean territory occupancy rate and population density, where population density is ordered as in (
     <span class="bold">b</span>), and (
     <span class="bold">d</span>) the interaction between overall mean territory brood size and population density, where population density is ordered as in (
     <span class="bold">b</span>) and (
     <span class="bold">c</span>),with the crossed random effects year, female identity and territory identity, on the hatching day-of-year. N = 992.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_43792_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e870" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
