<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec6" sec-type="discussion" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In our study population, hatching date has advanced almost nine days during the 34 years of the study. Seemingly, the dipper has advanced its breeding time to adjust for the earlier spring, indicated by the increased mean spring temperatures. Spring temperatures, altitude, and the interactions between population density and overall mean territory brood size, population density and distance from the coast, and population density and overall mean territory occupancy rate, respectively, explained 78% of the variation in breeding time. In general, birds breeding early enjoyed fitness benefits, which to some extent were explained by the effect of increased spring temperatures on fledging success. Fledging success also increased over the study period in response to warm spring temperatures, whereas there was no temporal trend in cold springs.</p>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The dipper’s breeding time advanced in response to warmer springs, a common finding in birds
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>
  </span>. Dunn
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span> found that 79% of the studied bird species had advanced laying date with increasing spring temperatures during the last decades. In the United Kingdom, Crick and Sparks
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>
  </span> found that 27 of 45 bird species had significantly advanced breeding date over time. They
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>
  </span> found a smaller change in breeding phenology in the dipper: only −1.52 days per 1 °C in the UK compared to −4.3 days in our study. Although our study period was shorter, 34 vs 57 years, it included 13 more recent years, many of them comparatively warm. Another potential difference might be that the change in temperatures might not have been of similar magnitude. This nevertheless suggests that the response to environmental change in this species is stronger in Northern than in Western Europe
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
  </span>, perhaps because snow and ice conditions are more important in the north
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As predicted, breeding phenology was delayed by approximately 3 days per 100 m increase in altitude. Analyses of spring phenology of terrestrial plants in Norway have shown a general delay of 2–3 days per 100 m increase in altitude
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>
  </span>. Delayed egg-laying with increasing altitude has also been observed in the great tit
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span>, suggesting that it was caused by changes in food availability and temperature. In this study we did not have such detailed data on temperature and food availability, but the strong correlation between altitude and distance from the coast (see methods), and the fact that temperature generally drops with 0.65° per 100 m increase in altitude, make a strong case for altitudinal and coastal effects being synonymous with a climatic gradient. The later breeding at higher elevations in our study may have been caused by later ice break-up at higher-elevation tributaries, since the break-up is caused by increasing spring temperatures and indicates when a territory becomes available. In essence, spring temperature measured at the regional level and local environmental conditions captured by the altitudinal especially was important in determining the timing of breeding in this study system.
 </p>
 <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Dippers in coastal areas bred earlier than inland ones, but this effect was exaggerated in years with high population density, indicating that intraspecific competition affected coastal and inland breeders differently. Competition in coastal areas advances breeding, presumably to gain competitive advantages for offspring after independence. In contrast, competition at inland areas delays breeding, indicating that competition might affect overall resource availability in the area. Presumably, territories at inland sites were marginal and when more territories were occupied, there were fewer unoccupied that could serve as extensions of occupied territories
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The territory variables overall mean territory occupancy rate and overall mean territory brood size interacted with population density and contributed to explaining the variation in timing of breeding. When population density was high, dippers on often occupied territories bred earlier than those on rarely occupied territories. When population density was low, on the other hand, dippers on territories that were rarely occupied bred earlier than those on often occupied territories. For overall mean territory brood size, dippers bred earlier on territories with overall larger mean brood size when population density was low. The effect of overall mean territory brood size was evened out in high density years. This result is to some extent consistent with Sergio and Newton’s findings in the black kite
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span>, where high-quality territories were occupied earlier than low-quality territories. The importance of the overall mean territory brood size indicates that not only will some territories produce larger broods, but also support earlier breeding, when population density and thus competition is low. Territories in this population are spatially fixed based on the availability of suitable nest sites in the terrain and they are used year after year. In addition, there is an obvious heterogeneity in territory occupancy rates, from being occupied only once to being occupied in all 34 years of the study. Because of the large fluctuations in population density in this population
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span>, competition for good territories is highly variable and it is unlikely that all the variation accounted for in the analyses by territory quality only reflects that high quality pairs occupied such territories. Indeed, the results from the present study indicate that the territory quality variables included in the analyses indeed captured different aspects of territory quality. Even though overall mean territory brood size is an averaged measurement commonly used in analyses of habitat quality
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span>, there is a risk that part of the correlation between reproductive output and timing of breeding is retained. The effect of overall mean territory brood size must therefore be interpreted with some caution.
 </p>
 <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Dippers breeding early raised larger broods and had more recruits than those breeding late. There was thus selection for early breeding
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span>. However, when the fitness measure was the number of fledglings given the number of eggs laid, the optimal breeding time was moderated by spring temperature. Recruitment rate was affected by timing of breeding only, suggesting that it was breeding time per se that was most important, and not factors associated with it, like territory quality. In general, early breeding is beneficial because: (i) if food is seasonally abundant, more may be available early in the season
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span>, (ii) offspring hatching early have more time to prepare for the winter (moult, migration or residency)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
  </span>, (iii) early terminated breeding may improve subsequent adult survival
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
  </span>, (iv) there are more opportunities for males to become polygynous, (v) there are more opportunities for rearing second broods
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span>, and (vi) more opportunities for renesting in case of failure. Note that only successful nests, i.e. nests producing fledglings, were included in the analyses (see methods for details).
 </p>
 <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The declining trend in reproductive output over the breeding season (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>) indicates a seasonal decline in feeding conditions. The dipper’s food source is mainly composed of larvae of may-, caddis- and stoneflies
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
  </span> (Orders Ephemeroptera, Tricoptera and Plecoptera) that may spend more than a year in the water to develop. Adult stoneflies hatch during a well-defined peak, while may- and caddisfly hatch asynchronously during spring and summer. The river is, thus, unlikely to be completely depleted from food resources during the dipper’s breeding time. It is therefore not obvious that the food abundance is strongly peaked, or strongly decreasing with season, as typically found in many populations of tits
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
  </span> and flycatchers
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
  </span>, which are depending on terrestrial prey. Also, as the prey is under water and therefore presumed to be less sensitive to changes in air temperature, the birds’ strong phenology response to air temperature is somewhat surprising. There might however be a potential mismatch later in the season that might hit juveniles that have reached independence
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span>. Despite using female identity as a random effect in our analyses, there is a risk that part of the seasonal decline in reproductive success arises from differences in individual quality, where high quality females breed earlier than low quality females
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>
  </span>. Consequently, it is still unclear whether the dipper responds directly to the ambient temperatures in air and water in spring, or indirectly mediated by changes in the phenology of its prey.
 </p>
 <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In conclusion, increasing spring temperatures have advanced breeding in a white-throated dipper population in southern Norway over a 34-year period. In addition, breeding time was strongly influenced by the location and the quality of the territory, where territories at low altitudes close to the fjord, particularly in high density years, were the first to hatch and thus commence breeding in spring. In low density years, birds on territories with high mean territory brood size bred earlier than those on less favourable territories, while there was no effect in high density years. Whether the abundance and the phenology of the prey proximately influenced the timing of breeding is unclear. However, early breeders produced significantly more offspring recruiting to the local breeding population than late breeders. In studies of breeding phenology, we recommend that habitat quality and altitudinal gradients are taken into account, in addition to the local weather conditions, because these might impose variation in breeding phenology not related to variation in annual spring weather. This may also be important when studying the importance of other predictor variables. Finally we found that breeding phenology may have strong effects on fitness and thus that breeding time is an important factor in a species that feeds mainly on aquatic rather than terrestrial prey.</p>
</sec>
