<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec7" sec-type="materials|methods" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Materials and Methods</div>
 <sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study population and data assimilation</div>
  <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The study population is located in the river Lyngdalselva in southernmost Norway (58° 08′–58° 40′N, 6° 56′–7° 20′E) and has been studied since 1978. Monitoring of the population is standardised (see
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>
   </span> for details). The river system of Lyngdalselva is not utilised for hydropower production or subject to other major regulations and there are no nest boxes available for breeding. It is thus a natural system for studying dipper ecology where natural nest sites are complemented by nest sites in and under bridges and other manmade structures. The study system contains a strong altitudinal gradient in addition to being located along a coastal-inland gradient, ranging from the coastal zone to 60 km inland and 700 m a.s.l. Dippers defend territories which contain one or more appropriate nest sites, which are situated so that the opening of the nest is almost always located right above fast-flowing water. Because suitable nest sites are limited and spatially segregated, there is a limited number of territories available in the river system. Within the river system we have identified a total of 158 spatially separated territories. While some of them are always occupied (34 years), others are only used a single year. It is therefore clear that some territories are preferred over others. The downstream and upstream boundaries might fluctuate slightly between years, particularly depending on whether the upstream or downstream neighbouring territories are occupied or not, but the major part of the territory will remain constant between years. The size of the study population has ranged from 20 to 117 breeding pairs over the years
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>
   </span>. The number of breeding pairs with recorded phenology data is 1045, out of 2264 pairs with recorded first clutches (renesting attempts and second broods excluded). Breeding phenology was estimated as the hatching date of the first clutch of a female, according to the methods described in
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
   </span>. In summary, hatching date was estimated based on the growth trajectory of the largest nestling in each brood. This implies that the phenology of nests that did not produce young, or produced young that were not measured, could not be estimated by this method. Breeding dippers were aged and sexed according to Svensson
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>
   </span>. At first encounter, breeding birds were ringed with an aluminium ring and given an individual colour code in the form of two plastic colour rings (95%). Consequently, birds did not have to be recaptured after ringing. Within the river system, the breeding outcome of almost all occupied nests was known and nearly all young were ringed.
  </p>
  <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Laying date could have been estimated based on hatching, the length of the incubation period, and the number of eggs laid, but such calculations would increase the amount of uncertainty in the estimates. In those instances where we had observed egg-laying date, there was no difference in phenology between those nests that produced young and those that failed (successful: mean = 19
   <span class="sup">th</span> of April, SD = 4.5 days, N = 93; failed: mean = 22
   <span class="sup">nd</span> of April, SD = 14.2 days, N = 27; two-sample t-test with Welch’s approximation for degrees of freedom: t = 0.7, df = 43, p = 0.5) and the correlation between hatching and laying date was very high (r = 0.98, df = 98, p &lt; 0.0001).
  </p>
  <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To assess the effect of climate change, we used mean spring temperature, defined as the average temperature during Feb–Apr, provided by the Norwegian Meteorological Institute (
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://om.yr.no/verdata/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://om.yr.no/verdata/</span>, see
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>
   </span> for details). The period Feb–Apr approximately encompasses the time immediately before initiation of breeding and the early stages of incubation.
  </p>
  <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Altitude and distance from the coast, indicating local climatic conditions at the location of each territory, were defined as the altitude (m a.s.l.) and the straight-line distance (m) to the river outlet of the most frequently occupied nest site within each territory. Altitude and distance from the coast were, as expected, correlated (r = 0.83, df = 156, p &lt; 0.0001). Territory quality was measured by four different methods: (1) occupancy rate of each territory averaged over the study period, given that the territory had been visited by us, (2) the rate of successful breeding at each territory, defined as the frequency of breeding events producing at least one ringed nestling, (3) mean clutch size at each territory, defined as the mean number of eggs laid in breeding attempts producing at least one egg, and (4) mean brood size at each territory, defined as the number of ringed nestlings in breeding events producing at least one nestling.</p>
  <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The field work was conducted with respect for the animals’ well-being and adheres to the Guidelines for the Use of Animals in Research
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>
   </span>. It complies with the laws and regulations for animals used in research in Norway. Ringing licenses were issued by the Norwegian Bird Ringing Centre.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analyses</div>
  <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To describe both the trend in breeding phenology and in climate, we modelled hatching date and mean spring temperature, respectively, over time with linear mixed-effects models, using year as the random intercept. In addition, mean spring temperature was used as a predictor variable to explain the variation in breeding phenology. To avoid any spurious effects due to a temporal trend in the breeding phenology and the mean spring temperature, we included the linear trend. We also explored a possible non-linear response to spring temperature by modelling hatching date in a generalised additive mixed-effects model, and compared its fit with that of the linear model using the Bayesian Information Criterion (BIC)
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>
   </span>. All statistics were performed in the program R, version 3.4.4
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>
   </span>, with add-on packages ‘lme4’
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>
   </span> for linear mixed-effects models, ‘glmmADMB’ for generalized linear mixed-effects models, ‘mgcv’
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>
   </span> for generalised additive models, ‘MuMIn’
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>
   </span> for model averaging and extracting marginal and conditional R
   <span class="sup">2</span> from mixed-effects models fitted with ‘lme4’, and ‘gamm4’
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>
   </span> for generalised additive mixed models. Apart from when using the ‘glmmADMB’ package which uses a slightly different method
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>
   </span> and apart from when performing likelihood ratio testing, mixed-effects models were fitted with maximum likelihood (ML) during model selection
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>
   </span>. For Gaussian mixed models (here as well as in the further analyses), we also estimated a measure of R
   <span class="sup">2</span> using package ‘MuMIn’ as the proportion of variance explained – at the level of the whole model (conditional R
   <span class="sup">2</span>)
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>
   </span> and at the level of fixed effects only (marginal R
   <span class="sup">2</span>) by means of variance partitioning
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
  <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To explain the variation in the timing of breeding, we evaluated the influence of each variable on breeding phenology in an explorative setting, using model-averaging in a Gaussian linear mixed-effects model selection framework, with the function ‘dredge’ in the ‘MuMIn’ package. Models were ranked according to BIC. We also calculated Bayesian weights (BIC
   <sub>w</sub>) for each candidate model, which can be interpreted as the relative probability that a given model is the best one for the observed data, given the set of candidate models
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>
   </span>. The variables we considered in the models were mean spring temperatures (Feb–Apr), altitude, distance from the coast, population density and the territory variables: overall mean territory occupancy rate, overall mean territory success rate, overall mean territory brood and clutch size. In addition, we included all two-way interactions with mean spring temperature and population density, respectively, because we were interested in potential interactions with these variables particularly. All models had the crossed (i.e. non-nested) random effects year, female and territory identity. Year was used as a random effect to capture annual variation not accounted for by the fixed effects, while female identity was needed due to the uneven contribution of individual females to the data. We also used territory identity as a random effect, because the study system contains a spatially fixed number of territories that do not change between years and are very different in occupancy rates, and, in addition, we need to capture territory-specific variation in the data. Only random intercept models were considered.
  </p>
  <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To address whether an early start of breeding resulted in higher fitness, we ran two parallel analyses using mixed-effects models. In the first one, the response variable was the brood size given the clutch size (the number of eggs), where the brood size more specifically is defined as the number of nestlings in a brood large enough to be ringed. In the second one, the response variable was the number of recruits given the brood size. We used generalized linear mixed-effects models with the function ‘glmmadmb’ in the ‘glmmADMB’ package
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>
   </span> and compared a range of likely models with the predictor variables hatching date, year, spring temperature, population density and altitude and the crossed random intercepts year, individual and territory identity, with a binomial error distribution, just as described above for the variation in the timing of breeding. A significant negative linear relationship between fitness and hatching date assumes that the earlier the better, which may be constrained by harsh conditions in very early spring; therefore, to control for a possible optimum in timing of breeding, we also included the quadratic effect of hatching day-of-year among the predictor variables.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
