<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analyses</div>
 <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To describe both the trend in breeding phenology and in climate, we modelled hatching date and mean spring temperature, respectively, over time with linear mixed-effects models, using year as the random intercept. In addition, mean spring temperature was used as a predictor variable to explain the variation in breeding phenology. To avoid any spurious effects due to a temporal trend in the breeding phenology and the mean spring temperature, we included the linear trend. We also explored a possible non-linear response to spring temperature by modelling hatching date in a generalised additive mixed-effects model, and compared its fit with that of the linear model using the Bayesian Information Criterion (BIC)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>
  </span>. All statistics were performed in the program R, version 3.4.4
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>
  </span>, with add-on packages ‘lme4’
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>
  </span> for linear mixed-effects models, ‘glmmADMB’ for generalized linear mixed-effects models, ‘mgcv’
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>
  </span> for generalised additive models, ‘MuMIn’
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>
  </span> for model averaging and extracting marginal and conditional R
  <span class="sup">2</span> from mixed-effects models fitted with ‘lme4’, and ‘gamm4’
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>
  </span> for generalised additive mixed models. Apart from when using the ‘glmmADMB’ package which uses a slightly different method
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>
  </span> and apart from when performing likelihood ratio testing, mixed-effects models were fitted with maximum likelihood (ML) during model selection
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>
  </span>. For Gaussian mixed models (here as well as in the further analyses), we also estimated a measure of R
  <span class="sup">2</span> using package ‘MuMIn’ as the proportion of variance explained – at the level of the whole model (conditional R
  <span class="sup">2</span>)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>
  </span> and at the level of fixed effects only (marginal R
  <span class="sup">2</span>) by means of variance partitioning
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To explain the variation in the timing of breeding, we evaluated the influence of each variable on breeding phenology in an explorative setting, using model-averaging in a Gaussian linear mixed-effects model selection framework, with the function ‘dredge’ in the ‘MuMIn’ package. Models were ranked according to BIC. We also calculated Bayesian weights (BIC
  <sub>w</sub>) for each candidate model, which can be interpreted as the relative probability that a given model is the best one for the observed data, given the set of candidate models
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>
  </span>. The variables we considered in the models were mean spring temperatures (Feb–Apr), altitude, distance from the coast, population density and the territory variables: overall mean territory occupancy rate, overall mean territory success rate, overall mean territory brood and clutch size. In addition, we included all two-way interactions with mean spring temperature and population density, respectively, because we were interested in potential interactions with these variables particularly. All models had the crossed (i.e. non-nested) random effects year, female and territory identity. Year was used as a random effect to capture annual variation not accounted for by the fixed effects, while female identity was needed due to the uneven contribution of individual females to the data. We also used territory identity as a random effect, because the study system contains a spatially fixed number of territories that do not change between years and are very different in occupancy rates, and, in addition, we need to capture territory-specific variation in the data. Only random intercept models were considered.
 </p>
 <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To address whether an early start of breeding resulted in higher fitness, we ran two parallel analyses using mixed-effects models. In the first one, the response variable was the brood size given the clutch size (the number of eggs), where the brood size more specifically is defined as the number of nestlings in a brood large enough to be ringed. In the second one, the response variable was the number of recruits given the brood size. We used generalized linear mixed-effects models with the function ‘glmmadmb’ in the ‘glmmADMB’ package
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>
  </span> and compared a range of likely models with the predictor variables hatching date, year, spring temperature, population density and altitude and the crossed random intercepts year, individual and territory identity, with a binomial error distribution, just as described above for the variation in the timing of breeding. A significant negative linear relationship between fitness and hatching date assumes that the earlier the better, which may be constrained by harsh conditions in very early spring; therefore, to control for a possible optimum in timing of breeding, we also included the quadratic effect of hatching day-of-year among the predictor variables.
 </p>
</sec>
