<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">There is little evidence that the major drivers of systemic biodiversity loss—disease, pollution, overexploitation, and habitat destruction—are operating in the Mojave. Invasive plants are in the Mojave, but they currently represent a small amount of cover at most of our sites and across the Mojave as a whole (
 <xref rid="r30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>) (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1805123115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <italic class="italic">SI Appendix</italic>
 </ext-link>). Instead, climate change, particularly decline in rainfall, was the most important driver of avian community dynamics in the Mojave Desert. Sites that received less precipitation in recent decades compared with early in the 20th century had higher local extinction probabilities (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" class="xref">Fig. 2</xref>). Most sites became drier (µ = −3.6%; σ = 5.9%), receiving up to 20% less precipitation. The causal relationship between precipitation and avian population dynamics has many linkages, given the widespread effects precipitation has on arid communities (
 <xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>). Dry periods can cause desert birds to operate at water deficits due to decreased access to water-rich food resources, which can negatively impact fitness (
 <xref rid="r31" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>). Reproduction and survival in many arid-land birds are positively related to precipitation, a response likely mediated through effects on food availability, predation, and nest parasitism in arid environments (
 <xref rid="r32" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r33" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>). Rainfall in the year before resurveys also had a positive relationship with local persistence, but the effect was weaker than the influence of long-term change in precipitation (
 <xref rid="t01" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref>). Even though California as a whole experienced a historic drought from 2012 to 2017, the most severe impacts occurred outside of the Mojave Desert (
 <xref rid="r34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>), and in the year before our resurveys rainfall was within normal variation (i.e., within 1 σ of 30-y averages) for all but three sites.
</p>
