<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Climate change influenced the collapse of the Mojave bird community primarily through precipitation change rather than temperature change. Long-term warming was not strongly related to avian decline, but there was an influence of maximum temperature in the year previous to resurveys (
 <xref rid="t01" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref>). Contrary to our expectations, however, community persistence was positively related to the maximum temperature in the year before resurveys, which could occur for several reasons. First, due to topographic complexity in the Mojave, there was high variability in site-level maximum temperatures in the year before resurveys (µ = 31.8 °C; σ = 5.6 °C). At high-elevation sites, warming may translate to a longer breeding season, leading to greater reproductive success (
 <xref rid="r35" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>). Second, observed temperatures may not yet be hot enough to have biological relevance. The physiological costs of heat avoidance and dissipation behaviors begin to negatively impact fitness of some desert birds when temperature exceeds 35 °C (
 <xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r36" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r37" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>); at temperatures &gt;40 °C, evaporative water loss accelerates and puts birds at risk for lethal dehydration (
 <xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>). These thermal limits were exceeded at only 26 and 9% of sites, respectively. Albright et al. (
 <xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>) suggested that body size would be an import predictor of decline and extirpation in desert bird communities based on its relationship with heat-related dehydration. Body size, however, was a poor predictor of decline in our study (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1805123115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <italic class="italic">SI Appendix</italic>, Table S3
 </ext-link>), which also supports our conclusion that the thermal environment did not appear to be a substantial contributor to Mojave bird declines.
</p>
