<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">However, there are several lines of evidence that lead us to suggest that the majority of the rapid changes observed here do stem from a geographically widespread external driver, with climate the most likely candidate. First, the year-to-year population crashes and explosions that we detected took place at a national scale (England). These are unlikely to be driven by more local factors, such as local habitat change, or local interactions between species that are unrelated to a widespread driver. Second, we found a strong positive correlation between the responses of our two groups of Lepidoptera (butterflies and moths) across years (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSTB20160144F2" class="xref">figure 2</xref>
 <italic class="italic">c</italic>), and a negative correlation between Lepidoptera and birds (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSTB20160144F2" class="xref">figure 2</xref>
 <italic class="italic">d</italic>). Given that the recording schemes for these three groups are independent, these correlations imply responses to climate events that are both geographically widespread and capable of generating between-year changes. Thirdly, the existence of statistically significant consensus years (and general agreement on whether these years are good or bad) again implies that some relatively fast-acting underlying causation is operating at the geographical scale of the whole of England. Changes in land-use and habitat management (which affect micro-climate), pesticides, the arrival of invasive species, and other drivers that contribute to longer-term trends are unlikely to act so broadly in a single year; it is only their interactions with widespread climatic factors that are likely to drive such effects [
 <xref rid="RSTB20160144C40" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>]. We conclude that most (but not all) of the extreme population crashes and explosions that we have detected stem directly or indirectly from a near-synchronous, geographically widespread process, which is most likely to be the climate.
</p>
