<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3dot1dot3-ijerph-12-15010" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1.3. Non-Public Health Perspectives on Barriers to Public Health Engagement</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In contrast, the “Non-PH” respondents identified very few barriers, and could identify numerous immediate roles for public health (described below in “3.2. Opportunities for Engagement”). However, “Non-PH” participants voiced frustration with the absence of public health agency leadership, action, and participation in contentious climate change policy-making: 
  <div class="disp-quote">
   <p>“I don’t know why public health feels that they are not allowed to do that. (A few public health leaders) are willing to stick their necks out, take political risks, and state what will happen to health with various policies.”</p>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This group of respondents believed that the compartmentalization and lack of coordination across funding streams prevents work on cross-cutting issues like climate change and health, and warned against dedicated categorical funding for climate change. One said: 
  <div class="disp-quote">
   <p>“One of the most disheartening times in the movement was when people started to just fund climate, thinking it was its own thing, but it’s connected to every issue we work on. If you’re working on clean air, on food, you’re working on climate.”</p>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Related to this, “Non-PH” participants described this as an important barrier, because: 
  <div class="disp-quote">
   <p>“
    <span class="italic">The siloed mentality also means we don’t get the big picture… this is all inter-related.”</span>
   </p>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another “Non-PH” participant agreed: 
  <div class="disp-quote">
   <p>“Part of the issue is a lack of integration and a lack of systems thinking. We look one piece at a time, but this affects us in a multitude of ways and we need to bring people together to solve these problems. We always solve one thing and create another problem, like with biofuels. There are water issues, rising food prices, even immigration problems that arise from making decisions in isolation.”</p>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
