<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">B1. Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Thank you for agreeing to meet with me/us. We are working with the Public Health Institute Center for Public Health and Climate Change on a project funded by the Kresge Foundation. We believe that climate change will pose a challenge to health and equity in the 21st century, and we also see that many climate action strategies could have very positive impacts on health. The goal of this project is to find out how to make it easier for the public health community to work on climate change, and strengthen partnerships between public health workers and others who are working on climate change. We also want to know how public health could help others working on climate change to bring a stronger health frame to their work. We are starting by speaking to people in public health, climate change, equity, planning, environmental justice, and other fields, to learn more about their work and get their ideas on what would be helpful.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We are going to ask you questions about climate change, but we know that it is not an issue that many people in public health know all that much about. So please don’t worry about whether or not your answers are “right”—for many of the questions there are no “right” answers. We are asking them so that we have a better understanding about where we should start when, later in our project, we develop some materials about climate change specifically for public health workers.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Everything you tell me will be kept confidential, unless we specifically ask for your permission to quote you. I’ll be taking notes, but only my co-investigator and I will have access to them. We will not quote you without asking specific permission.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">You should feel free at any time to ask me questions concerning the interview or the project or to decline to answer a question. Do you have any questions? OK, let’s get started.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It will help to define what we mean by public health and climate change up front.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We’re defining “public health” broadly to include the “upstream” or social, environmental and physical determinants of health, such as asthma from air pollution, housing conditions, education, income, access to healthy foods and transportation, 
  <span class="italic">etc</span>. When we talk about “public health workers” or “public health organizations”, we are talking about people both inside and outside of government that are working on any aspect of trying to improve population and community health.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When we talk about the impacts of climate change on health, we’re talking about both direct impacts like extreme heat, indirect impacts like rising food prices from drought, and the health effects of various strategies to reduce greenhouse gas emissions such as decreased air pollution from higher fuel efficiency. Also, this project is focused more on the U.S. than on international issues, even though we understand that the global impacts are very significant.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(Note: * indicates questions you can skip if pressed for time.)</p>
</sec>
