<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">B2. General Level of Awareness/Concern about Climate Change and Health</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">First, can you tell me a little about your organization, and the type of work that you do with your organization.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Let’s start talking a bit about climate change. When you hear that term, what comes to mind? Probes: 
  <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>How does that story make you feel?</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Are there any stories or things you’ve read or heard that particularly resonate for you?</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>What does this story or information make you feel?</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Why do you think it resonates for you? What is important about this?</p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Have your read or heard anything about the relationship between climate change and health or how climate change affects health? What have you heard?</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">* Are there particular things you’ve heard about climate change and health that are especially important to you? Probe: Are you concerned about a particular health endpoint, or something that impacts people’s health indirectly?</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">* How big of an issue do you think climate change is 
  <span class="underline">as a public health issue</span>? Do you think it will be a bigger issue for public health in the future? Why/why not?
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Do you ever talk about climate change with your co-workers, your staff, or your managers? Do you think they are aware of or concerned about climate change as a public health issue? Can you share any stories or examples that show their level of awareness or concern?</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">* We’re wondering what your clients or external stakeholders might think about the impacts of climate change on health. Can you give me some examples or stories that show their level of awareness or concern?</p>
</sec>
