<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3dot1dot1-ijerph-12-15010" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1.1. Public Health Perspectives on Individual-Level Constraints</div>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">Belief that Climate Change is not Urgent, Immediate, or a Priority</span> 
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The “PH engaged” respondents were, not surprisingly, highly aware of the health risks of climate change and the urgency of response. A number of these respondents from public health organizations recognized as leaders in climate change work did not feel it was a priority of their organization. The primary motivation for many “PH engaged” respondents’ engagement in climate change work is that those activities serve as a platform to address larger community health needs.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While there was interest and concern about climate change among “PH non-engaged” professionals, this group expressed less interest, urgency, or recognition of the breadth and currency of climate impacts on health, or that interventions are required now to prevent more severe future impacts. One respondent noted that the health impacts of climate change “
   <span class="italic">seem like a reach.”</span> Many of these respondents see the impacts as too distant in time and place to be of concern, “
   <span class="italic">a pervasive perception that climate change will happen in the future”,</span> although several acknowledged the need for public health response to extreme weather events. Almost all respondents—including those engaged with climate change—believe there is a lack of tangibility or immediacy to the issue; that makes it too abstract for people to engage with. For those “PH non-engaged” respondents that did perceive climate change as an immediate and urgent threat, it was not a priority for their organization or agency.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">“PH non-engaged” interviewees expressed skepticism that climate change was a pressing issue for the communities they serve, relative to gun violence, unemployment, or housing issues. One respondent pointed out: 
   <span class="italic">“We can’t expect people to think about the future if they don’t have their immediate needs met.”</span> The exception to this was “PH non-engaged” respondents working in environmental justice organizations, who highlighted the importance of environmental protection—including climate change—for the communities they represent: 
   <div class="disp-quote">
    <p>“In our community, there is a deep tie to the environment that is so dismissed: Latinos care about the environment because of the environment, not just for self-interest…People feel a strong tie with the land…We came from agrarian societies, and voters would support policies that protect water, trees, and land, even with costs associated. They understand the psychological benefits of preserving the earth, as well as the health benefits…That view is not well understood in the larger equity movement.”</p>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">Insufficient Understanding of Impacts, Connections, and Solutions</span> 
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Lack of self-efficacy emerged as a theme in several dimensions. The “PH non-engaged” respondents felt they lacked adequate information or expertise on health impacts of climate change, the health impacts of climate change planning and policies, and the connections between current public health work and climate change: 
   <div class="disp-quote">
    <p>“There is a lack of knowledge that climate change has impact across sectors…In public health, people work on one narrow issue and folks might have a hard time making the links between their public health work and climate change.”</p>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">“PH non-engaged” participants demonstrated low awareness of connections between climate change and their current work, as exemplified by these statements by three participants: 
   <div class="disp-quote">
    <p>
     <span class="italic">“We do air quality projects… I’m very familiar with the concept of co-benefits but have never thought about it with regard to climate change.”</span> And, 
     <span class="italic">“It’s uncanny how connected our work is to climate change. It’s almost coincidental. But I wouldn’t necessarily link Safe Routes to School or physical activity to climate change.”</span> Finally, 
     <span class="italic">“WIC would be active in obesity, nutrition, social and environmental determinants of nutrition, but I don’t think of it as a climate change issue. The climate change issue is what happens when the food supply gets disrupted. That is emergency preparedness.”</span>
    </p>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Other “PH non-engaged” respondents were aware of the connections between their work and climate change, but expressed distinct unease at making these links explicit with their peers, community stakeholders, or decision-makers because they are uncertain about the local impacts of climate change and how it will affect the communities they work with, One “PH non-engaged” respondent said, 
   <span class="italic">“I know it’s a big issue, but I lack data to talk to community and decision-makers at the appropriate scale.”</span> In fact, both groups of public health respondents cited a need for better down-scaling of local climate change impacts, research on community impacts, and methods to forecast local health impacts based on down-scaled climate data. Significantly, many “PH engaged” respondents also did not feel they were experts, understood only one area such as emergency preparedness, and did not think systemically or about multiple impacts.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Respondents from both public health groups expressed frustration at the difficulty of identifying specific meaningful solutions that match the scale and complexity of problem. Even respondents who understand that their own work may help to address climate change expressed skepticism about the effectiveness of their role: 
   <span class="italic">“The work of climate change gives me an overwhelmed feeling. I have a cynical feeling, like how much could it help, promoting Safe Routes to Schools?”</span>
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
