<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="Fig2" class="fig">
 <label class="label">Figure 2</label>
 <caption class="caption">
  <p class="p">Occurrence of brown bear bone remains and their detection probability in archaeofaunal records across Europe. (
   <bold class="bold">a</bold>,
   <bold class="bold">b</bold>), Brown bear detection probability estimated by the metapopulation model (
   <bold class="bold">a</bold>) as a function of the total number of bone remains of red deer (
   <italic class="italic">Cervus elaphus</italic>), roe deer (
   <italic class="italic">Capreolus capreolus</italic>) and brown bear per record, and (
   <bold class="bold">b</bold>) as a function of the type of excavation site. The model estimated detection probability based on whether or not brown bear bone remains had been detected in (
   <bold class="bold">c</bold>) archaeofaunal records on a 100 × 100 km
   <sup class="sup">2</sup> grid over Europe during the past 12,000 years. Records containing red deer or roe deer, but not brown bear, served as negative controls, because both deer species were typical elements of the European fauna during the Holocene and the most frequent prey of European Stone Age hunters
   <sup class="sup">
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" class="xref">25</xref>, 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" class="xref">26</xref>
   </sup>. This approach allowed us to account for imperfect detection in the archaeofaunal record, while simultaneously modelling the spatiotemporal variation in brown bear extinction and colonization rates across the European continent. Brown bear bone remains were present in 27% of the archaeofaunal records. The probability of detection increased with the total number of bone remains contained in a record (
   <bold class="bold">a</bold>), and was highest in records associated with burial sites (
   <bold class="bold">b</bold>), which reflects rituals and beliefs associated with bears in human cultures in the northern hemisphere
   <sup class="sup">
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" class="xref">55</xref>
   </sup>. (
   <bold class="bold">c</bold>) The distribution of the archaeofaunal records (
   <italic class="italic">n</italic> = 4,177) and the grid (cell size: 100 × 100 km
   <sup class="sup">2</sup>) that was used for the metapopulation model. Ticks in (
   <bold class="bold">a</bold>), and circles in (
   <bold class="bold">c</bold>) represent individual archaeofaunal records with (blue) and without (red) remains of brown bears. In (
   <bold class="bold">a</bold>), the black line represents the median model fit; the gray shade depicts the 95% credible interval from the posterior distribution. In (
   <bold class="bold">b</bold>), the violins represent the density distributions of estimated detection probability for each site type. The map in (
   <bold class="bold">c</bold>) was created with the statistical programming language 
   <italic class="italic">R</italic>
   <sup class="sup">
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" class="xref">68</xref>
   </sup> using the package 
   <italic class="italic">rworldxtra</italic>
   <sup class="sup">
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73" class="xref">73</xref>
   </sup>.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="41598_2017_10772_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e577" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
