<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec002" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec id="sec003" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Case description</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Five million students are enrolled in public schools in Canada, with approximately 350 000 students graduating from secondary school in a typical year [
   <a rid="pone.0218305.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref029">29</a>]. Canada is divided into ten provinces and three territories, each of which controls its own educational system. (As the territories are sparsely populated and mostly borrow educational materials from nearby provinces, in this paper we sometimes reference only “provinces” for the sake of simplicity). Education can vary between the provinces, resulting in different curriculum documents, standardized tests, teacher education programs and so forth. Within these educational systems, science is split into ‘silo’ subjects; chemistry, biology and physics are common, while earth and space science or environmental science are less likely to be present at all grade levels. Teachers at the secondary level are subject specialists, meaning they are trained to teach a few specific subjects, rather than all subjects. Amongst science teachers, for example, some are qualified to teach chemistry, but not biology or physics. This is important for climate change, which is not a ‘silo’ subject, but is instead interdisciplinary in nature.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec004" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Curriculum analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to analyze the high school science curricula from the 13 Canadian provinces and territories, we grouped learning objectives into six core topics (see 
   <a rid="pone.0218305.t001" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0218305.t001">Table 1</a>) associated with statements from the IPCC Fifth Assessment report [
   <a rid="pone.0218305.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref030">30</a>]. The IPCC makes use of a rigorous peer review process featuring 600 authors and several rounds of review, which is why it is regarded as the most reputable source of scientific understanding on climate change [
   <a rid="pone.0218305.ref031" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref031">31</a>]. Understanding of five of the six core topics has also been associated with support for climate change mitigation policies (see 
   <a rid="pone.0218305.t001" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0218305.t001">Table 1</a>). The topics include: foundational knowledge of the physical climate system (abbreviated as “It’s climate”), observations and proxies of rising temperature (“It’s warming”), anthropogenic contributions to climate change (“It’s us”), the scientific process of obtaining consensus (“Experts agree”), the various impacts associated with climate change (“It’s bad”), and the approaches and policies that can be used for mitigation (“We can fix it”).
  </p>
  <div id="pone.0218305.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0218305.t001</span>
   <span class="label">Table 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <div class="title">Framework for evaluating the scope of climate change knowledge addressed by secondary school curriculum documents.</div>
    <p>The first topic was added based on identifying widespread coverage in teaching materials after [
     <a rid="pone.0218305.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref030">30</a>]. The remaining five topics are summarized from research on public attitude and policy preferences [
     <a rid="pone.0218305.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref034">34</a>], with wording modified by comments on social media [
     <a rid="pone.0218305.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref035">35</a>].
    </p>
   </div>
   <div class="alternatives">
    <div id="pone.0218305.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0218305.t001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
     <colgroup span="1">
      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
     </colgroup>
     <thead>
      <tr>
       <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Core Topic</th>
       <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Evidence</th>
       <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Evidence for effectiveness of this message in behaviour/attitude change</th>
       <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Example of relevant learning objective</th>
      </tr>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">It’s climate</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Well-established physical principles, e.g., heat-trapping effects of greenhouse gases</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N/A</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Outline factors influencing the Earth’s radiation budget. (Manitoba Gr. 10 Science, S2-4-02)</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">It’s warming</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Globally averaged land and ocean temperature increased by 0.85°C from 1880 to 2012, based on multiple, independent datasets [
        <a rid="pone.0218305.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref036">36</a>]. More recent estimates are for approximately 1.0°C of global warming above pre-industrial levels [
        <a rid="pone.0218305.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref021">21</a>].
       </td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[
        <a rid="pone.0218305.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref034">34</a>]
        <span class="break"/>[
        <a rid="pone.0218305.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref037">37</a>]
        <span class="break"/>[
        <a rid="pone.0218305.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref038">38</a>]
       </td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Conduct an inquiry to determine how different factors (e.g., an increase in surface temperature, an increase in water temperature) affect global warming and climate change (Ontario Gr. 10 Science, D2.4)</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">It’s us</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Humans are the main cause of current warming, 95% certainty [
        <a rid="pone.0218305.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref036">36</a>]
       </td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[
        <a rid="pone.0218305.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref034">34</a>]
        <span class="break"/>[
        <a rid="pone.0218305.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref037">37</a>]
        <span class="break"/>[
        <a rid="pone.0218305.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref038">38</a>]
       </td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Provide examples of human actions that have contributed to the anthropogenic greenhouse effect. (Saskatchewan Gr. 10 Science, SCI10-CD1g)</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Experts agree</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zero out of 928 peer reviewed studies denied human role in climate change [
        <a rid="pone.0218305.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref016">16</a>]
        <span class="break"/>Degree of certainty in human role in climate change increases with increasing expertise [
        <a rid="pone.0218305.ref018" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref018">18</a>]
        <span class="break"/>97% of 11944 peer-reviewed abstracts support human role in climate change [
        <a rid="pone.0218305.ref017" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref017">17</a>]
       </td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[
        <a rid="pone.0218305.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref039">39</a>]
        <span class="break"/>[
        <a rid="pone.0218305.ref040" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref040">40</a>]
        <span class="break"/>[
        <a rid="pone.0218305.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref037">37</a>]
       </td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Examine the role of policies, summits, models, and organizations … in obtaining a high degree of consensus among scientists regarding anthropogenic climate change. (Saskatchewan Environmental Science 20, ES20-AS2c)</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">It’s bad</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cost of 5–10% of annual global GDP if climate change unchecked [
        <a rid="pone.0218305.ref041" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref041">41</a>]
        <span class="break"/>Extreme heat events will become more frequent and global sea level will continue to rise [
        <a rid="pone.0218305.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref036">36</a>]
        <span class="break"/>”extinction risks will accelerate with future global temperatures,
        <span class="break"/>threatening up to one in six species” [
        <a rid="pone.0218305.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref042">42</a>]
       </td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[
        <a rid="pone.0218305.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref034">34</a>]
        <span class="break"/>[
        <a rid="pone.0218305.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref038">38</a>]
       </td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Describe the impacts of climate change in Canada on human health. Include: (i) heat stress (ii) migration of diseases (Newfoundland and Labrador Environmental Science 3205, 5.24)</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">We can fix it</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">“CO
        <sub>2</sub> emissions reductions that limit global warming to 1.5°C with no or limited overshoot can involve different portfolios of
        <span class="break"/>mitigation measures, striking different balances between lowering energy and resource intensity, rate of decarbonization,
        <span class="break"/>and the reliance on carbon dioxide removal” [
        <a rid="pone.0218305.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref021">21</a>]
        <span class="break"/>Barriers to 100% conversion to wind, water and solar energy are mostly political and social not technical [
        <a rid="pone.0218305.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref043">43</a>]
       </td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">[
        <a rid="pone.0218305.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref034">34</a>]
        <span class="break"/>[
        <a rid="pone.0218305.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref038">38</a>]
        <span class="break"/>[
        <a rid="pone.0218305.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref044">44</a>]
       </td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Assess, on the basis of research, the effectiveness of some current individual, regional, national, or international initiatives that address the issue of climate change (Ontario Gr. 10 Science, D1.2)</td>
      </tr>
     </tbody>
    </table>
   </div>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To summarize the current scientific consensus on climate change: warming of the climate is unequivocal [
   <a rid="pone.0218305.ref031" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref031">31</a>] and its human cause has been established by exhaustive analyses of scientific literature and the scientific community [
   <a rid="pone.0218305.ref032" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref032">32</a>]. While some regions and sectors may experience slight benefits from climate change, a review of 3280 research papers concluded the overwhelming impacts on human and natural systems are negative and that the “small set of positive and neutral impacts cannot counterbalance any of the many detrimental impacts that were uncovered in our literature search, particularly when many of these impacts are related to the loss of human lives, basic supplies such as food and water, and undesired states for human welfare such as access to jobs, revenue and security” [
   <a rid="pone.0218305.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref033">33</a>]. In terms of human health for instance, the IPCC projects that “Any increase in global warming is projected to affect human health, with primarily negative consequences” [
   <a rid="pone.0218305.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref021">21</a>]. Looking ahead, staying below the internationally agreed temperature targets will reduce risks and requires deep cuts in greenhouse gas emissions within the coming decade [
   <a rid="pone.0218305.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref021">21</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To determine the extent to which different provinces were covering the current state of climate change knowledge (Column 1 of 
   <a rid="pone.0218305.t001" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0218305.t001">Table 1</a>), we read all high school science curriculum documents, and divided their relevant learning objectives into the six core topics. Learning objectives were not included if climate change was referenced as only one of several possible examples. For instance, in the Gr. 12 University/College Science Preparation course (SNC4M), one learning objective says, “explain the impact of various threats to public health, including infectious diseases (e.g., hepatitis, HIV/AIDS, tuberculosis, malaria, sexually transmitted diseases), chronic diseases (e.g., cardiovascular disease, diabetes, asthma), and environmental factors (e.g., climate change, air pollution, chemical pollutants, radiation)” [
   <a rid="pone.0218305.ref045" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref045">45</a>]. Although climate change is listed as a threat to public health (a statement that could fall under “It’s Bad”), in this case, because a teacher could choose many other examples to meet the objective instead, it did not count in our assessment. Similarly, if climate change was mentioned in supporting documentation (suggested resources, optional activities etc.), it was not counted towards any of the categories. Lastly, we noted when a course was mandatory for graduation from secondary school, or merely optional.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Canada has a parliamentary democratic system, with five major political parties in government as of early 2019. The parties range from the Conservative Party of Canada (CPC), whose leadership candidates mostly argue against climate change mitigation measures [
   <a rid="pone.0218305.ref046" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref046">46</a>], to the Green Party of Canada who propose halting expansion of the country’s lucrative oil sands [
   <a rid="pone.0218305.ref047" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref047">47</a>]. More generally, the strength of Green Parties in democratic systems has been found to have a positive effect on measurable environmental indicators such as air quality [
   <a rid="pone.0218305.ref048" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref048">48</a>] while political conservativism has been associated with lower levels of environmental concern [
   <a rid="pone.0218305.ref049" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref049">49</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0218305.ref050" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref050">50</a>] and lower levels of concern for climate change, even across different nations [
   <a rid="pone.0218305.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref014">14</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0218305.ref051" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref051">51</a>]. We therefore compared the provincial coverage of climate change in the curricula documents with the per capita greenhouse gas (GHG) emissions of the provinces, as well as with the breakdown of votes in the last federal election to search for indications that political forces influenced curriculum design. In undertaking this analysis, we suspected that certain provinces with a history of fossil fuel extraction (e.g. Alberta, Saskatchewan) would have less coverage of climate change in their curricula than provinces that have enacted climate policies such as a carbon tax (e.g. British Columbia, Ontario).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec005" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Curriculum development</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To gain a better understanding of the cause of differences between the provincial curricula, we asked contributors to each of the province’s science curriculum to participate in interviews. In total, representatives from six of the ten provinces agreed to interview. Interviewees included both contributing teachers as well as science consultants. Although the study scope exempted it from Swedish requirements for formal ethical review by an institutional review board, all procedures performed in this study involving human participants were in accordance with the ethical standards of the institution, and with the 1964 Helsinki declaration and its later amendments or comparable ethical standards. Prior, written informed consent was obtained from all individual participants included in the study (See consent form in 
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0218305.s001" href="#pone.0218305.s001">S1 Text</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The interviews were semi-structured, with questions provided beforehand to encourage thoughtful responses as some questions were difficult or referred to events that took place several years in the past (see 
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0218305.s002" href="#pone.0218305.s002">S2 Text</a> for interview questions). One potential explanation for provinces having dissimilar approaches to climate change could be that political differences between provinces result in different outcomes. For instance, in the United States, controversial issues such as evolution often result in school board policies or statewide educational legislation that causes education to differ greatly between jurisdictions [
   <a rid="pone.0218305.ref052" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref052">52</a>]. Additionally, the curriculum could be politically influenced without legislative force; internal political pressure from high-ranking public officials, NGOs, or concerned parents or members of the public might also result in more or less coverage of climate change (for instance). Interviewees were therefore asked if any political controversies around climate change affected their curriculum writing process. Further questions explored other possibilities for differences between provincial coverage of climate change, such as the use of government documents, the way in which curriculum writers are selected, the time period in which the curriculum was written, and the overall curriculum design process.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The interviews lasted approximately thirty minutes and were conducted via telephone or Skype depending on the preference of the interviewee, with one interviewee choosing to respond in written form. Interviews were recorded and then transcribed with pseudonyms and with identifying information removed. Transcripts of the interviews were provided to the interviewees. Those parts which would be used as quotations in the final publication were indicated separately for interviewees who then approved the accuracy of each quotation. Thematic analysis was used to analyze the interview transcripts, according to guidelines provided by Bryman [
   <a rid="pone.0218305.ref053" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref053">53</a>]. Following transcription of the recordings we tentatively identified common themes from the interviews. Some themes were simply straightforward responses to questions (such as whether controversy on the subject of climate change affected the curriculum design), while others were unsolicited ideas such as the need to teach about sustainability. We arranged the themes as rows in a spreadsheet and pasted relevant interviewee quotations into adjacent columns. While this type of qualitative analysis with a small sample does not definitively indicate trends, nonetheless we report when many of the interviewees responded in similar ways to the same question or mentioned similar themes without prompting, as an indication of which trends or practices were more salient in the curriculum design process.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec006" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Controversies in textbooks and curricula</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Having assessed the coverage of six topics in research question 1, we then analyzed curricula and textbooks to see how any controversies around climate change were presented. Analysis of curriculum documents for controversy occurred while recording coverage of the six core topics. Textbooks offer greater detail than curriculum documents and therefore can give further indication of the content being communicated to students. Ten textbooks used in seven Canadian provinces were therefore analyzed. Difficulties in obtaining texts used by the provinces of Alberta, Manitoba, and Nova Scotia prevented analysis of texts representing those areas, while the three territories make use of provincial resources that were included in our analysis. Those chapters pertaining to climate change were read in their entirety, and statements which encouraged debate or controversy on the subject of climate change were noted, with examples described below.</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
