<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">To our knowledge, we have developed the first global-level model for estimating future climate change–attributable stunting in which climate change acts through two interacting socioeconomic drivers: incomes of the bottom 20% of a population and food price relative to incomes. Previous global-level undernutrition models have focused on changed food production and calorie availability in fixed socioeconomic conditions (e.g., 
 <xref rid="c25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lloyd et al. 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="c33" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Nelson et al. 2010</xref>). Such models provide insights into a key influence on future undernutrition while placing other influences in the background. Previous work has also suggested that socioeconomic conditions play a major role in shaping future undernutrition (e.g., 
 <xref rid="c26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lloyd et al. 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="c42" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Schmidhuber and Tubiello 2007</xref>): our model attempts to offer new insights by focusing on two of these conditions while placing other influences in the background. Incomes of the poorest groups and food prices are likely to play a central role in shaping future undernutrition (
 <xref rid="c28" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Mazoyer and Roudart 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="c36" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Pogge 2010</xref>). In rural areas, smallholder farms (i.e., farms 
 <inline-formula class="inline-formula">
  <math id="M187" class="math">
   <mrow class="mrow">
    <mo class="mo">&lt;</mo>
    <mn class="mn">2</mn>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> hectares) are “home to about two billion people, including half the world’s undernourished people and the majority of people living in absolute poverty” (
 <xref rid="c19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">IFAD 2011</xref>). The urban poor are also at high risk of undernutrition and to the impacts of price and financial shocks (
 <xref rid="c41" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ruel et al. 2010</xref>).
</p>
