<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Carbon and nitrogen buried in sediment is a mixture between that originating from terrestrial ecosystems (termed as an allochthonous source) and that produced by primary production in lakes (termed as an autochthonous source) [
 <xref rid="B8-ijerph-15-02734" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. Allochthonous source input is controlled by human activities such as deforestation, urbanization, and the construction of reservoirs [
 <xref rid="B13-ijerph-15-02734" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. Allochthonous sources are related to productivity in lakes, which are affected by nutrient loading [
 <xref rid="B14-ijerph-15-02734" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. Therefore, identifying the changes of organic matter sources in sediment is important in understanding the historical change in the trophic status of a lake and its driving factors. Geochemical proxies such as the C/N ratio and the δ
 <sup class="sup">13</sup>C and δ
 <sup class="sup">15</sup>N values of organic matter in sediment can provide reliable paleo-environmental information [
 <xref rid="B2-ijerph-15-02734" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-ijerph-15-02734" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>] and have been widely used to identify organic matter sources in lakes. Different sources of organic matter are characterized by different C/N ratios. Autochthonous organic sources, such as algae, are marked by high protein content and low ratios of C/N, ranging from 3 to 8 [
 <xref rid="B27-ijerph-15-02734" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>]. Allochthonous sources, such as C3 and C4 land plants, are characterized by an abundance of cellulose and high C/N ratios (&gt;20) [
 <xref rid="B2-ijerph-15-02734" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. The range of carbon isotopic composition in organic matter shows an overlap between various sources where the typical range of δ
 <sup class="sup">13</sup>C values is −30‰ to −20‰ for algae in lake, −32‰ to −20‰ for C3 land plants and −15‰ to −10‰ for C4 land plants [
 <xref rid="B28-ijerph-15-02734" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>]. Even though δ
 <sup class="sup">13</sup>C values overlap, the different δ
 <sup class="sup">13</sup>C values of C3 land plants can be combined and used with the C/N ratios to assess the relative contribution of organic matter sources in sediment from lake-derived and terrestrial organic matter [
 <xref rid="B29-ijerph-15-02734" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>]. The δ
 <sup class="sup">15</sup>N value is also a widely used proxy to identify the sources of organic matter in sediment because of the difference in nitrogen availability for terrestrial plants and in-lake phytoplankton. Terrestrial plants that utilize nitrogen fixed by N
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>-fixer in soil are characterized by low δ
 <sup class="sup">15</sup>N values, with a mean value of 0‰ [
 <xref rid="B28-ijerph-15-02734" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>]. N
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>-fixing cyanobacteria in lakes using N
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> from the atmosphere have a similar value of 0‰ [
 <xref rid="B30-ijerph-15-02734" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>]. Nitrate is the most commonly utilized form of dissolved inorganic nitrogen (DIN) for non-N
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> fixing algae, which is mobile and easily exported from the terrestrial landscape. Nitrate originating from agricultural runoff and animal sewage are marked by typical isotopically heavy nitrogen (δ
 <sup class="sup">15</sup>N = +10 to +25‰) [
 <xref rid="B31-ijerph-15-02734" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>], which can elevate δ
 <sup class="sup">15</sup>N values in algae and organic matter. However, few studies have simultaneously utilized all three proxies to identify carbon and nitrogen burial variation and source changes in lake sediment and further provide a robust description of the driving factors on burial rates from climate change and human activities.
</p>
