<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s1" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1.</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A brief history—the Blue Carbon concept</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Research on different processes of the marine carbon cycle was already 100 years old in 1944 [
  <a rid="RSBL20180781C1" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSBL20180781C1">1</a>]. They focused predominantly on the contribution of oceanic phytoplankton, which still prevail in the current depictions of the global carbon cycle [
  <a rid="RSBL20180781C2" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSBL20180781C2">2</a>]. Earlier, however, in 1914 [
  <a rid="RSBL20180781C3" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSBL20180781C3">3</a>] some scientists concluded that seagrass (
  <span class="italic">Zostera marina</span>) contributed most of the carbon stocks in Danish coastal sediments, while others drew attention to the role of macrophytes as global carbon sinks [
  <a rid="RSBL20180781C4" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSBL20180781C4">4</a>], and provided a first estimate of their global contribution to carbon storage [
  <a rid="RSBL20180781C5" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSBL20180781C5">5</a>] and burial [
  <a rid="RSBL20180781C6" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSBL20180781C6">6</a>]. Two highly influential reports built on these and other advances in science and policy to describe what they called ‘Blue Carbon’. The volume by Nelleman 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. entitled 
  <span class="italic">Blue Carbon. The role of healthy oceans in binding carbon. A rapid response assessment</span>, gave us a very broad definition of Blue Carbon, starting with the following statement: ‘Out of all the biological carbon (or green carbon) captured in the world, over half (55%) is captured by marine living organisms—not on land—hence it is called Blue Carbon’ [
  <a rid="RSBL20180781C7" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSBL20180781C7">7</a>, p. 6]. The volume by Laffoley &amp; Grimsditch entitled 
  <span class="italic">The management of natural coastal carbon sinks</span> recognized the role of marine organisms in the capture of CO
  <sub>2</sub> within marine ecosystems, but took a pragmatic approach aiming to ‘…quantify the greenhouse gas implications of the management of particular coastal ecosystems, being careful to choose those whose management can be influenced by the application of existing policy agreements and well established area-based management tools and approaches’ [
  <a rid="RSBL20180781C8" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSBL20180781C8">8, p. 1</a>]. Underlying both these reports is the concept that marine ecosystems are important for CO
  <sub>2</sub> capture from the atmosphere. Both documents clearly articulated the imperative to focus on conserving and repairing marine ecosystems that contribute to this role, thereby avoiding CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions associated with their destruction and restoring their CO
  <sub>2</sub> capture potential, which would also reinstate many important ecosystem services these ecosystems provide.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The multifaceted nature of the Blue Carbon concept has led to a rich, varied and cross-disciplinary research that spans biophysical sciences, conservation, economics, policy and law (see this issue), leading to unprecedented levels of collaboration among contributors in different disciplines, institutions and governments geared toward conserving and restoring coastal ecosystems to mitigate greenhouse gas emissions, promote coastal adaptation to climate change and maintain ecosystem services. However, the multifaceted nature of Blue Carbon has also contributed to confusion and misunderstandings as to what Blue Carbon really is. The study of marine carbon stocks and cycles is important but is only a component of the Blue Carbon concept. The similarity, but divergent emphases of the two early reports [
  <a rid="RSBL20180781C7" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSBL20180781C7">7</a>,
  <a rid="RSBL20180781C8" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSBL20180781C8">8</a>] has propagated over the science and policy landscape as interest in Blue Carbon has grown and there are increasing numbers of contributors with new ideas entering into the discourse.
 </p>
</sec>
