<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s3" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ecosystems where Blue Carbon stocks and sequestration rates are being explored (emerging)</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While progress continues in the development of Blue Carbon projects in mangroves, tidal marshes and seagrass, there is debate as to whether other ecosystems, beyond angiosperm-dominated coastal ecosystems, are Blue Carbon ecosystems. Key criteria from 
  <a rid="RSBL20180781TB1" ref-type="table" href="#RSBL20180781TB1">table 1</a> can be used to guide research (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSBL20180781F1" href="#RSBL20180781F1">figure 1</a>), including whether these habitats can be managed to contribute to climate change mitigation and, if so, can outcomes be achieved through conservation that has adaptation benefits. Habitats dominated by calcifying organisms (e.g. coral reefs, oyster reefs) contribute to climate change adaptation, through energy dissipation and contribution to sediments, but not through greenhouse gas mitigation, as the process of calcification releases CO
  <sub>2</sub> and thus these ecosystems are likely to be net CO
  <sub>2</sub> sources rather than sinks [
  <a rid="RSBL20180781C20" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSBL20180781C20">20</a>]. However, future research on the role of calcifying organisms in organic matter sequestration could alter this view in the future. Pelagic ecosystems, including those with mobile marine fauna and phytoplankton, have also been suggested to be included as Blue Carbon ecosystems. Their contribution to climate change mitigation through long-term carbon preservation is uncertain and they do not contribute to climate change adaptation. Phytoplankton have been proposed to be used for climate change mitigation since the mid-1990s when the first ocean fertilization experiments were conducted [
  <a rid="RSBL20180781C21" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSBL20180781C21">21</a>]. Fertilizing the ocean with iron to stimulate the production of phytoplankton biomass which then sinks beyond the thermocline to be stored for thousands of years has been controversial mainly because evidence that a large amount of fixed carbon reaches the deep sea is equivocal and because a range of adverse, unintended consequences have been identified [
  <a rid="RSBL20180781C22" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSBL20180781C22">22</a>]. 
  <div id="RSBL20180781F1" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 1.</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Questions to establish research needs for emerging Blue Carbon ecosystems. GHG, greenhouse gas.</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="rsbl20180781-g1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Other coastal ecosystems that are considered as Blue Carbon ecosystems include tidally influenced freshwater forests, for example, bald cypress forests and 
  <span class="italic">Melaleuca</span> forests, which can have huge soil carbon stocks in their soils and which have been greatly reduced in cover [
  <a rid="RSBL20180781C23" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSBL20180781C23">23</a>]. Sabkhas, which comprise high intertidal salt flats dominated by microbial mats and which can be extensive in arid environments [
  <a rid="RSBL20180781C24" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSBL20180781C24">24</a>], may also be candidates for Blue Carbon-based conservation although information on C stocks and fluxes is currently limited as is information on their role in adaptation to climate change. Kelp and other seaweed beds are also being considered as Blue Carbon ecosystems [
  <a rid="RSBL20180781C25" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSBL20180781C25">25</a>]. There is evidence that seaweeds produce highly recalcitrant compounds [
  <a rid="RSBL20180781C26" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSBL20180781C26">26</a>] and that organic carbon may be buried in sediments or transported to the deep sea and thus stored for thousands of years [
  <a rid="RSBL20180781C25" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSBL20180781C25">25</a>]. In addition to conserving wild kelp beds, seaweed aquaculture offers opportunities for climate change mitigation and adaptation [
  <a rid="RSBL20180781C27" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSBL20180781C27">27</a>]. However, seaweeds and phytoplankton necessitate a different approach to those typically involved in established Blue Carbon ecosystems as they involve management of the fate of the carbon they produce and the locations in which carbon accumulates, which may be distant from the sites of production (e.g. in deep water) [
  <a rid="RSBL20180781C28" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSBL20180781C28">28</a>]. A key step in moving forward to including these ecosystems as Blue Carbon ecosystems is to provide enhanced scientific evidence of carbon storage, how it can be managed and also policy guidance on how the ecosystems may be included in greenhouse gas accounting.
 </p>
</sec>
