<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>This study was conducted in western South America between 25° and 47° latitude, on 142 species from six plant genera: 
 <italic>Chaetanthera</italic> (Asteraceae), 
 <italic>Eriosyce</italic> (Cactaceae), 
 <italic>Malesherbia</italic> (Passifloraceae), 
 <italic>Schizanthus</italic> and 
 <italic>Nolana</italic> (Solanaceae), and 
 <italic>Leucocoryne</italic> (Alliaceae). These genera have received substantial attention by botanists (
 <xref rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr">Gengler-Nowak, 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-38" ref-type="bibr">Meudt &amp; Simpson, 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-45" ref-type="bibr">Pérez, Arroyo &amp; Medel, 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-17" ref-type="bibr">Dillon et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr">Davies, 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-25" ref-type="bibr">Guerrero et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-26" ref-type="bibr">Guerrero, Durán &amp; Walter, 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-33" ref-type="bibr">Jara-Arancio et al., 2014</xref>), meaning that good occurrence data are available. To characterize climatic niches and to estimate species distributions, we used the occurrence data obtained directly from a Chilean herbaria (CONC, Herbarium University of Concepción and SGO, National Museum of Natural History), the literature (
 <xref rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr">Guerrero et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-33" ref-type="bibr">Jara-Arancio et al., 2014</xref>), field trips, and other databases (i.e., the PhD thesis of 
 <xref rid="ref-76" ref-type="bibr">Meudt, 2004</xref>). Bioclimatic variables were obtained from Worldclim (
 <xref rid="ref-31" ref-type="bibr">Hijmans et al., 2005</xref>). To select variables, we performed a Pearson correlation analysis in ENMTools (
 <xref rid="ref-68" ref-type="bibr">Warren, Glor &amp; Turelli, 2010</xref>), discarding those variables correlated by over 0.9. A total of 10 variables were retained: mean diurnal range, isothermality, temperature seasonality, maximum temperature of the warmest month, minimum temperature of the coldest month, precipitation seasonality, precipitation of the wettest quarter, precipitation of the driest quarter, precipitation of the warmest quarter, and precipitation of the coldest quarter. The resolution of all climatic layers was 1 km
 <sup>2</sup>. Managing climatic layers was performed with ArcGIS v. 10.0 (Esri, Redlands, CA, USA).
</p>
