<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Weakened Atlantic Niño–Pacific connection in future climate</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We compare the Atlantic Niño–Pacific connection in the 17 selected models between the present period and the future period (2000–2099). There is no consistent change in variability of Atlantic Niño (fig. S5). For each period, we regress grid-point SST anomalies onto the Atl-EOF index, yielding the response of the equatorial Pacific grid-point SST (D0JF1), per SD of the Atl-EOF time series. We obtain an average of regression coefficients over the grid points with statistically significant correlation coefficients above the 95% confidence level (see “Sign-dependent average” section in Materials and Methods). A total of 13 of 17 selected models, or 76%, generate a reduced response (
  <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2A</a>). Aggregated over the 17 models, there is a reduction of 47.8%, from −0.178°C SD
  <span class="sup">−1</span> in the present-day climate to −0.093°C SD
  <span class="sup">−1</span> in the future climate. This reduction is statistically significant above the 99% confidence level, according to the bootstrap method (see “Bootstrap test” section in Materials and Methods) (fig. S6A), supported by a comparison in the evolution of the Atlantic Niño–Pacific connection for the two periods (fig. S4), showing a conspicuous weakening in the connection.
 </p>
 <div id="F2" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Projected decrease in the Atlantic Niño–Pacific connection.</div>
   <p>(
    <span class="bold">A</span>) Comparison of the Pacific SST response (°C per SD) over the present-day (1900–1999; blue bars) and future (2000–2099; orange bars) 100-year periods in the 17 selected models. The four models that simulate an increase in response are grayed out. Error bars in the multimodel mean are calculated as 2 SDs (a 95% confidence interval based on normal distribution) of the 10,000 inter-realizations of a bootstrap method (see “Bootstrap test” section in Materials and Methods). The Pacific SST response is measured by regression coefficients of grid-point D0JF1 equatorial Pacific (5°S to 5°N and 160°E to 90°W) SST anomalies onto the Atl-EOF index (see “Sign-dependent average” section in Materials and Methods). (
    <span class="bold">B</span> and 
    <span class="bold">C</span>) Comparison of the occurrence ratio of Atlantic Niño (Atl-EOF index &gt; 0.5 SD) followed by La Niña (Niño3.4 index &lt; −1 SD) over the total Atlantic Niño events (B) and that of Atlantic Niña (Atl-EOF index &lt; −0.5 SD) followed by El Niño (Niño3.4 index &gt;1 SD) over the total Atlantic Niña events (C) over the present-day (1900–1999; 
    <span class="italic">x</span> axis) and future (2000–2099; 
    <span class="italic">y</span> axis) 100-year periods in the 17 selected models. Numbers in the top left (bottom right) indicate the number of models that produce stronger (weaker) impact of Atlantic Niño/Niña on ENSO under future climate.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="aax4111-F2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The reduced connection translates to a general reduction in Atlantic Niño/Niña events that are followed by Pacific Niña/Niño events. Using 0.5 SD as a threshold to define Atlantic Niño (|Atl-EOF index| &gt; 0.5 SD) events and 1.0 SD to define ENSO (|Niño3.4| &gt; 1.0 SD), most models generate a decreased occurrence ratio of Atlantic Niño (Niña) followed by La Niña (El Niño) in future climate (
  <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2, B and C</a>). This reduction generally translates into a decreased occurrence ratio in future climate in terms of Atlantic Niño followed by strong La Niña or Atlantic Niña followed by strong El Niño (fig. S6, B and C), in which a strong El Niño and strong La Niña is defined as when the amplitude of SST anomalies in their respective centers are greater than 1.5 and 1.75 SDs, respectively (see “E-index and C-index” section in Materials and Methods, describing SST variability at eastern Pacific for strong El Niño and at central Pacific for strong La Niña). Thus, the projected increase in frequency of strong El Niño and La Niña events under greenhouse warming, reported by other studies (
  <a rid="R26" ref-type="bibr" href="#R26">
   <span class="italic">26</span>
  </a>–
  <a rid="R28" ref-type="bibr" href="#R28">
   <span class="italic">28</span>
  </a>), occurs despite a decreased influence from the Atlantic, reinforcing the role of the future mean state changes of the Pacific Ocean in the projected ENSO changes (
  <a rid="R26" ref-type="bibr" href="#R26">
   <span class="italic">26</span>
  </a>–
  <a rid="R28" ref-type="bibr" href="#R28">
   <span class="italic">28</span>
  </a>).
 </p>
</sec>
