<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="materials|methods" disp-level="1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">MATERIALS AND METHODS</div>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Observed and CMIP5 data</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The observed monthly SST, three-dimensional oceanic temperature and atmospheric fields (three-dimensional velocities and precipitation) were from the Hadley Centre Sea Ice and Sea Surface Temperature dataset (HadISST; 1900–2017) (
   <a rid="R31" ref-type="bibr" href="#R31">
    <span class="italic">31</span>
   </a>), the Ocean Reanalysis System version 4 (ORAS4; 1976–2015) (
   <a rid="R32" ref-type="bibr" href="#R32">
    <span class="italic">32</span>
   </a>), and the National Center for Environmental Prediction (NCEP)/National Center for Atmospheric Research (NCAR) reanalysis 1 (1976–2015) (
   <a rid="R33" ref-type="bibr" href="#R33">
    <span class="italic">33</span>
   </a>), respectively. We analyzed 33 CMIP5 models’ historical simulations over the 1900–1999 period (present-day climate) and RCP8.5 experiments over the 2000–2099 period (future climate) (table S2) (
   <a rid="R34" ref-type="bibr" href="#R34">
    <span class="italic">34</span>
   </a>). The former runs were forced by the observed atmospheric composition in the 20th century, and the latter experiments were forced by an escalating radiative force throughout the 21st century (reaching approximately 8.5 W m
   <span class="sup">−2</span> in 2100).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">EOF analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To depict the Atlantic Niño unique to each model, we applied an EOF analysis to quadratically detrended JJA0 SST anomalies of tropical Atlantic (20°S to 20°N and 60°W to 20°E) to capture the observed and modeled Atlantic Niño (
   <a rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" href="#R3">
    <span class="italic">3</span>
   </a>, 
   <a rid="R21" ref-type="bibr" href="#R21">
    <span class="italic">21</span>
   </a>, 
   <a rid="R23" ref-type="bibr" href="#R23">
    <span class="italic">23</span>
   </a>). We did not use the commonly used ATL3 index defined as the SST anomaly in the central-eastern equatorial Atlantic (3°S to 3°N and 20°W to 0°E). Although this index captures the observed Atlantic Niño, it might be inappropriate for CMIP5 outputs because the pattern of Atlantic Niño varies substantially among models. For CMIP5 models, the EOF analysis was applied to the full 200-year period (1900–2099) to represent the overall simulations of Atlantic Niño in both the present-day and future climates. Anomalies here were computed by removing seasonal cycles referenced to the long-term mean and quadratic trends from the monthly data (for all the CMIP5 outputs, the anomalies were obtained on the basis of the full 200-year period). Following (
   <a rid="R13" ref-type="bibr" href="#R13">
    <span class="italic">13</span>
   </a>), the impact of ENSO was excluded first through linear regressions onto Niño3.4 SST (5°S to 5°N and 170°W to 120°W) in the previous D-1JF0.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sign-dependent average</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The correlation or regression coefficients in the equatorial Pacific region (5°S to 5°N and 160°E to 90°W) were averaged as follows. First, only correlation (or regression) coefficients at grid points that are statistically significant (more than 95% confidence level) were considered. Coefficients that are not significant were discarded. We then examined whether the retained values in terms of a whole-region average. If negative, then only the significant negative coefficients were averaged, or if positive, then only the significant positive coefficients were averaged. If there were no significant coefficients at any grid points in the equatorial Pacific region (5°S to 5°N and 160°E to 90°W), the result was set to be zero (see 
   <a rid="F1" ref-type="fig" href="#F1">Fig. 1A</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Model selection</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The normalized PC time series (defined as Atl-EOF index) was used to represent the temporal variability of Atlantic Niño. Although the Atlantic Niño was the dominant mode (EOF1) of tropical Atlantic in observations, it may appear as the second mode in some CMIP5 models (
   <a rid="R23" ref-type="bibr" href="#R23">
    <span class="italic">23</span>
   </a>). We thus calculated linear correlation of the leading two PCs and the following D0JF1 equatorial Pacific (5°S to 5°N and 160°E to 90°W) SST anomaly at each grid point, and computed the sign-dependent average correlations. Since the observed Atlantic Niño (JJA0) and Pacific SST (D0JF1) were negatively correlated, the minimum value between the correlation results of the two PCs was taken as a measurement of the Atlantic Niño–Pacific connection, with the corresponding 200-year PC time series being the model Atl-EOF index (table S2).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Bootstrap test</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used a bootstrap method (
   <a rid="R35" ref-type="bibr" href="#R35">
    <span class="italic">35</span>
   </a>) to examine whether the decreased response of Pacific SST is statistically significant. The 17 sign-dependent average regressions (R_SST hereafter) in the present-day and future climate periods from the 17 selected models were resampled randomly to construct respective 10,000 realizations of mean R_SST values. In this random resampling process, any model can be selected again. The doubled SDs of the 10,000 inter-realizations of mean R_SST for the present-day and future climate periods were 0.03 and 0.056, respectively. The decreased R_SST in the future period (0.091) is greater than the sum of these two doubled SD values (0.086), indicating statistical significance above the 99% confidence level (
   <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2A</a>). The same bootstrap tests were also applied to check the response of vertical velocity to diabatic heating (
   <a rid="F3" ref-type="fig" href="#F3">Fig. 3C</a>) and the model experiments results (
   <a rid="F5" ref-type="fig" href="#F5">Fig. 5</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">E-index and C-index</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We applied the EOF analysis to the quadratically detrended D0JF1 SST anomalies of equatorial Pacific (15°S to 15°N and 140°E to 80°W) in the 17 selected models, covering the 200-year period (1900–2099). The PC time series was scaled to have an SD of 1. We also made sure that the PC1 and PC2 correspond to the respective positive phase of EOF1 (warm anomaly center in the central eastern Pacific) and EOF2 (a warm anomaly center in the central Pacific and a cool anomaly aside). The temporal variability of the central Pacific–ENSO and eastern Pacific–ENSO (
   <a rid="R36" ref-type="bibr" href="#R36">
    <span class="italic">36</span>
   </a>) can be described by a C-index [(PC1 + PC2)/2] and an E-index [(PC1 − PC2)/2], respectively (
   <a rid="R37" ref-type="bibr" href="#R37">
    <span class="italic">37</span>
   </a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Model description</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We further examined our mechanism using an intermediate climate model (
   <a rid="R38" ref-type="bibr" href="#R38">
    <span class="italic">38</span>
   </a>, 
   <a rid="R39" ref-type="bibr" href="#R39">
    <span class="italic">39</span>
   </a>), which is a fully coupled system consisting of the Community Atmosphere Model version 3.1 (CAM3.1) and a 1.5-layer reduced-gravity ocean (RGO) model with flux corrections (CAM3.1-RGO model hereafter). The atmospheric component is part of the Community Climate System Model version 3 developed at the NCAR. It was based on a Eulerian spectral dynamical core, with a T42 horizontal resolution and 26 vertical levels. The land surface processes in CAM3.1 were represented by the Community Land Model version 3, a fully interactive land model. The oceanic component was an extended Zebiak-Cane type of 1.5-layer RGO model (
   <a rid="R40" ref-type="bibr" href="#R40">
    <span class="italic">40</span>
   </a>, 
   <a rid="R41" ref-type="bibr" href="#R41">
    <span class="italic">41</span>
   </a>). The active upper ocean layer was divided into a fixed-depth mixed layer to simulate SST variation and a subsurface layer to parameterize the entrained subsurface temperature through the multivariate linear relationship with thermocline depth. The ocean model covers a global domain (80°S to 80°N and 0°E to 360°E) with 1° latitude by 2° longitude resolution, which contains variability off the equatorial band [see more details in (
   <a rid="R36" ref-type="bibr" href="#R36">
    <span class="italic">36</span>
   </a>)]. The CAM3.1-RGO model was proved to be a useful and efficient tool to study climate change related questions (
   <a rid="R38" ref-type="bibr" href="#R38">
    <span class="italic">38</span>
   </a>, 
   <a rid="R39" ref-type="bibr" href="#R39">
    <span class="italic">39</span>
   </a>, 
   <a rid="R42" ref-type="bibr" href="#R42">
    <span class="italic">42</span>
   </a>), as the effects of different ocean and atmosphere dynamic processes are easier to decipher in this model than the CGCMs.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Model experiments</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We first conducted two simulations with long integration using CAM3.1-RGO, including a 500-year control run (control) and a 400-year quadrupled CO
   <sub>2</sub> concentration run (4× CO
   <sub>2</sub>). The latter starts from the 100th year of control with a sudden quadrupling (1420 ppm) of CO
   <sub>2</sub> concentration. Then, from the respective equilibrium state of control and 4× CO
   <sub>2</sub>, two sets of initial-value ensemble runs were carried out. For each member of the experiments, the quadrupled Atlantic Niño SST pattern derived from observations (fig. S1A) was initiated over the tropical Atlantic (20°S to 20°N) region on the first day of June and tracked for 1 year within the fully coupled environment. A total of 20-member ensemble experiments were performed for each set, with each member starting from a slightly different initial condition. We also carried out two parallel sets of 20-member ensemble experiments, where zero SST anomalies were initiated. The differences between the corresponding sets of experiments are the responses to the imposed Atlantic Niño SST anomalies. The result confirms a decreased Atlantic Niño–Pacific connection. Further, the system’s memory of the Atlantic’s initial conditions is likely to be weaker in the future.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
