<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Simulation of the Atlantic Niño–Pacific connection</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We identify CMIP5 models that are able to simulate the Atlantic Niño–Pacific connection. As for the observations, we applied EOF analysis to JJA0 SST anomalies quadratically detrended over the full 200 years (1900–2099). This allows our models to have an Atlantic Niño pattern that is different from the observed and different from one model to another. As in our analysis of the observed data, we correlate the Atl-EOF index (JJA0 PC time series) with grid-point D0JF1 equatorial Pacific SST anomalies over the 1900–1999 period, referred to as the present-day climate (see “Model selection” section in Materials and Methods). We use an average correlation over grid points with a significant coefficient to evaluate whether a model is able to simulate the Atlantic Niño–Pacific connection (see “Sign-dependent average” section in Materials and Methods). These approaches are adapted to select as many models as possible. A total of 17 models simulate a connection reminiscent of the observed, although the locations of correlation could be different (
  <a rid="F1" ref-type="fig" href="#F1">Fig. 1, B and D</a>). Ten models produce no such connection, whereas six models produce an opposite connection (
  <a rid="F1" ref-type="fig" href="#F1">Fig. 1, B and E</a>), consistent with previous findings that the Atlantic Niño–Pacific connection is not simulated by all models (
  <a rid="R23" ref-type="bibr" href="#R23">
   <span class="italic">23</span>
  </a>–
  <a rid="R25" ref-type="bibr" href="#R25">
   <span class="italic">25</span>
  </a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Atlantic Niño pattern simulated by the 17 selected models is comparable to that in the observation, although they are generally weaker and more equatorially confined than the observed pattern (fig. S2). Our approach is to examine how the Atlantic Niño–Pacific connection, as simulated by a model, may change under greenhouse warming. An intermodel relationship shows that correlation over the full 100-year period increases with the maximum of 20-year sliding correlations over the same 100 years (fig. S3). Thus, as in the observed data, the correlation coefficient over the 100-year period is contributed by period(s) of large statistically significant correlation embedded in multidecadal fluctuations. The 17 models in aggregation produce the observed forcing of Atlantic Niño on the Pacific, i.e., an Atlantic Niño leads to a Pacific La Niña and an Atlantic Niña leads to a Pacific El Niño (compare figs. S1 and S4), through the Pacific Bjerknes feedback involving winds, SST, and the thermocline.</p>
</sec>
