<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In terrestrial and intertidal systems, by far the most significant driver of ectotherm temperature is exposure to direct solar radiation (
 <xref rid="ref68" ref-type="bibr">Helmuth, 1998</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref139" ref-type="bibr">Scheffers 
  <italic>et al.,</italic> 2017
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref102" ref-type="bibr">Maclean 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2019
 </xref>). While mortality events are often associated with episodes of high air temperature (
 <xref rid="ref115" ref-type="bibr">Mislan 
  <italic>et al.,</italic> 2014
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref155" ref-type="bibr">Sorte 
  <italic>et al.,</italic> 2019
 </xref>) these only occur when both air temperature is elevated and solar radiation is at a maximum; both conditions are typically required in order for large-scale mortality to occur, and thus elevated air temperature alone is an effective indicator of mortality events 
 <italic>only</italic> when it occurs on cloud free days with maximum solar radiation (
 <xref rid="ref54" ref-type="bibr">Gilman 
  <italic>et al.,</italic> 2006
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref115" ref-type="bibr">Mislan 
  <italic>et al.,</italic> 2014
 </xref>). Because of the importance of solar radiation (
 <xref rid="ref105" ref-type="bibr">Marshall 
  <italic>et al.,</italic> 2010
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">Chapperon 
  <italic>et al.,</italic> 2016
 </xref>), the difference in temperature between an animal on a poleward-facing (shaded) microsite and one on a nearby equatorial-facing (sunny) microsite can easily exceed 15°C (
 <xref rid="ref70" ref-type="bibr">Helmuth and Hofmann, 2001</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref147" ref-type="bibr">Sears 
  <italic>et al.,</italic> 2011
 </xref>). Such large differences in thermal environments among shaded and unshaded surfaces have been shown to lead to even larger differences in physiology (
 <xref rid="ref79" ref-type="bibr">Jimenez 
  <italic>et al</italic>., 2015
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref113" ref-type="bibr">Miller 
  <italic>et al.,</italic> 2015
 </xref>), survival (
 <xref rid="ref58" ref-type="bibr">Harley, 2008</xref>), abundance (
 <xref rid="ref111" ref-type="bibr">Meager 
  <italic>et al</italic>., 2011
 </xref>) and selection for different species and genotypes (
 <xref rid="ref142" ref-type="bibr">Schmidt 
  <italic>et al</italic>., 2000
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref144" ref-type="bibr">Schneider and Helmuth, 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref145" ref-type="bibr">Seabra 
  <italic>et al</italic>., 2011
 </xref>). This non-linear translation between small changes in body temperature and large changes in physiological performance is best conceptualized using Jensen’s inequality (
 <xref rid="ref107" ref-type="bibr">Martin and Huey, 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref180" ref-type="bibr">Denny, 2019</xref>), which further highlights the dangers of using temporal or spatial averages to predict biological responses. Over geographic scales, the presence of shaded refugia has been proposed as a mechanism that allows species to extend their range boundaries beyond what they could survive if only sunny habitats were available (
 <xref rid="ref159" ref-type="bibr">Sunday 
  <italic>et al.,</italic> 2014
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref97" ref-type="bibr">Lima 
  <italic>et al.,</italic> 2016
 </xref>).
</p>
