<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="S0001" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">With increasing urgency, academic health sciences centers (AHCs) and health professional organizations are recognizing the need to foster the core competency of leadership, within their workforces and organizational cultures [
  <a rid="CIT0001" href="#CIT0001">1</a>–
  <a rid="CIT0003" href="#CIT0003">3</a>]. Indeed, among the 94 AHCs in Canada and the United States that responded to a national survey from the Study of Leadership Development Programs at North American Academic Health Centers in 2015 [
  <a rid="CIT0004" href="#CIT0004">4</a>], 99% of the responding AHCs provided some form of leadership development training such as informal single workshops, formal internal faculty leadership development programs (LDPs), or formal external LDPs. Over half (65%) of these AHCs reported offering at least one formal LDP. While research intense institutions were more likely to have LDPs; 42% of AHCs that did not offer a formal LDP cited lack of resources as a significant barrier. A majority of the AHCs (73%) sent participants to external LDPs rather than cultivating an LDP within their own institution.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In spite of increasing availability of leadership development opportunities, LDPs often fail to demonstrate efficacy in creating leaders [
  <a rid="CIT0005" href="#CIT0005">5</a>–
  <a rid="CIT0010" href="#CIT0010">10</a>]. In part, this is because of minimal program assessment. For example, while AHC LDPs obtain participant satisfaction data, less than 50% assess other outcomes, such as actual learning, behavioral change, or post program individual achievement [
  <a rid="CIT0004" href="#CIT0004">4</a>]. In addition, AHC LDPs most commonly deliver content in a traditional classroom format. This ignores best practices for the development of leaders, which include experiential application of skills, assessment of individual personal growth, and reflection on action [
  <a rid="CIT0005" href="#CIT0005">5</a>–
  <a rid="CIT0011" href="#CIT0011">11</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This article describes experience cultivating a LDP within an AHC, the University of California San Francisco (UCSF) in full partnership with Coro Northern California (Coro), a nonprofit organization focused on leadership development that uses a cohort-based experiential learning approach [
  <a rid="CIT0012" href="#CIT0012">12</a>]. Between 2005 and 2017, the 12-year UCSF-Coro Faculty Leadership Collaborative (FLC) had over 180 graduates. We conducted an online survey in 2013 with graduates from 2005 to 2012 that assessed participants’ perceived downstream behavioral change, including both individual growth and impact on institutional climate. We also reported program completion rate and proportions of graduates from the 2005 to 2012 cohorts attaining leadership positions within the institution (UCSF).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The authors are members of UCSF faculty leadership, Coro executive leadership, FLC staff administrators, and FLC graduates who have first-hand experience in various phases of the FLC implementation and outcome evaluation. The objective of this paper is to reflect 12 years of perspectives on cultivating a LDP within an AHC by describing the history, implementation, and longitudinal outcomes of FLC.</p>
</sec>
