<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div id="ijerph-16-02624-t002" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <span pub-id-type="pii" class="object-id">ijerph-16-02624-t002_Table 2</span>
 <span class="label">Table 2</span>
 <div class="caption">
  <p>Criteria in classifying research themes (adopted from Smith et al. [
   <a rid="B13-ijerph-16-02624" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13-ijerph-16-02624">13</a>]).
  </p>
 </div>
 <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
  <thead>
   <tr>
    <th align="left" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Theme</th>
    <th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Criteria</th>
   </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vulnerability to Disease and Injury Due to Climate Variability and Climate Change</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Studies that had findings on health vulnerabilities, such as socioeconomic status, age, and gender in relation to the effect of climate change.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Direct Impacts of Climate and Weather on Health</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Studies with the aim of and results on associating the direct effects of climate change with health outcomes like mortality and diseases unmediated by the ecosystem.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ecosystem-Mediated Impacts of Climate Change on Health Outcomes</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Studies with the aim of and results on associating climate change with vector-borne, food- and water-borne, as well as air quality-related health outcomes.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Health Impacts Heavily Mediated through Human Institutions</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Studies with the aim of and results on associating climate change with nutrition, occupational health, mental health, and violence and conflict.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adaptation to Protect Health</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Studies with the aim of and results on improving basic public health and health care services, as well as the formulation of adaptation policies and measures (including early warning systems) based on associated health impacts of climate change.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Co-benefits</td>
    <td align="left" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Studies with the aim of and results related to mitigation measures and their benefits to health outcomes.</td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
</div>
