<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Climate change is the single most pressing environmental issue for the Earth’s biotic environment with adverse implications for food security, freshwater supply and human health (United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change [UNFCCC] 
 <xref rid="CIT0059" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2007</xref>). Climate change is also the biggest challenge for tropical and subtropical countries of the world, especially for coastal areas and islands. The impact would be particularly severe in the tropical areas, which mainly consist of developing countries (Sathaye, Shukla &amp; Ravindranath 
 <xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2006</xref>), including Bangladesh. Bangladesh is exposed to climate-induced extreme events as a result of its geographical location (at the confluence of Ganges–Brahmaputra–Meghna [GBM] basin, Himalaya in the north and Bay of Bengal in the south), extremely low and flat terrain (almost 80% of total land area is floodplains and half of the area is within 10 m above the mean sea level), high population pressure (159.1 million in 2015) (World Bank 
 <xref rid="CIT0066" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>) and density (1237 people per km
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> in 2015) (World Bank 
 <xref rid="CIT0066" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>), high levels of poverty, nature-dependent economic activities (42.9% people employed in agriculture sectors and comprising about 15.5% of gross domestic product (GDP) at current prices in 2015) (World Bank 
 <xref rid="CIT0066" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>), and so on. The above physical, social and economic conditions make the country the sixth most climate-affected countries of the world for the period of 1997–2016 (Eckstein, Künzel &amp; Schäfer 
 <xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2017</xref>). Therefore, climate change may attenuate the ability of the country to achieve sustainable development through weakening the sustainability of livelihoods, especially natural-based rural livelihoods and wipe-out development efforts.
</p>
