<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Population includes the number of people; their demographic characteristics like age, sex, health, education and familial status; their demographic processes like birth, death, migration, the formation of unions and families and their dissolution; and the spatial distribution of people by geographic regions and size of settlements, from rural to urban (Cohen 
 <xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>). Therefore, population growth has diversified effects on development. On the contrary, the relationship between climate change and development is reciprocal. Social and economic development may be influenced by climate change, while society’s precedence on sustainable development influences the level of emissions of GHGs that are causing climate change (IPCC 
 <xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2007</xref>). Sustainable development is defined by the Brundtland Report as ‘the development that meets the need and demand of the present generations without compromising the ability of future generations to meet their own needs’ (Brundtland 
 <xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1987</xref>). The core concept of sustainability integrates economic, social and environmental aspect. Therefore, sustainable development may be difficult to attain if climate change continues to jeopardise economic growth, environmental stability as well as social progress. In reality, no country or nation is immune from the adverse impact of climate change. To realise present and future development gains, the Sustainable Development Goals (SDGs) have incorporated ‘(tackling) climate change’ as one of the important pillars to sustain the development beyond 2030 (United Nations 
 <xref rid="CIT0056" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2018</xref>). Being a densely populated and developing country, Bangladesh is particularly vulnerable to climate change and will have the least options to cope with the projected climatic shocks.
</p>
