<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Much research has been conducted on the impact of population growth and/or climate change on sustainable development at global scale (e.g. African Institute for Development Policy [AFIDEP] &amp; Population Action International [PAI] 
 <xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>; Bremner et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>; Cohen 
 <xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>; Donner &amp; Rodríguez 
 <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2008</xref>; Jiang &amp; Hardee 
 <xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>; Schneider et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>; Sherbinin et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2007</xref>); however, limited research has so far been conducted on those aspects in Bangladesh. The study of Islam and Islam (
 <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2017</xref>) focused on impact of climate change on sustainable development of the country. The demand of rice and wheat for the year 2050 with the projected population scenarios was calculated by Mainuddin and Kirby (
 <xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>) to analyse the food security status of Bangladesh. In their paper, Faisal and Parveen (
 <xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2004</xref>) studied the implication of food security of the country in consideration with climate change, population growth and limited resources. Solaiman and Belal (
 <xref rid="CIT0052" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1999</xref>) proposed a sustainable development process framework of the country which sets four interrelated issues: stabilisation of population, food security, optimum uses of natural resources and growth of economy and industry. Mahtab and Karim (
 <xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1992</xref>) set forth an analysis of agricultural carrying capacity with the projected population growth and land-use changes. All these studies, however, focused on either population or climate change. Thus, this study was an effort to investigate the implications of population growth and climate change of Bangladesh from a sustainability lens.
</p>
