<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion and Conclusion</div>
 <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We have analyzed the raw surface soil moisture outputs from all available GCMs for four RCP scenarios: RCP2.6, RCP4.5, RCP6.0, and RCP8.5 under the CMIP5 framework. We evaluate the statistical significance of change in surface soil moisture using a Wilcoxon signed-rank test for each grid and control for false discovery rate (FDR) at a significance level of 0.05. We have found statistically significant annual drying over most of Australia, South America, North America, south Africa, Europe and Mediterranean, and east Asia, with stronger drying as the strength of forcing increases, but statistically significant wetting in limited areas of east Africa, south Asia, and central Asia by the end of the 21st century. The soil moisture drying in the Mediterranean, southwestern USA, northeast South America, and southern African is mainly associated with the projected widening of the Hadley Circulation and increased temperature and evapotranspiration
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span>. The drying or wetting signal is more pronounced for seasonal than annual because of compensating effects for the whole year. We also have detected a strong seasonality in many regions in the mid- and high-latitude of North Hemisphere, with wetting in winter and drying in summer.
 </p>
 <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We calculate the duration, frequency, severity, and spatial extent of the severe agricultural drought (i.e., that which occurs approximately once every ten years for specific month). The multi-model median frequency of short-term drought is projected to increase by the end of the 21st century in most regions and most scenarios. In most cases, the increase in the frequency of short-term drought is higher for the RCP2.6 than the RCP8.5. In the latter scenario, individual months are more likely to cluster into consecutive dry months to form a long-term drought. The median frequency of long-term drought is also projected to increase in most regions, with the strongest increase in EUM, TSA, CAM, ENA, and SAF. The multi-model mean projects increased spatial extent of severe drought for all regions and all emission scenarios, with progressively larger spatial extent of severe drought as the strength of radiative forcing increases by the end of the 21st century. The multi-model and multi-scenario mean spatial extent of severe drought in CAM, EUM, TSA, and SAF are projected to increase the most. The increase in the spatial extent of drought tends to be larger in warmer seasons than cooler seasons in most regions because of increasing temperature and evapotranspiration. The inter-model variability is high and contributes the most to uncertainty in future projections and this source of uncertainty increases with radiative forcing, i.e., the model uncertainty is higher for RCP8.5 than for RCP2.6. Compared with the historical period (1976–2005), each individual GCM projection in the future (2071–2100) shows greater temporal (inter-month) variability in spatial extent of severe drought, indicating more widespread and extreme drought events. Furthermore, the variation in the spatial extent of drought across models are much larger than the variations across the RCP scenarios, i.e., the model spread is much larger than the scenario spread. The variation across models are also much larger than the variations across different regions, i.e., the model spread is much larger than the spatial heterogeneity.</p>
 <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition to visualizing the uncertainties, we have partitioned and quantified the three dominant sources of uncertainty with respect to decadal mean standardized soil moisture anomalies, decadal sum of 1-month drought occurrence, decadal sum of severity, and decadal mean spatial extent of drought from CMIP5 MMEs. We have found that more than 80% of the uncertainty associated with future drought projection in the 21st century comes from differences between GCMs, model uncertainty. This dominance results because of different treatment of clouds and precipitation in the models, as well as various local factors considered in soil moisture modeling. Regional patterns of uncertainty partition in spatial extent of drought for those 15 regions are similar to that for global and model uncertainty contributes approximately 80% of the total uncertainty. The differences across regions in uncertainty partition result mainly from the slight differences in the magnitude of scenario uncertainty.</p>
 <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When measured by simulated soil moisture conditions, drying occurs in large parts of the Mediterranean and Europe, many parts of the United States, Mexico, Southern Africa, many parts in Northern South America, Southeast China, West Australia, and the drying signal become stronger over lead time. However, since the inter-model variability is so high, the S/N of drying in soil moisture is less than −1 in only limited regions including the Mediterranean and Europe, the southwestern United States, and southern Africa. The wetting occurs in mid- to high-latitude Asia, high-latitude North America, India, east Argentina, and Sahara, but none of these regions have an S/N ratio greater than 1. The spread of uncertainty becomes larger as the signal becomes stronger and thus the spatial pattern and magnitude of S/N does not change significantly.</p>
 <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Improving future projection of agricultural drought depends on improved model performance in simulating soil moisture, e.g., improved representation of the surface hydrological process. The GCMs might have limited ability to simulate the water cycle and all relevant interactions between the atmosphere and land surface
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span>. This situation is further complicated by the fact of error propagation that model biases in one variable affect other variables through the causal chain (e.g. the simulation of soil moisture depends on the simulation of precipitation and evapotranspiration, representation of the soil layers and soil characteristics, etc.). The model uncertainty could be attributed to imperfect representation of the processes, or limited understanding of the very complex process, or inherent challenges in mathematically representing the processes
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span>, e.g., previous study also pointed out that there are large differences among CMIP5 GCMs to represent the permafrost soil thermal dynamics and the coupling between soil and air temperatures in the high latitude resulting in difference in snow physics and soil hydrology
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
  </span>. Additionally, this study uses the upper 10 cm surface soil moisture, instead of the total soil moisture. The surface soil moisture (upper 10 cm) data for different models are quantitatively more comparable than the total soil moisture due to the substantial differences between climate models in the soil depth and soil layers
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
  </span>. The total soil moisture should have more uncertainty than the surface soil moisture because of differences in soil depth and layers. Many vegetation types are able to extract water from deeper soil layers
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
  </span> and thus we need soil moisture of deeper layers with consistent soil depth and layers across different GCMs to better quantify the agricultural drought. Thus, we also advocate to standardize the soil schemes and improve the representation of soil layers across different GCMs from different modeling centers to reduce this structural uncertainty due to differences in soil depth and layers.
 </p>
</sec>
