<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Global multi-model mean surface soil moisture change</div>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We investigate future agricultural drought change by calculating the multi-model mean percentage change in annual/seasonal mean surface soil moisture for the period of 2071–2100 (RCP forcing) relative to 1976–2005 (historical forcing) for each emission scenario (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). Percentage change is calculated because the magnitude of surface soil moisture varies by model; a 30-year period is chosen to sufficiently filter out interannual variability, but maintain multi-decadal variability. We also evaluate the statistical significance of change using a Wilcoxon signed-rank test, which is a nonparametric distribution-free paired-sample hypothesis testing procedure. The Wilcoxon signed-rank test is usually used as an alternative to paired two-sample student t-test when the assumption of normality is violated. Here, 9746 out of 29376 (33.18%) Shapiro-Wilk normality tests on a per-pixel basis reject the null hypothesis that the annual mean surface soil moisture from different GCMs for the period of 1976–2005 or the period of 2071–2100 are normally distributed at a significance level of 0.05. Thus, we perform a Wilcoxon signed-rank test (two-tailed) for each grid and each scenario by testing the null hypothesis that the distribution of the annual/seasonal mean surface soil moisture for different GCMs for the period of 1976–2005 (historical forcing) and the period of 2071–2100 (RCP forcing) are the same. A paired two-sample hypothesis test is used to control sources of variability in which the annual/seasonal mean soil moisture for the two 30-year periods from the same GCM is a matched-pair sample. An independent two-sample test is not appropriate in such cases. Moreover, since we perform multiple comparisons using the Wilcoxon signed-rank test and calculate the p-values for more than 3000 grids for each scenario, we control for the false discovery rate (FDR) (i.e., the expected proportion of false discoveries among the total number of discoveries) for multiple comparisons at a significance level of 0.05 and adjust the p-value for each grid cell following the method of Benjamini and Hochberg
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span> (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>).
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Global multi-model mean percentage change in annual mean surface soil moisture for the period of 2071–2100 (RCP forcing) relative to 1976–2005 (historical forcing) based on CMIP5 multi-model ensembles (MMEs) under four scenarios: RCP2.6, RCP4.5, RCP6.0, and RCP8.5. The grids with stippling indicate statistical significance using the non-parametric Wilcoxon signed-rank test by controlling the false discovery rate (FDR) at a significance level of 0.05, i.e., there is a strong evidence that the distribution of annual mean surface soil moisture from different GCMs for period of 2071–2100 and the period of 1976–2005 is not the same for those grid cells. The results are based on all available models for each RCP scenario and the corresponding models in the historical forcing.</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_41196_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e402" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The annual mean surface soil moisture by the end of the 21st century shows statistically significant large-scale drying over most of Australia, South America, North America, southern Africa, Europe and Mediterranean, and east Asia, and statistically significant wetting in limited areas of east Africa, south Asia, and central Asia (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). The overall spatial patterns of drying and wetting are generally consistent across the four RCP scenarios, with stronger drying as forcing increases (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). The soil moisture drying in the Mediterranean, southwestern USA, northeast South America, and southern Africa is associated with projected widening of the Hadley Circulation that shifts downwelling and inhibits precipitation in these regions and globally increased temperature and evapotranspiration
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The changing signal is more pronounced in winter and summer than annually because of compensating effects during the whole year (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>, Supplementary Figs 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S1</a> and 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S2</a>). We have also detected a strong seasonality in many regions in the mid- and high-latitudes of the North Hemisphere, with wetting in the winter and drying in the summer (Supplementary Figs 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S1</a> and 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S2</a>) which is most likely due to increased temperature and evapotranspiration, increased precipitation throughout whole year, and earlier melting of ice and snow.
 </p>
</sec>
