<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Although this topic was identified in the initial framework,
 <xref rid="cit0002" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">[2]</sup>
 </xref> there continues to be an absence of literature on the mental health effects of climate change in workers.
 <xref rid="cit0166" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">[166]</sup>
 </xref> However, the link between extreme weather disasters such as floods, forest fires, heat waves, cyclones, and extreme anxiety reactions such as post-traumatic stress disorder is well established.
 <xref rid="cit0167" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">[167,168]</sup>
 </xref> Climate change may present acute and chronic stressors that may have severe mental health effects.
 <xref rid="cit0166" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">[166]</sup>
 </xref> Also, direct and indirect effects of climate change on mental health have been hypothesized.
 <xref rid="cit0166" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">[166,168,169]</sup>
 </xref> Workers may also be subject to the mental health effects of climate change in general; these may interact with work-related hazards. For example, workers in a drought area may have combined psychological stress from the weather in general as well as from psychological effects of heat exposure in their jobs.
 <xref rid="cit0020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">[20,72]</sup>
 </xref> Or the loss of workers' homes and property in floods could affect a worker's ability to concentrate and do work tasks safely. Long periods of high temperatures, heat, and drought put significant stress on communities that will be felt by workers in their jobs. Moreover, the loss of work capacity due to increasing heat exposure and the resulting loss of income is likely to cause mental health stresses in some workers.
 <xref rid="cit0018" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">[18,20]</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
