<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A study by 
 <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fpls.2019.00132" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Whipple et al.</uri> used long-term monitoring data to examine interactions among poor soil, severe drought, and moth herbivore susceptibility in a pinyon pine tree species that has suffered extensive climate change–related mortality. Contrary to the authors’ hypothesis, they found that chronically stressed and herbivore-susceptible trees had smaller declines in performance during drought years than less-stressed trees. Tree mortality was also higher in finer soils, and moth abundance declined during droughts. The authors concluded that the results support the notion that stressed trees have adapted or acclimatized to harsh conditions, rendering them less sensitive to drought and herbivore effects. In another moth herbivory study, 
 <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fpls.2018.01582" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Camarero et al.</uri> assessed the effects of climatic stress and European gypsy moth (
 <italic>Lymantria dispar dispar</italic>) outbreaks on wood characteristics of radiata pine and chestnut tree populations in Spain. Radial growth decreased substantially in both tree species because of defoliation. Climate explained the majority of growth variability in defoliated chestnuts. However, radial growth and wood density were important for radiata pine, and the authors suggest these variables could be used as indicators for susceptibility to defoliation by the gypsy moth. 
 <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3389/fpls.2018.01667" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Hentschel et al.</uri> performed an extensive analysis of ecological variables related to past outbreaks by three insect defoliators of Scots pine in Germany. They found that the dynamics of these herbivores were influenced by environmental variables in important but different ways. For example, 
 <italic>Lymantria monacha</italic> feeding was mainly dependent on the tree stand surroundings, whereas 
 <italic>Diprion pini</italic> was largely driven by climate, and 
 <italic>Dendrolimus pini</italic> followed a mixed pattern determined by climatic and forest structure parameters.
</p>
