<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A second important step in the prevention of heat-related illness and injury is understanding and implementing HA. Children acclimate to heat more slowly than adults [
 <xref rid="B72-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>] but will beneficially increase sweat capacity, reduce the onset threshold for sweating, and reduce overall physiological strain [
 <xref rid="B72-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>,
 <xref rid="B208-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">208</xref>]. Obese children possess lower levels of acclimation and therefore should be acclimated more progressively during summer months [
 <xref rid="B72-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>]. When exercising in the heat, children should follow appropriate hydration and exposure guidelines for the ambient conditions, with special consideration and awareness of their propensity for greater voluntary dehydration [
 <xref rid="B101-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>]. Hypohydration compromises thermoregulatory function to a greater extent in children compared to adults, making it an import factor to mitigate health risks during exposure. The American Academy of Pediatrics position stand addressing “Climatic Heat Stress and Exercising Children and Adolescents” [
 <xref rid="B52-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>] recommends multiple risk reduction strategies, including but not limited to:
 <list list-type="order">
  <list-item>
   <p>Increasing rest periods. Activities lasting &gt;15 min should be reduced in conditions of high solar radiation, high humidity, and ambient temperatures above critical limits.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>When beginning a strenuous exercise program or travelling to a warmer climate, HA over 10–14 days should be planned with reduced exercise intensity, duration, and protective clothing.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Ensure adequate hydration prior to extended exercise in the heat. Intermittent drinking periods should be enforced, regardless of thirst (100–250 mL every 20 min). Weighing a child pre/post-exercise can assist with verifying hydration.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Lightweight, light-colored, single-layer clothing should be worn that is absorbent. Sweat-soaked garments should be replaced.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>Child education on heat illness and hydration practices should be adopted to help raise awareness of prevention, and recognition of the signs and symptoms of heat-related illness and injury. Trained staff should be present, and an emergency plan should be in place.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
