<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par22" class="p">Interestingly, adult body condition and chick growth rates were higher when SIC was low, meaning that less sea-ice and higher SSTs provided better environmental conditions for breeding little auks in East Greenland. The link between environmental conditions and fitness proxies could be direct, as higher temperatures reduce energy requirements for thermoregulation
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" class="xref">33</xref>
 </sup>, and energy gained could then be reallocated to body maintenance or chick rearing. Linkages could also be indirect, via trophic interactions and bottom-up effects: lower SIC during summer reflects an earlier sea-ice breakup and a shorter lag between ice-algae bloom and pelagic phytoplankton bloom
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" class="xref">69</xref>
 </sup>. Our results suggest that prey quality and/or availability would be better when sea-ice breakup occurs earlier. However, this is not in accordance with previous findings from Spitsbergen, where earlier sea-ice breakup lead to a mismatch between algal blooms and copepod 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">glacialis</italic> phenology, and ultimately to a lower chick survival in little auks and Brünnich’s guillemots
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" class="xref">70</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71" class="xref">71</xref>
 </sup>. Changes in the trophic interactions occurring in the Western Greenland Sea are probably more complex and reflects high variability of local conditions throughout the Arctic
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">12</xref>
 </sup>. Lastly, SIC encountered during the study period (2004–2015, 9.1 ± 6.8%) were already lower than SIC encountered during the period 1979–2003 (20.0 ± 10.4%)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" class="xref">26</xref>
 </sup> and may already feature suboptimal conditions for little auks.
</p>
