<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">There is no universal best way to test for the effects of extremes on long-term trends, but we urge others to test rather than assume that the two will be linked. Weak associations are not particularly surprising. Only 6.2% of all between-year population changes qualified as extreme, and hence the magnitude of extreme events would have to be far greater than regular population changes for such events to leave a strong signature on the overall population trend. Reducing the threshold for detecting extremes (so there are many more of them) might increase the likelihood of detecting an association, but this would be counter to the notion that extreme events are, by definition, unusual. Altwegg 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="RSTB20160144C12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>] report that long-term observational studies of the impacts of extreme climatic events have tended to observe two or three extreme events during a median study duration of 10 years, which is comparable with the frequency of extreme population responses identified here. Of course, single events that reduce population densities by two or more orders of magnitude can happen [
 <xref rid="RSTB20160144C18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSTB20160144C26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>], but they are very rare when considering the number of between-year population changes that we studied. Long-term population trends are seemingly dominated by other factors, such as relatively gradual climatic changes, or by non-climatic events that accumulate over space and time. For example, many farmland birds showed declining trends during the 1970s and 1980s as a result of agricultural intensification operating over many years [
 <xref rid="RSTB20160144C44" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSTB20160144C45" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>]. Similarly, land-use change is the likely driver of the parallel long-term declines of many Lepidoptera species in the United Kingdom [
 <xref rid="RSTB20160144C46" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSTB20160144C47" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>]. In no single year would there be sufficient intensification to cause a detectable crash at a national scale, but the accumulation of local effects over many years seems to drive the long-term trend. Other factors such as the arrival of invasive species or other locally acting pressures can have similar effects provided they operate for long enough; multiplicative effects of climatic and non-climatic factors may also be important [
 <xref rid="RSTB20160144C40" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>].
</p>
