<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="Fig1" class="fig">
 <label class="label">Fig. 1</label>
 <caption class="caption">
  <p class="p">Comparison of CESM simulations against historical long-term changes in dust aerosol optical depth. 
   <bold class="bold">a</bold> Shown is the AVHRR satellite record of annually averaged dust AOD (black line and squares) over the dust-dominated region of 10–20°N and 20–30°W, off the West-African coast
   <sup class="sup">
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" class="xref">27</xref>,
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" class="xref">32</xref>
   </sup>. The CESM simulation with the BASE dust emission module (blue line and circles) poorly reproduces the magnitude and historical trend of the dust AOD, whereas CESM with the PHYS emission module (green line and triangles) better reproduces both the magnitude of the dust AOD and its long-term trend. The slope of the least-square linear fit lines (dashed lines) are −0.047 ± 0.011 per decade (corresponding to −13 ± 3% per decade) for the AVHRR data, −0.017 ± 0.005 per decade (corresponding to −9 ±2% per decade) for the BASE-AVHRR simulation, and −0.045 ± 0.010 per decade (corresponding to −14 ±3% per decade) for the PHYS-AVHRR simulation. 
   <bold class="bold">b</bold> Shown are the modeled long-term trends in AOD with the BASE and PHYS emission modules, compared against the measured trends at eight AERONET stations (see Supplementary Figs. 
   <xref ref-type="sec" rid="Sec16" class="xref">1</xref> and 
   <xref ref-type="sec" rid="Sec16" class="xref">2</xref> for results from the individual stations) for which these long-term changes are dominated by changes in dust aerosols (see Methods). The size of the symbols is proportional to the number of years of data for each station, and error bars were obtained from least-squares fitting of the modeled annually averaged AOD at each site. For both panels, 
   <italic class="italic">r</italic> denotes the Pearson correlation coefficients between the measured and modeled long-term trend in the annually averaged AOD
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="41467_2017_2620_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e1241" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
