<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Population sizes during the exhaustive mid‐January counts were compared at different geographical scales: (a) the national level, (b) four main geographical areas: the coastal departments bordering the Channel, the Atlantic coast, the Mediterranean coast (including Corsica), and all other noncoastal departments gathered within an “inland area,” (c) ecological areas gathering the departments into 15 main watersheds, and (d) the 95 administrative departments. It was not a mere sampling of roosts, the whole population was counted, so that standard deviation across years is not needed. Population dynamics (the number of cormorants from all 13 censuses) is shown at the scale of the 15 watersheds, while the timing of the strategy of occupancy of the country is presented on national maps for each department but only based on a sample of annual counts (all the first counts from 1983 to 1997, and then every 6 years: 2003, 2009, and 2015). The detailed distribution of all night roosts according to their size is only presented for five national censuses (every 5–6 years from 1992 to 2015) as an example of the dynamics of individual roosts. While the exact number of cormorants was used in all analyses, we grouped for the Figure 
 <xref rid="ece34348-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref> the roosts into seven exponential classes according to their size (number of cormorants) from the smallest (&lt;50 cormorants) to the biggest roosts (&gt;1,600). The range shift of the wintering population over the study period was calculated for each census by multiplying the number of cormorants wintering in all occupied departments in mid‐January by the geographical coordinates (in degrees and decimal degrees) of their centre, and then dividing their sum by the total number of wintering cormorants in the country (“weighted geographical centroid” from Maclean et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34348-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>). As a comparison, the range shift of the French breeding population of cormorants was calculated similarly from the localization of each colony over nine national counts coordinated by Loïc Marion, from 1983 to 2015.
</p>
