<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Survival of toadlets during overwintering was highest when exposed to a shortened hibernation period and elevated average winter temperature (61 days at 4.5 °C), and lowest under current average overwintering conditions (91 days at 1.5 °C). This result contradicts the hypothesis that milder winters could lead to increased mortality in poikilothermic amphibians due to elevated metabolic rates during a long period without feeding
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14" class="xref">14</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23" class="xref">23</xref>. Positive effects of milder winter temperatures and/or shorter winters on overwintering survival of anurans have also been found by a few correlative studies
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26" class="xref">26</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27" class="xref">27</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28" class="xref">28</xref>. The only other experimental study testing how climate change may affect hibernation success of an amphibian
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30" class="xref">30</xref> registered negligible mortality (3 out of 160 animals). Garner, 
 <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30" class="xref">30</xref> manipulated overwintering conditions by exposing juvenile common toads to different hibernation lengths of 51 and 11 days at 4 °C, which might have already exposed toads to more beneficial conditions than currently experienced in nature
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b35" class="xref">35</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b36" class="xref">36</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b37" class="xref">37</xref>, thereby possibly underestimating effects of climate change on hibernation success. Although we applied a fairly constant temperature treatment in our study, our results likely are valid for natural populations. Anholt, 
 <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26" class="xref">26</xref> found negative effects of highly variable winter temperatures on survival in a field study, but the recent report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change shows that low-percentile winter temperatures are predicted to increase faster than the mean, thereby decreasing temperature variability
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17" class="xref">17</xref>. This way, if we had included variability in our treatments, our simulated climate change scenario would have been not only warmer but also less variable than the current climate scenario; so it is likely that we would have found even more pronounced differences in favor of the climate change group. Our results, thus, bolster up conclusions of previous correlative studies by providing experimental evidence for the hypothesis that temperate-zone anurans, including common toads, may benefit from mildly increasing temperatures due to climate change via increased winter survival. Nevertheless, further experiments are needed to scrutinize the effects of temperature variability coupled with warming.
</p>
