<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="materials-and-methods" id="ece35162-sec-0004" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">MATERIAL AND METHODS</div>
 <sec id="ece35162-sec-0005" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Species collection</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Specimens (
   <span class="italic">n</span> = 72) of 
   <span class="italic">Corallina officinalis</span> Linneaus populations (
   <span class="italic">n</span> = 2) were collected intertidally, during low tide in an average depth of 0.31m from the water surface at sites in the South East Coast of the UK (central population 1: St Margarets Bay: N 51.148056, E 1.385056; population 2: Westbrook Bay: N 51.388840, E 1.367170; beeline distance between populations: 26.85 km) and the North West Coast of Spain (southern margin population 1: Illa del Arousa: N 42.56870, W 8.89171; population 2: Tragove: N 42.52444, W 8.82772; beeline distance between populations: 7.19 km) in February 2017. Specimens were transported into the laboratory at the Institute of Marine Sciences of the University of Portsmouth, UK, using temperature‐insulating containers. Only healthy specimens without epiphytes and indication of bleaching or damage were selected for this study.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece35162-sec-0006" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Species identification</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To verify species identification, genomic DNA was extracted from three replicates of each population using PowerSoil DNA Isolation Kit (MoBio Laboratories, Carlsbad, CA) in accordance with the manufacturer's instructions. Partial amplification of around 664‐bp fragment of standard DNA barcode region (COI‐5P) was performed using primers GazF1 and GazR with polymerase chain reaction conditions described in Pardo, Peña, Berreiro, and Bárbara (
   <a rid="ece35162-bib-0063" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35162-bib-0063">2015</a>). Amplified fragments were run in an ABI PRISM 3130xl automated capillary sequencer (Applied Biosystems, CCMAR Portugal). MtDNA sequences were aligned, proofread, and edited in GENEIOUS 3.8 (Drummond et al., 
   <a rid="ece35162-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35162-bib-0027">2011</a>). Determination of taxonomic status was made by comparing the sequences obtained in our study to published sequences retrieved from GenBank. For 
   <span class="italic">Corallina officinalis</span>: BM000806013, BM000804477, BM000804459, BM000804370, BM000804472 (Williamson et al., 
   <a rid="ece35162-bib-0078" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35162-bib-0078">2015</a>). For 
   <span class="italic">Ellisolandia elongata</span>: JQ615843, BM000806006 (Williamson et al., 
   <a rid="ece35162-bib-0078" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35162-bib-0078">2015</a>), KF461004, KF461018, KF461017 (Pardo et al., 
   <a rid="ece35162-bib-0063" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35162-bib-0063">2015</a>). For 
   <span class="italic">Corallina caespitosa</span>: BM000806012, BM000804521, BM000804492, BM000804378, BM000806003 (Williamson et al., 
   <a rid="ece35162-bib-0078" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35162-bib-0078">2015</a>). Following an alignment and trimming of GenBank sequences and the ones from this study, pairwise sequence similarity scores were calculated using CLUSTALW multiple sequence alignment program (Thompson, Higgins, &amp; Gibson, 
   <a rid="ece35162-bib-0070" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35162-bib-0070">1994</a>; Table 
   <a rid="ece35162-tbl-0001" ref-type="table" href="#ece35162-tbl-0001">1</a>).
  </p>
  <div id="ece35162-tbl-0001" xml:lang="en" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Table 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Pairwise sequence similarity scores (%)</p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/>
    <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/>
    <thead valign="top">
     <tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000">
      <th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </th>
      <th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
       <span class="italic">Corallina officinalis</span>—this study
      </th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
       <span class="italic">Corallina officinalis</span>—Williamson et al. (
       <a rid="ece35162-bib-0078" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35162-bib-0078">2015</a>)
      </td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.59–100</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
       <span class="italic">Corallina caespitosa</span>—Williamson et al. (
       <a rid="ece35162-bib-0078" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35162-bib-0078">2015</a>)
      </td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89.79–92.24</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
       <span class="italic">Ellisolandia elongata</span>—Williamson et al. (
       <a rid="ece35162-bib-0078" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35162-bib-0078">2015</a>) &amp; Pardo et al. (
       <a rid="ece35162-bib-0063" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35162-bib-0063">2015</a>)
      </td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.67–84.89</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
   <div class="permissions">
    <span class="copyright-holder">John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd</span>
   </div>
  </div>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece35162-sec-0007" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Experimental setup</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the laboratory, specimens were carefully placed upright onto a rock in the water, held in place with a net (2 mm mesh size) in order to simulate natural conditions and each population was color coded for future identification. Aquaria of 11.1 L (
   <span class="italic">n</span> = 3) for each of the two countries and temperature conditions (total 
   <span class="italic">n</span> = 12) were set up in a water bath (for detailed setup see Figure 
   <a rid="ece35162-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#ece35162-fig-0001">1</a>). 75% of the water in the replicate aquaria was changed every second day and treated with UV light (P2‐110W Commercial UV Steriliser, max. flow rate: 65 L/min. Tropic Marine Centre (TMC), London, UK) prior to the disposal. Temperature conditions were kept constant using TK‐2000 chillers (cooling capacity of 870 W, 800 L/hr. TECO, Ravenna, Italy). Each aquarium was equipped with a water pump (V
   <span class="sup">2</span>PowerPump 800, Flow rate: 700 L/hr. TMC, London, UK) and an air stone to simulate tidal water movements and ensure oxygen supply with ambient air. Specimens were kept at their respective local in situ temperatures measured during sampling (central conditions: temperature: 5.7°C, light: 57 μmol m
   <span class="sup">−2</span> s
   <span class="sup">−1</span>; southern conditions: temperature: 11.3°C, light: 184 μmol m
   <span class="sup">−2</span> s
   <span class="sup">−1</span>). Both treatments were subject to a light:dark cycle of 10:14 hr (taken from the average of natural conditions of center and southern locations) produced and controlled by AQUABEAM 600 Ultima Reef White lights with cloud function (TMC, London, UK). Additionally, sunset and sunrise were mimicked through a slow increase and decrease of light intensities over a period of 1 hr. All specimens were kept in their corresponding conditions for a minimum of 1 week to acclimate to aquaria conditions. Following the initial acclimatization, half of the central and southern populations were gradually acclimatized (increase/decrease of 1.5°C/week and 40 μmol m
   <span class="sup">−2</span> s
   <span class="sup">−1</span>/week, respectively) to the opposite temperature and light conditions over a period of 3.5 weeks. After acclimatization, specimens were randomly and equally distributed within the corresponding replicate aquaria and kept for three months (Figure 
   <a rid="ece35162-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#ece35162-fig-0001">1</a>).
  </p>
  <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece35162-fig-0001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p> Detailed schematic of the common garden experiment setup. Representing central (UK) conditions on the left in green and dark orange and southern (Spanish, SP) conditions on the right in red and light orange. Squares with “P” represent installed pumps for water movement. Gray squares represent pressure air adjustment valves</p>
   </div>
   <div id="nlm-graphic-3" xlink:href="ECE3-9-5787-g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece35162-sec-0008" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.4</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Monitoring of water parameters</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Temperature, salinity, dissolved oxygen, pH, and total alkalinity (A
   <sub>T</sub>) were monitored daily. Irradiance was measured once a month to monitor the decrease in light intensity using a HOBO UA‐002‐64 Pendant Temp/Light data logger (accuracy: 0.47°C, resolution: 0.1°C. Tempcon, Arundel, UK). Temperature and salinity were measured with a CO310‐1 portable salinity and temperature probe (accuracy: 0.2% for salinity, ±0.2°C for temperature; resolution: 0.1 for salinity, 0.1°C for temperature. VWR, Leicestershire, UK). Dissolved oxygen and pH were measured with an HQ30d portable multi‐parameter meter and a luminescent dissolved oxygen (LDO101, accuracy: ±0.1 mg/L. HACH, Manchester, UK) and pH probe (PHC301, accuracy: ±0.02 pH, HACH, Manchester, UK. Calibrated on the National Bureau of Standards (NBS) scale and converted into total scale values using Tris/HCl and 2‐aminopyridine/HCl buffer solutions after Dickson, Sabine, and Christian (
   <a rid="ece35162-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35162-bib-0024">2007</a>)). A
   <sub>T</sub> was monitored daily in one randomly chosen replicate for each treatment, using the alkalinity anomaly technique after Smith and Key (
   <a rid="ece35162-bib-0068" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35162-bib-0068">1975</a>), Chisholm and Gattuso (
   <a rid="ece35162-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35162-bib-0014">1991</a>), and Dickson et al. (
   <a rid="ece35162-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35162-bib-0024">2007</a>), (SOP 3b). A
   <sub>T</sub> titrations were carried out with an automatic titrator TitroLine 7000 (measurement accuracy: 0.002 ± 1 digit, dosing accuracy: 0.15%, dosing precision: 0.05%–0.07%. Schott SI Analytics, Mainz, Germany) to ensure minimal variation. As titrant, 0.1N hydrochloric acid (HCl) was used, which was validated against Certified Reference Material provided by Andrew G. Dickson (Batch 154, Scripps Institution of Oceanography).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece35162-sec-0009" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.5</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Physiological incubation procedures and measurements</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To determine saturating light levels of 
   <span class="italic">C. officinalis</span> populations before and after the experiment, the oxygen production (P‐I curve) and calcification (C‐I curve) evolution under increasing light conditions were measured. For this, 0.97 ± 0.07 g fresh weight of algal fronds was transferred into a clear closed cell 58 ml incubation chamber and incubated successively for 1 hr at each of the seven different light intensities (0, 20, 80, 160, 320, 500, and 700 μmol m
   <span class="sup">−2</span> s
   <span class="sup">−1</span>; AQUARAY Nature Perfect, TMC, London, UK), starting from the lowest to the highest to minimize stress. Three replicates per light intensity were incubated simultaneously and bubble‐free. To account and correct for metabolism effects by other organisms, reference incubations without algae were performed alongside the above‐described incubations for all light intensities. Aluminum foil was used to coat the chambers to determine calcification and respiration rates in the dark. Irradiance was measured with a Quantitherm PAR/Temperature Sensor with a QTP1 probe (resolution: 1 μmol m
   <span class="sup">−2</span> s
   <span class="sup">−1</span>, 0.02°C, respectively. Hansatech, Norfolk, UK).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Differences in oxygen concentration, pH, and A
   <sub>T</sub> were determined in order to calculate photosynthesis, respiration, and calcification rates by measuring oxygen, pH, and A
   <sub>T</sub>, respectively, before and after the incubations. Prior to the A
   <sub>T</sub> measurements, seawater samples were filtered through a syringe filter (hydrophilic 25 mm, 0.2 μm PTFE. Fisherbrand, Loughborough, UK) into sterile 50 ml tubes (Plastic Centrifuge Tubes. Fisherbrand, Loughborough, UK). Immediately after, potentiometric titrations were performed using an automatic titrator (details: see above) calibrated on the NBS scale. Results were calculated based on a Gran function after Dickson et al. (
   <a rid="ece35162-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35162-bib-0024">2007</a>). The carbonate system of the seawater was calculated from pH, A
   <sub>T</sub>, salinity, and temperature using the Excel Macro CO2Sys (Version 2.1, Lewis &amp; Wallace, 
   <a rid="ece35162-bib-0050" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35162-bib-0050">1998</a>) with K1 and K2 according to Mehrbach, Culberson, Hawley, and Pytkowicx (
   <a rid="ece35162-bib-0057" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35162-bib-0057">1973</a>) and refit by Dickson and Millero (
   <a rid="ece35162-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35162-bib-0023">1987</a>) (Table 
   <a rid="ece35162-tbl-0002" ref-type="table" href="#ece35162-tbl-0002">2</a>). Measurement ranges of pH values represent in situ values and are highly dependent on temperature.
  </p>
  <div id="ece35162-tbl-0002" xml:lang="en" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Table 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Carbonate system parameters of the whole setup during the 3‐month culturing of Corallina officinalis. All numbers are mean values (
     <span class="italic">n</span> = 81 ±
     <span class="italic">SD</span>). pH, salinity, temperature, and total alkalinity (A
     <sub>T</sub>) were measured while the other parameters were calculated
    </p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/>
    <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/>
    <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/>
    <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/>
    <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/>
    <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/>
    <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/>
    <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/>
    <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/>
    <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/>
    <thead valign="top">
     <tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000">
      <th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Treatment</th>
      <th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pH (total scale)</th>
      <th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sal</th>
      <th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">T [°C]</th>
      <th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A
       <sub>T</sub> [μmol/kg]
      </th>
      <th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">DIC [μmol/kg]</th>
      <th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">HCO
       <sub>3</sub>
       <span class="sup">‐</span> [μmol/kg]
      </th>
      <th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ω
       <sub>Ca</sub>
      </th>
      <th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ω
       <sub>Ar</sub>
      </th>
      <th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pCO
       <sub>2</sub> [μatm]
      </th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Center</td>
      <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.19 ± 0.07</td>
      <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.9 ± 0.6</td>
      <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.70 ± 0.73</td>
      <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,344 ± 43</td>
      <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,185.9 ± 46.6</td>
      <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2049.1 ± 50.6</td>
      <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.32 ± 0.27</td>
      <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.48 ± 0.17</td>
      <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">377 ± 61</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">South</td>
      <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.22 ± 0.08</td>
      <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.2 ± 0.5</td>
      <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11.33 ± 0.39</td>
      <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,326 ± 37</td>
      <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2,100.0 ± 46.4</td>
      <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1925.6 ± 54.3</td>
      <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.23 ± 0.30</td>
      <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.08 ± 0.19</td>
      <td align="char" char="±" rowspan="1" colspan="1">319 ± 45</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
   <div class="permissions">
    <span class="copyright-holder">John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd</span>
   </div>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To determine changes in photosynthesis, respiration, and calcification rates most likely to be found in the field, additional incubations (
   <span class="italic">n</span> = 3) of all treatments at ambient light conditions (57 μmol m
   <span class="sup">−2</span> s
   <span class="sup">−1</span> for center and 184 μmol m
   <span class="sup">−2</span> s
   <span class="sup">−1</span> for southern populations) were performed before and after the study following the protocol above. Calculations were performed following the methodology described above.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The weight of algae fronds used in the incubations was transformed from FW into dry weight (DW) by multiplying FW measurements with the factor 0.62286. This factor was determined from FW and DW weight measurements of thirty 1 g frond bundles from all populations before and after algae were left to dry for 48 hr in an oven at 60ºC.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece35162-sec-0010" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.6</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data and statistical analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The maximum potential photosynthetic rate per individual (
   <span class="italic">P</span>
   <sub>max</sub> [mg O
   <sub>2</sub> g
   <span class="sup">−1</span> FW hr
   <span class="sup">−1</span>]) was directly determined from the oxygen evolution curves, whereas the slope of the light‐limited region of the P‐I curve stating the efficiency of the algae to harvests light (α) was calculated using Excel. The irradiance at which photosynthesis is saturated (
   <span class="italic">I</span>
   <sub>K</sub> [μmol m
   <span class="sup">−2</span> s
   <span class="sup">−1</span>]) was calculated using the following relationship:
   <div id="ece35162-disp-0001" class="disp-formula">
    <span class="label">(1)</span>
    <div id="nlm-math-3" class="math">
     <div class="mrow">
      <div class="msub">
       <span class="mi">I</span>
       <span class="mi">k</span>
      </div>
      <span class="mo">=</span>
      <div class="mfrac">
       <div class="msub">
        <span class="mi">P</span>
        <span movablelimits="true" class="mo">max</span>
       </div>
       <span class="mi">α</span>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Primary production was measured using oxygen fluxes such as photosynthesis (
   <span class="italic">P</span>
   <sub>N</sub> [mg O
   <sub>2</sub> g
   <span class="sup">−1</span> FW hr
   <span class="sup">−1</span>]) and respiration (R [mg O
   <sub>2</sub> g
   <span class="sup">−1</span> FW hr
   <span class="sup">−1</span>]) and was calculated as follows:
   <div id="ece35162-disp-0002" class="disp-formula">
    <span class="label">(2)</span>
    <div id="nlm-math-4" class="math">
     <div class="mrow">
      <div class="msub">
       <span class="mi">P</span>
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">N</span>
      </div>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span width="0.333333em" class="mspace"/>
       <span class="mtext">or</span>
       <span width="0.333333em" class="mspace"/>
      </div>
      <span class="mi">R</span>
      <div close=")" open="(" separators="" class="mfenced">
       <div class="msub">
        <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">O</span>
        <span class="mn">2</span>
       </div>
      </div>
      <span class="mo">=</span>
      <div close=")" open="(" separators="" class="mfenced">
       <div class="mfrac">
        <div class="mrow">
         <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">Δ</span>
         <div class="msub">
          <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">O</span>
          <span class="mn">2</span>
         </div>
         <span class="mo">×</span>
         <span class="mi">V</span>
        </div>
        <div class="mrow">
         <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">Δ</span>
         <span class="mi">t</span>
         <span class="mo">×</span>
         <span class="mtext">FW</span>
        </div>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>with ∆O
   <sub>2</sub> as the change in dissolved oxygen concentration [mg/L], V as the volume of the incubation chamber [L], ∆
   <span class="italic">t</span> as the incubation time [hr], and FW as the fresh weight of the algae.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Calcification (
   <span class="italic">G</span> [meq CaCO
   <sub>3</sub> g
   <span class="sup">−1</span> FW hr
   <span class="sup">−1</span>]) rates were estimated using the following equation:
   <div id="ece35162-disp-0003" class="disp-formula">
    <span class="label">(3)</span>
    <div id="nlm-math-5" class="math">
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mi">G</span>
      <div close=")" open="(" separators="" class="mfenced">
       <div class="msub">
        <span class="mtext">CaCO</span>
        <span class="mn">3</span>
       </div>
      </div>
      <span class="mo">=</span>
      <span class="mo">−</span>
      <div close=")" open="(" separators="" class="mfenced">
       <div class="mfrac">
        <div class="mrow">
         <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">Δ</span>
         <div class="msub">
          <span class="mi">T</span>
          <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">A</span>
         </div>
         <span class="mo">×</span>
         <span class="mi">V</span>
        </div>
        <div class="mrow">
         <span class="mn">2</span>
         <span class="mo">×</span>
         <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">Δ</span>
         <span class="mi">t</span>
         <span class="mo">×</span>
         <span class="mtext">FW</span>
        </div>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>with ∆
   <span class="italic">A</span>
   <sub>T</sub> as the change in total alkalinity [meq/L].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All analyses were run in SPSS Statistics 24 (IBM Corp, 
   <a rid="ece35162-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35162-bib-0040">2016</a>), and data were tested for normality and homogeneity prior analyses (Shapiro–Wilk and Levene's test, for 
   <span class="italic">p</span> values, Table S1, see Data Repository). Data for net production (
   <span class="italic">n</span> = 3) were not normally distributed, resulting in statistical analysis using the nonparametric Kruskal–Wallis 
   <span class="italic">H</span> test. Data for respiration (
   <span class="italic">n</span> = 3) as well as dark calcification (
   <span class="italic">n</span> = 3) measurements showed a significant Levene's test with raw as well as transformed data due to high variance. Therefore, data were analyzed using multiple single comparisons of one‐way analysis of variance (ANOVA). Normally distributed data of the dependant variable light calcification (
   <span class="italic">n</span> = 3) were analyzed using two‐way ANOVAs for individuals from each country of origin (UK (center) or SP (southern margin)) with treatment (three levels: pre‐experiment, central conditions, and southern conditions) as the fixed factor. When significant effects were found, data were further explored by running a post hoc Tukey's HSD test. Tests were performed for central and southern populations under each temperature condition comparing measurements before and after the experiment.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Additional two‐way ANOVAs and Tukey's HSD post hoc tests of central and southern populations were performed to identify significant differences in their maximum oxygen production and calcification level of all populations in all temperature treatments.</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
