<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The effect of SLR on the astronomical tide was quantified through dynamic tidal ocean simulations (using the DFLOW FM model) (fig. S8). The simulations considered SLR scenarios resulting from the combination of steric changes with three land-ice scenarios of water contributions from ice sheets and glaciers (
 <xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">18</italic>
 </xref>). The analysis is described in detail in (
 <xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">17</italic>
 </xref>) with the only difference that we considered changes in the complete time series, rather than in the daily maxima only. Since the sensitivity of the final tide amplitude to the land-ice scenarios is very small (
 <xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">17</italic>
 </xref>), we considered the median of the three scenarios only. The actual observed time lag between the surge and astronomical tide sequences is random. The estimated CF return periods are thus just one random realization of all possible time lags between surges and astronomical tides. To get an estimate of a more likely CF return period, we computed the median of all possible estimates. We observe that this procedure does not allow one to take into account the variability of the return periods caused by the natural variability of the meteorological conditions. For the ERA-Interim–driven data, we obtained this estimate by calculating 240 individual estimates based on the superposition of (i) the simulated surge time series (including waves) and (ii) the randomly shifted tide time series. The part of the tide series beyond the length of the surge series was moved to the start date. From this ensemble, we computed the median of the CF return periods (
 <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig" class="xref">Fig. 2</xref>). It turned out that the difference between the standard estimate and the bootstrap-based estimate was small. As this procedure is computationally expensive, we therefore refrained from applying it to the CMIP5-based data.
</p>
