<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Change in RTS activity (1984–2015)</div>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We observed a remarkable increase in RTS activity (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2a</a>). Only 63 RTS appeared active on the entire island in 1984 (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2b</a>). Over the next three decades, more than 4500 RTS were initiated and the number of active RTS increased 60-fold, reaching a maximum of 4077 in 2013 (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2c</a>). 86% of these RTS were newly observed in the imagery from four of the 32 years: 1999 (1682 RTS), 2011 (445 RTS), 2012 (1385 RTS) and 2013 (379 RTS) (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2a</a>).
  <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Observations of active retrogressive thaw slumps on Banks Island (1984–2014). 
     <span class="bold">a</span> Annually resolved numbers of newly observed slumps (1985–2014) classified by location of initiation. Potential errors (not shown) are assessed as −5% to +10% (see Methods). 
     <span class="bold">b</span> Distribution of 63 retrogressive thaw slumps observed to be active in 1984 at the start of the Timelapse period. 
     <span class="bold">c</span> Distribution of retrogressive thaw slumps active in 2013 when numbers peaked at 4077. 
     <span class="bold">d</span> Relationship between 2-year weighted mean July–August air temperature (derived from the Hadley CRU dataset
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>,
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>
     </span>) and the number of newly observed retrogressive thaw slumps. Solid line is best-fit and dashed lines are 95% confidence intervals
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2019_9314_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e488" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The number of newly observed RTS was clearly linked to summer air temperature. It was predictable using a log-linear relation with a 2-year average of July–August air temperature weighted between the preceding summer (66.7%) and the current year (33.3%) (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2d</a>). The weighting reflects the possibility that RTS may become visible on Timelapse imagery in the actual year of their initiation or, more frequently, in the following year. The log-linear form of the relationship underlines that it is extreme positive summer air temperatures that are most significant to RTS initiation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">RTS initiated since 1984 had a 70% probability of remaining active for more than 20 ± 1 years with 50% expected to remain active for longer than 31 ± 1 years, enlarging throughout this period (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3a</a>). Using a sample of RTS areas (
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 341) (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3b</a>), we calculate that active RTS on Banks Island occupied a total area of 1.0 km
  <span class="sup">2</span> in 1984 but by 2015 this had greatly increased to 64.1 km
  <span class="sup">2</span> (range 55.0–73.2 km
  <span class="sup">2</span>) with a rate of annual expansion of 5.1 ± 0.2 km
  <span class="sup">2</span> yr
  <span class="sup">−1</span> (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4b</a>). The average RTS area was 1.63 ± 0.23 ha in 2015, but this varied through the years from a minimum of 0.37 (0.19–0.61) ha in 1999 to a maximum of 1.97 (1.75–2.19) ha in 2010 (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4a</a>). These variations reflect the formation of numerous small RTS during major initiation events and their subsequent enlargement through time. The largest single RTS had an area of 16 ha in 2015, which is smaller than mega-slumps farther south
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span>, but the latter were surpassed in area by several laterally conjoined RTS which occupied 125 ha and extended along a lakeshore for 2.5 km (Supplementary Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>, Supplementary Video 
  <a rid="MOESM5" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM5">1</a>).
  <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Longevity and growth of retrogressive thaw slumps. 
     <span class="bold">a</span> Percent of all observed features remaining active for a given duration. Best-fit relation is for retrogressive thaw slumps &gt;2 years old and for sample size &gt;30 (upper solid line). Dotted lines are 95% confidence intervals. Lower solid line is sample size. All retrogressive thaw slumps were active for at least 3 years. 
     <span class="bold">b</span> Measured area of sampled active retrogressive thaw slumps against age. Best-fit line was constrained through the origin. Dotted lines are 95% confidence intervals
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2019_9314_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e556" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <div id="Fig4" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Calculated area of active retrogressive thaw slumps on Banks Island (1984–2015). 
     <span class="bold">a</span> Average feature area based on population age distribution in each year and the area-age relationship in Fig. 
     <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3b</a>. Error bars are 95% confidence intervals. 
     <span class="bold">b</span> Total area of active retrogressive thaw slumps. Dotted lines are 95% confidence intervals
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2019_9314_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e574" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Assuming an average elevation loss associated with headscarp retrogression of 1–2 m on Banks Island
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
  </span>, the ice volume lost due to RTS activity from 1985–2015 is calculated to be 63.1–126.2 × 10
  <span class="sup">6</span> m
  <span class="sup">3</span> (range 54.0–146.4 × 10
  <span class="sup">6</span> m
  <span class="sup">3</span>). This is equivalent to a mass loss of 0.058–0.116 Gt (range 0.050–0.134 Gt) over three decades.
 </p>
</sec>
