<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Impacts on water bodies</div>
 <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Three lakes (each &lt;1.3 ha in area) were infilled completely by sediment from adjacent RTS. A further 285 lakes were impacted sufficiently to change colour in the satellite imagery, from dark blue to turquoise or beige (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig7">7a–c</a>), presumably as a result of increases in the concentration of sediment suspended in the water column. All but seven were located in the Jesse Moraine where fines contents (silt and clay) in the till average 59%
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
  </span>, representing significant quantities for potential suspension. More than 95% of these lakes had RTS on their shores or on slopes leading into the lake while 4% were impacted by RTS that were active up-basin. The colour changes affected lakes of all sizes, including the largest on the island (63 km
  <span class="sup">2</span>), which developed 83 active RTS on its shorelines (Supplementary Video 
  <a rid="MOESM5" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM5">1</a>).
  <div id="Fig7" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 7</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Lake colour change due to retrogressive thaw slump activity. 
     <span class="bold">a</span> Annually resolved time series of numbers of lakes visually changing colour (from dark blue to turquoise or beige) observed for Banks Island (1984–2016) using Timelapse. 
     <span class="bold">b</span>, 
     <span class="bold">c</span> Individual lake colour change from 1984 to 2016 due to retrogressive thaw slumps becoming active around the shoreline (73.08°N 117.67°W). 
     <span class="bold">d</span>, 
     <span class="bold">e</span> Example of the development of a new bay in a lake due to retrogressive thaw slump activity (71.65°N 121.91°W). More than 200 m of shoreline recession occurred from 2000–2016. Red circles in (
     <span class="bold">c</span> and 
     <span class="bold">e</span>) are locations of retrogressive thaw slumps which became active during the Timelapse period
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2019_9314_Fig7_HTML" id="d29e798" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The temporal pattern of lake colour change followed that of RTS initiation: the two summers with the highest number of observed changes were 1999 and 2012 (79 in each year). The number of lakes impacted simultaneously reached a peak of 254 in 2014 and the probability of changes persisting for more than 15 years was on average 63%, compared to the probability of RTS remaining active for the same duration of 79%. These results, and the observation that some lakes changed colour intermittently despite an adjacent RTS being continuously active, demonstrate that visible effects can vary through time, likely depending on the strength of the hydrological connections between the retrogressing headscarp where water and sediment are generated and the lacustrine system at the RTS outlet
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The impacts of the RTS on aquatic ecosystems in the region require additional investigation. Four fish species are present in lakes that were sampled in southwest Banks Island
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
  </span> but our dataset shows that none of these lakes has been affected by RTS activity since 1984. The complexity of ecosystems in the lakes actually affected by RTS is unknown, as are the impacts of additional sediment loading and changes in solutes
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>
  </span>. However, the new RTS dataset could be used to set up a well-constrained sampling scheme to examine the intensity and timing of impacts.
 </p>
 <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Timelapse images suggest a unique RTS triggering mechanism at six lakes ranging in size from 50–900 ha. RTS developed contemporaneously with rapid recession of the shoreline (5–22 m/year), possibly due to wave action and thermal abrasion
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span>. Timelapse revealed the formation of entirely new bays in the shorelines of these lakes (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig7">7d and e</a>; Supplementary Video 
  <a rid="MOESM11" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM11">7</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">River valleys were also impacted by sediment generated by RTS
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span>. Catchments in the eastern part of the island, in particular, were subject to extensive valley floor sedimentation from 1999 onwards and sediment was transported as far as the ocean
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
  </span> (Supplementary Videos 
  <a rid="MOESM6" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM6">2</a>, 
  <a rid="MOESM12" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM12">8</a> and 
  <a rid="MOESM13" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM13">9</a>). The quantity of organic carbon exported remains unknown at present.
 </p>
</sec>
