<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Spatial distribution</div>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">RTS activity was spatially concentrated, with most occurring in a 25–50 km wide band adjoining the eastern, southern and northern coasts of the island (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2c</a>), a distribution associated with the maximum extent of Late Wisconsinan glacial ice cover
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
  </span>. The area with active RTS comprised 17.3% of the 25 km
  <span class="sup">2</span> grid cells covering the island (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5a</a>). A small number of RTS were present on the west coast, including on offshore islands, and in interior areas along the track of ice that retreated southwards in the late Wisconsinan
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
  </span>. Maximum densities by number or by area affected were higher than previously reported
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span> reaching 18 RTS in a 1 km
  <span class="sup">2</span> grid cell and 88 RTS in a 25 km
  <span class="sup">2</span> cell (Supplementary Video 
  <a rid="MOESM6" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM6">2</a>). Using the average RTS area in 2015, these correspond respectively to disturbance totalling 29 ha km
  <span class="sup">−2</span> and 141 ha in 25 km
  <span class="sup">2</span>. Although active RTS cover only about 0.1% of the entire island, this extent is several orders of magnitude greater than in recently studied transects elsewhere in the Arctic
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
  </span>. This spatial clustering, linked to ground ice content and Quaternary history, underlines the heterogeneity of permafrost landscape vulnerability to climate warming
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span>.
  <div id="Fig5" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 5</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Distribution of all active retrogressive thaw slumps (1984–2015). 
     <span class="bold">a</span> Spatial concentration (25 km
     <span class="sup">2</span> grid cells). 
     <span class="bold">b</span> Distribution by locus of initiation
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2019_9314_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e670" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Most RTS were active in the southern and central parts of Banks Island prior to 2007 (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6</a>). In the last nine years of the record, however, &gt;500 RTS were initiated in the northern third of the island. This significant areal expansion coincided with increases in July–August air temperature measured in this part of the island (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6a</a>).
  <div id="Fig6" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 6</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Spatial response of retrogressive thaw slump initiation to differential warming. 
     <span class="bold">a</span> Weighted 2-year July–August average air temperature at three official climate stations on Banks Island: Sachs Harbour (1984–2015), Thomsen River (1998–2015) and Nangmagvik Lake (1997–2015). 
     <span class="bold">b</span> Total active retrogressive thaw slumps in southern (≤72.16°N—red line), central (72.17–73.23°N—blue line) and northern (&gt;73.23°N—purple line) zones. Inset map shows the boundaries of the three zones, the location of the three climate stations, and retrogressive thaw slumps first observed in 2012
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2019_9314_Fig6_HTML" id="d29e693" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">RTS were initiated most frequently next to rivers (45%), and less often on slopes (27%), around lakes (23%) and at the coast (5%) (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5b</a>; Supplementary Videos 
  <a rid="MOESM7" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM7">3</a>–
  <a rid="MOESM10" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM10">6</a>). As observed by Inuvialuit
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
  </span>, coastal RTS became proportionally less important during the record, declining from 24% of the overall RTS population in 1984 to 6% in 2015 (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2a</a>). Notwithstanding relative change by locus of initiation, each of the four types of RTS increased by at least 20 times in absolute numbers.
 </p>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The finding that all types of RTS increased in the major initiation years (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2a</a>) is unexpected. There is no obvious reason why processes as diverse as fluvial, lacustrine and coastal erosion or long-term talik development adjacent to lakes
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
  </span>, all previously linked to the initial exposure of ground ice
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>, should initiate large numbers of RTS in the same year. Our results, therefore, suggest an alternate mechanism. In a warm summer, as with active layer detachment formation, thaw consolidation at the base of the active layer or in the thawing transient layer leads to high porewater pressures, a reduction in effective shear strength, and slope failure where the factor of safety falls below unity
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
  </span>. This exposes ice-rich permafrost protected beneath previously undisturbed slopes, or underlying the floors of previously stabilised RTS and triggers new RTS. Fluvial, coastal and lacustrine erosion remain important over the long-term, acting as pre-conditioners to RTS initiation by de-buttressing slopes through lateral erosion, vertical incision or thaw settlement. The major initiator of RTS on Banks Island, however, is a deepening thaw layer
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
  </span> caused by particularly warm summers such as 1998
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>
  </span>. A progressive rise in mean summer air temperature due to climate change, punctuated by positive deviations from that moving average, is therefore expected to trigger new RTS (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2d</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
