<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Divergent magnitude and distribution of temperature effects</div>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our simulations reveal substantial inequality in the global-mean temperature response to identical total annual aerosol emissions in each region (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1b</a>, 
  <span class="italic">y</span>-axis). The largest global mean temperature change (−0.29 ± 0.01 °C, induced in our simulations by emissions from Western Europe) is approximately 14 times larger than the smallest global mean temperature changes (−0.02 ± 0.01 °C induced by emissions from India). Global-mean temperature effects correlate roughly with latitude, with higher latitude emitting regions typically generating stronger temperature effects than lower latitude regions, a behavior also seen in previous studies of the response to aerosol forcing in different latitude bands
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
  </span>. However, substantial differentiation occurs within latitude bands. For example, emissions sourced from East Africa generate approximately four times more cooling (−0.06 ± 0.01 °C) than emissions from India (−0.02 ± 0.02 °C) at similar latitudes—demonstrating the importance of our region-by-region focus.
 </p>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There are also important regional distinctions in the degree to which the temperature changes due to aerosol emissions are likely to be concentrated in the emitting region versus being felt globally (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1b</a>, placement relative to diagonals). Because aerosols generally remain concentrated near their source and most strongly influence surface temperature by attenuating incoming solar radiation to the regions they overlie, they cool the emitting region more strongly than the global mean in all cases (Figs. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1b</a>, 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>). However, although Indian emissions produce the smallest global-mean cooling effects, their impacts are much more strongly concentrated within the emitting region than for other regions. India experiences cooling from its own emissions at a level ~21 times greater than the global mean (−0.42 ± 0.03 K versus −0.02 ± 0.01 K), while Western European, and Indonesian emissions generate localized cooling (−0.50 ± 0.06, and −0.14 ± 0.05 K, respectively) that is less than two times as great as the respective global-mean cooling (−0.29 ± 0.01, and −0.07 ± 0.01 K, respectively). As a result, even though Western European emissions produce ~14 times the global mean cooling effect of Indian emissions, India and Western Europe experience comparable regional-mean cooling from their own emissions. In other words, regions like Western Europe, Indonesia, and (to a slightly lesser extent) the United States strongly export the climate impacts of their emissions, while regions like India more strongly experience the cooling effects of their own emissions.
  <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Patterns of surface air temperature response to identical aerosol emissions from eight regions. Spatial patterns of surface air temperature change in response to identical aerosol emission in each the eight regions are shown. Global mean temperature change (K) with standard error is shown in bottom left. Grid markings indicate regions that are not statistically significant at the 95% confidence level via 
     <span class="italic">t</span>-test
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2018_5838_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e420" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
