<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Connection to Pacific and Northern Hemisphere Holocene Climate.</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To explain the forcing behind the observed variations in OSIW ventilation, and in particular the Middle-Holocene climatic shift toward the modern well-ventilated regime, we compared our data to other regional records. Globally, and in regions influenced by the East Asian summer monsoon (EASM) (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">Figs. 2
   <span class="italic">F</span>
  </a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig04" href="#fig04">4
   <span class="italic">B</span>
  </a>), a Middle-Holocene shift is documented (
  <a rid="r28" ref-type="bibr" href="#r28">28</a>). Before 6 ka, a stronger EASM (
  <a rid="r29" ref-type="bibr" href="#r29">29</a>, 
  <a rid="r30" ref-type="bibr" href="#r30">30</a>) propagated further northeastward than at present, yielding higher precipitation and temperatures in the Okhotsk Sea hinterland (
  <a rid="r31" ref-type="bibr" href="#r31">31</a>), increasing runoff from the Amur River catchment into the Okhotsk Sea (
  <a rid="r32" ref-type="bibr" href="#r32">32</a>). Higher Amur freshwater discharge also transports significant amounts of heat to the Okhotsk Sea (
  <a rid="r32" ref-type="bibr" href="#r32">32</a>, 
  <a rid="r33" ref-type="bibr" href="#r33">33</a>), which suppresses sea ice formation and, in concert with stronger thermal stratification of the upper mixed layer (
  <a rid="r34" ref-type="bibr" href="#r34">34</a>), decreases OSIW ventilation. After 6 ka, strengthening and expansion of the winter Siberian High in concert with a southward retreating EASM front was likely responsible for strengthening cold northeasterly winds over the continental shelf region (
  <a rid="r35" ref-type="bibr" href="#r35">35</a>). In addition, the maximum sea ice extent in the Okhotsk Sea is dependent on mean sea surface temperature (SST) conditions in summer (
  <a rid="r36" ref-type="bibr" href="#r36">36</a>). We thus infer a longer and more extensive sea ice cover, more polynyas, and more vigorous mixing of the mixed layer after 6 ka, which together enhanced the ventilation of new OSIW.
 </p>
 <div id="fig04" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 4.</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Model results from the earth system model COSMOS. Results are plotted in all panels as anomalies, calculated as differences resulting from 9 ka minus PI runs. (
    <span class="italic">A</span>) Annual mean temperature (T) anomaly, shown on a meridional transect along 150° E from the equator to 60° N. The transect crosses directly into the Okhotsk Sea north of 42° N. (
    <span class="italic">B</span>) Same as in 
    <span class="italic">A</span> but for annual mean salinity (S) anomaly. (
    <span class="italic">C</span>) Sea ice volume anomaly 9 ka minus PI, calculated from sea ice concentration multiplied by sea ice thickness in the North Pacific. (
    <span class="italic">D</span>) Same as 
    <span class="italic">C</span>, but for sea ice thickness.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div id="gra4" xlink:href="pnas.1714754115fig04" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Alkenone-derived SSTs for the Okhotsk Sea and the Japan continental margin consistently show maxima in Holocene SSTs between ∼8 and 6 ka, decreasing SSTs between 6 and 4 ka, and a last shift toward persistent colder SSTs around 2 ka (
  <a rid="r37" ref-type="bibr" href="#r37">37</a>, 
  <a rid="r38" ref-type="bibr" href="#r38">38</a>) (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3
   <span class="italic">D</span>
  </a>). Our observed decrease in OSIW ventilation during the EMH is thus in close agreement with increased SSTs of about 1.5 to 2 °C derived from both regional and global reconstructions (
  <a rid="r38" ref-type="bibr" href="#r38">38</a>, 
  <a rid="r39" ref-type="bibr" href="#r39">39</a>). Importantly, recent low-latitude middepth thermocline temperature changes (at around 500 m water depth) in the equatorial West Pacific show concomitant higher temperatures in the EMH of similar magnitude, with northern NPIW-sourced thermocline or intermediate water temperatures (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3
   <span class="italic">C</span>
  </a>) being warmer by 2.1 ± 0.4 °C than during the last century (
  <a rid="r40" ref-type="bibr" href="#r40">40</a>), in strong accord with our assumed decrease in ventilation in OSIW and NPIW (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3 
   <span class="italic">A</span> and 
   <span class="italic">F</span>
  </a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results from Earth System Model COSMOS (Community Earth System Model) simulations corroborate our proxy-based assumptions. This model captures the modern physical characteristics of NPIW well under preindustrial (PI) conditions (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1714754115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S5 
   <span class="italic">A</span> and 
   <span class="italic">C</span>
  </span>). We analyzed Pacific data from PI and 9-ka time-slice runs (for details, see 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1714754115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, 
   <span class="italic">Paleoclimate Modeling</span>
  </span> and ref. 
  <a rid="r41" ref-type="bibr" href="#r41">41</a>). On a meridional transect along 150° E through the Okhotsk Sea toward the equatorial Pacific, our model results show a consistently warmer (around 1 to 2 °C) and saltier intermediate water layer at 9 ka than at PI conditions (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig04" href="#fig04">Fig. 4 
   <span class="italic">A</span> and 
   <span class="italic">B</span>
  </a> and 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1714754115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S5 
   <span class="italic">B</span> and 
   <span class="italic">D</span>
  </span>), matching the proxy-based temperature changes surprisingly well (
  <a rid="r40" ref-type="bibr" href="#r40">40</a>). Model-derived anomalies (9 ka minus PI) in sea ice dynamics show a localized, significant decrease of both sea ice volume (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig04" href="#fig04">Fig. 4
   <span class="italic">C</span>
  </a>) and thickness (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig04" href="#fig04">Fig. 4
   <span class="italic">D</span>
  </a>) in the Okhotsk Sea in the EMH, in agreement with our hypothesized reductions in sea ice and polynya formation in the OSIW source region that inhibited the modern ventilation regime.
 </p>
</sec>
