<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results and Discussion</div>
 <p content-type="flushleft" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used a suite of four sediment cores to reconstruct OSIW ventilation (for details, see 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1714754115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, 
   <span class="italic">Site Selection – Material and Methods</span> and Figs. S4 and S5
  </span>). Gravity core 108 was retrieved from the western Kamchatka continental margin (52°01.330′ N, 153°35.006′ E; 627 m water depth) in the pathway of inflowing North Pacific water to the formation region of OSIW on the northeastern Okhotsk Sea continental shelf. This core thus records the precursor water mass—Western Subarctic Pacific Water (WSAPW)—delivered via the East Kamchatka Current (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" href="#fig01">Fig. 1</a>). Three sites record changes in newly formed OSIW on the eastern Sakhalin continental margin, along the export pathway into the North Pacific. Site 78 (52°40.388′ N, 144°42.203′ E; 673 m water depth) and site 4 (51°08.475′ N, 145°18.582′ E, 674 m water depth) are located within the core layer of OSIW (
  <a rid="r19" ref-type="bibr" href="#r19">19</a>, 
  <a rid="r20" ref-type="bibr" href="#r20">20</a>). Site 79 (52°47.272′ N, 144°57.318′ E; 1,082 m water depth) complements the records with a deeper location at the lower boundary of OSIW. Based on an accelerator mass spectrometry (AMS) 
  <span class="sup">14</span>C-anchored stratigraphic framework (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1714754115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, 
   <span class="italic">Age Models and Stratigraphic Framework</span> and Fig. S2
  </span>), these cores yield sedimentation rates between 20 and 180 cm/ka, thus allowing for the reconstruction of millennial-scale changes in intermediate water ventilation.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Changes in δ
  <span class="sup">13</span>C for deeper water masses without contact with surface ocean and atmosphere become linearly correlated to regenerated nutrient and O
  <sub>2</sub> concentrations (
  <a rid="r21" ref-type="bibr" href="#r21">21</a>, 
  <a rid="r22" ref-type="bibr" href="#r22">22</a>). While in some oceanic regions, other factors alter this relationship (e.g., air–sea exchange processes, thermodynamic effects, or water mass mixing) (
  <a rid="r22" ref-type="bibr" href="#r22">22</a>, 
  <a rid="r23" ref-type="bibr" href="#r23">23</a>), in the Okhotsk Sea and North Pacific, the δ
  <span class="sup">13</span>C–nutrient–O
  <sub>2</sub> relationship has been shown to be relatively simple, and these secondary factors play a less important role (
  <a rid="r24" ref-type="bibr" href="#r24">24</a>, 
  <a rid="r25" ref-type="bibr" href="#r25">25</a>) under the considerations we follow here ( 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1714754115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Figs. S1 and S2
  </span>). To validate that heavier δ
  <span class="sup">13</span>C signatures represent better-ventilated OSIW compared to WSAPW, we measured water-column δ
  <span class="sup">13</span>C
  <sub>DIC</sub> (dissolved inorganic carbon) depth profiles from two stations near our inflow and outflow locations (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" href="#fig01">Fig. 1</a>). Compared with existing North Pacific data (
  <a rid="r14" ref-type="bibr" href="#r14">14</a>, 
  <a rid="r24" ref-type="bibr" href="#r24">24</a>), we identified about 0.2 to 0.3‰ higher δ
  <span class="sup">13</span>C
  <sub>DIC</sub> values in the OSIW outflow (Station LV29-72-4) than WSAPW mean values of about −0.5‰ (Station HS29, 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" href="#fig01">Fig. 1
   <span class="italic">B</span>
  </a>), corroborating our use of δ
  <span class="sup">13</span>C as proxy for middepth water mass ventilation (see 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1714754115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, 
   <span class="italic">Use of Stable Carbon Isotopes for Assessing OSIW/NPIW Ventilation</span>
  </span>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Before using down-core records for our OSIW reconstructions, we also tested the assumption that epibenthic foraminifera of the genus 
  <span class="italic">C. mundulus</span> are reliably recording δ
  <span class="sup">13</span>C of bottom water DIC and do not incorporate unidentified offsets as reported from other oceanic regions and time intervals (
  <a rid="r18" ref-type="bibr" href="#r18">18</a>). Our results from eight undisturbed sediment surface sites with corresponding bottom water δ
  <span class="sup">13</span>C
  <sub>DIC</sub> measurements within the Okhotsk Sea show that the δ
  <span class="sup">13</span>C of live (rose bengal-stained) 
  <span class="italic">C. mundulus</span> mirrors the δ
  <span class="sup">13</span>C of bottom waters within ∼0.1‰, which is within commonly accepted values for intrasample variability in benthic foraminifera (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1714754115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Table S1
  </span>).
 </p>
 <sec id="s2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A Middle-Holocene Threshold in OSIW Ventilation.</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Sakhalin margin cores that monitor OSIW (sites 4, 78, and 79) are characterized by high-amplitude variations throughout the Holocene, exceeding glacial–interglacial changes in Pacific Deep Water ventilation (
   <a rid="r14" ref-type="bibr" href="#r14">14</a>), with values between −0.8‰ and −0.1‰ and a close resemblance between single cores. Sample resolution in the deeper core 79 is slightly worse due to the partial absence of 
   <span class="italic">Cibicidoides</span> species from the benthic fauna; however, core 79’s overall δ
   <span class="sup">13</span>C pattern matches that of the other cores. In contrast, the Kamchatka margin core 108, representing WSAPW inflow, shows δ
   <span class="sup">13</span>C values ranging mostly between −0.2‰ and −0.5‰, similar to modern values (
   <a rid="r25" ref-type="bibr" href="#r25">25</a>) but with no discernible long-term trend over the Holocene (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">Fig. 2
    <span class="italic">B</span>
   </a>). For better comparison hereafter, we discuss principal characteristics of OSIW based on a combined record (named C-OSIW) of the three outflow, or “downstream” sites representing the OSIW (sites 4, 78, and 79) (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">Figs. 2 
    <span class="italic">C</span>–
    <span class="italic">E</span>
   </a> and 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">3
    <span class="italic">A</span>
   </a>). We stacked individual records on their own age models into one record and added a 25-point smoothing to the original data to highlight millennial-scale changes (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3
    <span class="italic">A</span>
   </a>).
  </p>
  <div id="fig02" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Fig. 2.</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Stable isotope records of studied cores indicating changes in OSIW ventilation in relation to reference records. (
     <span class="italic">A</span>) NGRIP ice core δ
     <span class="sup">18</span>O time series (
     <a rid="r63" ref-type="bibr" href="#r63">63</a>). (
     <span class="italic">B</span>) Kamchatka margin core 108 epibenthic δ
     <span class="sup">13</span>C, indicating WSAP water inflow. (
     <span class="italic">C</span>–
     <span class="italic">E</span>) Sakhalin margin cores epibenthic δ
     <span class="sup">13</span>C, indicating changes in OSIW ventilation: (
     <span class="italic">C</span>) core 78 from shallow N Sakhalin margin, (
     <span class="italic">D</span>) core 4 from shallow middle Sakhalin margin, and (
     <span class="italic">E</span>) core 79 from lower N Sakhalin margin, as labeled. (
     <span class="italic">F</span>) Dongge Cave speleothem δ
     <span class="sup">18</span>O time series, representing changes in Southeast Asian summer monsoon and links to North Atlantic climate (
     <a rid="r29" ref-type="bibr" href="#r29">29</a>). Colored background highlights the two different main ventilation phases from 0 to 6 ka (LH) and from 6 to 11 ka (EMH).
    </p>
   </div>
   <div id="gra2" xlink:href="pnas.1714754115fig02" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <div id="fig03" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Fig. 3.</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>OSIW ventilation dynamics and gradients compared with long-term changes in regional and global climate records. (
     <span class="italic">A</span>) δ
     <span class="sup">13</span>C
     <sub>OSIW</sub> combined record of sites 4, 78, and 79, indicating OSIW ventilation dynamics. Gray line: original data; black thick line: resampled 25-point moving average. (
     <span class="italic">B</span>) Proxy record for intensity of EASM changes in Huguangyan Maar Lake, southern China, as expressed in total organic carbon (TOC) content (
     <a rid="r30" ref-type="bibr" href="#r30">30</a>). Note inverted scale for better comparison with OSIW ventilation record. (
     <span class="italic">C</span>) Reconstruction of intermediate water temperature (IWT) (inverted) in the equatorial West Pacific at 500 m water depth, indicative of northern-sourced NPIW reaching the low-latitude thermocline. Calculated changes over the Holocene with reference to the last 100 y, based on Mg/Ca ratios of benthic foraminifera (
     <a rid="r40" ref-type="bibr" href="#r40">40</a>). (
     <span class="italic">D</span>) Composite alkenone-based high-resolution SST record from Japan margin (cores MD01-2421, KR02-06_MC, and KR02-06_GC) (
     <a rid="r38" ref-type="bibr" href="#r38">38</a>). (
     <span class="italic">E</span>) NE Pacific Santa Barbara Basin (SBB) δ
     <span class="sup">15</span>N
     <sub>bulk</sub> record, indicating denitrification and nutrient utilization changes in waters under NPIW influence (
     <a rid="r55" ref-type="bibr" href="#r55">55</a>). (
     <span class="italic">F</span>) Ventilation difference between OSIW and WSAPW, expressed as Δδ
     <span class="sup">13</span>C between the stacked C-OISW record and site 108 (this study). Positive values (above dashed “zero” line) denote active ventilation in the Okhotsk Sea; negative values indicate ventilation loss in the Okhotsk Sea due to remineralization processes and lack of new water mass formation. (
     <span class="italic">G</span>) Atmospheric CO
     <sub>2</sub> record from EPICA Dome C ice core record (
     <a rid="r64" ref-type="bibr" href="#r64">64</a>).
    </p>
   </div>
   <div id="gra3" xlink:href="pnas.1714754115fig03" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our C-OSIW δ
   <span class="sup">13</span>C record shows a subdivision of the Holocene into two periods that have differing ventilation patterns (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">Figs. 2</a> and 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">3
    <span class="italic">A</span>
   </a>). The EMH (11 to 6 ka) exhibits significantly lower than modern δ
   <span class="sup">13</span>C values (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">Figs. 2</a> and 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">3
    <span class="italic">A</span>
   </a>), suggesting persistent ventilation minima in OSIW. In contrast, Late Holocene (LH) (0–6 ka) ventilation increases after a sudden shift around 6 ka (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">Fig. 2 
    <span class="italic">C</span> and 
    <span class="italic">D</span>
   </a>) toward modern conditions, featuring a principal Middle-Holocene threshold (or “tipping point”) in NPIW ventilation. In addition, the LH (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3
    <span class="italic">A</span>
   </a>) shows a slight but more gradual increase in the C-OSIW stack toward modern values of δ
   <span class="sup">13</span>C over the last 1 to 2 ka of about 0.1‰ (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">Figs. 2 
    <span class="italic">C</span> and 
    <span class="italic">D</span>
   </a> and 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">3
    <span class="italic">A</span>
   </a>). Therefore, a critical initial observation of this C-OSIW ventilation reconstruction is that the subarctic North Pacific middepth water layer rapidly changed its characteristics during the Middle Holocene around 6 ka toward the present-day OSIW and the connected mesopelagic North Pacific ventilation prevalence. For a better comparison between the OSIW outflow site (cores 4, 78, and 79) and the WSAPW inflow site (core 108), we subtracted the latter from our C-OSIW record to create a Δδ
   <span class="sup">13</span>C time series (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3
    <span class="italic">F</span>
   </a>), after resampling our data in evenly spaced 50-y intervals. Our Δδ
   <span class="sup">13</span>C data (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3
    <span class="italic">F</span>
   </a>) reveal that OSIW ventilation decreased below values of its precursor WSAPW before the 6-ka shift. This negative OSIW–WSAPW gradient (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3
    <span class="italic">F</span>
   </a>) implies that OSIW export into the North Pacific was, in effect, not actively ventilated in the Okhotsk Sea before 6 ka.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We assume that under Holocene boundary conditions, the principles of OSIW formation through seasonal sea ice, polynya-induced brine rejection, and mixing between surface waters and WSAPW remained essentially similar. However, apparently, the intensity of mixing well-ventilated waters into middepth levels must have increased after the Middle Holocene toward the modern setting. Other processes like changed air–sea exchange or simple source water mass variations (e.g., through higher contributions of Pacific Deep Water or mixed layer water, respectively) cannot fully explain the large observed changes in absolute δ
   <span class="sup">13</span>C values on millennial timescales, and particularly the EMH negative Δδ
   <span class="sup">13</span>C gradient (
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1714754115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S10
   </span>). Earlier qualitative multiproxy studies of nearby sites in the Okhotsk Sea (
   <a rid="r17" ref-type="bibr" href="#r17">17</a>) showed oceanographic reorganizations around 6 ka. In those results, independent evidence from microfossil assemblages suggested higher mesopelagic productivity with increased microbial biomass and higher organic matter respiration in OSIW before 6 ka (see 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1714754115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, 
    <span class="italic">Previous Studies Indicating Okhotsk Sea Ventilation Changes</span>
   </span>), while support for reduced formation of OSIW and intensified OMZ conditions was also found in nearby sites (
   <a rid="r17" ref-type="bibr" href="#r17">17</a>, 
   <a rid="r26" ref-type="bibr" href="#r26">26</a>, 
   <a rid="r27" ref-type="bibr" href="#r27">27</a>). As a result, we presume that during the EMH, physical processes likely inhibited the modern ventilation scheme, while increased remineralization of organic matter through respiration within the mixed layer and in OSIW decreased the ventilation of OSIW relative to WSAPW entering the Okhotsk Sea, leading to higher inventories of nutrients and carbon in NPIW.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Connection to Pacific and Northern Hemisphere Holocene Climate.</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To explain the forcing behind the observed variations in OSIW ventilation, and in particular the Middle-Holocene climatic shift toward the modern well-ventilated regime, we compared our data to other regional records. Globally, and in regions influenced by the East Asian summer monsoon (EASM) (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">Figs. 2
    <span class="italic">F</span>
   </a> and 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig04" href="#fig04">4
    <span class="italic">B</span>
   </a>), a Middle-Holocene shift is documented (
   <a rid="r28" ref-type="bibr" href="#r28">28</a>). Before 6 ka, a stronger EASM (
   <a rid="r29" ref-type="bibr" href="#r29">29</a>, 
   <a rid="r30" ref-type="bibr" href="#r30">30</a>) propagated further northeastward than at present, yielding higher precipitation and temperatures in the Okhotsk Sea hinterland (
   <a rid="r31" ref-type="bibr" href="#r31">31</a>), increasing runoff from the Amur River catchment into the Okhotsk Sea (
   <a rid="r32" ref-type="bibr" href="#r32">32</a>). Higher Amur freshwater discharge also transports significant amounts of heat to the Okhotsk Sea (
   <a rid="r32" ref-type="bibr" href="#r32">32</a>, 
   <a rid="r33" ref-type="bibr" href="#r33">33</a>), which suppresses sea ice formation and, in concert with stronger thermal stratification of the upper mixed layer (
   <a rid="r34" ref-type="bibr" href="#r34">34</a>), decreases OSIW ventilation. After 6 ka, strengthening and expansion of the winter Siberian High in concert with a southward retreating EASM front was likely responsible for strengthening cold northeasterly winds over the continental shelf region (
   <a rid="r35" ref-type="bibr" href="#r35">35</a>). In addition, the maximum sea ice extent in the Okhotsk Sea is dependent on mean sea surface temperature (SST) conditions in summer (
   <a rid="r36" ref-type="bibr" href="#r36">36</a>). We thus infer a longer and more extensive sea ice cover, more polynyas, and more vigorous mixing of the mixed layer after 6 ka, which together enhanced the ventilation of new OSIW.
  </p>
  <div id="fig04" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Fig. 4.</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Model results from the earth system model COSMOS. Results are plotted in all panels as anomalies, calculated as differences resulting from 9 ka minus PI runs. (
     <span class="italic">A</span>) Annual mean temperature (T) anomaly, shown on a meridional transect along 150° E from the equator to 60° N. The transect crosses directly into the Okhotsk Sea north of 42° N. (
     <span class="italic">B</span>) Same as in 
     <span class="italic">A</span> but for annual mean salinity (S) anomaly. (
     <span class="italic">C</span>) Sea ice volume anomaly 9 ka minus PI, calculated from sea ice concentration multiplied by sea ice thickness in the North Pacific. (
     <span class="italic">D</span>) Same as 
     <span class="italic">C</span>, but for sea ice thickness.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div id="gra4" xlink:href="pnas.1714754115fig04" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Alkenone-derived SSTs for the Okhotsk Sea and the Japan continental margin consistently show maxima in Holocene SSTs between ∼8 and 6 ka, decreasing SSTs between 6 and 4 ka, and a last shift toward persistent colder SSTs around 2 ka (
   <a rid="r37" ref-type="bibr" href="#r37">37</a>, 
   <a rid="r38" ref-type="bibr" href="#r38">38</a>) (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3
    <span class="italic">D</span>
   </a>). Our observed decrease in OSIW ventilation during the EMH is thus in close agreement with increased SSTs of about 1.5 to 2 °C derived from both regional and global reconstructions (
   <a rid="r38" ref-type="bibr" href="#r38">38</a>, 
   <a rid="r39" ref-type="bibr" href="#r39">39</a>). Importantly, recent low-latitude middepth thermocline temperature changes (at around 500 m water depth) in the equatorial West Pacific show concomitant higher temperatures in the EMH of similar magnitude, with northern NPIW-sourced thermocline or intermediate water temperatures (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3
    <span class="italic">C</span>
   </a>) being warmer by 2.1 ± 0.4 °C than during the last century (
   <a rid="r40" ref-type="bibr" href="#r40">40</a>), in strong accord with our assumed decrease in ventilation in OSIW and NPIW (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3 
    <span class="italic">A</span> and 
    <span class="italic">F</span>
   </a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results from Earth System Model COSMOS (Community Earth System Model) simulations corroborate our proxy-based assumptions. This model captures the modern physical characteristics of NPIW well under preindustrial (PI) conditions (
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1714754115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S5 
    <span class="italic">A</span> and 
    <span class="italic">C</span>
   </span>). We analyzed Pacific data from PI and 9-ka time-slice runs (for details, see 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1714754115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, 
    <span class="italic">Paleoclimate Modeling</span>
   </span> and ref. 
   <a rid="r41" ref-type="bibr" href="#r41">41</a>). On a meridional transect along 150° E through the Okhotsk Sea toward the equatorial Pacific, our model results show a consistently warmer (around 1 to 2 °C) and saltier intermediate water layer at 9 ka than at PI conditions (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig04" href="#fig04">Fig. 4 
    <span class="italic">A</span> and 
    <span class="italic">B</span>
   </a> and 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1714754115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S5 
    <span class="italic">B</span> and 
    <span class="italic">D</span>
   </span>), matching the proxy-based temperature changes surprisingly well (
   <a rid="r40" ref-type="bibr" href="#r40">40</a>). Model-derived anomalies (9 ka minus PI) in sea ice dynamics show a localized, significant decrease of both sea ice volume (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig04" href="#fig04">Fig. 4
    <span class="italic">C</span>
   </a>) and thickness (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig04" href="#fig04">Fig. 4
    <span class="italic">D</span>
   </a>) in the Okhotsk Sea in the EMH, in agreement with our hypothesized reductions in sea ice and polynya formation in the OSIW source region that inhibited the modern ventilation regime.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Millennial-Scale Variations in Middepth Ventilation.</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Superimposed on the described stepwise background changes, we detected distinct cyclic millennial-scale variations in OSIW ventilation, visible in the δ
   <span class="sup">13</span>C C-OSIW ventilation record (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3
    <span class="italic">A</span>
   </a>) and in wavelet analyses of both the combined and individual records (
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1714754115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Figs. S7–S9
   </span>). These variations occur in the range of 1,500 to 1,800 y, which have been reported from a number of locations and Holocene proxy records (
   <a rid="r42" ref-type="bibr" href="#r42">42</a>, 
   <a rid="r43" ref-type="bibr" href="#r43">43</a>). Notably, this cyclicity is most prominent before the Middle-Holocene tipping point (
   <a rid="r28" ref-type="bibr" href="#r28">28</a>). While other records yielded comparable changes in terrestrial and surface ocean records, which were attributed to either internal (
   <a rid="r43" ref-type="bibr" href="#r43">43</a>) or external [e.g., solar (
   <a rid="r44" ref-type="bibr" href="#r44">44</a>)] forcing, evidence for a direct connection to middepth and deep water formation or ventilation patterns, such as we observe here, has remained relatively scarce to date (
   <a rid="r28" ref-type="bibr" href="#r28">28</a>, 
   <a rid="r42" ref-type="bibr" href="#r42">42</a>). Thus, our record provides evidence for the close link between high- to midlatitude surface ocean processes (SST and stratification changes) and intermediate water ventilation dynamics on Holocene millennial (and potentially shorter) timescales.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the subarctic Pacific, other evidence for Holocene millennial-scale cycles in marine sequences is scarce; however, a southerly located Japan margin SST record (
   <a rid="r38" ref-type="bibr" href="#r38">38</a>) also showed 1,500-y cycles in SST anomalies (see original data of ref. 
   <a rid="r38" ref-type="bibr" href="#r38">38</a> in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3
    <span class="italic">D</span>
   </a>). A northward propagation of low-latitude warm Kuroshio waters would plausibly explain the strong correspondence between Japan offshore SST records and Okhotsk Sea decreases in ventilation due to warming and salinification of upper ocean water masses (
   <a rid="r38" ref-type="bibr" href="#r38">38</a>), as well as the closer coupling between the midlatitude North Pacific and the subarctic Okhotsk Sea region. For future warming scenarios, such a pattern has been observed in recent modeling results, which indicated an intensification and northward shift of most Western Boundary Currents (
   <a rid="r45" ref-type="bibr" href="#r45">45</a>). As the 1,500-y variations are most prominent during the EMH in our records, we presume that during periods of suppressed OSIW ventilation, this modulation via oceanic forcing and the global Meridional Overturning Circulation gains importance.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">High-Latitude Mesopelagic Oxygenation and Remineralization Changes: Effects and Feedbacks.</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In principle, benthic δ
   <span class="sup">13</span>C may, in addition, provide qualitative information on past baseline variations of bottom water oxygenation (
   <a rid="r46" ref-type="bibr" href="#r46">46</a>, 
   <a rid="r47" ref-type="bibr" href="#r47">47</a>) (see 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1714754115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, 
    <span class="italic">Estimation of Past Oxygenation Based on δ
     <span class="sup">13</span>C Isotope Values
    </span>
   </span>). However, because O
   <sub>2</sub> in seawater equilibrates with the atmosphere almost instantaneously (i.e., on timescales of a year or less), whereas DIC and its carbon isotopes react on timescales of a decade [i.e., with about an order of magnitude difference (
   <a rid="r48" ref-type="bibr" href="#r48">48</a>)], only long-term, millennial-scale changes can be inferred. Correlation between dissolved water column O
   <sub>2</sub> and δ
   <span class="sup">13</span>C
   <sub>DIC</sub> based on water column data from the Okhotsk Sea (
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1714754115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Figs. S3 and S4
   </span>) can thus provide some insight into potential ranges of past Holocene middepth oxygenation levels. When applying this modern relationship between O
   <sub>2</sub> and δ
   <span class="sup">13</span>C to assess long-term oxygenation changes for OSIW, the last 0 to 6 ka would broadly range within modern instrumental data, indicating a moderately oxic environment (i.e., 100 to 200 µmol/L ± 50 µmol/L) (
   <a rid="r2" ref-type="bibr" href="#r2">2</a>, 
   <a rid="r3" ref-type="bibr" href="#r3">3</a>). In contrast, O
   <sub>2</sub> estimates for the preceding EMH interval, before the 6-ka threshold, show oxygenation levels that did not reach even the lower range of modern O
   <sub>2</sub> concentrations (
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1714754115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Figs. S3 and S4
   </span>). EMH O
   <sub>2</sub> values would have mostly yielded just 30 to 50% of modern ranges (50 to 120 µmol/L ± 50 µmol/L) and thus imply a substantial reduction in oxygenation of middepth waters. Taken at face value, OSIW oxygen supply would have been significantly reduced in a warmer-than-present EMH, changing the Okhotsk Sea from a modern mesopelagic O
   <sub>2</sub> source into an episodically hypoxic sink before 6 ka (
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1714754115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S4
   </span>), with likely limitations for marine life, OMZ strengthening (
   <a rid="r49" ref-type="bibr" href="#r49">49</a>, 
   <a rid="r50" ref-type="bibr" href="#r50">50</a>), and altered biogeochemical nutrient cycles (
   <a rid="r51" ref-type="bibr" href="#r51">51</a>, 
   <a rid="r52" ref-type="bibr" href="#r52">52</a>). This largely qualitative assessment, while not without methodological caveats like most proxy-based assessments of paleooxygenation levels (
   <a rid="r53" ref-type="bibr" href="#r53">53</a>, 
   <a rid="r54" ref-type="bibr" href="#r54">54</a>), is in agreement with synthesis results indicating an expansion of Early-Holocene OMZs on both a global scale and in the middepth Indo-Pacific (
   <a rid="r54" ref-type="bibr" href="#r54">54</a>). Also, independent evidence based on benthic foraminiferal assemblage analyses and multiproxy records recently indicated intensifications of O
   <sub>2</sub>-limited conditions in both the subarctic Northwest (
   <a rid="r27" ref-type="bibr" href="#r27">27</a>) and the Northeast Pacific, with more dysoxic conditions during the EMH (
   <a rid="r55" ref-type="bibr" href="#r55">55</a>, 
   <a rid="r56" ref-type="bibr" href="#r56">56</a>) (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3
    <span class="italic">E</span>
   </a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Modern NPIW provides nutrients, in particular silicate and phosphate, to lower latitudes via the “ocean tunnel” mechanism—that is, the meridional export of entrained nutrients in intermediate waters to subtropical and equatorial Pacific thermocline waters that are nutrient limited (
   <a rid="r57" ref-type="bibr" href="#r57">57</a>). Currently, nutrient limitation in these low-latitude regions hampers their efficiency of new and export biological production and the resulting sequestration of carbon to the deep ocean via the “biological carbon pump.” Thus, the modern low-latitude Pacific is one of the largest CO
   <sub>2</sub> source regions to the atmosphere. Today, while only about one-third of water reaching the equatorial thermocline is estimated to stem from NPIW, it provides about two-thirds of silicate and other nutrients needed to sustain biosiliceous primary production in the low-latitude Pacific (
   <a rid="r58" ref-type="bibr" href="#r58">58</a>, 
   <a rid="r59" ref-type="bibr" href="#r59">59</a>). On glacial–interglacial timescales, this nutrient transport might have increased during cold time intervals (
   <a rid="r60" ref-type="bibr" href="#r60">60</a>, 
   <a rid="r61" ref-type="bibr" href="#r61">61</a>). We suggest that, in the Holocene as well, NPIW export acted as a feedback mechanism on the biological carbon pump and thus atmospheric CO
   <sub>2</sub> (
   <span class="italic">i</span>) through intensification and deepening of remineralization processes, thereby storing higher amounts of organic carbon in North Pacific middepth waters; and (
   <span class="italic">ii</span>) by exporting larger amounts of nutrients, in particular silicate, through OSIW and NPIW to lower-latitude thermocline waters, thus attenuating silicate limitation in the northern subtropical-to-equatorial Pacific during warmer-than-present Holocene phases (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3 
    <span class="italic">D</span> and 
    <span class="italic">E</span>
   </a>). This latter process is supported by evidence for higher nutrient concentrations and utilization in the western equatorial Pacific and its subtropical marginal seas during the EMH that are currently under the influence of NPIW inflow (
   <a rid="r61" ref-type="bibr" href="#r61">61</a>) and concurrent minima in atmospheric CO
   <sub>2</sub> concentrations (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3
    <span class="italic">G</span>
   </a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In summary, our combined proxy- and modeling-based reconstructions show a crucial influence of Okhotsk Sea-sourced NPIW on Pacific Holocene oceanography. In particular, export of warmer, oxygen-poorer, and nutrient-richer NPIW from the subarctic domain likely reached and influenced the low-latitude Pacific thermocline during the warmer-than-present EMH, thus not only leading to increases in oceanic heat content (
   <a rid="r40" ref-type="bibr" href="#r40">40</a>), but also to significant changes in the biogeochemical signatures of thermocline waters, including equatorial Pacific nutrient and oxygen inventories (
   <a rid="r12" ref-type="bibr" href="#r12">12</a>, 
   <a rid="r52" ref-type="bibr" href="#r52">52</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
