<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In this study we use a model tree species, pinyon pine (
 <italic class="italic">P. edulis</italic>) to examine how soil type, intraspecific variation in drought tolerance and herbivore susceptibility interact to influence tree performance before and during long-term drought. Warming temperatures combined with extreme drought and herbivory resulted in significant 
 <italic class="italic">P. edulis</italic> mortality across 12,000 km
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> of the southwestern United States in 2002–2003 (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Breshears et al., 2005</xref>). Several studies have examined the physiological basis and environmental drivers (
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Adams et al., 2009</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Peterman et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Grossiord et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Redmond et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Guérin et al., 2018</xref>) of this large-scale mortality. A synthesis of this research indicated significant differences among studies in the importance of tree density, site elevation and soil type to mortality (
 <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Meddens et al., 2015</xref>). Also, while the contribution of bark beetle herbivory to tree mortality has been demonstrated in 
 <italic class="italic">P. edulis</italic> (
 <xref rid="B80" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Santos and Whitham, 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gaylord et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Anderegg et al., 2015a</xref>), other insect herbivores affect 
 <italic class="italic">P. edulis</italic> performance and may influence its future distribution. Larvae of the pinyon stem-boring moth (
 <italic class="italic">Dioryctria albovittella</italic>) feed preferentially on the terminal shoots and female cones of mature trees. In studies conducted before long-term drought, chronic herbivory by this moth reduced trunk growth and female cone production, and altered 
 <italic class="italic">P. edulis</italic> architecture to a shrub-like form (
 <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Whitham and Mopper, 1985</xref>). Despite their poor growth prior to drought, moth susceptible trees had three-fold higher survival during drought than moth resistant trees (
 <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Sthultz et al., 2009a</xref>), a trait also observed in their offspring (
 <xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Sthultz et al., 2009b</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gehring et al., 2017</xref>).
</p>
