<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>A Bayesian phylogeny was reconstructed in BEAST 2.0 [
 <xref rid="RSTB20190212C32" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], using date calibrated tips, the HKY + I substitution model and a uniform prior of the mutation rate of the mitochondrial genome set to 6.1 × 10
 <sup>−8</sup> to 1.0 × 10
 <sup>−7</sup> site
 <sup>−1</sup> yr
 <sup>−1</sup> (calculated for grey wolf, 
 <italic>Canis lupus</italic> [
 <xref rid="RSTB20190212C33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]). The substitution model was selected according to the Bayesian information criterion in JM
 <sc>odeltest</sc>2 [
 <xref rid="RSTB20190212C34" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. We investigated genetic variability in arctic foxes between time periods, using a median-joining network created in P
 <sc>op</sc>A
 <sc>rt</sc> 1.7 [
 <xref rid="RSTB20190212C35" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. We also estimated population genetic diversity parameters, such as haplotype and nucleotide diversity, with D
 <sc>na</sc>SP v5 [
 <xref rid="RSTB20190212C36" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Haplotype accumulation curves were constructed through random permutation subsampling without replacement using the functions haploAccum() and plot.haploAccum() supplied in the SPIDER package in R [
 <xref rid="RSTB20190212C37" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. We also used an approximate Bayesian computation (ABC) approach [
 <xref rid="RSTB20190212C38" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSTB20190212C39" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>] to estimate changes in female effective population size (
 <italic>N
  <sub>ef</sub>
 </italic>) over the last 150 years. Our model included a single human-induced decline occurring some 90–120 years ago, a generation time of 3 years and mean rate ranging from 1.85 × 10
 <sup>−7</sup> to 3.00 × 10
 <sup>−7</sup> substitutions generation
 <sup>−1</sup> (electronic supplementary material, table S4; [
 <xref rid="RSTB20190212C33" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]). In the model, we set the sampling times for modern and historical samples at 
 <italic>t</italic> = 0 generations and 
 <italic>t</italic> = 40 generations in the past, respectively. We used seven summary statistics and estimated posterior parameter distributions by retaining the 10 000 datasets (1%) with the smallest Euclidean distances to the observed dataset.
</p>
