<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.3 20070202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.3?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Front Bioeng Biotechnol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Front Bioeng Biotechnol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Front. Bioeng. Biotechnol.</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Frontiers in Bioengineering and Biotechnology</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2296-4185</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Frontiers Media S.A.</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6399304</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fbioe.2019.00032</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Bioengineering and Biotechnology</subject><subj-group><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Anadromous Arctic Char Microbiomes: Bioprospecting in the High Arctic</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>Erin F.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/622927/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Element</surname><given-names>Geraint</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/667017/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>van Coeverden de Groot</surname><given-names>Peter</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Engel</surname><given-names>Katja</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Neufeld</surname><given-names>Josh D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>Vishal</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/438252/overview"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>Virginia K.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c001"><sup>*</sup></xref><uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://loop.frontiersin.org/people/476125/overview"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><sup>1</sup><institution>Department of Biology, Queen's University</institution>, <addr-line>Kingston, ON</addr-line>, <country>Canada</country></aff><aff id="aff2"><sup>2</sup><institution>Department of Biology, University of Waterloo</institution>, <addr-line>Waterloo, ON</addr-line>, <country>Canada</country></aff><aff id="aff3"><sup>3</sup><institution>College of the Sciences and Mathematics, West Chester University</institution>, <addr-line>West Chester, PA</addr-line>, <country>United States</country></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Edited by: Steffen P. Graether, University of Guelph, Canada</p></fn><fn fn-type="edited-by"><p>Reviewed by: Ashok K. Dubey, Netaji Subhas Institute of Technology, India; Nadia Solovieva, University College London, United Kingdom</p></fn><corresp id="c001">*Correspondence: Virginia K. Walker <email>walkervk@queensu.ca</email></corresp><fn fn-type="other" id="fn001"><p>This article was submitted to Bioprocess Engineering, a section of the journal Frontiers in Bioengineering and Biotechnology</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>26</day><month>2</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>32</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>10</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>05</day><month>2</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2019 Hamilton, Element, van Coeverden de Groot, Engel, Neufeld, Shah and Walker.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Hamilton, Element, van Coeverden de Groot, Engel, Neufeld, Shah and Walker</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these terms.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Northern populations of Arctic char (<italic>Salvelinus alpinus</italic>) can be anadromous, migrating annually from the ocean to freshwater lakes and rivers in order to escape sub-zero temperatures. Such seasonal behavior demands that these fish and their associated microbiomes adapt to changes in salinity, temperature, and other environmental challenges. We characterized the microbial community composition of anadromous <italic>S. alpinus</italic>, netted by Inuit fishermen at freshwater and seawater fishing sites in the high Arctic, both under ice and in open water. Bacterial profiles were generated by DNA extraction and high-throughput sequencing of PCR-amplified 16S ribosomal RNA genes. Results showed that microbial communities on the skin and intestine of Arctic char were statistically different when sampled from freshwater or saline water sites. This association was tested using hierarchical Ward's linkage clustering, showing eight distinct clusters in each of the skin and intestinal microbiomes, with the clusters reflecting sampling location between fresh and saline environments, confirming a salinity-linked turnover. This analysis also provided evidence for a core composition of skin and intestinal bacteria, with the phyla Proteobacteria, Firmicutes, and Cyanobacteria presenting as major phyla within the skin-associated microbiomes. The intestine-associated microbiome was characterized by unidentified genera from families Fusobacteriaceae, Comamonadaceae, Pseudomonadaceae, and Vibrionaceae. The salinity-linked turnover was further tested through ordinations that showed samples grouping based on environment for both skin- and intestine-associated microbiomes. This finding implies that core microbiomes between fresh and saline conditions could be used to assist in regulating optimal fish health in aquaculture practices. Furthermore, identified taxa from known psychrophiles and with nitrogen cycling properties suggest that there is additional potential for biotechnological applications for fish farm and waste management practices.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Arctic char</kwd><kwd>salmonid fish</kwd><kwd>anadromous</kwd><kwd>microbiomes</kwd><kwd>bioprospecting</kwd><kwd>aquaculture</kwd><kwd>Arctic Ocean</kwd><kwd>aquatic biotechnology</kwd></kwd-group><counts><fig-count count="5"/><table-count count="4"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="64"/><page-count count="13"/><word-count count="9194"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Fish carry a mucous layer on their epithelial surfaces that consists of mucins, immunoglobulins, antimicrobial peptides, and commensal bacteria, which serve roles in friction reduction, waste removal, osmoregulation, as well as an early line of defense against pathogens (Esteban and Cerezuela, <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). In addition, variations in mucous layer microbiome composition occur across different life stages, among different species, and across distinct geographies in amphibians and marine mammals, which are known to share certain microbial species with the surrounding water (Boutin et al., <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Apprill et al., <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Kueneman et al., <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Chiarello et al., <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). Indeed, in farmed Atlantic salmon (<italic>Salmo salar</italic>), the abundance of certain bacterial phyla in skin- and intestine-associated microbiomes changed depending on the water source (Lokesh and Kiron, <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Dehler et al., <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Structural changes to the microbiota, however, have not been well-described in wild fish populations. This research is noteworthy because it indicates that deliberate shifts in community structure could potentially hinder the development of dysbiosis.</p><p>Arctic char (<italic>Salvelinus alpinus</italic>), a salmonid species, is of particular interest given the increased popularity of the farmed product in temperate regions. Wild <italic>S. alpinus</italic> stocks from high latitude waters with an anadromous life history, such that they spend the winter in freshwater lakes to avoid freezing and subsequently migrate to the more nutrient-rich Arctic sea in the summer, could provide insight into the purported turnover in char microbiomes and be of interest to aquaculture biotechnologists.</p><p>Although relatively unexploited commercially, Arctic char stocks in the lower Northwest Passage of the Kitikmeot region of Nunavut, Canada represent an essential subsistence fishery to indigenous Inuit communities. With recent altered sea ice patterns as a consequence of climate change, and the potential for increasing stress of pollutants associated with future industrialization, we considered it important to undertake genomic, demographic, physiological and microbial analyses on these fish populations. At present, the stocks are considered healthy due a general lack of commercial fisheries in this region, as well as the relatively long-life span of individual fish, which has been reported as up to 33 years in our samples. As part of this effort, an assessment of the mucosa-associated microbiomes of the skin and intestines of <italic>S. alpinus</italic> from the area in, and surrounding, King William Island Nunavut, has been undertaken. We further explored whether this increased understanding of the microbial communities could inform future biotechnological applications in the management of commercially farmed fish, in addition to other biotechnologies.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials and methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Study Area</title><p>Fishing was done within the Kitikmeot region of Nunavut, Canada in the Western Arctic, at seven distinct sites within 200 km of King William Island, located along the lower Northwest Passage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>; <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Fishing sites were chosen based on Traditional Ecological Knowledge shared by local Inuit elders and in association with the Hunters and Trappers Association of Gjoa Haven, NU, as part of a large-scale fisheries project (Towards; <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.arcticfishery.ca">www.arcticfishery.ca</ext-link>). At each fishing site, specific conductance of surface water was obtained with a conductivity meter (Traceable Fisherbrand, Fisher Scientific) to record conductivity and determine our site designations as either freshwater or saline sites (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The southern region of the study area is unique due to large freshwater influence from major river systems, including Murchison River, Legendary River, Back River, and Hayes River. Therefore, the major sea-water bodies within the region, namely Rasmussen Basin and Chantrey Inlet, are characterized by brackish salinities as defined by Watling (<xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>), with conductivities between 1,500 and 15,000 &#x003bc;S cm<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>, diverging from sea salinities more characteristic of the Pacific and Atlantic Oceans (Carmack, <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). Fishing sites within these locations are referred to as &#x0201c;saline&#x0201d; sites.</p><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>A map of the lower Northwest Passage in Nunavut, Canada and the location of seven distinct fishing sites initially chosen based on Inuit Traditional Ecological Knowledge. The sites fished include five freshwater sites (Port Perry, Swan Lake, Koka Lake, Murchison River, and Back River); and two saltwater sites (Back House Point and Legendary River estuary). Inset A outlines Nunavut, Canada, in red, while inset B showcases the lower Northwest Passage, in red.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fbioe-07-00032-g0001"/></fig><table-wrap id="T1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Location and GPS coordinates for each fishing site, followed by designated water source categories and specific conductance measurements shown as conductivity that were determined by a conductivity meter on-site.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Location and GPS coordinates</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Water source</bold></th><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Conductivity (&#x003bc;S cm<sup><bold>&#x02212;1</bold></sup>)</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Port Perry (N69&#x000b0;33&#x02032;28.764&#x02033;, W97&#x000b0;26&#x02032;13.884&#x02033;)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fresh</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">286</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Swan Lake (N68&#x000b0;40&#x02032;13.62, W95&#x000b0;56&#x02032;57.408&#x02033;)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fresh</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">880</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Koka Lake (N68&#x000b0;32&#x02032;5.1&#x02033;, W96&#x000b0;12&#x02032;45.899&#x02033;)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fresh</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">670</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Back House Point (N67&#x000b0;27&#x02032;27.2&#x02033;, W95&#x000b0;21&#x02032;38.6&#x02033;)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Saline</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8,240</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Legendary River (N67&#x000b0;31&#x02032;17.8&#x02033;, W96&#x000b0;26&#x02032;21.8&#x02033;)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Saline</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3,450</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Murchison River (N68&#x000b0;34&#x02032;1.2&#x02033;, W 93&#x000b0;22&#x02032;37.452&#x02033;)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fresh</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">225</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Back River (N66&#x000b0;57&#x02032;30.70&#x02033;, W95&#x000b0;18&#x02032;5.20&#x02033;)</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fresh</td><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Fish Collection</title><p>Commercial (140 mm mesh) and multi-mesh subsistence (5 or 8 panels of 38&#x02013;140 mm) fishing nets were set during December-June (freshwater lakes under thick ice) and August-September (at open water river estuaries during sea-ice formation and char migration) at distinct geographic sites over a period of 3 years. After setting for several hours, nets were retrieved, and fish were pulled from the nets with nitrile gloves. Using either sterile cotton swabs or an ethanol-sterilized scalpel, the surface mucosal layer of each fish was sampled once per fish with the swabs, or skin scrapings, taken from above the lateral line. The fish were then photographed, weighed, and measured, followed by dissection in an on-site mobile lab. Full intestines were removed using sterile technique, and both skin and intestinal samples were placed in sterile sample tubes or bags, respectively, and frozen at &#x02212;20&#x000b0;C in a freezer on-site. Samples were shipped frozen and subsequently stored at &#x02212;20&#x000b0;C until further processing. In addition to the skin and intestine samples, water samples were also taken at each fishing site, in which up to 2 L of water was filtered through sterile 0.22 &#x003bc;m PALL filters in triplicate. The filters were then frozen at &#x02212;20&#x000b0;C and were subsequently transported and stored at &#x02212;80&#x000b0;C until further processing.</p><p>Fish were sampled in accordance with issued licenses to fish for scientific purposes in the waters of the Northwest Territories, Yukon north slope, and Nunavut (in accordance with section 52 of the general fishery regulations of the fisheries act, Fisheries and Oceans, Canada) along with an associated animal care permit issued by the Fresh Water Institute Animal Care Committee of the Department of Fisheries and Oceans (current permit numbers S-18/19-1045-NU and FWI-ACC AUP-2018-63).</p></sec><sec><title>Sample Processing and DNA Extraction</title><p>After initial optimization experimentation to determine the selection of appropriate DNA extraction kits for each sample type, DNA from the skin samples was extracted using a NucleoSpin Soil Extraction Kit (Machery-Nagel, Bethlehem, PA), with modifications following the procedures of Kueneman et al. (<xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>) in which samples were incubated at 65&#x000b0;C for 10 min before mechanical lysis. In order to maximize yield, the initial lysis step was conducted twice, and double-distilled sterile water was left on the filter for 5 min prior to elution. Extracted DNA concentrations were assessed using an Invitrogen Qubit 4 Fluorometer and a QuantiFluor ONE dsDNA system (Promega Corporation, Madison, WI, USA), followed by qualitative analysis with agarose gel electrophoresis and a NanoDrop One Microvolume spectrophotometer (Thermo Scientific) set to A<sub>260/280</sub> absorbance. High concentration samples were diluted to 50 ng &#x003bc;L<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> prior to PCR amplification, in which starting material for PCR templates ranged from 1 to 50 ng &#x003bc;L<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. These skin-associated microbiome samples underwent a pre-amplification PCR step using primers 8F and 1406R (Lane, <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr">1991</xref>; Coolen et al., <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>) to amplify the variable V1&#x02013;V9 region of the bacterial 16S ribosomal RNA (rRNA) gene. The PCR mix for each reaction (50 &#x003bc;L total volume) contained 1X ThermoFisher DreamTaq Buffer (with 2 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>), 0.4 &#x003bc;M forward and reverse primers, 200 &#x003bc;M dNTPs, 400 ng BSA, 2.5 U ThermoFisher DreamTaq DNA Polymerase, and 2 &#x003bc;L of template. The PCR was performed as follows: 95&#x000b0;C for 5 min, 25 cycles of 95&#x000b0;C for 1 min, 52&#x000b0;C for 1 min, 72&#x000b0;C for 1 min, with a final extension of 72&#x000b0;C for 7 min.</p><p>Intestinal samples were partially thawed to excise three slices within the distal intestine (~2 cm from the vent), comprising a total of 5&#x02013;100 mg epithelial tissue, avoiding feces and connective tissue. The slices were pooled and DNA was extracted using MOBIO UltraClean Tissue and Cells DNA Isolation Kit (QIAGEN Inc., Toronto, ON) following the manufacturer's instructions, except that elution was achieved with double-distilled sterile water rather than EDTA. The DNA concentrations for the intestine-associated microbiome samples were estimated as described for the skin-associated microbiome preparations, but adjusted to 30 ng &#x003bc;L<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. Pre-amplified PCR products were also prepared as described above.</p><p>In addition, the V4 region of the 16S rRNA gene was amplified on an Illumina sequence platform from DNA isolated from the triplicate water filters using primers 515F and 806R (Caporaso et al., <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>16S rRNA Gene Sequencing of Mucosal Microbiomes</title><p>The V4-V5 region of the 16S rRNA gene was amplified from each of the skin and intestinal amplification products using primers 515F-Y (Parada et al., <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>) and 926R (Quince et al., <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). Each primer contained a 6-base index sequence for sample multiplexing as well as Illumina flow cell binding and sequencing sites (Bartram et al., <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). The PCR mix (25 &#x003bc;L total volume) contained 1X ThermoPol Buffer, 0.2 &#x003bc;M forward and reverse primers, 200 &#x003bc;M dNTPs, 15 &#x003bc;g BSA, 0.625 U Hot Start <italic>Taq</italic> DNA polymerase, and 1 &#x003bc;L of template. The PCR was performed as follows: 95&#x000b0;C for 3 min, 35 cycles of 95&#x000b0;C for 30 s, 50&#x000b0;C for 30 s, 68&#x000b0;C for 1 min, and a final extension of 68&#x000b0;C for 7 min. Each amplification reaction was done in triplicate. Equal quantities of each amplicon were pooled. Samples that did not yield a PCR product were not included. No-template controls were added to the Illumina sequencing pool (5 &#x003bc;L), even when amplicons were not detected. Pooled 16S rRNA gene amplicons were subsequently excised from an agarose gel and purified using the Wizard SV Gel and PCR Clean-Up System (Promega, WI, USA). A 5 pM library containing 15% PhiX Control v3 (Illumina Canada Inc, NB, Canada) was sequenced on a MiSeq instrument (Illumina Inc, CA, USA) using a 2 &#x000d7; 250 cycle MiSeq Reagent Kit v2 (Illumina Canada Inc., BC, Canada).</p></sec><sec><title>Sequence Data Analysis, OTU Tables, and Statistics</title><p>Sequence reads were demultiplexed using Illumina MiSeq Reporter software version 2.5.0.5. Reads were assembled using the paired-end assembler for Illumina sequences (PANDAseq version 2.8, Masella et al., <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>) with a quality threshold of 0.9, an 8 nucleotide minimum overlap, and 32 nucleotide minimum assembled read length. Assembled reads were analyzed using Quantitative Insights Into Microbial Ecology (QIIME version 1.9.0, Caporaso et al., <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). Sequences were clustered into operational taxonomic units (OTUs) using UPARSE algorithm USEARCH version 7.0.1090 (Edgar, <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>) at 97% identity and aligned with the Python Nearest Alignment Space Termination tool (PyNAST version 1.2.2, Caporaso et al., <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). All representative sequences were classified using the Ribosomal Database Project (RDP version 2.2, Wang et al., <xref rid="B59" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>) with a stringent confidence threshold (0.8) and the Greengenes database (McDonald et al., <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>) was used to assign taxonomy. Chimeric sequences were filtered with UCHIME (Edgar et al., <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). Before performing statistical analysis, OTUs observed in no-template PCR controls for a sample type were filtered from all samples of that type. OTUs with three or fewer reads within negative PCR controls were retained within the samples, since their low representation in the negative controls rendered them viable representatives in the samples. The OTUs were then rarefied to ~2,000 reads for skin and intestinal microbiome samples. Alpha and beta diversity for samples were analyzed based on rarified OTU tables generated using QIIME with principal coordinate analysis (PCoA). Additional visualizations were done using EMPeror (V&#x000e1;zquez-Baeza et al., <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Primer 7 software version 7.0.13 was used for analysis of similarity (ANOSIM) and similarity percentages (SIMPER) analyses (Clarke et al., <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Clustering analysis was performed using Statistica 13.0 Academic software.</p><p>The hypothesis that skin microbial community composition was linked to salinity was tested by performing hierarchical Ward's linkage clustering (Dillner et al., <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>). Tree cluster analysis was carried out using Ward's method as the amalgamation rule and the distance measured as Euclidean units (Dillner et al., <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>). Using K-means clustering, the samples were divided into K clusters by selecting the number of iterations as 10, and the initial cluster centers chosen to maximize initial between-cluster distances. The output of this step is the list of fish samples that are present in each cluster. The sequence data is publicly available in the European Nucleotide Archive within the European Bioinformatics Institute, under the study: Characterization and Analysis of Skin- and Intestine-associated Microbiomes in the Lower Northwest Passage (Nunavut, Canada) with the following accession number, <ext-link ext-link-type="EBI:ena" xlink:href="PRJEB29173">PRJEB29173</ext-link>.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Comparisons of Skin and Intestinal Microbiota Within Individual Fish</title><p>Based on fish sampled at seven distinct sites on or within 200 km of King William Island, located along the lower Northwest Passage (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>; <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>), microbiome sequences were successfully obtained for 118 skin mucosal samples and 202 intestinal samples. Grouping the skin microbiome consortia by environment showed that the freshwater samples contained significantly more Shannon diversity overall than those from saline water (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.11, <italic>F</italic> = 16.0, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05), whereas log<sub>10</sub> Chao1 OTU richness was not significantly different between the two environment types (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.00, <italic>F</italic> = 0.1, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003e; 0.05). In contrast, when intestinal microbiomes were grouped by environment, the saline water samples were more diverse overall than freshwater samples when log<sub>10</sub> Chao1 OTU richness was considered, though this difference was small (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.03, <italic>F</italic> = 4.7, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05). A significant difference was not observed in the intestinal microbiomes between the two environment types when Shannon diversity was considered (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.00, <italic>F</italic> = 0.1, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003e; 0.05). Of the 320 skin and intestine samples combined, 60 individual Arctic char had both sets of microbiome data, allowing a comparison of skin and intestinal flora from the same fish (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>). When comparing across these 60 fish, skin-associated microbiomes were significantly more diverse than intestine-associated microbiomes when both log<sub>10</sub> Chao1 OTU richness (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.60, <italic>F</italic> = 180.0, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) and Shannon diversity (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.52, <italic>F</italic> = 127.4, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.05) were considered. In addition, though the skin and intestine communities were distinct, the skin- and intestine-associated microbiomes among individual fish appeared to be more similar at freshwater sites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figures 2A,B</xref>) compared to saline water sites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figures 2C,D</xref>).</p><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Phyla comparison of skin and intestinal complementary microbiomes for individual fish, shown for samples collected at <bold>(A)</bold> freshwater sites Port Perry, Swan Lake, and Koka Lake for skin-associated microbiomes, <bold>(B)</bold> freshwater sites Port Perry, Swan Lake, and Koka Lake for intestine-associated microbiomes, <bold>(C)</bold> saltwater sites, Back House Point and Legendary River for skin-associated microbiomes, and <bold>(D)</bold> saltwater sites, Back House Point and Legendary River for intestine-associated microbiomes. Phyla with relative abundances (RA) &#x02265; 0.5% are shown. Phyla present at RA &#x0003c; 0.5% were pooled together.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fbioe-07-00032-g0002"/></fig><p>The relative abundance of rarified OTUs identified to the genus level, if known, for each of the total 320 skin and intestinal microbiome samples is presented in supplemental tables (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">Tables S1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM2">S2</xref>, respectively).</p></sec><sec><title>Skin and Intestinal Microbiota Compositions Linked to Salinity</title><p>At freshwater sites, most taxa from skin- and intestine-associated microbiome sequence data were affiliated with Proteobacteria, but many also classified to Actinobacteria, Cyanobacteria, and Firmicutes (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figures 2A,B</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">Tables S1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM2">S2</xref>). Although fish skin from saline environments was also colonized by Proteobacteria and Actinobacteria (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2C</xref>), other phyla, such as Acidobacteria and Bacteroidetes, were also prominent. Intestines derived from fish sampled in saline waters were similarly characterized by Proteobacteria, Actinobacteria, and Bacteroidetes, but also by Firmicutes, Spirochaetes and Tenericutes, with considerable variation across individual fish (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2D</xref>). Given these observations, depending on whether fish were sampled from fresh or saline waters, skin or intestinal bacterial communities appeared to change. For example, relative abundance based on rarified data of the psychrophile <italic>Photobacterium</italic> increased 200-fold in relative abundance in skin-associated microbiomes from saline sites, compared to freshwater sites (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2A</xref>). Similarly, relative abundance for <italic>Deinoccoccus</italic>, known for its ability to resist a variety of environmental stresses, increased 150-fold between fresh- and saline-caught skin microbiome fish samples. Taxa in the intestinal bacterial communities were also shown to change between fresh and saline-caught fish, with similar increases, but to a lesser magnitude including those belonging to the order Vibrionales (18-fold), the genus <italic>Photobacterium</italic> (14-fold), and an unknown genus in the class Mollicutes (14-fold; <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2B</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="T2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p><bold>(A)</bold> SIMPER analysis (Primer 7) output showing relative abundances and impact ratio of environmental change between freshwater and saline locations across 118 skin-associated microbiome samples <bold>(B)</bold> SIMPER analysis (Primer 7) output showing relative abundances and impact ratio of environmental change between freshwater and saline locations across 202 intestine-associated samples.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Taxonomy</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="2" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>Relative abundance</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Impact ratio (Saline: Fresh)</bold></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Saline</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Fresh</bold></th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="4" style="background-color:#bbbdc0" rowspan="1"><bold>(A)</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p: Proteobacteria c: Gammaproteobacteria o: Vibrionales f: Vibrionaceae g: <italic>Photobacterium</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.22</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">211</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p: Deinococcus c: Deinococci o: Deinococcales f: Deinococcaceae g: <italic>Deinococcus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.72</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">154</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p: Proteobacteria c: Alphaproteobacteria o: Rhodospirillales f: Acetobacteraceae g: Unknown</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.58</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.52</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.64</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p: Firmicutes c: Clostridia o: Clostridiales f: Clostridiaceae g: <italic>Clostridium</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.84</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.54</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p: Proteobacteria c: Betaproteobacteria o: Burkholderiales f: Comamonadaceae g: Other</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.97</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p: Proteobacteria c: Alphaproteobacteria o: Sphingomonadales f: Sphingomonadaceae g: <italic>Sphingomonas</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.69</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p: Bacteroidetes c: Saprospirae o: Saprospirales f: Chitinophagaceae g: Unknown</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.23</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.90</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p: Proteobacteria c: Alphaproteobacteria o: Rhodospirillales f: Rhodospirillaceae g: Unknown</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.90</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.69</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p: Proteobacteria c: Alphaproteobacteria o: Caulobacterales f: Caulobacteraceae g: Other</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.39</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p: Proteobacteria c: Betaproteobacteria o: Other f: Other g: Other</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.27</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p: Proteobacteria c: Alphaproteobacteria o: Sphingomonadales f: Sphingomonadaceae g: <italic>Novosphingobium</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.42</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p: Proteobacteria c: Gammaproteobacteria o: Xanthomonadales f: Sinobacteraceae g: Unknown</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.76</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p: Proteobacteria c: Betaproteobacteria o: Burkholderiales f: Oxalobacteraceae g: <italic>Cupriavidus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.90</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p: Cyanobacteria c: Nostocophycideae o: Stigonematales f: Rivulariaceae g: <italic>Rivularia</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.80</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p: Cyanobacteria c: Oscillatoriophycideae o: Oscillatoriales f: Phormidiaceae g: <italic>Phormidium</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.27</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="4" style="background-color:#bbbdc0" rowspan="1"><bold>(B)</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p: Proteobacteria c: Gammaproteobacteria o: Vibrionales f: Other g: Other</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.10</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18.23</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p: Tenericutes c: Mollicutes o: Unknown f: Unknown g: Unknown</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.32</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.08</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p: Proteobacteria c: Gammaproteobacteria o: Vibrionales f: Vibrionaceae g: <italic>Photobacterium</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.48</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.03</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p: Spirochaetes c: Brevinematae o: Brevinematales f: Brevinemataceae g: Unknown</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.54</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.41</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p: Proteobacteria c: Gammaproteobacteria o: Vibrionales f: Vibrionaceae g: Other</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.06</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.56</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p: Proteobacteria c: Gammaproteobacteria o: Vibrionales f: Vibrionaceae g: <italic>Aliivibrio</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.08</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.22</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.16</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p: Proteobacteria c: Alphaproteobacteria o: Sphingomonadales f: Sphingomonadaceae g: <italic>Sphingomonas</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.91</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.06</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.46</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p: Tenericutes c: Mollicutes o: Mycoplasmatales f: Mycoplasmataceae g: <italic>Mycoplasma</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.17</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.42</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p: Fusobacteria c: Fusobacteriia o: Fusobacteriales f: Fusobacteriaceae g: <italic>u114</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.77</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.12</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p: Proteobacteria c: Gammaproteobacteria o: Pseudomonadales f: Pseudomonadaceae g: <italic>Pseudomonas</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.65</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p: Proteobacteria c: Betaproteobacteria o: Burkholderiales f: Comamonadaceae g: Other</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.96</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p: Proteobacteria c: Gammaproteobacteria o: Pseudomonadales f: Pseudomonadaceae g: Other</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.23</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.91</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unclassified Taxa</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.23</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.65</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p: Proteobacteria c: Alphaproteobacteria o: Caulobacterales f: Caulobacteraceae g: <italic>Phenylobacterium</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.71</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p: Proteobacteria c: Betaproteobacteria o: Neisseriales f: Neisseriaceae g: <italic>Deefgea</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.86</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>Taxonomy from phylum (p) to clade (c) to order (o) to family (f) to genus (g) is shown</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Overall, PCoA combined with ANOSIM showed a statistically significant separation between samples obtained from freshwater and saline sites for both skin microbiomes (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3A</xref>), and intestinal microbiomes (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3B</xref>). This indicates that salinity is a primary factor in defining these microbial communities. For the 60 skin and intestinal microbiome samples used for within-fish comparisons where possible, ANOSIM showed that the communities obtained from the two sample types were significantly different (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Figure 4</xref>).</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Principal coordinate analysis (PCoA) showing grouping of <bold>(A)</bold> individual skin microbiomes at fresh (<italic>n</italic> = 55), and saline (<italic>n</italic> = 63) sites and <bold>(B)</bold> individual intestinal microbiomes at fresh (<italic>n</italic> = 144) and saline (<italic>n</italic> = 58) sites. PCoA ordinations are based on the Bray-Curtis dissimilarity metric. Freshwater sites include lake and river sites sampled in winter and spring while saline sites refer to sea shoreline locations sampled in autumn during the annual char run.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fbioe-07-00032-g0003"/></fig><fig id="F4" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Principal coordinate analysis (PCoA) showing clustering of individual skin and intestinal microbiome communities based on Bray-Curtis dissimilarity. For every skin-associated community represented, a counterpart intestine-associated community from the same <italic>S. alpinus</italic> individual is shown. Legend refers to the sample type and environment of where an <italic>S. alpinus</italic> individual was caught and includes skin microbiomes from freshwater sites (<italic>n</italic> = 30), and from saline sites (<italic>n</italic> = 30), as well as intestinal microbiomes from freshwater sites (<italic>n</italic> = 30) and from saline sites (<italic>n</italic> = 30). Fresh refers to lake and river sites sampled in winter and spring while saline refers to sea shoreline locations sampled in autumn during the annual char run.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fbioe-07-00032-g0004"/></fig><p>In addition, preliminary results show that the community structure of identified bacteria from water samples at sites corresponding to where fish were caught (excluding Back River) differs from that of the fish, suggesting that the distribution of microbiota identified on the fish are influenced by physiological processes inherent to the fish (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM7">Figure S1</xref>). However, the phyla Proteobacteria, Bacteroidetes, and Actinobacteria are represented in both the water microbiomes and in both skin- and intestine-associated microbiota. Across water samples, no significant difference was observed between freshwater and saline sites overall for either Chao1 OTU richness (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.01, <italic>F</italic> = 0.2, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003e; 0.05), or Shannon diversity (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> = 0.07, <italic>F</italic> = 1.6, <italic>p</italic> &#x0003e; 0.05). The most similarity was observed between samples from similar geographic regions. For example, Port Perry, Swan Lake, and Koka Lake were from freshwater sites on King William Island whereas the saline sites Back House Point, Legendary River, and the freshwater site Murchison River were from Chantrey Inlet.</p></sec><sec><title>Characterization of the Skin Microbiota</title><p>When the 118 skin-associated microbiome samples were analyzed using hierarchical Ward's linkage clustering (Dillner et al., <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>), eight distinct clusters were apparent in the amalgamation schedule graph (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5A</xref>), with the decreasing linkage distance after the seventh fusion step indicating a minimal difference for any newly formed clusters. Euclidean distances between the centers of clusters confirmed the distinct nature of each cluster, with all clusters largely apart from each other (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM3">Table S3</xref>). Subsequent K-means clustering was then carried out to identify members of each of the clusters (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3A</xref>). The largest cluster (#6) contained 98% of the freshwater (54/55) and 52% of the saline (32/62) samples, supporting the distinct grouping of saline and freshwater samples observed in the PCoA ordinations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>). Because many of the fish were netted in autumn, during the annual char migration, it is probable that some saline-associated microbiota could remain in the same cluster as the microbiota from freshwater fish. The ANOVA results show that of the 899 taxa used in the clustering analysis, 56 have a <italic>p</italic>-value below 0.05. These results also indicated that Proteobacteria, Cyanobacteria, and Firmicutes contributed most to the clustering analysis (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM4">Table S4</xref>). As an approach to identify a core microbiome for Arctic char skin, bacteria present across the eight clusters were identified (<xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4A</xref>). The fact that none of the nine taxa, except for <italic>Clostridium</italic>, matched to any known genus likely emphasizes the paucity of research for this wild species. For example, an unknown genus from the Acetobacteraceae family represents over 5% of the total microbiota. In contrast to the clustering based on a saline environment, no correlation was obtained between the presence of any of the microbial genus species and the sex, age, or size of the Arctic char samples (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003e; 0.05; data not shown).</p><fig id="F5" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Amalgamation schedule used to identify the number of major clusters (K) for <bold>(A)</bold> OTUs from skin-associated microbiomes and <bold>(B)</bold> OTUs from intestine-associated microbiomes. Linkage distance is shown in addition to the visualization of steps.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="fbioe-07-00032-g0005"/></fig><table-wrap id="T3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><bold>(A)</bold> Sample counts of each cluster, showing number of samples either caught in a saline or freshwater environment, as obtained using K mean clustering analysis using the skin microbiome data at genus level and <bold>(B)</bold> Sample counts of each cluster, showing number of samples either caught in a saline or fresh environment, as obtained using K mean clustering analysis using the intestinal microbiome data at genus level.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Cluster</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Saline</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Fresh</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="3" style="background-color:#bbbdc0" rowspan="1"><bold>(A)</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">54</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="3" style="background-color:#bbbdc0" rowspan="1"><bold>(B)</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">21</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="T4" position="float"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p><bold>(A)</bold> Microorganisms, classified to genus where possible, present in eight clusters along with the percentage within the skin microbiome of Arctic char and <bold>(B)</bold> Microorganisms, classified to genus where possible, present in eight clusters along with the percentage within the intestinal microbiome of Arctic char.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Taxonomy</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" colspan="8" style="border-bottom: thin solid #000000;" rowspan="1"><bold>Cluster number and percent abundance</bold></th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>3</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>5</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>6</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>7</bold></th><th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>8</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="9" style="background-color:#bbbdc0" rowspan="1"><bold>(A)</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other bacteria</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.96</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.61</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.93</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.74</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p: Actinobacteria c: Actinobacteria o: Actinomycetales f: Other g: Other</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.85</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p: Proteobacteria c: Other o: Other f: Other g: Other</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p: Proteobacteria c: Alphaproteobacteria o: Rhodospirillales f: Acetobacteraceae g: Unknown</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.73</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.52</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.15</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p: Cyanobacteria c: Other o: Other f: Other g: Other</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.99</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p: Firmicutes c: Bacilli o: Lactobacillales f: Other g: Other</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.67</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.94</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57.1</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p: Firmicutes c: Clostridia o: Clostridiales f: Clostridiaceae g: <italic>Clostridium</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.42</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">72.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p: Proteobacteria c: Alphaproteobacteria o: Rhodobacterales f: Rhodobacteraceae g: Other</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.94</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p: Proteobacteria c: Betaproteobacteria o: Burkholderiales f: Comamonadaceae g: Other</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.42</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.73</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" colspan="9" style="background-color:#bbbdc0" rowspan="1"><bold>(B)</bold></td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unclassified</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.17</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.48</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.26</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.28</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Other Bacteria</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.62</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.37</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p: Actinobacteria c: Actinobacteria o: Actinomycetales f: Other g: Other</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.59</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p: Firmicutes c: Bacilli o: Lactobacillales f: Streptococcaceae g: <italic>Streptococcus</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.28</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.35</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.81</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p: Fusobacteria c: Fusobacteriia o: Fusobacteriales f: Fusobacteriaceae g: <italic>u114</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84.2</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.64</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.70</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p: Proteobacteria c: Alphaproteobacteria o: Sphingomonadales f: Sphingomonadaceae g: <italic>Sphingomonas</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.56</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.62</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p: Proteobacteria c: Betaproteobacteria o: Burkholderiales f: Comamonadaceae g: Other</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.48</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.5</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p: Proteobacteria c: Gammaproteobacteria o: Alteromonadales f: Shewanellaceae g: <italic>Shewanella</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.74</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.29</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.50</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p: Proteobacteria c: Gammaproteobacteria o: Pseudomonadales f: Pseudomonadaceae g: Other</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.23</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.46</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.27</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.32</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">85.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p: Proteobacteria c: Gammaproteobacteria o: Pseudomonadales f: Pseudomonadaceae g: <italic>Pseudomonas</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.66</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.47</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.80</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p: Proteobacteria c: Gammaproteobacteria o: Vibrionales f: Vibrionaceae g: Other</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.43</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p: Proteobacteria c: Gammaproteobacteria o: Vibrionales f: Vibrionaceae g: <italic>Aliivibrio</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.13</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.80</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.47</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p: Proteobacteria c: Gammaproteobacteria o: Vibrionales f: Vibrionaceae g: <italic>Photobacterium</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.78</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.0</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.49</td></tr><tr><td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">p: Tenericutes c: Mollicutes o: Mycoplasmatales f: Mycoplasmataceae g: <italic>Mycoplasma</italic></td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.8</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.37</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.11</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.36</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.19</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42</td><td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.14</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>Taxonomy from phylum (p) to clade (c) to order (o) to family (f) to genus (g) is shown</italic>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Characterization of the Intestinal Microbiota</title><p>The 202 intestinal microbiome samples were tested by hierarchical Ward's linkage clustering (Dillner et al., <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>) to investigate the link between salinity and intestine-associated microbiota. The amalgamation schedule graph again showed seven major fusion steps, resulting in eight distinct clusters (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5B</xref>) with Euclidean distances between clusters showing their distinctive nature (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM5">Table S5</xref>). Of the 59 intestinal microbiome samples from freshwater and 143 from saline sites, two clusters (#6 and #8) were dominated by samples from saline water sites whereas another two clusters (#2 and #5) only showed samples from freshwater (<xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3B</xref>). Therefore, these clusters provide further support to the PCoA analysis (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>) that salinity is a statistically significant variable defining the Arctic char intestine-associated microbiome. The ANOVA results indicate that of the 507 taxa used in the clustering analysis, 50 have a <italic>p</italic>-value below 0.05. The phylum Proteobacteria accounted for 25 of these taxa (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM6">Table S6</xref>). Members defined as belonging to an &#x0201c;unidentified kingdom&#x0201d; represented over 6% of the microbial community in two clusters (#4 and #5). Overall, the intestinal core microbiome appears more diverse than that of the skin, with 14 taxa present in all eight clusters (<xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4B</xref>). Clusters (#1&#x02013;#7) included taxa that represented ~8% or more of the community, with 4 and 8 clusters with a single genus occupying over 50% of the entire intestinal microbiome. The taxa included unidentified genera from families Fusobacteriaceae, Comamonadaceae, Pseudomonadaceae, and Vibrionaceae. Other members of the intestinal-associated microbiome include <italic>Streptococcus, Sphingomonas, Shewanella, Pseudomonas, Aliivibrio, Photobacterium</italic>, and <italic>Mycoplasma</italic> (<xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4B</xref>). Again, no correlation was obtained between the presence of any of the microbial genus species and the sex, age, or size of the Arctic char (<italic>p</italic> &#x0003e; 0.05; not shown). Additionally, since hierarchical Ward's linkage clustering was implemented on skin and intestine samples without regard to fishing site, we postulate that the following results provide further evidence that the changes in microbiome between fish caught in saline and freshwater environments are strongly linked to salinity.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><sec><title>Microbial Structure in the Skin and Intestinal Mucous</title><p>The commensal microbes contributing to these Arctic char skin- and intestine-associated microbiome communities were found to be distinct from one another (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>; <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">Tables S1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM2">S2</xref>). There have been few published reports on skin-associated microbiomes, especially in wild fish, possibly because of the challenges associated with ensuring aseptic collection practices and optimal preservation techniques (Kueneman et al., <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Microbiome analysis on the skin of anadromous Atlantic salmon, <italic>S. salar</italic>, showed that Proteobacteria was the dominant phylum (Lokesh and Kiron, <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>), and it was also dominant in the majority of our skin samples taken from freshwater Arctic char (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2A</xref>). Significant differences in the microbiome from fish caught in fresh and saline waters suggests that the skin microbial community changes as the fish swim from one environment to another. Part of the challenge, and likely reflecting the generally unstudied field, is the large proportion of unknown genera in the skin-associated microbiome; 8 of 9 organisms making up the putative core microbiome are currently unknown, and in addition, over 1% of the microbial community belonged to unknown phyla (<xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4A</xref>). Some of these currently unknown members likely serve important roles in the skin mucous, suggesting that metagenomic analysis could perhaps be used to assign putative roles in waste removal, osmoregulation, glycoprotein-mediated drag reduction, and in immune function, and would be of interest for future experiments.</p><p>In contrast to the paucity of information on skin-associated microbiomes, intestine-associated microbiomes have been better studied, although not extensively in wild, ocean-going fish (Egerton et al., <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). Previously reported microorganisms present in the Arctic char gut include <italic>Aeromonas, Flavobacterium, Pseudomonas, Lactobacillus</italic>, and <italic>Vibrio</italic> (Ring&#x000f8; and Str&#x000f8;m, <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">1994</xref>; Ring&#x000f8; et al., <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr">1995</xref>; Nyman et al., <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Lactic acid bacteria (phylum Firmicutes), Fusobacteria, Bacteroidetes, Gammaproteobacteria, Planctomycetes, Clostridia, Verrumicrobia and Bacilli have all been reported as a normal part of the intestine-associated microbiomes in several fish species (Ring&#x000f8; and Gatesoupe, <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr">1998</xref>; Befring-Hovda, <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Ingerslev et al., <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Ghanbari et al., <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). The results reported here are therefore consistent with the previous literature, demonstrating that the community found in wild adult <italic>S. alpinus</italic> intestine-associated microbiomes is not fundamentally different from other fish.</p><p>The core intestine-associated microbiome in Arctic char includes taxa from the Gammaproteobacteria class as well as three genera within the Vibrionaceae family (<xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4B</xref>), similar to observations from Antarctic notothenioid fish species (Ward et al., <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). We also noted the presence of <italic>Streptococcus</italic> and <italic>Mycoplasma. Mycoplasma</italic> have been reportedly abundant in Antarctic fish and Atlantic salmon (Holben et al., <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>; Song et al., <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Dehler et al., <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Unlike in humans where <italic>Mycoplasma</italic> and certain <italic>Streptococcus</italic> are associated with dysbiosis, these genera are proposed to be important for lipid and sugar metabolism and are therefore included in the core intestinal microbiome for Atlantic salmon (Dehler et al., <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). In vertebrates, <italic>Sphingomonas</italic> have been associated with the early-life education of the immune system (Olszak et al., <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Wingender et al., <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Caballero and Pamer, <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Gensollen et al., <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>), and therefore may play a similar role in the gut of Arctic char.</p><p>Notwithstanding the distinct profiles of the skin- and intestine-associated microbiomes, they appear to share certain taxa, including psychrophilic genera, such as <italic>Psychrobacter, Shewanella, Flavobacterium, Acinetobacter, Photobacterium, Planctomyces</italic>, and <italic>Psychromonas</italic>, and including bacteria belonging to the phyla Firmicutes and Cyanobacteria, which could contribute to geochemical cycles, including the nitrogen cycle. Certainly, both microbial community compositions were significantly influenced by the environment in which the fish were caught (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figure 3</xref>; <xref rid="T3" ref-type="table">Table 3</xref>), with <italic>Photobacterium</italic> and <italic>Deinococcus</italic> increasing over 1&#x02013;2 orders of magnitude when intestine- and skin-associated microbiomes, respectively, were recovered from saline water samples. There was no apparent correlation with other measured biotic factors. Our results on wild Arctic char populations are in accord with previous reports including Atlantic salmon, in that they showed salinity-mediated turnover in microbial distributions across the skin and intestines (Schmidt et al., <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>; Lokesh and Kiron, <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">2016</xref>; Dehler et al., <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr">2017</xref>). Manipulation of the skin and intestinal microbiomes by deliberate salinity changes in aquaculture has not yet been explored, but our results suggest that a directed turnover in taxa might be achieved by such a protocol, and should be considered to prevent or inhibit dysbiosis. Although there has been some examination of the survival of farmed <italic>S. alpinus</italic> at higher salinities, consensus has not yet been reached on best practices for inland recirculating systems (J&#x000f8;rgensen et al., <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr">1993</xref>; Larsson and Berglund, <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr">1998</xref>; Summerfelt et al., <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>; Duston et al., <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). To date, existing aquaculture studies have focused on the osmoregulatory consequences of keeping stocks at low salinity or the transfer of young fish from freshwater to a potential saltwater grow-out phase (Arnesen et al., <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">1993</xref>; Aarset, <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>; Duston et al., <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>), but there has been little consideration of the Arctic char skin-associated microbiome, nor of skin- and intestine-associated microbiomes together, and yet the biotechnological applications for manipulation of the microbiota by probiotics is of considerable interest.</p></sec><sec><title>Bioprospecting in the Skin and Intestinal Microbiomes</title><p>Anadromous Arctic char from this high Arctic region grow more rapidly than other local salmonids and live several decades (McPhedran et al., unpublished data). Therefore, we posit that knowledge of the microbiota could be helpful in the development of sustainable and efficient aquaculture practices and to provide an alternate modality to overcome the adverse effects of antibiotics and drugs (Nayak, <xref rid="B41" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). As suggested above, consideration could be given to the manipulation of salt concentrations in Arctic char aquaculture to deliberately direct bacterial communities and possibly bypass dysbiotic episodes. Alternatively, individual isolates may prove valuable. Previously, lactic acid bacteria including <italic>Streptococcus</italic> have been used as probiotics and specifically for furunculosis in rainbow trout, <italic>Oncorhynchus mykiss</italic> (Balc&#x000e1;zar et al., <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Pandiyan et al., <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). This is a serious infection of farmed fish causing skin lesions, hemorrhaging, intestinal tissue damage, and death (Ring&#x000f8; et al., <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>). Other studies have reported the beneficial effect of <italic>Shewanella</italic> and <italic>Vibrio</italic> probiotics (Kamei et al., <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">1988</xref>; Irianto and Austin, <xref rid="B29" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>; D&#x000ed;az-Rosales et al., <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">2006a</xref>,<xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr">b</xref>). The bacteria that we detected in Arctic char skin- and intestine-associated microbiomes, especially those identified as part of the core microbiome, therefore have potential in probiotic applications for aquaculture where they could play a role in immune development and promote the health and growth of farmed fish.</p><p>Many OTUs in the skin and intestinal microbiomes represented unidentified microorganisms, and it suggests that the microbial diversity associated with these wild Arctic char provides fertile ground for bioprospecting for psychrophiles and osmotolerant organisms. For example, some known organisms that are psychrophilic and halophilic are a good source for polyunsaturated fatty acids (PUFA) (Russell and Nichols, <xref rid="B53" ref-type="bibr">1999</xref>). Russell (<xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">1998</xref>) proposed that PUFA in marine psychrophiles allows them to balance the requirement for a fluid membrane at low temperatures with the retention of a requisite level of order. Given these functions, PUFA-producing bacteria may represent an alternate source for human use, with the added advantage of containing only one long-chain PUFA rather than the multiple components present in fish or algal oils (de Pascale et al., <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>).</p><p>As indicated, taxa involved in nitrogen fixation (Cyanobacteria and Rhizobiales), nitrate oxidation (Nitrospirales), and nitrite oxidization (<italic>Nitrospira</italic>) are present in the skin- and intestine-associated microbiomes (<xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1">Tables S1</xref>, <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM2">S2</xref>). Their presence suggests that they may provide an inorganic source of nitrogen when organic nitrogen is low, such as when prey may not be as readily available during the winter under ice. Similar results have been observed by Lee and Childress (<xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr">1994</xref>) and Shah et al. (<xref rid="B55" ref-type="bibr">in press</xref>) in marine invertebrates. Isolates of Nitrospirales, <italic>Nitrospira</italic>, and <italic>Paracoccus</italic>, identified in Arctic char that are adapted to low temperature conditions might be employed in municipal and domestic wastewater treatment facilities where wastewater temperatures fall below 10 &#x000b0;C in winter, and when microbial activity is normally severely depressed (Xu et al., <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr">2018</xref>). Similarly, isolates of <italic>Pseudomonas, Shewanella, Bacillus, Arthrobacter</italic>, and <italic>Sphingobacterium</italic> in the intestine-associated microbiome (<xref rid="T4" ref-type="table">Table 4B</xref>) could play an important role in degradation of pollutants during wastewater treatment. Some bacteria (e.g., members of the Rhizobiales) could even find utility as nitrogen fixers if used for agricultural applications under low temperature conditions.</p><p>Bioprospecting need not be restricted to probiotics, however. Further exploration of identified extremophiles may be useful for other applications. For example, between 6 and 8 million tons of waste crab, shrimp, and lobster shells are produced globally, with the chitin-rich wastes dumped in landfills or the sea (Yan and Chen, <xref rid="B64" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). The presence of OTUs representing <italic>Photobacterium</italic>, in the intestine-associated microbiome of Arctic char (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2B</xref>), with members of this taxon known to aid in chitin digestion (MacDonald et al., <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">1986</xref>; Ramesh and Venugopalan, <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">1989</xref>; Itoi et al., <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>) is noteworthy. It suggests that in the future, chitin-containing seafood waste could be used as supplements for fish food in aquaculture facilities, and also used as a probiotic supplement for Arctic char and other fish.</p><p>In general, our results highlight the need to further explore structural and functional aspects of the microbial communities that naturally inhabit <italic>S. alpinus</italic>. The turnover of both the skin- and intestine-associated communities together during migration represents a previously underappreciated stressor for the species that could be exploited for biotechnological applications including advanced aquaculture systems. The specific taxa observed suggest the potential for isolating useful probiotics, whilst the number of undefined taxa exposes a lack of understanding of this ecosystem, the resolution of which could benefit our understanding of Arctic marine ecosystems as a whole.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="data-availability" id="s5"><title>Data Availability</title><p>The datasets generated for this study can be found in European Nucleotide Archive, <ext-link ext-link-type="EBI:ena" xlink:href="ERP111452">ERP111452</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Ethics Statement</title><p>Fish were sampled in accordance with an approved and issued license to fish for scientific purposes in the waters of the Northwest Territories, Yukon north slope, and Nunavut (in accordance with section 52 of the general fishery regulations of the fisheries act, Fisheries and Oceans, Canada; current permit number S-18/19-1045-NU) along with an associated animal care permit approved and issued by the Fresh Water Institute Animal Care Committee of the Department of Fisheries and Oceans (current permit number FWI-ACC AUP-2018-63).</p></sec><sec id="s7"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>PvCdG organized the fish collection. JDN and KE undertook sequencing and provided bioinformatics analysis. EFH and GE isolated the DNA and conducted statistical analyses. VS did additional statistical analyses. VKW designed the study. EFH, VS, and VKW drafted the manuscript. All authors have read and accepted the final manuscript.</p><sec><title>Conflict of Interest Statement</title><p>The authors declare that the research was conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a potential conflict of interest.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank the Gjoa Haven, NU community residents, the Hunters and Trappers Association (HTA), and all of the associated supporters of the Towards a Sustainable Fishery for Nunavummiut. We would like to thank all sampling personnel that provided invaluable help in the field, and particularly the Gjoa Haven fishermen who were integral to the fish sampling efforts. We would also like to thank Eric T. Daechsel for producing the map for this publication, Kristy Moniz for her valuable technical support throughout the sampling and processing efforts, and Dr. Charles W. Greer (National Research Council) for facilitating and providing the initial water microbiome analyses with alternative primers.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding.</bold> This work was funded by the Government of Canada through Genome Canada and the Ontario Genomics Institute (OGI-096). We also acknowledge funding from the Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council (Canada), the Ontario Ministry of Research and Innovation, CanNor, the Government of Nunavut, and the Northern Scientific Training Program (Polar Knowledge Canada).</p></fn></fn-group><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s8"><title>Supplementary Material</title><p>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fbioe.2019.00032/full#supplementary-material">https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fbioe.2019.00032/full#supplementary-material</ext-link></p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM1"><media xlink:href="Table_1.XLSX"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM2"><media xlink:href="Table_2.XLSX"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM3"><media xlink:href="Table_3.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM4"><media xlink:href="Table_4.xlsx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM5"><media xlink:href="Table_5.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM6"><media xlink:href="Table_6.xlsx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="SM7"><media xlink:href="Image_1.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aarset</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Aquacultural development, institution building and research and development policy: Norwegian salmon and Arctic char farming as cases</article-title>. <source>Aquacult. Econ. Manage.</source>
<volume>3</volume>, <fpage>177</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>191</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/13657309909380244</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Apprill</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Robbins</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Eren</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pack</surname><given-names>A. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Reveillaud</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mattila</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>Humpback whale populaions share a core skin bacterial community: towards a health index for marine mammals?</article-title>
<source>PLoS ONE.</source>
<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e90785</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0090785</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24671052?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24671052</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Arnesen</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>J&#x000f8;rgensen</surname><given-names>E. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jobling</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Feed intake, growth and osmoregulation in Arctic charr, <italic>Salvelinus alpinus</italic> (L.), transferred from freshwater to saltwater at 8 &#x000b0;C during summer and winter</article-title>. <source>FISH.</source>
<volume>12</volume>, <fpage>281</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>292</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 24202870?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24202870</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balc&#x000e1;zar</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Blas</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ruiz-Zarzuela</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vendrell</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Giron&#x000e9;s</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Muzquiz</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Enhancement of the immune response and protection induced by probiotic lactic acid bacteria against furuncolosis in rainbow trout (<italic>Oncorhynchus mykiss</italic>)</article-title>. <source>FEMS Immunol. Med. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>51</volume>, <fpage>185</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>193</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-695X.2007.00294.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17645738?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17645738</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bartram</surname><given-names>A. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lynch</surname><given-names>M. D. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stearns</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreno-Hagelsieb</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Neufeld</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Generation of multimillion-sequence 16S rRNA gene libraries from complex microbial communities by assembling paired-end Illumina reads</article-title>. <source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>77</volume>, <fpage>3846</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3852</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.02772-10</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21460107?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21460107</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Befring-Hovda</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <source>Application of PCR and DGGE to Characterize the Microflora of Farmed Fish.</source>
<publisher-loc>Bergen</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Doctoral Disseration, University of Bergen</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boutin</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bernatchez</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Audet</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Der&#x000f4;me</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Network analysis highlights complex interactions between pathogen, host and commensal microbiota</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>e84772</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0084772</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24376845?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24376845</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caballero</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pamer</surname><given-names>E. G.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Microbiota-mediated inflammation and antimicrobial defense in the intestine</article-title>. <source>Annu. Rev. Immunol.</source>
<volume>33</volume>, <fpage>227</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>256</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev-immunol-032713-120238</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25581310?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25581310</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caporaso</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kuczynski</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stombaugh</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bittinger</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bushman</surname><given-names>F. D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Costello</surname><given-names>E. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>QIIME allows analysis of high-throughput community sequencing data</article-title>. <source>Nat. Methods.</source>
<volume>7</volume>, <fpage>335</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>336</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.f.303</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20383131?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20383131</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Caporaso</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lauber</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Walters</surname><given-names>W. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Berg-Lyons</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lozupone</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Turnbaugh</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Global patterns of 16S rRNA diversity at a depth of millions of sequences per sample</article-title>. <source>PNAS</source>
<volume>108</volume>, <fpage>4516</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4522</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1000080107</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20534432?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20534432</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Carmack</surname><given-names>E. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>The alpha/beta ocean distinction: a perspective on freshwater fluxes, convection, nutrients and productivity in high-latitude seas</article-title>. <source>Deep Sea Res. Part II: Top Stud. Oceanogr.</source>
<volume>54</volume>, <fpage>2578</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2598</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.dsr2.2007.08.018</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chiarello</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vill&#x000e9;ger</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouvier</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bettarel</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouvier</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>High diversity of skin-associated bacterial communities of marine fishes is promoted by their high variability among body parts, individuals and species</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol. Ecol.</source>
<volume>91</volume>:<fpage>fiv061</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/femsec/fiv061</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26048284?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26048284</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clarke</surname><given-names>K. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gorely</surname><given-names>R. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Somerfield</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Warwick</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <source>Change in Marine Communities: An Approach to Statistical Analysis and Interpretation</source>, <edition>3rd edition</edition>
<publisher-loc>Plymouth</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>PRIMER-E</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coolen</surname><given-names>M. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Post</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>C. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Forney</surname><given-names>L. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>Characterization of microbial communities found in the human vagina by analysis of terminal restriction fragment length polymorphisms of 16S rRNA genes</article-title>. <source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>71</volume>, <fpage>8729</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8737</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.71.12.8729-8737.2005</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16332868?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16332868</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Pascale</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Santi</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fu</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Landfald</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>The microbial diversity of Polar environments is a fertile ground for bioprospecting</article-title>. <source>Mar. Genom.</source>
<volume>8</volume>, <fpage>15</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>22</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.margen.2012.04.004</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23199876?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23199876</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dehler</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Secombes</surname><given-names>C. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>S. A. M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Seawater transfer alters the intestinal microbiota profiles of Atlantic salmon (<italic>Salmo salar</italic> L.)</article-title>. <source>Sci. Rep.</source>
<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>13877</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-13249-8</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29066818?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29066818</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>D&#x000ed;az-Rosales</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chabrill&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arijo</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez-Manzanares</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mori&#x000f1;igo</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Balebona</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006b</year>). <article-title>Superoxide dismutase and catalase activities in photobacterium <italic>Damselae</italic> ssp</article-title>. <source>piscicida. J. Fish Dis.</source>
<volume>29</volume>, <fpage>355</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>364</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2761.2006.00726.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16768716?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16768716</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>D&#x000ed;az-Rosales</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Salinas</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodriguez</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cuesta</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chabrillon</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Balebona</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2006a</year>). <article-title>Gilthead seabream (<italic>Sparus aurata</italic> L.) innate immune response after dietary administration of heat-inactivated potential probiotics</article-title>. <source>Fish Shellfish Immun.</source>
<volume>20</volume>, <fpage>482</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>492</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fsi.2005.06.007</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16169250?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16169250</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dillner</surname><given-names>A. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Schauer</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>W. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cass</surname><given-names>G. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2005</year>). <article-title>A quantitiative method for clustering size distributions of elements</article-title>. <source>Atmos. Environ.</source>
<volume>39</volume>, <fpage>1525</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1537</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.atmosenv.2004.11.035</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Duston</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Astatkie</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Murray</surname><given-names>S. B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Effect of salinity at constant 10 &#x000b0;C on grow-out of anadromous Arctic charr from Labrador</article-title>. <source>Aquaculture.</source>
<volume>273</volume>, <fpage>679</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>686</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aquaculture.2007.10.035</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edgar</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>UPARSE: highly accurate OTU sequences from microbial amplicon reads</article-title>. <source>Nat. Methods.</source>
<volume>10</volume>, <fpage>996</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>998</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nmeth.2604</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23955772?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23955772</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edgar</surname><given-names>R. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Clemente</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Quince</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>UCHIME improves sensitivity and speed of chimera detection</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>
<volume>27</volume>, <fpage>2194</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2200</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/bioinformatics/btr381</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21700674?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21700674</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Egerton</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Culloty</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Whooley</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stanton</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>R. P.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>The gut microbiota of marine fish</article-title>. <source>Front. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>873</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3389/fmicb.2018.00873</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29780377?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29780377</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Esteban</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cerezuela</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>4-Fish mucosal immunity: skin A2</article-title>, in <source>Mucosal Health in Aquaculture</source>, eds <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>H.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peatman</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Elsevier Inc.</publisher-name>), <fpage>67</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>92</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/B978-0-12-417186-2.00004-2</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gensollen</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iyer</surname><given-names>S. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kasper</surname><given-names>D. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Blumberg</surname><given-names>R. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>How colonization by microbiota in early life shapes the immune system</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>352</volume>, <fpage>539</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>544</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aad9378</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27126036?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27126036</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghanbari</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kneifel</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Domig</surname><given-names>K. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>A new view of the fish gut microbiome: advances from next-generation sequencing</article-title>. <source>Aquaculture</source>
<volume>448</volume>, <fpage>464</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>475</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aquaculture.2015.06.033</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holben</surname><given-names>W. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saarinen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>S&#x000e4;rkilahti</surname><given-names>L. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Apajalahti</surname><given-names>J. H. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Phylogenetic analysis of intestinal microflora indicates a novel <italic>Mycoplasma</italic> phylotype in farmed and wild salmon</article-title>. <source>Microb. Ecol.</source>
<volume>44</volume>, <fpage>175</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>185</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00248-002-1011-6</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12082453?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12082453</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ingerslev</surname><given-names>H. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>von Gersdorff J&#x000f8;rgensen</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Strube</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Larsen</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dalsgaard</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boye</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>The development of the gut microbiota in rainbow trout (<italic>Oncorhynchus mykiss</italic>) is affected by first feeding and diet type</article-title>. <source>Aquaculture</source>
<volume>424</volume>, <fpage>24</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>34</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aquaculture.2013.12.032</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Irianto</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Austin</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2002</year>). <article-title>Use of probiotics to control furunculosis in rainbow trout, <italic>Oncorhynchus mykiss</italic> (Walbaum)</article-title>. <source>J. Fish Dis.</source>
<volume>25</volume>, <fpage>333</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>342</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2761.2002.00375.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Itoi</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Okamura</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Koyama</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sugita</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2006</year>). <article-title>Chitinolytic bacteria in the intestinal tract of Japanese coastal fishes</article-title>. <source>Can. J. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>52</volume>, <fpage>1158</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1163</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/w06-082</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17473885?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17473885</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>J&#x000f8;rgensen</surname><given-names>E. H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Christiansen</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jobling</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1993</year>). <article-title>Effects of stocking density on food intake, growth performance and oxygen consumption in Arctic charr (<italic>Salvelinus alpinus</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Aquaculture</source>
<volume>110</volume>, <fpage>191</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>204</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0044-8486(93)90272-Z</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kamei</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yoshimizu</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ezura</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kimura</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1988</year>). <article-title>Screening of bacteria with antiviral activity from fresh water salmonid hatcheries</article-title>. <source>Microbiol. Immunol.</source>
<volume>32</volume>, <fpage>67</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>73</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1348-0421.1988.tb01366.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 3374405?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3374405</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kueneman</surname><given-names>J. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parfrey</surname><given-names>L. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Woodhams</surname><given-names>D. C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Archer</surname><given-names>H. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>McKenzie</surname><given-names>V. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2014</year>). <article-title>The amphibian skin-associated microbiome across species, space and life history stages</article-title>. <source>Mol. Ecol.</source>
<volume>23</volume>, <fpage>1238</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1250</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/mec.12510</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24171949?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24171949</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lane</surname><given-names>D. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1991</year>). <article-title>16S/23S rRNA sequencing</article-title>. <source>Nucl. Acid Techniq. Bact. Systemat.</source>
<fpage>115</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>175</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Larsson</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Berglund</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Growth and food consumption of 0+ Arctic charr fed pelleted or natural food at six different temperatures</article-title>. <source>J. Fish Biol.</source>
<volume>52</volume>, <fpage>230</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>242</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1095-8649.1998.tb00795.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>R. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Childress</surname><given-names>J. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Assimilation of inorganic nitrogen by marine invertebrates and their chemoautotrophic and methanotrophic symbionts</article-title>. <source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>60</volume>, <fpage>1852</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1858</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 16349279?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16349279</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lokesh</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kiron</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Transition from freshwater to seawater reshapes the skin-associated microbiota of Atlantic salmon</article-title>. <source>Sci. Rep.</source>
<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>19707</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep19707</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26806545?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26806545</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>MacDonald</surname><given-names>N. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stark</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Austin</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1986</year>). <article-title>Bacterial microflora in the gastro-intestinal tract of Dover sole (<italic>Solea solea</italic> L.), with emphasis on the possible role of bacteria in the nutrition of the host</article-title>. <source>FEMS Microbiol. Lett.</source>
<volume>35</volume>, <fpage>107</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>111</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1574-6968.1986.tb01508.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Masella</surname><given-names>A. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bartram</surname><given-names>A. K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Truszkowski</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>D. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Neufeld</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>PANDAseq: paired-end assembler for Illumina sequences</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinformat.</source>
<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>31</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-13-31</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22333067?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22333067</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>M. N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodrich</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nawrocki</surname><given-names>E. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>DeSantis</surname><given-names>T. Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Probst</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>An improved Greengenes taxonomy with explicit ranks for ecological and evolutionary analyses of bacteria and archaea</article-title>. <source>ISME J.</source>
<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>610</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>618</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ismej.2011.139</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22134646?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22134646</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nayak</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2010</year>). <article-title>Probiotics and immunity: a fish perspective</article-title>. <source>Fish Shellfish Immun.</source>
<volume>29</volume>, <fpage>2</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fsi.2010.02.017</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20219683?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20219683</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nyman</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huyben</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lundh</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dicksved</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2017</year>). <article-title>Effects of microbe-and mussel-based diets on the gut microbiota in Arctic charr (<italic>Salvelinus alpinus</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Aquacult. Rep.</source>
<volume>5</volume>, <fpage>34</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>40</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aqrep.2016.12.003</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olszak</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>An</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zeissig</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vera</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Richter</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Franke</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Microbial exposure during early life has persistent effects on natural killer T cell function</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>336</volume>, <fpage>489</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>493</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1219328</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22442383?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22442383</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pandiyan</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Balaraman</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Thirunavukkarasu</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>George</surname><given-names>E. G. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Subaramaniyan</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Manikkam</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>Probiotics in aquaculture</article-title>. <source>Drug Invent. Today</source>
<volume>5</volume>, <fpage>55</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>59</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.dit.2013.03.003</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parada</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Needham</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuhrman</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>Every base matters: assessing small subunit rRNA primers for marine microbiomes with mock communities, time series and global field samples</article-title>. <source>Environ. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>18</volume>, <fpage>1403</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1414</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1462-2920.13023</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26271760?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26271760</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Quince</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lanzen</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Davenport</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Turnbaugh</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2011</year>). <article-title>Removing noise from pyrosequenced amplicons</article-title>. <source>BMC Bioinformat.</source>
<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>38</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2105-12-38</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21276213?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21276213</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ramesh</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Venugopalan</surname><given-names>V. K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1989</year>). <article-title>Response of enteric luminous bacteria to environmental conditions in the gut of the fish</article-title>. <source>J. Appl. Bacteriol.</source>
<volume>67</volume>, <fpage>529</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>533</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2672.1989.tb02536.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ring&#x000f8;</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gatesoupe</surname><given-names>F. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Lactic acid bacteria in fish: a review</article-title>. <source>Aquaculture.</source>
<volume>160</volume>, <fpage>177</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>203</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0044-8486(97)00299-8</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ring&#x000f8;</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jutfelt</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kanapathippillai</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bakken</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sundell</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Glette</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Damaging effect of the fish pathogen <italic>Aeromonas salmonicida</italic> ssp. <italic>salmonicida</italic> on intestinal enterocytes of Atlantic salmon <italic>(Salmo salar L.)</italic></article-title>. <source>Cell Tissue Res.</source>
<volume>318</volume>, <fpage>305</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>311</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00441-004-0934-2</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15503156?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15503156</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ring&#x000f8;</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Str&#x000f8;m</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1994</year>). <article-title>Microflora of Arctic charr, <italic>Salvelinus alpinus</italic> (L.): gastrointestinal microflora of free-living fish and effect of diet and salinity on intestinal microflora</article-title>. <source>Aquacult. Res.</source>
<volume>25</volume>, <fpage>623</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>629</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2109.1994.tb00726.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ring&#x000f8;</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Str&#x000f8;m</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tabachek</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1995</year>). <article-title>Intestinal microflora of salmonids: a review</article-title>. <source>Aquacult Res.</source>
<volume>26</volume>, <fpage>773</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>789</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2109.1995.tb00870.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>N. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1998</year>). <article-title>Molecular adaptations in psychrophilic bacteria: potential for biotechnological applications</article-title>, in <source>Biotechnology of Extremophiles. Advances in Biochemical Engineering/Biotechnology</source>, <volume>Vol 61</volume>, ed <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Antranikian</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>Heidelberg</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>), <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>21</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BFb0102287</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>N. J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>D. S.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>1999</year>). <article-title>Polyunsaturated fatty acids in marine bacteria- a dogma rewritten</article-title>. <source>Microbiology</source>
<volume>145</volume>, <fpage>767</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>779</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1099/13500872-145-4-767</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10220156?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10220156</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmidt</surname><given-names>V. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>K. F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Melvin</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Amaral-Zettler</surname><given-names>L. A.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Community assembly of a euryhaline fish microbiome during salinity acclimation</article-title>. <source>Mol. Ecol.</source>
<volume>24</volume>, <fpage>2537</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2550</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/mec.13177</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25819646?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25819646</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shah</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanacredi</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name></person-group> (in press). <article-title>Microbial flora associated with laboratory breed horseshoe crabs</article-title>, in <source>The Conservation Biology of Horseshoe Crabs: Social Ecological Global Perspectives.</source> ed <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Tanacredi</surname><given-names>J. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Botton</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shin</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheung</surname><given-names>S. G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carmichael</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Iwasaki</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group> (<publisher-loc>Dordrecht</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer Publishers</publisher-name>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Song</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2016</year>). <article-title>The gut microbial community of antarctic fish detected by 16S rRNA gene sequence analysis</article-title>. <source>Biomed Res. Int.</source>
<volume>2016</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2016/3241529</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27957494?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27957494</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Summerfelt</surname><given-names>S. T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilton</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rimmer</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Fonkalsrud</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2004</year>). <article-title>Developments in recirculating systems for Arctic char culture in North America</article-title>. <source>Aquacult. Eng.</source>
<volume>30</volume>, <fpage>31</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>71</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.aquaeng.2003.09.001</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>V&#x000e1;zquez-Baeza</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pirrung</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2013</year>). <article-title>EMPeror: a tool for visualizing high-throughput microbial community data</article-title>. <source>Gigascience</source>
<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>16</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/2047-217X-2-16</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24280061?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24280061</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Garrity</surname><given-names>G. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tiedje</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cole</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <article-title>Naive Bayesian classifier for rapid assignment of rRNA sequences into the new bacterial taxonomy</article-title>. <source>Appl. Environ. Microbiol.</source>
<volume>73</volume>, <fpage>5261</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5267</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.00062-07</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17586664?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17586664</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ward</surname><given-names>N. L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Steven</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Penn</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Meth,&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Detrich</surname><given-names>W. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2009</year>). <article-title>Characterization of the intestinal microbiota of two Antarctic notothenioid fish species</article-title>. <source>Extremophiles</source>
<volume>13</volume>, <fpage>679</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>685</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00792-009-0252-4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19472032?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19472032</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Watling</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2007</year>). <source>Queensland Government Natural Resources and Water.</source>
<publisher-name>Measuring salinity. (Report No. L137)</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wingender</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stepniak</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Krebs</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>McBride</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>. (<year>2012</year>). <article-title>Intestinal microbes affect phenotypes and functions of invariant natural killer T cells in mice</article-title>. <source>Gastroenterology</source>
<volume>143</volume>, <fpage>418</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>428</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/j.gastro.2012.04.017</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22522092?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22522092</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B63"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Yao</surname><given-names>J. Q.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ainiwaer</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y. J.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2018</year>). <article-title>Analysis of bacterial community structure of activated sludge from wastewater treatment plants in winter</article-title>. <source>Biomed Res. Int.</source>
<volume>2018</volume>, <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2018/8278970</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29707578?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29707578</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B64"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yan</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group> (<year>2015</year>). <article-title>Sustainability: don't waste seafood waste</article-title>. <source>Nature News.</source>
<volume>524</volume>:<fpage>7155</fpage>. <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/524155a</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26268177?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26268177</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>