<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec004" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There has been ongoing research about the relationship between religious beliefs and environmental attitudes. However, less research has focused on the link between religious affiliation and climate change beliefs, particularly in Australia. The results from this study provide clear evidence that among the Australian population attitudes to climate change and climate change policy differ across religious groups. The raw results suggest that Buddhists and Atheists/Agnostics/No Religion are likely to agree that there is climate change, it is human induced and to be supportive of policy. The Christian literalists are likely to have opposing views to this, and the Christian non-literalists are likely to hold opinions between the two extremes. These findings are consistent with those of Hand and van Liere [
  <a rid="pone.0134868.ref006" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0134868.ref006">6</a>] and Guth et al. [
  <a rid="pone.0134868.ref007" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0134868.ref007">7</a>] from the US, which showed a similar distribution of support for environmental policy among US secularists, Christian literalists and Christian non-literalists. Our results extend those of Tranter [
  <a rid="pone.0134868.ref002" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0134868.ref002">2</a>] who found that in Australia, there was a stronger support base for environmental action among those following eastern religious practices. By identifying the climate change attitudes of Buddhists, a group not previously evaluated in these earlier studies, we have contributed knowledge to this area of study. Furthermore, our results showed that Buddhists, like those in the Atheists/Agnostics/No Religion group, have a stronger potential for engagement in environmental issues than other religious groups; whereas Tranter [
  <a rid="pone.0134868.ref002" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0134868.ref002">2</a>] showed that “the non-religious are pro-environmental to a greater extent than those with religious affiliations”. These findings provide new insights into the linkages between religious belief and climate change attitudes.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Earlier studies [
  <a rid="pone.0134868.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0134868.ref014">14</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0134868.ref017" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0134868.ref017">17</a>] suggested that the effect of religious variables on environmental concern might simply reflect social, demographic and other factors such as political conservatism. Others [
  <a rid="pone.0134868.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0134868.ref021">21</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0134868.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0134868.ref023">23</a>] have suggested that scientific knowledge may similarly be a mediating influence between religious variables and environmental concern. For this reason, we ran a series of ordinal regressions to examine the effect of socio-demographic variables, environmental attitude and knowledge about climate change on segment membership. Our results indicate that for those who are Christian literalist or Christian non-literalist, the effect of their religious affiliation substantially diminishes with inclusion of socio-demographic variables, environmental attitudes and knowledge. Nevertheless, religious affiliation was still demonstrated to be a significant factor; Christians had a tendency to be more dismissive of climate change than secularists, while Buddhists had stronger engagement and support for climate change policy than secularists. For all three of these religious groups, the effects could not simply be explained by socio-demographic variables, environmental attitude or knowledge about climate change. There was a residual effect related to their religious beliefs. These findings contrast with the earlier literature [
  <a rid="pone.0134868.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0134868.ref014">14</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0134868.ref017" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0134868.ref017">17</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our findings provide new evidence to suggest that the differences associated with religious affiliation may in part be due to beliefs around human rule over nature. However, these beliefs are more nuanced than suggested by White [
  <a rid="pone.0134868.ref005" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0134868.ref005">5</a>]. Buddhists shared a similar level of support for human rule over nature with Christian literalists, though Buddhists had a strong level of support for pro-environment policies unlike Christian literalists. There was also a significant association between belief in human rule over nature and identification as a Christian non-literalist.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Christian literalists are likely to have a high belief in both human ingenuity to overcome environmental problems and in human rule over nature, and a low belief in earth limits. This set of beliefs is consistent with and may sustain a weak belief in (or even denial of) climate change as a problem and, if there is a problem, a strong belief in human capacity to overcome it. In contrast, those in the Atheist/Agnostic/No Religion group have the opposite views across these three dimensions. They tend to have a strong belief that there is a climate change problem and a weak belief in human capacity to overcome it.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While significant effects were identified in this study for all religious groups relative to the non-religious group, it should be borne in mind that these effects vary in magnitude. For the Buddhists, the effects were relatively large, and positively related to climate change engagement. For the Christian literalists and Christian non-literalists the effects were negatively related to climate change engagement and were similar in magnitude and direction to the effects of a number of socio-demographic variables such as, being male or being self-employed.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It would have been useful to have results that showed climate change attitudes and behavior for Indigenous Australians and those of different ethnic background. Unfortunately limitations of sample size prevented this. Some comments with respect to gender and education are, however, possible. From a literal Christian perspective, these results also present some further interesting challenges. Although the results show that the overall view in these congregations would be to disagree that there is climate change and that it is human induced, and to be unsupportive of policy, women members and those who are more highly educated would have a tendency to the opposite views on these issues.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For those of a Christian literalist or Christian non-literalist affiliation, the question arises about what should be done about these findings which show disengagement of Christians with climate change issues. One response is for denominations to seek to influence their members to bring an ethical dimension to the climate change issue, as recommended by Posas [
  <a rid="pone.0134868.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0134868.ref004">4</a>]. Indeed there has been evidence of this type of activity, such as in the Anglican diocese of Canberra and Goulburn (Australia) which has developed an environmental policy and is seeking to reduce climate change emissions from church buildings, and if possible by 50% by 2020 [
  <a rid="pone.0134868.ref041" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0134868.ref041">41</a>]. On a far larger scale is the Pope’s 2015 encyclical in which it is predicted that “he will define climate change as a fundamentally moral and religious challenge to the world” [
  <a rid="pone.0134868.ref011" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0134868.ref011">11</a>]. Climate change seems be an area in a deep state of flux as far as many religious groups are concerned. It is interesting that, in accord with our results, these examples of change in the positions of church leadership are from non-literal Christianity. An important question in this changing environment is the response among literal Christian leaders in the face of future climate change challenges. In this context, the response of conservative Christian leaders in the US has been to avoid the climate change issue [
  <a rid="pone.0134868.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0134868.ref015">15</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another possible response to our results is to seek a unified position across religious groupings on climate change, to seek to change community attitudes. Examples of these included the 2007 and 2009 resolutions of the United Churches of Christ in the USA, which comprises predominantly Congregational churches [
  <a rid="pone.0134868.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0134868.ref042">42</a>], the resolution of Evangelical Christian Leaders in the USA [
  <a rid="pone.0134868.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0134868.ref043">43</a>], as well as the position statements of the World Council of Churches [
  <a rid="pone.0134868.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0134868.ref044">44</a>]. Similar statements have also been released in Australia. For example, the Uniting Church [
  <a rid="pone.0134868.ref045" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0134868.ref045">45</a>] adopted a statement called “For the Sake of the Planet and all its People” that relates to climate change, and calls on church members to reduce carbon emission and advocate for governments to reduce dependence on carbon based energy sources. Similar efforts are being promoted by the Catholic Church through Catholic Earthcare Australia [
  <a rid="pone.0134868.ref046" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0134868.ref046">46</a>]. Evidence is emerging that these sorts of strategies have led to increased local level action to reduce carbon emissions [
  <a rid="pone.0134868.ref047" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0134868.ref047">47</a>]. However, as Ayre [
  <a rid="pone.0134868.ref047" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0134868.ref047">47</a>] suggests, ambiguity still remains for some Australian denominations about the church’s role in being vocal about the need for responsible care for the environment, and opportunity remains to better translate stated positions about climate change into effective work on the ground. Thus there remains opportunity for religious groups to do more to support the acceptance of human induced climate change and the need for policy responses, as well as action at a local level.
 </p>
</sec>
