<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ack class="ack">
 <title class="title">Acknowledgments</title>
 <p class="p">We would like to acknowledge the World Climate Research Program Working Group on Coupled Modelling responsible for CMIP5, the climate modeling groups for making the model output available, and P. Štěpánek (CzechGlobe) for valuable comments. We are grateful to the two anonymous reviewers for insightful comments, which improved the structure and clarity of the paper. 
  <bold class="bold">Funding:</bold> M.T., J.B., K.K., D.S., J.M., P.H., J.E.O., K.C.K., and U.B. acknowledge support from the SustES - Adaptation strategies for sustainable ecosystem services and food security under adverse environmental conditions (CZ.02.1.01/0.0/0.0/16_019/0000797), which enabled the study to be conducted. S.F. and W.H. were supported by the National Key R&amp;D Program of China (grant no. 2018YFA0606404). International collaboration was also made possible via a framework provided by the international research project FACCE MACSUR. J.E.O. received support from the Innovation Fund Denmark. R.P.R. received support from the SPACES program (grant no. 01LL1304A) of the German Federal Ministry of Education and Research (BMBF). Rothamsted Research received grant-aided support from the Biotechnology and Biological Sciences Research Council Designing Future Wheat Programme [BB/P016855/1]. M.R.-R. was supported by the Spanish National Institute for Agricultural and Food Research and Technology and the Ministry of Economy and Competitiveness (MACSUR02-APCIN2016-00050-00-00). K.C.K. was supported by the German Federal Ministry of Education and Research through MACSUR2 (031B0039C). 
  <bold class="bold">Author contributions:</bold> M.T. and S.F. designed the study. M.T., S.F., J.B., D.S., and W.H. performed the experiments. All coauthors analyzed the data and wrote the manuscript. 
  <bold class="bold">Competing interests:</bold> The authors declare that they have no competing interests. 
  <bold class="bold">Data and materials availability:</bold> All data needed to evaluate the conclusions in the paper are present in the paper and/or the Supplementary Materials. The original water scarcity datasets used in the study are available at 
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://alpha.czechglobe.cz/mirek" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://alpha.czechglobe.cz/mirek</ext-link>. Additional data related to this paper may be requested from the authors as instructed at 
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://alpha.czechglobe.cz/mirek" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://alpha.czechglobe.cz/mirek</ext-link>.
 </p>
</ack>
