<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We extracted a total of 2566 occurrence (longitude and latitude) records for four common 
 <italic class="italic">Sphagnum</italic> species found throughout North America from Duke University herbarium (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://herbarium.duke.edu/databases" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://herbarium.duke.edu/databases</ext-link>), Consortium of North American Bryophyte Herbaria (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bryophyteportal.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.bryophyteportal.org</ext-link>), and Consortium of Pacific Northwest Herbaria (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnwherbaria.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.pnwherbaria.org</ext-link>) databases. To reduce the influence of potentially uneven species detection efforts across the study region, a maximum of one record per species was used per 1-km
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> grid cell. This resulted in a total of 1496 occurrence records that were used in modelling, comprising 289 
 <italic class="italic">Sphagnum angustifolium</italic>, 435 
 <italic class="italic">S</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">fuscum</italic>, 414 
 <italic class="italic">S</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">magellanicum</italic>, and 358 
 <italic class="italic">S</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">rubellum</italic> records. Although 
 <italic class="italic">Sphagnum</italic> species can be difficult to identify, some such as 
 <italic class="italic">S</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">fuscum</italic> can be identified with relative ease. Although misidentifications may influence the modelled distribution of an individual species, we integrated occurrence records for some models, so we expect such occurrence errors to have negligible effects for determining peatland distributions. Also, because of their lack of roots and stomata, 
 <italic class="italic">Sphagnum</italic> species are opportunists and rarely occur individually, facilitating adequate representation of peatland habitat. Finally, integrating records from multiple databases that assemble records from expert sources should minimize errors due to misidentification and spatial bias.
</p>
