<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Marketing research has long looked at society’s expectations of corporations with regard to CSR, by examining consumer’s expectations. For example, 
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Mohr et al. (2001)</xref> conducted in-depth interviews with 48 people and found that over half desired moderately high or high levels of CSR from companies. 
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Maignan (2001)</xref> surveyed over 300 people from Germany, France, and USA; she found that consumers in France and Germany believed that companies were just as responsible for ethical and discretionary responsibilities as they were for economic outcomes. Moreover, although US consumers believed that companies had more responsibility for economic outcomes than philosophical or ethical endeavors, their scores on the latter (mean scores of 4.43 and 5.12 on a seven-point scale) indicate that they have moderately strong expectations for CSR. This previous research examined CSR more broadly than dealing with climate change and was focused on consumers rather than more general societal expectations, however, it does indicate that there are societal expectations for companies to be involved in CSR. Extrapolating from this, we propose that people in the community will also perceive that dealing with climate change is a corporation’s responsibility. In addition, rather than simply looking at mean scores, we also wanted to compare societal expectations for different loci of responsibility. To our knowledge, we are the first to compare loci of responsibility for dealing with climate change and therefore we do not have any evidence to suggest whether expectations for corporations are greater than that for other societal groups. Our first hypothesis, therefore, incorporates both our supposition that there will be high levels of expectations for corporations to deal with climate change and an exploratory examination of differences between societal groups:
</p>
