<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par18" class="p">The marine stickleback population studied here showed heritable genetic variation for body size, indicating that adaptive evolution of thermal reaction norms to environmental change is not constrained by the amount of standing genetic variation (see also ref. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" class="xref">48</xref>). Comparable results for this population have been shown for other life history (weight, survival) and morphological (shape) traits
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" class="xref">46</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" class="xref">47</xref>
 </sup>. Positive genetic correlations across environments also indicate that the evolutionary potential of offspring size in future conditions may be reliably predicted from current levels of standing genetic variation (see also
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" class="xref">47</xref>
 </sup>). In this study, genetic variance and total phenotypic variance of body size differed among offspring rearing temperatures (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table" class="xref">3</xref>). At the earliest growth stage (30d), genetic and phenotypic variance were highest when offspring were reared at 21 °C. After this initial phase, however, genetic and phenotypic variances were highest when offspring were reared in the stochastic environment. Stressful, unfavourable and/or novel conditions are known to contribute to changes in variance components and resulting heritability of traits across environments
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" class="xref">35</xref>
 </sup>. Mechanisms include changes to environmental variance, non-additive effects including maternal effects, G × E interactions, and release of cryptic genetic variation
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81" class="xref">81</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82" class="xref">82</xref>
 </sup>. Here, changes to total phenotypic variance may have been influenced by many of these mechanisms. First, environmental variance decreased over time within each of the offspring rearing temperatures, contributing to decreasing total phenotypic variance over time. Second, maternal and other non-additive effects may have contributed to changes in phenotypic variance across environments, however, these could not be partitioned out due to the full-sibling design. Nevertheless, the lack of maternal environment effects (Dam °C) or TGP on offspring size in some but not all families suggests that there is substantial variation for genetic as well as non-genetic maternal effects in the studied population. Third, G × E interactions had a strong influence on changes to V
 <sub class="sub">P</sub> across environments. Genetic and phenotypic variances also differed between the predictably variable and stochastic environments, again suggesting that the type of environmental predictability
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" class="xref">41</xref>
 </sup> in conjunction with the complex relationship between predictability and G × E
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" class="xref">31</xref>
 </sup> can shape the adaptive potential of a population.
</p>
