<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="gcb12978-sec-0009" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusions</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Recent discussions on the state of global oceans are often marked with mounting concerns for the fate of marine species and communities (e.g., McCauley 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0058" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0058">2015</a>). However, Duarte 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. (
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0021">2015</a>) argue for increased scrutiny of the available evidence for “ocean calamities” and suggest that several observation and citation biases may lead to an unsupported perception of ocean condition. The goal of our study was to examine the current discourse on changing ocean conditions across multiple marine disciplines, identify disciplinary trends, and determine areas where discourse on marine climate change has been lacking. We provided a novel cross‐disciplinary approach and reviewed a wider breadth of topics than previous syntheses, examining the nuanced intricacies of physical and chemical processes as well as biological impacts across research foci.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our comprehensive review of highly cited literature revealed that current discourse on ocean change is shaped by potential research biases, disciplinary differences in research scope, and numerous research gaps. We identify several regions, taxa, physical and chemical stressors, types of biological responses, and scale issues warranting increased investigation and reporting to better inform ecosystem‐based and interdisciplinary research, and to improve interpretation of climate change in marine systems (Table 
  <a rid="gcb12978-tbl-0003" ref-type="table-wrap" href="#gcb12978-tbl-0003">3</a>). Our synthesis suggests certain taxa are relatively understudied, such as archaea, bacteria, and viruses that serve critical roles in marine ecosystems and will likely be affected by climate change in unknown ways (Pörtner 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0073" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0073">2014</a>). While other studies have also diagnosed regional biases and mismatches in scales for marine biological responses (e.g., Poloczanska 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0071" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0071">2013</a>; Hoegh‐Guldberg 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0039">2014</a>), our review is distinctive by simultaneously comparing and contrasting both abiotic and biotic ocean change studies. It is our intent that the findings of this review will be used to inform future directions of ocean change research. For example, our review and others (e.g., Hoegh‐Guldberg 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0039">2014</a>) illustrate that some geographic regions have been extensively studied by several disciplines (e.g., North Atlantic and North Pacific), often for extended durations. We suggest these regions are fertile grounds for integrative studies that extend beyond single‐species examinations of climate change and incorporate potential effects of multiple stressors (e.g., Large 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0048" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0048">2015</a>), ultimately improving our ability to understand climate‐related ecosystem‐level changes (Pörtner 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0073" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0073">2014</a>). In the remainder of this section, we will discuss other ways in which our findings can be applied to future research efforts to support marine climate change research that can be compared across biotic and abiotic disciplines.
 </p>
 <div id="gcb12978-tbl-0003" xml:lang="en" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Table 3</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Critical research gaps in contemporary, highly cited ocean change literature and examples of potential effects on interpretation of climate impacts in marine systems</p>
  </div>
  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
   <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/>
   <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/>
   <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/>
   <thead valign="top">
    <tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000">
     <th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ocean change component</th>
     <th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Research gaps</th>
     <th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Effect on interpretation of climate impacts</th>
    </tr>
   </thead>
   <tbody>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Geographic examination (regional biases)</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lack of research in Indian, South Pacific, and South Atlantic basins</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Local climate measures vary globally, resulting in geographically distinct impacts (Garcia 
      <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
      <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0026">2014</a>). Regional over‐ or undersampling can bias an integrated interpretation of ocean change across the global ocean. Greater focus and broader disciplinary coverage in the North Atlantic and Pacific basins suggests these regions are more likely to foster cross‐disciplinary or ecosystem‐scale investigations
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Geographic examination (disciplinary biases)</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Incomplete representation among disciplines within regions</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">A limited representation of studies among the suite of taxa within a region can affect a comprehensive assessment of climate impacts.For example, organisms in polar regions adapted to extreme, yet relatively stable conditions, are considered at high risk to changing ocean conditions (e.g., Laidre 
      <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
      <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0047">2008</a>). Limited research on many biological systems in polar regions inhibits our ability to form a comprehensive understanding of climate change impacts on global marine ecosystems
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spatial and temporal scales</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scaling biological response studies from laboratory to natural settings</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Small‐scale, controlled studies conducted at the individual level are difficult to translate to regional or global impacts at the population or ecosystem level (Wahl 
      <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
      <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0089" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0089">2015</a>) and poorly replicate covariation among physical parameters or natural variability (Hofmann 
      <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
      <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0040">2011</a>; Reum 
      <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
      <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0076" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0076">2014</a>).
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spatial &amp; temporal scale</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Biological studies of long duration and large spatial scale</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Long‐term, large‐scale, and high‐resolution biological response studies have greater ability and more statistical power to attribute biological responses to climate‐mediated physical/chemical changes (Brown 
      <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
      <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0004">2011</a>; Parmesan 
      <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
      <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0067" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0067">2011</a>; O'Connor 
      <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
      <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0063" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0063">2015</a>) vs. natural variability (Doney &amp; Sailley, 
      <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0018">2013</a>)
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spatial and temporal scales</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lack of standardization in biologically relevant spatial and temporal scales</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The number of generations (temporal) or proportion of the home range examined (spatial) may be more biologically relevant than typical study scale measures, like study duration (years) or area (km
      <span class="sup">2</span>). Standardization of biologically relevant scales will improve the capacity to detect change when comparing and synthesizing biological responses among diverse marine species
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Biological themes</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Archaea, bacteria, viruses, turtles, mangroves</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sensitivities to physical and chemical environmental changes are highly species specific (Poloczanska 
      <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
      <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0071" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0071">2013</a>; Pörtner 
      <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
      <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0073" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0073">2014</a>). Focus on particular taxa or ‘model’ organisms and a lack of study of others can obstruct a more comprehensive, ecosystem‐based understanding of ocean change impacts, especially when underrepresented species play critical roles in marine ecosystems.
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physical/chemical oceanography themes</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acidity, dissolved oxygen</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physical/chemical themes were generally sampled over longer durations and greater study areas than biological themes. However, studies of OA and dissolved oxygen lagged behind other abiotic themes despite the need for high‐resolution physical time series in biological response studies (Hoegh‐Guldberg 
      <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
      <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0039">2014</a>)
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Physical/chemical stressors affecting biological responses</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dissolved oxygen, salinity, upwelling</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dissolved oxygen plays an important role in the ecophysiological response of many organisms to climate change (e.g., Pörtner &amp; Knust, 
      <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0072" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0072">2007</a>), and widespread changes in salinity and upwelling can alter abundance and distributions of marine species (Hays 
      <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
      <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0033">2005</a>; Doney 
      <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
      <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0020">2012</a>). Enhanced examination of the responses of these understudied stressors to climate change and their impacts on marine populations will improve an ecosystem‐wide understanding of ocean change
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Biological responses</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Evolutionary adaptations</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Adaptation is one of the four categories of biological response to climate change (O'Connor 
      <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
      <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0062">2012</a>). Research is needed on adaptive responses of marine organisms to fully understand the impact of changing ocean conditions
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of stressors examined</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Incorporating multiple and nonclimate stressors</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Multiple environmental factors covary in time and space (Rhein 
      <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
      <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0078" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0078">2013</a>). These synergistic stressors and other anthropogenic activities (e.g., fishing, pollution) may have difficult to predict interaction effects on biological responses (Doney 
      <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
      <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0020">2012</a>; Hoegh‐Guldberg 
      <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
      <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0039">2014</a>). Studies that test for multiple alternative stressors have greater ability to attribute biological responses to physical/chemical changes (O'Connor 
      <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
      <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0063" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0063">2015</a>)
     </td>
    </tr>
   </tbody>
  </table>
  <div class="permissions">
   <span class="copyright-holder">John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd</span>
  </div>
 </div>
 <sec id="gcb12978-sec-0010" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Spatial and temporal patterns of ocean change studies</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our review revealed several geographic biases, both general and discipline specific, in distributions of highly cited ocean change studies. However, a lack of demonstrated climate change impacts within a region does not necessarily mean impacts are absent (Hansen &amp; Cramer, 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0030" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0030">2015</a>). Many of these geographically based disparities are to be expected given accessibility, the predominance of scientists in northern countries, and the area covered by each taxonomic group. Some taxa and systems are limited by their biogeographic distribution (e.g., tropical coral reefs) or associations with localized physical phenomena (e.g., polar bears, 
   <span class="italic">Ursus marinus</span>, associated with Arctic sea ice). For example, the Arctic is home to some of the most rapidly and drastically transforming marine ecosystems on the planet (e.g., Serreze 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0085" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0085">2007</a>; Grebmeier, 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0028">2012</a>), as reflected by the relatively high number of Arctic ocean change studies. However, research on Arctic biological responses remains primarily limited to vertebrate studies largely focused on polar bears, ice‐associated seals, and a few marine bird species. Studies on benthic communities were notably absent from the highly cited Arctic studies. Wassmann 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>. (
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0090" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0090">2011</a>) found similar biases toward biological response studies focused on vertebrates in the Arctic and argued for increased effort at lower trophic levels. Some physical parameters also have geographic limits. For example, monitoring of sea ice extent is geographically restricted to the poles, which contributed the majority of the physical measurements in polar regions.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We show observation biases concerning the regions where highly cited ocean change research is conducted and how this varies among disciplines. In particular, Southern Hemisphere ocean basins (e.g., the South Atlantic and Pacific, Indian, and Southern Ocean) were characterized by a general lack of ocean change research, especially relative to their large proportional surface area of the global ocean. Human development (which “remains a composite index that measures progress in three basic dimensions – health, knowledge and income”, 2014 UN Human Development Reports: 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://hdr.undp.org/en/countries" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://hdr.undp.org/en/countries</span>) and technological capacity are highest in Western Europe, North America, and Australia and may partially explain geographic biases of greater research focus (by nearly 3×) in the Northern Hemisphere. Greater human development in Australia and parts of South America (e.g., Chile) may contribute to the relatively high prevalence of benthic studies, focused on coral reefs and kelp forests, in the South Pacific. Additionally, we focused on the most frequently cited papers, which may impose geographic biases due to citation patterns. There may be higher citation potential in areas where there are more researchers, such as the North Atlantic or Mediterranean. However, similar geographic biases have been described elsewhere in the biological impacts literature, such as the predominance of biological change studies in more temperate (Wernberg 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0091" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0091">2012</a>) and Northern Hemisphere (Poloczanska 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0071" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0071">2013</a>) waters, especially the northeast Atlantic basin (Hoegh‐Guldberg 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0039">2014</a>). Lenoir &amp; Svenning (
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0050" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0050">2015</a>) note that a geographic bias in the Northern Hemisphere was not as prominent in a review of the marine compared to terrestrial range shift literature. Our study highlights finer regional and thematic biases than previous studies and also offers direct comparisons between studies with abiotic and biological focus. For example, we show that the proportion of studies from each discipline was more similar in the North and South Atlantic and Pacific basins than other regions. The more representative coverage among disciplines, in addition to an overall greater geographic focus, suggests that studies in the North Atlantic and Pacific basin may have more power for ecosystem‐wide or cross‐disciplinary investigations than elsewhere.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition to basin‐specific patterns, we found that approximately 20% of the highly cited ocean change studies were multiregional or global in scale, providing the potential for a more representative view of ocean change (Parmesan 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0067" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0067">2011</a>). However, we also observed a trade‐off between geographic scale and sampling resolution (data not shown) for a number of studies in this review. Smaller‐scale environmental studies (&lt;10 km
   <span class="sup">2</span>) often had increased sampling frequency (hourly–weekly) compared to studies that covered a greater geographic extent (greater than monthly or discrete sampling). Hence, while more localized studies may not be able to extrapolate findings to the basin or global scale (appropriate for ecosystem‐wide assessments), they may be better suited to estimate rates of change on more localized scales (e.g., discrete populations). There is also the potential for citation biases for large‐scale studies, where such studies may be cited more frequently due to their broad geographic representation and therefore more represented in our analyses. Indeed, multiregional and global papers had a mean number of 149.4 citations compared to 82.2 citations for all other smaller‐scale papers included in this review. The potential citation bias associated with large‐scale papers may be explained by uncritical or superficial citations (Banobi 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0002">2011</a>) when used in introductory sentences rather than more substantive citations used to augment interpretations and discussion of research findings.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Studies covering physical/chemical signals of ocean change were typically the longest running and covered the largest study areas. A relatively small number of biological ocean change studies were conducted on similarly broad scales. The emerging field of ocean acidification (examining a suite of changes in OA including pH, aragonite saturation, and pCO
   <sub>2</sub>) was often conducted on smaller scales and had a much shorter temporal record (median = 10.5 year) relative to other physical/chemical studies with median durations ranging from 2× (sea ice) to nearly 5× (SST) longer. Physical records like SST, sea level height, and sea ice are largely drawn from worldwide networks of autonomous sensors (e.g., Argo floats), interpolation of data from cruises, or derived from satellite measurements over particular geographic regions (global oceans in the former and polar regions in the latter). Such approaches allow data to be collected across wide areas and over extended durations. Long‐term physical and chemical records are essential to understanding climate variability, especially when detecting and attributing biological responses to climate change (Hoegh‐Guldberg 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0039">2014</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Studies conducted over shorter time periods or lacking historical baselines have limited statistical power to demonstrate conclusively impacts due to climate (Edwards 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0023">2010</a>; Brown 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0004">2011</a>). Therefore, physical records, particularly the long duration and large spatial scale records for SST and sea level height, may ultimately have more statistical power to detect when a climate‐driven change has occurred. However, relating biological responses to physical changes is often complicated by mismatches in scale, sampling frequencies, or proximity of samples. The problem of pattern and scale (Levin, 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0052">1992</a>) is thus a key issue in attributing observed biological changes to climate (Rosenzweig 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0083" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0083">2008</a>). Biological responses are measured at local, regional, and global scales relative to an assortment of climate measures (Garcia 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0026">2014</a>), and confidence in the assessment of climate impacts on marine taxa is greatest for long‐term studies with fine‐resolution data (O'Connor 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0063" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0063">2015</a>) or those conducted on the scale of entire ocean basins or greater (Parmesan 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0067" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0067">2011</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Life‐history characteristics of biological taxa also complicate a straightforward interpretation of differences in scale among disciplines. Climate responses are species specific (Poloczanska 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0071" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0071">2013</a>; Pörtner 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0073" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0073">2014</a>), and standardizing for the dispersal abilities and productivity of a given organism could provide a more comprehensive understanding of whether biological studies are conducted at scales and sampling frequencies necessary to assess change adequately. For example, marine mammal studies tended to incorporate relatively large spatial scales, but many of these species migrate over vast areas. Thus, sampling a single or relatively large study area may still only investigate a small portion of their overall home range, ultimately leading to an inadequate estimation of changes like shifts in distribution (Przeslawski 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0074" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0074">2012</a>). Similarly, long study durations, such as those for coral reefs, may still be inadequate for species that have extended generation times (e.g., ~100 year for 
   <span class="italic">Porites</span> spp.; Veron, 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0088" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0088">1985</a>). On the other hand, plankton, that often have short generation times of days to months and limited motility, may actually be some of the best sampled marine organisms with respect to understanding baselines of population dynamics that are needed in assessing natural variability (on daily, seasonal, and interannual timescales) from climate‐mediated change. The number of generations studied ultimately may be a more relevant metric for biological responses than study duration and useful for standardization when comparing among species. For example, a zooplankton (e.g., calanoid copepod) study with a 1‐ to 2‐year duration, examining 1–10 generations, may be more comparable to a 10‐ to 15‐year study of marine mammals (e.g., phocid seals) that surveys one generation. While noting information on generation time and home range size may not be available for each species or population examined, we suggest a different impression of how completely taxonomic groups are sampled (in terms of scale and frequency) may emerge if standardization for home ranges and generation times were available for organisms studied in these ocean change studies. For example, the literature examining species range shifts in terrestrial systems uses km/decade as a common metric to compare responses among taxa, which have recently been applied to marine taxa (e.g., Pinsky 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0070" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0070">2013</a>) and is a standardization that has historically been lacking for marine climate impact studies (Richardson &amp; Poloczanska, 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0079" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0079">2008</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="gcb12978-sec-0011" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Biological responses to physical and chemical stressors</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our review indicates a strong reliance on laboratory experimentation to estimate biological responses to physical and chemical marine changes that occur in the field. This is particularly true for plankton and benthic invertebrates that are more easily cultivated and maintained in laboratory settings compared to large or highly mobile vertebrates. Laboratory studies typically are performed at small spatial and temporal scales and under controlled conditions that are not capable of mimicking the complexity of natural environments. For instance, over half of the biological papers considering OA effects on organisms were conducted in the laboratory because seawater chemistry can be manipulated more easily in a controlled environment. However, OA expresses complicated natural patterns of variability (Hofmann 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0040">2011</a>) and is poorly replicated in experimental biological response studies due to covariation with factors like temperature, oxygen, and salinity (Reum 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0076" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0076">2014</a>). Short‐term controlled studies of biological responses to chemical changes can provide direct measures of organismal responses; however, these studies are not easily scaled up or extrapolated to long‐term or ecosystem‐level effects (Wahl 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0089" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0089">2015</a>), and there is generally low‐to‐medium confidence in assessing the tolerance of many marine taxa to future CO
   <sub>2</sub> levels (Pörtner 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0073" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0073">2014</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Temperature was also frequently studied as a stressor under laboratory examination: 19% of biological responses considered temperature a primary stressor. Temperature in the ocean has been sampled widely for extended durations, and our results suggest that it is a readily available covariate in biological response studies. Despite being easy to sample, temperature may not always be the most ecologically meaningful stressor affecting a given marine species (Robinson 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0080" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0080">2011</a>). Instead, the physical or chemical factors most relevant to an organism or system of interest may be the best focus of examination. For example, changing temperature regimes may have little direct impact on warm‐blooded marine mammals, seabirds, and fish (e.g., tuna and some sharks) that maintain body temperatures above ambient conditions. On the other hand, marine reptiles like sea turtles have temperature‐dependent sex determination, such that increased nesting temperatures could bias sex ratios within populations (Hawkes 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0032">2009</a>). Thus, temperature was not surprisingly the most frequently studied stressor and, most appropriate, for marine turtle reproductive studies.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Temperature may be a key factor interacting with other important abiotic mechanisms that warrant simultaneous investigation. Sensitivity to changing thermal regimes may set the physiological limits for responses by some marine species, but other factors like oxygen, acidity, upwelling, and salinity can also complicate predictions of climate impacts (Pörtner 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0073" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0073">2014</a>). For example, a recent study demonstrated the importance of modeling interacting forces of acidification, temperature, and deoxygenation in understanding impacts on aerobic metabolic rates for teleost fishes (Del Raye &amp; Weng, 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0014">2015</a>). Dissolved oxygen was rarely studied as a primary stressor in biological response studies despite being an important ecophysiological factor affecting many marine organisms (e.g., Dodds 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0016">2007</a>; Pörtner &amp; Knust, 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0072" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0072">2007</a>; Froehlich 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0025">2015</a>) that is susceptible to climate variations (Deutsch 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0015">2011</a>). Hoegh‐Guldberg 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>. (
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0039">2014</a>) suggest that understanding the effects of declining oxygen concentrations is an emerging research need. Our study indicates that long‐term, high‐resolution data on dissolved oxygen are less available to researchers compared to data on temperature, which may contribute to the apparent lack of dissolved oxygen as a stressor in biological response studies. Similarly, climate‐related changes in salinity and upwelling can strongly influence primary productivity, as well as the abundance and distributions of marine organisms (Hays 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0033">2005</a>; Doney 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0020">2012</a>). Understanding changes in surface winds may be critical to understanding regional upwelling processes and how upwelling contributes to hypoxia at varying depths or other important ecosystem effects of ocean–atmosphere interactions (Hoegh‐Guldberg 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0039">2014</a>). Despite their regulatory influence on marine biota, salinity and upwelling were also poorly represented as primary stressors in our review of biological responses.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There is wide recognition in the literature of the importance of studying climate‐related responses to multiple stressors and their cumulative or synergistic impacts (e.g., Richardson &amp; Poloczanska, 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0079" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0079">2008</a>; Hoegh‐Guldberg 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0039">2014</a>; Pörtner 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0073" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0073">2014</a>). Nonetheless, few biological response studies considered the effects of more than two stressors, even though several environmental factors may covary in time or space. In addition, several nonclimate factors (e.g., commercial fishing, anthropogenic disturbance, pollution) may interact with and compound the effects of climate stressors. Distinguishing climate impacts from inherent variability and other drivers of change in marine systems can be complicated (Brown 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0004">2011</a>; Doney &amp; Sailley, 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0018">2013</a>), especially in the absence of long‐term records of physical or chemical variability (Hoegh‐Guldberg 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0039">2014</a>). Biological researchers should carefully consider other potential nonclimate factors (Brown 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0004">2011</a>; Doney 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0020">2012</a>). Incorporation of alternative mechanisms can also improve confidence in the attribution of climate impacts on biological responses in marine environments (O'Connor 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0063" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0063">2015</a>). Despite increasing interest in ecosystem‐based management addressing interactions among multiple factors (e.g., Lester 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0051" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0051">2010</a>; Lubchenco &amp; Sutley, 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0054">2010</a>), our findings suggest that, to date, the most highly cited ocean change research does not address multiple interacting stressors.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Range and phenological shifts are among the most commonly cited effects of climate change on global biodiversity (e.g., Parmesan &amp; Yohe, 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0066" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0066">2003</a>; Root 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0082" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0082">2003</a>; Chen 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0008">2011</a>), but our review indicates that these types of biological responses are less frequently cited for the marine environment. Instead, our review of the highly cited contemporary literature and those of others (e.g., Wassmann 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0090" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0090">2011</a>; Poloczanska 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0071" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0071">2013</a>) found that researchers most frequently studied changes in abundance or demography. Studies of marine range and phenological shifts have historically been disregarded and received lesser funding than those in terrestrial systems, the effects of which were amplified because marine ecologists did not always adopt the principles and standardizations used by terrestrial ecologists (Richardson &amp; Poloczanska, 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0079" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0079">2008</a>). Our current understanding of marine range shifts is largely consistent with climate change (e.g., Pinsky 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0070" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0070">2013</a>; Poloczanska 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0071" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0071">2013</a>; Wisz 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0093" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0093">2015</a>), but uncertainty remains regarding which species are shifting and the resulting impacts to ecosystems and communities (Hoegh‐Guldberg 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0039">2014</a>). Strict selection criteria, such as the exclusion of single‐species studies that could impose positive publication bias, can also impact the strength of conclusions about marine range shifts and changes in phenology (Parmesan, 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0065" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0065">2007</a>; Przeslawski 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0074" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0074">2012</a>). Range shifts must also be put into the context of localized climate changes, which may not necessarily be consistent with global patterns and could be multidimensional (e.g., latitude and depth), to consider overall species persistence (Lenoir &amp; Svenning, 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0050" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0050">2015</a>). Although projections for future distributions of marine species exist (e.g., Cheung 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0009">2009</a>; Hazen 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0034">2013</a>; Jones &amp; Cheung, 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0043">2014</a>), long‐term, corroborating observations necessary to detect contemporary shifts in species distribution appear to be rare in marine ecosystems.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Physiological responses were also frequently studied by the papers in our review, often in the laboratory and particularly for benthic communities. Of the 168 articles considering physiological responses, 63% investigated how OA was affecting processes like nutrient uptake or metabolism (phytoplankton, fish, seagrasses, kelp), tissue damage (fish), and calcification (rocky shore invertebrates, corals). Our findings suggest this focus on physiological effects is related to the recent proliferation of research on the effects of OA on marine species, especially calcifying organisms or those reliant on calcifiers (Orr 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0064" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0064">2005</a>; Hoegh‐Guldberg 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0038" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0038">2007</a>; Fabry 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0024">2008</a>; Doney 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0019">2009</a>). Despite this focus on physiological responses, research on how other stressors interact with OA and potentially nonlinear biological responses is still needed (Hoegh‐Guldberg 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0039">2014</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our review of highly cited marine biological responses yielded only one paper (i.e., Lohbeck 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0053">2012</a>) explicitly studying evolutionary implications of ocean change. Changes in gene frequency, via processes such as evolutionary or genetic rescue, are an increasingly recognized response to climate change (Carlson 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0006">2014</a>). The persistence of populations experiencing environmental change has been linked to individual performance regarding phenotypic plasticity, dispersal, and/or adaptive evolution (Merilä &amp; Hendry, 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0061">2014</a>), which can be categorized as acclimatization, colonization, adaptation, or extinction (O'Connor 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0062">2012</a>). We documented population‐level responses corresponding to acclimatization (i.e., phenological, behavioral, diet, and physiological responses), colonization (i.e., distribution shifts), and avoidance of extinction (i.e., via reproductive or demographic responses) in the highly cited marine literature. In contrast, we found a general lack of studies on adaptations (i.e., changes in gene frequency), except for a selection study conducted on multiple generations of a coccolithophore in the laboratory (Lohbeck 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0053">2012</a>). However, we reviewed no studies confirming adaptive evolution in the wild. Attribution of genetic changes to climate forcing requires intensive common‐garden experiments or genetic time series that are rarely done or available, especially for long‐lived or large‐bodied species. The evidence for adaptive evolution in response to climate change, whether marine or terrestrial, is actually quite rare (Gienapp 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0027">2008</a>). Rather, phenotypic plasticity is more apparent than adaptation (Hendry 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0035">2008</a>) and has been investigated for marine species (e.g., Reed 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0075" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0075">2009</a>; Kelly 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0044" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0044">2011a</a>). Ultimately, future marine research could more acutely focus on the adaptive abilities of marine species to cope with changing conditions in order to better understand future population viability.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Social science disciplines also warrant focus in studies of ocean change and are highly relevant to considerations of current and future changes in the marine environment. Although beyond the scope of our review, marine climate change clearly affects social systems and how individuals and communities are responding to ocean change (e.g., McCay 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0059">2011</a>; Pinsky &amp; Fogarty, 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0069" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0069">2012</a>; Lauer 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0049">2013</a>). A growing body of literature is developing to assess the effects of ocean changes on social–ecological systems. Like the other papers reviewed here, this literature varies greatly in terms of temporal and spatial scales and themes addressed. A notable difference between the social–ecological literature and the papers reviewed in this study is that the former tends to focus on projected responses and how ocean change will influence human society in the future (e.g., Cooley &amp; Doney, 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0012">2009</a>; Kelly 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0045" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0045">2011b</a>), whereas the latter tends to address changes that have already occurred. Thus, these social–ecological studies introduce another set of spatial and temporal scales as well as levels of complexity, moving beyond climate change impacts to marine biodiversity but also to human societies associated with the ocean.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="gcb12978-sec-0012" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Advancing ocean change research</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The study of ocean change is a rapidly growing field. We set out to review differences in approaches across marine disciplines that affect the collective interpretation of climate‐associated changes in the ocean. Our review specifically focuses on literature that is most frequently cited to identify research that shapes the current discourse on ocean change. We highlight a rich body of literature that indicates a suite of biological responses accompany several signals of physical and chemical changes occurring in the global ocean. By looking across disciplinary distinctions in sampling approaches for ocean change, we simultaneously emphasize previously identified issues as well as distinguish avenues for future research in both abiotic and biological realms. Our key results suggest that the current discourse on ocean change is sparser for: Southern Hemisphere ocean basins (notably the Indian, South Pacific, and South Atlantic basins), understudied marine taxa (archaea, bacteria, viruses, mangroves and turtles) and oceanographic properties (OA and dissolved oxygen, especially outside of laboratory manipulations), specific physical and chemical stressor effects on biota (dissolved oxygen, salinity, and upwelling), and biological responses of climate‐driven ocean change (evolutionary adaptation). We have shown that it is imperative to consider the statistical limitations associated with relatively short duration, small‐scale, and low‐resolution datasets when inferring broadscale signals of change, but also which datasets are applicable to the life history and population dynamics of target species. We invite future ocean change researchers studying biological systems to consider carefully the temporal (sampling duration and frequency) and spatial scales (study area) required to detect change beyond the level of an individual and establish critical baseline data. While broader‐scale studies are expected to have greater statistical power and confidence, we also urge biological researchers to consider and standardize measures of species generation times and proportion of the home range studied to enable comparable investigations at biologically relevant scales. Identification of disciplinary distinctions, similarities, and areas lacking scientific research with respect to climate‐mediated ocean change should facilitate cohesive research approaches and syntheses of observed impacts on the global ocean as well as more accurate forecasts for the future.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Calls for adaptive, ecosystem‐based, and interdisciplinary approaches in marine sciences are now commonplace (e.g., Edwards 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0023">2010</a>; Lester 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0051" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0051">2010</a>; Lubchenco &amp; Sutley, 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0054">2010</a>), yet best practices for integrative studies have been elusive (Samhouri 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0084" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0084">2013</a>). The comparative cross‐disciplinary approach taken in this paper and our ability to identify the associated effects on the interpretation of climate impacts in marine systems were possible because of an interdisciplinary early‐career training program. Syntheses, such as this one, that consider biotic and abiotic marine disciplines in concert are rare. The institutional structure to train interdisciplinary students in the conduct and design of crosscutting studies remains deficient and requires increased, continuing support (Christie, 
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0010">2011</a>). As noted in Hoegh‐Guldberg 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>. (
   <a rid="gcb12978-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb12978-bib-0039">2014</a>), we have yet to fully understand how single‐species or ocean processes will reorganize ecosystems and communities under climate change. Concerted efforts to improve interdisciplinary education at early‐career stages will provide future researchers with a necessary foundation for integrating and comparing disciplinary differences, and funding of early‐career interdisciplinary training should be continued and strengthened. Our study provides a novel example of how cross‐disciplinary research allowed for a comprehensive assessment of contemporary ocean change research that highlighted new research gaps and recommendations for future comparative research.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
