<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Estuaries are among the most productive of aquatic ecosystems and thus provide an abundant source of food for fishes and other fauna (Blaber &amp; Blaber, 
 <xref rid="ece34236-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1980</xref>; Elliott &amp; Whitfield, 
 <xref rid="ece34236-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>; Whittaker &amp; Likens, 
 <xref rid="ece34236-bib-0082" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1975</xref>). They are also widely used for recreational purposes such as fishing and boating. During recent decades, the hydrological characteristics of these important systems (and coastal seas) have become modified in many parts of the world as a result of changes in rainfall and other effects of climate change (Altieri &amp; Gedan, 
 <xref rid="ece34236-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Hewitt, Ellis, &amp; Thrush, 
 <xref rid="ece34236-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). For example, marked reductions in precipitation have led to declines in discharge and thus the effectiveness of flushing (Altieri &amp; Gedan, 
 <xref rid="ece34236-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Tweedley, Warwick, &amp; Potter, 
 <xref rid="ece34236-bib-0076" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). Such declines, in turn, increase residence time and thus the retention of nutrients and organic material and, consequently, increases in primary productivity, which can ultimately lead to marked eutrophication and the development of oxygen‐depleted “dead” zones (Diaz &amp; Rosenberg, 
 <xref rid="ece34236-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>; Thronson &amp; Quigg, 
 <xref rid="ece34236-bib-0502" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>). This problem is increasing in estuaries throughout the world (Paerl, Hall, Peierls, &amp; Rossignol, 
 <xref rid="ece34236-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). As estuaries are often surrounded by areas of agricultural, industrial and urban developments and therefore frequently receive substantial amounts of nutrients and organic material through runoff from surrounding land and by direct input, these systems are particularly prone to developing these detrimental effects. The effects of climate change on the discharges into estuaries, and thus of their flushing and the prevalence of oxygen‐depleted dead zones, have sometimes been exacerbated by the construction of structures, such as dams and reservoirs, for diverting river flow for agriculture, industry and/or human water usage (Mehran et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34236-bib-0048" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>; Stewardson et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34236-bib-0072" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>).
</p>
