<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="ack" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <div class="title">Acknowledgments</div>
 <p>We thank the Carlini (former Jubany)–Dallmann staff for their support, especially to our dive companions J. Kowalke, S. Künhe, A. Fernández, O. Rillos, M. Maglianesi, L. N. Argañaraz, and D. Maione. We are grateful to C. Richter, C. Smith, M. Fernández, C. Held, and P. K. Dayton for helpful comments that improved the manuscript. We also thank G. Tossonoto, O. González, A. Ulrich, E. Ruiz, and C. Haas for providing the bathymetry of Potter Cove. Finally, R.S. is especially grateful to L. A. Spinetta, C. García. M. Sosa, I. Solari, N. K. C. Fernández, and E. Carlotto for their ideas. 
  <span class="bold">Funding:</span> Logistic and financial support was provided by Instituto Antártico Argentino, Alfred Wegener Institut, CONICET, FONCyT (Fondo para la Investigación Científica y Tecnológica), SECyT-UNC (Secretaría de Ciencia y Tecnología–UNC), DFG (Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft), and EU (European Union) via grants PICTO-DNA N° 119 and 36323, DFG project no. BR 775/25-1, IMCOAST (Impact of climate induced glacial melting on marine coastal systems in the Western Antarctic peninsula region), ECLIPSE (Effects of Climate change in Polar Shallow benthic Ecosystems), and IMCONet [FP7 IRSES (International Research Staff Exchange Scheme), action no. 319718]. 
  <span class="bold">Author contributions:</span> R.S. designed the project, participated in the field sampling, carried out analyses, and wrote the original manuscript. C.L., L.T., F.M., P.M., I.S., D.K.A.B., and D.A. were major contributors, especially in the field sampling, photo and data analyses, development of conceptual and mathematical models (L.T. and F.M.), MAR
  <sub>BS</sub> analysis (P.M.), and writing. N.S., S.T., M.T., and N.Z. were large contributors in the field work and photo analysis, and D.A. is also responsible for the IMCONet frame for the development of this project. All authors discussed the manuscript. 
  <span class="bold">Competing interests:</span> The authors declare that they have no competing interests. 
  <span class="bold">Data and materials availability:</span> All data needed to evaluate the conclusions in the paper are present in the paper and/or the Supplementary Materials. Additional data related to this paper may be requested from the authors at 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pangaea.de" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.pangaea.de</span>; contact R.S. (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://rsahade@efn.uncor.edu" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">rsahade@efn.uncor.edu</span>).
 </p>
</div>
