<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece31848-sec-0008" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Field simulations</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Niche Mapper field simulations were conducted using a diurnally active, ellipsoidal (2.25 a:b ratio) pika and a wind velocity at pika height (9 cm) varying diurnally from 0.1 to 4.0 m/s. Hair lengths and depths were scaled according to the total mass of the modeled animal, for example, a 120 g pika had 20% shorter and shallower hair than a 150 g pika. Climate and weather data were retrieved from the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration website (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.noaa.gov" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.noaa.gov</span>) for Kalispell International Airport ([KIA] elevation 961 m), which is located ~30 km from Glacier National Park. When appropriate, we used a lapse rate of −8°C/km to derive mean monthly maximum and minimum temperatures (see below). In addition, we conducted sensitivity analyses to test Niche Mapper's robustness to input variable uncertainty (see Tables S1 and S4) and also compared its calculated above‐ and below‐talus temperatures to those we measured in the field. For simulations used as direct comparisons to field observations, we used site‐specific parameters, such as aspects and elevations of those sites, along with adjusted KIA temperatures from those days. For all other simulations, we used an eastern aspect, a 15° slope, GNP‐relevant elevations of 1500–2500 m, and long‐term (1981–2010) monthly averages from KIA.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We simulated a conservative warming scenario for 2100 of +5.0°C for all elevations (McWethy et al. 
  <a rid="ece31848-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0034">2010</a>). We used daily temperature ranges of 20°C, typical for summer months in GNP. The lowest temperature range (−10–10°C) is typical for June or September above 2500 m elevation. July and August temperature ranges at the lowest elevations in GNP (1500 m) are typically 4–22°C. We interpreted the ratio of the field metabolic rate over the BMR (FMR/BMR) to determine when pikas could be active above the talus. If an FMR/BMR ratio below 1.5 was required to remain below the animal's upper critical temperature, activity would probably be infeasible (Nagy 
  <a rid="ece31848-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0041">1987</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
