<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par5">Here we investigate the effects of SLR and TC climatology change on future flood hazards along the entire US Atlantic and Gulf Coasts. To do so, we apply the climatological–hydrodynamic approach
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>
 </sup> at the basin scale. Specifically, we use a statistical/deterministic hurricane model
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>
 </sup> to generate large numbers of synthetic TCs under historical (1980–2005) and future projected (2070–2095) climate conditions for the Atlantic basin. We apply a widely used hydrodynamic model
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>
 </sup> with a recently developed basin scale computational mesh
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>
 </sup> to simulate the storm tides (the combination of storm surge and astronomical tide) induced by these synthetic TCs for the US Atlantic and Gulf Coasts. Then we estimate the historical and future return periods of flood heights, defined as the combination of storm tide and SLR (based on a probabilistic projection
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>
 </sup>), for each county along the US Atlantic and Gulf Coasts. In particular, we examine the spatial variation of the flood return levels and relative impacts of SLR and TC climatology change along the US Atlantic and Gulf Coasts. We find that, under the compound effects of SLR and TC climatology change, the historical 100-year flood level would occur annually in New England and mid-Atlantic regions and every 1–30 years in southeast Atlantic and Gulf of Mexico regions in the late 21st century. The relative effect of TC climatology change increases continuously from New England, mid-Atlantic, southeast Atlantic, to the Gulf of Mexico, and the effect of TC climatology change is likely to be larger than the effect of SLR for over 40% of coastal counties in the Gulf of Mexico.
</p>
