<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ozone and stratospheric response of large tropical volcanic eruptions</div>
 <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to evaluate the effect that large Plinian eruptions have on the atmosphere and environment we have chosen the volatile mass of an average CAVA eruption as model input excluding the extremely large Los Chocoyos eruption
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span> (see Methods). Since the average consists of 28 eruptions of variable compositional signals (basaltic andesite to rhyolite)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span> along an entire arc and a long-lasting time interval (200 ka) we consider it representative for the whole CAVA and also for large sulfur- and halogen-rich eruptions globally
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span> (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>, Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>). We inject 10% of the erupted halogen mass (chlorine and bromine) into the stratosphere, a compromise given the large range and high uncertainties of injection efficiency estimates based on volcanic halogen observations in the UTLS
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>
  </span> and recent volcanic plume modelling
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>
  </span>. We run three ensemble simulations, each with eight members and 12-years duration, one with volcanic halogen injections (
  <span class="bold">Halog</span>); one with volcanic sulfuric acid aerosol (surface area density, 
  <span class="bold">SAD</span>); and one with both forcings applied (
  <span class="bold">Halog + SAD</span>). The initial conditions for the ensemble members were provided by branching from different years of the control simulation (additional details in Methods). The control simulation has constant 1850 forcings with duration of 30 years (
  <span class="bold">Ctr</span>). In addition, we performed a sensitivity simulation using 1% halogen injection efficiency and the same aerosol forcing (
  <span class="bold">1%Halog + SAD</span>). Table 
  <a rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" href="#Tab2">2</a> gives a summary of the parameters used in the experimental setups.
  <div id="Tab2" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Summary of model simulations.</p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th>Volcanic forcing experiment</th>
      <th>Sulfur aerosol forcing</th>
      <th>Cl injection (Mt)</th>
      <th>Br injection (kt)</th>
      <th>Halogen injection location</th>
      <th>Halogen Injection level</th>
      <th>Injection date</th>
      <th>Simulation length</th>
      <th>No. ensemble members</th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td>Control (Ctr)</td>
      <td>—</td>
      <td>—</td>
      <td>—</td>
      <td>—</td>
      <td>—</td>
      <td>—</td>
      <td>30 years</td>
      <td>1</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Halog</td>
      <td>—</td>
      <td>2.93</td>
      <td>9.5</td>
      <td>14°N, 89°W</td>
      <td>29.7 hPa</td>
      <td rowspan="5">January 1</td>
      <td rowspan="3">12 years</td>
      <td rowspan="3">8</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>SAD</td>
      <td>Prescribed El Chichón
       <span class="sup">
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91" href="#CR91">91</a>
       </span>
      </td>
      <td>—</td>
      <td>—</td>
      <td>—</td>
      <td>—</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Halog + SAD</td>
      <td>Prescribed El Chichón
       <span class="sup">
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91" href="#CR91">91</a>
       </span>
      </td>
      <td>2.93</td>
      <td>9.5</td>
      <td>14°N, 89°W</td>
      <td>29.7 hPa</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>1%Halog + SAD</td>
      <td>Prescribed El Chichón
       <span class="sup">
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91" href="#CR91">91</a>
       </span>
      </td>
      <td>0.293</td>
      <td>0.95</td>
      <td>14°N, 89°W</td>
      <td>29.7 hPa</td>
      <td>8 years</td>
      <td>1</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>HighHalogLev + SAD</td>
      <td>Prescribed El Chichón
       <span class="sup">
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91" href="#CR91">91</a>
       </span>
      </td>
      <td>Elevated surface emissions</td>
      <td>Elevated surface emissions</td>
      <td>—</td>
      <td>—</td>
      <td>10 years</td>
      <td>1</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In all simulations, background total stratospheric chlorine and bromine values are 0.47 ppbv and 5.68 ppt, respectively, originating from constant surface emissions of CH
  <sub>3</sub>Cl and CH
  <sub>3</sub>Br. These background values are consistent with previously reported pre-industrial background halogen levels
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>
  </span>. The stratospheric Br values in our simulations may be too low (3–5 ppt) due to a lack of natural oceanic emissions of bromine compounds (Dorf 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">59</a>
  </span> and updates), though there may be large uncertainties in the natural contribution of oceanic halogen emissions due to atmospheric and oceanic circulation changes (i.e., surface wind and sea surface temperature
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">60</a>
  </span>) in a pre-industrial atmosphere. We addressed this issue through a sensitivity simulation applying increased background levels of 1.12 ppbv Cl and 16.99 pptv Br and the SAD volcanic forcing scenario (
  <span class="bold">HighHalogLev + SAD</span>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The 
  <span class="bold">Halog + SAD</span> simulations show that a stratospheric injection of volcanic chlorine and bromine leads to a global increase of the total halogen concentrations in the middle atmosphere lasting more than 7 years (Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S1</a>). Partitioning between reactive (ClO
  <sub>x</sub> and BrO
  <sub>x</sub>) and non-reactive compounds (HCl, HBr, ClONO
  <sub>2</sub>, BrONO
  <sub>2</sub>) varies with a larger proportion of Br in the form of reactive compounds (not shown). Global mean stratospheric concentrations of total Cl and Br during the first post-eruption year are 5.27 ppbv (&gt;1000% increase) and 8.76 pptv (50% increase), respectively (Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S2</a>). Present-day values in 2012 have reached about ~3.3 ppbv total Cl and ~20 pptv total Br
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">61</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In response to the increase in halogen and sulfuric acid aerosol concentrations, 
  <span class="bold">Halog + SAD</span> globally averaged ozone levels drop to a minimum below 240 DU, a 20% decrease in global mean ozone column, during the first 18 months after the eruption (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2a</a>). Global ozone stays significantly below climatological levels for 10 years. The 
  <span class="bold">Halog</span> ensemble shows a smaller ozone response than 
  <span class="bold">Halog + SAD</span>. The difference between the two scenarios becomes markedly smaller after the first 3 years, when the SAD forcing has decayed. In the 
  <span class="bold">SAD</span> experiment the global ozone response shows a small increase, caused by increased heterogeneous chemistry, which reduces the concentrations of ozone-destroying NO
  <sub>x</sub>
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
  </span>, and by radiative-dynamical effects
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" href="#CR62">62</a>
  </span>.
  <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Column ozone response in [DU] for the different forcing experiments (see Table 
     <a rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" href="#Tab2">2</a>). Shown are the first 12 years after the eruption. Ensemble means (solid lines) and 2σ (shading). (
     <span class="bold">a</span>) Global; (
     <span class="bold">b</span>) Tropics; (
     <span class="bold">c</span>) Arctic; (
     <span class="bold">d</span>) Antarctic.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_45630_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e1295" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">These results are sensitive to the halogen injection efficiency. In the 
  <span class="bold">1%Halog + SAD</span> sensitivity simulation the mean increase of total Cl and Br over the first post-eruption year is 213% and 6% (Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S2</a>). This translates to a small decrease in column ozone (~5%), only slightly outside the natural variability of the control run (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>). In the 
  <span class="bold">HighHalogLev + SAD</span> sensitivity, increasing the background halogen concentration leads to lower global ozone levels as expected, while there is no clear ozone response to the SAD forcing (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>). In the following, we will focus on the ensemble mean of the 
  <span class="bold">Halog + SAD</span> runs when discussing regional responses and surface impacts.
 </p>
 <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The atmospheric response to the CAVA eruptions follows a distinct spatio-temporal evolution (Figs 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a> and 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>). The immediate response is in the tropics and middle latitudes on the NH, with column ozone dropping below 220 DU (with minimum below 200 DU) during the first two years. In the tropics, this corresponds to 10–20% ozone depletion, which is far outside the small tropical natural ozone variability. In the first autumn after the eruption, the Arctic minimum column ozone value of 200 DU occurs, while the maximum decline (45%, &gt;200 DU) takes place in the following spring. Analyzing the maximum spring depletion events of the post-eruption years 2 and 3 reveals average ozone decrease of more than 120 DU (20%) over the polar cap, reaching as far south as 50° N over certain regions (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>). In the Antarctic, a strong response is simulated during austral spring starting in the 3rd simulation year (Figs 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a> and 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>). Depletions below 220 DU occur over large parts of the Antarctic continent, similar to a present-day ozone hole (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>). This phenomenon appears during simulation years 3–6 with the minimum column ozone below 100 DU and maximum ozone hole area extent in October of simulation year 4 (not shown).
  <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Ensemble mean zonal mean ozone response to: (
     <span class="bold">a</span>) Climatological annual cycle of the column ozone from the control run. (
     <span class="bold">b</span>) Column ozone and (
     <span class="bold">c</span>) column ozone anomalies over the first 12 years after the eruption in the Halog + SAD forcing experiment. The black contour in (
     <span class="bold">b</span>,
     <span class="bold">c</span>) marks the region where column ozone drops below 220 DU which is the definition of the Antarctic ozone hole.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_45630_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e1361" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <div id="Fig4" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Ensemble mean Arctic (
     <span class="bold">a</span>,
     <span class="bold">b</span>) and Tropical (c-d) ozone response to the Halog + SAD forcing experiment. (
     <span class="bold">a</span>) April climatological column ozone. (
     <span class="bold">b</span>) Column ozone anomalies averaged over April of post-eruption years 2–3. (
     <span class="bold">c</span>) Annual mean climatological ozone. (
     <span class="bold">d</span>) Anomalies averaged over post-eruption year 1 and 2.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_45630_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e1389" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <div id="Fig5" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 5</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Antarctic ozone response to the Halog + SAD forcing experiment. (
     <span class="bold">a</span>) Antarctic climatological ozone for October. (
     <span class="bold">b</span>) Ensemble mean ozone anomalies for October, averaged over post-eruption years 3–6. (
     <span class="bold">c</span>) Annual Antarctic minimum column ozone for each ensemble member of the Halog + SAD experiment in the first 12 years after the eruption.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_45630_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e1407" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There is a large spread in the minimum Antarctic column ozone values between the model ensemble members, which corresponds to the transport of chlorine and bromine reservoir compounds to the Southern Hemisphere (SH) during the first post-eruption year (Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S3</a>). The intra-ensemble spread of the transport to the SH is large even though the models’ Quasi Biennial Oscillation is fixed in the easterly phase and sea surface temperatures are held constant, i.e., there is no El Niño Southern Oscillation variability. By post-eruption year 4 this translates into an intra-ensemble spread of the average SH concentration of stratospheric halogen of more than a factor of 2 between the lowest and highest ensemble members (Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S3c</a>). During Antarctic ozone depletion, heterogeneous chemistry on Polar Stratospheric Clouds (PSCs) is an important reaction for halogen radicals. The temporal evolution of PSC formation, halogen activation and subsequent denitrification of the Antarctic stratosphere closely follows observed present day ozone depletion (not shown). In the Arctic, in contrast, PSC formation is almost completely suppressed during post-eruption year 1, only re-emerging the following winter.
 </p>
 <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Profiles of global mean temperature anomalies averaged over the first six post-eruption years indicate that the stratospheric response to the 
  <span class="bold">Halog + SAD</span> forcing is distinct cooling at two layers (60 and 1 hPa) in the lower and upper stratosphere (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6</a>). (Lower stratosphere: 100–30 hPa (~16 to 24 km altitude); Upper stratosphere: 5–1 hPa (~35–50 km altitude)). Initially, the cooling is strongest in the lower stratosphere around 30 hPa (not shown). After simulation year 2 the maximum cooling of more than 3 K occurs in the upper stratosphere. The model experiments reveal that the ozone depletion by Cl and Br cools the stratosphere at these two distinct layers (60 hPa and 1–2 hPa) while in contrast the SAD enhancement causes warming in the lower stratosphere (around 50 hPa). As a consequence, the stratospheric cooling is most pronounced in the Halog experiment (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6</a>). Cooling of the lower stratosphere is much more pronounced in the NH and in the first two years post eruption, while the upper stratosphere cools globally with peak cooling in the third year after eruption.
  <div id="Fig6" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 6</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Global mean profiles averaged over post-eruption years 1–6 for the three forcing experiments. (
     <span class="bold">a</span>) Ozone concentration anomalies. (
     <span class="bold">b</span>) Temperature anomalies. Short wave (
     <span class="bold">c</span>) and long wave (
     <span class="bold">d</span>) heating rate anomalies.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_45630_Fig6_HTML" id="d29e1447" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The zonal wind response of WACCM to the combined volcanic forcing of the first post-eruption NH winter (DJF (December, January, February)) is a weakening of the westerly wind in the stratosphere (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig7">7a</a>) as the temperature gradient between the tropics and the NH high latitude is reduced (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig7">7b</a>). Ozone depletion in the tropical stratosphere causes reduced shortwave warming while depletion in the polar night causes warming by reducing the longwave cooling (not shown). The changes in zonal wind and temperature are significant at the 95% confidence level. The corresponding response for a typical sulfur-rich tropical eruption is a strengthening of the stratospheric westerlies of the first winter, caused by an increased meridional temperature gradient
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">63</a>
  </span>. Due to enhanced ozone depletion and strengthening of the polar vortex in Arctic spring (Figs 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a> and 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>), NH summer (JJA (June, July, August)) of post-eruption years 1–3 reveal positive zonal wind anomalies all the way to the surface, causing a positive phase of the Northern Annular Mode (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig7">7c,d</a>). (The Annular Modes are atmospheric circulation patterns with lower than normal pressures over the polar region and stronger surrounding westerly winds along ~60°)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" href="#CR64">64</a>
  </span>.
  <div id="Fig7" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 7</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Ensemble mean zonal wind and temperature response to the Halog + SAD forcing experiment during: (
     <span class="bold">a</span>,
     <span class="bold">b</span>) First post-eruption NH winter (DJF). (
     <span class="bold">c</span>,
     <span class="bold">d</span>) Averaged over NH summer of post-eruption years 1–3. (
     <span class="bold">e</span>,
     <span class="bold">f</span>) Averaged over SH spring (SON) of post-eruption year 3–6. (
     <span class="bold">g</span>,
     <span class="bold">h</span>) Averaged over SH summer (DJF) of post-eruption years 3–6. Gray contours represents the Control climatology of zonal wind (temperature) with intervals of 15 m/s (K). Stipling indicates changes at the 95% confidence level.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_45630_Fig7_HTML" id="d29e1507" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The SH winter (JJA) in post-eruption years 1–3 shows the same pattern as for the first NH winter, with a weakened polar vortex (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig7">7c,d</a>). During the averaged Antarctic ozone hole events of the post-eruption years 3–6 (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>), the polar vortex is strengthened from the upper mesosphere to the stratosphere during austral spring (SON (September, October, November)) (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig7">7e,f</a>) and migrating downwards to the lower stratosphere during DJF (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig7">7g,h</a>). During both seasons, SON and DJF, the significant increase in westerly wind reaches all the way down to the surface, leading to a positive phase of the Southern Annular Mode, similar as observed for present-day ozone hole conditions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" href="#CR65">65</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The atmospheric response in WACCM to our sulfur- and halogen-rich eruption deviates markedly from the well-known response to sulfur-rich, but halogen-poor eruptions like Pinatubo. In general, tropical sulfur-rich Plinian eruptions heat the tropical stratosphere and cool the polar stratosphere leading to an increase in the equator-pole temperature gradient resulting in increased strength of the polar vortices, particularly during the first post-eruption winter of the NH
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">63</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">66</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" href="#CR67">67</a>
  </span>. Our simulations highlight that with strong sulfur and halogen injections, the atmospheric circulation pattern is reversed in the first post eruption NH winter. The ozone depletion causes cooling of the tropical stratosphere and a reduced meridional temperature gradient resulting in a weaker and warmer polar vortex and strong ozone loss compared to the following 2
  <span class="sup">nd</span> and 3
  <span class="sup">rd</span> winters.
 </p>
</sec>
