<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Africa is epitomised as the most vulnerable continent to climate changes (Bwalya 
 <xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>; Masipa 
 <xref rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2017</xref>). The continent will experience increased water stress, decrease in yields and increased food insecurity and malnutrition because of climate change (IPCC 
 <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>). The African continent is most vulnerable to climate change and variability, increasing the hardships experienced by vulnerable communities (O’Brien et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2008</xref>; Scholtz 
 <xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>). By 2020, climate change will have impacted the lives and livelihoods of approximately 250 million people in Africa (Scholtz 
 <xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>). Extreme weather conditions such as droughts, floods and tropical storms are expected to increase in frequency and intensity across the continent (IPCC 
 <xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>). The continent will be affected because of its global position, its vulnerable populations and its poor land-use practices. A study in South Africa shows a 23% reduction in gross domestic product (GDP) as a result of climate change with an estimated 1.6% annual loss (Mthembu &amp; Zwane 
 <xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2017</xref>). South Africa will experience a 0.13 °C rise in day temperatures with dry land and smallholder farmers being mostly affected and reduction of rainfall will be extensive, ranging from 5% to 10%. Mashizha et al. (
 <xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2017b</xref>) highlight that food production assessment indicates that domestic food production has already declined by 10% in several of the sub-Saharan countries. Climate change scenarios across multiple general circulation models show increases in Zimbabwe’s average mean temperature. Predictions show that the mean daily temperature will rise by 3 °C – 5 °C throughout the country and the mean annual temperature will rise by 2 °C – 4 °C (Mashizha et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2017a</xref>). However, it is important to understand that many of Africa’s problems result from factors other than climate change (Brazier 
 <xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>). Population growth, urbanisation, agricultural growth and land-use change present the effects; hence, developing countries need to address resource management issues urgently. Africa will feel the impact more because of slow technological changes within the continent and its economies depend more on agriculture (Mathews 
 <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>; Mathews, Kruger &amp; Wentink 
 <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2018</xref>). Climate change impact studies, although they are still uncertain on the frequency and severity of adverse weather events, have shown that the effects are significant for low-input farming systems, such as subsistence farming in marginal areas and because of socio-economic, demographic and policy trends have the least capacity to adapt to changing climatic conditions (Mutekwa 
 <xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>). Climate change is a serious threat to development and poverty reduction efforts in Africa (Mugambiwa &amp; Dzomonda 
 <xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2018</xref>; Mugambiwa &amp; Tirivangasi 
 <xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2017</xref>). The continent is facing various health risks associated with climate change and threaten to reverse development efforts and subject the continent to long-term poverty. With a temperature increase of 3 °C alongside the global warming anomaly, about 250–550 million people may be at risk of hunger with more than half of these people concentrated in Africa (Kangalawe &amp; Lyimo 
 <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>).Vulnerability of the African continent to climate change is a function of many factors including long-term poverty, illiteracy, political and ethnic conflicts, poor governance, lack of skills, weak technical institutions, poor and probably limited infrastructure and poor technological development (Ndaki 
 <xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>). Thus, Zimbabwe faces the risks associated with climate change and the country is at a very high level in terms of vulnerability.
</p>
