<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Monthly and annual means were calculated to describe the seasonal and long-term trends of the meteorological and hydrographic variables in the PL system. 3.4-ENSO index anomalies were calculated and divided into La Niña (&lt;0) and El Niño (&gt;0) years for better visualization. In a meteorological context, anomalies assess the deviation in observed values of certain variables in relation to its historical or climatological means. Therefore, we estimated annual anomalies of air temperature and rainfall by the using the following equation: α
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">i</italic>
 </sub> = 
 <italic class="italic">x</italic>
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">i</italic>
 </sub> - 
 <inline-formula class="inline-formula">
  <math id="M1" class="math">
   <msub class="msub">
    <mrow class="mrow">
     <mover accent="true" class="mover">
      <mrow class="mrow">
       <mi class="mi">x</mi>
      </mrow>
      <mo class="mo">¯</mo>
     </mover>
    </mrow>
    <mrow class="mrow">
     <mi class="mi">i</mi>
    </mrow>
   </msub>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> where α corresponds to the anomaly of a certain variable (air temperature or rainfall), 
 <italic class="italic">i</italic> corresponds to a particular year, 
 <italic class="italic">x</italic> is the meteorological variable of a 
 <italic class="italic">i</italic> year 
 <inline-formula class="inline-formula">
  <math id="M2" class="math">
   <mover accent="false" class="mover">
    <mrow class="mrow">
     <mi class="mi">x</mi>
    </mrow>
    <mo accent="true" class="mo">¯</mo>
   </mover>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> and is the mean value of that variable taking into account the whole period of time. The seasonal and interannual variability in air temperature, rainfall, and freshwater discharge were analyzed by plotting respective trend lines. Published data (Yunes et al., 
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1998a</xref>; Odebrecht et al., 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2005</xref>; Rosa and Garcia, 
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>) and recent estimates of cyanobacterial abundance/biomass were overlaid as labels on the rainfall anomaly graph. Recent cyanobacteria abundance data were shown as minimum and maximum values of cell mL
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>.
</p>
