<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The behavior of cormorants (social attraction according to their geographical origin, fidelity to their wintering site, competition between sexes and ages, decreasing fear of humans…cf. Marion, 
 <xref rid="ece34348-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1994</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ece34348-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1995</xref>; Reymond &amp; Zuchuat, 
 <xref rid="ece34348-bib-0071" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1995</xref>; Van Eerden &amp; Munsterman, 
 <xref rid="ece34348-bib-0078" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1995</xref>) also played an important role in their strategies of habitat use. First (until 1989), the mean size of night roosts strongly increased, then the situation reversed (Figure 
 <xref rid="ece34348-fig-0011" ref-type="fig" class="xref">11</xref>), while the increasing rate of the number of roosts became higher than the rate of the number of cormorants (until 2011). This “atomization strategy” (decrease of the biggest roosts, Figure 
 <xref rid="ece34348-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref>) followed the same pattern as the numbers of breeding grey heron colonies in France after the species was first protected in 1975 (Marion, 
 <xref rid="ece34348-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1997b</xref>; Marion &amp; Marion, 
 <xref rid="ece34348-bib-0056" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1987</xref>; Marion, Van Vessem, &amp; Ulenaers, 
 <xref rid="ece34348-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2000</xref>). When wintering cormorants (or breeding grey heron) occupied France again once they were legally protected, safety still outweighed for a time all the other factors for the priority choice of big pre‐existing roosts. These roosts played the role of a safety index as compared to creating new but potentially unsafe roosts in vacant areas. When the birds became progressively less afraid of humans and used less safety sites, the biggest roosts were gradually fragmented into many smaller and smaller roosts. Smaller roosts were better adapted to the distribution of feeding resources, with optimized costs of feeding trips. This strategy allowed for a strong increase in the wintering or breeding populations (Marion, 
 <xref rid="ece34348-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1997a</xref>,
 <xref rid="ece34348-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" class="xref">b</xref>; Marion &amp; Marion, 
 <xref rid="ece34348-bib-0056" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1987</xref>). Paradoxically, the protection of these species caused their biggest roosts or colonies initially used as refuges to decrease.
</p>
