<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Woodlice generally are considered as having restricted dispersal abilities. Many species may hardly be able to expand their distribution ranges but some have been rather successful in colonising new territories. At the same time, distribution patterns of isopods reflect ecological tolerance at a macroecological scale. The activity radius of an individual is species specific, depending on certain ecomorphological, and life history characters, humidity requirements. 
 <italic>
  <named-content content-type="taxon-name">
   <named-content content-type="genus">Hemilepistus</named-content>
   <named-content content-type="species">reaumurii</named-content>
  </named-content>
 </italic>, for example, was found to cover several meters per day while foraging (
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr">Hoffmann 1984</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr">1989</xref>) whilst other species, mostly small-sized, soil-dwelling ‘creepers’ (
 <xref rid="B103" ref-type="bibr">Schmalfuss 1984</xref>), move only within a few centimeters. On the other side, locomotion is essential to find food, mate, and shelter or to escape predators. In a changing environment, species are forced either to go extinct under unfavorable conditions or to migrate, following the shift of favorable environmental conditions (diffusion-type dispersal). This may have happened repeatedly in the past, e.g., during the succession of glacial and interglacial periods in the Pleistocene. In North America, the species-rich southern parts could have acted as refugia and sources for northward dispersal (
 <xref rid="B141" ref-type="bibr">Van Name 1936</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr">Jass and Klausmeier 2000</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>). In addition, several species were introduced from Europe, arriving in soil ballast carried by ship mainly during the 19
 <sup>th</sup> century (
 <xref rid="B80" ref-type="bibr">Lindroth 1957</xref>), which is a jump-dispersal followed by local dispersion. 
 <xref rid="B80" ref-type="bibr">Lindroth (1957)</xref> examined critically the routes of introduction of European fauna into North America, both in recent times and in the late Pleistocene. A good example is the documented historical expansion of the, originally Mediterranean but now cosmopolitan, species 
 <italic>
  <named-content content-type="taxon-name">
   <named-content content-type="genus">Armadillidium</named-content>
   <named-content content-type="species">vulgare</named-content>
  </named-content>
 </italic> (Fig. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">8</xref>). Dispersal ability is the result of complex features and life-history processes. In fact, the spread of 
 <italic>
  <named-content content-type="taxon-name">
   <named-content content-type="genus">A.</named-content>
   <named-content content-type="species">vulgare</named-content>
  </named-content>
 </italic> in California grassland (
 <xref rid="B93" ref-type="bibr">Paris 1963</xref>) and in North America in general (
 <xref rid="B32" ref-type="bibr">Garthwaite et al. 1995</xref>) is a real ‘success story’. Terrestrial isopods are continuously introduced in the present time. Worldwide trade of living plants, establishing botanic gardens, parks with exotic trees and so on give opportunities to introduce and spread new, mainly tropical, subtropical, or Mediterranean soil-dwelling species all around the globe (Korsós et al. 2002, 
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr">Hornung and Szlavecz 2003</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr">Hornung et al. 2005</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B143" ref-type="bibr">Vilisics and Hornung 2009</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr">Gregory 2014</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr">2015</xref>). In some documented cases isopod swarming was observed in different species and geographical regions. This behaviour implies occasional mass occurrence and migration of great numbers of individuals of the same. The explanation is still not clear, but should be related to demographic factors (
 <xref rid="B153" ref-type="bibr">Warburg et al. 1984</xref>). Similar phenomena occur often also in 
 <named-content content-type="taxon-name">
  <named-content content-type="subphylum">Myriapoda</named-content>
 </named-content> (
 <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr">Korsós 1998</xref>).
</p>
