<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName archivearticle3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Ecol Evol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Ecol Evol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.1002/(ISSN)2045-7758</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ECE3</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Ecology and Evolution</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-7758</issn><publisher><publisher-name>John Wiley and Sons Inc.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Hoboken</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4717337</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ece3.1848</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ECE31848</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Modeling behavioral thermoregulation in a climate change sentinel</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="left-running-head">L. Moyer&#x02010;Horner <italic>et&#x000a0;al</italic>.</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="ece31848-cr-0001" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Moyer&#x02010;Horner</surname><given-names>Lucas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="ece31848-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="ece31848-aff-0002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="ece31848-cr-0002" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mathewson</surname><given-names>Paul D.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="ece31848-aff-0002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="ece31848-cr-0003" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>Gavin M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="ece31848-aff-0003">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="ece31848-cr-0004" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kearney</surname><given-names>Michael R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="ece31848-aff-0004">
<sup>4</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="ece31848-cr-0005" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>Warren P.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="ece31848-aff-0002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="ece31848-aff-0001"><label><sup>1</sup></label><named-content content-type="organisation-division">Department of Biology</named-content><institution>University of Utah</institution><named-content content-type="city">Salt Lake City</named-content><named-content content-type="country-part">Utah</named-content></aff><aff id="ece31848-aff-0002"><label><sup>2</sup></label><named-content content-type="organisation-division">Department of Zoology</named-content><institution>University of Wisconsin&#x02010;Madison</institution><named-content content-type="city">Madison</named-content><named-content content-type="country-part">Wisconsin</named-content></aff><aff id="ece31848-aff-0003"><label><sup>3</sup></label><named-content content-type="organisation-division">Department of Forest &#x00026; Wildlife Ecology</named-content><institution>University of Wisconsin&#x02010;Madison</institution><named-content content-type="city">Madison</named-content><named-content content-type="country-part">Wisconsin</named-content></aff><aff id="ece31848-aff-0004"><label><sup>4</sup></label><named-content content-type="organisation-division">Department of Zoology</named-content><institution>The University of Melbourne</institution><named-content content-type="city">Melbourne</named-content><named-content content-type="country-part">Victoria</named-content><country country="AU">Australia</country></aff><author-notes><corresp id="correspondenceTo"><label>*</label><bold>Correspondence</bold><break/>Lucas Moyer&#x02010;Horner, Department of Biology, University of Utah, Salt Lake City, UT.<break/>Tel: 801&#x02010;581&#x02010;3861<break/> Fax: 801&#x02010;581&#x02010; 4668<break/>E&#x02010;mail: <email>lucas.m.horner@utah.edu</email><break/></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>24</day><month>11</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>12</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>5</volume><issue>24</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ece3.2015.5.issue-24</issue-id><fpage>5810</fpage><lpage>5822</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>7</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>20</day><month>10</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>10</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><!--<copyright-statement content-type="issue-copyright"> &#x000a9; 2015 Published by John Wiley & Sons Ltd. <copyright-statement>--><copyright-statement content-type="article-copyright">&#x000a9; 2015 The Authors. <italic>Ecology and Evolution</italic> published by John Wiley &#x00026; Sons Ltd.</copyright-statement><license license-type="creativeCommonsBy"><license-p>This is an open access article under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution</ext-link> License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="file:ECE3-5-5810.pdf"/><abstract abstract-type="main" id="ece31848-abs-0001"><title>Abstract</title><p>When possible, many species will shift in elevation or latitude in response to rising temperatures. However, before such shifts occur, individuals will first tolerate environmental change and then modify their behavior to maintain heat balance. Behavioral thermoregulation allows animals a range of climatic tolerances and makes predicting geographic responses under future warming scenarios challenging. Because behavioral modification may reduce an individual's fecundity by, for example, limiting foraging time and thus caloric intake, we must consider the range of behavioral options available for thermoregulation to accurately predict climate change impacts on individual species. To date, few studies have identified mechanistic links between an organism's daily activities and the need to thermoregulate. We used a biophysical model, Niche Mapper, to mechanistically model microclimate conditions and thermoregulatory behavior for a temperature&#x02010;sensitive mammal, the American pika (<italic>Ochotona princeps</italic>). Niche Mapper accurately simulated microclimate conditions, as well as empirical metabolic chamber data for a range of fur properties, animal sizes, and environmental parameters. Niche Mapper predicted pikas would be behaviorally constrained because of the need to thermoregulate during the hottest times of the day. We also showed that pikas at low elevations could receive energetic benefits by being smaller in size and maintaining summer pelage during longer stretches of the active season under a future warming scenario. We observed pika behavior for 288&#x000a0;h in Glacier National Park, Montana, and thermally characterized their rocky, montane environment. We found that pikas were most active when temperatures were cooler, and at sites characterized by high elevations and north&#x02010;facing slopes. Pikas became significantly less active across a suite of behaviors in the field when temperatures surpassed 20&#x000b0;C, which supported a metabolic threshold predicted by Niche Mapper. In general, mechanistic predictions and empirical observations were congruent. This research is unique in providing both an empirical and mechanistic description of the effects of temperature on a mammalian sentinel of climate change, the American pika. Our results suggest that previously underinvestigated characteristics, specifically fur properties and body size, may play critical roles in pika populations' response to climate change. We also demonstrate the potential importance of considering behavioral thermoregulation and microclimate variability when predicting animal responses to climate change.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-generated"><kwd id="ece31848-kwd-0001">Activity</kwd><kwd id="ece31848-kwd-0002">American pika</kwd><kwd id="ece31848-kwd-0003">biophysical model</kwd><kwd id="ece31848-kwd-0004">elevation</kwd><kwd id="ece31848-kwd-0005">Glacier National Park</kwd><kwd id="ece31848-kwd-0006">Niche Mapper</kwd><kwd id="ece31848-kwd-0007"><italic>Ochotona princeps</italic></kwd><kwd id="ece31848-kwd-0008">protected area</kwd><kwd id="ece31848-kwd-0009">temperature</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>Glacier National Park Conservancy</funding-source></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>Department of Forest &#x00026; Wildlife Ecology at the University of Wisconsin&#x02010;Madison</funding-source></award-group></funding-group><counts><page-count count="13"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>source-schema-version-number</meta-name><meta-value>2.0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>component-id</meta-name><meta-value>ece31848</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>December 2015</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>details-of-publishers-convertor</meta-name><meta-value>Converter:WILEY_ML3GV2_TO_NLMPMC version:4.7.5 mode:remove_FC converted:19.01.2016</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="ece31848-sec-0001"><title>Introduction</title><p>Species respond to rising temperatures in numerous ways. For example, some shift the elevation or latitude of their range (Thomas <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0058" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>; Chen et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>). However, before shifting geographically, individuals attempt to tolerate novel environmental conditions and maintain their mass/energy balance through behavioral thermoregulation (Huey et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0023" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>). These earliest responses to environmental change may not initially reduce body condition below thresholds where individual survival or fecundity is impacted. However, as environmental conditions deviate further from the range of conditions to which organisms are ecologically adapted, individuals may be forced to make behavioral trade&#x02010;offs to maintain energy balance (Speakman and Kr&#x000f3;l <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0056" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>). Ultimately, these behavioral changes may impact individual fecundity (Parker et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0042" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>), which, on relatively short timescales, may lead to population&#x02010;level effects such as range shifts, local extirpations, and ultimately extinction (e.g., Sinervo et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0051" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>).</p><p>To understand and predict the earliest behavioral responses to climate change, we must consider the biophysical mechanisms that limit the activity of organisms. Optimality theory states that organisms evolve to make behavioral decisions so as to maximize their fitness, and these decisions are informed by environmental cues that may have historically limited fitness (Westneat and Fox <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0060" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>). For example, at the height of a temperate growing season, organisms may limit foraging time when temperatures are high, and instead rest or take refuge in cooler microclimates. Although foraging confers essential fitness benefits through the improvement or maintenance of body condition, resting or taking refuge when temperatures are high may confer even greater fitness benefits by reducing heat gain and avoiding hyperthermia (Ricklefs and Miller <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0047" ref-type="ref">2000</xref>). These critical decisions are fundamentally governed by the biophysical parameters of organisms (i.e., metabolic rate, surface properties) in combination with the external environmental conditions (i.e., landscape, microclimate) in which the organism resides, which together comprise the underpinning features of biophysical animal models. Biophysical models may prove useful in predicting how different animal populations are affected by climate and how they may respond; essential information for management and recovery of imperiled species. For example, biophysical models may allow us to better prioritize conservation efforts by identifying species with the least ability to tolerate rising temperatures through behavioral thermoregulation and also species whose fundamental and realized niches may move beyond the borders of current protected areas (Monzon et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0038" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>).</p><p>For many such species presumed and demonstrated to be at risk from climate change, considerable gaps in our understanding exist concerning the driving biological mechanisms, because fine&#x02010;scale data on the physiological effects of the thermal environment are rarely available (Beever and Belant <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>). Biophysical models therefore hold enormous potential for complementing traditional correlative approaches to fill gaps in knowledge for species of conservation concern. For the American pika (<italic>Ochotona princeps,</italic> Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece31848-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>), a temperature&#x02010;sensitive mammal inhabiting mountainous regions of the western Unites States (Smith and Weston <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0055" ref-type="ref">1990</xref>), such knowledge gaps were cited in a recent rejection of a petition to list the species as threatened by climate change under the Endangered Species Act (Crist <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0015" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>). In particular, more data are needed concerning pikas' abilities to tolerate high ambient temperatures through behavioral thermoregulation. This need, along with its known temperature sensitivity, makes the pika an ideal model organism for investigating temperature&#x02010;driven behavior modification from a biophysical perspective.</p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece31848-fig-0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>American pika, <italic>Ochotona princeps,</italic> in Glacier National Park, <styled-content style="fixed-case">MT</styled-content>,<styled-content style="fixed-case"> USA</styled-content>. Photo by Wendee Nicole Holtcamp.</p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-3" xlink:href="ECE3-5-5810-g001"/></fig><p>Pika basal metabolic rate (BMR) is high (143% of predicted weight&#x02010;specific value) and thermal conductance is low (101&#x02013;53% of predicted values; MacArthur and Wang <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">1973</xref>), resulting in elevated and stable body temperatures (mean = 40.1&#x000b0;C) and relatively low upper&#x02010;lethal temperatures (mean = 43.1&#x000b0;C; Smith <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0052" ref-type="ref">1974</xref>). These factors suggest that behavior plays an important role in pika thermoregulation (MacArthur and Wang <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">1974</xref>). Indeed, hyperthermia and death may occur at moderate (25.5&#x02013;29.4&#x000b0;C) ambient temperatures (MacArthur and Wang <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">1973</xref>; Smith <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0052" ref-type="ref">1974</xref>). These physiological sensitivities scale up to drive biogeographic distributional patterns in pikas; at high latitudes, <italic>O. princeps</italic> is found at elevations ranging from sea level to 4000&#x000a0;m, but pikas are rarely found below 2500&#x000a0;m where they meet their southern range boundary (Smith and Weston <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0055" ref-type="ref">1990</xref>). At these scales, pikas have responded to changes in climate both recently and historically by shifting upslope or becoming extirpated at low&#x02010;elevation sites across their range, suggesting vulnerability to rapid climate change in the 21st century (Hafner <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0020" ref-type="ref">1993</xref>; Grayson <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0018" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>; Moritz et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0039" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>; Beever et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>, <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0008" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>; Wilkening et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0061" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>). However, pika declines are not range&#x02010;wide (e.g., Millar and Westfall <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0036" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>; Erb et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0017" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>; Smith and Nagy <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0054" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>) and they persist at relatively warm and low&#x02010;elevation sites, especially where cooler and wetter microclimates exist (e.g., Beever <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">2002</xref>; Beever et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>; Simpson <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0050" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>; Rodhouse et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0048" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>; Jeffress et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0026" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>; Varner and Dearing <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0059" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>). The mechanisms driving pika range shifts and extirpations in certain subpopulations but not others remain unclear, primarily because we do not know enough about their biophysical tolerances and capacity to behaviorally thermoregulate.</p><p>We present an analysis of environmental drivers of pika activity using a multifaceted approach that includes both the use of biophysical modeling and direct observations of pika activity. To do this, we (1) used temperature and microclimate data from the pika's thermal environment coupled with fur properties, body size, and wind speed to build a biophysical model (Niche Mapper, Porter and Mitchell <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0044" ref-type="ref">2006</xref>) that could predict metabolic rate and activity hours of the American pika. We subsequently tested the biophysical model by simulating empirical metabolic chamber data. Next, we (2) performed statistical analyses using 288&#x000a0;h of field observations of pika activity from a series of field sites in Glacier National Park (GNP), Montana, USA, to understand how environmental variables were associated with pika activity in the field. We also predicted the available activity time at a series of field sites using our biophysical model and qualitatively compared predicted values to observed pika activity at those sites. Finally, (3) we used the biophysical model to predict how pikas may be forced to respond behaviorally to projected 21st century climate change.</p></sec><sec id="ece31848-sec-0002"><title>Material and methods</title><sec id="ece31848-sec-0003"><title>Building and validating the biophysical model</title><sec id="ece31848-sec-0004"><title>Microclimate data</title><p>We deployed AQA 8000 Series LogTag<sup>&#x02122;</sup> data loggers (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.logtagrecorders.com">www.logtagrecorders.com</ext-link>) at sites occupied by pikas in two stages. In the first stage, we used the loggers to estimate an altitudinal lapse rate for interpolating the elevation&#x02013;temperature relationship across GNP. In June and July 2008, we placed seven loggers in protected crevices 1&#x02013;2&#x000a0;m below the talus surface adjacent to a pika's food cache (or &#x0201c;hay&#x02010;pile&#x0201d;), one at each of seven sites with varying slope aspects and elevations ranging from 1512 to 2274&#x000a0;m. Two of these loggers at intermediate elevations were placed within 100&#x000a0;m of each other to assess small&#x02010;scale and potential logger variability. The loggers recorded temperature and relative humidity at 15&#x02010;min intervals. We calculated the lapse rate by fitting a linear regression to the instantaneous morning (07:00), midday (14:00), and evening (20:00) temperatures at each of the sites at one&#x02010;week intervals from July 28 to September 15.</p><p>In the second stage, we used four loggers to measure the thermal refuge provided by the talus by measuring above&#x02010; and below&#x02010;talus temperature at two locations representing elevation extremes (1056&#x000a0;m and 2521&#x000a0;m). At both sites, one logger was placed, unshaded, on top of the talus. The other was placed under the same rock and next to a hay&#x02010;pile. These loggers recorded temperature and relative humidity at 20&#x02010;min intervals. We did not deploy loggers at all behavioral observation sites, so in order to interpolate above&#x02010; and below&#x02010;talus temperatures at those sites, we applied our estimated lapse rate of &#x02212;8&#x000b0;C/km (from stage one) to the stage&#x02010;two thermal refuge data. Our estimated lapse rate fell within the range considered appropriate for GNP (Ray et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0046" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="ece31848-sec-0005"><title>Pika physical parameters</title><p>The pika physical properties used for biophysical modeling (see below) were either measured directly using a preserved pika specimen from the University of Wisconsin&#x02010;Madison Zoology Museum (with summer pelage, obtained in Colorado) or gleaned from the literature. We directly measured fur length and reflectivity for dorsal and ventral sections of the torso and legs. We assumed that winter fur was 50% longer than summer fur (Howell <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0022" ref-type="ref">1924</xref>), and that fur depth was always 50% of fur length. Animal model inputs are summarized in Table&#x000a0;S1 of the Supporting Information.</p></sec><sec id="ece31848-sec-0006"><title>Mechanistic model simulations</title><p>Niche Mapper is described in detail elsewhere (Porter and Mitchell <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0044" ref-type="ref">2006</xref>; Mathewson and Porter <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0032" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>). In brief, Niche Mapper consists of two submodels: a microclimate model and an endotherm model. The microclimate model computes the hourly values of local air temperature at animal height, ground surface temperatures, below ground soil temperatures, local wind speed and relative humidity, and direct and diffuse solar radiation in the sun and shade. The endotherm model numerically solves for metabolic rates that allow an animal to maintain its core temperature within a defined range under the computed environmental conditions. To do so, both models solve the generic heat balance model, <italic>Q</italic>
<sub>in</sub>
<italic>&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;Q</italic>
<sub>gen</sub>
<italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;Q</italic>
<sub>out&#x000a0;</sub>
<italic>+&#x000a0;Q</italic>
<sub>st</sub>; where heat in (<italic>Q</italic>
<sub>in</sub>) comes from solar and infrared radiation; <italic>Q</italic>
<sub>gen</sub> is metabolic heat generated (set to zero for the microclimate model); heat out (<italic>Q</italic>
<sub>out</sub>), is infrared radiation from the surface (ground or fur&#x02013;air interface), convective heat loss, and evaporative heat loss; and stored heat (<italic>Q</italic>
<sub>st</sub>), which is set to zero in the endotherm model for steady&#x02010;state simulations. Niche Mapper solves these equations for each hour of the day, enabling analyses such as how many hours of a month's &#x0201c;average&#x0201d; day a model animal will be either heat or cold stressed when trying to maintain a given activity level (quantified as a multiple of BMR). If the metabolic rate that solves the heat balance equation&#x000a0;is below the target activity level, the animal is predicted to overheat if active in those conditions and thus activity is not possible.</p><p>We tested Niche Mapper's ability to predict metabolic rates as a function of ambient air temperature prior to field simulations of pikas in GNP by simulating the metabolic chamber experiments of MacArthur and Wang (<xref rid="ece31848-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">1973</xref>), using the same mean pika mass (109&#x000a0;g) and constant wind speed (0.1&#x000a0;m/s) used in the experiments. We also conducted a series of sensitivity analyses to determine the influence of various animal and environmental properties on the model's metabolic rate predictions.</p></sec></sec><sec id="ece31848-sec-0007"><title>Field observations of pika activity in GNP</title><p>We observed pika activity at eight sites in GNP from 15 to 24 July, 2009. We chose sites that had relatively high pika densities across a broad range of elevations and slope aspects. We conducted twelve separate 3&#x02010;h observations per site during the following intervals: morning (05:15&#x02013;08:15), midday (13:00&#x02013;16:00), and evening (19:00&#x02013;22:00). We conducted observations over a 10&#x02010;day span to reduce the effect of seasonality; pikas are more active in late summer when caching food (Smith and Weston <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0055" ref-type="ref">1990</xref>). Morning observations commenced ~45&#x000a0;min prior to sunrise and evening observations concluded ~30&#x000a0;min after sunset. We observed pika activity passively from a high vantage point, because pikas pay little attention to quiet observers (Conner <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0014" ref-type="ref">1983</xref>). Trained observers continuously scanned the talus using the naked eye or 7&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;35 binoculars, and recorded the time of all visual and audible evidence of pika activity. Observers worked in pairs, but recorded data from nonoverlapping areas (~40&#x000a0;m radius) of the same talus patch, assigning pikas temporary ID numbers and sketching maps of their whereabouts to distinguish the activity of individuals (sensu Barash <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0002" ref-type="ref">1973</xref>). A single pika call or sighting was considered a &#x0201c;unique event&#x0201d;. Additional calls or sightings of the same individual within 30&#x000a0;sec were recorded, but not considered new unique events. In this way, we categorized brief flourishes of activity as single events. We identified the type of observed behavior under the following nonmutually exclusive categories: haying (collecting or carrying vegetation in the mouth), foraging (directly consuming vegetation), moving fast, moving slow, and vigilant (stationary). We assumed that imperfect detection of pikas played a relatively small role in data collection, because pikas are highly detectable (85&#x02013;95%) and relatively easy to identify for a stationary observer (Beever et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>; Moyer&#x02010;Horner et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0040" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>).</p><p>We used multiple regression to associate minimum above&#x02010;talus temperature (<italic>t</italic>) and two site&#x02010;level variables (elevation, <italic>e</italic>; slope aspect, <italic>a</italic>) with aggregate above&#x02010;talus pika activity observations to understand whether field observations were generally congruent with predictions from our biophysical model. We only modeled pika activity with minimum above&#x02010;talus temperature because of moderate to high collinearity with other temperature measurements (0.55&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;<italic>r&#x000a0;</italic>&#x0003c;<italic>&#x000a0;</italic>0.99) and because minimum above&#x02010;talus temperature best explained variability in pika activity in preliminary analysis (see Table&#x000a0;S2). There was no strong collinearity detected among the remaining predictor variables (<italic>r&#x000a0;</italic>=<italic>&#x000a0;</italic>0.06&#x02013;0.26). We developed a set of 10 a priori hypotheses relating minimum above&#x02010;talus temperature, elevation, and slope aspect to observed pika activity (see Table&#x000a0;S3) and evaluated relative empirical support for these hypotheses using AIC<sub>C</sub> (Burnham and Anderson <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">2002</xref>). We derived parameter estimates that accounted for model selection uncertainty by performing model averaging among models with &#x0003e;10% AIC weight and without uninformative parameters (Burnham and Anderson <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">2002</xref>; Arnold <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0001" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>). We log&#x02010;transformed the response variable (per capita pika sightings) to approximate a normal distribution (Ives <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>). Log&#x02010;linear forms of <italic>e</italic>,<italic> a</italic>, and <italic>t</italic> outperformed linear and quadratic forms in preliminary analysis (see Fig.&#x000a0;S1); therefore, we used log&#x02010;linear forms of our predictor variables in the final analysis. We fit models and performed model selection using the package &#x02018;AICcmodavg&#x02019; (Mazerolle <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0033" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>) in R version 3.1.1 (R Core Development Team).</p></sec><sec id="ece31848-sec-0008"><title>Field simulations</title><p>Niche Mapper field simulations were conducted using a diurnally active, ellipsoidal (2.25 a:b ratio) pika and a wind velocity at pika height (9&#x000a0;cm) varying diurnally from 0.1 to 4.0&#x000a0;m/s. Hair lengths and depths were scaled according to the total mass of the modeled animal, for example, a 120&#x000a0;g pika had 20% shorter and shallower hair than a 150&#x000a0;g pika. Climate and weather data were retrieved from the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration website (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.noaa.gov">www.noaa.gov</ext-link>) for Kalispell International Airport ([KIA] elevation 961&#x000a0;m), which is located ~30&#x000a0;km from Glacier National Park. When appropriate, we used a lapse rate of &#x02212;8&#x000b0;C/km to derive mean monthly maximum and minimum temperatures (see below). In addition, we conducted sensitivity analyses to test Niche Mapper's robustness to input variable uncertainty (see Tables S1 and S4) and also compared its calculated above&#x02010; and below&#x02010;talus temperatures to those we measured in the field. For simulations used as direct comparisons to field observations, we used site&#x02010;specific parameters, such as aspects and elevations of those sites, along with adjusted KIA temperatures from those days. For all other simulations, we used an eastern aspect, a 15&#x000b0; slope, GNP&#x02010;relevant elevations of 1500&#x02013;2500&#x000a0;m, and long&#x02010;term (1981&#x02013;2010) monthly averages from KIA.</p><p>We simulated a conservative warming scenario for 2100 of +5.0&#x000b0;C for all elevations (McWethy et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0034" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>). We used daily temperature ranges of 20&#x000b0;C, typical for summer months in GNP. The lowest temperature range (&#x02212;10&#x02013;10&#x000b0;C) is typical for June or September above 2500&#x000a0;m elevation. July and August temperature ranges at the lowest elevations in GNP (1500&#x000a0;m) are typically 4&#x02013;22&#x000b0;C. We interpreted the ratio of the field metabolic rate over the BMR (FMR/BMR) to determine when pikas could be active above the talus. If an FMR/BMR ratio below 1.5 was required to remain below the animal's upper critical temperature, activity would probably be infeasible (Nagy <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0041" ref-type="ref">1987</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="ece31848-sec-0009"><title>Results</title><sec id="ece31848-sec-0010"><title>Building and validating the biophysical model</title><sec id="ece31848-sec-0011"><title>Microclimate data</title><p>The observed altitudinal lapse rate varied depending on the prevailing daily weather patterns and time of day. Temperature inversions were more frequent during mornings (07:00) and in September (see Tables S5&#x02013;7). We measured a consistent lapse rate (<italic>R</italic>
<sup>2&#x000a0;</sup>&#x0003e;&#x000a0;0.75) during seven of 24 measurements, for which the mean lapse rate was &#x02212;9.46&#x000b0;C/km. The midday (14:00) mean for July and August measurements was &#x02212;8.08&#x000b0;C/km.</p><p>The difference between below&#x02010; and above&#x02010;talus temperature varied considerably depending on the time of day, and generally below&#x02010;talus temperatures were less variable than above&#x02010;talus temperatures. In the mornings (05:15&#x02013;08:15), temperatures below the talus were slightly warmer than above&#x02010;talus conditions, with higher minimum (mean&#x000b0;C below talus &#x02013; mean&#x000b0;C above talus [standard deviation]: +2.50&#x000b0;C [1.69&#x000b0;C]), and maximum temperatures (+2.62&#x000b0;C [1.69&#x000b0;C]). During the warmest part of the day (13:00&#x02013;16:00), the temperature&#x02010;damping effects of the below&#x02010;talus thermal refuge were most pronounced, exhibiting substantially lower minimum (&#x02212;13.08&#x000b0;C [2.42&#x000b0;C]) and maximum temperatures (&#x02212;15.44&#x000b0;C [1.94&#x000b0;C]). The evenings (19:00&#x02013;21:00) produced higher minimum temperatures below&#x02010;talus (+2.75&#x000b0;C [1.95&#x000b0;C]), but lower maximums (&#x02212;3.75&#x000b0;C [1.78&#x000b0;C]).</p><p>Sensitivity analyses of Niche Mapper's microclimate model revealed sufficient stability in response to input variability within ranges expected in the field, consistent with previous tests (Kearney et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0027" ref-type="ref">2014a</xref>,<xref rid="ece31848-bib-0028" ref-type="ref">b</xref>). Varying the specific heat of the talus by up to 30% (700&#x02013;1000&#x000a0;J/kg K) produced a maximum 12% change in modeled surface temperatures and 10% change in temperatures 15&#x000a0;cm below the surface. Increasing wind speed from 0.1 to 1.5&#x000a0;m/sec decreased modeled temperatures at animal height (9&#x000a0;cm) by a maximum of 15%; further increases from 1.5 to 9&#x000a0;m/sec produced at most a 10% temperature decrease. Modifying cloud cover from 0 to 100% and aspect from south to north produced a maximum 9% and 2.5% decrease in temperature at animal height, respectively. The remaining inputs produced &#x0003c;2% changes in modeled temperature when varied within expected ranges.</p><p>The microclimate model also produced relatively robust estimates of above&#x02010; and below&#x02010;talus temperatures when compared to field measurements (see Figs.&#x000a0;S2&#x02013;S5). Surface temperature estimates most closely matched observed when a &#x02212;8&#x000b0;C/km altitudinal lapse rate was used to estimate air temperature and when wind speed was allowed to vary diurnally from 0 to 4&#x000a0;m/sec. Below&#x02010;talus temperature estimates fit field measurements closest using a modeled depth of 20&#x000a0;cm for the 1056&#x000a0;m site and 15&#x000a0;cm for the 2521&#x000a0;m site. The microclimate model assumed a solid below&#x02010;surface substrate (in contrast to porous talus deposits); thus, simulated depths were 100&#x02013;200% less than the size of the rocks under which the loggers were placed.</p></sec></sec><sec id="ece31848-sec-0012"><title>Metabolic chamber simulations</title><sec id="ece31848-sec-0013"><title>Sensitivity analyses for key animal model inputs</title><p>The effect of ambient temperature on metabolic rate was most heavily influenced by the core temperature, body posture, size, and fur properties of the modeled pika. Increasing core temperature from 38 to 43&#x000b0;C produced 8&#x02013;25% higher metabolic demands (W/g), depending on ambient temperature. Changing posture from a 3:2 to 3:1 ellipsoid produced ~10% higher metabolic demands in a 150&#x000a0;g pika at temperatures ranging from &#x02212;15 to 30&#x000b0;C. At cooler temperatures, pikas with lower mass (e.g., 109&#x000a0;g), and thus smaller volume, were at an energetic disadvantage because they were required to generate proportionally more metabolic heat to maintain core temperatures. However, above 22&#x000b0;C, smaller pikas had an energetic advantage in that they were able to avoid overheating at higher temperatures. Additionally, summer fur allowed pikas of all sizes to stay in their thermal neutral zone at temperatures 4&#x000b0;C higher than those with winter fur (see Fig.&#x000a0;S6). Increasing fur density from 250 to 3000 hairs/cm<sup>2</sup> produced 61% lower metabolic rates at 0&#x000b0;C; further increases from 3000 to 15,000 hairs/cm<sup>2</sup> produced 15% lower rates. Increasing O<sub>2</sub> extraction efficiency from 5 to 30% produced up to 6% lower metabolic rates, while&#x000a0;increasing flesh thermal conductivity from 0.5 to 2.8 (W/mK) increased metabolic rates by up to 13%. Finally, when we modeled a constant solar input of 500&#x000a0;W/m<sup>2</sup> directly overhead, increasing pelt reflectivity from 15 to 90% produced 15% higher metabolic rates.</p></sec><sec id="ece31848-sec-0014"><title>Comparison to metabolic chamber measurements</title><p>Metabolic rate simulations for 109&#x000a0;g pikas fell within the range empirically derived by MacArthur and Wang (<xref rid="ece31848-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">1973</xref>) for a variety of body postures and fur properties (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece31848-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Niche Mapper simulated an upper critical temperature threshold (FMR&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;BMR) of ~25&#x000b0;C, which is similar to observed values (MacArthur and Wang <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">1973</xref>; Smith <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0052" ref-type="ref">1974</xref>).</p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece31848-fig-0002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Niche Mapper simulations of American pika metabolic rate (W) in a metabolic chamber at a range of temperatures, animal shape (ellipsoid a:b ratio 1.5 and 2.25) and fur properties. Solid lines represent the range of empirical minimum metabolic rates for pikas measured by MacArthur and Wang (<xref rid="ece31848-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">1973</xref>). The dashed lines represent the target <styled-content style="fixed-case">BMR</styled-content> range of 0.923&#x000a0;W&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;5%.</p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-5" xlink:href="ECE3-5-5810-g002"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="ece31848-sec-0015"><title>Field observations of pika activity in GNP</title><p>There were three closely competing models within 0.4 AIC that combined for ~90% of the total AIC weight; the top model, {ln(<italic>e</italic>) + ln(<italic>a</italic>) + ln(<italic>t</italic>) + [ln(<italic>e</italic>)&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;ln(<italic>a</italic>)]}, contained all covariates that were considered and therefore had the most parameters (<italic>k</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;5), followed by more parsimonious models [ln(<italic>e</italic>) + ln(<italic>a</italic>) + ln(<italic>t</italic>)] and [ln(<italic>a</italic>) + ln(<italic>t</italic>)] (see Table&#x000a0;S8). We calculated model&#x02010;averaged regression coefficients and unconditional 85% confidence intervals for parameters in these models to reduce model selection bias (Burnham and Anderson <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">2002</xref>; Arnold <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0001" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>) and produce conservative estimates of effect sizes (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece31848-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>A and B) because some estimates varied to an appreciable extent among models (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece31848-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>C and E). Model&#x02010;averaged parameter estimates suggested that pikas were generally more active at higher elevations (<mml:math id="nlm-math-1"><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>ln</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.36, SE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.35), on north&#x02010;facing slopes (<mml:math id="nlm-math-2"><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>ln</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.96, SE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1.00), and when minimum above&#x02010;talus temperatures were cooler (<mml:math id="nlm-math-3"><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>ln</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;0.76, SE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.22) (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece31848-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>A). Elevation and aspect were linked by a negative interaction (<mml:math id="nlm-math-4"><mml:msub><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="italic">&#x003b2;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">&#x000af;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">^</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mtext>ln</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>ln</mml:mtext><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:math>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;&#x02212;0.35, SE&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.59), which suggested that pikas on south&#x02010;facing slopes were less active at low elevations than at high elevations, but pikas were more active above the talus on north&#x02010;facing slopes regardless of elevation (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece31848-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>A).</p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece31848-fig-0003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Relationship between field&#x02010;based observations of pika activity, minimum above&#x02010;talus temperature, elevation, and slope aspect. The top graph (A) shows model&#x02010;averaged predicted regression surfaces at three temperatures: 25% quartile, mean, and 75% quartile. Beta coefficients and 85% confidence intervals (Arnold <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0001" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>) are shown (B) following model averaging, and for the (C) top&#x02010;ranked model, (D) second&#x02010;ranked model, and (E) third&#x02010;ranked model.</p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-7" xlink:href="ECE3-5-5810-g003"/></fig><p>In addition to our model selection&#x02010;based approach evaluating aggregate pika activity in relation to minimum above&#x02010;talus temperature and site&#x02010;level variables, we used an ANOVA&#x02010;based approach to evaluate whether minimum above&#x02010;talus temperature and time of day were significantly related to specific pika behaviors. We found that pikas were significantly more active in all behavior categories (except for haying) when minimum above&#x02010;talus temperature was below 20&#x000b0;C (all <italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.01), which corresponded with a metabolic threshold predicted by Niche Mapper (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece31848-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). Calls per occupant were influenced by time of day and temperature; there were 14.7 fewer calls per occupant during midday than during morning or evening (<italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.01) and 0.5 fewer calls per occupant for every 1&#x000b0;C (<italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.01, <italic>R</italic>
<sup>2&#x000a0;</sup>=&#x000a0;0.08). Data were also collected on whether or not pikas were exposed to direct sunlight while making short or long call vocalizations. Long calls are typically made by males and probably related to mating (Smith and Weston <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0055" ref-type="ref">1990</xref>). Only one of 149 (0.67%) recorded long calls and 400 of 6699 (6%) of short calls were made while pikas were exposed to direct sunlight.</p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece31848-fig-0004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>The top panel (A) shows <styled-content style="fixed-case">FMR</styled-content>/<styled-content style="fixed-case">BMR</styled-content> ratios across a range of temperatures. The red vertical line denotes the temperature threshold at which modeled 150&#x000a0;g pikas could not maintain an <styled-content style="fixed-case">FMR</styled-content>/<styled-content style="fixed-case">BMR</styled-content> above 1.5. The bottom panel (B) shows the per capita frequency of pika behaviors when minimum above&#x02010;talus temperature was above or below 20&#x000b0;C during field observations in <styled-content style="fixed-case">GNP</styled-content>. Error bars represent &#x000b1;1 <styled-content style="fixed-case">SE</styled-content>. *Denotes a significant difference between the two groups.</p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-9" xlink:href="ECE3-5-5810-g004"/></fig></sec><sec id="ece31848-sec-0016"><title>Field simulations</title><sec id="ece31848-sec-0017"><title>Comparing modeled and observed behavior</title><p>Niche Mapper's activity level predictions were similar to observations at field sites in GNP. Predicted activity levels, quantified by the ratio of maximum allowable FMR to BMR, were lowest when temperatures were high and increased as temperatures dropped. Above 20&#x000b0;C, modeled 150&#x000a0;g pikas began physiologically thermoregulating (vasodilation, raising body temperature) in order to maintain a target metabolic rate of 1.5&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0; their BMR, which corresponds to the minimum value necessary for activity (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece31848-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">4</xref>A). Additionally, increasing predicted allowable activity levels corresponded to the highest rates and variance of observed per capita pika activity (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece31848-fig-0005" ref-type="fig">5</xref>).</p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece31848-fig-0005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Comparison of Niche Mapper predicted maximum allowable activity at field sites (<italic>x</italic>&#x02010;axis) with observed pika activity frequency at those same sites in the field (<italic>y</italic>&#x02010;axis).</p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-11" xlink:href="ECE3-5-5810-g005"/></fig><p>Using 1.5 FMR/BMR as the minimum metabolic ratio for activity, a simulated 120&#x000a0;g pika in GNP was able to remain active above the talus during all available diurnal hours of the day (June and July&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;21, August&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;19&#x000a0;h), regardless of elevation or pelage (summer vs. winter). However, a 150&#x000a0;g pika with winter pelage faced physiological limitations that reduced allowable activity time by 19.0% in July at 1500&#x000a0;m, 4.8% in July at 1750&#x000a0;m, and 15.8% in August at 1500&#x000a0;m.</p></sec><sec id="ece31848-sec-0018"><title>Simulating the below&#x02010;talus thermal refuge</title><p>We simulated a heat wave with temperatures ~10&#x000b0;C higher than current July means at low elevations in GNP to explore how the talus might buffer a pika from acute heat stress. For several consecutive hours in the middle of the day, the model pika was unable to maintain even its BMR without overheating, suggesting death from hyperthermia. However, at sufficient depth below the surface, the model pika could retreat and maintain its BMR for all hours of the day without overheating (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece31848-fig-0006" ref-type="fig">6</xref>).</p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece31848-fig-0006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Niche Mapper simulations of <styled-content style="fixed-case">FMR</styled-content>/<styled-content style="fixed-case">BMR</styled-content> for a pika at three depths (surface, 15&#x000a0;cm below&#x02010;surface, and 20&#x000a0;cm below&#x02010;surface) during a heat wave. Activity cannot occur below 1.5 <styled-content style="fixed-case">FMR</styled-content>/<styled-content style="fixed-case">BMR</styled-content>.</p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-13" xlink:href="ECE3-5-5810-g006"/></fig></sec><sec id="ece31848-sec-0019"><title>Simulations under a future warming scenario</title><p>A 2100 warming scenario of +5&#x000b0;C resulted in restrictions in allowable activity time (diurnal + crepuscular hours) for simulated pikas in GNP, especially when pikas had a higher body mass and thicker fur. Simulations suggested that allowable activity time for a 120&#x000a0;g pika with summer fur in year 2100 will decline by 9.5%, but only in July and at a low elevation (1500&#x000a0;m). However, allowable activity time for a 150&#x000a0;g pika with summer fur declined by 10.5&#x02013;23.8% in July and August at both 1500&#x000a0;m (Fig&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece31848-fig-0007" ref-type="fig">7</xref>A) and 1750&#x000a0;m elevation sites.</p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece31848-fig-0007" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Niche Mapper simulations of percent (%) change in metabolically allowable daily above&#x02010;talus activity time by year 2100 for a pika at 1500&#x000a0;m elevation in Glacier National Park, <styled-content style="fixed-case">MT</styled-content>, for (A) a 150&#x000a0;g pika during summer months in summer fur and winter fur and (B) for different sizes of pikas with varying fur depths, during the month of August.</p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-15" xlink:href="ECE3-5-5810-g007"/></fig><p>With winter fur, potential activity time for a 150&#x000a0;g pika declined under the future warming scenario at elevations below 2500&#x000a0;m. In June, when many pikas may still have winter fur, allowable activity time declined by 23.8% and 4.8% at 1500&#x000a0;m and 1750&#x000a0;m, respectively. Further investigation of the impacts of interactions between body size and fur properties on allowable activity for a pika at low elevation (1500&#x000a0;m) in GNP in year 2100 revealed no activity restrictions for a 120&#x000a0;g pika with 30% shorter and shallower fur (compared to the measured specimen), but 37% fewer activity hours for a 180&#x000a0;g pika with 20% longer and thicker fur (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece31848-fig-0007" ref-type="fig">7</xref>B).</p></sec></sec></sec><sec id="ece31848-sec-0020"><title>Discussion</title><p>Our understanding of animal species' resilience to warming temperatures is a critical component of our ability to predict future range shifts and extirpations, and conserve biodiversity. Animals employ an array of behavioral strategies to avoid hyperthermia, such as changing body posture, seeking cooler microhabitats, reducing locomotion, and decreasing energy intake (Terrien et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0057" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>). Mammals in particular have the ability to regulate body temperature through fur properties, for example, by changing their seasonal molt timing. We examined some of these factors by presenting a coupled biophysical endotherm and microclimate model and comparing the results to empirical temperature and behavior data for a species, the American pika, whose ability to persist under future climate warming is unclear.</p><p>Although recent work has shown that pika extirpations during the past 35&#x02013;55&#x000a0;years in the Great Basin were correlated with high mean summer temperatures and both extreme heat in the summer and extreme cold in the winter (Beever et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">2003</xref>, <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>), the mechanisms driving these losses are unclear. A critical gap exists regarding our understanding of how climate and pika physiology interact to affect behavior. Thus, it is unclear how pika physiological tolerances and behavioral flexibility will impact their individual and population&#x02010;level responses to rapid climate change. To date, the most thorough studies of pika behavior relative to temperature found that pikas were less active during midday, especially at lower elevation sites (Smith <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0052" ref-type="ref">1974</xref>), and that activity durations were short. It was presumed that pikas used short activity bouts to limit heat accumulation and used the sub&#x02010;talus microclimate to dissipate heat (MacArthur and Wang <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">1974</xref>). Others have reported midday activity decreases in GNP (Barash <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0002" ref-type="ref">1973</xref>), as well as the Sierra Nevada (Severaid <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0049" ref-type="ref">1955</xref>) and Great Basin (Hall <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0021" ref-type="ref">1946</xref>). However, research in Colorado (Broadbooks <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">1965</xref>; Krear <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0029" ref-type="ref">1965</xref>), and the high Sierra (Grinnell and Storer <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">1917</xref>) suggested that pikas remained active throughout the day. Thus, analysis of the mechanisms driving pika extirpations requires a greater biophysical understanding of pikas as well as their capacity to behaviorally thermoregulate.</p><sec id="ece31848-sec-0021"><title>Microclimate data</title><p>Uncertainty in a temperature&#x02010;occupancy threshold for pikas in the literature (e.g., Beever et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>; Millar and Westfall <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0036" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>; Smith and Nagy <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0054" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>) may stem from a reliance on broad&#x02010;scale weather data in place of pika&#x02010;relevant microclimate data (Potter et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0045" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>). Mean free atmospheric lapse rates are too coarse to accurately characterize temperature over complex terrain and at fine spatial scales (Minder et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0037" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>). Instead, regional monthly and daily surface temperature lapse rates such as those we calculated are more appropriate (Blandford et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>), especially when combined with a microclimate model such as Niche Mapper's. We identified relatively large variation in the relationship between the microclimates available to pikas and elevation in GNP; when consistent, this lapse rate had a 1&#x02013;3&#x000b0;C greater magnitude than expected for the region (Ray et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0046" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>). Pikas could potentially exploit this variability during warmer summers by increasing their activity during short periods of favorable conditions or even increasing nocturnal activity (Severaid <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0049" ref-type="ref">1955</xref>; Smith <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0052" ref-type="ref">1974</xref>). We recommend caution when applying large&#x02010;scale climate data and model predictions, such as lapse rate estimates, in mountainous terrain.</p><p>The thermal refuge beneath the talus plays a critical role in pika thermoregulation. We found that it provided a buffer of up to 20&#x000b0;C during the hottest times of day, which is consistent with the literature (MacArthur and Wang <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">1974</xref>; Varner and Dearing <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0059" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>), although it can be more pronounced in the presence of subsurface ice features (Wilkening et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0062" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>). This buffer allows pikas to remain active under the talus surface and avoid acute heat stress or death on hot days (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece31848-fig-0006" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). However, our simulations showed that relatively shallow talus may provide insufficient thermal refuge during heat waves, especially in the late afternoon and early evening, such that microclimates become unsuitable both above and below the talus.</p></sec><sec id="ece31848-sec-0022"><title>Metabolic chamber simulations</title><p>We demonstrated that Niche Mapper accurately predicted pika metabolic rates from metabolic chamber experiments across a wide range of temperatures (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece31848-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Sensitivity analyses revealed that fur properties, animal size, and ambient wind speed had relatively large physiological, and thus behavioral, consequences. These factors are rarely considered in studies of pika behavior and occurrence, but our work suggests that they may play a critical role in pika persistence in a warming climate.</p></sec><sec id="ece31848-sec-0023"><title>Behavior observations</title><p>We found pika activity was lowest when temperatures were highest, which is consistent with the literature (e.g., Barash <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0002" ref-type="ref">1973</xref>; MacArthur and Wang <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">1974</xref>; Smith <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0052" ref-type="ref">1974</xref>). Niche Mapper identified a limiting temperature threshold of 20&#x000b0;C for a 150&#x000a0;g pika with summer fur, above which we observed restrictions in most above&#x02010;talus behaviors (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece31848-fig-0004" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). We found no correlation between behavior and temperature below this threshold, suggesting that other factors may exert stronger influences on behavior below 20&#x000b0;C. For example, the predominance of short activity bouts may play a role in predator avoidance. Pika calls, which were negatively correlated with temperature, probably serve as a conspecific territorial defense mechanism and a predator alarm (Conner <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0014" ref-type="ref">1983</xref>), but may also increase individual predation risk by revealing the caller's location (Smith and Ivins <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0053" ref-type="ref">1983</xref>). Our results suggest that temperature may modulate an individual's cost&#x02013;benefit curve for making vocalizations as well as restrict above&#x02010;talus activity.</p><p>Behavioral observations revealed that, in addition to temperature, site elevation and aspect combined to impact pika activity in complex ways. Pikas at higher elevations and north&#x02010;facing slopes were generally most active (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece31848-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). While high elevations and north&#x02010;facing slopes may contribute to the cooler conditions preferred by pikas, they also may contribute to differences in seasonality and phenology that are more pronounced at high latitudes. Later snowmelt and earlier, more frequent snowfall at high&#x02010;elevation north&#x02010;facing sites may constrain or shift the timing of the growing season, which could limit food availability. Pikas inhabiting such sites may be compelled to increase foraging and/or haying bouts per unit time relative to other sites to meet caloric demands for metabolic maintenance, reproduction, and food caching.</p><p>The seasonality of haying and breeding activities in pikas may have considerable impacts on observations of their behavior. Compared to higher elevations, pikas at lower elevations start and cease haying sooner, and breed up to 6&#x000a0;weeks sooner (Smith <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0052" ref-type="ref">1974</xref>), which could be driven by elevational gradients in vegetation senescence (Smith <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0052" ref-type="ref">1974</xref>; Huntly et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0024" ref-type="ref">1986</xref>). Additionally, pikas change their preferred forage throughout the season in response to changes in plant toxins and protein content, which may compel them to accelerate haying at different times (Dearing <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0016" ref-type="ref">1997</xref>). We conducted our field observations during a 10&#x02010;day period to reduce behavioral changes due to seasonality. However, spatial differences in seasonality across sites may have contributed to the support for elevation, aspect, and elevation &#x000d7; aspect terms as predictors of pika activity (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece31848-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="ece31848-sec-0024"><title>Field simulations and activity observations</title><p>We used simulations to demonstrate pika physiological activity constraints over a range of temperatures, elevations, and fur properties. The metabolic consequences of thermoregulation are reflected in the FMR/BMR ratio, which constrains animals at low and high temperature extremes. Pikas must maintain an FMR of at least 1.5&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0; BMR to remain active above the talus, but as low as possible above this threshold to conserve energy. While our summer&#x02010;month simulations produced FMR/BMR ratios no greater than 3.0, higher ratios could occur in winter when pikas face hypothermia.</p><p>We demonstrated that fur properties, molt timing, and animal size have significant metabolic impacts on pikas, thereby constraining activity time (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece31848-fig-0007" ref-type="fig">7</xref>). The role of fur properties in pika behavior, morphology, and physiology has, to date, been unexamined. To our knowledge, only three studies have documented pika fur properties. Krear (<xref rid="ece31848-bib-0029" ref-type="ref">1965</xref>) and Howell (<xref rid="ece31848-bib-0022" ref-type="ref">1924</xref>) documented two annual molts, noting that summer pelage is generally worn for &#x0003c; 2&#x000a0;months and that winter fur is up to twice the length of summer fur, while Severaid (<xref rid="ece31848-bib-0049" ref-type="ref">1955</xref>) examined the effect of reproductive status on molt timing. However, the extent to which subpopulations inhabiting disparate climatic regions (or microclimates on the same mountain) vary in fur properties and molt timing is not well known. Our simulations suggested that plasticity in molt timing, to a certain degree, may reduce activity restrictions predicted under future warming scenarios. In particular, pikas that shed their winter pelage sooner could be less restricted in early growing season activity.</p><p>Geographic variation in size and pelage can have substantial biophysical impacts on endotherms (Briscoe et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>). Range&#x02010;wide variation in pika body size is poorly documented, yet we demonstrated that body size could affect potential activity time under climate change. Smith and Weston (<xref rid="ece31848-bib-0055" ref-type="ref">1990</xref>) reported interpopulation variation in pika mean body mass ranging from 121 to 176&#x000a0;g, but their sample was relatively limited in size and geographic extent. In addition to limiting activity (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece31848-fig-0007" ref-type="fig">7</xref>), animal size may interact with temperature to impact dispersal. Smith (<xref rid="ece31848-bib-0052" ref-type="ref">1974</xref>) suggested that pikas at low elevations were limited primarily by low colonization success associated with higher temperatures, and that furthermore these pikas were forced to disperse during the hottest times of the season. However, smaller dispersing juveniles (Millar and Tapper <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0035" ref-type="ref">1973</xref>) can dissipate heat more efficiently and remain active at higher temperatures (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece31848-fig-0007" ref-type="fig">7</xref>). More range&#x02010;wide data on variation in fur properties, molt timing, and animal size, especially for at&#x02010;risk subpopulations, is critical to improve our understanding of pika thermoregulation and potential responses to future warming.</p><p>The nocturnal activity of pikas warrants further investigation, especially at warmer low&#x02010;elevation sites (e.g., Beever et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>). Little is known about nocturnal activity in pikas; nocturnal activity may be restricted to certain regions and subpopulations, or may be a behavioral adaptation available to all pikas. While several occurrences of nocturnal activity and vocalizations have been documented in the Sierra Nevada and GNP (Smith <xref rid="ece31848-bib-0052" ref-type="ref">1974</xref>; LMH <italic>pers. obs</italic>.), Krear (<xref rid="ece31848-bib-0029" ref-type="ref">1965</xref>) observed no nocturnal activity during extensive observations in Colorado. The risk of depredation by efficient nocturnal predators such as owls and weasels could play a role in restricting pika nocturnal activity.</p><p>The results presented here combine mechanistic biophysical and empirical correlative approaches to investigate the temperature&#x02010;limitations of American pikas. The approaches complemented one another, and together formed a more complete understanding of pika heat tolerance and thermoregulatory options. The empirical observations and correlative analyses provided critical support for the mechanistic model's predictions while also identifying important factors, in this case elevation, aspect, and possibly seasonality that were not modeled biophysically. In turn, the biophysical model provided mechanistic support for our understanding of the drivers of pika behaviors observed by us and other researchers. Future research could evaluate allowable activity time across the pika's range to model spatial patterns of occupancy and extirpation.</p><p>Niche Mapper simulations allowed us to identify additional significant factors and generate hypotheses for investigation by future empirical studies. In the case of American pikas, the complex relationship between fur properties, body size, behavior, and microclimate structure may be critical to species persistence. For instance, we found that smaller pikas with shorter fur were better able to tolerate higher temperatures and remain active longer than larger pikas with thicker fur. Rising temperatures will present selective pressures on pika populations relative to the characteristics that we identified. Approaches that combine correlative and mechanistic analyses are becoming increasingly necessary in an age of rapid climate change.</p></sec></sec><sec id="ece31848-sec-0026"><title>Conflict of Interest</title><p>None declared.</p></sec><sec id="ece31848-sec-0027"><title>Data Accessibility</title><p>Data are available from L. Moyer&#x02010;Horner upon request.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supporting information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data"><caption><p>
<bold>Figure&#x000a0;S1.</bold> Graphical representations of the supported log&#x02010;linear relationships between environmental variables and field&#x02010;based observations of pika activity in Glacier National Park, MT during the summers of 2008 and 2009.</p><p>
<bold>Figure&#x000a0;S2</bold>. Comparison of NicheMapper microclimate model surface temperature estimates to measured surface temperatures in GNP at 1056 m elevation, between July 15&#x02013;July 24, 2009.</p><p>
<bold>Figure&#x000a0;S3</bold>. Comparison of NicheMapper microclimate model surface temperature estimates to measured surface temperatures in GNP at 2521&#x000a0;m elevation, between July 15&#x02013;July 24, 2009.</p><p>
<bold>Figure&#x000a0;S4</bold>. Comparison of NicheMapper microclimate model below&#x02010;talus temperature estimates to measured below&#x02010;talus temperatures in GNP at 1056 m elevation, between July 15&#x02013;July 24, 2009.</p><p>
<bold>Figure&#x000a0;S5</bold>. Comparison of NicheMapper microclimate model below&#x02010;talus temperature estimates to measured below&#x02010;talus temperatures in GNP at 2521&#x000a0;m elevation, between July 15&#x02013;July 24, 2009.</p><p>
<bold>Figure&#x000a0;S6</bold>. Niche Mapper simulations of an American pika (<italic>Ochotona princeps</italic>) in a metabolic chamber, across a range of temperatures, varying the size and fur properties of the animal.</p><p>
<bold>Table&#x000a0;S1.</bold> Properties used to parameterize the biophysical model for an American pika (<italic>Ochotona princeps</italic>).</p><p>
<bold>Table&#x000a0;S2.</bold> Model selection results for the relationship between relevant temperature covariates and field&#x02010;based observations of pika activity in Glacier National Park, MT during the summers of 2008 and 2009.</p><p>
<bold>Table&#x000a0;S3.</bold> Set of 10 a priori hypotheses relating a suite of environmental variables (<italic>e</italic>, elevation; <italic>a</italic>, aspect; <italic>t</italic>, minimum above talus temperature) to field&#x02010;based observations of pika activity in Glacier National Park, MT during the summers of 2008 and 2009.</p><p>
<bold>Table&#x000a0;S4.</bold> Standard microclimate model inputs for Niche Mapper simulations of American pikas (<italic>Ochotona princeps</italic>) in Glacier National Park, Montana, USA.</p><p>
<bold>Table&#x000a0;S5.</bold> Temperature (&#x000b0;C) data from time 0700 on the dates indicated in 2008, 1&#x000a0;m below the talus surface at seven sites in Glacier National Park, Montana.</p><p>
<bold>Table&#x000a0;S6.</bold> Temperature (&#x000b0;C) data from time 1400 on the dates indicated in 2008 and 1 m below the talus surface at seven sites in Glacier National Park, Montana.</p><p>
<bold>Table&#x000a0;S7.</bold> Temperature (&#x000b0;C) data from time 2000 on the dates indicated in 2008 and 1 m below the talus surface at seven sites in Glacier National Park, Montana.</p><p>
<bold>Table&#x000a0;S8.</bold> Model selection results for analysis of field&#x02010;based observations of pika behavior (per capita pika activity) in Glacier National Park, Montana during the summers of 2008 and 2009.</p></caption><media xlink:href="ECE3-5-5810-s001.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack id="ece31848-sec-0025"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>L. Moyer&#x02010;Horner thanks his field assistants for their efforts during long days of behavioral observations. Thank you to the staff and scientists at GNP for their support and cooperation. Very special thanks to Steve Gniadek for encouragement, comments on grant applications, and advice on working in a national park. The field work was funded by a grant to L. Moyer&#x02010;Horner from the Glacier National Park Conservancy. The Department of Forest &#x00026; Wildlife Ecology at the University of Wisconsin&#x02010;Madison provided additional funding to help defray publication expenses.</p></ack><ref-list content-type="cited-references" id="ece31848-bibl-0001"><title>References</title><ref id="ece31848-bib-0001"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Arnold</surname>, <given-names>T. W.</given-names>
</string-name>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Uninformative parameters and model selection using Akaike's Information Criterion</article-title>. <source>J. Wildl. Manag.</source>
<volume>74</volume>:<fpage>1175</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1178</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0002"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Barash</surname>, <given-names>D. P</given-names>
</string-name>. <year>1973</year>
<article-title>Territorial and foraging behavior of pika (<italic>Ochotona princeps</italic>) in Montana</article-title>. <source>Am. Midl. Nat.</source>
<volume>89</volume>:<fpage>202</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>207</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0003"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Beever</surname>, <given-names>E. A.</given-names>
</string-name>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Persistence of pikas in two low&#x02010;elevation national monuments in the western United States</article-title>. <source>Park Sci.</source>
<volume>21</volume>:<fpage>23</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>29</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0004"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<string-name>
<surname>Beever</surname>, <given-names>E. A.</given-names>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>J. L.</given-names>
<surname>Belant</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2011</year>
<source>Ecological consequences of climate change: mechanisms, conservation, and management</source>. <publisher-name>CRC Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Taylor &#x00026; Francis Group. Boca Raton, FL, USA</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0005"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Beever</surname>, <given-names>E. A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>P. F.</given-names>
<surname>Brussard</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Berger</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2003</year>
<article-title>Patterns of apparent extirpation among isolated populations of pikas (<italic>Ochotona princeps</italic>) in the Great Basin</article-title>. <source>J. Mammal.</source>
<volume>84</volume>:<fpage>37</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>54</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0006"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Beever</surname>, <given-names>E. A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J. L.</given-names>
<surname>Wilkening</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>D. E.</given-names>
<surname>McIvor</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S. S.</given-names>
<surname>Weber</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>P. F.</given-names>
<surname>Brussard</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2008</year>
<article-title>American pikas (<italic>Ochotona princeps</italic>) in northwestern Nevada: a newly discovered population at a low&#x02010;elevation site</article-title>. <source>West. North Am. Nat.</source>
<volume>68</volume>:<fpage>8</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0007"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Beever</surname>, <given-names>E. A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
<surname>Ray</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>P. W.</given-names>
<surname>Mote</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>J. L.</given-names>
<surname>Wilkening</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2010</year>
<article-title>Testing alternative models of climate&#x02010;mediated extirpations</article-title>. <source>Ecol. Appl.</source>
<volume>20</volume>:<fpage>164</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>178</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20349838</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0008"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Beever</surname>, <given-names>E. A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
<surname>Ray</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J. L.</given-names>
<surname>Wilkening</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>P. F.</given-names>
<surname>Brussard</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>P. W.</given-names>
<surname>Mote</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2011</year>
<article-title>Contemporary climate change alters the pace and drivers of extinction</article-title>. <source>Glob. Change Biol.</source>
<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>2054</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2070</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0009"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Blandford</surname>, <given-names>T. R.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>K. S.</given-names>
<surname>Humes</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>B. J.</given-names>
<surname>Harshburger</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>B. C.</given-names>
<surname>Moore</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>V. P.</given-names>
<surname>Walden</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
<surname>Ye</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2008</year>
<article-title>Seasonal and synoptic variations in near&#x02010;surface air temperature lapse rates in a mountainous basin</article-title>. <source>J. Appl. Meteorol. Climatol.</source>
<volume>47</volume>:<fpage>249</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>261</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0010"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Briscoe</surname>, <given-names>N. J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Krockenberger</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>K. A.</given-names>
<surname>Handasyde</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>M. R.</given-names>
<surname>Kearney</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2014</year>
<article-title>Bergmann meets Scholander: geographical variation in body size and insulation in the koala is related to climate</article-title>. <source>J. Biogeogr.</source>
<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>791</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>802</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0011"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Broadbooks</surname>, <given-names>H. E</given-names>
</string-name>. <year>1965</year>
<article-title>Ecology and distribution of the pikas of Washington and Alaska</article-title>. <source>Am. Midl. Nat.</source>
<volume>73</volume>:<fpage>299</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>335</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0012"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<string-name>
<surname>Burnham</surname>, <given-names>K.P.</given-names>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>D. R.</given-names>
<surname>Anderson</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2002</year>
<source>Model selection and multimodel inference: a practical information&#x02010;theoretic approach</source>. <publisher-name>Springer Science &#x00026; Business Media</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Springer Verlag. New York, NY, USA</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0013"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Chen</surname>, <given-names>I.&#x02010;C.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J. K.</given-names>
<surname>Hill</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
<surname>Ohlem&#x000fc;ller</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>D. B.</given-names>
<surname>Roy</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>C. D.</given-names>
<surname>Thomas</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2011</year>
<article-title>Rapid range shifts of species associated with high levels of climate warming</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>333</volume>:<fpage>1024</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1026</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21852500</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0014"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Conner</surname>, <given-names>D. A.</given-names>
</string-name>
<year>1983</year>
<article-title>Seasonal changes in activity patterns and the adaptive value of haying in pikas (<italic>Ochotona princeps</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Can. J. Zool.</source>
<volume>61</volume>:<fpage>411</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>416</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0015"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<string-name>
<surname>Crist</surname>, <given-names>L</given-names>
</string-name>. <year>2010</year>
<source>Endangered and threatened wildlife and plants; 12&#x02010;month finding on a petition to list the American pika as threatened or endangered. FWS&#x02010;R6&#x02010;ES&#x02010;2009&#x02010;0021</source>. <publisher-name>US Fish and Wildlife Service, Utah Ecological Services Field Office</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>West Valley City, UT</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0016"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Dearing</surname>, <given-names>M. D.</given-names>
</string-name>
<year>1997</year>
<article-title>The manipulation of plant toxins by a food&#x02010;hoarding herbivore, <italic>Ochotona princeps</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Ecology</source>
<volume>78</volume>:<fpage>774</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>781</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0017"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Erb</surname>, <given-names>L. P.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
<surname>Ray</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
<surname>Guralnick</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2011</year>
<article-title>On the generality of a climate&#x02010;mediated shift in the distribution of the American pika (<italic>Ochotona princeps</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Ecology</source>
<volume>92</volume>:<fpage>1730</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1735</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21939069</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0018"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Grayson</surname>, <given-names>D. K.</given-names>
</string-name>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>A brief history of Great Basin pikas</article-title>. <source>J. Biogeogr.</source>
<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>2103</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2111</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0019"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Grinnell</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>T. I.</given-names>
<surname>Storer</surname>
</string-name>. <year>1917</year>
<article-title>The Yosemite cony</article-title>. <source>Sierra Club Bull.</source>
<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>159</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>164</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0020"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Hafner</surname>, <given-names>D. J.</given-names>
</string-name>
<year>1993</year>
<article-title>North American pika (<italic>Ochotona princeps</italic>) as a late quaternary biogeographic indicator species</article-title>. <source>Quatern. Res.</source>
<volume>39</volume>:<fpage>373</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>380</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0021"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<string-name>
<surname>Hall</surname>, <given-names>E. R.</given-names>
</string-name>
<year>1946</year>
<source>Mammals of Nevada</source>. <publisher-name>Univ. Calif. Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Berkeley</publisher-loc> 710 p.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0022"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Howell</surname>, <given-names>A. H.</given-names>
</string-name>
<year>1924</year>
<article-title>Revision of the American pikas (genus Ochotona)</article-title>. <source>North Am. Fauna</source>
<volume>47</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>57</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0023"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Huey</surname>, <given-names>R. B.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M. R.</given-names>
<surname>Kearney</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Krockenberger</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J. A. M.</given-names>
<surname>Holtum</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Jess</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>S. E.</given-names>
<surname>Williams</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2012</year>
<article-title>Predicting organismal vulnerability to climate warming: roles of behaviour, physiology and adaptation</article-title>. <source>Philos. Trans. Royal Soc. B: Biol. Sci.</source>
<volume>367</volume>:<fpage>1665</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1679</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0024"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Huntly</surname>, <given-names>N. J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A. T.</given-names>
<surname>Smith</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>B. L.</given-names>
<surname>Ivins</surname>
</string-name>. <year>1986</year>
<article-title>Foraging behavior of the pika (<italic>Ochotona princeps</italic>), with comparisons of grazing versus haying</article-title>. <source>J. Mammal.</source>
<volume>67</volume>:<fpage>139</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>148</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0025"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Ives</surname>, <given-names>A. R</given-names>
</string-name>. <year>2015</year>
<article-title>For testing the significance of regression coefficients, go ahead and log&#x02010;transform count data</article-title>. <source>Methods Ecol. Evol.</source>
<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>828</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>835</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0026"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Jeffress</surname>, <given-names>M. R.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>T. J.</given-names>
<surname>Rodhouse</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
<surname>Ray</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Wolff</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>C. W.</given-names>
<surname>Epps</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2013</year>
<article-title>The idiosyncrasies of place: geographic variation in the climate&#x02010;distribution relationships of the American pika</article-title>. <source>Ecol. Appl.</source>
<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>864</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>878</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23865236</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0027"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Kearney</surname>, <given-names>M. R.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A. P.</given-names>
<surname>Isaac</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>W. P.</given-names>
<surname>Porter</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2014a</year>
<article-title>microclim: Global estimates of hourly microclimate based on long&#x02010;term monthly climate averages</article-title>. <source>Scient. Data</source> Article number: 140006, doi:<ext-link ext-link-type="doi" xlink:href="10.1038/sdata.2014.6">10.1038/sdata.2014.6</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0028"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Kearney</surname>, <given-names>M. R.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Shamakhy</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
<surname>Tingley</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>D. J.</given-names>
<surname>Karoly</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A. A.</given-names>
<surname>Hoffmann</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>P. R.</given-names>
<surname>Briggs</surname>
</string-name>, et&#x000a0;al. <year>2014b</year>
<article-title>Microclimate modelling at macro scales: a test of a general microclimate model integrated with gridded continental&#x02010;scale soil and weather data</article-title>. <source>Methods Ecol. Evol.</source>
<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>273</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>286</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0029"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<string-name>
<surname>Krear</surname>, <given-names>H. R</given-names>
</string-name>. <year>1965</year>
<source>An ecological and ethological study of the pika (ochotana princeps saxatilis bangs) in the front range of Colorado</source>. <publisher-name>University Microfilms</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>University Microfilms</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0030"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>MacArthur</surname>, <given-names>R. A.</given-names>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>L. C.</given-names>
<surname>Wang</surname>
</string-name>. <year>1973</year>
<article-title>Physiology of thermoregulation in the pika, <italic>Ochotona princeps</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Can. J. Zool.</source>
<volume>51</volume>:<fpage>11</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>16</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4696076</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0031"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>MacArthur</surname>, <given-names>R. A.</given-names>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>L. C.</given-names>
<surname>Wang</surname>
</string-name>. <year>1974</year>
<article-title>Behavioral thermoregulation in the pika <italic>Ochotona princeps</italic>: a field study using radiotelemetry</article-title>. <source>Can. J. Zool.</source>
<volume>52</volume>:<fpage>353</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>358</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4819475</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0032"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Mathewson</surname>, <given-names>P. D.</given-names>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>W. P.</given-names>
<surname>Porter</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2013</year>
<article-title>Simulating polar bear energetics during a seasonal fast using a mechanistic model</article-title>. <source>PLoS ONE</source>
<volume>8(9)</volume>:<fpage>372863</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0033"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<string-name>
<surname>Mazerolle</surname>, <given-names>M</given-names>
</string-name>. <year>2013</year>
<source>AICcmodavg: Model selection and multimodel inference based on (Q) AIC (c), R package version 1.35</source>. <publisher-name>R Foundation for Statistical Computing</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Vienna</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0034"><mixed-citation publication-type="miscellaneous">
<string-name>
<surname>McWethy</surname>, <given-names>D.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Gray</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>P.</given-names>
<surname>Higuera</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Littell</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
<surname>Pederson</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Ray</surname>
</string-name>, et&#x000a0;al. <year>2010</year>
<article-title>Climate and terrestrial ecosystem change in the US Rocky Mountains and Upper Columbia Basin: historical and future perspectives for natural resource management</article-title>. Natural Resource Report NPS/GRYN/NRR&#x02014;2010/260. National Park Service, Fort Collins, Colorado.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0035"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Millar</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Tapper</surname>
</string-name>. <year>1973</year>
<article-title>Growth rates of pikas in Alberta</article-title>. <source>Can. Field Nat.</source>
<volume>87</volume>:<fpage>457</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>459</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0036"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Millar</surname>, <given-names>C. I.</given-names>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>R. D.</given-names>
<surname>Westfall</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2010</year>
<article-title>Distribution and climatic relationships of the American Pika (<italic>Ochotona princeps</italic>) in the Sierra Nevada and Western Great Basin, USA; Periglacial landforms as refugia in warming climates</article-title>. <source>Arct. Antarct. Alp. Res.</source>
<volume>42</volume>:<fpage>76</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>88</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0037"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Minder</surname>, <given-names>J. R.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>P. W.</given-names>
<surname>Mote</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>J. D.</given-names>
<surname>Lundquist</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2010</year>
<article-title>Surface temperature lapse rates over complex terrain: lessons from the Cascade Mountains</article-title>. <source>J. Geophys. Res. Atmosp.</source>
<volume>1984&#x02013;2012</volume>:<fpage>115</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0038"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Monzon</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
<surname>Moyer&#x02010;Horner</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>M. B.</given-names>
<surname>Palamar</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2011</year>
<article-title>Climate change and species range dynamics in protected areas</article-title>. <source>Bioscience</source>
<volume>61</volume>:<fpage>752</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>761</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0039"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Moritz</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J. L.</given-names>
<surname>Patton</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>C. J.</given-names>
<surname>Conroy</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J. L.</given-names>
<surname>Parra</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>G. C.</given-names>
<surname>White</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>S. R.</given-names>
<surname>Beissinger</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2008</year>
<article-title>Impact of a century of climate change on small&#x02010;mammal communities in Yosemite National Park, USA</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>322</volume>:<fpage>261</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18845755</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0040"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Moyer&#x02010;Horner</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M. M.</given-names>
<surname>Smith</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Belt</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2012</year>
<article-title>Citizen science and observer variability during American pika surveys</article-title>. <source>J. Wildl. Manag.</source>
<volume>76</volume>:<fpage>1472</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1479</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0041"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Nagy</surname>, <given-names>K. A</given-names>
</string-name>. <year>1987</year>
<article-title>Field metabolic rate and food requirement scaling in mammals and birds</article-title>. <source>Ecol. Monogr.</source>
<volume>57</volume>:<fpage>112</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>128</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0042"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Parker</surname>, <given-names>K. L.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>P. S.</given-names>
<surname>Barboza</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>M. P.</given-names>
<surname>Gillingham</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2009</year>
<article-title>Nutrition integrates environmental responses of ungulates</article-title>. <source>Funct. Ecol.</source>
<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>57</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>69</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0044"><mixed-citation publication-type="miscellaneous">
<string-name>
<surname>Porter</surname>, <given-names>W. P.</given-names>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>J. W.</given-names>
<surname>Mitchell</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2006</year>
<article-title>Method and system for calculating the spatial&#x02010;temporal effects of climate and other environmental conditions on animals</article-title>. Google Patents.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0045"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Potter</surname>, <given-names>K. A.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
<surname>Arthur Woods</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Pincebourde</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2013</year>
<article-title>Microclimatic challenges in global change biology</article-title>. <source>Glob. Change Biol.</source>
<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>2932</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2939</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0046"><mixed-citation publication-type="miscellaneous">
<string-name>
<surname>Ray</surname>, <given-names>A. J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J. J.</given-names>
<surname>Barsugli</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
<surname>Wolter</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Eischeid</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2010</year>
<article-title>Rapid&#x02010;response climate assessment to support the FWS status review of the American pika</article-title>. NOAA Earth System Research Laboratory. Retreived March 2011, from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.esrl.noaa.gov/psd/news/2010/020210.html">http://www.esrl.noaa.gov/psd/news/2010/020210.html</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0047"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<string-name>
<surname>Ricklefs</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
<surname>Miller</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2000</year>
<source>Ecology</source>, 4th edn. <publisher-name>WH Freeman &#x00026; Co</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>New York, NY, USA</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0048"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Rodhouse</surname>, <given-names>T. J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>E. A.</given-names>
<surname>Beever</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>L. K.</given-names>
<surname>Garrett</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>K. M.</given-names>
<surname>Irvine</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M. R.</given-names>
<surname>Jeffress</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Munts</surname>
</string-name>, et&#x000a0;al. <year>2010</year>
<article-title>Distribution of American pikas in a low&#x02010;elevation lava landscape: conservation implications from the range periphery</article-title>. <source>J. Mammal.</source>
<volume>91</volume>:<fpage>1287</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1299</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0049"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<string-name>
<surname>Severaid</surname>, <given-names>J. H.</given-names>
</string-name>
<year>1955</year>
<source>The Natural History of the Pikas (mammalian Genus Ochotona) h</source>. <publisher-name>University of California</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Berkeley</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0050"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Simpson</surname>, <given-names>W. G.</given-names>
</string-name>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>American pikas inhabit low&#x02010;elevation sites outside the species' previously described bioclimatic envelope</article-title>. <source>West. North Am. Nat.</source>
<volume>69</volume>:<fpage>243</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>250</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0051"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Sinervo</surname>, <given-names>B.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>F.</given-names>
<surname>Mendez&#x02010;De&#x02010;La&#x02010;Cruz</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>D. B.</given-names>
<surname>Miles</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
<surname>Heulin</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
<surname>Bastiaans</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Villagr&#x000e1;n&#x02010;Santa Cruz</surname>
</string-name>, et&#x000a0;al. <year>2010</year>
<article-title>Erosion of lizard diversity by climate change and altered thermal niches</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>328</volume>:<fpage>894</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>899</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20466932</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0052"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Smith</surname>, <given-names>A. T</given-names>
</string-name>. <year>1974</year>
<article-title>The distribution and dispersal of pikas: influences of behavior and climate</article-title>. <source>Ecology</source>
<volume>55</volume>:<fpage>1368</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1376</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0053"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Smith</surname>, <given-names>A. T.</given-names>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>B. L.</given-names>
<surname>Ivins</surname>
</string-name>. <year>1983</year>
<article-title>Colonization in a pika population: dispersal vs philopatry</article-title>. <source>Behav. Ecol. Sociobiol.</source>
<volume>13</volume>:<fpage>37</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>47</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0054"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Smith</surname>, <given-names>A. T.</given-names>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>J. D.</given-names>
<surname>Nagy</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2015</year>
<article-title>Population resilience in an American pika (<italic>Ochotona princeps</italic>) metapopulation</article-title>. <source>J. Mammal.</source>
<volume>96</volume>:<fpage>394</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>404</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0055"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Smith</surname>, <given-names>A. T.</given-names>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>M. L.</given-names>
<surname>Weston</surname>
</string-name>. <year>1990</year>
<article-title>Ochotona princeps</article-title>. <source>Mamm. Spec.</source>
<volume>352</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0056"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Speakman</surname>, <given-names>J. R.</given-names>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
<surname>Kr&#x000f3;l</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2010</year>
<article-title>Maximal heat dissipation capacity and hyperthermia risk: neglected key factors in the ecology of endotherms</article-title>. <source>J. Anim. Ecol.</source>
<volume>79</volume>:<fpage>726</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>746</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20443992</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0057"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Terrien</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Perret</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>F.</given-names>
<surname>Aujard</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2011</year>
<article-title>Behavioral thermoregulation in mammals: a review</article-title>. <source>Front Biosci.</source>
<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>1428</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1444</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0058"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Thomas</surname>, <given-names>C. D.</given-names>
</string-name>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Climate, climate change and range boundaries</article-title>. <source>Divers. Distrib.</source>
<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>488</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>495</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0059"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Varner</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>M. D.</given-names>
<surname>Dearing</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2014</year>
<article-title>The importance of biologically relevant microclimates in habitat suitability assessments</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e104648</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25115894</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0060"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<string-name>
<surname>Westneat</surname>, <given-names>D.</given-names>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
<surname>Fox</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2010</year>
<source>Evolutionary behavioral ecology</source>. <publisher-name>Oxford Univ. Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>New York, NY, USA</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0061"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Wilkening</surname>, <given-names>J. L.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
<surname>Ray</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>E. A.</given-names>
<surname>Beever</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>P. F.</given-names>
<surname>Brussard</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2011</year>
<article-title>Modeling contemporary range retraction in Great Basin pikas (<italic>Ochotona princeps</italic>) using data on microclimate and microhabitat</article-title>. <source>Quatern. Int.</source>
<volume>235</volume>:<fpage>77</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>88</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece31848-bib-0062"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<string-name>
<surname>Wilkening</surname>, <given-names>J. L.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>C.</given-names>
<surname>Ray</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Varner</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2015</year>
<article-title>Relating sub&#x02010;surface ice features to physiological stress in a climate sensitive mammal, the American Pika (<italic>Ochotona princeps</italic>)</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>e0119327</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25803587</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>