<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>While fluctuations in asynchronous local populations will be cancelled out in large‐scale population sizes, a high level of population synchrony may lead to mass extinctions, for instance under extreme events (Heino, Kaitala, Ranta, &amp; Lindstrom, 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0034" ref-type="ref">1997</xref>). Thus, strong, weather‐driven population synchrony is expected to increase extinction risk at the ‘meta‐population’ or species level (Engen et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0018" ref-type="ref">2002</xref>; Heino et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0034" ref-type="ref">1997</xref>; Ranta, Kaitala, Lindstrom, &amp; Linden, 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0066" ref-type="ref">1995</xref>) under widespread environmental change, such as global warming (Post &amp; Forchhammer, 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0061" ref-type="ref">2002</xref>). However, the observed strength and spatial scale of synchrony in population dynamics is usually much lower than that of climate itself (Sæther et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0070" ref-type="ref">2007</xref>, 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0071" ref-type="ref">2003</xref>; Stenseth et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0075" ref-type="ref">1999</xref>; Walter et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0087" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). A multitude of other drivers, which vary spatially, may also act on population growth rates or the ecological carrying capacity, desynchronizing population dynamics (Engen &amp; Sæther, 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0020" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>). Even the extent to which different populations respond to a specific weather driver often varies locally due, for instance, to habitat heterogeneity (Anders &amp; Post, 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">2006</xref>; Engen &amp; Sæther, 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0020" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>; Post, Brodie, et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0060" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>; Sæther, 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0069" ref-type="ref">1997</xref>). This may lead to uncorrelated dynamics in space that could moderate the effects of common environmental drivers, such as weather and climate, at the level of meta‐population or species (Hilborn, Quinn, Schindler, &amp; Rogers, 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0035" ref-type="ref">2003</xref>), thereby enhancing species persistence (Anders &amp; Post, 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">2006</xref>). Accordingly, to understand climate change effects at large spatial scales, we should assess how spatial heterogeneity in the environment or in the ecological responses averages out the effects of shared climate forcing acting across populations (Post, Forchhammer, et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0063" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>; Sheppard, Bell, Harrington, &amp; Reuman, 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0073" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>).
</p>
