<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Nevertheless, it was found that decreasing concentrate intake would decrease the protozoal population. The number of protozoa was related to level of concentrate feeding with reduction of concentrate leading to decreased protozoal population. Jouany [
 <xref rid="b32-ajas-31-12-1890" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>] reported that dietary factors, such as roughage to concentrate ratio, forage quality and level of feeding influenced protozoal populations. Another experiment using cassava hay as high quality roughage to reduce concentrate supplementation resulted in improved rumen ecology, particularly increased rumen bacterial and decreased protozoal population, which was associated with enhanced feeds digestibility, milk yield and milk components in dairy cows [
 <xref rid="b8-ajas-31-12-1890" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. This agrees with Martinez et al [
 <xref rid="b33-ajas-31-12-1890" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>] who found that in sheep a high ratio of concentrate feeding (30:70, R:C ratio) increased total number of protozoa as compared to a low ratio of concentrate (70:30, R:C ratio). In this case, reducing concentrate supplementation and therefore reducing starch and sugar that are the main feed resources for protozoa resulted in decreased protozoal growth. In addition, the populations of fungi were increased by reducing of concentrate supplementation due to increasing the roughage intake improved growing conditions of fungi. Kamra et al [
 <xref rid="b34-ajas-31-12-1890" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>] reported that the fungal growth was stimulated by the high fiber diets of buffalo when compared to high concentrate diets which rich in non-structural carbohydrates. These numbers of fungi propose to get adhered to the feed particle and related to the digestion efficiency in ruminants [
 <xref rid="b35-ajas-31-12-1890" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>]. Therefore, it could explain why the highest numbers of fungi were associated with the total SG feeding, with better NDF digestibility than an RS/1.0C. The current study revealed that rumen microorganism populations were highly related to nutrient digestibility, which has a significant role in feed degradation in the rumen, particularly bacterial and fungal populations [
 <xref rid="b36-ajas-31-12-1890" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="b37-ajas-31-12-1890" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>]. Moreover, this study suggests that feeding of concentrate supplementation at 0.5% BW with good quality roughage would support efficient rumen fermentation as resulted in the fermentation end-products.
</p>
