<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Spore germination in CCA is sensitive to elevated pCO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> and this sensibility is exacerbated considerably when spores are exposed to higher temperatures, such as those recorded during the austral summer in the southern GBR. We showed that spores incubated under the combination of elevated pCO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> and high temperature exhibited 40% less germination than spores kept under ambient pCO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> and temperature conditions. Although our study is the first to report inhibition of spore germination of coralline algae exposed to these conditions, other marine organisms also show similar responses, at least for elevated pCO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>. For example, the unicellular green alga 
 <italic class="italic">Chlorella</italic> experienced inhibition of cell division when exposed to CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> oversaturation [
 <xref rid="pone.0189122.ref061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">61</xref>]. Multicellular spores of the giant kelp 
 <italic class="italic">Macrocystis</italic> exposed to low pH (7.61) showed a significant reduction of spore germination [
 <xref rid="pone.0189122.ref052" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>]. The mechanisms explaining this decline are poorly understood, but could involve CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> saturation in the boundary layer affecting the transport systems and gas exchange altering cell divisions [
 <xref rid="pone.0189122.ref061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">61</xref>], or an impairment in early calcification processes in CCA. The cellular processes by which elevated temperature exacerbates the negative response of spore germination to high pCO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> are unknown and require experimental examination. Synergistic effects of high pCO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> and high temperature have also been documented in adult CCA populations [
 <xref rid="pone.0189122.ref022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0189122.ref038" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>], coral [
 <xref rid="pone.0189122.ref062" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">62</xref>] and abalone larvae [
 <xref rid="pone.0189122.ref063" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">63</xref>].
</p>
