<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Although we explicitly modelled the distribution of 
 <italic class="italic">Sphagnum</italic> peatlands, the positive relationship between SMD and TDQ is consistent with the pattern of distribution of northern peatlands (see [
 <xref rid="pone.0175978.ref061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">61</xref>]). The lack of correlation between these variables in the whole environmental space but their correlation for peatland records means that they are biologically associated. However, unlike MAT, TDQ is a cross-seasonal variable and is able to capture the short-term climate distribution (dryness) that is more pertinent to the regional (coast versus inland) distributions of 
 <italic class="italic">Sphagnum</italic>. The development and persistence of peatlands are controlled by the balance between precipitation and evaporation, and soil moisture availability in peatlands is determined by water availability or temperature [
 <xref rid="pone.0175978.ref031" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>]. In coastal regions, where precipitation occurs throughout the year, soil moisture is largely driven by precipitation; in continental regions, where the minimum summer temperature is relatively higher, temperature is the primary driver of soil moisture [
 <xref rid="pone.0175978.ref062" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">62</xref>]. Thus, in many of the continental areas where 
 <italic class="italic">Sphagnum</italic> peatlands occur (except those that are fed by perennial lakes), their persistence is likely maintained by the balance between low temperature and precipitation during dry periods, which is not adequately captured within MAP-MAT space. Whereas previous low-resolution models showed blanket distributions of 
 <italic class="italic">Sphagnum</italic> peatland across North America (e.g., [
 <xref rid="pone.0175978.ref034" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>]), our models provide more fine-scale spatial discrimination. MAT and MAP lack discriminative power because climate variables are normally generated from daily temperature and precipitation, which are then processed into calendar months and further as annual variables. This multi-level processing means that annual variables tend to conceal the variability in the climate of many biological systems.
</p>
