<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par17" class="p">Our analysis focused on a single global change factor—intensifying N deposition—due to its clear link to N supply. However, global change factors beyond N deposition such as increasing temperature, changing precipitation, and CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> fertilization could also influence the net CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>–N
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O effect of N-fixing trees. N-fixing trees are projected to increase in abundance due to increasing temperatures
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" class="xref">36</xref>
 </sup>, which would amplify their net CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>–N
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O effect. Additionally, increasing temperatures will increase soil N
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O emission rates
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" class="xref">37</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">38</xref>
 </sup>. N-fixing trees generally have a greater water use efficiency than non-fixing trees
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" class="xref">39</xref>
 </sup>, and are more abundant in arid conditions
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" class="xref">36</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" class="xref">40</xref>
 </sup>, suggesting that changing precipitation could either increase or decrease N-fixing tree abundance and their net CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>–N
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O effect (although forecasted changes in precipitation in the United States and Mexico are projected to have only a minor influence on N-fixing tree abundance
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" class="xref">36</xref>
 </sup>). Additionally, soil moisture strongly controls soil N
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O emission rates
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" class="xref">37</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">38</xref>
 </sup>. CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> fertilization has been suggested to promote N limitation via increased forest growth
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" class="xref">41</xref>
 </sup>, although empirical evidence is mixed
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" class="xref">42</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" class="xref">43</xref>
 </sup>. Intensifying N limitation could promote increasing N fixation rates
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" class="xref">44</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" class="xref">45</xref>
 </sup> and a net CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>–N
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O cooling effect of N-fixing trees relative to non-fixing trees, although this response could be limited by other nutrients
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" class="xref">44</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" class="xref">45</xref>
 </sup>. Our study only addresses intensifying N deposition as it has a direct influence on N limitation, but other global change factors should also be considered for a comprehensive analysis of how N-fixing trees will mitigate or exacerbate climate change.
</p>
