<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="methods" id="s4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec id="s4a" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ethics Statement</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The experiments reported here comply with the current law in The Netherlands and were carried out under licenses of the Animal Ethics Committee of the Royal Netherlands Academy of Arts and Sciences (KNAW; leptin specific licenses: CTE 09.05 &amp; NIOO 10.01; general field work license: NIOO 10.07).</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s4b" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study area and study species</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study consists of two field experiments (2009, 2010) and one experiment with captive female great tits (2010). The field experiments were carried out in the National park ‘De Hoge Veluwe’ (52°02′07″N 5°51′32″E). The study area consists of 171 ha of mixed woodland on poor sandy soils, dominated by oak and pine with about 400 nest boxes. Each year, up to 130 boxes are occupied by great tits, a small (∼18 grams) passerine bird species.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s4c" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Standard field protocol</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nest boxes were checked weekly from the beginning of April to monitor nest building, egg laying and incubation. Nests were visited daily from two days before the expected hatching date to ensure the exact hatching date (date at which at least one chick hatched ( = day 0)). When the nestlings were seven days of age, parents were caught using a spring loaded trap inside the nest box while feeding the nestlings. Parents were ringed with a uniquely numbered aluminium ring as well as with three colour rings coding a unique colour combination. Also, all nestlings were ringed with a uniquely numbered aluminum ring. Nest boxes were checked after fledging to record possible dead nestlings and unhatched eggs.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s4d" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Field experiment – Second broods</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">During the breeding season in 2009, 30 female great tits were caught while feeding nestlings (of 10 days old) using a spring trap inside the nest box (10 females per day on three consecutive days). Each day, five females were assigned to the placebo treatment and five to the leptin treatment. The leptin/placebo was administered in a custom made pellet (Innovative Research of America, Sarasota, Florida, USA; 3 mm in diameter; 16 mg) which continuously released chicken recombinant leptin (provided by A. Gertler, Protein Laboratories Rehovot Ltd., Rehovot, Israel) over a 14 day period. The leptin pellets were made of a matrix (mainly cholesterol) and 500 µg recombinant chicken leptin. As the matrix slowly dissolves leptin is released (about 2 µg per gram body mass per day). The placebo pellets were made of only the matrix and contained no leptin. Pellets (of the 2009 batch) were inserted subcutaneously in the field in the adult female when the nestlings of her first brood were 10 days old (fledging normally occurs at the age of 18 or 19 days).</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">After the implantation event the original box and surrounding nest boxes were checked twice times a week to monitor the initiation of second broods. Incubating females were identified based on their colour combination to ensure it had started a second brood. From then onwards, the protocol was the same as for the first broods.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s4e" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Field experiment – Timing of egg laying</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On March 22
   <span class="sup">nd</span> and 23
   <span class="sup">rd</span> 2010, 37 females great tits were implanted with a leptin or placebo pellet (leptin: 
   <span class="italic">n</span> = 19; placebo: 
   <span class="italic">n</span> = 18; using the 2010 batch of pellets). Their egg laying date was monitored via the standard field protocol.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s4f" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Aviary experiment – Body mass, foraging activity &amp; basal metabolic rate (BMR)</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In 2010, 15 captive female great tits originating from the Hoge Veluwe population were used to study the effect of leptin on body mass, foraging activity and BMR. These females were hand reared in 2009 from 10 days old. Since independence these females were housed indoors in controlled conditions. Females were already ringed with one uniquely numbered aluminum ring and were given a unique combination of two colour rings to make identification on the video possible to score foraging behaviour (see below). From the end of May, all females were housed at the previous location of the Netherlands Institute of Ecology (Heteren, The Netherlands; 51°57′20″N–5°44′34″E) in one large outdoor aviary under natural light and temperature conditions and 
   <span class="italic">ad libitum</span> food and water. Females were randomly assigned to the leptin or placebo treatment or not to be treated (
   <span class="italic">n</span> = 5 for each group). Leptin and placebo pellets (from the 2010 batch) were implanted on June 14
   <span class="sup">th</span>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We measured basal metabolic rate (BMR) in terms of oxygen consumption in an open-circuit respirometer. BMR was measured during three periods: before, during and after the treatment (July 7/6/8, July 18/19/20 and August 2/3/4 respectively; five females per night randomly spread over the treatments). Females were weighed to the nearest 0.1 g using an electronic balance (Sartorius PT 1500, USA) before going into the respirometer chamber. Birds were isolated in five sealed respirometer chambers (0.76 l) and placed in the darkness of a climate cabinet (Sanyo MIR-553, Sanyo E&amp;E Europe BV, Etten-Leur, The Netherlands) at 25°C (i.e. within their thermoneutral zone), always between 11PM and 1130PM. H
   <sub>2</sub>O and CO
   <sub>2</sub> were removed from the inlet air (blown into the respirometer chamber) respectively with Drierite® (6 mesh, Sigma-Aldrich Chemie BV, Zwijndrecht, The Netherlands) and Soda lime ® (Sigma-Aldrich Chemie BV, Zwijndrecht, The Netherlands). Air flow rate was set to 250 ml min
   <span class="sup">−1</span> with flowmeters (Brooks Instrument B.V., Ede, The Netherlands) previously calibrated using a soap bubble method (Bubble-O-Meter, LLC, Dublin, OH, USA). Oxygen content of outlet air was measured every 30 seconds with an oxygen analyser (Servomex 4100, Servomex BV, Zoetemeer, The Netherlands). Oxygen consumption (ml O
   <sub>2</sub> min
   <span class="sup">−1</span>) was calculated as the difference in oxygen concentration between air from the respirometer chambers and reference air from an empty chamber. As only one oxygen analyzer was used, measurements alternated between the five experimental and one reference chamber every 15 minutes. Measurements over the last 5 minutes of each 15 minute period were averaged and the period with the lowest averaged oxygen consumption was used to calculate BMR. The oxygen consumption was converted to metabolic rate (kJ 24 h
   <span class="sup">−1</span>) by assuming an energetic equivalence of 20 kJ L
   <span class="sup">−1</span> O
   <sub>2</sub>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Feeding rates were scored on the same captive female great tits by analyzing video recordings made of the feeding table before, during and after the leptin treatment (respectively July 11
   <span class="sup">th</span>, 16
   <span class="sup">th</span> and August 3
   <span class="sup">rd</span>). On each of the mornings, around 8.30AM, all left-over food of the previous day was removed. Fresh food was presented in a single tray and filmed with a digital video camera (JVC Everio, Germany). Females were identified based on their colour rings. Feeding frequencies for individual females were scored during the first hour after presenting the food. Only visits were food was taken were used in the analyses (541 of 579 visits (93.4%)).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s4g" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistics</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical tests are named in the results. All statistics were done using R version 2.10.1 
   <a rid="pone.0034090-R1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0034090-R1">[49]</a>.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
