<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s1a" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Multiple breeding attempts</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Multiple breeding attempts within the same breeding season is a common reproductive tactic in a variety of taxonomic groups, including birds 
  <a rid="pone.0034090-Verhulst1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0034090-Verhulst1">[2]</a>. In great tits (
  <span class="italic">Parus major</span>), a facultative multiple breeding species, early breeding pairs are more likely to initiate a second clutch 
  <a rid="pone.0034090-Verboven1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0034090-Verboven1">[3]</a>. Second clutches are mostly initiated just before or just after fledging of the first brood. Because the fledged nestlings receive about three weeks of parental care outside the nest box 
  <a rid="pone.0034090-Verhulst2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0034090-Verhulst2">[4]</a>, parental care has to be divided between the first and second brood once a second brood is initiated. Reduced parental care could lead to reduced survival of the first brood fledglings, but total recruitment could increase if fledglings of the second brood recruit in the population. Indeed, experimental removal of second broods in great tits resulted in increased breeding success of recruits of the first brood chicks the year after fledging 
  <a rid="pone.0034090-Verhulst1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0034090-Verhulst1">[2]</a>. Removal of second clutches also showed that female, but not male, survival increased, showing a cost to having multiple breeding attempts 
  <a rid="pone.0034090-Verhulst3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0034090-Verhulst3">[5]</a>, and experimental brood enlargement of the first brood in blue tits (
  <span class="italic">Parus caeruleus</span>) resulted in a reduced probability of initiating a second brood 
  <a rid="pone.0034090-Parejo1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0034090-Parejo1">[6]</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is unknown which cues are used in the decision to initiate a second brood. So far, one study was able to promote second brooding. Lõhmus and Björklund 
  <a rid="pone.0034090-Lhmus1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0034090-Lhmus1">[7]</a> showed, using a leptin manipulation in great tits, that increased perceived body condition at the end of the first brood increased the proportion of second broods. Unfortunately, no fitness effects were recorded.
 </p>
</sec>
