<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s1b" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Timing of reproduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Many bird species time their reproduction in a way that the period of maximum food requirements (feeding nestlings) coincides with the timing of maximum food availability (arthropod food peak). Breeding too late or too early has negative effects in terms of energy expenditure during chick feeding 
  <a rid="pone.0034090-teMarvelde1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0034090-teMarvelde1">[8]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0034090-Thomas1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0034090-Thomas1">[9]</a> and fitness 
  <a rid="pone.0034090-Visser1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0034090-Visser1">[10]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0034090-Nilsson1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0034090-Nilsson1">[11]</a>. In order to match the timing of food availability and food requirements, egg laying has to be initiated weeks before the occurrence of the food peak. Multiple environmental cues are used in the timing of reproduction. Besides photoperiod as initial predictive cue, supplementary cues like temperature are used to time reproduction 
  <a rid="pone.0034090-Wingfield1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0034090-Wingfield1">[12]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0034090-Dawson1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0034090-Dawson1">[14]</a>. In years with high spring temperatures, birds initiate timing of breeding earlier in the season. It could be that temperature in the period before egg laying itself is used as a cue. Alternatively, body condition before egg laying may be used as the cue 
  <a rid="pone.0034090-Schaper1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0034090-Schaper1">[15]</a>. For example, female mallards (
  <span class="italic">Anas platyrhynchos</span>) in good body condition breed earlier compared to females in poor body condition 
  <a rid="pone.0034090-Devries1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0034090-Devries1">[16]</a>. Since food availability and foraging success both increase as temperatures increase in spring 
  <a rid="pone.0034090-Avery1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0034090-Avery1">[17]</a>, it is likely that an increase in body condition is confounded with the increase of temperature. Experimental manipulation of the body condition is needed to study the effects of body condition on timing of reproduction.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Studying the fitness costs of advanced reproduction is particularly interesting in the Hoge Veluwe study population of great tits, because climate change caused the seasonal timing of the phenology of the food peak to shift earlier in the season the last four decades. Great tits have advanced egg laying, but have not advanced adequately to match the shift of their food peak 
  <a rid="pone.0034090-Visser1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0034090-Visser1">[10]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0034090-Visser2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0034090-Visser2">[18]</a>. We have two hypotheses for the lack of shift in timing of breeding. First, it is possible that great tits have not changed the way they use temperature as a cue (‘
  <span class="italic">cue hypothesis</span>’). Temperatures in early spring (the period when great tits have to decide to start laying eggs) have not increased as much as temperatures in late spring (the period which determines the timing of the caterpillar peak). Therefore, the correlation between temperatures in early and late spring have changed. If great tits still use the old rules to predict the timing of the caterpillar food peak using temperatures in early spring temperature, they will start egg laying too late. This hypothesis implies that egg laying could commence earlier, if the rules to predict timing of the food peak change. In this case, an advance of egg laying would lead to an increase in fitness due to the better match with the food peak. An alternative hypothesis as to why great tits lay their eggs too late is that early egg laying is constrained by food availability (‘
  <span class="italic">constraint hypothesis</span>’). Earlier egg laying would result in a higher workload, with likely negative effects of survival 
  <a rid="pone.0034090-Visser3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0034090-Visser3">[19]</a>. In this case, the fitness benefits of a better synchrony between the food peak and the nestlings' nutritional needs do not outweigh the decrease in fitness costs of earlier egg laying. Therefore, if the constraint hypothesis is true, advancing egg laying would lead to a decrease in fitness. Only experimental advancement of timing of reproduction could reveal potential fitness costs of increased energetic costs of early egg laying 
  <a rid="pone.0034090-teMarvelde2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0034090-teMarvelde2">[20]</a> and whether great tits in our study area are maladapted due to climate change 
  <a rid="pone.0034090-Visser4" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0034090-Visser4">[21]</a>. Providing supplementary food could increase body condition and affect timing of reproduction 
  <a rid="pone.0034090-Robb1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0034090-Robb1">[22]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0034090-Nager1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0034090-Nager1">[23]</a>, but this is of limited use when the focus of the study is to measure fitness effects of early reproduction because supplementary food alters the energy balance of adults; birds do not have to work for their food and do not pay the costs of foraging 
  <a rid="pone.0034090-Verhulst4" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0034090-Verhulst4">[24]</a>. Relaxing foraging effort by providing supplementary food before and during egg laying could potentially mask fitness costs of early egg laying on parental survival or fledgling recruitment when carry over effects of increased work load in the early stages of the reproductive cycle exist 
  <a rid="pone.0034090-Visser3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0034090-Visser3">[19]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0034090-Monaghan1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0034090-Monaghan1">[25]</a>. Instead, to measure fitness effects, the perception of body condition should be altered without influencing the food availability. This could be done by experimentally elevating leptin levels (see below).
 </p>
</sec>
