<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sampling and analysis of the femoral gland secretions</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Field-work was carried out between 9:00 a.m. and 2:00 p.m. We captured a total of 30 males, 
  <span class="italic">G. g. eisentrauti</span> (7), 
  <span class="italic">G. g. galloti</span> (7) and 
  <span class="italic">G. g. palmae</span> (7) in April, and 
  <span class="italic">G. g. eisentrauti</span> (5) and 
  <span class="italic">G. g. galloti</span> (4) in December, by using pitfall traps baited with banana and tomato (
  <a rid="ref-59" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-59">Oppliger, Vernet &amp; Baez, 1999</a>). All of the studied lizards were adults (snout-to-vent length range: 
  <span class="italic">G. g. eisentrauti</span>, 92–130 mm; 
  <span class="italic">G. g. galloti</span>, 92–125 mm; 
  <span class="italic">G. g. palmae,</span> 100–120 mm). Traps were hidden next to bushes and rocks to avoid exposure to direct sunlight. We checked traps every 15 min to avoid overheating of captured lizards. Due to the high air temperatures in the islands, lizards were transported within individual cotton bags to a cool room. Ethics clearance and permits for this research were obtained from Cabildo Insular de La Palma (sampling permit: 201302/030-A/OT-098/2013) and Tenerife (13796/JBFT/CPA/AFF 97/13, 2013-00484). We collected femoral glands secretions of males to analyze and describe their chemical composition. Secretions were extracted by gently pressing glands and were introduced in glass vials with glass inserts and teflon-lined stoppers. In order to obtain blank controls, we used the same procedure without collecting secretion. Samples were stored at −20 °C until analyses. Lizards were healthy and we released them within the next 24 h in the same place where they had been captured.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We analyzed secretion using a Finnigan-ThermoQuest Trace 2000 gas chromatograph (GC), fitted with a column (5% diphenyl/95% dimethylsiloxane; Supelco, Equity-5, 30 m length × 0.25 mm ID, 0.25-µm film thickness), and a Finnigan-ThermoQuest Trace mass spectrometer (MS) as a detector. We operated in splitless analysis mode. We analyzed 2 µl of each sample dissolved in 200 µl of n-hexane (99%; obtained from JT Baker, Deventer, The Netherlands). We used helium as the carrier gas during the injection (270 °C) and detection (250 °C) phases with a constant septum purge. The temperature analysis program began at 50 °C isothermal for 10 min, increased to 280 °C at a rate of 5 °C/min, and then isothermal (280 °C) for 20 min. Data recording began 7 min after the separation initiated using the Software XcaliburTM 1.4 (Thermo Fischer Scientific Inc., San Jose, CA, USA). Previous to the analytical process, we examined the repeatability of the GC-MS process with five consecutive injections of a standard compound (heptadecane) made in different days, being the relative standard deviation (RSD) always below 1 for retention times and 10 for peak areas, which ensures the repeatability of the analytical method. Because of the small amount of secretions that we could extract from each individual, samples were analyzed only once, as it is usually done in similar studies (
  <a rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-4">Alberts et al., 1992</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-19" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-19">Escobar, Labra &amp; Niemeyer, 2001</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-38" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-38">Khannoon, 2012</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-66" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-66">Sáiz et al., 2017</a>). Our analyses were focused on the lipophilic fraction of the femoral gland secretions and not in their proteins (
  <a rid="ref-46" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-46">Mangiacotti et al., 2016</a>). Impurities identified in the control vial samples were not considered.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the initial identification of compounds embodied in femoral gland secretions, we used the NIST/EPA/NIH 2002 computerized mass spectral library, through chemicals mass spectra comparison. When possible, identifications were confirmed by comparison of spectra and retention times with those of authentic standards (Sigma-Aldrich Chemical Co, St. Louis, MO, USA). Then, we calculated relative proportions of each compound determined as the percent of the total ion current (TIC) in each sample. For the comparison of overall chemical profiles (i.e., list of the identified compounds and their relative abundance per sample), we corrected the problem of non-independence of proportions using logit transformation of the proportion data by taking the natural logarithm of proportion / (1–proportion) (
  <a rid="ref-1" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-1">Aebischer, Robertson &amp; Kenward, 1993</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
