<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">CRISPR/Cas9 has been extensively carried out for plant genome editing to cope with abiotic and biotic stresses [
 <xref rid="B240-plants-08-00034" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">240</xref>]. A study was conducted to disrupt the gene 
 <italic class="italic">TaERF3</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">TaDREB2</italic> to produce abiotic stress resistance by using the CRISPR genome editing tool [
 <xref rid="B241-plants-08-00034" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">241</xref>]. Similarly, 21 KUP genes have been identified in cassava which were hyper-expressed under abiotic stresses. Differential expression analysis of KUP genes revealed that they induced drought resistance [
 <xref rid="B242-plants-08-00034" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">242</xref>]. For drought tolerance studies MAPKKK genes have been investigated by means of genome-wide analysis [
 <xref rid="B243-plants-08-00034" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">243</xref>]. CRISPR/Cas9 was applied in rice for producing triplet mutants. Genes 
 <italic class="italic">TGW6, GW5,</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">GW2</italic> have a function in regulating the seed size. By mutating this gene, the size of the seed was increased by 30% [
 <xref rid="B244-plants-08-00034" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">244</xref>]. CRISPR technology has been adopted for a mutation in 
 <italic class="italic">Brassica napus</italic> by knocking down the gene 
 <italic class="italic">CLVTA3</italic> which resulted in more seed production. A similar strategy was applied to increase the wheat seed size by knocking down the 
 <italic class="italic">TaGW2</italic> gene which has the ability to limit the seed size to increase [
 <xref rid="B245-plants-08-00034" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">245</xref>]. Without any transformation of a gene, wheat has been developed with a low gluten level by using CRISPR/Cas9 technique [
 <xref rid="B246-plants-08-00034" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">246</xref>]. Wang et al. (2017) studied the protein kinases 3 (
 <italic class="italic">slmapk3</italic>) gene to investigate its regulating mechanism to confer drought resistance in tomato. The CRISPR/Cas9 strategy was used to develop tomato mutant lines which showed a considerably enhanced concentration of proline, malondialdehyde, and H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>. The tomato mutant lines were susceptible to more oxidative stress in drought. The outcomes of this study revealed the importance of the 
 <italic class="italic">SlMAPK3</italic> gene in drought tolerance mechanisms and over-expression of this gene by genetic engineering provide improved drought tolerance [
 <xref rid="B247-plants-08-00034" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">247</xref>]. The 
 <italic class="italic">SlAGL6</italic> gene was knocked down by Klap et al. (2017) by using the CRISPR/Cas9 system to develop parthenocarpic fruits in response to heat stress. The resulting mutated tomato lines were the same as the normal plants having same shape and weight [
 <xref rid="B248-plants-08-00034" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">248</xref>]. Shen et al. (2017) studied japonica rice by knocking out the 
 <italic class="italic">Osann3</italic> gene. CRISPR/Cas9 technology was applied for mutant rice lines, resulting in the enhancement of tolerance under cold stress. This study showed the ability of the 
 <italic class="italic">OsANN3</italic> gene in cold tolerance and that it could be a potential gene for transgenic rice with increased cold tolerance [
 <xref rid="B249-plants-08-00034" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">249</xref>]. Herbicide tolerance was developed by knocking down 
 <italic class="italic">PmCDA1</italic> gene in mutant rice lines with the help of CRISPR/Cas9 [
 <xref rid="B250-plants-08-00034" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">250</xref>]. 
</p>
