<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We analyzed the effect of contemporary (plant, soil, current climate, and geographic distance) and paleoclimatic environmental factors on the richness and composition of total soil fungi and the various functional groups in temperate, tropic–subtropical, and all forest ecosystems. All statistical analyses were carried out in R version 3.3.1 (R Development Core Team, 
 <xref rid="ece35247-bib-0070" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>). The 
 <italic class="italic">p</italic>‐values were corrected using the Bonferroni method (
 <italic class="italic">p</italic>
 <sub class="sub">adj</sub>). To reduce the ten measured soil variables to a convenient number, principal component (PC) analysis was applied, using the rda function in the VEGAN package (Oksanen et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35247-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>). The first four soil PCs (largely reflecting variables of each PC in parentheses) explained 86.8% of the total variation of soil variables: PC1 (total P, C: P ratio, N: P ratio, total Ca, total Mg, and pH) 47.5%, PC2 (total C and C: N ratio) 19.7%, PC3 (total N and PSD) 10.3%, and PC4 (N: P ratio) 9.3% (Table 
 <xref rid="ece35247-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S3</xref>). The spatial principal coordinate of neighbor matrices (PCNM) vectors with positive eigenvalues were obtained based on the transformation of geographic distance (latitude and longitude) using the PCNM command in the PCNM package (Dray, Legendre, &amp; Peres‐Neto, 
 <xref rid="ece35247-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>). Rarefaction curves of the observed fungal OTUs were calculated in each plot (including 20 quadrats), using the specaccum function in the VEGAN package (Oksanen et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35247-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>). In order to estimate the importance of paleoclimatic (MAT velocity, MAP velocity, MAT anomaly, and MAP anomaly) and contemporary environmental (species richness and basal area of total, EM and non‐EM plants, soil PC1–PC4, MAP, MAT, spatial PCNM vectors, and altitude) variables to fungal richness, we conducted random forest models analysis using the randomforest package (Liaw &amp; Wiener, 
 <xref rid="ece35247-bib-0051" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2002</xref>). We also assessed the significance of both the model and each predictor with the rfutilities (Evans &amp; Murphy, 
 <xref rid="ece35247-bib-0030" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>) and rfpermute (Archer, 
 <xref rid="ece35247-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>) packages, respectively. To quantify the effects of paleoclimatic, contemporary environmental variables, and their interactions on richness of total soil fungi and the various functional groups, we employed linear mixed‐effects models to control for the random effect of sites, using the LME4 package (De Boeck et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35247-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>). Given the large number of potential predictor variables relative to the number of sites, we employed forward stepwise model selection to obtain a reduced model.
</p>
