<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Pairwise modified Raup‐Crick dissimilarity matrices were calculated to depict the community compositions that were independent of the variation in richness of fungi and plants (Chase, Kraft, Smith, Vellend, &amp; Inouye, 
 <xref rid="ece35247-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>). Pairwise Euclidean dissimilarity matrices were calculated for the plant (species richness and basal area of total, EM and non‐EM plants), spatial (altitude and geographic distance), soil (PC1‒PC4), current climatic (MAP and MAT), and paleoclimatic (MAT velocity, MAP velocity, MAT anomaly, and MAP anomaly) variables. The fungal and plant dissimilarity matrices were subjected to principal coordinate (PCo) analysis using the cmdscale command in the VEGAN package (Oksanen et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35247-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>). We selected the PCo vectors that could cumulatively explain 100% of the variation of the fungal and plant dissimilarity matrices for variation partitioning (Gower, 
 <xref rid="ece35247-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1966</xref>; Legendre &amp; Anderson, 
 <xref rid="ece35247-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1999</xref>). The variations of total composition of soil fungi and the various functional groups (PCo vectors) were partitioned among the plant, soil, current climatic, paleoclimatic, and spatial (altitude and PCNM vectors) variables using the varpart command in the VEGAN package (Oksanen et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35247-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>). The variables within each category were forward‐selected using the forward.sel command in the PACKFOR package (Dray, Legendre, &amp; Blanchet, 
 <xref rid="ece35247-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>), then subjected to variation partitioning (Legendre &amp; Legendre, 
 <xref rid="ece35247-bib-0050" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). In addition, permutational multivariate analysis of variance (PerMANOVA) using the adonis command in the VEGAN package (Oksanen et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35247-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>) was performed to disentangle the relative effect of paleoclimate, plant, current climate, soil, space (altitude and PCNM vectors), and their interactions between these variables on total soil fungi and the various functional groups.
</p>
