<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece34460-sec-0013" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.2</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">BR of tropical passerines suggest diet‐mediated stress responses</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">BR variation may be influenced by phylogenetic or biogeographic inertia like some other traits have been shown to be (e.g., Blomberg &amp; Garland, 
  <a rid="ece34460-bib-0005" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34460-bib-0005">2002</a>), so that certain species might show unusually high or low BR. Yet, we controlled our analysis for phylogenetic relatedness and found that herbivores showed higher BR at handling than omnivores. We found support, therefore, for the “diet‐mediated acute stress response hypothesis.” Previous research has shown that the strongest long‐term declines in response to fragmentation of natural habitats mainly corresponded to insectivores and large frugivores, while plant seed‐eating species show higher resilience to anthropogenic disturbance than other guilds (Bregman, Sekercioglu, &amp; Tobias, 
  <a rid="ece34460-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34460-bib-0010">2014</a>; Bregman et al., 
  <a rid="ece34460-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34460-bib-0009">2016</a>). On the other hand, another study has shown that nectarivores and plant seed eaters seem to be particularly constrained in tropical agrosystems (Tscharntke et al., 
  <a rid="ece34460-bib-0064" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34460-bib-0064">2008</a>). Our results support the view that plant seed‐eating species may cope with these disturbances by displaying increased stress responses, which may facilitate their persistence in anthropogenic habitats.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On the other hand, while increased BR may evidently signal increased stress, they could also be seen as a condition 
  <span class="italic">sine qua non</span> to thrive for certain species. In other words, for certain guilds or species, displaying marked acute stress responses could be necessary to thrive in these environments. However, the lack of changes in BR at handling of an herbivore species (scaly‐breasted munia) in response to increasing urbanization also suggests that this pattern may be intrinsically linked to herbivore ecology, rather than being a specific response to anthropogenic disturbance. Finally, decreased stress responses may be apparent in species particularly well suited to live in rural or urban areas (Partecke, Schwabl, &amp; Gwinner, 
  <a rid="ece34460-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34460-bib-0047">2006</a>). Yet, our results do not support this has happened in the bird communities we studied. We may just speculate that relatively low BR of omnivores in this area may be linked to a broader environmental tolerance than more specialized guilds (Bonier et al., 
  <a rid="ece34460-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34460-bib-0007">2007</a>; Devictor, Julliard, &amp; Jiguet, 
  <a rid="ece34460-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34460-bib-0019">2008</a>; but see Attum, Eason, Cobbs, &amp; Baha El Din, 
  <a rid="ece34460-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34460-bib-0003">2006</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Finally, urban individuals may show behavioral differences with nonurban individuals (i.e., bold personality, reduced antipredator behavior, and decreased fear to humans) (Charmantier et al., 
  <a rid="ece34460-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34460-bib-0014">2017</a>; Griffin et al., 
  <a rid="ece34460-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34460-bib-0024">2017</a>; Lapiedra, Chejanovski, &amp; Kolbe, 
  <a rid="ece34460-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34460-bib-0035">2017</a>; Samia, Nakagawa, Nomura, Rangel, &amp; Blumstein, 
  <a rid="ece34460-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34460-bib-0053">2015</a>; Sepp et al., 
  <a rid="ece34460-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34460-bib-0055">2018</a>; Sol et al., 
  <a rid="ece34460-bib-0058" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34460-bib-0058">2018</a>; see also Atwell et al., 
  <a rid="ece34460-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34460-bib-0004">2012</a>). However, we found no support to the “habituation‐induced stress response hypothesis.” Species inhabiting natural, rural, and urban locations, and individuals of the same species in rural and urban locations, showed similar BR at handling.
 </p>
</sec>
