<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">It is important to mention other approaches such as potential growth surfaces (PGS), climate envelops (CE), and plant-hardiness zones (PHZ) applied to study forest response to climate change [
 <xref rid="pone.0132066.ref060" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">60</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0132066.ref064" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">64</xref>]. These approaches mostly describe species response to climatic variables and ignore biotic factors critical to tree growth, such as inter- and intra-specific competition [
 <xref rid="pone.0132066.ref060" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">60</xref>]. Biotic factors may not be so important for studies at larger spatial scales, such as landscape or biomes, but they are particularly vital for stand- and regional-scale studies [
 <xref rid="pone.0132066.ref063" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">63</xref>]. In addition, PGS, CE, and PHZ are developed for discrete time intervals, taking into account 30-year climate normals and their modification under projected climate change [
 <xref rid="pone.0132066.ref060" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">60</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0132066.ref064" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">64</xref>]. Therefore, the inferences drawn based on these approaches are for certain time-periods assuming step-wise changes. However, as climate change is a gradual process, information about successional pathways that present-day forests are expected to take during the transition period is greatly desirable [
 <xref rid="pone.0132066.ref065" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">65</xref>]. Furthermore, PHZs define the climate ranges (mainly as a function of temperature) where certain plant species can survive based on species geographic presence-absence [
 <xref rid="pone.0132066.ref066" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">66</xref>]. PHZs are developed based on species existence and are not true illustrations of species-growth behaviour. Species can survive within defined PHZ ranges, but may not achieve optimal or even normal growth. Numerous researchers have suggested the importance of finding ways to combine empirical and process-based approaches in the development of hybrid models to address forest-growth response with climate change [e.g., 10,16]. In this study, we introduced a modelling approach to improve the scope of current G&amp;Y models by using knowledge acquired with process-based models [
 <xref rid="pone.0132066.ref015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>].
</p>
