<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="ece35817-abs-0001">
 <title>Abstract</title>
 <sec id="ece35817-sec-0001">
  <title>Aim</title>
  <p>Dryland ecosystems are exceedingly sensitive to climate change. Desertification induced by both climate changes and human activities seriously threatens dryland vegetation. However, the impact of climate change on distribution of dryland plant species has not been well documented. Here, we studied the potential distribution of four representative dryland plant species (
   <italic>Haloxylon ammodendron</italic>, 
   <italic>Anabasis aphylla</italic>, 
   <italic>Calligonum mongolicum</italic>, and 
   <italic>Populus euphratica</italic>) under current and future climate scenarios in a temperate desert region, aiming to improve our understanding of the responses of dryland plant species to climate change and provide guidance for dryland conservation and afforestation.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece35817-sec-0002">
  <title>Location</title>
  <p>Junggar Basin, a large desert region in northwestern China.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece35817-sec-0003">
  <title>Methods</title>
  <p>Occurrence data of the studied species were collected from an extensive field investigation of 2,516 sampling sites in the Junggar Basin. Ensemble species distribution models using 10 algorithms were developed and used to predict the potential distribution of each studied species under current and future climate scenarios.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece35817-sec-0004">
  <title>Result</title>
  <p>
   <italic>Haloxylon ammodendron</italic> and 
   <italic>A. aphylla</italic> were likely to lose most of their current suitable habitats under future climate scenarios, while 
   <italic>C. mongolicum</italic> and 
   <italic>P. euphratica</italic> were likely to expand their ranges or remain relatively stationary. Variable importance evaluation showed that the most important climate variables influencing species distribution differed across the studied species. These results may be explained by the different ecophysiological characteristics and adaptation strategies to the environment of the four studied species.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece35817-sec-0005">
  <title>Main conclusions</title>
  <p>We explored the responses of the representative dryland plant species to climate change in the Junggar Basin in northwestern China. The different changes in suitability of different species imply that policymakers may need to reconsider the selection and combination of the afforestation species used in this area. This study can provide valuable reference for the management and conservation of dryland ecosystems under future climate change scenarios.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
