<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Besides the advantages mentioned above, there are also several limitations that should be well studied in the future. One is that Relative Sensitivity is now designed for only one climate variable. In fact, changes in multiple climate variables could affect infectious diseases simultaneously. This issue should be well addressed in the future. Fortunately, Relative Sensitivity could be easily expanded to multiple climate variables, since the hypothesis test and linear regression model, as two crucial steps for Relative Sensitivity, for multiple variables have been well established. In addition, the current definition of Relative Sensitivity is the absolute value of differences between exposure and non-exposure groups, which loses the direction of changes of the infectious diseases caused by climate change. Thus, an improved version of Relative Sensitivity should be developed by considering both the magnitude and direction of relative sensitivity caused by climate change. Additionally, the Relative Sensitivity does not consider the temporal autocorrelation in incidence data. There are several reasons that might lead to temporal autocorrelation in incidence data. One reason is that there might be a time gap between getting infected and showing symptoms, which varies for different diseases. For diseases with long time gaps, the disease incidence for one month might be the result from infections during previous months. However, temporal autocorrelation caused by this could be partially avoided by using prior knowledge about specific diseases in epidemiology, such as applying lag days between getting infected and showing symptoms (or reporting incidence) to artificially match incidence data with climate variables of preceding months. Another reason for temporal autocorrelation is that high incidence in one month might increase transmission potential in subsequent months. This factor is difficult to address by statistical methods, since it is impossible to quantify this transmission potential using monthly aggregated incidence data. In order to quantify this influence, a dynamic model characterizing transmission process might be helpful. In further studies, combining transmission dynamic modeling and statistical approaches might be a potential way to address this issue.</p>
