<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0025" class="p">Looming over smallholder producers in sub-Saharan Africa (SSA) are constellations of climate change and ambitious development interventions that aim to enhance agricultural productivity as a way to end hunger and stimulate economic growth. Climate change models predict increased temperatures and erratic rainfall patterns that will likely challenge current modes of production and exacerbate food insecurity across the region (
 <xref rid="b0355" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Niang et al., 2014</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0340" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Muller et al., 2011</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0420" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Schmidhuber and Tubiello, 2007</xref>). A recent report by the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) notes that the 1.5 degree Celcius increase in mean global temperature expected by 2030 will severely impact rural livelihoods and human health in SSA (
 <xref rid="b9000" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hoegh-Guldberg et al., 2018</xref>). Meanwhile, development efforts in SSA have re-centered on smallholder agriculture as an engine of economic growth. Large-scale agricultural intensification schemes have proliferated across SSA over the past decade in effort to close crop ‘yield gaps’ (
 <xref rid="b0295" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lobell, Cassman, &amp; Field, 2009</xref>) and catalyze a ‘Green Revolution for Africa’ (
 <xref rid="b0490" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">United Nations, 2004</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0515" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">World Bank, 2007</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0120" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Diao et al., 2010</xref>). Within this context of rapid social-environmental change, smallholders (those with limited resources relative to other farmers)—already seen as among the most vulnerable to climatic variability and uncertainty (
 <xref rid="b0325" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Morton, 2007</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0380" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Oppenheimer et al., 2014</xref>)—will likely need to adapt livelihood portfolios and land use systems to ensure food security in the short term and equitable and sustainable growth and poverty reduction in the medium and longer term (
 <xref rid="b0415" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Rosenzweig et al., 2014</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0460" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Smith et al., 2014</xref>). This confluence of development transitions and climate change necessitates in-depth empirical studies that examine the mechanisms by which smallholders manage and adapt to multiple intersecting risks (
 <xref rid="b0020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Agrawal and Lemos, 2015</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0060" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Burnham and Ma, 2016</xref>). In particular, research is needed on how agricultural intensification policies enable and/or constrain smallholders from adapting to climate change (
 <xref rid="b0270" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lal et al., 2015</xref>).
</p>
