<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0030" class="p">Smallholder vulnerability to climate change is shaped by interacting environmental, social, political, and economic processes operating at multiple scales (
 <xref rid="b0130" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Eakin, 2005</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0305" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">McCubbin et al., 2015</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0370" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Nyantakyi-Frimpong and Bezner-Kerr, 2015</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0375" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">O'Brien and Leichenko, 2000</xref>). These multidimensional stressors and risks influence adaptation decisions (
 <xref rid="b0025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bassett and Koné, 2017</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0200" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Forsyth and Evans, 2013</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0310" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">McDowell and Hess, 2012</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0315" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Milman and Arsano, 2014</xref>). Recent work has shown how local institutions—formal and informal rules and norms—can mediate these decisions (
 <xref rid="b0015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Agrawal, 2010</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0445" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Shinn, 2016</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0500" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Wang et al., 2013</xref>). However, much uncertainty remains concerning smallholders’ current and future mechanisms of adaptation and how these strategies may shift in response to climate change interventions and development policies (
 <xref rid="b0060" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Burnham &amp; Ma, 2016</xref>). Conceptual and empirical work clarifying linkages between development policies and smallholder capacities to adapt to socio-environmental change is particularly limited (
 <xref rid="b0140" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Eakin and Lemos, 2010</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0290" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lemos et al., 2016</xref>), as is research on how social and political economic relations shape vulnerability to climate change (
 <xref rid="b0485" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Turner, 2016</xref>). As a result, climate risk management is seldom incorporated into development policies, leading to limited effectiveness in equitably addressing adaptation challenges (
 <xref rid="b0020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Agrawal &amp; Lemos, 2015</xref>). This has also meant little opportunity to address uneven power relations and social inequalities that may be at the root of these vulnerabilities (
 <xref rid="b0030" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bassett and Fogelman, 2013</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0410" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ribot, 2011</xref>).
</p>
