<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate change is a matter of public health</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate change is influencing mortality, injury and morbidity rates of both communicable (such as vector- and waterborne diseases) and non-communicable (such as cardiovascular and respiratory diseases as well as mental health issues) diseases [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The increasing frequency and intensity of extreme weather events due to climate change pose growing risks to human health. Heat-waves were the deadliest extreme climate event in Europe between 1991 and 2015, particularly in southern and western Europe. Several extreme heat-waves have occurred since 2000 (in 2003, 2006, 2007, 2010, 2014, 2015 and 2016) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>]. Exceptionally persistent and high July temperatures in 2018 baked countries across the WHO European Region, including northern Europe and even above the Arctic circle in Lapland, setting the stage for catastrophic forest fires in Greece, for example [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>]. Sweden experienced a large number of wildfires due to a prolonged heatwave in summer 2018, which the Swedish Civil Contingencies Agency considered the most serious in the modern history of the country [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>]. In the summer of 2017, Portugal was severely affected by wildfires, which occurred during a concurrent heatwave and severe drought, killing 65 people [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>]. In Greece, Italy and France, severe alert warning messages were also issued in 2017, indicating that even healthy and active people could suffer from possible negative effects. In Italy, hospital admissions went up by 15% during the heatwave [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>]. The heatwave during the summer of 2003 claimed more than 70,000 lives across mostly western European countries [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>], and in 2010 many eastern European cities recorded extremely high temperatures, particularly in the Russian Federation, where the deaths attributable to these high temperatures were estimated at around 55,000 [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>]. Urban populations are at risk of multiple exposures; for example air pollution also increases the health risks associated with high temperatures [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">High air temperatures can adversely affect food quality during transport, storage and handling. Elevated marine water temperatures accelerate the growth rate of certain pathogens, such as Vibrio species that can cause foodborne outbreaks after eating seafood and wound infections in injured skin exposed to contaminated marine water [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cold spells were the deadliest weather extremes in eastern Europe, with cumulative numbers of deaths of 28 per 1,000,000 people over the whole time period (1991–2015) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>]. Prolonged cold spells affect physiological and pathological health, especially among elderly people and those with respiratory and cardiovascular diseases [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">By the end of the 21st century, two thirds of Europeans could be exposed to weather-related disasters every year, compared with only 5% during the period 1981–2010. Climate change is the dominant driver of the projected trends, accounting for more than 90% of the rise in the risk to humans [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>]. Flood events registered since 1991 have caused the death of more than 2000 people in the WHO European Region, affected 8.7 million others and generated at least 72 billion Euro in losses [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>]. Two thirds of deaths associated with flooding occur from drowning; the rest result from physical trauma, heart attacks, electrocution, carbon monoxide poisoning or fire associated with flooding. Infectious disease vectors such as mosquitoes and rodents may also increase as a result of flooding [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate change is likely to cause changes in ecological systems that will affect the risk of infectious diseases in the WHO European Region through water, food, air, rodents and arthropod vectors [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>]. Waterborne pathogens may be transmitted through two major exposure pathways: drinking water (if water treatment and disinfection are inappropriate) and recreational water use. Heavy precipitation and flooding events can disrupt water treatment and distribution infrastructures, increasing the risk of ingress of faecal pathogens and thus of waterborne outbreaks [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate risks associated with increases in drought frequency and magnitude include impacts on quality and quantity of freshwater resources, including eutrophication and algae blooms, with possible impacts on drinking-water quality. Droughts may also compromise food safety and security and cause mental health effects, vector-borne diseases and injuries due to lower than usual water levels in lakes and rivers that are used for recreation [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>]. Many parts of the Mediterranean region experienced significant drought in 2017, including Italy with the most severe anomalies in annual rainfall 26% below the 1961–1990 average [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>]. Water scarcity is accelerating across the European Region and can pose additional challenges for providing sustainable water and sanitation services. The occurrence of waterborne diseases is related to water quality and may be affected by changes in runoff, seasonality and frequency of extreme events such as heavy rains, floods and droughts [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>]. Areas under high water stress, for example, are estimated to increase from 19% in 2007 to 35% by the 2070s, by which time the number of additional people affected is expected to reach 16 million to 44 million [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
