<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Some of the climatic change in recent years has established new record levels, such as for global and European temperatures, winter Arctic sea ice extent and sea levels [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>]. Climate change is already affecting human health, with increasing exposures and vulnerability recorded worldwide [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Key reports of global and European relevance include the series of government-approved reports from the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC), specifically the special report on the impacts of global warming of 1.5 °C [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>] and its fifth assessment report, which reviewed the evidence on climate change and health and provided summaries for policy-makers [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>]. The health synthesis report aims to summarize the findings of the IPCC special 1.5 report regarding the relationship between climate change and health [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>]. In 2015, the Lancet Commission published the report on climate change and global environmental change [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>]. In 2017, the WHO Regional Office for Europe presented an update on protecting health in Europe from climate change, drawing on the extensive body of new research and evidence [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Health impacts of climate change and variability are being observed: direct impacts result through temperature increases, heat waves, storms, forest fires, floods and droughts. Indirect impacts are mediated through the effects of climate change on biodiversity, vectors distribution, allergens, ecosystems and productive sectors, such as agriculture, water and food supplies.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate change will affect everybody, but vulnerability to weather and climate change depends on people’s level of exposure, their personal characteristics (such as age, education, income and health status) and their access to health services. Elderly people, children, outdoor workers and homeless people are particularly susceptible population groups [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>]. The effects of exposure can be direct or indirect, for example heat spells may directly cause heat stress, dehydration or heat stroke, while the worsening of cardiovascular and respiratory conditions or electrolyte disorders may be indirect consequences [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>]. Climate change affects environmental conditions and social infrastructure, which also determine the health effects, ranging from death to loss of well-being and productivity.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The pathways by which climate change can affect health have been explained in a number of conceptual frameworks [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>]. Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a> presents a combination and adaptation of these frameworks relevant to the WHO European Region [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>].
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Pathways of climate change and health (adapted from WHO Regional Office for Europe [
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>])
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="103_2019_2943_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e303" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The WHO Regional Office for Europe works with the Member States to generate evidence, develop supporting tools and to identify best policy options to minimize the health effects of climate change. The aim of this article is to support the communication and implementation of existing global and regional commitments and priorities to protect health from the adverse effects of climate change.</p>
</sec>
