<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Remote sensing analyses</div>
  <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To determine the area burned each year across the West, we used the MTBS fire perimeter data product that spans the 1984–2015 Landsat record at 30 m spatial resolution
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>
   </span>. Note that not all the 1980s and 1990s fires were mapped in MTBS
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
   </span>, potentially introducing bias in the early part of the trend curve. In addition, we do not consider changes in fire activity prior to 1984 when Landsat 5 measurements began. For fires which occurred in 2016 and 2017 we used the Geospatial Multi-Agency Coordination Group fire perimeter data available online at 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://rmgsc.cr.usgs.gov/outgoing/GeoMAC/historic_fire_data/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://rmgsc.cr.usgs.gov/outgoing/GeoMAC/historic_fire_data/</span>. Here, we defined the western U.S. as the 11 western states of Arizona, California, Colorado, Idaho, Montana, Nevada, New Mexico, Oregon, Utah, Washington, and Wyoming. Within the perimeters of burned areas, we evaluated changes in burned forested area in the seasonal snow zone. Forested area was defined by tree density &gt;20% in the LANDFIRE Existing Vegetation Cover (EVC) product
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>
   </span>. The seasonal snow zone was determined using the MOD10A1 8-day snow-covered area product from MODIS as regions where snow was present in &gt;25% of images centered on January 15 (2000–2017)
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
  <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We evaluated the difference in SDD before and after forest fire for all forests burned between 2004 to 2010 in the western seasonal snow zone included in the MTBS database. The SDD product was developed from 2000 to 2016 Moderate Resolution Imaging Spectroradiometer (MODIS) MOD10A1 daily 500 m snow-cover data
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>
   </span> as the last day snow cover was observed (centered on the first five-day period without snow). To account for year-to-year changes in SDD resulting from meteorologic and geographic variability, we compared the SDD in forested areas inside each burn perimeter (n = 841) with that in a surrounding 2 km buffer. This difference in burned and unburned SDD (dSDD) was computed from 2000 to 2016 for all areas that burned between 2004 and 2010 to obtain at least five pre- and post-fire years. The pre-fire average dSDD was subtracted from each annual value to determine the change in dSDD before and after fire (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>). To account for inter-annual variability in forest cover, climate, and snowfall as well as satellite retrievals, we compared snowmelt in the burned forest to the surrounding unburned forest for 10 years of pre-fire conditions and found essentially no difference. This suggests that this approach to determining changes in SDD was valid, although we acknowledge potential biases in estimating snow cover from satellite imagery
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>
   </span>. All spatial analyses were conducted in ArcInfo 10.4.1
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>
   </span>, and all statistical analyses were conducted in R version 3.3.3
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>
   </span>. Statistical relationships were tested for a significance level of 0.01.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Field sampling</div>
  <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We sampled snow from a chronosequence of seven winter-accessible pine-dominated forests in the western seasonal snow zone that burned severely over 20 km
   <span class="sup">2</span> within the past 15 years. These sites were located in Wyoming, Utah, and Colorado—within the headwaters of the largest volume rivers in the West including the Columbia, Colorado, and Rio Grande Rivers (Supplementary Table 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>). At each research site, we identified three replicate snow sampling locations in high-severity burned forested areas of &gt;1 km
   <span class="sup">2</span> using Landsat-derived delta normalized burn ratio threshold value of &gt;390
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>
   </span>. At each sampling location, we collected a snow-surface sample, a snow-core sample of the entire snowpack, and measured snowpack properties, including snow water equivalent (SWE) and snow depth
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
   </span>. We collected the top 3 cm from a 0.5 m × 1 m plot on the snowpack surface using sterile scoops and Whirl-Pak® bags. Snow samples were kept frozen until analyzed in the laboratory. At each snow sampling location, we measured SWE using a federal snow sampler, and snow depth using a depth probe at nine randomly selected locations within a 50 m radius of each snow sample location to obtain a local average.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Spectral albedo measurements</div>
  <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Prior to chemical and other analyses, we decontaminated the snow samples by removing the outer 1 cm of snow on all sides as well as scraped the tops and bottoms using a pre-cleaned ceramic knife. In our cold laboratory (−15 °C), we measured spectral albedo for each 1 nm band throughout the range from 350 to 2500 nm using an Analytical Spectral Devices® Full-Range Field Spectrometer (ASD-FR) with a contact probe mounted in an opaque Teflon
   <span class="sup">™</span> light exclusion chamber that held the probe 1 mm above the snow sample. We made the spectral albedo measurements relative to a Spectralon® white reference target for every 10 cm section of each snow sample. A spectral correction was applied to the original measurements to correct for the observed offset as a result of an imperfect white reference. We then integrated the spectral albedo measurements across the spectral range and normalized by the illumination spectrum for each snow-surface sample.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec11" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Geochemical analyses</div>
  <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">After sample decontamination and spectral measurements, we divided the snow samples into three subsample sets and stored them in Whirl-Pak bags for subsequent geochemical analysis. To evaluate the mass of small light-absorbing impurities (LAI), including BC and crustal dust, one subsample set was analyzed using a continuous flow analysis system normally used for ice core measurements
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
   </span>. Samples were melted in Whirl-Pak bags, sonicated for 3 min, and transferred into pre-cleaned sample vials. Using an autosampler, samples were pumped through a 20 µm stainless steel filter to remove large particles (to prevent clogging the lines) and then into a low-volume debubbler
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>
   </span>. From the debubbler, samples were split for measurements of BC in the size range 0.09–0.6 µm and insoluble particles used as a proxy for crustal dust in the size range 0.8–10 µm. We measured BC mass concentrations using a Single Particle Soot Photometer® (SP2; Droplet Measurement Technologies). SP2 measurements are based on incandescence. Instrument calibrations were conducted twice daily using three different standard concentrations. From replicate analyses of ice cores and snow samples, typical errors in concentration measurements are &lt;5%
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>–
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>
   </span>. Measurements of insoluble particle mass and size distribution were made using an Abakus® laser-based particle counter that determines semiquantitative, size-resolved particle counts
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>
   </span>. Concentrations from the Abakus measurements were binned into four sizes based on requirements for the radiative transfer model (0.8–1, 1–2.5, 2.5–5, and 5–10 µm).
  </p>
  <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To verify that insoluble particle concentrations from the Abakus measurements were composed largely of crustal dust, we analyzed one subsample set for total concentrations of a broad range of elements
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>
   </span> using inductively coupled plasma mass spectrometry (ICP-MS; Thermo® Element 2). Samples were melted in Whirl-Pak bags and transferred into acid-cleaned sample vials in a class-100 clean room. Samples were then acidified to 1% HNO
   <sub>3</sub> using concentrated ultrapure nitric acid and stored for 3 months
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>
   </span> prior to analysis. Ultrapure nitric acid spiked with indium was used as an external standard and introduced to the sample line just prior to sample injection into the ICP-MS instrument. Rare earth element (Ce, Dy, Gd, Pr) measurements made using the high-resolution ICP-MS confirmed that insoluble particles measured by the Abakus were composed largely of crustal dust (
   <span class="italic">r</span> = 0.68, 
   <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.01).
  </p>
  <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To determine the mass and organic composition by weight of larger impurities (e.g., micro-charcoal or burned woody debris) on the snowpack surface, one subsample set was melted in Whirl-Pak bags and vacuum-filtered using Whatman® GF/F glass fiber filters (average pore space 0.7 µm). Using loss-on-ignition to distinguish organic vs. inorganic debris concentrations on snowpack
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
   </span>, the filters were combusted in a muffle furnace for 2 h at 530 °C and the organic debris calculated as the difference in mass before and after combustion.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec12" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Radiative transfer modeling</div>
  <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To estimate the additional solar energy absorbed by a snowpack as a result of forest fire occurrence and subsequent deposition of LAI, we used BC and dust measurements in conjunction with the SNICAR model
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>
   </span> (available online at 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://snow.engin.umich.edu/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://snow.engin.umich.edu/</span>). SNICAR uses a two-stream radiative transfer solution
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>
   </span> to calculate snow albedo with known concentrations of BC and dust, snow-grain size, and incident-solar-flux characteristics. To isolate the impacts of LAI variability on radiative forcing from geographic location (e.g., slope, aspect, and latitude), we calculated the snow albedo for LAI-impacted and pristine snow using consistent parameters in SNICAR (i.e., direct radiation, effective grain size of 1500 µm, snowpack density of 300 kg m
   <span class="sup">−2</span>, average solar conditions for 15 January at 40°N latitude, including 4.225 MW m
   <span class="sup">−2</span> per day, solar zenith angle of 61°). The largest snow-grain size in SNICAR was selected to represent the isothermal at 0 °C snowpack consistent with field observations. We used optical parameters for hydrophobic BC in SNICAR based on the assumption that the BC was relatively recently emitted and deposited within or a short distance from the burned forest. Because the radiative properties of larger LAI particles (e.g., micro-charcoal, burned woody debris) are not well understood and therefore not included in the SNICAR model, we also used direct spectral albedo measurements to estimate radiative forcing on snow.
  </p>
  <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Post-fire radiative forcing was calculated as the modeled difference in net snowpack shortwave radiation between the dirty (LAI-impacted) snow albedo values (both SNICAR-modeled and directly measured) and an equivalent clean snow albedo (with background levels of LAI concentrations). Background BC concentrations of 1 ng g
   <span class="sup">−1</span> used in clean snow scenarios were derived from BC measurements in snow from the oldest (15-year old) fire, and were similar to pre-industrial background levels of BC in snow measured in ice dated from 1750 to 1850 from the Upper Fremont Glacier, Wyoming
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
   </span>. No background dust concentration was used in the clean snow scenarios because of the broad spatial variability in dust and that dust concentrations at each site were assumed to be unaffected by fire. A burned forest canopy with full snow surface irradiance was used for the LAI-impacted simulations. For the pristine snow simulations, we used an unburned forest canopy with a 60% reduction from full snow surface irradiance
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
   </span>. We assumed that the increase in incoming solar radiation as a result of the more open canopy was constant throughout the 15-year period of our analysis.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec13" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Geospatial analyses</div>
  <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To evaluate temporal variability in the maximum impact of forest fire effects to snowpack across the West for the period 1984–2017, we determined the radiative forcing each year for January 15th which is the average date of maximum North American seasonal snow cover extent
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
   </span>. Post-fire radiative forcing on snow coefficients were developed using a logistical regression of the SNICAR-modeled and measured albedo, and associated post-fire radiative forcing values during the 15 years following fire. The annual total daily post-fire radiative forcing on snow each year was calculated using the SNICAR-modeled and measured radiative forcing coefficients for the 15 years following fire (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>), applied cumulatively for the total forested area burned in seasonal snow (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>) within 15 years following fire. The spatial distribution of the post-fire radiative forcing on snow was evaluated for 2018 by integrating the radiative forcing on snow in forests burned within 15 years for each HUC 6 basin in the American West (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
