<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Forest-fire-related solar forcing on snow</div>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Both SNICAR-modeled and measured albedo were lowest during the first year following fire and increased during the 15-year chronosequence (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>; modeled; 
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.81, 
  <span class="italic">p</span> value &lt; 0.01; measured, 
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.88, 
  <span class="italic">p</span> value &lt; 0.01), from 0.62 to 0.68 and 0.2 to 0.51 for modeled and measured, respectively. We attribute the majority of SNICAR-modeled albedo change to BC concentrations (81% one winter following fire; 59% 15 winters following fire). Measured snow albedo incorporating impacts of both fine-grained (BC and dust) and course-grained (organic and inorganic) impurities showed greater changes than SNICAR-modeled snow albedo that included only fine-grained (BC and dust) impurities (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>). The difference between measured and simulated snow albedo values suggests that, in addition to BC and dust, larger impurities (e.g., micro-charcoal and burned woody debris) also make critical contributions to the snowpack energy balance and ultimately snowmelt.
 </p>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We determined the radiative forcing on snow associated with the SNICAR-modeled and measured albedo values using solar insolation at 40°N latitude on January 15—the day of year corresponding to maximum North American snow-covered area
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
  </span>. Calculated radiative forcing was 32 and 101 Wh m
  <span class="sup">−2</span> during the first winter following forest fire for the SNICAR-modeled and measured albedo values, respectively, declining to 23 and 44 Wh m
  <span class="sup">−2</span> after 15 years (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>). Combining satellite-measured recent increases in annual burned area in forests (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>) with 15-year persistence of post-fire radiative forcing (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>) indicates a 366% recent increase in the extent of western snowpack impacted by post-fire radiative forcing (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>)—from 2.4% in 1999 to 11.2% in 2018. Using the more conservative SNICAR-modeled snow albedo values, total daily post-fire radiative forcing in the West increased 372% from 10.6 × 10
  <span class="sup">3</span> GW in 1999 to 50.0 × 10
  <span class="sup">3</span> GW in 2018. Using measured snow albedo values, total daily post-fire radiative forcing increased 443% from 23.7 × 10
  <span class="sup">3</span> GW in 1999 to 128.7 × 10
  <span class="sup">3</span> GW in 2018. For perspective, the 2018 forcing was 3.6 times the annual energy output of the Grand Coulee Dam (the largest energy producing dam in the U.S.), and sufficient energy to melt 1.4 billion m
  <span class="sup">3</span> (1.1 million acre-feet) of ripe (i.e., isothermal at 0 °C) snowpack. Since 1984, however, 56% of forest area burned in the western seasonal snow zone occurred in the Columbia River Basin, the largest river by volume flowing into the Pacific Ocean from the western hemisphere, and the fourth largest river by volume in the U.S.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>
  </span>. Total daily 2018 post-fire radiative forcing on January 15 across the Columbia River Basin alone was sufficient to melt 0.82 billion m
  <span class="sup">3</span> (0.66 million acre-feet) of ripe snowpack, equivalent to 213% of the daily discharge on 15 January or 0.35% of annual Columbia River discharge (average discharge at Vancouver, WA from 2007 to 2017). Although substantial, these estimates of total post-fire radiative forcing on snow are conservative because they were calculated on January 15 to correspond with maximum snow-cover extent but when insolation is low. The majority of seasonal snow melts later in spring when insolation and thus the magnitude of post-fire radiative forcing are larger.
  <div id="Fig4" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Total daily post-fire radiative forcing on snow (PFRFS) in the western U.S. for 15 January 2018 based on measured albedo values from 2017 chronosequence of burned forests, and change from 1999 through 2018 based on SNICAR-modeled (red dots) and measured (red stars) albedo values (inset). A 372% (modeled) to 443% (measured) increase in post-fire radiative forcing on snow occurred since 1999, and currently over 11% of all forests in the seasonal snow zone are experiencing enhanced radiative forcing due to forest fire occurrence within the last 15 years</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2019_9935_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e596" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
