<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec11" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Geochemical analyses</div>
 <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">After sample decontamination and spectral measurements, we divided the snow samples into three subsample sets and stored them in Whirl-Pak bags for subsequent geochemical analysis. To evaluate the mass of small light-absorbing impurities (LAI), including BC and crustal dust, one subsample set was analyzed using a continuous flow analysis system normally used for ice core measurements
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
  </span>. Samples were melted in Whirl-Pak bags, sonicated for 3 min, and transferred into pre-cleaned sample vials. Using an autosampler, samples were pumped through a 20 µm stainless steel filter to remove large particles (to prevent clogging the lines) and then into a low-volume debubbler
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>
  </span>. From the debubbler, samples were split for measurements of BC in the size range 0.09–0.6 µm and insoluble particles used as a proxy for crustal dust in the size range 0.8–10 µm. We measured BC mass concentrations using a Single Particle Soot Photometer® (SP2; Droplet Measurement Technologies). SP2 measurements are based on incandescence. Instrument calibrations were conducted twice daily using three different standard concentrations. From replicate analyses of ice cores and snow samples, typical errors in concentration measurements are &lt;5%
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>
  </span>. Measurements of insoluble particle mass and size distribution were made using an Abakus® laser-based particle counter that determines semiquantitative, size-resolved particle counts
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>
  </span>. Concentrations from the Abakus measurements were binned into four sizes based on requirements for the radiative transfer model (0.8–1, 1–2.5, 2.5–5, and 5–10 µm).
 </p>
 <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To verify that insoluble particle concentrations from the Abakus measurements were composed largely of crustal dust, we analyzed one subsample set for total concentrations of a broad range of elements
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>
  </span> using inductively coupled plasma mass spectrometry (ICP-MS; Thermo® Element 2). Samples were melted in Whirl-Pak bags and transferred into acid-cleaned sample vials in a class-100 clean room. Samples were then acidified to 1% HNO
  <sub>3</sub> using concentrated ultrapure nitric acid and stored for 3 months
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>
  </span> prior to analysis. Ultrapure nitric acid spiked with indium was used as an external standard and introduced to the sample line just prior to sample injection into the ICP-MS instrument. Rare earth element (Ce, Dy, Gd, Pr) measurements made using the high-resolution ICP-MS confirmed that insoluble particles measured by the Abakus were composed largely of crustal dust (
  <span class="italic">r</span> = 0.68, 
  <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.01).
 </p>
 <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To determine the mass and organic composition by weight of larger impurities (e.g., micro-charcoal or burned woody debris) on the snowpack surface, one subsample set was melted in Whirl-Pak bags and vacuum-filtered using Whatman® GF/F glass fiber filters (average pore space 0.7 µm). Using loss-on-ignition to distinguish organic vs. inorganic debris concentrations on snowpack
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
  </span>, the filters were combusted in a muffle furnace for 2 h at 530 °C and the organic debris calculated as the difference in mass before and after combustion.
 </p>
</sec>
