<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Remote sensing analyses</div>
 <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To determine the area burned each year across the West, we used the MTBS fire perimeter data product that spans the 1984–2015 Landsat record at 30 m spatial resolution
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>
  </span>. Note that not all the 1980s and 1990s fires were mapped in MTBS
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span>, potentially introducing bias in the early part of the trend curve. In addition, we do not consider changes in fire activity prior to 1984 when Landsat 5 measurements began. For fires which occurred in 2016 and 2017 we used the Geospatial Multi-Agency Coordination Group fire perimeter data available online at 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://rmgsc.cr.usgs.gov/outgoing/GeoMAC/historic_fire_data/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://rmgsc.cr.usgs.gov/outgoing/GeoMAC/historic_fire_data/</span>. Here, we defined the western U.S. as the 11 western states of Arizona, California, Colorado, Idaho, Montana, Nevada, New Mexico, Oregon, Utah, Washington, and Wyoming. Within the perimeters of burned areas, we evaluated changes in burned forested area in the seasonal snow zone. Forested area was defined by tree density &gt;20% in the LANDFIRE Existing Vegetation Cover (EVC) product
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>
  </span>. The seasonal snow zone was determined using the MOD10A1 8-day snow-covered area product from MODIS as regions where snow was present in &gt;25% of images centered on January 15 (2000–2017)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We evaluated the difference in SDD before and after forest fire for all forests burned between 2004 to 2010 in the western seasonal snow zone included in the MTBS database. The SDD product was developed from 2000 to 2016 Moderate Resolution Imaging Spectroradiometer (MODIS) MOD10A1 daily 500 m snow-cover data
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>
  </span> as the last day snow cover was observed (centered on the first five-day period without snow). To account for year-to-year changes in SDD resulting from meteorologic and geographic variability, we compared the SDD in forested areas inside each burn perimeter (n = 841) with that in a surrounding 2 km buffer. This difference in burned and unburned SDD (dSDD) was computed from 2000 to 2016 for all areas that burned between 2004 and 2010 to obtain at least five pre- and post-fire years. The pre-fire average dSDD was subtracted from each annual value to determine the change in dSDD before and after fire (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>). To account for inter-annual variability in forest cover, climate, and snowfall as well as satellite retrievals, we compared snowmelt in the burned forest to the surrounding unburned forest for 10 years of pre-fire conditions and found essentially no difference. This suggests that this approach to determining changes in SDD was valid, although we acknowledge potential biases in estimating snow cover from satellite imagery
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>
  </span>. All spatial analyses were conducted in ArcInfo 10.4.1
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>
  </span>, and all statistical analyses were conducted in R version 3.3.3
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>
  </span>. Statistical relationships were tested for a significance level of 0.01.
 </p>
</sec>
