<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Life-history strategies vary among individuals, populations and species as a consequence of natural selection in response to ecological conditions (
  <a rid="ref-57" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-57">Stearns, 1976</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-25" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-25">Hill &amp; Kaplan, 1999</a>). Traditionally, trade-offs between life-history traits (e.g., maturation time, fecundity and body size) are at the core of life-history theory (
  <a rid="ref-57" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-57">Stearns, 1976</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-58" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-58">Stearns, 1989</a>). These trade-offs result in a slow-fast continuum with late maturing, slow growing organisms with a long lifespan and delayed reproduction on the one end and early maturing, fast growing organisms with a short lifespan and precocious reproduction on the other (
  <a rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-48">Réale et al., 2010</a>). Such patterns can result from differential investment in immediate versus future reproductive output as part of alternative life history strategies (
  <a rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-15">Dammhahn et al., 2018</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Recently, the pace-of-life hypothesis was expanded by including suites of coevolving life-history, physiological and behavioral traits (i.e., pace-of-life syndrome hypothesis, POLS) (
  <a rid="ref-51" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-51">Ricklefs &amp; Wikelski, 2002</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-48">Réale et al., 2010</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-2" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-2">Adriaenssens, 2017</a>). Specifically, behavioural and physiological traits that have a functional role in mediating life-history trade-offs were included (e.g., traits related to resource acquisition and risk-taking) (
  <a rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-15">Dammhahn et al., 2018</a>). Fast, ‘proactive’ life styles are expected to be associated with high activity, high boldness and a high metabolism while slow phenotypes exhibit low activity, shyness and a low metabolism (see 
  <a rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-48">Réale et al. (2010)</a> for a full overview). There is some support for this concept at the interspecies, inter-breed and population levels such as in domesticated dogs where variation in personality and life-history is constrained to a continuum between long-living, shy, breeds and more bold breeds with a shorter lifespan (
  <a rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-12">Careau et al., 2010</a>). This trait covariation has been assumed to either reflect a common underlying regulatory mechanism (e.g., pleiotropy) or correlational selection that drives co-evolution of traits by favoring trait combinations with the highest fitness advantage (
  <a rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-48">Réale et al., 2010</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition to stimulating the study of behavioral traits (e.g., spontaneous activity) as essential components of the POLS framework, 
  <a rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-48">Réale et al. (2010)</a> also suggested to apply the POLS to between-individual variation (
  <a rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-13">Careau et al., 2008</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-48">Réale et al., 2010</a>). Despite support for the POLS at higher levels of biological organization (
  <a rid="ref-70" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-70">Wikelski et al., 2003</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-69" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-69">Wiersma et al., 2007</a>), evidence to extend the concept to individual level differences has been mixed (
  <a rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-16">Debecker et al., 2016</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-2" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-2">Adriaenssens, 2017</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-15">Dammhahn et al., 2018</a>). In a recent meta-analysis, 
  <a rid="ref-52" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-52">Royauté et al. (2018)</a> evaluated 179 cases of how POLS applies to the integration of behaviors with physiology and life-history. Overall, this meta-analysis yielded very weak support for POLS, especially for vertebrates. To date, the incidence of POLS is not always fully understood, and it often remains unclear what mechanism underlie covariation patterns at different levels of biological organization (
  <a rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-48">Réale et al., 2010</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-2" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-2">Adriaenssens, 2017</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-15">Dammhahn et al., 2018</a>). The heuristic framework of POLS should be fine-tuned and, to this end, multi-level approaches could further elucidate how life-history variation is generated and maintained. In the current study, natural populations of annual killifish are used to investigate life-history and behavioral (co-)variation at multiple levels of biological organization and to test the idea that activity patterns are an integral component of POLS.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Nothobranchius</span> killifish are interesting model organisms to study the evolution of life-history variation, including variation in behavior (
  <a rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-14">Cellerino, Valenzano &amp; Reichard, 2015</a>). Fish of this African genus have an exceptionally short life cycle as an adaptation to the ephemeral nature of the temporary ponds they inhabit (
  <a rid="ref-45" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-45">Polačik, Blažek &amp; Reichard, 2016</a>). Killifish are limited by the length of the wet phase to complete the aquatic stage of their life cycle and shorter inundation lengths drive selection for fast maturation (
  <a rid="ref-65" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-65">Terzibasi et al., 2008</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-64" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-64">Terzibasi et al., 2013</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-14">Cellerino, Valenzano &amp; Reichard, 2015</a>). Upon maturation, 
  <span class="italic">Nothobranchius</span> species produce drought-resistant eggs that remain dormant in the sediment to bridge dry periods and that hatch at the onset of the rainy season when ponds start to flood (
  <a rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-14">Cellerino, Valenzano &amp; Reichard, 2015</a>). A fraction of these eggs will arrest development and hatch at a later inundation to prevent complete reproductive failure in case of an unsuitable inundation (
  <a rid="ref-44" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-44">Pinceel et al., 2015</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Especially 
  <span class="italic">Nothobranchius furzeri</span> Jubb 1971 (Turquoise killifish) is now a commonly used model in various fields of biological research as it exhibits the shortest captive life span recorded for vertebrates (typically 5–6 months) (
  <a rid="ref-65" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-65">Terzibasi et al., 2008</a>). Although individuals from all known populations have a relatively short lifespan, extensive intrinsic variation in lifespan between populations has been recorded. This variation likely evolved in relation to time stress that is associated with the length of the growing season (i.e., wet phase) of the source habitat, with populations from ponds with a shorter wet phase (in dry regions) exhibiting a shorter lifespan compared to populations from ponds with more relaxed time stress conditions (in more humid regions) (
  <a rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-14">Cellerino, Valenzano &amp; Reichard, 2015</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-10">Blažek et al., 2016</a>). Thus, pond permanence is a major environmental determinant of the lifecycle of killifish (
  <a rid="ref-20" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-20">Grégoir et al., 2017</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-21">Grégoir et al., 2018</a>). In the laboratory, dormant 
  <span class="italic">Nothobranchius</span> eggs can be easily stored and allow for synchronized hatching after a developmental period that can be manipulated in length by the researcher, ranging from 2 weeks to multiple years (
  <a rid="ref-45" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-45">Polačik, Blažek &amp; Reichard, 2016</a>). Next to a short lifespan and fast maturation, 
  <span class="italic">N. furzeri</span> is also a naturally bold species. This is illustrated by its risk-taking behavior in non-novel situations compared to other fish (model) species. Finally, the species is characterized by a clear sexual dichromatism and dimorphism (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1" href="#fig-1">Figs. 1A</a>–
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1" href="#fig-1">1C</a>). Combined, these are desirable characteristics of a model organism for behavioral studies (
  <a rid="ref-45" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-45">Polačik, Blažek &amp; Reichard, 2016</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-66" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-66">Thoré et al., 2018a</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-67" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-67">Thoré et al., 2018b</a>).
 </p>
 <div id="fig-1" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.7717/peerj.7177/fig-1</span>
  <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">
    <span class="italic">Nothobranchius furzeri</span> and the daily schedule during the observation period.
   </div>
   <p>(A, B) Conspicuously colored 
    <span class="italic">N. furzeri</span> males, red and yellow morph respectively, and (C) female 
    <span class="italic">N. furzeri</span>. (photographs by Arnout F. Grégoir). (D) Fish were kept at a 14 h: 10 h day:night regime (light period from 7am–9pm). Red arrows indicate the administration of live food (
    <span class="italic">Chironomus</span> larvae). Shaded boxes indicate the three daily sample bursts. Time of day is indicated for the light period.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="peerj-07-7177-g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although 
  <span class="italic">Nothobranchius</span> species have been proposed as promising model organisms for studying the effects of senescence on the circadian system (
  <a rid="ref-39" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-39">Lucas-Sánchez et al., 2014</a>), variation in diurnal activity changes among individuals and populations remains to be studied. Recently, diurnal variation in activity has been suggested as a novel dimension of animal personality (
  <a rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-4">Alós, Martorell-Barceló &amp; Campos-Candela, 2017</a>). Temporal segregation facilitates the co-existence of competitors or serves as a mechanism of predator avoidance (
  <a rid="ref-32" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-32">Kronfeld-Schor &amp; Dayan, 2003</a>). For instance, Norway rats (
  <span class="italic">Rattus norvegicus</span>) have been found to shift their nocturnal foraging activity to diurnal activity to minimize predation by nocturnal red foxes (
  <span class="italic">Vulpes vulpes</span>) (
  <a rid="ref-19" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-19">Fenn &amp; MacDonald, 1995</a>). Also, 
  <a rid="ref-3" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-3">Alanärä, Burns &amp; Metcalfe (2001)</a> demonstrated that foraging activity of dominant individuals of the brown trout (
  <span class="italic">Salmo trutta</span>) peaks at moments that are optimal to maximize food intake and when predation risks are minimal. In contrast, activity of subordinate individuals peaks at alternate moments to minimize competition with stronger individuals and differences in daily activity patterns increase with an increasing intensity of intraspecific competition. There is growing evidence for the adaptive value of circadian or diurnal activity changes (
  <a rid="ref-72" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-72">Yerushalmi &amp; Green, 2009</a>) and such changes have been shown to impact ecological processes such as predation, foraging efficiency and resource acquisition or competition. Still, intra- and interpopulation variation in activity changes is rarely studied and taken into account in ecology (
  <a rid="ref-46" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-46">Randler, 2014</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-73" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-73">Závorka et al., 2016</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Several researchers have suggested to include diurnal activity as a trait in POLS. Their case is supported by the fact that individuals or populations might differ consistently in diurnal activity change (see 
  <a rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-4">Alós, Martorell-Barceló &amp; Campos-Candela, 2017</a>) and that diurnal activity change is often correlated with life-history traits (
  <a rid="ref-41" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-41">Miyatake, 2017</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-40" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-40">Matsumura, Ryohei &amp; Miyatake, 2019</a>). Furthermore, such changes can impact fitness by mediating, for instance, reproductive success (
  <a rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-7">Beaver et al., 2002</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-72" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-72">Yerushalmi &amp; Green, 2009</a>), Finally, if not a consequence of POLS, consistent individual differences in diurnal activity pattern seem unlikely as it would be more beneficial to adjust activity patterns in response to the situation at hand (indefinite plasticity) or an ‘optimal’ diurnal activity pattern would be universally selected for.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While spontaneous activity and behavioral traits in general have been addressed in literature, most studies are biased towards male animals. Therefore, potential effects of sex on behavioral patterns such as diel rhythmicity are neglected (
  <a rid="ref-33" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-33">Kuljis et al., 2013</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-31" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-31">Krizo &amp; Mintz, 2015</a>). Such effects are likely since a large number of traits are sex dependent including morphology, physiology, life-history (
  <a rid="ref-54" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-54">Shaw, Kokko &amp; Neubert, 2017</a>), mating behavior (
  <a rid="ref-30" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-30">Killen et al., 2015</a>) and ecology (e.g., predation sensitivity) (
  <a rid="ref-23" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-23">Han, Jablonski &amp; Brooks, 2015</a>). Consequently, studies should take into account sex (
  <a rid="ref-8" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-8">Beery &amp; Zucker, 2011</a>). Although males and females typically differ in their energetic investment in different life-history traits and despite well-studied sex-specific differences in life-history strategies, so far sex-specificity of POLS has been largely ignored. This calls for theoretical and empirical studies on sex-specific differences in the POLS framework (
  <a rid="ref-42" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-42">Niemelä et al., 2012</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-16">Debecker et al., 2016</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-15">Dammhahn et al., 2018</a>; but see 
  <a rid="ref-22" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-22">Hämäläinen et al., 2018</a>). According to Bateman’s principle, males are assumed to benefit from allocating more energy to mating rate whereas females allocate more energy to egg production and longevity. 
  <a rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-16">Debecker et al. (2016)</a> applied this principle to damselflies and formulated the expectation that sexes would diverge along a fast-slow continuum, with males and females positioned at the fast and slow side of the spectrum respectively. Given that sex-specific POLS patterns are expected to be ubiquitous, a recent surge of scientific interest has been directed to this issue (
  <a rid="ref-22" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-22">Hämäläinen et al., 2018</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-28" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-28">Immonen et al., 2018</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-63" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-63">Tarka et al., 2018</a>). However, further empirical work to test these predictions is needed (
  <a rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-15">Dammhahn et al., 2018</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-10">Blažek et al. (2016)</a> contrasted two natural populations of 
  <span class="italic">N. furzeri</span> (Nf222 and Nf121, see 
  <a rid="table-1" ref-type="table" href="#table-1">Table 1</a>) and confirmed that the population originating from a more arid region (i.e., short wet phase) had a shorter lifespan compared to the population from a more humid region (i.e., longer wet phase). However, in contrast to predictions of the POLS this was not associated with divergence in growth rate, maturation time and active behavior at the interpopulation level. In the current study, we considered multiple levels of biological organization and investigated whether average activity levels and diurnal changes in activity of 
  <span class="italic">N. furzeri</span> differ among individuals, sexes and populations originating from ponds that differ in pond permanence within the framework of the POLS. For this, we observed activity of a total of 121 
  <span class="italic">N. furzeri</span> male and female individuals from four naturally-derived populations that were selected to cover variation in pond permanence (short-lived ponds vs. long-lived ponds, associated with short fish life expectancy vs. long life expectancy, respectively). In addition, we included the homozygous 
  <span class="italic">N. furzeri</span> laboratory strain (GRZ) as a fifth group to compare this commonly used strain in killifish research with natural populations (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supplemental-information" href="#supplemental-information">Supplemental Information</a>) (
  <a rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-14">Cellerino, Valenzano &amp; Reichard, 2015</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-45" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-45">Polačik, Blažek &amp; Reichard, 2016</a>). By also monitoring juvenile growth rate, maturation time, fecundity and adult body size of individual fish, we were able to assess correlation between life-history and behavior (including diurnal activity change), both at the individual and population level. The potential of diurnal activity change as a candidate-trait for life-history covariation in a POLS framework is explored and discussed.
 </p>
 <div id="table-1" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.7717/peerj.7177/table-1</span>
  <span class="label">Table 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Overview of the studied populations of 
    <span class="italic">N. furzeri</span> and their respective origins.
   </div>
  </div>
  <div class="alternatives">
   <div xlink:href="peerj-07-7177-g004" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <colgroup span="1">
     <col span="1"/>
     <col span="1"/>
     <col span="1"/>
     <col span="1"/>
     <col span="1"/>
     <col span="1"/>
     <col span="1"/>
     <col span="1"/>
     <col span="1"/>
     <col span="1"/>
    </colgroup>
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Population collection code</th>
      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Region</th>
      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Latitude</th>
      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Longitude</th>
      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Altitude (m)</th>
      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Water depth
       <a ref-type="fn" rid="table-1fn" href="#table-1fn">
        <span class="sup">a</span>
       </a> (cm)
      </th>
      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pond size
       <a ref-type="fn" rid="table-1fn" href="#table-1fn">
        <span class="sup">b</span>
       </a> (m
       <span class="sup">2</span>)
      </th>
      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">AAP
       <a ref-type="fn" rid="table-1fn" href="#table-1fn">
        <span class="sup">c</span>
       </a>
      </th>
      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">PET
       <a ref-type="fn" rid="table-1fn" href="#table-1fn">
        <span class="sup">d</span>
       </a>
      </th>
      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aridity index
       <a ref-type="fn" rid="table-1fn" href="#table-1fn">
        <span class="sup">e</span>
       </a>
      </th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NF2</td>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wet</td>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−24.06</td>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.73</td>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">77</td>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">20–60</td>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75–250</td>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">576</td>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,823</td>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3205</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NF121</td>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wet</td>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−24.36</td>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.97</td>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40–70</td>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">900–4,800</td>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">638</td>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,797</td>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3439</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NF222</td>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dry</td>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−21.87</td>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.80</td>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">158</td>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15–50</td>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">40–300</td>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">545</td>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,809</td>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3087</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">NF414</td>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dry</td>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">−22.55</td>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.73</td>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">97</td>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15–40</td>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">375–1,250</td>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">464</td>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1,823</td>
      <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2543</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
  </div>
  <div class="table-wrap-foot">
   <fn id="table-1fn" class="fn" xmlns="">
    <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
     <span class="bold">Notes.</span>
    </p>
   </fn>
   <fn id="table-1fn1" fn-type="other" class="fn" xmlns="">
    <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">NF222 and NF414 originate from the relatively arid region along the Chefu river in central Mozambique, while NF2 and NF121 originate from the humid region along the Limpopo river in southernmost Mozambique.</p>
   </fn>
   <fn id="table-1fn2" fn-type="other" class="fn" xmlns="">
    <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
     <div id="dl1" class="def-list">
      <div class="def-item">
       <span class="term"> AAP</span>
       <div class="def">
        <p>average annual precipitation (mm)</p>
       </div>
      </div>
      <div class="def-item">
       <span class="term"> PET</span>
       <div class="def">
        <p>potential evapotranspiration (mm/month)</p>
       </div>
      </div>
      <div class="def-item">
       <span class="term"> aridity index</span>
       <div class="def">
        <p>degree of water deficiency due to dryness of the climate, calculated as the ratio of average annual precipitation over potential evapotranspiration (a lower index indicates a more arid region)</p>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </p>
   </fn>
   <fn id="table-1fn3" class="fn" xmlns="">
    <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">a,b</span>
    <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Personal communication with Radim Blažek (Institute of Vertebrate Biology, Academy of Sciences of the Czech Republic).</p>
   </fn>
   <fn id="table-1fn4" class="fn" xmlns="">
    <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">c,d,e</span>
    <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data from WorldClim—Global Climate Data (
     <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.worldclim.org" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.worldclim.org</span>).
    </p>
   </fn>
  </div>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We hypothesize that, contrary to populations from long-lived ponds, populations from short-lived ponds, in which pond drying restricts the window for growth and reproduction, show early maturation, precocious reproduction and fast growth supported by a consistently high activity level throughout the day (i.e., fast pace-of-life). We expect these patterns of covariation also to be present among individuals within populations as hypothesized by 
  <a rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-48">Réale et al. (2010)</a>, where individuals are expected to differ in life-history and behavior along a fast-slow pace-of-life continuum. Given the strong sexual dimorphism in both size and coloration, and consistent with the predictions of 
  <a rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-16">Debecker et al. (2016)</a>, we expect to find sex-specific differences in life-history strategy and in behavior, with males and females positioned at the fast and slow end of the pace-of-life continuum, respectively.
 </p>
</sec>
