<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="materials|methods" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Materials and Methods</div>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fish breeding and source habitats</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used a total of five 
   <span class="italic">N. furzeri</span> populations, of which four natural-derived 
   <span class="italic">N. furzeri</span> populations (see 
   <a rid="table-1" ref-type="table" href="#table-1">Table 1</a>) that originate from habitats along an aridity gradient (see 
   <a rid="ref-65" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-65">Terzibasi et al., 2008</a>) (see 
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supplemental-information" href="#supplemental-information">Supplemental Information</a> for results on the homozygous laboratory strain GRZ, 
   <span class="italic">n</span> = 24). Two populations (NF222 and NF414, 
   <span class="italic">n</span> = 28 and 
   <span class="italic">n</span> = 24 respectively) originate from a relatively arid region from central Mozambique where inundations are typically short (i.e., short life expectancy). This is supported by datalogger measurements which were used to estimate pool inundations from 2011 to 2012 (
   <a rid="ref-64" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-64">Terzibasi et al., 2013</a>). The two other populations (NF2 and NF121, 
   <span class="italic">n</span> = 27 and 
   <span class="italic">n</span> = 18 respectively) originate from a more humid region in southern Mozambique, where inundations last longer (i.e., longer life expectancy) (
   <a rid="ref-65" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-65">Terzibasi et al., 2008</a>). From here onwards, these habitats will be referred to as short-lived and long-lived ponds, respectively. All populations were reared for at least three generations under optimal common garden conditions in the lab prior to the start of the experiment.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fish were hatched in 2L tanks by submerging eggs and peat in dechlorinated tap water (7.8 pH, 600µS/cm conductivity) at a temperature of 14 °C—method based on 
   <a rid="ref-45" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-45">Polačik, Blažek &amp; Reichard (2016)</a>. Two days post-hatching, fish larvae were transferred to individual 250 mL glass jars to allow individual monitoring. Starting at an age of four days up until one month, individual fish were housed in 1L plastic, transparent jars after which they were individually transferred to 2L plastic, transparent tanks until the end of the experiment. Each tank was provided with a small piece of filter wool (Belcopet NV, Brugge, Belgium) to sustain necessary microbiota for a good water quality. During the experiment, fish were kept in a climate-controlled room at a constant air temperature of 24 °C (water temperature 21.6 °C ± sd 0.75) and a 14 h: 10 h day:night regime. Twice per week, tanks were cleaned and the water was refreshed to ensure a constant and good water quality. Tanks were repositioned in a random fashion after every cleaning session to prevent site-specific habituation whilst allowing for visual contact between individuals of both sexes.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fish larvae were fed twice a day (8am and 5pm) an 
   <span class="italic">ad libitum</span> quantity of 
   <span class="italic">Artemia fransiscana</span> nauplii (Ocean Nutrition, Essen, Belgium). After three weeks their diet was supplemented with small live 
   <span class="italic">Chironomus</span> larvae (Aquaservice, Antwerp, Belgium). At an age of one month, only live 
   <span class="italic">Chironomus</span> larvae were provided every morning (8am) and evening (8pm) in an 
   <span class="italic">ad libitum</span> quantity to ensure a continuous supply of live food.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Monitoring life-history traits and activity</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Body size was determined at two, 16 and 94 days post-hatching. To this end, individual fish larvae were transferred to a petri dish and photographed from above. Size-calibrated photographs were analyzed using open source image processing software ImageJ 1.50i (
   <a rid="ref-53" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-53">Schneider, Rasband &amp; Eliceiri, 2012</a>). Juvenile growth rate was determined as the difference in body size between the age of two and 16 days while adult body size was approximated as the size at an age of 94 days, at which all fish were sexually mature. Juveniles were checked on a daily basis for any signs of male nuptial coloration. The first day at which these signs appeared was used to score the age of sexual maturity in males. Female maturation time was defined and assessed as the first time an egg was deposited.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Starting at an age of 8 weeks—and for a total of 15 spawning events—breeding pairs were assembled for each population. Males and females were paired (novel partner each spawning event) and placed in 1L plastic jars with sterilized sand as a spawning substrate to allow for egg deposition. Excess males or females were paired with a non-experimental fish of the same age and population. After 1 h of spawning, sand was sieved and the amount of eggs was assessed as a measure for female fecundity. Fish were allowed to spawn two to three times per week (Monday, Wednesday and Friday). During the two-week period when activity data was collected (see below), fish were paired only on Monday and Friday.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">At an age of 90 days, the activity level of each individual was monitored by a single observer (E Thoré) during three daily sample bursts every Wednesday and Thursday in two consecutive weeks (amounting to a total of 12 sample bursts) (fish: 
   <span class="italic">n</span> = 121, total observations: 
   <span class="italic">n</span> = 1,426). Daily sample bursts (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1" href="#fig-1">Fig. 1D</a>) were organized as follows: morning (start at 8h45), afternoon (start at 12 h 45) and evening (start at 16 h 45), each lasting on average 2 h 30 min, during which individuals were repeatedly scanned for 20 consecutive ‘active or passive’ observations. Fish were scored active and assigned a score of ‘1’ when swimming and passive (score of ‘0’) if they remained motionless during the first three seconds after being spotted—method after 
   <a rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-9">Biro &amp; Adriaenssens (2013)</a>. Per sample burst, a total activity score was calculated for each individual by taking the sum of the collected scores (maximum score 20, minimum score 0). During the four observation days, tanks were visually separated from each other by means of plastic opaque dividers to prevent social interaction during the activity assays.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All experiments and methods were approved by the ethical committee of KU Leuven (file number: P070/2016).</p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analyses</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All statistical analyses were conducted in R 3.3.1 (
   <a rid="ref-47" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-47">R Development Core Team, 2008</a>) at a significance level of alpha = 0.05. For all analyses, model assumptions including distributional fit and homogeneity of variances were verified graphically.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Maturation time, juvenile growth, adult body size and peak fecundity (i.e., maximum clutch size per female over the observation period) were analyzed by means of univariate mixed-effect models with Gaussian error distribution using the lme4 package (
   <a rid="ref-6" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-6">Bates et al., 2017</a>). Maturation time was analyzed for males and females separately as maturation time was scored differently between sexes. To improve distributional fit, male maturation time was log-transformed; however, we note that the assumption of residual normality could not be entirely met for male maturation, so results should be interpreted with care. Population type (long-lived, short-lived, inbred) and—identity were added to the model as fixed and random effect respectively. For juvenile growth and adult body size, sex and the interaction of sex with population type were added as additional fixed effects. In addition, analyses of maturation time, juvenile growth and peak fecundity were also run with adult body size as covariate.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fecundity was analyzed using mixed-effects modelling with Poisson distribution (lme4 package). Population type, age and age
   <span class="sup">2</span> (
   <span class="italic">z</span>-transformed) were added as fixed effects to the model since fecundity often increases with age in younger animals and decreases again when animals senesce. Fish and population identity were added to the model as random effects. In addition, an observation-level random effect was modelled to accommodate overdispersion.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Significance of the fixed effect was tested using parametric bootstrapping with 1,000 simulations using the afex package (
   <a rid="ref-56" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-56">Singmann et al., 2017</a>), and post-hoc differences between population types were assessed by means of Tukey-corrected pairwise comparisons using the lsmeans package (
   <a rid="ref-35" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-35">Lenth &amp; Love, 2017</a>). Population-level variation (significance of the random term) was determined by means of log-likelihood ratio tests using the rptR package (
   <a rid="ref-60" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-60">Stoffel, Nakagawa &amp; Schielzeth, 2018</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A multilevel random regression approach (lme4 package) with Gaussian error distribution was adopted to analyze activity data and estimate individual behavioral repeatability, following the method outlined by 
   <a rid="ref-5" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-5">Araya-Ajoy, Mathot &amp; Dingemanse (2015)</a>. Activity level was 
   <span class="italic">Z</span>-transformed and we included a random intercept for population identity, fish identity and the interaction between fish identity and observation day (further on referred to as series), as well as a random slope with respect to moment of day (referring to morning, afternoon and evening, coded as −1, 0 and 1 respectively) at both the fish identity and series hierarchical levels. Covariance between the random intercepts and the slopes of the behavioral reaction norms was allowed. Moment of day (
   <span class="italic">Z</span>-transformed), population type and sex—including their full interaction—were added as fixed effects and also the interaction between moment of day and observation day was added. Slope coefficients of activity during the day for each population and both sexes were calculated using the phia package (
   <a rid="ref-17" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-17">De Rosario-Martinez &amp; Fox, 2015</a>). Significance of the fixed effects was tested using parametric bootstrapping with 1,000 simulations (afex package), and post-hoc differences were assessed using Tukey-corrected pairwise comparisons (lsmeans package). Repeatability of reaction norm intercepts (i.e., individual average activity level) was calculated as the among-individual variance in intercepts divided by the summation of the among-individual variance in intercepts and the within-individual variance in intercepts among series. Repeatability of reaction norm slopes (i.e., individual diurnal activity change) was calculated as the among-individual variance in slopes divided by the summation of the among-individual variance in slopes and the within-individual variance in slopes among series. See 
   <a rid="ref-5" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-5">Araya-Ajoy, Mathot &amp; Dingemanse (2015)</a> for a more elaborate discussion on how to calculate repeatability of reaction norm intercepts and slopes. Parametric bootstrapping with 1,000 iterations was used to obtain the 95% confidence interval for the repeatability estimates to determine if repeatability differs significantly from zero (i.e., when 95% CI does not span zero).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Life-history and activity level correlation at the population level was analyzed for both sexes separately by randomly sampling 70% of the original data per population for a total of 1,000 times, each time calculating the pearson-correlation coefficient between maturation time, juvenile growth rate and adult body size (and total fecundity for females) on the one hand and total activity score (summated across the 12 sample bursts) on the other hand. The result was considered significant if the middle 95% of the distribution excluded zero. At the individual level, correlation patterns between life-history and activity level (approximated by total activity score, summated across the 12 sample bursts; i.e., at the unpartitioned phenotypic level) were assessed by means of pearson-correlation tests for both sexes separately. Correlation between life-history and diurnal activity change (at the individual level trait value, i.e., as individual random slopes with respect to moment of day, extracted as best linear unbiased predictors, BLUPs, from the above mixed model) at the population and individual level was analyzed using a similar approach (pearson-correlation tests). It should be noted that using BLUPs is an anti-conservative approach as this method does not carry forward the inherent error around the predictions of individual-level estimates to the subsequent correlation tests (see 
   <a rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-27">Houslay &amp; Wilson, 2017</a>).This method, however, allows for a uniform testing of life-history and activity correlations of all traits on both the individual and population level.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
