<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec021" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Effects of climate on the present distribution of migratory birds</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Species distribution is shaped by features acting at different scales [
  <a rid="pone.0146958.ref064" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146958.ref064">64</a>]. In the case of migratory birds, distribution results from large-scale geographical and climate processes affecting the historical configuration of migratory routes [
  <a rid="pone.0146958.ref065" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146958.ref065">65</a>] and the local arrangement of individuals according to their particular habitat preferences [
  <a rid="pone.0146958.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146958.ref029">29</a>]. Multi-scale approaches are thus required to detect the contribution of climate versus other features on the distribution of migratory birds [
  <a rid="pone.0146958.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146958.ref023">23</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146958.ref066" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146958.ref066">66</a>]. This has been the aim of the present study in which the distribution of wintering pipits and chiffchaffs has been related to large scale (geography and climate) and local (vegetation cover) predictor variables (
  <a rid="pone.0146958.t001" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0146958.t001">Table 1</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The effect of latitude on bird distribution provided inconclusive results. The meadow pipit was more abundant in the northernmost sectors supporting the predicted effect of the distance to breeding grounds on winter distribution. However, the occupancy of the chiffchaff showed an opposite pattern, perhaps because in this species many individuals winter in the Sahel [
  <a rid="pone.0146958.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146958.ref043">43</a>]. Thus, the study area is not the actual southern border of its wintering area. After controlling for the geographical effects, the results supported habitat structure and climate as key players in bird distribution. Woodland cover was related to the occurrence of the chiffchaff (positive) and the meadow pipit (negative). In both cases, abundance was positively related to grass cover. These results are congruent with the habitat preferences of the species since the meadow pipit prefers grass patches in open habitats and the chiffchaff feeds on a broad variety of substrata (included tall grasses) in shrub- and tree-covered habitats [
  <a rid="pone.0146958.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146958.ref042">42</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146958.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146958.ref043">43</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate variables were related to bird distribution supporting the presence of more pipits and chiffchaffs in warmer sectors (
  <a rid="pone.0146958.t001" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0146958.t001">Table 1</a>). Preferences for warmer areas could be explained by the predicted direct effect of low temperatures on thermoregulation costs (see 
  <a rid="sec001" ref-type="sec" href="#sec001">Introduction</a>). In an area dominated by cold mountains and highlands (
  <a rid="pone.0146958.g001" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0146958.g001">Fig 1</a>), where most sectors show mean winter temperatures (mean ± SE: 9.36°C ± 0.18; min-max: -2.2 to 16.7°C; n = 493; see 
  <a rid="sec005" ref-type="sec" href="#sec005">methods</a>) under the usual thermoneutral zone of passerines [
  <a rid="pone.0146958.ref067" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146958.ref067">67</a>], birds may be forced to increase metabolism [
  <a rid="pone.0146958.ref068" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146958.ref068">68</a>] or to leave colder sectors [
  <a rid="pone.0146958.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146958.ref036">36</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146958.ref069" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146958.ref069">69</a>]. In addition to this effect of thermal landscape on bird distribution, meadow pipits were positively related to precipitation. Autumn and winter rains mitigate the effect of summer drought in the Mediterranean and favour primary productivity and food availability for wintering birds [
  <a rid="pone.0146958.ref011" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146958.ref011">11</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0146958.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146958.ref039">39</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146958.ref040" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146958.ref040">40</a>]. This effect could be magnified by the use of ground by the meadow pipits as feeding substratum [
  <a rid="pone.0146958.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146958.ref042">42</a>]. In the Mediterranean region, grass growth and the superficial activity of ground invertebrates are strongly related to the moisture produced by autumn and winter rains on dry ground layers resulting from summer drought [
  <a rid="pone.0146958.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146958.ref038">38</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146958.ref070" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146958.ref070">70</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146958.ref071" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146958.ref071">71</a>]. In this way, more precipitation will result in more suitable food patches for this species [
  <a rid="pone.0146958.ref048" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146958.ref048">48</a>]. Thus, it can be concluded that rain-mediated productivity and thermal landscapes can provide a causal explanation of climate features affecting the distribution of these small passerines in the study area.
 </p>
</sec>
