<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec024" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Prospects</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study suggests five main aspects for consideration in the assessment of the weaknesses and strengths of the resulting patterns. First, it is important to consider the representativeness of the two model species. They are insectivorous and ubiquitous birds similar to many other European partial-migratory passerines [
  <a rid="pone.0146958.ref010" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146958.ref010">10</a>]. However, the alleged ability of pipits and chiffchaffs to track climate change over the study region may not apply to stenotopic species or birds forced to track resources with patchy distribution (e.g. water birds, frugivorous species). Second, it is important to state that these results refer to a scenario in which other features (e.g. vegetation cover and composition, agricultural practices, etc.) will also vary as a response to climate change [
  <a rid="pone.0146958.ref075" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146958.ref075">75</a>]. As a result, climate change could promote synergetic interactions within and among species, evolutionary and ecological processes and human impact that are difficult to predict [
  <a rid="pone.0146958.ref005" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146958.ref005">5</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146958.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146958.ref033">33</a>]. Third, temperature and precipitation appear to be two main drivers of bird distribution because changes in these parameters affect the energy available for birds (see 
  <a rid="sec001" ref-type="sec" href="#sec001">Introduction</a>). Since energy availability has been reported to be a global driver of bird distribution, changes in these variables are probably suitable indicators of changes in other species and regions [
  <a rid="pone.0146958.ref076" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146958.ref076">76</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0146958.ref077" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146958.ref077">77</a>]. Finally, the results highlight the main role of elevation in shaping the retreat of low latitudinal margins of Mediterranean winter ranges of birds reported in this paper. This role of elevation will probably apply in other highlands of the Mediterranean basin (
  <a rid="pone.0146958.g001" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0146958.g001">Fig 1</a>) and the planet where winter conditions for birds can benefit from warming [
  <a rid="pone.0146958.ref067" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146958.ref067">67</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146958.ref070" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146958.ref070">70</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146958.ref078" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146958.ref078">78</a>]. This main role of highlands in reshuffling the wintering ranges of migratory birds in the Mediterranean basin suggests two additional observations: a) Mediterranean highlands are usually reported as refuges for species retreating northwards due to the effect of postglacial warming [
  <a rid="pone.0146958.ref079" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146958.ref079">79</a>]. The results in this paper suggest a similar buffer effect on wintering ranges of migratory birds. The huge expanses of Mediterranean highlands (
  <a rid="pone.0146958.g001" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0146958.g001">Fig 1</a>), usually avoided by many birds in winter [
  <a rid="pone.0146958.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146958.ref039">39</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0146958.ref040" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146958.ref040">40</a>], would progressively increase climate suitability as warming progresses. b) However, this projected climate improvement of highlands will not be sufficient to predict an increase in migratory populations in this wintering region since warming in northern areas may reduce migratory journeys to the south [
  <a rid="pone.0146958.ref003" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146958.ref003">3</a>]. Alternatively, it has been postulated that warming of Mediterranean highlands could exert a positive influence on the size of local bird populations favouring winter residency and enhancing winter survival [
  <a rid="pone.0146958.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146958.ref028">28</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
