<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Malar J</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Malar. J</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Malaria Journal</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1475-2875</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6528306</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">2808</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12936-019-2808-9</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>The current distribution and characterization of the <italic>L1014F</italic> resistance allele of the <italic>kdr</italic> gene in three malaria vectors (<italic>Anopheles gambiae, Anopheles coluzzii, Anopheles arabiensis</italic>) in Benin (West Africa)</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Koukpo</surname><given-names>Come Z.</given-names></name><address><email>zkoukpo@yahoo.fr</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fassinou</surname><given-names>Ars&#x000e8;ne Jacques Y. H.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Oss&#x000e8;</surname><given-names>Razaki A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Agossa</surname><given-names>Fiacre R.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sovi</surname><given-names>Arthur</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sewad&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>Wilfrid T.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Aboubakar</surname><given-names>Sidick</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Assogba</surname><given-names>B&#x000e9;no&#x000ee;t S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Akogbeto</surname><given-names>Martin C.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sezonlin</surname><given-names>Michel</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Cotonou Entomological Research Centre (CREC), Cotonou, Benin </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Laboratory Evolution, Biodiversity of Arthropods and Sanitation, FAST-UAC, Abomey-Calavi, Benin </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>School Doctoral Sciences of Life and Earth, FAST-UAC, Abomey-Calavi, Benin </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>Ecole de Gestion Et D&#x02019;Exploitation Des Syst&#x000e8;mes D&#x02019;Elevage, Universit&#x000e9; Nationale D&#x02019;Agriculture, K&#x000e9;tou, Benin </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0382 0205</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.412037.3</institution-id><institution>Regional Institute of Public Health, </institution><institution>University of Abomey Calavi, </institution></institution-wrap>01BP918 Abomey Calavi, Benin </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>21</day><month>5</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>21</day><month>5</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>18</volume><elocation-id>175</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>22</day><month>2</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>10</day><month>5</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">The fight against malaria faces various biological obstacles, including the resistance of parasites to anti-malarial drugs and the resistance of mosquito vectors to insecticides. The resistance of <italic>Anopheles gambiae </italic>sensu lato (s.l.) to pyrethroids, the only class of insecticides used to impregnate mosquito nets, is known in Benin; the expansion of this resistance is influenced by the existence of gene flow between species, otherwise by the presence or absence of the <italic>kdr</italic> mutation in them. The objective of this study is to determine the spatial distribution of <italic>An. gambiae</italic> and the level of expression of the pyrethroid resistance <italic>kdr</italic> gene in seven agro-ecological zones of Benin.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">The study was conducted in 18 localities belonging to seven agro-ecological zones where environmental parameters varied. The sites represent the main areas of eco-epidemiological malaria in Benin. <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> larvae were collected in natural breeding sites using ladles and dipping method and reared under standard conditions. These larvae were reared under standard conditions of temperature and humidity (26&#x000a0;to 30&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C and 60 to 90%) at the insectarium of the Centre de Recherche Entomologique de Cotonou (CREC). Adult female mosquitoes having emerged are morphologically and molecularly identified. Homozygous resistant (<italic>1014F/1014F</italic>), homozygous sensitive (<italic>1014L/1014L</italic>) and heterozygous (<italic>1014F/1014L</italic>) genotypes of the <italic>L1014F</italic>
<italic>kdr</italic> gene mutation are determined by PCR.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">A total of 677 <italic>An. gambiae</italic> was subjected at the PCR. The results revealed the presence of three vector species of the <italic>An. gambiae</italic> complex, of which 409 <italic>Anopheles coluzzii</italic>, 259 <italic>An.</italic>
<italic>gambiae</italic>, 5 hybrids (<italic>An. coluzzii</italic>/<italic>An. gambiae</italic>) and 4 <italic>Anopheles arabiensis</italic> in the different agro-ecological zones. The four <italic>An. arabiensis</italic> were only found in Dassa, a locality in the cotton zone of central Benin. The frequency of distribution of the <italic>L1014F</italic> allele of the <italic>kdr</italic> gene varies from 84.48 to 100% in <italic>An. gambiae</italic>, from 80 to 100% in <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> and from 0 to 75% in <italic>An. arabiensis</italic> in the different agro-ecological zones. Moreover, a significant difference is generally observed in the distribution of the <italic>L1014F</italic> allele (P&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). By comparing in pairs the distribution frequencies of this allele in the two species by agro-ecological zone, only a significant difference is noted in the central cotton and fishery zones (P&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0496).</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par4">In summary, even if the data are in small portions, the <italic>An</italic>. <italic>Arabiensis</italic> species was found only in central Benin and the <italic>L1014F</italic> allele of the <italic>kdr</italic> gene is widespread and seems to fix in all the species recorded in the different agro-ecological zones. This situation amplifies the problem of resistance, which could eventually be a significant obstacle for the malaria vectors control. Similarly, a study of their genetic structure via the <italic>L1014F</italic> allele is necessary in order to put in place strategies to manage this resistance. These strategies will take into account both the ecology and the genetic diversity of the organisms involved to preserve the effectiveness of pyrethroids, the only insecticides used for the impregnation of mosquito nets.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Malaria</kwd><kwd><italic>kdr</italic></kwd><kwd>Gene flow</kwd><kwd><italic>An. gambiae</italic></kwd><kwd>Pyrethroids</kwd><kwd>Benin</kwd><kwd>West Africa</kwd></kwd-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par9">The malaria control faces various biological obstacles, including the resistance of parasites to anti-malarial drugs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>] and of mosquito vectors to insecticides [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. So far, the fight against this disease is essentially based on chemotherapy targeting the parasite in humans using anti-malarial drugs, as well as actions aiming at simultaneously reducing the human-vector contact, the density and the longevity of <italic>Anopheles</italic> vectors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. As a result of years of efforts to control or even eradicate malaria, it still remains a global public health problem [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>].</p><p id="Par10">In the absence of a vaccine to immunize humans against harmful actions of the pathogen, vector control appears for the moment as the best preventive tool [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Among the different methods that are commonly used are long-lasting insecticidal nets (LLINs) and indoor residual spraying (IRS) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. With the increased use of insecticides from different classes to combat mosquitoes effectively, vector populations resistant to these chemicals have become increasingly important [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. The rationales are to be found in the maintenance of ancestral polymorphism and the vertiginous selection of resistance alleles that are, the most advantageous in the new environment created by the misuse of these insecticides. Indeed, several cases of emergence of vector resistance to insecticides have been described in Eastern [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>] and Western [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>] Africa.</p><p id="Par11">Studies carried out in Burkina Faso [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>], Benin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>] and C&#x000f4;te d'Ivoire [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>] have shown that the frequency of the <italic>L1014F</italic> resistance allele of the <italic>kdr</italic> gene is higher in <italic>Anopheles gambiae </italic>sensu lato (s.l.) in agricultural areas usually treated with insecticides, as compared to rural areas where farmers grow only food or local consumption products. The hypothesis of the contribution of certain agricultural practices to the selection and extension of resistance in vectors cannot be excluded. In the current context where pyrethroids resistance is very widespread in Africa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>], studies on the diversity of this insecticide resistance gene in vector populations are important to improve the control tools used against <italic>An. gambiae,</italic> major vector of malaria.</p><p id="Par12">Globally, the larvae of <italic>An. gambiae</italic> grow in small, shallow, relatively clean and sunny water reservoirs (puddles of water, stagnant water) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. The increasing presence of <italic>An. gambiae</italic> s.l. in ecological sites, which were originally inappropriate and unsuitable for this species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>], leads to believe that this species has developed mechanisms that allow it to adapt to xenobiotics present in these new environments, the said mechanisms being characteristic of the normal biological evolution of these vectors. Clearly, the link between resistance and these new adaptations is still not formally established. Benin is a country of great geographical (climatic, relief) and ecological variability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. It is, therefore, imperative to develop more molecular studies on the vectors that are encountered in order to propose more effective and sustainable control methods that take into account the genetic diversity within the <italic>An. gambiae</italic> complex according to the different ecological and geographical niches. In addition to the fact that the resistance of <italic>An. gambiae</italic> to pyrethroids, the only class of insecticides used for the impregnation of mosquito nets [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>], is known and well documented in Benin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>], the expansion of this genetic and hereditary trait is strongly influenced by the existence of gene flows maintained through migration, preferential mating or inbreeding between different populations of the same species. In view of the dynamics that characterize populations of living organisms, it is important to focus on the biological evolution in time and space of <italic>An. gambiae </italic>sensu stricto (s.s.)<italic>, An. coluzzii</italic> and <italic>An. arabiensis</italic>, three sibling species taken into account in the current study. Thus, we will to study the spatial distribution of these three species and of the resistance allele <italic>L1014F</italic> of the <italic>kdr</italic> gene within them in seven agro-ecological zones in order to better orient the control methods.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Characteristics of the study area</title><p id="Par13">The current study was implemented in Benin, a West African country located in the intertropical zone between the equator and the Tropic of Cancer, more precisely between the parallels 6&#x000b0;30&#x02032;and 12&#x000b0;30&#x02032; of latitude North on the one hand, and the meridian 1&#x000b0; and 3&#x000b0;40&#x02032; East longitude on the other hand. Benin has a subequatorial climate with four seasons (two rainy seasons interspersed by two dry seasons) in the south; a Sudano-Guinean transitional climate with four seasons similar to that of the South in the Centre of the country and, a Sudanese climate with two seasons (a rainy and a dry) in the north [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. The relief of Benin is not very rugged but has a low coastal and sandy region limited by lagoons. It also presents a plateau of ferruginous clay, a silico-clay plateau dotted with some undergrowth [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. In the north-west of the country is the massive Atacora with a height of 800 m and in the north-east, the silico&#x02013;clay fertile plains of Niger [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Benin has a large hydrographic network with two important basins namely: the Niger basin with several tributaries and the coastal basin whose rivers (Ou&#x000e9;m&#x000e9;, Zou, Mono) reach the Atlantic Ocean. Each basin is dotted with small permanent or temporary water bodies that maintain agro-pastoral activities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Overall, eight agro-ecological zones have been defined in Benin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>], namely: the far north zone of Benin (Zone 1), the northern cotton zone of Benin (Zone 2), the food crop production zone of South-Borgou (Zone 3), Western Atacora Zone (Zone 4), Cotton Zone of Centre (Zone 5), bar land Zone (Zone 6), Depression Zone (Zone 7) and Fisheries Zone (Zone 8). Seven of the eight Zones are subject to this study. They are classified on the basis of homogeneity taking into account the consideration of climatic and agro-pedological parameters, cropping systems, population density and vegetation cover [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. In total, eighteen study sites were selected from seven different agro-ecological zones (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Thus, the districts of Dogbo, Hou&#x000e9;yogb&#x000e9;, Toviklin, Bohicon and Porto-Novo have been selected in the bar land Zone. Those of Dassa, Sav&#x000e8;, Ou&#x000e8;ss&#x000e8;, Djidja and K&#x000e9;tou were selected in the cotton zone of central Benin. The districts of Malanville, Kandi and Copargo are, respectively, located in the zones of the far north, Northern cotton and Western Atacora. The districts of Kalal&#x000e9; and P&#x000e9;hunco are considered as being in the food crop production zone of South Borgou, while those of Cotonou, Com&#x000e8; and S&#x000f4;-Ava are in the fishery zone.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1&#x000a0;</label><caption><p>Map of the different agro-ecological zones of Benin with the communes of studies</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="12936_2019_2808_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Sampling and treatment of mosquitoes</title><sec id="Sec53"><title>Larvae collections and mosquito rearing</title><p id="Par14">Larvae collections were conducted in all study sites from May 2015 to December 2017. They are made only during rainy seasons. Larvae of <italic>An. gambiae</italic> were collected from the positive breeding sites encountered using the dipping method. The latter consists in collecting mosquito larvae from the surface of the breeding sites through a ladle. The collected larvae were filtered and kept in labeled jars according to the surveyed sites and then transported to the insectary of the Center for Entomological Research of Cotonou (CREC). These larvae were raised under standard conditions of temperature (27&#x000a0;&#x000b0;C&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2) and humidity (65%&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;10) until adult stage.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec50"><title>Molecular identification and species distribution</title><p id="Par15">Adult female mosquitoes resulting from reared larvae were morphologically identified using morphological identification keys of Gillies and Coetzee [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>] and of, Gillies and De Meillon [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. They are then subjected to the polymerase chain reaction (PCR). Thus, at least 30 mosquitoes were analysed by site. The SINE 200 PCR of Santolamazza et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>] and the PCR protocol of Scott et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>] were carried out for the identification of the species of the <italic>An. gambiae</italic> complex.</p></sec><sec id="Sec51"><title>Determination of the <italic>L1014F</italic> mutation of the <italic>kdr</italic> gene in the three species</title><p id="Par16">The resistant allele <italic>L1014F</italic> of the <italic>kdr</italic> gene was determined according to the protocol of Martinez-Torres et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. This PCR diagnostic test consists in using four oligonucleotides or primers (Agd1, Agd2, Agd3, Agd4) and a Taq polymerase to search by amplification for resistant or susceptible alleles on a DNA fragment coding for the voltage-dependent sodium channel in each tested mosquito. The Agd1/Agd2 primers pair flanks the <italic>kdr</italic> gene by amplifying a 293&#x000a0;bp product as a control. The pair of Agd3/Agd1 primer pairs only with the resistance portion of the <italic>kdr</italic> gene to amplify a 195pb fragment. The Agd4 /Agd2 pair associates only with the portion of the sensitive gene by amplifying a 137&#x000a0;bp fragment. According to the protocol of Martinez-Torres et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>], the nucleotide sequences of these primers are: Agd1: 5&#x02032;-ATAGATTCCCCGACCATG-3&#x02032;; Agd2: 5&#x02032;-ACAAGGATGATGAACC-3&#x02032;; Agd3: 5&#x02032;-AATTTGCATTACTTACGACA-3&#x02032;; Agd4: 5&#x02032;-CTGTAGTGATAGGAAATTTA-3'.</p></sec><sec id="Sec52"><title>Analysis of the geographical distribution of the <italic>L1014F</italic> allele of the <italic>kdr</italic> gene in <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic>, <italic>Anopheles coluzzii</italic> and <italic>Anopheles arabiensis</italic></title><p id="Par17">The frequencies of the <italic>L1014F</italic> allele of the <italic>kdr</italic> gene were determined by agro-ecological zone. They were calculated using the F-statistics formula [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>] of the Genepop software version 4.2. The confidence intervals of the allelic frequencies were calculated using the binomial formula. The proportion test [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>] of the R software, version 3.3.3 was used to compare the distribution of the different species and the of <italic>L1014F</italic> allele frequencies within these species of the various agro-ecological zones. It was therefore assessed whether the species and their resistance allele are distributed in the same way in the different zones.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec10"><title>Molecular identification and distribution of the different species</title><p id="Par18">Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> provides results obtained from the molecular identification of species. After molecular species identification performed on <italic>An.</italic><italic>Gambiae,</italic> the presence of three sibling vector species was revealed. They were distributed in variable proportions with a total of 409 <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> (60.41%&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.68), 259 <italic>An. gambiae </italic>s.s. (38.26%&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.66), 05 hybrids ((0.74%&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.64) <italic>An. coluzzii</italic>/<italic>An. gambiae</italic>) and 04 <italic>An. arabiensis</italic> (0.59%&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.58).<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Distribution frequency and number of <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic>, <italic>Anopheles coluzzii</italic> and <italic>Anopheles arabiensis</italic> in the different agro-ecological zones</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Agro-ecological zones</th><th align="left">Localities</th><th align="left">Geographical coordinates</th><th align="left">Number tested</th><th align="left"><italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> N (%, IC)</th><th align="left"><italic>Anopheles coluzzii</italic> N (%, IC)</th><th align="left"><italic>Hybrides forms</italic> N (%, IC)</th><th align="left"><italic>Anopheles arabiensis</italic> N (%, IC)</th><th align="left"><italic>p-</italic>values</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Far north zone</td><td align="left">Malanville</td><td align="left">11&#x000b0;51&#x02032;48&#x02033;N 3&#x000b0;23&#x02032;3,29&#x02033;E</td><td align="left">30</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">30</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">Total</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">30</td><td align="left">0 (0%)</td><td align="left">30 (100%)</td><td align="left">0 (0%)</td><td align="left">0 (0%)</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Northern cotton zone</td><td align="left">Kandi</td><td align="left">11&#x000b0;7&#x02032;49,869&#x02033;N 2&#x000b0;55&#x02032;57,282&#x02033;E</td><td align="left">30</td><td align="left">29</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">Total</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">30</td><td align="left">29 (96.67&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;6.42)</td><td align="left">1 (3.33&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;6.42)</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">South-Borgou food crop production zone</td><td align="left">Kalal&#x000e9;</td><td align="left">10&#x000b0;17&#x02032;24,469&#x02033;N 3&#x000b0;22&#x02032;54,215&#x02033;E</td><td align="left">30</td><td align="left">30</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">P&#x000e9;hunco</td><td align="left">10&#x000b0;14&#x02032;13,431&#x02033;N 2&#x000b0;0&#x02032;10,209&#x02033;E</td><td align="left">30</td><td align="left">28</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">Total</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">60</td><td align="left">58 (96.67&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.54)</td><td align="left">2 (96.67&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.54)</td><td align="left">0 (0%)</td><td align="left">0 (0%)</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Western Atacora zone</td><td align="left">Copargo</td><td align="left">9&#x000b0;50&#x02032;22,8&#x02033;N 1&#x000b0;32&#x02032;50,995&#x02033;E</td><td align="left">31</td><td align="left">27</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">Total</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">31</td><td align="left">27 (87.10&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;11.80)</td><td align="left">4 (12.90&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;11.80)</td><td align="left">0 (0%)</td><td align="left">0 (0%)</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5">Central cotton zone</td><td align="left">Dassa</td><td align="left">7&#x000b0;47&#x02032;5,671&#x02033;N 2&#x000b0;11&#x02032;674&#x02033;E</td><td align="left">30</td><td align="left">18</td><td align="left">7</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">4</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Sav&#x000e8;</td><td align="left">8&#x000b0;2&#x02032;1&#x02033;N 2&#x000b0;29&#x02032;6&#x02033;E</td><td align="left">30</td><td align="left">11</td><td align="left">19</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Ou&#x000e8;ss&#x000e8;</td><td align="left">8&#x000b0;29&#x02032;465&#x02033;N 2&#x000b0;25&#x02032;24,03&#x02033;E</td><td align="left">30</td><td align="left">23</td><td align="left">7</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">K&#x000e9;tou</td><td align="left">7&#x000b0;21&#x02032;37&#x02033;N 2&#x000b0;36&#x02032;14&#x02033;E</td><td align="left">30</td><td align="left">8</td><td align="left">22</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Djidja</td><td align="left">7&#x000b0;20&#x02032;46&#x02033;N 1&#x000b0;56&#x02032;8&#x02033;E</td><td align="left">30</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">28</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">Total</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">150</td><td align="left">62 (41.33&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;7.88)</td><td align="left">83 (55.33&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;7.96)</td><td align="left">1 (0.67&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.30)</td><td align="left">4 (2.67&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.58)</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="5">Bar land zone</td><td align="left">Bohicon</td><td align="left">7&#x000b0;10&#x02032;48&#x02033;N 2&#x000b0;5&#x02032;12&#x02033;E</td><td align="left">39</td><td align="left">35</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Dogbo</td><td align="left">6&#x000b0;48&#x02032;17&#x02033;N 1&#x000b0;47&#x02032;17&#x02033;E</td><td align="left">39</td><td align="left">12</td><td align="left">27</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Toviklin</td><td align="left">6&#x000b0;56&#x02032;20,73&#x02033;N 1&#x000b0;46&#x02032;24,083&#x02033;E</td><td align="left">30</td><td align="left">6</td><td align="left">24</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Hou&#x000e9;yogb&#x000e9;</td><td align="left">6&#x000b0;31&#x02032;55,83&#x02033;N 1&#x000b0;52&#x02032;15,1&#x02033;E</td><td align="left">30</td><td align="left">18</td><td align="left">12</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Porto-Novo</td><td align="left">6&#x000b0;29&#x02032;47&#x02033;N 2&#x000b0;37&#x02032;44&#x02033;E</td><td align="left">54</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">47</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">Total</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">192</td><td align="left">75 (39.06&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;6.90)</td><td align="left">114 (59.38&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;6.94)</td><td align="left">3 (1.56&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.75)</td><td align="left">0 (0%)</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="3">Fishery zone</td><td align="left">Cotonou</td><td align="left">6&#x000b0;21&#x02032;54&#x02033;N 2&#x000b0;27&#x02032;53&#x02033;E</td><td align="left">102</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">99</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">S&#x000f4;-Ava</td><td align="left">6&#x000b0;27&#x02032;57,687&#x02033;N 2&#x000b0;24&#x02032;4,004&#x02033;E</td><td align="left">50</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">50</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Com&#x000e8;</td><td align="left">6&#x000b0;24&#x02032;34,62&#x02033;N 1&#x000b0;53&#x02032;7,82&#x02033;E</td><td align="left">32</td><td align="left">6</td><td align="left">26</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char"/></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left">Total</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">184</td><td align="left">8 (4.35&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.95)</td><td align="left">175 (95.11&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.12)</td><td align="left">1 (0.54&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.06)</td><td align="left">0 (0%)</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Total</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left">677</td><td align="left">259 (38.26&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.66)</td><td align="left">409 (60.41&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.68)</td><td align="left">5 (0.74&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.64)</td><td align="left">4 (0.59&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;0.58)</td><td char="." align="char">&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par19">Overall, the frequency of distribution ranged from 0 to 96.67% in <italic>An. gambiae </italic>s.s., from 3.33 to 100% in <italic>An. coluzzii</italic>, and from 0 to 2.67% for <italic>An. arabiensis</italic> according to the agro-ecological zones.</p><p id="Par20"><italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> was found in the proportions of 96.67% in the cotton zone of north and food crop production zone of South Borgou and, 87.10%, 41.33%, 4.35% and 39.06% respectively in the Western Atacora, Central Cotton, bar land and fisheries zones. The distribution frequencies of <italic>An. coluzzii</italic>, was 3.33% in the Northern cotton and food crop production zones of South Borgou, 100%, 12.90%, 55.33%, 59.38% and 95.11% respectively in the Far North, Western Atacora, central cotton, bar land and fisheries zones. <italic>Anopheles arabiensis</italic> was absent in the different surveyed zones except for of the central cotton zone where it was 2.67%. A significant difference is noted in the distribution of sibling species within different agro-ecological zones (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001).</p><p id="Par21"><italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> and <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> live in sympatry in six zones except the northern extreme zone. <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> is widespread in northern Benin while, <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> was the major species from Central to South. It is observed that the distribution is more or less homogeneous with characteristic ecological preferences. Thus, <italic>An. gambiae</italic> is more adapted to the ecology of the North with high frequencies in the zones of cotton production of North (96.67%&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;6.42), of food crop production of South Borgou (96.67%&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.54) and Western Atacora (87.10%&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;11.80). <italic>Anopheles coluzzii</italic> prefers the southern zones with high frequencies in the central cotton (55.33%&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;7.96), bar land (59.38%&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;6.94) and fisheries (95.11%&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.12) zones even though we noted its exclusive presence in the far north. <italic>Anopheles arabiensis</italic> was found only in Dassa, the central cotton zone, but with a low number, which may be an ecological indicator.</p></sec><sec id="Sec55"><title>Distribution of the frequency of the <italic>L1014F kdr</italic> mutation in <italic>An. coluzzii</italic>, <italic>An. gambiae</italic> and <italic>An. arabiensis</italic></title><p id="Par22">Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> presents the frequency distribution of the <italic>L1014F</italic> resistant allele of the <italic>kdr</italic> gene in <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> and <italic>An. gambiae </italic>s.s. in the different surveyed agro-ecological zones. Overall, the frequency of the <italic>L1014F</italic> resistant allele of the <italic>kdr</italic> gene ranged from 84.48 to 100% in <italic>An. gambiae</italic> and from 80 to 100% in <italic>An. coluzzii</italic>.<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Distribution frequency of the <italic>L1014F</italic> resistant allele of the <italic>Kdr</italic> gene F (<italic>L1014F</italic>) in the <italic>An.</italic><italic>Coluzzii</italic> and <italic>An.</italic><italic>Gambiae</italic> species</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="3">Agro-ecological zones</th><th align="left" rowspan="3">N<sub>T</sub></th><th align="left" rowspan="3">N</th><th align="left" colspan="4">
<italic>An. gambiae</italic>
</th><th align="left" colspan="4">
<italic>An. coluzzii</italic>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="3">P-value</th></tr><tr><th align="left">N<sub>1</sub><break/>
<italic>1014F/</italic>
</th><th align="left">N<sub>2</sub><break/>
<italic>1014F/</italic>
</th><th align="left">N<sub>3</sub><break/>
<italic>1014L/</italic>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">F<italic>(L1014F)%</italic></th><th align="left">N<sub>1</sub><break/>
<italic>1014F/</italic>
</th><th align="left">N<sub>2</sub><break/>
<italic>1014F/</italic>
</th><th align="left">N<sub>3</sub><break/>
<italic>1014L/</italic>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">F<italic>(L1014F)%</italic></th></tr><tr><th align="left">
<italic>1014F</italic>
</th><th align="left">
<italic>1014L</italic>
</th><th align="left">
<italic>1014L</italic>
</th><th align="left">
<italic>1014F</italic>
</th><th align="left">
<italic>1014L</italic>
</th><th align="left">
<italic>1014L</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Far north zone</td><td char="." align="char">30</td><td char="." align="char">0</td><td char="." align="char">0</td><td char="." align="char">0</td><td char="." align="char">0</td><td align="left">0</td><td char="." align="char">21</td><td char="." align="char">6</td><td char="." align="char">3</td><td align="left">80&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;10.12</td><td align="left">-</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Northern cotton zone</td><td char="." align="char">30</td><td char="." align="char">29</td><td char="." align="char">23</td><td char="." align="char">3</td><td char="." align="char">3</td><td align="left">84.48&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;9.32</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td char="." align="char">0</td><td char="." align="char">0</td><td align="left">100</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">South-Borgou food crop production zone</td><td char="." align="char">60</td><td char="." align="char">58</td><td char="." align="char">50</td><td char="." align="char">6</td><td char="." align="char">2</td><td align="left">91.38&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.11</td><td char="." align="char">2</td><td char="." align="char">0</td><td char="." align="char">0</td><td align="left">100</td><td align="left">1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Western Atacora zone</td><td char="." align="char">31</td><td char="." align="char">27</td><td char="." align="char">25</td><td char="." align="char">2</td><td char="." align="char">0</td><td align="left">96.30&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.04</td><td char="." align="char">3</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td char="." align="char">0</td><td align="left">87.5&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;22.92</td><td align="left">0.842</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Central cotton zone</td><td char="." align="char">150</td><td char="." align="char">62</td><td char="." align="char">54</td><td char="." align="char">8</td><td char="." align="char">0</td><td align="left">93.55&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.32</td><td char="." align="char">65</td><td char="." align="char">12</td><td char="." align="char">6</td><td align="left">85.54&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;5.35</td><td align="left">0.0496</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Bar land zone</td><td char="." align="char">192</td><td char="." align="char">75</td><td char="." align="char">74</td><td char="." align="char">1</td><td char="." align="char">0</td><td align="left">99.33&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;1.30</td><td char="." align="char">89</td><td char="." align="char">22</td><td char="." align="char">3</td><td align="left">87.72&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;4.26</td><td align="left">&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Fishery zone</td><td char="." align="char">184</td><td char="." align="char">8</td><td char="." align="char">8</td><td char="." align="char">0</td><td char="." align="char">0</td><td align="left">100</td><td char="." align="char">140</td><td char="." align="char">31</td><td char="." align="char">4</td><td align="left">88.86&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;3.30</td><td align="left">0.3181</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Total</td><td char="." align="char">677</td><td char="." align="char">259</td><td char="." align="char">234</td><td char="." align="char">20</td><td char="." align="char">5</td><td align="left">94.21&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.01</td><td char="." align="char">321</td><td char="." align="char">72</td><td char="." align="char">16</td><td align="left">87.29&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;2.28</td><td align="left">&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>F (<italic>L1014F</italic>)%: frequency of the <italic>L1014F</italic> allele of the <italic>Kdr</italic> gene of the different species; NT: cumulative total number of species by agro - ecological zone; N: represents the number of each species; N1: number of homozygous resistant genotype <italic>1014F/1014F</italic>; N2: the heterozygous genotype <italic>1014F/1014L</italic>; N3: number of susceptible homozygous genotype <italic>1014L/1014L</italic>; <italic>1014F/1014F</italic>: resistant homozygous genotype; <italic>1014F/1014L</italic>: heterozygous genotype; <italic>1014L/1014L</italic>: susceptible homozygous genotype</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par23">In <italic>An. gambiae</italic>, the frequencies were 0%, 84.48%, 91.38%, 96.30%, 93.55%, 99.33%, and 100% respectively in the Far North, Northern Cotton, food crop producing of South Borgou, West-Atacora, Central Cotton, laterite and Fisheries zones.</p><p id="Par24">In <italic>An. coluzzii</italic>, the frequencies were 100% in the northern cotton and food crop production zones of South Borgou, and 80%, 87.5%, 85.54%, 87.72%, 88.86% and 87.29% respectively in the far north, western Atacora, central cotton, bar land and fisheries zones. On the other hand, a significant difference is generally observed in the distribution of the <italic>L1014F</italic> allele (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). The frequencies of the <italic>L1014F</italic> allele of the <italic>kdr</italic> gene are similar between <italic>An. gambiae</italic> and <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> in all agro-ecological zones except for the central cotton (p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0496) and of the fishery (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001) zones. The small number (n&#x02009;=&#x02009;4) of <italic>An. arabiensis</italic> detected did not allow a valid comparison of the frequency of the <italic>L1014F</italic> allele of the <italic>kdr</italic> gene of this species with the one of <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> and <italic>An. gambiae</italic>.</p><p id="Par25">Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> shows that the frequency of the <italic>L1014F</italic> allele of the <italic>kdr</italic> gene is at least 80%&#x02009;&#x000b1;&#x02009;10.12 in the different species of the different agro-ecological zones. In the same agro-ecological zone, there is no significant difference (p&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.05) in the distribution of this allele in the two species except in the central cotton (p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.0496) and bar land zones (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.001). Similarly, within the agro-ecological zones of the northern (far North, Western Atacora, North cotton and food crop production of South Borgou zones), no significant difference is noted in the distribution of this allele among the different species (p&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.05). On the other hand, in the southern part of Benin (central cotton and bar land zones), there is a significant difference in the distribution of this allele among the different species (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05) except for the fishery zone (p&#x02009;=&#x02009;0.3181).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Discussion</title><p id="Par26">The results of this study showed an heterogeneous distribution of <italic>An. gambiae</italic> and <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> in the different geographical areas of Benin and a strong sympatry between these two species in some localities. The presence of hybrids (<italic>An. gambiae</italic> /<italic>An. coluzzii</italic>) recorded in some study areas corroborates the results previously obtained by several authors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>] and supports the hypothesis of gene flow between the two species despite the well advanced speciation. The presence of hybrid suggests incomplete reproductive isolation between <italic>An. gambiae</italic> and <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. On the other hand, the fertility and the reproductive capacity of these hybrids remain to be proven since their number is small.</p><p id="Par27">Overall, the results show that <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> was the predominant species in the southern regions of the country while <italic>An. gambiae</italic> was the major species in the northern and central regions. This distribution of species could be due to variable climatic conditions (a subequatorial climate with 4-seasons, 2 rainy seasons interspersed with two dry seasons in the south; a Sudano-Guinean transition climate with four seasons similar to that of the South at the center and, a Sudanese climate with a wet and a dry season in the north [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]) as well as with the ecological characteristics (physico-chemical properties of the mosquito breeding sites) of the selected areas and the sampling periods depending on the dry or rainy season. According to Mbida et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>], <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> is associated to permanent breeding sites and those resulting from human activity, while <italic>An. gambiae</italic> is more frequent in rain-dependent temporary breeding sites. The same authors also concluded that <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> prefers urban water collections and adapts quickly to pollution. These results corroborate those obtained by Djogb&#x000e9;nou et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. The absence of <italic>An. gambiae</italic> in the agro-ecological zone of the far north could be due to the small number of surveyed localities in the only district of Malanville or to the physico-chemical properties of the breeding sites from which larvae were sampled [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>].</p><p id="Par28">In addition, only four individuals of <italic>An. arabiensis</italic> in Dassa, a savanna species previously found in northern Benin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. According to Djogb&#x000e9;nou et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>] and Gnangu&#x000e8;non et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>], <italic>An. arabiensis</italic> would have moved to the centre of the country because of drought and human activities (destruction of forests concomitantly with the use of large areas for agriculture, hunting, grazing and timber harvesting and urbanization). Thus, the fact of finding it in the centre of the country (Dassa) testifies to its adaptation to the new climatic conditions, an evolutionary capacity peculiar to living beings. Although the effects of climate change such as drought and rain are not yet clearly quantifiable, it could be one of the causes of the displacement of living organisms. Insects are one of the best indicators to better appreciate the phenomenon. Species migration, such as the hypothesis given in the case of <italic>An. arabiensis</italic> for the present study, may contribute to the spread of this vector in Central and Southern Benin.</p><p id="Par29">Considering the different surveyed zones, no significant difference was noted between the frequencies of the resistant allele <italic>L1014F</italic> of the <italic>kdr</italic> gene in the populations of <italic>An. gambiae</italic> and <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> (p&#x02009;&#x0003e;&#x02009;0.05) except for those the central cotton and bar land zones (p&#x02009;&#x0003c;&#x02009;0.05). Benin is a country where the most practiced activity is agriculture with similar agricultural practices (the use of pesticides and chemical fertilizers) from one locality to another. This could contribute to the wide distribution of the <italic>L1014F</italic> locus. Also, the climatic conditions of the laterite and central cotton agro-ecological zones are close or even identical. On the other hand, these two zones do not share the same climatic conditions as the agro-ecological zones of the north (far north of Benin, food crop producing of South-Borgou and Western Atacora) which are themselves close or even identical. This could also be a justifying argument. According to Akogb&#x000e9;to et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>] and Yadoul&#x000e9;ton et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>], agricultural practices constitute a pressure of selection which spread the resistance allele in Benin. National coverage of insecticide-treated mosquito nets in the country could also contribute to the selection of the <italic>L1014F</italic> resistant allele. The presence and attachment of the <italic>L1014F</italic> allele of the <italic>kdr</italic> gene in some populations of <italic>An. coluzzii</italic>, which was not the case a few years ago [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>] are evolutionary realities in our study area. This could possibly be generalized very soon. This is proof of the increase of the receptive potential the <italic>L1014F</italic> allele of the <italic>kdr</italic> gene in <italic>An. gambiae</italic><italic>s.l</italic>. And certainly by genetic self-stop of the expansion of resistance genes in Benin. With this spectrum of expression of the resistance gene, It is inevitably moving towards a lack of effectiveness of the insecticide-based tools currently used in the fight against malaria vectors. The presence of this allele in <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> differs from one author to another, and several have reported its presence only in <italic>An. gambiae</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. The existence of the <italic>L1014F</italic> allele of the <italic>kdr</italic> gene in <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> could also be due to an ancestral phylogenetic inheritance or introgression process within its populations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>], or to the migration of <italic>An. coluzzii</italic> carrying the resistant allele <italic>kdr</italic> "<italic>L1014F</italic>" from one locality to another [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>] given the proximity of some of our areas. These results corroborate those obtained in Benin, Burkina Faso [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>] and Mali [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. The <italic>L1014F</italic> allele of the <italic>kdr</italic> gene is not directly distributed according to geography, but the ecology of the vectors in question is an indispensable factor in the selection of the resistant allele of the gene [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. A study of the genetic structure of these populations is necessary in order to explore their genetic dynamics in the different agro-ecological zones.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Conclusion</title><p id="Par30">In summary, for the moment that even if the data are in small portions, the <italic>An</italic>. <italic>Arabiensis</italic> species was found only in central Benin and the <italic>L1014F</italic> allele of the <italic>kdr</italic> gene is widespread and seems to fix in all the species recorded in the different agro-ecological zones. This situation amplifies the problem of resistance, which could eventually be a significant obstacle for the malaria vectors control. Similarly, a study of their genetic structure via the <italic>L1014F</italic> allele is necessary in order to put in place strategies to manage this resistance. These strategies will take into account both the ecology and the genetic diversity of the organisms involved to preserve the effectiveness of pyrethroids, the only insecticides used for the impregnation of mosquito nets.</p></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>CREC</term><def><p id="Par5">Cotonou Entomological Research Center</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>PNLP</term><def><p id="Par6">Programme National de Lutte contre le Paludisme</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>KDR</term><def><p id="Par7">knockdown resistance</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>WHO</term><def><p id="Par8">Word Health Organization</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</bold></p><p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank the anonymous reviewers for their constructive comments on manuscript. We also thank the Cotonou Entomological Research Center (CREC), mainly the director for his support of the study.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>CZK, MS and MCA designed the study. CZK, FRA, BSA, AJYHF, WTS, AS, SA and RO Performed the experiment. CZK, RO and MS analysed the data. CZK wrote the manuscript. RO, MS and MCA reviewed the manuscript critically. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="funding-information"><title>Funding</title><p>The research leading to these results was made possible thanks to our efforts and with the support of the Center of Entomological Research of Cotonou (CREC).</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p>The data supporting the conclusions of this article are included in the article. Raw data will be available upon request to the corresponding author.</p></notes><notes><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p>Not applicable.</p></notes><notes><title>Consent for publication</title><p>Not applicable.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Plowe</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The evolution of drug-resistant malaria</article-title><source>Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg.</source><year>2009</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.trstmh.2008.11.002</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18768191</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ranson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>N&#x02019;Guessan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Lines</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Moiroux</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Nkuni</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Corbel</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pyrethroid resistance in African anopheline mosquitoes: what are the implications for malaria control?</article-title><source>Trends Parasitol.</source><year>2011</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>98</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pt.2010.08.004</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20843745</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">WHO. World Malaria Report 2015. Geneva: World Health Organization; 2015.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kelly-Hope</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ranson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hemingway</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Lessons from the past: managing insecticide resistance in malaria control and eradication programmes</article-title><source>Lancet Infect Dis.</source><year>2008</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>387</fpage><lpage>389</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(08)70045-8</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18374633</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hemingway</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawkes</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mccarroll</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Ranson</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The molecular basis of insecticide resistance in mosquitoes</article-title><source>Insect Biochem Mol Biol.</source><year>2004</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>653</fpage><lpage>665</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ibmb.2004.03.018</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15242706</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vulule</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Beach</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Atieli</surname><given-names>FK</given-names></name><name><surname>Roberts</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Mount</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Mwangi</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Reduced susceptibility of <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> to permethrin associated with the use of permethrin-impregnated bednets and curtains in Kenya</article-title><source>Med Vet Entomol.</source><year>1994</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>71</fpage><lpage>75</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2915.1994.tb00389.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8161849</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akogb&#x000e9;to</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Yakoubou</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Resistance of malaria vectors to pyrethroids used for impregnated bednets, Benin, West Africa (in French)</article-title><source>Bull Soc Pathol Exot.</source><year>1999</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>123</fpage><lpage>130</lpage><?supplied-pmid 10399604?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10399604</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Corbel</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>N&#x02019;Guessan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Brengues</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandre</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Djogbenou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Multiple insecticide mechanisms in <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> and <italic>Culex quinquefasciatus</italic> from Benin, West Africa</article-title><source>Acta Trop.</source><year>2007</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>207</fpage><lpage>216</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.actatropica.2007.01.005</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17359927</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yadouleton</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>Asidi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Djouaka</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Braima</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Agossou</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name><name><surname>Akogb&#x000e9;to</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Development of vegetable farming: a cause of the emergence of insecticide resistance in populations of <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> in urban areas of Benin</article-title><source>Malar J.</source><year>2009</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>103</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1475-2875-8-103</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19442297</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chandre</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Darrier</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Manga</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Akogbeto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Faye</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Mouchet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Status of pyrethroid resistance in <italic>Anopheles gambiae sensu</italic><italic>lato</italic></article-title><source>Bull World Health Org.</source><year>1999</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>230</fpage><lpage>234</lpage><?supplied-pmid 10212513?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10212513</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Diabat&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldet</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandre</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Akogb&#x000e9;to</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Guiguemba</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Darriet</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The role of agricultural use of insecticides in resistance to pyrethroids in <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic><italic>sl</italic> in Burkina Faso</article-title><source>Am J Trop Med Hyg.</source><year>2002</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>617</fpage><lpage>622</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4269/ajtmh.2002.67.617</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12518852</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yadoul&#x000e9;ton</surname><given-names>AW</given-names></name><name><surname>N&#x02019;Guessan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Allagb&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Asidi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Boko</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Oss&#x000e8;</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The impact of the expansion of urban vegetable farming on malaria transmission in major cities of Benin</article-title><source>Parasit Vectors.</source><year>2010</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>118</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1756-3305-3-118</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21143999</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tia</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Chouaibou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gbal&#x000e9;gba</surname><given-names>CNG</given-names></name><name><surname>Boby</surname><given-names>AMO</given-names></name><name><surname>Kon&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kadjo</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distribution of species and <italic>kdr</italic> gene frequency among <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic><italic>ss</italic> and <italic>Anopheles coluzzii</italic> populations in five agricultural sites in C&#x000f4;te d&#x02019;Ivoire (in French)</article-title><source>Bull Soc Pathol Exot.</source><year>2017</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>130</fpage><lpage>134</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13149-017-0554-1</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28357641</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Carnevale P, Robert V. Les anoph&#x000e8;les: biologie, transmission du Plasmodium et lutte antivectorielle. IRD Editions. 2009.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kudom</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Larval ecology of <italic>Anopheles coluzzii</italic> in Cape Coast, Ghana: water quality, nature of habitat and implication for larval control</article-title><source>Malar J.</source><year>2015</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>447</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12936-015-0989-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26558365</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Rapport national sur le d&#x000e9;veloppement humain. Agriculture, S&#x000e9;curit&#x000e9; alimentaire et D&#x000e9;veloppement Humain au B&#x000e9;nin; 2015. p. 54&#x02013;8.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Adam KS, Boko M. Le B&#x000e9;nin. Nouvelle &#x000e9;dition mise &#x000e0; jour. Cotonou : Editions du Flamboyant, Paris : EDICEF, 1993. p. 95.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gillies</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Coetzee</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Supplement to the Anophelinae of Africa South of the Sahara (Afrotropical Region)</article-title><source>Publ South Afr Inst Med Res.</source><year>1987</year><volume>1987</volume><fpage>55</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gillies</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>De Meillon</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Anophelinae of Africa South of the Sahara (Ethiopian Zoogeographical Region)</article-title><source>Publ South Afr Inst Med Res.</source><year>1968</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>343</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Santolamazza</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Mancini</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Simard</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Qi</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Tu</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Della Torre</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Insertion polymorphisms of SINE200 retrotransposons within speciation islands of <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> molecular forms</article-title><source>Malar J.</source><year>2008</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>163</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1475-2875-7-163</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18724871</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Broodon</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name><name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of single specimens of the <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> complex by the polymerase chain reaction</article-title><source>Am J Trop Med Hyg.</source><year>1993</year><volume>49</volume><fpage>520</fpage><lpage>529</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4269/ajtmh.1993.49.520</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8214283</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Martinez-Torres</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandre</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Williamson</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Darriet</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Berge</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Devonshire</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular characterization of pyrethroid knockdown resistance (<italic>kdr</italic>) in the major malaria vector <italic>Anopheles gambiae </italic> ss</article-title><source>Insect Mol Biol.</source><year>1998</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>179</fpage><lpage>184</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2583.1998.72062.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9535162</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weir</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Cockerham</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimating F-statistics for the analysis of population structure</article-title><source>Evolution</source><year>1984</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>1358</fpage><lpage>1370</lpage><?supplied-pmid 28563791?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28563791</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">R Development Core Team: R: A language and environment for statistical computing. R Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna, Austria 2011. ISBN 3-900051-07-0, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.R-project.org/">https://www.R-project.org/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Della Torre</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Fanello</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Akogbeto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dossou-yovo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Favia</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Petrarca</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Molecular evidence of incipient within <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic><italic>ss</italic> in West Africa</article-title><source>Insect Mol Biol.</source><year>2001</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>9</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2583.2001.00235.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11240632</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>P&#x000e9;ka</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><source>Evaluation de la sensibilit&#x000e9; aux pyr&#x000e9;thrino&#x000ef;des des populations d&#x02019;<italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic><italic>s.l.</italic> de la zone c&#x000f4;ti&#x000e8;re de C&#x000f4;te d&#x02019;Ivoire</source><year>2001</year><publisher-loc>M&#x000e9;moire DEA</publisher-loc><publisher-name>CEMV, Universit&#x000e9; de Bouak&#x000e9;</publisher-name><fpage>57</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Djogbenou</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Pasteur</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Bio-Bangana</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldet</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Irish</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Akogb&#x000e9;to</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Malaria vectors in the Republic of Benin: distribution of species and molecular forms of the<italic> Anopheles gambiae</italic> complex</article-title><source>Acta Trop.</source><year>2010</year><volume>114</volume><fpage>116</fpage><lpage>122</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.actatropica.2010.02.001</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20138819</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Tour&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name><name><surname>Carnahan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Norris</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolo</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Traor&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Gene flow among populations of the malaria vector,<italic> Anopheles gambiae</italic>, in Mali</article-title><source>West Africa. Genetics.</source><year>2001</year><volume>157</volume><fpage>743</fpage><lpage>750</lpage><?supplied-pmid 11156993?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11156993</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mbida Mbida</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Etang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Akono Ntonga</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Eboumbou Moukoko</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Awono-Ambene</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Tagne</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>New insight into <italic>Anopheles coluzzii</italic> Coetzee &#x00026; Wilkerson, 2013 larval ecology in the Wouri estuary, Littoral-Cameroon (in French)</article-title><source>Bull Soc de Pathol Exot.</source><year>2017</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>92</fpage><lpage>101</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s13149-016-0519-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gnanguenon</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Govoetchan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Agossa</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Oss&#x000e8;</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Oke-Agbo</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Azondekon</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Transmission patterns of <italic>Plasmodium falciparum</italic> by <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> in Benin</article-title><source>Malar J.</source><year>2014</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>444</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1475-2875-13-444</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25412948</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akogbeto</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Djouaka</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Kinde&#x02013;Gazard</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Screening of pesticide residues in soil and water samples from agricultural settings</article-title><source>Malar J</source><year>2006</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>22</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1475-2875-5-22</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16563153</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Euz&#x000e9;by J. Grand dictionnaire illustr&#x000e9; de parasitology m&#x000e9;dicale et v&#x000e9;t&#x000e9;rinaire. &#x000c9;ditions Lavoisier. 2008; 832.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Diabate</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldet</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandre</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Dabire</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>Kengue</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Guiguemde</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Kdr mutation, a genetic marquer to asses events of introgression between the molecular M and S forms of <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> (Diptera: Culicidae) in the tropical savanna area of West Africa</article-title><source>J Med Entomol.</source><year>2003</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>195</fpage><lpage>198</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1603/0022-2585-40.2.195</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12693848</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tour&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>YT</given-names></name><name><surname>Petrarca</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Traor&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Coulibaly</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Maiga</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sankar&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The distribution and inversion polymorphism of chromosomally recognized taxa of the <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> complex in Mali, West Africa</article-title><source>Parassitologia.</source><year>1998</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>477</fpage><lpage>511</lpage><?supplied-pmid 10645562?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10645562</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Edi</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Koudou</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellai</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Adja</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Chouaibou</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonfoh</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Long-term trends in <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> insecticide resistance in C&#x000f4;te d&#x02019;Ivoire</article-title><source>Parasit Vectors.</source><year>2014</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>500</fpage><?supplied-pmid 25429888?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25429888</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weill</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chandre</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Brengues</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Manguin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Akogbeto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pasteur</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The <italic>kdr</italic> mutation occurs in the Mopti form of <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic><italic>ss</italic> through introgression</article-title><source>Insect Mol Biol.</source><year>2000</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>451</fpage><lpage>455</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2583.2000.00206.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11029663</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cisse</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Keita</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Dicko</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dengela</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucas</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Characterizing the insecticide resistance of <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic> in Mali</article-title><source>Malar J.</source><year>2015</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>327</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12936-015-0847-4</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26296644</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>