<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="ack" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <div class="title">Acknowledgments</div>
 <p>We thank I. Macadam for the original software and document on the REML method. This paper is a contribution to the CLIVAR International Climate of the Twentieth Century Plus project. 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cola.gmu.edu/c20c/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://cola.gmu.edu/c20c/</span>. 
  <span class="bold">Funding:</span> C.K.F. and A.C. were funded by the Joint UK Department for Business, Energy and Industrial Strategy/Defra Met Office Hadley Centre Climate Programme (GA01101). O.B. was funded by the CNRS. D.E.P., formerly funded as for C.K.F. and A.C., is now an independent researcher. 
  <span class="bold">Author contributions:</span> C.K.F. carried out the bulk of the work, including calculations, and wrote the drafts of the paper. O.B. helped with the development of the exponential response times, ideas about the recalcitrant response, and the presentation of the paper, while A.C. carried out the map-based calculations and advised on some of the diagrams. D.E.P. advised on the presentation of results and on modifications to and interpretation of the REML software and made some revisions of the paper. 
  <span class="bold">Competing interests:</span> The authors declare that they have no competing interests. 
  <span class="bold">Data and materials availability:</span> The monthly transformed, normalized forcing data and the observed GST are available on the CLIVAR [Climate and Ocean: Variability, Predictability and Change (one of the four core projects of the World Climate Research Programme)] Climate of the Twentieth Century Plus web site at 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cola.gmu.edu/c20c/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://cola.gmu.edu/c20c/</span> through the sidebar “Experiments.” The full HadISST2.1.0.0 data set is available from the corresponding author. All data needed to evaluate the conclusions in the paper are present in the paper and/or the Supplementary Materials. Additional data related to this paper may be requested from the authors.
 </p>
</div>
