<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="introduction" disp-level="1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">INTRODUCTION</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The recent slowdown in the warming of global mean surface temperature (GST) around 1998–2013 has caused much discussion about its causes (
  <a rid="R1" ref-type="bibr" href="#R1">
   <span class="italic">1</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R2" ref-type="bibr" href="#R2">
   <span class="italic">2</span>
  </a>), including the sequestration of heat in the deeper oceans (
  <a rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" href="#R3">
   <span class="italic">3</span>
  </a>), as many climate models appear to overestimate recent warming of GST (
  <a rid="R4" ref-type="bibr" href="#R4">
   <span class="italic">4</span>
  </a>). Here, we analyze the causes of GST variations from 1891 to 2015, placing the causes of the recent slowdown in a longer-term context. We do not use the words “pause” or “hiatus” as, particularly in the recent slowdown, GST warming did not entirely cease on decadal time scales. Therefore, pause and hiatus cause semantic difficulties that are best avoided (
  <a rid="R5" ref-type="bibr" href="#R5">
   <span class="italic">5</span>
  </a>). However, the recent slowdown was one of at least three slowdown or cooling periods lasting about 15 years or more since 1891. The best-known apparent multidecadal cooling episode lasted from the early 1940s to 1975 (
  <a rid="R6" ref-type="bibr" href="#R6">
   <span class="italic">6</span>
  </a>). This has been called the big pause (
  <a rid="R6" ref-type="bibr" href="#R6">
   <span class="italic">6</span>
  </a>), so we will term this the big slowdown. An earlier cooling period occurred around 1896–1910, partly associated with volcanic eruptions in the West Indies (
  <a rid="R7" ref-type="bibr" href="#R7">
   <span class="italic">7</span>
  </a>), although it has not been fully explained. Not surprisingly, the uncertainty in GST data was appreciably greater at that time than during the recent slowdown (
  <a rid="R8" ref-type="bibr" href="#R8">
   <span class="italic">8</span>
  </a>). GST also shows two periods of strong warming around 1911–1940 and 1976–1997, although as throughout the instrumental GST record, temperatures showed considerable variability on subdecadal time scales. Current understanding of the veracity of the leading instrumental records of GST has recently been thoroughly reviewed (
  <a rid="R9" ref-type="bibr" href="#R9">
   <span class="italic">9</span>
  </a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Turning first to observational papers, a number of reconstructions of instrumental GST, based on forms of multiple regression against forcing factors, have been recently reviewed (
  <a rid="R10" ref-type="bibr" href="#R10">
   <span class="italic">10</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R11" ref-type="bibr" href="#R11">
   <span class="italic">11</span>
  </a>), although some reconstructions only go back to about 1950 (
  <a rid="R12" ref-type="bibr" href="#R12">
   <span class="italic">12</span>
  </a>–
  <a rid="R14" ref-type="bibr" href="#R14">
   <span class="italic">14</span>
  </a>). One review (
  <a rid="R11" ref-type="bibr" href="#R11">
   <span class="italic">11</span>
  </a>) analyzed annual mean GST data from these papers and concluded that detection of an anthropogenic signal was robust when signals from the El Niño–Southern Oscillation (ENSO), the Atlantic Multidecadal Oscillation (AMO) (
  <a rid="R15" ref-type="bibr" href="#R15">
   <span class="italic">15</span>
  </a>), total incident solar radiation (TSI), and volcanic (VOLC) forcing signals were included. The motivation for these studies was sometimes forecasting rather than mechanistic explanation or detection and attribution, leading, for example, to skillful real-time forecasts of GST 1 year ahead since 2000 (
  <a rid="R12" ref-type="bibr" href="#R12">
   <span class="italic">12</span>
  </a>) (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.metoffice.gov.uk/news/releases/2016/global-forecast-2017" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.metoffice.gov.uk/news/releases/2016/global-forecast-2017</span>, as of 30 January 2018). Alternative methodologies more concerned with low-frequency GST variations use empirical mode decomposition (
  <a rid="R16" ref-type="bibr" href="#R16">
   <span class="italic">16</span>
  </a>) or low-pass filtering (
  <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">
   <span class="italic">17</span>
  </a>). Both methods enhance the magnitude of multidecadal AMO-like influences on GST compared to those found in regression-based papers quoted above that also include the contribution of the AMO to GST (
  <a rid="R11" ref-type="bibr" href="#R11">
   <span class="italic">11</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R12" ref-type="bibr" href="#R12">
   <span class="italic">12</span>
  </a>), although the reason is not obvious. These alternative methodologies also reduce the inferred anthropogenic warming component of GST in the last few decades and explain the big slowdown of 1941–1975 as being largely due to 60- to 80-year natural variability associated with the AMO.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Dynamical climate models with external and internal forcings, averaged over many ensemble members over the past century and earlier, inevitably remove the signals of internal climate variability and so only respond to external forcings. These studies include an early, although quite skillful, attempt to reconstruct GST variations and trends since 1860 (
  <a rid="R18" ref-type="bibr" href="#R18">
   <span class="italic">18</span>
  </a>). Since then, many climate models have included this period in their analyses, most recently the 40 CMIP5 models or so (
  <a rid="R10" ref-type="bibr" href="#R10">
   <span class="italic">10</span>
  </a>) that collectively provide estimates of reconstructed uncertainties in GST and its mean. Since the late 19th century, multidecadal trends in average GST have been picked up quite well by CMIP5, mainly due to the net warming effect of increasing greenhouse gases and anthropogenic aerosols. The short-term cooling effects of major volcanic eruptions are also reconstructed quite well. Nevertheless, a common problem in CMIP5 simulations is an inability to reproduce the level of observed warmth in GST around the Second World War. Some of this deficiency is likely to be due to a peak in the AMO around 1940, inevitably not picked up by CMIP5 or the earlier CMIP3 averages (
  <a rid="R19" ref-type="bibr" href="#R19">
   <span class="italic">19</span>
  </a>). Early 20th-century warming is explained as partly due to an increase in TSI, a lack of volcanic eruptions, and a small anthropogenic component due to slowly increasing greenhouse gases, much as in the earliest skillful climate model paper (
  <a rid="R18" ref-type="bibr" href="#R18">
   <span class="italic">18</span>
  </a>). Notably, recent estimates of past TSI variations (
  <a rid="R20" ref-type="bibr" href="#R20">
   <span class="italic">20</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R21" ref-type="bibr" href="#R21">
   <span class="italic">21</span>
  </a>) indicate that the increase in TSI over 1891–1950 is likely to be less than originally estimated (
  <a rid="R22" ref-type="bibr" href="#R22">
   <span class="italic">22</span>
  </a>), especially during minima of the 11-year cycle. Relatively recent climate model results (
  <a rid="R23" ref-type="bibr" href="#R23">
   <span class="italic">23</span>
  </a>–
  <a rid="R25" ref-type="bibr" href="#R25">
   <span class="italic">25</span>
  </a>) also show that the AMO could have contributed appreciably to warming of the Northern Hemisphere and, considerably more weakly, the entire globe, during the years 1975–2005, a period of strong overall warming. However, compared to the first model, the second model study (
  <a rid="R24" ref-type="bibr" href="#R24">
   <span class="italic">24</span>
  </a>) shows about twice the sensitivity of an increase in Northern Hemisphere temperature to these AMO changes (
  <a rid="R23" ref-type="bibr" href="#R23">
   <span class="italic">23</span>
  </a>). The implied sensitivity of GST to the AMO in the second study is similar to that of the observational analyses that used alternative statistical methodologies (
  <a rid="R16" ref-type="bibr" href="#R16">
   <span class="italic">16</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">
   <span class="italic">17</span>
  </a>). If true, then these results would also imply a markedly smaller contribution to warming of the net effect of increasing greenhouse gases and anthropogenic aerosols (usually called GA in the remainder of this paper) than shown by CMIP5 models over the same period. The third of these studies (
  <a rid="R25" ref-type="bibr" href="#R25">
   <span class="italic">25</span>
  </a>) identifies internal variability as the time-varying difference between observations and a CMIP5 66-member ensemble mean with anthropogenic and natural forcings during 1920–2013, after scaling down temperature trends in the latter by ~14% to compensate for the models’ overestimation of observed warming. The implied internal variability in GST is associated mainly with a pattern resembling the Interdecadal Pacific Oscillation (IPO) and, to a lesser extent, with an AMO-like pattern.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">With this background, we reconstruct the monthly GST records using, separately, the main forcing factors at monthly resolution identified by previous authors and the average of a large number of cross-validated regression calculations (see Materials and Methods). Monthly data better represent short-term GST variability than do annual data, especially that due to ENSO. Furthermore, we transform the raw forcing data to represent the delayed response of GST to each forcing. Because these responses are often uncertain, we use a range of response functions, and to incorporate uncertainty in GST into the reconstructions, we use three separate GST data sets. As a result, we create 54 sets of cross-validated multiple regressions. Forcing factors first include GA, as tabulated by the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (
  <a rid="R20" ref-type="bibr" href="#R20">
   <span class="italic">20</span>
  </a>). The greenhouse gas and aerosol forcing components of GA must be combined in a regression model because of their strong colinearity: Their correlation is −0.98 over 1891–1996 and −0.97 over 1896–2011 (
  <a rid="R20" ref-type="bibr" href="#R20">
   <span class="italic">20</span>
  </a>). We then include the AMO, ENSO, IPO (
  <a rid="R26" ref-type="bibr" href="#R26">
   <span class="italic">26</span>
  </a>), and volcanic and TSI forcing (absolute values of volcanic, TSI, and GA forcing are shown in fig. S1 and section S1, normalized values of the two AMO indices are shown in fig. S2A and section S2, and normalized values of the ENSO and IPO indices are separately shown in fig. S2B). Because we use monthly data, we can also include the influence on GST of the Arctic Oscillation (AO) between December and March, as detected in the recent GST slowdown (
  <a rid="R27" ref-type="bibr" href="#R27">
   <span class="italic">27</span>
  </a>). Earlier work (
  <a rid="R28" ref-type="bibr" href="#R28">
   <span class="italic">28</span>
  </a>) used a Northern Hemisphere Cold Ocean Warm Land (COWL) index that is negatively correlated with the AO, but the COWL depends on temperature observations. For completeness, an adjustment is added to GA forcing to account for a deep-ocean impact on sea surface temperature (SST) operating on time scales of about 200 years (see Materials and Methods). This is currently very small but could well become considerably larger in the future.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We divide the instrumental record into five periods, three exhibiting GST slowdowns or actual cooling (1896–1910, 1941–1975, and 1998–2013 and its subperiods 2001–2010 and 2001–2013) and two strong warming periods (1911–1940 and 1976–1997). We selected slowdown and warming periods with approximately maximum contrast in trends according to visual inspection of the GST series. Piecewise continuous trends (section S3) show that the trends changed quickly around the dates we selected for the beginnings and ends of subperiods, although we did not carry out a formal change-point analysis in view of the absence of true discontinuities and the slight differences between observational data sets. Because the main focus of the paper is on slowdown periods, these are analyzed using regression model training data independent of the slowdown period being studied. However, the results are rather insensitive to whether these independent periods are used or not, as can be deduced from the overview discussion below using 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Fig. 1</a> where no independent periods are used compared to later sections where they are. Our reconstructions of the two warming periods use all cross-validated monthly data from 1891 to 2015. The GST records are taken from three key data sets in current use for climate monitoring [HadCRUT4.6, updated from HadCRUT4 (
  <a rid="R8" ref-type="bibr" href="#R8">
   <span class="italic">8</span>
  </a>), Goddard Institute for Space Studies Surface Temperature Analysis (GISTEMP) (
  <a rid="R29" ref-type="bibr" href="#R29">
   <span class="italic">29</span>
  </a>), and the National Climatic Data Center (NCDC) data set (
  <a rid="R5" ref-type="bibr" href="#R5">
   <span class="italic">5</span>
  </a>)]. We call the average of these three series the World Meteorological Organization (WMO) data set as it is used by WMO to assess global and large-scale temperature changes (for example, for 2016, 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://public.wmo.int/en/resources/library/wmo-statement-state-of-global-climate-2016" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://public.wmo.int/en/resources/library/wmo-statement-state-of-global-climate-2016</span>, as of 30 January 2018). Further details are given in Materials and Methods.
 </p>
 <div id="F1" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Observed, reconstructed, and CMIP5 simulated GST for the whole period 1891–2015.</div>
   <p>(
    <span class="bold">A</span>) Monthly GST anomalies (January 1891 to September 2017) from the three analyses that make up the WMO data set and the WMO average. Shown are the two warming and three slowdown periods. Estimated 95% confidence limits on the WMO data set are shown in brown. (
    <span class="bold">B</span>) Reconstructions of monthly GST 1891–2015 from each of the various forcing factors. This uses the average of 81,000 cross-validated regression equations calculated from data covering this whole period. (
    <span class="bold">C</span>) (a) Average cross-validated reconstruction (red) of observed monthly WMO GST (black) for the whole period 1891–2015. (b) As in (a) but using the CMIP5 40 model average (blue) of monthly GST.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="aao5297-F1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The purpose of the regression analyses is to determine their skill at reproducing GST in each period and to explain the causes of its variations and trends, in principle down to the monthly time scale. We also compare the skill of the reconstructions over the five periods with that of the average of simulations from 40 CMIP5 models (table S1 and section S4). The reconstructions have an important advantage over CMIP5 in that they incorporate internal variability via the observed climate modes such as the AMO, IPO, and ENSO, which the models cannot do. We also calculate the linear component of changes in GST over each period shown by observations, reconstructions, and CMIP5. This is achieved using a method called restricted maximum likelihood regression or REML. This is well adapted to estimating trends over short periods and allows for the sometimes very large serial correlation in trend residuals and data uncertainties (Materials and Methods and section S3). Finally, we show reconstructions of worldwide maps of GST to further investigate some key results and problems. For TSI, we often use the word “solar” in the diagrams. We mainly highlight changes, trends, or correlations significant at the 1% level or better, rather than 5%, as true statistical significance could be easily overestimated given the many statistics in this paper.</p>
</sec>
