<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Overview</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Figure 1A</a> shows monthly WMO GST and its constituent HadCRUT4.6, NCDC, and GISTEMP GST anomalies relative to a 1961–1990 average, together with 95% confidence ranges around the WMO average for each month. The year 1891 is chosen as the first year analyzed as uncertainties in GST increase quite rapidly before then. On decadal time scales, the only periods of obvious observed GST cooling after 1891 are around 1896–1910 and 1941–1950. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Figure 1B</a> shows the average influences of the various forcings on GST using the multiple regression reconstructions where cross-validation is carried out over the whole period 1891–2015. This particular reconstruction uses the average of 81,000 fairly similar regression equations throughout the record (see Materials and Methods). The total of 81,000 equations first results from the use of separate regression equations for each of the 1500 months over 1891–2015. In addition, there are 18 predictor combinations for each of the three GST series. The 18 predictor combinations are derived from two or three variants of the ENSO or IPO, volcanic, TSI, and GA forcings, as well as fixed AMO and AO forcings. These combinations are shown in table S2 of section S5. 
  <a ref-type="disp-formula" rid="E1" href="#E1">Equation 1</a> is an example, calculated from the average of 1272 cross-validated equations (training period 1891–1996) for 1998–2013, based on a typical set of the 54 GST and predictor combinations used for this period
  <div id="E1" class="disp-formula">
   <div id="m1" class="math">
    <div class="mrow">
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mtext">GST</span>
      <span class="mo"> </span>
      <span class="mo">=</span>
      <span class="mo">−</span>
      <span class="mn">0.0595</span>
      <span class="mo">+</span>
      <span class="mn">0.0172</span>
      <span class="mo">*</span>
      <span class="mtext">AMO</span>
      <span class="mo"> </span>
      <span class="mo">+</span>
      <span class="mn">0.0617</span>
      <span class="mo">*</span>
      <span class="mtext">ENSO</span>
      <span class="mo"> </span>
      <span class="mo">+</span>
      <span class="mn">0.0441</span>
      <span class="mo">*</span>
      <span class="mtext">VOLC</span>
      <span class="mo"> </span>
      <span class="mo">+</span>
      <span class="mn">0.0457</span>
      <span class="mo">*</span>
      <span class="mtext">TSI</span>
      <span class="mo"> </span>
      <span class="mo">+</span>
      <span class="mn">0.2802</span>
      <span class="mo">*</span>
      <span class="mtext">GA</span>
      <span class="mo"> </span>
      <span class="mo">+</span>
      <span class="mn">0.0219</span>
      <span class="mo">*</span>
      <span class="mtext">AO</span>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
   <span class="label">(1)</span>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Monthly forcing values are normalized over 1891–2015 so that regression coefficient magnitudes can be compared directly. The other 53 equations vary sufficiently to be used to estimate uncertainties in the reconstructions. ENSO and unfiltered IPO are highly correlated (monthly 
  <span class="italic">r</span> = 0.76) and thus are each used in 9 (of 18) different predictor combinations for each version of GST (Materials and Methods and section S5). Furthermore, VOLC has a positive value at times when negative volcanic forcing is less than the average for 1961–1990, while the AO is set to zero from April to November (Materials and Methods) as its sign and magnitude do not relate clearly to higher-latitude Northern Hemisphere surface temperature anomalies at these times of the year. The dominant factor in all equations is GA. 
  <a ref-type="disp-formula" rid="E1" href="#E1">Equation 1</a> is quite similar to that published for standardized annual forcing and GST data over 1947–2006 (
  <a rid="R12" ref-type="bibr" href="#R12">
   <span class="italic">12</span>
  </a>), although the AO was not included.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Fig. 1B</a> (b), ENSO influences are combined with those of the IPO. Much of the influence of the December–March AO is intermonthly, but interannual fluctuations also occur, including a decadal decline in the Northern Hemisphere winter AO around 2000–2010 previously highlighted (
  <a rid="R27" ref-type="bibr" href="#R27">
   <span class="italic">27</span>
  </a>). A larger than usual influence of the TSI 11-year cycle that reduces GST from about 2001 to 2010 by about 0.08°C (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Fig. 1B</a>, d) is also notable. Changing GA increases GST at all times, most slowly in the two decades after the Second World War, but increases GST at its strongest and nearly constant rate from the late 1970s. In the early 21st-century slowdown of 1998–2013, the SD of the monthly regression residuals (observed GST minus reconstructed GST) using all the chosen forcing factors is very similar to the assessed uncertainties in monthly observed GST itself (section S6 and fig. S5). However, the structure of the mean residuals (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Fig. 1B</a>, g) is complex before 1950, reflecting poorly reconstructed cold conditions around 1907–1910, a short sharp peak of unexplained observed warmth in the sparse observed data of the First World War and a peak in unexplained observed warmth during the Second World War (see the “Using global maps to investigate reconstruction biases in 1907–1910 and 1944–1945” section). After 1950, mean residuals appear quasi-random, although they have an intermonthly correlation near 0.5 falling to near zero at 6 months lag.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Figure 1C</a> (a) provides an overview of the GST reconstructions using all data. It shows high reconstruction skill on interannual time scales (2- to 5-year high-pass–filtered period; correlation, 0.78 with observed GST; significance, &lt;0.01%) and for the whole spectrum (correlation, 0.93; significance, 0.5%). Materials and Methods describes correlation significance calculations. For the average GST from the 40 CMIP5 models (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Fig. 1C</a>, b), its correlation with observed GST over 1891–2015, dominated by trend, is only modestly less at 0.89 (significance, 0.5%), but there is relatively little high-pass 2- to 5-year skill (correlation, 0.06; significance, 2%). High-pass skill results almost entirely from skillful simulations of episodic volcanic forcings of GST around 1902–1906, 1965–1969, 1983–1985, and 1991–1995. The cool period before 1915 is missed by CMIP5 but is somewhat better in the reconstructions (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Fig. 1C</a>, a), although the cold conditions in 1907–1910 are underestimated by the reconstructions. The observed rate of warming from 1911 to 1940 is markedly better reconstructed than simulated by CMIP5, with CMIP5 simulating this warming trend too weakly. The CMIP5 models reproduce the observed slowing of GST warming from about 1940 to 1975, but the observed peak of warmth during the Second World War is missed, just as it is by the reconstructions (see the “Using global maps to investigate reconstruction biases in 1907–1910 and 1944–1945” section). The warming from around 1976 to 1997 is well reconstructed and well simulated by CMIP5, but the slowdown in GST around 1998–2013, particularly 2001–2013, is missed entirely by CMIP5 but is very well reconstructed. The rate of simulated warming by CMIP5 of 0.22° ± 0.06°C per decade over the period 1976–2015 is somewhat greater than that observed at 0.17° ± 0.02°C. By contrast, the reconstruction gives the same rate of warming as observed, 0.17° ± 0.01°C per decade. This CMIP5 overestimate of recent observed warming in GST, although not quite significant at the 10% level using CMIP5 uncertainties, is shown below to derive from a relatively large overestimate of warming in the recent slowdown since 1998. This overestimate is at least partly due to missing natural forced and internal variability. For obvious reasons, CMIP5 models were unable to simulate the observed changes in the IPO/ENSO, AMO, and the AO, and they were also not provided with observed solar and volcanic forcings for much of this period.
 </p>
</sec>
