<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="app" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <div class="title">SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIALS</div>
 <div content-type="local-data" class="supplementary-material">
  <p>Supplementary material for this article is available at 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://advances.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/4/6/eaao5297/DC1" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://advances.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/4/6/eaao5297/DC1</span>
  </p>
  <p>section S1. Key forcings used expressed in absolute units</p>
  <p>section S2. Separating the two AMO time series and ENSO from the IPO</p>
  <p>section S3. The REML linear temperature change method</p>
  <p>section S4. CMIP5 model experiments used</p>
  <p>section S5. Structure of the regression equations and cross-correlation of predictors</p>
  <p>section S6. Comparison of annual reconstruction and CMIP5 root mean square errors with estimated WMO GST annual uncertainties</p>
  <p>section S7. Reconstruction and CMIP5 correlation statistics for 1941–1975</p>
  <p>section S8. Substituting ERA Interim GST for WMO GST for 1997–2015</p>
  <p>section S9. Response times of GST to TSI forcing</p>
  <p>section S10. Further details of the WMO data sets</p>
  <p>section S11. Structure of multiple regression residuals and cross-correlation of predictors</p>
  <p>fig. S1. Volcanic, solar, and GA forcings in original units without smoothing, expressed as anomalies from their 1961–1990 averages.</p>
  <p>fig. S2. Additional details of monthly time series of the predictors.</p>
  <p>fig. S3. Maximum likelihood plot of the serial correlation of the residuals and their variance for the reconstructed linear component of WMO temperature change over 2001–2013.</p>
  <p>fig. S4. Identifying the boundaries between consecutive slowdown and warming periods using trend analysis.</p>
  <p>fig. S5. Reconstructed and CMIP5 root mean square errors for annual data compared to 1σ uncertainties in annual WMO GST values including additional uncertainties due to the spread of the three component data sets.</p>
  <p>fig. S6. Comparing the reconstructions using ERA Interim and WMO GST during slowdown period 3.</p>
  <p>fig. S7. As in the 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F6" href="#F6">Fig. 6C</a> panels for 1998–2013, 2001–2010, and 2001–2013 in the main text but for ERA Interim.
  </p>
  <p>fig. S8. Original (unfiltered) and e-folded monthly TSI time series January 1981 to December 2015 reflecting the three sets of delayed e-folding response times used in the paper.</p>
  <p>table S1. CMIP5 models and historical experiments used in this paper.</p>
  <p>table S2. Combinations of predictors used in the 18 main regression equations.</p>
  <p>table S3. Correlation skill of average reconstruction GST and CMIP5 average GST with WMO GST in slowdown period 2, 1941–1975.</p>
  <p>table S4. Cross-correlation of monthly predictors 1891–2015.</p>
  <p>table S5. Cross-correlation of monthly predictors 1951–2015.</p>
  <p>References (
   <a rid="R57" ref-type="bibr" href="#R57">
    <span class="italic">57</span>
   </a>–
   <a rid="R59" ref-type="bibr" href="#R59">
    <span class="italic">59</span>
   </a>)
  </p>
 </div>
</div>
