<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par36" class="p">Nevertheless, it is also clear that many individual models and their applications provide examples of good practice upon which to build. We therefore offer our suggestions for how the modelling community should move forward with improving the simulation of climate change adaptation, reflecting the value to be gained from integrating a bottom-up understanding of adaptation as a socio-ecological process into computational models:
 <list list-type="bullet" class="list">
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par37" class="p">Move beyond unrealistic ‘business as usual’ scenarios that extrapolate the recent past without taking account of the numerous disruptive technologies, social movements or behaviours that might occur (O’Neill et al. 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" class="xref">2017</xref>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par38" class="p">Embrace scenario uncertainty rather than trying to identify predictable or ‘most likely’ scenarios, while a single optimum model solution to adaptation might appear attractive, relying on an apparent ability to predict future risks or to foresee the eventual outcomes of decisions is an inappropriate and unreliable paradigm (Lempert and Collins 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" class="xref">2007</xref>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par39" class="p">Analyse adaptation responses via uncertainty-based frameworks such as robust decision-making and adaptive planning (e.g. Gleeson et al. 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" class="xref">2011</xref>; Holman and Trawick 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" class="xref">2011</xref>) or precautionary cost-benefit (Beven 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">2011</xref>) to identify low or no-regret options.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par40" class="p">Work with stakeholders and decision-makers to better understand the triggers and goals of adaptation policies and measures.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par41" class="p">Reflect on the importance of extreme events in driving adaptation (Berrang-Ford et al. 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">2011</xref>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par42" class="p">Include adaptations that take advantage of climate change rather than simply defensively respond to negative impacts (Berrang-Ford et al. 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">2011</xref>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par43" class="p">Embed human and social behaviours and constraints within models, either through integrating agent-based models with process-based models or through structured approaches to constrain model input changes that reflect time-varying scenario-specific settings.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par44" class="p">Account for the full cost of adaptation, in terms of the type and the amount that can occur, reflecting the financial constraints on adaptation.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par45" class="p">Allow for positive and negative effects on resource availability: while implementing some types of adaptation can use up the availability of some capital types (e.g. financial and manufactured), the implementation of some people-based adaptation measures can increase human and social capital.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par46" class="p">Recognise the importance of cross-sectoral interactions and dependencies that can enhance the overall benefits of adaptation or lead to trade-offs and unintended consequences (Harrison et al. 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" class="xref">2016</xref>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par47" class="p">Focus on capturing the spatial and temporal dependencies in adaptation options, capacities, decisions and effects.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par48" class="p">Relax the (artificial) distinction between autonomous and planned adaptation, which can obscure the roles of the state and society in producing the circumstances in which autonomous adaptations can or cannot occur (Adger et al. 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" class="xref">2003</xref>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par49" class="p">Adopt a diversity of approaches, in a diversity of sectors and scales, to build up a picture of adaptation. ‘Open recognition of the limited set of assumptions contained in any one study of adaptation demands that authors clearly note that each individual study can represent only a fraction of plausible outcomes’ (Schneider et al. 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71" class="xref">2000</xref>) .
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par50" class="p">Recognise that adaptation can be hierarchical, with adaptation decisions at one level (of governance or scale) potentially leveraging or otherwise influencing adaptation decisions at other levels.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par51" class="p">Account for external adaptations occurring (or required) outside a given jurisdiction, which may influence domestic outcomes or adaptation requirements.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par52" class="p">Consider adaptation alongside mitigation within an integrated climate policy framework.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
