<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Uncertainties stated concerning CMIP5 ensemble means are the standard deviation of the ensemble (multimodel mean). Uncertainties stated concerning temporal means from observational data (i.e. global spatial patterns of atmospheric fluxes, temperature, and salinity) or CMIP5 mean uncertainties (i.e. average of individual model uncertainties) are the standard deviation of the yearly detrended timeseries and uncertainties in linear trends are the standard error of a linear fit (least squares). Although CMIP5 results are not used to calibrate the method, CMIP5 spread is used to estimate the method uncertainty i.e. from the standard deviation of inferred versus calculated water cycle change in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4" class="xref">Fig. 4a</xref>. Total uncertainty in 
 <italic class="italic">F</italic>
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">cycle</italic>
 </sub> change for the three observational datasets is calculated as the root mean square of the method uncertainty and the data uncertainty in 
 <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq3" class="xref">equation (1)</xref>, which is consistent in the two types of uncertainty are normal. Data uncertainty is derived from the standard error of the linear fit of 
 <italic class="italic">W</italic> annual timeseries and the standard deviation of the mixing timescale 
 <italic class="italic">τ</italic> temporal mean. Data uncertainty in the three observational datasets (~30–32% of the mean water change) is higher than the method uncertainty (~22% of the mean water cycle change). Where a single observationally based estimate of water cycle change is stated it is the arithmetic mean of estimates based on the three datasets and the uncertainty is the root mean square of their uncertainties. In most models the water cycle amplitude increases very close to linearly from the late 1970 s to the end of 21st century following the global surface warming. A more sophisticated fit taking into account the exponential nature of the CC relationship
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33" class="xref">33</xref> could be used but since trends are small and uncertainties are quite large for simplicity a linear fit is applied.
</p>
