<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par25" class="p">Hg concentrations during summer increased in adult little auks, likely linked to an increase in prey Hg concentrations over time
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" class="xref">37</xref>
 </sup>, but also to changes in diet towards prey that are higher in the food chain (biomagnifications)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77" class="xref">77</xref>
 </sup>, as reflected by the increase in δ
 <sup class="sup">15</sup>N in adult blood (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" class="xref">4a</xref>). Although measured Hg concentrations were below toxicity thresholds
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">38</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78" class="xref">78</xref>
 </sup>, they were negatively related to adult body condition and chick growth rate. These observed effects suggest that Hg might act as a cumulative stressor which, in combination with other environmental constraints like the quality of their habitat or resource availability
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" class="xref">41</xref>
 </sup>, could impact the condition of marine predators beyond its single effects. In addition, one should also bear in mind that little auks are exposed not only to Hg, but to a variety of pollutants reaching the Arctic from northern mid-latitude industrial regions, some of them emerging but already of high concern in this sensitive region
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79" class="xref">79</xref>
 </sup>. We specifically focused on Hg, which is known to bioaccumulate in polar regions and severely impact marine top predators
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">38</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78" class="xref">78</xref>
 </sup>, but these other pollutants may as well impact little auk metabolism and ultimately their body condition and growth rate, such as organochlorine pesticides or PFASs
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80" class="xref">80</xref>
 </sup>. In addition, Hg disrupts breeding behavior in black-legged kittiwakes and snow petrels
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" class="xref">40</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81" class="xref">81</xref>
 </sup> and this mechanism could also explain reduced chick growth when Hg concentrations are high in our study. However, no link was found between Hg and adult survival in our study, as well as in other seabird species
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" class="xref">48</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82" class="xref">82</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84" class="xref">84</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
