<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We reconstructed a mtDNA‐based dated phylogeny to verify the existence of any genetic groups determined by BAPS, as well as to estimate divergence times. First, we used PartitionFinder 1.1.0 (Lanfear, Calcott, Ho, &amp; Guindon, 
 <xref rid="ece35065-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>) to determine the best partitioning scheme, and the Bayesian Information Criterion in jModelTest v.2.1.10 (Darriba, Taboada, Doallo, &amp; Posada, 
 <xref rid="ece35065-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>) to identify the optimal model of sequence evolution. The best‐fit model for all three codon positions was HKY + I (Hasegawa, Kishino, &amp; Yano, 
 <xref rid="ece35065-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1985</xref>). Then, to estimate a dated phylogeny, we used BEAST v.2.4.5 (Bouckaert et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35065-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>), with a relaxed log‐normal molecular clock (Drummond, Ho, Phillips, &amp; Rambaut, 
 <xref rid="ece35065-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>), and a coalescent tree prior. We used broad mutation rate priors. For the mtDNA locus, the range included Brower's (
 <xref rid="ece35065-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1994</xref>) commonly used insect rate of 1.15% sequence divergence per lineage per million years, and Luchetti, Marini, and Mantovani (
 <xref rid="ece35065-bib-0066" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2005</xref>) faster rate of up to 140% per million years, which was estimated from COII in European 
 <italic class="italic">Reticulitermes</italic> taxa. Based on point estimates obtained using approximate Bayesian computation (ABC; Beaumont, Zhang, &amp; Balding, 
 <xref rid="ece35065-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2002</xref>) assessments of competing phylogeographic hypotheses (described in Section 2—Step 3), we set the mean mutation rate at 12% per million years (see Section 3—Step 3) for the mtDNA locus. Since there was no mutation rate information available for the nDNA locus in 
 <italic class="italic">Reticulitermes</italic>, we estimated the mean mutation rate in BEAST by conditioning on the mtDNA locus and setting the initial mean value at 0.6% with a range of 0.2%–2% (obtained using ABC; see Section 3—Step 3). BEAST was run for 50 million Markov chain Monte Carlo generations, with samples saved every 2,500 generations, after discarding the first 5 million generations as burn‐in. We used Tracer 1.6 (Rambaut, Drummond, Xie, Baele, &amp; Suchard, 
 <xref rid="ece35065-bib-0083" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2018</xref>) to examine the stationarity of parameter estimates and to determine that effective sample sizes were greater than 500. BEAST was run with and without the out‐group 
 <italic class="italic">Reticulitermes</italic> taxa using the same settings. Results were summarized via a Maximum Clade Credibility tree in TreeAnnotator v.2.4.4 (Bouckaert et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35065-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>), with the first 25% of trees discarded as burn‐in.
</p>
