<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Climate data used in this study include precipitation (P) and potential evapotranspiration (PET), where the latter was derived from maximum (Tmax) and minimum (Tmin) temperatures [
 <xref rid="pone.0163941.ref011" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>]. Basconcillo et al. (2015) [
 <xref rid="pone.0163941.ref012" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>] statistically downscaled three GCMs under the Coupled Model Intercomparison Project Phase 3 (CMIP3) via the FAO-MOSAICC Portal (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mosaicc.da.gov.ph" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://mosaicc.da.gov.ph</ext-link>). ERA-Interim (1979-2010) is the reanalysis dataset used to generate climate data in the absence of actual climate observations. The quasi-observations were used as predictors for calibrating statistical downscaling models, which Manzanas et al., (2015) [
 <xref rid="pone.0163941.ref013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>] attested to its better performance compared to the JRA-25 (1.125° x 1.125°) when compared with actual observations in the Philippines. ERA-Interim data was also used as quasi-observational inputs into the hydrological model because of its spatial and temporal homogeneity compared to the Philippines weather station observations that contained many missing values. The atmospheric elements used as predictors are meridional/zonal wind (U/V), specific humidity (Q) and temperature (T). The identified set of predictors used for downscaling are—U850, Q850, T1000—for Tmin and Tmax and—U850, U300, Q850, and T1000—for precipitation. The study downscaled these three variables at the weather station level using the three selected GCMs. There are 47/33/36 Philippine Atmospheric Geophysical and Astronomical Services Administration (PAGASA) stations for precipitation/Tmin/Tmax, respectively. The study also spatially interpolated the station-level downscaled climate data using the Analyse Utilisant le RELief pour l'HYdromt́éorologie (AURELHY) technique to obtain 10 km-gridded data for the whole country.
</p>
