<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract class="abstract">
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Background:</title>
  <p class="p">Detection and attribution of health impacts caused by climate change uses formal methods to determine 
   <italic class="italic">a</italic>) whether the occurrence of adverse health outcomes has changed, and 
   <italic class="italic">b</italic>) the extent to which that change could be attributed to climate change. There have been limited efforts to undertake detection and attribution analyses in health.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Objective:</title>
  <p class="p">Our goal was to show a range of approaches for conducting detection and attribution analyses.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Results:</title>
  <p class="p">Case studies for heatwaves, Lyme disease in Canada, and 
   <italic class="italic">Vibrio</italic> emergence in northern Europe highlight evidence that climate change is adversely affecting human health. Changes in rates and geographic distribution of adverse health outcomes were detected, and, in each instance, a proportion of the observed changes could, in our judgment, be attributed to changes in weather patterns associated with climate change.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Conclusions:</title>
  <p class="p">The results of detection and attribution studies can inform evidence-based risk management to reduce current, and plan for future, changes in health risks associated with climate change. Gaining a better understanding of the size, timing, and distribution of the climate change burden of disease and injury requires reliable long-term data sets, more knowledge about the factors that confound and modify the effects of climate on health, and refinement of analytic techniques for detection and attribution. At the same time, significant advances are possible in the absence of complete data and statistical certainty: there is a place for well-informed judgments, based on understanding of underlying processes and matching of patterns of health, climate, and other determinants of human well-being. 
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1289/EHP1509" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://doi.org/10.1289/EHP1509</ext-link>
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
