<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2. Experimental Section</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Canadian and U.S. literature was searched using PubMed, SCOPUS and Cochrane Collection databases. The following search terms were included: drought, arid 
  <span class="bold">*</span> (
  <span class="bold">*</span> = the wildcard search character), desiccation, dry spell, water AND (shortage
  <span class="bold">*</span> OR scarcity), (low OR drop OR reduc 
  <span class="bold">*</span>) AND (water AND (level OR table)), Canada, Canadian, health. Articles published over the 20 years from 1993 to 2013 were considered for the initial search. Articles were screened by scanning titles and/or abstracts. Full articles were scanned where abstracts were missing or unclear. Articles were included where the linkages to human health and drought were made explicit. Articles from reference lists and/or in-text citations meeting these criteria, as well as from climate change and vector-borne disease expert-provided sources (peer-reviewed and grey literature) were also included.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The international literature was searched using the OVID Medline and Web of Knowledge databases. The following search terms were included: climate, climate change, health, public health, drought, adaptation, response. Articles published at any time up to December 2013 were considered. Relevant websites, such as the World Health Organization, IPCC, United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change were also searched using the same key words. Where appropriate, the entire article was reviewed for more detailed information. Articles were included if they discussed drought and human health effects and made explicit the link between the two, or if they discussed potential adaptations or responses to drought conditions. They were also included if the study was not limited to the examination of drought in a developing country/region and/or the results were applicable to the Canadian context. A number of articles were excluded given their limited relevance to the Canadian context including those focused on malnutrition, or infectious diseases that are rare in Canada, such as malaria, chikungunya, schistosoma and tick-borne relapsing fever [
  <a rid="B37-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37-ijerph-12-08359">37</a>,
  <a rid="B38-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38-ijerph-12-08359">38</a>,
  <a rid="B39-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39-ijerph-12-08359">39</a>,
  <a rid="B40-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40-ijerph-12-08359">40</a>]. Vector-borne disease expert articles were also included. The review of the Canadian and U.S. literature identified 64 records and the international literature yielded 72 records (duplicates were removed). This total (136) included 22 publications identified by climate change or vector-borne disease experts and 59 records identified within the in-text citations and references from the sources mentioned above. Broadly, evidence from developed countries and particularly from the U.S., Australia and the UK was considered to have greater potential relevancy than research focused on developing countries for this review, given their greater similarity to the Canadian context and of their populations in aspects that could modify health impacts related to drought (e.g., lifestyle, infrastructure and public services).
 </p>
</sec>
