<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.10. Socioeconomic Pathways Leading to Human Health Impacts</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Drought can affect social and economic wellbeing within a community through changes to water availability that can impact agriculture [
  <a rid="B176-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B176-ijerph-12-08359">176</a>]. The Canadian agricultural sector produced crop and livestock products totaling over $41 billion in 2010 [
  <a rid="B197-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B197-ijerph-12-08359">197</a>]. Costs associated with a drought can be significant. For example, total costs of drought across the Prairies in 1990 exceeded $800 million (equivalent 2011 Canadian dollars) [
  <a rid="B198-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B198-ijerph-12-08359">198</a>]. The more recent drought of 2001–2002 was responsible for $3.6 billion in direct losses related to agricultural production [
  <a rid="B199-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B199-ijerph-12-08359">199</a>]. Impacts on agriculture are passed on to the broader community and may lead to temporary unemployment [
  <a rid="B200-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B200-ijerph-12-08359">200</a>] and increase stress levels [
  <a rid="B176-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B176-ijerph-12-08359">176</a>,
  <a rid="B201-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B201-ijerph-12-08359">201</a>]. The U.S. drought in the 1930s and its impact on agriculture contributed to the Great Depression; there was high unemployment, increased demands on government aid programs and community impacts as millions of people affected by the drought moved to other communities [
  <a rid="B202-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B202-ijerph-12-08359">202</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The impact of drought on different segments of a society can vary [
  <a rid="B203-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B203-ijerph-12-08359">203</a>]. For example, the 2001–2002 drought brought significant impacts on agricultural production in Alberta’s “Special Areas”, but it was mainly an inconvenience for residents and businesses outside the agricultural sector [
  <a rid="B203-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B203-ijerph-12-08359">203</a>]. Similarly, the 1987–1992 drought in California (U.S.) led to primarily behavioral rather than economic impacts for residents [
  <a rid="B200-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B200-ijerph-12-08359">200</a>]. Loss of agricultural output in one area may drive up the demand and prices for farmers unaffected by the drought suggesting that some economic impacts may be highly localized [
  <a rid="B204-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B204-ijerph-12-08359">204</a>]. Globally, the impact of climate change on agriculture in different regions and countries, such as other developed grain-exporting countries can affect the competitiveness of Canada’s agricultural sector, particularly for wheat [
  <a rid="B174-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B174-ijerph-12-08359">174</a>]. A widespread U.S. drought in 2012 increased crop prices, resulting in new record highs for Canadian farm incomes overall [
  <a rid="B205-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B205-ijerph-12-08359">205</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The international literature suggests that drought can impact communities by shifting resources from services such as public health to address more immediate needs (e.g., sanitation), as well as leading to conflict over water between groups and regions [
  <a rid="B2-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-ijerph-12-08359">2</a>,
  <a rid="B42-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42-ijerph-12-08359">42</a>,
  <a rid="B59-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B59-ijerph-12-08359">59</a>,
  <a rid="B90-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B90-ijerph-12-08359">90</a>,
  <a rid="B206-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B206-ijerph-12-08359">206</a>,
  <a rid="B207-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B207-ijerph-12-08359">207</a>,
  <a rid="B208-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B208-ijerph-12-08359">208</a>]. Recent media attention around conflicts over water in the western U.S. states among farmers, activists, developers and governments at state and local levels suggests that conflict over water in developed countries such as Canada could be a concern [
  <a rid="B209-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B209-ijerph-12-08359">209</a>]. During periods of drought, water-related recreational activities may be cancelled or closed, such as during the 2001–2002 drought in the Prairies and the 1987–1992 drought in the U.S., which can have social impacts [
  <a rid="B174-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B174-ijerph-12-08359">174</a>,
  <a rid="B176-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B176-ijerph-12-08359">176</a>,
  <a rid="B200-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B200-ijerph-12-08359">200</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the Canadian context, data from 2005 show that over 90% of the water withdrawn in the country was to support economic activity [
  <a rid="B12-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12-ijerph-12-08359">12</a>]. The impact of drought on economic activities overall, in particular through reductions in power generation capacity, could be considerable. For example, between 1999 (winter) and 2004 (fall), seasonal decreases in precipitation of up to 60% compared to normal conditions were observed in the Canadian cities of Calgary, Edmonton and Saskatoon [
  <a rid="B9-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9-ijerph-12-08359">9</a>]. Hydroelectricity generation accounts for 62% of electricity generation in Canada [
  <a rid="B12-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12-ijerph-12-08359">12</a>] (A large amount of hydroelectricity is generated in Canada and when in-stream use is taken into account, this industry accounts for the largest amount of water use in Canada [
  <a rid="B12-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12-ijerph-12-08359">12</a>]. The volume of water used for hydroelectricity generation was over 70 times the total of all other combined water use in Canada in 2005 [
  <a rid="B12-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12-ijerph-12-08359">12</a>]. Thermal (nuclear and fossil fuel) power generation and manufacturing are responsible for the largest and second largest total withdrawals of freshwater in Canada [
  <a rid="B12-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12-ijerph-12-08359">12</a>,
  <a rid="B334-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B334-ijerph-12-08359">334</a>]). Shortfalls in this area could further amplify costs and stresses associated with drought, for example through the lack of revenue or the need to purchase alternative energy (see 
  <a ref-type="sec" rid="sec3dot12dot2-ijerph-12-08359" href="#sec3dot12dot2-ijerph-12-08359">section 3.12.2</a> for additional discussion of the health impacts of these shortfalls). During the 2001 drought, hydroelectric power generation in Saskatchewan fell to 66% of the past four year average in the province resulting in power being purchased from other jurisdictions to meet electricity needs [
  <a rid="B174-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B174-ijerph-12-08359">174</a>]. During the 1987–1992 drought in California (U.S.), hydroelectricity generation fell to under 60% of normal levels [
  <a rid="B200-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B200-ijerph-12-08359">200</a>]. Additional energy was purchased from more expensive sources [
  <a rid="B200-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B200-ijerph-12-08359">200</a>] and led to more than a $3 billion increase in electricity costs for consumers [
  <a rid="B204-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B204-ijerph-12-08359">204</a>]. Drought may exacerbate the substantial impacts anticipated with climate change. The climate change-related decrease in water levels anticipated across the Great Lakes is expected to result in direct economic impacts between 2014 and 2030 of $9.61 billion (2012 USD) due to impacts on recreation, shipping and harbours, hydroelectricity generation, waterfront property values and groundwater use [
  <a rid="B210-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B210-ijerph-12-08359">210</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
