<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.13.4. Public Education and Outreach</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Public education is a key adaptation to protect health from drought. Personal protection measures that can be promoted by public health officials can include reducing water- and vector-borne disease exposures [
  <a rid="B59-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B59-ijerph-12-08359">59</a>], wearing respiratory masks on days when ambient air quality could impact health [
  <a rid="B51-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51-ijerph-12-08359">51</a>], and the promotion of hand washing [
  <a rid="B74-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B74-ijerph-12-08359">74</a>]. Education for travelers to and from Canada can raise awareness about diseases such as malaria [
  <a rid="B80-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B80-ijerph-12-08359">80</a>], or tuberculosis, which may be increasingly transmitted under social conditions created by drought in developing countries [
  <a rid="B52-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B52-ijerph-12-08359">52</a>]. To prevent spinal cord injuries resulting from diving in shallow waters, some jurisdictions have implemented public education, including the posting of notices where diving is not safe [
  <a rid="B170-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B170-ijerph-12-08359">170</a>]. For example, brain and spinal cord injury prevention programs have been carried out in Saskatchewan and Ontario (Canada) and in Washington State (U.S.) [
  <a rid="B250-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B250-ijerph-12-08359">250</a>,
  <a rid="B251-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B251-ijerph-12-08359">251</a>,
  <a rid="B252-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B252-ijerph-12-08359">252</a>]. However, evaluations of these programs suggest that program delivery needs to be well designed and robust to be effective. Although the initiative in Saskatchewan was found to change knowledge among students, in the Toronto (Ontario) case only 16% of students in schools where the program video was distributed viewed the information [
  <a rid="B250-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B250-ijerph-12-08359">250</a>]. The one time intervention in Washington State, where students attended a session which included a video, lecture and personal testimony around traumatic brain and spinal cord injury, had little impact on knowledge or behavior [
  <a rid="B252-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B252-ijerph-12-08359">252</a>]. Similarly, evidence suggests that boil water advisories may not be adhered to by everyone. During the gastroenteritis outbreak in Walkerton, Ontario (Canada), some residents under the boil water advisory continued to use and occasionally drink the water without boiling it [
  <a rid="B85-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B85-ijerph-12-08359">85</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The link between water and hygienic practices should be considered when developing drought adaptation measures. Conservation should take into consideration on-farm agricultural practices, regional water management and treatment and allow for and encourage individual hygienic practices such as hand washing [
  <a rid="B46-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46-ijerph-12-08359">46</a>]. In the later example, homes and businesses could also promote both water conservation and hand washing by installing low-flow faucet aerators [
  <a rid="B46-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46-ijerph-12-08359">46</a>]. Education of health care providers can also benefit efforts to address drought impacts on health [
  <a rid="B53-ijerph-12-08359" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53-ijerph-12-08359">53</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
