<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Induction of NO accumulation and the complex signaling activities of reactive nitrogen as a result of exposure to atmospheric NO
 <sub class="sub">x</sub> means that all of the above interactions are relevant to our understanding of how both plants and their pathogens will react to changing atmospheric composition. As detailed here, these interactions are multi-layered and extraordinarily complex (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref>). This means that precise predictions of impact and risk will be difficult to generate, but nevertheless, some general points can be made. As the human population increases, leading to greater energy expenditure and to reliance upon ever more intensive agricultural systems, we can expect an amplification of risk from certain crop pathogens. As atmospheric CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> concentrations increase, we expect temperatures to increase in combination with higher or lower humidities in different areas, along with increased risks from unpredictable events like flooding and droughts. These abiotic stresses will combine with atmospheric NO
 <sub class="sub">x</sub> and other factors to alter plant stress signaling and thus susceptibility to disease (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3</xref>). Outcomes are likely to depend heavily upon pathogen lifestyle, which may alter the prevailing risks in a climate- and nitrogen deposition-dependent manner. Due to agricultural intensification and the fact that intensive agro-ecosystems and agricultural trade favor the evolution and dissemination of pathogens, it is likely that any group of pathogens favored in a given area will emerge as a serious threat to the food-security of that region. Mitigation of disease risk is likely to depend upon broad and flexible contingency planning; the most useful models are likely to be those built on a case-by-case basis, incorporating well-studied hosts and pathogens in specific geographical regions. 
</p>
