<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Land and ocean surface temperatures have increased globally by approximately 0.85°C since the late 19th century due to climate change (
 <xref rid="c19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hansen et al. 2010</xref>). The European marine temperate regions have been disproportionally affected and experienced a disproportionate warming at a rate of 4- to 7-fold the global rate (
 <xref rid="c44" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Reid et al. 2011</xref>). Indeed, over the last decades, northern Europe experienced a series of heatwaves, notably in 1994, 1997, 2003, 2006, 2010, and 2014, all of which were associated with a spike of domestic 
 <italic class="italic">Vibrio</italic> cases. Of these heatwave years, 2014 was the hottest year in Sweden since observations began in 1860, with a mean annual temperature 0.18°C higher than the preceding record in 1934 (
 <xref rid="c59" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Swedish Meteorological and Hydrological Institute 2014</xref>). The highest temperature this century in Sweden was recorded in August 2014. In Finland, 2014 was the second warmest year on record and 1.6°C warmer than the long-term average for the period 1981–2010 (
 <xref rid="c15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Finnish Meteorological Institute 2015</xref>). In July and August 2014, the SST in the northern part of the Baltic exceeded historic records; indeed, in some areas the SST exceeded the long-term average by approximately 10°C. 
 <italic class="italic">Vibrio</italic> infections during the summer and autumn of 2014 in Sweden and Finland exceeded the number previously recorded (
 <xref rid="c4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Baker-Austin et al. 2016</xref>). Across the Baltic Sea, 89 cases of 
 <italic class="italic">Vibrio</italic> infections were recorded in these two countries alone. Cases were also detected in the north of Scandinavia in the subarctic region that was affected by the 2014 heatwave. The SST anomalies correlated with the spatial and temporal distribution of 
 <italic class="italic">Vibrio</italic> cases in Sweden and Finland. A generalized linear model of these data indicated that maximum SST explained a significant amount of the variability in 
 <italic class="italic">Vibrio</italic> infections: an increase in the maximum SST resulted in a significant increase in 
 <italic class="italic">Vibrio</italic> cases (
 <xref rid="c4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Baker-Austin et al. 2016</xref>).
</p>
