<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The distributions of the majority of the native landcover categories grouped by climate are predicted to be reduced in total area, except closed forest. Therefore, there will be losses of total area for four of the five landcover categories climatically defined, which correspond to those that already occupy the smallest areas. Losses of these landcover categories range from approximately 20% under optimistic scenarios (RCP = 4.5) to their complete extirpation under pessimistic scenarios (RCP = 8.5), which could result in the extinction of many species and particularly habitat-specialists. In contrast, area coverage was predicted to increase for closed vegetation. At first, our results seem to contrast with most other studies, which predict that climate change will cause a reduction in forested areas. This outcome is particularly expected in Amazonia, where a savannization process [
 <xref rid="pone.0162500.ref062" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">62</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0162500.ref066" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">66</xref>], through a replacement of forested land by open and/or sparse vegetation is the most supported scenario [
 <xref rid="pone.0162500.ref062" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">62</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0162500.ref064" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">64</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0162500.ref067" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">67</xref>]. However, this contraction is expected to occur mainly in the central area of South America, where dryer environments are located [
 <xref rid="pone.0162500.ref068" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">68</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0162500.ref070" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">70</xref>]. The expansion of closed forest in our results is predicted mainly in the direction of the West and North coasts of the continent, with some contraction in the middle of the continent where Amazonian savannization is also predicted [
 <xref rid="pone.0162500.ref071" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">71</xref>]. However, the savannization hypothesis is still little tested, with supporting evidence only at a local scale [
 <xref rid="pone.0162500.ref071" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">71</xref>], demonstrating that more attention should be given to investigating this possibility. By predicting westward expansion of the Amazonian forest, our results bring more uncertainty to this discussion.
</p>
