<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Previous research [
 <xref rid="pone.0168880.ref004" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0168880.ref006" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0168880.ref013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>] demonstrated that avian malaria is a key factor affecting the elevational distribution, dramatic decline, and extinction of many native Hawaiian forest birds. Development of malaria parasites and mosquito demography are closely linked to climate [
 <xref rid="pone.0168880.ref011" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0168880.ref027" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>]; therefore, future climate changes are expected to exacerbate current malaria impacts on forest birds by extending season length and intensity of malaria transmission, as well as expanding the range of infection into high-elevation refugia. Benning et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0168880.ref022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>] first recognized the significance of malaria risks posed by future climate change in the Hawaiian system. They predicted a 2°C increase in temperature by 2100 would dramatically reduce the malaria-free zone found on several Hawaiian Islands, causing additional extinctions of many endemic species. Fortini et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0168880.ref025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>] used a temperature based species distribution model and the A1B climate scenario, with 2.6°C increase by 2100, to show that future habitat for many Hawaiian species will substantially decline as climate warms, purportedly as a result of increasing malaria risk. Despite the dire predictions of Benning et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0168880.ref022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>] and Fortini et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0168880.ref025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>], our analyses using a mechanistic mosquito-malaria-forest bird model for the Island of Hawai’i predicted higher future malaria transmission because temperatures used by Benning et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0168880.ref022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>] and Fortini et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0168880.ref025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>] are likely conservative (compared to a higher temperature RCP8.5 projection) and the impact of higher rainfall on mosquito dynamics for the A1B projection [
 <xref rid="pone.0168880.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. Despite these quantitative differences our results qualitatively agreed with previous studies [
 <xref rid="pone.0168880.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0168880.ref022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0168880.ref025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]: many threatened or endangered Hawaiian forest birds currently found in high-elevation disease-free forests will likely be extirpated, or severely reduced in both mid- and high-elevation forests as global temperatures and avian malaria transmission increase during the 21
 <sup class="sup">st</sup> century.
</p>
