<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">To counter these future threats to endemic Hawaiian forest birds requires the development and implementation of significant new conservation actions. Our results indicated the potential success of alternative strategies varied with the susceptibility of avian species to malaria, future climatic projections, and elevation. Apapane, which have both lower susceptibility to malaria and favorable population demographics compared to other species, were likely to persist at relatively high population levels during the 21
 <sup class="sup">st</sup> century despite increased malaria risk caused by climate change [
 <xref rid="pone.0168880.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. Therefore, conservation programs aimed specifically at Apapane were not likely necessary. In contrast, Amakihi, with intermediate levels of malaria susceptibility and capacity for demographic response, may be a suitable species for evaluating conservation actions in mid-elevation forests where they are currently relatively abundant. In addition, low-elevation Amakihi are one of the few Hawaiian species that have evolved tolerance to malaria infection; providing future hope that other Hawaiian species may also adapt to malaria. Iiwi, which have limited demographic ability to compensate for their high malaria fatality rate (&gt; 90%), are currently abundant only in high-elevation forests where malaria transmission is limited. Their high susceptibility means that future increases in malaria transmission will severely jeopardize this iconic species. Our results indicated conservation actions that maintain Iiwi populations in high-elevation forests under adverse climate projections (RCP8.5) would also benefit less susceptible species (Apapane and Amakihi). More importantly they would likely benefit other malaria-sensitive threatened and endangered Hawaiian honeycreepers that currently only exist in these disease refugia. In mid-elevation forests, single mitigation strategies were unsuccessful in maintaining (PGR near 1) or restoring (PGR &gt;&gt; 10) the scarce Iiwi populations. Instead integrated mitigation strategies were required to substantially recover (PGR &gt;&gt; 10) Iiwi to levels similar to those found in high-elevation forests.
</p>
