<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In an increasingly globalizing and specializing society, we are ever more dependent on what 
 <xref rid="bibr28-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Giddens (1990)</xref> termed 
 <italic class="italic">abstract</italic> or 
 <italic class="italic">expert</italic> systems. This is especially true for potentially globalized phenomena such as nuclear war or ecological catastrophe that people cannot “opt out of” (
 <xref rid="bibr28-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Giddens, 1990</xref>, p. 84). Such large-scale phenomena necessarily place the responsibility for management of associated risks on large, complex institutional contexts (
 <xref rid="bibr26-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Freudenburg, 1993</xref>). As society has become progressively more reliant on expert systems to manage risk, trust in the capacity of those systems and their component agencies and organizations to fulfill their mandate has come to have a significant influence on perceptions of large-scale risk (
 <xref rid="bibr26-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Freudenburg, 1993</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bibr38-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kahan et al., 2011</xref>). While “the central tendency is to see most such technological systems as having worked properly, the vast majority of the time” (
 <xref rid="bibr5-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Alario &amp; Freudenburg, 2003</xref>, p. 199), periodic failures that cause harm can also lead to questioning of the ability “of institutional actors to carry out their responsibilities with the degree of vigor necessary to merit the societal trust they enjoy” (
 <xref rid="bibr5-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Alario &amp; Freudenburg, 2003</xref>, p. 200). Thus, perceptions of the seriousness of risks depend in large part on the degree to which we trust actors in expert systems to manage them appropriately (
 <xref rid="bibr26-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Freudenburg, 1993</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bibr38-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kahan et al., 2011</xref>).
</p>
