<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par15">The overview piece in this issue is prepared by Busby (2018), Taking Stock: The Field of Climate and Security [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. In this essay, Busby surveys the progression and state of the science on climate and security over the past 15 years and outlines potential directions for policy-relevant research. He argues that researchers should focus their efforts on elucidating the intermediary mechanisms and contextual factors that may link climate change to conflict rather than continue to debate whether or not there are any direct associations. While efforts that focus on the causal pathways may be better matched to the needs of policymakers, Busby emphasizes that the existing academic evidence thus far is too limited and inconclusive to inform policy on specific practices, institutional arrangements, and other factors to mitigate the risk of climate-related conflict and insecurity [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. He suggests investigating the following pathways and contextual factors: shocks to food prices or changes in agricultural production, economic mechanisms, environmentally driven migration, and the role of institutions [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. He further stresses the potential for more complex interactions, such as disasters, which might lead to conflict via economic mechanisms or inadequate government response. He also addresses the strengths and limitations of the different methods. Statistical analysis may be useful in identifying hotspots of vulnerability and developing early warning systems similar to FEWSNET [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. However, Busby urges scholars to apply theories and knowledge to specific cases and ideally comparative case studies to generate the kind of contextual understanding and to ask questions that address the policy-makers’ need to design effective interventions [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>].
</p>
