<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Major decarbonisation of the energy system has a large part to play in climate change mitigation (Bruckner et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">2014</a>). However, components of the energy system are also affected by climate change itself, via long-term changes in climate parameters, variability and extreme weather events (Field et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">2014</a>). In this fast-moving field of research, it is vital that we take stock of the literature quantifying the impacts, assess how that understanding is being used in energy system models and identify key research priorities.
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate change impacts are expected throughout the energy system. On the demand side, the balance of heating and cooling demand patterns is changing due to rising temperatures. On the supply side, impacts include changes to the averages and variability of wind, solar and hydropower resources; the availability of crops for bioenergy feedstocks; costs and availability of fossil fuels due to melting sea ice and permafrost; the efficiency of PV panels, thermo-electric power plants and transmission lines due to rising temperatures; technology downtime due to changes in the frequency and intensity of extreme weather events (Ebinger and Vergara 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">2011</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">These physical effects have implications for the reliability, cost and local environmental impacts of energy supply. Furthermore, some impacts may result in an increased use of fossil fuels or reinforced infrastructure, and thereby increase greenhouse gas (GHG) emissions; for example, reductions in the efficiency of power stations, reductions in renewable energy resources or increased risks of storm damage to coastal infrastructure. These would undermine efforts to decarbonise the energy sector. To ensure mitigation and adaptation options can be comprehensively examined, it is therefore imperative that climate change impacts are thoroughly accounted for in the models which are used to examine the feasibility, costs and implications of energy system decarbonisation pathways. Further research into climate impacts on the energy system and their inclusion in cross-sectoral integrated modelling is highlighted in the Fifth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC AR5, Clarke et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">2014</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A number of previous reviews examine elements of this topic (Mideksa and Kallbekken 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">2010</a>; Ebinger and Vergara 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">2011</a>; Schaeffer et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" href="#CR62">2012</a>; Arent et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">2014</a>; Stanton et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">2016</a>; Chandramowli and Felder 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">2014</a>; Ciscar and Dowling 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">2014</a>). These focus largely on the climate change impacts on technologies currently in use and include relatively little discussion of the impacts on technologies which may become important in the future (e.g. bioenergy, carbon capture and storage), the levels of agreement between the results of different studies or the relative importance of impacts within regional energy systems. Comments on the strengths and weaknesses of the models used and the associated confidence that can be assigned to the results are also limited.
 </p>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To facilitate the further inclusion of climate change impacts in integrated assessment models of the electricity or energy system (IAMs), we aim to address these gaps by examining the following research questions: (i) In which areas does the literature largely agree on the direction and magnitude of the impacts? (ii) Which elements are not well covered in the literature? (iii) What are the key reasons for disagreement between results? (iv) How have climate change impacts been incorporated in IAMs? (v) Which research areas should be prioritised?</p>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This paper provides an updated, extended review of the literature on supply-side climate change impacts. Methods to incorporate impacts on heating and cooling demand in IAMs, mainly with heating and cooling degree days, have already been demonstrated by several IAMs (see OR2). So we focus here on supply-side impacts: on primary resources, generation technologies and energy transport. To examine the robustness of trends indicated in the impacts literature, we examine the levels of agreement between studies and the extent to which the system elements and regions of the world are covered (Section 
  <a rid="Sec3" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec3">3</a>). As climate change hazards, physical and operational resilience and adaptation capability vary significantly around the world, findings from impacts literature cannot be automatically applied across regions. We discuss the principal sources of disagreement between studies (Section 
  <a rid="Sec11" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec11">4</a>) and the ways in which climate impacts have been incorporated into IAMs (Section 
  <a rid="Sec12" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec12">5</a>), so that we can finally prioritise the remaining research gaps (Sections 
  <a rid="Sec13" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec13">6</a> and 
  <a rid="Sec20" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec20">7</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
