<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Literature review method</div>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For this review, we define ‘impact studies’ as those which model the physical effects of changing climate on one or more elements of the energy supply system, such as a primary resource or generation technology. We define IAMs as those which represent interactions between the wider electricity or energy system and some part of the earth system such as hydrology or climate.</p>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A semi-systematic search method was employed. Supply-side impact studies were identified via the references of previous reviews on this subject (Mideksa and Kallbekken 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">2010</a>; Ebinger and Vergara 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">2011</a>; Schaeffer et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" href="#CR62">2012</a>; Chandramowli and Felder 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">2014</a>) and a SCOPUS search using combinations of keywords relating to climate change, impacts and energy. From those search results, papers were selected providing they were published in English in a peer-reviewed journal since 2000 and focussed explicitly on physical impacts on at least one element of the energy system. For bioenergy, studies referring specifically to dedicated bioenergy crops were included. Studies employing both detailed climate change scenarios and fixed temperature/precipitation inputs were included. A database of the 106 supply-side impact studies, with details of their authors, subjects, modelling techniques and key findings, is presented in the Online Resource 
  <a ref-type="sec" rid="Sec21" href="#Sec21">1</a> (OR1). Studies which have incorporated one or more supply-side climate change impacts in IAMs were identified during the search described above and using additional search terms relating to electricity and integrated models. This method aimed to thoroughly identify the key literature, while remaining flexible and allowing for some judgement on the importance of various elements.
 </p>
</sec>
