<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" sec-type="discussion" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Adopting no-till management has many benefits for sustainable management of soils, such as improving soil structure, reducing erosion, enhancing soil moisture, and C storage
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span>. While many articles have promoted the last of these benefits
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
  </span>, our results suggests that no-till adoption on existing cropland is not universally applicable for mitigation of greenhouse gas emissions. In particular, reduced amounts of SOC deeper in soils may offset an increased amount of SOC near the soil surface with no-till management
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>
  </span>. However, there is a sufficient amount of SOC in the topsoil according to our analysis to enhance the amount of SOC across the profile in sandy soils of tropical moist/wet, tropical dry, warm temperate moist and cool temperate moist climates, as well as loamy, silty and clayey soils in tropical moist/wet, warm and cool temperate moist climates. The results are less conclusive for all soil types in cool and warm temperate dry climates, and loamy, silty, and clayey soils in tropical dry climates. Our mean estimates imply that ΔSOC is higher in soils managed with no-till, but there is also a chance that ΔSOC may be negative according to our confidence intervals (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>). Therefore, we cannot conclude that soils managed with no-till have more SOC than soils managed with full tillage for these soil types and climates.
 </p>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is important to note that in some cases, the larger amount of SOC in no-till soil may represent an increase or sequestration of C from the atmosphere if the soil is gaining C overall, but in other cases, may represent a lower loss of C, for example if a native grassland or forest land has been converted to cultivated cropland during recent years
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
  </span>. In either case, there is more C in the soil with no-till management compared to full tillage management, and therefore less C in the atmosphere.
 </p>
 <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In general, ΔSOC is greater in warmer and wetter climates than drier and cooler climates
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span>. The reasons for this cannot be determined based on our data, but explanations are likely related to differences in C input, decomposition rates and physical protection of C in the soil. In general, no-till reduces soil disturbance and increases aggregate stability, and enhances SOC in surface soils
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span>. However, there are constraints on physical protection of SOC in colder environments due to soil freezing and thawing that disrupts soil aggregates
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>
  </span>, and in drier environments due to rewetting of soils that can accentuate SOC mineralization
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
  </span>. Such processes may reduce the positive effect of no-till on C storage in soils that occur in drier and cooler climates. Another possibility is that crop production and C input is reduced with no-till management in drier and cooler climates. The literature on productivity differences between tilled and no-till soils does not indicate productivity and C input increases with no-till adoption in moist or wet climates
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>
  </span> and some results even suggest that there could be declines in productivity, particularly in cooler and wetter conditions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
  </span>. Furthermore, no-till has been shown to increase crop productivity under drier conditions, which may be explained by the benefit of no-till for enhancing residue cover and soil moisture availability
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>
  </span>. Soil biota also may react differently to management changes in dry compared to moist conditions. For example soil fauna may increase more in drier climates compared to wet climates following no-till adoption, thus increasing decomposition of residues
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>
  </span>. However, soil fauna may also stabilize SOC in soil aggregates
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>
  </span>, and therefore, it is not clear if the effect of soil faunal activity leads to a decrease or increase in SOC stocks
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There was a lack of detectable differences between inversion and mixing tillage. This suggests that turning the soil with inversion tillage and placing residue at a deeper depth compared to mixing in residues throughout the tilled soil layer does not lead to more SOC deeper in the profile with full tillage compared to no-till management. This is similar to other studies that have also failed to detect differences between these tillage types
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>
  </span>. Furthermore, there have been studies that found significantly higher SOC stocks with no-till adoption compared to systems with tillage management, but no differences between inversion tillage and reduced tillage management that also mix residue into the topsoil without inversion
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span>. Additional studies, particularly those that include both tillage types in the same experiment and measure SOC stocks deep into the profile are needed to further evaluate differences in stocks over the soil profile between inversion and mixing tillage. Until the differences between mixing and inversion tillage are determined with confidence, it is appropriate to pool these full tillage types to quantify the effect of no-till adoption on SOC stocks.
 </p>
 <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Erosion and deposition are key processes influencing the amount of SOC storage across landscapes. Eroded sites tend to have greater potential to stabilize organic C on soil mineral surfaces that are brought into the topsoil with erosion of soil on the surface; and deposition sites tend to bury C deeper in the profile where decomposition rates are lower
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>
  </span>. In fact, investigators have concluded from a global analysis that these processes have increased SOC storage by 78 Pg C in the terrestrial biosphere due to cultivation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>
  </span>. Agricultural experiments, where our data mainly originates, tend to be conducted on level terrain in which erosion and deposition are limited, and so our estimated ΔSOC does not likely incorporate this impact. Adopting no-till in fields subject to high erosion will reduce erosion due to protection of soil surface by crop residues. Retaining the topsoil likely better maintains productivity and thereby C input to the soil compared to sites allowed to become severely eroded over time to the point that production significantly declines. Maintaining productivity benefits food security and the associated C input will increase the 
  <span class="italic">in situ</span> C levels in soils. While studies suggest that tilling soils and enhancing erosion may increase C storage in soils
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>
  </span>, such practices cannot be recommended on highly erodible sites as a way to contribute to climate stabilization due to loss of substrate for crop production. The adoption of no-till on erodible sites may still be appropriate for food security as well as to reduce other negative effects of erosion regardless of the net effect on SOC storage across landscapes.
 </p>
 <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results have large uncertainties with confidence intervals that include rates of less than 0.1 tonnes C ha
  <span class="sup">−1</span> yr
  <span class="sup">−1</span> for many of the regions. In particular, uncertainty is high for loamy, silty and clayey soils, which is largely due to the equivalent mass adjustment associated with the impact of tillage on soil bulk density
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
  </span>. Sandy soils have a less developed structure, and so tillage appears to have limited or at least an ephemeral impact on soil bulk density, and consequently less uncertainty based on our analysis.
 </p>
 <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is also important to recognize that longer-term impacts of no-till management on SOC storage cannot be quantified from the existing experimental data. The longest study in our dataset is 45 years (See Supplementary Material, Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S1</a>). Long-term stabilization of C in soils is linked with bonding of microbial products in organo-mineral complexes
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>
  </span>. It is conceivable that the reduction of C in subsoils of no-till management systems could be reversed over time as microbial products in dissolved organic matter are leached from the topsoil into the subsoil and stabilized in mineral-associated organic matter. Further study will be needed to understand the longer-term dynamics associated with no-till adoption.
 </p>
 <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is essential to recognize that C storage has not been nor will be the primary reason to adopt no-till although this could be a misconception from articles that focus on this issue
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
  </span>. The value of no-till in minimizing erosion on cropland is well established worldwide to prevent or reverse soil degradation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">60</a>
  </span>. Furthermore, no-till adoption increases water conservation and crop water use efficiency, and investigators have concluded that global adoption of conservation agriculture, including no-till, is needed to overcome inherent water-related limitations to crop production if the world is to meet future food requirements
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">61</a>
  </span>. Greater water-use efficiency is related to direct benefits of crop residue left on the surface in reducing loss of water from evaporation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" href="#CR62">62</a>
  </span> as well as improved infiltration and soil water-holding capacity
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">63</a>
  </span>. No-till can also improve resource use efficiency through enhanced nutrient retention and availability. In a global meta-analysis, investigators
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" href="#CR64">64</a>
  </span> found no-till increased the amount of N mineralization by 13% compared to full tillage, and no-till can enhance cation exchange capacity
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" href="#CR65">65</a>
  </span>, which increases retention of several plant nutrients, such as potassium. No-till can also reduce the number of field operations and days that are needed to plant crops
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">66</a>
  </span>, which in turn, reduces fuel usage and associated GHG emissions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" href="#CR67">67</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" href="#CR68">68</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Even though at least 178 experiments have been conducted evaluating the impact of no-till on SOC, there is still insufficient information to make precise estimates of the ΔSOC, particularly deeper in the soil profile
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>
  </span>. Some combination of process-based model development and soil monitoring networks may lead to more precise predictions of ΔSOC potential in the future
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" href="#CR69">69</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" href="#CR70">70</a>
  </span>, but it seems unlikely that there will be sufficient studies in the near term to significantly reduce these uncertainties. Therefore, policy programs will need to consider the risk associated with the uncertainty in ΔSOC from no-till adoption relative to other options for stabilizing the climate by reducing anthropogenic greenhouse gas emissions. Other benefits of no-till adoption may be provide more compelling reasons for promoting this management practice
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71" href="#CR71">71</a>
  </span>, with C storage being a co-benefit for society to the extent that greenhouse gas emissions are reduced.
 </p>
</sec>
