<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Tussocks of the exotic hybrids between the native European cordgrass 
 <italic class="italic">S. maritima</italic> (2
 <italic class="italic">n</italic> = 6x = 60) and the invasive 
 <italic class="italic">S. densiflora</italic> (2
 <italic class="italic">n</italic> = 7x = 70) have been observed in these three estuaries. Two different reciprocal hybrids have been described, one whose seed parent is 
 <italic class="italic">S. densiflora</italic> (
 <italic class="italic">S. densiflora × maritima</italic>, 2
 <italic class="italic">n</italic> = 6.5x = 65) that colonizes middle marshes where its maternal species is more frequent, and the other is 
 <italic class="italic">S. maritima × densiflora</italic> (2
 <italic class="italic">n</italic> = 9.5x = 95, by unreduced gamete of 
 <italic class="italic">S. maritima</italic>) whose habitat is low marshes as well as its seed parent 
 <italic class="italic">S. maritima</italic>. These 
 <italic class="italic">Spartina</italic> hybrids are particularly abundant in the Guadiana Estuary (hundreds) while they are very rare (&lt;10 tussocks) in the Tinto-Odiel and Piedras Estuaries (
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Castillo J.M. et al., 2010</xref>). Both parental species are abundant in every location where the hybrids have established. 
 <italic class="italic">Spartina maritima</italic> is more abundant at low elevations (low marshes, drainage channels and intertidal ponds at middle marshes) and 
 <italic class="italic">S. densiflora</italic> typically forms dense stands in middle- high marshes, though it can also invade low marshes (
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gallego-Tévar et al., 2018a</xref>). Both 
 <italic class="italic">Spartina</italic> hybrids exhibit certain transgressive traits that confer hybrid vigor (
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gallego-Tévar et al., 2018b</xref>). These hybrids invade throughout the entire elevation range of the intertidal gradient, from low to high marshes, where they are able to displace native species and alter the typical plant zonation pattern of these salt marshes (
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gallego-Tévar et al., 2018a</xref>). At present, the current sterility of both reciprocal hybrids, 
 <italic class="italic">S. maritima × densiflora</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">S. densiflora × maritima</italic>, limits their expansion, but fertility by allopolyploidization is known to be a frequent process in 
 <italic class="italic">Spartina</italic> hybrids (
 <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Strong and Ayres, 2013</xref>). Both hybrids can be clearly differentiated in the field based on their phenotypes: 
 <italic class="italic">S. maritima × densiflora</italic> shows less dense tussocks with shorter flowered tillers with more nodes and shorter leaves than 
 <italic class="italic">S. densiflora × maritima</italic> (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1" class="xref">Supplementary Figures S1</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1" class="xref">S2</xref>). The flowering period for 
 <italic class="italic">S. maritima</italic> has been described between May and July and for 
 <italic class="italic">S. densiflora</italic> between June and December (
 <xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Valdes et al., 1987</xref>). The tussocks of these hybrid modular plants were considered genets (clones) that were composed by units of rhizome and aerial shoots or tillers (ramets). Genets (
 <italic class="italic">Spartina</italic> clones) were clearly differentiated since they formed distinct circular tussocks separated from each other by unvegetated spaces or by cover of other halophyte species. Those few clones that did not present clear boundaries or were coalescing with adjacent clones were excluded from our study.
</p>
