<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We assessed how well our climate sensitivity rankings matched three existing conservation priority assessments: Partners in Flight (PIF) maximum threat scores [
 <xref rid="pone.0135350.ref038" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>], IUCN Red List (IUCN) [
 <xref rid="pone.0135350.ref039" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>], U.S. federal status and Birds of Conservation Concern (FED/BCC) [
 <xref rid="pone.0135350.ref040" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>]. Federal status and Birds of Conservation Concern assessments were combined because the BCC list was developed to complement the federal list. For this composite category each species was assigned to one of three groups: FED, BCC, or neither. Measuring the relationship between Audubon climate sensitivity status and existing conservation priority assessments required that we assign numerical ranks to species based on their conservation status. PIF scores were already numerical, but Audubon climate sensitivities, FED/BCC, and IUCN categories had to be assigned ranks. We converted Audubon climate risk status to rankings, with the highest threat being assigned the lowest rank and the 
 <italic class="italic">climate stable</italic> group being assigned the highest rank (marginal and introduced species were excluded from this analysis as many of them are not classified according to one or more of the assessments). For FED/BCC, species were assigned a rank of 1 if they were federally listed, 2 if they were of conservation concern, and 3 if neither label applied. For the IUCN categories, species were assigned a rank of 1 if they were considered endangered, 2 if threatened, and 3 if considered to be of least concern. We then used Kendall rank correlation analysis to examine the relationships between climate sensitivity and existing conservation priority assessments (one correlation for each comparison—Audubon vs. PIF, Audubon vs. IUCN, and Audubon vs. FED/BCC).
</p>
