<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To investigate survival and the factors influencing it, we used data of 820 individually marked Natterer's bats and 625 individually marked Daubenton's bats at the hibernaculum “Brunnen Meyer,” an old well shaft within a small, permanently for bats accessible house, in North Rhine‐Westphalia (Stumpf et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35292-bib-0052" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>; Trappmann, 
 <xref rid="ece35292-bib-0053" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>), which was continuously monitored. By positioning harp traps at the entrance of the well house on multiple nights between 15th of August and 1st of October each year (Table 
 <xref rid="ece35292-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref>), Natterer's bats were captured and RFID‐tagged (ID‐100, Trovan) since 2002, Daubenton's bats since 2008. Age class (juvenile or adult) and sex were recorded for each individual (Brunet‐Rossinni &amp; Wilkinson, 
 <xref rid="ece35292-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>). Juveniles were distinguished from adults under careful consideration of several age characteristics (e.g., coloration of chin spots, epiphyseal closure, level of dental calculus and tooth abrasion, as well as the lack of signs of reproduction; Brunet‐Rossinni &amp; Wilkinson, 
 <xref rid="ece35292-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>; Racey, 
 <xref rid="ece35292-bib-0041" ref-type="ref">1974</xref>; Richardson, 
 <xref rid="ece35292-bib-0042" ref-type="ref">1994</xref>). If we were not able to identify an individual as juvenile without a doubt, it was treated as adult. All handling and marking of the bats were conducted under the permits for species protection issued by the nature conservation authority of the district Coesfeld (70.2.2.27, 70.2‐0197/08, 70.2‐0228/10, and 70.2‐2012/0254). A RFID‐logger antenna system (LID‐650, EURO I.D.) was positioned at the two small entrances of the hibernaculum. This allowed us to record continuously the unique transponder ID as well as the date and time of passing of tagged individuals during five hibernation periods (2010/2011‐2014/2015) without disturbing the bats (Kerth &amp; König, 
 <xref rid="ece35292-bib-0022" ref-type="ref">1999</xref>; Kerth et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35292-bib-0023" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>).
</p>
