<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Frost Occurrence: a Relevant Metric for Impacts on Mountain Environment and Societies</div>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We focus here on frost frequency evolutions, since this metric is of major importance for the rain-snow line, glacier melting or ice accumulation, the hydrology of the region and rock wall erosion though cryoclasty. Variability and long-term changes in frost frequency are thus accompanied by dramatic effects on the environment
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span>, landscape
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span>, and human activities
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span>. Under current climate conditions (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>), in the morning (Tn) during the winter season, the 0 °C threshold is almost never exceeded, except in the bottom of the lower valleys like Chamonix or Courmayeur (&lt;1200–1500 m). In the afternoon (Tx), the air mass warms and the occurrence of frost strongly decreases under 1500 and 2000 m asl. In summer frost is circumscribed to higher elevations, and frost predominates above 2500–3000 m asl for Tn and 3500–4000 m asl for Tx. These estimates (obtained as multiple regression based on observed temperature measurements
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span>: the “interpolation” step
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span>), are associated with very weak errors and uncertainties, and can thus be considered as reliable.
  <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Average frost occurrence (%, see colorbar) for Tn and Tx and for summer and winter seasons under current climate conditions (period 1979–2014) according to spatially interpolated observations. The black star corresponds to the Chamonix Mont-Blanc station in France (1035 m), the red star to the Mont-Blanc summit (4810 m) and the green star to the Courmayeur station in Italy (1224 m).</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_41398_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e378" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The next step consists in applying the same spatial models to downscale climate change simulations (the “downscaling” 
  <span class="italic">per se</span>
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span>). In such temperature estimates, the spatial variability is thus inherited from the statistical laws deduced, under current climate conditions, from the aforementioned interpolations, while the large-scale temporal variability of air temperature is derived from the global models involved in the Coupled Model Inter-comparison Project phase 5
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
  </span> (CMIP5). Using the same 200-m horizontal projected grid over the Mont-Blanc Massif and its surroundings, summer (JJA) and winter (DJF) mean temperature evolutions from 1850 to 2100 are compared to interpolated observations (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>). Our data clearly show the heat wave for summer of 2003
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>
  </span>, while the trimester of DJF 1989–1990 holds the record for winter temperature over the period. Over their common period, the difference between observations and historical simulations allows for an estimate of the typical errors of climate models over this region (Supplementary Figure 2). Models over-estimate Tn both in summer and winter, and produce much more realistic results for Tx estimates. The amplitude of the future warming is strongly dependent on the emission scenario. Optimistic RCP2.6 produces stabilized temperatures at about +1.5 °C compared to pre-industrial levels: it is the only scenario that meets the terms of the Paris Agreement on climate change locally, that is, a “temperature rise this century well below 2 Celsius degrees above pre-industrial levels”. Pessimistic RCP8.5 leads to a warming of roughly +2 °C in wintertime (+2.8 °C in summertime) by the mid-century, these values reaching respectively +3.8 °C and +5.6 °C for the late century. Although all downscaled models produce qualitatively similar results, uncertainties remain large, as denoted by the inter-model spread in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>. For the late 21
  <span class="sup">st</span> century for instance, and from one model to another, summer temperature rise is comprised between +5 and nearly +9 °C for Tx (+4 °C to +7.5 °C for Tn). Depending on the models, the record heat wave of 2003 could become representative of a typical summer season between 2060 and 2075. The abnormally warm winter of 1989–1990 could represent the typical winters of the years 2070–2080.
  <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Spatially-averaged temperature evolutions over the Mont-Blanc Massif for Tn and Tx and for summer and winter seasons. The spatial domain used for computation is that shown in Fig. 
     <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>. Black curves: spatially interpolated observations, period 1979–2014. Blue colours: historical (HIST) simulations, period 1850–2005. The solid curve shows the ensemble mean, the colour shading extends to ± 1 standard deviation to show model uncertainties. Green colours: the same for RCP2.6 simulations, period 2006–2100. Red colours: the same for RCP8.5 simulations, period 2006–2100.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_41398_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e416" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
