<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusions and Perspectives</div>
 <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In summary, the detection of a potential link between long-period climatic cyclicities (driven by astronomy and/or tectonics) and events provides insights into multi-disciplinary studies involving acyclic versus cyclic nature of Earth’s interior dynamics, astronomical forcing at multi-Myr timescales, and the possible interaction between astronomical and tectonic forcings. The correspondence between very long climate cycle extremes and events during the mid-Cretaceous to Cenozoic time interval suggests a highly nonlinear mechanism response, if the events were responding to insolation, such as astronomical pacing, at boundary conditions, of gravitational perturbation of the Earth’s spin axis and shape. This may, in turn, affect the gravitational deformation of the mantle, stimulate mantle convection and the dynamic topography, hence the occurrence of geodynamically paced climatic events. Cyclic tectonic forcing at the 9 and 36 Myr cycle bands, without evoking the nonlinear astronomical driving force, remains equally plausible.</p>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Future studies should focus on the cyclic vs acyclic nature of Earth’s interior dynamics (tectonics, volcanism,…), at ten to tens of Myr, and likely on how could Earth’s interior dynamics vary or interact with climate
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>
  </span>, and its potential link with the recognized climatic events. Other potential questions remain open, e.g., what would be the paleoenvironmental implications of the strong decoupling, at the 9 Myr oscillations, between climate and carbon cycles during the Paleocene-Eocene extreme greenhouse? Future studies should also focus on the origin of the ~36 Myr climatic cyclicity, by exploring the hypothesis of the possible link between GCR driven climates from vertical motion of the solar system, and insolation (Milankovitch) forced climates.
 </p>
</sec>
