<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with OASIS Tables v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archive-oasis-article1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jpoasis-nisons2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Environ Health Perspect</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Environ. Health Perspect</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">EHP</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Environmental Health Perspectives</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">0091-6765</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1552-9924</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Environmental Health Perspectives</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5743612</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">28731409</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">EHP669</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1289/EHP669</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Assessment of the Probability of Autochthonous Transmission of Chikungunya Virus in Canada under Recent and Projected Climate Change</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>Victoria</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fazil</surname><given-names>Aamir</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gachon</surname><given-names>Philippe</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Deuymes</surname><given-names>Guillaume</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a2"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Radojevi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>Milka</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a3"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mascarenhas</surname><given-names>Mariola</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Garasia</surname><given-names>Sophiya</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a4"><sup>4</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>Michael A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a5"><sup>5</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ogden</surname><given-names>Nicholas H.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="a1"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><aff id="a1"><label><sup>1</sup></label><institution>National Microbiology Laboratory</institution>, <institution>Public Health Agency of Canada</institution>, <institution>Guelph, Ontario and Saint-Hyacinthe</institution>, Qu&#x000e9;bec, <country>Canada</country></aff><aff id="a2"><label><sup>2</sup></label>ESCER (&#x000c9;tude et Simulation du Climat &#x000e0; l&#x02019;&#x000c9;chelle R&#x000e9;gionale) centre, <institution>Universit&#x000e9; du Qu&#x000e9;bec &#x000e0; Montr&#x000e9;al</institution>, Montr&#x000e9;al, Qu&#x000e9;bec, <country>Canada</country></aff><aff id="a3"><label><sup>3</sup></label><institution>Centre Europ&#x000e9;en de Recherche et de Formation Avanc&#x000e9;e en Calcul Scientifique</institution>, Toulouse, <country>France</country></aff><aff id="a4"><label><sup>4</sup></label>Department of Population Medicine, <institution>University of Guelph</institution>, Guelph, Ontario, <country>Canada</country></aff><aff id="a5"><label><sup>5</sup></label>Dengue Branch, Division of Vector-Borne Diseases, <institution>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</institution>, San Juan, Puerto Rico, <country>USA</country></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">Address correspondence to V. Ng, Public Health Risk Sciences Division, National Microbiology Laboratory, Public Health Agency of Canada, Suite 206, 160 Research Lane, Guelph, Ontario N1G 5B2, Canada. Telephone: (226) 971-1697. E-mail: <email>victoria.ng@phac-aspc.gc.ca</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>05</day><month>6</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>6</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>125</volume><issue>6</issue><elocation-id>067001</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>15</day><month>6</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>07</day><month>9</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>30</day><month>9</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><license license-type="public-domain"><license-p><italic>EHP</italic> is an open-access journal published with support from the National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences, National Institutes of Health. All content is public domain unless otherwise noted.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="EHP669.alt.pdf"/><abstract><sec><title>Background:</title><p>Chikungunya virus (CHIKV) is a reemerging pathogen transmitted by <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> and <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic> mosquitoes. The ongoing Caribbean outbreak is of concern due to the potential for infected travelers to spread the virus to countries where vectors are present and the population is susceptible. Although there has been no autochthonous transmission of CHIKV in Canada, there is concern that both <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> and CHIKV will become established, particularly under projected climate change. We developed risk maps for autochthonous CHIKV transmission in Canada under recent (1981&#x02013;2010) and projected climate (2011&#x02013;2040 and 2041&#x02013;2070).</p></sec><sec><title>Methods:</title><p>The risk for CHIKV transmission was the combination of the climatic suitability for CHIKV transmission potential and the climatic suitability for the presence of <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic>; the former was assessed using a stochastic model to calculate <inline-formula><mml:math id="M1"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and the latter was assessed by deriving a suitability indicator (SIG) that captures a set of climatic conditions known to influence the ecology of <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic>. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M2"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and SIG were calculated for each grid cell in Canada south of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M3"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>60</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, for each time period and for two emission scenarios, and combined to produce overall risk categories that were mapped to identify areas suitable for transmission and the duration of transmissibility.</p></sec><sec><title>Findings:</title><p>The risk for autochthonous CHIKV transmission under recent climate is very low with all of Canada classified as unsuitable or rather unsuitable for transmission. Small parts of southern coastal British Columbia become progressively suitable with short-term and long-term projected climate; the duration of potential transmission is limited to 1&#x02013;2 months of the year.</p></sec><sec><title>Interpretation:</title><p>Although the current risk for autochthonous CHIKV transmission in Canada is very low, our study could be further supported by the routine surveillance of <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> in areas identified as potentially suitable for transmission given our uncertainty on the current distribution of this species in Canada. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1289/EHP669">https://doi.org/10.1289/EHP669</ext-link></p></sec></abstract></article-meta><fn-group><fn fn-type="other"><p>Supplemental Material is available online (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1289/EHP669">https://doi.org/10.1289/EHP669</ext-link>).</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p>The authors declare they have no actual or potential competing financial interests.</p></fn><fn fn-type="other"><p><bold>Note to readers with disabilities:</bold>
<italic>EHP</italic> strives to ensure that all journal content is accessible to all readers. However, some figures and Supplemental Material published in <italic>EHP</italic> articles may not conform to <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ehp.niehs.nih.gov/accessibility/">508 standards</ext-link> due to the complexity of the information being presented. If you need assistance accessing journal content, please contact <email>ehponline@niehs.nih.gov</email>. Our sta&#x0fb00; will work with you to assess and meet your accessibility needs within 3 working days.</p></fn></fn-group></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Chikungunya is a reemerging tropical arboviral disease transmitted by <italic>Aedes</italic> (<italic>Ae.</italic>) mosquitoes. Chikungunya virus (CHIKV) was first isolated from human sera and mosquitoes in the Makonde Plateau of the Southern Province of Tanganyika (present day Tanzania) (<xref rid="c79" ref-type="bibr">Robinson 1955</xref>; <xref rid="c80" ref-type="bibr">Ross 1956</xref>). CHIKV disease is typically characterized by fever, headache, fatigue, and debilitating polyarthralgia and myalgia (<xref rid="c73" ref-type="bibr">Pialoux et al. 2007</xref>; <xref rid="c78" ref-type="bibr">Rezza et al. 2007</xref>; <xref rid="c79" ref-type="bibr">Robinson 1955</xref>). Symptoms generally resolve within 7&#x02013;10 days with the exception of polyarthralgia that may persist for several months to years (<xref rid="c9" ref-type="bibr">Brighton et al. 1983</xref>; <xref rid="c34" ref-type="bibr">Fourie and Morrison 1979</xref>; <xref rid="c44" ref-type="bibr">Javelle et al. 2015</xref>). Accordingly, the term chikungunya was applied to the disease and roughly translates as &#x0201c;that which bends up&#x0201d; the joints in the local language of the Makonde people (<xref rid="c79" ref-type="bibr">Robinson 1955</xref>; <xref rid="c80" ref-type="bibr">Ross 1956</xref>). Infrequently, the disease has been suspected to cause complications in severe cases with underlying medical conditions, including death (<xref rid="c26" ref-type="bibr">Economopoulou et al. 2009</xref>; <xref rid="c77" ref-type="bibr">Renault et al. 2007</xref>). There are no vaccines and treatment is supportive. Asymptomatic cases are rare and clinical manifestations so very characteristic for clinical diagnosis (<xref rid="c4" ref-type="bibr">Ayu et al. 2010</xref>; <xref rid="c34" ref-type="bibr">Fourie and Morrison 1979</xref>; <xref rid="c41" ref-type="bibr">Higgs and Vanlandingham 2015</xref>; <xref rid="c59" ref-type="bibr">Lumsden 1955</xref>). Post-infection immunity is life-long (<xref rid="c59" ref-type="bibr">Lumsden 1955</xref>; <xref rid="c73" ref-type="bibr">Pialoux et al. 2007</xref>).</p><p>CHIKV circulates via two distinct transmission cycles: <italic>a</italic>) a sylvatic enzootic cycle transmitted by a wide range of <italic>Aedes</italic> mosquitoes and among wild primate reservoirs in Africa with occasional spillover to humans; and <italic>b</italic>) an urban human&#x02013;mosquito&#x02013;human epidemic cycle observed in Asia and the Indian subcontinent (<xref rid="c49" ref-type="bibr">Kendrick et al. 2014</xref>) transmitted by two main vectors, <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> and <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> (<xref rid="c23" ref-type="bibr">Diallo et al. 1999</xref>; <xref rid="c47" ref-type="bibr">Jupp and McIntosh 1988</xref>). Until recently, the virus was restricted to Africa, Asia, and the Indian subcontinent where sporadic and isolated outbreaks are reported (<xref rid="c10" ref-type="bibr">Burt et al. 2012</xref>; <xref rid="c73" ref-type="bibr">Pialoux et al. 2007</xref>; <xref rid="c81" ref-type="bibr">Rougeron et al. 2015</xref>; <xref rid="c82" ref-type="bibr">Schwartz and Albert 2010</xref>). CHIKV appeared to subside in the 1980s and 1990s only to reemerge in urban outbreaks in Asia and Africa, initiating a large outbreak in 2005&#x02013;2006 involving millions in the Indian Ocean Islands and southern and central India (<xref rid="c10" ref-type="bibr">Burt et al. 2012</xref>; <xref rid="c48" ref-type="bibr">Kalantri et al. 2006</xref>; <xref rid="c73" ref-type="bibr">Pialoux et al. 2007</xref>; <xref rid="c92" ref-type="bibr">Weaver 2014</xref>). The unexpected reemergence of CHIKV in the Indian Ocean region was associated with the mutation of the virus that facilitated virus replication in, and transmission by, <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> mosquitoes (<xref rid="c85" ref-type="bibr">Thiberville et al. 2013</xref>; <xref rid="c88" ref-type="bibr">Tsetsarkin et al. 2007</xref>). Consequently, the mutation supported the geographic expansion of CHIKV into sub-Saharan Africa, Southeast Asia, and Europe (<xref rid="c85" ref-type="bibr">Thiberville et al. 2013</xref>). Autochthonous outbreaks of CHIKV in Europe were first documented in Italy in 2007 (<xref rid="c78" ref-type="bibr">Rezza et al. 2007</xref>), and in France in 2010 (<xref rid="c36" ref-type="bibr">Gould et al. 2010</xref>) and 2014 (<xref rid="c21" ref-type="bibr">Delisle et al. 2015</xref>). These outbreaks were initiated by infected travelers returning from CHIKV-endemic countries to regions in Europe where <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> is present (<xref rid="c92" ref-type="bibr">Weaver 2014</xref>). More recently, the first cases of autochthonous transmission of CHIKV in the Caribbean were reported in December 2013 on the island of Saint Martin (<xref rid="c71" ref-type="bibr">Pan American Health Organization and World Health Organization 2013</xref>). The outbreak has subsequently expanded and is currently ongoing with approximately 1.8 million probable and 65,000 confirmed autochthonous cases reported across 47 countries and territories in the Caribbean, Central America, and South America (<xref rid="c70" ref-type="bibr">Pan American Health Organization 2016</xref>; <xref rid="c90" ref-type="bibr">Vega-R&#x000fa;a et al. 2015</xref>). Although the outbreak in the Caribbean is caused by an Asian strain that is thought not to be efficiently transmitted by <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> (<xref rid="c63" ref-type="bibr">Morrison 2014</xref>; <xref rid="c92" ref-type="bibr">Weaver 2014</xref>), and the principal vector is likely <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic>, there is potential for the spread of imported cases by <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> (<xref rid="c41" ref-type="bibr">Higgs and Vanlandingham 2015</xref>; <xref rid="c90" ref-type="bibr">Vega-R&#x000fa;a et al. 2015</xref>). Associated with the Caribbean outbreak, 11 autochthonous cases of CHIKV were reported in 2014 in Florida where local <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> and <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> populations are established (<xref rid="c16" ref-type="bibr">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention 2015</xref>; <xref rid="c41" ref-type="bibr">Higgs and Vanlandingham 2015</xref>).</p><p>To date, there has been no local transmission of CHIKV in Canada due to the absence (to our knowledge) of reproducing populations of <italic>Ae. aegypti and Ae. albopictus</italic>. The cooler Canadian climate is likely a limiting factor for the establishment of these species, particularly <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic>, which is thought to require a tropical or subtropical climate to survive (<xref rid="c20" ref-type="bibr">Christophers 1960</xref>). It may be unlikely that <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> will become established in Canada even if temperatures continue to increase due to climate change (<xref rid="c14" ref-type="bibr">Capinha et al. 2014</xref>; <xref rid="c51" ref-type="bibr">Khormi and Kumar 2014</xref>). However, <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> is a cold-tolerant invasive species with the ability to overwinter in a temperate climate (<xref rid="c67" ref-type="bibr">Nicholson et al. 2014</xref>), which raises the possibility of the establishment of this species in southern parts of Canada. Occasional <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> mosquitos have been found in southern Ontario, although these are thought to be &#x0201c;adventitious&#x0201d; individuals rather than evidence of reproducing populations (<xref rid="c35" ref-type="bibr">Giordano et al. 2015</xref>; <xref rid="c75" ref-type="bibr">Public Health Ontario 2013</xref>). The species is, however, found in the United States where <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> is thought to be endemic to some southeastern states (<xref rid="c39" ref-type="bibr">Hahn et al. 2016</xref>; <xref rid="c52" ref-type="bibr">Kraemer et al. 2015</xref>; <xref rid="c69" ref-type="bibr">Ogden et al. 2014</xref>; <xref rid="c72" ref-type="bibr">Petersen et al. 2016</xref>; <xref rid="c91" ref-type="bibr">Waldock et al. 2013</xref>). The rapid rate at which <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> has spread and established across the United States and parts of Africa and Europe suggests that there is potential for this species to become more widely distributed in the United States and perhaps Canada, particularly under projected climate change (<xref rid="c27" ref-type="bibr">Enserink 2008</xref>).</p><p>For autochthonous CHIKV transmission to occur in a previously nonendemic location, four conditions must be met: introduction of CHIKV via an infected traveler (condition C1), a susceptible human population (condition C2), climatic suitability for a competent vector (condition C3) and climatic suitability for CHIKV transmission potential by that vector (condition C4) (<xref rid="c68" ref-type="bibr">Ogden et al. 2015</xref>). Canada is one of the leading destination countries for travelers returning from CHIKV-endemic countries over the summer months (<xref rid="c50" ref-type="bibr">Khan et al. 2014</xref>). In 2014, there were 320 confirmed and 159 probable CHIKV cases returning to Canada, up from 1&#x02013;20 cases per year in previous years (<xref rid="c24" ref-type="bibr">Drebot et al. 2014</xref>; <xref rid="c70" ref-type="bibr">Pan American Health Organization 2016</xref>). Because CHIKV infections can cause high viremia and a significant proportion (20%) of infected returned Canadian travelers are viraemic at the time of seeking medical treatment (<xref rid="c24" ref-type="bibr">Drebot et al. 2014</xref>), condition C1 is likely currently met although worth noting is that the majority of Canadians travel to CHIKV-affected countries during winter when virus transmission risk is lowest in Canada (<xref rid="c84" ref-type="bibr">Statistics Canada 2016</xref>). Although there is no population immunity to CHIKV in Canada, it may be that Canadian residents spend enough of their time during the summer months indoors in air-conditioned buildings and homes that the frequency of mosquito bites is too low to maintain person-to-person transmission. However, the endemic (and sometimes epidemic) transmission of West Nile virus resulting in human cases during the summer months in Canada lends support for the existence of condition C2. Although conditions C1 and C2 are important for autochthonous CHIKV transmission, this study focused on the ecological risk factors essential for endemic CHIKV transmission in Canada (conditions C3 and C4). The current climatic suitability for the presence of <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> in Canada (condition C3) was identified as unsuitable with the exception for southern coastal British Columbia and in south central and southeastern Canada, but northward expansion is possible with anticipated climate change (<xref rid="c69" ref-type="bibr">Ogden et al. 2014</xref>). However, we do not know the current and future climatic suitability for CHIKV transmission in Canada (condition C4), specifically, the effect of temperature on virus survival and replication within mosquitoes, mosquito survival beyond the extrinsic incubation period (EIP) (the time required for the development of CHIKV to spread from the mosquito&#x02019;s gut to the salivary glands where the virus can be transmitted), and virus transmissibility between humans and mosquitoes. In this study we explore the potential for autochthonous, but not necessarily sustained, transmission of CHIKV in Canada. We used a stochastic mathematical model parameterized for <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> under climatic conditions in the warmest months of the year in locations across Canada. We then combined the climatic suitability for CHIKV transmission potential in the warmest months of the year (condition C4) with climatic suitability indicators for the endemic presence of <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> (condition C3) to produce risk maps identifying areas in Canada most suitable for autochthonous CHIKV transmission under recent and projected climate.</p></sec><sec id="s2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="s2.1"><title>Climatic Suitability for Chikungunya Virus Transmission Potential</title><p>Transmission potential for CHIKV was explored by modeling the basic reproductive number (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M4"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) of the virus. We calculated <inline-formula><mml:math id="M5"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> using a model previously developed for yellow fever and CHIKV that accounts for the temperature-dependent EIP of CHIKV in the vector population and subsequent vector survival beyond the EIP (<xref rid="c45" ref-type="bibr">Johansson et al. 2012</xref>; <xref rid="c46" ref-type="bibr">Johansson et al. 2014</xref>). In this model, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M6"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the combination of two components, the average number of infectious mosquitoes produced per infectious human, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M7"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, and the average number of infectious humans produced per infectious mosquito, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M8"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>:
<disp-formula id="e1"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="EHP669_e1.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M9"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p><inline-formula><mml:math id="M10"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the product of the numbers of mosquitoes per person (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M11"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003c6;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>), the contact rate between humans and mosquitoes (daily biting rate) (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M12"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003b1;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>), the probability a mosquito acquires CHIKV from an infectious human during a blood meal (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M13"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), the duration in days that a human is infectious (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M14"><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>), and the proportion of mosquitoes surviving the EIP (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M15"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>):
<disp-formula id="d1"><label><x xml:space="preserve">[</x>1<x xml:space="preserve">]</x></label><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="EHP669_d1.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M16"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p><inline-formula><mml:math id="M17"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the product of the contact rate between humans and mosquitoes (daily biting rate) (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M18"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003b1;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>), the probability a human acquires CHIKV from a feeding infected mosquito (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M19"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), and the number of days an infectious mosquito survives (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M20"><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>):
<disp-formula id="d2"><label><x xml:space="preserve">[</x>2<x xml:space="preserve">]</x></label><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="EHP669_d2.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M21"><mml:mrow><mml:msubsup><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msubsup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p>The expected number of human infections arising from a single infected human in a completely susceptible population is therefore:
<disp-formula id="d3"><label><x xml:space="preserve">[</x>3<x xml:space="preserve">]</x></label><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="EHP669_d3.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M22"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003b1;</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p><xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref> is a summary of the parameters used in the calculation of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M23"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, which were obtained from a comprehensive scoping review for the parameter values (S. Garasia et al. unpublished data, 2016). The <inline-formula><mml:math id="M24"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> calculation incorporates three temperature-dependent parameters (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M25"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003c6;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M26"><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>, and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M27"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>). A stochastic model was fitted using the parameters summarized in <xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref> to calculate <inline-formula><mml:math id="M28"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for the temperature range between <inline-formula><mml:math id="M29"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M30"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>40</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. This range captures the temperature range over the summer months (June, July, and August) across Canada when mosquito vectors of CHIKV would most likely be active. To account for uncertainty in the parameters, a total of 50,000 iterations&#x02014;each sampling from specific distributions for each parameter (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t1">Table 1</xref>)&#x02014;was used to calculate <inline-formula><mml:math id="M31"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. The relationship between temperature and average daily mortality (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M32"><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>) was fitted to a polynomial curve using Matlab R2014a version 8.3. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M33"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> was calculated using Palisades Corporation @Risk for Excel v6.3.</p><table-wrap id="t1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Assumptions, distributions and mathematical equations used to estimate parameters in the calculation of the basic reproductive number (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M34"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) for CHIKV.</p></caption><alt-text>Table 1 lists parameters in the first column. The corresponding descriptions, assumption, and references; sampling distributions; and mathematical equations are listed in the other columns.</alt-text><!--OASIS TABLE HERE--><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="center"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left">Parameter (<italic toggle="yes">label</italic>)</th><th align="center">Description, assumptions, and references</th><th align="center">Sampling distribution</th><th align="center">Mathematical equation</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Daily biting rate (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M35"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003b1;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>)</td><td align="center">The number of bites on a human, per mosquito, per day. Parameter values for <italic toggle="yes">Ae. albopictus</italic> in other studies include estimates of 0.31 per day observed in Macao, China (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c1">Almeida et al. 2005</xref>) to a range of 0.19 to 0.39 per day in modeling studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c18">Christofferson et al. 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c60">Manore et al. 2014</xref>). We assume a modal value of 0.31 blood meals per day for <italic toggle="yes">Ae. albopictus</italic> in Canada (SD 0.04).</td><td align="center">Pert (0.19, 0.31, 0.39)</td><td align="center">&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Human-to-mosquito transmissibility (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M36"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>)</td><td align="center">The probability of a mosquito acquiring CHIKV from an infectious human during a single blood meal. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M37"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> has been estimated to be 0.37 to 0.40 for CHIKV in <italic toggle="yes">Ae. albopictus</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c25">Dumont et al. 2008</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c95">Yakob and Clements 2013</xref>). Recent changes in the virus indicate <inline-formula><mml:math id="M38"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> may be as high as 0.95 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c25">Dumont et al. 2008</xref>). <inline-formula><mml:math id="M39"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>H</mml:mi><mml:mi>M</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> was assumed to have a modal value of 0.40 (SD 0.09).</td><td align="center">Pert (0.37, 0.40, 0.95)</td><td align="center">&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mosquito-to-human transmissibility (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M40"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>)</td><td align="center">The probability of a human acquiring CHIKV from an infected mosquito during a single blood meal. <inline-formula><mml:math id="M41"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for CHIKV in <italic toggle="yes">Ae. albopictus</italic> has been estimated to range from 0.5 to 0.8 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c25">Dumont et al. 2008</xref>). <inline-formula><mml:math id="M42"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>M</mml:mi><mml:mi>H</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> was assumed to have a modal value of 0.65 (SD 0.06) with a lower value of 0.5 and an upper value of 0.8.</td><td align="center">Pert (0.5, 0.65, 0.8)</td><td align="center">&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Duration of the human infectious period (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M43"><mml:mi>V</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>)</td><td align="center">The period of time in days when infected humans can infect mosquitoes with CHIKV. The viraemic period for CHIKV is up to 8 days, with viral load peaking during the first 3 days of illness and declining from days 4 to 8 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c2">Appassakij et al. 2013</xref>). It is also assumed that humans are infectious a day or two prior to becoming ill (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c53">Lam et al. 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c58">Liumbruno et al. 2008</xref>).We assume a mean viraemic period of 6 days (SD 1.1).</td><td align="center">Gamma (30, 0.2)</td><td align="center">&#x02014;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Average adult mosquito lifespan in days (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M44"><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>)</td><td align="center">The life expectancy of adult <italic toggle="yes">Ae. albopictus</italic> at temperature (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M45"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) is calculated as follows, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M46"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M47"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is defined by a polynomial representing the relationship between temperature and the average daily mortality (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c46">Johansson et al. 2014</xref>). The following polynomial was fitted to <italic toggle="yes">Ae. albopictus</italic> survival in the field across a temperature range (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M48"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.1</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>33.0</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c6">Brady 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c8">Brady et al. 2013</xref>): <inline-formula><mml:math id="M49"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.33048</mml:mn><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x02013;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2.32772</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>01</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.68529</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>02</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>&#x02013;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mn>5.61719</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>04</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mn>3</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>+</mml:mo><mml:mn>7.91643</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>06</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mn>4</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>&#x02013;</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mn>2.72000</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>08</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msup><mml:msup><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mn>5</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:math></inline-formula> (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M50"><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.99</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>).</td><td align="center">-</td><td align="center"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M51"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Extrinsic incubation period (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M52"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>)</td><td align="center">The mean EIP (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M53"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003bc;</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) is a function of temperature (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M54"><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>) where:
<list list-type="order"><list-item><label>1.</label><p>Estimated EIP at <inline-formula><mml:math id="M55"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>28</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M56"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>28</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) is 6 days (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c46">Johansson et al. 2014</xref>)</p></list-item><list-item><label>2.</label><p>Relationship with temperature is assumed to be similar to those of dengue viruses, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M57"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.08</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c17">Chan and Johansson 2012</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c46">Johansson et al. 2014</xref>).</p></list-item></list></td><td align="center"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M58"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>28</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Gamma</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>9</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mn>0.667</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula><inline-formula><mml:math id="M59"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Normal</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.08</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mn>0.02</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="center"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M60"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003bc;</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">log</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>28</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>28</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Proportion of mosquitoes surviving the EIP (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M61"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003b3;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>)</td><td align="center">Temperature-dependent <italic toggle="yes">Ae. albopictus</italic> survival is calculated as follows, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M62"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02013;</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M63"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">log</mml:mi><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>28</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003b2;</mml:mi><mml:mi>T</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>28</mml:mn><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <inline-formula><mml:math id="M64"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mn>1</mml:mn><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M65"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003bc;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mi>T</mml:mi><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mtext>fitted</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>polynomial</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>described</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>above</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c6">Brady 2013</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c8">Brady et al. 2013</xref>).</td><td align="center"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M66"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:msub><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mn>28</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Gamma</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>9</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mn>0.667</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="center"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M67"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003b3;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mi>e</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>E</mml:mi><mml:mi>I</mml:mi><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mosquito density per human (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M68"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003c6;</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>)</td><td align="center">Under ideal weather, mosquito density is proportional to the minimal mortality where <inline-formula><mml:math id="M69"><mml:mi>L</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula> is the temperature-dependent average mosquito lifespan (see formula above) and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M70"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is the maximum mean lifespan; 10.9 days observed at <inline-formula><mml:math id="M71"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>27</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. In modeling papers, the mosquito density is estimated to be between 1 and 3 mosquitoes per person (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c19">Christofferson and Mores 2011</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c18">Christofferson et al. 2014</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="c46">Johansson et al. 2014</xref>). We assume for Canada that there are on average two mosquitoes per person under ideal weather conditions (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M72"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) (SD 0.6).</td><td align="center"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M73"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mtext>Gamma</mml:mtext><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:mn>0.4</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td><td align="center"><inline-formula><mml:math id="M74"><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003c6;</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mfrac><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>L</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mi>m</mml:mi><mml:mi>a</mml:mi><mml:mi>x</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:mfrac><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center">&#x000a0;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn fn-type="abbr"><p>Note: SD, standard deviation.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1</xref> describes the uncertainty of the parameters on the predicted <inline-formula><mml:math id="M75"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> between <inline-formula><mml:math id="M76"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M77"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>40</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. The mean <inline-formula><mml:math id="M78"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> values across 50,000 simulations were used to develop cutoffs for risk categories representing the transmission potential for CHIKV, these were <inline-formula><mml:math id="M79"><mml:mi>a</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>) unsuitable when mean <inline-formula><mml:math id="M80"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02264;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.5</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (corresponding to <inline-formula><mml:math id="M81"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10.0</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> to <inline-formula><mml:math id="M82"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mn>20.3</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M83"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02265;</mml:mo><mml:mn>35.7</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), <inline-formula><mml:math id="M84"><mml:mi>b</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>) rather unsuitable when <inline-formula><mml:math id="M85"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.5</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> mean <inline-formula><mml:math id="M86"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02264;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.7</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (corresponding to <inline-formula><mml:math id="M87"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02265;</mml:mo><mml:mn>20.3</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> to <inline-formula><mml:math id="M88"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mn>21.5</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M89"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02265;</mml:mo><mml:mn>34.7</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> to <inline-formula><mml:math id="M90"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mn>35.7</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), <inline-formula><mml:math id="M91"><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>) partly suitable when <inline-formula><mml:math id="M92"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.7</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> mean <inline-formula><mml:math id="M93"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02264;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.9</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (corresponding to <inline-formula><mml:math id="M94"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02265;</mml:mo><mml:mn>21.5</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> to <inline-formula><mml:math id="M95"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mn>22.3</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M96"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02265;</mml:mo><mml:mn>34.0</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> to <inline-formula><mml:math id="M97"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mn>34.7</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), <inline-formula><mml:math id="M98"><mml:mi>d</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>) rather suitable when <inline-formula><mml:math id="M99"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.9</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> mean <inline-formula><mml:math id="M100"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02264;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (corresponding to <inline-formula><mml:math id="M101"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02265;</mml:mo><mml:mn>22.3</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> to <inline-formula><mml:math id="M102"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mn>22.8</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M103"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02265;</mml:mo><mml:mn>33.6</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> to <inline-formula><mml:math id="M104"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mn>34.0</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M105"><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:math></inline-formula>) suitable when mean <inline-formula><mml:math id="M106"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x0003e;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (corresponding to <inline-formula><mml:math id="M107"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02265;</mml:mo><mml:mn>22.8</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> to <inline-formula><mml:math id="M108"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mn>33.6</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>). The <inline-formula><mml:math id="M109"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> cutoff values were selected on the assumption that transmission would not be sustainable when <inline-formula><mml:math id="M110"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02264;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.5</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, incrementally sustainable with increasing <inline-formula><mml:math id="M111"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> values between <inline-formula><mml:math id="M112"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x0003e;</mml:mo><mml:mn>0.5</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M113"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, and sustainable when <inline-formula><mml:math id="M114"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x0003e;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> where the virus is expected to spread in a susceptible population. To assign mean <inline-formula><mml:math id="M115"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> values and risk categories to recent Canadian climate, raw netCDF (network Common Data Form) files containing climate data (ANUSPLIN) derived from the interpolation of daily station-based temperature observations from Environment Canada were obtained for the period 1981&#x02013;2010 (<xref rid="c42" ref-type="bibr">Hutchinson et al. 2009</xref>; <xref rid="c62" ref-type="bibr">McKenney et al. 2011</xref>). The gridded observations covered all of Canada south of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M116"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>60</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> on a Lambert conformal conic projection with <inline-formula><mml:math id="M117"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>5</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x02032;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> arc minutes spacing (equivalent to a horizontal resolution of roughly <inline-formula><mml:math id="M118"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mspace width="0.3em"/><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">km</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>).</p><fig id="f1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1.</label><caption><p>Distribution of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M119"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> across temperature range at 25th, 50th, 75th, and 97.5th percentiles and the mean. Shaded contours represent corresponding risk categories for the mean <inline-formula><mml:math id="M120"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> curve representing the climatic suitability for CHIKV transmission potential.</p></caption><alt-text>Line graph indicating basic reproductive number (y-axis) across temperatures (x-axis) ranging from 10.0&#x000b0;C to 40.0&#x000b0;C (x-axis). The risk categories plotted are unsuitable, rather unsuitable, partly suitable, rather suitable, and suitable.</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="EHP669_f1"/></fig><p>Mean monthly temperature (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M121"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">T</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>mean</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) for each year for each grid cell was calculated by averaging the mean daily maximum and mean daily minimum temperatures together. The warmest month of the year was identified for each grid cell and a 5-year moving average was calculated for each grid cell to correct for interannual variability, and an overall mean was calculated for each grid cell representing the mean temperature of the warmest month of the year. A risk category corresponding to the mean temperature of the warmest month of the year was assigned to each <inline-formula><mml:math id="M122"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mtext>&#x02009;</mml:mtext><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">km</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> grid cell to reflect the transmission potential for CHIKV under recent climate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1</xref>). The number of months with temperature suitable for CHIKV transmission was also explored, which we considered to be those months with <inline-formula><mml:math id="M123"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x0003e;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (corresponding to <inline-formula><mml:math id="M124"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02265;</mml:mo><mml:mn>22.8</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> to <inline-formula><mml:math id="M125"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mn>33.6</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>). The climate data were processed using Climate Data Operator (CDO) version 1.6, Max-Planck-Institut f&#x000fc;r Meteorologie, Germany and NetCDF Operator (NCO) version 4.5 (<xref rid="c96" ref-type="bibr">Zender 2015</xref>). <inline-formula><mml:math id="M126"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>ArcGIS</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x000ae;</mml:mo><mml:mn>10.3</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (Environmental Systems Research Institute [ESRI], Inc.) and Panoply 4.5.0 (National Aeronautics and Space Administration) were used to create temporal-spatial risk maps based solely on mean <inline-formula><mml:math id="M127"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> values and corresponding risk categories.</p></sec><sec id="s2.2"><title>Bias Correction of Climate Models</title><p>Data from a simulation of one regional climate model (RCM) for the time periods 2011&#x02013;2040 and 2041&#x02013;2070 were used to explore CHIKV transmission potential under short-term and long-term projected climate change, respectively. The Canadian Regional Climate Model version 5 (CRCM5) (<xref rid="c40" ref-type="bibr">Hern&#x000e1;ndez-D&#x000ed;az et al. 2013</xref>; <xref rid="c54" ref-type="bibr">Laprise et al. 2013</xref>; <xref rid="c61" ref-type="bibr">Martynov et al. 2013</xref>; <xref rid="c83" ref-type="bibr">&#x00160;eparovi&#x00107; et al. 2013</xref>) was selected because this RCM has been extensively evaluated over North America. The CRCM5 has shown to have been substantially improved compared to previous Canadian RCMs in terms of seasonal mean statistics for both temperature and precipitation comparable to other modern RCMs (<xref rid="c61" ref-type="bibr">Martynov et al. 2013</xref>) and has the greatest skill among other RCMs for simulated precipitation (<xref rid="c22" ref-type="bibr">Diaconescu et al. 2016</xref>). The simulations used have horizontal grid meshes of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M128"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>0.44</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b0;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (corresponding to approximately 50-km horizontal resolution) and are driven by the recent version of the Environment Canada CCCma (Canadian Centre for Climate modelling and analysis) global climate model (GCM) or global Earth System Model version 2 (CanESM2) (<xref rid="c3" ref-type="bibr">Arora et al. 2011</xref>). With the historical period (1961&#x02013;2005) simulation, two runs were selected per future time period using the Representative Concentration Pathway (RCP, or greenhouse gas emission scenarios) 4.5 and 8.5 (RCP4.5 and RCP8.5), these scenarios represent an intermediate and a high greenhouse gas emission scenario, respectively (<xref rid="c89" ref-type="bibr">van Vuuren et al. 2011</xref>).</p><p>We used the Linear Scaling (LS) bias correction method (<xref rid="c94" ref-type="bibr">White and Toumi 2013</xref>) in order to adjust RCM time series with correction values based on the differences between mean observed (gridded ANUSPLIN) values and RCM simulation. The LS method aims to perfectly match the monthly mean of corrected values with that of observed ones (<xref rid="c56" ref-type="bibr">Lenderink et al. 2007</xref>). It operates with monthly correction values based on the differences between observed and raw data (raw RCM simulated data in this case). The LS method was applied to the CRCM5 simulation over the historical period as well as on the RCP4.5 and RCP8.5 future simulations. Comparison between the bias-corrected climate data from the CRCM5 model driven by CanESM2 under RCP4.5 and RCP8.5 and climate data from other RCMs driven by CanESM2 or the Irish Centre for High-End Computing EC Earth climate model (ICHEC-EC-EARTH) under RCP4.5 and RCP8.5 over two time periods (2011&#x02013;2040 and 2041&#x02013;2070) across Canada showed that the bias-corrected climate data from CRCM5-CanESM2-RCP4.5 and CRCM5-CanESM2-RCP8.5 used in this study were not far outliers compared to other models and did not deviate significantly from the ensemble mean (see Figure S1). The bias-corrected minimum and maximum temperature for each month and each CRCM5 grid were used to obtain <inline-formula><mml:math id="M129"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> values for each grid cell for the hottest month of the year, and to calculate the number of months each cell was suitable (if at all) for CHIKV transmission. A risk category corresponding to the mean temperature of the warmest month of the year was assigned to each <inline-formula><mml:math id="M130"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>50</mml:mn><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">km</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> grid cell representing the transmission potential for CHIKV under short-term and long-term projected climatic conditions simulated using the two different emission scenarios.</p></sec><sec id="s2.3"><title>Climatic Suitability for the Presence of <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic></title><p>We used the linear index of precipitation and air temperature suitability described by a sigmoidal function (SIG) to assess the climatic suitability for <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic>. The SIG index was originally developed to assess the climatic suitability of <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> in Europe (<xref rid="c11" ref-type="bibr">Caminade et al. 2012</xref>; <xref rid="c28" ref-type="bibr">European Center for Disease Prevention and Control 2009</xref>) and was found to be a good fit to the current distribution of this species in the United States (<xref rid="c69" ref-type="bibr">Ogden et al. 2014</xref>). The SIG index is defined by three components: <italic>a</italic>) January mean temperatures (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M131"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">T</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>mean</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>), <italic>b</italic>) summer mean temperatures (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M132"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">T</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>mean</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> from June to August) and <italic>c</italic>) total annual precipitation; each component is transformed into an interval ranging between 0 and 255 using sigmoidal functions. These three components are then linearly combined using the arithmetic mean and rescaled to a range between 0 and 100 to derive a suitability indicator that captures a set of climatic conditions known to influence the ecology of <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> as previously described (<xref rid="c11" ref-type="bibr">Caminade et al. 2012</xref>). A SIG value was calculated for each grid cell below <inline-formula><mml:math id="M133"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>60</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> covering Canada using observed climate data (ANUSPLIN, over the 1981&#x02013;2010 period) and bias-corrected projected climate simulated data (CRCM5 under the RCP4.5 and RCP8.5, over the 2011&#x02013;2040 and 2041&#x02013;2070 periods). Bias-corrected temperature and precipitation data for each grid cell were detrended over time periods using 5-year moving averages. In the United States, <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> was not observed below a SIG value of 66.7 (sensitivity of 84.5% and specificity of 92.2%) (<xref rid="c69" ref-type="bibr">Ogden et al. 2014</xref>). Accordingly, suitability classes corresponding to SIG values were derived for Canada, these were <italic>a</italic>) unsuitable when <inline-formula><mml:math id="M134"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>SIG</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mn>66.7</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <italic>b</italic>) moderate when <inline-formula><mml:math id="M135"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>SIG</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x02265;</mml:mo><mml:mn>66.7</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M136"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>SIG</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mn>75</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <italic>c</italic>) high when <inline-formula><mml:math id="M137"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>SIG</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x02265;</mml:mo><mml:mn>75</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M138"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>SIG</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mn>85</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, <italic>d</italic>) very high when <inline-formula><mml:math id="M139"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>SIG</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x02265;</mml:mo><mml:mn>85</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M140"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>SIG</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mn>95</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, and <italic>e</italic>) totally suitable when <inline-formula><mml:math id="M141"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>SIG</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x02265;</mml:mo><mml:mn>95</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. The SIG cutoff values were selected to approximately distribute values from 66.7 to 100 equally across suitability classes on the assumption that <inline-formula><mml:math id="M142"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>SIG</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x02265;</mml:mo><mml:mn>66.7</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> is not suitable for <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic>, incrementally suitable with increasing SIG values between 66.7 and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M143"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x0003c;</mml:mo><mml:mn>95</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, and very suitable when <inline-formula><mml:math id="M144"><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>SIG</mml:mtext><mml:mo>&#x02265;</mml:mo><mml:mn>95</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. A suitability class corresponding to SIG values was assigned to each grid cell for each of the five climate datasets.</p></sec><sec id="s2.4"><title>Climatic Suitability for Potential Autochthonous CHIKV Transmission in Canada</title><p>The risk categories for CHIKV transmission potential (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M145"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) were overlain with the SIG suitability classes representing the presence of <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> to produce overall risk categories that allowed risk maps to be drawn that identify areas in Canada at risk for short-term autochthonous CHIKV transmission under recent and projected climate change. Similar to other studies in Europe (<xref rid="c29" ref-type="bibr">Fischer et al. 2010</xref>; <xref rid="c32" ref-type="bibr">Fischer et al. 2013</xref>), we assumed that climatic suitability for CHIKV transmission potential in combination with climatic suitability for the presence of <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> results in higher risk for autochthonous CHIKV transmission via this particular vector. Accordingly, the <inline-formula><mml:math id="M146"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> values and their corresponding risk categories reflecting the transmission potential for CHIKV for each grid cell (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1</xref>) were combined with the SIG values and their corresponding suitability classes reflecting the climatic suitability for <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> for each grid cell to produce an overall CHIKV suitability risk category (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure 2</xref>). This overall CHIKV suitability risk classification was then assigned to each grid cell in Canada for each of the five climate datasets. ArcGIS&#x000ae;10.3 [Environmental Systems Research Institute (ESRI), Inc.] and Panoply 4.5.0 (National Aeronautics and Space Administration) were used to create temporal-spatial risk maps based on the overall CHIKV suitability risk classification.</p><fig id="f2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2.</label><caption><p>Risk categories for autochthonous CHIKV transmission by <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> in Canada derived from combining the climatic suitability for CHIKV transmission potential (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M147"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) with the climatic suitability for the presence of <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> (SIG index).</p></caption><alt-text>Table indicates CHIKV transmission potential, the corresponding temperature intervals, and the climatic suitability for the presence of Aedes albopictus (SIG index). The grid plots their relationships as CHIKV suitability risk categories, namely, unsuitable, rather unsuitable, partly suitable, rather suitable, and suitable.</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="EHP669_f2"/></fig></sec><sec id="s2.5"><title>Sensitivity Analysis</title><p>We assessed the sensitivity of our assessments to the selection of parameter values in the transmission model by mapping the risk for autochthonous CHIKV transmission when using parameter values for the 75th percentile value of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M148"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (see Figure S2) rather than mean <inline-formula><mml:math id="M149"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2">Figure 2</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec id="s3.1"><title>Risk Classification for Chikungunya Virus Transmission Potential</title><p>Our model of climatic suitability for CHIKV transmission potential indicated optimal suitability when the mean monthly temperature of the warmest month of the year is between <inline-formula><mml:math id="M150"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02265;</mml:mo><mml:mn>22.8</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M151"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>33.6</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M152"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x0003e;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure 1</xref>). <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure 3</xref> shows the areas in Canada that have at least 1 month in the year where the climate is suitable for autochthonous CHIKV transmission based solely on modeling temperature-dependent <inline-formula><mml:math id="M153"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> without consideration of the climatic suitability for the presence of <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic>. Under recent climate (observed ANUSPLIN 1981-2010), the majority of Canada does not have 1 month in the year when mean temperature is <inline-formula><mml:math id="M154"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02265;</mml:mo><mml:mn>22.8</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and thus is not currently climatically suitable for autochthonous CHIKV transmission. One small area in southern Ontario, where mean summer temperature is <inline-formula><mml:math id="M155"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02265;</mml:mo><mml:mn>22.8</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, was suitable but this is limited to only 1 month of the year (July) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Figure 4</xref>). Under short-term projected climate (2011&#x02013;2040) for both RCP4.5 and RCP8.5 scenarios, locations in southern parts of the provinces of Ontario, Qu&#x000e9;bec, British Columbia, and the Canadian Prairies (Alberta, Saskatchewan, and Manitoba) become increasingly favorable for CHIKV transmission based solely on modeling temperature-dependent <inline-formula><mml:math id="M156"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure 3</xref>), although this is limited to 2 months in the year (July and August) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Figure 4</xref>). Under long-term projected climate (2041&#x02013;2070) for both emission scenarios, further areas across Canada become favorable for CHIKV transmission based solely on modeling temperature-dependent <inline-formula><mml:math id="M157"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure 3</xref>) and the transmission period expands to 3 months in the year (June to August) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">Figure 4</xref>). However, the risk maps in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figures 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4">4</xref> are based solely on <inline-formula><mml:math id="M158"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and the recent climate (1980&#x02013;2010) risk maps are only relevant if vectors competent for transmitting CHIKV other than <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> exist in Canada given the absence of this vector under the current climate. However, it is possible that <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> could survive in some of the identified risk areas under short-term (2011&#x02013;2040) and long-term (2041&#x02013;2070) projected climate.</p><fig id="f3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3.</label><caption><p>Risk maps for autochthonous CHIKV transmission in Canada based solely on CHIKV transmission potential (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M159"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>); transmission potential represents risk based on having at least 1 month per year with CHIKV transmission potential. Provincial and territorial boundaries of Canada, 2001. Source: &#x000a9; 2003. Government of Canada with permission from Natural Resources Canada.</p></caption><alt-text>Five maps indicating recent climate (1981&#x02013;2010), short-term projected climate (2011&#x02013;2040) for RCP4.5 and RCP8.5, and long-term projected climate (2041&#x02013;2070) for RCP4.5 and RCP8.5. Chikangunya virus transmission potential (R subscript 0) ranges are less than or equal to 0.5; greater than 0.5 to less than or equal to 0.7; greater than 0.7 to less than or equal to 0.9; greater than 0.9 to less than or equal to 1.0; and greater than 1.0.</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="EHP669_f3"/></fig><fig id="f4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4.</label><caption><p>Duration in months where mean <inline-formula><mml:math id="M160"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x0003e;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (mean monthly temperature between <inline-formula><mml:math id="M161"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02265;</mml:mo><mml:mn>22.8</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> and <inline-formula><mml:math id="M162"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>33.6</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) in Canada based solely on CHIKV transmission potential (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M163"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>). Provincial and territorial boundaries of Canada, 2001. Source: &#x000a9; 2003. Government of Canada with permission from Natural Resources Canada.</p></caption><alt-text>Five maps indicating recent climate (1981&#x02013;2010), short-term projected climate (2011&#x02013;2040) for RCP4.5 and RCP8.5, and long-term projected climate (2041&#x02013;2070) for RCP4.5 and RCP8.5. The number of months where R subscript 0 is greater than 1.0 are 0, 1 (July), 2 (July and August), and 3 (June, July, and August).</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="EHP669_f4"/></fig><p>When using transmission model parameter values for the 75th percentile value of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M164"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> rather than mean <inline-formula><mml:math id="M165"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, a larger area of southern Ontario becomes suitable for transmission (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M166"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x0003e;</mml:mo><mml:mn>1.0</mml:mn></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) under recent climate but this remains limited to 1 month of the year (July) (see Figure S3). Under RCP4.5 2011&#x02013;2040, areas suitable for transmission have expanded across southern Ontario and Qu&#x000e9;bec and into British Columbia. Under RCP4.5 2041&#x02013;2070, larger areas of southern Ontario, Qu&#x000e9;bec, and British Columbia become suitable for transmission, in addition, parts of southern Alberta, Saskatchewan, Manitoba, New Brunswick, Nova Scotia, and western Ontario become suitable for transmission. Under RCP8.5 for both 2011&#x02013;2040 and 2041&#x02013;2070, the southern parts of provinces between British Columbia and Qu&#x000e9;bec become suitable for transmission with concentration of suitability expanding significantly in southern Alberta, Saskatchewan, Manitoba and Qu&#x000e9;bec and western and southern Ontario under long-term projected climate. Additional areas in southern New Brunswick and Nova Scotia become suitable under long-term projected climate. No new high risk areas were identified when compared with maps produced using mean <inline-formula><mml:math id="M167"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure 3</xref>). The time period of possible transmission remains between 2 and 3 months (June to August) under RCP4.5 2011&#x02013;2040, RCP4.5 2041&#x02013;2070 and RCP8.5 2011&#x02013;2040 scenarios but increases to up to 4 months (June to September) under RCP8.5 2041&#x02013;2070 (see Figure S4).</p></sec><sec id="s3.2"><title>Risk Classification for Autochthonous Chikungunya Virus Transmission in Canada</title><p>When climatic suitability risk categories of CHIKV transmission potential (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M168"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) were overlain with climatic suitability for the presence of <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> populations, the risk for autochthonous CHIKV transmission by <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> under recent climate (1981&#x02013;2010) was very low with all of Canada classified as unsuitable or rather unsuitable for CHIKV transmission (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Figure 5</xref>). Under short-term projected climate (2011&#x02013;2040) for both RCP4.5 and RCP8.5 scenarios, a small area of southern coastal British Columbia becomes partly suitable for CHIKV transmission but the rest of Canada remains unsuitable or rather unsuitable for transmission (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Figure 5</xref>). Under long-term projected climate (2041&#x02013;2070), for both emission scenarios, an increasingly larger area of southern coastal British Columbia becomes rather suitable or suitable for CHIKV transmission (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Figure 5</xref>). However, for these areas the duration of climate suitable for potential transmission is limited to 1&#x02013;2 months in the year (August under RCP4.5 and July&#x02013;August under RCP8.5) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6">Figure 6</xref>). The rest of Canada remains unsuitable or rather unsuitable for CHIKV transmission under long-term projected climate (2041&#x02013;2070) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Figure 5</xref>). Although the risk maps for transmission based solely on CHIKV transmission potential (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M169"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) suggests southern Ontario is currently most suitable due to warmer summer temperature (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3">Figure 3</xref>), after taking into account climatic requirements for the presence of <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic>, the current climatic suitability for CHIKV transmission via this vector in southern Ontario and the rest of Canada is very low (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Figure 5</xref>). Therefore, the future climatic suitability for autochthonous CHIKV transmission in Canada via <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> is expected to be limited to southern coastal British Columbia with possible transmission restricted to 1&#x02013;2 months in the year (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5">Figures 5</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6">6</xref>).</p><fig id="f5" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5.</label><caption><p>Risk maps for autochthonous CHIKV transmission in Canada combining the climatic suitability for CHIKV transmission potential (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M170"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) with the climatic suitability for the presence of <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> (SIG index). Provincial and territorial boundaries of Canada, 2001. Source: &#x000a9; 2003. Government of Canada with permission from Natural Resources Canada.</p></caption><alt-text>Five maps indicating recent climate (1981&#x02013;2010), short-term projected climate (2011&#x02013;2040) for RCP4.5 and RCP8.5, and long-term projected climate (2041&#x02013;2070) for RCP4.5 and RCP8.5. The risk categories for climatic suitability for Chikungunya transmission are unsuitable, rather unsuitable, partly suitable, rather suitable, and suitable.</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="EHP669_f5"/></fig><fig id="f6" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6.</label><caption><p>Duration in months for potential autochthonous CHIKV transmission in Canada combining the climatic suitability for CHIKV transmission potential (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M171"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) with the climatic suitability for the presence of <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> (SIG index). Provincial and territorial boundaries of Canada, 2001. Source: &#x000a9; 2003. Government of Canada with permission from Natural Resources Canada.</p></caption><alt-text>Five maps indicating recent climate (1981&#x02013;2010), short-term projected climate (2011&#x02013;2040) for RCP4.5 and RCP8.5, and long-term projected climate (2041&#x02013;2070) for RCP4.5 and RCP8.5. The number of months of climatic suitability for Chikungunya transmission are 0, 1 (August), and 2 (July and August).</alt-text><graphic xlink:href="EHP669_f6"/></fig><p>The implications of using the 75th percentile value of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M172"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> rather than the mean <inline-formula><mml:math id="M173"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> in sensitivity analysis was similar for the <inline-formula><mml:math id="M174"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> model. Under recent climate, all of Canada remains unsuitable or rather unsuitable for CHIKV transmission (see Figure S5). Under short-term projected climate (2011&#x02013;2040) for both RCP4.5 and RCP8.5 scenarios, the small area of southern coastal British Columbia that was identified as partly suitable for transmission using mean <inline-formula><mml:math id="M175"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> has become rather suitable for transmission but the rest of Canada remains unsuitable or rather unsuitable for transmission. Under long-term projected climate (2041&#x02013;2070), for both emission scenarios, an increasingly larger area of southern coastal British Columbia becomes rather suitable and suitable for transmission; these areas are larger and further north along the coast compared to areas identified as suitable for transmission using mean <inline-formula><mml:math id="M176"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. The rest of Canada remains unsuitable or rather unsuitable for CHIKV transmission under long-term projected climate. The duration of climate suitable for potential transmission remains limited to 1&#x02013;2 months of the year (July&#x02013;August) (see Figure S6) and no new high risk areas were identified.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><p>In this study we investigated the climatic suitability for autochthonous CHIKV transmission in Canada. The objective was to quantitatively assess the current and future climatic suitability for CHIKV transmission under two greenhouse gas emissions scenarios (RCP4.5 and RCP8.5) using simulations from RCM to provide insight into where, when and for how long local transmission of CHIKV might occur in Canada. To achieve this, we assessed the climatic suitability for CHIKV transmission potential (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M177"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) and combined this with the climatic suitability for the presence of <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> (<xref rid="c68" ref-type="bibr">Ogden et al. 2015</xref>), on the assumption that for autochthonous transmission to occur, there must be climatic suitability for both pathogen transmission for a minimum of 1 month, and for the vector over a sustained period (<xref rid="c32" ref-type="bibr">Fischer et al. 2013</xref>). Clearly with a minimum EIP duration of approximately 6 days at <inline-formula><mml:math id="M178"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>28</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for CHIKV (<xref rid="c46" ref-type="bibr">Johansson et al. 2014</xref>), autochthonous transmission could occur in locations where temperature conditions suitable for transmission occur for periods shorter than 1 month. However, in Canada, temperatures are not frequently <inline-formula><mml:math id="M179"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02265;</mml:mo><mml:mn>28</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for sustained periods. The mean monthly temperature for the warmest month of the year for Canada south of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M180"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>60</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">N</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> under recent climate was <inline-formula><mml:math id="M181"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>15.7</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> with a range of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M182"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>3.5</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> to <inline-formula><mml:math id="M183"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>23.4</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>. The mean EIP from 50,000 iterations in the <inline-formula><mml:math id="M184"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> model was approximately 14.4 days when temperature was held at <inline-formula><mml:math id="M185"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>23.4</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, suggesting monthly values are appropriate to explore the CHIKV transmission cycle period in Canada. There may be a slight underestimate of risk of autochthonous transmission were endemic mosquito species to be competent vectors but as <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> population persistence depends on year-round temperature conditions it should have a lesser effect on risk of transmission by this species. Most of the areas that were identified as climatically suitable for CHIKV transmission were not suitable for <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> due to the latter having requirements for generally warmer climate. The climatic suitability for CHIKV transmission potential is driven by temperature, in particular the temperature-dependent EIP of CHIKV in the vector population and vector survival beyond the duration of the EIP (<xref rid="c46" ref-type="bibr">Johansson et al. 2014</xref>), while climatic suitability for the presence of <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> is dependent on bioclimatic conditions that are known to influence the vector&#x02019;s ecology including the ability of eggs to overwinter, precipitation to initiate egg hatching and warm summer temperature for mosquitoes to reach a viable reproducing population over a sustained period for successive transmission cycles (<xref rid="c11" ref-type="bibr">Caminade et al. 2012</xref>).</p><p>Our study suggests that Canada is currently not climatically suitable for autochthonous CHIKV transmission. Although we have the climatic suitability for limited CHIKV transmission over the summer period, the long and harsh winters impede survival of mosquito eggs and subsequently the establishment of the two known CHIKV vectors, <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> and <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic>. The former has a minimum egg survival temperature threshold of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M186"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>2</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>, whereas the latter has a threshold of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M187"><mml:mrow><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mn>10</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> for exposures over 12 h (<xref rid="c86" ref-type="bibr">Thomas et al. 2012</xref>). Because <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> is more cold tolerant, it is expected that this species would be the one to realistically have a chance of becoming established in Canada, as has occurred in temperate Europe (<xref rid="c21" ref-type="bibr">Delisle et al. 2015</xref>; <xref rid="c36" ref-type="bibr">Gould et al. 2010</xref>; <xref rid="c78" ref-type="bibr">Rezza et al. 2007</xref>). It is likely that our current winter temperature is below the minimum threshold for either <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> or <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> to survive and establish in most parts of Canada, which is a hypothesis consistent with studies on these species globally (<xref rid="c5" ref-type="bibr">Bonizzoni et al. 2013</xref>; <xref rid="c14" ref-type="bibr">Capinha et al. 2014</xref>; <xref rid="c51" ref-type="bibr">Khormi and Kumar 2014</xref>; <xref rid="c52" ref-type="bibr">Kraemer et al. 2015</xref>; <xref rid="c91" ref-type="bibr">Waldock et al. 2013</xref>). Nevertheless, given recent evidence for the survival of these species in urban areas (<xref rid="c57" ref-type="bibr">Lima et al. 2016</xref>) and reports of <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> along the southern shore of Lake Erie, which is geographically close to areas of southern Ontario (<xref rid="c39" ref-type="bibr">Hahn et al. 2016</xref>), surveillance to rule out their presence may be prudent.</p><p>Our study did identify the potential for parts of southern coastal British Columbia to become progressively suitable for CHIKV transmission under short-term and long-term projected climate, particularly driven by a high emission scenario (RCP8.5). The duration of the transmission season, although short, is expected to expand from 1 month in a very small area in British Columbia in the short-term to 2 months covering a larger area in British Columbia in the long-term. This would be sufficient to sustain short-term autochthonous CHIKV transmission were pathogen and vector to co-occur (<xref rid="c76" ref-type="bibr">Reiskind et al. 2008</xref>). <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic> has not been detected in British Columbia although routine surveillance in this province has been sporadic and targeted to <italic>Culex</italic> spp. vectors of West Nile virus (communication, M. Morshed, May 2017, BCCDC). Our findings suggest that CHIKV and mosquito surveillance in the identified risk areas in British Columbia may be prudent, particularly as <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> has been found in at least one county in the adjacent state of Washington (<xref rid="c39" ref-type="bibr">Hahn et al. 2016</xref>). However, if other species of Canadian-endemic mosquitoes turn out to be competent vectors for CHIKV, or if <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> becomes more adapted to a cooler environment, the area of risk would expand further north and inland than currently expected and surveillance of the pathogen and vector should also be considered in southern Ontario, Qu&#x000e9;bec, and the Canadian Prairies. Worth noting is that our study only considered two greenhouse gas emission scenarios (RCP4.5 and RCP8.5) representing intermediate and high emission scenarios, respectively. Implementation of the recent 2016 Paris Climate Agreement puts Canada on track for the RCP4.5 path, in which case the risk maps for CHIKV transmission under the RCP4.5 scenario would be the most likely projection. Under this scenario, we would expect reduced areas to be suitable for CHIKV transmission and a shorter duration of transmission in southern coastal British Columbia, and much lower risk for the rest of Canada compared to the RCP8.5 scenario. However, if the agreement fails, Canada will be on track for the RCP8.5 path, and the RCP8.5 projections will be the most likely.</p><p>While our findings are not surprising given the small number of cases of autochthonous transmission of CHIKV in North America, our study is the first to quantify the risk of CHIKV transmission in Canada in terms of when, where, and for how long transmission may occur, which is useful for forming public health policy. Furthermore, this study shows where northern/southern temperature regions will likely be under different climate projections, this is particularly useful for indicating where the borderline for exotic vector-borne pathogens transmitted by <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> will likely be under climate change.</p><p>The work presented in this study could have implications for other mosquito-borne pathogens sharing the same vectors as CHIKV. At the time of writing, the outbreak of Zika virus (ZIKV) in the Americas and the Caribbean was causing concern due to the potential for returning Canadian travelers to spread the disease in the susceptible Canadian population (<xref rid="c33" ref-type="bibr">Fonseca et al. 2014</xref>; <xref rid="c64" ref-type="bibr">Musso et al. 2016</xref>; <xref rid="c72" ref-type="bibr">Petersen et al. 2016</xref>). ZIKV is an emerging disease transmitted by <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic>, <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> mosquitoes and other <italic>Aedes</italic> spp. mosquitoes (<xref rid="c38" ref-type="bibr">Grard et al. 2014</xref>; <xref rid="c55" ref-type="bibr">Ledermann et al. 2014</xref>; <xref rid="c66" ref-type="bibr">Musso et al. 2014</xref>; <xref rid="c65" ref-type="bibr">Musso and Gubler 2016</xref>; <xref rid="c72" ref-type="bibr">Petersen et al. 2016</xref>). With additional data input specific to ZIKV such as the relationship between temperature and the EIP of ZIKV in the vectors, and the duration of the human ZIKV viraemia, the research presented here could be updated rapidly to assess the climatic suitability for autochthonous mosquito-borne ZIKV transmission in Canada. We do not currently have ZIKV-specific transmission parameters, but given that the epidemiology of ZIKV is similar to CHIKV and dengue, they are transmitted by the same vectors and they appear to co-circulate (<xref rid="c12" ref-type="bibr">Campos et al. 2015</xref>; <xref rid="c13" ref-type="bibr">Cao-Lormeau and Musso 2014</xref>; <xref rid="c65" ref-type="bibr">Musso and Gubler 2016</xref>), it is likely that Canada is currently not climatically suitable for autochthonous mosquito-borne ZIKV transmission, nor would we expect the risk for transmission to increase significantly with short-term and long-term projected climate. This conclusion is not surprising given ZIKV (and CHIKV) have historically been restricted to tropical and subtropical biomes (<xref rid="c72" ref-type="bibr">Petersen et al. 2016</xref>; <xref rid="c93" ref-type="bibr">Weaver and Lecuit 2015</xref>). This does not preclude autochthonous ZIKV transmission in Canada via secondary transmission routes such as sexual transmission; which was first reported in April 2016 (<xref rid="c74" ref-type="bibr">Public Health Agency of Canada 2016</xref>). Similar to our risk assessment for CHIKV, we cannot rule out other competent ZIKV vectors that may already be established in Canada. Routine surveillance of ZIKV and potential ZIKV vectors should be considered in southern Ontario, Qu&#x000e9;bec, the Canadian Prairies, and southern coastal British Columbia.</p><p>There are a number of limitations in this quantitative risk assessment; one of the main assumptions is that climatic conditions can accurately identify suitable habitat for vectors and thus classify risk areas for mosquito-borne diseases. This does not account of the possibility that vectors evolve over time and that changes in their distribution may not be exclusively linked to climatic conditions (<xref rid="c30" ref-type="bibr">Fischer et al. 2014</xref>). Although there are many other factors that contribute to the overall risk, ecological risk is considered a primary driver for where CHIKV transmission may occur and climate-driven species distribution models, including models for <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic>, have been shown to predict the distribution of mosquitoes and the diseases that they can transmit with acceptable accuracy in a public health context (<xref rid="c7" ref-type="bibr">Brady et al. 2014</xref>; <xref rid="c11" ref-type="bibr">Caminade et al. 2012</xref>; <xref rid="c28" ref-type="bibr">European Center for Disease Prevention and Control 2009</xref>; <xref rid="c31" ref-type="bibr">Fischer et al. 2011</xref>; <xref rid="c69" ref-type="bibr">Ogden et al. 2014</xref>). Our study focused on climatic conditions during the warmest months of the year in Canada because they present the highest risk for virus transmission; however, as travel to CHIKV-affected countries by Canadians peak in winter (<xref rid="c84" ref-type="bibr">Statistics Canada 2016</xref>), the risk of viraemic travelers returning to Canada during the summer is lower. The impact of this reduced risk was not explored in this study because we focused on the ecological risk factors essential for CHIKV transmission rather than behavioral factors, but risk for autochthonous CHIKV transmission in Canada is likely influenced by this factor. We also calculated mean monthly temperature (<inline-formula><mml:math id="M188"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">T</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>mean</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula>) by averaging the mean daily maximum and mean daily minimum temperatures together rather than take into account of the daily temperature ranges. Our calculation of <inline-formula><mml:math id="M189"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">T</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>mean</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> does not take into account of the sensitivity to temperature extremes of <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> egg survival over a short period of time (<xref rid="c86" ref-type="bibr">Thomas et al. 2012</xref>) nor how daily temperature fluctuations might impact other aspects of their life cycle as observed in <italic>Ae. aegypti</italic> (<xref rid="c15" ref-type="bibr">Carrington et al. 2013</xref>), thus our risk maps based on <inline-formula><mml:math id="M190"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">T</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mtext>mean</mml:mtext></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> may overestimate the risk for CHIKV transmission. Another limitation is that this study only considers how changes in climate may affect future CHIKV transmission risk in Canada, it does not consider other factors that may influence the future risk such as advances in medicine (development of a CHIKV vaccine or effective treatment for CHIKV), changes in socioeconomic, demographic, and population factors that influence human exposure and changes in human behavior relating to climate change such as spending more time outdoors or indoors. Although future changes in these factors cannot be projected, it is likely they will have an impact on the possibility of CHIKV transmission in Canada in the future.</p><p>There are some data quality issues in this study. Data inputs for the CHIKV transmission model were based on very few CHIKV studies to date with some substitution of dengue data for CHIKV given the similarities between the epidemiology of the two viruses, their shared vectors and cocirculation (<xref rid="c12" ref-type="bibr">Campos et al. 2015</xref>; <xref rid="c13" ref-type="bibr">Cao-Lormeau and Musso 2014</xref>; <xref rid="c65" ref-type="bibr">Musso and Gubler 2016</xref>). There are few field estimates of biting rates and the numbers of mosquitoes per human, and how human behaviors and interventions (mosquito avoidance, mosquito control), infrastructure and environment in Canada (where the majority of Canadians live in an urbanized setting, i.e., air-conditioned homes, lack of stagnant water) affect these is unknown. We also do not have precise information on where Canadian travelers might be returning home from CHIKV-affected countries. However, we used a stochastic model, drawing from a range of probability distributions that were informed by a recent and comprehensive scoping review (S. Garasia et al. unpublished data, 2016) to account for uncertainty in the input parameters. Sensitivity analysis indicate risk maps produced using the 75th percentile <inline-formula><mml:math id="M191"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> values did not significantly change the conclusions using the mean <inline-formula><mml:math id="M192"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> values, and the model outputs are reasonable when compared to the temperature limits of historical CHIKV outbreaks and <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> survival in other countries (<xref rid="c8" ref-type="bibr">Brady et al. 2013</xref>; <xref rid="c32" ref-type="bibr">Fischer et al. 2013</xref>; <xref rid="c59" ref-type="bibr">Lumsden 1955</xref>; <xref rid="c87" ref-type="bibr">Tilston et al. 2009</xref>). We ran an additional sensitivity analysis (not presented) to modify the EIP at <inline-formula><mml:math id="M193"><mml:mrow><mml:mn>28</mml:mn><mml:mo>&#x000b0;</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">C</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> from a mean of 6 days to a mean of 5 days given the temperature-EIP relationship for CHIKV is not well understood and may be shorter than for DENV. We found that the temperature range corresponding to <inline-formula><mml:math id="M194"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> values were very similar to those using the 75th percentile <inline-formula><mml:math id="M195"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">R</mml:mi><mml:mn>0</mml:mn></mml:msub></mml:mrow></mml:math></inline-formula> values, thus a shorter EIP is expected to increase the distribution and duration of CHIKV transmission in Canada. Also, there are uncertainties regarding the climatic limits for, and current distribution of, <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> that requires further study (<xref rid="c69" ref-type="bibr">Ogden et al. 2014</xref>).</p><p>Data quality issues with the climate models used include uncertainty in climate scenarios from one single model and one bias correction approach used to drive the models, and only using data up until 2010. As the risk maps do not incorporate the five most recent years of climate data, the current risks identified is likely an underestimation of the risk given the climate in Canada over the last 5 years has been systematically warmer in the majority of the country compared to previous decades (1980s and 1990s) and climate baseline (<xref rid="c37" ref-type="bibr">Government of Canada 2016</xref>). Although the climate data from the bias-corrected models in this study were not far outliers compared to other RCMs and did not deviate significantly from the ensemble mean (see Figure S1), we note that over the summer months the models predicted higher temperatures and drier summers than the ensemble mean. The former is likely to result in a conservative estimate in the risk maps, whereas the latter may result in the under-prediction of the suitability for <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic>. Future research is needed to explore the impact of variations in climate model outputs on projected distributions by using model ensembles (<xref rid="c43" ref-type="bibr">IPCC 2013</xref>).</p><p>With the data we have at present, the current risk of autochthonous CHIKV transmission in Canada appears to be very low, and risk is restricted to very small parts of Canada under short-term and long-term projected climate. While our findings are not surprising, our study is the first to quantify the risk of CHIKV transmission in Canada which is useful for forming public health policy by identifying the risk of incursion of exotic vector-borne pathogens that are currently endemic to tropical and subtropical regions, into countries at high latitudes with climate change. This study identifies that southern Canada may be the very northern limit for transmission of these pathogens with climate change. Other factors need to be explored however, which include understanding when and where Canadian travelers are likely to return, infrastructure in Canada that may support vector populations in what would be expected to be climatically unsuitable regions, and whether or not there are other competent vectors in Canada. Further research to close the gap on our current understanding of CHIKV and CHIKV vectors, improved surveillance on <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> in North America, and enhanced climate projection models (using model ensembles) will allow us to better predict the current and future risk of transmission of CHIKV and other exotic vector-borne pathogens in Canada.</p></sec><sec><title>Supplemental Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="EHP669.s001"><label>(198 KB) PDF</label><media xlink:href="EHP669.s001.acco.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We would like to thank L. Sushama and K. Winger [Centre pour l&#x02019;&#x000e9;tude et la simulation du climat &#x000e0; l&#x02019;&#x000e9;chelle r&#x000e9;gionale (ESCER), Universit&#x000e9; du Qu&#x000e9;bec &#x000e0; Montr&#x000e9;al (UQAM)], who provided the CRCM5 simulations. We also acknowledge the support of Compute Canada national HPC platform and the Calcul Qu&#x000e9;bec regional HPC platform to run the CRCM5 model.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="c1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Almeida</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baptista</surname><given-names>SS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sousa</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Novo</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Panella</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<year>2005</year>. <article-title>Bioecology and vectorial capacity of <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic> (Diptera: Culicidae) in Macao, China, in relation to dengue virus transmission</article-title>. <source>J Med Entomol</source>
<volume>42</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>419</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>428</lpage>, PMID: 15962796.<?supplied-pmid 15962796?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15962796</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Appassakij</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Khuntikij</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kemapunmanus</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wutthanarungsan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Silpapojakul</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>. <article-title>Viremic profiles in asymptomatic and symptomatic chikungunya fever: a blood transfusion threat?</article-title>
<source>Transfusion</source>
<volume>53</volume>(<issue>10 Pt 2</issue>):<fpage>2567</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2574</lpage>, PMID: 23176378, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1537-2995.2012.03960.x</pub-id>.<?supplied-pmid 23176378?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23176378</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Arora</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scinocca</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boer</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Christian</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Denman</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Flato</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Carbon emission limits required to satisfy future representative concentration pathways of greenhouse gases</article-title>. <source>Geophys Res Lett</source>
<volume>38</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>L05805</fpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1029/2010GL046270</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ayu</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lai</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>YF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hatim</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hairi</surname><given-names>NN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ayob</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<year>2010</year>. <article-title>Seroprevalence survey of Chikungunya virus in Bagan Panchor, Malaysia</article-title>. <source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source>
<volume>83</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>1245</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1248</lpage>, PMID: 21118929, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4269/ajtmh.2010.10-0279</pub-id>.<?supplied-pmid 21118929?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21118929</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c5"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bonizzoni</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gasperi</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>James</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>. <article-title>The invasive mosquito species <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic>: current knowledge and future perspectives</article-title>. <source>Trends Parasitol</source>
<volume>29</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>460</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>468</lpage>, PMID: 23916878, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pt.2013.07.003</pub-id>.<?supplied-pmid 23916878?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23916878</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c6"><mixed-citation publication-type="web">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brady</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Model of Adult Aedes albopictus Survival/Mortality at Different Temperatures</article-title>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://figshare.com/articles/Model_of_adult_Aedes_albopictus_survival_mortality_at_different_temperatures/865035">https://figshare.com/articles/Model_of_adult_Aedes_albopictus_survival_mortality_at_different_temperatures/865035</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brady</surname><given-names>OJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Golding</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pigott</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kraemer</surname><given-names>MU</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Messina</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reiner</surname><given-names>RC</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Global temperature constraints on <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> and <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> persistence and competence for dengue virus transmission</article-title>. <source>Parasit Vectors</source>
<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>338</fpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1756-3305-7-338</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25052008</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brady</surname><given-names>OJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guerra</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bhatt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Golding</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pigott</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Modelling adult <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> and <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic> survival at different temperatures in laboratory and field settings</article-title>. <source>Parasit Vectors</source>
<volume>6</volume>:<fpage>351</fpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1756-3305-6-351</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24330720</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c9"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brighton</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Prozesky</surname><given-names>OW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>de la Harpe</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1983</year>. <article-title>Chikungunya virus infection. a retrospective study of 107 cases</article-title>. <source>S Afr Med J</source>
<volume>63</volume>(<issue>9</issue>):<fpage>313</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>315</lpage>, PMID: 6298956.<?supplied-pmid 6298956?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6298956</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Burt</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rolph</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rulli</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mahalingam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heise</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>. <article-title>Chikungunya: a re-emerging virus</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>
<volume>379</volume>(<issue>9816</issue>):<fpage>662</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>671</lpage>, PMID: 22100854, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(11)60281-X</pub-id>.<?supplied-pmid 22100854?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22100854</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Caminade</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Medlock</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ducheyne</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McIntyre</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leach</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baylis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<year>2012</year>. <article-title>Suitability of European climate for the Asian tiger mosquito <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic>: recent trends and future scenarios</article-title>. <source>J R Soc Interface</source>
<volume>9</volume>(<issue>75</issue>):<fpage>2708</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2717</lpage>, PMID: 22535696, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rsif.2012.0138</pub-id>.<?supplied-pmid 22535696?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22535696</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Campos</surname><given-names>GS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bandeira</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sardi</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>. <article-title>Zika virus outbreak, Bahia, Brazil</article-title>. <source>Emerging Infect Dis</source>
<volume>21</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>1885</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1886</lpage>, PMID: 26401719, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3201/eid2110.150847</pub-id>.<?supplied-pmid 26401719?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26401719</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cao-Lormeau</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Musso</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>. <article-title>Emerging arboviruses in the Pacific</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>
<volume>384</volume>(<issue>9954</issue>):<fpage>1571</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1572</lpage>, PMID: 25443481, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(14)61977-2</pub-id>.<?supplied-pmid 25443481?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25443481</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Capinha</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rocha</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sousa</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>. <article-title>Macroclimate determines the global range limit of <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic></article-title>. <source>Ecohealth</source>
<volume>11</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>420</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>428</lpage>, PMID: 24643859, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10393-014-0918-y</pub-id>.<?supplied-pmid 24643859?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24643859</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Carrington</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seifert</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Willits</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lambrechts</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>. <article-title>Large diurnal temperature fluctuations negatively influence aedes aegypti (diptera: Culicidae) life-history traits</article-title>. <source>J Med Entomol</source>
<volume>50</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>43</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>51</lpage>, PMID: 23427651, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1603/ME11242</pub-id>.<?supplied-pmid 23427651?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23427651</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c16"><mixed-citation publication-type="web"><collab>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention</collab>. <year>2015</year>
<article-title>Chikungunya: Information for Vector Control Programs</article-title>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cdc.gov/chikungunya/pdfs/CHIKV_VectorControl.pdf">http://www.cdc.gov/chikungunya/pdfs/CHIKV_VectorControl.pdf</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>. <article-title>The incubation periods of Dengue viruses</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>7</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<elocation-id>e50972</elocation-id>, PMID: 23226436, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0050972</pub-id>.<?supplied-pmid 23226436?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23226436</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Christofferson</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chisenhall</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wearing</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mores</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>. <article-title>Chikungunya viral fitness measures within the vector and subsequent transmission potential</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>9</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<elocation-id>e110538</elocation-id>, PMID: 25310016, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0110538</pub-id>.<?supplied-pmid 25310016?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25310016</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Christofferson</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mores</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>. <article-title>Estimating the magnitude and direction of altered arbovirus transmission due to viral phenotype</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>6</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<elocation-id>e16298</elocation-id>, PMID: 21298018, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0016298</pub-id>.<?supplied-pmid 21298018?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21298018</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c20"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Christophers</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1960</year>
<source>Aedes Aegypti (L.), the Yellow Fever Mosquito. its Life History, Bionomics, and Structure</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, New York</publisher-loc>:<publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Delisle</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rousseau</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Broche</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leparc-Goffart</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>L&#x02019;Ambert</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cochet</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Chikungunya outbreak in Montpellier, France, September to October 2014</article-title>. <source>Euro Surveill</source>
<volume>20</volume>(<issue>17</issue>):<fpage>21108</fpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2807/1560-7917.ES2015.20.17.21108</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25955774</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Diaconescu</surname><given-names>EP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gachon</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laprise</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Scinocca</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Evaluation of precipitation indices over North America from various configurations of regional climate models</article-title>. <source>Atmosphere-Ocean</source>
<volume>54</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>418</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>439</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/07055900.2016.1185005</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Diallo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thonnon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Traore-Lamizana</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fontenille</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>. <article-title>Vectors of Chikungunya virus in Senegal: current data and transmission cycles</article-title>. <source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source>
<volume>60</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>281</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>286</lpage>, PMID: 10072152.<?supplied-pmid 10072152?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10072152</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Drebot</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Holloway</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zheng</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ogden</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Travel-related chikungunya cases in Canada</article-title>. <source>Canada Communicable Disease Report</source>
<volume>41</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>2</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dumont</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chiroleu</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Domerg</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>. <article-title>On a temporal model for the Chikungunya disease: modeling, theory and numerics</article-title>. <source>Math Biosci</source>
<volume>213</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>80</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>91</lpage>, PMID: 18394655, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.mbs.2008.02.008</pub-id>.<?supplied-pmid 18394655?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18394655</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Economopoulou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal>et al.</etal>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Atypical Chikungunya virus infections: clinical manifestations, mortality and risk factors for severe disease during the 2005&#x02013;2006 outbreak on R&#x000e9;union</article-title>. <source>Epidemiol Infect</source>
<volume>137</volume>:(<fpage>4):534</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>541</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0950268808001167</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Enserink</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>. <article-title>Entomology. a mosquito goes global</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>320</volume>(<issue>5878</issue>):<fpage>864</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>866</lpage>, PMID: 18487167, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.320.5878.864</pub-id>.<?supplied-pmid 18487167?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18487167</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c28"><mixed-citation publication-type="report"><collab>European Center for Disease Prevention and Control</collab>. <year>2009</year>
<source>Development of Aedes albopictus Risk Maps, Technical Report 0905</source>. 0905. Stockholm.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beierkuhnlein</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>. <article-title>Temperature-derived potential for the establishment of phlebotomine sandflies and visceral leishmaniasis in Germany</article-title>. <source>Geospat Health</source>
<volume>5</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>59</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>69</lpage>, PMID: 21080321, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4081/gh.2010.187</pub-id>.<?supplied-pmid 21080321?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21080321</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Neteler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tjaden</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beierkuhnlein</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Climatic suitability of aedes albopictus in europe referring to climate change projections: comparison of mechanistic and correlative niche modelling approaches</article-title>. <source>Euro Surveill</source>
<volume>19</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>20696</fpage>, 20696, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2807/1560-7917.ES2014.19.6.20696</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24556349</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Niemitz</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Reineking</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beierkuhnlein</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Projection of climatic suitability for <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic> Skuse (Culicidae) in Europe under climate change conditions</article-title>. <source>Global and Planetary Change</source>
<volume>78</volume>:<fpage>54</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>64</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.gloplacha.2011.05.008</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Suk</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sudre</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hess</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tjaden</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<year>2013</year>. <article-title>Climate change effects on Chikungunya transmission in Europe: geospatial analysis of vector's climatic suitability and virus&#x02019; temperature requirements</article-title>. <source>Int J Health Geogr</source>
<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>51</fpage>, PMID: 24219507, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1476-072X-12-51</pub-id>.<?supplied-pmid 24219507?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24219507</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fonseca</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Suk</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sudre</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hess</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tjaden</surname><given-names>NB</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<year>2014</year>. <article-title>First case of Zika virus infection in a returning Canadian traveler</article-title>. <source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source>
<volume>91</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1035</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1038</lpage>, PMID: 25294619, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4269/ajtmh.14-0151</pub-id>.<?supplied-pmid 25294619?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25294619</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Fourie</surname><given-names>ED</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1979</year>. <article-title>Rheumatoid arthritic syndrome after chikungunya fever</article-title>. <source>S Afr Med J</source>
<volume>56</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>130</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>132</lpage>, PMID: 494034.<?supplied-pmid 494034?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">494034</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c35"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Giordano</surname><given-names>BV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gasparotto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>FF</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>. <article-title>A checklist of the 67 mosquito species of Ontario, Canada</article-title>. <source>J Am Mosq Control Assoc</source>
<volume>31</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>101</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>103</lpage>, PMID: 25843183, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2987/14-6456R.1</pub-id>.<?supplied-pmid 25843183?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25843183</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gould</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gallian</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>De Lamballerie</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Charrel</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>. <article-title>First cases of autochthonous dengue fever and chikungunya fever in France: from bad dream to reality!</article-title>
<source>Clin Microbiol Infect</source>
<volume>16</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>1702</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1704</lpage>, PMID: 21040155, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-0691.2010.03386.x</pub-id>.<?supplied-pmid 21040155?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21040155</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c37"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>Government of Canada</collab>. <year>2016</year>
<source>Climate Data and Scenarios for Canada: Synthesis of Recent Observation and Modelling Results</source>. <publisher-name>Gatineau, QC</publisher-name>, Canada:Environment Canada.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grard</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Caron</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mombo</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nkoghe</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mboui Ondo</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<year>2014</year>. <article-title>Zika virus in Gabon (Central Africa)&#x02014;2007: a new threat from <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic>?</article-title>
<source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source>
<volume>8</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<elocation-id>e2681</elocation-id>, PMID: 24516683, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0002681</pub-id>.<?supplied-pmid 24516683?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24516683</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eisen</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eisen</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Boegler</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McAllister</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Reported distribution of <italic>Aedes (Stegomyia) aegypti</italic> and <italic>Aedes (Stegomyia) albopictus</italic> in the United States, 1995&#x02013;2016 (Diptera: Culicidae)</article-title>. <source>J Med Entomol</source>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jme/tjw072</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c40"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hern&#x000e1;ndez-D&#x000ed;az</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laprise</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sushama</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martynov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Winger</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dugas</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Climate simulation over CORDEX Africa domain using the fifth-generation Canadian Regional Climate Model (CRCM5)</article-title>. <source>Clim Dyn</source>
<volume>40</volume>:<fpage>1415</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1433</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00382-012-1387-z</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c41"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Higgs</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vanlandingham</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>. <article-title>Chikungunya virus and its mosquito vectors</article-title>. <source>Vector Borne Zoonotic Dis</source>
<volume>15</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>231</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>240</lpage>, PMID: 25674945, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/vbz.2014.1745</pub-id>.<?supplied-pmid 25674945?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25674945</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hutchinson</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McKenney</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pedlar</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hopkinson</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Milewska</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Development and testing of Canada-wide interpolated spatial models of daily minimum&#x02013;maximum temperature and precipitation for 1961&#x02013;2003</article-title>. <source>J Appl Meteor Climatol</source>
<volume>48</volume>:<fpage>725</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>741</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1175/2008JAMC1979.1</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c43"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>IPCC (Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change)</collab>. <year>2013</year>
<source>Climate Change 2013: the Physical Science Basis. Contribution of Working Group I to the Fifth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change</source>. <publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc>:<publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Javelle</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ribera</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Degasne</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ga&#x000fc;z&#x000e8;re</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marimoutou</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Simon</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>. <article-title>Specific management of post-chikungunya rheumatic disorders: a retrospective study of 159 cases in Reunion Island from 2006&#x02013;2012</article-title>. <source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source>
<volume>9</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<elocation-id>e0003603</elocation-id>, PMID: 25760632, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0003603</pub-id>.<?supplied-pmid 25760632?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25760632</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arana-Vizcarrondo</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Biggerstaff</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gallagher</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marano</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Staples</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>. <article-title>Assessing the risk of international spread of yellow fever virus: a mathematical analysis of an urban outbreak in Asuncion, 2008</article-title>. <source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source>
<volume>86</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>349</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>358</lpage>, PMID: 22302873, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4269/ajtmh.2012.11-0432</pub-id>.<?supplied-pmid 22302873?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22302873</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c46"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Johansson</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Powers</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pesik</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Staples</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>. <article-title>Nowcasting the spread of chikungunya virus in the Americas</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>9</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<elocation-id>e104915</elocation-id>, PMID: 25111394, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0104915</pub-id>.<?supplied-pmid 25111394?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25111394</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c47"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><string-name><surname>Jupp</surname>
<given-names>PG</given-names></string-name>, <string-name><surname>McIntosh</surname>
<given-names>BB.</given-names></string-name>
<year>1988</year>
<chapter-title>Chikungunya virus disease</chapter-title> In: <source>The Arboviruses: Epidemiology and Ecology</source>. <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Monath</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name></person-group>, ed. <publisher-loc>Boca Raton, Florida</publisher-loc>:<publisher-name>CRC Press</publisher-name>, <fpage>137</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>157</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kalantri</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Joshi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Riley</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>. <article-title>Chikungunya epidemic: an Indian perspective</article-title>. <source>Natl Med J India</source>
<volume>19</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>315</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>322</lpage>, PMID: 17343016.<?supplied-pmid 17343016?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17343016</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kendrick</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stanek</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blackmore</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<collab>Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC)</collab>. <year>2014</year>
<article-title>Notes from the field: transmission of chikungunya virus in the continental United States&#x02014;Florida, 2014</article-title>. <source>MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep</source>
<volume>63</volume>(<issue>48</issue>):<fpage>1137</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25474035</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bogoch</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brownstein</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Miniota</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nicolucci</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal>et al.</etal>
<year>2014</year>. <article-title>Assessing the origin of and potential for international spread of chikungunya virus from the Caribbean</article-title>. <source>PLoS Curr</source>
<volume>6</volume>, PMID: 4055609, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/currents.outbreaks.2134a0a7bf37fd8d388181539fea2da5</pub-id>.<?supplied-pmid 4055609?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4055609</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Khormi</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>. <article-title>Climate change and the potential global distribution of Aedes aegypti: spatial modelling using GIS and CLIMEX</article-title>. <source>Geospat Health</source>
<volume>8</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>405</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>415</lpage>, PMID: 24893017, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4081/gh.2014.29</pub-id>.<?supplied-pmid 24893017?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24893017</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kraemer</surname><given-names>MU</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sinka</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Duda</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mylne</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Shearer</surname><given-names>FM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Brady</surname><given-names>OJ</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<year>2015</year>. <article-title>The global compendium of <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> and <italic>Ae. albopictus</italic> occurrence</article-title>. <source>Sci Data</source>
<volume>2</volume>:<fpage>150035</fpage>, PMID: 26175912, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sdata.2015.35</pub-id>.<?supplied-pmid 26175912?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26175912</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lam</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chua</surname><given-names>KB</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hooi</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rahimah</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kumari</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tharmaratnam</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<year>2001</year>. <article-title>Chikungunya infection&#x02014;an emerging disease in Malaysia</article-title>. <source>Southeast Asian J Trop Med Public Health</source>
<volume>32</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>447</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>451</lpage>, PMID: 11944696.<?supplied-pmid 11944696?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11944696</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Laprise</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hern&#x000e1;ndez-D&#x000ed;az</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tete</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sushama</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>&#x00160;eparovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martynov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Climate projections over CORDEX Africa domain using the fifth-generation Canadian Regional Climate Model (CRCM5)</article-title>. <source>Clim Dyn</source>
<volume>41</volume>(<issue>11</issue>):<fpage>3219</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3246</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00382-012-1651-2</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ledermann</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Guillaumot</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yug</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Saweyog</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tided</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Machieng</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<year>2014</year>. <article-title><italic>Aedes hensilli</italic> as a potential vector of Chikungunya and Zika viruses</article-title>. <source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source>
<volume>8</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<elocation-id>e3188</elocation-id>, PMID: 25299181, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0003188</pub-id>.<?supplied-pmid 25299181?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25299181</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lenderink</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buishand</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Deursen</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Estimates of future discharges of the river Rhine using two scenario methodologies: direct versus delta approach</article-title>. <source>Hydrol Earth Syst Sci</source>
<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1145</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1159</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5194/hess-11-1145-2007</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lovin</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hickner</surname><given-names>PV</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Severson</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>. <article-title>Evidence for an overwintering population of <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic> in Capitol Hill neighborhood, Washington, DC</article-title>. <source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source>
<volume>94</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>231</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>235</lpage>, PMID: 26526922, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4269/ajtmh.15-0351</pub-id>.<?supplied-pmid 26526922?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26526922</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Liumbruno</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Calteri</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Petropulacos</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mattivi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Po</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Macini</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<year>2008</year>. <article-title>The Chikungunya epidemic in Italy and its repercussion on the blood system</article-title>. <source>Blood Transfus</source>
<volume>6</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>199</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>210</lpage>, PMID: 19112735.<?supplied-pmid 19112735?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19112735</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lumsden</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1955</year>. <article-title>An epidemic of virus disease in Southern Province, Tanganyika Territory, in 1952&#x02013;53. II. General description and epidemiology</article-title>. <source>Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg</source>
<volume>49</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>33</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>57</lpage>, PMID: 14373835.<?supplied-pmid 14373835?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14373835</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Manore</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hickmann</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wearing</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hyman</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>. <article-title>Comparing dengue and chikungunya emergence and endemic transmission in <italic>A. aegypti</italic> and <italic>A. albopictus</italic></article-title>. <source>J Theor Biol</source>
<volume>356</volume>:<fpage>174</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>191</lpage>, PMID: 24801860, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jtbi.2014.04.033</pub-id>.<?supplied-pmid 24801860?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24801860</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Martynov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laprise</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sushama</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Winger</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>&#x00160;eparovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dugas</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Reanalysis-driven climate simulation over CORDEX North America domain using the Canadian Regional Climate Model, version 5: model performance evaluation</article-title>. <source>Clim Dyn</source>
<volume>41</volume>:<fpage>2973</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3005</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00382-013-1778-9</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>McKenney</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hutchinson</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Papadopol</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lawrence</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pedlar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Customized spatial climate models for North America</article-title>. <source>Bull Amer Meteor Soc</source>
<volume>92</volume>:<fpage>1611</fpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1175/2011BAMS3132</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c63"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>. <article-title>Reemergence of chikungunya virus</article-title>. <source>J Virol</source>
<volume>88</volume>(<issue>20</issue>):<fpage>11644</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11647</lpage>, PMID: 25078691, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JVI.01432-14</pub-id>.<?supplied-pmid 25078691?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25078691</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c64"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Musso</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Baud</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gubler</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>. <article-title>Zika virus: what do we know?</article-title>
<source>Clin Microbiol Infect</source>
<volume>22</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>494</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>496</lpage>, PMID: 27067096, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cmi.2016.03.032</pub-id>.<?supplied-pmid 27067096?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27067096</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c65"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Musso</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gubler</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>. <article-title>Zika virus</article-title>. <source>Clin Microbiol Rev</source>
<volume>29</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>487</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>524</lpage>, PMID: 27029595, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/CMR.00072-15</pub-id>.<?supplied-pmid 27029595?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27029595</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c66"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Musso</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nilles</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cao-Lormeau</surname><given-names>VM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>. <article-title>Rapid spread of emerging Zika virus in the Pacific area</article-title>. <source>Clin Microbiol Infect</source>
<volume>20</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>O595</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>O596</lpage>, PMID: 24909208, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1469-0691.12707</pub-id>.<?supplied-pmid 24909208?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24909208</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c67"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Nicholson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ritchie</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Russell</surname><given-names>RC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zalucki</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Van Den Hurk</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>. <article-title>Ability for Aedes albopictus (Diptera: Culicidae) to survive at the climatic limits of its potential range in eastern Australia</article-title>. <source>J Med Entomol</source>
<volume>51</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>948</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>957</lpage>, PMID: 25276922.<?supplied-pmid 25276922?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25276922</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c68"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ogden</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lindsay</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Coulthart</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<article-title>Is there a risk of chikungunya transmission in Canada?</article-title>
<source>Canada Communicable Disease Report</source>
<volume>41</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>11</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c69"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ogden</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Milka</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Caminade</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gachon</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Recent and projected future climatic suitability of north america for the asian tiger mosquito <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic></article-title>. <source>Parasites Vectors</source>
<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>532</fpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13071-014-0532-4</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25441177</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c70"><mixed-citation publication-type="web"><collab>Pan American Health Organization</collab>. <year>2016</year>
<article-title>Number of Reported Cases of Chikungunya Fever in the Americas, by Country or Territory 2013&#x02013;2016. Cumulative Cases. Epidemiological Week 11</article-title>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.paho.org/hq/index.php?option=com_topics&#x00026;view=readall&#x00026;cid=5927&#x00026;Itemid=40931&#x00026;lang=en">http://www.paho.org/hq/index.php?option=com_topics&#x00026;view=readall&#x00026;cid=5927&#x00026;Itemid=40931&#x00026;lang=en</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c71"><mixed-citation publication-type="report"><collab>Pan American Health Organization and World Health Organization</collab>. <year>2013</year>
<source>Epidemiological alert</source>. Chikungunya fever. 9 December 2013.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c72"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>LR</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jamieson</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Powers</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Honein</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<article-title>Zika virus</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>
<volume>374</volume>:<fpage>1552</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1563</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMra1602113</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27028561</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c73"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pialoux</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ga&#x000fc;z&#x000e8;re</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jaur&#x000e9;guiberry</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Strobel</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>. <article-title>Chikungunya, an epidemic arbovirosis</article-title>. <source>Lancet Infect Dis</source>
<volume>7</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>319</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>327</lpage>, PMID: 17448935, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1473-3099(07)70107-X</pub-id>.<?supplied-pmid 17448935?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17448935</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c74"><mixed-citation publication-type="web"><collab>Public Health Agency of Canada</collab>. <year>2016</year>
<article-title>Statement from the Chief Public Health Officer of Canada and Ontario&#x02019;s Chief Medical Officer of Health on the First Positive Case of Sexually Transmitted Zika Virus</article-title>. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://news.gc.ca/web/article-en.do?nid=1056379&#x00026;_ga=1.218498143.730471110.1461176631">http://news.gc.ca/web/article-en.do?nid=1056379&#x00026;_ga=1.218498143.730471110.1461176631</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c75"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>Public Health Ontario</collab>. <year>2013</year>
<source>Vector-Borne Diseases 2013 Summary Report</source>. <publisher-loc>Toronto</publisher-loc>, <publisher-name>Ontario:Public Health Ontario</publisher-name>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c76"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Reiskind</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Pesko</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Westbrook</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mores</surname><given-names>CN</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>. <article-title>Susceptibility of Florida mosquitoes to infection with chikungunya virus</article-title>. <source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source>
<volume>78</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>422</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>425</lpage>, PMID: 18337338.<?supplied-pmid 18337338?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18337338</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c77"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Renault</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Solet</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sissoko</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Balleydier</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Larrieu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Filleul</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<year>2007</year>. <article-title>A major epidemic of chikungunya virus infection on Reunion Island, France, 2005&#x02013;2006</article-title>. <source>Am J Trop Med Hyg</source>
<volume>77</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>727</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>731</lpage>, PMID: 17978079.<?supplied-pmid 17978079?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17978079</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c78"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rezza</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nicoletti</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Angelini</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Romi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Finarelli</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Panning</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<year>2007</year>. <article-title>Infection with chikungunya virus in Italy: an outbreak in a temperate region</article-title>. <source>Lancet</source>
<volume>370</volume>(<issue>9602</issue>):<fpage>1840</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1846</lpage>, PMID: 18061059, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(07)61779-6</pub-id>.<?supplied-pmid 18061059?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18061059</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c79"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1955</year>. <article-title>An epidemic of virus disease in Southern Province, Tanganyika Territory, in 1952&#x02013;53. I. Clinical features</article-title>. <source>Trans R Soc Trop Med Hyg</source>
<volume>49</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>28</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>32</lpage>, PMID: 14373834.<?supplied-pmid 14373834?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14373834</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c80"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ross</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1956</year>. <article-title>The Newala epidemic. III. The virus: isolation, pathogenic properties and relationship to the epidemic</article-title>. <source>J Hyg (Lond)</source>
<volume>54</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>177</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>191</lpage>, PMID: 13346078.<?supplied-pmid 13346078?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">13346078</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c81"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rougeron</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sam</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Caron</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nkoghe</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Leroy</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roques</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>. <article-title>Chikungunya, a paradigm of neglected tropical disease that emerged to be a new health global risk</article-title>. <source>J Clin Virol</source>
<volume>64</volume>:<fpage>144</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>152</lpage>, PMID: 25453326, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jcv.2014.08.032</pub-id>.<?supplied-pmid 25453326?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25453326</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c82"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Albert</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>. <article-title>Biology and pathogenesis of chikungunya virus</article-title>. <source>Nat Rev Microbiol</source>
<volume>8</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>491</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>500</lpage>, PMID: 20551973, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrmicro2368</pub-id>.<?supplied-pmid 20551973?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20551973</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c83"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>&#x00160;eparovi&#x00107;</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Alexandru</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Laprise</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Martynov</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sushama</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Winger</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Present climate and climate change over North America as simulated by the fifth-generation Canadian regional climate model</article-title>. <source>Clim Dyn</source>
<volume>41</volume>:<fpage>3167</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3201</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00382-013-1737-5</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c84"><mixed-citation publication-type="report"><collab>Statistics Canada</collab>. <year>2016</year>
<source>This analysis is based on the Statistics Canada <italic>International Travel Survey (2010&#x02013;2014)</italic></source>. All computations, use and interpretation of these data are entirely that of Aamir Fazil.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c85"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thiberville</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moyen</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dupuis-Maguiraga</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nougairede</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gould</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Roques</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<year>2013</year>. <article-title>Chikungunya fever: epidemiology, clinical syndrome, pathogenesis and therapy</article-title>. <source>Antiviral Res</source>
<volume>99</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>345</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>370</lpage>, PMID: 23811281, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.antiviral.2013.06.009</pub-id>.<?supplied-pmid 23811281?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23811281</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c86"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Obermayr</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kreyling</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Beierkuhnlein</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Low-temperature threshold for egg survival of a post-diapause and non-diapause European aedine strain, <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic> (Diptera: Culicidae)</article-title>. <source>Parasit Vectors</source>
<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>100</fpage>, [doi], <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1756-3305-5-100</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22621367</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c87"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tilston</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Skelly</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weinstein</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Pan-European Chikungunya surveillance: designing risk stratified surveillance zones</article-title>. <source>Int J Health Geogr</source>
<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>61</fpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1476-072X-8-61</pub-id>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19878588</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c88"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Tsetsarkin</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vanlandingham</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McGee</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Higgs</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>. <article-title>A single mutation in chikungunya virus affects vector specificity and epidemic potential</article-title>. <source>PLoS Pathog</source>
<volume>3</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<elocation-id>e201</elocation-id>, PMID: 18069894, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.ppat.0030201</pub-id>.<?supplied-pmid 18069894?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18069894</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c89"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>van Vuuren</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name></person-group>
<etal>et al.</etal>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>The representative concentration pathways: an overview</article-title>. <source>Clim Change</source>
<volume>109</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>5</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>31</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10584-011-0148-z</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c90"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Vega-R&#x000fa;a</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Louren&#x000e7;o-de-Oliveira</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mousson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vazeille</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fuchs</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Y&#x000e9;bakima</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<year>2015</year>. <article-title>Chikungunya virus transmission potential by local <italic>Aedes</italic> mosquitoes in the Americas and Europe</article-title>. <source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source>
<volume>9</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<elocation-id>e0003780</elocation-id>, PMID: 25993633, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0003780</pub-id>.<?supplied-pmid 25993633?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25993633</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c91"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Waldock</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chandra</surname><given-names>NL</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lelieveld</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Proestos</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Michael</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Christophides</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>, <etal>et al.</etal>
<year>2013</year>. <article-title>The role of environmental variables on <italic>Aedes albopictus</italic> biology and chikungunya epidemiology</article-title>. <source>Pathog Glob Health</source>
<volume>107</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>224</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>241</lpage>, PMID: 23916332, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1179/2047773213Y.0000000100</pub-id>.<?supplied-pmid 23916332?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23916332</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c92"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2014</year>. <article-title>Arrival of chikungunya virus in the new world: prospects for spread and impact on public health</article-title>. <source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source>
<volume>8</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<elocation-id>e2921</elocation-id>, PMID: 24967777, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0002921</pub-id>.<?supplied-pmid 24967777?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24967777</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c93"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lecuit</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>. <article-title>Chikungunya virus and the global spread of a mosquito-borne disease</article-title>. <source>N Engl J Med</source>
<volume>372</volume>(<issue>13</issue>):<fpage>1231</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1239</lpage>, PMID: 25806915, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJMra1406035</pub-id>.<?supplied-pmid 25806915?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25806915</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c94"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>White</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Toumi</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>The limitations of bias correcting regional climate model inputs</article-title>. <source>Geophys Res Lett</source>
<volume>40</volume>(<issue>12</issue>):<fpage>2907</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2912</lpage>, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/grl.50612</pub-id>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c95"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Yakob</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Clements</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2013</year>. <article-title>A mathematical model of chikungunya dynamics and control: the major epidemic on R&#x000e9;union Island</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>8</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<elocation-id>e57448</elocation-id>, PMID: 23554860, <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0057448</pub-id>.<?supplied-pmid 23554860?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23554860</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="c96"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zender</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2015</year>. NetCDF Operator (NCO) User Guide. A Suite of netCDF Operators Edition 4.5.1, for NCO Version 4.5.1 July 2015.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>