<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The southern Appalachian Mountains represent some of the oldest uplands in North America (~471–480 million years old; Hibbard, Meehl, Cox, &amp; Friedlingstein, 
 <xref rid="ece35065-bib-0045" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref> and references therein) and harbor high levels of biodiversity (Crandall &amp; Buhay, 
 <xref rid="ece35065-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>; Marek &amp; Bond, 
 <xref rid="ece35065-bib-0069" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>; Petranka, 
 <xref rid="ece35065-bib-0080" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1998</xref>; Rissler &amp; Smith, 
 <xref rid="ece35065-bib-0086" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>). This topographically complex temperate region is characterized by steep environmental gradients, which have promoted population divergence in many species, particularly those with poor dispersal abilities (Hedin &amp; Wood, 
 <xref rid="ece35065-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2002</xref>). Paleoclimatic (Loehle, 
 <xref rid="ece35065-bib-0065" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>), biogeographic (Swenson &amp; Howard, 
 <xref rid="ece35065-bib-0094" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2005</xref>) and comparative phylogeographic (Soltis, Morris, McLachlan, Manos, &amp; Soltis, 
 <xref rid="ece35065-bib-0090" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>) data indicate that the southern Appalachians remained free from Pleistocene ice sheet advances, and consequently, retained numerous refugial areas for forest‐dependent biota during cool and dry glacial periods. Indeed, short‐range endemism and high diversity have been well documented in plethodontid salamanders (Petranka, 
 <xref rid="ece35065-bib-0080" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1998</xref>) and other amphibians (Rissler &amp; Smith, 
 <xref rid="ece35065-bib-0086" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>). Similar patterns have also been reported for invertebrate groups such as crayfish (Crandall &amp; Buhay, 
 <xref rid="ece35065-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>), arachnids (Hedin &amp; Wood, 
 <xref rid="ece35065-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2002</xref>; Thomas &amp; Hedin, 
 <xref rid="ece35065-bib-0098" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>), and millipedes (Marek, 
 <xref rid="ece35065-bib-0068" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>). While the role of the southern Appalachian Mountains as a major barrier driving an east‐west divide among lowland taxa is widely recognized (Soltis et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35065-bib-0090" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref> and references therein), there have been surprisingly few biogeographic and phylogeographic studies of upland species that occupy the mid‐ and high‐elevation ridgelines, and research on invertebrates, in particular, is underrepresented.
</p>
