<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Evidence for changes in sediment provenance and charcoal</div>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Charcoal arriving in marine environments follows two main routes: atmospheric deposition in the case of smaller particles and riverine discharge for small and large particles alike
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span>. Today, the Danube provides 53% of the fresh water and sediment discharge into the Black Sea, the Dnepr and Don provide about 30%, and rivers flowing from the south and southeast ~4% (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). However, source-to-sink analysis shows that the provenance of Black Sea sediments 1050–755 m below sea floor (mbsf) (~10–5 Ma) was predominantly from southerly to southwesterly sources such as the Balkan and Anatolian rivers (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2a</a>)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span>. A transition to a northerly Russian Platform source with episodic delivery of sediments from the Danube occurred between ~5 and 4.3 Ma (755–708 mbsf), and sediments were sourced almost solely from the Russian Platform between ~4.3 and 2.6 Ma (708–651 mbsf). The influx of Danube-supplied sediment to the southwestern Black Sea began after ~4.3 Ma
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span>, however, the final arrival of Danube sediments into the Black Sea took place during the Pleistocene i.e., 571 mbsf (~2 Ma)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span>.
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Sediment transport into the Black Sea. Major rivers draining into the Paratethys highlight major sediment transport routes
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>
     </span>. Arrows show the dominant direction of sediment transport into the Black Sea during the assigned ages
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
     </span> whereas the bold numbers denote Ma. The location of DSDP Site 380/380 A in the Black Sea is indicated by the blue dot labelled ‘380’, along with modern vegetation distribution in the entire region.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_43094_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e384" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Biomass burning, fuel type, vegetation, and climatic conditions during the Miocene to early Pleistocene (~10–2 Ma). (
     <span class="bold">a</span>) Changes in sediment provenance;
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
     </span> ‘D’ is Danube) are shown within the chronological framework of this study. (
     <span class="bold">b</span>) The relative abundance of five ecological groups based on the pollen record:
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>
     </span> 1 = subtropical forest, 2 = warm temperate forest, 3 = coniferous forest, 4 = herbs, and 5 = steppe elements. (
     <span class="bold">c</span>) Biomass burning reconstructed from total charcoal concentrations and percentages and fuel type and fire intensity based on charcoal morphologies (Poaceae, forbs, wood). Total herbs sums Poaceae and forb morphotypes. Poaceae and forb morphologies originate from burning by low-intensity surface fires, whereas wood morphology primarly originates from severe burning of the tree crown. Charcoal class size (90, 125 and 180 μm) is given in percentages. (
     <span class="bold">d</span>) Climatic conditions derived from the hydrogen isotopic compositions (δD) of C
     <sub>29</sub> long-chain 
     <span class="italic">n</span>-alkanes and C
     <sub>37</sub> alkenones (an evaporation proxy) from the same DSDP core
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
     </span>. ‘MSC’ denotes the Messinian Salinity Crisis.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_43094_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e427" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
