<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The link between fire and vegetation turnover: implication for grassland expansion</div>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although grasslands are poorly competitive against trees, they tolerate soils with permanent or seasonal moisture deficits, temperature extremes, and disturbances by fires and herbivores, which otherwise limit the establishment and growth of woody plants
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>
  </span>. It has been shown that the global tendency towards cool and arid conditions that characterised the late Miocene gave rise to an open biome
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
  </span>, although the extension of grass-dominated habitats in the Mediterranean region has been demonstrated to occur as soon as the early Miocene
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span>. The onset of the expansion of open habitat vegetation from ~8.5 to 5.97 Ma in the Black Sea region was concurrent with slightly enhanced biomass burning (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2b–d</a>) and largely increasing evaporative conditions in the Black Sea basin, as indicated by the alkenone-based hydrogen isotopic (δD) record (an evaporation proxy) measured from the same core
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
  </span>. The presence of carbonate nodules requiring strong climate seasonality show that evaporative conditions affected the entire circum-Black Sea region around 8.5 Ma
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span>. This part of the sedimentary sequence is primarily sourced from the Balkans and Anatolia, although charcoal fragments transported by water and air could have originated from the entire Black Sea region (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). A pytholith-based vegetation reconstruction from Turkey indicates a C
  <sub>3</sub>-grass-dominated savanna mosaic at that time
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
  </span>. Similarly, stable carbon isotopic analyses (δ
  <span class="sup">13</span>C) of palaeosols from the Greco-Iranian region and pollen records from Bulgaria indicate the development of open vegetation in the late Miocene
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span>. Further support for the progressive drying of the late Miocene environment (~8–5.3 Ma) around the Black Sea and Eastern Mediterranean is found in the rise of large mammals adapted to open habitats
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
  </span>. It is therefore probable that the warm and especially dry climatic conditions that prevailed during large intervals between ~8.5 and 5.97 Ma around the Black Sea may have led to the drying of fuels in the subtropical-warm temperate deciduous-coniferous forests and promoted mixed surface and crown fires. An increasing proportion of herbaceous plants in formerly closed forests may have provided a favorable fuel mix, i.e., fine herbs and coarse wood, therefore escalating ignition potential, flammability, and fire spread
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climatic conditions became increasingly dry and temperatures declined during the late Miocene to middle Pliocene (~5.97–4.3 Ma), especially in the northern Black Sea
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span>. Though fluctuating, biomass burning peaked and the more frequent fires likely promoted grassland expansion, accelerated the forest to open woodland transition and sustained a more flammable ecosystem (Figs 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2b,c</a> and 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S2</a>). Studies of grass evolution in tropical savannas (C
  <sub>4</sub>-type) indicate that their fine fuels with rapid curing, low bulk densities, and fast regrowth rates led to frequent surface fires, and that woody species, adapted to infrequent fires, were unable to complete their life cycle
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
  </span>. Sediment provenance analysis suggests continued sediment transport from the Balkan and Anatolian rivers (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>), thus areas increasingly covered by open vegetation, although this source becomes uncertain towards the later part of this interval, i.e., ~5.33–4.3 Ma (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2a</a>). Pollen records from northern regions (i.e., the Ukrainian Plain) corroborate an increasingly cold and dry climate along a west-to-east gradient during this time, and vegetation dominated by forest-steppe and open xerophytic herbs
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span>. It is noteworthy that the sustained decline in biomass burning from ~5.8 to 5.33 Ma was coeval with the Messinian Salinity Crisis (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2d</a>), a period characterised by a large disruption in the regional hydrological cycle, a major water level drop in the Mediterranean Sea
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
  </span>, and enhanced northern hemisphere glaciation that culminated during the TG 20 and TG 22 glacial peaks
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A tipping point in the fire regime occurred at ~4.3 Ma and the new established fire regime lasted at least until the end of our record (~1.9 Ma, early Pleistocene). It is evident as a decrease in burning activity, the predominance of herbaceous charcoal fuel and the maximum extent of grassy vegetation (Figs 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2b,c</a> and 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S2</a>). A regional differentiation in climate, vegetation, and fauna assemblages was apparent between ~4.2 and 2 Ma, when Central and Eastern Europe (the major source feeding sediments into the Black Sea at that time) remained arid, while the Mediterranean region became more humid
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
  </span>. We propose that low vegetation productivity and thus fuel availability of grassy vegetation limited the biomass burned yet, surface fires were perhaps frequent. Low amounts of burned biomass and/or frequent fires have been documented in modern low productivity grassy environments and during past dry and cold climatic periods of slow vegetation growth and fuel accumulation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
  </span>. Herbivores are also known to remove vegetation load, leading to reduced fuel availability and therefore biomass burned
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>
  </span>. By ~15 Ma, ca. 25% of the world’s mammals were typically hypsodont grazers and 35% of mixed diet
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>
  </span>, whereas hypsodont grazers rose to dominance in Eurasia from ~8 to 4.5 Ma
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
  </span>. It is therefore probable that the observed decline in biomass burning may have also been a response to increased grazing pressure and reduced fuel availability.
 </p>
 <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We further tested whether periods of high fire occurrence coincided with increased representation of C
  <sub>4</sub> plants in the surrounding vegetation, as this vegetation type has a strong competitive advantage under frequent fires
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>
  </span>. In eastern Eurasia, C
  <sub>3</sub> plants dominated throughout the Neogene, whereas C
  <sub>4</sub> grasses were of little ecological importance
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
  </span>. The δ
  <span class="sup">13</span>C values of C
  <sub>29</sub> long-chain 
  <span class="italic">n</span>-alkanes from the same Black Sea record covering the period ~10–5 Ma are in the range of C
  <sub>3</sub> plant communities (−27 to −30‰; Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S2</a>). This indicates that the enhanced late Miocene fire activity was associated with the dominance of C
  <sub>3</sub> grasses and further highlights that fire has been a significant ecological agent for C
  <sub>3</sub> plants in the Black Sea region. Simulated late Miocene vegetation scenarios for Africa, show that fire allowed both C
  <sub>3</sub> and C
  <sub>4</sub> grasses to expand into forests
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
</sec>
