<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Variation in cereal production is directly linked with variations in precipitation and temperature and evident in the historical yield records. Projections of future changes in climate with warming temperatures and more variable precipitation will have impacts on crop productivity (
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Tao et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hao et al., 2013</xref>) and the recent analysis by 
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hatfield et al. (2017)</xref> for maize and soybean revealed that a combination of July maximum temperatures, August minimum temperatures, and July–August precipitation explained yield gaps across the Corn Belt. In this research study, we found for wheat in the Great Plains of the United States that precipitation was the dominant factor, with amounts during the grain-filling period the most critical in terms of affecting yield. Projections of precipitation for the critical months for wheat production in the Midwest obtained from 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://climatetoolbox.org/tool/future-climate" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://climatetoolbox.org/tool/future-climate</ext-link> show that amounts will increase coupled with increased variation. We could expect yield variation among years to increase; however, the tendency to increase total amounts would suggest years with low yields may decrease leading to an overall increase in wheat productivity across the Great Plains until temperature increases become the dominant factor affecting grain yields. The projection that precipitation will become more variable during the spring months creates a situation in which management of soil water for the crop will be a necessary adaptation strategy to cope with climate change (
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Melillo et al., 2014</xref>). Protection of the soil resource to ensure available soil water will be critical to overcoming these impacts.
</p>
