<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In the first study in sociology that takes such an approach, Jorgenson and Clark (
 <xref rid="wcc554-bib-0127" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>) use interactions between GDP per capita and time in longitudinal models of anthropogenic carbon emissions for samples of developed and developing countries covering the 1960–2005 period. Three measures of national carbon emissions are analyzed: total emissions, per capita emissions, and emissions per unit of GDP. The results indicate a strong relationship between per capita emissions and GDP per capita in developed nations that is stable in magnitude through time. For developing countries they find that the association between emissions and GDP per capita increases in magnitude through time, the opposite of decoupling, but still remains smaller in magnitude than the relationship between per capita emissions and GDP in developed countries. For total emissions, the estimated effect of GDP per capita decreased in magnitude over time in developed countries, providing some evidence of a decoupling for such nations, while for developing countries the results indicate a stable effect of GDP per capita on total emissions through time. The analysis of emissions per unit of GDP suggests a slight decoupling for the sample of developed nations, while the findings for the sample of developing countries are inconclusive. In a more recent longitudinal study that extends the temporal scope of the analysis to 2010, Thombs (
 <xref rid="wcc554-bib-0218" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2018a</xref>) replicates the findings of Jorgenson and Clark (
 <xref rid="wcc554-bib-0127" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>) across all three measures of emissions. Overall, this body of research on decoupling provides mixed support for ecological modernization theory and treadmill of production theory, and suggests that both frameworks could benefit from further consideration of how the global organization of production and the structure of international trade influence the relationship between carbon emissions and economic development.
</p>
