<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Yet, the few studies that have assessed future climate impacts on Chinese air quality have relied on global climate/chemistry models whose resolution is too coarse to capture localized features that lead to the extremely high concentrations of aerosols in densely populated urban areas especially harmful to human health (
 <xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>). Similarly, previous studies quantifying future climate-driven air quality changes have focused on assessment of mean climate diagnostics (
 <xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>), neglecting the potentially important role of extreme weather events such as heat waves, heavy precipitation, and atmospheric stagnation on air quality, which may be important climate mechanisms leading to deadly air pollution events. Although more frequent and intense extreme weather events are projected under future climate change (
 <xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>
 <xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr"/>–
 <xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>
 <xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr"/>–
 <xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>), their impacts on atmospheric pollutant concentrations have not been quantified, which are the ultimate determinants of air quality and associated health outcomes (
 <xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>). The role of climate extremes in future air quality and the associated health impacts are not well recognized and are rarely quantified. Yet, policy makers and the public are concerned not only with average air quality but also with extreme air pollution events, which may have a disproportionate effect on human health, and are thus a focus of clean air policies. Critical research questions for the scientific community are thus related to whether such extremes may change in the future as a result of climate change, and the underlying climate mechanisms that affect air quality. Our goal is thus to link together studies of how extreme weather events will change under climate change and studies focused on how climate change will affect air quality.
</p>
