<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par33" class="p">We use long-run income elasticities and temperature semi-elasticities estimated by DCSW
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">24</xref>
 </sup> to explore uncertainty in projected energy demand impacts across a range of climate models and socioeconomic scenarios. DCSW
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">24</xref>
 </sup> uses unbalanced panel data of energy demand, income per capita, prices, and weather covariates for 204 countries over the period 1970–2014 (see detailed references in DCSW
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">24</xref>
 </sup>) to estimate income elasticities and temperature semi-elasticities of sectoral energy demand across two regions (temperate, tropical), three energy carriers (electricity, natural gas, and petroleum products), and four sectors (residential, commercial, industry, and agriculture). Differently from the customary approach used in the climate-economy literature
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">12</xref>
 </sup>, DCSW
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">24</xref>
 </sup> models, the relationship between energy demand, weather, income, and prices as a dynamic adjustment process. The adjustment in energy demand following a shock is not immediate, because of capital fixity and adjustments in expectations. At each point in time, changes in energy demand are a function of weather, income, and price shocks, as well as of the adjustment process induced by shocks that took place in the previous period (year). Adjustments in energy use to price, income, and weather shocks occur over time, in line with studies finding evidence of persistency
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">12</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" class="xref">54</xref>
 </sup>. DCSW estimates the model as a dynamic panel using an Error-Correction Model (ECM), which yields short- and long-run elasticities. Over the long run, adjustments on the extensive margin (e.g., purchase of air conditioners, improvements in energy efficiency) also affect the use of energy, and this additional effect is being captured by the long-run elasticities, which we use here in this paper. The ECM can also be represented as an Autoregressive-Distributed-Lag model, and it also allows obtaining statistical inference that is robust to nonstationary data. Long-run estimates can be seen as a weighted average of elasticities estimated in the first difference or using a static model (Hendry, 1995
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" class="xref">55</xref>
 </sup>, see also Table 
 <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" class="xref">2</xref>).
</p>
