<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The uptake of atmospheric carbon (C) by plants and subsequent storage in soils may be an effective means to lower atmospheric carbon dioxide (CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>) concentrations and to help mitigate climate change. Integrated assessment models (IAMs), which are used to explore future energy, land-use, and greenhouse gas (GHG) emission scenarios, currently rely on bioenergy with carbon capture and storage (BECCS) as a principal negative emission technology to reach climate change mitigation targets, but generally do not consider the possibility of C drawdown and soil organic C (SOC) sequestration from improved land management (
 <xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">1</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">2</italic>
 </xref>). Improved land management, without changing land use, may be an additional C sequestration option that does not require more land conversion. Land-use change and poor management practices have resulted in the loss of more than 130 Pg C from agricultural soil (
 <xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">3</italic>
 </xref>), leaving &gt;1 billion hectares of degraded soil worldwide (
 <xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">4</italic>
 </xref>). Site-based studies and ecosystem-scale models have shown that degraded and managed agricultural lands have great potential to contribute to increased SOC sequestration through improved management (
 <xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">5</italic>
 </xref>–
 <xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">7</italic>
 </xref>). We define soil C sequestration as a net increase in SOC storage. Several agricultural (cropland and grazing land) management practices have been shown to increase soil C sequestration including organic amendments (
 <xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">8</italic>
 </xref>–
 <xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">10</italic>
 </xref>), cover crops, reduced tillage, improved crop rotations (
 <xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">5</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">11</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">12</italic>
 </xref>), and improved grazing management (
 <xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">13</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">14</italic>
 </xref>). Citing these proven practices and others, France and 33 other countries recently instituted a challenge to increase soil C by 4 per mil per year (
 <xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">15</italic>
 </xref>). However, the actual potential of these practices to contribute to lowering global temperature over time is poorly understood, despite recent efforts to quantify the amenable global land area and near-term sequestration rates associated with various practices (
 <xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">16</italic>
 </xref>–
 <xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">18</italic>
 </xref>). This is primarily due to uncertainty regarding the maintenance of soil C sequestration rates over time, the C sequestration capacity of different soils under different managements, and the sensitivity of global temperature changes to CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> emission and sequestration.
</p>
