<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In China, there are two types of wheat, winter wheat and spring wheat, which are named according to their growing period. Wheat is cultivated mainly in Hebei, Shanxi, Henan, Shandong, Anhui, Hubei, Jiangsu, Sichuan, and Shaanxi. Due to differences in climate conditions and precipitation patterns in different regions, the impacts of climate change/variability on wheat growth and yield differ as well. For example, You et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0184474.ref049" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>] found that climate warming reduced wheat yield growth; a 1°C increase in temperature during the wheat growing period reduced wheat output by 3–10%. Similarly, Tao et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0184474.ref004" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>] investigated climate-crop relationships and concluded that the total yield of wheat was estimated to change by -1.2*10
 <sup class="sup">5</sup> t. Tao et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0184474.ref015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>] found that for the northern China, climate change increased wheat yield by 1.2–10.2%. In contrast, some studies have shown that the impact of climate change on the wheat yield was positive. Zhang et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0184474.ref037" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>] suggested that in the past two decades, climate warming has benefited the wheat yield in the north-central region of China, although the effect of the average temperature and diurnal temperature range on the wheat yield was overall negative. Consistent with Zhang et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0184474.ref037" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>] and based on experimental observations at agricultural meteorological stations in China, Tao et al. found that changes in temperature, precipitation and solar radiation from 1981 to 2009 jointly increased the wheat yield in northern China by 0.9–12.9% but reduced the wheat yield in southern China by 1.2–10.2% [
 <xref rid="pone.0184474.ref015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>]. In addition, some researchers have investigated the future impacts of climate change on wheat yield. Tao et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0184474.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>] evaluated the possible impacts of climate change on the winter wheat yield in the North China Plain under 10 climate scenarios and found a high probability that climate warming could increase winter wheat yield in the future. Simulated results have also indicated that relative to 1961–1990, the wheat yield will increase by up to 37.7% (18.6%), 67.8% (23.1%), and 87.2% (34.4%) with (without) CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> fertilization effects during the 2020s, 2050s, and 2080s, respectively [
 <xref rid="pone.0184474.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>].
</p>
