<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">INTRODUCTION</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The biological sciences include topics that are viewed as controversial and even antithetical to the beliefs of some members of the public. Thus, research into new teaching methods, strategies, and tools for controversial topics could strengthen the educational experience as well as offer an assessment of teaching outcomes with respect to both material mastery and general attitudes toward science. When presenting science to general audiences, the primary goals often are to develop a fundamental appreciation of science and the scientific process in addition to specific content knowledge (
  <a rid="b32-jmbe-17-107" ref-type="bibr" href="#b32-jmbe-17-107">32</a>, 
  <a rid="b34-jmbe-17-107" ref-type="bibr" href="#b34-jmbe-17-107">34</a>, 
  <a rid="b35-jmbe-17-107" ref-type="bibr" href="#b35-jmbe-17-107">35</a>). This appreciation of science can be developed through engaging students of all ages—from elementary to elderly—in explicit and reflective discussion and hands-on experiences, i.e., research (
  <a rid="b1-jmbe-17-107" ref-type="bibr" href="#b1-jmbe-17-107">1</a>, 
  <a rid="b33-jmbe-17-107" ref-type="bibr" href="#b33-jmbe-17-107">33</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Among the topics perceived as controversial in the biological sciences, perhaps the most commonly discussed is evolution (
  <a rid="b4-jmbe-17-107" ref-type="bibr" href="#b4-jmbe-17-107">4</a>, 
  <a rid="b31-jmbe-17-107" ref-type="bibr" href="#b31-jmbe-17-107">31</a>, 
  <a rid="b55-jmbe-17-107" ref-type="bibr" href="#b55-jmbe-17-107">55</a>). In recent decades, the educational setbacks and gains from teaching evolution in the United States provide a needed frame of reference and offer insights into instructional methods (
  <a rid="b22-jmbe-17-107" ref-type="bibr" href="#b22-jmbe-17-107">22</a>) for other “hot” topics such as climate change, genetically modified organisms (GMOs), and cloning, among others. Teaching climate change content in a biology classroom is complicated by many factors, some of which are present also when teaching evolution. Biology instructors and researchers regularly encounter the interconnected nature of the environment and organisms; contemporary discussions of climate change therefore should be enriched by fundamental concepts such as evolution and extinction.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Citizen science, the practice of nonscientists collecting information for investigations in an organized manner that yields data to test hypotheses, represents a key method to link science education and environmental education (
  <a rid="b5-jmbe-17-107" ref-type="bibr" href="#b5-jmbe-17-107">5</a>, 
  <a rid="b6-jmbe-17-107" ref-type="bibr" href="#b6-jmbe-17-107">6</a>, 
  <a rid="b7-jmbe-17-107" ref-type="bibr" href="#b7-jmbe-17-107">7</a>, 
  <a rid="b12-jmbe-17-107" ref-type="bibr" href="#b12-jmbe-17-107">12</a>, 
  <a rid="b15-jmbe-17-107" ref-type="bibr" href="#b15-jmbe-17-107">15</a>, 
  <a rid="b48-jmbe-17-107" ref-type="bibr" href="#b48-jmbe-17-107">48</a>, 
  <a rid="b54-jmbe-17-107" ref-type="bibr" href="#b54-jmbe-17-107">54</a>). Additionally, it may create a foundation for enhancing the engagement of citizens of all ages with the sciences by allowing them to participate actively rather than passively in science. The expansion of inquiry-based education to encourage curiosity also has led to the rise of publishable research based on well-crafted testable hypotheses, with students participating in the faculty member’s research project (
  <a rid="b25-jmbe-17-107" ref-type="bibr" href="#b25-jmbe-17-107">25</a>). Citizen-science projects in evolution have shown success in allowing ordinary citizens to help test important hypotheses, a notable example being the large-scale Evolution MegaLab project, which spanned 15 countries and involved over 6,000 participants (
  <a rid="b56-jmbe-17-107" ref-type="bibr" href="#b56-jmbe-17-107">56</a>). Other notable citizen-science examples include eBird and Zooniverse (
  <a rid="b6-jmbe-17-107" ref-type="bibr" href="#b6-jmbe-17-107">6</a>, 
  <a rid="b18-jmbe-17-107" ref-type="bibr" href="#b18-jmbe-17-107">18</a>, 
  <a rid="b50-jmbe-17-107" ref-type="bibr" href="#b50-jmbe-17-107">50</a>, 
  <a rid="b59-jmbe-17-107" ref-type="bibr" href="#b59-jmbe-17-107">59</a>). Additional projects cover a variety of areas, from ecology to comparative genomics (
  <a rid="b27-jmbe-17-107" ref-type="bibr" href="#b27-jmbe-17-107">27</a>, 
  <a rid="b46-jmbe-17-107" ref-type="bibr" href="#b46-jmbe-17-107">46</a>, 
  <a rid="b48-jmbe-17-107" ref-type="bibr" href="#b48-jmbe-17-107">48</a>). Recently, developments in smartphone use platforms (
  <a rid="b36-jmbe-17-107" ref-type="bibr" href="#b36-jmbe-17-107">36</a>) and social networking patterns (
  <a rid="b16-jmbe-17-107" ref-type="bibr" href="#b16-jmbe-17-107">16</a>) have multiplied the ways popular technologies can be integrated into citizen-science research. Mobile devices and social media may be useful tools for encouraging participation. However, regardless of these advances and expanding projects, the results of such research are not often accepted as traditionally publishable data in the peer review process, but instead as education or outreach only (
  <a rid="b7-jmbe-17-107" ref-type="bibr" href="#b7-jmbe-17-107">7</a>). New interest from scientific and educational research perspectives must be utilized to validate the data generated and develop an appreciation for the scientific process.
 </p>
</sec>
