<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The Caatinga Phytogeographic Domain (CPD) is a seasonally dry tropical forest (SDTF) endemic to Brazil and represents one of the largest semiarid regions in South America, occurring over approximately 800,000 km
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> [
 <xref rid="pone.0217028.ref051" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">51</xref>]. The Caatinga is located in northeastern Brazil, abutting the Atlantic forest domain to the east and the Cerrado to the west and south. The seasonality and rainfall distribution, associated with elevated temperatures and highly variable edaphic conditions, drive a diverse spectrum of Caatinga phytogeographic formations (e.g. [
 <xref rid="pone.0217028.ref052" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0217028.ref055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>]). These range from open areas with shrub and herbaceous vegetation, such as the inselbergs, to areas where tree species predominate in both species’ richness and abundance, such as arboreal Caatingas (
 <italic class="italic">sensu</italic> [
 <xref rid="pone.0217028.ref056" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">56</xref>]). The Caatinga flora is considered the most diverse SDTF on Earth, harboring 298 endemic species [
 <xref rid="pone.0217028.ref057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>], representing 31 genera of flowering plants [
 <xref rid="pone.0217028.ref058" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">58</xref>]. Future climatic conditions for the Caatinga vegetation cover indicate that some regions will likely experience high levels of aridity and subsequent desertification [
 <xref rid="pone.0217028.ref004" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0217028.ref059" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">59</xref>], resulting in changes in plant species diversity and distribution [
 <xref rid="pone.0217028.ref001" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0217028.ref006" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>] and key ecological processes such as pollination and associated functions [
 <xref rid="pone.0217028.ref013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. Due to the characteristics mentioned above, the Caatinga represents an ideal tropical model for studies on the effects of climate change on species distributions.
</p>
