<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<app-group class="app-group">
 <app id="app1" class="app">
  <title class="title">Appendix 1: Q-sample</title>
  <list list-type="order" class="list">
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">The climate is a natural part of the world we just have to accept and live with.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">The climate is complicated.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">The climate is unpredictable.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">The climate is not changing.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">There is something wrong with the climate.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">Climate change is not a sign that the world is ending.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">Natural disasters happen when nature wants to reshape itself.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">The climate is determined by God.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">Climate change is not punishment for the sins that people commit.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">Climate change is caused by the fighting of the ancestors.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">Traditional healers cause the climate to change.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">The climate is affected by the behaviour of people.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">Increasing population growth causes climate change.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">Climate change is not caused by technology.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">Climate change is related to the burning of fossil fuels and pollution.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">The climate influences the growth of crops and the production of food.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">People are trying to make money, that’s why they are damaging the environment.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">The climate was not better when I was younger.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">We can solve environmental problems by returning to the ways of the past.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">The next generation will be influenced by our current behaviour towards nature.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">We must act now to prevent the climate problems of the future.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">Young people can help older people catch up with new knowledge about the climate.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">We have the right to know about climate issues that affects us directly and indirectly.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">Educating people about climate change will anger the ancestors and cause bad luck.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">It is not the duty of the government to inform people about climate change.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">We can address climate problems by drafting laws that protect the environment.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">We can solve climate problems when we stand together and unite.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">It is possible for humans to control the climate through technology.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">Using sustainable technology is not good for the climate.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">It is difficult to care about climate change because of economic pressures.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">The climate does not play an important role in our lives.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">We do not have to respect the environment.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">It is difficult to educate people about climate change because of their beliefs.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">It is possible to change my beliefs when someone else tells me to.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">In order to change our beliefs about the climate, we must sit down and discuss the matter.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">My beliefs can change if I see in reality that things are different from my beliefs.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">My beliefs about the climate can change when mechanisms are in place to protect us.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">I am open to change my beliefs, because I learn new things all the time.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">It is not possible to change my beliefs.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">The climate influences how people feel emotionally and that may cause changes in their beliefs.</p>
   </list-item>
  </list>
 </app>
</app-group>
