<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par54" class="p">Across the four landscapes, managers face common barriers to advancing adaptation, including lack of political support, resource deficits, competing pressures from land use changes, and uncertainty in designing management actions to address the impacts of climate change. Resource deficits, particularly funding, are frequently cited as a primary explanation for why practitioners have not begun implementation of adaptation actions (Moser and Ekstrom 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" class="xref">2010</xref>; Archie et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">2012</xref>; Kemp et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" class="xref">2015</xref>). While 79% of survey participants in this study considered lack of financial resources an important barrier, other barriers emerged as more influential in most landscapes, an indication that participants perceive more diverse challenges to adaptation. In particular, participants in all the landscapes but Arctic Alaska identified lack of political will and support as a top impediment to adaptation, particularly as it related to initial problem recognition, priority setting and allocation of resources. This finding is consistent with the international literature for urban and rural settings, which shows that a lack of high level government support can inhibit climate change adaptation efforts at local scales (Measham et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">2011</xref>; Aylett 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">2015</xref>; Lemieux et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" class="xref">2015</xref>). In our study, survey respondents in every landscape identified the challenge of sustaining political support for long-term action as one of the top two most influential barriers to adaptation action. Similarly, participants highlighted the difficulty of addressing the scale and complexity of climate change within the constraints of one or two-year funding cycles. Taken together, our results support other findings that suggest the short-term nature of political agendas and funding cycles has significant effects on an organization’s capacity to implement actions to address climate change (Crabbé and Robin 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">2006</xref>; Ford et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">2011</xref>; Bierbaum et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">2013</xref>; Aylett 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">2015</xref>).
</p>
