<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par55" class="p">Barriers related to climate change data and information, such as uncertainty of climate change projections and poor information transfer between researchers and practitioners are well-documented (Jantarasami et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" class="xref">2010</xref>; Murthy et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" class="xref">2010</xref>; Kemp et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" class="xref">2015</xref>); however, these particular barriers did not emerge as influential in our study suggesting there has been progress in making climate change information more readily available, in these landscapes at least. More significant and pervasive across all landscapes were barriers related to understanding how climate change interacts with complex social, ecological and political dynamics, ongoing land uses and other changes affecting wild ecosystems, and identifying appropriate management actions in response to those interactions. This finding reflects the results from Aylett (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">2015</xref>), who found that barriers become more pronounced as one moves from general climate change information to understanding local impacts and formulating definitive management plans. Our interview responses strongly suggest that even when managers accept climate change as a critical threat to resources and ecosystems, the general challenge of ‘not knowing what to do about it’ may prevent them from taking meaningful action (Jantarasami et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" class="xref">2010</xref>; Archie et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">2012</xref>; Kemp et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" class="xref">2015</xref>), especially if they simultaneously face other limitations, e.g., funding deficits, staffing and time constraints, and a lack of political support. Such findings indicate that barriers cannot be understood as isolated factors, but as interconnected and cumulative influences on adaptation action (Eisenack et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" class="xref">2014</xref>).
</p>
