<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap id="table002" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="table-wrap">
 <label class="label">Table 2.</label>
 <caption class="caption">
  <p class="p">Sample assessments for climate change and health.</p>
 </caption>
 <table frame="box" rules="all" class="table">
  <tbody class="tbody">
   <tr class="tr">
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="td">Group presentation</td>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="td">As a doctor representing the Fijian Government, outline the local climate and health issues and propose adaptation and mitigation priorities to the World Health Organisation’s regional office. As a doctor representing the Australian Medical Association, discuss the health concerns of climate change and specify federal policy priorities on national radio.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr class="tr">
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="td">Essay or in-class debate</td>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="td">Climate change is the greatest health threat of the 21st century. Climate change mitigation is more important than adaptation for health. Divestment from fossil fuels in an ethical and professional obligation of health services.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr class="tr">
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="td">Reflective piece</td>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="td">Reflect on prominent public health successes to discuss the role of the doctor in advocacy and policy.
     <break class="break"/>Will climate change influence your personal and professional life, if so, how? Present a case history of a patient, identifying environmental and social determinants of health.
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr class="tr">
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="td">Short answer questions</td>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="td">List two direct, indirect and delayed health risks of climate change. Apply your understanding of vulnerability and determinants of health to explain how you would manage an elderly person living alone during a heatwave. Examine the following excerpt about a town in Bangladesh: what are its exposure, sensitivity and adaptive capacity to climate change? What priorities do you recommend to protect and promote health?</td>
   </tr>
   <tr class="tr">
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="td">Placement project</td>
    <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="td">Conduct a waste or energy audit of a clinic, ward or operating theatre and recommend strategies that promote health and reduce environmental impact. Conduct a review of a local council’s processes to ensure the health of elderly residents during a heatwave or bushfire</td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
</table-wrap>
