<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A weakened connection driven by a more stable troposphere</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Atlantic Niño–Pacific connection is underpinned by the response of equatorial Atlantic convection to the Atlantic Niño/Niña (
  <a rid="R8" ref-type="bibr" href="#R8">
   <span class="italic">8</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R10" ref-type="bibr" href="#R10">
   <span class="italic">10</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R11" ref-type="bibr" href="#R11">
   <span class="italic">11</span>
  </a>), manifested in a rising motion commencing approximately 600 hPa in both the present day and future climates (
  <a rid="F3" ref-type="fig" href="#F3">Fig. 3, A and B</a>). In response to diabatic heating anomalies, the response of vertical velocity is smaller in the future than in the present-day climate in the majority of models (
  <a rid="F3" ref-type="fig" href="#F3">Fig. 3C</a>), with 14 of 17 models generating a weaker response in the future climate. Aggregated over all models, there is a statistically significant weakening in the multimodel response of the vertical velocity to the Atl-EOF index, by as much as 47%, as can be seen from comparison of slopes for the present-day and future climates (
  <a rid="F3" ref-type="fig" href="#F3">Fig. 3D</a>). The weakened convection response is accompanied by a decreased precipitation response to Atlantic Niño/Niña under future climate, with a strong (14 of 17) intermodel consensus (fig. S7).
 </p>
 <div id="F3" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Projection of decreased response to a diabatic equatorial Atlantic heating.</div>
   <p>Multimodel (the 17 selected models) average of boreal summer (JJA0) regression of equatorial (10°S to 10°N) vertical atmospheric velocity (pascals per second; color) and equatorial atmospheric flow vectors (zonal wind and vertical velocity scaled by a factor of 300) onto the Atl-EOF index of the present-day (1900–1999) (
    <span class="bold">A</span>) and future (2000–2099) (
    <span class="bold">B</span>) 100-year periods. Values exceeding 1 SD are shown in shaded contour and black vectors. The color map and reference vector are labeled in the middle of (A) and (B). (
    <span class="bold">C</span>) Comparison of vertical velocity response to the Atl-EOF index over the present-day (blue bars) and future (orange bars) 100-year periods in the 17 selected models. The three models that simulate an increase in response are marked in gray. Error bars in the multimodel mean are calculated as 2 SDs (the 95% confidence interval based on normal distribution) of the 10,000 inter-realizations of a bootstrap method (see “Bootstrap test” section in Materials and Methods). The vertical velocity response is measured by the regression coefficients (pascals per second per SD) of the JJA0 vertical velocity anomalies at 600 hPa averaged over the equatorial Atlantic (5°S to 5°N and 45°W to 20°E) and the respective Atl-EOF index. (
    <span class="bold">D</span>) Responses of JJA0 vertical velocity anomalies at 600 hPa averaged over the equatorial Atlantic (5°S to 5°N and 45°W to 20°E) (pascals per second) to JJA0 Atl-EOF index using all samples of 17 selected models. The vertical velocity anomalies are binned in 0.1 SD. Atl-EOF index intervals and the median vertical velocity anomaly and index are identified for each bin (dots). Blue and red dots indicate values in the present-day and future 100-year periods, respectively. The corresponding linear fitting lines (with the values of the slopes plus and minus the 95% confidence values from the Student’s 
    <span class="italic">t</span> test) are also shown.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="aax4111-F3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Under global warming, the midtroposphere warms faster than the near-surface levels (
  <a rid="F4" ref-type="fig" href="#F4">Fig. 4A</a>) (
  <a rid="R29" ref-type="bibr" href="#R29">
   <span class="italic">29</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R30" ref-type="bibr" href="#R30">
   <span class="italic">30</span>
  </a>), reducing the boreal summer mean negative vertical temperature gradient, defined as the difference between the boreal summer mean temperature at 600 hPa and the temperature at 925 hPa. This weakened negative vertical gradient is seen in all selected models (
  <a rid="F4" ref-type="fig" href="#F4">Fig. 4B</a>). It is this more stable troposphere that weakens the convective response, leading to the weakened Atlantic Niño–Pacific connection; models that generate a larger reduction in the background temperature gradient tend to simulate a weaker boreal winter Pacific SST response (
  <a rid="F4" ref-type="fig" href="#F4">Fig. 4B</a>), and the tendency is statistically significant. The weakened connection occurs despite a strengthening ocean-atmosphere coupling in the equatorial Pacific under greenhouse warming (
  <a rid="R28" ref-type="bibr" href="#R28">
   <span class="italic">28</span>
  </a>), which would otherwise enhance the connection.
 </p>
 <div id="F4" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Mechanism for the projected decrease in the Atlantic Niño–Pacific connection.</div>
   <p>(
    <span class="bold">A</span>) Warming trend of the boreal summer mean (JJA0) air temperature (AirT) over the equatorial Atlantic (5°S to 5°N and 45°W to 20°E) at different levels during 2000–2099. (
    <span class="bold">B</span>) Intermodel relationship between the change (between future and present-day climates) of boreal summer mean (JJA0) atmospheric stratification and the Pacific SST response. The atmospheric stratification is calculated as the difference between the boreal summer mean (JJA0) temperature at 600 hPa and the temperature at 925 hPa, both averaged over the equatorial Atlantic. The linear fit (solid line) is displayed together with the correlation coefficient 
    <span class="italic">r</span>, slope, and 
    <span class="italic">P</span> value from the regression. To enhance the intermodel comparability, we scale both the warming trend in (A) and the changes in (B) by the increase in global mean temperature over the present-day and future periods.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="aax4111-F4" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The increased tropospheric stability under greenhouse warming also occurs in the equatorial Pacific. In the Pacific, however, this is offset by an increased probability of atmospheric deep convection over the equatorial eastern Pacific, where the fastest warming in the tropics occurs (fig. S8), leading to an increased rainfall response of SST anomalies under greenhouse warming (
  <a rid="R26" ref-type="bibr" href="#R26">
   <span class="italic">26</span>
  </a>). In the equatorial Atlantic, SST warms slower and more uniform than that in the equatorial Pacific (fig. S8), and the damping effect of increased atmosphere stability dominates.
 </p>
</sec>
