<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Observed Atlantic Niño–Pacific connection</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To depict the observed Atlantic Niño and its impact on the Pacific Ocean, we applied empirical orthogonal function (EOF) analysis to quadratically detrended SST anomalies (see “EOF analysis” section in Materials and Methods) averaged over boreal summer (June, July, and August or JJA0, where “0” refers to current year), in which an Atlantic Niño peaks. This yields a dominant principal pattern, and a principal component (PC) time series scaled to have a standard deviation (SD) of 1. In place of an index commonly taken as an average over a fixed area (
  <a rid="R8" ref-type="bibr" href="#R8">
   <span class="italic">8</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R10" ref-type="bibr" href="#R10">
   <span class="italic">10</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R11" ref-type="bibr" href="#R11">
   <span class="italic">11</span>
  </a>), we take the PC time series as the Atlantic Niño/Niña index, hereafter referred to as Atl-EOF index. Together with its associated pattern, the Atl-EOF index describes the anomaly pattern and evolution of the Atlantic Niño/Niña.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Given that the impact on the tropical Pacific reaches a maximum two seasons later (i.e., December, January, and February or D0JF1, where “1” refers to the following year), we measure the evolution of Atlantic Niño–Pacific connection by a correlation between the Atl-EOF index (i.e., PC1 at JJA0) and D0JF1 SST anomalies averaged over the equatorial Pacific (5°S to 5°N and 160°E to 90°W), in sliding 20-year windows with the result recorded in the last year of the window (black curve in 
  <a rid="F1" ref-type="fig" href="#F1">Fig. 1A</a>). Substantial fluctuations in the connection are seen, culminating in a persistent strong connection since the late 1960s. Considering that the relationship might not be statistically significant over the entire area of the equatorial Pacific, for each 20-year period, we calculated correlations with grid-point D0JF1 SST anomalies, but only significant grid-point correlations are averaged (red points in 
  <a rid="F1" ref-type="fig" href="#F1">Fig. 1A</a>) (see “Sign-dependent average” section in Materials and Methods). This confirms a persistent connection since the late 1960s.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The persistent connection reflects an important relationship between ENSO events (defined by National Ocean Atmosphere Administration) and the Atlantic Niño events (defined by a 0.5 SD threshold of Atl-EOF index) (table S1). A total of 10 of 17 Atlantic Niño events are followed by La Niña events, including the more extreme events of 1988 and 1998. Eight of 17 Atlantic Niña events were followed by El Niño events, including the 1982, 1997, and 2015 extreme El Niño events. Because of the recent persistent correlation, a statistically significant Atlantic Niño–Pacific connection over the 1900–1999 period is seen in much of the equatorial Pacific (black bar in 
  <a rid="F1" ref-type="fig" href="#F1">Fig. 1B</a> and hashed area in 
  <a rid="F1" ref-type="fig" href="#F1">Fig. 1C</a>). Recent studies have shown that including this equatorial Atlantic influence improves ENSO prediction (
  <a rid="R18" ref-type="bibr" href="#R18">
   <span class="italic">18</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R19" ref-type="bibr" href="#R19">
   <span class="italic">19</span>
  </a>). Below, we examine the Atlantic Niño–Pacific connection under historical forcing and the representative concentration pathway 8.5 (RCP8.5) emission scenario in climate models participating in phase 5 of Coupled Model Intercomparison Project (CMIP5) (see “Observed and CMIP5 data” section in Materials and Methods).
 </p>
</sec>
