<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The risk categories for CHIKV transmission potential (
 <inline-formula class="inline-formula">
  <math id="M145" class="math">
   <mrow class="mrow">
    <msub class="msub">
     <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">R</mi>
     <mn class="mn">0</mn>
    </msub>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula>) were overlain with the SIG suitability classes representing the presence of 
 <italic class="italic">Ae. albopictus</italic> to produce overall risk categories that allowed risk maps to be drawn that identify areas in Canada at risk for short-term autochthonous CHIKV transmission under recent and projected climate change. Similar to other studies in Europe (
 <xref rid="c29" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Fischer et al. 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="c32" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Fischer et al. 2013</xref>), we assumed that climatic suitability for CHIKV transmission potential in combination with climatic suitability for the presence of 
 <italic class="italic">Ae. albopictus</italic> results in higher risk for autochthonous CHIKV transmission via this particular vector. Accordingly, the 
 <inline-formula class="inline-formula">
  <math id="M146" class="math">
   <mrow class="mrow">
    <msub class="msub">
     <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">R</mi>
     <mn class="mn">0</mn>
    </msub>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> values and their corresponding risk categories reflecting the transmission potential for CHIKV for each grid cell (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1" class="xref">Figure 1</xref>) were combined with the SIG values and their corresponding suitability classes reflecting the climatic suitability for 
 <italic class="italic">Ae. albopictus</italic> for each grid cell to produce an overall CHIKV suitability risk category (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f2" class="xref">Figure 2</xref>). This overall CHIKV suitability risk classification was then assigned to each grid cell in Canada for each of the five climate datasets. ArcGIS®10.3 [Environmental Systems Research Institute (ESRI), Inc.] and Panoply 4.5.0 (National Aeronautics and Space Administration) were used to create temporal-spatial risk maps based on the overall CHIKV suitability risk classification.
</p>
