<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We applied the land ecosystem model JSBACH (
 <xref rid="B104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Raddatz et al., 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B107" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Reick et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Goll et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gao et al., 2016</xref>) and the stand growth model PREBAS (
 <xref rid="B129" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Valentine and Mäkelä, 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B95" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Peltoniemi et al., 2015b</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B78" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Minunno et al., 2016</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2019</xref>) for the land area of mainland Finland, using input data in spatial resolution ranging from 16 m (forest resources, PREBAS), 0.1° (land surface characteristics, JSBACH) to a 0.2° × 0.1° longitude-latitude grid (climate data). We report simulated results for a set of biophysical variables for four time periods (1981–2010, 2011–2040, 2041–2070, 2071–2100). Two variables reflect directly ecosystem C fluxes: gross primary productivity (GPP; gCm
 <sup class="sup">-2</sup> yr
 <sup class="sup">-1</sup>) and net ecosystem exchange (NEE; gCm
 <sup class="sup">-2</sup> yr
 <sup class="sup">-1</sup>). Ecosystem phenology is described by three variables: the length of vegetation active period (VAPlength; days), when terrestrial vegetation is assimilating C through photosynthesis, the start (end) of vegetation active period (VAPstart; VAPend; days from January 1st, when the daily level of photosynthesis first exceeds, or returns to below 15% of its summertime value). Stemwood growth (m
 <sup class="sup">3</sup> yr
 <sup class="sup">-1</sup>) was simulated with PREBAS, and the number of summer dry days (soil moisture &lt; 5th percentile of reference period) and number of winter days with soil frost were simulated with JSBACH. The models have been compared earlier and found to produce similar GPP estimates at local and national level (
 <xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Peltoniemi et al., 2015a</xref>). Here we use the two models in parallel to provide further information about the changes in biophysical variables under climate change, and also in supplementing each other for variables predicted by only one of the models. We present the results as boxplots and tabulated percentile values, and cumulative distribution functions aggregated over the whole area, as well as time series and maps for some variables.
</p>
