<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec004" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The main objective of DNA barcoding is to help with the identification of unknown specimens and facilitate the discovery of new taxa. To be able to undertake these objectives using the DNA barcoding approach, a threshold is needed. This threshold should be high enough to separate specimens that belong to different species and low enough to recognize recently diverged species. Hebert et al. [
  <a rid="pone.0154454.ref008" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0154454.ref008">8</a>] proposed a threshold to define new species, which he called the "barcoding gap", defined as ten times the mean intraspecific variation for the studied group. In this study, the mean intraspecific divergence was 0.62% for the samples analyzed, and the resulting barcoding gap of 6.2% is indeed less than the lowest observed interspecific distance of 6.8%. Hence, for the species in our study, the barcoding gap worked effectively. A distribution of intra- and interspecific divergence frequencies is given in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0154454.g002" href="#pone.0154454.g002">Fig 2</a>. A study on avian diversification showed that the average intraspecific distance was 0.32% for the Palearctic dataset [
  <a rid="pone.0154454.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0154454.ref021">21</a>], dropping to 0.19% if highly variable species are excluded. For the Aras samples, the exclusion of highly variable species dropped the average intraspecific distance to 0.30%. A study on North American birds [
  <a rid="pone.0154454.ref008" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0154454.ref008">8</a>] indicated that some species have deep intraspecific divergences that are 9- to 17-fold higher than the average distances, whereas the most divergent Aras samples had intraspecific divergence values 8-fold higher.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The patterns observed in the 33 species define four main groups. The first group consists of the seven species for which DNA barcodes did not uniquely define species. These likely represent cases of mitochondrial introgression between species, which has been previously documented in birds [
  <a rid="pone.0154454.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0154454.ref022">22</a>]. The DNA barcodes of 
  <span class="italic">Coturnix coturnix</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Ficedula parva</span> had high overlap with species that were previously recognized as their subspecies [
  <a rid="pone.0154454.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0154454.ref023">23</a>]. The DNA barcode of 
  <span class="italic">Coturnix coturnix</span> had 97.94% similarity with that of 
  <span class="italic">Coturnix japonica</span> and the DNA barcode of 
  <span class="italic">Ficedula parva</span> had 94.52% similarity with that of 
  <span class="italic">Ficedula albicilla</span>. Although we accepted 
  <span class="italic">Coturnix japonica</span> as a distinct species in this study, there is disagreement about recognizing it as a distinct species [
  <a rid="pone.0154454.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0154454.ref023">23</a>]. Accepting 
  <span class="italic">Coturnix japonica</span> as a distinct species meant that no intraspecific divergence was observed in 
  <span class="italic">Coturnix coturnix</span> samples from Russia, Sweden, and Turkey. On the other hand, 
  <span class="italic">Ficedula parva</span> samples had a mean intraspecific divergence of 1.6% as a result of the divergent South Korean samples. The 
  <span class="italic">Ficedula parva</span> sample from South Korea clustered into the 
  <span class="italic">Ficedula albicilla</span> clade. Since 
  <span class="italic">Ficedula albicilla</span> is an Asian taxon and is still recognized as 
  <span class="italic">Ficedula parva albicilla</span> by some authorities [
  <a rid="pone.0154454.ref024" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0154454.ref024">24</a>], it is possible that the South Korean sample retrieved from the BOLD may actually be 
  <span class="italic">Ficedula albicilla</span>, instead of 
  <span class="italic">Ficedula parva</span>. Regardless, the non-overlapping distribution [
  <a rid="pone.0154454.ref025" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0154454.ref025">25</a>] and large divergence of the eastern and western haplotypes suggest long-term isolation between these taxa.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another member of the first group that was not suitable for barcoding is 
  <span class="italic">Cuculus canorus</span>, since its DNA barcode had 99.53% similarity with that of 
  <span class="italic">Cuculus optatus</span>. This species also had large intraspecific divergence, with a mean of 1.4%. 
  <span class="italic">Cuculus canorus</span> is a brood parasite so lays its eggs in the nests of other bird species. Since cuckoos use different species as hosts, they evolve different gentes to mimic eggs of hosts. As a result, the risk of the eggs being rejected by the hosts is reduced. Gentes are restricted to female lineages; since males are genetically identical, the common cuckoo remains genetically as one species. Studies [
  <a rid="pone.0154454.ref026" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0154454.ref026">26</a>] show that there is differentiation between gentes in maternally inherited mitochondrial DNA, but not in microsatellite loci of nuclear DNA. The causes of the shared mitochondrial haplotypes between these species are not yet determined and hybrids have never been documented [
  <a rid="pone.0154454.ref026" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0154454.ref026">26</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A different pattern in the first group was observed in the Emberizidae family and in 
  <span class="italic">Oenanthe hispanica</span>. Sister species from Emberizidae family were phenotypically distinct but their mitochondrial DNA is similar [
  <a rid="pone.0154454.ref010" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0154454.ref010">10</a>]. The DNA barcodes of 
  <span class="italic">Emberiza citrinella</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Emberiza leucocephalos</span> showed 99.77% similarity with each other. These species breed across western and central Siberia, with 
  <span class="italic">Emberiza citrinella</span> extending to Western Europe and 
  <span class="italic">Emberiza leucocephalos</span> extending to the Far East. Although two species differ phenotypically, they become more similar across their sympatric ranges, which suggests that they could be hybridizing [
  <a rid="pone.0154454.ref027" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0154454.ref027">27</a>]. 
  <span class="italic">Emberiza hortulana</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Emberiza caesia</span> are also phenotypically distinct sister species with 99.2% similarity in the COI regions. There is no evidence for the hybridization of 
  <span class="italic">Emberiza hortulana</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Emberiza caesia</span> and their ranges hardly overlap [
  <a rid="pone.0154454.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0154454.ref028">28</a>]. Studies indicate that the cytochrome-b sequences are more similar in the two sister pairs 
  <span class="italic">Emberiza leucocephalos</span>–
  <span class="italic">Emberiza citrinella</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Emberiza hortulana</span>–
  <span class="italic">Emberiza caesia</span> than in other sister species. Similarly, 
  <span class="italic">Oenanthe hispanica</span> and its sister species 
  <span class="italic">Oenanthe pleschanka</span> had DNA barcodes that were 99.82% similar. The main reason for this similarity could again be introgression between the two species [
  <a rid="pone.0154454.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0154454.ref022">22</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A different example of the pattern observed in the first group is seen in 
  <span class="italic">Saxicola maurus</span>, with its 99.35% DNA barcode similarity to 
  <span class="italic">Saxicola torquatus</span>. This species had three different haplotypes, which are from three distinct geographical areas: Turkey, Central Asia and Eastern Asia. Although Turkey is not geographically in between Eastern and Central Asia, the Turkish haplotype was between the Asian haplotypes in the haplotype network. These three haplotypes may belong to three different subspecies since the ranges of subspecies were consistent with the ranges of haplotypes. In this case, the Turkish haplotype could represent 
  <span class="italic">Saxicola maurus armenicus</span> since this subspecies is found in the mountains of eastern Turkey to Transcaucasia and Iran. Haplotypes from Central Asia possibly belong to 
  <span class="italic">Saxicola maurus maurus</span> since this subspecies is found in East Russia to central Asia, and the third haplotype might be 
  <span class="italic">Saxicola maurus stejnegeri</span>, with a range covering East Siberia to Japan and Korea. This pattern is parallel to that reported by Illera et al. [
  <a rid="pone.0154454.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0154454.ref029">29</a>] and Zink et al. [
  <a rid="pone.0154454.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0154454.ref030">30</a>] in 
  <span class="italic">Saxicola</span>, and corroborates their findings.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In group II, 
  <span class="italic">Acrocephalus palustris</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Emberiza calandra</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Saxicola rubetra</span> had six, three and five haplotypes, respectively. Samples were from Turkey, Russia, Norway and Sweden. Although three new haplotypes were recorded for 
  <span class="italic">Acrocephalus palustris</span>, all haplotypes were nearly identical. For 
  <span class="italic">Lanius minor</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Merops apiaster</span>, the different haplotypes had only two or three bp differences. This result confirms the absence of subspecies in these species, since there was no genetic divergence between the samples collected from different locations.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All members of group III have several subspecies, and these subspecies are generally defined according to the differences in morphology like size, bill size or plumage color. For instance, there are seven subspecies recognized for 
  <span class="italic">Alcedo atthis</span>, and samples from Russia, Turkey, Sweden, Norway, Kazakhstan, Mongolia, and South Korea were analyzed in this study. Although European and Korean samples belong to different subspecies, no significant intraspecific genetic variance was observed in the DNA barcodes. Other studies also confirm the absence of genetic variability between 
  <span class="italic">Alcedo atthis</span> subspecies [
  <a rid="pone.0154454.ref031" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0154454.ref031">31</a>]. Similarly, there are five recognized subspecies for 
  <span class="italic">Sylvia atricapilla</span>, seven for 
  <span class="italic">Muscicapa striata</span>, nine for 
  <span class="italic">Passer montanus</span>, 11 for 
  <span class="italic">Luscinia svecica</span>, 15 for 
  <span class="italic">Turdus merula</span>, 16 for 
  <span class="italic">Emberiza schoeniclus</span>, and 37 for 
  <span class="italic">Galerida cristata</span> (three of these subspecies, 
  <span class="italic">Galerida cristata caucasica</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Galerida cristata subtaurica</span>, and 
  <span class="italic">Galerida cristata zion</span> are observed in Turkey [
  <a rid="pone.0154454.ref032" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0154454.ref032">32</a>]. Samples from an extensive area, including Russia, Turkey, Mongolia, Kazakhstan, South Korea, Sweden and Norway, were analyzed for these species. Although these countries cover the ranges of many subspecies, all COI sequences were nearly identical within each species. Haplotypes for each species differed by only one to eight bp. Since the subspecies of these species are mainly defined by color or size differentiation, the genetic similarity and the lack of genetic differentiation among these different subspecies is interesting, suggesting that phenotypic differences are not always reflected in differences in mtDNA. It should be noted that mtDNA goes through selective sweeps and bottlenecks frequently [
  <a rid="pone.0154454.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0154454.ref033">33</a>], and the lack of differentiation based on mtDNA alone does not necessarily mean a lack of evolutionary divergence.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A subset of the third group consists of 
  <span class="italic">Locustella luscinioides</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Phylloscopus trochilus</span>. Both of these species have three recognized subspecies. Four 
  <span class="italic">Locustella luscinioides</span> samples from Turkey and Sweden were analyzed. Samples from Turkey (subspecies 
  <span class="italic">L</span>. 
  <span class="italic">l</span>. 
  <span class="italic">fusca</span>), were differentiated from the Swedish samples (
  <span class="italic">L</span>. 
  <span class="italic">l</span>. 
  <span class="italic">luscinioides</span>). Similarly, the DNA barcode differentiation of 
  <span class="italic">Phylloscopus trochilus</span> samples we analyzed was in concordance with the accepted subspecies designations. According to our study, samples from both countries had similar DNA barcodes.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In group III, the COI sequences for 
  <span class="italic">Passer domesticus</span> samples from Russia, Turkey, Argentina, Norway, Kazakhstan, Canada, and Sweden analyzed in this study, a maximum of six base pair differences were observed, although 12 subspecies are recognized for this species. Being an introduced species might be the main reason behind the similarity in the DNA barcodes for the North American samples. Although the native range of the house sparrows contains most of Europe and Asia, this species is now found on every continent except Antarctica. Even though house sparrows exhibit broad phenotypic divergence in body mass, sexual dimorphism and metabolic rate in both their native and introduced ranges, DNA barcodes analyzed in this study and others are highly similar [
  <a rid="pone.0154454.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0154454.ref034">34</a>]. DNA barcode for species such as 
  <span class="italic">Locustella luscinioides</span> or 
  <span class="italic">Passer domesticus</span> can distinguish them from other species, but are not useful for genetically diagnosing subspecies.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For another species in the third group, 
  <span class="italic">Cettia cetti</span>, although three recognized subspecies exist, the analyzed samples from Russia and Turkey had identical DNA barcodes. These samples may belong to 
  <span class="italic">Cettia cetti orientalis</span> or 
  <span class="italic">Cettia cetti cetti</span>, since these subspecies are observed both in Turkey and Russia. Another species in group III, 
  <span class="italic">Coracias garrulus</span> has two subspecies in its range. 
  <span class="italic">Coracias garrulous garrulus</span> was found in North Africa, Europe to Iran and southwest Siberia and 
  <span class="italic">Coracias garrulus semenowi</span> was found in Iraq to west Xinjiang and south Kazakhstan. Both subspecies winter in South Africa but in distinct locations [
  <a rid="pone.0154454.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0154454.ref035">35</a>]. For this species, samples from Russia, Turkey, Sweden, and Kazakhstan were analyzed. Again all samples had nearly identical COI sequences. In these cases, it was harder to state the absence of genetic divergence between subspecies, since all analyzed samples may belong to the same subspecies, and there was no previously available genetic data for different subspecies to use as a basis for diagnosis.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Also in the third group were species for which all the barcodes in the BOLD most likely came from a single subspecies. Both 
  <span class="italic">Oriolus oriolus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Sylvia nisoria</span> have two subspecies in their ranges. For 
  <span class="italic">Oriolus oriolous</span>, one of the subspecies is observed in the eastern part of its range from west Siberia to the Indian subcontinent, whereas the other occurs in the western portion, from Europe to the Ural Mountains. All samples that were analyzed in this study were from the western subspecies, 
  <span class="italic">O</span>. 
  <span class="italic">o</span>. 
  <span class="italic">oriolus</span>. Similarly, for 
  <span class="italic">Remiz pendulinus</span>, all samples analyzed in this study belonged to 
  <span class="italic">R</span>. 
  <span class="italic">p</span>. 
  <span class="italic">pendulinus</span>. As expected, all analyzed DNA barcodes were very similar to each other for these species, as they represent samples from only one subspecies for each species examined.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All members of group IV had several genetically divergent subspecies with unique DNA barcodes. For both 
  <span class="italic">Caprimulgus europaeus</span> (six subspecies) and 
  <span class="italic">Sylvia curruca</span> (two subspecies), two main divergent and geographically isolated haplotype groups were observed. First haplotype group was common in the western parts of the species’ range, whereas the second group was common in the east. Therefore, these species exhibit an allopatric population system. Mean intraspecific divergences were 1.7% and 3.2% for 
  <span class="italic">Caprimulgus europaeus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Sylvia curruca</span>, respectively.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In 
  <span class="italic">Erithacus rubecula</span>, despite covering the ranges of different subspecies, there were only two haplotypes. The samples from Russia, Sweden, Turkey, and Norway were genetically different from the sample from Russia. The mean intraspecific divergence was 0.9%.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A different pattern in group IV was observed for 
  <span class="italic">Parus major</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Phoenicurus phoenicurus</span>. Three and two main different haplotype groups were observed for 
  <span class="italic">Parus major</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Phoenicurus phoenicurus</span>, respectively. These different haplotypes had overlapping ranges. Mean intraspecific divergence was 1.7% for 
  <span class="italic">Parus major</span> and 2.6% for 
  <span class="italic">Phoenicurus phoenicurus</span>. The most common haplotype of 
  <span class="italic">Parus major</span> was widely distributed, and observed in Sweden, Norway, Russia, Lithuania, and the study site (Aras). According to Kvist et al. [
  <a rid="pone.0154454.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0154454.ref036">36</a>], this observation supports a scenario of a recent range expansion, which can be explained by the confinement of this species to a single refugium during the Pleistocene. After the end of this period, the species spread to new habitats. For the case of 
  <span class="italic">Phoenicurus phoenicurus</span>, genetic lineages appear to be largely sympatric [
  <a rid="pone.0154454.ref010" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0154454.ref010">10</a>], since there is a 26 base pair difference even among the Norwegian samples. Such a range overlap of two divergent clades might suggest the presence of two species, rather than subspecies, and detailed taxonomic evaluation of individuals from each clade might help elucidate the issue.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The first barcoding study of birds in Turkey showed that the bird community of Aras River wetlands, 1650 kilometers east of Bulgaria and 5 km west of Armenia, has mostly an eastern European-western Russian genetic signature, a result of its important location at the intersection of three major migratory flyways from western Palearctic to Middle East, India and Africa [
  <a rid="pone.0154454.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0154454.ref037">37</a>]. Even though our barcoding results mostly agreed with morphological/phenotypic species identifications, our findings from seven species in group I show that even for some “well-known” and morphologically distinct European bird species, molecular barcoding results may not agree with phenotypic species identifications based on morphology. The fact that molecular barcoding results in 21% (seven out of 33) well-known European bird species did not distinguish them sufficiently from similar species suggests that: 1-the genetic sequence used for molecular barcoding may not be diverse enough to accurately identify every species in a community; 2- hybridization, introgression, and shared mitochondrial haplotypes in some species limit the effectiveness of barcoding, and 3-barcoding data should not be relied upon exclusively for identifying bird species and need be interpreted in light of other genetic, morphological and vocal analyses, especially given that molecular barcoding is still evolving and many bird species have not been studied with this method. Especially in bird banding studies and other research that involves the capturing of birds, we recommend that tissue samples (ideally blood, if not at least feathers) are taken from every individual to be barcoded and the birds are morphologically identified to subspecies if possible. If this were done for every bird that is banded, every year we would be able to barcode millions of individuals of thousands of bird species. The resulting increase in our knowledge would tremendously improve our understanding of avian phylogenies, would reveal new cryptic bird species, and would help resolve much of the discrepancies currently observed between species identifications based on morphology and phenotypes versus molecular barcoding and genotypes.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">DNA barcoding can also help to identify patterns of migratory connectivity for populations breeding in unstudied areas. Many of the species that pass through the Aras banding station are on their way to remote breeding grounds in Russia and Siberia. Because breeding ecology information from this area is so limited, DNA samples from en route migrants can be used to establish patterns of genetic similarity. The degree of genetic similarity can then be used to infer distinct breeding populations and migratory connectivity.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The gathering of the DNA barcoding data also made it possible to have a snapshot of the genetic diversity in the region before the possible building of the intended Tuzluca dam on the Aras River [
  <a rid="pone.0154454.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0154454.ref012">12</a>] that would destroy this critical migratory stopover, breeding and wintering site if the efforts to stop the dam fail [
  <a rid="pone.0154454.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0154454.ref013">13</a>]. Turkey has already lost 1.3 million hectares of its wetlands since the 1950s and the recent dismantling of Turkey’s environmental laws have [
  <a rid="pone.0154454.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0154454.ref038">38</a>] enabled the destruction of many remaining wetlands in the past decade. Over 75,000 birds from dozens of countries on three continents have been banded at Aras River wetlands and millions of birds likely use this riparian oasis. If constructed, the Tuzluca dam will wipe out vital habitat for this international bird community. The data collected in this study will also make it possible to document the impact of the Tuzluca dam on the genetic composition of the new bird community if Government Hydraulic Works (DSI) of Turkey ends up destroying the globally important Aras River Bird Paradise, home to at least 264 bird species at the confluence of three global migratory flyways [
  <a rid="pone.0154454.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0154454.ref037">37</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
