<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We used the Dynamic Fire extension to simulate wildfire on the landscape. We divided the landscape into three fire regions based on the probability of fire ignitions. Fire ignition probability was determined by reproducing an analysis from Dickson et al. (
 <xref rid="eap1979-bib-0008" ref-type="ref">2006</xref>) using topographic roughness, presence of ponderosa pine, and precipitation as independent variables and historical fires &gt;1 ha (Short 
 <xref rid="eap1979-bib-0055" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>) as the dependent variable. Fire size distribution, seasonal foliar moisture content (FMC), and number of ignitions were input for each fire region (Data 
 <xref rid="eap1979-sup-0004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref>). Fire size distribution and number of ignitions for each fire region were obtained from Short (
 <xref rid="eap1979-bib-0055" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). FMC was calculated for each season (spring/summer/fall) using the latitude/longitude and average elevation of each ecoregion (Forestry Canada 
 <xref rid="eap1979-bib-0502" ref-type="ref">1992</xref>), and day of the year for the beginning and end of each season based on local fire staff knowledge and fire database information (Short 
 <xref rid="eap1979-bib-0055" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). Fire weather index was also calculated at a daily time scale for the entirety of the simulation, using daily climate projections. Fire weather index was binned into severity classes (1–5), to provide specific weather information for future simulated fires. When running LANDIS‐II, fire occurrence is determined based on the number of ignitions for each fire region and the probability of fire initiation. We used the number of fires &gt;1 ha from the fire database (Short 
 <xref rid="eap1979-bib-0055" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>) as the number of ignitions in each fire region and the probability of fire initiation was determined by the dominant vegetation type. Fire spread in LANDIS‐II is determined by fire weather, topography, and fuel conditions (Sturtevant et al. 
 <xref rid="eap1979-bib-0057" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>). Once a fire is initiated, the fire spreads until it reaches the predetermined fire size as selected from a lognormal distribution from user input μ (mean fire size) and σ
 <sup>2</sup> (standard deviation of fire size). Future fire weather was randomly selected from a distribution of fire weather days from each decadal fire weather file. Likelihood of cohort mortality is based on the severity of the fire and the age class of the cohort; this is parameterized in the Dynamic Fire input text file (Data 
 <xref rid="eap1979-sup-0004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref>). For each age cohort that is killed in a fire, a user‐defined proportion remains on site as dead wood and a proportion is volatilized. These proportions for wood and litter vary by fire severity and are parameterized in the fire reduction table in the NECN Succession text file (Data 
 <xref rid="eap1979-sup-0004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref>).
</p>
