<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="mec13452-sec-0025" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Prospects for molecular quantitative genetics in wild populations</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results of four complementary approaches in two populations lend support to the hypothesis that all eight traits are polygenic. However, our efforts highlight the lack of power even a study of this size (within population, between 416 and 1949 phenotyped individuals genotyped at 5591 SNPs) may have to dissect the genetic architecture of quantitative traits. In particular, it is now becoming clear that a QTL linkage analysis approach suffers from very limited power in pedigreed wild populations (Santure 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. 
  <a rid="mec13452-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" href="#mec13452-bib-0054">2013</a>; Slate 
  <a rid="mec13452-bib-0058" ref-type="ref" href="#mec13452-bib-0058">2013</a>; and data presented in this manuscript) and will in most cases only allow the identification of genes of very large effect sizes. Our simulation results (Appendix S5, Supporting information) indicate that for most traits, it would be impossible to make robust conclusions about trait architectures from the QTL results alone. This low power is most strongly influenced by the limited numbers of phenotyped individuals available in such populations (as illustrated by the power analysis, Appendix S5, Supporting information), but is also likely to be affected by the structure of the pedigree. For example, short lifespans and high fledgling mortality in great tits mean that there are likely to be relatively few close relative pairs where IBD can be accurately inferred (compared to, for example, longer‐lived species where half‐ or full‐sib families are more common).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Similarly, although the data set currently represents one of the largest genomic data sets for a wild population, LD between the SNP markers is low (I. De Cauwer, A. W. Santure, K. van Oers, N. E. M. van Bers, R. P. M. A. Crooijmans, B. C. Sheldon, M. E. Visser, M. A. M. Groenen &amp; J. Slate, unpublished data), suggesting that the set of SNP markers provides insufficient power to detect causal variants using genome‐wide association scans. The fact that for many traits the proportion of phenotypic variance explained by the SNPs is substantially lower than the heritability supports the hypothesis that the genome is not adequately tagged by the current set of SNPs. Identifying loci contributing to trait variation, and testing for shared genetic architectures in these populations, will therefore likely require many more markers. With that in mind, we would advise researchers to work towards the development of SNP data sets that will allow GWAS, chromosome partitioning and other molecular quantitative genetic analyses, which are likely to enable much finer‐scale dissection of genetic architectures and trade‐offs than will be possible from QTL mapping. SNP data sets of ~37 000 SNPs (after quality control) enabled the identification of a handful of loci influencing clutch size in collared flycatchers (Husby 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. 
  <a rid="mec13452-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" href="#mec13452-bib-0034">2015</a>) and leg length traits in Soay sheep (Bérénos 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. 
  <a rid="mec13452-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" href="#mec13452-bib-0008">2015</a>), although it should be noted that these loci explain a minor proportion of total heritability. Further, the use of genomic relatedness is likely to offer a promising approach for estimating heritabilities in wild populations when pedigrees may be incomplete or incorrect, and may also allow for more accurate estimation of maternal effects (Bérénos 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. 
  <a rid="mec13452-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" href="#mec13452-bib-0007">2014</a>). For some species such as great tits, which have a very large effective population size and correspondingly low levels of LD, describing the genetic architecture of polygenic traits likely means genotyping many hundreds of thousands of loci. Perhaps more soberingly, regardless of LD, accurate inferences about the genetic architecture of quantitative traits in wild populations may require phenotypic data from considerably larger numbers of individuals than will be possible to sample under most circumstances, and in many cases, the availability of phenotypic data for analysis will depend on decisions taken by investigators in the past.
 </p>
</sec>
