<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par2" class="p">A projected consequence of climate change is the decrease of farmland and crop production
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">1</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">3</xref>
 </sup> in established agricultural regions due to more irregular and extreme weather throughout the cropping season
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">4</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">5</xref>
 </sup>. Climate change is highly likely to result in an elevated temperature, which is above the stress thresholds for many crops, especially at night
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">6</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>
 </sup>. However, northward shift of warmer climate
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">8</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">9</xref>
 </sup> might create an opportunity for a re-evaluation of the currently unexploited areas in the boreal region as to their suitability for agriculture
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">11</xref>
 </sup>, regions where arable agriculture is currently not considered feasible
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">12</xref>
 </sup>. Although a gain of agricultural areas in the northern region has been proposed
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">11</xref>
 </sup>, many land-use projections are confounded by high uncertainties resulting from different biophysical and socio-economic assumptions and modelling approaches, with most uncertainties associated with less surveyed marginal regions, such as boreal regions
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">13</xref>
 </sup>. In previous studies, the gain of agronomically feasible areas was projected based on assumptions of temporally stable edaphic conditions
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>
 </sup> and by employing a single climate model, thus not accounting for kinetic and model-related uncertainties. Crop suitability modelling largely depends on a range of highly variable edaphic parameters that are in turn affected by interactions with parameters of a changing climate and management changes
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">3</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">14</xref>
 </sup>. Hence, understanding of the areas that might reach climatic feasibility for future agronomic use ought to be the first step for any consideration of a northward extension of agriculture. The projection of the future extent of climatically feasible areas requires suitable understanding of plant available heat units and temperature ranges in relation to crop phenology and growth, both commonly integrated and described by growing degree days (GDD) intervals
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">15</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>
 </sup>. GDD values are calculated by summing the daily degrees above a reference temperature (T
 <sub class="sub">base</sub>) within the frost-free period
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">17</xref>
 </sup>. A common T
 <sub class="sub">base</sub> for colder regions is 5 °C (GDD
 <sub class="sub">5</sub>)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">18</xref>
 </sup>, but it varies with crop types. Here we used the GDD
 <sub class="sub">5</sub> ≥ 1200 (°C) threshold to predict future climatic suitability for crops in boreal regions. The GDD
 <sub class="sub">5</sub> values were derived from the temperature outputs of seven global climate models (GCMs). Areas with GDD
 <sub class="sub">5</sub> ≥ 1200 (°C) are considered feasible for small cereal crops, such as barley and oat, and used to describe the minimal climatic requirements for agriculture
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">9</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">18</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">21</xref>
 </sup>. In addition, the interaction between the GDD shift and photoperiod needs to be acknowledged
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">21</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">22</xref>
 </sup>. Crops are sensitive, neutral or insensitive to photoperiod, with differences that may be dependent upon phenological stages
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">15</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" class="xref">19</xref>
 </sup>. Information about future precipitation patterns and potential evapotranspiration (PET)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">23</xref>
 </sup> during the growing seasons also informs decisions on the feasibility of agronomic activities
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">24</xref>
 </sup>. Here we aimed to assess the spatial and temporal nature of the expansion of agriculturally feasible climatic conditions in the boreal zone by the end of the 21
 <sup class="sup">st</sup>-century. Thus, we offer a baseline for the identification of regions that might warrant in-depth, structured agronomic research, that also addresses comprehensively crop, edaphic and economic constraints.
</p>
