<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The presence of endophytic fungi–both in natural soils and after re-inoculation of sterilized soils—had significant positive effects on 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">quitensis</italic> growth, photochemical performance, and survival under both current and simulated future conditions. Their positive influence was stronger under current conditions than under the simulated future (assumed to be less stressful) conditions. It has been suggested that the positive symbiotic association between plant and fungal endophytes could be a key factor in the adaptation and performance of plant species, especially in stressful environments [
 <xref rid="pone.0164844.ref068" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">68</xref>]. Previous studies in Antarctica have shown that the symbiotic association between fungal endophytes (dark septate fungi) and vascular plants is a general phenomenon [
 <xref rid="pone.0164844.ref032" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0164844.ref034" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>] and is important in the plants’ success, possibly through their role in the uptake of nutrients and water [
 <xref rid="pone.0164844.ref036" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0164844.ref069" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">69</xref>]. Functional symbiosis between Antarctic plants and endophytes appears to be an important strategy adopted by plants in order to survive the extreme environmental conditions of Antarctica. The stress gradient hypothesis proposes that, as stress levels increase, mutually supportive interactions became more significant (
 <italic class="italic">sensu</italic> [
 <xref rid="pone.0164844.ref070" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">70</xref>]). However, a reduction in the significance of these interactions can be predicted for the maritime Antarctic ecosystems studied here in a GCC scenario, as stress will generally be reduced by increasing temperatures and water availability [
 <xref rid="pone.0164844.ref006" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>]. Our results are consistent with this hypothesis, as the positive effects of the presence of endophytic fungi were lower under less stressful conditions. Future studies should address the possible evolutionary consequences of environmental change on mutualistic relationships such as functional symbiosis between fungal endophytes and vascular plants.
</p>
