<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Altitude</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One study has examined nest site selection and nest design in relation to decreasing ambient temperatures as altitude increases. On Hawaii, the nests of Common Amakihi (
  <span class="italic">Hemignathus virens virens</span>), which are small finches in the Hawaiian honeycreeper subfamily (Whittow and Berger 
  <a rid="b181" ref-type="bibr" href="#b181">1977</a>), were compared at two sites at different altitudes (Kern and van Riper 
  <a rid="b72" ref-type="bibr" href="#b72">1984</a>). Common Amakihi's breed during the wet season and so irrespective of altitude, all nests were located within tree canopies so that they were protected from the rain. However, nests at higher altitudes were more likely to be placed higher in the canopies and closer to the edge of trees than nests at lower altitudes, so that they would be warmed by radiant solar energy. Common Amakihi's breeding at higher altitudes also built nests with denser, but not thicker, walls that also contained more cup lining material. This resulted in them having higher insulation capacity, but being less porous and slower drying, than nests built by conspecifics at lower altitudes (Kern and van Riper 
  <a rid="b72" ref-type="bibr" href="#b72">1984</a>). This study provides good evidence that birds vary the design and structure of their nests in relation to decreasing ambient temperatures as altitude increases, but further studies are required to assess the generality of this trend.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Therefore, given that nest design varies adaptively in relation to predictable changes in temperature at small spatial scales, such as those found within a study area, then nest design should also be expected to vary adaptively over large spatial scales, such as with decreasing ambient temperatures as latitude increases.</p>
</sec>
