<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Female-built nests</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Meanwhile, there is a growing appreciation that female-built nests reflect the phenotype of the building female in a similar way to male-built nests (Moreno et al. 
  <a rid="b118" ref-type="bibr" href="#b118">2008</a>, 
  <a rid="b120" ref-type="bibr" href="#b120">2010</a>; Lambrechts et al. 
  <a rid="b79" ref-type="bibr" href="#b79">2012</a>). However, studies examining the function of female-built nests are less common than studies of male-built nests for two reasons. First, female-built nests are considered to be relatively uncommon when compared to male-built and bi-parentally built nests (Collias and Collias 
  <a rid="b28" ref-type="bibr" href="#b28">1984</a>; Hansell 
  <a rid="b55" ref-type="bibr" href="#b55">2000</a>), and second, the theory of extended phenotypic signals has focused disproportionately on male signals (Andersson 
  <a rid="b4" ref-type="bibr" href="#b4">1982</a>; Moreno 
  <a rid="b115" ref-type="bibr" href="#b115">2012</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Observational studies of female-built nests are relatively scarce, but one study showed that female spotless starlings, which placed feathers in their nests within nestboxes whenever they were locally available, did so in a nonrandom manor (Veiga and Polo 
  <a rid="b175" ref-type="bibr" href="#b175">2005</a>). Wood pigeon (
  <span class="italic">Columba palumbus</span>) and spotless starling feathers that show higher ultraviolet and visible reflectance on their reverse side were overwhelmingly placed with this side upwards, jay feathers which have higher reflectance on the obverse side were overwhelmingly placed with this side upwards, while azure-winged magpie (
  <span class="italic">Cyanopica cyana</span>) feathers were placed randomly as both sides have similar reflectance values. This indicates that feathers were placed so that their conspicuousness was maximized and suggests that they play a role in sexual selection (Veiga and Polo 
  <a rid="b175" ref-type="bibr" href="#b175">2005</a>). In blue tits meanwhile, healthier females that were less infected with 
  <span class="italic">Trypanosoma avium</span> built heavier nests than females that had higher infection rates (Tomás et al. 
  <a rid="b170" ref-type="bibr" href="#b170">2006</a>). While it is generally acknowledged that female blue tits build the nest alone, a recent study examined why males sometimes carry feathers into nests. Males that delivered feathers had longer tarsi and fed their offspring more frequently than males that did not deliver feathers, and females responded to the delivery of feathers by reducing their own provisioning rates. Nevertheless, the females still obtained direct fitness benefits as the nestlings fledged in better condition than nestlings in those nests where males did not carry feathers to the nest (Sanz and García-Navas 
  <a rid="b146" ref-type="bibr" href="#b146">2011</a>). When feathers were experimentally added to blue tit nests, thereby mimicking nest building by extra-pair males, social males responded to such uncertainty over their own paternity by reducing the frequency at which they provisioned the offspring and in their nest defense behavior, when compared to control males (García-Navas et al. 
  <a rid="b49" ref-type="bibr" href="#b49">2013</a>). In ecologically similar great tits (
  <span class="italic">Parus major</span>) meanwhile, the phenotypic quality of females did not correlate with nest size or characteristics (Álvarez and Barba 
  <a rid="b2" ref-type="bibr" href="#b2">2008</a>), but nest size and characteristics were positively correlated with reproductive success (Alabrudzińska et al. 
  <a rid="b1" ref-type="bibr" href="#b1">2003</a>; Álvarez and Barba 
  <a rid="b3" ref-type="bibr" href="#b3">2011</a>). This discrepancy may be explained by another study which found that females with relatively high chromatic breast plumage, and not body size 
  <span class="italic">per se</span>, built bigger nests and particularly so when paired to males with relatively high chromatic breast plumage (Broggi and Senar 
  <a rid="b18" ref-type="bibr" href="#b18">2009</a>). Elsewhere, young female tree swallows (
  <span class="italic">Tachycineta bicolor</span>) built nests with fewer feathers and had reduced fledging success when compared to older females (Lombardo 
  <a rid="b86" ref-type="bibr" href="#b86">1994</a>), suggesting that experience may play a part in determining variation in nest design.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Experimental studies of female-built nests are rare, but one study examined how the amount of green plant material placed in blue tit nests influenced male behavior. When the size of nests and the amount of green plant material were experimentally enlarged or reduced, male risk-taking behaviors were found to be significantly lower at those nests reduced in size and significantly higher at nests where green plants were added. Males that exhibited increased risk-taking behaviors at nests with more green plant material resulted those pairs having increased reproductive success, meaning that females that placed more green plant material in their nests accrued fitness benefits via increased male investment (Tomás et al. 
  <a rid="b171" ref-type="bibr" href="#b171">2013</a>). In summary, the evidence to date suggests that female-built nests are extended phenotypic signals, but experimental studies examining these issues are generally lacking, and this is clearly an area where further research is warranted (Tomás et al. 
  <a rid="b171" ref-type="bibr" href="#b171">2013</a>; Moreno 
  <a rid="b115" ref-type="bibr" href="#b115">2012</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
