<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nest building is a taxonomically widespread activity, with birds, mammals, reptiles, fish, and insects all constructing nests of some description in which to lay eggs and/or raise offspring (Hansell 
  <a rid="b55" ref-type="bibr" href="#b55">2000</a>). There is a huge amount of variation in nest design across taxa, with nests varying from underground burrows dug by mammals, minimal nest scrapes on the ground in which game birds lay their eggs, the craters constructed by fish on the bed of water bodies, the huge mounds constructed by termites through to the cup-shaped nests of song birds in trees and bushes (Collias and Collias 
  <a rid="b28" ref-type="bibr" href="#b28">1984</a>; Reichman and Smith 
  <a rid="b139" ref-type="bibr" href="#b139">1990</a>; Hansell 
  <a rid="b56" ref-type="bibr" href="#b56">2005</a>). Even within taxa, there is a great deal of variation in nest design and in birds, nests range from the small but elaborate cup-shaped nests built by passerine birds through to the huge mounds built by megapodes (Hansell 
  <a rid="b55" ref-type="bibr" href="#b55">2000</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nest design varies considerably between and even within taxa, yet all nests have the same basic, minimal, function which is to provide a receptacle in which animals can lay their eggs and/or raise their developing offspring (Heenan 
  <a rid="b62" ref-type="bibr" href="#b62">2013</a>). This rather simplistic view of nests has generally prevailed over the years, and studies examining the function of birds' nests have been scarce, particularly when compared to other stages of reproduction (Lessells 
  <a rid="b82" ref-type="bibr" href="#b82">1991</a>; Hansell 
  <a rid="b56" ref-type="bibr" href="#b56">2005</a>). Illustratively, a study of six commonly studied nestbox-breeding passerine birds showed that fewer than 6% of 676 published studies reported any aspect of nest characteristics, despite researchers using nestbox-breeding birds as model systems due to the ease with which their reproductive parameters can be quantified (Lambrechts et al. 
  <a rid="b78" ref-type="bibr" href="#b78">2010</a>). This oversight is unfortunate as there is considerable evidence that nests are sophisticated structures that require considerable cognitive abilities to construct (Collias 
  <a rid="b27" ref-type="bibr" href="#b27">1986</a>; Muth and Healy 
  <a rid="b121" ref-type="bibr" href="#b121">2011</a>; Walsh et al. 
  <a rid="b178" ref-type="bibr" href="#b178">2011</a>). Fortunately, our understanding of the design and function of birds' nests has increased considerably in recent years, and here, we review the functions of birds' nests. We begin by examining the influence of natural and sexual selection, before examining the influence of parasites and environmental variation in determining nest-building behaviors and nest design.
 </p>
</sec>
