<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nests as extended phenotypic signals</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The process of fetching material to construct nests intuitively appears costly, yet such potential costs have generally been overlooked as they were often assumed to be negligible, particularly when compared to the costs of producing eggs or provisioning offspring (Dolnik 
  <a rid="b36" ref-type="bibr" href="#b36">1991</a>; Hansell 
  <a rid="b56" ref-type="bibr" href="#b56">2005</a>; Heenan 
  <a rid="b62" ref-type="bibr" href="#b62">2013</a>). However, there is a growing awareness that the costs of constructing a nest are far higher than previously imagined and indirect evidence of such costs comes from behaviors suggesting that animals minimize the costs of nest construction. Illustratively, some species exploit the efforts of others by stealing nesting material or completed nests from conspecifics (Moreno et al. 
  <a rid="b117" ref-type="bibr" href="#b117">1995</a>; Lindell 
  <a rid="b85" ref-type="bibr" href="#b85">1996</a>) or heterospecifics (Ewins et al. 
  <a rid="b43" ref-type="bibr" href="#b43">1994</a>; Schulz 
  <a rid="b152" ref-type="bibr" href="#b152">1997</a>), while other species breed in old nests despite incurring costs due to ectoparasitism (Brown and Brown 
  <a rid="b20" ref-type="bibr" href="#b20">1986</a>; Møller 
  <a rid="b112" ref-type="bibr" href="#b112">1990b</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Direct evidence that nest building is a costly process comes from studies that have estimated the costs, with one study showing that cliff swallows (
  <span class="italic">Petrochelidon pyrrhonota</span>) constructing a 600 g nest expend 122 kJ by making an estimated 1400 trips to collect construction materials (Withers 
  <a rid="b186" ref-type="bibr" href="#b186">1977</a>). Meanwhile, observational evidence that nest construction behaviors accurately reflect the quality of the builder/s comes from studies which report a positive correlation between the phenotype of the building parent and the time to completion of nests (Lens et al. 
  <a rid="b80" ref-type="bibr" href="#b80">1994</a>; De Neve and Soler 
  <a rid="b33" ref-type="bibr" href="#b33">2002</a>) and the size of completed nests (Moreno et al. 
  <a rid="b116" ref-type="bibr" href="#b116">1994</a>; Lens et al. 
  <a rid="b80" ref-type="bibr" href="#b80">1994</a>; Fargallo et al. 
  <a rid="b44" ref-type="bibr" href="#b44">2001</a>; Tomás et al. 
  <a rid="b170" ref-type="bibr" href="#b170">2006</a>; Mainwaring et al. 
  <a rid="b97" ref-type="bibr" href="#b97">2008</a>). Elsewhere, a comparative analysis by Soler et al. (
  <a rid="b165" ref-type="bibr" href="#b165">2007</a>) found a positive correlation between nest-building effort and immunity both among European passerine birds and among barn swallows (
  <span class="italic">Hirundo rustica</span>), thereby demonstrating that birds in higher body condition invested more energy in nest building.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Experimental studies have also demonstrated that nest building is costly. For example, male Australian reed warblers (
  <span class="italic">Acrocephalus australis</span>) build multiple nests within their territories, which consist of one “type 1” nest that is structurally capable of holding eggs and nestlings and one or more “type 2” nests that are not structurally capable of holding eggs and nestlings. When experimental males were provided with supplementary food, they built more “type 2” nests within their territories than unfed control males (Berg et al. 
  <a rid="b11" ref-type="bibr" href="#b11">2006</a>). Meanwhile, supplementary fed female blue tits (
  <span class="italic">Cyanistes caeruleus</span>) built heavier nests than unfed control females in one study (Mainwaring and Hartley 
  <a rid="b94" ref-type="bibr" href="#b94">2009</a>) and shallower nests in another study (Smith et al. 
  <a rid="b158" ref-type="bibr" href="#b158">2012</a>), while great tit nest sizes did not differ between treatments (Smith et al. 
  <a rid="b158" ref-type="bibr" href="#b158">2012</a>). Therefore, despite none of these studies demonstrating any advantages of larger nests to the builders, nest-building behaviors appear to be limited by the availability of food. Other studies have further tested the costs of nest construction by directly manipulating nest-building effort, rather than carrying out indirect manipulations of food availability. When the nests and eggs of experimental pairs of pied flycatchers (
  <span class="italic">Ficedula hypoleuca</span>) were removed, thereby forcing them to build a second nest, experimental females built smaller nests than control females (Moreno et al. 
  <a rid="b118" ref-type="bibr" href="#b118">2008</a>). Further, when the costs of nest building were experimentally reduced in pied flycatchers, experimental females spent more time incubating their eggs before provisioning their nestlings at a higher rate than control females. This resulted in nestlings in experimental nests having longer tarsi at prefledging than nestlings in control nests (Moreno et al. 
  <a rid="b120" ref-type="bibr" href="#b120">2010</a>), although the advantages accrued by having longer tarsi are presently unclear (Mainwaring and Hartley 
  <a rid="b95" ref-type="bibr" href="#b95">2012</a>). Meanwhile, Lambrechts et al. (
  <a rid="b79" ref-type="bibr" href="#b79">2012</a>) experimentally removed the nests and eggs of blue tits after about 5 days of incubation and found that experimental females, which were forced to expend effort by building a second nest, built smaller nests and laid smaller clutches than control females.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To summarize, there is now observational, comparative, and experimental evidence that nest construction is a costly process. While these studies have focused disproportionately on birds, presumably because their nest-building visits can be accurately counted and their completed nests can be weighed and measured (Mainwaring and Hartley 
  <a rid="b96" ref-type="bibr" href="#b96">2013</a>), there is no reason to suggest that nest construction is not associated with costs in other taxa (Barber 
  <a rid="b9" ref-type="bibr" href="#b9">2013</a>). There is strong evidence that nest construction is costly (Maynard Smith and Harper 
  <a rid="b101" ref-type="bibr" href="#b101">2003</a>; Schaedelin and Taborsky 
  <a rid="b148" ref-type="bibr" href="#b148">2009</a>), and so nest-building behaviors and nest design have the capacity to act as extended phenotypic signals, which may be influenced by sexual selection (Andersson 
  <a rid="b4" ref-type="bibr" href="#b4">1982</a>; Moreno 
  <a rid="b115" ref-type="bibr" href="#b115">2012</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
