<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Parasites and host fitness</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Birds host a variety of parasites including lice, fleas, mites, ticks, leeches, fungi, and bacteria, yet relatively little was known about the impact of such parasites on their hosts, aside from commercially valuable game birds, until the 1980s (Clayton and Moore 
  <a rid="b26" ref-type="bibr" href="#b26">1997</a>). Then, an influential paper by Hamilton and Zuk (
  <a rid="b54" ref-type="bibr" href="#b54">1982</a>) argued that the elaborate displays of a range of North American birds evolved as a consequence of parasite-mediated sexual selection, which led to an increased interest in the impacts of parasites on wild birds. Many studies have since shown that parasites can have severe consequences for their host's fitness by reducing their survival and reproductive success (Loye and Zuk 
  <a rid="b91" ref-type="bibr" href="#b91">1991</a>; Clayton and Moore 
  <a rid="b26" ref-type="bibr" href="#b26">1997</a>; Proctor 
  <a rid="b134" ref-type="bibr" href="#b134">2003</a>). For example, when the number of hen fleas (
  <span class="italic">Ceratophyllus gallinae</span>) was experimentally increased in great tit nests, it was found that when compared to control pairs, experimental pairs laid their eggs later in the season, the parents deserted their clutches more frequently during the incubation period and hatched and fledged fewer nestlings (Oppliger et al. 
  <a rid="b124" ref-type="bibr" href="#b124">1994</a>). Meanwhile, a study that experimentally increased the number of fowl mites (
  <span class="italic">Ornithonyssus bursa</span>) in multibrooded barn swallow nests found that when compared to control pairs, experimental pairs had lower reproductive success as indicated by a reduced number of independent fledglings from first clutches and reduced clutch sizes, brood sizes, and the number of independent fledglings from second clutches (Møller 
  <a rid="b112" ref-type="bibr" href="#b112">1990b</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Given the negative effect of parasites, it is unsurprising that hosts have evolved a wide variety of defenses against them (Loye and Zuk 
  <a rid="b91" ref-type="bibr" href="#b91">1991</a>; Clayton and Moore 
  <a rid="b26" ref-type="bibr" href="#b26">1997</a>). In birds, such defenses include plumage maintenance behaviors such as molting feathers, the use of feather toxins, body maintenance behaviors such as preening and dusting, and a range of nest maintenance behaviors (Toft 
  <a rid="b169" ref-type="bibr" href="#b169">1991</a>; Loye and Zuk 
  <a rid="b91" ref-type="bibr" href="#b91">1991</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
