<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The brown macroalga 
 <italic class="italic">Ascophyllum nodosum</italic> is a key foundation species, as it plays a strong role in structuring coastal communities (Schmidt et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" class="xref">2011</xref>), that occurs along sheltered intertidal rocky shores of North Atlantic coasts, from 41.3°N to 69.7°N (South and Titley 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" class="xref">1986</xref>; Lüning 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">1990</xref>). Greenland, North Norway and South Baffin Island (Canada) host the northernmost 
 <italic class="italic">A. nodosum</italic> populations described to date (Lüning 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">1990</xref>; Pedersen 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">2011</xref>). The broad geographical distribution of 
 <italic class="italic">A. nodosum</italic> reflects its wide thermal tolerance, which ranges from less than 0 °C and up to about 25 °C with optimal temperature at around 15 °C (Fortes and Lüning 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">1980</xref>), considerably above current temperatures in the sub-arctic and arctic region. 
 <italic class="italic">A. nodosum</italic> is a branched perennial species, with thalli that persist for 10–20 years (Stengel and Dring 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">1997</xref>) and the lifespan of individuals modelled at up to 300 years (Åberg 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">1992</xref>). Vegetative growth occurs primarily through elongation of the tips of the thallus while producing annually one bladder per tip (Macfarlane 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">1933</xref>). The growth form and architecture of 
 <italic class="italic">A. nodosum</italic> thereby enable to retrospectively quantify growth of the thallus based on a single sampling event, and explore the possible drivers (e.g., climate change) of decadal variability in the growth records. Hence, the retrospective assessment of 
 <italic class="italic">A. nodosum</italic> growth in relation to temperature changes can help assessing the possible impact of arctic climate change on its populations, even at remote sites such as the northern edge of the distribution range. This approach as has been done in the past for the arctic cockle 
 <italic class="italic">Clinocardium ciliatum</italic> to test the effect of the length of sea ice season on annual growth (Sejr et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" class="xref">2009</xref>). While studies of 
 <italic class="italic">A. nodosum</italic> response to climate change have been conducted at the southern edge of the geographical distribution (Araújo et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" class="xref">2014</xref>; Viana et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" class="xref">2014</xref>), no similar reports exist for the northern edge of its geographical distribution. The few projections of northern range expansion do not include the northernmost Greenland 
 <italic class="italic">A. nodosum</italic> populations (Jueterbock et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">2013</xref>; Neiva et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" class="xref">2016</xref>).
</p>
