<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" class="supplementary-material">
 <p class="p">Supplementary material for this article is available at 
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://advances.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/3/5/e1603055/DC1" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://advances.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/3/5/e1603055/DC1</ext-link>
 </p>
 <p class="p">Supplementary Text</p>
 <p class="p">fig. S1. Average environmental conditions during the study period.</p>
 <p class="p">fig. S2. Relationships between changes in species abundance, PDSI, temperature, and total tree basal area.</p>
 <p class="p">fig. S3. Box plots of functional trait values for species that experienced different longitudinal shifts (E0, nonsignificantly eastward; E1, significantly eastward; W0, nonsignificantly westward; W1, significantly westward).</p>
 <p class="p">fig. S4. Box plots of latitudinal and longitudinal stem density shifts by physiological trait groups.</p>
 <p class="p">fig. S5. Box plots of functional trait values for species that experienced different latitudinal shifts (N0, nonsignificantly northward; N1, significantly northward; S0, nonsignificantly southward; S1, significantly southward).</p>
 <p class="p">fig. S6. Box plots of latitudinal and longitudinal stem density shifts by dispersal trait groups.</p>
 <p class="p">fig. S7. Latitudinal species abundance shift mapped on a phylogram representing evolutionary relationships among the 86 study species.</p>
 <p class="p">table S1A. Summary of shift percentage and distance by directions.</p>
 <p class="p">table S1B. Shift of species abundance for all trees during the last three decades.</p>
 <p class="p">table S1C. Shift of species abundance for sapling-sized trees during the last three decades.</p>
 <p class="p">table S1D. Shift of species abundance for adult trees during the last three decades.</p>
 <p class="p">table S2. Linear mixed-effect model parameter estimates and significance for the relationships between species shift and changes in environmental variables and successional processes.</p>
 <p class="p">table S3. Description of functional traits used in the analysis.</p>
 <p class="p">table S4. Years during which the first inventory (T1) and second inventory (T2) were completed for each state.</p>
 <p class="p">table S5. Species used in the study and their sample sizes and their mean density at the first and second inventories.</p>
</supplementary-material>
