<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2d" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conventional PCR, sequencing and phylogenetic analysis</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">PCR amplifications were performed on all 87 samples using primers HepF300 and HepR900 
  <a rid="pone.0095010-Ujvari1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Ujvari1">[69]</a> that target part of the 
  <span class="italic">Hepatozoon</span> 18 S rRNA gene. The PCR reactions using the Hep primers were run in a 20 µl reaction mixture containing 1 U of GoTaq DNA Polymerase (5 u/µl), 1.5 mM MgCl
  <sub>2</sub> (25 mM), 0.125 mM of each nucleotide, 1 X GoTaq Flexi Buffer, 0.6 mM of each primer, and 2 µl of DNA. The reaction mix was heated to 94°C for 3 min, and amplification was performed through at 94°C for 30 s, 60°C for 30 s, and 72°C for 1 min, in 35 cycles, with a final 10 min extension at 72°C. Two negatives (one blank and one known 
  <span class="italic">Hepatozoon</span> negative) and one positive control (one known 
  <span class="italic">Hepatozoon</span> positive) were run with each reaction. Sequencing of the positive PCR products was performed in both directions outsource (Macrogen Europe, The Netherlands). Geneious v6.0.3 was used for contig assembly and visualization of sequences. The “heterozygotes plugin” with 30% peak similarity was used to search for possible heterozygous positions. Consensus sequences for each individual were deposited in GenBank under the accession numbers KJ189387-KJ189433 (
  <span class="italic">Hepatozoon</span>), KJ189382-KJ189385 (
  <span class="italic">Schellackia</span>) and KJ189386 (
  <span class="italic">Lankesterella</span>). One representative of each of the three 
  <span class="italic">Hepatozoon</span> haplotypes (KJ189418, KJ189426 and KJ189390), of the two 
  <span class="italic">Schellackia</span> haplotypes (KJ189382 and KJ189384), and the single 
  <span class="italic">Lankesterella</span> haplotype (KJ189386), were aligned with published data on GenBank using the MUSCLE alignment 
  <a rid="pone.0095010-Edgar1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Edgar1">[70]</a> with default parameters and “Refine Existing Alignment” option implemented in Geneious. The alignment consisted of 75 taxa and was 641 bp long. Two different phylogenetic analyses (Maximum Likelihood and Bayesian Inference) were conducted. Maximum Likelihood (ML) analysis with random sequence addition (100 replicate heuristic searches) was used to assess evolutionary relationships, using the software PhyML 3.0 
  <a rid="pone.0095010-Guindon1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Guindon1">[71]</a>. Support for nodes was estimated using the bootstrap technique 
  <a rid="pone.0095010-Felsenstein1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Felsenstein1">[72]</a> with 1000 replicates. The AIC criterion conducted in jModeltest 0.1.1 
  <a rid="pone.0095010-Posada1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Posada1">[73]</a> was used to choose the model of evolution (TIM1+G). Bayesian analysis was implemented using Mr. Bayes v.3.1 
  <a rid="pone.0095010-Ronquist1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Ronquist1">[74]</a> with parameters estimated as part of the analysis. The analysis was run for 10×10
  <span class="sup">6</span> generations, saving one tree with random tree sampling each 1000 generations. All trees prior to reaching stationarity (25% of the run) were discarded as burn-in samples, and the remaining trees were combined in a 50% majority consensus tree.
 </p>
</sec>
