<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2c" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">DNA extraction and sample preparation</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the total number of samples (
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 87), DNA was extracted from blood using the Speedtools tissue DNA extraction kit (Biotools, Madrid). In a subset of 47 individuals, in which we compared various methodological approaches, DNA was extracted from two biological sources: blood drops stored in Whatman filter paper (approximately 3 mm by 3 mm) and tail-tip muscle tissue (approximately 2 mm by 2 mm with skin removed). On these samples we used two extraction protocols: the Speedtools commercial kit following manufacturer's instructions, and the standard saline protocol 
  <a rid="pone.0095010-Sambrook1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Sambrook1">[67]</a>. Briefly, the saline method used consisted of adding 600 µl of lysis buffer (0.5 M tris; 0.1 M EDTA; 2% SDS; pH 8.0) and 10 µl of proteinase K (25 mg/ml) to the cut material, which was incubated at 56°C overnight. After incubation, 300 µl of ammonium acetate (5 M; pH 8.0) was added and centrifuged for 15 min at 14000 rpm at 4°C. The supernatant was carefully transferred to new eppendorf tubes, 600 µl of ice-cold isopropanol was added and samples were frozen between 3 h to overnight. After incubation, samples were centrifuged for 25 min at 14000 rpm at 4°C, and the supernatant was carefully discarded. Then, 1000 µl of ice-cold ethanol (70%) was added and centrifuged for 15 min at 14000 rpm at 4°C. The supernatant was carefully discarded and samples were left to evaporate at room temperature. When completely evaporated, 50 µl of ultra-pure water was added and samples were left to hydrate at ambient temperature in an agitator for 2 h. For qPCR analyses, samples were diluted to 10 ng/µl with nuclease-free water (QIAGEN) using an ND-1000 Spectrophotometer (NanoDrop Technologies, Inc.). Quality of DNA for all samples was verified with the nm wavelength within the excepted range for pure DNA according to the manufacturer's manual (260 nm/280 nm ratio mean was 1.98, and the 260 nm/230 nm ratio mean was 2.1). This standardization procedure allows to control for the amount of host DNA, which can interfere with amplification of parasite DNA 
  <a rid="pone.0095010-GmezDaz1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-GmezDaz1">[16]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0095010-Cogswell1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Cogswell1">[68]</a>.
 </p>
</sec>
