<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <sec id="s4a" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methodological recommendations</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this study we compared the performance of various detection methods and DNA extraction protocols, and evaluated how the detection method can constrain the estimation of biological relevant infection parameters. First, by comparing various methodological approaches, we found that qPCR was the most accurate and sensitive method for estimating 
   <span class="italic">Hepatozoon</span> prevalence and intensity, especially in cases of low intensity levels, which is concordant with previous studies conducted on 
   <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span>
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Perandin1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Perandin1">[21]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Mangold1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Mangold1">[22]</a>. To our knowledge, this is the first quantitative PCR assay of 
   <span class="italic">Hepatozoon</span> parasites of reptiles, with the few qPCR studies on 
   <span class="italic">Hepatozoon</span> focusing on carnivore hepatozoonosis 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Kelly1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Kelly1">[17]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-CriadoFornelio1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-CriadoFornelio1">[18]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Li1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Li1">[20]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Allen2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Allen2">[54]</a>. Second, by comparing various extraction protocols on standardized DNA samples, we show that blood samples provide the best estimates of 
   <span class="italic">Hepatozoon</span> prevalence and intensity levels, regardless of the extraction protocol, and should therefore be the preferred collection method during fieldwork when possible. Our results also show that the traditional saline DNA extraction protocol can be used as an effective low-cost alternative to the tested commercial DNA extraction kit, since it provides similar estimations of hemoparasite infections. This result is in agreement with previous parasitological studies using alternative protocols to commercial kits 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Maia1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Maia1">[50]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Whiteman1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Whiteman1">[78]</a>–
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Perera1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Perera1">[80]</a>. At low intensity levels, protocols had different sensitivities, which pinpoints that performing a preliminary methodological comparison prior to the commencement of the study can be a cost/time effective strategy. Finally, the performance of tissue samples was poorer than blood, with higher number of false negatives for an equivalent DNA concentration (i.e. 10 ng/µl of total DNA). However, tissues still represent a valuable biological source in parasitological studies because voucher specimens and tail-tip tissue have been traditionally collected in reptile studies, and can provide information about past infections and the evolution of specific pathogens 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Tsangaras1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Tsangaras1">[81]</a>. For each DNA extraction protocol, 
   <span class="italic">Hepatozoon</span> infection intensity from tissue was proportionally lower than blood, probably because a piece of tail-tip muscle contains less DNA, than a blood drop stored in Whatman filter paper. It is possible that increasing the DNA concentration of tissue extractions used in qPCR would yield similar results to blood, but this was not tested in this study. The same applies to tissue extracted with kit and tissue extracted with the saline protocol, the latter providing lower overall estimates of 
   <span class="italic">Hepatozoon</span> infection. Thus, we recommend the use of higher DNA concentrations when using tissue samples. Our results highlight the need of comparing multiple methods in a case-base manner as a preliminary step, in order to minimize imperfect detection that can ultimately lead to erroneous ecological and epidemiological inferences 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Banoo1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Banoo1">[14]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-GmezDaz1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-GmezDaz1">[16]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Altwegg1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Altwegg1">[82]</a>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this study we found mixed infection of 
   <span class="italic">Hepatozoon</span> (Adeleorina) with two genera of Eimeriorinid parasites (
   <span class="italic">Schellackia</span> and 
   <span class="italic">Lankesterella</span>). These parasites were detected by the three detection methods (microscopy, PCR and qPCR), but with different sensitivities. Conventional PCR using the Hep primers only allow the amplification of either hemogregarines or other apicomplexans, and preferentially amplify non-hemogregarine parasites when present in mixed infections 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Harris1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Harris1">[57]</a>. So this method requires at least one additional PCR run using hemogregarine-specific primers (e.g. HEMO 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Perkins1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Perkins1">[83]</a>). If mixed infections are suspected, we recommend complementing the qPCR approach with conventional PCR that allows newly discovered parasite lineages to be set in a phylogenetic framework. On the other hand, microscopy and qPCR allow the simultaneous detection and differentiation of mixed infections, but failed to detect a few of the 
   <span class="italic">Schellackia</span> positives detected by PCR. The false Eimeriorina negative of the qPCR approach could be due to handling errors (e.g. pipetting) or, most likely, because of the preferential binding of the qPCR primers towards 
   <span class="italic">Hepatozoon</span>. Despite the qPCR melting curve analysis allowed us to differentiate between parasite genera, specificity was not high enough to discriminate at lower levels, i.e. between closely related 
   <span class="italic">Hepatozoon</span> haplotypes. This result is not unexpected, as the aim of this study was to simultaneously detect and quantify various hemogregarine parasites in reptile samples with high accuracy and sensitivity, so the primer set used herein targets an invariable region of the 18 S rRNA gene (see 
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0095010.s001" href="#pone.0095010.s001">Fig. S1</a>). Thus, future studies aimed at discriminating between and within closely related hemogregarine species may need to refine the proposed qPCR approach by targeting a more variable region or a faster-evolving gene 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Bensch1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Bensch1">[84]</a>. But in order to do so, a more comprehensive characterization on hemogregarine diversity and taxonomy in multiple hosts and across populations is needed. Eimeriorina infections estimates agree with previous studies that also report low prevalence of these parasites in 
   <span class="italic">P. hispanica</span>
   <a rid="pone.0095010-MegaPalma1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-MegaPalma1">[56]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Harris1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Harris1">[57]</a>. This finding is relevant since these coccidian parasites are poorly studied and taxonomy is controversial in some taxa 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Morrison1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Morrison1">[85]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Jirk1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Jirk1">[86]</a>. The sequences obtained here resemble 
   <span class="italic">Schellackia</span> and 
   <span class="italic">Lankesterella</span> parasites (Apicomplexa: Lankesterellidae). The fact that they are present in both 
   <span class="italic">Podarcis</span> species at low prevalence and low intensities may be an indication of the opportunistic nature of the interaction, and/or the fact that this parasite may have detrimental effects on hosts. Co-infection implications in wildlife hosts remain poorly investigated but interaction among parasite heterospecifics in mixed infections is often asymmetrical 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Poulin1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Poulin1">[3]</a> and the effects of their coexistence may be more detrimental than the additive effects of single infections, resulting in stronger selective pressures on hosts 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Tompkins1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Tompkins1">[8]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Simberloff1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Simberloff1">[9]</a>. More sensitive and accurate approaches such as the qPCR assay developed in this study, which simultaneously detects hemogregarine and eimeriorinid parasites, can allow the investigation of the occurrence of mixed infections in natural populations in a systematic and more standardized way.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s4b" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Between-host differences in infection patterns</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on qPCR estimates (from blood-kit DNA extraction) we investigated 
   <span class="italic">Hepatozoon</span> infection parameters in two 
   <span class="italic">Podarcis</span> sympatric species. Our results show high levels of prevalence with no significant differences between host species and sexes within each species. Prevalence can be determined by the rate at which parasites encounter suitable hosts 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Simberloff1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Simberloff1">[9]</a>, environmental factors 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Wood1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Wood1">[87]</a> and by the distribution of suitable vectors 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Eisen1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Eisen1">[88]</a>. Thus, the observed pattern may arise because these hosts' species share the same habitat and are exposed to the same parasites and vectors, both being suitable hosts for hemogregarine parasites. This finding differs however with results from a previous study showing differences in prevalence in these two host species from different locations in the Iberian Peninsula 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Maia1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Maia1">[50]</a>. These contrasting patterns may be the result of the differences between method detection accuracy, as shown in this study, or due to the influence of temporal, ecological, evolutionary and behavioural factors in hemoparasite infection 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Knowles1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Knowles1">[6]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Poulin6" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Poulin6">[44]</a>. Interestingly, we found three haplotypes and heterozygous individuals, consistent with what has been previously reported by other studies 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Maia1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Maia1">[50]</a>. The importance of this variation should be further studied as the co-occurrence of various parasite species and lineages within a host may contribute increasing parasite and/or host diversity and speciation 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-PrezTris1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-PrezTris1">[89]</a> and parasite clonal diversity can maintain high parasite diversity in host populations 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Vardo1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Vardo1">[90]</a>. Clearly, integrative studies that involve all these variables are needed in wild reptiles.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Regarding 
   <span class="italic">Hepatozoon</span> intensity of infection, we found that it was positively associated with body size within each host species, which seems to be a common pattern among short-lived reptile species (e.g. 
   <span class="italic">Iberolacerta monticola</span>
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Amo2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Amo2">[43]</a>, 
   <span class="italic">P. lilfordi</span>
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Garrido2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Garrido2">[51]</a> and 
   <span class="italic">Lacerta viridis</span>
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Molnr1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Molnr1">[91]</a>). Body size has been used as an estimator of age in reptiles 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Halliday1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Halliday1">[92]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Pough1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Pough1">[93]</a>, with older individuals of the same species usually being larger in size. It is assumed that intensity of infection may increase with longevity due to more encounters with parasites, more time to develop infections and less immunocompetence in older animals 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Amo1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Amo1">[37]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Poulin5" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Poulin5">[42]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Palacios1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Palacios1">[94]</a>. However, this pattern is not linear among hemogregarine infections, especially when considering long-lived reptile species. Studies conducted on snakes 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Madsen1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Madsen1">[35]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Brown1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Brown1">[36]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Madsen2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Madsen2">[95]</a> and tuataras 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Godfrey1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Godfrey1">[96]</a> have found an inverse association to that reported here, with larger individuals having lower intensities. These contrasting infestation patterns may be related to differences in the pathogenesis of hemogregarine infections between short- and long-lived reptiles. In short-lived species, such as lizards, hemogregarine infections are often regarded as non-detrimental to host condition 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Amo3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Amo3">[97]</a>, while in long-lived species hemogregarine infection appears linked to detrimental effects on life-history traits, including growth rate, juvenile survival and female reproductive output 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Madsen1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Madsen1">[35]</a>. These contrasting effects may be due to the continued parasite acquisition through time in larger, and older, individuals, in the case of non-detrimental infections 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Thomas2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Thomas2">[26]</a>, while in detrimental infections only those individuals that manage to reduce or clear infection can have longer lifespans and reach larger sizes 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Simberloff1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Simberloff1">[9]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Madsen1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Madsen1">[35]</a>. Given the strong relationship of host longevity and body size on parasite infection in reptiles in nature, it would be interesting to investigate hemogregarine infection patterns in species with intermediate size and longevity to determine if such an intermediate parasite infection pattern is found.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When comparing intensity levels between the two species, the smaller sized species (
   <span class="italic">P. hispanica</span>) harboured significantly higher intensity levels of 
   <span class="italic">Hepatozoon</span> parasites. The association between body size and intensity of infection differed for the two species, being more pronounced in 
   <span class="italic">P. bocagei</span>, for which a lower proportion of smaller animals and a higher proportion of bigger animals, are infected. Also, males had higher intensities than females. Several factors may explain these patterns including: host immunocompetence and susceptibility to infection 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-SchmidHempel1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-SchmidHempel1">[41]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Telfer1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Telfer1">[98]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Brunham1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Brunham1">[99]</a>, parasite specialization to both the intermediate 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Poulin6" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Poulin6">[44]</a> and definitive hosts 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-MartnezdelaPuente1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-MartnezdelaPuente1">[100]</a>–
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Hellgren1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Hellgren1">[102]</a>, host microhabitat preference 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Eisen1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Eisen1">[88]</a>, abundance of suitable vectors 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Ishtiaq1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Ishtiaq1">[101]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Perkins2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Perkins2">[103]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Reardon1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Reardon1">[104]</a>, and behaviour heterogeneity of host species and sexes 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Simberloff1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Simberloff1">[9]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Fenner1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Fenner1">[40]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Lee1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Lee1">[105]</a>. In our system, the smaller-sized species, 
   <span class="italic">P. hispanica</span>, and males within each species, can be more susceptible to infection and/or can differ immunologically/hormonally, and thus harbour higher hemogregarine intensity levels. Differences in leukocyte counts have been reported between 
   <span class="italic">Podarcis</span> species 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Sacchi1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Sacchi1">[106]</a>, which can result in differential immune responses. Associations between individual- and species- specific immune responses and parasitemia levels for various blood parasite groups have been widely reported in birds 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Figuerola1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Figuerola1">[107]</a>–
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Westerdahl1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Westerdahl1">[110]</a>, and, to a lesser extent, in reptiles 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Madsen2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Madsen2">[95]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Ujvari2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Ujvari2">[111]</a>. Likewise, a male-biased pattern is commonly observed in hemoparasite infections, which is often attributed to hormonal and immunocompetence differences between sexes 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Salkeld1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Salkeld1">[112]</a>–
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Restif1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Restif1">[114]</a>. Future studies should now look for an association between immunological variables and hemogregarine infection in sympatric species.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hemoparasite infection parameters can vary temporally and spatially, which is especially important in complex parasite systems that have heteroxenous lifecycles and are vector-borne, such as 
   <span class="italic">Hepatozoon</span>. For instance, a cross-sectional study of two malaria parasite species has shown parasite-specific variation in the spatial patterns of disease risk in two closely related sympatric bird species, with consistency between years 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Lachish1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Lachish1">[115]</a>. Seasonal variations (or environmental variations due to climate change 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Mller1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Mller1">[116]</a>) can not only affect vector abundance 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Ferraguti1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Ferraguti1">[117]</a> and influence rates of parasite development in these vectors 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Altizer1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Altizer1">[118]</a>, but also influence vertebrate host behaviour 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Uchii1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Uchii1">[119]</a> and host immune condition 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Huyghe1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Huyghe1">[120]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0095010-Mller2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Mller2">[121]</a>. So studies on various populations and/or across different seasons and years should be conducted in these sympatric species, provided that this system presents a good host-parasite interaction assessment for comparing differences between species and sexes. Finally, a fundamental question on the biology of these parasites that remains, is to identify and compare host-specificity and competence of the definitive invertebrate host(s) for reptile hemogregarines which is fundamental to better understand the evolutionary ecology and transmission dynamics of these parasites.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
