<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s4a" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methodological recommendations</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this study we compared the performance of various detection methods and DNA extraction protocols, and evaluated how the detection method can constrain the estimation of biological relevant infection parameters. First, by comparing various methodological approaches, we found that qPCR was the most accurate and sensitive method for estimating 
  <span class="italic">Hepatozoon</span> prevalence and intensity, especially in cases of low intensity levels, which is concordant with previous studies conducted on 
  <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span>
  <a rid="pone.0095010-Perandin1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Perandin1">[21]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0095010-Mangold1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Mangold1">[22]</a>. To our knowledge, this is the first quantitative PCR assay of 
  <span class="italic">Hepatozoon</span> parasites of reptiles, with the few qPCR studies on 
  <span class="italic">Hepatozoon</span> focusing on carnivore hepatozoonosis 
  <a rid="pone.0095010-Kelly1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Kelly1">[17]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0095010-CriadoFornelio1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-CriadoFornelio1">[18]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0095010-Li1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Li1">[20]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0095010-Allen2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Allen2">[54]</a>. Second, by comparing various extraction protocols on standardized DNA samples, we show that blood samples provide the best estimates of 
  <span class="italic">Hepatozoon</span> prevalence and intensity levels, regardless of the extraction protocol, and should therefore be the preferred collection method during fieldwork when possible. Our results also show that the traditional saline DNA extraction protocol can be used as an effective low-cost alternative to the tested commercial DNA extraction kit, since it provides similar estimations of hemoparasite infections. This result is in agreement with previous parasitological studies using alternative protocols to commercial kits 
  <a rid="pone.0095010-Maia1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Maia1">[50]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0095010-Whiteman1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Whiteman1">[78]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0095010-Perera1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Perera1">[80]</a>. At low intensity levels, protocols had different sensitivities, which pinpoints that performing a preliminary methodological comparison prior to the commencement of the study can be a cost/time effective strategy. Finally, the performance of tissue samples was poorer than blood, with higher number of false negatives for an equivalent DNA concentration (i.e. 10 ng/µl of total DNA). However, tissues still represent a valuable biological source in parasitological studies because voucher specimens and tail-tip tissue have been traditionally collected in reptile studies, and can provide information about past infections and the evolution of specific pathogens 
  <a rid="pone.0095010-Tsangaras1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Tsangaras1">[81]</a>. For each DNA extraction protocol, 
  <span class="italic">Hepatozoon</span> infection intensity from tissue was proportionally lower than blood, probably because a piece of tail-tip muscle contains less DNA, than a blood drop stored in Whatman filter paper. It is possible that increasing the DNA concentration of tissue extractions used in qPCR would yield similar results to blood, but this was not tested in this study. The same applies to tissue extracted with kit and tissue extracted with the saline protocol, the latter providing lower overall estimates of 
  <span class="italic">Hepatozoon</span> infection. Thus, we recommend the use of higher DNA concentrations when using tissue samples. Our results highlight the need of comparing multiple methods in a case-base manner as a preliminary step, in order to minimize imperfect detection that can ultimately lead to erroneous ecological and epidemiological inferences 
  <a rid="pone.0095010-Banoo1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Banoo1">[14]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0095010-GmezDaz1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-GmezDaz1">[16]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0095010-Altwegg1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Altwegg1">[82]</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this study we found mixed infection of 
  <span class="italic">Hepatozoon</span> (Adeleorina) with two genera of Eimeriorinid parasites (
  <span class="italic">Schellackia</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Lankesterella</span>). These parasites were detected by the three detection methods (microscopy, PCR and qPCR), but with different sensitivities. Conventional PCR using the Hep primers only allow the amplification of either hemogregarines or other apicomplexans, and preferentially amplify non-hemogregarine parasites when present in mixed infections 
  <a rid="pone.0095010-Harris1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Harris1">[57]</a>. So this method requires at least one additional PCR run using hemogregarine-specific primers (e.g. HEMO 
  <a rid="pone.0095010-Perkins1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Perkins1">[83]</a>). If mixed infections are suspected, we recommend complementing the qPCR approach with conventional PCR that allows newly discovered parasite lineages to be set in a phylogenetic framework. On the other hand, microscopy and qPCR allow the simultaneous detection and differentiation of mixed infections, but failed to detect a few of the 
  <span class="italic">Schellackia</span> positives detected by PCR. The false Eimeriorina negative of the qPCR approach could be due to handling errors (e.g. pipetting) or, most likely, because of the preferential binding of the qPCR primers towards 
  <span class="italic">Hepatozoon</span>. Despite the qPCR melting curve analysis allowed us to differentiate between parasite genera, specificity was not high enough to discriminate at lower levels, i.e. between closely related 
  <span class="italic">Hepatozoon</span> haplotypes. This result is not unexpected, as the aim of this study was to simultaneously detect and quantify various hemogregarine parasites in reptile samples with high accuracy and sensitivity, so the primer set used herein targets an invariable region of the 18 S rRNA gene (see 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0095010.s001" href="#pone.0095010.s001">Fig. S1</a>). Thus, future studies aimed at discriminating between and within closely related hemogregarine species may need to refine the proposed qPCR approach by targeting a more variable region or a faster-evolving gene 
  <a rid="pone.0095010-Bensch1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Bensch1">[84]</a>. But in order to do so, a more comprehensive characterization on hemogregarine diversity and taxonomy in multiple hosts and across populations is needed. Eimeriorina infections estimates agree with previous studies that also report low prevalence of these parasites in 
  <span class="italic">P. hispanica</span>
  <a rid="pone.0095010-MegaPalma1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-MegaPalma1">[56]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0095010-Harris1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Harris1">[57]</a>. This finding is relevant since these coccidian parasites are poorly studied and taxonomy is controversial in some taxa 
  <a rid="pone.0095010-Morrison1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Morrison1">[85]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0095010-Jirk1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Jirk1">[86]</a>. The sequences obtained here resemble 
  <span class="italic">Schellackia</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Lankesterella</span> parasites (Apicomplexa: Lankesterellidae). The fact that they are present in both 
  <span class="italic">Podarcis</span> species at low prevalence and low intensities may be an indication of the opportunistic nature of the interaction, and/or the fact that this parasite may have detrimental effects on hosts. Co-infection implications in wildlife hosts remain poorly investigated but interaction among parasite heterospecifics in mixed infections is often asymmetrical 
  <a rid="pone.0095010-Poulin1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Poulin1">[3]</a> and the effects of their coexistence may be more detrimental than the additive effects of single infections, resulting in stronger selective pressures on hosts 
  <a rid="pone.0095010-Tompkins1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Tompkins1">[8]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0095010-Simberloff1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Simberloff1">[9]</a>. More sensitive and accurate approaches such as the qPCR assay developed in this study, which simultaneously detects hemogregarine and eimeriorinid parasites, can allow the investigation of the occurrence of mixed infections in natural populations in a systematic and more standardized way.
 </p>
</sec>
