<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2e" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">qPCR design and protocol</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">qPCR assays for detecting 
  <span class="italic">Hepatozoon</span> species in canids have been previously designed 
  <a rid="pone.0095010-CriadoFornelio1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-CriadoFornelio1">[18]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0095010-Li1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Li1">[20]</a>. We first tested the former protocol in reptile-infected samples, and we obtained a double dissociation peak in the Melting Curve Analysis (MCA). Therefore we designed a qPCR assay targeting the 18 S rRNA gene of hemogregarine species in reptiles taking into account the variation previously reported in 
  <span class="italic">Hepatozoon</span> and other apicomplexans (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0095010.s001" href="#pone.0095010.s001">Fig. S1</a>). For this purpose we designed Hemogregarine specific primers JM4_F (
  <div content-type="gene" class="named-content">5′-ACTCACCAGGTCCAGACATAGA-3′</div>) and JM5_R (
  <div content-type="gene" class="named-content">5′-CTCAAACTTCCTTGCGTTAGAC-3′</div>) using Primer3Plus 
  <a rid="pone.0095010-Rozen1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Rozen1">[75]</a>. We constructed a reference plasmid containing the target 
  <span class="italic">Hepatozoon</span> 18 S rDNA fragment (171 bp) amplified from a positive 
  <span class="italic">P. hispanica</span> individual (JX531917) that we used as amplification standard for the qPCR assay. The PCR product was cloned to a plasmid using the TOPO TA Cloning kit (Invitrogen, California) following the manufacturer's instructions. One Shot TOP10 Competent Cells were used for transformation and we used the Purelink Quick Plasmid Miniprep Kit (Invitrogen, California) to isolate the plasmid (aliquots are available upon request). Successful plasmid integration of the 
  <span class="italic">Hepatozoon</span> gene fragment was assessed using M13 primers following manufacturer's instructions. Serial 10-fold dilutions containing from 500,000 to 5 copies of plasmid were performed to produce a standard curve for 
  <span class="italic">Hepatozoon</span> quantification that was included in each qPCR plate. A MyiQ qPCR machine (Applied Biosystems) was used with the following protocol: 95°C 10 min, 95°C 10 s, 63°C 20 s, 72°C 25 s (with melting), 95°C 1 min, 63°C 30 s, melting from 63–95°C by increments of 0.2°C every 10 s. Reactions contained iQ SYBR Green supermix at 0.5x, each primer at 0.5 mM, 2 µl of 10 ng/µl genomic DNA, in a total volume mix of 20 µl. To estimate the number of copies in unknown samples, raw qPCR results were exported using the program iQ5 R&amp;D version 2.1 (Biorad) and the baseline threshold was determined individually for each plate using the algorithm implemented in LinRegPCR 
  <a rid="pone.0095010-Ruijter1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0095010-Ruijter1">[76]</a>. Validation was performed by direct sequencing on a total of 33 qPCR positive individuals. These included qPCR positives displaying a single peak (negatives and positives for 
  <span class="italic">Hepatozoon</span> from microscopy and PCR) and all those displaying mixed infection peaks. These sequences have been deposited in GenBank under accession numbers KJ189434-KJ189463. For this experiment, samples with all threshold cycles (CTs) higher than 35 were considered negative because repeatability decreased significantly after cycle 35, with most replicates differing by more than one Ct. Mixed infection intensity estimates (
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 6) were discarded from subsequent analyses.
 </p>
</sec>
