<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The water resources supplied by the upper Indus basin (UIB) are essential to millions of people and future changes in both demand and supply may have large impacts [
 <xref rid="pone.0165630.ref001" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>]. The UIB provides water for the world's largest continuous irrigation scheme through several large reservoirs (e.g. the Tarbela and Mangla dams, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0165630.g001" class="xref">Fig 1</xref>), which depend for more than 50% of their annual inflow on snow and glacier melt water [
 <xref rid="pone.0165630.ref002" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0165630.ref005" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>]. In combination with variable precipitation patterns, the intra-annual variation in streamflow is high [
 <xref rid="pone.0165630.ref006" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>] and so is the supply to the downstream areas. Water demands are high, primarily because of water consumption by irrigated agriculture [
 <xref rid="pone.0165630.ref007" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>], and hydropower generation [
 <xref rid="pone.0165630.ref008" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. At the same time the downstream part of the basin is characterized by very dry conditions [
 <xref rid="pone.0165630.ref009" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>], making it largely dependent on water supply from the upstream areas. The downstream demands exceed the supply and on an annual basis groundwater resources are depleted by an estimated 31 km
 <sup class="sup">3</sup> [
 <xref rid="pone.0165630.ref010" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>], which makes the Indus basin aquifer the most overstressed aquifer in the world [
 <xref rid="pone.0165630.ref011" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0165630.ref012" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. The uncertainty in the future mountain water resources combined with the Indus basin’s large dependency on these upstream water resources, makes the Indus basin a climate change hotspot [
 <xref rid="pone.0165630.ref001" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0165630.ref013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. This vulnerability is enhanced by an expected large regional population growth in the coming decades [
 <xref rid="pone.0165630.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>], associated with increases in water and energy demand in the basin. Extreme weather events are likely to become more frequent in the region in the future [
 <xref rid="pone.0165630.ref015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0165630.ref016" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>], which poses serious threats for a region which is already facing severe flooding events [
 <xref rid="pone.0165630.ref017" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>] and other natural hazards.
</p>
