<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Rising temperatures in basins strongly dependent on glacier melt are likely to result in an increase in stream flow in the near future and a decline in the far future. This is caused by the fact that the total amount of glacier melt is a trade-off between increasing melt rates on one hand and reduced glacier volumes on the other hand. The moment when the trend in glacier melt changes from positive to negative is highly variable [
 <xref rid="pone.0165630.ref037" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0165630.ref038" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>]. Analysis of a 1961 to 2009 record of reservoir inflow at Tarbela, which is the largest reservoir on the main stem of the Indus river (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0165630.g001" class="xref">Fig 1</xref>), indicates a declining trend, although statistically insignificant [
 <xref rid="pone.0165630.ref006" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>]. Further upstream trend analysis on streamflow records at different locations identified stable or declining trends in runoff too [
 <xref rid="pone.0165630.ref032" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0165630.ref039" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0165630.ref040" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>]. These studies indicate that large parts of the UIB are (not yet) experiencing accelerated melt, which could indeed be partly attributed to the Karakoram anomaly. However, contrary to these findings, a recent study in the Shigar river basin reports rising river flows [
 <xref rid="pone.0165630.ref041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>]. However, the authors do not relate this to the existence of the Karakoram anomaly. Instead, they argue that an increase in runoff is possible under neutral glacier mass balance conditions as a result of increasing temperature and precipitation, i.e. the mass turnover of the glacier is increasing, yet the mass balance remains neutral.
</p>
