<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Climate simulations are used to generate projections of future climate change in the UIB. Analysis of precipitation change signals in a large number of General Circulation Model (GCM) runs indicates that an increase in summer precipitation and on average no significant change in winter precipitation are likely [
 <xref rid="pone.0165630.ref042" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>]. However, the spread in the precipitation changes from the GCM ensemble is large, because the complex UIB climate is difficult to simulate [
 <xref rid="pone.0165630.ref043" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>]. Analysis with regional climate models (RCM) reveals consistent warming until the end of the century with greater warming in the upper Indus than in the lower Indus. Precipitation projections show a non-uniform change with increases projected for the upper parts and decreases for the lower parts [
 <xref rid="pone.0165630.ref044" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0165630.ref045" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>]. However care needs to be taken in using RCMs directly in impact studies. A recent study that analyzed the uncertainty of the CORDEX South Asia regional climate models showed that the RCMs exhibit large uncertainties in both temperature and precipitation, that they exhibit a large cold bias and that they are unable to reproduce observed warming trends [
 <xref rid="pone.0165630.ref046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>]. Empirical-statistical downscaling, which may be better suited under such complex conditions, is another approach to generate forcing for climate change impact models, where climate model output is statistically corrected using transfer functions with local observations during a historical period. Empirical-statistical downscaling of GCMs in the UIB based on an ensemble of selected GCMs showed a modest increase in precipitation and a consistent warming, which is stronger in the upper parts of the basin [
 <xref rid="pone.0165630.ref003" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0165630.ref037" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>]. The application of a stochastic weather generator to downscale RCM data in the northern UIB lead to a projection of year-round increasing precipitation, with increased intensity during the wettest months and year-round uniformly increasing temperatures [
 <xref rid="pone.0165630.ref047" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>].
</p>
