<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The acclimation temperature effect on burst performance at high temperature in 
 <italic class="italic">X. tropicalis</italic> is at odds with our results for 
 <italic class="italic">X. laevis</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">Xenopus tropicalis</italic> is a tropical species of frog that rarely encounters extensive temperature variability in its environment (e.g. fluctuating between an average of 25.2 and 28.5°C between the hottest and the coldest month in southern Ivory Coast; 
 <xref rid="ref30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kouassi 
  <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 2010
 </xref>). In contrast, 
 <italic class="italic">X. laevis</italic> encounters larger temperature fluctuations throughout the year in its native range (e.g. fluctuating between an average of 19.1 and 25.3°C in winter and summer in Cape Town, respectively
 <bold class="bold">;</bold>
 <xref rid="ref33" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Levey, 1996</xref>), which may be even exacerbated in the invasive populations in France where ponds may freeze in winter. Our results on these two closely related species of different climatic regions tend to reject the hypothesis of 
 <xref rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Janzen (1967</xref>) (i.e. greater acclimation capacity at high latitude) and rather support the hypothesis that ectotherms living in more stable environments or at lower latitudes are more likely to exhibit thermal acclimation on their physiological traits (
 <xref rid="ref54" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Temple and Johnston, 1998</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Seebacher 
  <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 2014
 </xref>). Thus, acclimation likely does not provide the invasive 
 <italic class="italic">X. laevis</italic> with a benefit enabling it to adapt to different climatic zones. More likely, this species possesses a broad thermal optimum allowing it to do well in a broad range of climatic zones. Yet, this remains to be tested. However, differences in acclimation capacity between our two species might also be explained by other differences besides latitude. For example, specimens of 
 <italic class="italic">X. laevis</italic> were sampled from a single pond and consequently this population may have reduced genetic variability (and thus respond differently to acclimation treatment) compared to 
 <italic class="italic">X. tropicalis</italic> sampled from different ponds. Rigorous studies combining ecological data of the local environment with complete information of each specimen (i.e. genetic diversity, relatedness between individuals and age) could resolve this issue and provide further insights into the observed species differences.
</p>
