<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par14" class="p">Cryptic lineages were found in 
 <italic class="italic">A</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">hyacinthus</italic>, while only one lineage is dominant in the temperate region and is apparently expanding to the north. The Kuroshio-associated barrier found in the numerical simulation and/or the lack of adaptability to the temperate environment could hinder northward migration of the blue/red lineages (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref>). The Kuroshio-associated barrier also matched the Watase Line, which is the biogeographic barrier that separates terrestrial fauna and was caused by land bridges and sea barriers in past climates
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>
 </sup>. Larval dispersal simulations using particle tracking averaged over 24 years indicated discontinuous patterns of connectivity between Yakushima and the Amami Islands (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" class="xref">6</xref>). This discontinuity is possibly due to the Kuroshio path crossing between Yakushima and the Amami Islands, which prevents direct dispersal of single generations from the subtropics to areas further north (referred to as the Kuroshio-associated dispersal barrier). This study demonstrates that the Watase Line can be found in marine species due to the existence of the Kuroshio-associated dispersal barrier. The limited larval transport from subtropical to temperate regions within a single generation (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" class="xref">6</xref>) suggested that the probability of future poleward migration of the other lineages (red/blue in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref>) of 
 <italic class="italic">A</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">hyacinthus</italic> would depend on whether the larvae of these lineages could pass through this barrier via long or multi-generation dispersal. Further regular monitoring of the distributions of all cryptic lineages using genetic markers is necessary to assess the poleward migration of the species.
</p>
