<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par22" class="p">Although corals in subtropical regions are threatened due to climate change, they are expanding and propagating into temperate regions
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">3</xref>
 </sup>. Many climate change predictions of the species distributions of corals show a general loss of reef habitats in many areas except for the relatively robust eastern marginal Pacific region, including temperate Japan
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" class="xref">36</xref>
 </sup>. Given the moderate levels of neutral genetic diversity and the persistence and increase in coral cover before and after the rise in sea water temperatures in pre-existing temperate coral populations, we propose that some of the pre-existing temperate regions in Japan would be good refugia for at least one of the 
 <italic class="italic">A</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">hyacinthus</italic> lineages. Pre-existing temperate regions are indeed the potential habitats that “part of biodiversity retreat to, persist in and can potentially expand” under climate change conditions. In temperate regions, seaweed beds have been replaced by temperate corals, including 
 <italic class="italic">A</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">hyacinthus</italic>, and the coral cover is currently expanding in these regions
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" class="xref">37</xref>
 </sup>. Although a direct association between neutral genetic diversity and resilience of coral populations against environmental change is partly under debate
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">8</xref>
 </sup>, some coral genotypes are known to be associated with stress tolerances such as disease and higher water temperature
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">38</xref>
 </sup>. Thus, moderate genetic diversity in pre-existing temperate populations may indicate stability and higher tolerance against unexpected extreme environmental changes such as local anthropogenic stress. Nonetheless, much less attention has been paid to coral assemblages and their conservation in temperate regions than in subtropical regions. Unlike in subtropical regions, where tourism, recreation, and fisheries are directly associated with the abundance of corals, temperate corals are sometimes regarded as a nuisance by local fishermen in temperate regions because subtropical fishes are of low economic value in these areas. In addition, expensive fishing nets become entangled on and broken by hard corals, causing pecuniary damage to fishermen (N. Yasuda personal communication with local fishermen in Miyazaki). Because reef-building corals help to increase overall biodiversity
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" class="xref">39</xref>
 </sup> by providing food and habitats with complex structures in coastal ecosystems, there is a need to review the value of temperate corals for conservation.
</p>
