<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Current climate for FFDI</div>
 <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Previous studies have shown that near-surface fire weather conditions as represented by the FFDI can provide complementary information to that provided by the CH in relation to the risk of dangerous wildfire and pyroconvection events in Australia
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>
  </span>. In contrast to CH which is based on lower to mid-tropospheric stability and moisture measures, the FFDI is based on combining daily maximum temperature (at a height of 2 m) with mid-afternoon values of relative humidity (at a height of 2 m) and wind speed (at a height of 10 m) as well as a drought factor representing fuel availability (based on rainfall and temperature to indicate a temporally accumulated fuel moisture deficit). Details on the FFDI are provided in the Methods section.
 </p>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figure 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a> shows FFDI values mapped throughout Australia for the period 1990–2009, including mean values and the 95
  <span class="sup">th</span> percentile of daily FFDI. Results are shown using an observations-based data set of FFDI
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
  </span> as well as FFDI calculated here from the same set of models as used for CH (i.e., the same ensembles for the GCM, CCAM and WRF data as described in the Methods section).
  <div id="Fig4" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Historical near-surface fire weather conditions based on daily values of FFDI for the period 1990–2009. Mean values of FFDI are shown for different data sets: (
     <span class="bold">a</span>) observations-based data; (
     <span class="bold">b</span>) GCMs; (
     <span class="bold">c</span>) CCAM; and (
     <span class="bold">d</span>) WRF (d). 95
     <span class="sup">th</span> percentiles of FFDI are shown for different data sets: (
     <span class="bold">e</span>) observations-based data; (
     <span class="bold">f</span>) GCMs; (
     <span class="bold">g</span>) CCAM; and (
     <span class="bold">h</span>) WRF.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_46362_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e662" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The different FFDI datasets show broadly similar results to each other, including higher values in regions further inland away from the coast in general, with the highest values occurring in the central and northwest regions of Australia. These general features of the FFDI climatology are similar to those discussed in previous studies, including based on gridded data
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
  </span> and station observations
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
</sec>
