<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In addition to climate change, plant invasion and population change, other factors may affect ragweed allergy moving into the future. By 2041–2060, levels of ozone air pollution across Europe are likely to decrease (
 <xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Colette et al. 2012</xref>), potentially suppressing the allergenicity of ragweed pollen (
 <xref rid="r21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Pasqualini et al. 2011</xref>). Conversely, ragweed pollen allergenicity may be elevated through higher atmospheric CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> levels and increasing drought (
 <xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">El Kelish et al. 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="r27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Singer et al. 2005</xref>). Inclusion of changing allergenicity is a priority for future research. By 2041–2060, the median age of the European population is projected to increase from 38 to 52 years (
 <xref rid="r32" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">World Bank 2015</xref>), and ragweed allergy is more difficult to treat in aged populations owing to greater difficulty in diagnosis and limited treatment options because of comorbidities and ongoing medication use (
 <xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Cardona et al. 2011</xref>). Appropriate management and use of medication can significantly improve allergy symptoms (
 <xref rid="r22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Pawankar 2014</xref>). Such management can be economically beneficial, and appropriate therapy for allergic diseases can be 5% of the cost of untreated disease (
 <xref rid="r34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Zuberbier et al. 2014</xref>). Therefore, the overall impact of increasing ragweed allergy will be influenced by the adaptation capacities of individuals and by those of healthcare systems across Europe. 
 <xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ebi (2014)</xref> argued that the capacity of healthcare systems to adapt to climate change will depend upon the development pathways taken by individual countries. Pathways leading to increased inequalities and fragmentation in society present most of the challenges to adaptation (
 <xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ebi 2014</xref>) and hence to the potential problem of increasing ragweed allergy.
</p>
