<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The global evidence base of information about climate change impacts on health has grown over the last few decades through the publication of Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) reports [
 <xref rid="B2-ijerph-15-02626" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-ijerph-15-02626" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>], analysis of the global burden of disease from climate change [
 <xref rid="B1-ijerph-15-02626" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-ijerph-15-02626" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>] and related studies [
 <xref rid="B5-ijerph-15-02626" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-ijerph-15-02626" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-ijerph-15-02626" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>]. Direct and indirect health impacts associated with climate change are caused by rising temperatures, altered precipitation patterns as well as increasingly severe and frequent extreme weather events [
 <xref rid="B2-ijerph-15-02626" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-ijerph-15-02626" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-ijerph-15-02626" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-ijerph-15-02626" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. Direct health impacts arise from hazards such as heat-waves, droughts and storms, and indirect impacts come from exposures to disease vectors and air and water pollution. Rising carbon dioxide levels, which contribute to climate change, may also reduce the nutrient value in staple crops. This could increase food insecurity among some populations, particularly those in developing countries [
 <xref rid="B17-ijerph-15-02626" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. A range of social factors can act to either exacerbate the health impacts of the environmental effects of climate change or to help mitigate them with public health interventions (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-15-02626-f001" class="xref">Figure 1</xref>). Knowledge gaps about the impacts of climate change on public health, food distribution, poverty, rural communities and indigenous groups and marginalized people exist [
 <xref rid="B4-ijerph-15-02626" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>].
</p>
