<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Heterochiasmy</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Heterochiasmy was examined on three different scales, using the sex-specific maps option in CriMap (see section Map Construction). First, the genome-wide male and female total map lengths were compared. Second, male and female map lengths were estimated for each chromosome. Third, local levels of heterochiasmy were estimated using sex-specific map lengths in a window size of 20 markers and then sliding the window in five marker increments. For this analysis, markers common to comprehensive maps in both populations were used: Parus major (PMA) linkage groups PMA1, 1A, 2–4, 4A, 5–15, 17–21, 23, 24 and 26 contained enough shared comprehensive map markers to estimate local heterochiasmy. Following 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41" href="#bib41">Poissant 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span> (2010)
  </a>, heterochiasmy was measured using the size dimorphism index (SDI) developed by 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35" href="#bib35">Lovich and Gibbons (1992)</a>. This index is considered the best estimator of sexual size dimorphism because, in contrast to ratios, it does not suffer from the fact that heterochiasmy is bound at zero in one sex and unbounded in the other sex. The SDI was obtained with the following formula:
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div id="equ1" class="disp-formula">
   <div xlink:href="hdy2013107e1.jpg" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Following convention (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib35" href="#bib35">Lovich and Gibbons, 1992</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41" href="#bib41">Poissant 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2010
  </a>), estimates were then made positive when the female value was largest and negative when the male value was largest. To distinguish between whole-chromosome/whole-genome heterochiasmy and local heterochiasmy, we use the notation SDI and SDI_local, respectively.
 </p>
</sec>
