<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Heterochiasmy</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">According to the Haldane–Huxley rule, the recombination rate should be reduced in the heterogametic sex, that is, female maps are expected to be shorter than male maps in birds (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25" href="#bib25">Haldane, 1922</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31" href="#bib31">Huxley, 1928</a>). Our results add to a number of birds where whole-genome map sizes between males and females do not differ, at least not dramatically (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52" href="#bib52">Stapley 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2008
  </a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24" href="#bib24">Groenen 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2009
  </a>). However, despite the relatively little genome-wide difference in male and female recombination rates, our results show that heterochiasmy is present at a more subtle, yet consistent scale both between and, especially, within chromosomes. Importantly, these findings are repeatable across populations, indicating that they are real features of the great tit genome rather than sex-biased random sampling of where recombination events were observed in the genome.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is possible that the relative position of the centromere is important with respect to local heterochiasmy. Unfortunately, we do not have information on centromere positions, and can, therefore, only speculate on this. Several studies have shown that recombination rates in birds are lowest around the centromeres, and that they increase towards the telomeres (see for example, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7" href="#bib7">Backström 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2010
  </a>), though these patterns have not previously been shown to differ between the two sexes. One intriguing possibility that requires further exploration is that local variation in heterochiasmy is related to the location of sexually antagonistic loci. It is well known that directional selection on any trait can result in an increase in recombination rate (see 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib40" href="#bib40">Otto and Lenormand, 2002</a>). Therefore, conserved heterochiasmy on a local scale could indicate regions of the genome where selection is stronger in one sex than the other. For example, loci that explain variation in male fitness might be expected to be in regions of male-biased recombination rate and vice-versa. Measuring the fitness consequences of individual loci in wild populations remains notoriously difficult, but is perhaps possible in populations with extensive life history data and rapidly developing genomics resources, such as the great tit. The discovery of subtle, yet real, sex differences in recombination rates illustrates the advantages of replicating mapping studies in two independent mapping populations.
 </p>
</sec>
