<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Interchromosomal rearrangements</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We found only one putative interchromosomal rearrangement when comparing our map with other whole-genome high-density avian linkage maps. No previous evidence exists to expect that PMA25A and PMA25B represent two separate great tit chromosomes. A lack of power due to a lower number of markers on these linkage groups in combination with higher recombination rates in microchromosomes may, therefore, be the cause for not detecting linkage between these groups of markers. This observation is consistent with an earlier mapping study in zebra finch, where the homologues of several chicken microchromosomes were found to be split among more than one zebra finch linkage group (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52" href="#bib52">Stapley 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2008
  </a>), despite chromosome painting results, indicating that these linkage groups are physically on the same chromosome (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32" href="#bib32">Itoh and Arnold, 2005</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37" href="#bib37">Nanda 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2011
  </a>). However, when markers from PMA25A and PMA25B were mapped together in a single linkage group, there was relatively weak evidence of linkage between markers on these linkage groups in the NL data set and no evidence in the UK data set. At this stage it is unclear whether these linkage groups represent one or two chromosomes. Comparative mapping of the macrochromosomes gave identical results to a recent mapping study of the zebra finch, where markers aligning to GGA1 were found on three linkage groups (TGU1, TGU1A and TGU1B) and GGA4 was found to be homologous to two macrochromosomes (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52" href="#bib52">Stapley 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2008
  </a>). When more markers were added, TGU1 and TGU1B were merged (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7" href="#bib7">Backström 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2010
  </a>), which was confirmed in our study. This also confirms the results from chromosome painting studies for great tit, zebra finch and several other passerines (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32" href="#bib32">Itoh and Arnold, 2005</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37" href="#bib37">Nanda 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2011
  </a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The large blocks of synteny apparent by comparing the green anole lizard and the passerine great tit genome are, in general, consistent with an earlier comparison of green anole lizard and chicken (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib2" href="#bib2">Alfoldi 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2011
  </a>). However, by comparing SNP locations in the great tit with their locations in the zebra finch, chicken and green anole lizard genomes, it was possible to infer the ancestral state of some of the largest differences between galliform and passerine karyotypes. Our results strongly suggest that chromosomes 1 and 1A were separate in a common avian ancestor, but became fused in the lineage that led to chickens. Similarly, PMA4 aligned to only one single 
  <span class="italic">Anolis carolinensis</span> chromosome (
  <span class="italic">A. carolinensis</span> 5), whereas none of the 115 SNPs that were present on PMA4A aligned to a position on the 
  <span class="italic">A. carolinensis</span> genome. Although this is not direct proof that PMA4 and PMA4A originate from two distinct ancestral chromosomes, it is consistent with the idea that these chromosomes also underwent a fusion in the chicken ancestor (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib22" href="#bib22">Griffin 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2008
  </a>). The ancestral states of other chromosomes cannot be inferred from our data.
 </p>
</sec>
