<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the last decade, linkage mapping projects in the bird species have been extended from studies of agriculturally important organisms, such as chickens (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23" href="#bib23">Groenen 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2000
  </a>), to a much more diverse set of species including other galliformes such as the turkey (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib45" href="#bib45">Reed 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2007
  </a>), anseriformes such as the mallard duck (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib30" href="#bib30">Huang 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2006
  </a>) and several passerine species including the collared flycatcher (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8" href="#bib8">Backström 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2008
  </a>), the blue tit (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27" href="#bib27">Hansson 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2010
  </a>), the zebra finch (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52" href="#bib52">Stapley 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2008
  </a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7" href="#bib7">Backström 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2010
  </a>) and the great reed warbler (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26" href="#bib26">Hansson 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2005
  </a>). Although the most comprehensive whole-genome maps have been constructed for galliformes it is notable that passerines, by far the largest order in the class Aves, represent the majority of other species for which such resources have been developed. Linkage maps have been constructed with two main purposes in mind: (1) to identify regions of the genome that are responsible for genetic variation in quantitative traits, that is, to map quantitative trait loci and (2) to understand the genomic features and evolution of avian karyotypes. Often, however, particular species are well suited to investigating both types of question. In this manuscript we describe linkage maps of the great tit (
  <span class="italic">Parus major</span>) a species that is widely studied in ecology and evolutionary biology (see below).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A motivation for constructing linkage maps in wild bird species, especially passerines, which have been the focus of many ecological and evolutionary studies (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib11" href="#bib11">Bennett and Owens, 2002</a>), is to provide understanding of how evolution operates in natural populations. Quantitative trait loci mapping can unravel knowledge of the molecular genetic basis of ecologically relevant traits, which are usually expected to have a complex genetic architecture (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib51" href="#bib51">Slate, 2005</a>). Although linkage mapping is being superseded by genome-wide association studies, an approach that does not directly require a linkage map, linkage maps remain useful tools for identifying the chromosomal location and order of markers used in a genome-wide association studies.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition to understanding the genetic basis of ecologically important traits, linkage maps provide valuable insight into the evolution of genome organisation. For example, they help to reveal and explain the recombination landscape across the genome, how recombination rates might differ between the sexes and how species are characterised by structural genomic changes. Studies of bird genome evolution have identified a number of interesting features. First, bird karyotypes are remarkably highly conserved, with the majority of species having a haploid number of 38–42 chromosomes, and most species showing conserved synteny (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib34" href="#bib34">Kayang 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2006
  </a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib8" href="#bib8">Backström 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2008
  </a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52" href="#bib52">Stapley 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2008
  </a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18" href="#bib18">Ellegren, 2010</a>). Second, recombination is usually not evenly distributed between and within chromosomes. Macrochromosomes tend to have lower recombination rates (per Mbp) than microchromosomes, presumably because all chromosomes have an obligate crossing-over during meiosis, even if they are physically short (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib23" href="#bib23">Groenen 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2000
  </a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52" href="#bib52">Stapley 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2008
  </a>). Within macrochromosomes of zebra finches, recombination rates are lower at the centre relative to telomeric regions (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52" href="#bib52">Stapley 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2008
  </a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7" href="#bib7">Backström 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2010
  </a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib53" href="#bib53">Stapley 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2010
  </a>), although this phenomenon has not been observed to the same extent in chickens (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24" href="#bib24">Groenen 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2009
  </a>). Third, some bird species display heterochiasmy, that is, a difference in recombination rates between sexes.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Heterochiasmy was first believed to reflect pleiotropic consequences of selection against recombination between the sex chromosomes (the Haldane−Huxley rule) (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib25" href="#bib25">Haldane, 1922</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib31" href="#bib31">Huxley, 1928</a>). More recently, several evolutionary hypotheses have been developed, where generally differences in recombination rates between sexes are expected to be due to sex differences in selection pressures. For example, in mammals recombination in males is commonly found to be lower than in females (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42" href="#bib42">Popa 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2012
  </a>), possibly to reduce the possibility of recombination breaking up favourable gene combinations in the sex with more intense selection (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib55" href="#bib55">Trivers, 1988</a>). Other possible evolutionary explanations for heterochiasmy are that the sexes have different selective optima to balance the deleterious mutation rate and the cost of efficient repair (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17" href="#bib17">Ellegren, 2007</a>). However, pronounced heterochiasmy is not a general feature in all animals and is certainly not ubiquitous in birds (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52" href="#bib52">Stapley 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2008
  </a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib24" href="#bib24">Groenen 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2009
  </a>). The most striking example has been observed in the great reed warbler, where a female:male map length ratio of 2.15 was initially observed (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib26" href="#bib26">Hansson 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2005
  </a>), although a subsequent study with more markers revised this down (female:male ratio=1.56; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib1" href="#bib1">Åkesson 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2007
  </a>). In the blue tit recombination rates are slightly greater in females (female:male ratio=1.07; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib27" href="#bib27">Hansson 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2010
  </a>) and in a study of turkey the opposite pattern was found: (female:male ratio=0.86; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib4" href="#bib4">Aslam 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2010
  </a>). Apart from the overall differences in total genome map length for males and females, substantial variation in recombination rates between sexes may also exist within and between autosomes of the same species (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib16" href="#bib16">Dunn and Bennett, 1967</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib46" href="#bib46">Robertson, 1984</a>). For example, in humans, levels of heterochiasmy are associated with the physical location on the chromosome relative to the centromere, where recombination rates tended to be female biased near the centromere and male biased towards the telomeres (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib12" href="#bib12">Broman 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 1998
  </a>), with a possible relationship between heterochiasmy and GC content (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib42" href="#bib42">Popa 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2012
  </a>). In birds, levels of heterochiasmy have not been studied at either the within- or between-chromosome scale, which are essential starting points if trying to understand how sexual selection may cause variation in recombination rates (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib17" href="#bib17">Ellegren, 2007</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In most species, especially of natural populations, mapping studies have been conducted on single populations only (but see 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib41" href="#bib41">Poissant 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2010
  </a> for an exception, albeit with a modest number of markers). In order to make further progress in understanding bird genomes, high-density linkage maps, replicated across populations of the same species are highly desirable. The initial observation that gene order was highly conserved over large evolutionary distances, for example, between passerines and galliformes, was shown to be only partially true once higher density maps with sufficient resolution to detect minor within-chromosome rearrangements became available (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib6" href="#bib6">Backström 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2006
  </a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib52" href="#bib52">Stapley 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2008
  </a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib7" href="#bib7">Backström 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2010
  </a>). However, alternative marker orders often have similar statistical probabilities (likelihoods) and so determining whether subtle differences in gene order are real is not straightforward. If a particular marker order is identified in two independent populations of the same species, the evidence for rearrangements becomes much greater. Similarly, the replication of linkage maps in two populations can help understand whether heterochiasmy is present on a (genomically) local scale. If particular regions of the genome display apparent heterochiasmy, then without replication, it is difficult to rule out random, non-repeatable, sex-biased sampling of the location of recombination events as the cause, rather than a conserved feature of a species' genome. Constructing maps in two independent populations overcome this problem, because observing similar patterns in both populations provide strong support for true species-level differences in male and female recombination rates.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The great tit, a passerine of the family 
  <span class="italic">Paridae</span>, is a model organism for evolutionary and ecological research in wild populations, with a wide body of work, addressing topics such as life history evolution (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib20" href="#bib20">Garant 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2005
  </a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib43" href="#bib43">Postma and van Noordwijk, 2005</a>), parasite infestation (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib39" href="#bib39">Norris 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 1994
  </a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib28" href="#bib28">Heeb 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 1999
  </a>), climate change (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib60" href="#bib60">Visser 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 1998
  </a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib13" href="#bib13">Charmantier 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2008
  </a>), plumage characteristics (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib19" href="#bib19">Evans and Sheldon, 2012</a>), song (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib50" href="#bib50">Slabbekoorn and Peet, 2003</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib36" href="#bib36">Naguib 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2010
  </a>) and personality (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib14" href="#bib14">Dingemanse 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2002
  </a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15" href="#bib15">Drent 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2003
  </a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib44" href="#bib44">Quinn 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2009
  </a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib59" href="#bib59">van Oers and Naguib, 2013</a>). The development of a genome-wide linkage map is, therefore, essential to help shed light on the link between genotypic and phenotypic variation in such studies. Using chromosome painting, the karyotype of great tit has been estimated at 2
  <span class="italic">n</span>=80 (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37" href="#bib37">Nanda 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2011
  </a>), similar to other passerines including the zebra finch (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib32" href="#bib32">Itoh and Arnold, 2005</a>). The zebra finch and great tit diverged from a common ancestor 40–45 million years ago (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib10" href="#bib10">Barker 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2004
  </a>), but given the highly conserved nature of avian karyotypes, a high degree of shared synteny between zebra finch and great tit genomes is expected. As with most bird species, great tit chromosomes vary in size (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib37" href="#bib37">Nanda 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2011
  </a>), over a range of almost two orders of magnitude. Around 10 large macrochromosomes typically have similar sizes to most mammal chromosomes and in addition there are numerous smaller microchromosomes (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib18" href="#bib18">Ellegren, 2010</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this study, we describe the construction and analysis of two high-density whole-genome linkage maps of the great tit. To construct the maps we used a set of SNP markers originating from a 9193 SNP chip (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib56" href="#bib56">van Bers 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2012
  </a>). We genotyped a captive F2 inter-cross population from selected lines on high and low early exploratory behaviour (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15" href="#bib15">Drent 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2003
  </a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58" href="#bib58">van Oers 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2004
  </a>) at the Netherlands Institute of Ecology (NIOO-KNAW), NL and birds from a wild pedigreed long-term study population (Wytham Woods) near Oxford, UK. Producing independent replicate maps for separate populations should (i) give insight into how accurate/robust linkage maps are, (ii) allow tests of whether variation in recombination rates across a chromosome are consistent across populations, (iii) allow tests of whether small differences in recombination rates between sexes (heterochiasmy) are chance departures from 1:1 or are consistent across populations and (iv) allow tests of whether minor rearrangements between bird species are genuine or an artefact of minor errors caused by alternative marker orders having very similar likelihoods. It will, thus, provide more robust insight into avian karyotype evolution, if within-species patterns are demonstrated to be repeatable.
 </p>
</sec>
