<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study species and mapping populations</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the construction of the linkage maps, we used 398 great tits originating from a captive population at the NIOO-KNAW, Wageningen, NL and 1656 individuals from a pedigreed long-term natural population (Wytham Woods) near Oxford, UK. The genotyped individuals in the NL population were selected from 480 genotyped individuals of the fourth generation of artificial selection on fast and slow early exploratory behaviour (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib15" href="#bib15">Drent 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2003
  </a>) and the F1 and F2 intercrosses between the fast and slow lines (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="bib58" href="#bib58">van Oers 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2004
  </a>). The final mapping pedigree (
  <span class="italic">N</span>=398) included all F2 intercross individuals (
  <span class="italic">N</span>=251), their F1 parents, the siblings of these F1 parents and all full-sib selection line families with their parents. These individuals were manually split into 35 subfamilies, with mean family size 15.0 (range 5–35). Sex and parentage of all individuals was confirmed from the genotypes. Owing to a small number of parent-offspring genotype mismatches, we removed five individuals from the data set, leaving 393 individuals for analysis (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1" href="#sup1">Supplementary Methods</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A subset of 1656 Wytham individuals with confirmed first degree pedigree links (genotyped parents and/or sibs and/or offspring) and confirmed sex were chosen for constructing the UK great tit linkage map (see 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1" href="#sup1">Supplementary Methods</a> for more details). For the UK population, complex pedigrees were first split into 61 subfamilies (of up to approximately 50 individuals and three generations) using the CRIGEN command (options: -size 50 and -gen 3) in Crimap (see below). Parent-offspring genotype mismatches were removed from the data set.
 </p>
</sec>
