<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par2" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nearly 54% of world’s population lives in urban areas and it is expected to increase up to 66% by 2050 and most of these urban areas are coastal cities. The 2014 revision of the World Urbanization Prospects by UN DESA’s Population Division says that the huge rate of urban growth will take place especially in India, China and Nigeria
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span>. While, these urban systems are most critical structures in modern societies under changing climate scenarios, have disruptions and significant effects on the daily life of urban inhabitants
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span>. As per the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) Assessment Report 5, the number of heavy precipitation events has increased on land regions. In the Asian region, strong variability is observed in precipitation trends and extremes in different parts and seasons of Asia
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span>. This changes in climate will disproportionately affect cities mostly located in climate-sensitive areas such as floodplains and coastal zones. The most important effects of climate change on cities are likely to be on water availability, flooding (pluvial, fluvial and coastal) from heavy precipitation, increased surface and stream erosion and overloading of storm water treatment systems during high flow events. In typical urban storm water networks, vulnerabilities such as flooding arise as the capacity of components within the system is overloaded and runoff accumulates at the surface. Studies to date indicate that the response of drainage systems to projected climate changes is site dependent
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span>. These conditions have implications for site-specific storm water and floodplain management as local decision makers look to improve existing infrastructure and build new storm water systems. There is an increased attention on urban storm water management and flood mitigation in vulnerable regions especially in developing countries such as India. The recent climate impact assessment studies provide insights into how climate change information can be incorporated into local planning and decision making through an integrated approach for sustainable urban water management
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Recent extreme rainfall events resulting in flooding across many of the Indian cities have forced governments to initiate actions towards the impact of climate change on local conditions and adaptation/mitigation actions that can fit into decision-making processes. Being a coastal city, Chennai faces flood threats often both through cyclonic activities and monsoon rains. In the past, several flood events were recorded at Chennai and the flood incidences were repeatedly reported in the recent decades during 2002, 2005, 2006, 2007, 2008, 2010, 2015 and 2016. Chennai was severely flooded due to heavy rains (16–20 cm) during October 30 to November 2, 2002. Residential areas became ‘islands’ and were cut-off, causing disruption in services and trade, including transport, communication, etc. A deep depression over the Bay of Bengal brought about 42 cm rainfall within a 40 h duration during the North-East monsoon of 2005
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>
  </span>. During the flood in 2008 which was of moderate intensity, residential areas near Taramani link road got submerged in rain water. During November and December 2015 Chennai witnessed heavy rainfall incidence that took away many lives and caused water logging in many parts of the city. The severity of flood was extreme and the financial cost of the flood was unprecedented. The entire commercial, trading, transport (both land and air) and industrial activity stopped for several days. These extreme events stress the need for flood assessment in Chennai under future climate change scenarios. In 2016, cyclone ‘Vardah’ brings heavy rainfall in Chennai and many area were inundated.
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Recent heavy flooding events in Chennai have prompted to have a relook into existing state of storm water drains stresses the need for flood management studies under present and future climate scenarios. The study area Velachery in Chennai Metropolitan Area is frequently affected by flood resulting in water stagnation. The present study addresses the impacts of climate change on storm water management at Velachery – a flood-prone area of Chennai. Velachery, a rapidly growing zone of southern Chennai Metropolitan Area lies between Latitudes 12°58′20″N and 12°58′33″N and Longitudes 80°13′35″E and 80°13′17″E. The boom in Information Technology during the last decade has accelerated the growth of Velachery into a commercial and residential hub. Rapid urbanization is continuously encroaching on the drainage system of Velachery. This area is known for frequent inundation, resulting from storm water stagnation and choking of storm drain network. The storm water from Velachery passes through the Pallikaranai marshland and reaches Okkiyam Maduvu channel. Storm water from Okkiyam Maduvu then passes through Buckingham Canal and reaches the sea at Muttukadu, Kovalam. Okkiyam Maduvu is a 2.8 kilometres long water channel originates as a narrow canal from the Pallikaranai marshland and drains into the Buckingham canal which flows south and enters the Kovalam estuary. The location of the study area is shown in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>. Thus, this work is carried out to evaluate the storm water drain performance under climate change scenarios and to identify the vulnerable hot spots in Velachery Zone &amp; propose mitigation measure for free flow of the storm water. The scientific knowledge of the study will help city planners to design intelligent climate-proof urban storm water drainage design.
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Location map of the study area.</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_43859_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e295" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
