<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Applications of our study</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Phenotypic plasticity in response to spring temperature can be an effective way for birds to keep adequate timing of life-history events in the face of climate change (reviewed in Charmantier and Gienapp 
  <a rid="b16" ref-type="bibr" href="#b16">2014</a>). For example, Vedder et al. (
  <a rid="b79" ref-type="bibr" href="#b79">2013</a>) have shown with a population persistence model that the actual level of individual plasticity in timing of breeding observed in great tits of Wytham Woods (UK) lowers their extinction risk by about 500-fold. However, the success of a population response to climate change via phenotypic plasticity can depend on many other environmental components. For example, degradation of environmental conditions in a Finnish population of pied flycatchers (
  <span class="italic">Fiducela hypoleuca</span>) is suspected to be a cause for the observed mismatch between breeding time and phenology of the environment (Laaksonen et al. 
  <a rid="b40" ref-type="bibr" href="#b40">2006</a>). Studying all potential factors influencing phenological traits is crucial for a more complete understanding of the potential of phenotypic plasticity to adequately track environmental changes. Here, our initial choice of environmental variables was based on factors previously shown to influence tree swallow laying date, but was also guided by data availability. Ideally, we should have used a measurement of habitat quality (e.g. food availability) rather than a proxy (i.e. breeder density) and also a finer measurement of climatic variables (e.g. temperature and rainfall for each farm). Yet, using the best proxy available is arguably a better option than not taking it into account when analysing plasticity.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Environmental conditions have changed over the study period in our system, with both an increase in spring temperature and a diminution in breeder density (see also Rioux Paquette et al. 
  <a rid="b65" ref-type="bibr" href="#b65">2014</a>). These changes influenced the phenological response to environmental cues in contrasting ways. While we found a phenotypically plastic response for changes in spring temperature, the more limited capacity to respond to temperature cues (i.e. reduced individual plasticity) that we suspect in lower density habitats is worrying for tree swallow populations in the context of concurrent climate change, population decline and reduced fitness for individuals breeding later (Millet et al. 
  <a rid="b49" ref-type="bibr" href="#b49">2015</a>). Multiple environmental drivers of phenotypic changes can act in synergy and accelerate the rate of extinction (Brook et al. 
  <a rid="b12" ref-type="bibr" href="#b12">2008</a>). Unfortunately, models predicting species response to climate change rarely included phenotypic plasticity, population-level response and/or multidimensional environmental factors despite evidences of important bias caused by such omissions (Chevin et al. 
  <a rid="b17" ref-type="bibr" href="#b17">2010</a>; Reed et al. 
  <a rid="b63" ref-type="bibr" href="#b63">2011</a>; Bellard et al. 
  <a rid="b4" ref-type="bibr" href="#b4">2012</a>; Valladares et al. 
  <a rid="b78" ref-type="bibr" href="#b78">2014</a>). If plastic responses are constrained in lower quality habitats, and that several human-driven changes are occurring simultaneously, the ability of species to respond to climate change may be jeopardized and lead to further biodiversity loss. Studies such as this one are still necessary to improve our knowledge of the effects of important environmental factors, to understand how they interact together and to assess, rather than assume, the importance of plastic responses underlying observed phenotypic changes. Altogether, our results enlighten the complexity of phenotypic plasticity as a way for populations to cope with current climate change.
 </p>
</sec>
