<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Individual plasticity and between-individual effect</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Evidence of individual plasticity in laying date in response to spring temperature in both plasticity analyses suggests that this environmental variable may potentially act as a cue for timing of breeding in tree swallows. Our first observation that changes in temperature experienced by a female will lead to changes in its timing of breeding has been supported by the within-subject centring technique where individual plasticity (within-individual component, 
  <span class="italic">β</span>
  <sub>W</sub>) remained significant despite the heterogeneity observed in sampling (between-individual component, 
  <span class="italic">β</span>
  <sub>B</sub>). It is possible that different mechanisms drive the patterns observed at the population and individual levels even if the trends are similar in direction and magnitude. However, the similarity in coefficients for within- and between-individual spring temperature components potentially suggests that the population trend observed can be explained by individual phenotypic plasticity (see Brouwer et al. 
  <a rid="b13" ref-type="bibr" href="#b13">2013</a> and Gienapp and Brommer 
  <a rid="b29" ref-type="bibr" href="#b29">2014</a> for similar interpretations when 
  <span class="italic">β</span>
  <sub>W</sub> = 
  <span class="italic">β</span>
  <sub>B</sub>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Density of breeders in our study system is probably not a social cue for reproductive timing, but could instead reflect a variation in individual capacity to initiate breeding linked with habitat quality. Our first individual plasticity analysis has shown no effect of variation in breeder density on individual laying date adjustment, and this finding was further supported by our second analysis showing that the within-individual component (
  <span class="italic">β</span>
  <sub>W</sub>) was not different from zero (i.e. no individual plasticity). These results combined with the observed negative population trend (
  <span class="italic">β</span>
  <sub>B</sub>) in laying date in our data suggested that changes in density a female will experience across breeding seasons will not affect her plastic response (i.e. not act as an environmental cue for timing of breeding) and that all females living on average at higher densities laid their eggs earlier (and 
  <span class="italic">vice versa</span>). The possible constraint on plasticity for females at lower densities (lower quality habitats) suggested from the steeper laying date–spring temperature slope with increasing breeder density in the population-level analysis was further supported by the slightly stronger individual plastic response of laying date as function of temperature observed at high densities in our complementary analyses (Table B1–B3). Environmental constraints on phenotypic plasticity have also been described in song sparrows (
  <span class="italic">Melospiza melodia</span>) on Mandarte Island (British Columbia, Canada), where cohorts born in better environmental conditions showed higher plastic response in response to the El Niño Southern Oscillation (Wilson et al. 
  <a rid="b85" ref-type="bibr" href="#b85">2007</a>). While we believe that the pattern described here is likely to be nonadaptive, given that tree swallows breeding later show a reduced fitness in most years (Millet et al. 
  <a rid="b49" ref-type="bibr" href="#b49">2015</a>), further investigations are needed to clearly conclude on the effects of reduced plasticity in lower density habitats (e.g. compare selection gradients between low and high breeder density farms).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Variability in individual responses to the environment (IxE) is considered the raw material for phenotypic plasticity evolution (Nussey et al. 
  <a rid="b53" ref-type="bibr" href="#b53">2007</a>). In birds, IxE for laying date in response to temperature has been observed in most populations studied (reviewed in Gienapp and Brommer 
  <a rid="b29" ref-type="bibr" href="#b29">2014</a>). Here, the absence of IxE for spring temperature (i.e. no phenotypic variation in slopes), along with similar plastic responses at the population and individual levels, suggests that tree swallows can track temperature changes, probably as long as the observed variation is within the usual range of temperatures they are adapted to. The presence of IxE is usually tested by stepwise model building, where improvement in model likelihood when adding the IxE component is sufficient to suggest variation in the slope and thus individual variation in plasticity. Our results questioned this approach of assessing IxE. A first problem with this approach is the fact that an improvement to the model could be mainly due to the presence of a significant covariance between the slope and intercept rather than to a significant IxE interaction. Also, while we observed no variation in the slope for the spring temperature reaction norm, we observed individual variation in slope for breeder density (model 5, Table
  <a ref-type="table" rid="tbl3" href="#tbl3">3</a>), but no direction or pattern in the way individuals respond to variation in breeder density (i.e. 
  <span class="italic">β</span>
  <sub>W</sub>, individual plasticity). Previous studies argued that heterogeneity in residual variance could lead to an over-estimation of IxE (Brommer 
  <a rid="b9" ref-type="bibr" href="#b9">2013</a>; Nicolaus et al. 
  <a rid="b52" ref-type="bibr" href="#b52">2013</a>), a phenomenon that cannot be discarded here. For all these reasons, the presence of a significant IxE interaction involving breeder density as random individual responses may not be representative of variability in phenotypic plasticity at the individual level.
 </p>
</sec>
