<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Volume of paradigm combinations</div>
 <p id="Par35" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">So far, we have visualized the parameter space of our stylized tipping element model in two dimensional sections and fixed the remaining parameters for illustrative purposes. By doing so, we showed the mutual dependence between parameters, foremost the discount factor γ and the collapse probability 
  <span class="italic">δ</span>. However, in the light of considerable parameter uncertainty we ask how large the eight regimes of paradigm combinations are, given the whole parameter space (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>).
  <div id="Fig4" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Ratios of parameter space volumes for all eight paradigms combination. All parameters (
     <span class="italic">δ</span>, 
     <span class="italic">ρ</span>, 
     <span class="italic">γ</span>, 
     <span class="italic">r</span>
     <sub>l</sub>/
     <span class="italic">r</span>
     <sub>h</sub>, 
     <span class="italic">r</span>
     <sub>min</sub>/
     <span class="italic">r</span>
     <sub>h</sub>) were chosen linearly between 0 and 1 for both the risky and the cautious policy. As a direct consequence of our definitions of the safe operating space paradigm and the cautious and risky policy, all paradigm combinations which are safe correspond to the use of the cautious policy, in all others the risky policy was applied. A random decision making agent within a random tipping element will most likely end up with a policy that is neither optimal, neither sustainable nor safe, followed by the parameter sweet spot regime where the policy is simultaneously optimal, sustainable and safe. Interestingly, the third likeliest option is a parameter regime which is optimal, but neither sustainable nor safe
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2018_4738_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e1460" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par36" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We observe the most likely option to be the regime that is neither optimal, neither sustainable nor safe followed by the parameter sweet spot regime in which all paradigms yield the cautious policy as optimal, sustainable and safe. Together they constitute a parameter space volume of approx. 45% in which the three paradigms of economic optimization, sustainability and safe operating space align with each other in yielding the same policy. Interestingly, the third likeliest option is the paradigm combination in which the risky policy is optimal but neither sustainable nor safe. This is the most likeliest parameter regime among those where the paradigms yield different policies. Thus, blindly applying economic optimization in a our stylized tipping element has a significant chance of leading to policies that are neither sustainable nor safe.</p>
 <p id="Par37" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On the other hand, the volume of the safe and just operating space (gray and cyan bars in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>) is comparable to the most likeliest (black) regime. Thus, about one out of four random decision making agents interacting with a random tipping element will end up in the safe and just operating space.
 </p>
</sec>
