<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" sec-type="box" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Box 1 CCAP Compendium of General Adaptation Strategies, Adaptation Options, and Climate-Smart Design Considerations</div>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The CCAP Compendium (West et al. 2016) provides examples of management adaptation options for coral reef ecosystems compiled from the literature. These are organized using a structure (adapted from West and Julius 2014) for brainstorming and ‘binning’ adaptation options according to categories of ecologically-oriented general strategies familiar to managers, but specifically viewed through the climate change lens. These include:
  <div id="Taba" class="table-wrap">
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td>
       <span class="bold">General Strategy</span>
      </td>
      <td>
       <span class="bold">Definition</span>
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>A. Reduce Non-Climate Stresses</td>
      <td>Minimize localized human stressors that hinder the ability of species or ecosystems to withstand or adjust to climatic events</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>B. Ensure Connectivity</td>
      <td>Protect habitats that facilitate movement of organisms (and gene flow) among resource patches</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>C. Support Evolutionary Potential</td>
      <td>Protect a variety of species, populations and ecosystems in multiple places to bet-hedge against losses from climate disturbances, and where possible manage these systems to assist positive evolutionary change</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>D. Protect Key Ecosystem Features</td>
      <td>Focus management on structural characteristics, organisms, or areas that represent important ‘underpinnings’ or ‘keystones’ of the current or future system of interest</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>E. Restore Structure &amp; Function</td>
      <td>Rebuild, modify or transform ecosystems that have been lost or compromised, in order to restore desired structures and functions</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>F. Protect Refugia</td>
      <td>Protect areas less affected by climate change as sources of ‘seed’ for recovery or as destinations for climate-sensitive migrants</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>G. Relocate Organisms</td>
      <td>Engage in human-facilitated transplanting of organisms from one location to another in order to bypass a barrier (e.g., conflicting current)</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Within each general strategy, the Compendium provides a variety of ideas for management adaptation options for coral reefs, along with examples of climate-smart design considerations. In conjunction with available vulnerability information, these can provide a starting point for identifying any gaps in your current plan and crafting specific place-based actions to add to your list.</p>
 <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="bold">Source:</span> ‘Adaptation Design Tool: Corals &amp; Climate Adaptation Planning’, NOAA Technical Memorandum (Parker et al. 2017); 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.coris.noaa.gov/activities/CCAP_design" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.coris.noaa.gov/activities/CCAP_design</span>. Full Compendium available therein, and in West et al. (2016).) The example adaptation options and climate‐smart design considerations in the Compendium are meant to be illustrative rather than comprehensive and to stimulate ideas for site‐ releva nt po ss ibil itie s. As new re search a nd practice s e merge, th e rang e o f examples will continue to grow and the Compendium will need to be reviewed and updated over time.
 </p>
</sec>
