<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par6" class="p">Like all climate departures
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>
 </sup>, departure intensification in summer temperature and precipitation is a coarse-filter indicator of ecological risk. Nevertheless, some specific potential impacts can be identified. Host–parasite interactions can be much more disruptive to the host species than the physiological effects of environmental change alone
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" class="xref">2</xref>
 </sup>. Fungal and microbial plant pathogens are of particular concern because of their responsiveness to growing season temperature and precipitation
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" class="xref">37</xref>
 </sup>, and their impacts on food security, forest health, and ecosystem services. For example, the global increase in the incidence and severity of 
 <italic class="italic">Dothistroma</italic> fungal needle blight outbreaks in pine plantations has been linked to anomalously warm and wet conditions in many regions
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">38</xref>
 </sup>. Mosquito-borne diseases such as malaria and dengue fever are also of concern, because both the vector and pathogen are responsive to heat accumulation and standing water availability
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" class="xref">39</xref>
 </sup>. The departure intensification effect suggests that the response of these agents to simultaneously warmer and wetter conditions may be out of proportion to their local historical response to unsynchronized anomalies of similar magnitude in temperature or precipitation alone. These disruptions could offset the benefits of increased precipitation in reducing hotter droughts
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" class="xref">40</xref>
 </sup> induced by regional warming. Assessment of departure intensification in precipitation, temperature, and other coupled variables can provide an early warning of rapid ecological change that would not be apparent in analysis of individual climate variables.
</p>
