<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Current climate data and projections for 2050 and 2070 were obtained from the WorldClim database (available at: 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://worldclim.org" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://worldclim.org</ext-link>; accessed 24 November 2016) at a resolution of 5 arcmin (~10km at the equator) for the Neotropical region (spatial limits of 110째 to 30째W; 25째N to 60째S). This resolution was chosen due to the high computational power demanded for modelling such a high number of species, their broad distributional area and high number of scenarios. After performing a pairwise Pearson correlation test for all 20 variables (19 bioclimatic and altitude) to remove those that were highly correlated (r&gt;0.85), we selected 11 as our predictors: annual mean temperature, mean diurnal range, temperature seasonality, temperature annual range, mean temperature of warmest quarter, annual precipitation, precipitation of driest month, precipitation seasonality, precipitation of warmest quarter, precipitation of coldest quarter and altitude. Future climatic projections were derived from general circulation model (GCM) simulations from the Community Climate System Model (CCSM4), a well-known and frequently used GCM (e.g., [
 <xref rid="pone.0215229.ref040" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0215229.ref041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>]). In addition, among the various GCMs, the Amazonia rainfall and its seasonality have highly variable bias (which account to the uncertainty in forecasting future atmospheric CO2 concentration and climate change), yet the CCSM4 is one of the models that best represent the main climatic drivers on the region [
 <xref rid="pone.0215229.ref042" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0215229.ref043" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>]. Three representative concentration pathway scenarios (RCPs 2.6, 6.0 and 8.5) were projected, representing a broad range of climate outcomes from the most to the least optimistic scenario.
</p>
