<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece31954-sec-0001" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">BMR (Basal metabolic rate) is probably one of the most commonly measured physiological traits in endothermic animals. It represents the minimal energy expenditure for a resting, fasting animal at thermoneutrality and thus represents the lowest sustainable energetic cost of running and maintaining the body (McNab 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0024">2002</a>). In most cases, BMR represents a significant proportion of animal energy budgets (Speakman 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0034">2000</a>; Burton et al. 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0007">2011</a>), as well as being positively related to sustained peak work rate (Hammond and Diamond 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0013">1997</a>; Nilsson 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0025">2002</a>), and is therefore an important trait in the life of endothermic animals.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In most species, intraspecific variation in BMR is fairly large, but individual BMR is generally repeatable over both short and long timescales (Labocha et al. 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0018">2004</a>; Rønning et al. 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0030" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0030">2005</a>; Broggi et al. 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0006">2009</a>), indicating a consistent interindividual variation. This consistency in individual levels of BMR may depend on both genetic and nongenetic effects. Both of these have been demonstrated to influence BMR, for example, rearing conditions (Verhulst et al. 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0039">2006</a>), maternal effects (Tobler et al. 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0038" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0038">2007</a>; Nilsson et al. 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0028">2011</a>), and heritability (Konarzewski et al. 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0015">2005</a>; Rønning et al. 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0031">2007</a>; Nilsson et al. 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0027">2009</a>; Wone et al. 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0045" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0045">2009</a>; Careau et al. 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0009">2011</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Common garden experiments have shown that the differences in BMR between populations have a strong genetic component (Wikelski et al. 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0043">2003</a>; Broggi et al. 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0004">2005</a>). Moreover, a selection experiment in mice has shown that BMR responds to artificial selection (Ksiazek et al. 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0016">2004</a>; Gebczynski and Konarzewski 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0012">2009</a>). This shows that BMR has a genetic component and thus that the average trait value could also change in the wild due to the selection. However, as is the case for many physiological traits, BMR also exhibits a great deal of phenotypic plasticity (Tieleman et al. 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0036">2003</a>; Swanson 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0035">2010</a>). This phenotypic plasticity is manifested both in reversible intraindividual seasonal variation in sedentary animals – for example, an increase in BMR during winter (McKechnie 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0022">2008</a>) – and as short‐term adjustments in relation to immediate variation in the environment – for example, an increase in BMR in response to decreasing temperatures (Broggi et al. 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0005" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0005">2007</a>; McKechnie 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0022">2008</a>). Thus, each genotype can produce a range of phenotypic trait values in response to, for example, variable ambient temperature, that is, reaction norms. However, the variation in the shape of the reaction norm seems to also include additive genetic variation (Broggi et al. 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0004">2005</a>; McKechnie 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0022">2008</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In both small birds and small mammals, BMR increases gradually with latitude (Wiersma et al. 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0042">2007</a>; Raichlen et al. 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0029">2010</a>; Smit and McKechnie 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0033">2010</a>). Species living at high latitudes, in cold environments, generally have higher BMR than species living at low latitudes in hot and arid environments. This relation is also common within species (Broggi et al. 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0003">2004</a>), and BMR is generally higher in winter than in summer in at least some small temperate birds (Cooper 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0011">2002</a>; Liknes et al. 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0021">2002</a>; McKechnie 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0022">2008</a>; Swanson 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0035">2010</a>). This increase in BMR in cold environments has been suggested to be functionally correlated with improved cold resistance and to be part of the winter acclimatisation process (Liknes and Swanson 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0020">1996</a>; White et al. 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0041">2007</a>; Smit and McKechnie 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0033">2010</a>). Moreover, a direct, positive relation between seasonally increased BMR and temperature‐induced summit metabolism is usually also found (Liknes and Swanson 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0020">1996</a>; Liknes et al. 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0021">2002</a>). Furthermore, experimentally induced reductions in ambient temperature generally result in an increase in BMR after some acclimation time (McKechnie 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0022">2008</a>; Caro and Visser 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0010">2009</a>), a relation that also holds within individuals (McKechnie et al. 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0023">2007</a>). Thus, it seems that decreasing ambient temperatures, calling for increased capacity for thermogenesis, commonly result in an increased BMR. Individuals with a high BMR also have a better capacity to respond to a sudden decrease in temperature and still maintain energy balance than individuals with a low BMR (Ksiazek et al. 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0017">2009</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Given the pronounced portion of the total energy turnover rate that can be ascribed to BMR (e.g., thermoregulation during the night at a temperature of 0°C in blue tits and −10°C in great tits (
  <span class="italic">Parus major</span>) increases the metabolic rate by 0.6 and 0.8 times BMR, respectively) (Nilsson and Svensson 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0026">1996</a>; Broggi et al. 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0003">2004</a>), it is reasonable to expect that variation in BMR will lead to fitness differences. Fitness consequences of interindividual variation in BMR have received comparatively little attention, especially in natural conditions (Burton et al. 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0007">2011</a>). In the few studies looking for a relation between survival and BMR, both negative (Larivée et al. 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0019">2010</a>) and positive (Jackson et al. 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0014">2001</a>) relations have been found. Together with the large variation between individuals found in many populations (Versteegh et al. 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0040">2008</a>), this could indicate either weak selection on BMR or spatially or temporally varying selection pressures. The link between BMR and fitness has also been proposed to be context dependent, possibly allowing different metabolic phenotypes to be favoured depending on the prevailing conditions (Burton et al. 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0007">2011</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this study, we investigated how winter BMR affected the survival from the winter to the following breeding season in a wild population of blue tits. Many animals experience highest mortality during the winter months, and as environmentally induced metabolic requirements increase during the winter, we predict that variation in BMR should have a pronounced effect on survival.</p>
</sec>
