<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece31954-sec-0002" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Materials and Methods</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The study was conducted on a population of free‐living blue tits in southern Sweden (55° 42′ N, 13° 28′ E) between 2004 and 2006. Temperature data were obtained from a climate station in the middle of the study area. Birds were caught during winter while roosting in nest boxes, and BMR was measured the same night as the overnight oxygen consumption (VO
  <sub>2</sub>) in an open‐circuit respirometer. The metabolic measurements lasted until the morning (before dawn) to ensure that the BMR measurement was taken when the birds were in a postabsorptive state. Each bird was placed in a sealed Plexiglas
  <span class="sup">®</span> chamber (1.6 L) and then placed in the darkness of a climate cabinet (type VEM 03/500, Heraeus Vötsch, Hanau, Germany) at 25°C, that is, within their thermoneutral zone. The respirometer consisted of two identical blocks, each with a carbon dioxide analyser and an oxygen analyser. Within a block, an automatic valve control system was used to switch between the two chambers and baseline every 20 min, thus allowing the measurement of four birds per night (two per block). All chambers had their own pump, ensuring an even airflow through the chambers at all times. Air was pulled from the respirometer chamber and dried with silica gel before passing through the carbon dioxide analyser (Servomex 1440 two‐channel analyzer, Crowborough, U.K.), after which it passed through the oxygen analyser (Servomex 4100 two‐channel analyser, Crowborough, U.K.). The carbon dioxide analyser was zero‐calibrated with pure nitrogen (99.998% N
  <sub>2</sub>). The oxygen analyser was also zero‐calibrated with pure nitrogen and then calibrated with dry ambient air to 20.95% oxygen before measurements started each evening. High‐precision flow meters (Bronkhorst HI‐TEC, Ruurlo, the Netherlands), positioned before the carbon dioxide analyser, were used to adjust the flow rate to 166 mL min
  <span class="sup">−1</span>. This flow rate was chosen because, assuming an oxygen consumption of 0.77 mL O
  <sub>2</sub> min
  <span class="sup">−1</span> (Nilsson and Svensson 
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0026">1996</a>), it would reduce the proportion of oxygen in excurrent air to 20.5% and would thereby be within the range of best accuracy of the oxygen analyser. Oxygen and carbon dioxide concentrations were automatically recorded on a Squirrel data logger (model 1202, Grant instruments, Cambridge, U.K.) every minute throughout the measurement sessions. VO
  <sub>2</sub> and VCO
  <sub>2</sub> were calculated according to the equation in Withers (
  <a rid="ece31954-bib-0044" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31954-bib-0044">2001</a>), accounting for the fact that CO
  <sub>2</sub> was not scrubbed prior to the measurements. The lowest 10‐min running average of VO
  <sub>2</sub> was used as a measure of BMR, excluding the first two minutes in all measurement cycles to allow the flushing of the respirometer. The RQ (respiratory quotient) was calculated as RQ = VCO
  <sub>2</sub>/VO
  <sub>2</sub>. Before dawn, all birds were returned to the nest box where they had been caught, to minimise any potential disturbance. All birds were ringed with individually numbered aluminum rings. No birds in the study were sampled more than once.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Birds that were recaptured in the population during the following breeding season or later (until winter 2008) were categorised as survivors. Birds that were not resighted could have either died or dispersed. However, dispersal is unlikely as the study was conducted during winter and most blue tit dispersal occurs during the autumn. Furthermore, from the distribution of ages and sexes among the birds roosting in the nest boxes compared with the population in general, we concluded that it is the most dominant segment of the population that has access to the boxes. This is further strengthened by actual spring dispersal distances from roosting to breeding nest box as 63% of first‐year breeders were found to breed in the same nest box pair and 86% bred within 300 m of their roosting box. The longest dispersal distance between roosting box and breeding box was 2300 m. In a study site of 64 km
  <span class="sup">2</span>, this implies that few roosting birds subsequently dispersed to other areas before breeding. The density of the boxes in our study area was low; thus, some blue tits bred in natural cavities within the study area. We assumed that the sample of blue tit pairs breeding in the boxes is random in relation to BMR. The fixed number of nest boxes in combination with a preference for nest boxes over natural cavities also results in low variation in the number of nest box occupants between years. During the winter 2004–2005, birds were caught between 27th of December and 3rd of February; during the winter 2005–2006, birds were caught between 1st of December and 21st of February.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All statistics were calculated in SAS 9.3(SAS Institute Inc., Cary, NC, USA). A general linear mixed model was used to calculate BMR residuals (BMR as a dependent factor, body mass as a covariate, and respirometer channel as a random factor). The Satterthwaite approximation was used to calculate the denominator degrees of freedom. A linear probability model (SAS GENMOD with logit function) was used to model the survival probability in relation to BMR residuals, age, sex, tarsus length, year, and date of capture. All two‐way interactions were included in the initial model. Factors, covariates, and interactions with 
  <span class="italic">P</span> &gt; 0.1 were removed from the final model.
 </p>
</sec>
