<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">CESM1-CAM5-BGC-Large Ensemble</div>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Community Earth System Model Large Ensemble (CESM-LE) is designed with an explicit goal of enabling assessment of recent past and near-future climate change (1920–2080) in the presence of internal climate variability. Quiet often the internal climate variability is confused with model error
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
  </span> and at times difficult to disentangle. All CESM-LE simulations use a single CMIP5 coupled climate model: the Community Earth System Model, version 1, with the Community Atmosphere Model, version 5 [CESM1 (CAM5)] with a horizontal resolution, approximately 1° in all model components. The CESM1 (CAM5) consists of coupled atmosphere, ocean, land, and sea ice component models. In addition to land carbon cycle calculations, the CESM-LE simulations also include diagnostic biogeochemistry (BGC) calculations for the ocean ecosystem and the atmospheric carbon dioxide cycle
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
  </span>. Each CESM-LE ensemble member has a unique climate trajectory because of small round-off level differences in their atmospheric initial conditions. In other words, the CESM-LE ensemble spread results from internally generated climate variability alone. After initial condition memory is lost, within a time span of few weeks in the atmosphere, each member evolves chaotically and is affected by the atmospheric circulation fluctuations, which is the characteristic of a random and stochastic process
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>
  </span>. The CESM-LE experiment, therefore, uniquely enables to assess the relative influence of internal climate variability and forced climate change on the climate system.
 </p>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Usually, the CESM-LE was started with a multi-century 1850 control simulation with constant preindustrial forcing. The first ensemble member with initial conditions was simulated from a randomly selected date in the 1850 control run: 1 January, year 402 and was integrated forward from 1850 to 2100. Ensemble members 2–30 were all started on 1 January 1920 using slightly different initial conditions and the spread in ensemble members 3–30 was generated by round-off level differences in their initial air temperature fields (order of 10
  <span class="sup">−14</span> K). Except the differences in the initial air temperature field, all the simulations had the same initial conditions. Moreover, all the 35 CESM-LE members share essentially the same ocean initial conditions; the CESM-LE does not sample internal climate variability resulting from differing ocean states.
 </p>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The historical forcings are applied from 1920 to 2005
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
  </span> and representative concentration pathway 8.5 (RCP8.5) forcing
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
  </span> from 2006 to 2080. The CESM-LE simulations used the ozone concentrations calculated by a high-top coupled chemistry–climate model {CESM1 [Whole Atmosphere Community Climate Model (WACCM)]} with specified ozone depleting substances
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
</sec>
