<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">This paper devises a Bayesian time-varying model that tracks periods at which conformance to Benford’s Law is lower. Our methods are motivated by recent attempts to assess how the quality and homogeneity of large datasets may change over time by using the First-Digit Rule (e.g. [
 <xref rid="pone.0213300.ref006" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0213300.ref008" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]). As we show in the numerical studies in the Supplementary Materials (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0213300.s001" class="xref">S1 File</xref>), the empirical-based approach by [
 <xref rid="pone.0213300.ref008" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>] suffers often from bias (cf 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0213300.g004" class="xref">Fig 4</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0213300.s001" class="xref">S1 File</xref>)—thus questioning some of their key empirical findings. Our Bayesian smooth multinomial logistic model is however accurate (cf numerical studies in 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0213300.s001" class="xref">S1 File</xref>), and it is tailored—by construction—for capturing the dynamics governing the proportion of first digits. We apply the proposed model to global tropical cyclone tracks over the past two centuries, and compare our empirical findings with those of [
 <xref rid="pone.0213300.ref008" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. An application of our model indicates that cumulative technological improvements may have only had a moderate influence on the homogeneity of the dataset. Indeed, although technological improvements are cumulative we find that the most recent heterogeneity levels actually tend to be higher than the ones from 1842 to 1890 (cf 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0213300.g004" class="xref">Fig 4</xref>, below); this finding seems to be in contradiction with [
 <xref rid="pone.0213300.ref008" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>] (cf 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0213300.g005" class="xref">Fig 5</xref> in their paper), possibly due to the above-mentioned bias issue. Finally, while we center the article on the tropical cyclone application, our Bayesian time-varying approach has the potential to be employed on other contexts where the target is on learning about the dynamics governing conformance to Benford’s Law—including fraud analysis.
</p>
