<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par66" class="p">These estimates for the surface, atmospheric and TOA global mean shortwave, longwave and net cloud radiative effects inferred here and illustrated in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig15" ref-type="fig" class="xref">15</xref> can then be compared to the respective values determined in the various CMIP5 models (multi-model means in Table 
 <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" class="xref">2</xref>, individual models in Figs. 
 <xref rid="Fig16" ref-type="fig" class="xref">16</xref>, 
 <xref rid="Fig17" ref-type="fig" class="xref">17</xref>, 
 <xref rid="Fig18" ref-type="fig" class="xref">18</xref>). In the multi-model global mean, both shortwave and longwave cloud radiative effects agree within a few Wm
 <sup class="sup">−2</sup> with the reference estimates derived here (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" class="xref">2</xref>). Global mean cloud radiative effects of individual models, however, vary substantially, with largest spreads and standard deviations occurring in the simulated surface estimates (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" class="xref">2</xref>; Figs. 
 <xref rid="Fig16" ref-type="fig" class="xref">16</xref>, 
 <xref rid="Fig17" ref-type="fig" class="xref">17</xref>, 
 <xref rid="Fig18" ref-type="fig" class="xref">18</xref>). This leads in some of the models to substantial deviations compared to the reference values developed here, in some cases exceeding 10 Wm
 <sup class="sup">−2</sup> on a global mean basis (Figs. 
 <xref rid="Fig16" ref-type="fig" class="xref">16</xref>, 
 <xref rid="Fig17" ref-type="fig" class="xref">17</xref>, 
 <xref rid="Fig18" ref-type="fig" class="xref">18</xref>). The deviations of the model-calculated surface cloud radiative effects from the reference values, together with the biases in their associated clear-sky fluxes, may give an indication for each individual model to what extent its cloud-free atmosphere or its clouds contribute to the overall biases noted in the simulated (all-sky) surface fluxes in previous studies.
</p>
