<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">General approach</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our aim was to build a population model that includes climate effects on all demographic rates and at all ages of the life cycle of a white-throated dipper population while also accounting for other sources of environmental and demographic stochasticity and, in addition, density dependence. The model was built to, first, gain a good understanding of the demographic responses of the population to changes in its environment and, second, use this knowledge to project the fate of the population under different climate scenarios. We proceeded by several steps:</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(i) We estimated the annual survival and recruitment rates of breeding females of age classes 1, 2, 3, and 4. We also jointly estimated the annual age-specific densities. These estimates were obtained from 1978 to 2013.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(ii) We explored the effects of climate variables (mean winter temperature, mean winter precipitation, and NAO index) and density on age-specific survival and recruitment rates and also on the number of immigrants joining the population.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(iii) On the basis of these relationships between demographic rates and climate-density, we built a CDDPM that predicts the age-specific numbers of breeding females under given conditions of climate-density. Using the observed time series of climate variables between 1979 and 2013, we reconstructed the past population structure and compared it with the observed number of breeding females during this period.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(iv) By feeding this CDDPM with climate scenarios from the study area, we projected the population to mid-century and examined its properties (population structure and population size).</p>
</sec>
