<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Peasant farmers in Zvimba District have not only resorted to crop diversification to deal with the effects of climate change but also resorted into livelihood diversification. Livelihood diversification is now an important aspect that minimises the effects of climate change on food security and becoming an important adaptation strategy. Participants for this study indicated that more people were migrating to nearest towns such as Chegutu, Chinhoyi and Norton and these migrations were climate change–related ones. Murombedzi and its surrounding areas no longer receive adequate rainfall that sustains crop cycle; hence, farmers harvest insufficient grain. Thus, people are migrating to nearest town. Young and energetic people are going as far as South Africa and Zambia and their families depend on remittances to supplement agricultural incomes and buying of food commodities during drought periods. Other community members have resorted to artisanal mining in areas such as Gadzema in Chegutu and Chinhoyi, although they know very well that the activity is illegal and causes environmental degradation. From the total of 40 respondents selected, all respondents indicated that casual labour is a livelihood adaptation strategy against climate, 38 indicated selling of fruits (guavas), 37 indicated gathering of fruits (mazhanje), 36 indicated artisanal mining, 31 indicated migration, 24 indicated small businesses such as kiosks and 22 indicated petty business (selling of juice cards) as shown in 
 <xref rid="T0001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>. In times of severe droughts, households rely on food aid from NGOs and the government. This is supported by Kangalawe and Lyimo (
 <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>), who in their research findings in Tanzania argue that diversification and adaptive strategies such as water harvesting for small-scale irrigation, integration of livestock and crop production, and non-farm activities are crucial to ensure sustainable livelihoods in a changing climate.
</p>
