<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="results" disp-level="1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">RESULTS</div>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Transient model simulations</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">CLIMBER-2 includes atmosphere, ocean, vegetation, global carbon, and dust models and the three-dimensional thermomechanical ice sheet model SICOPOLIS (
   <a rid="R25" ref-type="bibr" href="#R25">
    <span class="italic">25</span>
   </a>). It has been recently applied for simulating the last four glacial cycles with a fully interactive carbon cycle (
   <a rid="R26" ref-type="bibr" href="#R26">
    <span class="italic">26</span>
   </a>). There, we demonstrated that glacial lowering of atmospheric CO
   <sub>2</sub> in the model is controlled by lowered sea surface temperatures (SSTs) and changes in ocean circulation, in particular enhancement of Antarctic bottom waters and decrease of deep ocean ventilation. Elevated carbonate weathering on exposed shelves and enhanced nutrient utilization in the Southern Ocean due to enhanced dust deposition also play important roles, especially toward glacial maxima (
   <a rid="R27" ref-type="bibr" href="#R27">
    <span class="italic">27</span>
   </a>). Reorganizations of the Atlantic meridional overturning circulation during glacial terminations contribute substantially to deglacial CO
   <sub>2</sub> rise. The terrestrial carbon cycle, which includes novel components such as permafrost carbon, peat, and carbon buried under ice sheets, plays a minor role in atmospheric CO
   <sub>2</sub> dynamics on orbital time scales (
   <a rid="R26" ref-type="bibr" href="#R26">
    <span class="italic">26</span>
   </a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To perform multiple simulations covering the entire Quaternary, we use a novel technique of splitting long-term simulations over the past 3 Ma into shorter intervals. In total, we perform more than 1000 model simulations, each 500 ka long, starting from the same initial conditions but at different points in time (Materials and Methods and fig. S1). This approach allows us to analyze the robustness of glacial cycles by testing whether different simulations converge to the same solution, and also has the advantage that it reduces the potential problem with long-term model drifts in the global carbon cycle. Model drifts can occur because, in our modeling setup, the carbon cycle is not closed. There are geologic sinks (burial in ocean sediments) and sources (carbonate weathering and volcanic CO
   <sub>2</sub> outgassing), and even a tiny imbalance between them can cause a pronounced drift toward too high or too low CO
   <sub>2</sub> concentrations on time scales of millions of years.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">CO
   <sub>2</sub> outgassing and regolith scenarios
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To test the effect of a gradual CO
   <sub>2</sub> decrease on Quaternary climate dynamics, we use prescribed volcanic CO
   <sub>2</sub> outgassing to control the mean CO
   <sub>2</sub> concentration in the model. Small changes in volcanic outgassing represent a possible candidate to explain a long-term CO
   <sub>2</sub> decrease, because even the value for the current volcanic outgassing is very uncertain (
   <a rid="R28" ref-type="bibr" href="#R28">
    <span class="italic">28</span>
   </a>). Alternatively, the same trend in CO
   <sub>2</sub> can be explained by a similarly small increase in average weathering rate and/or organic carbon burial in deep-sea sediments (
   <a rid="R29" ref-type="bibr" href="#R29">
    <span class="italic">29</span>
   </a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On the basis of the evidence for CO
   <sub>2</sub> decrease and regolith removal over the Quaternary, we created different scenarios for CO
   <sub>2</sub> outgassing and regolith distribution, which were then used to drive the model together with orbital variations (see Materials and Methods; 
   <a rid="F1" ref-type="fig" href="#F1">Fig. 1, B and C</a>; and fig. S3). The need for these scenarios originates from the absence of appropriate models that can be used to simulate the evolution of these two factors on the million-year time scale. The initial and final values of volcanic outgassing are determined using an inverse modeling approach (see Materials and Methods), while the initial and final spatial distributions of regolith are either known from observation or strongly constrained by empirical data. Therefore, the scenarios differ only in their temporal evolution (
   <a rid="F1" ref-type="fig" href="#F1">Fig. 1, B and C</a>). For each of the 16 different combinations of regolith and volcanic outgassing scenarios, we run the model over the past 3 Ma using the time-splitting technique and selected the best scenario by minimizing the difference between simulated and observed benthic δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O (
   <a rid="F1" ref-type="fig" href="#F1">Fig. 1D</a>; see also Materials and Methods) (
   <a rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" href="#R3">
    <span class="italic">3</span>
   </a>).
  </p>
  <div id="F1" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <div class="title">External drivers and best scenarios.</div>
    <p>(
     <span class="bold">A</span>) Summer solstice insolation at 65°N (S65N) (
     <a rid="R44" ref-type="bibr" href="#R44">
      <span class="italic">44</span>
     </a>). (
     <span class="bold">B</span>) Scenarios for the evolution of area of exposed crystalline bedrock (
     <span class="italic">A</span>
     <sub>rock</sub>) resulting from the gradual removal of regolith by glacial erosion over North America and Scandinavia (see Materials and Methods and fig. S3 for a spatially explicit illustration). (
     <span class="bold">C</span>) Volcanic CO
     <sub>2</sub> (Volc C) outgassing scenarios (see Materials and Methods). (
     <span class="bold">D</span>) Root mean square error (rmse) and correlation (corr) between modeled and observed (
     <a rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" href="#R3">
      <span class="italic">3</span>
     </a>) benthic δ
     <span class="sup">18</span>O for simulations driven by the combination of different regolith removal and volcanic CO
     <sub>2</sub> outgassing scenarios in (B) and (C). PD, present-day constant regolith and volcanic CO
     <sub>2</sub> outgassing. The optimal scenarios, those minimizing root mean square error and maximizing correlation, are indicated by the white circles in (D) and by the thicker lines in (B) and (C).
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="aav7337-F1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Transient simulations with optimal CO
   <sub>2</sub> outgassing and regolith scenarios
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When the model is driven by orbital variations and the optimal regolith and volcanic outgassing scenarios, it reproduces the evolution of many reconstructed characteristics of Quaternary glacial cycles (
   <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2</a>). It simulates most of the details of the observed benthic δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O curve (
   <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2A</a>), including long-term trends and glacial-interglacial variability. The relative contribution of deep-sea temperature and sea-level variations to δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O variability changes substantially through time, with temperature variations being more important during the early Quaternary and sea-level variations dominating the signal during the late Quaternary (
   <a rid="F3" ref-type="fig" href="#F3">Fig. 3</a>). The model also captures the secular cooling trend of ~−1°C/Ma in SSTs (
   <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2E</a>). The intensification of NH glaciation after ~2.7 Ma ago is marked by a rather abrupt increase in global ice volume variations (
   <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2B</a>) and an increase in ice flux from the Laurentide ice sheet into the North Atlantic, in good agreement with a proxy for ice-rafted debris (
   <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2C</a>) (
   <a rid="R30" ref-type="bibr" href="#R30">
    <span class="italic">30</span>
   </a>). Interglacial atmospheric CO
   <sub>2</sub> concentrations decrease from values of ~350 parts per million (ppm) during the late Pliocene to values between 260 and 290 ppm, typical of the past 800 ka, at ~1 Ma ago (
   <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2D</a>). The amplitude of glacial-interglacial CO
   <sub>2</sub> variations increases from ~50 ppm at the beginning of the Quaternary to ~80 to 90 ppm during the 100-ka cycles of the past million years. This suggests that, for the early Quaternary, the large spreading between and within different CO
   <sub>2</sub> reconstructions markedly overestimates real CO
   <sub>2</sub> variability. In agreement with (
   <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">
    <span class="italic">17</span>
   </a>), a substantial fraction of the increase in the magnitude of glacial-interglacial CO
   <sub>2</sub> changes is attributed to a larger contribution of the iron fertilization mechanism, which, in turn, is related to an increase in dust deposition rate over the Southern Ocean during late Quaternary glacial cycles (
   <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2G</a>). Various previous modeling studies have attempted to derive continuous CO
   <sub>2</sub> records for the pre–ice core time using different methods and assumptions. van de Wal 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span> (
   <a rid="R31" ref-type="bibr" href="#R31">
    <span class="italic">31</span>
   </a>) derived CO
   <sub>2</sub> concentrations that are substantially lower than our estimates for the late Pliocene and early Quaternary, with values never exceeding 300 ppm (fig. S6B). The more recent reconstruction by (
   <a rid="R32" ref-type="bibr" href="#R32">
    <span class="italic">32</span>
   </a>) shows a much larger glacial interglacial variability, particularly before the MPT, compared to our results. The CO
   <sub>2</sub> scenario that we derived for the Pliocene-Pleistocene between 3 and 2.4 Ma ago in a previous study (
   <a rid="R1" ref-type="bibr" href="#R1">
    <span class="italic">1</span>
   </a>) is comparable to the results presented in this study (fig. S6B). During the late Pliocene, simulated global surface air temperature varies by less than 1°C in response to variations in Earth’s orbit, with interglacial temperatures ~1.5°C warmer than at preindustrial (
   <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2F</a>). Successively, glacial-interglacial temperature variability gradually increases, reaching values up to ~6°C during the past million years. Simulated global temperatures never exceed 2°C above the preindustrial over the past 3 Ma (
   <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2F</a>). At ~1 Ma ago, the main periodicity of modeled δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O variations changes from 41 to 100 ka (
   <a rid="F4" ref-type="fig" href="#F4">Fig. 4</a>). Before that, the model mostly responds to obliquity forcing at the 41-ka period, in agreement with data (
   <a rid="F4" ref-type="fig" href="#F4">Fig. 4</a>). However, the model shows a larger response to precession than is observed, possibly because of a missing dynamic Antarctic ice sheet in the model (
   <a rid="R33" ref-type="bibr" href="#R33">
    <span class="italic">33</span>
   </a>) or because the benthic δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O stack is orbitally tuned to obliquity (
   <a rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" href="#R3">
    <span class="italic">3</span>
   </a>). SST, CO
   <sub>2</sub>, and sea level show a similar transition from 41 to 100 ka (fig. S5). The ice sheets are generally thinner before compared to after the MPT (
   <a rid="F5" ref-type="fig" href="#F5">Fig. 5</a>), but the pre- and post-MPT maximum areal ice extent is comparable over Scandinavia and eastern North America, broadly in accordance with available observations (
   <a rid="R7" ref-type="bibr" href="#R7">
    <span class="italic">7</span>
   </a>). The model results are compared to additional observations in fig. S6.
  </p>
  <div id="F2" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <div class="title">Transient modeling results.</div>
    <p>Results of model simulations driven by orbital forcing, optimal regolith removal scenario, and optimal volcanic outgassing scenario. In all panels, observations are shown in black and model results are shown as colored lines. (
     <span class="bold">A</span>) Benthic δ
     <span class="sup">18</span>O compared to the stack of (
     <a rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" href="#R3">
      <span class="italic">3</span>
     </a>). (
     <span class="bold">B</span>) Relative sea level compared to (
     <a rid="R49" ref-type="bibr" href="#R49">
      <span class="italic">49</span>
     </a>). (
     <span class="bold">C</span>) Calving from the Laurentide ice sheet into the North Atlantic compared to a proxy for ice-rafted debris at site U1313 (
     <a rid="R30" ref-type="bibr" href="#R30">
      <span class="italic">30</span>
     </a>). (
     <span class="bold">D</span>) Atmospheric CO
     <sub>2</sub> concentration compared to ice core data (solid line) (
     <a rid="R50" ref-type="bibr" href="#R50">
      <span class="italic">50</span>
     </a>) and other proxies [circles: (
     <a rid="R16" ref-type="bibr" href="#R16">
      <span class="italic">16</span>
     </a>); squares: (
     <a rid="R18" ref-type="bibr" href="#R18">
      <span class="italic">18</span>
     </a>); *: (
     <a rid="R51" ref-type="bibr" href="#R51">
      <span class="italic">51</span>
     </a>); + and ×: (
     <a rid="R19" ref-type="bibr" href="#R19">
      <span class="italic">19</span>
     </a>); diamonds: (
     <a rid="R52" ref-type="bibr" href="#R52">
      <span class="italic">52</span>
     </a>); black box: (
     <a rid="R15" ref-type="bibr" href="#R15">
      <span class="italic">15</span>
     </a>); dotted lines: (
     <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">
      <span class="italic">17</span>
     </a>)]. (
     <span class="bold">E</span>) SST anomalies compared to the stack of (
     <a rid="R18" ref-type="bibr" href="#R18">
      <span class="italic">18</span>
     </a>). (
     <span class="bold">F</span>) Global annual surface air temperature compared to reconstructions (
     <a rid="R53" ref-type="bibr" href="#R53">
      <span class="italic">53</span>
     </a>). (
     <span class="bold">G</span>) Southern Ocean dust deposition compared to data (
     <a rid="R54" ref-type="bibr" href="#R54">
      <span class="italic">54</span>
     </a>).
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="aav7337-F2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <div id="F3" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <div class="title">Benthic δ
     <span class="sup">18</span>O decomposition.
    </div>
    <p>(
     <span class="bold">A</span>) Contribution of sea level and deep ocean temperature to benthic δ
     <span class="sup">18</span>O variability through time, computed as moving SD with a window of 150 ka. The modeled total δ
     <span class="sup">18</span>O variability (gray lines) is compared to the variability of the stack from (
     <a rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" href="#R3">
      <span class="italic">3</span>
     </a>) (black). The modeled contribution of deep ocean temperature and sea level to δ
     <span class="sup">18</span>O variability is shown by the green and magenta lines, respectively. The decomposition in terms of sea level, 
     <span class="italic">z</span>
     <sub>SL</sub>, and deep ocean temperature, 
     <span class="italic">T</span>
     <sub>d</sub>, is derived using the following formula: δ
     <span class="sup">18</span>O = 4.0 − 0.22 
     <span class="italic">T</span>
     <sub>d</sub> − 0.01 
     <span class="italic">z</span>
     <sub>SL</sub>. (
     <span class="bold">B</span>) Ratio between deep ocean temperature and sea-level contribution to the total δ
     <span class="sup">18</span>O variability.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="aav7337-F3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <div id="F4" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <div class="title">Power and wavelet spectra of benthic δ
     <span class="sup">18</span>O.
    </div>
    <p>(
     <span class="bold">A</span>) Power spectra of modeled δ
     <span class="sup">18</span>O (blue) compared to power spectra of the δ
     <span class="sup">18</span>O stack of (
     <a rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" href="#R3">
      <span class="italic">3</span>
     </a>) (black) for different time intervals, as indicated above the panels. Wavelet spectra of (
     <span class="bold">B</span>) the benthic δ
     <span class="sup">18</span>O stack of (
     <a rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" href="#R3">
      <span class="italic">3</span>
     </a>) and (
     <span class="bold">C</span>) modeled δ
     <span class="sup">18</span>O. Black contours indicate the 5% significance level against red noise. The horizontal white lines represent the orbital periods of precession (∼23 ka), obliquity (∼41 ka), and eccentricity (∼100 ka). The model spectra are derived from the average δ
     <span class="sup">18</span>O computed over all ensemble members resulting from the time-splitting technique.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="aav7337-F4" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <div id="F5" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Fig. 5</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <div class="title">Pre- and post-MPT ice sheets.</div>
    <p>Modeled maximum ice thickness in each grid cell (
     <span class="bold">A</span>) before and (
     <span class="bold">B</span>) after the MPT. The dotted lines in (B) indicate the reconstructed ice extent at the last glacial maximum.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="aav7337-F5" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The fact that our model has problems at simulating the strong glacial cycle between 500 and 400 ka ago is not surprising because it occurred during a period of very weak orbital forcing. There were so far only few attempts to simulate this period of time with sufficiently realistic climate–ice sheet models (
   <a rid="R9" ref-type="bibr" href="#R9">
    <span class="italic">9</span>
   </a>, 
   <a rid="R34" ref-type="bibr" href="#R34">
    <span class="italic">34</span>
   </a>), and they all reveal problems with simulation of this time interval, suggesting that current climate–ice sheet models are not nonlinear enough to properly simulate this challenging interval.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Robustness of glacial cycles</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The question of whether glacial cycles are deterministic or stochastic has been highly debated, and a complete spectrum of opinions—from chaotic to perfectly deterministic—exists (
   <a rid="R35" ref-type="bibr" href="#R35">
    <span class="italic">35</span>
   </a>–
   <a rid="R37" ref-type="bibr" href="#R37">
    <span class="italic">37</span>
   </a>). In most cases, our model simulations that started at different points in time converge to one and the same solution (
   <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2</a> and fig. S1), close to reconstructions, providing a strong indication that glacial cycles are robust. The glacial cycles of the 41-ka world are particularly robust, which is expected because they represent a relatively linear response to variations in obliquity (
   <a rid="R4" ref-type="bibr" href="#R4">
    <span class="italic">4</span>
   </a>). The 100-ka cycles appear to be less robust, because they involve a much more nonlinear response to orbital forcing. However, the good agreement between the bulk of the model simulations and the reconstructed glacial cycles evolution over the past 1 Ma (
   <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2A</a>), except for MIS11, indicates that the observed realization was the most likely, although not the only possible one. This finding is fully consistent with that of Tzedakis 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>. (
   <a rid="R35" ref-type="bibr" href="#R35">
    <span class="italic">35</span>
   </a>), who demonstrated that the most probable timing of the most recent glacial terminations is close to that seen in paleoclimate records.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Separate effects of CO
   <sub>2</sub> outgassing and regolith scenarios
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To assess the influence of the different factors on Quaternary glacial cycles, we performed a set of additional experiments where we fixed regolith distribution and/or volcanic outgassing to present-day conditions. When the model is driven by orbital variations as the only external forcing (
   <a rid="F1" ref-type="fig" href="#F1">Fig. 1A</a>), modeling results and data diverge markedly before the MPT, with the model simulating pronounced 100-ka cycles throughout the whole 3 Ma (
   <a rid="F6" ref-type="fig" href="#F6">Fig. 6A</a>). These results confirm that orbital forcing alone cannot explain the evolution in Quaternary glacial cycles. When the optimal regolith removal scenario (
   <a rid="F1" ref-type="fig" href="#F1">Fig. 1B</a>) is prescribed additionally to orbital forcing, but volcanic outgassing is held constant, the model simulates a transition from 41- to 100-ka cycles (
   <a rid="F6" ref-type="fig" href="#F6">Fig. 6B</a>), with the precise timing of this transition depending on the regolith removal scenario (fig. S4). At the same time, these simulations fail to reproduce the general increase in δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O between 3 and 1 Ma ago (
   <a rid="F6" ref-type="fig" href="#F6">Fig. 6B</a>) and the reconstructed global cooling trend in SSTs (fig. S8D). Last, a decrease in volcanic CO
   <sub>2</sub> outgassing (
   <a rid="F1" ref-type="fig" href="#F1">Fig. 1C</a>), together with orbital forcing but with the prescribed present-day regolith cover, captures the trends in δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O (
   <a rid="F6" ref-type="fig" href="#F6">Fig. 6C</a>) and SSTs (fig. S2C). It can also explain a transition from 41- to 100-ka glacial cycles, but for any plausible CO
   <sub>2</sub> scenario, this transition occurs much earlier than in reality (fig. S2).
  </p>
  <div id="F6" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Fig. 6</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <div class="title">External drivers and model response.</div>
    <p>Modeled benthic δ
     <span class="sup">18</span>O compared to observations (black) (
     <a rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" href="#R3">
      <span class="italic">3</span>
     </a>) for (
     <span class="bold">A</span>) simulations driven only by variations in orbital configuration (green), (
     <span class="bold">B</span>) simulations driven by orbital forcing and optimal regolith removal scenario (red), and (
     <span class="bold">C</span>) simulations driven by orbital forcing and optimal volcanic outgassing scenario (blue).
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="aav7337-F6" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </sec>
</sec>
