<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Separate effects of CO
  <sub>2</sub> outgassing and regolith scenarios
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To assess the influence of the different factors on Quaternary glacial cycles, we performed a set of additional experiments where we fixed regolith distribution and/or volcanic outgassing to present-day conditions. When the model is driven by orbital variations as the only external forcing (
  <a rid="F1" ref-type="fig" href="#F1">Fig. 1A</a>), modeling results and data diverge markedly before the MPT, with the model simulating pronounced 100-ka cycles throughout the whole 3 Ma (
  <a rid="F6" ref-type="fig" href="#F6">Fig. 6A</a>). These results confirm that orbital forcing alone cannot explain the evolution in Quaternary glacial cycles. When the optimal regolith removal scenario (
  <a rid="F1" ref-type="fig" href="#F1">Fig. 1B</a>) is prescribed additionally to orbital forcing, but volcanic outgassing is held constant, the model simulates a transition from 41- to 100-ka cycles (
  <a rid="F6" ref-type="fig" href="#F6">Fig. 6B</a>), with the precise timing of this transition depending on the regolith removal scenario (fig. S4). At the same time, these simulations fail to reproduce the general increase in δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O between 3 and 1 Ma ago (
  <a rid="F6" ref-type="fig" href="#F6">Fig. 6B</a>) and the reconstructed global cooling trend in SSTs (fig. S8D). Last, a decrease in volcanic CO
  <sub>2</sub> outgassing (
  <a rid="F1" ref-type="fig" href="#F1">Fig. 1C</a>), together with orbital forcing but with the prescribed present-day regolith cover, captures the trends in δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O (
  <a rid="F6" ref-type="fig" href="#F6">Fig. 6C</a>) and SSTs (fig. S2C). It can also explain a transition from 41- to 100-ka glacial cycles, but for any plausible CO
  <sub>2</sub> scenario, this transition occurs much earlier than in reality (fig. S2).
 </p>
 <div id="F6" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 6</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">External drivers and model response.</div>
   <p>Modeled benthic δ
    <span class="sup">18</span>O compared to observations (black) (
    <a rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" href="#R3">
     <span class="italic">3</span>
    </a>) for (
    <span class="bold">A</span>) simulations driven only by variations in orbital configuration (green), (
    <span class="bold">B</span>) simulations driven by orbital forcing and optimal regolith removal scenario (red), and (
    <span class="bold">C</span>) simulations driven by orbital forcing and optimal volcanic outgassing scenario (blue).
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="aav7337-F6" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
