<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Transient simulations with optimal CO
  <sub>2</sub> outgassing and regolith scenarios
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When the model is driven by orbital variations and the optimal regolith and volcanic outgassing scenarios, it reproduces the evolution of many reconstructed characteristics of Quaternary glacial cycles (
  <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2</a>). It simulates most of the details of the observed benthic δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O curve (
  <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2A</a>), including long-term trends and glacial-interglacial variability. The relative contribution of deep-sea temperature and sea-level variations to δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O variability changes substantially through time, with temperature variations being more important during the early Quaternary and sea-level variations dominating the signal during the late Quaternary (
  <a rid="F3" ref-type="fig" href="#F3">Fig. 3</a>). The model also captures the secular cooling trend of ~−1°C/Ma in SSTs (
  <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2E</a>). The intensification of NH glaciation after ~2.7 Ma ago is marked by a rather abrupt increase in global ice volume variations (
  <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2B</a>) and an increase in ice flux from the Laurentide ice sheet into the North Atlantic, in good agreement with a proxy for ice-rafted debris (
  <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2C</a>) (
  <a rid="R30" ref-type="bibr" href="#R30">
   <span class="italic">30</span>
  </a>). Interglacial atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub> concentrations decrease from values of ~350 parts per million (ppm) during the late Pliocene to values between 260 and 290 ppm, typical of the past 800 ka, at ~1 Ma ago (
  <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2D</a>). The amplitude of glacial-interglacial CO
  <sub>2</sub> variations increases from ~50 ppm at the beginning of the Quaternary to ~80 to 90 ppm during the 100-ka cycles of the past million years. This suggests that, for the early Quaternary, the large spreading between and within different CO
  <sub>2</sub> reconstructions markedly overestimates real CO
  <sub>2</sub> variability. In agreement with (
  <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">
   <span class="italic">17</span>
  </a>), a substantial fraction of the increase in the magnitude of glacial-interglacial CO
  <sub>2</sub> changes is attributed to a larger contribution of the iron fertilization mechanism, which, in turn, is related to an increase in dust deposition rate over the Southern Ocean during late Quaternary glacial cycles (
  <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2G</a>). Various previous modeling studies have attempted to derive continuous CO
  <sub>2</sub> records for the pre–ice core time using different methods and assumptions. van de Wal 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span> (
  <a rid="R31" ref-type="bibr" href="#R31">
   <span class="italic">31</span>
  </a>) derived CO
  <sub>2</sub> concentrations that are substantially lower than our estimates for the late Pliocene and early Quaternary, with values never exceeding 300 ppm (fig. S6B). The more recent reconstruction by (
  <a rid="R32" ref-type="bibr" href="#R32">
   <span class="italic">32</span>
  </a>) shows a much larger glacial interglacial variability, particularly before the MPT, compared to our results. The CO
  <sub>2</sub> scenario that we derived for the Pliocene-Pleistocene between 3 and 2.4 Ma ago in a previous study (
  <a rid="R1" ref-type="bibr" href="#R1">
   <span class="italic">1</span>
  </a>) is comparable to the results presented in this study (fig. S6B). During the late Pliocene, simulated global surface air temperature varies by less than 1°C in response to variations in Earth’s orbit, with interglacial temperatures ~1.5°C warmer than at preindustrial (
  <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2F</a>). Successively, glacial-interglacial temperature variability gradually increases, reaching values up to ~6°C during the past million years. Simulated global temperatures never exceed 2°C above the preindustrial over the past 3 Ma (
  <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2F</a>). At ~1 Ma ago, the main periodicity of modeled δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O variations changes from 41 to 100 ka (
  <a rid="F4" ref-type="fig" href="#F4">Fig. 4</a>). Before that, the model mostly responds to obliquity forcing at the 41-ka period, in agreement with data (
  <a rid="F4" ref-type="fig" href="#F4">Fig. 4</a>). However, the model shows a larger response to precession than is observed, possibly because of a missing dynamic Antarctic ice sheet in the model (
  <a rid="R33" ref-type="bibr" href="#R33">
   <span class="italic">33</span>
  </a>) or because the benthic δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O stack is orbitally tuned to obliquity (
  <a rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" href="#R3">
   <span class="italic">3</span>
  </a>). SST, CO
  <sub>2</sub>, and sea level show a similar transition from 41 to 100 ka (fig. S5). The ice sheets are generally thinner before compared to after the MPT (
  <a rid="F5" ref-type="fig" href="#F5">Fig. 5</a>), but the pre- and post-MPT maximum areal ice extent is comparable over Scandinavia and eastern North America, broadly in accordance with available observations (
  <a rid="R7" ref-type="bibr" href="#R7">
   <span class="italic">7</span>
  </a>). The model results are compared to additional observations in fig. S6.
 </p>
 <div id="F2" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Transient modeling results.</div>
   <p>Results of model simulations driven by orbital forcing, optimal regolith removal scenario, and optimal volcanic outgassing scenario. In all panels, observations are shown in black and model results are shown as colored lines. (
    <span class="bold">A</span>) Benthic δ
    <span class="sup">18</span>O compared to the stack of (
    <a rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" href="#R3">
     <span class="italic">3</span>
    </a>). (
    <span class="bold">B</span>) Relative sea level compared to (
    <a rid="R49" ref-type="bibr" href="#R49">
     <span class="italic">49</span>
    </a>). (
    <span class="bold">C</span>) Calving from the Laurentide ice sheet into the North Atlantic compared to a proxy for ice-rafted debris at site U1313 (
    <a rid="R30" ref-type="bibr" href="#R30">
     <span class="italic">30</span>
    </a>). (
    <span class="bold">D</span>) Atmospheric CO
    <sub>2</sub> concentration compared to ice core data (solid line) (
    <a rid="R50" ref-type="bibr" href="#R50">
     <span class="italic">50</span>
    </a>) and other proxies [circles: (
    <a rid="R16" ref-type="bibr" href="#R16">
     <span class="italic">16</span>
    </a>); squares: (
    <a rid="R18" ref-type="bibr" href="#R18">
     <span class="italic">18</span>
    </a>); *: (
    <a rid="R51" ref-type="bibr" href="#R51">
     <span class="italic">51</span>
    </a>); + and ×: (
    <a rid="R19" ref-type="bibr" href="#R19">
     <span class="italic">19</span>
    </a>); diamonds: (
    <a rid="R52" ref-type="bibr" href="#R52">
     <span class="italic">52</span>
    </a>); black box: (
    <a rid="R15" ref-type="bibr" href="#R15">
     <span class="italic">15</span>
    </a>); dotted lines: (
    <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">
     <span class="italic">17</span>
    </a>)]. (
    <span class="bold">E</span>) SST anomalies compared to the stack of (
    <a rid="R18" ref-type="bibr" href="#R18">
     <span class="italic">18</span>
    </a>). (
    <span class="bold">F</span>) Global annual surface air temperature compared to reconstructions (
    <a rid="R53" ref-type="bibr" href="#R53">
     <span class="italic">53</span>
    </a>). (
    <span class="bold">G</span>) Southern Ocean dust deposition compared to data (
    <a rid="R54" ref-type="bibr" href="#R54">
     <span class="italic">54</span>
    </a>).
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="aav7337-F2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <div id="F3" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Benthic δ
    <span class="sup">18</span>O decomposition.
   </div>
   <p>(
    <span class="bold">A</span>) Contribution of sea level and deep ocean temperature to benthic δ
    <span class="sup">18</span>O variability through time, computed as moving SD with a window of 150 ka. The modeled total δ
    <span class="sup">18</span>O variability (gray lines) is compared to the variability of the stack from (
    <a rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" href="#R3">
     <span class="italic">3</span>
    </a>) (black). The modeled contribution of deep ocean temperature and sea level to δ
    <span class="sup">18</span>O variability is shown by the green and magenta lines, respectively. The decomposition in terms of sea level, 
    <span class="italic">z</span>
    <sub>SL</sub>, and deep ocean temperature, 
    <span class="italic">T</span>
    <sub>d</sub>, is derived using the following formula: δ
    <span class="sup">18</span>O = 4.0 − 0.22 
    <span class="italic">T</span>
    <sub>d</sub> − 0.01 
    <span class="italic">z</span>
    <sub>SL</sub>. (
    <span class="bold">B</span>) Ratio between deep ocean temperature and sea-level contribution to the total δ
    <span class="sup">18</span>O variability.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="aav7337-F3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <div id="F4" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Power and wavelet spectra of benthic δ
    <span class="sup">18</span>O.
   </div>
   <p>(
    <span class="bold">A</span>) Power spectra of modeled δ
    <span class="sup">18</span>O (blue) compared to power spectra of the δ
    <span class="sup">18</span>O stack of (
    <a rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" href="#R3">
     <span class="italic">3</span>
    </a>) (black) for different time intervals, as indicated above the panels. Wavelet spectra of (
    <span class="bold">B</span>) the benthic δ
    <span class="sup">18</span>O stack of (
    <a rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" href="#R3">
     <span class="italic">3</span>
    </a>) and (
    <span class="bold">C</span>) modeled δ
    <span class="sup">18</span>O. Black contours indicate the 5% significance level against red noise. The horizontal white lines represent the orbital periods of precession (∼23 ka), obliquity (∼41 ka), and eccentricity (∼100 ka). The model spectra are derived from the average δ
    <span class="sup">18</span>O computed over all ensemble members resulting from the time-splitting technique.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="aav7337-F4" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <div id="F5" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 5</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Pre- and post-MPT ice sheets.</div>
   <p>Modeled maximum ice thickness in each grid cell (
    <span class="bold">A</span>) before and (
    <span class="bold">B</span>) after the MPT. The dotted lines in (B) indicate the reconstructed ice extent at the last glacial maximum.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="aav7337-F5" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The fact that our model has problems at simulating the strong glacial cycle between 500 and 400 ka ago is not surprising because it occurred during a period of very weak orbital forcing. There were so far only few attempts to simulate this period of time with sufficiently realistic climate–ice sheet models (
  <a rid="R9" ref-type="bibr" href="#R9">
   <span class="italic">9</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R34" ref-type="bibr" href="#R34">
   <span class="italic">34</span>
  </a>), and they all reveal problems with simulation of this time interval, suggesting that current climate–ice sheet models are not nonlinear enough to properly simulate this challenging interval.
 </p>
</sec>
