<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="introduction" disp-level="1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">INTRODUCTION</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Quaternary is characterized by the appearance of glacial-interglacial cycles caused by the cyclic growth and decay of continental ice sheets in the Northern Hemisphere (NH). Before the initiation of NH glaciation at ~2.7 million years (Ma) ago, as indicated by the appearance of ice-rafted debris in the North Atlantic, the growth of NH ice sheets was probably suppressed by elevated atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub> (
  <a rid="R1" ref-type="bibr" href="#R1">
   <span class="italic">1</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R2" ref-type="bibr" href="#R2">
   <span class="italic">2</span>
  </a>). Afterward, benthic δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O records (
  <a rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" href="#R3">
   <span class="italic">3</span>
  </a>) show a trend toward larger ice sheets and colder climate over the Quaternary, together with an increase in the amplitude of the glacial-interglacial variability (
  <a rid="R4" ref-type="bibr" href="#R4">
   <span class="italic">4</span>
  </a>). Of particular interest is the transition between ~1.25 and ~0.7 Ma ago, known as the mid-Pleistocene transition (MPT) (
  <a rid="R5" ref-type="bibr" href="#R5">
   <span class="italic">5</span>
  </a>–
  <a rid="R7" ref-type="bibr" href="#R7">
   <span class="italic">7</span>
  </a>), from mostly symmetric cycles with a period of about 41 thousand years (ka) to strongly asymmetric 100-ka cycles. Several hypotheses for the mechanism of the MPT have been proposed. One of them invokes a gradual decline of CO
  <sub>2</sub> during the past 3 Ma to explain both the onset of Greenland (
  <a rid="R2" ref-type="bibr" href="#R2">
   <span class="italic">2</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R8" ref-type="bibr" href="#R8">
   <span class="italic">8</span>
  </a>) and, more generally, NH glaciations (
  <a rid="R1" ref-type="bibr" href="#R1">
   <span class="italic">1</span>
  </a>) and the MPT transition (
  <a rid="R9" ref-type="bibr" href="#R9">
   <span class="italic">9</span>
  </a>–
  <a rid="R11" ref-type="bibr" href="#R11">
   <span class="italic">11</span>
  </a>). Another hypothesis attributes the MPT to a gradual removal of a thick regolith layer from North America and northern Europe (
  <a rid="R12" ref-type="bibr" href="#R12">
   <span class="italic">12</span>
  </a>–
  <a rid="R14" ref-type="bibr" href="#R14">
   <span class="italic">14</span>
  </a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub> concentration is accurately known only for the past ~800 ka, the period covered by ice core data. Nevertheless, proxy-based reconstructions suggest that, over the past ~2 Ma, CO
  <sub>2</sub> was not very different from the concentrations measured in ice cores (
  <a rid="R15" ref-type="bibr" href="#R15">
   <span class="italic">15</span>
  </a>–
  <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">
   <span class="italic">17</span>
  </a>) but that it was substantially higher during the late Pliocene (
  <a rid="R18" ref-type="bibr" href="#R18">
   <span class="italic">18</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R19" ref-type="bibr" href="#R19">
   <span class="italic">19</span>
  </a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It has been postulated that NH continents were all covered by regolith before the Quaternary, an expected outcome of the 10
  <span class="sup">7</span> to 10
  <span class="sup">8</span> years that the bedrock was exposed to weathering before the initiation of glacial cycles (
  <a rid="R7" ref-type="bibr" href="#R7">
   <span class="italic">7</span>
  </a>). The observed present-day regolith distribution (
  <a rid="R20" ref-type="bibr" href="#R20">
   <span class="italic">20</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R21" ref-type="bibr" href="#R21">
   <span class="italic">21</span>
  </a>), which is characterized by exposed bedrock over large parts of northern North America and Eurasia, is a result of glacial erosion by Quaternary ice sheets. A gradual removal of regolith by glacial erosion could have changed the ice sheets’ response to orbital forcing. Changes in regolith distribution may affect glacial cycles through several mechanisms. The first one is based on the fact that, in the case of temperate-base ice sheets, the sliding velocity of ice is much higher in the presence of a thick regolith layer as compared to exposed rocks (
  <a rid="R12" ref-type="bibr" href="#R12">
   <span class="italic">12</span>
  </a>). This makes ice sheets more mobile, thinner, and more susceptible to orbital forcing. In addition to this mechanism, Ganopolski and Calov (
  <a rid="R13" ref-type="bibr" href="#R13">
   <span class="italic">13</span>
  </a>) also found that, in the case when ice sheets expand well into areas covered by regolith, enhanced deposition of glaciogenic dust over the southern margins of NH ice sheets substantially lowers snow albedo, thereby facilitating melting and preventing growing of large ice sheets.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It has been shown that modeling of long (100 ka) and strongly asymmetric glacial cycles of the late Quaternary requires both the presence of large areas of northern continents with exposed rocks and a relatively low atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub> concentration (
  <a rid="R13" ref-type="bibr" href="#R13">
   <span class="italic">13</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R22" ref-type="bibr" href="#R22">
   <span class="italic">22</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R23" ref-type="bibr" href="#R23">
   <span class="italic">23</span>
  </a>). Here, we investigate the origin of the major transitions in Quaternary climate dynamics by performing a large set of transient simulations with the Earth system model of intermediate complexity CLIMBER-2 (
  <a rid="R24" ref-type="bibr" href="#R24">
   <span class="italic">24</span>
  </a>).
 </p>
</sec>
