<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Volcanic CO
  <sub>2</sub> outgassing scenarios
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To control the mean atmospheric concentration of CO
  <sub>2</sub> in the model, we used small changes in the prescribed volcanic CO
  <sub>2</sub> outgassing. The present-day volcanic outgassing used in the model is 5.3 Tmol C/year, which is the value that balances the weathering rate (
  <a rid="R26" ref-type="bibr" href="#R26">
   <span class="italic">26</span>
  </a>). The value of volcanic CO
  <sub>2</sub> outgassing for ~3 Ma ago has been derived from fitting modeling results to the benthic δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O stack. For that, we used an ensemble of transient model simulations initialized at 3.2 Ma ago and run for 500 ka driven by orbital variations, with continents fully covered by regolith and prescribed constant volcanic CO
  <sub>2</sub> outgassing ranging from 5.3 to 6.5 Tmol C/year. The different values of volcanic CO
  <sub>2</sub> outgassing lead to different modeled CO
  <sub>2</sub> concentrations. A best fit of modeled benthic δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O to the stack of (
  <a rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" href="#R3">
   <span class="italic">3</span>
  </a>) during interglacials is used to constrain the value of CO
  <sub>2</sub> outgassing to 6.2 Tmol C/year for the time interval between 3 and 2.7 Ma ago. Some recent studies suggest that Antarctica could have contributed up to 20 m of sea-level equivalent during the late Pliocene/early Pleistocene (
  <a rid="R47" ref-type="bibr" href="#R47">
   <span class="italic">47</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R48" ref-type="bibr" href="#R48">
   <span class="italic">48</span>
  </a>). That would translate in a ~0.2‰ reduction in δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O, which, in turn, would lead to lower volcanic CO
  <sub>2</sub> outgassing values ~6.0 Tmol C/year to be more appropriate for the early Pleistocene. As a consequence, modeled atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub> concentration would also be lower by ~30 ppm. We then constructed four different scenarios for the temporal evolution of volcanic CO
  <sub>2</sub> outgassing between 3 Ma ago and the present day. All scenarios consist of a long-term decrease from 6.2 Tmol C/year at 3 Ma ago to 5.3 Tmol C/year at present, but the timing and rate of the decrease vary between scenarios (
  <a rid="F1" ref-type="fig" href="#F1">Fig. 1C</a>). A decrease from 6.2 to 5.3 Tmol C/year corresponds to a decrease of less than 20%. Because even the value for the present-day volcanic outgassing is known with an uncertainty of more than 100% (~3 to 10 Tmol C/year) (
  <a rid="R28" ref-type="bibr" href="#R28">
   <span class="italic">28</span>
  </a>), changes in volcanic outgassing represent a possible candidate to explain the long-term CO
  <sub>2</sub> decrease. However, the aim of our study is not to explain the causes of the CO
  <sub>2</sub> decrease, and other processes such as changes in weathering (
  <a rid="R7" ref-type="bibr" href="#R7">
   <span class="italic">7</span>
  </a>) or organic carbon burial in deep-sea sediments (
  <a rid="R29" ref-type="bibr" href="#R29">
   <span class="italic">29</span>
  </a>) would also be potential candidates to explain the long-term CO
  <sub>2</sub> decline.
 </p>
</sec>
