<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3" class="p">
 <italic class="italic">Asclepias syriaca</italic> (Common Milkweed) is a plant with a highly specialized pollination system that requires insect visitors to transport pollen, making it susceptible to pollen limitation
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">8</xref>
 </sup> and reduced fruit production if its flower period shifts. Additionally, recent studies have indicated that the Common Milkweed is declining in the USA by proportions ranging from approximately 50 through 90%, depending on geographic area and habitat
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">9</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">11</xref>
 </sup>. Its decline is especially concerning because it may be contributing to the decline of 
 <italic class="italic">Danaus plexippus</italic> (Monarch Butterfly)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">12</xref>
 </sup>, which relies on 
 <italic class="italic">A. syriaca</italic> as a host plant
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">13</xref>
 </sup>. Given 
 <italic class="italic">A. syriaca</italic>’s potential susceptibility to the negative consequences of phenological shift, recent decline, and importance as a host plant, it is critical to this plants future conservation that its potential response to climate change is investigated. As a first step toward that goal, I used phenological and climate data from the USA National Phenology Network (USA-NPN)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">14</xref>
 </sup> along with climate data from the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">15</xref>
 </sup> to examine the relationship between 
 <italic class="italic">A. syriaca</italic> flowering date and climate (temperature and precipitation) from 2011 through 2016.
</p>
