<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec21" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p id="Par39" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study represents an opportunity to learn from a system encouraging EBP implementation [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>] and can inform future policy and research. First, in a public system supporting EBP implementation, EBP use increased over time and clinicians who participated in system-sponsored training initiatives increased their EBP use even more. Second, proficient organizational culture modified the effect of system efforts to increase implementation, which elucidates a potential future target for implementation strategy trials [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74" href="#CR74">74</a>]. While prior work has identified correlational associations between determinants like proficient organizational culture and outcomes, this study advances the field by prospectively elucidating the relationship between proficient culture and change over time. Despite our enthusiasm about these findings, it is important to note that they are preliminary given study limitations (i.e., self-reported measure of practice use and lack of a comparison system).
 </p>
 <p id="Par40" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As expected, clinician use of EBPs modestly increased over the 5 years in which the system created a centralized infrastructure to de-silo EBP implementation [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>]. Although only half the clinicians in the study participated in system-sponsored EBP initiatives, there was a significant increase in clinicians’ use of EBPs system-wide during the study period. Potential explanations include that supervisors trained in these EBPs through EBP initiatives may have supported clinicians not formally trained in applying these techniques, that peer interactions may have increased clinician interest in these techniques, or that the changing system culture might reflect new organizational priorities. Clinicians participating in system-sponsored EBP training initiatives increased their use of EBPs twice as much as those not formally trained. Although these increases are promising, the effects were not large in magnitude and raise questions about clinical significance. In a large system serving over 30,000 children and families annually, an increase of 6% might have a population mental health impact, but further research is needed to understand the clinical impact of small, system-wide increases in use of EBPs. Future studies evaluating the impact of system-wide implementation must include client outcomes using hybrid effectiveness-implementation designs [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75" href="#CR75">75</a>] to ensure that the end goal of implementation efforts (i.e., client reach and outcomes) is achieved and that questions related to clinical significance and cost-effectiveness can be answered.
 </p>
 <p id="Par41" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Consistent with the literature [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76" href="#CR76">76</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78" href="#CR78">78</a>], clinicians working in organizations with more proficient cultures at baseline exhibited greater increases in CBT use. This extends previous findings by prospectively linking proficiency culture to increased EBP use over time. Clinicians working in such organizations may be more motivated to improve their competence in up-to-date practices and have more opportunities to participate in EBP training because of leaders’ EBP prioritization. Although proficient culture is a more distal construct on the causal implementation pathway, these preliminary results suggest the importance of attending to general organizational factors in the implementation process. Future work should clarify if proficient culture is a more powerful target for implementation efforts versus training and ongoing support initiatives or if they result in a synergistic effect.
 </p>
 <p id="Par42" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Clinicians’ self-reported non-evidence-based technique use remained stable. Given that there is little knowledge of the effect of delivering EBPs alongside potentially contraindicated approaches [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>], these findings point to the importance of attending to deimplementation [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79" href="#CR79">79</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80" href="#CR80">80</a>]. Further, this finding provides evidence of discriminant validity and suggests that the relationships observed between initiative participation and proficient organizational culture are not due to spurious findings or common method error variance [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81" href="#CR81">81</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par43" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study methodological limitations include that this study was only conducted in one system and that CBT increases observed may be a national trend; that results may be influenced by cohort effects; that we relied on self-reported clinician use of techniques [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82" href="#CR82">82</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83" href="#CR83">83</a>] [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84" href="#CR84">84</a>] rather than actual clinician behavior or patient outcomes; that the response rate was only 60%; that implementation strategies were not experimentally manipulated; and that these results may not generalize to smaller organizations and/or single clinician organizations given that we focused our sampling on organizations with larger programs. Study analytical limitations include that we conducted multiple tests of moderators given our exploratory aims, which increased the likelihood of a type I error; that the study may have been underpowered to detect effects of organizational moderators given the sample of 20 organizations at level 3; and that results included large confidence intervals on all effects that almost overlap with zero.
 </p>
</sec>
