<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec19" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Relation of EBP initiative participation to clinicians’ psychotherapy technique use</div>
 <p id="Par37" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Clinicians’ participation in EBP initiatives during the study was positively related to increased use of CBT techniques, controlling for wave and all covariates (
  <span class="italic">B</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">adj</span>
  </sub> = .09, 
  <span class="italic">SE</span> = .04, 
  <span class="italic">p</span> = .019). For each additional EBP initiative, clinician CBT technique use increased by 3%. For clinicians who did not participate in any EBP initiatives, average adjusted CBT use increased from wave 1 (
  <span class="italic">M</span> = 3.14) to wave 3 (
  <span class="italic">M</span> = 3.28) by 
  <span class="italic">d</span> = .21, a small effect. On average, clinicians in the study participated in .85 EBP initiatives by the study’s end which corresponds to an adjusted average increase in CBT use from wave 1 (
  <span class="italic">M</span> = 3.14) to wave 3 (
  <span class="italic">M</span> = 3.36) of 7% or 
  <span class="italic">d</span> = .32, a small effect. For clinicians who participated in two EBP initiatives by the study’s end, average adjusted CBT use increased from wave 1 (
  <span class="italic">M</span> = 3.14) to wave 3 (
  <span class="italic">M</span> = 3.46) by 10% or 
  <span class="italic">d</span> = .47, a medium effect. For the 9.6% of clinicians who participated in three or more EBP initiatives by the study’s end, average adjusted CBT use increased by 
  <span class="italic">d =</span> .61 (13%) or more, a medium-to-large effect. See Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>. Participation in EBP initiatives was not related to clinicians’ psychodynamic technique use (
  <span class="italic">B</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">adj</span>
  </sub> = .01, 
  <span class="italic">SE</span> = .04, 
  <span class="italic">p</span> = .709).
  <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Adjusted mean change in CBT use for a clinician who participated in 0, 1, and 4 initiatives</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="13012_2019_912_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
