<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Setting</div>
 <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Prior to 2013, DBHIDS supported EBPs via separate “EBP initiatives” that included training and expert consultation for enrolled clinicians lasting approximately 1 year, as recommended by treatment developers [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>]. Between 2007 and 2019, through these initiatives, DBHIDS supported the implementation of a variety of cognitive behavioral therapy-focused practices addressing a range of psychiatric disorders including cognitive therapy [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>], prolonged exposure [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>], trauma-focused CBT [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>], dialectical behavior therapy [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>], and parent-child interaction therapy [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>] (all currently ongoing; see Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). Initially, DBHIDS largely guided organization selection for initiative participation; more recently, organizations have applied for participation through a competitive process. Organizations decided which of their clinicians would participate [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>].
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Timeline of evidence-based practice initiatives, Evidence-Based Practice Innovation Center (EPIC), and data collection</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="13012_2019_912_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As system leaders identified similar barriers across single EBP initiatives, the DBHIDS Commissioner (ACE) convened a task force of academics and policy-makers in 2012 to apply best practices from implementation science to support EBP implementation. This resulted in EPIC, an entity intended to provide a centralized infrastructure for EBP administration. EPIC was formally launched in 2013 and oversees all EBP implementation efforts in the Philadelphia public behavioral health system. EPIC is led by a Director and currently supported by two staff who provide technical assistance to organizations around EBP implementation through meetings, telephone calls, and regular events. In addition to supporting the EBP initiatives, which predated the creation of this centralized infrastructure, EPIC aligned policy, fiscal, and operational approaches by developing systematic processes to contract for EBP delivery, hosting events to publicize EBP delivery, designating providers as EBP agencies, and creating enhanced rates for the delivery of some EBPs. For more details on the approach taken by EPIC and DBHIDS, please see [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>]. All organizations and clinicians were exposed to system-level support provided by EPIC from 2013 to 2017. Data collection in 2013 occurred prior to the official launch of EPIC.
 </p>
</sec>
