<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The differing predictions largely contradict our original hypothesis that climate change will result in the evolution of greater vegetative dormancy. Our hypothesis was based on the assumptions that vegetative dormancy is a response to stress, and that climate change is stressful. The former assumption is rooted in 
 <italic class="italic">in situ</italic> experiments showing decreased sprouting after defoliation in 
 <italic class="italic">Cypripedium calceolus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Cephalanthera longifolia</italic> [
 <xref rid="RSOS160647C29" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>], and after experimental pollination in 
 <italic class="italic">Cypripedium acaule</italic> [
 <xref rid="RSOS160647C60" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">60</xref>], and in the hypothesis that sprouting itself may be costly, despite being necessary [
 <xref rid="RSOS160647C26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSOS160647C28" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>]. The assumption that climate change is stressful is based on empirical data suggesting that many natural plant populations are currently experiencing stress, as illustrated by decreased population growth rates and increased extinction risks [
 <xref rid="RSOS160647C61" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">61</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSOS160647C62" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">62</xref>]. However, in the three study species, higher temperature was often associated with higher survival, while higher precipitation often had the opposite effect (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS160647F3" class="xref">figure 3</xref>
 <italic class="italic">a</italic>–
 <italic class="italic">d</italic>; electronic supplementary material, tables S1–S3). Furthermore, population growth rate is forecast to decline in 
 <italic class="italic">C. parviflorum</italic>, the species which is predicted to evolve greater sprouting (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS160647F4" class="xref">figure 4</xref>
 <italic class="italic">a</italic>,
 <italic class="italic">b</italic>; electronic supplementary material, figure S4
 <italic class="italic">a</italic>), while 
 <italic class="italic">Ophrys</italic> is predicted to evolve greater dormancy, while exhibiting an increasing population growth rate (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS160647F4" class="xref">figure 4</xref>
 <italic class="italic">e</italic>,
 <italic class="italic">f</italic>; electronic supplementary material, figure S4c). In 
 <italic class="italic">Ophrys</italic>, annual recruitment and mortality are both positively correlated with the previous year's temperature, whereas the proportion of plants that flower shows the opposite pattern [
 <xref rid="RSOS160647C38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>]. Recent northwards range expansion of this species in the UK [
 <xref rid="RSOS160647C37" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>] suggests that the overall effect of contemporary climate change on 
 <italic class="italic">Ophrys</italic> is beneficial, despite being associated with decreased sprouting. Indeed, although survival and flowering are expected to decline with increased hours of sunshine in 
 <italic class="italic">Ophrys</italic> (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS160647F3" class="xref">figure 3</xref>), the number of hours of sunshine is not expected to change substantially before 2099 (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS160647F1" class="xref">figure 1</xref>). As climate is predicted to become warmer and wetter at both study sites, these results cast doubt on the notion that climate change will be a major source of stress for these species over the next century.
</p>
