<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par10" class="p">Ours is the first study to directly test for the effects of a fungal parasite on the upper thermal tolerance of its hosts. Existing literature on the interactions between infection and the upper thermal tolerance of animals is limited to six marine mollusk host species, one freshwater mollusk host species, eight freshwater fish host species, and one amphibian host species (a newt), with trematodes as the dominant parasite (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table" class="xref">3</xref>). Whereas upper thermal tolerance of hosts was enhanced in only 10.5% (2/19) of these host-parasite systems and did not change in 31.5% (6/19) of these systems, our finding that Bd infections lowered host thermal tolerance is consistent with 58% (11/19) of host thermal responses to parasites (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table" class="xref">3</xref>), including the only previous study of thermal thresholds in parasitized amphibians
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" class="xref">19</xref>
 </sup> and similar studies of parasitized fish
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">20</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">21</xref>
 </sup> and mollusks
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">22</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>
 </sup>. What does this mean for the present and coming decades, during which animals will face unprecedented changes in the global climate and in rates of infectious disease emergence? Our results suggest that infections by parasites and pathogens may profoundly alter the thermal physiology of hosts, often eliciting significantly reduced heat tolerance. We argue that a diminished upper temperature threshold may not only increase risk of population losses in accordance with the warming tolerance hypothesis
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">8</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">11</xref>
 </sup>, but also to perpetuate infections by altering host thermoregulatory behavior, with added implications for host survival. 
</p>
