<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In boreal and temperate ecosystems, a substantial increase in temperature and in the frequency of extreme events (e.g. severe droughts or heat waves) is projected for the upcoming century (IPCC, 
 <xref rid="nph14968-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). Poleward climatic niche shifts are expected (e.g. McKenney 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="nph14968-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>), therefore raising questions about the ability of trees to cope with those rapid changes (Price 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="nph14968-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). Migration and long‐term genetic adaptation are expected to be too slow to keep pace with climatic niche shifts (Jump &amp; Peñuelas, 
 <xref rid="nph14968-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2005</xref>; Aitken 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="nph14968-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>; Jump 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="nph14968-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>; Jezkova &amp; Wiens, 
 <xref rid="nph14968-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). Nevertheless, populations may persist in their current location depending on species sensitivity and adaptive capacity to future environmental changes (Aubin 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="nph14968-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). To better predict the fate of tree species, knowledge is needed about the climatic constraints affecting their growth/development and the key genetic and physiological mechanisms involved in the response to those constraints (Aubin 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="nph14968-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>; Urban 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="nph14968-bib-0081" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). These knowledge gaps challenge the forecast of species’ responses to shifting climatic conditions and the implementation of forest management strategies such as assisted gene flow from pre‐adapted populations (Aitken &amp; Whitlock, 
 <xref rid="nph14968-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). Without a genuine tree‐centered approach based on time‐series data to evaluate sensitivity to fluctuating environmental conditions, elucidating the genetic architecture of adaptation to climate throughout a tree's lifespan will remain difficult (Alberto 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="nph14968-bib-0005" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>).
</p>
