<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">As suggested by Chant (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">2008</xref>), stereotypes around the relationships between gender, as a homogeneous group, and the environment mask inequalities and obscure complex environmental and gender challenges. Some other interesting findings from our empirical work reinforce such an argument and evidence the dynamics of constant re-negotiation of women’s roles and responsibilities. For instance, in Bihar, our results show that a small group of women who belong to higher castes and have higher levels of education and wealth (i.e. good access to access, information, credit and animals and multiple sources of on-farm and off-farm income) are more able to re-negotiate their roles in decision-making and develop a range of proactive ecosystem-based management strategies, decreasing their vulnerability to crisis. Further, the results suggest that the participation in training and extension programmes promoted by NGOs and intergovernmental organizations and programmes has a positive influence on such adaptation process (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" class="xref">5</xref>, axis 1). However, this result appears to be location sensitive. For instance, higher caste women from the other site (site 2, Muzzafarpur) are neither involved in such training nor in decision-making, probably as a result of more rigid system values leading to the greater seclusion of women from public activity (including outdoor work) (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" class="xref">5</xref>, axis 2). By contrast, lower caste, less-educated women are less subject to such seclusion and are therefore more likely to work as agricultural labourers. These women consequently adopt mainly reactive livelihood security strategies, but, to some extent, also technological adaptation strategies, especially those related to the introduction of hybrid seeds (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" class="xref">5</xref>, axis 1). Our findings show lower adoption rates of ecosystem-based strategies by such group of poor women, who are net labour sellers in the area, because they are more likely than rich women, who are net labour buyers, and men to face time constraints, as a response to the increased burden of day-to-day activities as workers. This may affect their ability to participate in accessing information and community-based climate adaptation initiatives (Behrman et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">2014</xref>) such as the ‘climate smart agriculture’ promoted by CCAFS which requires high labour inputs in the first years. As a consequence, they show a higher exposure to perturbations and crisis. In the other site (site 1, Vaishali), the access to schooling, the participation in training and the awareness of climate change are driven by external interventions and influence mainly the adoption of agro-biodiversity management and social ties and knowledge management as relevant strategies (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" class="xref">5</xref>, axis 2). As suggested by Mehar et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" class="xref">2016</xref>) in a recent study in the same area, our findings confirm that the awareness on a wide range of ecosystem-based strategies through extension programmes may influence their adoption. Therefore, in line with the findings of Agarwal (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">2000</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">2009</xref>), we argue that is important to ensure the institutional integration of gender and power analysis in planning ecosystem based adaptation processes. Such integration may avoid recommendations that lead to adaptation pathways for some groups which carry potential maladaptation for others (Barnett and O’Neill 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">2010</xref>), thereby burdening the most vulnerable groups.
</p>
