<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3">In the troposphere, ozone is produced by a complicated chemical process, which initializes by the photochemical reactions of ozone precursors, such as nitrogen oxides (NO
 <sub>X</sub>) and volatile organic carbons (VOC
 <sub>S</sub>)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>
 </sup>. As the increase in industrial activity and number of automobiles, the precursors of ozone (O
 <sub>3</sub>) and the global budget of oxidization are also significantly increased
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>
 </sup>. Although photochemical process is important to determine ozone concentrations, previous studies suggest that local meteorological parameters such as temperature, solar radiation, relative humidity, horizontal wind speed and direction, and cloud cover also play important roles in controlling ozone concentrations. For example, elevated ozone concentration is usually accompanied with strong solar radiation and small winds, which is favorable for the photochemical production of ozone and the accumulation of ozone and its precursor
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>
 </sup>. Tie 
 <italic>et al</italic>. (2009) suggest that radiation, wind speed and wind direction are the most important meteorological factors for causing the variability of surface ozone concentrations in Shanghai. These factors directly affect the photochemical reaction, regional transportation and diffusion process of ozone. Furthermore, synoptic-scale weather pattern, with spatial scale less than 1000 km, is also an important factor in controlling ozone variability
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>
 </sup>. For example, anticyclones (i.e., high pressure systems) produce favorable conditions for ozone production. At the center of anticyclones, it is normally sunny weather, with low wind velocity, causing high O
 <sub>3</sub> production and accumulation
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>
 </sup>. In coastal cities, sea-land breeze can be an important meteorological factor to affect ozone distributions. Tie 
 <italic>et al</italic>. (2009) finds that the impact of sea breeze on O
 <sub>3</sub> concentration is noticeable in the city of Shanghai under calm weather condition.
</p>
