<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Our findings are broadly consistent with a previous coarser scale ENM analysis of adult mosquitoes in Ecuador, which suggests that while 
 <italic class="italic">Aedes</italic> mosquitoes may shift into highland areas under changing climate conditions, the total area of suitable habitat will ultimately decrease as localized climatic conditions favor extirpation [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007322.ref032" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>]. However, models of 
 <italic class="italic">Aedes</italic> distribution in the previous study were made through the year 2100, representing an extended time horizon for guiding agency decision making. While predicted ranges in 2100 are visually similar to results presented here, notable discrepancies exist between the spatial distributions predicted in our models and the previous study for 2050, where the previous model predicts widespread absence of mosquitoes in central Ecuador and presence throughout much of the eastern Amazon basin. In contrast to our methods, Escobar 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007322.ref032" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>] used a different niche modeling algorithm, a different model of climate change (A2), a coarser spatial resolution (20 km), and combined global species occurrence for two adult arbovirus vectors, 
 <italic class="italic">Ae</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">aegypti</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Ae</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">albopictus</italic>, to predict pooled arbovirus risk throughout Ecuador. Though 
 <italic class="italic">Ae</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">aegpyti</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Ae</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">albopictus</italic> are competent vectors of diseases that occur in Ecuador (e.g. dengue, chikungunya, Zika), these species differ significantly in their physiology, possibly driving observed discrepancies between the models of pooled adult 
 <italic class="italic">Aedes</italic> spp. risk and larval 
 <italic class="italic">Ae</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">aegypti</italic> range [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007322.ref068" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">68</xref>]. Reaching consensus across ENMs is a known area of conflict in ecology that requires more research, where various methodologies can lead to vastly different forecasts of geographic distributions and risk, making direct comparisons between models difficult [
 <xref rid="pntd.0007322.ref069" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">69</xref>]. Future studies combining multiple approaches and comparing the impact of input on models could help resolve this conundrum.
</p>
