<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">No doubt, climate change should be integrated into the curricula for medical, public health, and nursing students [
 <xref rid="B52-ijerph-15-02650" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>]. Nevertheless, this is by no means a simple and straightforward task. There are a number of challenges: (1) Medical curricula have already been overcrowded [
 <xref rid="B27-ijerph-15-02650" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>]; (2) We need to apply different pedagogies in teaching for different health professionals [
 <xref rid="B44-ijerph-15-02650" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>]; (3) Our understanding on the mechanisms of health impacts of climate change is still limited; and, (4) There is a serious shortage of academic staff in medical, public health, and nursing schools who are competent in teaching and research into the area of climate change. At this stage, most “climate change” education programs have restricted contents to the trend and causes of climate change. Although this is important for raising awareness and building motivations for actions, it is far less than enough to empower health professionals to engage in actions on climate change. Research into the underlying mechanisms of health impacts of climate change needs to be strengthened. There is also a need to change the culture of professional practices: health professionals need to see themselves as an integral part of the global action on climate change. Environmental education is important [
 <xref rid="B53-ijerph-15-02650" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">53</xref>,
 <xref rid="B54-ijerph-15-02650" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>], but it needs to be integrated into the professional education programs as a higher order of learning beyond the confines of professional knowledge and skills [
 <xref rid="B16-ijerph-15-02650" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. Teaching about climate change typically takes a wider sustainability focus [
 <xref rid="B18-ijerph-15-02650" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B48-ijerph-15-02650" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>]. The Higher Education Academy (HEA) in the UK developed some examples about skills and knowledge that are necessary for an “action-oriented, sustainability literate” graduate [
 <xref rid="B18-ijerph-15-02650" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>].
</p>
