<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="f4" class="fig">
 <label class="label">Figure 4</label>
 <caption class="caption">
  <title class="title">Areas with climate suitable to provide attainable yields greater than present-day median attainable yields.</title>
  <p class="p">Present day median attainable yields are 8.1 t ha
   <sup class="sup">−1</sup> for maize, 4.6 ton ha
   <sup class="sup">−1</sup> for wheat and 5.2 ton ha
   <sup class="sup">−1</sup> for rice. Note that climatically suitable does not necessarily mean economically or socially viable. Grid-cells are coloured black, purple, or blue when analogues produce attainable yields over the crop-specific thresholds for four out of five GCMs. Black shows grid-cells (0.5° × 0.5°) meeting the yield criteria which are currently heavily cropped (&gt;50,000 ha harvested area over all crop types). Purple colours show grid-cells which are currently lightly cropped (1,000–50,000 ha harvested area). Grid-cells which have a current harvested area &lt;1,000 ha are coloured blue. Red grid-cells show cropped areas which had an attainable yield over the threshold in the present day, but fell below this threshold in the future. White areas do not obtain the yield threshold. Panels 
   <bold class="bold">a</bold>,
   <bold class="bold">d</bold> and 
   <bold class="bold">g</bold> show the current situation
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4" class="xref">4</xref>, 
   <bold class="bold">b</bold>,
   <bold class="bold">e</bold> and 
   <bold class="bold">h</bold> the situation in 2041–2059 based on climate analogues from the ensemble of climate models, and 
   <bold class="bold">c</bold>,
   <bold class="bold">f</bold> and 
   <bold class="bold">i</bold> the same for 2081–2099. Current cropland areas are taken from Monfreda 
   <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18" class="xref">18</xref>. Areas with soils classed as fundamentally unsuitable for cropping over at least 90% of the 0.5° grid-cell are masked out in light grey, whilst areas with very low precipitation relative to the typical growing conditions of that crop are masked out in dark grey (Methods section).
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="ncomms12608-f4" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
