<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Land use has repeatedly been shown to be the key predictor variable determining plant species distribution (Yang et al., 
 <xref rid="B82" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>). 
 <italic class="italic">R. ponticum</italic> can invade a range of land cover categories, including natural to semi-natural, upland heaths, and occasionally grasslands. In Britain, earlier studies reporting on its occurrence suggest that woodland is the land cover type most affected by the invasion of 
 <italic class="italic">R. ponticum</italic> (Dehnen-Schmutz et al., 
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2004</xref>). Our findings are in agreement with these reports; 
 <italic class="italic">R. ponticum</italic> has the highest probability of occurrence in land cover categories representing “6: Mosaic Tree &amp; Shrub” and “8: Needle Leaved Forest.” There are numerous reasons why 
 <italic class="italic">R. ponticum</italic> favors woodland in Wales, for example, the availability of a microenvironment suitable for seed germination (Stephenson et al., 
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2006</xref>) or growing under tree canopies to spread “under-cover” and thus avoid eradiation likely play a role. Crucially, the presence of dead plant material or moss cover may be critical to 
 <italic class="italic">R. ponticum</italic> establishment (Cross, 
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1981</xref>). In our study, Mosaic Tree &amp; Shrub and Forests were the land cover categories which are likely to contain these substrates in the understory. Both of these land cover categories favored by 
 <italic class="italic">R. ponticum</italic> are predicted to experience only a minor change (a decrease of −2.62% in category “6” while an increase of 4.52% in category “8”). Thus, the range contraction in 
 <italic class="italic">R. ponticum</italic> seems to be much larger than the predicted change of suitable habitat types. This suggests that the predicted contraction in 
 <italic class="italic">R. ponticum</italic> future range may not be primarily governed by land cover changes. These results are in agreement with some earlier studies suggesting that species' range may drastically contract even if there is only a little shift in land cover types (Charbonnel et al., 
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>). Among topographic variables, aspect makes a major contribution in our model. We show that 
 <italic class="italic">R. ponticum</italic> clearly favors the northern aspect for its establishment and growth. North-facing slopes at the latitude of Wales are likely to offer greater soil moisture, in addition to lower direct insulation intensity. Many other studies on 
 <italic class="italic">R. ponticum, R. simsii</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">R. ferrugineum</italic> suggest that northern slopes (in the Northern hemisphere) offer more favorable conditions for Rhododendron growth (Taylor et al., 
 <xref rid="B75" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>; Christiaens et al., 
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>; Francon et al., 
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2017</xref>). Our results show that the probability of occurrence of 
 <italic class="italic">R. ponticum</italic> in Snowdonia is negatively correlated with slope. Earlier studies have suggested that shallow-slope areas are typically those with high soil moisture and nutrient availability, thus offering more favorable microenvironment for plant proliferation (Kang et al., 
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>). Altitude explained a minor share of the variation in the training set of occurrence observations in this study. Even though altitude is considered an indirect variable since it has no direct effect on plant growth and physiology, it acts as a very good proxy of other un-measured or un-used variables. The reported altitudinal range of 
 <italic class="italic">Rhododendron</italic> in Snowdonia National Park is well within the global range inhabited by this species. Therefore, it is likely that altitude 
 <italic class="italic">per se</italic> does not represent a set of critically limiting variables in our study, but more likely acts as a proxy for auxiliary variables such as hydrology, exposure to light, wind speed, soil type and others which are not included in our model. There is strong evidence that the inclusion of indirect variables can enhance the predictive performance of SDMs, however their collinearity with direct variables must be addressed (Austin, 
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2002</xref>; West et al., 
 <xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>).
</p>
