<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Although our model has pointed out drastic reduction in distribution of 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">macropomum</italic> in both native and invaded regions based on variations in temperature and rainfall dynamics, it is possible that physiological mechanisms, which were not evaluated here, can act to minimize the range losses. Wide tolerance to temperature increases, low concentrations of gases and high concentrations of toxins are traits that should alleviate the climate change effects on aquatic organisms. Only high water temperatures (approximately 35°C) can be considered critical for 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">macropomum</italic> [
 <xref rid="pone.0179684.ref061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">61</xref>]. A study found that individuals with a body weight above 250 g have tolerance to low oxygen concentrations due to high temperatures [
 <xref rid="pone.0179684.ref062" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">62</xref>]. In addition, the ability of 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">macropomum</italic> to obtain O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> from an oxygen-rich air-water interface [
 <xref rid="pone.0179684.ref063" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">63</xref>] may attenuate the effects of low concentrations of oxygen expected with global warming. However, it is also expected that higher temperatures increase bacterial nitrification in the water, also increasing the metabolic needs of the fish and accumulating NO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> in the blood and tissues, which is toxic to fish [
 <xref rid="pone.0179684.ref064" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">64</xref>]. 
 <italic class="italic">Colossoma macropomum</italic> has a high sensitivity to NO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>, which makes increases in water temperature potentially harmful for its homeostasis, both in natural environments and fish farming [
 <xref rid="pone.0179684.ref065" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">65</xref>]. Thus, a mechanistic approach of ecological niche modeling including adaptive characteristics could be useful to obtain more details about the effect of climate change on 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">macropomum</italic> invasion (see [
 <xref rid="pone.0179684.ref066" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">66</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0179684.ref067" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">67</xref>] for details about mechanistic models).
</p>
