<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div id="grl58185-sec-0010" class="ack" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <div class="title">Acknowledgments</div>
 <p>C. J. S. and P. F. acknowledge support from Regional and Global Climate Modeling Program of the U.S. Department of Energy Office of Environmental and Biological Sciences under grant DE‐SC0012549 and UK Natural Environment Research Council grant NE/N006038/1. R. J. K. was supported by NASA grant 17‐EARTH17R‐015. D. W. P. acknowledges funding from Natural Environment Research Council projects NE/L01355X/1 (CLARIFY) and NE/J022624/1 (GASSP). G. M., Ø. H., and B. H. S. were funded by the Research Council of Norway, through the grant NAPEX (229778). D. O. and A. K. were supported by the Norwegian Research Council through the projects EVA (229771), EarthClim (207711/E10), NOTUR (nn2345k), and NorStore (ns2345k). O. B. acknowledges HPC resources from TGCC under the gencmip6 allocation provided by GENCI (Grand Equipement National de Calcul Intensif). P. S. acknowledges funding from the European Research Council project RECAP under the European Union's Horizon 2020 research and innovation program with grant agreement 724602 and support from the Alexander von Humboldt Foundation. T. A. was supported by the Met Office Hadley Centre Climate Programme funded by BEIS and Defra. M. K. and A. V. were supported by the Natural Environment Research Council under grant NE/K500872/1. T. T. was supported by the supercomputer system of the National Institute for Environmental Studies, Japan; the Environment Research and Technology Development Fund (S‐12‐3) of the Environmental Restoration and Conservation Agency of Japan; and JSPS KAKENHI grant JP15H01728. Simulations with HadGEM3‐GA4 were performed using the MONSooN system, a collaborative facility supplied under the Joint Weather and Climate Research Programme, which is a strategic partnership between the Met Office and the Natural Environment Research Council. Climate modeling at GISS (D. S. and G. F.) is supported by the NASA Modeling, Analysis and Prediction program and GISS simulations used resources provided by the NASA High‐End Computing Program through the NASA Center for Climate Simulation at Goddard Space Flight Center. The ECHAM6‐HAM2 simulations were performed using the ARCHER UK National Supercomputing Service. The ECHAM‐HAMMOZ model is developed by a consortium composed of ETH Zurich, Max Planck Institut für Meteorologie, Forschungszentrum Jülich, University of Oxford, the Finnish Meteorological Institute, and the Leibniz Institute for Tropospheric Research and managed by the Center for Climate Systems Modeling (C2SM) at ETH Zurich. The HadGEM2 radiative kernels are available from 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.5518/406" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://doi.org/10.5518/406</span>. For access to PDRMIP model data please see 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cicero.oslo.no/en/PDRMIP/PDRMIP-data-access" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.cicero.oslo.no/en/PDRMIP/PDRMIP‐data‐access</span>.
 </p>
</div>
