<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="grl58185-sec-0009" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusions</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Understanding how models respond to different forcing agents is critical to reducing uncertainty in climate‐model projections of the Earth's energy budget and ultimately climate sensitivity (Forster et al., 
  <a rid="grl58185-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58185-bib-0016">2016</a>). This work has found that ERF is distinctly different from RF across forcing mechanisms, indicating that for all forcings analyzed rapid adjustments have an important role to play in the quantification of the perturbation of the Earth's energy budget from human activities and the overall heating of the oceans. For CO
  <sub>2</sub> competing tropospheric and land surface rapid adjustment effects cancel, meaning the overall estimates of ERF are similar to the stratospheric temperature adjusted RF. For the other mechanisms tropospheric rapid adjustments significantly alter forcing estimates. Tropospheric temperature (partially offset by water vapor) and cloud changes are the principal sources of adjustment, with stratospheric temperature adjustment playing a lesser role. Clouds have an appreciable effect on the overall forcings, particularly for CO
  <sub>2</sub>, BC, and sulfate, and it is shown that intermodel diversity is high and diagnostic methods do not necessary agree. For CH
  <sub>4</sub> the sign of the cloud adjustment, and total rapid adjustment, depends on whether SW absorption of methane is included in the radiation scheme. This highlights the importance of the UTLS region in the radiative balance and has important consequences for model development.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The vertical resolution and truncation height of both the radiative kernel and model output may affect the rapid adjustment due to stratospheric temperature calculated for CO
  <sub>2</sub> forcing. It may be the case that adjustments or climate feedbacks are underestimated using radiative kernels or model output, which is not well resolved in the stratosphere. As radiative kernels have been used extensively for multiple‐CO
  <sub>2</sub> studies or anthropogenic forcing pathways where CO
  <sub>2</sub> is the dominant forcing agent, further work is needed to determine whether this is a significant effect.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In general, noncloud adjustments agree well between methods and models, and radiative kernels provide a robust framework for decomposing ERF into IRF and rapid adjustments. However, cloud adjustments are not consistent between models and methods, particularly for sulfate forcing, and require more understanding. Further modeling work should focus on improving our understanding of cloud adjustments, and output of ISCCP simulator diagnostics as standard in climate models would be beneficial to enable a consistent method of directly estimating these effects. A further progression is to constrain rapid adjustment calculations with observations. A historical reanalysis data set can be used to determine the evolution of rapid adjustments over time. In the present day, satellite and ground‐based stations can be used to observationally constrain the spatial distribution of aerosol concentrations, which would be particularly important for black carbon where the adjustment strength (and possibly sign) is sensitive to the vertical profile of the aerosol.</p>
</sec>
