<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="grl58185-sec-0007" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Rapid Adjustments by Forcing Agent</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figure 
  <a rid="grl58185-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#grl58185-fig-0001">1</a> shows the IRF, ERF, and rapid adjustments for each of the five climate forcers. The rapid adjustments to 2xCO
  <sub>2</sub> forcing are positive overall and constitute 30% of the ERF, whereas for 10xBC forcing they are negative and are 107% of the absolute ERF, therefore offsetting more than half of the positive IRF. Rapid adjustments to 2%Sol and 5xSul are slightly negative, whereas they are close to zero for 3xCH
  <sub>4</sub>.
 </p>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="grl58185-fig-0001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Instantaneous radiative forcing, effective radiative forcing, and rapid adjustments for five different climate change drivers. Each bar represents a multimodel mean and each model is given equal weight with up to six different methods of calculating each adjustment for each model (Figure 
    <a rid="grl58185-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#grl58185-supitem-0001">S3</a> in the 
    <a rid="grl58185-supInfo-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#grl58185-supInfo-0001">supporting information</a>). The error bars are the 95% confidence range weighting each method and model sample equally.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-1" xlink:href="GRL-45-12023-g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Adjustments are calculated individually for each model and kernel (Figure 
  <a rid="grl58185-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#grl58185-supitem-0001">S3</a> in the 
  <a rid="grl58185-supInfo-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#grl58185-supInfo-0001">supporting information</a>), and the responses are averaged first over kernels and then over models so that each model has equal weight in Figure 
  <a rid="grl58185-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#grl58185-fig-0001">1</a>. In previous work it has been shown that differences in kernel base climatology and radiative transfer are typically minimal (Soden et al., 
  <a rid="grl58185-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58185-bib-0043">2008</a>), and differences are only significant where climate perturbations are larger than in this study (Jonko et al., 
  <a rid="grl58185-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58185-bib-0023">2012</a>). In general, we find this to be true as interkernel agreement is good except for stratospheric temperature adjustment to 2xCO
  <sub>2</sub> forcing as discussed below. Interkernel agreement is also good for cloud adjustments, although cloud adjustments calculated using MMPRPs differ somewhat from the kernel‐derived methods. For 5xSul we only use cloud adjustments calculated from the MMPRP for Figure 
  <a rid="grl58185-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#grl58185-fig-0001">1</a> except from the NCAR‐CESM1‐CAM4 model, which does not include cloud microphysical changes in its PDRMIP configuration. This is to isolate the component of the cloud lifetime effect (Albrecht, 
  <a rid="grl58185-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58185-bib-0001">1989</a>) from the cloud microphysical effect (Twomey, 
  <a rid="grl58185-bib-0048" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58185-bib-0048">1977</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The residual term 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <span class="bold">
    <span class="italic">ϵ</span>
   </span>
  </div> in equation 
  <a rid="grl58185-disp-0001" ref-type="disp-formula" href="#grl58185-disp-0001">(1)</a> should be no more than 10% of the ERF for the kernel method to be valid (Shell et al., 
  <a rid="grl58185-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58185-bib-0039">2008</a>). For most models and experiments the true IRF is not available as this requires a double radiation call. However, in some situations the shortwave (SW) or LW IRF is known to be 0. This occurs when either SW or LW absorption of a particular species is not present in a model's radiation code. In these cases, any difference between the ERF and the sum of all rapid adjustments is a residual by equation 
  <a rid="grl58185-disp-0001" ref-type="disp-formula" href="#grl58185-disp-0001">(1)</a>. Figure 
  <a rid="grl58185-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#grl58185-fig-0002">2</a> shows the ERF, rapid adjustment, and residual for 10xBC LW, 3xCH
  <sub>4</sub> SW, and 2%Sol LW for those models, which do not include LW absorption of BC or SW absorption of methane in their radiation schemes (no models include LW solar absorption). In each of the three cases it can be seen that the residual term is small, being 6%, 12%, and 2% of the ERF for 10xBC LW, 3xCH
  <sub>4</sub> SW, and 2%Sol LW in magnitude, respectively. The larger multimodel residual in the 3xCH
  <sub>4</sub> SW case is biased by a large relative residual in the HadGEM2 model, whereas residuals in the other four models analyzed are close to 0.
 </p>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="grl58185-fig-0002" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Effective radiative forcing, rapid adjustments, and residuals in models where instantaneous radiative forcing is known to be exactly 0. Each point is a multikernel mean for each model and outlined bars show the multimodel means from this subset of models.</p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-3" xlink:href="GRL-45-12023-g002" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figure 
  <a rid="grl58185-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#grl58185-fig-0003">3</a> shows the contribution to the total rapid adjustment for each atmospheric mechanism. Adjustments normalized by IRF and the mean change in individual model atmospheric profiles are shown in Figures 
  <a rid="grl58185-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#grl58185-supitem-0001">S4</a> and 
  <a rid="grl58185-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#grl58185-supitem-0001">S5</a> in the 
  <a rid="grl58185-supInfo-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#grl58185-supInfo-0001">supporting information</a>.
 </p>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="grl58185-fig-0003" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Rapid adjustments decomposed by mechanism. The bars represent multimodel means. The error bars are the 95% confidence range weighting each method and model sample equally (see Figure 
    <a rid="grl58185-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#grl58185-supitem-0001">S3</a> for individual model and kernel responses).
   </p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-5" xlink:href="GRL-45-12023-g003" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For 2xCO
  <sub>2</sub>, the adjustment due to stratospheric temperature change is strong and positive due to stratospheric cooling. The stratospheric cooling is the largest temperature response throughout the atmospheric column and is consistently present in all models. It is a remarkable coincidence that the stratospheric temperature adjustment for 2xCO
  <sub>2</sub> is the same size as the total adjustment, despite the nonnegligible contributions from other adjustments, which sum to 0. This can explain why stratospherically adjusted RF has for a long time been a useful metric for evaluating the energetic effects of CO
  <sub>2</sub> forcing. The larger error bar for the total adjustment reflects the assessment of Myhre et al. (
  <a rid="grl58185-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58185-bib-0031">2013</a>) that ERF is expected to be similar to RF for CO
  <sub>2</sub> forcing with a larger uncertainty due to the inclusion of the tropospheric and surface adjustments.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There is some disagreement between kernels for the stratospheric temperature adjustment for 2xCO
  <sub>2</sub>, for which the ECMWF‐ERA‐Interim/Oslo kernel projects a stronger adjustment in most models. The reason for this is that the ECMWF‐ERA‐Interim/Oslo kernel has a higher resolution in the stratosphere than the other kernels considered in this study. The ECMWF‐ERA‐Interim/Oslo kernel has 60 model levels with the highest at 0.1 hPa, whereas the other five kernels use the 17 standard pressure levels in CMIP5 (Taylor et al., 
  <a rid="grl58185-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58185-bib-0047">2012</a>) with 10 hPa being the highest. The difference is largest in models for which the output is also highly resolved in the stratosphere, such as CanESM2. This additional contribution to the stratospheric cooling accounts for about an additional +0.4 W/m
  <span class="sup">2</span> allocated to stratospheric adjustment in CanESM2 using the ECMWF‐ERA‐Interim/Oslo kernel compared to other kernels.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Black carbon shows a strong negative total adjustment (Stjern et al., 
  <a rid="grl58185-bib-0044" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58185-bib-0044">2017</a>), for which the largest (absolute) negative contributions are tropospheric temperature and clouds. The largest positive adjustment in absolute terms is due to the change in water vapor, which opposes tropospheric temperature changes. The vertical profiles associated with BC forcing show a warming and wetting throughout the atmosphere coupled with a large reduction in cloud fraction, particularly at higher levels. Unlike for 2xCO
  <sub>2</sub>, the stratospheric temperature adjustment is negative rather than positive in 10xBC, due to a warming stratosphere (Hansen et al., 
  <a rid="grl58185-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58185-bib-0020">1997</a>). The total adjustment is substantially different from the stratospheric temperature adjustment, so RF is not an appropriate measure of ERF for BC forcing. The strong negative adjustment to black carbon forcing indicates that the equilibrium global mean near‐surface temperature response to a black carbon forcing is smaller than indicated by its direct effect. Unlike CO
  <sub>2</sub>, BC (and sulfate) mass mixing ratios are spatially variable, and rapid adjustments depend on the location of the aerosol perturbation (Samset &amp; Myhre, 
  <a rid="grl58185-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58185-bib-0036">2015</a>). An increase in solar forcing is not distributed equally either, as more solar radiation is received in the tropics, and this zonal asymmetry can drive different circulation responses compared to CO
  <sub>2</sub> (Guo et al., 
  <a rid="grl58185-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58185-bib-0019">2018</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the 2%Sol experiment, the tropospheric temperature adjustment (partially offset by water vapor) also dominates over the stratospheric temperature adjustment. Net cloud adjustments are negative rather than positive for 2%Sol as seen by the change in vertical cloud fraction profile but are smaller in magnitude relative to the IRF than for 10xBC. Again, the rapid adjustment due to stratospheric temperature change does not equal the total adjustment.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The stratospheric temperature adjustment in 3xCH
  <sub>4</sub> shows a much smaller level of change than 2xCO
  <sub>2</sub>, as stratospheric temperature changes are much less pronounced. The small stratospheric temperature adjustment could be due to competition between radiative absorption and emission processes in the upper troposphere/lower stratosphere (UTLS; Zhong et al., 
  <a rid="grl58185-bib-0057" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58185-bib-0057">1993</a>), unlike for CO
  <sub>2</sub> in which emission from the upper troposphere dominates due to its relatively higher abundance in the atmosphere (Forster et al., 
  <a rid="grl58185-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58185-bib-0015">1997</a>; Stocker et al., 
  <a rid="grl58185-bib-0045" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58185-bib-0045">2001</a>). Therefore, for 3xCH
  <sub>4</sub>, more of the LW emission from the warming troposphere passes through the stratosphere and reaches the TOA. However, overlap with water vapor bands for CH
  <sub>4</sub> is also important. The subset of models with an explicit treatment of SW absorption by methane (CanESM2, MIROC‐SPRINTARS, MPI‐ESM, and NCAR‐CESM1‐CAM5) exhibits a UTLS warming and a negative stratospheric temperature adjustment to methane forcing; the opposite is true for those that do not (Figures 
  <a rid="grl58185-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#grl58185-supitem-0001">S5</a>b and 
  <a rid="grl58185-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#grl58185-supitem-0001">S6</a> in the 
  <a rid="grl58185-supInfo-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#grl58185-supInfo-0001">supporting information</a>). Inclusion or omission of SW methane absorption also determines whether cloud adjustments are negative or positive. In the multimodel mean, the stratospheric temperature adjustment is similar to the total adjustment, but for the subset of models that either exclude or include SW absorption of methane, they do not agree. This may indicate that ERF also differs from RF for methane.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In 5xSul, noncloud adjustments are generally small in comparison to the IRF, and cloud adjustments, which are larger in magnitude and spread, are described in the following subsection.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In all experiments there is an anticorrelation between tropospheric temperature and water vapor adjustments, which is a result of the Clausius‐Clapeyron relationship. This is shown by observing that the water vapor adjustment is dominated by the adjustment calculated assuming a constant relative humidity for the tropospheric temperature change in each model and experiment (Figure 
  <a rid="grl58185-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#grl58185-supitem-0001">S7</a> in the 
  <a rid="grl58185-supInfo-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#grl58185-supInfo-0001">supporting information</a>). By decomposing tropospheric temperature responses into Planck and lapse‐rate components, we also show that the model spread in lapse‐rate plus constant relative humidity is smaller than in each of the individual components, reinforcing this anticorrelation and in line with feedback studies (Soden et al., 
  <a rid="grl58185-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58185-bib-0043">2008</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
