<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="par0185" class="p">Designing crop ideotypes, based on crop physiological knowledge, has recently been reviewed and prioritized in order to raise the genetic yield potential of wheat and other cereals under climate change (
 <xref rid="bib0130" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Foulkes et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0165" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hawkesford et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0280" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Parry et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0305" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Reynolds et al., 2011</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib0300" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>). We have identified the important cultivar parameters and plant traits ranging from phenology, canopy structure to root water uptake, and calculated their optimal combinations quantitively to achieve the best possible wheat yield under targeted climatic condition in 2050 (
 <italic class="italic">HadGEM2</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">RCP8.5</italic>) in the UK and NZ. We have optimized wheat ideotypes by using the full parameter ranges in a multidimensional space of cultivar parameters and plant traits, considering the basis of crop physiology and the existence of natural genetic variations in wheat germplasm (
 <xref rid="tbl0015" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 3</xref>). In our simulation experiments, we assumed that cultivar parameters selected for optimization (
 <xref rid="tbl0015" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 3</xref>) could be changed independently from each other by the EASA evolutionary algorithm during optimization process. This might not be always the case. For example, a high value for maximum area of flag leaf 
 <italic class="italic">A
  <sub class="sub">max</sub>
 </italic> may require a higher value for phyllochron 
 <italic class="italic">P
  <sub class="sub">h</sub>,
 </italic> to provide sufficient time for larger leaves to grow. Dependencies between parameters or any other constrains, if known, can be incorporated in the current modelling framework in the same way as we accounted for restrictions in the maximum value of harvest index HI or yield coefficient of variation 
 <italic class="italic">CV</italic>. Nevertheless, once parameters sampled from the parameter spaces, all known interactions and trade-offs among them were taken into account within the Sirius model. Some of the cultivar parameters, such as phyllochron 
 <italic class="italic">P
  <sub class="sub">h</sub>,
 </italic> which determined phenological development and strongly affected grain yield, were subject to strong selection pressure and converged to an optimal single value for all sites. Some other parameters, such as ‘stay green’ 
 <italic class="italic">S
  <sub class="sub">G</sub>
 </italic> or ‘response of photosynthesis to water stress’ 
 <italic class="italic">W
  <sub class="sub">sa</sub>
 </italic>, did not converged to an optimal value at individual site, because their values had smaller effects on grain yield. Rather, their evolution represented a “random walk”. As a result, their final values varied substantially between sites (
 <xref rid="tbl0020" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 4</xref>). Ranges of parameter values for optimization, where possible, were determined from existing genetic variations reported in the literature (
 <xref rid="tbl0015" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 3</xref>). However, for some parameters, such as drought tolerance, 
 <italic class="italic">W
  <sub class="sub">sa</sub>
 </italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">W
  <sub class="sub">ss</sub>
 </italic>, such information was not available. In this case, we defined range of parameter values by using cultivars previously calibrated for Sirius in diverse environments. We designed wheat ideotypes for 2050-climate using climate projection from a single global climate model (GCM), 
 <italic class="italic">HadGEM2</italic>, and a single emission scenario, 
 <italic class="italic">RCP8.5</italic>. Design of ideotype may change if a different GCM or RCP is selected from the CMIP5 ensemble. To assess uncertainty in ideotype design related to uncertainty in future climate, ideally design should be run for the entire CMIP5 ensemble due to nonlinear nature of the Sirius wheat model. However, CMIP5 includes over 50 variants of GCMs, which sample uncertainties in model structures and initial conditions, and four emission scenarios, 
 <italic class="italic">RCP2.6</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">RCP4.5</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">RCP6.0</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">RCP8.5</italic>. For computationally demanding tasks, such as ideotype design, it is not practical to explore all possible combinations of GCM and RCP. A potential solution to reduce number of simulations could be the use of climate sensitivity index to select a subset of GCMs which preserves the range of uncertainty found in CMIP5 itself (
 <xref rid="bib0375" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Semenov and Stratonovitch, 2015</xref>). This would allow to quantify uncertainty in design resulting from the CMIP5 ensemble by conducting fewer simulation experiments. Nevertheless, the design of wheat ideotypes in our study could be used as a road map by plant breeders for future wheat improvement and genetic adaptation to increase yield potential under future climatic conditions in the UK and NZ. Recent advances in annotated reference wheat genome (
 <xref rid="bib0175" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">IWGSC, 2018</xref>), modern plant breeding technologies (e.g., wide crossing and resynthesis, molecular-marker-assisted breeding, QTL-mapping, genomics-assisted breeding, chemical and genetic modulation, gene-editing, etc.) (
 <xref rid="bib0030" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Breseghello and Coelho, 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0210" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kole et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0295" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Rauf et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib0300" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Reynolds et al., 2009</xref>) and the existence of large natural genetic variation in the target traits of wheat (
 <xref rid="tbl0015" ref-type="table" class="xref">Tables 3,4</xref>) could help plant breeders to breed desirable wheat cultivars based on ideotypes optimized for the target future climate. Constraints or difficulties in improving certain traits and achieving any given combinations physiologically or genetically could be incorporated in the optimization procedure by reducing the range for such parameters, or introducing dependencies between parameters.
</p>
