<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Feeds for domestic livestock</div>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Annual concentrate feed commodities for livestock increased from 373 million-tons dry matter (Mt DM) in 1961 to 1186 Mt DM in 2012 (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a</a>). The interannual variation of the feed could be due to many factors, such as market price of feed (supply-side) and livestock products (demand-side), climate (mainly supply-side), and even epidemic disease (demand-side). We will only focus on decadal average and long-term trend in this study. The feed model estimated that poultry and pigs consumed about half (53%) of the concentrate feeds in 1960s, the rest being for ruminants. In 2000s, 68% of the concentrate feeds were used for poultry and pig production against 32% for ruminants. The increasing share of concentrate feeds for poultry and pigs could be due to the larger increase in the production of poultry and pigs (increased by 11.9, 5.1, and 4.5-folds for poultry meat, eggs and pig meat production, respectively, between 1961 and 2012) compared with that of ruminant (increased by 2.1-fold between 1961 and 2012), and the farming intensity change. Annual concentrate feeds consumed by ruminants represented 213 Mt DM yr
  <span class="sup">−1</span> in the 1960s, peaked at 402 Mt DM yr
  <span class="sup">−1</span> in the 1980s and then decreased to 332 Mt DM yr
  <span class="sup">−1</span> in the 2000s. The C4 concentrate feeds comprise 35% (1980s) to 37% (1990s) of the total concentrate feed commodities for livestock.
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>The changes in concentrate feeds for poultry, pigs, and ruminants, and in the composition of feeds for ruminants over the period of 1961–2012. The concentrate feeds for poultry, pigs, and ruminants are presented as stacked area chart in (
     <span class="bold">a</span>). The feeds for ruminants are concentrates (including all crop concentrate feed commodities for ruminants, C3-based or C4-based), grass (including C3 and C4 grasses), and other feeds (i.e., stover and occasional including C3 and C4 part) following ref. 
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
     </span>. The light and dark green lines in (
     <span class="bold">b</span>) show the mean amount of C3 and C4 other feeds consumed by ruminants estimated in this study derived from Monte Carlo ensembles (
     <span class="italic">n</span> = 1000) from the range of uncertainty reported on feed digestibilities (i.e., 
     <span class="italic">f</span>
     <sub>DE-s+o</sub>, 
     <span class="italic">f</span>
     <sub>DE-concentrates</sub>, and 
     <span class="italic">f</span>
     <sub>DE-grass</sub>; see Methods section) and on the fraction of digestible energy available in diet used for maintenance (REMs; REM parameter values themselves dependent on 
     <span class="italic">f</span>
     <sub>DE</sub>; see Methods). The green shaded areas show the 95% confidence interval of the estimates. Source data are provided as a Source Data file
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2019_11066_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e1053" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">C3-based concentrate feeds constitute more than half of the ruminants’ concentrate feeds over the past five decades. The share of C4 in total ruminant’s concentrate feeds decreased from 43% in 1960s to 28% in 2000s. Concentrate feeds comprised only 8.0% [6.5–9.6%] of total dry matter consumption by ruminants in the 2000s, compared with 11.9% [9.9–13.9%] in the 1980s.</p>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Grass-biomass is the largest share of ruminants’ dry matter consumption comprising about 63% [52–74%] of the total dry matter intake. It is noteworthy that the share of C4 grasses in grass feed increased significantly from 24.3% in 1960s to 31.3% in 2000s mainly due to the rapid C4 grass feed increase in Latin America and Caribbean (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Other feeds represent the second largest share of total dry matter consumption by ruminants, ranging from 25.8% [14.0–38.4%] in 1980s to 29.1% [15.3–42.3%] in 2000s (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1b</a>). The share of C4 other feeds in total other feeds follows that of the grass feed, given the assumptions made in Methods (the C3:C4 ratio of other feeds the same as the ratio of grasses for each country).
 </p>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In total, the C4 diet of ruminant weighted by the fraction of each type of feed increased from 25.2% [24.8–25.8%] in the 1960s to 30.3% [30.2–30.4%] in the 2000s.</p>
</sec>
