<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par45" class="p">Predicting HeV spillover with the methods we used carries considerable uncertainty. Sources of uncertainty may be related to: (1) the type of presence only data used limits the number of analytical methods that can be used and hampers the identification of limiting factors; (2) the effects of climate on HeV spillover act at several different levels of ecological organisation and are not well understood, for instance temperature, humidity and ground vegetation might also limit the available pathways for HeV transmission to horses (Martin et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" class="xref">2017</xref>), and temperature can regulate the flowering status of native plants (Hudson et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">2010</xref>), the main source of food for flying foxes; (3) flying fox species distributions do not depend entirely on climate (Tidemann et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" class="xref">1999</xref>; Vardon et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71" class="xref">2001</xref>), but are greatly affected by native plant phenology (Giles et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">2016</xref>), and have an apparently innate preference for fragmented and urbanised landscapes (Tait et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" class="xref">2014</xref>); (4) the predicted distributions of flying foxes in response to climate change do not account for other organisms’ shifting distributions that affect bats’ distributions. Other organisms shifting distributions might give rise to novel and unpredictable interactions and effects on bats’ distributions (Eby et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">1999</xref>; Eby and Law 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">2008</xref>; Giles et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">2016</xref>); and (5) climate change could also affect horse behaviour and susceptibility to diseases. For instance, horses have limited thermal tolerance. Exceeding their comfort levels can alter their behaviour (Castanheira et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">2010</xref>) and increase the frequency of interaction with tree shaded areas (Jørgensen and Bøe 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" class="xref">2007</xref>), which is where HeV is usually excreted (Field et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">2011</xref>). All of these issues warrant further research to increase understanding of HeV epidemiology and bat virus spillover in general.
</p>
