<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Inequalities in access to resources can be seen across regions of even the wealthiest countries and across communities and neighborhoods within the same city (e.g., Shearer, 
 <xref rid="wcc565-bib-0151" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012a</xref>). In this context, a hazard such as a hurricane or drought only becomes a disaster when some groups lack the adaptive capacity to protect themselves from it. In other words, “natural” disasters are actually human disasters (Gaillard et al., 
 <xref rid="wcc565-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; O'Keefe, Westgate, &amp; Wisner, 
 <xref rid="wcc565-bib-0115" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1976</xref>; Wisner, 
 <xref rid="wcc565-bib-0176" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2001</xref>). When Superstorm Sandy hit New York and New Jersey in 2012, over 100 people were killed (Kunz et al., 
 <xref rid="wcc565-bib-0079" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). These deaths were concentrated among the elderly in part because they lacked access to healthcare and transportation (Kunz et al., 
 <xref rid="wcc565-bib-0079" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). By comparison, Hurricane Katrina killed about 1,800 people in the relatively impoverished coastal areas of Louisiana and Mississippi. Here too, a majority of the victims were elderly, but in New Orleans a large group was also poor and black, especially in the Lower Ninth Ward, close to where the levees were breached (Brunkard, Namulanda, &amp; Ratard, 
 <xref rid="wcc565-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>; Diakakis, Deligiannakis, Katsetsiadou, &amp; Lekkas, 
 <xref rid="wcc565-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Jonkman, Maaskant, Boyd, &amp; Levitan, 
 <xref rid="wcc565-bib-0072" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>). Hurricane Katrina only became a disaster because the neglected infrastructure failed, poverty and segregation were common in New Orleans, and many people lacked the resources to prepare for, avoid, and recover from the storm. Comparing the devastation caused by Hurricane Maria in Puerto Rico with that caused by Hurricane Harvey in Texas in 2017 provides another stark example of the social nature of disasters (Weiss, Lebrón, &amp; Chase, 
 <xref rid="wcc565-bib-0173" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2018</xref>). Puerto Rico was devastated and remained so several months later, while Texan communities were able to recover much more quickly.
</p>
