<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">These changes in synoptic activity have consequences not only for the mean precipitation but also for the extremes. Flooding over central and northern India is often associated with LPS activity (
 <xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r28" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>). Also, a recent increase in rainfall extremes over central India has been attributed to increased synoptic activity over that continental region (
 <xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r29" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>). 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig04" class="xref">Fig. 4
  <italic class="italic">D</italic>
 </xref> shows the climatology and the difference between RCP8.5 and HIST simulations of the 95th percentile of daily precipitation over the Indian region. The nonorographic precipitation extremes occur most frequently slightly south of the peak swath of synoptic activity (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" class="xref">Figs. 1
  <italic class="italic">A</italic>
 </xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" class="xref">2 
  <italic class="italic">A</italic> and 
  <italic class="italic">C</italic>
 </xref>), consistent with the fact that the peak precipitation in LPS typically occurs southwest of the vortex center (
 <xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>). The future changes in precipitation extremes over India reflect the changes in LPS activity, with a poleward shift clearly evident in the 95th percentile of precipitation (compare 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig04" class="xref">Figs. 4
  <italic class="italic">D</italic>
 </xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" class="xref">2 
  <italic class="italic">B</italic> and 
  <italic class="italic">D</italic>
 </xref>). One caveat is that GCMs with parameterized convection typically do not simulate extreme precipitation accurately, so such projections should be treated with caution. Also, we lack a long-term record of observed rainfall over the BoB that could be used to assess the fidelity of historical model simulations in that oceanic region.
</p>
