<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">This experiment was conducted six days after spawning, and tested the individual and interactive effects of temperature and salinity on larval settlement of 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">acuta</italic>. Experimental design followed those described in Chui and Ang [
 <xref rid="pone.0179423.ref018" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>]. Briefly, a factorial experimental design (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0179423.g001" class="xref">Fig 1</xref>) was employed with four levels of temperature (24, ambient 27, 30, 32°C) and six levels of salinity (ambient 33, 30, 26, 22, 18, 14 psu). The temperature range used encompasses current and future projected temperature conditions under global climate change. Temperature of 27°C is the mean ambient temperature of the spawning months in Hong Kong, whereas elevated temperature represents the average summer maximum in the study site (+3°C, i.e. 30°C) as well as an estimated increase in SST by 2100 (+5°C, i.e. 32°C) [
 <xref rid="pone.0179423.ref016" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. All water baths were regulated with chiller and heater to minimize daily temperature fluctuation. HOBO Temperature Pendant data loggers (Onset) were deployed in the water baths to record temperature at 30-min intervals. The levels of salinity employed also represented some realistic ranges recorded in Hong Kong waters. Low salinity ranges are usually recorded in western waters of Hong Kong where the influence of the Pearl River discharge is significant. Low salinity could also be recorded in eastern waters where most corals are found. For example, on May 2014, salinity of 26 psu persisted for more than a day throughout the coastal water column in the study area due to continuous discharge of underground seepage after a heavy downpour [
 <xref rid="pone.0179423.ref018" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>]. These low salinity ranges therefore represent potential scenarios that could be encountered by corals in Hong Kong.
</p>
