<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Regardless of the causes, the increased length of the marshes' growing season has a potentially important impact on the global carbon cycles. The extended growing seasons of the intermediate and brackish marshes directly reflect an increase in aboveground primary production (and possibly an increase in the belowground biomass; Langley et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35215-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>). On average, roughly 20% of the marshes net primary production results in carbon storage (Duarte &amp; Cebrian, 
 <xref rid="ece35215-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">1996</xref>). The increase in aboveground biomass allows for an increase in photosynthesis and CO
 <sub>2</sub> uptake, providing a negative feedback mechanism to the elevated atmospheric CO
 <sub>2</sub> and climate change. On the other hand, the loss of the brackish and saline marshes impairs the ecosystems' potential to capture CO
 <sub>2</sub> and the stability of the existing carbon storage, which is quite large in the coastal marsh anaerobic substrates (long‐term C accumulation rate at 18‐1713 g C m
 <sup>−2</sup> yr
 <sup>−1</sup>; McLeod et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35215-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>; Nahlik &amp; Fennessy, 
 <xref rid="ece35215-bib-0036" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>). The stored carbon will be released into the ocean or the atmosphere—which can also be in the form of methane, a more potent greenhouse gas, under the marshes' anaerobic conditions (Whiting &amp; Chanton, 
 <xref rid="ece35215-bib-0059" ref-type="ref">1993</xref>)—providing a positive feedback mechanism to climate change. The Louisiana coastal marshes are representatives of coastal ecosystems around the world experiencing various climatic and anthropogenic stressors (Bianchi &amp; Allison, 
 <xref rid="ece35215-bib-0002" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>; Wang et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35215-bib-0057" ref-type="ref">2007</xref>). This study documents the climate‐driven long‐term phenological shifts of the marshes that, in turn, provide a negative feedback mechanism to the changing climate. A stable coastal marsh system will capture and store more carbon under a changing climate, and compensate, to some extent, for anthropogenic carbon emissions. Such mechanisms highlight the marshes' critical role in climate mitigation and emphasize the importance of the conservation and restoration of coastal ecosystems under the changing climate.
</p>
