<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="jame20804-sec-0005" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Control of Global Mean Temperature and Aggregation by SST Gradients</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As soon as deep convection is triggered, local SST gradients of small amplitude appear, mainly because of the shadowing effect of deep convective clouds on the underlying surface and the increased surface evaporation they generate in their surrounding. But it is only once these SST gradients of small amplitude have reached a sufficiently large scale and force convection to move toward the warm regions that convective self‐aggregation is triggered (see section 
  <a rid="jame20804-sec-0011" ref-type="sec" href="#jame20804-sec-0011">5.1</a>). The amplitude of the SST gradients is so small that, when stratified by the large‐scale velocity at 500 hPa over the 300 days following the maximum of self‐aggregation, the SST is almost uniform (darkest red line in Figure 
  <a rid="jame20804-fig-0005" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20804-fig-0005">5</a>a). Then, the amplitude of SST gradients between convective and subsidence regimes increases almost linearly as the system cools down (red line in Figure 
  <a rid="jame20804-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20804-fig-0003">3</a>a). Note that a minimum fraction of low‐cloud fraction appears once convective aggregation generates a sufficiently strong subsidence in the subsiding regions (between 1.5 and 2.5 years in Figure 
  <a rid="jame20804-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20804-fig-0002">2</a>b).
 </p>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="jame20804-fig-0005" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 5</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>(a) Anomalies of surface temperature (relative to the globally averaged value) and (b) low‐cloud amount stratified by the vertical velocity at 500 hPa for simulation 1xCO
    <sub>2</sub>. (c) is the same as (a), and (d) is the same as (b) but for simulation 2xCO
    <sub>2</sub>. Colors follow time in each simulation but are reversed between the two simulations so that global mean surface temperature always increases from blue to red. For the 1xCO
    <sub>2</sub> simulation, the first time step indicated by the red line corresponds to the period just after self‐aggregation (beginning of “medium” period, after red dashed line in Figure 
    <a rid="jame20804-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20804-fig-0002">2</a>b). The 2xCO
    <sub>2</sub> starts from the beginning with the dark blue line. The mean global fraction of low clouds in the subsidence regions is specified in the box. Each line is a time average over 300 consecutive days. Dashed black arrows indicate the time evolution.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-9" xlink:href="JAME-10-3123-g005" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="alt-text">jame20804-fig-0005</span>
  </div>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Inspection of 1xCO
  <sub>2</sub> shows that the return to the equilibrium temperature of the reference simulation is made possible because of the increase in the low‐cloud fraction that occurs after a sufficiently large cooling (around Δ
  <span class="italic">T</span>
  <sub>S</sub>=+6 K, green line in Figure 
  <a rid="jame20804-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20804-fig-0003">3</a>a). At that time, the subsidence triggered by convective aggregation generates areas of strong static stability in the cold subsiding regions and promotes the formation of low clouds. Through their contribution to the planetary albedo, their shadowing effect on the underlying SST and their interaction with surface fluxes, the formation of these clouds enhances the cooling of the system and help temperature to go back to its equilibrium value.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To highlight the evolution of the SST contrast between convective and subsidence regions and its link to the low‐cloud fraction as the global climate cools in 1xCO
  <sub>2</sub> (from red to blue as time passes in Figures 
  <a rid="jame20804-fig-0005" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20804-fig-0005">5</a>a and 
  <a rid="jame20804-fig-0005" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20804-fig-0005">5</a>b), the low‐cloud fraction is stratified by the large‐scale vertical velocity at 500 hPa. The surface temperature first decreases almost uniformly while only a small amount of low clouds (∼6%) is present in the main subsiding regions (around 20–30 hPa/day in Figure 
  <a rid="jame20804-fig-0005" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20804-fig-0005">5</a>b). The presence of low clouds helps to cool the subsidence regions and then to increase the SST gradient between subsidence and convection regions. This likely triggers the formation of additional low clouds in the cold subsiding regions, which further strengthens the SST gradients. When the gradients become strong enough, the subsidence is amplified and further reinforces the cooling by increasing the amount of low clouds.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To summarize, depending on the impact of low clouds on the surface, the system can experience two different types of cooling: either a uniform cooling or a patterned cooling with subsiding regions cooling more than convective regions. Both types are at play in 1xCO
  <sub>2</sub>. When the system is forced to cool from very high global surface temperature (just after convective self‐aggregation; Figure 
  <a rid="jame20804-fig-0006" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20804-fig-0006">6</a>a), this cooling is initially almost uniform, until a small amount of low clouds can sufficiently cool the underlying surface and generate SST gradients. These newly formed gradients in turn favor the low‐cloud formation in some of the coldest regions of the domain (Figure 
  <a rid="jame20804-fig-0006" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20804-fig-0006">6</a>b). The formation of this small amount of low clouds is primarily due to the large‐scale circulation that emerges right after the triggering of self‐aggregation and that increases the static stability in subsiding regions. When low clouds develop further, they tend to cool the underlying surface and thus to increase the SST gradients, thereby reinforcing the large‐scale circulation that promoted their formation (Figure 
  <a rid="jame20804-fig-0006" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20804-fig-0006">6</a>c). This positive feedback leads to a stronger decrease of the temperature in the cold cloudy regions and decreases the global temperature until the system reaches equilibrium. This mechanism explains why the equilibrium temperature of the system is influenced by the changes in SST pattern.
 </p>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="jame20804-fig-0006" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 6</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>(a) Idealized large‐scale subsidence (arrow) forced by the emergence of convective aggregation and a sea surface temperature (SST) gradient of small amplitude (red line), with convection above warm SSTs and clear‐sky areas above cold SSTs. (b) Formation of boundary layer clouds over the cold, subsiding regions capped by a temperature inversion due to this large‐scale circulation while the system cools uniformly until it reaches a temperature where low clouds can influence the surface significantly and strengthen the SST gradients. (c) The increased SST gradient reinforces the large‐scale circulation and the low‐cloud amount over the cold subsiding regions, which cools the subsiding regions further, hence strengthening the spatial gradient of SST between convective and subsiding regions, as well as the large‐scale circulation.</p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-11" xlink:href="JAME-10-3123-g006" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="alt-text">jame20804-fig-0006</span>
  </div>
 </div>
</sec>
