<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="jame20804-sec-0003" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Interplay Between Aggregation and SST Gradients in 1CO
  <sub>2</sub> Climate
 </div>
 <sec id="jame20804-sec-0004" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Impact of Self‐Aggregation on Global Mean Surface Temperature</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To study the impact of self‐aggregation in 1CO
   <sub>2</sub> conditions, we start with disaggregated convection. Right after the homogenization at 
   <span class="italic">t</span> = 0, the aggregation index SF is equal to 0.5 (Figures 
   <a rid="jame20804-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20804-fig-0002">2</a>a and 
   <a rid="jame20804-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#jame20804-supitem-0001">S3</a>a). Because homogenizing the atmosphere induces a strong energetic disequilibrium, as long as convection remains disaggregated, the surface temperature increases rapidly. At some point, deep convection is triggered and rapidly self‐aggregates (blue lines in Figures 
   <a rid="jame20804-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20804-fig-0002">2</a>a, 
   <a rid="jame20804-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20804-fig-0002">2</a>b, and 
   <a rid="jame20804-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#jame20804-supitem-0001">S4</a>a).
  </p>
  <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="jame20804-fig-0002" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>(a) Time evolution of surface temperature (red) and aggregation (SF, in blue) for the reference simulation and in 1xCO
     <sub>2</sub>. The vertical black line indicates the time when the sea surface temperature, 
     <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">q</span>, 
     <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">T</span>, 
     <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">u</span>, and 
     <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">v</span> are spatially averaged. (b) Zoom over the first 10 years of 1xCO
     <sub>2</sub>. The low‐cloud fraction in the subsiding regions (green) and the vertical velocity at 500 hPa (black) in those regions are also reported. We call subsiding regions all model grid points where the vertical velocity at 500 hPa is positive. Shadings around the temperature line represent the 25th and 75th percentiles of the surface temperature. The vertical dashed blue and red lines indicate the start of self‐aggregation and the beginning of the decrease in surface temperature, respectively. The periods noted as “early,” “medium,” and “late” are positioned over different periods to emphasize more easily the different transitions in Figures 
     <a rid="jame20804-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20804-fig-0003">3</a> and 
     <a rid="jame20804-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20804-fig-0004">4</a>. SF = subsiding fraction.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div id="nlm-graphic-3" xlink:href="JAME-10-3123-g002" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <span class="alt-text">jame20804-fig-0002</span>
   </div>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Before self‐aggregation occurs (phase called “early”), the surface temperature rises uniformly and 
   <span class="italic">σ</span>
   <sub>
    <span class="italic">T</span>
    <span class="italic">s</span>
   </sub>, the spatial standard deviation of SST over the globe (our proxy for SST gradients) remains very low (red line in Figures 
   <a rid="jame20804-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20804-fig-0003">3</a>a and 
   <a rid="jame20804-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#jame20804-supitem-0001">S3</a>a). The radiative imbalance at the top of the atmosphere Δ
   <span class="italic">R</span> decreases slowly (green dashed line in Figures 
   <a rid="jame20804-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20804-fig-0004">4</a>a and 
   <a rid="jame20804-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#jame20804-supitem-0001">S6</a>). As soon as self‐aggregation is triggered (blue line going up in Figure 
   <a rid="jame20804-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20804-fig-0003">3</a>a), Δ
   <span class="italic">R</span> exhibits a large drop that precedes a rapid decrease in global mean surface temperature, suggesting a strong cooling effect of self‐aggregation. Indeed, as soon as aggregation is maximum, the global mean surface temperature drops (Figure 
   <a rid="jame20804-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20804-fig-0002">2</a>b). This is consistent with the findings of Hohenegger and Stevens (
   <a rid="jame20804-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20804-bib-0020">2016</a>) obtained using another GCM. As temperature decreases back to the equilibrium temperature of the reference simulation, SF also starts to decrease until it goes back to the reference temperature level, suggesting a role of convective aggregation in the regulation of temperature, at least under certain conditions.
  </p>
  <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="jame20804-fig-0003" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>(a) Evolution of 
     <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">σ</span>
     <sub>
      <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">T</span>
      <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">s</span>
     </sub> (red), convective aggregation SF (blue), and the low‐cloud fraction in subsiding regions 
     <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">f</span>
     <sub>
      <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">L</span>
     </sub> (green) as a function of Δ
     <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">T</span>
     <sub>
      <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">S</span>
     </sub> (difference between the surface temperature of the simulation and the equilibrium temperature of the reference simulation) in 1xCO
     <sub>2</sub>. b) Same as (a) but in 2xCO
     <sub>2</sub>. Δ
     <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">T</span>
     <sub>
      <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">S</span>
     </sub> is calculated as the difference between the surface temperature of 2xCO
     <sub>2</sub> and the equilibrium temperature of 1xCO
     <sub>2</sub>. 
     <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">σ</span>
     <sub>
      <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">T</span>
      <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">s</span>
     </sub>, SF, and 
     <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">f</span>
     <sub>
      <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">L</span>
     </sub> are binned by sea surface temperature warming (bin size of 0.4 K, based on monthly averaged data). For 1xCO
     <sub>2</sub>, the binning process is done separately for the periods before and after self‐aggregation. The dashed lines in (a) are linear regressions designed to emphasize the transitions in low‐cloud fraction and subsiding fraction. The vertical dashed gray line in (b) indicates the ECS of the 2xCO
     <sub>2</sub> simulation. The gray area around the ECS shows the range of temperature where the system is dominated by the internal variability around equilibrium and convective aggregation is out of phase with global mean surface temperature (cf. Coppin &amp; Bony, 
     <a rid="jame20804-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20804-bib-0011">2017</a>). The periods named early, medium, and late are the same as in Figure 
     <a rid="jame20804-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20804-fig-0002">2</a>. SF = subsiding fraction; ECS = equilibrium climate sensitivity.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div id="nlm-graphic-5" xlink:href="JAME-10-3123-g003" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <span class="alt-text">jame20804-fig-0003</span>
   </div>
  </div>
  <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="jame20804-fig-0004" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Figure 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Evolution of Δ
     <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">R</span> as a function of Δ
     <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">T</span>
     <sub>
      <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">S</span>
     </sub> for (a) 1xCO
     <sub>2</sub> and (b) 2xCO
     <sub>2</sub>. Δ
     <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">R</span> is binned by sea surface temperature anomaly (using monthly data and bins of 0.4 K). For 1xCO
     <sub>2</sub>, Δ
     <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">T</span>
     <sub>
      <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">S</span>
     </sub> and Δ
     <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">R</span> are calculated as differences with the equilibrium of the reference simulation. For 2xCO
     <sub>2</sub>, they are relative to the equilibrium of the 1xCO
     <sub>2</sub> simulation. The size of the black circles indicates the number of points included in each bin. For 1xCO
     <sub>2</sub>, the binning process is done separately for the periods before and after self‐aggregation. The colored dashed lines correspond to linear regression over different parts of 1xCO
     <sub>2</sub> (early, medium, and late, respectively). Dashed lines of the same color have the same slope (see Table 
     <a rid="jame20804-tbl-0002" ref-type="table" href="#jame20804-tbl-0002">2</a>). The linear regression for 2xCO
     <sub>2</sub> is calculated over the first 10 years to avoid the equilibrium period during which Δ
     <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">R</span> is dominated by internal variability (gray area). Identical color indicates the same value. All coefficient values and standard deviation (W/m
     <span class="sup">2</span>/K) are calculated over the ensembles (Figures 
     <a rid="jame20804-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#jame20804-supitem-0001">S6</a> and 
     <a rid="jame20804-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#jame20804-supitem-0001">S7</a>).
    </p>
   </div>
   <div id="nlm-graphic-7" xlink:href="JAME-10-3123-g004" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <span class="alt-text">jame20804-fig-0004</span>
   </div>
  </div>
 </sec>
 <sec id="jame20804-sec-0005" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Control of Global Mean Temperature and Aggregation by SST Gradients</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As soon as deep convection is triggered, local SST gradients of small amplitude appear, mainly because of the shadowing effect of deep convective clouds on the underlying surface and the increased surface evaporation they generate in their surrounding. But it is only once these SST gradients of small amplitude have reached a sufficiently large scale and force convection to move toward the warm regions that convective self‐aggregation is triggered (see section 
   <a rid="jame20804-sec-0011" ref-type="sec" href="#jame20804-sec-0011">5.1</a>). The amplitude of the SST gradients is so small that, when stratified by the large‐scale velocity at 500 hPa over the 300 days following the maximum of self‐aggregation, the SST is almost uniform (darkest red line in Figure 
   <a rid="jame20804-fig-0005" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20804-fig-0005">5</a>a). Then, the amplitude of SST gradients between convective and subsidence regimes increases almost linearly as the system cools down (red line in Figure 
   <a rid="jame20804-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20804-fig-0003">3</a>a). Note that a minimum fraction of low‐cloud fraction appears once convective aggregation generates a sufficiently strong subsidence in the subsiding regions (between 1.5 and 2.5 years in Figure 
   <a rid="jame20804-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20804-fig-0002">2</a>b).
  </p>
  <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="jame20804-fig-0005" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Figure 5</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>(a) Anomalies of surface temperature (relative to the globally averaged value) and (b) low‐cloud amount stratified by the vertical velocity at 500 hPa for simulation 1xCO
     <sub>2</sub>. (c) is the same as (a), and (d) is the same as (b) but for simulation 2xCO
     <sub>2</sub>. Colors follow time in each simulation but are reversed between the two simulations so that global mean surface temperature always increases from blue to red. For the 1xCO
     <sub>2</sub> simulation, the first time step indicated by the red line corresponds to the period just after self‐aggregation (beginning of “medium” period, after red dashed line in Figure 
     <a rid="jame20804-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20804-fig-0002">2</a>b). The 2xCO
     <sub>2</sub> starts from the beginning with the dark blue line. The mean global fraction of low clouds in the subsidence regions is specified in the box. Each line is a time average over 300 consecutive days. Dashed black arrows indicate the time evolution.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div id="nlm-graphic-9" xlink:href="JAME-10-3123-g005" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <span class="alt-text">jame20804-fig-0005</span>
   </div>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Inspection of 1xCO
   <sub>2</sub> shows that the return to the equilibrium temperature of the reference simulation is made possible because of the increase in the low‐cloud fraction that occurs after a sufficiently large cooling (around Δ
   <span class="italic">T</span>
   <sub>S</sub>=+6 K, green line in Figure 
   <a rid="jame20804-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20804-fig-0003">3</a>a). At that time, the subsidence triggered by convective aggregation generates areas of strong static stability in the cold subsiding regions and promotes the formation of low clouds. Through their contribution to the planetary albedo, their shadowing effect on the underlying SST and their interaction with surface fluxes, the formation of these clouds enhances the cooling of the system and help temperature to go back to its equilibrium value.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To highlight the evolution of the SST contrast between convective and subsidence regions and its link to the low‐cloud fraction as the global climate cools in 1xCO
   <sub>2</sub> (from red to blue as time passes in Figures 
   <a rid="jame20804-fig-0005" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20804-fig-0005">5</a>a and 
   <a rid="jame20804-fig-0005" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20804-fig-0005">5</a>b), the low‐cloud fraction is stratified by the large‐scale vertical velocity at 500 hPa. The surface temperature first decreases almost uniformly while only a small amount of low clouds (∼6%) is present in the main subsiding regions (around 20–30 hPa/day in Figure 
   <a rid="jame20804-fig-0005" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20804-fig-0005">5</a>b). The presence of low clouds helps to cool the subsidence regions and then to increase the SST gradient between subsidence and convection regions. This likely triggers the formation of additional low clouds in the cold subsiding regions, which further strengthens the SST gradients. When the gradients become strong enough, the subsidence is amplified and further reinforces the cooling by increasing the amount of low clouds.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To summarize, depending on the impact of low clouds on the surface, the system can experience two different types of cooling: either a uniform cooling or a patterned cooling with subsiding regions cooling more than convective regions. Both types are at play in 1xCO
   <sub>2</sub>. When the system is forced to cool from very high global surface temperature (just after convective self‐aggregation; Figure 
   <a rid="jame20804-fig-0006" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20804-fig-0006">6</a>a), this cooling is initially almost uniform, until a small amount of low clouds can sufficiently cool the underlying surface and generate SST gradients. These newly formed gradients in turn favor the low‐cloud formation in some of the coldest regions of the domain (Figure 
   <a rid="jame20804-fig-0006" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20804-fig-0006">6</a>b). The formation of this small amount of low clouds is primarily due to the large‐scale circulation that emerges right after the triggering of self‐aggregation and that increases the static stability in subsiding regions. When low clouds develop further, they tend to cool the underlying surface and thus to increase the SST gradients, thereby reinforcing the large‐scale circulation that promoted their formation (Figure 
   <a rid="jame20804-fig-0006" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20804-fig-0006">6</a>c). This positive feedback leads to a stronger decrease of the temperature in the cold cloudy regions and decreases the global temperature until the system reaches equilibrium. This mechanism explains why the equilibrium temperature of the system is influenced by the changes in SST pattern.
  </p>
  <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="jame20804-fig-0006" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Figure 6</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>(a) Idealized large‐scale subsidence (arrow) forced by the emergence of convective aggregation and a sea surface temperature (SST) gradient of small amplitude (red line), with convection above warm SSTs and clear‐sky areas above cold SSTs. (b) Formation of boundary layer clouds over the cold, subsiding regions capped by a temperature inversion due to this large‐scale circulation while the system cools uniformly until it reaches a temperature where low clouds can influence the surface significantly and strengthen the SST gradients. (c) The increased SST gradient reinforces the large‐scale circulation and the low‐cloud amount over the cold subsiding regions, which cools the subsiding regions further, hence strengthening the spatial gradient of SST between convective and subsiding regions, as well as the large‐scale circulation.</p>
   </div>
   <div id="nlm-graphic-11" xlink:href="JAME-10-3123-g006" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <span class="alt-text">jame20804-fig-0006</span>
   </div>
  </div>
 </sec>
 <sec id="jame20804-sec-0006" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.3</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Modulation of Climate Feedback by SST Gradients</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The 1xCO
   <sub>2</sub> simulation gives us the opportunity to estimate the total feedback parameter 
   <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">λ</span>. We estimate it using a Gregory‐like approach (Gregory et al., 
   <a rid="jame20804-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20804-bib-0019">2004</a>), that is, by calculating the slope of the linear regression between Δ
   <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">R</span> and Δ
   <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">T</span>
   <sub>
    <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">S</span>
   </sub> (lines in Figure 
   <a rid="jame20804-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20804-fig-0004">4</a>a). As long as self‐aggregation is not triggered, the system is transitioning toward an equilibrium without convective aggregation: the radiative imbalance Δ
   <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">R</span>, which is maximum after the homogenization of the atmosphere decreases while temperature increases (early period, the slope of the green dashed line representing 
   <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">λ</span>). After the triggering of self‐aggregation, aggregation remains constant and strong for 2 years while the SST gradients increase and the system cools down (medium period). Once the low‐cloud amount is large enough in the subsiding regions, convective aggregation decreases and 
   <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">λ</span> changes (“late” period).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To isolate the relative influences of SST gradients and convective aggregation on the feedback parameter, we decompose it into three components. The first one does not depend on SST gradients nor aggregation. This “background” feedback, which includes other feedbacks such as the Planck response, water vapor, lapse‐rate, and cloud feedbacks, corresponds to the green line with 
   <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">λ</span>=−1.42 ± 0.02 W/m
   <span class="sup">2</span>/K in Figure 
   <a rid="jame20804-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20804-fig-0004">4</a>a. The second component includes in addition the effect of SST gradients (blue line), and the third one includes the background feedback, the feedback from SST gradients, and the feedback associated with the interaction of convective aggregation with the SST gradients (red line).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To calculate the second component (background plus SST gradient feedback), we focus on the lower right branch of 1xCO
   <sub>2</sub> where convective aggregation and low clouds are constant but the SST gradients increase (between 6 and 8 K in Figure 
   <a rid="jame20804-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20804-fig-0003">3</a>a). This medium period lasts only 2 years in the example shown and even less in the other members of the ensemble (Figures 
   <a rid="jame20804-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#jame20804-supitem-0001">S4</a>a and 
   <a rid="jame20804-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#jame20804-supitem-0001">S5</a>a). During this period, the net feedback parameter is positive and equal to +1.32 ± 0.20 W/m
   <span class="sup">2</span>/K (blue line in Figure 
   <a rid="jame20804-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20804-fig-0004">4</a>a). Assuming that the background feedback remains similar implies that the positive feedback associated with the buildup of SST gradients is +2.74 W/m
   <span class="sup">2</span>/K. This positive feedback may come from a reorganization of the circulation while aggregation remains constant.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To infer the feedback associated with convective aggregation (see Appendix 
   <a rid="jame20804-app-0001" ref-type="app" href="#jame20804-app-0001">A</a> for an attempt to conceptualize the impact of aggregation on global mean surface temperature), we consider the red line in Figure 
   <a rid="jame20804-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20804-fig-0004">4</a>a (part late). Assuming that the combined effect of the background plus the SST gradients remains similar, the negative feedback necessary to get the total climate feedback is the difference between the total feedback and this combined feedback (blue line), namely −1.20–1.32 = −2.52 W/m
   <span class="sup">2</span>/K, the feedback due to aggregation changes. Since this value also includes the low‐cloud positive feedback that occurs when SST gets cooler, that is, below the 6 K warming in 1xCO
   <sub>2</sub> (green line in Figure 
   <a rid="jame20804-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20804-fig-0003">3</a>a), we expect the negative feedback of aggregation changes on temperature to be even stronger. However, in a coupled system with interactive SST gradients and preindustrial CO
   <sub>2</sub> conditions, its impact is more than compensated by the positive feedback associated with the change in SST pattern and low‐cloud feedbacks (−2.52 vs. +2.74 W/m
   <span class="sup">2</span>/K).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The question now arises whether this behavior is representative of a changing climate perturbed by an increase in greenhouse gases in the atmosphere. To answer this question, we analyze a 2xCO
   <sub>2</sub> experiment.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
