<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="jame20804-sec-0011" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">5.1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Faster Self‐Aggregation</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The 1CO
  <sub>2</sub> ensembles of simulations run with or without SST gradients start from uniform conditions and without any large‐scale circulation. As long as a large‐scale circulation does not develop, the surface temperature remains nearly homogeneous, even when SST gradients are free to develop, and the two ensembles of simulations are almost identical (first months in Figure 
  <a rid="jame20804-fig-0008" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20804-fig-0008">8</a>). They start to diverge as soon as deep convection and a large‐scale circulation emerge, and promotes the development of SST gradients. In 1xCO
  <sub>2</sub>uni, convective aggregation increases very quickly and reaches a maximum shortly after the start of the self‐aggregation process. In contrast, in 1xCO
  <sub>2</sub>, aggregation increases more slowly and therefore the system keeps warming for a longer time until aggregation reaches its maximum and temperature starts to decrease.
 </p>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="jame20804-fig-0008" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 8</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Same as Figure 
    <a rid="jame20804-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20804-fig-0002">2</a> but for 1xCO
    <sub>2</sub> (plain line) and 1xCO
    <sub>2</sub>uni (dashed lines). SF = subsiding fraction.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-15" xlink:href="JAME-10-3123-g008" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="alt-text">jame20804-fig-0008</span>
  </div>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This different behavior between 1xCO
  <sub>2</sub> and 1xCO
  <sub>2</sub>uni is directly related to the emergence of SST gradients in 1xCO
  <sub>2</sub>once deep convection is triggered. The ocean below convective clouds cools down, mainly because of the shadowing effect of clouds on the surface and the increase in evaporation in the vicinity, thus favoring the emergence of SST gradients. The slight cooling of SST under convective clouds relative to non‐convective areas generates a circulation that opposes the shallow circulation that gives rise to convective self‐aggregation (Hohenegger &amp; Stevens, 
  <a rid="jame20804-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20804-bib-0020">2016</a>). It becomes harder for convection to self‐aggregate, hence the delayed self‐aggregation. It is only when SST gradients cover a sufficiently large area of the domain that convection moves toward the warmest SSTs and that the system starts to cool.
 </p>
</sec>
