<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="jame20804-sec-0012" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">5.2</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Impact on Climate Feedbacks</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Even though the system in 1xCO
  <sub>2</sub>uni stabilizes at a much higher global temperature than 1xCO
  <sub>2</sub> (warmer by 4 K, Figure 
  <a rid="jame20804-fig-0008" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20804-fig-0008">8</a>), the initial cooling following self‐aggregation is qualitatively similar to the uniform cooling that happens over the medium period in 1xCO
  <sub>2</sub>, as shown by Figures 
  <a rid="jame20804-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20804-fig-0003">3</a>a and 
  <a rid="jame20804-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#jame20804-supitem-0001">S5</a>a–
  <a rid="jame20804-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#jame20804-supitem-0001">S5</a>c. Both ensembles diverge when the SST gradients become strong enough to increase the subsidence velocity and the low‐cloud cover in 1xCO
  <sub>2</sub> (black and green lines in Figure 
  <a rid="jame20804-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#jame20804-supitem-0001">S4</a>) and activate the feedback loop that leads to a further cooling of the system. This emphasizes the importance of SST gradients for the regulation of the global mean surface temperature of the coupled ocean‐atmosphere system.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When the CO
  <sub>2</sub> concentration is abruptly doubled from the equilibrium of 1xCO
  <sub>2</sub>uni, the global surface temperature increases by 2 K while convection aggregation (SF) remains constant (Figure 
  <a rid="jame20804-fig-0009" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20804-fig-0009">9</a>). This saturation of convective aggregation at a very high value, as well as the way it is organized, is reminiscent of what happens at high surface temperature with prescribed uniform SSTs. The calculation of 
  <div id="nlm-math-20" class="math">
   <div class="msub">
    <div class="mrow">
     <div separators="" open="(" close=")" class="mfenced">
      <div class="mrow">
       <div class="mfrac">
        <div class="mrow">
         <span class="mi">∂</span>
         <span class="mtext">SF</span>
        </div>
        <div class="mrow">
         <span class="mi">∂</span>
         <div class="msub">
          <span class="mi">T</span>
          <span class="mi">S</span>
         </div>
        </div>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
    <div class="mrow">
     <div class="msub">
      <span class="mtext">CO</span>
      <span class="mn">2</span>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div> and 
  <div id="nlm-math-21" class="math">
   <div class="msub">
    <div class="mrow">
     <div separators="" open="(" close=")" class="mfenced">
      <div class="mrow">
       <div class="mfrac">
        <div class="mrow">
         <span class="mi">∂</span>
         <span class="mtext">SF</span>
        </div>
        <div class="mrow">
         <span class="mi">∂</span>
         <div class="msub">
          <span class="mtext">CO</span>
          <span class="mn">2</span>
         </div>
        </div>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
    <div class="mrow">
     <div class="msub">
      <span class="mi">T</span>
      <span class="mi">S</span>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div> (0.1×10
  <span class="sup">−2</span> K
  <span class="sup">−1</span> and 0.1×10
  <span class="sup">−1</span> [CO
  <sub>2</sub>]
  <span class="sup">−1</span>, respectively, Table 
  <a rid="jame20804-tbl-0002" ref-type="table" href="#jame20804-tbl-0002">2</a>) confirms that, in the absence of SST gradients, convective aggregation behaves like in experiments with prescribed uniform SSTs (section 
  <a rid="jame20804-sec-0008" ref-type="sec" href="#jame20804-sec-0008">4.1</a>), thus confirming that simulations with SST gradients exhibit a weaker direct effect of CO
  <sub>2</sub> but a stronger sensitivity to temperature.
 </p>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="jame20804-fig-0009" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 9</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Time evolution of surface temperature (red) and aggregation (SF, in blue) for the end of 1xCO
    <sub>2</sub>uni and 2xCO
    <sub>2</sub>uni. The vertical black line indicates the time when the CO
    <sub>2</sub> is abruptly doubled at the beginning of 2xCO
    <sub>2</sub>uni. (b) Evolution of convective aggregation SF (blue) and the low‐cloud fraction in subsiding regions 
    <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">f</span>
    <sub>
     <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">L</span>
    </sub> (green) as a function of Δ
    <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">T</span>
    <sub>
     <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">S</span>
    </sub> (difference between the surface temperature of the simulation and the equilibrium temperature of 1xCO
    <sub>2</sub>uni) for the simulation 2xCO
    <sub>2</sub>uni. (c) Same as Figure 
    <a rid="jame20804-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20804-fig-0004">4</a> but for 2xCO
    <sub>2</sub>uni. Δ
    <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">T</span>
    <sub>
     <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">S</span>
    </sub> is calculated as the difference between the surface temperature of 2xCO
    <sub>2</sub>uni and the equilibrium temperature of 1xCO
    <sub>2</sub>uni. SF, 
    <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">f</span>
    <sub>
     <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">L</span>
    </sub>, Δ
    <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">R</span>, and Δ
    <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">T</span>
    <sub>
     <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">S</span>
    </sub> are binned by sea surface temperature warming (bin size of 0.4 K with monthly averaged data). The green dashed line corresponds to 
    <span style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">λ</span> = −1.43 W/m
    <span class="sup">2</span>/K. SF = subsiding fraction.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-17" xlink:href="JAME-10-3123-g009" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="alt-text">jame20804-fig-0009</span>
  </div>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Convective aggregation does not increase further with temperature. Yet the climate feedback parameter 
  <span class="italic">λ</span> = −1.42 W/m
  <span class="sup">2</span>/K is more negative in 2xCO
  <sub>2</sub>uni than in 2xCO
  <sub>2</sub>, leading to a lower ECS (2 K compared to 2.5 K in 2xCO
  <sub>2</sub>). The slope of the green dashed lines in Figures 
  <a rid="jame20804-fig-0009" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20804-fig-0009">9</a>c and 
  <a rid="jame20804-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20804-fig-0004">4</a>a (or Figures 
  <a rid="jame20804-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#jame20804-supitem-0001">S8</a> and 
  <a rid="jame20804-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#jame20804-supitem-0001">S9</a>) suggests that it does not result from a dependence on the mean state. On the other hand, even if the low‐cloud fraction is still decreasing in 2xCO
  <sub>2</sub>uni (Figure 
  <a rid="jame20804-fig-0009" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20804-fig-0009">9</a>b), its decrease rate is weaker than in 2xCO
  <sub>2</sub> (Figure 
  <a rid="jame20804-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#jame20804-fig-0003">3</a>b). Low clouds are less sensitive to the increase in surface temperature when SST gradients are absent. This results in a much smaller positive low‐cloud feedback in the absence of SST gradients (no robust positive trend emerges) than with SST gradients: 0.5 W/m
  <span class="sup">2</span>/K in 2xCO
  <sub>2</sub> (not shown). The total climate feedback is thus more negative and the ECS lower in 2xCO
  <sub>2</sub>uni compared to 2xCO
  <sub>2</sub>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">These findings emphasize the fact that the coupling of the atmosphere with SST fundamentally affects the system's response to a global increase in surface temperature. The framework with uniform but evolving SST shares a lot of similarities with the prescribed and uniform high SST simulations: same organization of convection, saturation of convective aggregation for high SST, stronger dependence of aggregation on CO
  <sub>2</sub> rather than on surface temperature, and same large‐scale circulation. On the contrary, the framework with interactive SST is more representative of less idealized setups (Figure 
  <a rid="jame20804-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#jame20804-supitem-0001">S2</a>). This study thus casts doubt on the ability of the prescribed SST framework to correctly assess the impact of convective aggregation on the climate sensitivity, at least for our model.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Yet a large literature has shown how relevant prescribed SST frameworks can be to interpret climate feedbacks in coupled frameworks (e.g; Brient &amp; Bony, 
  <a rid="jame20804-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20804-bib-0007">2013</a>; Ringer et al., 
  <a rid="jame20804-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20804-bib-0029">2014</a>). One possible explanation for this apparent contradiction could be the saturation of convective aggregation at high SST in our model. The prescribed SST framework might still be relevant to assess the impact of convective aggregation on climate in other models where this saturation does not occur or even at smaller SSTs when convective aggregation is not saturated (for models where it will saturate at higher SST). As a matter of fact, in our model, the organization of convection at these smaller SSTs is more similar across configurations (see Figures 2.7 and 2.8 of Coppin, 
  <a rid="jame20804-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20804-bib-0009">2017</a>, for the same comparison as in section 
  <a rid="jame20804-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#jame20804-supitem-0001">S1</a> between the reference simulation, a prescribed and uniform SST of 298 K, the AMIP (Atmospheric Model Intercomparison Project) simulation over the tropical oceans and AquaControl over the tropics). To answer this contradiction, the impact of convective aggregation on climate should be investigated with other models in coupled frameworks.
 </p>
</sec>
