<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="jame20804-sec-0001" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An important metric for climate change studies is the equilibrium change in global mean near‐surface air temperature that would result from a sustained doubling of the atmospheric carbon dioxide concentration, a quantity referred to as the equilibrium climate sensitivity (ECS). Although a precise estimate of the ECS has remained elusive for almost four decades (Charney et al., 
  <a rid="jame20804-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20804-bib-0008">1979</a>; Stevens et al., 
  <a rid="jame20804-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20804-bib-0031">2016</a>), much progress has been made in understanding the different physical processes that control it. In particular, recent studies have pointed out two factors that could modulate the strength of the water vapor and cloud feedbacks and therefore affect ECS. One of them is the role of convective organization (Holloway et al., 
  <a rid="jame20804-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20804-bib-0021">2017</a>; Wing et al., 
  <a rid="jame20804-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20804-bib-0033">2017</a>). As first hypothesized by Khairoutdinov and Emanuel (
  <a rid="jame20804-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20804-bib-0024">2010</a>) with a toy model, the ability of deep convection to aggregate into clusters and to extend the area covered by clear, dry regions, would enhance the ability of the Earth to radiate heat to space and would lower ECS (Hohenegger &amp; Stevens, 
  <a rid="jame20804-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20804-bib-0020">2016</a>; Pierrehumbert, 
  <a rid="jame20804-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20804-bib-0028">1995</a>). Recently, Cronin and Wing (
  <a rid="jame20804-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20804-bib-0012">2017</a>) confirmed that this effect exists in cloud‐resolving model channel radiative‐convective equilibrium (RCE) simulations. Whether this mechanism also affects ECS in general circulation models (GCMs) remains an open issue (Mauritsen &amp; Stevens, 
  <a rid="jame20804-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20804-bib-0025">2015</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another factor that can influence ECS but remains poorly understood is the evolution of spatial patterns of sea surface temperature (SST) with global warming (Senior &amp; Mitchell, 
  <a rid="jame20804-bib-0030" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20804-bib-0030">2000</a>), an effect now referred to as “pattern effect” (Stevens et al., 
  <a rid="jame20804-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20804-bib-0031">2016</a>). Depending on where and when a change in surface temperature takes place, it can exert a different radiative impact and strongly amplify or dampen the radiative feedbacks. This pattern effect, which is present in many models, has been shown to strongly influence cloud feedbacks and to induce an apparent time dependence of climate feedbacks (Andrews et al., 
  <a rid="jame20804-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20804-bib-0002">2012</a>; Armour et al., 
  <a rid="jame20804-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20804-bib-0003">2013</a>; Block &amp; Mauritsen, 
  <a rid="jame20804-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20804-bib-0004">2013</a>; Zhou et al., 
  <a rid="jame20804-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20804-bib-0034">2016</a>). In particular, it is thought to be partly responsible for the apparent discrepancy between the ECS estimates inferred from historical climate records and the estimates derived from long‐term climate change experiments from GCMs (Armour et al., 
  <a rid="jame20804-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20804-bib-0003">2013</a>; Gregory &amp; Andrews, 
  <a rid="jame20804-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20804-bib-0018">2016</a>). Studies exploring the role of convective aggregation in climate sensitivity using the RCE framework often use prescribed and spatially uniform SST (Cronin &amp; Wing, 
  <a rid="jame20804-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20804-bib-0012">2017</a>). The question thus arises as to whether, and how, the impact of convective aggregation on climate sensitivity might depend on SST patterns. The question arises all the more that Coppin and Bony (
  <a rid="jame20804-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" href="#jame20804-bib-0011">2017</a>) showed that convective aggregation and SST patterns can actually be closely coupled.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The aim of this paper is to use a GCM to explore how the interaction between SST gradients and convective aggregation modulates climate feedbacks and impacts the climate sensitivity in the idealized framework of RCE. We describe the experimental setup and the different experiments (section 
  <a rid="jame20804-sec-0002" ref-type="sec" href="#jame20804-sec-0002">2</a>), look at the behavior of the simulation with SST gradients in 1CO
  <sub>2</sub> conditions and after an abrupt doubling of CO
  <sub>2</sub> (section 
  <a rid="jame20804-sec-0003" ref-type="sec" href="#jame20804-sec-0003">3</a> and 
  <a rid="jame20804-sec-0007" ref-type="sec" href="#jame20804-sec-0007">4</a>), before discussing in more details the role of SST gradients on convective aggregation and climate sensitivity (section 
  <a rid="jame20804-sec-0010" ref-type="sec" href="#jame20804-sec-0010">5</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
