<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="S0004" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on the results of previous studies, Iranian patients with type 2 diabetes were not entirely satisfied with the health-care services provided, and suffered from irreversible complications that were partly due to defects in their health care.
  <a rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0032">32</a>,
  <a rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0033">33</a>,
  <a rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0044">44</a>–
  <a rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0046">46</a> The existence of a standard tool to identify the extent of support provided by HCPs for patients with type 2 diabetes could help these patients and contribute toward the effective implementation and impact evaluation of intervention programs.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The main purpose of this study was to investigate the psychometric properties of the HCCQ-P and assess its potential applicability in studies on the supportiveness of health-care delivery environments for health behavior change in patients with type 2 diabetes. The health-care climate is considered as one of the most influential elements in motivating behavioral change in patients with chronic diseases.
  <a rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0005">5</a>,
  <a rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0007">7</a>–
  <a rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0009">9</a> In addition, the use of the HCCQ in health-care environments can reduce the incidence of disease complications by positively affecting clinical results and improving health outcomes, especially the control of blood glucose levels and decrease in Hb
  <sub>A1c</sub> levels.
  <a rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0007">7</a>,
  <a rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0047">47</a>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As the distribution of the study attendants’ major sociodemographic characteristics was sought to be representative of the largest population of Iranian patients with type 2 diabetes, the study results demonstrate the applicability of the HCCQ-P as a suitable instrument for assessing the degree of health-care climate supportiveness for Iranian patients with type 2 diabetes. The psychometric analysis of the HCCQ-P on the studied Iranian patients produced similar results to the findings of previous studies on psychometric assessment of the HCCQ in France,
  <a rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0014">
   <span class="sup">14</span>
  </a> the USA,
  <a rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0030">
   <span class="sup">30</span>
  </a> the Netherlands
  <a rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0018">18</a>,
  <a rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0024">24</a> and Germany
  <a rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0019">.
   <span class="sup">19</span>
  </a>
 </p>
 <sec id="S0004-S2001" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Content validity</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The translated Persian version of the HCCQ was proven to be a valid scale based on the CVR and CVI scores. Based on the experts’ opinions, the HCCQ-P can be used to measure Iranian patients’ perceptions concerning the extent of autonomy support provided by the country’s health-care system in general and their HCPs in particular.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="S0004-S2002" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Construct validity</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The study results showed an excellent KMO factor structure, which indicates sufficient sample size for factor analysis. The estimated index was similar to the findings obtained in the psychometric evaluation of the German version of the HCCQ.
   <a rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0019">19</a> In this study, the EFA output indicated a one-factor solution as the best model fit (
   <a rid="F0002" ref-type="fig" href="#F0002">Figure 2</a>). This solution was in agreement with the findings of the original study in verifying the psychometric properties of the HCCQ scale
   <a rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0017">.
    <span class="sup">17</span>
   </a> Several previous studies have also reported a one-factor solution as the best model fit in HCCQ psychometric appraisal.
   <a rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0014">14</a>,
   <a rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0024">24</a> In the German version of the scale, however, two major factors were found: a factor with 14 items and a factor with only one item (item 13), which had a negative load
   <a rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0019">.
    <span class="sup">19</span>
   </a> The results of CFA in the present study confirmed the fitness of the model obtained from EFA, which was consistent with the results reported in previous studies.
   <a rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0014">14</a>,
   <a rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0024">24</a>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="S0004-S2003" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Feasibility</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on the study results, a partial ceiling effect was observed (the highest score was achieved by 16.9%), which is consistent with the ceiling effect reported in the HCCQ psychometric assessment by Frielink et al
   <a rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0024">24</a> and Schmidt et al.
   <a rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0019">19</a> However, no ceiling and floor effects were reported in the study by Czajkowska et al.
   <a rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0014">14</a>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="S0004-S2004" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Reliability</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The estimated internal consistency index for the HCCQ-P was similar to the reported measure in the original HCCQ assessment study
   <a rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0017">17</a> and other validation studies on HCCQ.
   <a rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0014">14</a>,
   <a rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0018">18</a>,
   <a rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0019">19</a> The test–retest reliability index in this study was higher than that obtained in the study by Czajkowska et al.
   <a rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0014">14</a>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="S0004-S2005" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Limitations</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Despite an acceptable representation of the validity and reliability measures, the study findings should be interpreted with caution. The studied sample’s imbalanced gender ratio and distinct sociodemographic characteristics of the participants have the potential to cause bias in the study findings. The participants’ previous experiences in dealing with the health-care system, their trust in the health-care system, baseline mental status and overall life satisfaction are other factors that might be considered in the interpretation of the results.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As a brief tool, the HCCQ focuses on the overall supportiveness of the health-care delivery setting rather than the details and several dimensions of the appropriateness of the provided care. Further studies are required to verify these preliminary results by recruiting samples from various parts of the country, which has a very diverse socioeconomic, geographic and development profile.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The observed small ceiling effect in this study is a common limitation in research on patient satisfaction, since study respondents are generally reluctant to criticize their HCPs, for several reasons.
   <a rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0019">19</a> However, sociocultural differences may exist based on literacy level, previous experiences, insurance coverage and social norms, which should be considered in the interpretation of the findings.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Long-term stability of the patients’ views should also be assessed in future studies because of the influences that contextual factors (eg, economic turbulence) may have on the patients’ prospects.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Convergent and divergent validities of the translated HCCQ were not studied in this research since a reliable scale was not identified by the authors to measure the health-care system supportiveness. Therefore, further assessment of the HCCQ-P’s construct validity using a comparable tool is recommended.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The study findings cannot be generalized beyond outpatient care settings since the sample was drawn only from the outpatient diabetes clinic. Additional studies are required if application of the HCCQ-P is to be considered on authentic and complex inpatient diabetes cases, as recommended in other relevant studies.
   <a rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0019">19</a>
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Despite the above limitations, strengths of this study are the applied explicit cultural adaptation in the translation process and the high participation rate, which suggests a low risk of selection bias that would otherwise have had the potential to affect the findings.</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
