<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="S0002-S2002" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study sample</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on the recommended sample size for accurate and precise factor analysis,
  <a rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0034">34</a> 177 patients with type 2 diabetes registered in the diabetes clinic of the Shahid Madani Hospital in the city of Khoy, north-west Iran, were recruited out of 1,600 active patients' files with a random sampling method. The inclusion criteria were type 2 diabetes, over 30 years of age and being a native resident of the city; and the exclusion criteria were type 1 diabetes, gestational diabetes, having mental disorders such as Alzheimer's disease, dementia or congenital mental retardation, or having a severe limiting disability such as quadriplegia or limiting cardiovascular disease.
 </p>
 <sec id="S0002-S2002-S3001" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Content validity</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Standard translation/back-translation procedures
   <a rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0035">35</a>-
   <a rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0037">37</a> were performed to prepare a preliminary draft of the scale in Persian. In the first stage, the original instrument (Table S1) was translated into Persian by two professional translators; and in the next stage, the Persian version (Figure S1) was translated into English by two other professional translators who were familiar with the main study topic. In the third stage, the back-translated English version of the HCCQ was compared with the original version in terms of content, and idiomatic and semantic affinity. Minor corrections were made as a consequence and the final draft was approved by the researchers. The face and content validity of the translated version was checked by a group of experts consisting 15 academic staff of the Tabriz University of Medical Sciences, who had work experience in the field of type 2 diabetes. Clarity of the wording, placement of the items and scoring were checked by the experts at this stage, and their feedback was followed to make corrections. Content validity ratio (CVR) and content validity index (CVI) scores were calculated to determine the suitability of items on the translated questionnaire. A CVI of 0.80 or higher
   <a rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0038">38</a> for individual items and a CVR above 0.49 were deemed as acceptable cut-off points.
   <a rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0039">39</a> The translated questionnaire was also pilot tested on 20 patients regarding understandability of the questions and response items.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="S0002-S2002-S3002" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Reliability</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Reliability of the HCCQ-P was assessed using Cronbach’s alpha and intraclass correlation coefficients (ICCs).</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="S0002-S2002-S3003" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data collection</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Trained interviewers were employed for collecting face-to-face data about age, gender, marital status, occupation, level of education, place of residence, income level, type of medication (oral/injectable) and having hypertension or type 2 diabetes-related complications, in addition to the HCCQ-P items.</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
