<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="S0002-S2004" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analysis</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Individual participants’ total scores, their means and standard deviations were calculated after applying a reverse-coding mechanism for item 13, as recommended by the scale’s developer, owing to the negative wording of the question in that item.
  <a rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0041">41</a>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Pearson’s coefficient of skewness and Fisher’s measure of kurtosis were used to assess the asymmetry of the study data at the next stage. The range of skewness coefficient was deemed to be between −1 and +1, and Fisher’s measure of kurtosis was considered to be between −1.96 and +1.96.
  <a rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0042">42</a>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ceiling and floor effects were checked for detecting outliers (ie, more than 15% of the respondents reached the lowest or highest possible scores)
  <a rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0034">.
   <span class="sup">34</span>
  </a> The Cronbach’s alpha coefficient was calculated to appraise the scale’s internal consistency, and values greater than or equal to 0.7 were considered to be acceptable.
  <a rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0034">34</a> The test–retest procedure was used and the ICC was calculated by asking 20 patients with type 2 diabetes to fill in the study questionnaire after 20 days. ICC values below 0.4, between 0.41 and 0.6, and above 0.8 were considered as weak, moderate, and good and excellent indicators of the participants’ performance in the two measurements, respectively.
  <a rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0034">34</a> To facilitate the decision-making process, values above 0.7 were considered acceptable.
  <a rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0043">43</a>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The correlation between the scale items’ scores and the total scale score was examined and found to be in the range of 0.82–0.91, representing a high consistency between items.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To perform psychometric verification of the translated questionnaire, half of the collected data, selected at random, was used for EFA and the rest for CFA. The Keyser–Meyer–Olkin (KMO) indicator was used to verify the adequacy of the sample size and Bartlett’s test of sphericity was devised to confirm the correlation between items and suitability of performing factor analysis. During the exploratory factor analysis, principal axis factoring and direct oblimin rotation were applied; eigenvalues greater than 1 were used to determine the number of factor solutions, and factor loadings greater than 0.3 were considered to assign questions to factors. The required modifications were also performed to improve the model fit in the CFA. All statistical analyses in this study were implemented with SPSS 20, STATA 15 and AMOS 20 software.</p>
</sec>
