<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We used a model of intermediate complexity (MICE) for five baleen whale species (blue, fin, humpback, southern right and Antarctic minke), and their krill and copepod prey (Tulloch et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-bib-0109" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). We extend the model to include two‐way predator–prey interactions and allow for three alternative versions that include or exclude links with climate change (Figure 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). In the primary model (Model 1), we coupled krill dynamics to future changes in SST and chlorophyll, with indirect links between climate and whales through changing prey availability and whale breeding success (Figure 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, Table 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-tbl-0001" ref-type="table">1</xref>). In Model 2, we included all links from Model 1 among climate, prey and whales, but added links between future changes in sea‐ice extent to hypothesized changes in whale distribution (Figure 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, Table 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-tbl-0001" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Finally, we ran a comparative scenario (Model 3) where climate drivers were decoupled from species dynamics, and changes in whale and krill numbers were driven by predation and competition between whales alone (Figure 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, Table 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-tbl-0001" ref-type="table">1</xref>). All models were fitted to an index of abundance from available surveys for krill and the five whale species (Tulloch et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-bib-0109" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>) using AD Model Builder (Fournier et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-bib-0024" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>). The models first simulate historical whale trajectories from 1890 to 2013 for two regions (Pacific and Atlantic/Indian) and two seasons (feeding and breeding, Figure 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1</xref>), driven largely by the historical commercial whaling records from the IWC (Figure 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a, b). The model then predicts krill and whale numbers to the end of the 21st century driven by projections from the NPZD model. The NPZD model future predictions were coupled to climate drivers under Representative Concentration Pathways (RCP) 8.5 (Meinshausen et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-bib-0058" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>) adopted by the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) Fifth Assessment Report (AR5) (IPCC, 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-bib-0034" ref-type="ref">[Link]</xref>) (Figure 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>c). We use this single scenario because climate estimates are currently tracking the highest RCP pathway 8.5 (Sanford, Frumhoff, Luers, &amp; Gulledge, 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-bib-0087" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>), but the projected changes here might be considered an upper bound if emissions were dramatically reduced.
</p>
