<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Prior to estimating ENM’s we performed a paired Pearson correlation analysis based on the extracted environmental data of all the occurrence points. Then we selected a set of uncorrelated variables (Pearson correlation coefficients below 0.7) as environmental inputs. The latter resulted in a set of eight bioclimatic variables (i.e., BIO2 = Mean Diurnal Range (Mean of monthly (max temp—min temp), BIO4 = Temperature Seasonality (standard deviation *100), BIO5 = Max Temperature of Warmest Month, BIO6 = Min Temperature of Coldest Month, BIO9 = Mean Temperature of Driest Quarter, BIO12 = Annual Precipitation, BIO14 = Precipitation of Driest Month, BIO15 = Precipitation Seasonality (Coefficient of Variation). In addition, a principal component analysis (PCA) analysis was conducted to corroborate the most significant climate variables (see results in 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp-5">Fig. S1</xref>) using the statistical software R with the package 
 <italic>raster</italic> (
 <xref rid="ref-57" ref-type="bibr">Thuiller et al., 2016</xref>). Species distribution modeling (SDM) were estimated using the maximum entropy algorithm (MaxEnt) implemented in the R package 
 <italic>biomod2</italic> (
 <xref rid="ref-57" ref-type="bibr">Thuiller et al., 2016</xref>). For each species, occurrence data was divided using 70% of the records for training the models and 30% for testing them. A total of 10 replicates per each species were used and from these, geographic predictions and performance was averaged per species. Model performance was estimated for the projections in the climatic scenario for the present using the statistical metrics relative operating characteristic (ROC), TSS (true skill statistic) and Kappa. Values for ROC range from zero to one, with values greater than 0.5 meaning the model predicts testing points better than a random expectation. TSS and Kappa values range from −1 to 1 where values close to 0 indicate a prediction not different than random whereas positive values indicate predictions better than random. To integrate most of the variation observed in the bioclimatic variables, we alternatively performed a multivariate analysis. A PCA was performed using 19 bioclimatic variables of all the climatic scenarios used in this study and reduce the observed variation on a set of uncorrelated PC axes. Then, we used the PC scores of these axes to generate raster layers for each climate scenario as environmental inputs to estimate SDMs and perform geographic projections. The first six PC axes explained more than 95% of the observed variation and were used to estimate SDMs. Loading contributions for each of the PC axes used are showed in 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp-4">Table S4</xref>. PCA analyses were conducted in the statistical software R using the package 
 <italic>raster</italic> (
 <xref rid="ref-57" ref-type="bibr">Thuiller et al., 2016</xref>).
</p>
