<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Using the modified CSM-CERES-Pearl Millet model, we evaluated the genetic traits of pearl millet for adaptation to climate change at selected locations in West Africa and India. The study revealed that in the higher rainfall environments of Aurangabad and Bijapur, the potential yield gains with the 10% longer maturity cultivar are to the extent of 47% as compared to the baseline cultivar (Sharda) under current climate and climate change by midcentury (
 <xref rid="t0030" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 6</xref>). At other locations (Hisar, Jaipur, Jodhpur and Bikaner) although the yields increased with 10% longer maturity, they were statistically non-significant (p &lt; 0.05) in the both present and future climates. So the baseline cultivar life cycle duration (ICMH 356) remained the highest yielding at the four locations under both climate regimes, possibly because of better fit to the rainfall patterns of those sites which minimized benefit of the longer maturity types. Similarly, at Sadore and Cinzana under base climate the yields were higher for the baseline cultivar (CIVT) as compared to the yields with the 10% shorter or longer maturity cultivar (
 <xref rid="t0035" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 7</xref>). Under climate change the baseline cultivar gave the highest yield at Sadore; however, at Cinzana a 4% increase in yield was simulated with 10% longer maturity cultivar, which was statistically non-significant (p &lt; 0.05). For the favorable rainfall conditions of future, the cultivars that are of longer maturity in current climate will generally be more suitable as the warmer climate typically shortens the life cycle and longer maturity cultivars will compensate for these conditions and produce higher yields than the default baseline cultivars. Identifying a proper cultivar according to length of growing period is one of the best ways to tackle climate change impacts as sufficient genetic diversity exists in pearl millet maturity groups (
 <xref rid="bb0170" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Rai et al., 1999</xref>). This would minimize drought and heat stress during the crop life cycle and the available seasonal resources would be fully utilized.
</p>
