<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Incorporating drought tolerance in pearl millet by increasing density of roots in the subsoil and, therefore, greater soil water extraction with depth was tried as another way to adapt to climate change. In India under baseline climate, the yield improvements due to drought tolerance traits were the highest at Bikaner followed by Jodhpur, Bijapur, Hisar, Jaipur and Aurangabad; while in West Africa the yield gains were higher at Sadore than at Cinzana. The reason for differential response was mainly due to differences in soil water availability at the target locations as determined by the water holding capacity of soils and the amount and distribution of rainfall. Except for the Bikaner site, the percent yield gains due to drought tolerance of virtual cultivars under climate change were either the same or somewhat less than those simulated under baseline climate, in part because of increasing rainfall under climate change in much of India. The locations where rainfall is projected to decrease during mid-century period, the drought tolerant cultivars were found to be more promising adaptation option. Further, even at locations where the rainfall is projected to increase in future, the drought-tolerant virtual cultivars were still found to be suitable as the crops will still suffer from drought due to increased water demand caused by higher air temperatures as projected during mid-century. In addition to other multiple mechanisms, increasing root length density (RLD) and rooting depth in the subsoil are suggested as the prominent mechanisms for drought tolerance and higher yields in pearl millet and other dryland crops (
 <xref rid="bb0235" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Vadez et al., 2012</xref>). Genetic variation in root traits of pearl millet exists, which can be used for breeding drought tolerant cultivars (
 <xref rid="bb0130" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kusaka et al., 2005</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0235" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Vadez et al., 2012</xref>). Increased RLD in subsoil, thus greater soil water extraction with depth, also enhances water use efficiency (yield/evapotranspiration) of the crop because most of the additional water uptake from the subsoil is lost as transpiration. Thus, the approach used in the model to simulate drought tolerance of virtual cultivars is appropriate. However, there is a chance that drought-tolerant cultivars may also result in greater extraction of subsoil water which will impact the following crop in a cropping system. Hence, the analysis on system prospective to study the carry-over effect of water to the next crop is needed.
</p>
