<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s4d" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Contact zone and the refuge theory</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Contact zones generally refer to the sympatric areas of closely related species which have their own separated primary distributions. Contact zones are important to understand the process of speciation, dispersal and vicariance. It is known that many closely related species pairs of birds are distributed in parapatry or allopatry with narrow contact zones 
  <a rid="pone.0029329-Haffer1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0029329-Haffer1">[72]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0029329-Aliabadian1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0029329-Aliabadian1">[74]</a>. In this study, we found a narrowly circumscribed intraspecific contact zone whereby lineage B was parapatrically distributed with each of the two related lineages in LJ and PZH respectively.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A plethora of hypotheses have been suggested to explain the cause of contact zones, such as the refuge, river refuge and disturbance-vicariance hypotheses 
  <a rid="pone.0029329-Haffer2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0029329-Haffer2">[73]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0029329-Haffer3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0029329-Haffer3">[75]</a>. Among these, the refuge theory of Haffer 
  <a rid="pone.0029329-Haffer2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0029329-Haffer2">[73]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0029329-Haffer3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0029329-Haffer3">[75]</a> argued that the contractions and expansions of species range influenced by the climatic fluctuation would establish secondary contact zones. Our ENMs reconstructions support this theory. As can be seen in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029329-g004" href="#pone-0029329-g004">Fig. 4</a>, the contact zone was projected as unsuitable for the black-throated tit during LIG and LGM though the present ENMs showed that the habit was suitable. The present parapatry of these lineages could be the result of the recent expansions in the range of lineages B and C indicated by the BSP analysis into the present suitable environment. In addition, several species or species group have differentiated in a similar way of the black-throated tit, such as 
  <span class="italic">Seicercus affinis</span>
  <a rid="pone.0029329-Olsson1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0029329-Olsson1">[76]</a>, 
  <span class="italic">Cettia flavolivacea</span>
  <a rid="pone.0029329-Olsson2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0029329-Olsson2">[77]</a>, 
  <span class="italic">Certhia discolor</span>
  <a rid="pone.0029329-Tietze1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0029329-Tietze1">[78]</a>, and species group of 
  <span class="italic">Phylloscopus cantator</span> and 
  <span class="italic">P. ricketti</span>
  <a rid="pone.0029329-Alstrm1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0029329-Alstrm1">[79]</a>, especially for a subspecies group between 
  <span class="italic">Certhia familiaris bianchii</span> and 
  <span class="italic">C. f. khamemsis</span>
  <a rid="pone.0029329-Tietze1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0029329-Tietze1">[78]</a>. Although, the contact zone hotspot of birds appears to be located in Middle East 
  <a rid="pone.0029329-Haffer2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0029329-Haffer2">[73]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0029329-Aliabadian1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0029329-Aliabadian1">[74]</a>, these findings indicate that areas between LJ and PZH may also be a contact zone hotspot whereby this range has been considered to play an important role in avian endemism and speciation in China 
  <a rid="pone.0029329-Lei1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0029329-Lei1">[19]</a>.
 </p>
</sec>
