<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s3b" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Phylogenetic relationships</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Maximum likelihood and Bayesian phylogenetic inferences both divided our data into three major clades with strong support for both the lineages themselves and the relationships between them (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0029329-g002" href="#pone-0029329-g002">Fig. 2</a>). The primary geographical lineages identified are as follows:
 </p>
 <div id="pone-0029329-g002" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0029329.g002</span>
  <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Phylogenetic relationships among haplotypes.</div>
   <p>The inferred phylogenetic tree and the Major-joining network based on the combined COI, 
    <span class="italic">cyt b</span> and ND2 genes. Numbers above tree branches are the posterior probabilities for the BI and bootstrap values for the ML below. Dashes and numbers in the network represent the corresponding mutation steps.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0029329.g002" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Clade A: A lineage comprising sampling areas spanning Yunnan Province.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Clade B: This lineage is restricted to the region between northern Yunnan Province (Lijiang) and southwest Sichuan Province (Panzhihua, Yanbian and Miyi counties).</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Clade C: The largest lineage which is distributed from the western border of Guizhou and Guangxi, across the wide areas of central China, to the eastern seaboard.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All three lineages are strongly supported by posterior probabilities (PP&gt;95%) and bootstrap values (BV&gt;70). The relationships among these lineages are also supported at greater than 95% PP and 70 BV. Lineage B and C are inferred to be sister taxa, whereas lineage A is a sister to B and C. Several well supported clades (PP&gt;95%) are apparent within lineage C. In terms of the current taxonomy, subspecies 
  <span class="italic">A. c. talifuensis</span> includes lineages A and B, whereas lineage C, with the exception of samples collected at site PZH which includes individuals of both lineages B and C, exhibits strong concordance between the geographical mtDNA lineage and the currently described nominate subspecies, 
  <span class="italic">A. c. concinnus</span>.
 </p>
</sec>
