<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s4a" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">MtDNA lineages diversification and the demography history</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Previous studies suggested that there was no genetic divergence within 
  <span class="italic">A. c. concinnus</span>-
  <span class="italic">talifuensis</span>
  <a rid="pone.0029329-Eck1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0029329-Eck1">[28]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0029329-Pckert1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0029329-Pckert1">[29]</a>. In contrast, we found significant genetic divergence in this group, despite its current continuous distribution. Both phylogenetic inferences and haplotype network analyses revealed the existence of three distinct evolutionary lineages in 
  <span class="italic">A. c. concinnus</span>-
  <span class="italic">talifuensis</span>. Node support for each lineage is high and missteps in haplotype network connections are large, especially between lineages A and B–C (up to 141 steps). Furthermore, analysis of molecular variance partitioned data into three phylogroups with clearly defined geographical population structures. We noticed that the sampling sites of specimens for 
  <span class="italic">A. c. talifuensis</span> analyzed by the previous studies were located in the area of lineage C. Thus, we compared the genetic distance (cyt b, p-distance) for a specimen of lineage A (
  <span class="italic">A. c. talifuensis</span>) with other two subspecies specimens (
  <span class="italic">A. c. manipurensis</span> and 
  <span class="italic">A. c. iredalei</span>) which are available at GenBank (Accessions: HM185382, GU244428, GU244426). The genetic distance was 4.9% between 
  <span class="italic">A. c. talifuensis</span> and 
  <span class="italic">A. c. manipurensis</span> and 5.1% between 
  <span class="italic">A. c. talifuensis</span> and 
  <span class="italic">A. c. iredalei</span>. These results suggest that the black-throated tit displays high genetic differentiation and zones of lineage endemism even within the Chinese part of its range.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The significant values for Tajima's D and Fu's 
  <span class="italic">Fs</span> statistical tests and the unimodal mismatch distribution suggest that lineage C has undergone a past population expansion. For lineage A and lineage B, however, values of statistical tests (significantly negative or negative) and mismatch distributions (multimodal but not significant values of goodness-of-fit tests) were not consistent with each other well. The coalescent-based method, which incorporates information from the genealogical tree structure of DNA sequences, seemed to be a more effective way of estimating demographic processes. Bayesian skyline plots indicate different population dynamics among lineages; a relatively constant population size in lineage A, a past population reduction and recent slight increase in lineage B, and successive population expansions in lineage C. Although BSP confidence intervals for lineage B were large, they are all supported by the ENMs. ENMs indicate that the amount of suitable habitat available was constant for lineage A, very limited range for lineage B during both the LIG and LGM, and a reduced distribution for lineage C during LIG.
 </p>
</sec>
