<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2d" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Phylogenetic analyses</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Maximum likelihood (ML) and Bayesian methods (BI) were used to identify major lineages and evaluate relationships among haplotypes. An individual from the great tit 
  <span class="italic">(Parus major)</span> and long-tailed tit 
  <span class="italic">(Aegithalos caudatus)</span> were used as outgroups. The substitution models for each of the three gene sequence and the concatenated data sets were selected using MrMODELTEST 2.2 
  <a rid="pone.0029329-Nylander1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0029329-Nylander1">[37]</a> as implemented in MrMTgui (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://genedrift.org/mtgui.php" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://genedrift.org/mtgui.php</span>) based on the Akaike information criterion 
  <a rid="pone.0029329-Akaike1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0029329-Akaike1">[38]</a>. The best fit models for the COI and ND2 sequence data sets were GTR+I. The best fit model for the cytochrome-b sequence data set was HKY+I and the GTR+I+G model was selected as the best fit model for the concatenated data set.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">ML trees were constructed using PhyML version 3 
  <a rid="pone.0029329-Guindon1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0029329-Guindon1">[39]</a>. The GTR model was used and the number of rate categories was set to 6. Proportion of invariable sites and gamma shape parameter were 0.92 and 1.92 respectively (estimated by MrMODELTEST). The robustness of lineages in the ML tree was tested by the bootstrap test with 100 resamplings. Bayesian inference (BI) was conducted in “partitioned by gene” using MrBayes 3.1.2 
  <a rid="pone.0029329-Ronquist1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0029329-Ronquist1">[40]</a>. The concatenated sequence data was divided into three different partitions corresponding to the three mitochondrial regions and applied the best fit model for each partition. The model parameters were as following: lset applyto = (1, 3) nst = 6 rates = propinv; lset applyto = (2) nst = 2 rates = propinv. We allowed the overall rate to vary between partitions by setting the priors &lt;ratepr = variable&gt; and model parameters (e.g. gamma shape, proportion of invariable sites) unlinked across partitions. Four Metropolis-coupled Markov chains Monte Carlo (one cold and three heated) were run for 15 million iterations, with trees sampled every 1000 iterations. The first three million iterations (3000 trees) were discarded (‘burn-in’ period), and the posterior probabilities were estimated for remaining sampled iterations. Two independent Bayesian runs initiated from random starting trees were performed, and the log-likelihood values, posterior probabilities and average deviations of split frequencies were checked to ascertain that the chains had reached convergence.
 </p>
</sec>
