<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s4c" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The LGM effect on species' distribution</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Last Glacial Maximum of Pleistocene climatic oscillations (0.021−0.018 Ma) had a profound impact on species' distribution and population sizes, e.g. in the heavy ice sheets covering northern regions of Europe and North America 
  <a rid="pone.0029329-Hewitt4" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0029329-Hewitt4">[5]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0029329-Conroy1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0029329-Conroy1">[7]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0029329-Fedorov1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0029329-Fedorov1">[67]</a>. In contrast, our results show that LGM had little impact on the geographic distribution of 
  <span class="italic">A. c. talifuensis–concinnus.</span> This conclusion is supported by both the ENMs and phylogeographic analyses. For instance, the ENMs suggest that there has been suitable environment for lineage A in Yunnan since the LIG. This result, combined with the constant population suggested by Bayesian skyline analyses, indicates that LGM may have had little impacts on this lineage. For lineage C, Bayesian skyline and mismatch analyses detect a strong signal of a recent population expansion across most of this lineage's current range. However, because the ENMs suggest that a similar geographic range as the present during the LGM and much of its LGM habitat was uninhabitable during the LIG, and the genetic data suggest that the range of this lineage expanded before the LGM (about 0.07 Ma), we think that LGM effects were limited. This is also true for lineage B, as our result showed that this lineage has a more restricted distribution during LGM than it does at present but more suitable habitat than it had during LIG. However, the significant genetic divergence between the western (PZH and JZS) and other populations within lineage C suggests that small refugia may have existed. Similar results were found in a phylogeographic study of the canopy tree 
  <span class="italic">Eurycorymbus cavaleriei</span>
  <a rid="pone.0029329-Wang2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0029329-Wang2">[68]</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In fact, our reconstructions of LGM distribution are much congruent with previous phylogeographic studies 
  <a rid="pone.0029329-Song1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0029329-Song1">[23]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0029329-Huang1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0029329-Huang1">[25]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0029329-Flanders1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0029329-Flanders1">[59]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0029329-Gao1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0029329-Gao1">[69]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0029329-Qiu1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0029329-Qiu1">[70]</a>. These studies suggested the existence of multiple refugia, but species all showed population expansion before the LGM. Our ENMs and molecular data support that East China was not subjected to significant glacial advances 
  <a rid="pone.0029329-Williams1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0029329-Williams1">[71]</a>, at least with respect to the period of LGM. Unexpectedly, our ENMs results provide a distinct perspective for the climatic impact of LIG. However, this conclusion requires evaluation in other taxa with different life-history traits and biology.
 </p>
</sec>
