<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Climate factors such as temperature and precipitation significantly affect the life cycle of dengue mosquitoes [
 <xref rid="pone.0199205.ref008" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0199205.ref015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>]; thus, these factors need to be included in mathematical models of dengue transmission. Many studies have investigated the effects of climate factors on dengue transmission. Climate change impacts factors relevant to the mosquito population. In particular, the temperature has a strong influence on dengue transmission and the 
 <italic class="italic">Aedes</italic> mosquito population [
 <xref rid="pone.0199205.ref008" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0199205.ref010" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. Chen and Hsieh investigated the impact of temperature variation on dengue transmission dynamics in a single-strain model [
 <xref rid="pone.0199205.ref011" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>]. A susceptible-exposed-infectious-recovered (SEIR) model with four dengue strains has been employed to study the seasonal population dynamics of mosquitoes [
 <xref rid="pone.0199205.ref012" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. Dengue incidences in Thailand, Taiwan, Singapore, and Brazil are associated with seasonal patterns in temperature, relative humidity, and rainfall [
 <xref rid="pone.0199205.ref011" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0199205.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. Statistical approaches have revealed that these seasonal patterns play a significant role in dengue transmission [
 <xref rid="pone.0199205.ref008" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0199205.ref016" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. A two-patch dengue transmission model incorporating seasonality has been employed to explore the impact of different patch-specific control strategies [
 <xref rid="pone.0199205.ref017" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. In [
 <xref rid="pone.0199205.ref018" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0199205.ref019" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>], the temperature-dependent parameters obtained from laboratory data ranged from 10°
 <italic class="italic">C</italic> to 37°
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. Moreover, the amount of rainfall may affect the larval population size [
 <xref rid="pone.0199205.ref015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>], and the rainfall pattern has a certain effect on the larval density [
 <xref rid="pone.0199205.ref020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. A recent study by ten Bosch et al. considered six different dengue models, with important dengue characteristics such as cross-immunity, antibody-dependent enhancement and seasonal forcing [
 <xref rid="pone.0199205.ref021" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>]. The authors adopted a pattern-oriented modeling strategy to capture dengue dynamics such as multi-annual fluctuations and the mean duration between peaks.
</p>
