<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="discussion" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">DISCUSSION</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In an MCI, both EMS transportation time and distance have a high impact in a compressed window of emergency medical care when seconds and meters could mean life or death. Issues such as how to reduce the transportation time and distance will always be discussed for efficient solutions.
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="R20" ref-type="bibr" href="#R20">20</a>,
   <a rid="R28" ref-type="bibr" href="#R28">28</a>–
   <a rid="R33" ref-type="bibr" href="#R33">33</a>
  </span> In this research, a method of sequential-conveyance is conducted to promote the EMS transportation time and distance efficiency in 52.15% (app. TEmin) and 56.02% (app. DEmin), respectively, compared with the nonprogrammed conventional method. The findings also show that if all patients were retained in an MEMC, a value of app. TEmax and app. DEmax of 63.22% and 66.88%, respectively, would be obtained.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The app. TEmin and app. DEmin plots (Figure 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F3" href="#F3">3</a>) show the efficiency of time and distance in the condition of no casualty retention in an MEMC. Patients in this situation are first transported to an MEMC with triage and first-aid treatments and then to different lines of hospitals at once. The process without any patient retention in an MEMC is considered as redundant, regardless the triage and the basic treatment by the medical personnel. A conservative MEMC capacity is determined by a positive or zero value of app. TEmin and app. DEmin, despite the contribution of app. TEmax and app. DEmax. For this case study, the selection of Jiasion elementary school as an MEMC could obtain a negative app. TEmin beyond 128 of patients (
  <span class="italic">PR</span> ≅ 0.9481). The lowest value of app. TEmin of the 135 of patients (PR = 1) is –2.41%. This is just a slight negative descent compared with the TEmin plot. The data show that the broad spectrum of the positive app. TEmin in the sequential-conveyance method can result in selecting a good location of the MEMC. In other words, when choosing the Jiasion elementary school as an MEMC, the minimum time efficiency can be kept under a capacity of 128 patients, even if all the casualties may eventually be removed to the requested hospitals without any retention in situ. The additional saved time can be used for triage and first-aid assistance to more patients. For the value of app. DEmin, the negative value begins at 135 of patients wherein –0.34% has been defined. It implies that the selected MEMC has distance ascendancy under a capacity of 134 patients.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In Panel A of Figure 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F3" href="#F3">3</a>, the y-interceptions of app. TEmax and app. TEmin plots are on the same point (0.6183) because there is no patient available (PR = 0) for further transfer. It appears that the selected MEMC (the school) as a refuge has a time efficiency of 61.83%. Theoretically, the 135 nonpatient survivors are transferred to the 5 recorded refuges with a fixed flow ratio in the conventional method, whereas in the sequential-conveyance method, they are transported to the MEMC. In addition, the y-interception of app. DEmax and app. DEmin is 0.6572 (Figure 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F3" href="#F3">3</a>: Panel B).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">How to select an adequate MEMC by analyzing TE and DE? If the app. TEmax plot is closer to the TEmax plot and the app. TEmin plot has a positive shift from the TEmin plot, then these imply that the selected MEMC has time efficiency in the sequential-conveyance method, by keeping the advantage of the TEmax and by limiting the disadvantage of the TEmin. The same results are taken from a discussion either from the app. DEmax and the DEmax or the app. DEmin and the DEmin.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Aside all the positives, there is also a discussion about whether MEMCs’ bypass could cause an adverse effect for the patients who require immediate resuscitation. Some similar case studies regarding hospital bypassing to trauma centers may preclude the link between the bypass time and the survival in the study of Level I trauma patients.
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="R34" ref-type="bibr" href="#R34">34</a>
  </span> Moreover, patients with severe multiple traumas in the rural areas are suggested for triage and stabilization in Level III EDs before they are transferred to Level I regional trauma centers.
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="R35" ref-type="bibr" href="#R35">35</a>
  </span> In Taiwan, a previous study shows that there are no significant differences in mortality of severe trauma patients between a direct transportation to the study ED and a bypass transfer from another hospital after stabilization.
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="R36" ref-type="bibr" href="#R36">36</a>
  </span> Therefore, the establishment of MEMCs for patient triage, first-aid care, and stabilization before a long journey to hospitals are highly recommended in this research.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In Taiwan, patients are sent to the nearest hospitals depending on their own will or the judgment of their families, without any medical evaluation.
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="R36" ref-type="bibr" href="#R36">36</a>
  </span> This may lead to disturbance or overcrowding in the EDs, especially in an MCI and may cause an inadequate transferral or a redundant subsequent diversion. Given the benefits of MEMCs, all patients are diagnosed, treated, and clinical judged by the prehospital physicians therein; however, serious cases are suggested adequately to transfer to a requested hospital for intensive care. Controversies over the competencies and advantages for prehospital physicians are consistent with this scenario for MEMCs’ setting.
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="R37" ref-type="bibr" href="#R37">37</a>,
   <a rid="R38" ref-type="bibr" href="#R38">38</a>
  </span>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The MEMCs should be set up as less as possible while a catastrophe occurs to avoid the silo-effect
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="R39" ref-type="bibr" href="#R39">39</a>
  </span> and a disordered cross-communication. Additionally, in Taiwan, the 3 phases of prehospital patient care may not be suitable for adoption due to the short-distance transportation of the patients and the lack of systemic guidelines.
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="R40" ref-type="bibr" href="#R40">40</a>
  </span>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Under the issue of the climate change, a catastrophic calamity of an extreme weather event will force the EMS to do some adjustments for adaptation. It is difficult with a traditional method to manage a large caseload of casualty smoothly and methodically. That is why a systematic adaptation for EMS transportation is suggested because this strategy not only succeeds in efficient emergency transportation, but also highly regulates the distribution of patients to release the overcrowding of the responsible hospitals. Hence, additional practical work should be launched to collect more precise quantitative data.</p>
</sec>
