<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Future Evolution of the Sea-Ice Cover</div>
 <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The sensitivity of Arctic sea ice as described by the linear relationship between global-mean temperature and Arctic sea-ice coverage has been found to remain constant in model simulations across a wide spectrum of temperature trajectories [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>]. In particular, the linearity holds in all CMIP5 models until summer sea ice vanishes in individual simulations. Hence, the observed sensitivity can be extrapolated to directly estimate the response of the Arctic sea-ice cover to future warming.
 </p>
 <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Unfortunately, as shown by the values for the September sea-ice cover listed in Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>, uncertainty exists as to the true sensitivity of the sea-ice cover to a given amount of warming. The main sources of uncertainty are the choice of the underlying observational records of sea-ice coverage and global-mean temperature, and the method used to estimate the sensitivity from any given pair of observational records. Regarding the latter, [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>] divide the temporal trend of sea-ice coverage by the temporal trend of global-mean temperature to estimate sea-ice sensitivity, while all other estimates in Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a> are based on an ordinary least-square regression of sea-ice coverage on global-mean temperature. This latter approach has been suggested to underestimate the true sensitivity of the sea-ice cover [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>], as it implies a primarily unidirectional relationship between the two variables. Therefore, the inverse of temperature regressed on sea-ice area gives a higher estimate than the direct regression of sea-ice area on temperature. However, one could also argue that the simple linear regression is justified by the primarily one-way causal relationship between global warming and sea-ice loss, suggesting that this estimate reflects the true sensitivity. 
  <div id="Tab1" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Overview of published sensitivities of the September sea-ice cover to global warming</p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th align="left">Sensitivity</th>
      <th align="left">Ice-free at</th>
      <th align="left">Sea-ice data</th>
      <th align="left">Temperature data</th>
      <th align="left">Time period</th>
      <th align="left">Ref</th>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <th align="left">[10
       <span class="sup">6</span> km
       <span class="sup">2</span>/K]
      </th>
      <th align="left"/>
      <th align="left"/>
      <th align="left"/>
      <th align="left"/>
      <th align="left"/>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" colspan="6">Based on sea-ice extent</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left">− 5.7
       <span class="sup">+</span>
      </td>
      <td align="left">+ 0.6 
       <span class="sup">∘</span>C
      </td>
      <td align="left">NSIDC sea-ice index</td>
      <td align="left">GISTEMP</td>
      <td align="left">1979–2013</td>
      <td align="left">[
       <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>]
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left">− 4.4</td>
      <td align="left">+ 0.8 
       <span class="sup">∘</span>C
      </td>
      <td align="left">NSIDC sea-ice index</td>
      <td align="left">GISTEMP</td>
      <td align="left">1979–2014</td>
      <td align="left">[
       <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>]
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" colspan="6">Based on sea-ice area</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left">− 2.6</td>
      <td align="left">+ 0.9 
       <span class="sup">∘</span>C
      </td>
      <td align="left">HadISST 1
       <span class="sup">∗</span>
      </td>
      <td align="left">GISTEMP</td>
      <td align="left">1979–2007</td>
      <td align="left">[
       <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>]
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left">− 4.1</td>
      <td align="left">+ 0.6 
       <span class="sup">∘</span>C
      </td>
      <td align="left">Sea-ice index &amp; HadISST 1
       <span class="sup">∗</span>
      </td>
      <td align="left">HadCRUT4</td>
      <td align="left">1953–2016</td>
      <td align="left">[
       <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>]
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left">− 3.3</td>
      <td align="left">+ 0.7 
       <span class="sup">∘</span>C
      </td>
      <td align="left">HadISST 2.2</td>
      <td align="left">GISTEMP</td>
      <td align="left">1953–2016</td>
      <td align="left">[
       <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>]
      </td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
   <div class="table-wrap-foot">
    <p>The first column is the estimated observed sea-ice loss per degree of global warming. The second column is the additional warming above present levels needed to obtain an Arctic sea-ice coverage of less than 1 million km
     <span class="sup">2</span> (based on average September sea-ice extent of past ten years of 4.7 million km
     <span class="sup">2</span> and average September sea-ice area of 3.3 million km
     <span class="sup">2</span> [
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>]). 
     <span class="sup">∗</span>Note that [
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>] identified an inconsistency in the HadISST 1 sea-ice area, and recommended that it should only be used when merged with a consistent satellite record. 
     <span class="sup">+</span>This estimate is based on the gradient ratio of the temporal trend of global-mean warming and of the temporal trend of sea-ice coverage. All other estimates are based on ordinary regression of sea-ice coverage on global-mean temperature (see [
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>] for details)
    </p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Despite these uncertainties, the different estimates result in a relatively narrow range of additional warming above present that is required to obtain a near-ice free Arctic Ocean during summer, defined as the total sea-ice coverage dropping below 1 million km
  <span class="sup">2</span>. Based on an average sea-ice extent during September of 4.7 million km
  <span class="sup">2</span> and an average sea-ice area during September of 3.3 million km
  <span class="sup">2</span> as given by the NSIDC sea-ice index for the past 10 years [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>], the additional warming needed to reduce the sea-ice coverage to less than 1 million km
  <span class="sup">2</span> is found to be between + 0.6 and + 0.9 
  <span class="sup">∘</span>C relative to the average global-mean temperature of the past ten years (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>). As current warming levels are about + 1 
  <span class="sup">∘</span>C above pre-industrial levels, the Arctic Ocean can be expected to have an average ice coverage of less than 1 million km
  <span class="sup">2</span> during summer for less than 2 
  <span class="sup">∘</span>C global warming.
 </p>
 <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Estimates from model simulations that either capture the observed sensitivity or have been bias-corrected, result in similar estimates [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>]. Because of the robust relationship between sea-ice coverage and global-mean temperature, the time scale for establishing a given warming is irrelevant. As soon as the global-mean temperature has risen by slightly below 2 
  <span class="sup">∘</span>C, the Arctic Ocean is expected to be on average nearly ice-free during September.
 </p>
 <p id="Par28" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The linearity can also be exploited to estimate the future seasonal cycle of the Arctic sea-ice cover directly from the observational record (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). This is because the linearity holds for every month of the year [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>]. 
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Estimated evolution of the Arctic sea-ice cover in response to mean global warming. The figure is based on the extrapolation of the linear relationship between monthly mean Arctic sea-ice area and global-mean temperature provided by [
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>]. The ice-free range of their high-sensitivity observational record is shown as the water-filled area, while the ice-free range of their low-sensitivity observational record is shown as the dashed line. The estimated warming until 2018 is marked with “today”
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="40641_2018_113_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">With temperature being the main driver of the long-term sea-ice evolution of the Arctic, regardless of the drivers for that temperature increase, the future evolution of the sea-ice cover is most robustly described in reference to this variable. However, because the observed near linear relationship between global-mean temperature and cumulative anthropogenic CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions has been found to very likely remain unchanged for the foreseeable future [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>], this relationship can be exploited to describe the future evolution of the sea-ice cover in response to cumulative future CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>]. The observed sensitivity of the Arctic sea-ice cover to cumulative anthropogenic CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions suggests an on average ice-free Arctic Ocean throughout August and September for an additional maximum 800 Gt of anthropogenic CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions. This estimate is based on the observed sensitivity of about 3-m
  <span class="sup">2</span> sea-ice-area loss per ton of CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions in these months [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>] and the average sea-ice area of the past 10 years. For an additional 1400 Gt of anthropogenic CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions, the Arctic Ocean will become largely sea-ice free from July to October [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A possible modification of these estimates might be caused by the future evolution of anthropogenic aerosols, as they are expected to become less abundant over the next few decades. While in the past decades, rather constant levels of anthropogenic aerosols have minimized the impact of aerosols on the loss of Arctic sea ice [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>], in climate-model simulations the expected aerosol reduction causes additional ice loss relative to the one driven by anthropogenic CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>]. This would imply that the estimates given here are too conservative.
 </p>
 <p id="Par31" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A substantial number of studies that have examined the possible occurrence of an ice-free Arctic Ocean have not estimated the necessary warming, but instead describe the future evolution of the sea-ice cover primarily as a function of time [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>]. However, time is not a control variable of the system. Instead, the link to time is established via the global-mean warming in a given year, which in turn is primarily a function of cumulative future emissions. Hence, any estimate of a given year during which the Arctic will lose its ice cover will always be as uncertain as the future evolution of anthropogenic CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions, which makes it impossible to estimate the future evolution of the Arctic sea-ice cover as a function of time alone.
 </p>
</sec>
