<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Models</div>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Any climate model has limitations that must be kept in mind when employing it to understand the evolution of the sea-ice cover in the real world.</p>
 <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">First, climate models cannot capture all processes that govern the evolution of our climate system, and hence usually represent the real evolution of an observable less realistically than a given observational record. This is particularly true for sea ice, where climate-model simulations have been found to have substantial biases compared to the observed evolution of the ice cover. Among others, the models usually have a too low sensitivity of the simulated ice loss to simulated warming [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>] and to simulated CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>], they often have a too low or too high mean sea-ice area [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>], they often have an erroneous distribution of ice thickness [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>], and they can have substantial biases in the albedo evolution throughout summer [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>]. These biases must be kept in mind when assessing the robustness of model-based studies on the future trajectory of Arctic sea ice.
 </p>
 <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Second, the relationship of a model to the real world is often very difficult to estimate [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>], which makes it difficult to infer robust quantitative statements from model simulations. In particular, internal variability renders a perfect agreement of a model simulation with reality impossible, such that a disagreement between a model simulation and the real world does not allow one to directly obtain insights on the quality of a particular model simulation [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>]. Any model evaluation must hence take internal variability into account [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>]. On the other hand, an agreement of a specific model simulation with some observed record does not necessarily indicate a reasonable description of the underlying processes in the numerical code of the model, but might instead just indicate a reasonable tuning of the model to match the observational record [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>] or be caused by compensating errors. For example, [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>] suggest that models participating in the fifth phase of the Coupled Model Intercomparison Project (CMIP5 [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>]) better reproduce the observed loss of Arctic sea ice compared to the models participating in CMIP3, because in CMIP5, the prescribed external forcing from volcanic eruptions is too strong. Furthermore, agreement of a model with the past evolution of an observable is not necessarily an indication for reliable projections of the future evolution of that observable [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On the plus side, however, models overcome many of the mentioned limitations of observational records: models can be run several times and over long periods to capture the range of possible internal variability, they provide full three-dimensional fields of all major climate variables at nearly any desired temporal resolution, and they are internally consistent. In addition, they reflect possible future changes in the physical processes that drive the evolution of the sea-ice cover. Such future changes can obviously not be observed, which is why model simulations contribute important insights into the future evolution of the ice cover that can not be inferred from the observational record.</p>
 <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Most recent studies that employ climate-model simulations to explore the ongoing and future evolution of Arctic sea ice are based on the coordinated set of simulations from about 40 different climate models that participated in CMIP5. In addition, some recent studies are based on large ensembles of simulations with individual models. Such single-model large ensembles have been used for sea-ice-related studies for the Community Earth System Model (CESM [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>]), the Canadian Earth System Model (Can-ESM [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>]), and the Max Planck Institute Earth System Model (MPI-ESM). These large ensembles allow for robust insights into the impact of internal variability in individual models.
 </p>
</sec>
