<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">By providing a countrywide disaggregated approach on tick-borne diseases, this study provides essential preliminary information to build up a national public health policy based on spatial surveillance of tick-borne diseases [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B103" href="#B103">103</a>] and help to delineate priorities for future investigations. These are summarised in Table 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="T6" href="#T6">6</a>. (1) Regarding tick presence, this study highlights the lack of information about current species, and the need to search for species present in bordering regions. (2) In terms of tick distribution, occurrence data offers a useful picture, and this, particularly if the lack of detailed distribution of major determinants (hosts, predators) impeded building of adequate distribution models. However, modelling tick distribution could provide information in places not surveyed, clarify ecology and attach local probabilities to tick presence [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B104" href="#B104">104</a>]. For modelling exophilic tick distribution (
  <span class="italic">I. ricinus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">D. reticulatus</span>)
  <span class="italic">,</span> examples in the field of malaria vectors show that occurrences can prove useful to delineate species distribution [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B105" href="#B105">105</a>]. However, models perform better when explanatory variables englobe most ecologically relevant parameters [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B106" href="#B106">106</a>]. Because of their influence on ticks and on the pathogens presence and abundance, distribution of relevant host species or valuable proxies [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B3" href="#B3">3</a>] should be integrated in the models with major habitat characteristics. Distribution of nidiculous species could be approached by mapping their specific hosts. (3) Because of the above, the potential roles (hosts, pathogen reservoir versus accidental host [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B107" href="#B107">107</a>], influencing tick abundance, influencing pathogen prevalence, and predators) of the birds, mammals, reptiles, amphibian or other local species should be assessed and their distribution investigated. (4) With regards to pathogens, their presence needs to be clarified. The list of micro-organisms/tick associations provided here needs to be narrowed by investigating pathogenicity, identifying reservoirs (ticks and other species), selecting pathogens for which reservoirs are present, and identifying vector capacity for associated ticks. (5) With regards to pathogen distribution, pathogens should be monitored in ticks, reservoirs or any hosts to provide a spatial distribution per pathogen. (6) Human vector contact could be approached using public knowledge from groups at risk, such as nature lovers, hunters, foresters, veterinarians, health practitioners or even the general public. Such facilities for recording tick bites were developed successfully in the Netherlands [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B9" href="#B9">9</a>]. (7) Finally a risk map should provide the following locally: integration of the above distribution maps to determine the probability of being bitten by a tick, to obtain an infected tick bite per pathogen, and a list of potential pathogens locally. In this context, potential hotspots could be identified as well as places needing further investigation. This would provide a spatial disaggregation of risk and prepare analysis of seasonal or yearly variations.
 </p>
 <div position="float" id="T6" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Table 6</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Main findings and suggestions for further research priorities</p>
  </div>
  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1">
   <colgroup>
    <col align="left"/>
    <col align="left"/>
    <col align="left"/>
   </colgroup>
   <thead>
    <tr>
     <th align="left"> </th>
     <th align="left">
      <span class="bold">Current knowledge</span>
     </th>
     <th align="left">
      <span class="bold">Suggestions for future research priorities</span>
     </th>
    </tr>
   </thead>
   <tbody>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" valign="bottom">Tick presence
      <span class="hr"/>
     </td>
     <td align="left" valign="bottom">• The current national list of occurring tick species (not previously available)
      <span class="hr"/>
     </td>
     <td align="left" valign="bottom">• Search for tick species recorded in neighbouring countries country (targeting prefered host species or habitat)
      <span class="hr"/>
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="top">Tick distribution
      <span class="hr"/>
     </td>
     <td align="left" valign="bottom">• A first distribution map for 
      <span class="italic">Ixodes ricinus </span>based on occurrences which highlights presence of the species in all the provinces
      <span class="hr"/>
     </td>
     <td align="left" valign="bottom">• Build up a distribution model for exophilic species such as 
      <span class="italic">Ixodes ricinus </span>and 
      <span class="italic">Dermacentor reticulatus </span>based on habitat preferences and distribution of other influencing species
      <span class="hr"/>
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" valign="bottom">• Current very partial knowledge of distribution for the other tick species
      <span class="hr"/>
     </td>
     <td align="left" valign="bottom">• Build up a distribution model for nidiculous species based on distribution of major host species
      <span class="hr"/>
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" valign="bottom"> 
      <span class="hr"/>
     </td>
     <td align="left" valign="bottom">• Perform a systematic tick survey across the country
      <span class="hr"/>
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">Tick hosts/ reservoirs
      <span class="hr"/>
     </td>
     <td align="left" valign="bottom">• Provide for each tick a list of hosts on which they have been recorded in the country
      <span class="hr"/>
     </td>
     <td align="left" valign="bottom">• For each local vertebrate species check potential host status for each tick species or potential influence on tick population
      <span class="hr"/>
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" valign="bottom"> 
      <span class="hr"/>
     </td>
     <td align="left" valign="bottom">• Map the distribution of relevant species
      <span class="hr"/>
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="top">Presence of pathogens
      <span class="hr"/>
     </td>
     <td align="left" valign="bottom">• Potential presence of pathogens such as 
      <span class="italic">Borrelia burgdoferi s.l. </span>in many tick species
      <span class="hr"/>
     </td>
     <td align="left" valign="bottom">• Check the pathogenicity of each micro-organisms species
      <span class="hr"/>
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" valign="bottom">• List of microorganisms potentially present locally or aborad in local ticks species
      <span class="hr"/>
     </td>
     <td align="left" valign="bottom">• For pathogenic microorganisms check vector status of associated ticks Identify presence of potential reservoirs for pathogens (tick/ hosts)
      <span class="hr"/>
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" valign="bottom">• List of tick/ micro-organisms associations
      <span class="hr"/>
     </td>
     <td align="left" valign="bottom">• Investigate pathogen distribution across species to better comprehend
      <span class="hr"/>
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" valign="bottom"> 
      <span class="hr"/>
     </td>
     <td align="left" valign="bottom">• risk before modelling risk map
      <span class="hr"/>
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">Pathogen distribution
      <span class="hr"/>
     </td>
     <td align="left" valign="bottom">• First map of (suspected) pathogens found in ticks
      <span class="hr"/>
     </td>
     <td align="left" valign="bottom">• Search for additional pathogens in ticks of the country
      <span class="hr"/>
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" valign="bottom"> 
      <span class="hr"/>
     </td>
     <td align="left" valign="bottom">• Make a pathogen distribution map (found in ticks, hosts, reservoirs)
      <span class="hr"/>
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" valign="bottom">Human-vector contact
      <span class="hr"/>
     </td>
     <td align="left" valign="bottom"> 
      <span class="hr"/>
     </td>
     <td align="left" valign="bottom">• Use public knowledge from nature defense group, scouts, veterinary, general practitioner to localise and quantify tick bites
      <span class="hr"/>
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="top">Tick-borne diseases risk map</td>
     <td align="left" valign="bottom">• Some hot spot with highest 
      <span class="italic">I. ricinus </span>abundance are highlighted but because of unreliable sampling those should be further investigated
      <span class="hr"/>
     </td>
     <td align="left" valign="bottom">• Investigate presence and prevalence of pathogenic species
      <span class="hr"/>
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" valign="bottom"> 
      <span class="hr"/>
     </td>
     <td align="left" valign="bottom">• Make a countrywide standardised survey to allow comparing abundance between sites.
      <span class="hr"/>
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left"> </td>
     <td align="left">• In a given area, what is the probability 1) to get a tick bite, 2) that this tick was infected with pathogens 3) infected by which pathogen(s)</td>
    </tr>
   </tbody>
  </table>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">I. ricinus</span> is the main vector of diseases in Belgium because it is present in most vegetated areas, carries many pathogens and is responsible for most tick bites in humans. Its distribution highlights the possibility of becoming infected by the pathogenic agent of Lyme borreliosis in any province. Other species might play a role by maintaining pathogens present in wildlife, or by bringing pathogens closer to people in their houses and gardens. While the number of bites on humans caused by other species is less than by 
  <span class="italic">I. ricinus</span>, occurrence of such an event in unexpected areas such as houses or gardens or during the winter season extends the risk to people not considered to be at risk and increases the probability of a tick bite being ignored. Some places seem to pose a greater risk with more abundant tick populations, higher diversity of pathogens or both, but this should be confirmed. Current prevention measures target 
  <span class="italic">B. burgdorferi s.l.</span> mainly through deticking. Other pathogens are increasingly investigated and found in domestic animals, wildlife or humans and transmission of some of those can occur at the time of the tick bite without delay (e.g. TBEV). Avoidance behaviour should be promoted such as avoiding areas with ferns [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B108" href="#B108">108</a>], wearing boots and long trousers or repellent, using deticking as the second line measure. Another reason to avoid ticks is that in Belgium only 30% of Lyme patients remember a bite and 35% never develop 
  <span class="italic">Erythema migrans</span>[
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B109" href="#B109">109</a>]. Lyme disease can be difficult to diagnose in the absence of 
  <span class="italic">Erythema migrans</span> and particularly if additional symptoms are caused by co-occurring pathogens.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The analysis of the presence of pathogens in ticks might be easier than in human blood as organisms are more easily detected by PCR in ticks than in blood. Systematic surveys using ticks as sentinels could assess the prevalence of the pathogens in wildlife. Geolocation of tick and pathogen records allows integration into a more general databases such as those developed in the framework of The Vbornet [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B5" href="#B5">5</a>] or the TICK MAP initiative [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B110" href="#B110">110</a>] and could help fulfil the empty maps for tick and tick-borne disease occurrence in Belgium [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B4" href="#B4">4</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B6" href="#B6">6</a>]. This study based on imperfect sampling data calls for an increased surveillance of ticks and tick-borne species at a detailed spatial scale as well as clarification of local vector status for tick species and pathogens which occur in these species. A systematic survey of ticks and associated pathogens is called for in Europe, as well as better characterisation of species interaction in the ecology of tick-borne diseases.
 </p>
</sec>
