<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="methods" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Three sources of tick locations were considered: new tick collections, literature collections and “grey datasets”. Quality levels are proposed for each record to document for example accuracy of tick location according to type of host/vegetation (lower if captured on moving animals such as dog or deer). Information on localisation, collection, vegetation or host, pathogen load, and original data source were compiled in an excel database (Additional file 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">1</a>). A systematic literature search was made based on ISI web of knowledge using the keywords “tick AND ecology” from 1989 to 2001 and “tick” from 2002 to 2011. Additional articles resulted from a specific search on presence and pathogenicity of microorganisms found in ticks. The database and additional literature articles form the basis for this paper and are examined for the following items: geographical distribution, species behaviour, ecology, presence of micro-organisms. Consequences for public health and prevention are highlighted. For some sites additional details were provided by authors, however, the methodology is already described in published articles and summarised in the Additional file 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">1</a>. This includes (1) Collection BAYER, 579 sites [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B13" href="#B13">13</a>], (2) Collection RLVBD, 51 sites [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B14" href="#B14">14</a>], (3) Collection UGENT FOREST, 33 sites [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B15" href="#B15">15</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B16" href="#B16">16</a>], (4) Collection ARSIA, 17 sites [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B17" href="#B17">17</a>], (5) Collection UCLIREC, 5 sites [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B18" href="#B18">18</a>], and (6) Collection UA1, 16 sites [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B7" href="#B7">7</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B19" href="#B19">19</a>-
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B22" href="#B22">22</a>]. Collection GREY DATA includes tick field observations from the website of NATAGORA and NATUURPUNT (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.observations.be" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.observations.be</span>, 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.waarnemingen.be" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.waarnemingen.be</span>) by registered users involved with nature related activities from 1980 until February 2012. Methodologies for original tick collections are described in detail below:
 </p>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Collection VANIMPE</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the framework of the convention 5284a funded by IRSIA (Institut pour l′encouragement de la recherche dans l′industrie et l′agriculture), the center of acarology (UCL) led two collection campaigns in the Campine, the plateau brabançon and the Condroz. The regions were selected based on local Lyme borreliosis cases and favourable tick habitat. The first campaign in 1989 targeted 30 sites and the second campaign prospected 234 sites from May to October 1990 including 79 days of prospection. Ticks were collected from the environment by flagging. Each collection lasted 2 hours and UTM coordinates were checked on maps (100 m).</p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Collection WILDSCREEN</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From 2007 to 2009, ticks from wild cervids (
   <span class="italic">Cervus elaphus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">Capreolus capreolus</span>) found dead, hunted or killed for sanitary reasons were collected by the Wild Screen Network disease monitoring activities in Southern Belgium [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B23" href="#B23">23</a>]. Ticks were preserved in 70% ethanol at room temperature, and morphologically identified up to stage and species level (by L. Lempereur and A. Nahayo). Sex and repletion were recorded. 
   <span class="italic">Dermacentor reticulatus</span> was also collected on wild cervids from 2010 to 2012. As 
   <span class="italic">D. reticulatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">D. marginatus</span> may show overlapping phenotypes [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B24" href="#B24">24</a>], a PCR was used for confirmation, targeting the 
   <span class="italic">Dermacentor</span> second Internal Transcribed Spacer 2 (ITS2) with the following primers: ITS_forward (5′-GTG-CGT-CCG-TCG-ACT-CGT-TTT-GA-3′) and ITS_reverse (5′-ACG-GCG-GAC-TAC-GAC-GGA-ATG-C-3′) [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B25" href="#B25">25</a>]. The DNA purification was carried out using the NucleoSpin tissue kit for tissue protocol (Macherey-Nagel GmbH, Germany). Samples were frozen in liquid nitrogen and homogenized on a Tissue Lyser
   <span class="sup">®</span> (Qiagen, GmbH, Germany). PCR conditions were as follow: each reaction was carried out in 50 μL volume containing 4 μl of the DNA preparation, 5 μl of each 2 mM dNTP, 2 μl of each 10 μM oligonucleotide primer, 2 U of TaqDNA polymerase (New England Bio labs) with 5 μl of the 10x PCR supplied buffer and completed to 50 μl with sterile water. PCR was achieved with an initial denaturation cycle at 95°C for 5 min, followed by 35 cycles (94°C, 45 s), annealing (53°C, 45 s), extension (72°C, 70 s) and a final extension step at 72°C for 10 min. All ITS2 PCR products were sequenced using a modified Sanger method with the Big Dye terminator kit version 3.1 and resolved with a 3730 ABI capillary sequencer (Applied Bio systems). Sequencing reaction was performed with the same primers as for the PCR and sequences aligned by BLAST search.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Collection ITG</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ticks were collected by flagging for several years (site 1, 60, 172).</p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Collection IRSNB</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Additional tick locations registered in museum collections were provided by the IRSNB (Institut Royal des Sciences Naturelles de Belgique).</p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Collection DGZ</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While investigating anaplasmosis in 11 farms in Flanders, in 2011, the Dierengezonheidzorg (DGZ – Animal Health Care Flanders, Belgium) recorded 
   <span class="italic">I. ricinus</span> ticks on several animals from those 11 farms.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Collection GLAXOSMITHKLINE</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ticks were captured by flagging in 1999 in 3 sites in Belgium (sites 228, 242, 353).</p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Collection MARTIN</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">D. reticulatus</span> was found on a human around Namur and a trypanosome discovered in the intestine of 
   <span class="italic">I. ricinus</span> in the context of other research [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B26" href="#B26">26</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Collection UGENT VETE</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The clinic of poultry diseases of Ghent University performs diagnosis required by individuals. In this framework they recorded a tick infestation on a pigeon from 
   <span class="italic">Argas</span> species, probably 
   <span class="italic">Argas reflexus</span> in July 2012 near Berlaar (site 303) in the province of Antwerp.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
