<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ecological traits influencing the potential vector role of tick species</div>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The major vector 
   <span class="italic">I. ricinus</span> – a generalist species
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">I. ricinus</span> is a confirmed vector for many human pathogens (Table 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="T5" href="#T5">5</a>). Several factors contribute to the efficiency of 
   <span class="italic">I. ricinus</span>[
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B55" href="#B55">55</a>]: (1) it is the most abundant tick species in Europe with all stages readily biting humans [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B56" href="#B56">56</a>]. (2) This species takes one meal on 3 different hosts in one life cycle and parasitizes a wide range of hosts from mammals (
   <span class="italic">e.g.</span> squirrels, badgers, wild boars, cervids, foxes, dogs, cats, cows, rodents, bats) to birds (common blackbird, European robin, pheasant, nest of the Eagle owl), reptiles, lizards and amphibians [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B57" href="#B57">57</a>-
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B59" href="#B59">59</a>]. Larvae and nymphs are found on any hosts and frequently on rodents or birds [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B60" href="#B60">60</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B61" href="#B61">61</a>]. Adults feed on larger mammals. A large range of hosts means that there are opportunities to encounter many pathogens and disperse in many habitats, with for example 
   <span class="italic">I. ricinus</span> representing 20% of ticks found on 
   <span class="italic">Parus major</span>[
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B7" href="#B7">7</a>]. (3) Phenologic plasticity is wide with all stages surviving 2 weeks under water, several ticks surviving at -10°C, and non engorged nymphs kept alive several months in a fridge (5°C) waking up in minutes if heated by hand contact. The species is vulnerable to desiccation and will not be encountered in arid or non-vegetated environments. Temperatures over 35°C for two weeks will kill all stages [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B35" href="#B35">35</a>]. Tolerance to desiccation can be higher in ticks infected by pathogens [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B62" href="#B62">62</a>]. This species walks on average 40 cm around its questing post and finds shelter in litter or soil cracks [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B35" href="#B35">35</a>]. While ticks interrupt questing to move down the vegetation, in order to rehydrate (quiescence), Perret 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span> discovered that after dark, quiescence was often interrupted by walking events not necessarily leading to questing, with ticks walking repeatedly 9 m. They suggested that some of these movements represent horizontal walks if the ticks were not confined to their experimental vertical channels and that some of these movements represent activities that enable ticks to find a favourable questing site in nature [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B63" href="#B63">63</a>]. Similar experiments but in horizontal arenas did not record such movements [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B64" href="#B64">64</a>]. 
   <span class="italic">I. ricinus</span> is widely distributed in Belgium with sites of apparently higher occurrence (around sites 219, 286, 288, 374, 499) (Figure 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F3" href="#F3">3</a>). Lack of standardisation impedes calculation of tick densities and tick abundance and is presented here as the total number of specimens collected in a site. While abundance is expected to decrease from East to West with decreasing forest cover, this is not what comes out of the general map. Few occurrences are recorded in the Southeast despite high forest cover, but few surveys are carried out in that region, while many surveys took place in Campine to clarify tick presence. The large abundance around the Meuse area is picked up as well as decreased abundance between the Meuse and Brussels, which corresponds to a highly cultivated area (Hesbaye). Abundance is also lower along the coast, which is intensely cultivated. High abundances are recorded along the Dutch border and might reflect an increase in tick populations such as recorded in the Netherlands. These trends need, however, to be confirmed because of the lack of standardisation in sampling.
  </p>
  <div id="F3" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>
     <span class="bold">Map of </span>
     <span class="bold">
      <span class="italic">I. ricinus </span>
     </span>
     <span class="bold">with abundance and hot spots. </span>Map of existing 
     <span class="italic">I. ricinus</span> records in Belgium. Abundance is based on number of ticks collected and is not standardized between sites. Collection lasted days in some sites and only a few hours in other sites, however, details on collection methods are often lacking and raw numbers of collected ticks are thus presented. Numbers labelling each site correspond to site number in Additional file 
     <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">1</a>.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="1756-3305-6-190-3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Secondary vectors 
   <span class="italic">I. hexagonus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">D. reticulatus</span>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">I. hexagonus</span> is a confirmed vector of 
   <span class="italic">B. burgdorferi s.l.</span>[
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B65" href="#B65">65</a>] with 28% prevalence recorded [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B66" href="#B66">66</a>]. It is a nidiculous species found in burrows and occasionally in caves [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B44" href="#B44">44</a>]. This reduces human vector contact but several characteristics must be highlighted: 1) human infestations were frequent during the war when people sheltered in underground sites during air raids [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B45" href="#B45">45</a>] and 
   <span class="italic">I. hexagonus</span> is considered a common parasite of man in Germany and the United Kingdom [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B43" href="#B43">43</a>], 2) the species has a wide range of hosts such as hedgehogs, mustelids, foxes, polecat, badger, roe deer [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B30" href="#B30">30</a>], as well as dogs and cats which can increase the spread of ticks and import ticks in gardens close to humans, 3) 
   <span class="italic">I. hexagonus</span> is found in urban gardens [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B33" href="#B33">33</a>], 4) most hedgehogs are infested [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B67" href="#B67">67</a>] and the presence of ticks in their surface nests is a potential threat when gardening [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B33" href="#B33">33</a>], 5) This species brings pathogens to people normally not at risk for tick bites (just gardening) and can remain undetected for a longer time, 6) it is active throughout the year [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B68" href="#B68">68</a>], 7) because of 
   <span class="italic">B. burgdorferi s.l.</span> transovarial transmission [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B65" href="#B65">65</a>], this species could maintain a silent high rate of infection creating long term foci of high infection in the wildlife in areas where it acts as reservoir, 8) finally, Lyme borreliosis could be picked up by 
   <span class="italic">I. ricinus</span> sharing the same host. In Belgium, 
   <span class="italic">I. hexagonus</span> is widespread on cats and dogs [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B13" href="#B13">13</a>] and has been observed on many mammals (Table 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="T3" href="#T3">3</a>), on humans [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B27" href="#B27">27</a>], in nests, burrows, caves (sites 594, 617), house (site 200) and on grass (sites 492, 670). Populations might fluctuate between years [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B27" href="#B27">27</a>]. The species in Belgium carries all the pathogenic species of 
   <span class="italic">Borrelia burgdorferi s.l</span>., 
   <span class="italic">A. phagocytophilum</span> as well as the suspected pathogen 
   <span class="italic">R. helvetica</span>[
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B13" href="#B13">13</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">D. reticulatus</span> might be restricted to limited areas and not actively questing in the warm months when people are entering risky areas. 
   <span class="italic">D. reticulatus</span> is reported on wild boar, cervids, dogs, horses and cats in the French Ardennes [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B37" href="#B37">37</a>], wolves or rarely birds [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B27" href="#B27">27</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B32" href="#B32">32</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B43" href="#B43">43</a>]. It can bite humans [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B69" href="#B69">69</a>]. Adults are captured by flagging but immatures are nidiculous. This species seems to be expanding its distribution in Europe. In Belgium, the tick has probably been present for some time with one specimen recorded on vegetation in 1950 (site 553), on a dog (site 567) and a human in the eighties (site 376). Established populations have only recently been monitored. Between 2007 and 2009, 16 out of 2297 ticks taken from 161 wild cervids [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B23" href="#B23">23</a>] (WILDSCREEN collection) were 
   <span class="italic">D. reticulatus.</span> From 2010 until March 2012, 150 additional 
   <span class="italic">D. reticulatus</span> were discovered on 3 cervids in 6 sites including one confirmed by flagging (site 797). Confirmation of the species at a molecular level was carried out when sequences of the 646 bp of a part of the ITS2 gene were successfully obtained for 16 
   <span class="italic">D. reticulatus</span>. These 6 sites are in the Southeast but this tick is found on vegetation in the North (60, 130, 172, 535) [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B34" href="#B34">34</a>] and on hosts in other locations [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B13" href="#B13">13</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ticks parasite of birds</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Birds probably carry ticks to most geographical locations but this does not mean that ticks will survive in these locations. The presence of all pathogenic species of 
   <span class="italic">B. burgdorferi s.l.</span> in 
   <span class="italic">I. frontalis</span> and 
   <span class="italic">I. arboricola</span> in Belgium suggests a potential role in the 
   <span class="italic">Borrelia</span> life cycle [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B7" href="#B7">7</a>]. Up to 50% of 
   <span class="italic">I. frontalis</span>[
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B69" href="#B69">69</a>] and also 
   <span class="italic">I. lividus</span>[
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B70" href="#B70">70</a>] were infected with 
   <span class="italic">B. burgdorferi s.l</span>. in other countries. While seldom reported as biting humans, they might maintain the pathogen cycle in wildlife
   <span class="italic">. I. frontalis</span> (previously 
   <span class="italic">I. pari</span>) is associated with a broad range of songbirds, including thrushes (Turdidae), the Great tit and the collared dove [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B7" href="#B7">7</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B28" href="#B28">28</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B43" href="#B43">43</a>], with up to 30 specimens per bird [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B71" href="#B71">71</a>]. 
   <span class="italic">I. frontalis</span> is occasionally collected by flagging [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B72" href="#B72">72</a>] and evidence suggests that it might be more often present in under-storey vegetation than in nests [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B7" href="#B7">7</a>]. In Belgium it has been found on birds in 11 sites. 
   <span class="italic">I. arboricola</span> is found mainly in Europe but was recorded in Egypt on birds coming back to Europe [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B27" href="#B27">27</a>]. It is a nidicolous tick infesting birds and bats [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B73" href="#B73">73</a>]. The Great tit might be the dominant host but heavy infestations occur on the Common starling and Peregrine falcon [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B32" href="#B32">32</a>]. In Belgium it was recorded in 10 places including 3 sites with 70 specimens (sites 233, 252, 337) where the species was actively surveyed. Specimens were found on birds (Table 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="T3" href="#T3">3</a>) and in nests of the House martin. 
   <span class="italic">I. lividus</span> is found on the Sand martin and in their nests [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B27" href="#B27">27</a>]. Experimental records showed that these ticks were collected on the Great tit [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B74" href="#B74">74</a>] and it was found repeatedly in nests of the House martin in Japan [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B75" href="#B75">75</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ticks parasite of rodents and small mammals</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Small mammals and particularly rodents are reservoirs of many diseases, but few studies have targeted ticks on rodents in Belgium. Next to 
   <span class="italic">I. ricinus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">I. hexagonus</span>, ticks present on rodents and small mammals include 
   <span class="italic">I. canisuga, I. trianguliceps</span> and 
   <span class="italic">I. acuminatus.</span> These species are carriers of some pathogens (Table 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="T5" href="#T5">5</a>) including 
   <span class="italic">B. burgdorferi s.l.</span>[
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B76" href="#B76">76</a>-
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B78" href="#B78">78</a>] with 30% prevalence for 
   <span class="italic">I. canisuga</span> in Spain [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B66" href="#B66">66</a>]. 
   <span class="italic">I. canisuga</span> is part of a group of species difficult to discriminate morphologically (including 
   <span class="italic">I. hexagonus</span>, 
   <span class="italic">I. arboricola</span> and 
   <span class="italic">I. lividus</span>) [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B27" href="#B27">27</a>]. 
   <span class="italic">I. canisuga</span> is widely distributed and found on half of the foxes in Northern France [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B30" href="#B30">30</a>] but also on polecats, weasels, badgers, Eurasian owls, dogs and cats [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B79" href="#B79">79</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B80" href="#B80">80</a>] with up to 200 specimens reported on one dog [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B81" href="#B81">81</a>]. In Great Britain, 11% of the ticks found on dogs were 
   <span class="italic">I. canisuga</span>[
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B80" href="#B80">80</a>] but none were reported in a Belgian survey [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B13" href="#B13">13</a>]. This nidiculous species is found in nests, burrows or rarely in caves [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B44" href="#B44">44</a>] with fed females climbing upwards in crevices above ground [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B28" href="#B28">28</a>]. In Belgium, only two specimens were found, on a polecat (site 132) and a nest (site 207). 
   <span class="italic">I. trianguliceps</span> is found almost exclusively on micromammals including shrews and rodents, exceptionally on moles, birds or goats and very rarely on humans [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B27" href="#B27">27</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B55" href="#B55">55</a>]. The tick is nidiculous but may wait for hosts on the soil surface [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B82" href="#B82">82</a>]. It is commonly found in wet biotopes including moorlands, meadows, or pine, deciduous and birch forests [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B83" href="#B83">83</a>]. In France, immature are found with immature of 
   <span class="italic">D. reticulatus</span>, 
   <span class="italic">I. acuminatus</span>, and 
   <span class="italic">I. ricinus</span> on the same rodents [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B84" href="#B84">84</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B85" href="#B85">85</a>]. In Belgium, 
   <span class="italic">I. trianguliceps</span> is probably frequent and found on rodents in 8 sites. 
   <span class="italic">I. acuminatus</span> parasitizes small mammals, birds and sometimes humans and is mostly found in nests and burrows [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B28" href="#B28">28</a>]. Only one specimen was found in Belgium on a wood mouse (site 630).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Other tick species sharing habitats with humans</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Three tick species are not frequent but bite humans and can establish populations inside houses, making them a potential threat. 
   <span class="italic">Rhipicephalus sanguineus</span> is a tropical tick imported on dogs or rarely with hares, cattles, horses, or plants [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B55" href="#B55">55</a>]. The tick cannot survive outside but multiplies inside houses and dog kennels [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B27" href="#B27">27</a>]. Ticks hunt for hosts by moving actively [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B86" href="#B86">86</a>], can drink free water and survive for years inside. This was shown to cause house infestations in 12 cities in the Netherlands, in Switzerland [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B87" href="#B87">87</a>] and 334 foci in Berlin [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B88" href="#B88">88</a>]. Tick populations can build up in some years from one engorged female to thousands of ticks and eggs [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B87" href="#B87">87</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B89" href="#B89">89</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B90" href="#B90">90</a>]. Eggs are hidden in cracks and crevices and ticks crawl around. Mean temperature probably limits its northward distribution [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B91" href="#B91">91</a>]. This species is rarely found on humans [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B27" href="#B27">27</a>], but seems to more willingly bite humans occasionally, representing at times up to 7% of ticks biting men [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B92" href="#B92">92</a>]. Up to 22 ticks on one man were reported in France [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B93" href="#B93">93</a>]. Some studies suggest that this highlights a change of behaviour related to temperature increase [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B94" href="#B94">94</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B95" href="#B95">95</a>] but this needs to be further investigated. 
   <span class="italic">R. sanguineus</span> is a vector of highly pathogenic 
   <span class="italic">Rickettsiae conorii</span> with confirmed transovarial passage [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B96" href="#B96">96</a>]. Prevalence in nymphs infesting houses can reach up to 40% [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B87" href="#B87">87</a>], against usually 1% [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B94" href="#B94">94</a>] outside. In Belgium, 
   <span class="italic">R. sanguineus</span> was found in houses in Antwerp [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B27" href="#B27">27</a>] (site 210), Hoboken (site 199) [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B90" href="#B90">90</a>] and Maldegem (site 71), but also on dogs with a travel history (e.g. sites 338, 426, 536, 684) [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B13" href="#B13">13</a>] and on humans (site 210) [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B27" href="#B27">27</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">Argas reflexus</span> is frequent mainly on pigeons but readily bites humans, chickens or horses in buildings in the absence of pigeons [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B43" href="#B43">43</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B55" href="#B55">55</a>]. With 
   <span class="italic">Argas vespertilionis</span> (see below) this species belongs to the Argasidae family, which differs from Ixodidae in their feeding habits. Ticks take many short meals. Nymphs and adults engorge in less than an hour. Ticks feed on eight to twelve hosts per life cycle and spend most of their life in the hosts’ habitat [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B97" href="#B97">97</a>]. Building infestations are undetected for years because of nocturnal host-seeking behaviour, high host specificity and short meals [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B98" href="#B98">98</a>]. However, when pigeons are eradicated, 
   <span class="italic">A. reflexus</span> appear seeking for alternative hosts [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B97" href="#B97">97</a>]. Even if the build-up of a large number of ticks takes years, thousands of ticks were found repeatedly when investigating 188 infested buildings in Germany [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B98" href="#B98">98</a>]. Searching for ticks before renovating is now a current recommendation in Germany. Particularities include a long lifetime of up to 9 years without food, low water loss rate, absorption of water vapour at 75% relative humidity and high tolerance of temperature extremes. Movements are restricted to periods of host-seeking, the remaining time being spent resting aggregated in cracks of walls [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B97" href="#B97">97</a>-
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B99" href="#B99">99</a>]. In Belgium ticks were recorded in 7 sites from pigeons, pigeon houses, houses and flats. The bites may cause allergy, anaphylactic shock or loss of consciousness [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B100" href="#B100">100</a>]. It is an unconfirmed vector of human pathogens.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">Argas vespertilionis</span> parasitizes bats [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B43" href="#B43">43</a>]. They stay the whole year in or near caves or other shelters (roofs of houses), the hosts being present or not. Eggs were found together with eggs of 
   <span class="italic">I. hexagonus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">I. vespertilionis</span>[
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B43" href="#B43">43</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B44" href="#B44">44</a>]. Ticks bite alternative hosts in the absence of their usual host and readily bite man. People reported being bitten in caves or in their bed when bats are in the attics [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B55" href="#B55">55</a>]. Larvae attach for 19 days. Nymphs and adults feed in less than one hour [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B97" href="#B97">97</a>]. They take many small meals on many hosts potentially accumulating pathogens. 
   <span class="italic">A. vespertilionis</span> causes irritating bites on humans and viable strains of 
   <span class="italic">C. burnetii</span> were isolated from ticks which had been dead for a year [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B97" href="#B97">97</a>]. While 84% of museum specimens tested positive for 
   <span class="italic">B. burgdorferi s.l.</span> in the UK [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B78" href="#B78">78</a>], this might reflect sample contamination. 
   <span class="italic">Borrelia</span> sp. organisms related to 
   <span class="italic">Borrelia recurrentis</span>, 
   <span class="italic">B. duttonii</span> and 
   <span class="italic">B. crocidurae</span> were present in numbers in a dying bat in the UK [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B101" href="#B101">101</a>] parasitized by 
   <span class="italic">A. vespertilionis</span>. In Belgium, 11 ticks were found on hosts in four locations.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Species of little interest for human health</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">Ixodes vespertilionis</span> was never recorded biting man. It parasites the Lesser horseshoe and the Great bats. It actively searches for hosts by walking slowly on very long legs in caves. It is restricted to the darkest part of the caves, offering 100% humidity [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B28" href="#B28">28</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B102" href="#B102">102</a>]. Decrease of humidity to 61% increases tick activity until they die after a few hours. All stages are mainly found in caves, moving away with the host but coming back for molting and egg laying [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B102" href="#B102">102</a>]. Specimens are not on the ground but on walls and roof crevices. In West France low densities are present in most caves. Ticks were found in caves or on bats in 10 sites in East Belgium [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B27" href="#B27">27</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
