<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="supplementary-material" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Supplementary Material</div>
 <div content-type="local-data" id="S1" class="supplementary-material" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Additional file 1</div>
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Detailed information available per sites of occurrence for ticks recorded in Belgium.</span> Description: table per site with geographical coordinates in latitude-longitude and in Belgian Lambert, list of records included in the site, list of species included in the sites, literature/collection references for the sites and general quality level. Additionally to the main tab a Memo tab describes each field. 
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="1756-3305-6-190-S1.xls" class="media" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Click here for file</p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </div>
 <div content-type="local-data" id="S2" class="supplementary-material" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Additional file 2</div>
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Records of tick occurrence in Belgium. </span>Description: a kmz file to open in Google Earth with 5 folders to navigate into the database. (1) Records per tick species: one point per record classified in folders by tick species, (2) Records per pathogens: one point per record classified in folders by pathogen genus then species, (3) Records per authors: one point per record classified in folders by authors, (4) Sites: one point per site with information on tick species and pathogens, (5) Records: One point per record with information available in the Additional file 
    <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">1</a> included.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="1756-3305-6-190-S2.kmz" class="media" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Click here for file</p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </div>
 <div content-type="local-data" id="S3" class="supplementary-material" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Additional file 3</div>
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Micro-organisms found locally or abroad in tick species present or potentially present in Belgium. </span>Description: tick species, reference of the article and details on the records, discussion on pathogenicity to humans and potential transmission by tick species, and pathogenicity status as well as reference to specific articles and overall assessment of vector status.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="1756-3305-6-190-S3.xls" class="media" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Click here for file</p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </div>
</sec>
