<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Secondary vectors 
  <span class="italic">I. hexagonus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">D. reticulatus</span>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">I. hexagonus</span> is a confirmed vector of 
  <span class="italic">B. burgdorferi s.l.</span>[
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B65" href="#B65">65</a>] with 28% prevalence recorded [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B66" href="#B66">66</a>]. It is a nidiculous species found in burrows and occasionally in caves [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B44" href="#B44">44</a>]. This reduces human vector contact but several characteristics must be highlighted: 1) human infestations were frequent during the war when people sheltered in underground sites during air raids [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B45" href="#B45">45</a>] and 
  <span class="italic">I. hexagonus</span> is considered a common parasite of man in Germany and the United Kingdom [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B43" href="#B43">43</a>], 2) the species has a wide range of hosts such as hedgehogs, mustelids, foxes, polecat, badger, roe deer [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B30" href="#B30">30</a>], as well as dogs and cats which can increase the spread of ticks and import ticks in gardens close to humans, 3) 
  <span class="italic">I. hexagonus</span> is found in urban gardens [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B33" href="#B33">33</a>], 4) most hedgehogs are infested [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B67" href="#B67">67</a>] and the presence of ticks in their surface nests is a potential threat when gardening [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B33" href="#B33">33</a>], 5) This species brings pathogens to people normally not at risk for tick bites (just gardening) and can remain undetected for a longer time, 6) it is active throughout the year [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B68" href="#B68">68</a>], 7) because of 
  <span class="italic">B. burgdorferi s.l.</span> transovarial transmission [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B65" href="#B65">65</a>], this species could maintain a silent high rate of infection creating long term foci of high infection in the wildlife in areas where it acts as reservoir, 8) finally, Lyme borreliosis could be picked up by 
  <span class="italic">I. ricinus</span> sharing the same host. In Belgium, 
  <span class="italic">I. hexagonus</span> is widespread on cats and dogs [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B13" href="#B13">13</a>] and has been observed on many mammals (Table 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="T3" href="#T3">3</a>), on humans [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B27" href="#B27">27</a>], in nests, burrows, caves (sites 594, 617), house (site 200) and on grass (sites 492, 670). Populations might fluctuate between years [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B27" href="#B27">27</a>]. The species in Belgium carries all the pathogenic species of 
  <span class="italic">Borrelia burgdorferi s.l</span>., 
  <span class="italic">A. phagocytophilum</span> as well as the suspected pathogen 
  <span class="italic">R. helvetica</span>[
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B13" href="#B13">13</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">D. reticulatus</span> might be restricted to limited areas and not actively questing in the warm months when people are entering risky areas. 
  <span class="italic">D. reticulatus</span> is reported on wild boar, cervids, dogs, horses and cats in the French Ardennes [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B37" href="#B37">37</a>], wolves or rarely birds [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B27" href="#B27">27</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B32" href="#B32">32</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B43" href="#B43">43</a>]. It can bite humans [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B69" href="#B69">69</a>]. Adults are captured by flagging but immatures are nidiculous. This species seems to be expanding its distribution in Europe. In Belgium, the tick has probably been present for some time with one specimen recorded on vegetation in 1950 (site 553), on a dog (site 567) and a human in the eighties (site 376). Established populations have only recently been monitored. Between 2007 and 2009, 16 out of 2297 ticks taken from 161 wild cervids [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B23" href="#B23">23</a>] (WILDSCREEN collection) were 
  <span class="italic">D. reticulatus.</span> From 2010 until March 2012, 150 additional 
  <span class="italic">D. reticulatus</span> were discovered on 3 cervids in 6 sites including one confirmed by flagging (site 797). Confirmation of the species at a molecular level was carried out when sequences of the 646 bp of a part of the ITS2 gene were successfully obtained for 16 
  <span class="italic">D. reticulatus</span>. These 6 sites are in the Southeast but this tick is found on vegetation in the North (60, 130, 172, 535) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B34" href="#B34">34</a>] and on hosts in other locations [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B13" href="#B13">13</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
