<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The major vector 
  <span class="italic">I. ricinus</span> – a generalist species
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">I. ricinus</span> is a confirmed vector for many human pathogens (Table 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="T5" href="#T5">5</a>). Several factors contribute to the efficiency of 
  <span class="italic">I. ricinus</span>[
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B55" href="#B55">55</a>]: (1) it is the most abundant tick species in Europe with all stages readily biting humans [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B56" href="#B56">56</a>]. (2) This species takes one meal on 3 different hosts in one life cycle and parasitizes a wide range of hosts from mammals (
  <span class="italic">e.g.</span> squirrels, badgers, wild boars, cervids, foxes, dogs, cats, cows, rodents, bats) to birds (common blackbird, European robin, pheasant, nest of the Eagle owl), reptiles, lizards and amphibians [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B57" href="#B57">57</a>-
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B59" href="#B59">59</a>]. Larvae and nymphs are found on any hosts and frequently on rodents or birds [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B60" href="#B60">60</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B61" href="#B61">61</a>]. Adults feed on larger mammals. A large range of hosts means that there are opportunities to encounter many pathogens and disperse in many habitats, with for example 
  <span class="italic">I. ricinus</span> representing 20% of ticks found on 
  <span class="italic">Parus major</span>[
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B7" href="#B7">7</a>]. (3) Phenologic plasticity is wide with all stages surviving 2 weeks under water, several ticks surviving at -10°C, and non engorged nymphs kept alive several months in a fridge (5°C) waking up in minutes if heated by hand contact. The species is vulnerable to desiccation and will not be encountered in arid or non-vegetated environments. Temperatures over 35°C for two weeks will kill all stages [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B35" href="#B35">35</a>]. Tolerance to desiccation can be higher in ticks infected by pathogens [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B62" href="#B62">62</a>]. This species walks on average 40 cm around its questing post and finds shelter in litter or soil cracks [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B35" href="#B35">35</a>]. While ticks interrupt questing to move down the vegetation, in order to rehydrate (quiescence), Perret 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span> discovered that after dark, quiescence was often interrupted by walking events not necessarily leading to questing, with ticks walking repeatedly 9 m. They suggested that some of these movements represent horizontal walks if the ticks were not confined to their experimental vertical channels and that some of these movements represent activities that enable ticks to find a favourable questing site in nature [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B63" href="#B63">63</a>]. Similar experiments but in horizontal arenas did not record such movements [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B64" href="#B64">64</a>]. 
  <span class="italic">I. ricinus</span> is widely distributed in Belgium with sites of apparently higher occurrence (around sites 219, 286, 288, 374, 499) (Figure 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F3" href="#F3">3</a>). Lack of standardisation impedes calculation of tick densities and tick abundance and is presented here as the total number of specimens collected in a site. While abundance is expected to decrease from East to West with decreasing forest cover, this is not what comes out of the general map. Few occurrences are recorded in the Southeast despite high forest cover, but few surveys are carried out in that region, while many surveys took place in Campine to clarify tick presence. The large abundance around the Meuse area is picked up as well as decreased abundance between the Meuse and Brussels, which corresponds to a highly cultivated area (Hesbaye). Abundance is also lower along the coast, which is intensely cultivated. High abundances are recorded along the Dutch border and might reflect an increase in tick populations such as recorded in the Netherlands. These trends need, however, to be confirmed because of the lack of standardisation in sampling.
 </p>
 <div id="F3" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Map of </span>
    <span class="bold">
     <span class="italic">I. ricinus </span>
    </span>
    <span class="bold">with abundance and hot spots. </span>Map of existing 
    <span class="italic">I. ricinus</span> records in Belgium. Abundance is based on number of ticks collected and is not standardized between sites. Collection lasted days in some sites and only a few hours in other sites, however, details on collection methods are often lacking and raw numbers of collected ticks are thus presented. Numbers labelling each site correspond to site number in Additional file 
    <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">1</a>.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="1756-3305-6-190-3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
