<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>There are three potential options to lessen future risks to both vulnerable whale species and krill. First, greenhouse gas emissions could be reduced. With global emissions tracking the highest greenhouse gas emissions scenario (RCP8.5 (Peters et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-bib-0069" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>)), emission reductions will slow the trophic impacts of warming on Antarctic ecosystems, such as changes in krill biomass. It is beyond the year 2030–2040 where the projected trajectories of some whale populations start to diverge in the vulnerable Pacific region given climate change. There is still time to reduce emissions and minimize the impact of climate change on recovering whale populations. This will also have direct implications for maintaining commercial krill fisheries in the Southern Ocean, particularly given the expected future expansion of krill fisheries, which is likely to further compromise the recovery of baleen whales. Second, consideration of the climate‐driven trophic impacts on krill could inform setting sustainable catch limits in the future (Kawaguchi, Nicol, &amp; Press,
 <xref rid="gcb14573-bib-0039" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>), which would improve resilience of dependent predators such as whales (Trivelpiece et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-bib-0108" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>). This is particularly important considering the expected future expansion of krill fisheries (Nicol et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-bib-0067" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>), and projected warming to a level that exceeds the thermal tolerance of krill, leading to reduced catch potential in the Atlantic/Indian region where krill fisheries and many whales are currently concentrated (Constable, 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-bib-0017" ref-type="ref">2002</xref>; Hewitt, Watters et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">2004</xref>; Kock, Purves, &amp; Duhamel, 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-bib-0044" ref-type="ref">2006</xref>). The temperature threshold in our krill growth model resulted in a stepwise (nonlinear) more negative impact on krill, highlighting the need to avoid extreme temperature thresholds to maintain a safe operating space within which Southern Ocean ecosystems can continue to recover and thrive (Rockström et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-bib-0086" ref-type="ref">2009b</xref>; Scheffer et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-bib-0088" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>). This is consistent with the growing consensus towards a “2°C guardrail” approach, whereby the rise in global mean temperature is contained to no more than 2°C above the preindustrial level (Rockström et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-bib-0085" ref-type="ref">2009a</xref>). Last, there is the potential to reduce nonclimate stressors such as fishing gear interactions, ship strikes, noise pollution and commercial whale harvest, all of which reduce whale numbers or negatively affect whale fitness (Clapham, 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>; National Academies of Sciences,
 <xref rid="gcb14573-bib-0066" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). Our findings show Pacific blue, fin and southern right whales are the most at risk, and continued monitoring of these populations is needed. Given that both humpback and southern right whales, currently listed as Least Concern by the IUCN Red List (Reilly et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-bib-0081" ref-type="ref">2008a</xref>, 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-bib-0082" ref-type="ref">2008b</xref>, 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-bib-0083" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>), were predicted to decline in numbers, re‐evaluation of these taxa against the Red List criteria might be warranted in the near future, to higher risk categories (Akçakaya, Butchart, Mace, Stuart, &amp; Hilton‐Taylor, 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-bib-0002" ref-type="ref">2006</xref>; Van Der Hoop et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-bib-0111" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>). However, without immediate reduction in emissions to reduce global warming, the success of other regional management actions may be limited (Simmonds &amp; Eliott, 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-bib-0095" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>; Simmonds &amp; Isaac, 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-bib-0096" ref-type="ref">2007</xref>).
</p>
