<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We found fairly minor differences in historical whale trajectories and hence in the quality of model fits between our models. This was because historically the changes in temperature in the southern oceans have been small and hence there are no historical analogues to validate the influence of rising temperatures on krill and whales at large scales. Climate change is expected to accelerate in the future, with an increase in atmospheric CO2 of another 560 ppm expected by the end of the century (940 ppm) under the RCP8.5 scenario, and hence the model predictions for whale populations start to diverge. Additionally, there are too few survey and other data available to reliably distinguish between alternative models attempting to explain recent changes in whale populations due to environmental changes over the past two–three decades (the period for which data are available from our model and which includes a slow rise in SST) (Punt, 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-bib-0073" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>; Punt, Bando, Hakamada, &amp; Kishiro, 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-bib-0074" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>). Our historical estimates of total circumpolar whale numbers are consistent with previous estimates (Mori &amp; Butterworth, 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-bib-0063" ref-type="ref">2006</xref>; Tulloch et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-bib-0109" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). Hence, although we did not find a statistically significant difference between our no‐climate and climate‐forced historical model, this also means that including environmental drivers and assuming that these influenced whale dynamics historically is not inconsistent with past observations and provides a comparably good alternative explanation of observed changes over recent years. Other evidence from studies of whale ecology suggests the model of climate effects on whales via their prey (Model 1) is most realistic. Whale populations historically may have responded fairly dramatically to changes in krill due to the massive declines in whales from historical harvesting (Ainley et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-bib-0001" ref-type="ref">2007</xref>; Surma, Pakhomov, &amp; Pitcher, 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-bib-0102" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>), although this is still subject to debate (Ballance et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">2006</xref>). Evidence for strong density dependence in response to prey availability in these whale populations is supported further by demographic data documenting changes in the age at first reproduction (e.g. minke whales (Masaki, 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-bib-0052" ref-type="ref">1979</xref>) and fin whales (Lockyer, 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-bib-0051" ref-type="ref">1972</xref>)). Given these uncertainties, future research into the strength of feedbacks between whale population size and krill numbers is therefore important for predicting the response of whales to climate change.
</p>
