<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="gcb13152-sec-0005" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Length of time series required to detect trends</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For a trend to be rapidly detectable, the ratio of the signal (i.e. the trend magnitude) to the noise (i.e. the variability) needs to be high. The number of years of data needed to detect a trend (
  <span class="italic">n*</span>) in biogeochemical variables is shown in Fig. 
  <a rid="gcb13152-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#gcb13152-fig-0001">1</a>. The natural variability, here defined as the standard deviation of the residuals (see 
  <a rid="gcb13152-sec-0002" ref-type="sec" href="#gcb13152-sec-0002">Materials and methods</a>), is presented in Fig. S2. In many variables, 
  <span class="italic">n*</span> is shorter at low than at high latitudes. This arises because at low latitudes trends are strong but variability tends to be smaller than at high latitudes, and therefore fewer years of data are needed to detect a long‐term trend. An example of how the noise and signal interact in estimating 
  <span class="italic">n*</span> can be found in the Northeast Pacific oxygen content, where low noise and a strong decreasing trend result in an estimated ~25 years of data needed to detect a trend. A scenario at the other extreme is nitrate concentration in the Southern Ocean which has weak noise, but also a weak trend, resulting in larger 
  <span class="italic">n*</span> (&gt;40 years).
 </p>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="gcb13152-fig-0001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Number of years of data needed to distinguish a climate change‐driven trend from natural variability for (a) 
    <span style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">pH</span>, (b) 
    <span style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">SST</span>, (c) oxygen, (d) nitrate, (e) nondiatom 
    <span style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">PP</span>, (f) chlorophyll, (g) export and (h) 
    <span style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">PP</span>. White areas are where less than half of the eight models used here agree on the sign of the trend. Grey dots indicate where the climate change trend does not exceed the natural variability in the timeframe of the simulations (95 years).
   </p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-1" xlink:href="GCB-22-1561-g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The climate change‐driven trends in pH and SST are most rapidly distinguished from natural variability, requiring just 13.9 and 15.5 years of data, respectively (global median values; Table 
  <a rid="gcb13152-tbl-0001" ref-type="table-wrap" href="#gcb13152-tbl-0001">1</a>). Strong trends in response to anthropogenic forcing and, in the case of pH, low natural variability result in rapidly detectable trends, in particular in low latitude regions. For SST, between 20 and 50 years of data are needed to detect a trend in the Southern Ocean and high latitude North Atlantic where warming trends are smallest.
 </p>
 <div id="gcb13152-tbl-0001" xml:lang="en" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Table 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Global median 
    <span class="italic">n*</span> and footprint size
   </p>
  </div>
  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
   <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/>
   <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/>
   <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/>
   <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/>
   <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/>
   <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/>
   <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/>
   <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/>
   <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/>
   <thead valign="top">
    <tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000">
     <th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
     <th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PP (integrated)</th>
     <th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SST (surface)</th>
     <th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">pH (surface)</th>
     <th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Oxygen (200–600 m)</th>
     <th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nitrate (surface)</th>
     <th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chlorophyll (surface)</th>
     <th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Export (100 m)</th>
     <th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nondiatom PP (integrated)</th>
    </tr>
   </thead>
   <tbody>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
      <span class="italic">n</span>*, years
     </td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.3</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.5</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.9</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.3</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29.7</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.5</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.0</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.9</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Footprint, 10
      <span class="sup">6</span> km
      <span class="sup">2</span> (% ocean covered)
     </td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.9 (11)</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.6 (13)</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.5 (15)</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.4 (9)</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.1 (13)</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.9 (12)</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.7 (11)</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.4 (11)</td>
    </tr>
   </tbody>
  </table>
  <div class="table-wrap-foot">
   <fn id="gcb13152-note-0001" class="fn" xmlns="">
    <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Global median value of number of years of data required to detect a climate change‐driven trend above background variability (
     <span class="italic">n*</span>) for eight biogeochemical variables. Global coverage for each variable (10
     <span class="sup">6</span> km
     <span class="sup">2</span>) with percentage of ocean surface covered given in brackets. Full information on 
     <span class="italic">n*</span> and footprint size for all BGC‐SO sites considered can be found in Supporting Information (Tables S2 and S3, respectively).
    </p>
   </fn>
  </div>
  <div class="permissions">
   <span class="copyright-holder">John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd</span>
  </div>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Aside from SST and pH, all other biogeochemical variables require, as a global average, 26–33 years of data to detect a trend (Table 
  <a rid="gcb13152-tbl-0001" ref-type="table-wrap" href="#gcb13152-tbl-0001">1</a>). Of these, trends in oxygen are most rapidly detectable, particularly in the North Pacific and eastern Indian Ocean (15–20 years) where strong decreasing trends in oxygen content are predicted (Fig. S1). Nitrate, chlorophyll, PP, nondiatom PP and export all have a minimum in 
  <span class="italic">n*</span> (&lt;20 years) in the equatorial Atlantic and Benguela region. Trends in nitrate and both total and nondiatom PP are also rapidly detectable (
  <span class="italic">n*</span> &lt; 25 years) in the Atlantic and Indian sectors of the Southern Ocean, at approximately the latitude of the Antarctic Circumpolar Current.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Strong decreasing trends in nitrate and chlorophyll in the Atlantic and east Pacific sectors of the Arctic result in rapidly detectable trends (
  <span class="italic">n*</span> &lt; 25 years). Nevertheless, PP, nondiatom PP and export all have strong increasing trends, although this doesn't necessarily result in shorter 
  <span class="italic">n*</span> due to high natural variability (Fig. S2) in these regions.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As an indication of the overall rapidity with which climate change trends may be detectable in a range of parameters, the median 
  <span class="italic">n*</span> calculated across all eight variables is plotted in Fig. 
  <a rid="gcb13152-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#gcb13152-fig-0002">2</a>. The regions where detecting trends requires the shortest time series of observations (&lt;20 years) are the equatorial Atlantic and Benguela upwelling, in which all variables have relatively short 
  <span class="italic">n*</span> (Fig. 
  <a rid="gcb13152-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#gcb13152-fig-0001">1</a>) due to strong trends and weak natural variability. With 25 years of data, trends are detectable in large parts of the Indian Ocean, particularly the Arabian Sea, and parts of the South and North Pacific gyres, plus a band at 40°S. Long time series of data (&gt;40 years) are needed to detect trends in parts of the Southern Ocean, Northeast Pacific, South Atlantic gyre and northern North Atlantic. In the case of the North Atlantic (Irminger Basin), all variables except pH require very long time series to detect a trend. For the other regions, 
  <span class="italic">n*</span> is long in all variables except pH, SST and oxygen.
 </p>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="gcb13152-fig-0002" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>(a) Map of ocean time series stations with a biogeochemical component (referred to as 
    <span style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">BGC</span>‐
    <span style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">SO</span>s in the text). The map includes only currently operating and planned stations, according to 
    <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.oceansites.org" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.oceansites.org</span>. (b) Median value of 
    <span class="italic">n*</span> (number of years of data required to detect a climate change‐driven trend above background variability) for all eight variables considered here. Plotted is the multivariable median of the multimodel medians shown in Figure 
    <a rid="gcb13152-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#gcb13152-fig-0001">1</a>. White stars mark locations of 
    <span style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">BGC</span>‐
    <span style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">SO</span>s.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-3" xlink:href="GCB-22-1561-g002" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Also plotted in Fig. 
  <a rid="gcb13152-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#gcb13152-fig-0002">2</a> are the positions of 33 planned and existing ocean observing stations which have a significant biogeochemical component. In some cases (Table S2), these stations are located in regions where climate change should be relatively rapidly detectable, for example at ALOHA (ranging from ~13 years for SST to ~29 years for chlorophyll concentration) or the PIRATA stations in the equatorial Atlantic (from ~11 years for SST to ~26 years for oxygen at the southerly station). At other stations, considerably longer time series would be needed to distinguish a climate change trend, for example at BATS (ranging from ~11 years for SST, ~47 years for export flux, to undetectable in a 95 year record for PP) or the Southern Ocean Time Series station off Tasmania (from ~20 years in SST to ~46 years in chlorophyll, to undetectable in export flux).
 </p>
</sec>
