<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="gcb13152-sec-0008" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Limitations</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results presented here are dependent on the ability of the models used to represent the observed natural variability. Global‐scale information on variability derived from satellite data is only available for SST and chlorophyll concentration (and derived products, such as PP). Overall, the models represent the natural variability in SST very well, although it is underestimated in the Arctic (Fig. S4). For chlorophyll, observed variability is generally larger than modelled in the coastal and polar regions (Fig. S5). Typically, modelled variability is lower than observed variability, particularly in biogeochemical parameters (e.g. Cadule 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb13152-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb13152-bib-0004">2010</a>; Laepple &amp; Huybers, 
  <a rid="gcb13152-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb13152-bib-0018">2014</a>). Generally, we find a similar pattern, although with some exceptions such as chlorophyll in the oligotrophic gyres in the HadGEM models (see Fig. S5). Increased levels of variability would result in weaker signal to noise ratio, and thus longer 
  <span class="italic">n*</span>. Note also that the observations do not represent purely natural variability as they contain responses to both natural and anthropogenic forcing. The modelled spatial footprints are similar to those calculated from observed SST and chlorophyll (Fig. S6, compare to Fig. 
  <a rid="gcb13152-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#gcb13152-fig-0003">3</a>b, f). For SST, the pattern and shape of the footprints are very similar in observations and models, although they are slightly larger in the observations so that 18% of the ocean is covered by BGC‐SOs (13% for models). In chlorophyll, results are mixed with the size, shape and isotropy of the footprints being similar in observations and models for some BGC‐SOs, for example BATS and PAP, but not in others, for example OOI‐Argentine. Both observations and models suggest that 12% of the ocean is represented by BGC‐SOs for chlorophyll, although the distribution of coverage is slightly different.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The size and shape of the footprints is also dependent on our definition of ‘representative’, which takes into account the mean and variability of time series. For some studies, other metrics of representativeness will be more appropriate and the size of the footprints would thus change accordingly. Additionally, we test repeatedly for statistical significance. At the 5% critical level chosen here, 1 in 20 regressions will produce a ‘false positive’ (i.e. significant when no correlation is actually present), and therefore footprints may in reality be smaller than shown here. Finally, the relatively coarse resolution of the models excludes (sub)‐mesoscale variability which will act to reduce the size of the footprints.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In our analysis, we test only for linear trends by using a generalized least squares approach. In reality, trends may be nonlinear. We tested whether our linear fits are reasonable by verifying the underlying assumptions that the residuals are AR(1) and normally distributed with a constant variance and found that the majority (~66%) of calculated trends meet these assumptions. Furthermore, even though the linear trends estimated using generalized least squares seem reasonable to estimate 
  <span class="italic">n*</span> in most cases, using different trend detection techniques based on nonparametric statistics or Bayesian approaches (e.g. Chandler &amp; Scott, 
  <a rid="gcb13152-bib-0005" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb13152-bib-0005">2011</a>) may result in different estimates of 
  <span class="italic">n*</span>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Finally, the coarse spatial resolution (1°) of the models (i.e. mesoscale variability is not simulated) and the potential underestimation of temporal variability in the models imply that our results are likely to be a ‘best case’ scenario. In reality, the footprints are likely to be smaller than estimated here, due to unresolved mesoscale variability; similarly, 
  <span class="italic">n*</span> is likely to be longer than estimated here, due to unresolved temporal variability.
 </p>
</sec>
