<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="gcb13152-sec-0002" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Materials and methods</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Output from eight Earth System Models (Table S1) forced with the IPCC's ‘business‐as‐usual’ scenario (RCP8.5; Moss 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb13152-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb13152-bib-0022">2010</a>) for the period 2006–2100 and historical (1860–2005) and control runs (last 100‐year chunk available) was downloaded from the CMIP5 archive (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pcmdi9.llnl.gov" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://pcmdi9.llnl.gov</span>). The variables used were annual average sea surface temperature (SST), surface pH, surface chlorophyll concentration and surface nitrate concentration, annual integrated PP and nondiatom PP, annual total export flux at 100 m depth, and annual average oxygen concentration averaged over the 200–600 m depth range, which encompasses the main thermocline (Gruber, 
  <a rid="gcb13152-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb13152-bib-0011">2011</a>; Bopp 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb13152-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb13152-bib-0003">2013</a>). Nondiatom PP is used here as a proxy for changes in the relative importance of smaller phytoplankton. These variables were chosen as they are routinely measured at ocean observing stations either autonomously (e.g. temperature, chlorophyll, oxygen) or during regular ship servicing (e.g. PP, export). Additionally, this set of variables is available from a sufficient number of different models to incorporate a quantification of model uncertainty in our analysis.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The linear trend in annual values of the variable for the period of simulation 2006–2100 is calculated using generalized least squares regression: 
  <div id="gcb13152-disp-0001" class="disp-formula">
   <span class="label">(1)</span>
   <div id="nlm-math-1" class="math">
    <div class="mrow">
     <div class="msub">
      <span class="mi">Y</span>
      <span class="mi">t</span>
     </div>
     <span class="mo">=</span>
     <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">μ</span>
     <span class="mo">+</span>
     <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">ω</span>
     <div class="msub">
      <span class="mi">X</span>
      <span class="mi">t</span>
     </div>
     <span class="mo">+</span>
     <div class="msub">
      <span class="mi">N</span>
      <span class="mi">t</span>
     </div>
     <span class="mo">,</span>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div> where 
  <span class="italic">Y</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">t</span>
  </sub> is the time series, 
  <span class="italic">μ</span> is the intercept, 
  <span class="italic">ω</span> is the slope (i.e. magnitude of the trend), 
  <span class="italic">X</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">t</span>
  </sub> is the time in years and 
  <span class="italic">N</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">t</span>
  </sub> is the noise, or portion of the data unexplained by the trend. The noise is assumed to be autoregressive of the order 1 so that successive measurements are correlated, as 
  <span class="italic">ϕ </span>= Corr (
  <span class="italic">N</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">t</span>
  </sub>, 
  <span class="italic">N</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">t</span>−1
  </sub>). The number of years of continuous data needed to distinguish a climate change trend from background natural variability is calculated following the method of Tiao 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. (
  <a rid="gcb13152-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb13152-bib-0026">1990</a>) and Weatherhead 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. (
  <a rid="gcb13152-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb13152-bib-0028">1998</a>). The number of years, 
  <span class="italic">n*</span>, required to detect a trend with a probability of detection of 90% and a confidence level of 95% is: 
  <div id="gcb13152-disp-0002" class="disp-formula">
   <span class="label">(2)</span>
   <div id="nlm-math-2" class="math">
    <div class="mrow">
     <div class="msup">
      <span class="mi">n</span>
      <span class="mo">∗</span>
     </div>
     <span class="mo">=</span>
     <div class="msup">
      <div close="]" open="[" separators="" class="mfenced">
       <div class="mfrac">
        <div class="mrow">
         <span class="mn">3.3</span>
         <div class="msub">
          <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">σ</span>
          <span class="mi">N</span>
         </div>
        </div>
        <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">ω</span>
       </div>
       <div class="msqrt">
        <div class="mfrac">
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mn">1</span>
          <span class="mo">+</span>
          <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">ϕ</span>
         </div>
         <div class="mrow">
          <span class="mn">1</span>
          <span class="mo">−</span>
          <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">ϕ</span>
         </div>
        </div>
       </div>
      </div>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mn">2</span>
       <span stretchy="false" class="mo">/</span>
       <span class="mn">3</span>
      </div>
     </div>
     <span class="mo">,</span>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div> where 
  <span class="italic">σ</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">N</span>
  </sub> is the standard deviation of the noise (residual after trend has been removed). Where less than half of the eight models agree on the sign of the trend, or have nonsignificant trends, those pixels are excluded from further analysis.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The locations of ocean observing stations that include a biogeochemical component were taken from the OceanSites database (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.oceansites.org" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.oceansites.org</span>). Here, we limit our analysis to fixed point observatories that are identified in the OceanSites database as currently operational or planned, and which have a biogeochemical component, although they may not measure all the variables explored here (hereinafter these are referred to as BGC‐SOs).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To approximate the region over which samples collected at an observing station are representative (the ‘footprint’), pixels which have similar mean and variability to the time series at the station are identified. First, the time series at each station from a 100‐year section of the model control run for each variable is linearly correlated against every other pixel in the model domain. Where the linear correlation is statistically significant at the 95% level (i.e. 
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.05), and where the pixel is within ±2 standard deviations of the time series mean at the station, the pixel is considered to be representative of conditions at that station. Only regions which are positively correlated with the observing station time series, fall within ±2
  <span class="italic">σ</span>, and are contiguous with it are retained for further analysis. In addition, only pixels in which the contiguous patches overlie in at least half of the eight models used here are retained for analysis.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To evaluate the likely realism of the spatial and temporal scales estimated by the model analysis presented here, comparisons to available satellite observations are made. Comparisons of the coefficient of variation and footprint are presented in the Supporting Information. In general, the model‐derived estimates of 
  <span class="italic">n*</span> may be underestimates in specific regions such as the equatorial Pacific for SST and coastal upwelling regions for chlorophyll, as observed variability tends to be larger than modelled variability (see Supporting Information).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Finally, a note on terminology: here we use the term ‘natural variability’ to indicate interannual, decadal, or multidecadal variability forced by oscillatory or transient conditions (e.g. El Niño‐Southern Oscillation, North Atlantic Oscillation etc.). In contrast, ‘trends’ is used to refer to long‐term (multidecadal or longer) changes driven by persistent anomalous forcing (in this case global climate change).</p>
</sec>
