<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="gcb13152-sec-0006" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Spatial footprints of current ocean observatory network</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ocean observing stations are typically single point locations, although in some cases arrays of sampling may be carried out, such as the CALCOFI (southern California) grid covered by regular cruises. Here, we assess whether the current network of ocean observing stations provides adequate coverage of ocean conditions to determine a climate change trend. The spatial area wherein each observing station is statistically similar, in terms of its mean and variability, with surrounding conditions (see 
  <a rid="gcb13152-sec-0002" ref-type="sec" href="#gcb13152-sec-0002">Materials and methods</a>) provides an indication of each station's ‘footprint’, that is where single‐point observing stations may be considered representative of conditions in a larger area.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figure 
  <a rid="gcb13152-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#gcb13152-fig-0003">3</a> shows the footprint size at selected BGC‐SOs for all eight variables. Generally, the stations are representative of biogeochemical properties in fairly localized areas, ~1.1 × 10
  <span class="sup">6</span> km
  <span class="sup">2</span> on average. Stations in the Arabian Sea, North Pacific and Southern Ocean are representative of the largest areas (e.g. ~4.85 × 10
  <span class="sup">6</span> km
  <span class="sup">2</span> for A7, median for all eight variables), whilst those in the Mediterranean are representative of the smallest regions (e.g. ~0.18 × 10
  <span class="sup">6</span> km
  <span class="sup">2</span> for LION, median for all eight variables). The variables with the largest footprints are SST, pH and nitrate (Fig. 
  <a rid="gcb13152-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#gcb13152-fig-0003">3</a>), but nevertheless the current network of BGC‐SOs is still only representative of 13–15% of the ocean (Table 
  <a rid="gcb13152-tbl-0001" ref-type="table-wrap" href="#gcb13152-tbl-0001">1</a>). A second group of variables (chlorophyll, PP, nondiatom PP and export) are the biological response to changing physical and chemical conditions and have smaller footprints so that BGC‐SOs represent 11–12% of the ocean. Oxygen concentration has the smallest footprint, with only 9% of the ocean covered by existing BGC‐SOs. For all variables, any region not in close proximity to a BGC‐SO is unrepresented, mainly in the Southern Hemisphere and Arctic. A table with full listing of areal extent represented by each BGC‐SO and variable is in Table S3.
 </p>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="gcb13152-fig-0003" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Spatial footprint maps calculated for (a) 
    <span style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">pH</span>, (b) 
    <span style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">SST</span>, (c) oxygen, (d) nitrate, (e) nondiatom 
    <span style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">PP</span>, (f) chlorophyll, (g) export and (h) 
    <span style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">PP</span>. Each 
    <span style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">BGC</span>‐
    <span style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">SO</span> is represented by a dot with its corresponding footprint contoured in the same colour.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-5" xlink:href="GCB-22-1561-g003" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Spatial patterns of coverage for all variables are shown in Fig. S3 which plots the number of BGC‐SOs that are representative of each 1 × 1° pixel, that is the regions of overlap in Fig. 
  <a rid="gcb13152-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#gcb13152-fig-0003">3</a>. Some ocean regions are very well‐represented by multiple BGC‐SOs, such as the west coast of the USA. Much of the North and equatorial Atlantic, North Pacific, western Indian Ocean and Mediterranean are covered by existing BGC‐SOs, but vast tracts of the Southern Hemisphere are not.
 </p>
</sec>
