<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Safety-Specific Active Transactional Leadership, Performance Goal Orientation, and Near-Miss Recognition</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Unlike safety-specific transformational leadership, safety-specific active transactional leadership improves employees’ safety performance by clearly conveying contingent incentives and penalties and providing active supervision. Previous research has indicated that safety-specific active transactional leadership can motivate subordinates to obey safety regulations and seek to avoid mistakes and punishment (
  <a rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" href="#B55">Wallace and Chen, 2006</a>; 
  <a rid="B56" ref-type="bibr" href="#B56">Wallace et al., 2008</a>; 
  <a rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34">Kark et al., 2015</a>). When motivated by a leader who provides clear incentives and penalties, employees pay more attention to possible rewards and losses, and thus remain highly sensitive to near misses in safety management. Therefore, we propose the following hypothesis:
 </p>
 <div list-type="simple" prefix-word="simple" class="list" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Hypothesis 2a:</span> Safety-specific transactional leadership is positively associated with employees’ near-miss recognition.
   </p>
  </div>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Individuals with a high level of performance goal orientation exhibit more external task motivation and tend to seek more positive and less negative feedback (
  <a rid="B57" ref-type="bibr" href="#B57">Wolters et al., 1996</a>; 
  <a rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6">Brett and VandeWalle, 1999</a>; 
  <a rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" href="#B54">VandeWalle et al., 2001</a>). Individuals with this orientation seek to improve their safety performance to compensate for deficiencies in their work-related ability (
  <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">Elliot and Church, 1997</a>) and avoid negative feedback (
  <a rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13">Cron et al., 2005</a>). Therefore, individuals with high level of performance goal orientation are more sensitive to potential safety hazards and thus better able to recognize near misses in safety management. Safety-specific active transactional leadership, an important environmental factor, can affect employees’ safety performance by stimulating their extrinsic motivations. Previous research has shown that employees’ extrinsic motivations mediate the relationship between safety-specific active transactional leadership and employees’ performance (
  <a rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30">Islam et al., 2012</a>). Studies of safety management have indicated that safety-specific active transactional leadership improves employees’ safety compliance by motivating them to avoid mistakes in safety operations (
  <a rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34">Kark et al., 2015</a>). Researchers have also found that employees’ extrinsic motivations mediate the relationship between transactional leadership and safety compliance (
  <a rid="B45" ref-type="bibr" href="#B45">Pilbeam et al., 2016</a>). Therefore, employees under high level of safety-specific active transactional leadership are better able to recognize near misses because they usually consider near misses as a source of punishment and make more effort to prevent accidents. We thus propose the following hypothesis:
 </p>
 <div list-type="simple" prefix-word="simple" class="list" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Hypothesis 2b:</span> Employees’ performance goal orientation is positively associated with their near-miss recognition.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Hypothesis 2c:</span> Employees’ performance goal orientation mediates the relationship between safety-specific active transactional leadership and employees’ near-miss recognition.
   </p>
  </div>
 </div>
</sec>
