<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Safety-Specific Transformational Leadership, Learning Goal Orientation, and Near-Miss Recognition</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">According to SDT, leadership, as an environmental factor, influences employees’ safety performance through their motivations. Safety-specific transformational leadership is a leadership style that delivers a shared vision of safety to employees and encourages them to exercise their energy, skills, and self-efficacy to realize this vision. In practice, a leader with a safety-specific transformational leadership style enhances employees’ safety performance, such as safety participation and compliance with safety regulations, through idealized influence, inspirational motivation, and intellectual stimulation (
  <a rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2">Barling et al., 2002</a>; 
  <a rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29">Inness et al., 2010</a>). Employees under high level safety-specific transformational leadership, put more energy into safety management and detecting potential safety hazards. Therefore, we propose the following hypothesis:
 </p>
 <div list-type="simple" prefix-word="simple" class="list" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Hypothesis 1a:</span> Safety-specific transformational leadership has a positive effect on employee’s near-miss recognition.
   </p>
  </div>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Individuals with a learning goal orientation are likely to adopt in-depth learning strategies (
  <a rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23">Elliot and McGregor, 2001</a>) and diversified solutions (
  <a rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4">Bereby-Meyer and Kaplan, 2005</a>) to satisfy their need to understand and master the surrounding environment. They view deficiencies in current safety management as opportunities to improve their ability to master situations in the workplace. Therefore, we speculate that employees with high level of learning goal orientation tend to recognize more potential safety hazards in safety management, enhancing their near-miss recognition.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Safety-specific transformational leadership can affect employees’ safety performance by stimulating their motivation. Research has shown that intrinsic motivations mediate the influence of transformational leadership not only on sports performance (
  <a rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9">Charbonneau et al., 2001</a>), but also on employees’ creativity (
  <a rid="B52" ref-type="bibr" href="#B52">Shin and Zhou, 2003</a>). Some studies on safety management have found that safety-specific transformational leadership is positively associated with employees’ safety compliance via employees’ intrinsic motivations (
  <a rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12">Conchie and Donald, 2009</a>). 
  <a rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11">Conchie (2013)</a> also found that intrinsic motivations mediate the relationship between safety-specific transformational leadership and employees’ safety citizenship behavior (i.e., voice behavior).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Combining all of the above evidence, and in light of SDT, we argue that safety-specific transformational leadership triggers employees’ intrinsic motivations through idealized influence, inspirational motivation, and intellectual stimulation (
  <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">Button et al., 1996</a>; 
  <a rid="B43" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43">Payne et al., 2007</a>). This in turn fosters a learning goal orientation and thus enhances near-miss recognition. Therefore, we propose the following hypothesis:
 </p>
 <div list-type="simple" prefix-word="simple" class="list" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Hypothesis 1b:</span> Employees’ learning goal orientation has a positive effect on their near-miss recognition.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Hypothesis 1c:</span> Employees’ learning goal orientation mediates the relationship between safety-specific transformational leadership and near-miss recognition.
   </p>
  </div>
 </div>
</sec>
