<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Moderating Effects of Safety Climate</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Drawing on SDT, we anticipate that the effects of safety-specific leadership on employees’ goal orientation depend on employees’ perception of the extent to which safety is valued in their group. This shared perception is also known as the safety climate (
  <a rid="B59" ref-type="bibr" href="#B59">Zohar, 2000</a>). Research has suggested that the safety climate varies dramatically across workgroups (e.g., 
  <a rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27">Hofmann and Stetzer, 1996</a>, 
  <a rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28">1998</a>; 
  <a rid="B59" ref-type="bibr" href="#B59">Zohar, 2000</a>; 
  <a rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26">Hofmann et al., 2003</a>), and that the strength of the safety climate affects how individuals react to leaders’ behaviors. For example, 
  <a rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26">Hofmann et al. (2003)</a> found that high-quality leader-member exchanges lead to stronger safety citizenship role definitions in a higher-safety climate. 
  <a rid="B33" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33">Kapp (2012)</a> also suggested that supervisors’ contingent reward leadership practices are more closely related to employee safety compliance or participation when the safety climate is stronger.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When a workgroup has a strong safety climate, members of the group support, value, and appreciate safety practices, such as consistently improving organizational reliability, promoting new security systems, and identifying safety hazards. Therefore, a strong safety climate supports the efforts of transformational leaders, who focus on improving safety performance, and thus enhances their motivational influence. Such a climate also supports the efforts made by active transactional leaders, who focus on minimizing safety hazards in the workplace by adhering to safety regulations, recognizing near misses, and preventing accidents. In contrast, when the safety climate is weak, employees may be extremely uncertain as to whether safety behavior and practices are appreciated and valued by other group members. In such situations, the motivational effects of safety-specific leadership on employees’ goal orientation tend to be weaker. Therefore, we offer the following hypotheses:</p>
 <div list-type="simple" prefix-word="simple" class="list" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Hypothesis 3a:</span> The relationship between safety-specific transformational leadership and an individual’s learning goal orientation is moderated by the safety climate, such that the relationship is stronger at high levels of safety climate.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Hypothesis 3b:</span> The relationship between safety-specific transactional leadership and an individual’s performance goal orientation is moderated by the safety climate, such that the relationship is stronger at high levels of safety climate.
   </p>
  </div>
 </div>
</sec>
