<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">This study has shown that the richness of total soil fungi and various functional groups were not affected by late Quaternary climate change. While there is a paucity of studies to compare this to, it has been shown that fungal richness in the sediment of two European lakes was not related to the past two millennia of paleoclimatic variations (Capo et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35247-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). Some fungal taxa increased in richness but some decreased in richness under late Quaternary climate change which might result in the overall fungal richness remaining unchanged, as expectation that different fungal taxa have different response to climatic changes (Newsham et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35247-bib-0058" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). This is different from the effect of Quaternary climate change on bacterial species richness in a global scale (Delgado‐Baquerizo, Bissett, et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35247-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>). The difference might be explained partly by the different traits between fungi and bacteria. Soil fungi are more resistant to climatic changes than bacteria (Barnard, Osborne, &amp; Firestone, 
 <xref rid="ece35247-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; De Vries et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35247-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>; De Vries &amp; Shade, 
 <xref rid="ece35247-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). This trait of fungi may reduce species' vulnerability to range loss, avoid extinction risk, and improve persistent ability of fungi encountering the late Quaternary climate change, resulting that fungal richness was not related to late Quaternary climate change. Alternatively, bacterial research was conducted in a global scale, but this study was carried out in a regional scale, as the response of microbial richness depends on biogeographical scales (Bahram et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35247-bib-0005" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>; Martiny, Eisen, Penn, Allison, &amp; Horner‐Devineet, 
 <xref rid="ece35247-bib-0056" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>).
</p>
