<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In addition to late Quaternary climate change, we found that contemporary environmental factors, such as plant community composition, soil, current climate, and space, affected total and functional group fungal community compositions in temperate, tropic–subtropical, and all forests, as reported in previous studies (e.g., Barberán et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35247-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Gao et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35247-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>; Tedersoo et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35247-bib-0080" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>; Talbot et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35247-bib-0079" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). However, some different contemporary environmental variables affected total and functional group fungal community compositions in temperate and tropic–subtropical forests. For example, we found that total, saprotrophic, pathogenic, and EM fungal community compositions were related to soil C or no variables in temperate forest, but to soil nutrients, PSD, or pH in tropic–subtropical forest. In the study sites, the range of soil C concentration (3.08–30.39 g/kg vs. 1.4–24.78 g/kg) was wider in temperate forest than in tropic–subtropical forest, but the ranges of soil nutrient concentrations (0.23–33.93 g/kg vs. 0.02–14.53 g/kg), pH (3.31–6.87 vs. 4.4–7.22), and PSD (2.44–2.72 vs. 2.42–2.68) were wider in tropic–subtropical forest than in temperate forest. The wider ranges of soil variables would provide more niche spaces to promote species coexistence of fungal community in different forest ecosystems (Peay et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35247-bib-0066" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>). In addition to soil variables, pathogenic fungal community composition was related to plant community composition in tropic–subtropical forests in this study. It is possible that pathogenic fungi as host‐specific enemies would have stronger effect in plant species‐rich tropic–subtropical regions than in plant species‐poor temperate areas (Johnson, Beaulieu, Bever, &amp; Clay, 
 <xref rid="ece35247-bib-0044" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). Furthermore, we found that EM fungal community composition was related to non‐EM plant community composition in tropic–subtropical forest. In the study sites, there are higher non‐EM plant species richness and abundance (on average, 83.7% vs. 66.2% of plant species and 74.3% vs. 48.3% of plant individuals) in tropic–subtropical forest than in temperate forest (Table 
 <xref rid="ece35247-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S6</xref>), and these EM plant individuals are surrounded by a large number of the non‐EM plants to form many small tree islands which prevent the spread of EM fungi through underground hyphae in tropic–subtropical forest (Gao et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35247-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Tedersoo, Sadam, Zambrano, Valencia, &amp; Bahram, 
 <xref rid="ece35247-bib-0083" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>).
</p>
