<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">This paper explores the past, present and future role of broadcasting, above all via the medium of television, in shaping how societies talk, think about and act on issues surrounding material demand. It takes the outputs and decision-making of the UK's largest public service broadcaster, the BBC, as its primary focus. Although television outputs represent just one media form, and the BBC is just one broadcaster among many globally, there are reasons why this medium, and this broadcaster, hold particular significance in relation to global environmental change issues. The BBC's formal obligation to public service makes it a revealing case study. Its governance and funding is distinctive: it includes a near-universal requirement to pay a license fee, and is overseen by a trust, independent of government. This results in a profoundly challenging and sometimes conflicting set of obligations around diverse audience reach, popularity, comprehensiveness and accuracy in coverage, and impartiality. These obligations are summarized in a phrase coined by the institution's first director general, Lord Reith, which insists that the Corporation exists to ‘inform, educate and entertain’. The institution's distinctive governance and funding structure make it a particularly telling illustration of media engagement with a bundle of topics that generate a specific and complex cultural politics. The distinctive temporality and spatiality of climate change, and the relationships of vulnerability and responsibility that it generates pose particular challenges for storytellers in any form. Television is the predominant setting for the long-form narration of any major issue for public audiences throughout the period within which global environmental change issues have emerged. Furthermore, the BBC's formal obligations to attend to questions of civic significance 
 <italic class="italic">and</italic> maintain popularity make it a powerful case study of the challenges of reaching wide audiences with ‘difficult’ issues. They are also unusual in being a global broadcaster (through World Service radio and later television channels), and for having participated in international co-production throughout the period. For all these reasons, the BBC's 50-year journey with topics that relate population, consumption, resources and environmental change make them a key reference point for any discussion of the mass-mediation of ideas around material demand reduction.
</p>
