<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Growing sensitivity of maize production to water</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To determine whether the gap between irrigated and rainfed maize yields in the region is increasing, rainfed yield was expressed as a percentage of irrigated yield for all combinations of two kinds of varieties and two climate periods (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f3" href="#f3">Fig. 3</a>). For the entire CMB, yield was 5% lower for rainfed maize than for irrigated maize when varieties used in the 1980s were combined with climates from either the 1980s or the 2000s. For the entire CMB, yield was 10% lower when varieties used in the 2000s were combined with the climate from the 2000s. The increased difference in rainfed vs. irrigated maize mostly occurred in the NE and NCP, while water remained a non-limiting factor in SW China. The importance of climate in causing the drop in rainfed vs. irrigated yields was most apparent in the NE (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f3" href="#f3">Fig. 3</a> and 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">Supplementary Figure S7</a>), which is partly related to slight reductions in precipitation (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f1" href="#f1">Fig. 1f</a>) and to increased evaporative demand in a warmer climate
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b26" href="#b26">26</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To meet yield potential without irrigation, we found that the critical level of precipitation was 462 mm during the maize growing season for the modern, longer-maturing varieties in the CMB (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f4" href="#f4">Fig. 4</a>). Among regions, the NE and NCP required similar levels of precipitation (446–460 mm) to fully achieve the yield potential whereas lower levels of precipitation did not affect yields in the SW (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">Supplementary Figure S8</a>). Current precipitation in 40% of the entire CMB failed to meet the demand of the modern varieties. Precipitation in 62% of the NE and 60% of the NCP failed to meet the demand of modern varieties. For example, precipitation during the maize growing season in Hebei, Shannxi and Shanxi Provinces in the NCP was only about 350 mm, resulting in a 100-mm gap between maize water demand and supply. This gap substantially decreases the possibility that yield potential will be achieved without irrigation.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The importance of water as a limiting factor is increasing because of the shift to longer-maturing varieties, and because of the adoption of other agronomic measures that have been used to increase yield. In the Midwest of the USA, for example, farmers have increased planting density, which obviously increases the demand for water
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b27" href="#b27">27</a>. Because the CMB encompasses regions with diverse climates, research from the CMB concerning the effects of changes in varieties and climates on maize yields is relevant to many other parts of the world. In many developing countries in southern Asia, Africa,the Middle East, and South America, precipitation in the maize growing season ranges from 300–500 mm, which is near or below the level required to obtain the maize yield potential
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b6" href="#b6">6</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b7" href="#b7">7</a>; maize yield in these areas is severely limited by water
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b21" href="#b21">21</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As water resources become increasingly scarce, especially under climate change, securing food supplies will depend on increases in water use efficiency
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b28" href="#b28">28</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b29" href="#b29">29</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b30" href="#b30">30</a>. Water use efficiency in maize systems can be increased by optimizing irrigation (e.g., by deficit irrigation) and by increasing soil water retention via conservation agriculture, minimum tillage, and the covering of the soil surface in the field (with crop residues or plastic)
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b28" href="#b28">28</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b30" href="#b30">30</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b31" href="#b31">31</a>. Water-use efficiency can also be increased by rotations that include crops that are especially efficient in their use of water
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b32" href="#b32">32</a>. Another important approach is to develop high-yielding, stress-tolerant maize varieties
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b1" href="#b1">1</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b33" href="#b33">33</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In summary, we found that the gap between rainfed yields and irrigated yields substantially increased from 5% in the 1980s to 10% in the 2000s and that 40% of the maize production area in CMB now fails to receive the precipitation required to achieve full yield potential. Growing sensitivity of maize production to water scarcity resulting from a shift to longer-maturing varieties makes adaptation to climate change especially difficult and suggests that new adaptation measures are needed. These measures include new approaches to agronomic management and water management and the breeding of new varieties.</p>
</sec>
