<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par2" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The history of food production is characterized by some of humankind’s most brilliant achievements along with a questionable environmental legacy. Thanks to the development of agriculture more than 10,000 years ago, and advances in agricultural technology made possible by the industrial revolution, today’s human population has increased to 7.5 billion. These advances have also created civilizations and advanced social systems capable of influencing global ecosystems.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span> While the green revolution may have saved the most human life ever,
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span> extensive use of synthetic fertilizers, pesticides, and high-yielding crop varieties has created global footprints that could trigger the planet’s sixth massive human extinction event.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span> This brings into question the sustainability of primary food production in terms of material resources and both environmental and human health. Already, the biogeochemical flow of agricultural inputs such as nitrogen, phosphorus, and carbon is exceeding planetary limits, and the irreversible loss of genetic diversity could dramatically alter the integrity of the biosphere.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span> Healthcare expenditure has become one of the heaviest economic burdens in both developed and developing countries.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span> The overall problem is linked with conventional food production systems and the diet-environment-health trilemma, where only two of these three options can be selected.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
  </span> A return to a sustainable trajectory requires a drastic and fundamental reformation of conventional food systems over the entire value chain of production, distribution, and consumption.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
  </span>
 </p>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The spatial and temporal scales related to food production and consumption are various, ranging from the global environment to the molecular functions involved in health. Figure 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a> summarizes the relationship between scientific and industrial domains and their respective effects on the environment. Most biological studies related to food products are somewhat limited because they are produced in highly controlled laboratory conditions, such as 
  <span class="italic">in vitro</span> tissue culture or 
  <span class="italic">in vivo</span> tests on a small number of model organisms. This is not a critique of the methodological limitations of food science but rather a reminder of the importance of carefully selecting those factors associated with food production. The ongoing feedback between field/farm production and laboratory evaluation will become more important in wider contexts.
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Scale of scientific and industrial domains and associated human impacts on food production. Horizontal axis represents the degree of technological complexity required for realization. Vertical axis is the spatial-temporal scale involved for the maintenance from small (bottom) to large (top) scale, in which experimental systems in science and production modes in industry can be represented as 
     <span class="italic">in vitro</span>, 
     <span class="italic">in vivo</span>, 
     <span class="italic">in cultura</span>, and 
     <span class="italic">in natura</span> conditions. As a solution for future food production, anthropogenic augmentation of ecosystems is situated at the top right, which combines enhanced agricultural biodiversity with the support of information and communication technologies (ICT), making use of various biological resources in dense and mixed polyculture situations without external material inputs. (See more explanation in Supplementary Material 2)
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41538_2018_26_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e277" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The actual operating scale for primary food production is the open field, with interventions ranging from monoculture farming (referred to as 
  <span class="italic">in cultura</span>) and hunting-gathering in natural ecosystems (referred to as 
  <span class="italic">in natura</span>
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>
  </span>). For example, agronomy focuses mainly on yield optimization using monoculture (i.e., 
  <span class="italic">in cultura</span>), while ecology principally investigates the natural formation of ecosystems (
  <span class="italic">in natura</span>) with various degrees of disturbance. In the ecological theory of productivity optimization, the physiological optimum is defined as the optimization of a single organism (e.g., plant or animal) grown 
  <span class="italic">in cultura</span>, while 
  <span class="italic">in natura</span>, it is defined as the spontaneous organization of a community, where a species grows in association with others (i.e., the ecological optimum).
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>
  </span> Modern societies are mainly situated under the strong regulations of a natural environment dictated by human activities (
  <span class="italic">in cultura</span>), where most of the medical cohort studies are performed. The loss of natural ecosystems under human population pressure has increased consistently throughout the history of agriculture, just as 
  <span class="italic">in cultura</span> conditions dominated over 
  <span class="italic">in natura</span> conditions in the human habitat and agricultural landscape. Changes in global biogeochemical cycles as a result of human activity is referred to as the Anthropocene epoch.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
  </span>
 </p>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figure 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a> shows the range and types of consequences that can arise spatially and temporally (
  <span class="italic">y</span>-axis) as a function of the increasing complexity of technology (
  <span class="italic">x</span>-axis). While conventional scenarios of city and farmland development would eventually lead to a global state shift typically represented as desertification,
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span> innovative technologies for future food production would tend to focus on controlled environment solutions such as autonomous farming and plant factories, similar to 
  <span class="italic">in vivo</span> experiments
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>
  </span> and 
  <span class="italic">in vitro</span> cultured meat production.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span> These emerging alternatives are based on highly controlled and confined environments compatible with cGMP laboratories and, in a most extreme case, with spacecraft on interplanetary journeys.
 </p>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Building on studies using closed systems (e.g., laboratories), conventional science has been extending its reach to applications in the open environment, which features multiple external loads (area inside purple dotted line, Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). Here, there is a serious need for a better management framework, particularly with a novel formalization called open systems science (area inside red dotted line). Open systems science puts strong emphasis on relationships with surrounding systems when solving problems and makes extensive use of computational technologies to dynamically update the definition of the problem domain, its structure, and its functions so as to deliver timely and effective control within limited observation conditions.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span> Management of 
  <span class="italic">in natura</span> ecosystems under a given climate condition has the potential to enable an augmented state of biodiversity through the application of open systems science and the development of supportive information and communication technologies (ICT) such as satellite remote sensing, cloud computing, artificial intelligence, and internet of things (IoT)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span> (top right, Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). This is qualitatively different from so-called “smart agriculture” based on the application of ICT to conventional methodologies, since the augmentation imposes the net increase of ecosystem functioning beyond natural organization.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>
  </span> Generally, the ecological optimum is the description of an eventually established form of ecosystem based on the assumption that the evolutionary nurtured self-organization capacity is performing some kind of comprehensive optimization of ecosystem functions at the community level (i.e., naturally formed ecosystem multifunctionality
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
  </span>). Due to the nature of ecosystems that develop in harmony with the vegetation, the diversity of ecological transitions, and the existence of alternative stable states,
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
  </span> ecosystem functions that occur with the composition of different species under the same environmental condition could be different and bring different levels of ecosystem services. This implies that, by the manipulation of artificial species diversity, the ecological optimum has an expandable range compared to naturally occurring ecosystems.
 </p>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Y-dimension in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a> (purple and red arrows) represents the degree of human impact with respect to negative (downward, purple) and positive (upward, red) effects on biodiversity. Effective mitigation scenarios should prevent the environmental load from exceeding natural resilience, which requires the augmentation of ecosystems towards higher 
  <span class="italic">in natura</span> organization, in order to cancel out total loss and achieve net positive impact.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>
  </span> Often, the offset argument of biodiversity and carbon neutrality mistakes the basal line as the conventional load instead of natural state: for example, the much-touted high biodiversity in farmland is not necessarily higher than the natural preservation state, which is lost anyway during the initial land conversion to farmland, which accounts for 1/6 of the annual greenhouse gas emission on the planet
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>
  </span> and is the principal driver of mass extinction (more so than the extinction pressure of climate change
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
  </span>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Understanding the environmental load and possible mitigation and resilience measures requires a multi-scale integrative framework of the complex systems involved. Since the conventional load is estimated to impose social and ecological state shift by the middle of this century,
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
  </span> the offsetting and recovery of material cycles and biodiversity with a proper evaluation regime is the baseline task. This includes foresight toward sustainable intensification in food production, including a shift of culture and food systems to a vegetarian diet with respect to forest protection;
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>
  </span> the amelioration of inappropriate production and distribution;
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>
  </span> the enhancement of local production in urban agriculture;
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>
  </span> the search for ecologically and nutritionally sound alternative diets such as insect food;
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span> the diverse tailoring of small-scale agriculture for resource-poor farmers;
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span> and the planned management of fishery resources based on the functional capacity of ecosystems.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
  </span> Moreover, the measures should incorporate the resolution of both environmental and health risks beyond mitigation so as to achieve a net positive impact and compensate for the population increase and social inequality.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>
  </span>
 </p>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The integrated approach is also crucial in light of climate change. Agriculture, forestry, and other land use related to food production account for 25% of global human-caused greenhouse gas emissions.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
  </span> The countries most vulnerable to climate change are also more likely to foster social corruption,
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span> hunger,
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
  </span> and biodiversity hotspots, especially in coastal areas.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
  </span> Primary food production in these countries is supported mainly by small-scale, family-owned farms, which occupy about 87% of the world’s agricultural land.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
  </span> Globally, small and medium farms produce up to 77% of major commodities and nutrients.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
  </span>
 </p>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">These problems are clearly out of the reach of conventional food production optimization techniques such as precision agriculture, which is based on the business-as-usual scenario and R&amp;D investment policy in developed countries. For example, only a 1–3 percent increase of net returns is reported through the adoption of precision agriculture by large farms in the U.S.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
  </span> In European countries, despite partial reduction of conventional inputs, alternative costs for implementation rise, and no profitability has been demonstrated so far in the investigated cases and scenarios.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>
  </span> Since it is qualitatively based a priori on the negative impact on the environment, the scaling-out of monoculture solutions cannot neutralize the adverse ecological effect in the context of increasing world population and the anticipated global collapse of ecosystems.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
  </span> Even leading-edge agricultural technologies such as genetically modified crop production cannot ensure secure and sufficient biodiversity for essential regulation services, which has been exclusively nurtured by the natural vegetation holding an astronomical number of active genetic resources. Genetically modified organisms (GMO) in the open field rather entail a potential risk of gene diversity homogenization through crossing with wild relatives and interspecific gene transfer as a generic mechanism of genome evolution.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>
  </span>
 </p>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Global synthesis of scientific knowledge has resulted in continuous alerts on the falling trajectory of the Earth system over the past 25 years.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
  </span> Sustainable food production, if such a category could exist, should incorporate the overall trade-off and potential synergy of multi-scale interactions among 
  <span class="italic">in vitro-in vivo-</span>
  <span class="italic">in cultura-in natura</span> phenomena toward the end goal of a biological diversity that is balanced with, or superior to, human activities across the whole value chain of research, policy making, production, distribution, consumption, recycling, and health effect. Designing societies that sustain an anthropogenic biosphere with nonhuman natures is crucial in the present era of Anthropocene.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>
  </span> Altogether with the integration of agronomy and ecology, food science is poised to play a central role in the integrity of food production by substantially incorporating ecological effects and benefits derived in the long-term as an integrated life science that advocates health and abundance for both humanity and nature.
 </p>
</sec>
