<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Future Sea Level Rise</div>
 <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Arctic will be a major source area for future sea level rise. Greenland is now a larger contributor than the world’s glaciers and ice caps (Antarctica currently trails both), while Arctic glaciers and ice caps (including Greenland’s periphery) are the largest combined source outside of the ice sheets [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72" href="#CR72">72</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ice loss from the GrIS will continue to 2100 under all of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) Representative Concentration Pathways (RCPs) used for projecting the climate response to varying additional levels of radiative forcing (e.g., RCP8.5 refers to 8.5 W/m
  <span class="sup">2</span> additional radiative forcing in 2100 as compared to pre-industrial values) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>••]. In fact, ice loss is expected to continue for many centuries to millennia. Projections across different scenarios are fairly consistent for the next few decades but diverge substantially after ~ 2050 depending on greenhouse gas emissions [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73" href="#CR73">73</a>••, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74" href="#CR74">74</a>]. Over decadal to centurial timescales, SMB will continue to dominate Greenland ice loss relative to ice discharge changes [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>], with SMB variability also expected to increase [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>•, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>]. Recent work projects that sea level rise contributions in 2100 from GrIS SMB will be 92 ± 45 mm under RCP8.5 forcing [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>], similar to the likely range of the last IPCC assessment of 30–160 mm [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>••]. The latter projects GrIS solid ice discharge contributions of 20–70 mm. One recent study (using a higher-order ice-dynamic model forced by 10 atmosphere and ocean general circulation models and four RCP scenarios) projects sea-level rise in the range from 42 ± 18 mm for RCP2.6 to 102 ± 32 mm for RCP8.5 from combined SMB and solid ice discharge changes [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par28" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Unconnected and weakly connected glaciers and ice caps in the GrIS periphery, typically assessed separately, are projected to contribute roughly 20 mm to sea-level rise under RCP8.5 [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75" href="#CR75">75</a>]. Significant ice loss will also continue outside of Greenland. Projections for Gulf of Alaska glacier mass loss over 2010–2100 indicate sea level rise contributions of 14 ± 5 mm under RCP2.6 to 29 ± 6 mm under RCP8.5 [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>]. Projections for Canadian Arctic glaciers and ice caps under RCP4.5 suggest that the region will contribute 33 mm to sea level rise by 2100, at a rate of 0.35 ± 0.24 mm/year [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76" href="#CR76">76</a>], though other efforts suggest more modest contributions of ~ 20 mm [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>]. Sea level rise due to Russian High Arctic ice loss, estimated by applying RCP4.5 and RCP8.5 emissions scenarios to 14 global climate models, is projected at 20–28 mm by 2100 [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">63</a>]. Recent projections of Iceland contributions under RCP8.5 agree well at 4.7 ± 1.7 mm [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>] and 4.9 mm [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">63</a>]. For Svalbard, a study using the Modèle Atmosphérique Régional (MAR) regional climate model with RCP8.5 projects a rapid acceleration of surface melt near mid-century, with a negative surface mass balance over all glaciated areas by 2085 [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" href="#CR69">69</a>]. Projections for Svalbard mass loss during 2006–2100 using RCP4.5 are 12.4 mm sea-level equivalent (~ 55% of the total ice volume) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">63</a>], while estimated Svalbard mass loss under RCP8.5 forcing ranges from 14.0 to 16.4 mm [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">63</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75" href="#CR75">75</a>]. Ice loss from glaciers and ice caps will continue after 2100, perhaps even without further warming. For example, recent computer simulations show that the Canadian Barnes Ice Cap, a remnant of the Laurentide Ice Sheet, will disappear within the next millennium under current climate conditions [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77" href="#CR77">77</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While we have presented estimates of the mean Arctic contributions to sea level rise, local sea level rise can be much higher or lower than the global mean. Local sea level rise is influenced by factors including land subsidence, ocean currents, atmospheric circulation, and the origin of ice loss. The loss of gravitational pull caused by ice mass loss, along with vertical land motion associated with unweighting, means that sea level can fall locally (within ~ 2000 km of the location of ice mass loss) while rising in more distant locations [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78" href="#CR78">78</a>]. Fortunately, understanding of the zone of influence for ice mass loss has improved through a better understanding of where ice loss is expected and improved modeling of the resultant fingerprint of sea level rise [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78" href="#CR78">78</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79" href="#CR79">79</a>•]. For example, sea level rise in Los Angeles is more responsive to Greenland ice loss than other major US coastal cities and southeast Greenland ice loss is more important for sea level rise in Kodiak, AK, while northeast Greenland ice loss is more important for Miami, FL [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79" href="#CR79">79</a>•]. As our abilities to project the location and rate of ice loss improve, that can inform and improve our understanding of where sea levels will rise most rapidly, and by how much, worldwide.
 </p>
</sec>
