<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="FPar18" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Understanding Ice Sheet and Glacier Response to Varying Environmental Forcings</div>
 <p id="Par46" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Given the profound changes already occurring in the Arctic and the dramatic shift expected into the future, efforts must continue to investigate the influence of a changing ocean and atmosphere on land ice. Climate states like the AMO, NAO, and atmospheric blocking events all influence ice loss [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR102" href="#CR102">102</a>]. With increased knowledge, we can quantify variability to better characterize trends and understand the influence of potential long-term shifts in climate modes on ice loss.
 </p>
 <p id="Par47" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As observational records continue to improve, one can envision near-term advances that combine observational records and computational techniques, such as machine learning, to make short-term projections of glacier change for both mountain glaciers and large ice-sheet outlet glaciers. Observational advances will also support improved model projections of short-term and long-term ice mass loss.</p>
 <p id="Par48" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Future modeling advances can also reduce uncertainties. First, ice sheet models must incorporate a wider range of spatial and temporal scales. Higher-order ice flow models are now capable of simulating the whole GrIS on century to millennial scales [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>•]. Some models use unstructured and adaptive meshes that allow lower resolution and simplified mathematics in the ice sheet interior, with higher-resolution and more computationally expensive techniques near the ice edge [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103" href="#CR103">103</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR104" href="#CR104">104</a>]. It remains challenging, however, to resolve sub-km processes on long time scales and to capture the full range of dynamics from narrow fast-flowing glaciers to large slow-moving regions. Second, models must accurately simulate migration of the grounding line (the boundary between grounded and floating ice), which requires not only high grid resolution but also accurate bed topography [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>•]. Third, models need to better represent key physical processes such as ice fracture and calving, surface darkening, englacial and subglacial hydrology, subaqueous melting, and sea ice and ice mélange buttressing.
 </p>
 <p id="Par49" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">High-resolution models with more realistic physics will enable detailed simulations of small, distinct glacier regions. For example, modeling efforts project a slow, steady retreat for Greenland’s Nioghalvfjerdsfjorden (79 North), in contrast to a rapid multi-decade retreat for Zachariae Isstrøm once it loses its floating ice tongue, with subglacial topography acting as the primary control [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>•]. This type of capability needs to continue to expand towards capturing larger multi-glacier regions and, eventually, the full ice sheet. We may see Arctic-wide glacier projections within the coming decade, especially as model boundary conditions (e.g., bed topography) and parameterizations for ice-ocean interaction improve.
 </p>
</sec>
