<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="S4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion and Summary</div>
 <p id="P16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We have shown that the presence of magnetite and wüstite in 2.7 Ga micrometeorites is consistent with the surface pressure of the 2.7 Ga Earth being much less than today. This fits well with other evidence of low atmospheric surface pressures on the Archean Earth (
  <span class="italic">e</span>.
  <span class="italic">g</span>., 
  <a rid="R19" ref-type="bibr" href="#R19">Som 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 2016
  </a>).
 </p>
 <p id="P17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a rid="R9" ref-type="bibr" href="#R9">Kopparapu 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>. (2014)
  </a> have investigated the effect on climate when atmospheres are at low pressures. At low pressures and without a cold trap, water vapour extends much further into the upper atmosphere. This by itself resolves the Faint Young Sun Paradox (
  <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">Sagan and Mullen, 1972</a>), possibly providing too much of a correction as, with water being such a strong greenhouse gas, there is the risk such atmospheres enter a runaway greenhouse state. However, low pressure atmospheres are not necessarily unstable (
  <a rid="R9" ref-type="bibr" href="#R9">Kopparapu 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 2014
  </a>), and the growing evidence for low atmospheric pressures on the 2.7 Ga Earth suggest that somehow the Earth avoided this runaway scenario.
 </p>
 <p id="P18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A low surface pressure on the early Earth may be explained by a reasonably fast rate of abiotic nitrogen fixation without any efficient abiotic mechanism for restoring nitrogen (
  <a rid="R19" ref-type="bibr" href="#R19">Som 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 2016
  </a>). Alternatively, 
  <a rid="R10" ref-type="bibr" href="#R10">Lammer 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>. (2018)
  </a> have speculated that the Earth’s nitrogen reservoir was largely held within its interior following the lunar impactor stripping the Earth of its primordial atmosphere. The N
  <sub>2</sub> would take some time to build up because of slower N
  <sub>2</sub> outgassing under abiotic conditions (
  <a rid="R12" ref-type="bibr" href="#R12">Mikhail 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 2014
  </a>), and more rapid N
  <sub>2</sub> removal from fixation and escape due to heightened solar activity (
  <a rid="R10" ref-type="bibr" href="#R10">Lammer 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span> 2018
  </a>). 
  <a rid="R10" ref-type="bibr" href="#R10">Lammer 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>. (2018)
  </a> consider these sources and sinks and estimate that the N
  <sub>2</sub> partial pressure at 2.7 Ga was somewhere between 0.1 and 0.5 bar. The consequences of an initially low and increasing nitrogen content need to be explored, both for understanding the effects of low pressure on the evolution of climate, atmosphere, crust and upper mantle, and for identifying further tests of this low pressure hypothesis.
 </p>
</sec>
