<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Participants completed an online survey which contained an experimental manipulation. Participants read one of several consensus messages, or an attention check in the control condition (3 participants failing this check were removed). In the consensus message conditions, participants were presented with a single simple statement relating a high (97%) or low (63%) level of consensus regarding the reality of climate change or the safety of GM food. The climate change consensus messages read: 
 <italic class="italic">“Did you know</italic>? 
 <italic class="italic">A recent survey shows that [97%][63%] of climate scientists agree that climate change is occurring and caused by humans</italic>.
 <italic class="italic">”</italic> The GM messages were: “
 <italic class="italic">Did you know</italic>? 
 <italic class="italic">A recent survey shows that [97%][63%] of food scientists agree that genetically modified food is safe to eat</italic>.
 <italic class="italic">”</italic> These statements were modelled on previous studies, which found that short simple statements significantly influence participants’ estimates of consensus [
 <xref rid="pone.0200295.ref028" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0200295.ref029" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0200295.ref041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>]. The ‘high’ value of 97% consensus was selected as it reflects current estimates of scientific consensus regarding climate change [
 <xref rid="pone.0200295.ref008" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. Previous data from this student population indicate the mean estimate of scientific consensus among climate scientists to be approximately 80% [
 <xref rid="pone.0200295.ref049" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>] thus the figure of 63% was selected as the ‘low’ figure, being equidistant from this mean. As there were no prior data available for estimates of the level of scientific consensus on GM food safety in this population, the 97% and 63% values were used for consistency in an exploratory capacity. Participants who read a consensus statement also completed an attention check on the same page as the statement, entering a number in response to the following request: 
 <italic class="italic">To make sure you understood the text</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">could you please enter the percentage of scientists in agreement according to the statement above</italic>. Participants who failed this check were removed from the sample (11 participants).
</p>
