<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec019" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Analyses</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Five analyses were conducted on the expert scores of climate exposure, sensitivity attributes, and directional effect. 1) Overall climate vulnerability was calculated from a combination of climate exposure factors and biological sensitivity attributes. 2) Potential for a change in species distribution was calculated using a subset of sensitivity attributes. 3) Bootstrap analyses were used to evaluate the certainty in the overall vulnerability, potential for a change in distribution, and directional effect of climate change. 4) Leave-one-out sensitivity analyses were used to evaluate the effects exposure factors and sensitivity attributes in determining overall vulnerability. 5) Overall climate vulnerability, potential for distribution change, and directional effect of climate change were analyzed by functional groups to identify larger patterns in climate effects.</p>
 <sec id="sec020" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Estimate of Overall Vulnerability</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Overall climate vulnerability was estimated using a four step process. First, the component scores (low, moderate, high and very high) were assigned a numerical value (1, 2, 3, and 4). Second, an average score for each climate exposure factor and sensitivity attribute was calculated as the weighted-mean of the experts’ tallies. Third, an overall exposure and sensitivity score was calculated from the weighted means using a logic rule (
   <a rid="pone.0146756.t003" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0146756.t003">Table 3</a>). Fourth, an overall climate vulnerability score was calculated by multiplying the overall exposure and sensitivity scores. The product of the two component numeric scores results in a value between 1 and 16. The overall climate vulnerability rank is then classified as follows: 1–3 low, 4–6 moderate, 8–9 high, and 12–16 very high.
  </p>
  <div id="pone.0146756.t003" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0146756.t003</span>
   <span class="label">Table 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <div class="title">Logic rule for calculating overall species’ climate exposure and biological sensitivity.</div>
    <p>The scoring rubric is based on a logic model where a certain number of individual scores above a certain threshold are used to determine the overall climate exposure and overall biological sensitivity.</p>
   </div>
   <div class="alternatives">
    <div id="pone.0146756.t003g" xlink:href="pone.0146756.t003" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
     <colgroup span="1">
      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
     </colgroup>
     <thead>
      <tr>
       <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall Sensitivity or Exposure Score</th>
       <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Numeric Score</th>
       <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Logic Rule</th>
      </tr>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <tr>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Very High</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3 of more attributes or factors mean ≥ 3.5</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">High</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 of more attributes or factors mean ≥ 3.0</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Moderate</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 of more attributes or factors mean ≥ 2.5</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All other scores</td>
      </tr>
     </tbody>
    </table>
   </div>
  </div>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec021" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Potential for Distribution Change</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">High potential for change in species distribution was defined as highly mobile adults, broadly dispersing early life stages, low habitat specificity, and high temperature sensitivity [
   <a rid="pone.0146756.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref034">34</a>]. These attributes have some skill in predicting species that can change distribution in response to climate change; increased dispersal capacity and ecological generalism promote changes in distribution [
   <a rid="pone.0146756.ref074" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref074">74</a>]. The potential for a change in species distribution was estimated using these attributes, reversing the scores for Adult Mobility, Early Life Stage Dispersal, and Habitat Specificity, and applying the same logic rule as in the general vulnerability calculation.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec022" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Certainty in Vulnerability Scores</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Bootstrap analysis was used to calculate the certainty of the climate vulnerability scores, potential for change in distribution scores and directional effect scores. Using the climate vulnerability scores as the examples, the scores across all experts for a given exposure factor (n = 20; 4 experts and 5 tallies) or sensitivity attribute (n = 25; 5 experts and 5 tallies) were drawn randomly with replacement. This was repeated 10,000 times for each of the 12 sensitivity attributes and the 12 exposure factors, and the overall vulnerability score was calculated for each iteration. The outcomes of each iteration was recorded and the proportion of these 10,000 repetitions that scored in each overall vulnerability bin was enumerated. A similar bootstrapping analysis was conducted on the potential for a distribution change (n = 25; 5 experts and 5 tallies) and the directional effect scoring (n = 12; 3 experts and 4 tallies).</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec023" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Importance of Climate Exposure Factors and Sensitivity Attributes</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the sensitivity analysis, the overall vulnerability score for each species was calculated leaving out the scores for each sensitivity attribute or exposure factor. These analyses were then evaluated across species to determine influential factors and attributes in the overall vulnerability rank.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec024" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Functional Group Evaluation</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To evaluate the similarity of vulnerability across functional groups, overall climate vulnerability, potential for distribution change, and directional effect of climate change were pooled by functional group. In addition, sensitivity attribute scores within and among functional groups was evaluated using non-metric multidimensional scaling.</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
