<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We advocate that the Fisheries Climate Vulnerability Assessment should be conducted iteratively. Most fishery stock assessments are conducted iteratively [
 <xref rid="pone.0146756.ref101" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">101</xref>] and we recommend conducting the climate vulnerability assessments following the same interval as the IPCC Assessment Reports. Similarly, Integrated Ecosystem Assessments are planned to be iterative [
 <xref rid="pone.0146756.ref102" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">102</xref>]. The implementation of the Climate Vulnerability Assessment Methodology was successful (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0146756.s013" class="xref">S11 Supporting Information</xref>). However, there are improvements that should be considered for the next iteration. First, bottom temperature and improved ocean acidification projections should be included; both of these would require some form of regional downscaling [
 <xref rid="pone.0146756.ref077" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">77</xref>] or higher resolution climate models [
 <xref rid="pone.0146756.ref103" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">103</xref>]. Second, the ensemble uncertainty in climate change could also be included formally in the assessment (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0146756.s014" class="xref">S12 Supporting Information</xref>), along with different emission scenarios and potentially time periods. Third, the next iteration should include an update of the species profiles and rescoring of both the climate exposure and sensitivity attributes. If information on species specific plasticity or evolutionary adaptability exist by the next iteration, this information should be included to improve the evaluation of adaptive capacity [
 <xref rid="pone.0146756.ref033" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0146756.ref104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">104</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0146756.ref105" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">105</xref>]. Fourth, the next assessment should include experts from a broader background than used here. This assessment included only NMFS employees with some outside observers. One of the main objectives of this effort was to provide the first implementation of NMFS Methodology [
 <xref rid="pone.0146756.ref034" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>]. This will not be an objective of the next iteration and efforts should be made to include a broad array of fisheries, protected species, and ecosystem stakeholders. Fifth, there are potential links that could be made between Overfishing Vulnerability Assessments [
 <xref rid="pone.0146756.ref024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0146756.ref025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>], Habitat Vulnerability Assessments [
 <xref rid="pone.0146756.ref106" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">106</xref>] and Social Vulnerability Assessments [
 <xref rid="pone.0146756.ref107" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">107</xref>]. The vulnerability assessment framework provides a powerful tool that can complement other assessment techniques and support the broader implementation of Ecosystem-Based Management and climate change adaptation strategies.
</p>
