<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">High temperature negatively impacts tuber yield and quality through inhibition of carbon synthesis and its subsequent translocation to stolon (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" class="xref">Figure 1</xref> and 
 <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref>). It has been suggested that the optimum temperature for photosynthesis and biomass accumulation in potato is about 20°C and an increment of every 5°C above the optimum may decrease photosynthetic rate by 25% (
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Burton, 1981</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B128" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Timlin et al., 2006</xref>). In another study Burton reported that temperatures higher than 30°C cause a complete inhibition of the net photosynthesis in potato (
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Burton, 1972</xref>). However, the response of potato plants to temperature varies across the cultivars, for instance, the commercial cultivar Russet Burbank exhibited maximum rates of photosynthesis at 24 to 30°C with photosynthetic reduction observed only at or above 35°C (
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Dwelle et al., 1981</xref>). Similarly, although growth at 30/20°C day/night temperature reduced tuber yield, the high temperature stimulated the rates of photosynthesis (
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hancock et al., 2014</xref>). High temperature-induced inhibition of rates of photosynthesis is associated with a reduction in RuBisCO activation state, irreversible photosystem II damage and increased rates of photorespiration in many plant species including wheat, rye and canola (
 <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Long et al., 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B114" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Salvucci and Crafts-Brandner, 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ainsworth and Rogers, 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B73" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kumar et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Dahal et al., 2012</xref>). In potato, although few studies suggest that high temperature inhibits PSII activity (
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Havaux, 1993</xref>), its effect on RuBisCO activity and photorespiration is still not known. Additionally, heat stress has been suggested to inhibit tuberization and tuber yield through change in assimilate partitioning and impaired sucrose translocation to tubers (
 <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref>). The delayed tuberization is associated with high temperature-induced inhibition of tuberization signal (
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ewing, 1981</xref>), which is thought to be an ortholog of the Arabidopsis protein FLOWERING LOCUS T (FT) known as StSP6A (
 <xref rid="B94" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Navarro et al., 2011</xref>). High temperature decreases harvest index and thus, tuber weight by inhibiting the carbon export to the sink organs (tubers) from the source leaf. The assimilated carbon is accumulated to source leaves or diverted to other leaves as indicated by increased leaf dry matter (
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hancock et al., 2014</xref>). It has been reported that the accumulation of carbon in the source leaves has multiple consequences including feedback limitation of photosynthesis.
</p>
