<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>One of the main factors commonly associated with forest dieback events under drought conditions is the carbon starvation (CS) due to the depletion of nonstructural carbohydrates (NSCs), as a result of a negative carbon balance (Flexas, Bota, Galmés, Medrano, &amp; Ribas‐carbo, 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0083" ref-type="ref">2006</xref>; McDowell et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0156" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>; Mitchell et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0160" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>; O'Grady, Mitchell, Pinkard, &amp; Tissue, 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0171" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>; Weber et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0241" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>). This imbalance involves a complex network of interconnected factors, which include the reduction in carbon assimilation via impairment of photosynthesis rates, both due to diffusive (e.g., reduced stomatal and mesophyll conductance) and biochemical (inhibition of specific metabolic processes) limitations (Flexas et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0082" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>), and the increase in metabolic costs to repair disrupted structures (e.g., membranes, proteins, and nucleic acids), and to produce defense molecules, coupled with the possible increase in respiration (
 <italic>R</italic>) and photorespiration rates (
 <italic>P</italic>
 <sub>R</sub>; Dias &amp; Brüggemann, 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0063" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>; Maroco, Rodrigues, Lopes, &amp; Chaves, 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0145" ref-type="ref">2002</xref>; PARRY, 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0179" ref-type="ref">2002</xref>; Tezara, Mitchell, Driscoll, &amp; Lawlor, 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0226" ref-type="ref">1999</xref>). However, although CS has been suggested as one of the main triggers of tree mortality under drought conditions (McDowell et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0156" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>), this topic is still under intense debate due to some uncertainties. One of this uncertainties involves the fact that the vast majority of studies on C dynamics under drought conditions use only small tree segments (e.g., roots and shoots), which make it difficult to address the role of carbon storage and remobilization in whole‐tree dieback events (Hartmann et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0096" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>; Kono et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0116" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>). In addition, under severe stress conditions, plants also can use alternative molecules (e.g., lipids and organic acids) to fulfill the respiratory process (Araújo, Tohge, Ishizaki, Leaver, &amp; Fernie, 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0020" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>; Pires et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0182" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>; Weber et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0241" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>), a strategy that is usually neglected in drought mortality studies. Thus, to better understand the impact that the fluctuations in the C metabolism may lead to the behavior of tree species under severe drought events, it is essential to deeply investigate the whole‐tree C dynamics and how the use of alternative energetic molecules can postpone the collapse of the respiratory metabolism (Hartmann et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0096" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>). However, although the role of CS in triggering tree mortality remains controversial (Hartmann et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0096" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>; Körner, 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0117" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>), the negative carbon balance induced by drought can have a profound impact on the dynamics of carbon flux on a global scale. In fact, some studies have associated drought events with a reduction in the primary productivity of several plant communities (Brzostek et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0040" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>; Hilker et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0100" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>; Yuan et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0250" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>; Zhao &amp; Running, 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0256" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>).
</p>
