<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In addition to perturbations in the carbon balance, impaired water transport has also been suggested as a major factor causing death in plants exposed to drought (Anderegg et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0015" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>; Choat et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0050" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>; Corlett, 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0060" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>; McDowell et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0156" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>; O'Brien et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0168" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>; Rodríguez‐Calcerrada et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0191" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>; Tai, Mackay, Anderegg, Sperry, &amp; Brooks, 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0223" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>). This occurs because despite the partial closure of stomata, decreased water availability can considerably increase the tension in xylem vessels, a process that may result in cavitation (Tyree &amp; Sperry, 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0229" ref-type="ref">1989</xref>). As a consequence, cavitation can lead to extensive hydraulic failure (HF), reducing a plant's ability to replenish the water lost through transpiration and resulting in extreme desiccation and death (Mitchell et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0160" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>; Rodríguez‐Calcerrada et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0191" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>; Rowland et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0192" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>) (Figure 
 <xref rid="ece35663-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a). In fact, several studies have emphasized the HF as the main determinant of the drought‐induced tree mortality across contrasting vegetation types (e.g., tropical, temperate, boreal, and Mediterranean forests), whereby species less vulnerable to cavitation tend to be more drought‐tolerant (Anderegg, Anderegg, Kerr, &amp; Trugman, 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>; Anderegg, Flint, et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>; Choat et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0050" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>; Greenwood et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0091" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>; O'Brien et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0168" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). Vulnerability to cavitation, in turn, is directly related to a series of anatomical (pit membranes, diameter, and frequency of xylem vessels), morphological (wood density, root depth, sapwood to leaf area), and physiological (control of stomatal movement and phenological stage) factors, which vary widely between species and functional groups (Greenwood et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0091" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>; Jacobsen, Ewers, Pratt, Paddock, &amp; Davis, 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0106" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>; Lens et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0125" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>; Markesteijn, Poorter, Paz, Sack, &amp; Bongers, 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0144" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>; McAdam &amp; Brodribb, 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0150" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>; Santiago et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0199" ref-type="ref">2004</xref>; Scoffoni et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0209" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>; Trueba et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0228" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). Despite this great variability in vulnerability to cavitation, recent studies have shown that most forest communities around the globe operate within a very narrow hydraulic safety margin, placing species from virtually all biomes at risk (Choat et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0050" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>). However, although HF has been pointed as a major determinant of tree mortality (Anderegg, Flint, et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>; Hartmann et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0096" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>), the lack of key information regarding the stability of water transport under drought makes it difficult to predict the behavior of trees under such conditions. For example, until now there is no consensus about what is the lethal point in which xylem embolism develops into HF (Hartmann et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0096" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>), especially in angiosperms, and neither if some mechanisms of xylem repair, as the controversial refiling (Charrier et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0048" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>; Sperry, 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0215" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>), can reestablish the water transport after extreme drought events. Thus, it is of pivotal importance to determine specific thresholds of recovery and fatal embolism and to better understand whether the mechanisms of xylem repair can mitigate the occurrence of such catastrophic events (Hartmann et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0096" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>).
</p>
