<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par5">Here, we identify the cues and functional gene networks underlying plasticity of skin resistance to water loss (
 <italic>r</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>i</italic>
 </sub>) in a fully terrestrial, montane salamander (
 <italic>Plethodon metcalfi</italic>). The cues and mechanisms are particularly relevant for salamanders because resistance to desiccation determines the spatial distribution of their fundamental niche
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>
 </sup> and regions with the highest extinction risk under climate change
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>
 </sup>. In the present study, we identify the potential for temperature to act as a cue for high and more variable VPDs at local and global scales. We explicitly assess temperature, VPD, and their interaction as cues for plasticity at the physiological and regulatory level in a month-long acclimation experiment with a randomized, full factorial experimental design. We use a high throughput RNA-seq approach to sequence total RNA from experimental salamanders, build a de novo transcriptome, and link gene expression in the skin to phenotypic changes using multiple independent analyses on gene expression. Our analysis includes targeted gene ontology terms based upon the mechanisms known to influence plasticity in amphibian water loss physiology, specifically involving lipid barrier formation
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>
 </sup> and regulation of the skin’s vasculature
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>
 </sup>. We find that temperature is an important cue for regulating water loss rates in salamanders and might act as a similar cue for plants and animals across the globe. We also discovered that 
 <italic>P. metcalfi</italic> appears to regulate 
 <italic>r</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>i</italic>
 </sub> using temperature-dependent regression and regeneration of bloody vessels in their skin.
</p>
