<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Theory predicts that climate change will predominantly threaten tropical ectotherms, which are currently living very close to their optimal temperature, while temperate ectotherms, which are living in climates that are currently cooler than their physiological optima, are expected to resist or even benefit from warming [
 <xref rid="pbio.1002323.ref021" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>]. However, Bestion et al. [
 <xref rid="pbio.1002323.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>] show, using a large-scale outdoor mesocosm experiment, that this generality is by no means universal. Experimental warming of ambient temperature (+ 2°C) increased the juvenile growth rate and reduced the reproduction age of common lizards (
 <italic class="italic">Zootoca vivipara</italic>). However, these temperature-driven enhancements to juvenile and reproductive fitness came at a harmful cost to adult survival. By integrating experimental estimates of survival, growth, and reproduction into population models, Bestion et al. [
 <xref rid="pbio.1002323.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>] found that even moderate (and very likely) temperature increases for Europe (+ 2°C) will result in regional extinctions of 
 <italic class="italic">Z</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">vivipara</italic> at the southern range of their distribution. These results are a far cry from showing that 
 <italic class="italic">Z</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">vivipara</italic> will resist or even benefit from climate change, as has been suggested for temperate ectotherms more generally. Even more alarming is the fact that 
 <italic class="italic">Z</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">vivipara</italic> is not a physiological specialist with respect to temperature (having a wide-range across Europe and Asia) and therefore not an obvious “at risk” species from climate change [
 <xref rid="pbio.1002323.ref022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>]. Nevertheless, 21st century climate change is likely to have a strong deleterious effect on its range dynamics, causing regional extinctions that will lead to wide-scale range contraction.
</p>
