<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s1" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Understanding the relationship between environmental cues and breeding phenology, and the physiological mechanisms mediating these relationships, is essential for predicting organismal responses to climate change [
  <a rid="RSOS140301C1" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS140301C1">1</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS140301C2" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS140301C2">2</a>]. In seasonally breeding birds, the timing and duration of breeding are ultimately determined by the food available to support offspring growth during the chick-rearing phase of reproduction [
  <a rid="RSOS140301C3" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS140301C3">3</a>]. However, seasonal gonadal development and egg laying can be temporally separated from the chick-rearing phase by several weeks or even months owing to the time required for the extensive physiological and behavioural preparation for breeding [
  <a rid="RSOS140301C4" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS140301C4">4</a>]. Therefore birds, and many other animals, use environmental cues for timing of breeding that can reliably predict, in advance, when food will be plentiful for breeding much later in the season. We have had a working model for control of seasonal reproduction for 40 or more years (reviewed in Williams [
  <a rid="RSOS140301C4" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS140301C4">4</a>]) which suggests that day length provides reliable ‘initial predictive information’ for general timing of seasonal breeding, perhaps determining a photoperiodic window during which breeding can occur. Then various ‘supplemental factors’ closer to onset of breeding, such as temperature [
  <a rid="RSOS140301C2" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS140301C2">2</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS140301C5" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS140301C5">5</a>], fine-tune the actual timing of egg laying to annual variation in 
  <span class="italic">local</span> breeding conditions (e.g. colder, later, versus warmer, earlier spring temperatures [
  <a rid="RSOS140301C6" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS140301C6">6</a>–
  <a rid="RSOS140301C9" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS140301C9">9</a>]).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Most studies to date have shown that temperatures closest to onset of egg laying (less than 1 month), commonly referred to as ‘spring temperatures’, are most highly correlated with laying date [
  <a rid="RSOS140301C10" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS140301C10">10</a>–
  <a rid="RSOS140301C12" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS140301C12">12</a>]. This is consistent with our current model of timing of breeding (
  <span class="italic">sensu</span> [
  <a rid="RSOS140301C8" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS140301C8">8</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS140301C9" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS140301C9">9</a>]) and suggests that spring temperatures are an important supplemental cue determining breeding phenology (although many aspects of temperature cues remain poorly understood [
  <a rid="RSOS140301C13" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS140301C13">13</a>]). In general, the greater the time-lag between perception of a cue and the fitness consequences of the response to that cue the less informative cues are likely to be to an organism [
  <a rid="RSOS140301C14" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS140301C14">14</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS140301C15" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS140301C15">15</a>]. Lag times are important because they increase the probability of mismatches between the environment and the phenotype of the individual [
  <a rid="RSOS140301C14" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS140301C14">14</a>], and this therefore has important implications for effects of climate change [
  <a rid="RSOS140301C16" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS140301C16">16</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS140301C17" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS140301C17">17</a>]. Most studies to date therefore also support this idea that birds use information from supplemental cues with short lag times in order to decrease potential mismatch between the environment and reproductive decisions [
  <a rid="RSOS140301C14" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS140301C14">14</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS140301C15" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS140301C15">15</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS140301C18" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS140301C18">18</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here we investigated the relationship between pre-breeding temperature and laying date in a species with highly synchronous breeding within- and among years: the European starling (
  <span class="italic">Sturnus vulgaris</span>; mean laying date ±4 days among years for first nests). Initially, we predicted (i) that there would be only a weak, or no, relationship between temperature and laying date if photic cues (day length) were sufficient to time synchronous breeding periods, but that (ii) if pre-breeding temperature and laying date were correlated then temperatures closest to onset of egg laying (less than 1 month) would be most highly correlated with laying date, as these would provide the most accurate cue information indicating conditions during egg laying and chick rearing. Although we find a strong, negative correlation between pre-breeding temperature and timing of onset of egg laying, mid-winter temperature (January–February) 
  <span class="italic">ca</span> 50–90 days before onset of egg laying, not later spring temperature (less than 1 month before), predicted timing of egg laying. These data suggest a complex relationship between temperature, phenology of prey availability and timing of breeding which might explain species-specific variation in responses to climate change (e.g. [
  <a rid="RSOS140301C19" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS140301C19">19</a>]).
 </p>
</sec>
