<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec7" sec-type="conclusion" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusions</div>
 <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our simulations clearly show that the evolution of the deepening and expansion of the continental margins influences the dynamical states of the AIS, independently from the atmospheric forcing (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>). Atmospheric forcing then modulates the magnitude of the AIS response to both bathymetry and ocean forcing. We suggest that by gradually eroding the continental margins, the AIS increased its own sensitivity to ocean forcing, which becomes a primary factor of AIS substantial variability during interglacials. We also suggest that this sensitivity is partly compensated by the large Pleistocene global atmospheric and oceanic cooling.
 </p>
 <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The interplay between atmospheric and oceanic conditions, sea level and bed morphology has a transient nature. In the present study, we used steady-state climate forcing to our ice-sheet simulations. It is likely that, in transient ice sheet simulations some compensation occurs between the atmospheric forcing and the oceanic sub-shelf melting that could have dampened the sensitivity to the various oceanic forcing tested in our study. Spatial resolution in our simulations is low, 40 km, and increasing resolution would probably induce different AIS dynamical behaviors since a more resolved subglacial topography would present different pining areas. Nevertheless, we maintain that our simulations show the primary mechanisms and interplay between the evolution of the subglacial topography, the deepening of continental shelf and the atmospheric and oceanic forcing. With these simulations, we show that the AIS contributed to the amplification of its own sensitivity to climatic conditions (atmosphere + ocean) by gradually eroding the continental margins, which likely changed its tipping points through time. The lack of past topographic reconstructions implies that we still have an imprecise idea of AIS response to past climate evolution, which is crucial to determine the AIS future evolution.</p>
</sec>
