<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec015" sec-type="materials|methods" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We use multiple linear regression to assess associations among the constructs in the hypothesized learning model (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0202877.g004" href="#pone.0202877.g004">Fig 4</a>). The dependent variables are the gains, 
  <span class="italic">G</span>, between the pre- and post-surveys for each of the constructs, 
  <span class="italic">C</span>, identified through EFA, 
  <span class="italic">G</span> = 
  <span class="italic">C
   <sub>Post</sub>
  </span> − 
  <span class="italic">C
   <sub>Pre</sub>
  </span>. For each focal construct, (e.g., the gain in 
  <span class="italic">Intent</span>), the independent variables are the gains in the other constructs (e.g., gains in knowledge of climate change 
  <span class="italic">Impacts</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Urgency</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Hope</span>). We include a variety of controls, including the pre-survey value of the constructs to test for ceiling effects that might arise in cases with high pre-survey values, and fixed effects to control for potential influence of participant or session characteristics. Controls for participants’ sociodemographic characteristics include gender, age, education, parents’ education, and perceived socioeconomic status. Session-level controls include whether the session was held in a developed or developing country, in a secondary or post-secondary educational setting, and was run by an experienced facilitator or someone with no or minimal formal training in 
  <span class="italic">World Climate</span> (see 
  <a rid="pone.0202877.t001" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0202877.t001">Table 1</a>, 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0202877.s001" href="#pone.0202877.s001">S1</a> and 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0202877.s002" href="#pone.0202877.s002">S2</a> Tables). Pearson’s correlation coefficients across session- and participant-level variables are provided in 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0202877.s003" href="#pone.0202877.s003">S3 Table</a>. For all regressions, tests for collinearity and outliers included ensuring that all tolerance statistics were &gt; 0.2, variance inflation factors (VIF) were &lt; 10, and Cook’s distance values were &lt;4/N.
 </p>
</sec>
