<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">For survival, we tested for differences among years and age classes; however, we were most interested in the potential relationships between survival and annually varying ice, temperature, and wind conditions in the Bering Sea, and global atmospheric patterns such as the Arctic Oscillation (AO) and Pacific Decadal Oscillation (PDO). Annual indices of AO, PDO, mean winter sea surface temperature, and a measure of winter North‐South wind anomalies in the Bering Sea were downloaded from the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration's Bering Climate data portal (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.beringclimate.noaa.gov/data/index.php" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.beringclimate.noaa.gov/data/index.php</ext-link>). The four 25 × 25 km cells defining the core wintering area were originally identified by (Petersen &amp; Douglas, 
 <xref rid="ece34637-bib-0044" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2004</xref>) based on utilization distributions of 13 satellite‐tagged individuals from 1993 to 1997, confirmed by aerial surveys of overwintering Spectacled Eiders. Observed sea ice concentrations were extracted for the core wintering area from daily gridded (25 km resolution) estimates that were derived from passive microwave satellite imagery using the Bootstrap Algorithm and disseminated by the National Snow and Ice Data Center, Boulder, CO (Comiso, 
 <xref rid="ece34637-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>). The core wintering area spanned four grid cells, and the ice concentration for a given day was defined as the minimum among the four cells. We calculated number of days from November through April with &gt;95% ice cover (hereafter, “extreme ice days”), and an index of sea ice severity based on the number of consecutive days with heavy sea ice (Flint et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34637-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). For this index, we counted the number of consecutive days with &gt;95% sea ice cover, allowing for 1‐day drops below 95%. Isolated one‐day events of high sea ice cover were not counted. The ice index accounted for both the length of high‐ice periods and the frequency of these periods for each year. We used the following equation to calculate the index (
 <italic class="italic">I</italic>; Flint et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34637-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>):
 <disp-formula id="ece34637-disp-0001" class="disp-formula">
  <math id="nlm-math-1" class="math">
   <mrow class="mrow">
    <mi class="mi">I</mi>
    <mo class="mo">=</mo>
    <munderover class="munderover">
     <mo movablelimits="false" class="mo">∑</mo>
     <mrow class="mrow">
      <mrow class="mrow">
       <mi class="mi">i</mi>
       <mo class="mo">=</mo>
       <mi class="mi">I</mi>
      </mrow>
     </mrow>
     <mi class="mi">B</mi>
    </munderover>
    <mi class="mi">D</mi>
    <mo class="mo">×</mo>
    <mtext class="mtext">ln</mtext>
    <mfenced close=")" open="(" class="mfenced">
     <mi class="mi">D</mi>
    </mfenced>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </disp-formula>where 
 <italic class="italic">B</italic> is the total number of periods within a year and 
 <italic class="italic">D</italic> is the number of days within each period. According to this equation, years with lengthy contiguous periods of high sea ice cover will have a higher ice index. For all climate covariates except for wind anomaly, quadratic terms were considered to test for non‐linear effects. Models with all combinations of climate and sea ice covariates were tested (see Supporting Information Table 
 <xref rid="ece34637-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S2</xref> for full list of models). Because models that replace time‐varying survival with a covariate derived estimate tend to have large differences in numbers of parameters, we conducted an Analysis of Deviance (ANODEV), which provides a means of assessing whether a covariate explains a significant amount of deviance (Skalski, Hoffman, &amp; Smith, 
 <xref rid="ece34637-bib-0056" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1993</xref>).
</p>
