<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In our assessment of climatic stressors on ocean ecosystems, we suggest that the main question that should be asked is when a stressor begins to fall outside of either the range of natural (before the anthropogenic influence; Landres 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="gcb13247-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1999</xref>) or a baseline (a given fixed period) variability, and if such an occurrence is part of a consistent trend. To quantify such conditions, here we use a criterion of two standard deviations from the mean for the period 1990–2010. If a stressor consistently falls outside this range, this criterion strongly suggests that the system is undergoing significant change relative to the baseline. The analysis of SST, stratification (expressed as maximum depth of winter mixing), nitrate concentration within top 100 m and water column primary production show that the rise of SST is unequivocal in all hotspots areas (Fig. 
 <xref rid="gcb13247-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3</xref>), although its impact on ecosystems might manifest itself differently (depending upon factors such as local habitats and biota). The fastest rise of SST amongst the focal hotspots is in the eastern Australia hotspot (Fig. 
 <xref rid="gcb13247-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>c); however, this area is also characterized by strong interannual variability (Fig. 
 <xref rid="gcb13247-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3</xref>a). Will the historical hotspots identified in HP14 remain the fastest warming areas in the future? CMIP5 model SST trends to 2050 generally agree that the fastest warming areas will carry on being associated with the western boundary currents. Further, because of polar amplification, the Northern Hemisphere will continue to have both a greater number and more intense hotspots than the Southern Hemisphere (e.g. Pithan &amp; Mauritsen, 
 <xref rid="gcb13247-bib-0075" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). However, east Australia remains a hotspot across the majority of the models, and there are indications that the Brazilian hotspot will also persist into the future. Nevertheless, all five focus hotspots remain the fastest warming areas of the Southern Hemisphere.
</p>
