<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Ocean deoxygenation is widely considered as one of the major human‐induced stressors of ocean ecosystems (e.g. Bopp 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="gcb13247-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). It is anticipated to accelerate in the next century as a result of the reduced solubility of oxygen (a temperature effect), reduced ocean ventilation (a stratification effect), increasingly shallow remineralization of sinking organic material (a temperature effect) and an increase in productivity in some areas. That said, dynamic effects can counterbalance these factors and may even lead to contractions of OMZs (e.g. Deutsch 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="gcb13247-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). The major large‐scale OMZs are associated with the eastern boundaries of the tropical Pacific, Atlantic and northern Indian oceans, and their recent expansion and intensification has been detected in observations (Stramma 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="gcb13247-bib-0093" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>). As the distribution of OMZs is set by a balance between the vertical profile of organic material remineralization, ocean ventilation and circulation, reproducing OMZ distribution and variability in numerical models is challenging (cf. Stramma 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="gcb13247-bib-0094" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). Nevertheless, our model reproduces the general geographical distribution of the OMZs and generally forecasts their expansion into the future (Yool 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="gcb13247-bib-0109" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013b</xref>). However, the reader should note that our analysis of OMZs is limited as MEDUSA does not include either denitrification or nitrogen fixation, both of which would affect local DIN concentrations. Only one of our focus hotspots, the Indian hotspot (Fig. S8), is located within a large‐scale OMZ, in the Northern Indian Ocean (Gilly 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="gcb13247-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). By decade 2050–2060, the OMZ in this region is forecast to expand into the Arabian Sea, but at the same time, it weakens in the northern part of the Bay of Bengal. This illustrates that, although climate change is global, regional impacts need not track average change (e.g. Cocco 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="gcb13247-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>).
</p>
