<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="pr0010" class="p">The upper Blue Nile Basin (uBNB) in the Highlands of Ethiopia plays a key role in the hydrology of the Nile region. More than 60% of the total Nile river streamflow that reaches Sudan and Egypt is generated in the Ethiopian part of the BNB. This hydrological imbalance has, in the past, caused controversy and dissatisfaction among the affected riverine countries. With climate change looming and uncertainty rising as to its potential impacts, research is needed that examines how possible changes might affect the region. The potential impacts of climate change on the Nile Basin are of particular concern given their geopolitical and socio-economic implications (
 <xref rid="br0450" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Niang et al., 2014</xref>). The Blue Nile is expected to have a lower streamflow by the end of the 21st century because of declining precipitation and increasing use of water for irrigation and hydropower (
 <xref rid="br0270" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Elshamy et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="br0400" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Mccartney et al., 2012</xref>). Accordingly, 
 <xref rid="br0180" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Beyene and Meissner (2010)</xref> estimated that Nile flows will first increase until mid-century, and then begin declining under scenarios A2 and B1 (see subsection 
 <xref rid="se0240" ref-type="sec" class="xref">5.2</xref> on page 17 for details) because of increased evaporation and declining rainfall. 
 <xref rid="br0060" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Abdo et al. (2009)</xref> projected a decline of outflow from Lake Tana by 2080, while 
 <xref rid="br0520" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Taye et al. (2011)</xref> reported inconclusive findings as to possible changes in runoff. There have been several studies on future hydroclimatic variability impacting the BNB (
 <xref rid="br0070" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Adem et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="br0080" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Aich et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="br0130" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Arsano and Tamrat, 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="br0180" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Beyene and Meissner, 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="br0510" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Sutcliffe and Parks, 1999</xref>) as well as on corresponding historic variability (
 <xref rid="br0220" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Conway, 2000</xref>; 
 <xref rid="br0350" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kebede et al., 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="br0400" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Mccartney et al., 2012</xref>). Very few studies have coupled climate change models with watershed models (
 <xref rid="br0070" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Adem et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="br0190" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Beyene et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="br0570" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Wagena et al., 2016</xref>). Model coupling is critical to assess the possible impacts of climate change on both regional water resources and local landscape erosion. Most of the relevant studies used low-resolution spatial input data (FAO, SRTM, global land cover) and a limited number of gauges for calibration (
 <xref rid="br0080" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Aich et al., 2014</xref>). 
 <xref rid="br0540" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Taye et al. (2015)</xref> compared several studies on climate change in the BNB. They reported changes in future streamflow from 10% to 94%. 
 <xref rid="br0190" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Beyene et al. (2009)</xref> reported projections of precipitation increase as high as 25% by the end of the century (2070–2099).
</p>
