<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="s1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Aedes aegypti</span> (L.) is the principal vector for many arboviral diseases, including dengue, chikungunya, yellow fever, and Zika (
  <a rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1">1</a>–
  <a rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4">4</a>). They have (re-) emerged in many densely populated, tropical and sub-tropical areas around the globe, in part due to global trade and travel (
  <a rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5">5</a>–
  <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">8</a>). Almost half of the world's population is now at risk from these diseases (
  <a rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9">9</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">A. aegypti</span> is an ectotherm species, dependent on warm and humid conditions for reproduction and disease transmission. Despite these physiological constraints, it is not well-understood to what extent climate and climate change have contributed to the global expansion of 
  <span class="italic">A. aegypti</span>. Moreover, it is not clear whether climatic factors have affected its abundance, critical for an epidemic threshold. Socio-economic factors have been found to correlate with the immature-stage population of 
  <span class="italic">Aedes albopictus</span> mosquitos in the USA through variations in the number and the type of breeding sites, e.g., storage and disused containers (tires, food/drink containers) (
  <a rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10">10</a>, 
  <a rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11">11</a>). In general, the lower the neighborhood income, the higher the 
  <span class="italic">Aedes</span> mosquito production (
  <a rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11">11</a>). However, from malaria studies, socio-economic development is found to decrease the global distribution of malaria (
  <a rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12">12</a>). The concurrent contributions of changes in climate and socio-economic development have been difficult to disentangle. A number of attempts have been made to map the spatial presence of two 
  <span class="italic">Aedes</span> vectors (
  <span class="italic">A. aegypti</span> and 
  <span class="italic">A. albopictus</span>) (
  <a rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13">13</a>–
  <a rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16">16</a>). However, despite these comprehensive efforts on its presence, vector abundance is still poorly understood. There is no spatial map on 
  <span class="italic">Aedes'</span> vector abundance global distribution from either empirical data or from modeling. Neither can we find the vector's abundance seasonal patterns globally.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical modeling has been used to estimate vector presence, for example, from Kraemer et al. (
  <a rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14">14</a>) and Santos and Meneses (
  <a rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17">17</a>). Among environmental and climatic covariates, climatic conditions were the most important predictors of vector presence in this model, ahead of the vegetation parameter (
  <a rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14">14</a>). In contrast, urbanization accounted only for 2% of the variance, which is difficult to reconcile in light of large-scale domestication of 
  <span class="italic">A. aegypti</span> and adaptation to urban settings (
  <a rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14">14</a>, 
  <a rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18">18</a>, 
  <a rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19">19</a>). A possible explanation is that statistical niche models suffer from under-reporting and collection bias, inherent in even the most comprehensive global vector surveillance repository. Moreover, data on vector abundance are largely unavailable. Niche modeling is also affected, albeit indirectly, by socio-economic (e.g., land use) and public health factors (e.g., vector control activities), which in turn affect the presence/absence of 
  <span class="italic">A. aegypti</span>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In contrast, mathematical modeling has been used to predict vector population dynamics based on documented biological processes (rather than vector presence/absence data), the vector's lifecycle, breeding and survival rates, and the influence of external drivers for vector development (
  <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">20</a>–
  <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">22</a>). This vector development mechanism can be parametrized with empirical data from the laboratory or field. Such a mathematical model can be built on collectively gathered empirical evidence to estimate vector proliferation, and then combined with climatic, environmental, and socio-economic factors. By applying such a dynamic system to estimation of vector development and demography, the vector population can be described in spatio-temporal terms.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">However, most prior researches in this field have not dynamically adjusted the parameters in space and time, to reflect naturally occurring changes in weather and climate. Instead they have retained constant parameters throughout (
  <a rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23">23</a>), fixed seasonal variation (
  <a rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24">24</a>), or considered mainly temperature with limited or no rainfall (
  <a rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7">7</a>, 
  <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">21</a>, 
  <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">22</a>). Previous mathematical models have all focused on vector population dynamic for one or two specific areas only (
  <a rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7">7</a>, 
  <a rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17">17</a>, 
  <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">21</a>, 
  <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">22</a>). No study has described global vector distribution and abundance, past trends and future scenarios. In addition, socio-economic factors have not been considered in mathematical modeling of 
  <span class="italic">A. aegypti</span> vector population dynamics. Our recent work has demonstrated that process-based mathematical modeling is a very good tool to study the vector infestation of new areas through its growth rate. We have shown how the climate change may affect the future infestation of 
  <span class="italic">A. aegypti</span> in Europe (
  <a rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25">25</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this study we use the same process-based mathematical model to estimate the global distribution and abundance of 
  <span class="italic">A. aegypti</span>, in response to climatic variables and socio-economic factors. We validate this model against global vector presence data. Then we project the global distribution, the potential abundance, and the vector density from the past to the future, taking into account either climate as a sole factor or climate and socio-economic factors together. Future climate scenarios are used to project the potential vector abundance to the end of the twenty-first century.
 </p>
</sec>
