<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sensitivity of Realized Abundance to Socioeconomic Development</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In a second model, using multiple drivers (Model B) we estimated the global distribution of vector population per area due to both climatic and socio-economic influences. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Figure 5</a> shows a comparison of different driving forces for the global abundance of female adult 
  <span class="italic">A. aegypti</span>, averaged over the past decade. In 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Figure 5A</a> we use only climate as the driving force for vector abundance (per breeding site) using a linear scale. In 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Figure 5B</a> (linear scale) and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Figure 5C</a> (log scale) (2006–2015) we use climate, human population, and GDPpc as the driving forces. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Figure 5C</a> overlays also the occurrence data (
  <a rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35">35</a>).
 </p>
 <div id="F5" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 5</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Model comparison of different drivers on the global distribution for potential abundance and vector density of female 
    <span class="italic">Aedes aegypti</span>: using climate only (
    <span class="bold">A</span>—Model A) and climate, human population and GDPpc (
    <span class="bold">B,C</span>—Model B). 
    <span class="bold">(A)</span> shows potential vector abundance (per larval site) averaged over the decade 2000–2009 in linear scale. 
    <span class="bold">(B,C)</span> show population density averaged over 2006–2015 in linear scale 
    <span class="bold">(B)</span> and in log scale where occurrence data was also overlaid 
    <span class="bold">(C)</span>.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="fpubh-07-00148-g0005" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Figure 5B</a>, similar to 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Figure 5A</a>, the highest vector abundance is observed around the equator, in tropical areas. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Figure 5B</a> highlights the more densely populated vector areas with the linear color scale used, and thus emphasizes human influence on vector abundance in urban settings, such as Asia and Africa. The log scale in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Figure 5C</a> better illustrates the vector presence areas with low vector density, such as Australia, North Africa, and America. It compares better with the reported occurrence data, the black dots as shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Figure 5C</a>. The difference between 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Figures 5A,B</a> is clearly shown in North Australia and the Amazon area of Brazil, where human population is low but the natural environment is suitable for this vector to flourish.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on Model B, we estimated the global 
  <span class="italic">A. aegypti</span> annual abundance averaged over two periods, 1951–1970 and 1996–2015, as shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F6" href="#F6">Figure 6</a>. This analysis considers the change in climate, population and GDPpc. Over the 45-year time span, the vector density increased. The area with higher population density of 
  <span class="italic">A. aegypti</span> is postdicted to spread from coastal areas toward more continental areas, following patterns of economic activity and higher human population density.
 </p>
 <div id="F6" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 6</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Comparison two-decades averaged global distribution of female 
    <span class="italic">Aedes aegypti</span> vector density over 45 years using Model B.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="fpubh-07-00148-g0006" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The log color scale is used to illustrate more clearly the low vector density areas, such as Australia and North America, where some increases are also observed.</p>
</sec>
