<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We assume there are no significant density-dependent compensatory mechanisms in operation in the populations considered. Although these effects should be an important part of this story [
 <xref rid="pone.0203124.ref069" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">69</xref>], we believe their role is still not always understood [
 <xref rid="pone.0203124.ref070" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">70</xref>] and is likely to differ across the wide range of organisms we consider, so we defer a discussion of their effects to a later paper. Here, we will use two idealized density-independent stochastic population models. The first model is used to derive explicit results for the response to influence from environmental variability. We show how the dynamics of populations with Type III strategies should have stronger influence from environmental variability. The second model generalizes the first model by allowing age-structured survival and fecundity. This Leslie matrix model is parameterized with demographic data for various species. We then use simulations that confirm the results of model-1, showing that population variability due to environmental changes increases as Type III strategies that are more extreme. We further consider the sensitivity of extinction risk to varying autocorrelation in environmental forcing. We show a practical application of these analyses through weighing the benefits of a variety of conservation actions across demographic units of populations with Type I, Type II, and Type III life history strategies. Although our model ignores many important features of population dynamics such as spatial effects and density dependence, which will need to be addressed if we wish to apply our findings to conservation decisions, we believe our framework brings new insights about the interaction between life history strategies and different types of environmental stochasticity including climatic changes for a large range of organisms.
</p>
