<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Statistically downscaled projections were further used to compute ecologically meaningful variables related to growing season temperatures, length of the growing season, climatic water balance, and seasonality (
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Metzger et al., 2013</xref>). Computation of such generally more meaningful variables with regard to plant ecology is needed to better represent the actual “climate envelopes” of tree species (
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hijmans and Graham, 2006</xref>). In order to simplify the multidimensionality of the obtained data, we computed the spatiotemporal mean for each of the obtained variables (i.e., for each grid cell and time step) across the 16 selected models. To select the most appropriate variables for the definition of climate analogs, we finally tested a large number of various variable combinations regarding their ability to represent the well-known Köppen-Geiger climate classification (
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Köppen, 1900</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Geiger, 1961</xref>) as well as two more recent global climate classifications (
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Olson et al., 2001</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Metzger et al., 2013</xref>). This was done by comparing corresponding classifications representative of the respective variable selection (computed to comprise 32 climate zones using the partitioning around medoids method) with the considered, existing classifications (i.e., Köppen-Geiger, Metzger, and Olson). As a measure of match, we computed the so-called Kappa-statistic and used the threshold values introduced by 
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Monserud and Leemans (1992)</xref> which revealed good to very good agreement (Kappa ranging from 0.58 to 0.79) of the finally selected variable combination with the chosen classifications. Following this approach, we eventually selected 11 variables which are listed and described in detail in Supplementary Table 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1" class="xref">S2</xref>. The corresponding climate classification is shown in the supplementary (Supplementary Figure 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1" class="xref">S1</xref>). The spatial extent of the generated climate parameters was finally matched with the forest inventory data (see Section “Forest Inventory Data”), i.e., longitude ranging from 10.75° W to 32.75° E and latitude ranging from 35.75° N to 70.75° N resulting in altogether 3,949 considered grid cells.
</p>
