<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par18" class="p">In this study, we evaluated the ability of 15 CMIP5 models to simulate ENSO from a new perspective, namely as a climate network. By constructing the upper SAT as a network and studying its percolation properties under different SST conditions, we found that most models can simulate the percolation properties of the SAT network successfully at weak SST anomalies, but fail to correctly simulate the percolation phase transition when the SST anomalies were strong enough to trigger a state change of the SAT network. For the 15 models, four models missed the observed percolation phase transition, seven models reproduced the percolation phase transition at incorrect critical point 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">c</italic>
 </sub>. Only four models (NorESM1-M, CNRM-CM5, FGOALS-s2, and CESM1-FASTCHEM) seemed to be able to capture the desired percolation phase transition, but their skill scores calculated from Taylor diagrams were relatively low. As the percolation property essentially measures the fragmentation and functionality of a network, its phase transition indicates a state conversion
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" class="xref">40</xref>
 </sup>. Therefore, whether the models simulated the percolation phase transition of the SAT network successfully is related to the models’ ability to fully capture the influences of SSTA on the upper SAT field, or, in other words, the sea-air interaction. In this work, we find most models fail to fully capture the sea-air interactions. By comparing Figs 
 <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" class="xref">6</xref> with 
 <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" class="xref">7</xref>, it is found that for most models the regions with strong absolute SSTA are different from the regions with high node vulnerability in the SAT network. Only a few models, such as NorESM1-M and FGOALS-s2, produced similar spatial patterns of the node vulnerability (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" class="xref">6</xref>) and the SSTA (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" class="xref">7</xref>). This inconsistency implies the improper simulations of the percolation phase transition may rely on the mismatches of the SSTA pattern and the 
 <italic class="italic">F</italic>
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">i</italic>
 </sub> pattern in the tropical central eastern Pacific, which suggests a new direction for further improvement of dynamical models.
</p>
