<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We showed that a simulated time-constraint was effective in triggering different molting patterns 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-Vgsi1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-Vgsi1">[24]</a> within the bounds found in free-living birds (
  <a rid="pone.0040651-Perrins1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-Perrins1">[29]</a> and personal observation). The more rapid molt of experimental birds was detrimental for flight and body feather quality, which might ultimately have fitness costs (see Introduction). Moreover, the fitness costs of lower quality flight and body feathers may be exacerbated over time because the non-living tissue of poor-quality feathers deteriorates to a greater extent between molts 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-Dawson1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-Dawson1">[4]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-Serra1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-Serra1">[16]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-Vgsi2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-Vgsi2">[43]</a>. Note that these results were obtained using a relatively mild photoperiod treatment (confer with 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-Dawson1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-Dawson1">[4]</a>) and a sedentary model organism. We conclude that the sedentary lifestyle does not equate to release from the molt rate–feather quality trade-off. The experimental birds harbored more fault bars (also known as stress bars), which might indicate that accelerated molting was stressful 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-Bortolotti1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-Bortolotti1">[49]</a>. This suggests that corticosterone (‘stress hormone’) may be a mediator of the molt rate–feather quality trade-off, as corticosterone is known to affect a wide range of feather attributes 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-DesRochers1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-DesRochers1">[50]</a>. Importantly, these results were not confounded by aggression between birds housed in flocks in accordance with our previous work 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-Vgsi1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-Vgsi1">[24]</a> where groups did not differ in the frequency of fighting, and fighting success did not affect plumage ornament expression.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Birds that underwent an accelerated molt developed shorter flight feathers. These results agree with and complement previous studies on the molt rate–feather quality trade-off in migratory or partially migratory species 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-Dawson1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-Dawson1">[4]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-Hall1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-Hall1">[15]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0040651-Dawson2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-Dawson2">[19]</a>. An experimentally accelerated molt resulted in shorter and lighter primaries in starlings, and shorter primaries and wings in lesser whitethroats 
  <span class="italic">Sylvia curruca</span>
  <a rid="pone.0040651-Dawson1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-Dawson1">[4]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-Hall1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-Hall1">[15]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-Dawson2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-Dawson2">[19]</a>. A faster molt resulted in less durable primaries and a greater loss of wing length between molts in grey plovers 
  <span class="italic">Pluvialis squatarola</span>
  <a rid="pone.0040651-Serra1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-Serra1">[16]</a>, lighter feathers in summer-molting passerines 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-delaHera1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-delaHera1">[17]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-delaHera2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-delaHera2">[18]</a>, and thinner, but surprisingly more rigid (stiffer), rachis in blackcaps 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-delaHera3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-delaHera3">[28]</a>. The molt rate is not the only driver of feather quality because other challenges during molt alter the same feather traits in a similar direction, e.g. infestation 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-Pap2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-Pap2">[42]</a>. Given that investment in molt and immune function interfere 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-MorenoRueda1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-MorenoRueda1">[14]</a>, suppressed immunity and consequent higher susceptibility to parasites may indirectly connect molt with feather quality. The rachis width was not influenced by molt rate 
  <span class="italic">per se</span> or its interaction with body condition. The second moment of the cross-sectional area of the rachis is related to its material rigidity 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-Weber1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-Weber1">[51]</a>, so we infer that this was probably less likely to be affected by the molt rate of a sedentary species as opposed to a more time-constrained migratory species (
  <a rid="pone.0040651-Dawson1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-Dawson1">[4]</a>; but see 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-delaHera3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-delaHera3">[28]</a> for how selection on migratory species that rely on assiduous long-distance flights might have led to the evolution of high flexural stiffness).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study is the first, as far as we are aware, to test the effects of molt speed on body feather structure using an experimental approach that enables the inference of causality. Rapid molting resulted in shorter and smaller feathers with a higher barbule density and a lower proportion of plumulaceous barbs 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-Broggi1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-Broggi1">[20]</a>. This feather architecture is proposed to have a lower capacity for heat conservation because it captures less air due to inferior coverage by small feathers and its less fluffy structure (fewer plumulaceous barbs and a higher barbule density; 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-Broggi1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-Broggi1">[20]</a> and refs therein). Thus, this study provides experimental support for the underlying mechanism proposed by Nilsson and Svensson 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-Nilsson1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-Nilsson1">[3]</a> and the supposition of Dawson et al. 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-Dawson1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-Dawson1">[4]</a> and Broggi et al. 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-Broggi1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-Broggi1">[20]</a> that the MCH might also apply to body feathers. Our results entirely corroborate those found by Broggi et al. 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-Broggi1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-Broggi1">[20]</a> and highlight that merely an accelerated molt rate could be sufficient to produce the inter-population differences in contour body feather structure found in great tits. Thus, great tits living on the northern margins of their European distribution might develop feathers with an impaired insulation capacity because of a time-constrained molt. As a consequence, fast-molting birds might expend more energy during thermal challenges 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-Nilsson1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-Nilsson1">[3]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-Broggi2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-Broggi2">[52]</a>. These molt rate-mediated costs could influence population processes and be responsible for the sink population attributes (e.g. lower survival rate) in the northern margins of the distribution range of the great tit 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-Broggi1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-Broggi1">[20]</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An interesting aspect we found is that body condition was positively associated with feather traits either irrespective of the treatment (primaries’ rachis width and mantle feather length) or only in the experimental group (wing, tail and primary lengths). Therefore, feather traits could be honest indicators of the bearer’s condition (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0040651-g002" href="#pone-0040651-g002">Figs. 2</a>,
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0040651-g003" href="#pone-0040651-g003">3</a>) in concert with Moreno-Rueda’s 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-MorenoRueda1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-MorenoRueda1">[14]</a> proposal. Birds can achieve functionally adequate plumage by starting to molt early in the season, but only birds with a good body condition can buffer against a compromised molt (interactions on 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0040651-g002" href="#pone-0040651-g002">Figs. 2</a>,
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0040651-g003" href="#pone-0040651-g003">3</a>) if they “miss the boat” of early molt. Nestling growth and body condition have been under scientific siege in avian evolutionary ecology for a long while. Early-life growth costs were addressed frequently by means of brood size manipulation experiments (e.g. 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-AlonsoAlvarez1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-AlonsoAlvarez1">[53]</a>). A general pattern emerged where growth-related costs were masked under good environmental condition (brood size reduction), whereas they were ubiquitous in the opposite situation (brood size enlargement). To the best of our knowledge, this is the first report of the body condition-dependent costs of somatic growth during adulthood using a manipulative tool. Under good environmental condition (relaxed molt), sparrows were capable of growing good-quality feathers independent of their body condition. However, only birds with a good body condition were capable of doing so in a challenging situation (rapid molt). In other words, good condition birds had narrower reaction norms (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0040651-g002" href="#pone-0040651-g002">Figs. 2</a>,
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0040651-g003" href="#pone-0040651-g003">3</a>); they could withstand challenging environmental circumstances better and by virtue of their higher quality they endure the increased demands of molt (i.e. show higher developmental homeostasis). These conclusions agree with de la Hera et al.’s 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-delaHera1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-delaHera1">[17]</a> graphical model, as well as the molt–mass trade-off and mass-mediated molt–immunity trade-off reported by Moreno-Rueda 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-MorenoRueda1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-MorenoRueda1">[14]</a>. We argue that the link between feather quality and body condition persists outside the molting period owing to a positive feedback loop across years. That is, the growth of low-quality feathers in a given year is followed by lower condition and breeding performance in the next year, which compromises the molt once again as a consequence (this is referred to as the ‘running wheel’ effect because of the predictable cycle of states in sequential life stages). At least two lines of empirical evidence support this reasoning. First, feather quality depended on condition-indicator traits throughout the entire annual cycle of great tits 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-Vgsi2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-Vgsi2">[43]</a>. Second, feather traits were repeatable over years within individual blackcaps 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-delaHera5" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-delaHera5">[54]</a>. Low-quality birds in particular are most probably trapped in this ‘running-wheel’ because they are often late breeders and thus have deferred molt onset 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-Mller2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-Mller2">[55]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-Verhulst1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-Verhulst1">[56]</a>. Understanding how individuals carry over effects from one season to the next has crucial importance, e.g. for population dynamics 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-Webster1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-Webster1">[57]</a>, and molt appears to be a potent modulator of such inter-season connectivity.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results have implications for (1) the evolution of feather trait diversity among avian taxa and (2) selective forces acting on annual routines. These results may stimulate future inquiry. First, based on current knowledge, we argue that constrained molt could be a more general mechanism at least among small-sized birds that molt their whole plumage once each year. Poor-quality flight and body feathers might have a marked imprint on the residual fitness, which provides a substrate for evolution 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-Desrochers1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-Desrochers1">[58]</a> given the inheritance of feather traits, molt timing and the feather growth rate 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-Jensen1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-Jensen1">[34]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-Gienapp1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-Gienapp1">[39]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-Lessells1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-Lessells1">[59]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0040651-Helm2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-Helm2">[62]</a>. Consequently, species that thrive in different environmental conditions and have diverse annual routines may be exposed to species-specific selective forces, which act on molt rate- and condition-mediated feather quality, and this could have led to the perplexingly high diversity in feather shape, structure and their material properties (e.g. 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-Wang1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-Wang1">[63]</a>). Second, the mismatch between the timing of parental labor and food peaks due to climate change could drive population declines 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-Nussey1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-Nussey1">[64]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-Both1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-Both1">[65]</a>. Besides this climate-driven selection, our results suggest that there may be an additional selective advantage of early breeding to acquire better quality feathers via a slower molting rate. Sedentary birds may benefit in terms of molting due to the progressive advancement of spring. By contrast, this may have a highly negative impact on summer-molting migrants due to the mismatch of the timing of breeding and food abundance, which might be followed by compromised condition and molting. These aspects suggest that pluralistic approaches are needed by also looking through the prism of molting to better understand eco-evolutionary processes.
 </p>
</sec>
