<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2b" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">General Procedures</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We caught 50 non-molting adult male house sparrows at a cattle farm near Cluj Napoca (46°46′N, 23°33′E, Transylvania, Romania) on 25 July 2008. Birds were transferred to the Campus of Babeş-Bolyai University, Cluj Napoca and randomly assigned in equal numbers into two indoor aviaries (each 4 m L×3.5 m W×4 m H). Birds allocated to the aviaries did not differ in any measured aspect (one-way ANOVA, pre-molt wing length: 
  <span class="italic">F</span>
  <sub>1,47</sub> = 0.09, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.76; pre-molt tail length: 
  <span class="italic">F</span>
  <sub>1,43</sub> = 0.22, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.64; body mass: 
  <span class="italic">F</span>
  <sub>1,44</sub> = 1.47, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.23; tarsus length: 
  <span class="italic">F</span>
  <sub>1,47</sub> = 0.14, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.71). During confinement, birds had 
  <span class="italic">ad libitum</span> access to protein-rich food (seed mixture supplemented with grated boiled eggs or mealworms on odd days; 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-Pap1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-Pap1">[13]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-Vgsi1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-Vgsi1">[24]</a>), sand and daily exchanged drinking water. Aviaries contained bushes, perches and nest boxes. Coccidian parasites that emerge spontaneously in captive populations were purged by an anticoccidial drug (toltrazuril) administered in the drinking water 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-Vgsi1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-Vgsi1">[24]</a>. Except one sparrow from the control group that died for unknown reasons, the rest of the birds were released back to the population of origin in good body condition after the termination of the experiment (on 15 November 2008).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Aggressive behavior can determine resource acquisition and has physiological bases (e.g. steroid hormones) that are recognized to influence keratin synthesis. Still, group housing was issued because free-ranging house sparrows are gregarious in the molting period 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-Perrins1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-Perrins1">[29]</a>. To preclude the possible confounding effects caused by male–male interactions, we recorded within flock agonistic behavior of individually marked sparrows from a hide, calculated fighting success (% fights won out of total) and included this in all subsequent statistical analyses (see 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-Vgsi1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-Vgsi1">[24]</a> for details).
 </p>
</sec>
