<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2e" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical Procedures</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All statistical analyses were performed in the R statistical environment version 2.14.1 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-R1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-R1">[45]</a>. We built linear models (LMs) separately for each response variable except the total number of fault bars, which was analyzed by generalized linear model (GLM) with Poisson error distribution. Treatment was entered as factor and the correlated trait, if any, of focal variables as covariate to deal with the few inter-correlations between response variables. In addition, scaled mass index (SMI; 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-Peig1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-Peig1">[32]</a>) and square root-transformed fighting success were also entered as covariates. SMI 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <span xlink:href="pone.0040651.e001.jpg" mimetype="image" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div> is a size-corrected body condition index calculated as
  <div class="disp-formula">
   <div xlink:href="pone.0040651.e002.jpg" mimetype="image" position="float" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>where 
  <span class="italic">M
   <sub>i</sub>
  </span> and 
  <span class="italic">L
   <sub>i</sub>
  </span> are the mass and tarsus length of 
  <span class="italic">i</span>th individual, respectively, 
  <span class="italic">L</span>
  <sub>0</sub> is the mean tarsus length of the sample and exponent 
  <span class="italic">b</span>
  <sub>SMA</sub> is the slope of log-log model II standardized major axis (SMA) regression of mass on tarsus length (‘lmodel2’ package for R; 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-Legendre1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-Legendre1">[46]</a>). To test whether treatment has a condition-dependent effect, the treatment × SMI interaction term was also entered. Because the widely used condition proxy computed as residuals from mass on skeletal length ordinary least squares regression violates certain statistical assumptions 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-Green1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-Green1">[37]</a>, we calculated SMI (g) as this more accurately indicates non-skeletal mass. SMI was scaled to mean = 0 in each model by subtracting the sample’s mean SMI from each individual’s value in order to gain meaningful parameter estimates. Entering both SMI and fighting success as continuous predictors is reasonable because they are unrelated (Pearson’s product-moment correlation, 
  <span class="italic">r</span> = 0.01, 
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 49, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.98). We first built saturated models that were simplified to minimum adequate models (MAMs) by backward stepwise procedure dropping the predictor with lowest improvement of model fit. For this selection we chose the 
  <span class="italic">P</span>&lt;0.1 criteria to retain confounding variables with weaker influence. MAMs were not allowed to differ from the saturated model in explanatory power. The treatment main effect was always kept in the model, while SMI only when it was significant itself or non-significant itself but significantly interacted with treatment. We adopt stepwise elimination as it performs similarly as information theory approach 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-Murtaugh1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-Murtaugh1">[47]</a>. The requirements of MAMs were checked by plot diagnosis. Each model suited the requirements of linearity, residual’s variance and distribution, and no outliers (i.e. standardized residuals &gt; |3|) were detected.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Only the MAMs are presented. Tests are two-tailed and type I error probabilities were set to 0.05. Mean ± SE of raw data and model estimate 
  <span class="italic">b</span> ± SE for covariates are reported throughout. Sample sizes are 
  <span class="italic">n</span>
  <sub>CP</sub> = 24 and 
  <span class="italic">n</span>
  <sub>EP</sub> = 25 for each variable except for post-molt tail length for which 
  <span class="italic">n</span>
  <sub>CP</sub> = 21 and 
  <span class="italic">n</span>
  <sub>EP</sub> = 24. We were unable to measure post-molt tail length for some birds because of broken feathers. Repeatability calculations were performed as per Nakagawa and Schielzeth 
  <a rid="pone.0040651-Nakagawa1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0040651-Nakagawa1">[48]</a> using the ‘rptR’ package for R and restricted maximum likelihood method.
 </p>
</sec>
