<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Delta Smelt, Mississippi Silversides, and Largemouth Bass were exposed to three different experimental stressor regimes over time to test the effect of multiple stressors experienced in series on physiological tolerance. Three experimental regimes (shown in Fig. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="coy076F2" class="xref">2</xref>) were as follows: (1) 
 <italic class="italic">Control</italic>, where fish were held at constant salinity and temperature conditions for 25 days (T
 <sub class="sub">Low</sub>, S
 <sub class="sub">Low</sub>; 16°C and 2.4 ppt), (2) 
 <italic class="italic">Warm/Sal</italic>, where fish spent 7 days at control conditions (T
 <sub class="sub">Low</sub>, S
 <sub class="sub">Low</sub>), followed by 7 days at elevated temperature (T
 <sub class="sub">High</sub>, S
 <sub class="sub">Low</sub>; 20°C and 2.4 ppt), followed by a subsequent salinity increase under elevated temperature conditions for another 7 days (multiple stressor, T
 <sub class="sub">High</sub>, S
 <sub class="sub">High</sub>; 20°C and 12 ppt), and lastly, (3) 
 <italic class="italic">Sal/Warm</italic>, where fish were exposed to 7 days to control conditions (T
 <sub class="sub">Low</sub>, S
 <sub class="sub">Low</sub>), followed by increased salinity for 7 days (S
 <sub class="sub">High</sub>, T
 <sub class="sub">Low</sub>; 16°C and 12 ppt), followed by a subsequent increase in temperature under increased salinity conditions for 7 days (same multiple-stressor as in Warm/Sal, S
 <sub class="sub">High</sub>, T
 <sub class="sub">High</sub>; 20°C and 12 ppt). The control temperature of 16°C was selected based on the low-to-middle range of temperatures where Delta Smelt are found in the wild (
 <xref rid="coy076C5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bennett, 2005</xref>) and for comparison with a previous study (
 <xref rid="coy076C38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Komoroske 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic> 2015
 </xref>). The high temperature of 20°C was selected as &gt;90% of wild smelt are caught below 20°C, with most found around 18°C (
 <xref rid="coy076C5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bennett, 2005</xref>). The experimental salinity exposure of 12 ppt was selected as 92% of smelt are caught below 6 ppt (
 <xref rid="coy076C40" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Komoroske 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2016
 </xref>). A pilot experiment exposing four, 7-month old Largemouth Bass (a stricter freshwater species) to 12 ppt for 25 days revealed 50% mortality (data not shown), and hence to ensure that non-lethal physiological and hematological markers could be assessed, the elevated salinity exposure for Largemouth Bass experiments was decreased to 8 ppt. It should be noted that some biologists may argue &lt;22°C and &lt;25°C for Delta Smelt and Largemouth Bass, respectively, may not be considered ‘stressful’. There is uncertainty that temperatures of wild caught Delta Smelt reflect only where biologist choose to sample and may be missing Delta Smelt occupying warmer habitats in the SFE; however, previous studies have demonstrated sub-lethal physiological effects of Delta Smelt at 20°C (
 <xref rid="coy076C33" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Jeffries 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2016
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="coy076C38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Komoroske 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2015
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="coy076C40" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>). Therefore, for comparative purposes and the uncertainty of Delta Smelt sensitivity to multiple stressors of 20°C and 12 ppt, the described moderate ‘stressors’ were selected acknowledging are not severe.
</p>
