<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Although temperature itself is a dominant driver of biological processes [
 <xref rid="pone.0179498.ref013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>], the timing and seasonal fluctuations of water temperature are likely as important, or more important. Although the predicted average summer temperatures (M30AT) are unlikely to have acute effects, such as extirpation, for many taxa in SRM lakes, the potential chronic effects of changes in thermal regime may greatly influence the physical habitats of these biota and ecosystem processes that support them. For example, the warming surface water temperatures are unlikely to influence hypolimnetic temperatures [
 <xref rid="pone.0179498.ref054" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>], but related abiotic conditions such as hypolimnetic volume will likely decrease as thermocline depth increases [
 <xref rid="pone.0179498.ref002" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0179498.ref055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>]. Primary producers, which form the trophic base of food webs in these lakes, are likely to be strongly influenced by warming temperatures. Potential consequences include increases in frequency and severity of harmful algal blooms [
 <xref rid="pone.0179498.ref017" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0179498.ref056" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">56</xref>], and earlier spring phytoplankton blooms [
 <xref rid="pone.0179498.ref057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>]. In the SRM, shifts to earlier ice-off dates are increasing chorophyll 
 <italic class="italic">a</italic> values (an indicator of phytoplankton production), suggesting that this thermal metric is an important driver of SRM lake primary production [
 <xref rid="pone.0179498.ref036" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>]. Climate change induced alterations of phytoplankton dynamics [
 <xref rid="pone.0179498.ref058" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">58</xref>] can also lead to decreases in hypolimnetic dissolved oxygen concentration [
 <xref rid="pone.0179498.ref018" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0179498.ref059" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">59</xref>] and, consequently, reduced densities of benthic invertebrates [
 <xref rid="pone.0179498.ref060" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">60</xref>]. Pelagic invertebrates are also influenced by warming thermal conditions of lakes through changes in zooplankton phenology [
 <xref rid="pone.0179498.ref016" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>] and increases in zooplankton productivity [
 <xref rid="pone.0179498.ref061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">61</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0179498.ref062" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">62</xref>]. Climate driven thermal changes in SRM lakes may interact synergistically with elevated rates of atmospheric nitrogen deposition in high-elevation landscapes [
 <xref rid="pone.0179498.ref063" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">63</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0179498.ref064" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">64</xref>], with the potential to alter nutrient dynamics [
 <xref rid="pone.0179498.ref065" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">65</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0179498.ref066" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">66</xref>] in these normally oligotrophic systems, pushing them toward mesotrophic or eutrophic states [
 <xref rid="pone.0179498.ref067" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">67</xref>].
</p>
