<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Although our results indicate a warming trend in overall thermal regimes of high-elevation SRM lakes, our study has potential limitations. First, the rates of change we present are based on climate projections using a medium to high emission scenario, which may be higher than those predicted under lower emissions. Using multiple emission scenarios would not influence the direction of these changes, but could alter the magnitudes of rates of change that our models predicted. Second, our focus on lake surface temperature does not address potential changes to other limnological features such as water column stratification and thermocline depth. Third, collection of more detailed data on drivers of ice cover phenology (e.g., timing and amount of snowfall or rain; [
 <xref rid="pone.0179498.ref036" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>]) could help refine predictions of ice dynamics in mountain lakes. Likewise, gathering basic physiographic data for lakes such as detailed bathymetry and continuous vertical thermal profiles would allow future studies of mountain lake temperature regimes to include more detailed processes such as water residence time, timing of runoff, and mixing dynamics (sensu [
 <xref rid="pone.0179498.ref002" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0179498.ref051" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">51</xref>]). These more detailed processes are particularly important to ice-off timing in SRM lakes which is likely driven by air temperature along with the timing and amount of snowfall or rain [
 <xref rid="pone.0179498.ref036" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>]. Finally, there are potential biases in the SNOTEL air temperature data caused by changes in sensor type and placement at SNOTEL sites, which mainly influenced daily maximum and minimum air temperature values [
 <xref rid="pone.0179498.ref076" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">76</xref>]. This bias was strongest for minimum temperatures (warmer), whereas the bias in maximum temperature was weaker and varied by season (cooler in summer and warmer in winter). For our analysis we used SNOTEL daily mean air temperature, which was not addressed in the previously mentioned bias analysis [
 <xref rid="pone.0179498.ref076" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">76</xref>]. We suggest that this bias is likely small, possibly influencing the magnitude but not the direction of these trends.
</p>
