<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="P28" class="p">Human health responses are influenced by ozone concentration, duration of exposure, the rate of change of ozone concentration over a period of exposure, frequency of exposures, level of exertion during exposure, health, age, sex, and other risk factors (
 <xref rid="R199" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">US EPA, 2013</xref>). Lung function and airway inflammation variables are the most frequently used measures to assess the effects of ozone exposure. The development and intensity of typical subjective symptoms, such as cough, shortness of breath, chest tightness, and throat irritation depend on the level of ozone exposure. Human laboratory studies frequently use the product of ozone concentration, duration of exposure, and minute ventilation (the amount of air inhaled or exhaled in one minute) as determinants of effective dose (
 <xref rid="R174" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Silverman et al., 1976</xref>). These authors already recognized that “for a given effective dose, exposure to a high concentration for a short period had more effect than a longer exposure to a lower concentration” stating indirectly that peak concentrations induce greater decrements in spiro-metric lung function effects. Minute ventilation, a product of breathing frequency and tidal volume (amount of air inhaled or exhaled in a single breath), reflects the intensity of physical activity. However, other dose metrics (e.g., impact, local, etc.) have been used to express exposure burden on the individual. In general, the health effects response of individuals to ozone inhalation are also influenced by demographic, physiological, exposure, environmental, and socio-economic factors with exposure and physiological factors being the main determinants of the magnitude of exposure-induced health effects. All these factors contribute to considerable inter-individual variability in health response to ozone, which is measured by a variety of physiological tests assessing inflammatory, immune, and symptomatic effects, as well as functional responses primarily of the cardiopulmonary system. Depending on the combination of the above factors during exposure, the response will vary in intensity from minimal respiratory function changes to clinically significant pathophysiological responses of the cardiopulmonary system. Sequential exposures will lead to attenuation of response in many health variables (
 <xref rid="R50" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Folinsbee et al., 1980</xref>; 
 <xref rid="R69" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hazucha, 1993</xref>). Co-exposure with or a sequential exposure to other air pollutants may have additive, synergistic, potentiating, or antagonistic effects on the extent of physiologic response as compared to the effects of ozone alone (
 <xref rid="R123" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Linn et al., 1994</xref>; 
 <xref rid="R71" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hazucha et al., 1994</xref>). The findings of human laboratory studies that control most of the abovementioned factors and determinants of health effects response serve as a database for development of population exposure models. Depending on the objectives of the studies, the human health response may be assessed in terms of exposure-response, concentration-response, or dose-response relationships.
</p>
