<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">
 <italic class="italic">Plethodon cinereus</italic> in our population are largely underground during the summer and winter due to unfavorable environmental conditions (Taub, 
 <xref rid="ece32573-bib-0078" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1961</xref>). Even during peak surface activity, 
 <italic class="italic">P. cinereus</italic> may be unavailable for capture because they retreat to underground refugia (Bailey, Simons, &amp; Pollock, 
 <xref rid="ece32573-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2004</xref>). We used robust design models that estimate within‐season detection probabilities and among‐season survival rates while accounting for this temporary unavailability (Kendall, Nichols, &amp; Hines, 
 <xref rid="ece32573-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1997</xref>; Pollock, 
 <xref rid="ece32573-bib-0060" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1982</xref>). Detection probabilities reflect both the probability an individual was on the surface and the probability it was captured and identified. We can therefore estimate when, or under what conditions, salamanders are more likely to be on the surface and how this probability varies within each spring and autumn. Detection probability, parameter 
 <italic class="italic">p</italic>, was modeled using a quadratic function to estimate the optimal environmental condition under which surface use peaked. We tested whether optima were different between morphs for three variables (Table 
 <xref rid="ece32573-tbl-0001" ref-type="table-wrap" class="xref">1</xref>): calendar day (prediction 1), the 3‐day average rainfall (prediction 2), and the 11‐day average of air temperature, which roughly characterizes surface soil temperature (prediction 3; Kang, Kim, Oh, &amp; Lee, 
 <xref rid="ece32573-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2000</xref>). This resulted in three separate models, one for each environmental predictor. These models included a fixed effect of morph, a fixed effect for morph–environment interactions, and a fixed effect for plot to account for site differences (Table 
 <xref rid="ece32573-tbl-0002" ref-type="table-wrap" class="xref">2</xref>). Parameters were estimated using closed‐population robust design models in program MARK (White &amp; Burnham, 
 <xref rid="ece32573-bib-0085" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1999</xref>). See Appendix 
 <xref rid="ece32573-app-0001" ref-type="app" class="xref">A</xref> for further details on model development.
</p>
