<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Expression profiling of 
  <span class="italic">Protolaeospira stalagmia</span>
 </div>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The cellular responses to warming of the endemic biota on the heated panels were analysed via RNA-Seq expression profiling of the spirorbid (
  <span class="italic">P. stalagmia</span>). Assembly of the raw reads from all samples produced over five million contigs greater than 100 bp that contained over 4.28 Gb of data (Supplementary Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>). A series of filtering steps (described in Transcriptome methods) provided a reference transcriptome containing 61,421 high-quality transcripts with the mean length of 486 bp and a total size of 29.92 Mb. Of these transcripts, 23.86% contained putative protein sequences, out of which 63.45% showed matches to known proteins from the Swiss-Prot database and 33.92% possessed functional information based on GO terms. While comprehensive searches were conducted using different sequence databases (e.g., Pfam, SignalP, TmHMM, eggnog, KEGG and GO), the most comprehensive annotations were provided by the Swiss-Prot database (BlastX and BlastP).
 </p>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Differential expression analysis was then performed on the +1 and +2 samples, using the control samples as a baseline in both cases. In the +1 sample versus control analysis, a total of 14,631 transcripts were significantly differentially expressed. The majority of these transcripts (13,034) were up-regulated in the +1 samples compared with the controls. Fewer transcripts were differentially expressed between the +2 samples and the controls (1020 in total) of which 1013 were up-regulated in the +2 samples and only 7 down-regulated. Principal component analysis (PCA) on the normalised and filtered expression data revealed there was significant separation between each set of samples (control, +1, and +2), with the first principle component explaining approximately 57% of the variance of the data (
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.004) (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). The PCA plot shows that while there is good separation between the +1 samples and both the other groups, one of the +2 samples clusters with the control samples, which may explain why fewer transcripts were differentially expressed in the +2 treatment compared to controls. GO enrichment analyses were performed to identify if specific metabolic pathways or functional groups were preferentially expressed in a particular treatment. These analyses showed significant enrichment below the threshold of the false discovery rate (FDR) of 0.05 for only the control versus +2 comparison, which meant that these processes were up-regulated and enriched in the +2 samples. There was a significant reduction in representation of GO categories involved in transcription (Molecular Function: rRNA binding and DNA directed 5′–3′ RNA polymerase activity) in the control samples compared with the +2 samples (Supplementary Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2</a>).
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>PCA plot on normalised and filtered expression data of the different treatments. 
     <span class="bold">a</span> First and second components of the PCA. 
     <span class="bold">b</span> Second and third components of the PCA. Source data are provided as a Source Data file
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2019_11348_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e496" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Thousands of transcripts were up-regulated in the +1 treatment (14,631, or approximately 25% of the transcripts identified in this study), which indicated that even with +1 °C of warming, the animals had to significantly alter their cellular processes and cellular physiologies to accommodate to the new temperature. Given the lack of any GO enrichment for particular categories of gene functions and the large number of transcripts involved, more detailed analyses concentrated on the expression profiles of the +2 samples examining the annotation of the up-regulated transcripts. Of the 1013 transcripts up-regulated in the +2 animals (compared with controls), 312 were annotated via BlastX and BlastP searches (Supplementary Data 
  <a rid="MOESM5" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM5">1</a>). Most striking about this annotated gene set was the large-scale up-regulation of transcription and translation processes, comprising almost one-third of transcripts. The majority of these sequences were ribosomal genes, but elongation and translation factors were also present. These results corroborate the GO enrichment analyses described above (Supplementary Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2</a>). Similarly there was up-regulation of transcripts putatively involved in cell division (e.g., G2/mitotic-specific cyclins, proliferation proteins), histones, which play major roles in chromatin organisation and regulation, transcripts for protein degradation (e.g., E3 ubiquitin ligases), and cellular respiration (e.g., cytochrome 
  <span class="italic">c</span> oxidases). A number of classical stress response transcripts were also up-regulated including numerous heat-shock proteins and other chaperone transcripts coding for T-complex proteins and peptidyl-prolyl 
  <span class="italic">cis</span>-
  <span class="italic">trans</span> isomerases (Supplementary Data 
  <a rid="MOESM5" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM5">1</a>). To identify critical biochemical pathways, the STRING programme was used to visualise protein–protein interactions and analyse enrichment. This uncovered statistically significant enrichment of certain functional groups of proteins (
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 1.0e
  <span class="sup">−16</span>), with a major cluster of transcription and translation proteins and satellite clusters of proteins involved in post-translational modification, the cell cycle, cytoskeleton and energy production (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>). PANTHER enrichment results, of the same dataset, were dominated by GO terms associated with RNA metabolism and cell division (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>). Overall, these data indicated the induction of the classical stress response to the warmer conditions and a lack of acclimation. The latter was further tested via acute UTL analysis.
  <div id="Tab1" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>PANTHER v13.1 GO-slim overrepresentation tests for 
     <span class="italic">P. stalagmia</span>
    </p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th>Process</th>
      <th>GO identifier</th>
      <th>FDR</th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td colspan="3">Biological processes for +2 °C up-regulated transcripts</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td> Translation</td>
      <td>0006412</td>
      <td>2.02e
       <span class="sup">−13</span>
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td> rRNA metabolic process</td>
      <td>0016072</td>
      <td>4.05e
       <span class="sup">−06</span>
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td> Protein folding</td>
      <td>0006457</td>
      <td>8.62e
       <span class="sup">−03</span>
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td> Generation of precursor metabolites and energy</td>
      <td>0006091</td>
      <td>4.05e
       <span class="sup">−03</span>
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td> Cellular component biogenesis</td>
      <td>0044085</td>
      <td>7.04e
       <span class="sup">−10</span>
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td> Cell cycle</td>
      <td>0007049</td>
      <td>2.90e
       <span class="sup">−04</span>
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td> Organelle organisation</td>
      <td>0006996</td>
      <td>8.26e
       <span class="sup">−07</span>
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Biosynthetic process</td>
      <td>0009058</td>
      <td>8.95e
       <span class="sup">−06</span>
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td colspan="3">Molecular function for +2 °C up-regulated transcripts</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td> Structural component of ribosome</td>
      <td>0003735</td>
      <td>2.57e
       <span class="sup">−42</span>
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td> Translation elongation factor activity</td>
      <td>0003746</td>
      <td>7.32e
       <span class="sup">−03</span>
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td> Translation initiation factor activity</td>
      <td>0003743</td>
      <td>4.55e
       <span class="sup">−02</span>
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td> Translation regulator activity</td>
      <td>0045182</td>
      <td>5.76e
       <span class="sup">−04</span>
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td> Hydrogen ion transmembrane transporter activity</td>
      <td>0015078</td>
      <td>3.46e
       <span class="sup">−03</span>
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td> Structural component of cytoskeleton</td>
      <td>0005200</td>
      <td>2.23e
       <span class="sup">−08</span>
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td> Nucleotide binding</td>
      <td>0000166</td>
      <td>6.70e
       <span class="sup">−05</span>
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td> mRNA binding</td>
      <td>0003729</td>
      <td>2.44e
       <span class="sup">−04</span>
      </td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
