<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Panel sample collection</div>
 <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Samples were taken for molecular analyses from heated (+1 and +2 °C above ambient sea water temperatures) and non-heated (control) panels after 18 months immersion at 15 m depth near Rothera Research Station, Adelaide Island, Antarctic Peninsula (67°4′07″S, 68°07′30″W). These treatments are referred to as control +1 and +2 in the following methods. At the start of the 18-month deployments, all panels were brand new, placed on site and then gradually warmed up to the relevant temperature for colonisation in situ. Three sites around Rothera were used for the original study, with panels deployed in South Cove, Hangar Cove and North Cove on concrete substrata. At each site, four heated panels for each temperature (total of 12 panels per site) were laid in a random design in batches of four with position generated by a random number generator and this design was random with regard to both the position and the concrete block. Because of iceberg impact damage, one set of panels was retrieved from South Cove after 9 months and held in the Rothera flow-through aquarium. The water intake for the aquarium is not filtered; the inlet is at 7M and only boulder covered to protect from ice. Therefore, the animals in the aquarium experienced the same sea water, food availability and environmental conditions as the original site for a further 9 months (South Cove panels). It should furthermore be noted that most of this final 9-month period took place during winter when phytoplankton levels are extremely low. Another set of panels (North Cove panels) remained in the sea for the whole 18-month period. It was not possible to use the Hangar Cove panels in this study, as predation by urchins had dramatically altered the community composition of the panels at this site. Experimental organisms were non-regulated so ethical approval was not required. After a preliminary environmental assessment (PEA #14-11) collections were made within the Antarctic Act, permit number S7-10/2015, as granted under section 7 of the Antarctic Act 1994.</p>
</sec>
