<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">UTL analysis of 
  <span class="italic">Romanchella perrieri</span>
 </div>
 <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Whole animal acclimation is traditionally tested using acute UTL analyses. Due to the limited representation of 
  <span class="italic">P. stalagmia</span> on the panels, a closely related spirorbid species (
  <span class="italic">R. perrieri</span>) was used to test UTLs associated with treatment, with animals taken from the same sets of panels, as were used as a source for the 
  <span class="italic">P. stalagmia</span> and the transcriptome experiments The UTL data supported the 
  <span class="italic">P. stalagmia</span> transcriptome analyses, with a lack of whole animal acclimation in 
  <span class="italic">R. perrieri</span> and a reduction in thermal resilience associated with increased panel temperature (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>). A Kruskal–Wallis test confirmed that there was a statistically significant effect of panel treatment on the UTL of 
  <span class="italic">R. perrieri</span> (
  <span class="italic">H</span> = 26.65, DF = 2, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.000) and that mean UTL of the animals declined with panel temperature (control = 20.20 °C ± 0.167 SE mean, +1 panels = 19.26 °C ± 0.269 SE mean and +2 panels = 18.62 °C ± 0.167 SE mean). Mann–Whitney pairwise comparisons revealed statistically significant differences between all the treatments (control vs. +1 
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.0129; control vs. +2 
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.000; +1 vs. +2 
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.0179) (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>). Thus the UTL declined in the warmed individuals, contributing to evidence of a stress response, as indicated in the molecular results above.
  <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Box plot showing acute UTLs for the spirobid polychaete 
     <span class="italic">R. perrieri</span>. Central line of each box denotes the median, the top and bottom edges of the box show the 25% and 75% percentile, with the 10% and 90% percentiles shown by the upper and lower whiskers; outliers are shown as circles. Letters denote statistically significant differences between treatments (a: 
     <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.0129; b: 
     <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.000; c: 
     <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.0200) (Mann–Whitney pairwise comparisons). Source data are provided as a Source Data file
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2019_11348_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e824" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
