<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The most authoritative statements on physical aspects of climate change come from Working Group I (WGI) of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC). In the Summary for Policymakers of the last (Fifth) IPCC WGI Assessment Report [
 <xref rid="RSPA20190013C2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>], atmospheric circulation is scarcely mentioned, and all the statements of confidence are based on thermodynamics. This remarkable fact evidences better than anything else the lack of scientific consensus on dynamical aspects of climate change. Moreover, the statements of confidence are crafted to be reliable, generally by emphasizing global rather than regional aspects of change. A good example is the headline statement on the water cycle: 
 <disp-quote>
  <p>Changes in the global water cycle in response to the warming over the 21st century will not be uniform. The contrast in precipitation between wet and dry regions and between wet and dry seasons will increase, although there may be regional exceptions. [
   <xref rid="RSPA20190013C2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, p. 20]
  </p>
 </disp-quote> This statement is based on the sound physical principle that, all else being equal, a moister atmosphere will exhibit an accelerated hydrological cycle [
 <xref rid="RSPA20190013C10" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. The statement achieves its reliability in the tropics by including oceanic regions (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSPA20190013F1">figure 1</xref>); indeed, a key observation supporting the statement is the increased salinity in the subtropical upper oceans (due to increased evaporation). However, it is precipitation over land that matters for climate impacts, and there have been many studies showing that the ‘wet get wetter, dry get drier’ paradigm does not hold over land regions [
 <xref rid="RSPA20190013C12" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>–
 <xref rid="RSPA20190013C14" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], as is reflected in the general lack of stippling over these regions (apart from the high northern latitudes) in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSPA20190013F1">figure 1</xref>. The statement is perfectly reliable as an explanation of how the global climate system works, but it does not provide useful information at the regional scale, as the final caveat makes clear. In this way, reliability is achieved at the price of informativeness.
</p>
