<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>To find a high-level statement on dynamical aspects of climate change in the IPCC WGI Fifth Assessment Report, one must look one level down, in the Technical Summary [
 <xref rid="RSPA20190013C2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. The statements are uniformly characterized by low levels of confidence and a lack of informativeness at the regional scale. An illustrative example is the statement on changes in Northern Hemisphere (NH) storm tracks, which are an important determinant of mid-latitude weather: 
 <disp-quote>
  <p>Substantial uncertainty and thus low confidence remains in projecting changes in NH storm tracks, especially for the North Atlantic basin. [
   <xref rid="RSPA20190013C2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, p. 90]
  </p>
 </disp-quote> Furthermore, IPCC WGI uses a likelihood scale in which the term ‘unlikely’ is used to describe likelihoods of up to 33%. This terminology seems rather perverse from a lay perspective; in most areas of life, one would pay attention to likelihoods that high, especially if the consequences were serious—as they are with climate change. (Would you board an aeroplane if you were told that it had a 33% chance of crashing?) Yet in the WGI report, the term ‘unlikely’ is generally used to dismiss rather than to highlight a possibility. Consider this example from the Technical Summary, again with reference to the North Atlantic storm track: 
 <disp-quote>
  <p>…it is unlikely that the response of the North Atlantic storm track is a simple poleward shift [
   <xref rid="RSPA20190013C2" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, p. 108]
  </p>
 </disp-quote> The context here is that, despite the lack of an agreed upon theoretical explanation, the concept of a poleward storm track shift under climate change has become a general expectation [
 <xref rid="RSPA20190013C5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. However, projected changes in the North Atlantic storm track do not conform to that expectation [
 <xref rid="RSPA20190013C15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. An equivalent version of the statement would be ‘…it is likely that the response of the North Atlantic storm track [to climate change] is not a simple poleward shift’. Because, in the present state of knowledge, a consensus statement could not be crafted on what was likely to happen, the authors instead chose to emphasize what was not likely to happen. Yet, there are several possibilities for what might happen, each with its own implications for climate risk, which could have been articulated (e.g. [
 <xref rid="RSPA20190013C16" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]). However, the simultaneous consideration of contradictory futures is not naturally expressed through statements of confidence. Thus, reliability is again achieved at the price of informativeness.
</p>
