<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The impacts on health systems and those that support them are not well documented [
 <xref rid="B13-ijerph-15-00538" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. However, there is potential for climate change to impact health facilities and systems not only through extremes in weather and climate events, but also through sea level rise in the context of exposed coastal facilities, as well as increasing burden on the health system through climate-sensitive diseases, such as dengue, malaria, or non-communicable diseases. As a result, these impacts of climate change and disasters on health systems can cause additional indirect health impacts. While these areas are not as well documented as the population health impacts [
 <xref rid="B13-ijerph-15-00538" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B57-ijerph-15-00538" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>,
 <xref rid="B62-ijerph-15-00538" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">62</xref>,
 <xref rid="B63-ijerph-15-00538" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">63</xref>], health systems and the systems that support health is becoming an area of increasing concern. The impacts of climate change and disasters on health systems can be categorised in terms of:
 <list list-type="bullet" class="list">
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">Changes in volume and patterns of health service demand from increased morbidity and mortality [
    <xref rid="B15-ijerph-15-00538" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>,
    <xref rid="B21-ijerph-15-00538" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>,
    <xref rid="B58-ijerph-15-00538" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">58</xref>,
    <xref rid="B64-ijerph-15-00538" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">64</xref>,
    <xref rid="B65-ijerph-15-00538" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">65</xref>];
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">Reduced capacity to meet the primary and public health needs due to interruption of vital components of the health system (e.g., infrastructure or equipment damage, reduced staff) [
    <xref rid="B13-ijerph-15-00538" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>,
    <xref rid="B15-ijerph-15-00538" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>,
    <xref rid="B18-ijerph-15-00538" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>,
    <xref rid="B21-ijerph-15-00538" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>,
    <xref rid="B58-ijerph-15-00538" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">58</xref>,
    <xref rid="B64-ijerph-15-00538" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">64</xref>]; and
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">Interruption of health-determining services such as access to clean water, sanitation, food, energy, communication, etc. [
    <xref rid="B58-ijerph-15-00538" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">58</xref>,
    <xref rid="B64-ijerph-15-00538" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">64</xref>,
    <xref rid="B65-ijerph-15-00538" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">65</xref>].
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
