<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec022" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusions</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">European wetlands currently provide abundant prey resources for breeding wetland migrants, but it is predicted that climate warming will further increase overall prey abundance [
  <a rid="pone.0159933.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0159933.ref042">42</a>], and that higher abundances of prey will become available earlier in the breeding season. To investigate the effects of such climate-driven increases and phenological advances in food availability, in the present study individual breeding pairs received either an unlimited food supply or natural food availability under current climate conditions. The results suggest that reed warblers advance the initiation of first broods in response to earlier onset of suitable foraging and nesting conditions, whereas clutch size, incubation duration and hatching success were not directly affected by additional food. First brood productivity was higher in food supplemented treatment groups, which is due to lower rates of predation. Further research is needed to test the possibility that offspring survival and recruitment may be increased through lower predation and earlier fledging of supplemented nests. Despite their access to extensive periods of abundant invertebrate food throughout the breeding period, the success rate of subsequent breeding attempts in reed warblers is low (≤30% [
  <a rid="pone.0159933.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0159933.ref030">30</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0159933.ref031" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0159933.ref031">31</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0159933.ref041" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0159933.ref041">41</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0159933.ref052" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0159933.ref052">52</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0159933.ref069" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0159933.ref069">69</a>]. Our ongoing research efforts will focus on whether earlier completion of the first brood actually leads to greater chance of success in subsequent breeding attempts.
 </p>
</sec>
