<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Applying the Underhill–Zucchini molt model</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The frequently used methods to estimate the start date and duration of molt involves regressing molt scores of all birds against the date. This method is unsatisfactory because, using the standard field technique for recording primary molt data (Ginn and Melville 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b14" href="#b14">1983</a>), it appears as if the rate molt decreases over time (Summers et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b37" href="#b37">1983</a>). This is, in part, due to the fact that primary feathers vary greatly in length. The outer primaries are much larger than the inner primaries but the growth stage of all feather are scored equally. Rather than assuming that molt score increases linearly with time, it is more realistic to assume that feather material is produced at a constant rate (Summers et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b37" href="#b37">1983</a>; Underhill 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b43" href="#b43">1985</a>; demonstrated in Remisiewicz et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b30" href="#b30">2009</a>; Barshep et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b3" href="#b3">2011a</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b4" href="#b4">b</a>). Application of the UZ model therefore requires the conversion of molt scores into proportion of feather material grown (PFMG) given by the equation:
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div class="disp-formula">
   <div xlink:href="ece30003-1967-m2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">where m
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </sub> is the mass of the 
  <span class="italic">i</span>th primary relative to the total mass of all the primaries, and 
  <span class="italic">p</span>(
  <span class="italic">s</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </sub>) is the mass of a feather with score s
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">i</span>
  </sub> relative to its mass when it is fully grown (see full details in Underhill and Zucchini 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b47" href="#b47">1988</a>). This conversion essentially “straightens” the progress of molt (Summers et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b37" href="#b37">1983</a>) while the molt model estimates the dates of commencement and completion of primary molt of the “average” bird.
 </p>
</sec>
