<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Arctic data</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Separate lemming and weather data sets were considered for Australia and SA because birds wintering in Australia are likely to originate from the eastern breeding range of the species while birds wintering in Africa are likely to originate from the western breeding range (Wymenga et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b52" href="#b52">1990</a>; Minton 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b23" href="#b23">2005</a>). Population records of lemming abundance from Yamal (70°N, 70°E), Taymyr Peninsula (74°N, 98°E), western Yakutia, and the lower Lena River (73°N 127°E) were extracted from the Arctic Breeding Birds Survey (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.arcticbirds.net/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.arcticbirds.net/</span>) and from literature (Underhill 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b44" href="#b44">1987</a>; Summers et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b38" href="#b38">1998</a>). Lemming abundance was scored on a four-graded scale 0–3 categorized as very low, low, moderate, and high. We merged the data sets on lemming abundance for each breeding region by taking the average and rounding to the nearest integer. The index of predation pressure was calculated using the formula of Blomqvist et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b6" href="#b6">2002</a>):
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div class="disp-formula">
   <div xlink:href="ece30003-1967-m1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">based on the change in lemming abundance from the previous year (
  <span class="italic">X</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">t</span>−1
  </sub>) to the focal year (
  <span class="italic">X</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">t</span>
  </sub>). Therefore, a predation index of 0 is due to an increase in lemming abundance from the previous to the focal year. The index ranges between 0 and 3, with 0 representing the minimum and 3 representing the maximum predation.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Temperature data were used as a proxy for weather conditions in the Arctic during the breeding period in June and July (Tomkovich and Soloviev 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b42" href="#b42">2006</a>). Although other climate parameters such as precipitation and timing of snowmelt could also have been of major importance, temperature was the only variable for which it was possible to obtain consistent, long-term data for the period of interest. For Australia, data on temperature in June and July were obtained from the weather stations of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA) located in Yakutia (70°N, 85°E) while for SA, temperature data were obtained from the weather station in Taymyr (74°N, 95°E). The proportion of juvenile birds in catch totals was used as an index of breeding success (Minton et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b24" href="#b24">2005</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
