<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Consequences of molt schedules</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The end date of molt significantly affected the amount of fat reserved birds are able to put on prior to spring migration. Results indicate that when the end date of molt is delayed, birds are in poorer body condition prior to spring migration. To overcome this problem, birds in SA and SEA generally molted faster in years when molt started later. The decrease in molt duration was enough to compensate for the late start of molt, consequently, the end date of molt was more synchronized than the beginning in both SA and SEA. A similar study on Bar-tailed Godwits, 
  <span class="italic">Limosa lapponica baueri</span>, in New Zealand also shows that delays in wing molt led to an increase in molt rate and a decrease in the total duration of molt (Conklin and Battley 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b8" href="#b8">2012</a>). Why Curlew Sandpipers in NWA did not compensate for the late start of molt by molting faster is not known, but it might be because NWA is 
  <span class="italic">c</span> 3000 km closer to the breeding area than SEA, therefore birds wintering there are not under the same time constraints as the birds in SEA.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Because females generally started molt later than males, they compensate for the late start of molt by molting faster, thus having a shorter duration of molt. There is a price to pay for a fast molt, for while it might give the birds enough time to store up fat reserves, they run the risk of producing low-quality feathers in terms of strength and durability (Dawson et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b10" href="#b10">2000</a>; Serra 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b33" href="#b33">2001</a>), which might jeopardize future survival or breeding success. It is possible, that fitness consequences related to poor feather quality might be sex specific as well.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In conclusion, the results of this study revealed that pre-migratory fattening is prioritized over a rigid molt schedule. Because of the variability in the start dates of molt, it necessitates flexibility in the duration of molt in order to avoid a late molt and poor body condition during spring migration. With climate change modifying trophic interactions in the Arctic (e.g., Ims and Fuglei 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b20" href="#b20">2005</a>) and modifying the phenology of breeding and migration in birds (e.g., Walther et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b51" href="#b51">2002</a>; Both et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b7" href="#b7">2005</a>), the statistical method of Underhill and Zucchini (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b47" href="#b47">1988</a>), and its extension represents a significant advancement in understanding how these changes might affect the timing of molt and how these birds cope with potential carry-over effects.
 </p>
</sec>
