<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Using the UZ models, it was possible to statistically test and quantify the effect environmental factors have on the start and duration of molt making it possible to demonstrate that a disturbance at a certain stage within the annual cycle of migratory birds can alter the next biological event through carry-over effects. The timing of migration in most Arctic breeding waders is governed by the end of breeding, and because predation pressure and temperature are some of the important factors affecting the outcome of breeding in most waders (Meltofte et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b22" href="#b22">2007</a>), these were found to alter the timing of molt on the non-breeding areas in this long-distance migratory bird. Warm temperature during the breeding period encourages the initiation and completion of breeding while cold temperatures might discourage breeding altogether (Meltofte et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b22" href="#b22">2007</a>). The link between the timing of molt on the non-breeding areas in SA and Australia with environmental conditions on the breeding area suggests that such carry-over effects affect the entire species and not just a particular population.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The effect, environmental conditions have on the timing of molt was found to be sex specific. In general, males started molt earlier than females. This difference in the molt schedule of the sexes can be linked to their parental care roles. In Curlew Sandpipers, only the females partake in parental care (Tomkovich and Soloviev 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b42" href="#b42">2006</a>). Thus, the timing of their migration and, consequently, molt will depend on the length of the breeding season which will, in turn, depend on variables that affect breeding success. When predation on the eggs and chicks is low or the temperature when the chicks hatch in July is high, females will remain on the breeding grounds caring for the young until they fledge (Schekkerman et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b31" href="#b31">1998</a>; Soloviev et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b34" href="#b34">2006</a>). In these years, the onset of molt at the non-breeding grounds was later compared to years when predation pressure was high and/or temperatures were low.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Males, who play no part in parental care, leave the breeding grounds and begin migration to the non-breeding areas soon after the females start incubation of eggs (Holmes and Pitelka 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b18" href="#b18">1964</a>; Tomkovich 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b41" href="#b41">1988</a>) thus factors which affect the onset of breeding would potentially affect the timing of molt. It has been shown that the temperature in June, when the birds arrive the arctic breeding areas, is one the important factors which determines the timing of breeding (Tomkovich and Soloviev 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b42" href="#b42">2006</a>; Meltofte et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b22" href="#b22">2007</a>). The warmer the temperature is in June, the earlier the start and completion of egg-laying and the earlier the departure of males from the breeding areas. Consequently, the start of molt in males would be earlier, as confirmed by our results. A similar relationship between parental care roles of the sexes and the onset of molt has been found in Wilson's Phalarope (Jehl 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b21" href="#b21">1987</a>), Purple Sandpiper 
  <span class="italic">Calidris maritima</span> (Morrison 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b26" href="#b26">1976</a>; Summers et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b39" href="#b39">2004</a>), and Dunlin (Greenwood 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b15" href="#b15">1983</a>) where the sex least involved in parental care started molt ahead of the sex that cared for the young.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Related studies examining the link between temperature, duration of breeding season, and molt in Common Starlings 
  <span class="italic">Sturnus vulgaris</span> (Dawson 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b9" href="#b9">2005</a>) and Great Tit 
  <span class="italic">Parus major</span> (Visser et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b50" href="#b50">2011</a>) show that at high temperatures, gonadal regression was earlier, leading to a shorter breeding season and earlier start of postnuptial molt. The contrast in the results of the above-mentioned studies and our result might be due to differences in study species, but it does draw to attention the possibility that latitude might influence the effect of temperature on the length of the breeding season and the response of different species.
 </p>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Consequences of molt schedules</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The end date of molt significantly affected the amount of fat reserved birds are able to put on prior to spring migration. Results indicate that when the end date of molt is delayed, birds are in poorer body condition prior to spring migration. To overcome this problem, birds in SA and SEA generally molted faster in years when molt started later. The decrease in molt duration was enough to compensate for the late start of molt, consequently, the end date of molt was more synchronized than the beginning in both SA and SEA. A similar study on Bar-tailed Godwits, 
   <span class="italic">Limosa lapponica baueri</span>, in New Zealand also shows that delays in wing molt led to an increase in molt rate and a decrease in the total duration of molt (Conklin and Battley 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b8" href="#b8">2012</a>). Why Curlew Sandpipers in NWA did not compensate for the late start of molt by molting faster is not known, but it might be because NWA is 
   <span class="italic">c</span> 3000 km closer to the breeding area than SEA, therefore birds wintering there are not under the same time constraints as the birds in SEA.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Because females generally started molt later than males, they compensate for the late start of molt by molting faster, thus having a shorter duration of molt. There is a price to pay for a fast molt, for while it might give the birds enough time to store up fat reserves, they run the risk of producing low-quality feathers in terms of strength and durability (Dawson et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b10" href="#b10">2000</a>; Serra 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b33" href="#b33">2001</a>), which might jeopardize future survival or breeding success. It is possible, that fitness consequences related to poor feather quality might be sex specific as well.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In conclusion, the results of this study revealed that pre-migratory fattening is prioritized over a rigid molt schedule. Because of the variability in the start dates of molt, it necessitates flexibility in the duration of molt in order to avoid a late molt and poor body condition during spring migration. With climate change modifying trophic interactions in the Arctic (e.g., Ims and Fuglei 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b20" href="#b20">2005</a>) and modifying the phenology of breeding and migration in birds (e.g., Walther et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b51" href="#b51">2002</a>; Both et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b7" href="#b7">2005</a>), the statistical method of Underhill and Zucchini (
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b47" href="#b47">1988</a>), and its extension represents a significant advancement in understanding how these changes might affect the timing of molt and how these birds cope with potential carry-over effects.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
