<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Corporate social responsibility (CSR) is based on the assumption that, at any given point in time, there is a social contract between an organization and society in which the organization has not only economic and legal responsibilities but also ethical and philanthropic responsibilities (
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Carroll, 1991</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1999</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Donaldson and Dunfee, 1994</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1999</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2000</xref>). Building on 
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Carroll’s (1991</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1999</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2000</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2004</xref>) work, 
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Dahlsrud (2008)</xref> conducted a review of CSR definitions and suggested that the majority of definitions include at least two of the following dimensions (although they very rarely have all of them): societal concerns, interacting with stakeholders and social contract, an economic upside, environmental issues, and actions performed voluntarily. As such, we define CSR as a societal expectation, based on stakeholder perspectives (
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Carroll, 2004</xref>), that organizations should address economic, legal, ethical, and discretionary responsibilities. Within this research we are interested in two areas of CSR that 
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Dahlsrud (2008)</xref> found to be less represented in current definitions – that of environmental issues and voluntary vs. forced action – and explore both what the social contract is surrounding these dimensions and how belief in anthropogenic climate change and free market ideology affect those societal views.
</p>
