<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The 19 bioclimatic variables downloaded from the WorldClim dataset with 30″ resolution (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.worldclim.org" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.worldclim.org</ext-link>) [
 <xref rid="pone.0182837.ref044" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>] were used to determine current and future climate data. Future climate scenarios were the same as those used in the MB index calculations (five GCMs and four RCPs). In addition to these bioclimatic variables, we used an aridity index as an environmental variable, because growth and mortality of 
 <italic class="italic">Pinus</italic> trees is greatly affected by drought conditions [
 <xref rid="pone.0182837.ref045" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>]. The aridity index was calculated as the ratio of mean annual precipitation (P) and mean annual potential evapotranspiration (PET) as follows [
 <xref rid="pone.0182837.ref046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>]: 
 <disp-formula id="pone.0182837.e001" class="disp-formula">
  <alternatives class="alternatives">
   <graphic xlink:href="pone.0182837.e001.jpg" id="pone.0182837.e001g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   <math id="M1" class="math">
    <mrow class="mrow">
     <mtext class="mtext">AI</mtext>
     <mo class="mo">=</mo>
     <mtext class="mtext"> </mtext>
     <mfrac class="mfrac">
      <mi class="mi">P</mi>
      <mrow class="mrow">
       <mi class="mi">P</mi>
       <mi class="mi">E</mi>
       <mi class="mi">T</mi>
      </mrow>
     </mfrac>
    </mrow>
   </math>
  </alternatives>
 </disp-formula> using the mountain microclimate simulation model (MTCLIM) [
 <xref rid="pone.0182837.ref047" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>], which has been used to estimate and extrapolate daily temperature, precipitation, humidity, and radiation over large regions of complex terrain [
 <xref rid="pone.0182837.ref048" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>]. The acceptable performance of this scheme has also been assessed [
 <xref rid="pone.0182837.ref049" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0182837.ref050" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>]. We included only variables with a Pearson correlation coefficient ≤ 0.70 and with high ecological importance in the predictive model; namely, mean diurnal range, maximum temperature of the warmest month, minimum temperature of the coldest month, mean temperature of the wettest quarter, precipitation seasonality, precipitation of the warmest quarter, precipitation of the coldest quarter, and the aridity index.
</p>
