<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par15" class="p">Using the above adaptation characteristics as a framework, we reviewed the representation of adaptation within a range of modelling studies in the land and water sectors. The review was based on literature reported in international peer-reviewed journal articles using a number of independent searches in the Web of Science bibliographic database and snowballing (of journal articles and grey literature reports published by funding bodies) to identify models dealing with adaptation in distinct ways and to ensure representative coverage of CCIAV studies and models in these sectors (see search terms and references within the 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">Supplementary Material</xref>). The review was not intended to be all-encompassing, but examined a cross-section of relevant models covering different modelling approaches, research questions, adaptation measures and spatial and temporal scales. For the water sector, these spanned models representing river channels, catchments/river basins and water resource systems; and study foci on management of flood risk, water resources and quality, water demand and infrastructure (abstraction, distribution and supply). For the land sector, a range of model types (including Agent-based, statistical allocation, partial equilibrium models etc) operating at scales from farm to global and representing all major forms of productive human land use were included, with particular foci on agriculture, forestry, and cross-sectoral dynamics. . We sought to evaluate each model’s treatment of the above dimensions of adaptation both statically and dynamically by assessing the following criteria:
 <list list-type="bullet" class="list">
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par16" class="p">The spatial, temporal and geographical scales over which the model was applied;</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par17" class="p">The extent to which adaptation, if included explicitly, was represented objectively on the basis of exceedance of defined realistic impact triggers (as opposed to being implemented by the modeller through the modification of input parameters following some arbitrary impact change);</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par18" class="p">The type (autonomous or planned) and timing (reactive or anticipatory) of adaptation included;</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par19" class="p">The actors involved—whether individual, institutional, governmental, aggregate or unspecified;</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par20" class="p">How adaptation effectiveness is modelled, especially with respect to timelags, constraints (biophysical, social, human, financial or manufactured) and rates or processes of uptake;</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par21" class="p">Any temporal (scenario-based) variability in modelled adaptation.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
