<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3-ijerph-12-13162" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3. Methods </div>
 <sec id="sec3dot1-ijerph-12-13162" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1. Research Model</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study was based on the TPB, and oriented from mitigating global warming to develop the model of efficiency action toward climate change (ECC) model. Notably, some studies on environmental behavior have measured intention behavior instead of actual behavior [
   <a rid="B22-ijerph-12-13162" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-ijerph-12-13162">22</a>,
   <a rid="B23-ijerph-12-13162" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-ijerph-12-13162">23</a>,
   <a rid="B49-ijerph-12-13162" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49-ijerph-12-13162">49</a>]. This study considered the appliances of households that remained in use and had not been recently replaced. Therefore, this study examines intentions regarding pro-environmental behaviors, not actual behaviors.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although the TPB allows additional variables to be included in the model, Ajzen [
   <a rid="B14-ijerph-12-13162" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14-ijerph-12-13162">14</a>] clearly outlined the ways in which central model variables should be measured. In the ECC model, all the independent variables of the TPB (EA, SN, and PBC) are presumed to predict the dependent variable (intention toward efficiency actions, IEA). In addition, as an independent variable, BOC is also assumed to predict IEA.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3dot2-ijerph-12-13162" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2. Research Design</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The population of Taiwan is approximately 23 million, and the 
   <span class="italic">per capita</span> CO
   <sub>2</sub> emissions are approximately 11.1 t [
   <a rid="B50-ijerph-12-13162" ref-type="bibr" href="#B50-ijerph-12-13162">50</a>], which is close to the OECD average of 12.76 t [
   <a rid="B51-ijerph-12-13162" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51-ijerph-12-13162">51</a>] and far in excess of the global 
   <span class="italic">per capita</span> emissions of 3.96 t. Direct energy use by Taiwanese households accounted for approximately 27 million metric tons of carbon in 2000 and 32 million metric tons in 2010 [
   <a rid="B45-ijerph-12-13162" ref-type="bibr" href="#B45-ijerph-12-13162">45</a>]. Kaohsiung, the most important industrial metropolis in Taiwan, has an annual average 
   <span class="italic">per capita</span> CO
   <sub>2</sub> emission of 26.3 t [
   <a rid="B52-ijerph-12-13162" ref-type="bibr" href="#B52-ijerph-12-13162">52</a>]. Notably, the majority of CO
   <sub>2</sub> emissions in Kaohsiung originate in the industrial sector (68%), followed by the commercial and household sectors (23%). Therefore, the Taiwanese government encouraged households to purchase energy-saving appliances and classified the energy consumption of appliances into five levels. Level one represents the most energy-efficient appliances, which typically have the highest prices. This study aimed to develop the ECC model and applied structural equation modeling (SEM) to confirm the model’s applicability in the study’s sample of Kaohsiung residents.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec3dot3-ijerph-12-13162" sec-type="subjects" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.3. Research Participants</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study employed a sample of 236 Kaohsiung residents and used questionnaires and face-to-face interviews to collect information. Among the 235 valid responses in this study, females (55.3%) outnumbered males (44.7%). Respondents aged 20–29 years (25.1%), followed by those aged 30–39 years (18.7%). The majority of respondents had completed a college education (36.6%). Of the respondents, 54.9% were not married. The largest group of respondents reported TWD$5,000 (US$175) in personal monthly disposable income. Finally, with respect to religion, the largest category was respondents with “no religious beliefs” (38%), followed by Buddhists (20%) and Taoists (12.6%).</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
