<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Similarly, the NNA and the Southern Ocean exhibit early TSCs and low signal‐to‐noise ratios, but both 
 <inline-formula class="inline-formula">(
  <italic class="italic">m</italic>
  <sub class="sub">max</sub> − 
  <italic class="italic">m</italic>
  <sub class="sub">end</sub>)
 </inline-formula> and 
 <inline-formula class="inline-formula">
  <italic class="italic">ϵ</italic>
 </inline-formula> are larger in the Southern Ocean than in the NNA. Portions of the NNA and Southern Ocean have such pronounced internal variability that the MMM warming through the entire simulation period is within uncertainty of the 23rd century warming rates. These correspond with regions that have 
 <inline-formula class="inline-formula">
  <italic class="italic">ξ</italic>≈
 </inline-formula> 1 or less. As expected, the areal extent of such regions is greater in the lowest‐emission scenario considered here, that is, experiment B1 (SI). The early TSCs found in the Southern Ocean and NNA correspond with high 
 <inline-formula class="inline-formula">
  <italic class="italic">m</italic>
  <sub class="sub">end</sub>/
  <italic class="italic">m</italic>
  <sub class="sub">max</sub>
 </inline-formula> ratios (Figure 
 <xref rid="grl58884-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3</xref>d), that is, the highest 23rd century warming rates relative to maximum warming rates, meaning that models project these regions' long‐term warming rates will be globally the most similar to their 21st century rates. This reflects the delayed warming in the Southern Ocean and NNA, which is understood to be driven by ocean circulation (Marshall et al., 
 <xref rid="grl58884-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). Previous studies have shown that the Southern Ocean responds as a passive tracer to anthropogenic forcing due to northward ocean heat transport and upwelling of deep ocean water in the region (Armour et al., 
 <xref rid="grl58884-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>), whereas the depressed warming in the NNA has been attributed to the meridional ocean heat flux carrying more heat out of the region than into the region (Marshall et al., 
 <xref rid="grl58884-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). The ubiquitously large noise terms (i.e., 
 <inline-formula class="inline-formula">
  <italic class="italic">ϵ</italic>
 </inline-formula>) in high latitudes of the Southern Hemisphere may be, in part, a manifestation of the response of the Antarctic Oscillation to this GHG scenario, where northern high latitudes warm faster than southern high latitudes during transient periods followed by a reversal of the trend during stabilization of GHG (Cai et al., 
 <xref rid="grl58884-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2003</xref>).
</p>
