<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec017" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Limitations and further steps</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The relative simplicity of the Baltic Sea food web was ideal for our study as it enabled us to focus on model formulations, instead of, for example, different definitions of functional groups. However, in other, more diverse, systems the latter can be a major source of model disagreements [
  <a rid="pone.0211320.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211320.ref042">42</a>]. In those systems it is especially important to develop more formal protocols to make certain decisions more systematic during model development, i.e. the number and specification of included groups [
  <a rid="pone.0211320.ref083" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211320.ref083">83</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A typical shortcoming of fisheries-focused ecosystem models is not accounting for economic and especially social drivers of the system [
  <a rid="pone.0211320.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211320.ref009">9</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0211320.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211320.ref020">20</a>]. This is also true for our models and we acknowledge that our profit estimations can only be interpreted as proxies. Fuel price and market demand are classic examples of important aspects which affect fisheries profits. However, profit estimations here were meant to highlight relative differences among management scenarios, instead of trying to make realistic predictions of their exact outcomes. Relative differences among scenarios are not necessarily highly affected by external factors, such as prices and demand for fish, which are largely driven by the global economy and lifestyles. A possible improvement for real-life usage of the modelling frameworks would be to account for national differences in the profit and costs. Such differences exist, especially in costs, although regarding prices the Baltic market is relatively homogeneous as vessels are free to choose their landing ports. Some dynamic feedbacks between ecosystem and economic components could not be captured using the simplistic approach of the models presented. A larger integration of economics into ecosystem models could be achieved, for example, by treating economic data as any other data component in Gadget, by using an effort- instead of fishing mortality based approach in EwE or by linking different types of modelling approaches together, including ecosystem and economic models and data (e.g. as in [
  <a rid="pone.0211320.ref084" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211320.ref084">84</a>]). Stakeholders are generally very interested in economic and social outcomes of the management scenarios.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another problematic issue commonly occurring in long-term simulations is that some parameters affecting growth, predation and reproduction in the ecosystem models are fixed. Thus, the results of our extreme scenario simulations are prone to process error. This is a problem for all models to a varying degree, but it is difficult to estimate to what extent. This issue may be investigated in the future, for example by running a Management Strategy Evaluation with different models using Atlantis or similar whole-system models as an operational model [
  <a rid="pone.0211320.ref003" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211320.ref003">3</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0211320.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211320.ref012">12</a>]. A related issue is that we did not include simulations using a range of parameters by each model to estimate parameter uncertainty and we did not examine the models’ sensitivity to input data. Existing methods to conduct such sensitivity analyses are highly model-specific and the comparability of the resulting parameter uncertainty ranges is questionable. In addition, complete sensitivity analysis may be impossible in case of some models such as EwE and Gadget [
  <a rid="pone.0211320.ref026" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211320.ref026">26</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0211320.ref076" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211320.ref076">76</a>]. This is an argument to use a number of complementary modelling approaches to provide advice, as model uncertainty tends to be larger than parameter uncertainty.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When we quantified overall model agreement, we considered all models as equally valid representations of the ecosystem. We are aware that this is a simplification and that more sophisticated approaches for model averaging exist, e.g. Bayesian weighting to combine model results based on how well they represent certain processes according to expert opinion, or based on their hindcast ability [
  <a rid="pone.0211320.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211320.ref022">22</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0211320.ref085" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211320.ref085">85</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0211320.ref086" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211320.ref086">86</a>]. However, the first method is not objective, and the second method has a limitation in that hindcast ability does not necessarily reflect forecast ability and it is sensitive to errors in data [
  <a rid="pone.0211320.ref005" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211320.ref005">5</a>]. We argue that model weighting is less of a problem here as our model ensemble is not biased towards a particular method. Nevertheless, to use our models in an actual decision support process, decision support tools that can integrate information from multiple models in relatively flexible ways are useful [
  <a rid="pone.0211320.ref087" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0211320.ref087">87</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
