<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The recent expansion and intensification of bioenergy crops have raised environmental concerns regarding their real impacts on air, water, and soil quality and their direct and indirect effects on wildlife and biodiversity as well as the spread of genes and plants into native communities [
 <xref rid="pone.0207124.ref077" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">77</xref>]. Soil erosion, degradation of water resources, or the conversion of land from natural vegetation to energy cropland could affect natural ecosystems and reduce available natural habitats [
 <xref rid="pone.0207124.ref077" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">77</xref>]. It may also generate conflicts related to the multi-functional character of the land, since land dedicated to energy crops is not committed to food, timber, fiber production, cattle raising, or other purposes [
 <xref rid="pone.0207124.ref078" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">78</xref>]. Thus, energy production in territories already dedicated to agriculture, which is based on plants not suitable for agro-food use and native to these territories, has been proposed as a way of mitigating the negative consequences on biodiversity and the rise in raw food matter [
 <xref rid="pone.0207124.ref079" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">79</xref>]. The cultivation of a bioenergy crop species native to the Mediterranean Basin as white mustard, with few ecological requirements (a weed), is particularly interesting to complement other non-annual local crops. Crops can be grown without compromising land for other purposes. In particular, white mustard could be grown within stable croplands, such as olive or almonds orchards, in Southern Europe (Spain, Italy, Portugal, Greece, and southern France), where the species grows extensively as a native weed. It could be intercropped as a managed ground cover between rows of trees, allowing farmers to cultivate two different crops simultaneously (fruits and white mustard oilseed). Beyond providing additional yield, white mustard cultivation would have ecological, environmental, and agronomic benefits. It could serve as a ground-cover herb (native to the region) to decrease soil loss and increase water infiltration and nutrient retention. The species also has well-known bio-fumigant properties, since it contains glucosinolates, which control pathogens, weeds, insects, and nematodes [
 <xref rid="pone.0207124.ref080" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">80</xref>]. Adequately managed, it may further contribute to the maintenance of biodiversity and ecosystem function in these agroecosystems. However, towards Central Europe, the cultivation of white mustard would replace in the future to rapeseed in those areas that due to climate change would no longer climatically suitable. Hence, in Central Europe, white mustard should be planted in a relatively similar manner to current rapeseed cultivation to sustain the biofuel industry.
</p>
