<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="editorial"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//ES//DTD journal article DTD version 5.5.0//EN//XML?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName art550.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 5.5.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName elsevier2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><?origin publisher?><?FILEmeta_BTRE304 xml ?><?FILEmain xml ?><?FILEmain pdf ?><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Biotechnol Rep (Amst)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Biotechnol Rep (Amst)</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Biotechnology Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2215-017X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Elsevier</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6325081</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">S2215-017X(19)30012-8</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.btre.2019.e00304</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">e00304</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Editorial introduction to the special issue from ICAFE-2017: The 2nd international conference on alternative fuels &#x00026; energy</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Munoz</surname><given-names>Raul</given-names></name><email>mutora@iq.uva.es</email><xref rid="aff0005" ref-type="aff">a</xref><xref rid="cor0005" ref-type="corresp">&#x0204e;</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff0005"><label>a</label>Institute of Sustainable Processes, University of Valladolid, Spain</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kumar</surname><given-names>Gopalakrishnan</given-names></name><email>gopalakrishnan.kumar@uis.no</email><xref rid="aff0010" ref-type="aff">b</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff0010"><label>b</label>Institute of Chemistry, BioScience and Environmental Engineering, University of Stavanger, Norway</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>Sang-Hyoun</given-names></name><email>sanghkim@yonsei.ac.kr</email><xref rid="aff0015" ref-type="aff">c</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff0015"><label>c</label>School of Civil and Environmental Engineering, Yonsei University, 03722, Republic of Korea</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor0005"><label>&#x0204e;</label>Corresponding author. <email>mutora@iq.uva.es</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>06</day><month>1</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on <pub-date
						pub-type="epub">.--><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>3</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>06</day><month>1</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>21</volume><elocation-id>e00304</elocation-id><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2019 Published by Elsevier B.V.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><copyright-holder/><license license-type="CC BY-NC-ND" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the CC BY-NC-ND license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/).</license-p></license></permissions></article-meta></front><body><p id="par0005">Energy is an important factor for the economic, social development and improved quality of life in both the developing and developed world. According to a recent report, millions of tonnes of energy-related pollutants are released each year: emissions from using traditional biomass for cooking, from cars and trucks, factories, power plants and other sources. Nowadays, much of the world's energy is produced and consumed in ways that are not eco-friendly and environmentally sustainable. Therefore, meeting the energy requirements of the world in this XXI century presents various challenges, as well as new opportunities for process industries that must include new sources of biomass and the bioconversion of organic pollution into biofuels. In this regard, and considering the severe shortage of fossil fuel supply in the local and international markets, environmentalists and researchers are finding alternative energy sources which are clean and renewable in nature. With this background, the 2nd International Conference on Alternative Fuels &#x00026; Energy (ICAFE-2017) was held in October 23&#x02013;25, 2017, in Daegu (Republic of Korea). The conference had 8 keynote speakers, 8 invited speakers, 90 oral presentations and 94 poster presentations that covered the following topics: development of new alternative fuels, biofuels processing technologies, novel biofuel feedstocks, role of microalgae for biofuels production, the use of biotechnologies (e.g. bioelectrochemical systems) for the production of biohydrogen, biobutanol, bioethanol, the development of new techniques for improving the properties of alternative fuels blends, and the application of modelling tools for predicting the performance of engines and emissions from alternative fuels. After the conference, Dr. Eldon R. Rene (IHE-Delft, the Netherlands) conducted a one day workshop on &#x02018;&#x02019;scientific writing and skill development&#x02019;&#x02019;, at Daegu University, to the student participants who attended the conference. The different keynote and invited speakers discussed the following topics at the conference.</p><sec id="sec0005"><title>Topics of the keynote speakers</title><p id="par0010">Keynote speaker 1: Anaerobic digestion biorefinery for bioenergy and biobased products, <italic>Samir Kumar Khanal</italic> (University of Hawai'i at M&#x00101;noa, USA)</p><p id="par0015">Keynote speaker 2: Engineered yeast to produce biofuels and chemicals from renewable biomass and carbon dioxide, <italic>Yong-Su Jin</italic> (University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, USA)</p><p id="par0020">Keynote speaker 3: HyMeTek for innovative biogas of symbiotic sustainability, <italic>Chiu-Yue Lin</italic> (Feng Chia University, Taiwan)</p><p id="par0025">Keynote speaker 4: Perspectives of anaerobic digestion in Korea, <italic>Hang-Sik Shin</italic> (Korea Advanced Institute of Science and Technology, Republic of Korea)</p><p id="par0030">Keynote speaker 5: Status, challenges and perspectives of advanced biofuels, <italic>Jin-Suk Lee</italic> (Korea Institute of Energy Research, Republic of Korea)</p><p id="par0035">Keynote speaker 6: Biomass-based biorefineries: A case study of sorghum, <italic>Ashok Pandey</italic> (CSIR-Indian Institute for Toxicology Research, India)</p><p id="par0040">Keynote speaker 7: Biodiesel production by various oleaginous microorganisms from organic wastes, <italic>Jong Moon Park</italic> (Pohang University of Science and Technology, Republic of Korea)</p><p id="par0045">Keynote speaker 8: High gas-liquid mass transfer bioreactor for syngas fermentation, <italic>In Seop Chang</italic> (Gwangju Institute of Science and Technology, Republic of Korea)</p></sec><sec id="sec0010"><title>Topics of the invited speakers</title><p id="par0050">Invited speaker 1: Industrial wastewater for biogas production: Use of tannery wastewater as an alternative substrate and a pre-treatment medium, Jin M. Triolo (University of Southern Denmark, Denmark)</p><p id="par0055">Invited speaker 2: Recent progress in upgradation of biomass fuel via torrefaction, Quang-Vu Bach (Chung-Ang University, Republic of Korea)</p><p id="par0060">Invited speaker 3: Greenhouse gas biorefineries as a platform for a cost-effective climate change mitigation, Raul Mu&#x000f1;oz (Valladolid University, Spain)</p><p id="par0065">Invited speaker 4: Source of biofuels in arid agricultural land,Ala&#x02019;a H. Al-Muhtaseb(Sultan Qaboos University, Oman)</p><p id="par0070">Invited speaker 5: BioH2technologies &#x00026; perspectives,Eric Trably(INRA, French National Institute for Agricultural Research, France)</p><p id="par0075">Invited speaker 6: Synergistic approaches to microalgae: Phycoremediation, biofuels and nutraceutical,Archana Tiwari(Amity University, India)</p><p id="par0080">Invited speaker 7: Valorization of spent coffee grounds recycling: An experimental perspective,</p><p id="par0085">Abdulaziz Atabani(Erciyes University, Turkey)</p><p id="par0090">Invited speaker 8: An outlook on the integration of membranes with alternative (fermentation and bioelectrochemical) fuel technologies: from separation to process enhancement,P&#x000e9;ter Bakonyi(University of Pannonia, Hungary)</p><p id="par0095">This conference provided an international forum for the presentation and exchange of ideas and creation of knowledge on topics related to the recent advances made on alternative fuels. In particular, the optimization of the production and upgrading of biogas from organic waste, the application of molecular tools in waste-to-biofuel production processes and the cultivation in wastewater of a microalgae biomass to be used as a feedstock for the production of multiple biofuels were presented and discussed at ICAFE 2017. The guest editors are grateful to all the authors who contributed to this special issue, the scientific committee members for their valuable input, the keynote and invited speakers for sharing their expertise in respective topics and to all the reviewers for their timely feedback and support.</p><p id="par0100">This Special issue contains various papers dealing with the original research topics of &#x0201c;Algal cultivation technologies and subsequent application of the biomass in energy production&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;Catalyst synthesis for biodiesel production from waste date pits&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;Mathematical modelling of insitu micro aerobic desulfurization of biogas from sewage sludge digestion&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;Effects of lipid concentration of thermophilic AD of Food waste and grease trap waste&#x0201d; and also included the review articles on the topics of &#x0201c;Biohydrogen production- microbiome involvement&#x0201d;, &#x0201c;Flocculation mechanisms in algal cultivation systems&#x0201d;.</p><p id="par0105">We thank Prof. Bo Mattiasson (Editor-in-chief) for providing us an opportunity to highlight and promote some of the latest scientific and technological advances presented at the conference. Thanks to Dr. Sherrer, Lynn (Publisher at Elsevier), Divya Pillai (Publishing Content Specialist) and Saritha Bhawarlal (Journal Manager), and members of the Elsevier production team for supporting us during this editorial process. The guest editors would also like to thank the MS/PhD students and staffs of Daegu University for their assistance and support in organizing this edition of the ICAFE conference series in Republic of Korea.</p></sec></body></article>