<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We assigned crops to IWMI land use and land cover map of the Gomti River basin considering the cropping pattern of Uttar Pradesh (UP) assessed using IRS-P6 (AWiFS) data (Singh et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" class="xref">2011</xref>). They showed that the rice–wheat is the main cropping pattern and the order of the cropping pattern in UP in terms of area is rice–wheat &gt; sugarcane &gt; rice–pulses &gt; sugarcane–wheat etc. The land cover category R-08 was assigned to irrigated rice (
 <italic class="italic">kharif</italic>) and wheat (
 <italic class="italic">rabi</italic>). The R-02 category was assigned to rice (
 <italic class="italic">kharif</italic>) and pulses (
 <italic class="italic">rabi</italic>) and R-03 category was assigned to sugarcane (
 <italic class="italic">annual</italic>) crop. R-08, R-02, and R-03 occupy 59.58, 32.45, and 1.38 % areas, respectively, in the basin. The management inputs on planting, harvesting and irrigation were obtained from the available literature pertaining to the area (Hobbs et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">1992</xref>; Gangwar and Singh 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">2011</xref>). Considerable part of the Gomti River basin is supplied with canal water from Sharda Sahayak canal system. Therefore, water source for the simulation of the rice, sugarcane, and pulse (lentil) was considered as canal water in HRUs, where canal is located, and SWAT recognized the source as outside unlimited source. For the other rice growing HRUs where canal is not located, source of irrigation was considered as shallow aquifer located in the same sub-basin. For irrigation of wheat, auto irrigation option of SWAT was used in which source of irrigation water was considered as shallow aquifer located in the same sub basin. For auto-irrigation, the plant water stress threshold that triggers irrigation was set to 0.9 initially (Arnold et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">2012</xref>). The HRUs under sugarcane and pulse (lentil) crops were irrigated similarly as that of area under wheat. The sugarcane and pulse crops were simulated as part of land use category in the model setup but they are not calibrated and validated and hence not reported in this paper. We selected automatic fertilization option for fertilizing the crops because of the difficulty in obtaining fertilizer schedules for each crop at each HRUs.
</p>
