<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec002" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec id="sec003" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Identifying ecosystem-forming bivalve species</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A primary objective of this study was to identify common ecosystem-forming species in light of a general underappreciation of shellfish ecosystems as a unique marine ecosystem in Australia, highlighted previously by Alleway and Connell [
   <a rid="pone.0190914.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0190914.ref037">37</a>]. For instance, despite numerous historical references to shellfish ecosystems in state government reports pre-1950 (see below), modern state and federal environmental government agencies do not typically recognise shellfish ecosystems as a marine ecosystem type. Consequently, government-initiated marine ecosystem mapping programs rarely map shellfish ecosystem extent or provide definitions of ecosystem type. We therefore used a process of expert elicitation through members of the Australian Shellfish Reef Restoration Network (
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.shellfishrestoration.org.au" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.shellfishrestoration.org.au</span>) to nominate and evaluate whether candidate bivalve species should be considered ecosystem-forming in an Australian context. We evaluated species against two predefined criteria: 1) confirm to the definition of shellfish ecosystems (as defined in the Introduction and [
   <a rid="pone.0190914.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0190914.ref038">38</a>]) and 2) sufficient information in the published and/or grey literature to infer classification as an ecosystem-forming species. We limited our assessment to those species that formed primary biogenic ecosystem on soft sediments and/or rocky areas rather than those which may form dense aggregations only on plants or animals. We also excluded species that predominantly reside in sediments (endobenthic), such as Mesodesmatidae (surf clams), Cardiidae (cockles), Donacidae (pipis) and some species of mussels (
   <span class="italic">Xenostrobus inconstans</span>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec004" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Knowledge review: Indigenous and colonial use, historical harvest and regulation, past extent and current distributions</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In 2015, the Australian National Environmental Science Programme Marine Biodiversity Hub supported a series of expert workshops and regionally focused reports which aimed to summarise Indigenous and early colonial uses of shellfish ecosystems including historical harvest, food consumption and regulation. This body of work also aimed to provide a cursory review of ecosystem-forming species and their past and current extents [workshops and report findings summarised in 35]. We used this research as the basis of our analysis and identified further evidence through: 1) a review of published and grey data sources likely to have information related to the nominated ecosystem-forming species 2) an appraisal of available wild oyster and mussel harvest records and newspaper accounts, 3) identification of historical or current bivalve aquaculture sites and 4) identification of localities where names are related to oysters and mussels (e.g. Oyster Harbour, Limeburners Bay). Methods undertaken to conduct 1–4 above are described below.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To conduct the literature review, we identified published journal articles for all nominated ecosystem forming species using the database Scopus (
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.scopus.com/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.scopus.com/</span>) supplemented by Google Scholar (
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://scholar.google.com/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://scholar.google.com/</span>). The search terms: ‘Australia’, ‘oyster’, ‘mussel’ and each of the species names listed in 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="pone.0190914.t001" href="#pone.0190914.t001">Table 1</a> were used to build a bibliography of all papers published up until March 2016 (
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0190914.s001" href="#pone.0190914.s001">S1 Table</a>). We reviewed the primary objectives and results of each paper and categorised them according to several, non-discrete groups related to shellfish ecosystem ecology, aquaculture or both.
  </p>
  <div id="pone.0190914.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0190914.t001</span>
   <span class="label">Table 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <div class="title">Description of Australian ecosystem-forming bivalve species.</div>
   </div>
   <div class="alternatives">
    <div id="pone.0190914.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0190914.t001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
     <colgroup span="1">
      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
     </colgroup>
     <thead>
      <tr>
       <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Species</th>
       <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Distribution
        <a ref-type="table-fn" rid="t001fn001" href="#t001fn001">
         <span class="sup">a</span>
        </a>
       </th>
       <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Habit</th>
       <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Comments</th>
      </tr>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <tr>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">
         <span class="italic">Brachidontes erosus</span>
        </span>
        <span class="break"/>(Lamarck 1819)
        <span class="break"/>Eroded mussel
       </td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TAS, VIC, SA, WA</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intertidal to shallow subtidal on hard substrates</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No recorded fishery or aquaculture within Australia. May only form ecosystems occasionally or in association with other ecosystem-forming shellfish species.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">
         <span class="italic">Brachidontes rostratus</span>
        </span>
        <span class="break"/>(Dunker 1857)
        <span class="break"/>Beaked mussel
       </td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SA,VIC, TAS, southern NSW</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intertidal to shallow subtidal on hard substrates</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No recorded fishery or aquaculture within Australia. May only form ecosystems occasionally or in association with other ecosystem-forming shellfish species.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">
         <span class="italic">Crassostrea gigas</span>
        </span>
        <span class="break"/>(Thunberg 1793)
        <span class="break"/>Japanese oyster, Pacific oyster (introduced)
       </td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">TAS, VIC, SA, NSW</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intertidal to shallow subtidal forming reefs on hard substrates</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Introduced from Japan in 1947 for aquaculture. Aquaculture current in TAS, SA and NSW. Wild populations likely growing in extent in NSW, TAS and SA.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">
         <span class="italic">Isognomon ephippium</span>
        </span>
        <span class="break"/>(Linnaeus 1758)
        <span class="break"/>leaf oyster, rounded toothed pearl shell
       </td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NSW, QLD, northern WA.</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intertidal forming beds on mudflats, sandy bottoms and hard substrates</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No recorded fishery or aquaculture within Australia. Previously not recorded as ecosystem-forming.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">
         <span class="italic">Limnoperna (Xenostrobus) pulex</span>
        </span>
        <span class="break"/>(Lamarack 1819)
        <span class="break"/>Flea mussel
       </td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WA, VIC, TAS, NSW</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intertidal forming beds on hard surfaces</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No recorded fishery or aquaculture within Australia. Typically forms small beds on exposed intertidal platforms.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">
         <span class="italic">Malleus meridianis</span>
        </span>
        <span class="break"/>(Cotton 1930)
        <span class="break"/>Southern hammer oyster
       </td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WA, SA</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subtidal on broken rubble and sheltered habitats</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No recorded fishery or aquaculture within Australia. May only form ecosystems occasionally or in association with other ecosystem-forming shellfish species, particularly in SA.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">
         <span class="italic">Mytilus</span> (
         <span class="italic">edulis</span>) galloprovincialis
        </span> (Lamarck 1819)
        <span class="break"/>blue mussel, bay mussel
       </td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">southwest WA, SA, VIC, TAS, NSW</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intertidal and subtidal to 10 m forming beds on hard surfaces and sandy bottoms</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Historic dredge fishery in VIC. Aquaculture current in TAS, NSW, VIC, SA and WA. Common ecosystem-forming species.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">
         <span class="italic">Ostrea angasi</span>
        </span>
        <span class="break"/>(Sowerby 1871)
        <span class="break"/>Angasi oyster, flat oyster, mud oyster, Port Lincoln oyster
       </td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NSW, VIC, TAS, SA, WA</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Subtidal to 30 m forming reefs on hard substrates and soft sediments</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Substantial dredge fishery occurred from mid-1800s to mid-1900s in all states. Aquaculture current or previously attempted in TAS, NSW, VIC, SA and WA. Common ecosystem-forming species.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">
         <span class="italic">Pinctada albina sugillata</span>
        </span>
        <span class="break"/>(Reeve 1857)
        <span class="break"/>pearl oyster
       </td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NT, QLD, and upper Spencer Gulf, SA</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low intertidal to at least 50 m forming beds on hard substrates</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No recorded fishery or aquaculture within Australia. Forms ecosystems only occasionally in upper Spencer Gulf, SA, possibly near Groote Eylandt, NT and southern QLD.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">
         <span class="italic">Pinna bicolour</span>
        </span>
        <span class="break"/>(Gmelin 1791)
        <span class="break"/>Razor fish, razor clam
       </td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WA, NT, QLD, NSW</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intertidal and subtidal to 10 m on sand and broken bottoms</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No recorded fishery or aquaculture within Australia. May only form ecosystems occasionally (particularly in SA) or in association with other ecosystem-forming shellfish species.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">
         <span class="italic">Saccostrea cucullata</span>
        </span>
        <span class="break"/>(Born 1778)
        <span class="break"/>Milky oyster, coral-rock oyster
       </td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">QLD, NT, WA</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intertidal forming reefs on hard substrates including mangroves and dead coral</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Previously formed an important local hand harvest fishery in central and southern QLD. Current small-scale harvest and aquaculture trials. Common ecosystem-forming species.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">
         <span class="italic">Saccostrea echinata</span>
        </span>
        <span class="break"/>(Quoy &amp; Gaimard 1835)
        <span class="break"/>Black lip oyster
       </td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NT, QLD</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intertidal and shallow subtidal hard surfaces</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No recorded fishery or aquaculture within Australia. May only form ecosystems occasionally or in association with other ecosystem-forming shellfish species</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">
         <span class="italic">Saccostrea glomerata</span>
        </span>
        <span class="break"/>(Gould 1850)
        <span class="break"/>rock oyster
       </td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Southern QLD, NSW, far eastern VIC</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Intertidal forming reefs on hard and soft substrates. Historical records describe subtidal reefs to 8 m</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dredge and hand fishery on the east coast of Australia from early 1800s, aquaculture in NSW, QLD and WA. Common ecosystem-forming species.</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="bold">
         <span class="italic">Trichomya hirsuta</span>
        </span>
        <span class="break"/>(Lamarck 1819)
        <span class="break"/>hairy mussel
       </td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SA, VIC, northern TAS, NSW, QLD.</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Low intertidal on hard substrates often in bands below oysters to at least 3.5 m</td>
       <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No recorded fishery or aquaculture within Australia. May only form ecosystems occasionally or in association with other forming shellfish species.</td>
      </tr>
     </tbody>
    </table>
   </div>
   <div class="table-wrap-foot">
    <fn id="t001fn001" class="fn" xmlns="">
     <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
      <span class="sup">a</span> NT = Northern Territory, WA = Western Australia, SA = South Australia, VIC = Victoria, TAS = Tasmania, NSW = New South Wales, QLD = Queensland.
     </p>
    </fn>
   </div>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We considered early explorer accounts from 1770 and historical fisheries records maintained by state government fishery agencies from ~1850 to October 2015 for all coastal states (excluding the Northern Territory). We also searched historical newspaper articles for references to wild oyster or mussel fishing, harvesting, and/or dredging from 1800 to 1950 using the online database 
   <span class="italic">Trove</span>- a national online catalogue of over 124 million newspaper articles maintained by the National Library of Australia (
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://trove.nla.gov.au" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://trove.nla.gov.au</span>). We searched for locality names containing Oyster, Mussel or Limeburner using the online database Gazetteer of Australian Place Name Search (
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ga.gov.au" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.ga.gov.au</span>) and obtained data on shellfish aquaculture locations from relevant state government agencies.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To determine the past and current extent of shellfish ecosystems we followed the methods of Kirby [
   <a rid="pone.0190914.ref007" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0190914.ref007">7</a>], Zu Ermgassen et al. [
   <a rid="pone.0190914.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0190914.ref013">13</a>] and Alleway and Connell [
   <a rid="pone.0190914.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0190914.ref037">37</a>], where in the absence of historical quantitative data on shellfish density or extent (e.g. commercial harvest records or ecological surveys), we applied a ‘threshold approach’ as a proxy for historical shellfish ecosystem extent. This method uses the presence of commercial shellfish harvesting which occurred prior to 1950 as a proxy for high oyster and mussel density, thus indicating a strong likelihood of a shellfish ecosystem occurring at the identified locality. We attributed historical commercial fishing (and thus the presence of a shellfish ecosystem) to a location if a primary or secondary source was able to provide a description of: (1) commercial shellfish harvesting occurring at a specified location (2) a method of extraction (e.g. hand harvest, oyster dredge) and, where possible, (3) the amount of extraction (e.g. bags, bushels, number of oysters or mussels, tonnes).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To enable a comparison of historical and current extents, we defined the minimum, comparable geographic unit across time as a single reef or bed covering &gt; 1 ha in size, or, a system of reefs or beds covering &gt; 1 ha in size which we collectively termed ‘reef system’. We selected 1 ha reef systems as a comparable unit of measurement based on: 1) the assumption that historical commercial fishing was unlikely to occur in areas where ecosystem extent was less than 1 ha in size (as described above, constituting a minimum harvestable threshold), 2) a review of the only commercially-harvested natural shellfish ecosystem remaining in Australia which includes the shellfish ecosystem covering a similar spatial scale [
   <a rid="pone.0190914.ref040" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0190914.ref040">40</a>] and 3) general consensus amongst workshop participants that 1 ha was a conservative yet comparable geographic unit of measurement to assess historical and current shellfish ecosystem extent. Due to the lack of available data, we were unable to use a smaller unit of measurements such as those normally used to define shellfish ecosystems (i.e. areas typically consisting multiple reef or bed patches, with at least some of the patches being larger than 5 m
   <span class="sup">2</span> and dominated by at least 25% cover of live shell matter [
   <a rid="pone.0190914.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0190914.ref038">38</a>]).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We therefore consider our analysis of the decline in distribution for 
   <span class="italic">O</span>. 
   <span class="italic">angasi</span> and 
   <span class="italic">S</span>. 
   <span class="italic">glomerata</span> to be conservative, as we only measure decline in extent for localities where the shellfish ecosystem occurred in areas &gt; 1 ha in size. It is highly plausible that shellfish ecosystems occurred at smaller scales (i.e. &gt; 5m
   <span class="sup">2</span> but smaller than &lt; 1 ha in extent) in many other historical localities not identified in our study. Our analysis is therefore a comparison of the number of 
   <span class="italic">localities</span> (i.e. bays, estuaries) across Australia that contained a minimum area of shellfish ecosystem &gt; 1 ha in size, prior to 1950 compared to 2015. This constitutes an assessment of extent of occurrence at the locality-scale rather than total area of occupancy within and across localities.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used the presence of modern shellfish aquaculture as a second line of evidence for identifying locations with historical shellfish ecosystems, since historical accounts often described the development of shellfish aquaculture in the same locations as historical harvesting [
   <a rid="pone.0190914.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0190914.ref035">35</a> and refs there in, 
   <a rid="pone.0190914.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0190914.ref043">43</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0190914.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0190914.ref044">44</a>]. We used locality names containing ‘Oyster*’, ‘Mussel*’ and ‘Limeburner*’ (with * denoting a wildcard for the associated geographic feature e.g., harbour, bay, estuary) as a third line of evidence to identify localities where shellfish abundance was clearly a historical distinguishing feature of the local geography or as further evidence that commercial fishing occurred in close proximity (oyster shells were burnt in kilns to make lime used in building materials, hence locality name of Limeburners). We attribute a locality name to a species only when a single, commercially harvested, ecosystem-forming species occurred at that location (i.e. 
   <span class="italic">O</span>. 
   <span class="italic">angasi</span> in southern Western Australia, South Australia, Victoria or Tasmania). Where more than one commercially harvested species occurred in a region (i.e. 
   <span class="italic">S</span>. 
   <span class="italic">glomerata</span> and 
   <span class="italic">O</span>. 
   <span class="italic">angasi</span> in New South Wales, we assumed the locality was named after the species primarily harvested and sold at market (
   <span class="italic">S</span>. 
   <span class="italic">glomerata</span> for New South Wales).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We note not all states had comparable amounts of data, for instance, early government fisheries records and maps from New South Wales are largely absent prior to September 1882, due to a fire at the Garden Palace Library in Sydney destroying all historical records. The current locations of 
   <span class="italic">O</span>. 
   <span class="italic">angasi</span> and 
   <span class="italic">S</span>. 
   <span class="italic">glomerata</span> reefs were identified by expert elicitation [
   <a rid="pone.0190914.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0190914.ref035">35</a>] and from the scientific and grey literature according to the criteria described above (i.e. localities with ecosystem extent &gt; 1 ha).
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
