<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Homeostatic regulators of physiological, hematological, endocrine, and molecular pathways drive the acute heat stress response, which in turn is modified by the genetic architecture (Mitchell et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2018</xref>). Cattle rely more on evaporative cooling for heat dissipation (Mitchell et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2018</xref>), with humidity as the limiting factor in humid climates and temperature in dry climates (Bohmanova et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>). The body weight and height of adult DCB range from 50 to 130 kg and 61 to 90 cm, respectively. To meet the growing demand for milk and meat, crossbred cattle (SCB), which are crosses of taurine breeds (Holstein‐Friesian, Jersey, and Brown Swiss) with standard‐sized indicine/zebu breeds (mostly Red Sindhi), were introduced to Kerala in the 1960 s. They now account for approximately 93% of the cattle population in Kerala. The average height and weight of SCB are 120–150 cm and 300–375 kg, respectively. Vechur has a high genetic distance from other Indian DCB such as Malanad Gidda and Punganur (Ramesha et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0071" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). A decline in body size is considered consistent with warming (Gardner et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>; Klockmann et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0046" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>) as smaller individuals are better able to dissipate heat (Martin et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0056" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2018</xref>). As observed in our study, under high humidity SCB cannot exchange heat optimally, resulting in heat accumulation. The dynamics of climate driven diversification and distribution change with the growth and accumulation of clades over time at different locations (Machac et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2018</xref>). Thus, the positive heat balance in SCB over an evolutionary period may have caused genetic changes resulting in dose‐dependent variation in traits including body size, eventually resulting in the origin of dwarf cattle in hot and humid southern coastal areas of the Indian subcontinent (Martin et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0056" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2018</xref>; Rozzi, 
 <xref rid="ece34550-bib-0073" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>).
</p>
