<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Metabolic energy (
 <italic>M</italic>) is either converted into external work (
 <italic>W</italic>; negligible in most conditions) or thermal energy, which must be dissipated from the body to avoid an increase in heat storage (S). Heat exchange (both losses and gains) occurs via dry heat loss mechanisms; conduction (
 <italic>K</italic>), radiation (
 <italic>R</italic>), convection (
 <italic>C</italic>), in addition to evaporative heat loss (
 <italic>E</italic>), primarily from sweat on the skin surface but to a minor extent via the respiratory tract. Rates of heat gain and dissipation must be equivalent to maintain heat balance (S = 0) and a stable 
 <italic>T
  <sub>c</sub>
 </italic> [
 <xref rid="B25-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. Under normothermic conditions, cutaneous vasomotor adjustments facilitate convective heat loss (or gain) at the skin surface to counter minor fluctuations in body temperature. During exercise and/or exposure to high ambient temperatures, heat gains exceed heat losses (S &gt; 0), and increased 
 <italic>T
  <sub>c</sub>
 </italic> and skin (
 <italic>T
  <sub>sk</sub>
 </italic>) temperatures elicit more pronounced cutaneous vasodilation and initiation of sudomotor responses [
 <xref rid="B26-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B27-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. SkBF can increase from ~0.25–0.30 L/min during normothermic conditions to 6–7 L/min during extreme heat exposure. To facilitate increased SkBF (and muscle blood flow during exercise in the heat), in addition to providing blood plasma as a precursor for sweat production, cardiac output (Q) increases to meet demands. Notably, when ambient temperature (
 <italic>T
  <sub>a</sub>
 </italic>) exceeds 
 <italic>T
  <sub>sk</sub>
 </italic>, a reversal of the temperature gradient prevents dry heat losses from the body, and heat is gained, increasing thermal load. Evaporation of sweat is the greatest avenue of heat loss from the body during exercise and heat exposure, varying with age, exercise intensity, and hydration status. Thermoregulatory function is influenced by many factors, including cardiovascular responses, sweating rate (SR), body surface area (BSA) to mass ratio, body composition, hydration status, and nonthermal inputs. During hyperthermia, increased 
 <italic>T
  <sub>c</sub>
 </italic> and 
 <italic>T
  <sub>sk</sub>
 </italic> elicit thermoregulatory responses to balance heat losses and gains and stabilize 
 <italic>T
  <sub>c</sub>
 </italic> (compensable conditions) [
 <xref rid="B25-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. If heat loss mechanisms are not sufficient, conditions are said to be uncompensable and 
 <italic>T
  <sub>c</sub>
 </italic> will continue to rise, with potential progression to heat-related illness and injury, including fatal heat stroke [
 <xref rid="B29-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>].
</p>
