<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">This change can, in part, be attributed to a low efficiency of the leishmaniasis control program. Nevertheless, bioclimatic, soil, vegetation, and climate change, as well as other socioeconomic factors, may also contribute to the dynamic and geographic expansions of these diseases see 
 <xref rid="ijerph-15-01542-t001" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref> [
 <xref rid="B12-ijerph-15-01542" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-ijerph-15-01542" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-ijerph-15-01542" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-ijerph-15-01542" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>]. To address changes in their preferred bioclimatic niches driven by climate change, Phlebotomine vectors, as well as mammalian reservoirs, can spread to new more suitably available habitats. However, these movements are limited by their own intrinsic biological resilience and the potential of these vectors and reservoirs [
 <xref rid="B19-ijerph-15-01542" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>]. In Iran, models using degree/day highlighted a link between the climatic variable and the dynamics of activity of the main vector of VL in this country [
 <xref rid="B20-ijerph-15-01542" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. A high level of precipitation and vegetative foliage are favorable habitats for both reservoirs and vectors of cutaneous leishmaniasis [
 <xref rid="B11-ijerph-15-01542" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-ijerph-15-01542" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. In addition, climate change may also have effects on the transmission, via the socio-economic change they produce, i.e., the impact on the amount of human contact with the transmission [
 <xref rid="B4-ijerph-15-01542" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B21-ijerph-15-01542" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>]. This opinion paper will focus on the impact of climate change on the epidemiology of leishmaniases in Morocco and will discuss methods to turn this knowledge into intervention.
</p>
