<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="brv12356-sec-0014" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(c)</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Dispersal evolution and the genetic architecture of inbreeding depression</span>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">More‐explicit genetic architecture has been considered in models investigating the role of inbreeding depression in the evolution of emigration probability (Morgan, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0252" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0252">2002</a>; Roze &amp; Rousset, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0326" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0326">2005</a>, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0327" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0327">2009</a>; Guillaume &amp; Perrin, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0143" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0143">2006</a>, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0144" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0144">2009</a>; Ravigné 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0303" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0303">2006</a>; Henry 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0167" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0167">2016</a>). While the dispersal trait is still coded by a single locus, different multilocus architectures are implemented for loci determining inbreeding depression, thus allowing it to evolve. In these models, the mutation load is determined by multiple diploid loci carrying deleterious mutations. At each locus, the fitness effect of the deleterious mutation is determined by the selection coefficient against the mutation and its dominance coefficient (Higgins &amp; Lynch, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0168" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0168">2001</a>). Typically, models assume selection and dominance coefficients to be the same for all loci and also assume multiplicative effects on fitness across loci. These models have revealed important effects of the genetic architecture of the mutation load on inbreeding depression and, consequently, on the evolution of dispersal. For example, Guillaume &amp; Perrin (
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0143" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0143">2006</a>) showed that in small populations, inbreeding depression, and consequent heterosis, can drive dispersal evolution as a means of inbreeding avoidance when deleterious mutations are strongly recessive, so that they do not go to fixation and are not purged from the population, thus maintaining heterosis. However, mildly deleterious and partially recessive mutations appearing at high rates may quickly accumulate in small populations, increasing the mutation load to the point of causing population extinctions and high demographic stochasticity, which also induces selection for higher dispersal. The amount of heterosis maintained in the population, and hence the strength of selection for increased dispersal, also depends on the number of loci that contribute to inbreeding depression, where a low number of loci can substantially decrease heterosis (Roze &amp; Rousset, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0327" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0327">2009</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
