<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="brv12356-sec-0012" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(a)</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">The ‘phenotypic gambit’: modelling dispersal phenotypes with hints of genetic architecture</span>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Early analytical models focused on the evolution of emigration rate. They typically proceeded by considering the fate of a single mutant allele, or phenotype, of a small effect in an otherwise monomorphic haploid population. These models predicted the circumstances under which an optimal dispersal rate is evolutionarily stable, and can be reached by small mutational steps. Such models usually considered asexual species with a single phenotype that had one of two possible states, migrant 
  <span class="italic">versus</span> non‐migrant, or resident 
  <span class="italic">versus</span> mutant, in game‐theoretical or adaptive dynamics approaches (e.g. Hamilton &amp; May, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0147" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0147">1977</a>; Comins 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0061">1980</a>; Hastings, 1983; Levin 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0216" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0216">1984</a>; Frank, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0110" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0110">1986</a>; Taylor, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0355" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0355">1988</a>; see online Table 
  <a rid="brv12356-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#brv12356-supitem-0001">S2</a>). A few early population‐genetic models considered sexual species with either a haploid locus bearing discrete alleles (e.g. van Valen, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0380" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0380">1971</a>; Motro, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0253" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0253">1982a</a>) or a diploid bi‐allelic locus, that directly set the dispersal probability of the gene carriers and followed changes in allele frequencies (e.g. Roff, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0311" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0311">1975</a>; Motro, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0254" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0254">1982b</a>, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0255" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0255">1983</a>). Although more complex analytical models are being developed and are still being used fruitfully (e.g. Ravigné 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0303" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0303">2006</a>; Vitalis 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0387" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0387">2013</a>; Blanquart &amp; Gandon, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0024">2014</a>; Massol &amp; Debarré, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0234" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0234">2015</a>), such models still focus on discrete phenotypes and ignore their complex polygenic determination and any genetic mechanisms that might impact its evolution. While this approach might be appropriate to answer questions on what strategy eventually evolves and if it is evolutionarily stable, it does not allow consideration of transient dynamics that are likely to be most affected by the genetic architecture, and are fundamental in eco‐evolutionary dynamics and responses to environmental changes (see Sections 
  <a rid="brv12356-sec-0015" ref-type="sec" href="#brv12356-sec-0015">III.2
   <span class="italic">d</span>
  </a> and 
  <a rid="brv12356-sec-0016" ref-type="sec" href="#brv12356-sec-0016">III.3</a>; Dunlop, Heino &amp; Dieckmann, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0097" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0097">2009</a>; North 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0271" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0271">2011</a>). Ultimately, the constraints imposed by the genetic architecture and the possibility for eco‐evolutionary dynamics (see Section 
  <a rid="brv12356-sec-0015" ref-type="sec" href="#brv12356-sec-0015">III.2
   <span class="italic">d</span>
  </a>) may even determine the possibility of reaching alternative evolutionary outcomes (Crespi, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0072" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0072">2004</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the last three decades, the theory of dispersal evolution has benefited from the development of more flexible population‐based and individual‐based simulation models (see online Table 
  <a rid="brv12356-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#brv12356-supitem-0001">S2</a>). While these approaches have less generality, they can achieve greater realism of the modelled evolutionary scenarios. However, in terms of genetic realism, these models remain simplistic. For example, emigration probability is usually coded by a single haploid or diploid locus carrying continuous and additive allelic values bounded between 0 and 1 (e.g. Poethke &amp; Hovestadt, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0294" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0294">2002</a>; Travis &amp; Dytham, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0369" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0369">2002</a>; Guillaume &amp; Perrin, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0143" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0143">2006</a>), or a set of discrete allelic values (e.g. McPeek &amp; Holt, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0244" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0244">1992</a>; Travis &amp; Dytham, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0368" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0368">1999</a>). The advantage of this simplification, however, is the possibility to match analytical model predictions with simulation results, and to ignore complications arising from multi‐locus genetics.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Some simple elements of single‐locus genetic architectures have been implemented in population‐genetic and individual‐based simulation models (see online Table 
  <a rid="brv12356-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#brv12356-supitem-0001">S2</a>). Regarding intra‐locus allelic interactions, in most of the diploid models the two alleles are co‐dominant in heterozygotes and the genotypic value at the locus is determined by either the arithmetic mean or the sum of the two allelic values. A few models with discrete alleles consider dominance interactions, generally modelling complete dominance of one allele over the other (Leimar &amp; Norberg, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0213" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0213">1997</a>; Motro, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0254" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0254">1982b</a>; Roff, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0312" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0312">1994</a>). More recently, Fronhofer 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. (
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0116" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0116">2011</a>) modelled evolution of emigration probability considering evolution of dominance interactions between two continuous alleles at a single locus. The dominance of one allele over the other was determined by a ‘dominance modifier’ diploid locus determining the dominance value of each allele. Dominance interactions were therefore allowed to evolve from co‐dominance, to partial dominance, to complete dominance. Interestingly, this study showed that evolving dominance allows the maintenance of dispersal polymorphisms, which otherwise disappear when assuming fixed co‐dominance.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The mapping between genotype and phenotype is most often very simple, with complete equivalence being assumed, and hence no environmental variance. Thus, most models consider the heritability of the modelled phenotypes to be equal to 1. Very few models have taken a more explicit quantitative‐genetic approach (e.g. Perkins 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0284" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0284">2013</a>) where environmental variance contributes to the dispersal phenotype, hence decreasing the heritability of traits to less than 1. Phenotypic expression, typically of wing dimorphism, has also been modelled through the quantitative genetic threshold model (Roff, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0312" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0312">1994</a>). Here, a continuous and normally distributed characteristic, called liability (Falconer &amp; Mackay, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0106" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0106">1996</a>), underlies a discrete phenotypic variation (e.g. dimorphism). Individuals with liability above a certain threshold express one morph (e.g. wings), while individuals with liability below the threshold express the alternative morph (e.g. no wings). While the liability might potentially be modelled in a genetically explicit manner (i.e. with individuals carrying multiple loci; e.g. Duthie, Bocedi &amp; Reid, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0100" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0100">2016</a>), we are not aware of models that do so for dispersal traits. Models considering the evolution of sex‐biased dispersal assume sex‐limited phenotypic expression, where two loci carried by both sexes separately code for male and female dispersal, while each sex expresses only the relevant phenotype (e.g. Motro, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0256" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0256">1991</a>; Guillaume &amp; Perrin, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0143" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0143">2006</a>, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0144" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0144">2009</a>; Gros, Hovestadt &amp; Poethke, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0139" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0139">2008</a>; Gros, Poethke &amp; Hovestadt, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0140" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0140">2009</a>; Meier, Starrfelt &amp; Kokko, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0245" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0245">2011</a>; Shaw &amp; Kokko, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0342" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0342">2014</a>, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0343" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0343">2015</a>; Henry, Coulon &amp; Travis, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0167" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0167">2016</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
