<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="brv12356-sec-0018" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(a)</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">The model</span>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We modelled a spatially explicit landscape of 400 patches, each with a carrying capacity of 30 individuals. Individuals are hermaphroditic and generations are non‐overlapping. Each individual in a patch produces a number of offspring drawn from a Poisson distribution with mean 3. These offspring are each fathered by an individual randomly drawn from the same patch. Selfing occurs with the same probability as mating with any other individual. Individuals have a diploid genome composed of L freely recombining loci (L = 1, 2, 5, 10, 20, 40 loci) with continuous alleles, coding for an individual's probability of leaving the natal patch. The individual's genotype is calculated as the sum of the 2L allelic values. Phenotypic values are directly determined by genotypes (heritability equals 1). The phenotypic value of an individual gives the probability that the individual will emigrate from its natal patch and therefore, while alleles can assume any continuous value, phenotypic values are constrained between 0 and 1. We assume no environmental variance. To ensure that the initial phenotypic variance is the same among simulations with varying numbers of loci (L), we scale the distribution of allelic and mutational effects by L. At initialization, individuals are assigned allelic values drawn from a normal distribution with a zero mean and standard deviation (
  <span class="italic">σ</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">a</span>
  </sub>) that has been scaled according to the number of loci, 
  <div id="brv12356-disp-8500" class="disp-formula">
   <div id="nlm-math-1" class="math">
    <div class="msub">
     <span class="mi">σ</span>
     <span class="mi">a</span>
    </div>
    <span class="mo">=</span>
    <div class="mfrac">
     <span class="mi">σ</span>
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mn">2</span>
      <span class="mi">L</span>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div> where 
  <span class="italic">σ</span> is the initial standard deviation equal to 0.5. Offspring inherit their dispersal alleles from their parents with a probability of mutation 
  <span class="italic">μ</span> = 0.001 per allele per generation. When a mutation occurs, it is sampled from the same distribution as above and added to the existing allele value.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Thus for small genomes, alleles have larger effects and few large‐effect mutations occur; for large genomes, alleles have small effects and many small‐effect mutations occur. If an offspring disperses, it moves to one of eight neighbouring cells with equal probability and a 0.05 chance of mortality. Additional mortality is incurred by dispersing out of suitable patches upon habitat fragmentation. After dispersal, the pool of individuals in each patch is reduced to carrying capacity. Density regulation is random with respect to an individual's genotype and results in patches filled to capacity when enough individuals are present. The model initially runs for 50000 generations with 100% of patches suitable to ensure equilibrium in emigration probability is reached. After this time a sudden habitat fragmentation event occurs and the proportion of suitable patches is reduced to 60%. Patches that remain suitable are chosen at random. The model then runs for a further 10000 generations.</p>
</sec>
