<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="brv12356-sec-0005" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(3)</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Artificial selection and experimental evolution of dispersal</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Besides the approaches detailed above that characterize genetic variation for dispersal, indirect evidence for the genetic basis of dispersal can be provided through studies that elicit evolutionary responses directly by imposing selection on dispersal phenotypes. Experimental evolution and artificial selection can be used to estimate heritability (e.g. Jordan 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0185" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0185">2007</a>; Kawecki 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0190" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0190">2012</a>), but they can also directly demonstrate the evolutionary potential of a trait. Experimental evolution allows evolutionary changes of dispersal in experimental populations subjected to specific conditions while artificial selection exerts selection on dispersal traits alone by breeding partners chosen for their dispersal phenotype (Zera &amp; Brisson, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0412" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0412">2012</a>). This type of approach is hence very powerful but its application is generally limited to species that can easily be reared in the laboratory.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Part of the current knowledge of the evolutionary potential of dispersal comes from artificial selection on domesticated species, particularly plants, and on model micro‐organisms. Decreased seed dispersal has been subject to strong artificial selection in diverse domesticated plant species (Li &amp; Gill, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0220" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0220">2006</a>; Weeden, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0391" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0391">2007</a>; Meyer &amp; Purugganan, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0248" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0248">2013</a>; Mach, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0228" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0228">2015</a>), and reversion to dispersing forms has been documented in naturalized crop species (De Wet &amp; Harlan, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0084" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0084">1975</a>). Based on genetic analyses of domestication traits, Fuller &amp; Allaby (
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0119" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0119">2009</a>) inferred that domestication first imposed selection on seed size and germination even before agriculture was widely practiced, and as crops became cultivated, selection for lack of dispersal followed. Similarly in bacteria, experimental evolution and selection experiments show that bacterial motility, as well as sporulation, are evolvable traits (Girgis 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0132" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0132">2007</a>; Brown 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0043">2011</a>; Koskella 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0202" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0202">2011</a>; Taylor &amp; Buckling, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0356" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0356">2011</a>). Mobility was also successfully selected for in the nematode 
  <span class="italic">Caenorhabditis elegans</span> (Friedenberg, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0112" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0112">2003</a>), in a protist (Fronhofer &amp; Altermatt, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0113" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0113">2015</a>), and in different mite species (Gu &amp; Danthanarayana, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0141" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0141">1992</a>; Knülle, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0198" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0198">1995</a>; Nachappa 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0260" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0260">2010</a>; Bal, Michel &amp; Grewal, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0007">2014</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results of selection experiments on dispersal traits are however not always straightforward, as exemplified by the case of the spider mite 
  <span class="italic">Tetranychus urticae</span>. In this species, aerial dispersal was initially found to be highly heritable in a narrow sense (Li &amp; Margolies, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0217" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0217">1993</a>, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0218" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0218">1994</a>) but recently, this trait has been discovered to be driven by epigenetic control (van Petegem 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0288" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0288">2016</a>). Yano &amp; Takafuji (
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0403" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0403">2002</a>) reported a response to selection, while Tien, Sabelis &amp; Egas (
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0363" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0363">2011</a>) did not detect any response for this trait. A third trait, dispersal distance, was not amenable to selection due to substantial intergenerational plasticity (Bitume 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0023">2011</a>, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0022">2015</a>). Experimental landscapes that differed in the spatial correlation of patch extinctions were found to cause evolution of dispersal in the spider mite, with increased spatial correlation selecting for less emigration (departure) but more long‐distance dispersal (Fronhofer 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0118" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0118">2014</a>). Further work using experimental metapopulations showed that increased spatial variation in habitat availability reduced dispersal rates in terms of departure from patches (De Roissart, Wang &amp; Bonte, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0082" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0082">2015</a>; De Roissart 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0083" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0083">2016</a>). Although the various traits involved in dispersal contrasted in their response to selection, experimental evolution in the spider mite has resulted in some responses to selection, demonstrating both a genetic basis of dispersal and existing variation for dispersal within sampled populations.
 </p>
</sec>
