<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="brv12356-sec-0009" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">III.</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">REPRESENTATION OF DISPERSAL GENETICS IN MODELS</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To date, models that explore the evolution of dispersal have almost exclusively been developed to provide general, and typically qualitative, theoretical insights. This is largely because without information on dispersal genetics it is extremely challenging to develop models that can provide more quantitative insights into, for example, the number of years we might expect it to take for emigration rate of a particular mammal species to evolve to a new equilibrium following fragmentation of its habitat. As we have seen above, it is only in very recent years that we have begun to gain empirical understanding of dispersal genetics. This will now allow us to develop models that can make the more quantitative predictions that are required if we are to integrate dispersal evolution into models developed for forecasting how ecological systems will respond to environmental changes (Urban 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0379" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0379">2016</a>), and for informing management. In this section, we start by reviewing the questions asked, and approaches typically used, in theoretical models for dispersal evolution. We subsequently highlight how new theory can usefully be developed by considering greater genetic complexity. New genetically explicit models can, together with the emerging empirical information, provide the foundations required to build a new generation of models that can yield (quantitative) eco‐evolutionary predictions and that can be used to develop more‐effective management practices.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When developing general theory about the evolution of any aspect of life history, biological assumptions need to be justified. While it is understood that dispersal phenotypes are the product of multiple traits, our review below illustrates that most models have not incorporated the underlying complex mechanisms. Rather, models generally represent compound phenotypes, such as the rate of leaving the natal patch (a proportion), or parameters of a simple dispersal kernel (i.e. the distribution of distances over which individuals are displaced from their natal site). Despite the potentially complex genetic architecture and apparently polygenic genetic basis of dispersal, models have remained genetically very simple, with most of them assuming a single locus affecting a single trait. Such an oversimplification of the genetic basis of a phenotype has been dubbed the ‘phenotypic gambit’ (Grafen, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0136" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0136">1984</a>), because the loss of genetic realism trades off favourably with the mathematical/computational tractability and generality of the models.
 </p>
 <sec id="brv12356-sec-0010" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(1)</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">What dispersal phenotypes are modelled?</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Theoretical models have typically focused on the evolution of one of the three phases of dispersal (departure, transfer or settlement) and have fixed the other two (see online Table 
   <a rid="brv12356-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#brv12356-supitem-0001">S2</a>). The vast majority of models have focused on the departure phase by modelling the evolution of rate/probability of emigration from a natal patch (see online Table 
   <a rid="brv12356-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#brv12356-supitem-0001">S2</a>). Early models, considering context‐ (e.g. density‐) independent rates of emigration, were fundamental in elucidating what we now understand to be the major drivers of selection for emigration, such as kin‐competition (e.g. Hamilton &amp; May, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0147" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0147">1977</a>; Motro, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0253" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0253">1982a</a>
   <span class="italic">,</span>
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0254" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0254">
    <span class="italic">b</span>
   </a>; Frank, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0110" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0110">1986</a>; Taylor, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0355" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0355">1988</a>; Gandon &amp; Michalakis, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0123" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0123">1999</a>), environmental variability (e.g. Comins, Hamilton &amp; May, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0061">1980</a>; Hastings, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0158" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0158">1983</a>; Levin, Cohen &amp; Hastings, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0216" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0216">1984</a>) and inbreeding depression (e.g. Motro, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0256" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0256">1991</a>; Gandon, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0122" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0122">1999</a>; Perrin &amp; Mazalov, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0285" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0285">1999</a>). There is now an increasing number of models that explore the evolution of more‐complex emigration rules that may depend, for example, on environmental conditions, local density of conspecifics (McPeek &amp; Holt, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0244" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0244">1992</a>; Travis, Murrell &amp; Dytham, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0371" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0371">1999</a>; Poethke &amp; Hovestadt, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0294" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0294">2002</a>; Kun &amp; Scheuring, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0206" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0206">2006</a>), and local density of prey/parasites/predators (Travis 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0367" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0367">2013a</a>; Iritani &amp; Iwasa, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0181" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0181">2014</a>). Further, some recent work has begun to consider how the quality of information available to actively dispersing individuals influences the evolution of emigration and the evolution of investment in the acquisition of information (Armsworth, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0004">2009</a>; Enfjäll &amp; Leimar, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0103" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0103">2009</a>; Bocedi, Heinonen &amp; Travis, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0027">2012</a>; Delgado 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0079" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0079">2014</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An interesting set of studies explores the evolution of dispersal kernels (see online Table 
   <a rid="brv12356-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#brv12356-supitem-0001">S2</a>). These studies focus primarily on the distances over which individuals are selected to travel, so they consider mainly the transfer phase of dispersal. However, it should be noted that in some cases, the dispersal kernel that evolves also determines the emigration rate, since only those individuals that disperse far enough to leave their natal habitat are emigrants (e.g. Hovestadt, Messner &amp; Poethke, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0176" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0176">2001</a>; Rousset &amp; Gandon, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0325" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0325">2002</a>; North, Cornell &amp; Ovaskainen, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0271" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0271">2011</a>; Fronhofer, Poethke &amp; Dieckmann, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0115" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0115">2015b</a>). Notably, these studies on the evolution of dispersal kernels have not tackled context dependencies in the dispersal distances to the same degree as context‐dependent emigration has been treated. Recent theory has taken an alternative approach to modelling the transfer phase by incorporating evolution into more‐mechanistic descriptions of movement. Examples include the evolution of plant height (and thus seed release) with a mechanistic model determining how far individual seeds are dispersed (Travis 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0375" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0375">2010b</a>), the evolution of the correlation of animal movement trajectories (Heinz &amp; Strand, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0161" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0161">2006</a>; Bartoń 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0011">2009</a>, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0010">2012</a>), the evolution of boundary‐crossing behaviours (Martin &amp; Fahrig, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0233" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0233">2015</a>), and the evolution of behavioural rules in plankton that influence the currents in which individuals are dispersed and thus how far they travel (Pringle 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0298" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0298">2014</a>). Theory on the settlement phase of dispersal is the scarcest. There are however a handful of examples looking at the evolution of settlement behaviours (typically probability of settling) based on habitat selection (Stamps, Krishnan &amp; Reid, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0349" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0349">2005</a>), mate finding (Shaw &amp; Kokko, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0342" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0342">2014</a>, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0343" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0343">2015</a>), prey (Travis 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0367" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0367">2013a</a>) and conspecific density (Poethke 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0293" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0293">2011b</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="brv12356-sec-0011" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(2)</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">How is the genetics of dispersal modelled?</div>
  <sec id="brv12356-sec-0012" class="sec">
   <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(a)</span>
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <span class="italic">The ‘phenotypic gambit’: modelling dispersal phenotypes with hints of genetic architecture</span>
   </div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Early analytical models focused on the evolution of emigration rate. They typically proceeded by considering the fate of a single mutant allele, or phenotype, of a small effect in an otherwise monomorphic haploid population. These models predicted the circumstances under which an optimal dispersal rate is evolutionarily stable, and can be reached by small mutational steps. Such models usually considered asexual species with a single phenotype that had one of two possible states, migrant 
    <span class="italic">versus</span> non‐migrant, or resident 
    <span class="italic">versus</span> mutant, in game‐theoretical or adaptive dynamics approaches (e.g. Hamilton &amp; May, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0147" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0147">1977</a>; Comins 
    <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0061">1980</a>; Hastings, 1983; Levin 
    <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0216" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0216">1984</a>; Frank, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0110" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0110">1986</a>; Taylor, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0355" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0355">1988</a>; see online Table 
    <a rid="brv12356-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#brv12356-supitem-0001">S2</a>). A few early population‐genetic models considered sexual species with either a haploid locus bearing discrete alleles (e.g. van Valen, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0380" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0380">1971</a>; Motro, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0253" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0253">1982a</a>) or a diploid bi‐allelic locus, that directly set the dispersal probability of the gene carriers and followed changes in allele frequencies (e.g. Roff, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0311" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0311">1975</a>; Motro, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0254" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0254">1982b</a>, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0255" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0255">1983</a>). Although more complex analytical models are being developed and are still being used fruitfully (e.g. Ravigné 
    <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0303" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0303">2006</a>; Vitalis 
    <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0387" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0387">2013</a>; Blanquart &amp; Gandon, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0024">2014</a>; Massol &amp; Debarré, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0234" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0234">2015</a>), such models still focus on discrete phenotypes and ignore their complex polygenic determination and any genetic mechanisms that might impact its evolution. While this approach might be appropriate to answer questions on what strategy eventually evolves and if it is evolutionarily stable, it does not allow consideration of transient dynamics that are likely to be most affected by the genetic architecture, and are fundamental in eco‐evolutionary dynamics and responses to environmental changes (see Sections 
    <a rid="brv12356-sec-0015" ref-type="sec" href="#brv12356-sec-0015">III.2
     <span class="italic">d</span>
    </a> and 
    <a rid="brv12356-sec-0016" ref-type="sec" href="#brv12356-sec-0016">III.3</a>; Dunlop, Heino &amp; Dieckmann, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0097" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0097">2009</a>; North 
    <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0271" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0271">2011</a>). Ultimately, the constraints imposed by the genetic architecture and the possibility for eco‐evolutionary dynamics (see Section 
    <a rid="brv12356-sec-0015" ref-type="sec" href="#brv12356-sec-0015">III.2
     <span class="italic">d</span>
    </a>) may even determine the possibility of reaching alternative evolutionary outcomes (Crespi, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0072" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0072">2004</a>).
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the last three decades, the theory of dispersal evolution has benefited from the development of more flexible population‐based and individual‐based simulation models (see online Table 
    <a rid="brv12356-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#brv12356-supitem-0001">S2</a>). While these approaches have less generality, they can achieve greater realism of the modelled evolutionary scenarios. However, in terms of genetic realism, these models remain simplistic. For example, emigration probability is usually coded by a single haploid or diploid locus carrying continuous and additive allelic values bounded between 0 and 1 (e.g. Poethke &amp; Hovestadt, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0294" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0294">2002</a>; Travis &amp; Dytham, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0369" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0369">2002</a>; Guillaume &amp; Perrin, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0143" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0143">2006</a>), or a set of discrete allelic values (e.g. McPeek &amp; Holt, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0244" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0244">1992</a>; Travis &amp; Dytham, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0368" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0368">1999</a>). The advantage of this simplification, however, is the possibility to match analytical model predictions with simulation results, and to ignore complications arising from multi‐locus genetics.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Some simple elements of single‐locus genetic architectures have been implemented in population‐genetic and individual‐based simulation models (see online Table 
    <a rid="brv12356-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#brv12356-supitem-0001">S2</a>). Regarding intra‐locus allelic interactions, in most of the diploid models the two alleles are co‐dominant in heterozygotes and the genotypic value at the locus is determined by either the arithmetic mean or the sum of the two allelic values. A few models with discrete alleles consider dominance interactions, generally modelling complete dominance of one allele over the other (Leimar &amp; Norberg, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0213" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0213">1997</a>; Motro, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0254" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0254">1982b</a>; Roff, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0312" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0312">1994</a>). More recently, Fronhofer 
    <span class="italic">et al</span>. (
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0116" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0116">2011</a>) modelled evolution of emigration probability considering evolution of dominance interactions between two continuous alleles at a single locus. The dominance of one allele over the other was determined by a ‘dominance modifier’ diploid locus determining the dominance value of each allele. Dominance interactions were therefore allowed to evolve from co‐dominance, to partial dominance, to complete dominance. Interestingly, this study showed that evolving dominance allows the maintenance of dispersal polymorphisms, which otherwise disappear when assuming fixed co‐dominance.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The mapping between genotype and phenotype is most often very simple, with complete equivalence being assumed, and hence no environmental variance. Thus, most models consider the heritability of the modelled phenotypes to be equal to 1. Very few models have taken a more explicit quantitative‐genetic approach (e.g. Perkins 
    <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0284" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0284">2013</a>) where environmental variance contributes to the dispersal phenotype, hence decreasing the heritability of traits to less than 1. Phenotypic expression, typically of wing dimorphism, has also been modelled through the quantitative genetic threshold model (Roff, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0312" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0312">1994</a>). Here, a continuous and normally distributed characteristic, called liability (Falconer &amp; Mackay, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0106" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0106">1996</a>), underlies a discrete phenotypic variation (e.g. dimorphism). Individuals with liability above a certain threshold express one morph (e.g. wings), while individuals with liability below the threshold express the alternative morph (e.g. no wings). While the liability might potentially be modelled in a genetically explicit manner (i.e. with individuals carrying multiple loci; e.g. Duthie, Bocedi &amp; Reid, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0100" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0100">2016</a>), we are not aware of models that do so for dispersal traits. Models considering the evolution of sex‐biased dispersal assume sex‐limited phenotypic expression, where two loci carried by both sexes separately code for male and female dispersal, while each sex expresses only the relevant phenotype (e.g. Motro, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0256" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0256">1991</a>; Guillaume &amp; Perrin, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0143" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0143">2006</a>, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0144" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0144">2009</a>; Gros, Hovestadt &amp; Poethke, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0139" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0139">2008</a>; Gros, Poethke &amp; Hovestadt, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0140" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0140">2009</a>; Meier, Starrfelt &amp; Kokko, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0245" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0245">2011</a>; Shaw &amp; Kokko, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0342" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0342">2014</a>, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0343" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0343">2015</a>; Henry, Coulon &amp; Travis, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0167" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0167">2016</a>).
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="brv12356-sec-0013" class="sec">
   <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(b)</span>
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <span class="italic">Reaction norms and multiple‐traits models</span>
   </div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Several studies have investigated the evolution of plastic phenotypic responses to biotic or abiotic conditions (reaction norms) where, for example, the probability of emigration depends on conspecific density or habitat quality. In this case, the modelled phenotype is a function describing the individual's response to a varying condition. Each of the function's parameters (one or more) is coded by one locus, and free recombination and no pleiotropy are assumed among loci coding for different parameters (e.g. Kun &amp; Scheuring, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0206" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0206">2006</a>; Bonte &amp; De La Peña, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0033">2009</a>; Enfjäll &amp; Leimar, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0103" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0103">2009</a>; Travis 
    <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0373" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0373">2009</a>; Shaw &amp; Kokko, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0343" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0343">2015</a>).
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A few studies have modelled the joint evolution of multiple dispersal traits, for example traits involved in more than one dispersal phase (e.g. Yukilevich, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0407" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0407">2005</a>; Poethke 
    <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0293" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0293">2011b</a>; Travis 
    <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0372" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0372">2012</a>), and some studies have considered joint evolution of dispersal and other traits (see online Table 
    <a rid="brv12356-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#brv12356-supitem-0001">S2</a>). These include local adaptation (Billiard &amp; Lenormand, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0021">2005</a>; Kubisch 
    <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0203" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0203">2013</a>; Blanquart &amp; Gandon, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0024">2014</a>; Berdahl 
    <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0016">2015</a>; Hargreaves, Bailey &amp; Laird, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0157" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0157">2015</a>; ), rate of self‐fertilization (Cheptou &amp; Massol, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0057" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0057">2009</a>; Sun &amp; Cheptou, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0354" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0354">2012</a>), seed dormancy fraction (Vitalis 
    <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0387" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0387">2013</a>), sex‐ratio (Leturque &amp; Rousset, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0215" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0215">2003</a>), animal perceptual range (Delgado 
    <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0079" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0079">2014</a>), and resource investment in reproduction and competitive ability (Burton, Phillips &amp; Travis, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0048" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0048">2010</a>; Fronhofer &amp; Altermatt, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0113" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0113">2015</a>; Fronhofer 
    <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0117" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0117">2017</a>) or in acquisition of information (Bocedi 
    <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0027">2012</a>). As for the single‐trait models, multiple‐trait models include analytical and quantitative genetic models, as well as population‐genetic and individual‐based models. Where a genetic basis is modelled, each trait is coded by one locus. Different loci are unlinked (i.e. freely recombining) in most models (e.g. Poethke, Dytham &amp; Hovestadt, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0292" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0292">2011a</a>; Bocedi 
    <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0027">2012</a>; Travis 
    <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0372" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0372">2012</a>; Kubisch 
    <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0203" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0203">2013</a>), but in others are completely linked assuming a biologically sensible trade‐off (Fronhofer 
    <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0116" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0116">2011</a>), or recombine at a certain rate (Billiard &amp; Lenormand, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0021">2005</a>; Yukilevich, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0407" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0407">2005</a>; Blanquart &amp; Gandon, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0024">2014</a>). We are not aware of any model implementing pleiotropy, where the same gene can affect more than one trait.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="brv12356-sec-0014" class="sec">
   <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(c)</span>
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <span class="italic">Dispersal evolution and the genetic architecture of inbreeding depression</span>
   </div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">More‐explicit genetic architecture has been considered in models investigating the role of inbreeding depression in the evolution of emigration probability (Morgan, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0252" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0252">2002</a>; Roze &amp; Rousset, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0326" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0326">2005</a>, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0327" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0327">2009</a>; Guillaume &amp; Perrin, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0143" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0143">2006</a>, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0144" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0144">2009</a>; Ravigné 
    <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0303" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0303">2006</a>; Henry 
    <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0167" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0167">2016</a>). While the dispersal trait is still coded by a single locus, different multilocus architectures are implemented for loci determining inbreeding depression, thus allowing it to evolve. In these models, the mutation load is determined by multiple diploid loci carrying deleterious mutations. At each locus, the fitness effect of the deleterious mutation is determined by the selection coefficient against the mutation and its dominance coefficient (Higgins &amp; Lynch, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0168" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0168">2001</a>). Typically, models assume selection and dominance coefficients to be the same for all loci and also assume multiplicative effects on fitness across loci. These models have revealed important effects of the genetic architecture of the mutation load on inbreeding depression and, consequently, on the evolution of dispersal. For example, Guillaume &amp; Perrin (
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0143" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0143">2006</a>) showed that in small populations, inbreeding depression, and consequent heterosis, can drive dispersal evolution as a means of inbreeding avoidance when deleterious mutations are strongly recessive, so that they do not go to fixation and are not purged from the population, thus maintaining heterosis. However, mildly deleterious and partially recessive mutations appearing at high rates may quickly accumulate in small populations, increasing the mutation load to the point of causing population extinctions and high demographic stochasticity, which also induces selection for higher dispersal. The amount of heterosis maintained in the population, and hence the strength of selection for increased dispersal, also depends on the number of loci that contribute to inbreeding depression, where a low number of loci can substantially decrease heterosis (Roze &amp; Rousset, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0327" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0327">2009</a>).
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="brv12356-sec-0015" class="sec">
   <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(d)</span>
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <span class="italic">Eco‐evolutionary dynamics and the importance of genetic architecture</span>
   </div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Dispersal is key in linking ecological and evolutionary dynamics as it connects populations both demographically and genetically (Hanski, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0152" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0152">2012</a>; Hendry, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0163" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0163">2016</a>). Variation in population densities and demography caused by dispersal feeds back on the evolutionary dynamics of the dispersal trait itself, or other life‐history or fitness‐related traits, by affecting changes in allele frequencies, the strength of density‐dependent mechanisms, the opportunity to either avoid conspecifics (e.g. Ronce, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0322" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0322">2007</a>; Kubisch 
    <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0204" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0204">2014</a>) or to follow them in some other cases (e.g. Penteriani &amp; Delgado, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0282" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0282">2011</a>; Coppock, Gardiner &amp; Jones, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0062">2016</a>). The resulting eco‐evolutionary dynamics (also called eco‐evolutionary feedback when the effects between ecology and evolution are reciprocal; Post &amp; Palkovacs, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0296" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0296">2009</a>; Hanski, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0152" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0152">2012</a>) are characterized by rapid evolution due to strong selection, and are likely to occur, or at least to be most detectable, during environmental change or in highly spatio‐temporally variable environments (Reznick &amp; Ghalambor, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0304" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0304">2001</a>; Crespi, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0072" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0072">2004</a>; Hanski, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0151" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0151">2011</a>, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0152" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0152">2012</a>). Accordingly, rapid evolution of dispersal has been predicted and documented during range expansion or shifts and as a consequence of habitat fragmentation (see Section 
    <a rid="brv12356-sec-0003" ref-type="sec" href="#brv12356-sec-0003">II.1</a>; Hanski, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0152" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0152">2012</a>; Cheptou 
    <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0056" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0056">2017</a>; Legrand 
    <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0211" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0211">2017</a>).
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Theoretical models predict interesting eco‐evolutionary dynamics involving dispersal evolution (see also Section 
    <a rid="brv12356-sec-0003" ref-type="sec" href="#brv12356-sec-0003">II.1</a>). For example, both ‘evolutionary rescue’ determined by evolution of increased dispersal, and ‘evolutionary suicide’ determined by loss of dispersal, can be predicted for species expanding over fragmented landscapes or experiencing a sudden fragmentation event (Leimar &amp; Norberg, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0213" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0213">1997</a>; Heino &amp; Hanski, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0160" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0160">2001</a>; Gyllenberg 
    <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0145" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0145">2002</a>; Travis 
    <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0375" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0375">2010b</a>; Poethke 
    <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0292" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0292">2011a</a>). The outcome will depend on factors such as the stage of expansion, the manner and rapidity of fragmentation and, importantly, the amount of genetic variation in dispersal traits. Further, models of range shifting following a shift in environmental conditions predict ‘elastic’ range margins, where the range shifts and expands due to rapid increase in dispersal during the environmental change, but then retracts due to decreased dispersal following the cease of the change (Holt, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0174" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0174">2003</a>; Kubisch, Hovestadt &amp; Poethke, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0205" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0205">2010</a>; Henry, Bocedi &amp; Travis, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0166" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0166">2013</a>). The type of environmental gradient determines the amplitude of the fluctuation in range size.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The impact of the genetic architecture of dispersal traits on dispersal eco‐evolutionary dynamics has mostly been ignored. An exception is the model by Kubisch 
    <span class="italic">et al</span>. (
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0204" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0204">2014</a>) which showed that ploidy affects dispersal evolution, and hence rate of range expansion, depending on the type of environmental gradient over which expansion occurs. While clonal species expanded faster in shallow gradients relative to sexually reproducing species, they expanded more slowly over steeper gradients. Whether or not genetic architecture might affect evolutionary equilibria, it surely affects the rate of evolution (see Section 
    <a rid="brv12356-sec-0005" ref-type="sec" href="#brv12356-sec-0005">II.3</a>) which is key for eco‐evolutionary dynamics to occur. For example, rapid evolutionary changes likely involve a combination of standing genetic variation and new mutations (Hendry, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0162" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0162">2013</a>), with the balance between the two determining not only the speed of evolutionary changes, but also the likelihood that eco‐evolutionary dynamics will occur (Becks 
    <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0014">2010</a>). For example, North 
    <span class="italic">et al</span>. (
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0271" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0271">2011</a>) showed that high mutation rates allowed maintenance of dispersal polymorphisms in fragmented landscapes with high patch turnover rate. In turn, the occurrence or not of eco‐evolutionary feedbacks might affect the amount of adaptive genetic variation that is maintained (Becks 
    <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0014">2010</a>; Hanski, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0152" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0152">2012</a>). Hence, the underlying genetic architecture determining maintenance of genetic variation prior to changes, as well as mutation rate and magnitude, will likely affect dispersal eco‐evolutionary dynamics (R. C. Henry, G. Bocedi &amp; J. M. J. Travis, in preparation). How much additive genetic variation is generally present within a population is still much debated and indeed this might be idiosyncratic to the population, its evolutionary history and spatial location (e.g. marginal 
    <span class="italic">versus</span> core habitats; bottlenecks) (Kawecki, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0189" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0189">2008</a>; Hanski, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0152" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0152">2012</a>; Hendry, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0162" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0162">2013</a>). However, even in cases where populations seem to be genetically depauperate, rapid evolution (including of dispersal) has been observed (e.g. Rollins 
    <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0321" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0321">2015</a>). The genetic mechanisms behind this are unknown although heritable epigenetic variation might be a potential one (Bonduriansky &amp; Day, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0030" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0030">2009</a>; Rollins 
    <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0321" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0321">2015</a>; Legrand 
    <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0211" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0211">2017</a>). Further genetic variation can be maintained by non‐additive genetic effects (dominance and epistasis) and be converted to additive genetic variation following a bottleneck (Roff &amp; Emerson, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0317" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0317">2006</a>). Finally, genetic covariances among traits might either favour or hinder rapid evolutionary responses (Reznick &amp; Ghalambor, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0304" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0304">2001</a>; Etterson, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0104" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0104">2004</a>; Hendry, 
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0162" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0162">2013</a>).
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While a few theoretical studies have begun to consider explicit genetic architecture in modelling the eco‐evolution of dispersal, models developed and parameterized for addressing questions related to particular species in particular environments remain even scarcer. A recent exception is Hanski 
    <span class="italic">et al</span>. (
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0155" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0155">2017</a>), who used a metapopulation model to predict the distribution of the Glanville fritillary butterfly over 22 years across the heterogeneous landscape of the Åland islands SW Finland. Of the 125 population networks 33 were above the extinction threshold for long‐term persistence. Spatial configuration and habitat area predicted metapopulation size and persistence, but interestingly in the 33 networks above the extinction threshold, allelic variation in SNPs of the 
    <span class="italic">Pgi</span> gene explained ∼30% of variation in metapopulation size. Based on previous knowledge (see Section 
    <a rid="brv12356-sec-0004" ref-type="sec" href="#brv12356-sec-0004">II.2</a>), this indicates that individuals with specific 
    <span class="italic">Pgi</span> genotypes that are more dispersive increase colonization rate and decrease extinction rate of these population networks (Hanski 
    <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0155" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0155">2017</a>). Consistently, three viable networks that were extinct for at least 5 years had lower frequency of the dispersive genotype than the 27 networks that persisted for the full 22 years (Hanski 
    <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
    <a rid="brv12356-bib-0155" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0155">2017</a>).
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="brv12356-sec-0016" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(3)</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Why is it important to include the genetic architecture of dispersal in models?</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Dispersal traits are often quantitative traits showing continuous and heritable variation within populations (see Section 
   <a rid="brv12356-sec-0002" ref-type="sec" href="#brv12356-sec-0002">II</a> and see online Table 
   <a rid="brv12356-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#brv12356-supitem-0001">S1</a>) and can thus be assumed polygenic in nature. This assumption, however, potentially introduces many complications when modelling the evolution of a trait. Ignoring, or not, these complications may matter in some cases but not in others. For example, and as alluded to above, details of the distribution of allelic effects at loci affecting a trait will affect its evolutionary dynamics. Previous models, nevertheless, have ignored these genetic details and have been based on much simpler assumptions (reviewed in Section 
   <a rid="brv12356-sec-0011" ref-type="sec" href="#brv12356-sec-0011">III.2
    <span class="italic">a</span>
   </a>), in part for practical reasons but also because modellers were mostly interested in finding optimal strategies, corresponding to equilibrium points located at maxima of fitness landscapes. Whether and how the optimal strategy is reached by evolution then depends mostly on the shape of the adaptive landscape around an equilibrium point and less on the genetic architecture of the trait [see Ronce, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0322" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0322">2007</a> for a review of modelling techniques]. This is because we generally assume that, as long as genetic variation exists in the direction of selection on the adaptive landscape, a population will reach the equilibrium point.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Details of the genetic architecture of dispersal trait(s) may then matter most when considering the evolutionary dynamics of a (meta)population, especially in non‐equilibrium situations such as range expansions, or extinction–colonization dynamics. That is, the number of loci, their distribution of allelic effects and possible epistatic interactions, their mutation and recombination rates, and their number of pleiotropic effects will all affect the rate of trait evolution towards an optimal strategy even if they do not affect the existence or position of that strategy on an adaptive landscape. However, when dispersal evolution and eco‐evolutionary dynamics are co‐determined, for instance during range expansion, genetic details underlying trait variation may have quantitative and qualitative effects on model outcomes. Typically, of the features just enumerated, some will enhance and some will constrain the rate of evolution of a dispersal trait and are thus worth considering because they may feedback on the evolutionary process itself. We will, however, not provide an exhaustive review of all possible effects of complex polygenic architectures on trait evolution but rather focus on a few simple examples.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">First, keeping in mind that rates of evolution depend on the amount of additive (heritable) genetic variation in a trait, any characteristic that increases the genetic and thus the phenotypic variance of a trait will be favourable under directional selection towards an optimum value. Increasing the number of loci, the mutation rate, or the mutational effect size (i.e. proportion of variance contributed by a locus) will speed up evolution by increasing trait variation, but will become an impediment when selection is stabilizing by generating a variance load (i.e. reduction of mean population fitness due to phenotypic variation around the optimum). Furthermore, when loci contribute unequally to trait variation, the shape of the phenotypic distribution may depart from normality, and become skewed, or have higher kurtosis. For example, Débarre, Yeaman &amp; Guillaume (
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0077" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0077">2015</a>) showed that when traits are affected by a few loci of large effect (i.
   <span class="italic">E. major</span> loci) together with many loci of small effect (i.
   <span class="italic">E. minor</span> loci), they are better able to resist homogenization by gene flow and lead to better local adaptation under diversifying selection between divergent habitats than when only minor loci are considered. In Débarre 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>. (
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0077" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0077">2015</a>), increasing the allelic effect of major loci increased the skewness of the phenotypic distributions in divergent populations connected by gene flow, which increases the response to selection towards phenotypic optima. The enhancing effect of major loci on rates of evolution has also been shown when populations face a sudden, large shift in their environment and when a trait is determined by a mix of major and minor loci (Gomulkiewicz 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0134" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0134">2010</a>), or during range expansion on coarse or stepwise environmental gradients (Gilbert &amp; Whitlock, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0129" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0129">2017</a>). Traits determined by many minor loci can, however, confer faster adaptation to coarse gradients when the mutation rate is large (Gilbert &amp; Whitlock, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0129" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0129">2017</a>). Finally, genetic architectures with many possible mutational paths will cause faster trait evolution than genetic architectures that constrain trait variation on a single path. That is, traits determined by many loci at which multiple allelic combinations may provide the same trait value (i.e. when there is genetic redundancy) will achieve higher rates of evolution compared to when trait values can only be reached by a single combination of alleles (Yeaman, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0404" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0404">2015</a>). All these aspects must thus be carefully considered when modelling dispersal as a polygenic trait.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Second, when selection acts on allelic variants at multiple loci, statistical linkage, and thus linkage disequilibrium (LD) may ensue because some allelic combinations may be favoured over others. Selection will then maintain LD among beneficial allelic combinations, which contributes to adaptation in heterogeneous environments despite recombination and sometimes strong gene flow (Le Corre &amp; Kremer, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0209" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0209">2003</a>, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0210" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0210">2012</a>). This is especially true when adapting from standing genetic variation in the presence of gene flow and for genetic architectures with high genetic redundancy, which can maintain clusters of co‐adapted loci that can function as loci of major effect (Yeaman &amp; Guillaume, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0405" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0405">2009</a>; Yeaman &amp; Whitlock, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0406" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0406">2011</a>). The rate of recombination, in addition to the number and effect sizes of loci under selection, is thus an important parameter to consider when modelling polygenic traits.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Third, dominance and epistasis, both representing non‐additive allelic effects, are important in the evolution of quantitative traits because of their contributions to trait genetic variance (Falconer &amp; Mackay, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0106" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0106">1996</a>; Lynch &amp; Walsh, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0227" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0227">1998</a>). They are seldom taken into account, mostly because both are very complex features to model in multi‐locus systems, and are expected to be of most influence in small or inbred populations (e.g. for dominance: Wolak &amp; Keller, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0402" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0402">2014</a>; see Section 
   <a rid="brv12356-sec-0012" ref-type="sec" href="#brv12356-sec-0012">III.2
    <span class="italic">a</span>
   </a> for single‐locus models with dominance). Whether epistasis contributes significantly to trait evolution is also still under intense debate (e.g. Hansen, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0150" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0150">2013</a>; Barton, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0012">2017</a>). However, it is safe to assume that epistasis can be ignored for polygenic traits affected by many loci of small effects at which selection is of the same intensity as drift, in which case epistasis will not contribute much to trait variation (Barton, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0012">2017</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Finally, genetic non‐independence among traits, caused by physically linked or pleiotropic loci, has the potential either to constrain or enhance the co‐evolution of correlated traits (Lande, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0207" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0207">1979</a>; Walsh &amp; Blows, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0388" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0388">2009</a>). For instance, traits that are under uniform selection across populations, such as dispersal traits or other life‐history traits, may be displaced from their optimum if they are genetically correlated to traits under directional selection (Guillaume, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0142" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0142">2011</a>). Such genetic non‐independence may have far‐reaching eco‐evolutionary consequences (see Section 
   <a rid="brv12356-sec-0015" ref-type="sec" href="#brv12356-sec-0015">III.2
    <span class="italic">d</span>
   </a>). As reviewed in Section 
   <a rid="brv12356-sec-0007" ref-type="sec" href="#brv12356-sec-0007">II.5</a>, many dispersal traits are strongly correlated with each other and/or with other traits under selection. While the mechanisms underlying these correlations (e.g. pleiotropy, physical linkage, environmentally induced correlations) have been identified in only a few cases, many of these traits likely share a common genetic basis and are subject to correlated evolution. However, current models consider different traits as evolving independently. In some models, correlated evolution can arise because of imposed or emerging trade‐offs (e.g. dispersal 
   <span class="italic">versus</span> reproductive abilities), likely generating statistical linkage, but genetic constraints have not yet been considered.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="brv12356-sec-0017" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(4)</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Case study: habitat fragmentation and the genetic architecture of dispersal</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To assess the importance of considering genetic architecture when modelling eco‐evolutionary dynamics of dispersal, we present results from a genetically and spatially explicit individual‐based model used to investigate how the genetic architecture of dispersal affects a population's response to habitat fragmentation. Specifically, we illustrate that a population's evolutionary response to habitat fragmentation is slowed when a large number of loci with frequent smaller mutations, as opposed to a small number of loci with fewer larger mutation, are controlling a dispersal trait.</p>
  <sec id="brv12356-sec-0018" class="sec">
   <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(a)</span>
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <span class="italic">The model</span>
   </div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We modelled a spatially explicit landscape of 400 patches, each with a carrying capacity of 30 individuals. Individuals are hermaphroditic and generations are non‐overlapping. Each individual in a patch produces a number of offspring drawn from a Poisson distribution with mean 3. These offspring are each fathered by an individual randomly drawn from the same patch. Selfing occurs with the same probability as mating with any other individual. Individuals have a diploid genome composed of L freely recombining loci (L = 1, 2, 5, 10, 20, 40 loci) with continuous alleles, coding for an individual's probability of leaving the natal patch. The individual's genotype is calculated as the sum of the 2L allelic values. Phenotypic values are directly determined by genotypes (heritability equals 1). The phenotypic value of an individual gives the probability that the individual will emigrate from its natal patch and therefore, while alleles can assume any continuous value, phenotypic values are constrained between 0 and 1. We assume no environmental variance. To ensure that the initial phenotypic variance is the same among simulations with varying numbers of loci (L), we scale the distribution of allelic and mutational effects by L. At initialization, individuals are assigned allelic values drawn from a normal distribution with a zero mean and standard deviation (
    <span class="italic">σ</span>
    <sub>
     <span class="italic">a</span>
    </sub>) that has been scaled according to the number of loci, 
    <div id="brv12356-disp-8500" class="disp-formula">
     <div id="nlm-math-1" class="math">
      <div class="msub">
       <span class="mi">σ</span>
       <span class="mi">a</span>
      </div>
      <span class="mo">=</span>
      <div class="mfrac">
       <span class="mi">σ</span>
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mn">2</span>
        <span class="mi">L</span>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div> where 
    <span class="italic">σ</span> is the initial standard deviation equal to 0.5. Offspring inherit their dispersal alleles from their parents with a probability of mutation 
    <span class="italic">μ</span> = 0.001 per allele per generation. When a mutation occurs, it is sampled from the same distribution as above and added to the existing allele value.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Thus for small genomes, alleles have larger effects and few large‐effect mutations occur; for large genomes, alleles have small effects and many small‐effect mutations occur. If an offspring disperses, it moves to one of eight neighbouring cells with equal probability and a 0.05 chance of mortality. Additional mortality is incurred by dispersing out of suitable patches upon habitat fragmentation. After dispersal, the pool of individuals in each patch is reduced to carrying capacity. Density regulation is random with respect to an individual's genotype and results in patches filled to capacity when enough individuals are present. The model initially runs for 50000 generations with 100% of patches suitable to ensure equilibrium in emigration probability is reached. After this time a sudden habitat fragmentation event occurs and the proportion of suitable patches is reduced to 60%. Patches that remain suitable are chosen at random. The model then runs for a further 10000 generations.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="brv12356-sec-0019" class="sec">
   <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(b)</span>
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <span class="italic">Findings</span>
   </div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Prior to the fragmentation event the mean and variance of the phenotypic distributions of dispersal probability are similar between simulations with different numbers of loci (Fig. 
    <a rid="brv12356-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#brv12356-fig-0001">1</a>). Despite this, the speed of the response to fragmentation differs among simulations and this has associated effects on the population sizes. In populations in which a large number of loci control dispersal, emigration probability evolves less quickly to low values, and there is typically a smaller reduction in population size (Fig. 
    <a rid="brv12356-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#brv12356-fig-0002">2</a>). This is because when dispersal probabilities take longer to decline, more individuals disperse and thus recolonize empty suitable patches despite the higher chance of dispersal mortality due to the presence of unsuitable habitat.
   </p>
   <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="brv12356-fig-0001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Distribution of phenotypes for dispersal probability in the population prior to the fragmentation event, generation 49999, for scenarios with one locus (A), 10 loci (B), and 40 loci (C).</p>
    </div>
    <div id="nlm-graphic-1" xlink:href="BRV-93-574-g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
     <span class="alt-text">BRV-12356-FIG-0001-b</span>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="brv12356-fig-0002" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>(A) Evolution of dispersal and (B) total population size after a fragmentation event, highlighted by the dashed line at generation 50000. Lines represent the mean and shading, when shown, represents the standard error of the mean of 30 replicates. L = number of loci.</p>
    </div>
    <div id="nlm-graphic-3" xlink:href="BRV-93-574-g002" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
     <span class="alt-text">BRV-12356-FIG-0002-c</span>
    </div>
   </div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">These results highlight that the genetic architecture underlying dispersal, even simply the number of loci controlling dispersal traits, can have evolutionary and ecological consequences for populations. In this case, alternative monogenic and polygenic representations of the genetic architecture of dispersal led to significant differences in the rate of dispersal evolution, although the direction was the same. There is clearly much scope for future work on the effect of genetic architecture on the evolution of dispersal traits and their demographic consequences.</p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
</sec>
