<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="brv12356-sec-0011" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(2)</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">How is the genetics of dispersal modelled?</div>
 <sec id="brv12356-sec-0012" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(a)</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">The ‘phenotypic gambit’: modelling dispersal phenotypes with hints of genetic architecture</span>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Early analytical models focused on the evolution of emigration rate. They typically proceeded by considering the fate of a single mutant allele, or phenotype, of a small effect in an otherwise monomorphic haploid population. These models predicted the circumstances under which an optimal dispersal rate is evolutionarily stable, and can be reached by small mutational steps. Such models usually considered asexual species with a single phenotype that had one of two possible states, migrant 
   <span class="italic">versus</span> non‐migrant, or resident 
   <span class="italic">versus</span> mutant, in game‐theoretical or adaptive dynamics approaches (e.g. Hamilton &amp; May, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0147" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0147">1977</a>; Comins 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0061">1980</a>; Hastings, 1983; Levin 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0216" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0216">1984</a>; Frank, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0110" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0110">1986</a>; Taylor, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0355" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0355">1988</a>; see online Table 
   <a rid="brv12356-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#brv12356-supitem-0001">S2</a>). A few early population‐genetic models considered sexual species with either a haploid locus bearing discrete alleles (e.g. van Valen, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0380" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0380">1971</a>; Motro, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0253" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0253">1982a</a>) or a diploid bi‐allelic locus, that directly set the dispersal probability of the gene carriers and followed changes in allele frequencies (e.g. Roff, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0311" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0311">1975</a>; Motro, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0254" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0254">1982b</a>, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0255" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0255">1983</a>). Although more complex analytical models are being developed and are still being used fruitfully (e.g. Ravigné 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0303" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0303">2006</a>; Vitalis 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0387" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0387">2013</a>; Blanquart &amp; Gandon, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0024">2014</a>; Massol &amp; Debarré, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0234" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0234">2015</a>), such models still focus on discrete phenotypes and ignore their complex polygenic determination and any genetic mechanisms that might impact its evolution. While this approach might be appropriate to answer questions on what strategy eventually evolves and if it is evolutionarily stable, it does not allow consideration of transient dynamics that are likely to be most affected by the genetic architecture, and are fundamental in eco‐evolutionary dynamics and responses to environmental changes (see Sections 
   <a rid="brv12356-sec-0015" ref-type="sec" href="#brv12356-sec-0015">III.2
    <span class="italic">d</span>
   </a> and 
   <a rid="brv12356-sec-0016" ref-type="sec" href="#brv12356-sec-0016">III.3</a>; Dunlop, Heino &amp; Dieckmann, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0097" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0097">2009</a>; North 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0271" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0271">2011</a>). Ultimately, the constraints imposed by the genetic architecture and the possibility for eco‐evolutionary dynamics (see Section 
   <a rid="brv12356-sec-0015" ref-type="sec" href="#brv12356-sec-0015">III.2
    <span class="italic">d</span>
   </a>) may even determine the possibility of reaching alternative evolutionary outcomes (Crespi, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0072" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0072">2004</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the last three decades, the theory of dispersal evolution has benefited from the development of more flexible population‐based and individual‐based simulation models (see online Table 
   <a rid="brv12356-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#brv12356-supitem-0001">S2</a>). While these approaches have less generality, they can achieve greater realism of the modelled evolutionary scenarios. However, in terms of genetic realism, these models remain simplistic. For example, emigration probability is usually coded by a single haploid or diploid locus carrying continuous and additive allelic values bounded between 0 and 1 (e.g. Poethke &amp; Hovestadt, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0294" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0294">2002</a>; Travis &amp; Dytham, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0369" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0369">2002</a>; Guillaume &amp; Perrin, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0143" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0143">2006</a>), or a set of discrete allelic values (e.g. McPeek &amp; Holt, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0244" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0244">1992</a>; Travis &amp; Dytham, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0368" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0368">1999</a>). The advantage of this simplification, however, is the possibility to match analytical model predictions with simulation results, and to ignore complications arising from multi‐locus genetics.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Some simple elements of single‐locus genetic architectures have been implemented in population‐genetic and individual‐based simulation models (see online Table 
   <a rid="brv12356-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#brv12356-supitem-0001">S2</a>). Regarding intra‐locus allelic interactions, in most of the diploid models the two alleles are co‐dominant in heterozygotes and the genotypic value at the locus is determined by either the arithmetic mean or the sum of the two allelic values. A few models with discrete alleles consider dominance interactions, generally modelling complete dominance of one allele over the other (Leimar &amp; Norberg, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0213" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0213">1997</a>; Motro, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0254" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0254">1982b</a>; Roff, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0312" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0312">1994</a>). More recently, Fronhofer 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>. (
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0116" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0116">2011</a>) modelled evolution of emigration probability considering evolution of dominance interactions between two continuous alleles at a single locus. The dominance of one allele over the other was determined by a ‘dominance modifier’ diploid locus determining the dominance value of each allele. Dominance interactions were therefore allowed to evolve from co‐dominance, to partial dominance, to complete dominance. Interestingly, this study showed that evolving dominance allows the maintenance of dispersal polymorphisms, which otherwise disappear when assuming fixed co‐dominance.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The mapping between genotype and phenotype is most often very simple, with complete equivalence being assumed, and hence no environmental variance. Thus, most models consider the heritability of the modelled phenotypes to be equal to 1. Very few models have taken a more explicit quantitative‐genetic approach (e.g. Perkins 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0284" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0284">2013</a>) where environmental variance contributes to the dispersal phenotype, hence decreasing the heritability of traits to less than 1. Phenotypic expression, typically of wing dimorphism, has also been modelled through the quantitative genetic threshold model (Roff, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0312" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0312">1994</a>). Here, a continuous and normally distributed characteristic, called liability (Falconer &amp; Mackay, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0106" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0106">1996</a>), underlies a discrete phenotypic variation (e.g. dimorphism). Individuals with liability above a certain threshold express one morph (e.g. wings), while individuals with liability below the threshold express the alternative morph (e.g. no wings). While the liability might potentially be modelled in a genetically explicit manner (i.e. with individuals carrying multiple loci; e.g. Duthie, Bocedi &amp; Reid, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0100" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0100">2016</a>), we are not aware of models that do so for dispersal traits. Models considering the evolution of sex‐biased dispersal assume sex‐limited phenotypic expression, where two loci carried by both sexes separately code for male and female dispersal, while each sex expresses only the relevant phenotype (e.g. Motro, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0256" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0256">1991</a>; Guillaume &amp; Perrin, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0143" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0143">2006</a>, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0144" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0144">2009</a>; Gros, Hovestadt &amp; Poethke, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0139" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0139">2008</a>; Gros, Poethke &amp; Hovestadt, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0140" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0140">2009</a>; Meier, Starrfelt &amp; Kokko, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0245" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0245">2011</a>; Shaw &amp; Kokko, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0342" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0342">2014</a>, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0343" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0343">2015</a>; Henry, Coulon &amp; Travis, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0167" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0167">2016</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="brv12356-sec-0013" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(b)</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">Reaction norms and multiple‐traits models</span>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Several studies have investigated the evolution of plastic phenotypic responses to biotic or abiotic conditions (reaction norms) where, for example, the probability of emigration depends on conspecific density or habitat quality. In this case, the modelled phenotype is a function describing the individual's response to a varying condition. Each of the function's parameters (one or more) is coded by one locus, and free recombination and no pleiotropy are assumed among loci coding for different parameters (e.g. Kun &amp; Scheuring, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0206" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0206">2006</a>; Bonte &amp; De La Peña, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0033">2009</a>; Enfjäll &amp; Leimar, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0103" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0103">2009</a>; Travis 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0373" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0373">2009</a>; Shaw &amp; Kokko, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0343" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0343">2015</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A few studies have modelled the joint evolution of multiple dispersal traits, for example traits involved in more than one dispersal phase (e.g. Yukilevich, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0407" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0407">2005</a>; Poethke 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0293" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0293">2011b</a>; Travis 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0372" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0372">2012</a>), and some studies have considered joint evolution of dispersal and other traits (see online Table 
   <a rid="brv12356-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#brv12356-supitem-0001">S2</a>). These include local adaptation (Billiard &amp; Lenormand, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0021">2005</a>; Kubisch 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0203" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0203">2013</a>; Blanquart &amp; Gandon, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0024">2014</a>; Berdahl 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0016">2015</a>; Hargreaves, Bailey &amp; Laird, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0157" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0157">2015</a>; ), rate of self‐fertilization (Cheptou &amp; Massol, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0057" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0057">2009</a>; Sun &amp; Cheptou, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0354" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0354">2012</a>), seed dormancy fraction (Vitalis 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0387" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0387">2013</a>), sex‐ratio (Leturque &amp; Rousset, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0215" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0215">2003</a>), animal perceptual range (Delgado 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0079" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0079">2014</a>), and resource investment in reproduction and competitive ability (Burton, Phillips &amp; Travis, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0048" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0048">2010</a>; Fronhofer &amp; Altermatt, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0113" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0113">2015</a>; Fronhofer 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0117" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0117">2017</a>) or in acquisition of information (Bocedi 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0027">2012</a>). As for the single‐trait models, multiple‐trait models include analytical and quantitative genetic models, as well as population‐genetic and individual‐based models. Where a genetic basis is modelled, each trait is coded by one locus. Different loci are unlinked (i.e. freely recombining) in most models (e.g. Poethke, Dytham &amp; Hovestadt, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0292" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0292">2011a</a>; Bocedi 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0027">2012</a>; Travis 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0372" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0372">2012</a>; Kubisch 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0203" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0203">2013</a>), but in others are completely linked assuming a biologically sensible trade‐off (Fronhofer 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0116" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0116">2011</a>), or recombine at a certain rate (Billiard &amp; Lenormand, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0021">2005</a>; Yukilevich, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0407" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0407">2005</a>; Blanquart &amp; Gandon, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0024">2014</a>). We are not aware of any model implementing pleiotropy, where the same gene can affect more than one trait.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="brv12356-sec-0014" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(c)</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">Dispersal evolution and the genetic architecture of inbreeding depression</span>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">More‐explicit genetic architecture has been considered in models investigating the role of inbreeding depression in the evolution of emigration probability (Morgan, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0252" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0252">2002</a>; Roze &amp; Rousset, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0326" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0326">2005</a>, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0327" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0327">2009</a>; Guillaume &amp; Perrin, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0143" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0143">2006</a>, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0144" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0144">2009</a>; Ravigné 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0303" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0303">2006</a>; Henry 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0167" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0167">2016</a>). While the dispersal trait is still coded by a single locus, different multilocus architectures are implemented for loci determining inbreeding depression, thus allowing it to evolve. In these models, the mutation load is determined by multiple diploid loci carrying deleterious mutations. At each locus, the fitness effect of the deleterious mutation is determined by the selection coefficient against the mutation and its dominance coefficient (Higgins &amp; Lynch, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0168" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0168">2001</a>). Typically, models assume selection and dominance coefficients to be the same for all loci and also assume multiplicative effects on fitness across loci. These models have revealed important effects of the genetic architecture of the mutation load on inbreeding depression and, consequently, on the evolution of dispersal. For example, Guillaume &amp; Perrin (
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0143" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0143">2006</a>) showed that in small populations, inbreeding depression, and consequent heterosis, can drive dispersal evolution as a means of inbreeding avoidance when deleterious mutations are strongly recessive, so that they do not go to fixation and are not purged from the population, thus maintaining heterosis. However, mildly deleterious and partially recessive mutations appearing at high rates may quickly accumulate in small populations, increasing the mutation load to the point of causing population extinctions and high demographic stochasticity, which also induces selection for higher dispersal. The amount of heterosis maintained in the population, and hence the strength of selection for increased dispersal, also depends on the number of loci that contribute to inbreeding depression, where a low number of loci can substantially decrease heterosis (Roze &amp; Rousset, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0327" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0327">2009</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="brv12356-sec-0015" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(d)</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">Eco‐evolutionary dynamics and the importance of genetic architecture</span>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Dispersal is key in linking ecological and evolutionary dynamics as it connects populations both demographically and genetically (Hanski, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0152" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0152">2012</a>; Hendry, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0163" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0163">2016</a>). Variation in population densities and demography caused by dispersal feeds back on the evolutionary dynamics of the dispersal trait itself, or other life‐history or fitness‐related traits, by affecting changes in allele frequencies, the strength of density‐dependent mechanisms, the opportunity to either avoid conspecifics (e.g. Ronce, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0322" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0322">2007</a>; Kubisch 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0204" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0204">2014</a>) or to follow them in some other cases (e.g. Penteriani &amp; Delgado, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0282" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0282">2011</a>; Coppock, Gardiner &amp; Jones, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0062">2016</a>). The resulting eco‐evolutionary dynamics (also called eco‐evolutionary feedback when the effects between ecology and evolution are reciprocal; Post &amp; Palkovacs, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0296" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0296">2009</a>; Hanski, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0152" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0152">2012</a>) are characterized by rapid evolution due to strong selection, and are likely to occur, or at least to be most detectable, during environmental change or in highly spatio‐temporally variable environments (Reznick &amp; Ghalambor, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0304" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0304">2001</a>; Crespi, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0072" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0072">2004</a>; Hanski, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0151" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0151">2011</a>, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0152" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0152">2012</a>). Accordingly, rapid evolution of dispersal has been predicted and documented during range expansion or shifts and as a consequence of habitat fragmentation (see Section 
   <a rid="brv12356-sec-0003" ref-type="sec" href="#brv12356-sec-0003">II.1</a>; Hanski, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0152" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0152">2012</a>; Cheptou 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0056" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0056">2017</a>; Legrand 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0211" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0211">2017</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Theoretical models predict interesting eco‐evolutionary dynamics involving dispersal evolution (see also Section 
   <a rid="brv12356-sec-0003" ref-type="sec" href="#brv12356-sec-0003">II.1</a>). For example, both ‘evolutionary rescue’ determined by evolution of increased dispersal, and ‘evolutionary suicide’ determined by loss of dispersal, can be predicted for species expanding over fragmented landscapes or experiencing a sudden fragmentation event (Leimar &amp; Norberg, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0213" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0213">1997</a>; Heino &amp; Hanski, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0160" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0160">2001</a>; Gyllenberg 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0145" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0145">2002</a>; Travis 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0375" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0375">2010b</a>; Poethke 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0292" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0292">2011a</a>). The outcome will depend on factors such as the stage of expansion, the manner and rapidity of fragmentation and, importantly, the amount of genetic variation in dispersal traits. Further, models of range shifting following a shift in environmental conditions predict ‘elastic’ range margins, where the range shifts and expands due to rapid increase in dispersal during the environmental change, but then retracts due to decreased dispersal following the cease of the change (Holt, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0174" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0174">2003</a>; Kubisch, Hovestadt &amp; Poethke, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0205" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0205">2010</a>; Henry, Bocedi &amp; Travis, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0166" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0166">2013</a>). The type of environmental gradient determines the amplitude of the fluctuation in range size.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The impact of the genetic architecture of dispersal traits on dispersal eco‐evolutionary dynamics has mostly been ignored. An exception is the model by Kubisch 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>. (
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0204" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0204">2014</a>) which showed that ploidy affects dispersal evolution, and hence rate of range expansion, depending on the type of environmental gradient over which expansion occurs. While clonal species expanded faster in shallow gradients relative to sexually reproducing species, they expanded more slowly over steeper gradients. Whether or not genetic architecture might affect evolutionary equilibria, it surely affects the rate of evolution (see Section 
   <a rid="brv12356-sec-0005" ref-type="sec" href="#brv12356-sec-0005">II.3</a>) which is key for eco‐evolutionary dynamics to occur. For example, rapid evolutionary changes likely involve a combination of standing genetic variation and new mutations (Hendry, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0162" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0162">2013</a>), with the balance between the two determining not only the speed of evolutionary changes, but also the likelihood that eco‐evolutionary dynamics will occur (Becks 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0014">2010</a>). For example, North 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>. (
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0271" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0271">2011</a>) showed that high mutation rates allowed maintenance of dispersal polymorphisms in fragmented landscapes with high patch turnover rate. In turn, the occurrence or not of eco‐evolutionary feedbacks might affect the amount of adaptive genetic variation that is maintained (Becks 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0014">2010</a>; Hanski, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0152" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0152">2012</a>). Hence, the underlying genetic architecture determining maintenance of genetic variation prior to changes, as well as mutation rate and magnitude, will likely affect dispersal eco‐evolutionary dynamics (R. C. Henry, G. Bocedi &amp; J. M. J. Travis, in preparation). How much additive genetic variation is generally present within a population is still much debated and indeed this might be idiosyncratic to the population, its evolutionary history and spatial location (e.g. marginal 
   <span class="italic">versus</span> core habitats; bottlenecks) (Kawecki, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0189" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0189">2008</a>; Hanski, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0152" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0152">2012</a>; Hendry, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0162" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0162">2013</a>). However, even in cases where populations seem to be genetically depauperate, rapid evolution (including of dispersal) has been observed (e.g. Rollins 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0321" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0321">2015</a>). The genetic mechanisms behind this are unknown although heritable epigenetic variation might be a potential one (Bonduriansky &amp; Day, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0030" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0030">2009</a>; Rollins 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0321" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0321">2015</a>; Legrand 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0211" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0211">2017</a>). Further genetic variation can be maintained by non‐additive genetic effects (dominance and epistasis) and be converted to additive genetic variation following a bottleneck (Roff &amp; Emerson, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0317" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0317">2006</a>). Finally, genetic covariances among traits might either favour or hinder rapid evolutionary responses (Reznick &amp; Ghalambor, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0304" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0304">2001</a>; Etterson, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0104" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0104">2004</a>; Hendry, 
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0162" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0162">2013</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While a few theoretical studies have begun to consider explicit genetic architecture in modelling the eco‐evolution of dispersal, models developed and parameterized for addressing questions related to particular species in particular environments remain even scarcer. A recent exception is Hanski 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>. (
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0155" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0155">2017</a>), who used a metapopulation model to predict the distribution of the Glanville fritillary butterfly over 22 years across the heterogeneous landscape of the Åland islands SW Finland. Of the 125 population networks 33 were above the extinction threshold for long‐term persistence. Spatial configuration and habitat area predicted metapopulation size and persistence, but interestingly in the 33 networks above the extinction threshold, allelic variation in SNPs of the 
   <span class="italic">Pgi</span> gene explained ∼30% of variation in metapopulation size. Based on previous knowledge (see Section 
   <a rid="brv12356-sec-0004" ref-type="sec" href="#brv12356-sec-0004">II.2</a>), this indicates that individuals with specific 
   <span class="italic">Pgi</span> genotypes that are more dispersive increase colonization rate and decrease extinction rate of these population networks (Hanski 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0155" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0155">2017</a>). Consistently, three viable networks that were extinct for at least 5 years had lower frequency of the dispersive genotype than the 27 networks that persisted for the full 22 years (Hanski 
   <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
   <a rid="brv12356-bib-0155" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0155">2017</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
