<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="brv12356-sec-0004" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(2)</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Genetic architecture of dispersal</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A fundamental question regarding the evolution of any trait is whether the trait's heritable variation arises from a single gene, a few genes (each of large effect, oligogenic), or many genes (each of very small effect, polygenic; Appendix I) (Mackay, Stone &amp; Ayroles, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0230" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0230">2009</a>; Rockman, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0309" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0309">2012</a>; Zera &amp; Brisson, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0412" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0412">2012</a>). While research has revealed some loci of major effect affecting a range of quantitative traits (reviewed in Slate, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0346" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0346">2005</a>; Schielzeth &amp; Husby, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0336" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0336">2014</a>), more recent work using linkage analysis or association analysis [genome‐wide association study (GWAS); Appendix I] indicates that many quantitative traits are polygenic (MacKay 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0229" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0229">2012</a>; Husby 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0178" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0178">2015</a>; Santure 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0333" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0333">2015</a>; Kardos 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0187" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0187">2016</a>). The form of the genetic architecture has significant impacts on evolutionary dynamics, and this will be discussed in more detail in Section 
  <a rid="brv12356-sec-0009" ref-type="sec" href="#brv12356-sec-0009">III</a>. Below we review studies that have attempted to characterize loci associated with dispersal and the magnitude of their effects, as well as some studies that have identified genes associated with dispersal.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Pea aphid, 
  <span class="italic">Acyrthosiphon pisum</span>, offers the most obvious example of pronounced genetic determination of dispersal, as male wing polymorphism is determined by a single locus on the X‐chromosome (Caillaud 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0051" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0051">2002</a>). Beyond this example, we lack a robust mechanistic insight into loci with large dispersal effects for most organisms. In 
  <span class="italic">Drosophila melanogaster</span> studies of variation affecting locomotion behaviour provide us with a list of potential candidate genes for dispersal (Jordan 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0185" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0185">2007</a>, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0186" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0186">2012</a>) (Appendix I), and these genes may also regulate dispersal in other organisms [see also reviews by Zera &amp; Brisson, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0412" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0412">2012</a> and by Wheat, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0393" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0393">2012</a>]. One of the first genes identified to influence both larval and adult locomotion behaviour was the foraging gene (Pereira &amp; Sokolowski, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0283" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0283">1993</a>), where larvae with the dominant ‘rover’ allele (
  <span class="italic">for</span>
  <span class="sup">R</span>) move further than individuals homozygous for the ‘sitter’ allele (
  <span class="italic">for</span>
  <span class="sup">S</span>) in the presence of food (Edelsparre 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0102" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0102">2014</a>). Importantly, adult dispersal distance in the field is also higher for individuals with the 
  <span class="italic">for</span>
  <span class="sup">R</span> allele (Edelsparre 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0102" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0102">2014</a>). In both cases, detailed functional genomic validation has demonstrated that these effects arise from variation in expression of the gene itself. A transcriptome study of long‐wing and short‐wing artificially selected lines of the cricket 
  <span class="italic">Gryllus firmus</span> identified a number of large‐magnitude differences in expression of genes that function in flight and reproduction (Nanoth Vellichirammal 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0261" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0261">2014</a>; reviewed in Zera, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0410" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0410">2016</a>). These data on genetic covariances in expression of genes related to flight and reproduction are also relevant to the discussion of genetic correlations (see Section 
  <a rid="brv12356-sec-0007" ref-type="sec" href="#brv12356-sec-0007">II.5</a>). By developing a state‐of‐the‐art phenotyping platform, a further recent study of the cotton bollworm 
  <span class="italic">Helicoverpa armigera</span> showed that a suite of expressed candidate genes linked to physiological adaptations are required for long‐distance flight, allowing this insect to respond to deteriorating conditions (Jones 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0184" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0184">2015</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Indications of oligogenic architectures related to dispersal have also been uncovered in other organisms. Allelic variation in the gene responsible for the enzyme phosphoglucose isomerase (
  <span class="italic">Pgi</span>), which is associated with dispersal rate in the Glanville fritillary butterfly (
  <span class="italic">Melitaea cinxia</span>), is probably the most thoroughly studied case (reviewed by Niitepõld &amp; Saastamoinen, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0267" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0267">2017</a>). 
  <span class="italic">Pgi</span> is a metabolic enzyme responsible for cellular energetics (e.g. Mattila &amp; Hanski, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0239" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0239">2014</a>). The butterfly forms a metapopulation in the Åland Islands, Finland, and more‐dispersive individuals are known to establish new populations (Hanski 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0153" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0153">2004</a>). This is especially true in habitat patches that are more isolated from established populations. The frequency of a specific allele of the 
  <span class="italic">Pgi</span> gene is highest in these newly established, isolated populations (Haag 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0146" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0146">2005</a>). In addition, individuals with this allele have a higher flight metabolic rate as well as higher dispersal propensity in the field (Haag 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0146" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0146">2005</a>; Niitepõld 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0268" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0268">2009</a>, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0266" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0266">2011</a>). Allelic variations are under balancing selection according to their associated higher individual fitness under different environmental conditions (Saastamoinen, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0329" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0329">2008</a>; Klemme &amp; Hanski, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0197" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0197">2009</a>; Orsini 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0276" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0276">2009</a>; Saastamoinen, Ikonen &amp; Hanski, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0330" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0330">2009</a>; Wheat 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0395" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0395">2010</a>). These changes in 
  <span class="italic">Pgi</span> allele frequencies translate into phenotypic variation in dispersal, and hence influence demographic rates in ways that impact population dynamics (Saccheri &amp; Hanski, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0332" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0332">2006</a>; Hanski, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0151" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0151">2011</a>). Recently, alleles of a second gene, 
  <span class="italic">succinate dehydrogenase D</span> (
  <span class="italic">sdhd</span>), have been found to show epistatic interaction with 
  <span class="italic">Pgi</span> (Wheat 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0394" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0394">2011</a>). 
  <span class="italic">sdhd</span> affects flight endurance through oxygen delivery (Marden 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0232" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0232">2003</a>) and as for 
  <span class="italic">Pgi, sdhd</span> alleles also differ in frequency between new and established populations within the metapopulation (Wheat 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0394" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0394">2011</a>). It is notable, however, that detailed functional genomic validation of 
  <span class="italic">Pgi</span> has not been demonstrated, and hence the causal role of 
  <span class="italic">Pgi</span> as a driver of the above‐mentioned processes has not been proven [see Niitepõld &amp; Saastamoinen, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0267" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0267">2017</a> and Wheat &amp; Hill, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0396" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0396">2014</a> for more details].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All studies examining the genetic basis of dispersal in natural populations in animals have so far either used a candidate gene approach (e.g. the 
  <span class="italic">Pgi</span> studies described above) or a limited number of markers (all other studies than the 
  <span class="italic">Pgi</span> studies described above). The low resolution of marker densities, often in combination with a small number of genotyped individuals, means that the power to detect genetic variants associated with dispersal is modest at best. One way to circumvent such issues is to study dispersal in model systems, for instance using the Drosophila Genetic Reference Panel (Mackay 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0229" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0229">2012</a>), which consists of more than 200 fully sequenced inbred lines derived from North Carolina (Mackay 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0229" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0229">2012</a>), and thus offers genomic tools for understanding the genetic basis of complex traits with high precision and statistical power. Jordan 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. (
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0186" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0186">2012</a>) investigated the genomic regions affecting locomotion variation across 167 lines of 
  <span class="italic">D. melanogaster</span>. Using nearly 2.5 million single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) to explain inter‐line variation in locomotion, they found 220 SNPs (Appendix I) in 192 genes associated with this phenotype. Of these, 12 SNPs explained about 60% of the variation observed in both sexes. Importantly, they found a negative relationship between the effect size of individual SNPs and their frequency in the sample as a whole, indicating that rare alleles had the largest effects. Similar results appear to be emerging from a recent study in the 
  <span class="italic">M. cinxia</span> butterfly's metapopulation (Fountain 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0108" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0108">2016</a>). In this study, individual butterflies were genotyped for 222 SNPs across the genome, including SNPs from candidate genes and neutral regions. Fifteen SNP loci, mostly associated with flight, changed in frequency in a non‐random way in response to habitat fragmentation (Fountain 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0108" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0108">2016</a>). These loci were identified in comparisons of new 
  <span class="italic">versus</span> old populations and therefore are likely enriched in rare alleles with respect to the entire metapopulation.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In plants, the best‐studied examples of genes involved in dispersal come from domesticated species and model genetic organisms. In domesticated species, research has focused on dispersal features such as seed shattering in cereals (Konishi 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0199" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0199">2006</a>), and fruit/pod shattering (dehiscence) of multi‐seeded fruits such as pods in legumes and siliques in the mustard family, Brassicaceae (Raman 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0301" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0301">2014</a>) or on the proportion of central achenes produced per capitulum of some species of the Asteraceae family (Imbert, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0179" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0179">2001</a>). Depending on the species and population studied, genetic analysis of pod shattering has documented between one and 13 quantitative trait loci (QTLs) or causative loci associated with this trait (Konishi 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0199" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0199">2006</a>; Raman 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0301" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0301">2014</a>; reviewed by Li &amp; Olsen, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0219" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0219">2016</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In contrast to the above examples, where the small number of loci associated with dispersal variation suggests an oligogenic genetic architecture, numerous studies (outside the field of dispersal) indicate that quantitative traits generally arise 
  <span class="italic">via</span> a polygenic architecture (Mackay 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0229" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0229">2012</a>; Husby 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0178" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0178">2015</a>; Santure 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0333" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0333">2015</a>). While the relatively few examples of genes with large effect size could arise from underpowered QTL or GWA studies, it could also indicate the absence of such loci. Indeed, it has been argued that publishing bias is responsible for inflating the frequency of known oligogenic examples relative to their true general relevance for evolution in the wild (Rockman, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0309" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0309">2012</a>). The multi‐factorial nature of dispersal is frequently manifested as quantitative phenotypic variation in dispersal and in traits that contribute to dispersal. On the whole, there is good evidence for genetic variation in dispersal in natural populations, and evidence from other complex life‐history traits suggests that this variation is seldom caused by single genes of large effect. Instead, multiple loci probably combine to affect dispersal. Further studies, using genome‐wide approaches, are required to confirm this hypothesis.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Why is knowing the number of genes contributing to dispersal variation relevant? One reason is that it may influence patterns of convergent evolution. With a small number of genes involved in trait expression, the same genes may evolve in multiple taxa to create similar phenotypes. For example, orthologues of a number of candidate genes identified in 
  <span class="italic">D. melanogaster</span> also appear to regulate dispersal in other insects (Wheat, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0393" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0393">2012</a>). In plants, orthologues of a major gene that controls pod shattering INDEHISCENT (IND), are expressed in diverse species in the mustard family (Brassicaceae); in 
  <span class="italic">Lepidium campestre</span>, which has dehiscent fruits, expression patterns of the dehiscence‐pathway genes were similar to that in 
  <span class="italic">Arabidopsis thaliana</span> (Lenser &amp; Theißen, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0214" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0214">2013</a>). Homologues of IND have been found even outside of the Brassicaceae (Gioia 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0131" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0131">2013</a>). Another reason is that deciphering the genetic architecture of dispersal may provide information on the speed at which this phenotype may evolve in response to environmental changes (Hoffmann &amp; Willi, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0172" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0172">2008</a>). For example, the existence of complex epistatic interactions (Appendix I) between genes involved in quantitative traits can decrease the amount of genetic variation at these genes compared to an additive architecture (Hansen, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0149" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0149">2006</a>). This means that a complex epistatic architecture of dispersal may limit its evolutionary potential in the context of environmental changes because of a limited pool of available genetic variants on which selection can act.
 </p>
</sec>
