<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="brv12356-sec-0008" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(6)</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Genotype–environment interactions</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Active dispersers are known to adjust their dispersal decisions according to the environmental conditions they encounter at each of the three dispersal stages (i.e. context‐dependent dispersal or conditional dispersal; Clobert 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0059">2009</a>). Similarly, passive dispersal can be impacted by the environment indirectly – such as temperature effects on plant height and thus dispersal distance (Zhang, Jongejans &amp; Shea, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0417" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0417">2011</a>) – or directly, such as changes in ocean currents transporting plankton (McManus &amp; Woodson, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0243" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0243">2012</a>). At the molecular level, the associations between certain candidate genes and dispersal have also been shown to depend on environmental conditions. Dispersal phenotypes therefore result from the combination of genetic (G) and environmental (E) effects, and genotype–environment (G × E) interactions. For instance, the associations between the 
  <span class="italic">Pgi</span> gene and flight metabolic rate or other traits (see Section 
  <a rid="brv12356-sec-0004" ref-type="sec" href="#brv12356-sec-0004">II.2</a>) depend on thermal conditions in several butterfly species (Karl &amp; Fischer, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0188" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0188">2008</a>; Niitepõld, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0265" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0265">2010</a>; Mattila, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0238" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0238">2015</a>) and food availability in the blue‐tailed damselfly 
  <span class="italic">Ischnura elegans</span> (Block &amp; Stoks, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0025">2012</a>). Similarly, when 
  <span class="italic">D. melanogaster</span> larvae are reared under low‐nutrient conditions, adults with 
  <span class="italic">for</span>
  <span class="sup">S</span> alleles exhibit more exploratory behaviour and a lower reproductive output than 
  <span class="italic">for</span>
  <span class="sup">R</span> individuals, the opposite association than when reared under high‐nutrient conditions (Burns 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0047">2012</a>). Studies of the migratory African armyworm, 
  <span class="italic">Spodoptera exempta</span>, are good examples of the existence of G × E interaction (Gatehouse, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0126" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0126">1989</a>, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0127" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0127">1997</a>). Selection experiments of this species show that only individuals raised in the laboratory under high density are selected to fly long distances. Otherwise, individuals showed a short flight duration. The existence of significant G × E interactions would indicate that genetic variation underlies such plasticity, and the potential for selection to act on conditional dispersal (e.g. Venable, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0383" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0383">1985</a>; Gatehouse, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0126" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0126">1989</a>, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0127" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0127">1997</a>; Imbert &amp; Ronce, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0180" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0180">2001</a>; Riba 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0305" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0305">2009</a>, reviewed in Zera &amp; Brisson, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0412" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0412">2012</a>; Arendt, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0003">2015</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While evidence of conditional dispersal is substantial, quantitative studies on the genetic component of such plasticity are still relatively rare. Pennekamp 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. (
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0281" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0281">2014</a>) quantified the contribution of G, E, and G × E to this variable for 44 different genotypes from three population densities in the ciliate 
  <span class="italic">Tetrahymena thermophila</span>. They found that 43% of the variance in dispersal propensity was explained by G, 13% by E and 2% by G × E, with reaction norms (Appendix I) to density varying among genotypes from negative to positive density dependencies (see also Fronhofer, Kropf &amp; Altermatt, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0114" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0114">2015a</a>). A recent study showed that this significant G × E interaction could be explained by other traits like cooperation and result in the variation of dispersal syndromes along a density gradient (Jacob 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0182" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0182">2016</a>). In the spider 
  <span class="italic">Erigone atra</span>, temperatures during development affected both long‐ and short dispersal strategies (Bonte 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0036">2008</a>). Using parent–offspring regressions, Bonte 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. (
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0038" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0038">2003</a>) found that 16 and 13% of the phenotypic variation in pre‐dispersal behaviour in response to multiple stressors could be attributed to genotypic and genotype × environment interactions, respectively. Both studies thus point to the existence of substantial genetic variation in dispersal reaction norms for long‐distance dispersal strategies, but not for more routine (short‐distance) behaviours. In another study using saltmarsh‐inhabiting wolf spiders 
  <span class="italic">Pardosa purbeckensis</span>, population‐specific reaction norms relative to wind conditions were found to be adaptive relative to putative costs of transfer. Genetic variation in the reaction norms declined significantly with habitat and thus population size (Bonte 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0031">2007</a>). Similarly, in the plant 
  <span class="italic">Arabidopsis thaliana</span>, significant heritability was detected for seed dispersal patterns, but the magnitude of heritability depended on the density at which the plants were grown (Donohue 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0092" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0092">2005</a>). Since density is, in part, determined by seed dispersal patterns, this suggests that the evolutionary potential (expression of genetic variation) of dispersal could depend on the level of dispersal itself. Hence, evolutionary or plastic changes in dispersal, which determine post‐dispersal density, could either mask or release further genetic variation for dispersal, depending on specific patterns of genotype–environment interaction (Donohue, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0091" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0091">2005</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Importantly, the environmental conditions that influence dispersal can be experienced by the individual itself either during its development or during the adult stage, but also by its parents (so‐called parental or transgenerational effects; e.g. Sinervo 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0345" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0345">2006</a>; Tschirren, Fitze &amp; Richner, 
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0377" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0377">2007</a>; Ducatez 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0094" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0094">2012</a>; Bestion 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0020">2014</a>; van Petegem 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0287" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0287">2015</a>). When plasticity occurs through maternal effects, it might be difficult to tease apart environmental from genotype × environment effects. This is because maternal genes and broad‐sense epigenetic factors (including hormonal conditions or endosymbionts) are confounded, and maternal environmental conditions can select simultaneously for different genotypes through selective embryo mortality (Duong 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0098" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0098">2011</a>). Maternal effects can be distinguished from genetic effects through comparisons between father–offspring and mother–offspring regression (Charmantier 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0053">2011</a>), Animal Models using full pedigrees (Charmantier 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0053">2011</a>), or manipulations of endosymbiotic communities or of the environmental conditions of mothers during gestation (Sinervo 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0345" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0345">2006</a>; Tschirren 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0377" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0377">2007</a>; Goodacre 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0135" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0135">2009</a>; Bestion 
  <span class="italic">et al.,</span>
  <a rid="brv12356-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" href="#brv12356-bib-0020">2014</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
