<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec010" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.4.3. Climate change data</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Future climate data used for model prediction were derived from the third generation Canadian-GCM (CGCM3-T47) for the fourth assessment period of the IPCC [
  <a rid="pone.0132066.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132066.ref001">1</a>]. Climate data produced were based on future emission scenarios of greenhouse gases defined by IPCC. Three illustrative emission scenarios chosen for the study include B1, A1B, and A2 [
  <a rid="pone.0132066.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132066.ref042">42</a>]. The emission scenarios were based on future global development with a particular emphasis on greenhouse gases and aerosol-precursor emissions [
  <a rid="pone.0132066.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132066.ref043">43</a>]. The A1B scenario was developed to reflect the world in an era of balanced energy use of fossil and non-fossil fuels, rapidly growing economy, and an increasing world population achieving a maximum in the middle of the current century. The B1 scenario reflects an environment friendly world, population trend similar to A1B, and global economy rapidly moving towards a service and information framework with the introduction of clean and efficient energy technologies. The A2 scenario signifies a heterogeneous world, moderate economic growth, and high population growth throughout the century [
  <a rid="pone.0132066.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132066.ref042">42</a>]. Ninety year projections of monthly mean temperatures and precipitation (2012–2102) relevant to selected locations of NS were obtained from the CGCM3-T47 simulations for B1, A1B, and A2 climate scenarios. Discrepancy in CGCM3-T47 produced data was calculated by comparing past weather records with the relevant predictions for each location. Monthly mean temperatures were adjusted by accounting for the mean bias, whereas ratio adjustments were used to correct future estimates of precipitation [
  <a rid="pone.0132066.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132066.ref029">29</a>]. In this study, we define B1 as a minimal impact, A1B as a moderate impact, and A2 as a maximum impact scenario.
 </p>
</sec>
