<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec016" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Many ANNs with random initialisation of weights were trained to avoid the problem of local minima [
  <a rid="pone.0132066.ref049" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132066.ref049">49</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0132066.ref050" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132066.ref050">50</a>]. Results presented in 
  <a rid="pone.0132066.t003" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0132066.t003">Table 3</a> are the best three runs for each model structure as to individual training accuracies for different number of hidden nodes. With all the runs and model structures examined, the best ANNs for modelling BA and volume increments consisted of eight hidden nodes. Optimised ANNs for both variables consisted of 13 input nodes, eight hidden-layer nodes, and one output node.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There are few related studies available in the literature to compare against, as this is the first time that a G&amp;Y model has been developed and validated against tree data for both present-day (i.e., PSP data) and projected future climates (JABOWA-3 generated data). Statistical indicators of model accuracy (i.e., BIAS, RMSE, and ME) demonstrate good overall model performance compared to conventional models designed for static climatic conditions. The Forest Vegetation Simulator-Inland Empire model (i.e., FVS-IE), generally over-predicted diameter increments by 14% compared to field records, whereas discrepancy in predicting different species diameter ranged from -49.1% to 5.9% [
  <a rid="pone.0132066.ref051" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132066.ref051">51</a>]. This was reported in a study validating the BA increment component of FVS-IE with forest inventory data across the Inland Empire region, USA. Basal area increment models developed in Norway generated coefficients of determination (r
  <span class="sup">2</span>) ranging from 0.26 to 0.55 for different tree species [
  <a rid="pone.0132066.ref052" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132066.ref052">52</a>]. A study evaluated conventional tree-level models for Finland and obtained overall relative BIAS of 2.3 to -6.0% in the prediction of stand BA [
  <a rid="pone.0132066.ref053" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132066.ref053">53</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Previous studies modelling individual-tree growth with ANNs based on data from the province of NS, reported a RMSE of 26.14 and 23.50, respectively, and ME of 0.39 and BIAS of 0.1356 for BA increment [
  <a rid="pone.0132066.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132066.ref034">34</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0132066.ref054" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132066.ref054">54</a>]. In general, the model developed in this study demonstrated better overall performance in terms of BIAS and ME compared to past studies in NS, albeit with a slight increase in RMSE for both BA and volume predictions compared to those reported by Ashraf 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.[
  <a rid="pone.0132066.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132066.ref034">34</a>]. Addition of JABOWA-3 growth data to account for climate change has increased the dispersion in target data. High R and ME values can also be attributed to the addition of JABOWA-3 generated growth data in the training dataset and should not be interpreted that the newly developed ANNs are substantially better than the other models.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There is always a certain level of uncertainty in model predictions as forest G&amp;Y models are abstractions of highly complex, nonlinear systems. It would be unrealistic to expect that a model can replicate all natural variation exhibited by biological systems. Potential sources of model discrepancy in JABOWA-3 calculations may arise from inaccuracies in GCM-produced future climates [
  <a rid="pone.0132066.ref055" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132066.ref055">55</a>] and climate-response functions in JABOWA-3 [
  <a rid="pone.0132066.ref056" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132066.ref056">56</a>]. Further discussion about the limitations of gap models is available in published scientific literature [
  <a rid="pone.0132066.ref007" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132066.ref007">7</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0132066.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132066.ref021">21</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0132066.ref057" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132066.ref057">57</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All residuals were randomly dispersed along the horizontal axis indicating good overall model performance [
  <a rid="pone.0132066.ref058" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132066.ref058">58</a>]. This demonstrates, with field records spanning ~40 years of present-day climate, that most stands are young to immature (0–40 years) due to intensive harvests in the past [
  <a rid="pone.0132066.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132066.ref037">37</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0132066.ref059" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132066.ref059">59</a>]. However, dispersion of data points along the x-axis (BA) increased in 
  <a rid="pone.0132066.g005" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0132066.g005">Fig 5
   <span class="italic">b</span>–5
   <span class="italic">d</span>
  </a>, since these Figs show results of 90 years growth predicted by JABOWA-3 under climate change scenarios.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The expanded range in some of the residual points in 
  <a rid="pone.0132066.g005" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0132066.g005">Fig 5
   <span class="italic">b</span>–5
   <span class="italic">d</span>
  </a> indicated that ANNs cannot predict a number of data points (tree growth) produced with JABOWA-3 for future climate scenarios. However, most of the other data points (~98%) were within the same range as in 
  <a rid="pone.0132066.g005" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0132066.g005">Fig 5
   <span class="italic">a</span>
  </a> for existing field records. Residual analysis revealed that most data points (-∞,-300] or [300, ∞) belonged to red maple (
  <span class="italic">Acer rubrum</span> L.) with its growth expected to increase with climate change [
  <a rid="pone.0132066.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132066.ref029">29</a>]. Similar trends were observed in residual plots (
  <a rid="pone.0132066.g006" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0132066.g006">Fig 6</a>) for volume growth predictions. Generally, these results indicated the advantage of pooling data (JABOWA-predicted + PSP tree data) together for joint influence on ANN development. As the number of data points associated with field-measured PSP data was greater than that of the JABOWA predictions, the PSP data may have helped to adjust some over-prediction with red maple under scenarios of climate change.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is important to mention other approaches such as potential growth surfaces (PGS), climate envelops (CE), and plant-hardiness zones (PHZ) applied to study forest response to climate change [
  <a rid="pone.0132066.ref060" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132066.ref060">60</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0132066.ref064" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132066.ref064">64</a>]. These approaches mostly describe species response to climatic variables and ignore biotic factors critical to tree growth, such as inter- and intra-specific competition [
  <a rid="pone.0132066.ref060" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132066.ref060">60</a>]. Biotic factors may not be so important for studies at larger spatial scales, such as landscape or biomes, but they are particularly vital for stand- and regional-scale studies [
  <a rid="pone.0132066.ref063" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132066.ref063">63</a>]. In addition, PGS, CE, and PHZ are developed for discrete time intervals, taking into account 30-year climate normals and their modification under projected climate change [
  <a rid="pone.0132066.ref060" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132066.ref060">60</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0132066.ref064" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132066.ref064">64</a>]. Therefore, the inferences drawn based on these approaches are for certain time-periods assuming step-wise changes. However, as climate change is a gradual process, information about successional pathways that present-day forests are expected to take during the transition period is greatly desirable [
  <a rid="pone.0132066.ref065" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132066.ref065">65</a>]. Furthermore, PHZs define the climate ranges (mainly as a function of temperature) where certain plant species can survive based on species geographic presence-absence [
  <a rid="pone.0132066.ref066" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132066.ref066">66</a>]. PHZs are developed based on species existence and are not true illustrations of species-growth behaviour. Species can survive within defined PHZ ranges, but may not achieve optimal or even normal growth. Numerous researchers have suggested the importance of finding ways to combine empirical and process-based approaches in the development of hybrid models to address forest-growth response with climate change [e.g., 10,16]. In this study, we introduced a modelling approach to improve the scope of current G&amp;Y models by using knowledge acquired with process-based models [
  <a rid="pone.0132066.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132066.ref015">15</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate change impact assessments always have uncertainty due to the complex and stochastic nature of biological and climate systems [
  <a rid="pone.0132066.ref062" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132066.ref062">62</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0132066.ref063" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132066.ref063">63</a>]. Although model parameters need to be fine-tuned, gap models are considered to have the best model structure for assessing impacts of climatic change over the transitional period of present-day forests [
  <a rid="pone.0132066.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0132066.ref029">29</a>]. Moreover, gap models can be tailored to provide individual-tree data in the same format as provided by PSP records. In this study, projecting tree growth under the influence of climate change with a gap model in developing empirical G&amp;Y models is a unique contribution to forest modelling addressing non-static growing conditions. However, opportunities exist for expanded studies using other types of process-based models and comparative studies of different modelling techniques in assessing forest-related climate change impacts.
 </p>
</sec>
