<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s3j" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Adaptation in island 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> in the presence of gene flow
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Body size is determined by several selection forces, some of which act in opposite directions (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F4" href="#BIO013839F4">Fig. 4</a>). The direction and strength of selection are determined by environmental conditions and behaviour and depend on the current body size. When body size has reached its optimal value, the conflicting selection forces balance out. But if conditions are different in a newly colonized area, directional selection sets in and acts to shift body size towards a new optimum. While a trait is in the process of responding to a recent selection force, the gap becomes progressively narrower between the current state and the optimum. But the strength of directional selection diminishes as the phenotype nears its optimal state, which is therefore approached asymptotically and ever more slowly. 
  <div id="BIO013839F4" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 4.</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>
     <span class="bold">Ecological selection forces acting on the body size of 
      <span class="italic">P. ater</span>.
     </span> Open arrows symbolize selection pressures on 
     <span class="italic">P. ater</span> when 
     <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
     <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> are present, solid arrows when they are absent. Arrow length in each pair indicates presumed relative selection strengths in sympatry and allopatry, respectively. Conditions on the left side act to increase body size and they gain in importance in allopatry on the islands. Those on the right side act to reduce body size and they lose significance on the islands. When 
     <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
     <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> are absent, 
     <span class="italic">P. ater</span> takes over the vacant space, which creates a new selection regime. The widened food base permits a higher population density. It probably increases intraspecific, interference competition, which in turn selects for a large body size. And the take-over of foraging sites on the inner parts of branches and on the trunk, normally occupied by 
     <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
     <span class="italic">P. montanus</span>, gives more opportunity for obtaining food by pecking and tearing, which selects for a large size. In sympatry on the mainland, 
     <span class="italic">P. ater</span> forages mainly in the canopy periphery, which requires high manoeuvrability and is expensive in energy. A low body mass improves manoeuvrability and reduces energy costs for locomotion and, in addition, facilitates access to tight spaces in the canopy periphery. The frequent use of outer branch parts by 
     <span class="italic">P. ater</span> on the mainland therefore selects for a small body size. But when 
     <span class="italic">P. ater</span> exploits the foraging sites of the absentees on the islands, it cuts down on its use of the canopy periphery, which relaxes selection for a small body size. Conflicting selection forces therefore cancel out at a larger body size of 
     <span class="italic">P. ater</span> on the islands than on the mainland where it coexists with 
     <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
     <span class="italic">P. montanus</span>.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="biolopen-4-013839-g4" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Adaptive evolution on the islands will also be slowed by gene flow from the mainland population due to the occasional arrival of immigrants and ensuing interbreeding events. And adaptation comes to an end when the strength of directional selection has dropped to the level where it is offset by the rate of inflow of those genes that are selected against. In the presence of gene flow, adaptation therefore ceases before the optimal state is reached. The higher the rate of gene flow the wider the gap between the attainable character state and the optimal state. For these reasons, the locally optimal body size of 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> may not be attained on the islands.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> is a permanent resident the whole year through within its range on the mainland of Norway, Sweden and Finland as well as on the islands. But it occasionally performs irruptive migrations. In the 41-year period from 1973 to 2013, an unusually large autumn irruption occurred in 1975, when 15,515 individuals of 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> were recorded on migration at Falsterbo Bird Observatory on the SW-most point of Sweden (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F1" href="#BIO013839F1">Fig. 1</a>). Smaller autumn irruptions occurred in the following years, with bird counts in parentheses: 1982 (518), 1986 (277), 1988 (2175), 1990 (4479), 1991 (1976), 1993 (504), 1996 (129), 2003 (880), 2008 (320) and 2012 (533). In the other years, only a few migrating birds were recorded and in 15 of the 41 years there was not a single record of 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> at Falsterbo Bird Observatory, from which these migration counts were obtained.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Judging from ringing data from Scandinavian bird observatories, migrating 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> stay inland of the west and east coastlines of Sweden (
  <a rid="BIO013839C58" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C58">Ottenby Report, 1989</a>). Therefore, and because irruptions are infrequent, gene flow is probably weak to the most isolated islands Gotska Sandön, Gotland, Bornholm, Anholt and Læsø.
 </p>
</sec>
