<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s3h" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Body shape of 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span>, 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> from the Swedish mainland compared with 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> from six islands
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Body shape is described here in terms of ratios between various measurements in 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB2" href="#BIO013839TB2">Tables 2</a>-
  <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB4" href="#BIO013839TB4">4</a>. Seven ratios, defined in 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB5" href="#BIO013839TB5">Table 5</a>, were calculated for each of the 12 samples. We also calculated the average value of each ratio across the three mainland samples from SW, SE and SC Sweden. Because mainland birds belong to the same uniform population, we weighted the sub-samples in relation to their size. But populations on each of the six islands Gotska Sandön through to Læsø are separate entities. Therefore, we calculated the average ratios across these islands by giving equal weight to each island. The average ratios are set in boldface in 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB5" href="#BIO013839TB5">Table 5</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the absence of 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> from the islands, 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> might be expected to evolve morphologically in the direction of one or the other of the missing congeners, or towards some average of their respective shapes. Therefore, we also present ratios as averaged across 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> from the Swedish mainland, using data from 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB2" href="#BIO013839TB2">Tables 2</a>-
  <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB4" href="#BIO013839TB4">4</a> and giving equal weight to each species. These across-species average ratios are set in boldface at the bottom of 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB5" href="#BIO013839TB5">Table 5</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">First and foremost, there are only small differences in the shape and proportions of the wing, leg and bill between 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span>, 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> on the Swedish mainland. Therefore, one would not expect any large changes in body proportions of 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> in places where 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> are lacking. And overall, the body proportions of 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> are rather similar between the islands and the Swedish mainland. However, in a few cases, set out in bold italics in 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB5" href="#BIO013839TB5">Table 5</a> and reviewed below, the shape of 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> differs between the islands and the Swedish mainland.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Wing loading is equal to (body weight)/(wing area) and is proportional to 
  <span class="italic">l</span>
  <span class="sup">3</span>/
  <span class="italic">l
   <span class="sup">2</span>
  </span>∝
  <span class="italic">l</span> under geometric similarity, 
  <span class="italic">l</span> being a representative length. So, wing loading is scale dependent and varies in proportion to the linear dimension among different sized animals of the same shape. The wing loading is 4.4% larger in 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 5.5% larger in 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> than in 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> in the pooled mainland sample (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB5" href="#BIO013839TB5">Table 5</a>). But the linear wing dimensions of 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> exceed those of 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> by about the same percentages as the wing loading (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F2" href="#BIO013839F2">Fig. 2</a>). Therefore, the higher wing loading in 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> is largely a scale effect of their larger body size. But it is noteworthy that even though 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> is larger on the islands than on the mainland the wing loading is not higher in island birds, so in this respect there is no convergence on 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB5" href="#BIO013839TB5">Table 5</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The proportion that the hand-wing makes up of the wing span is 1% smaller in 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 1.5% smaller in 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> than in mainland 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span>, but it is identical between mainland and island 
  <span class="italic">P. ater.</span> And the wing aspect ratio is similar between 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and mainland 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span>, whereas it is 2.6% smaller in 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> than in mainland 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span>. But the aspect ratio of 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span>, as averaged across the six islands, is equal to that of mainland 
  <span class="italic">P. ater.</span> So, wing shape of 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> has not changed on the islands.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ratio between tarsus and tibiotarsus is 1–3.3% larger on the islands of Gotska Sandön (ad, 0.776) and Gotland (juv, 0.777) than in mainland conspecifics (ad, 0.767; juv 0.762), so on these islands 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> approaches the leg shape of 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB5" href="#BIO013839TB5">Table 5</a>). But this is not a general trend for the islands; the tarsus/tibiotarsus ratio of 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> as averaged across all six islands, from Gotska Sandön through to Læsø, is 0.763 for juveniles (
  <span class="italic">n</span>=91) and 0.767 for adults (
  <span class="italic">n</span>=27). This is in close agreement with the ratios 0.762 and 0.767, respectively, for the unified mainland sample (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB5" href="#BIO013839TB5">Table 5</a>). What is more, the tarsus/tibiotarsus ratio of mainland 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> is similar to the mean ratio taken across 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> in allopatry on the Swedish mainland. Therefore, there should not be any directional selection on leg proportions in 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> when 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> are absent.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The bill is the same length in 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB4" href="#BIO013839TB4">Table 4</a>). But it is stouter in 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span>, being both deeper and wider and in both respects differs from 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> at the 0.001 significance level. As a result, the bill's depth/length and width/length ratios are larger in 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> than in 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span>. In 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> from the Swedish mainland, both ratios are halfway between those of 
  <span class="italic">P montanus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB5" href="#BIO013839TB5">Table 5</a>). So, when each of the depth/length and width/length bill ratios is averaged across 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span>, the mean across-species ratios are 0.376 and 0.396, respectively, which is strikingly similar to the corresponding ratios 0.376 and 0.393 of 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> on the mainland (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB5" href="#BIO013839TB5">Table 5</a>). Therefore, there is no obvious direction in which bill shape of 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> might be expected to evolve on islands in the absence of 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">But there are a few local deviations in bill shape. On the island of Anholt, the depth/length ratio of the bill of 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> stands out by being 6.1% lower in juveniles and 8.1% lower in adults than in mainland conspecifics. In this respect, 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> on Anholt has converged on the bill shape of mainland 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> to the extent that they are almost identical; the bill's depth/length ratio of 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> on Anholt is 0.353 in juveniles (
  <span class="italic">n</span>=11) and 0.350 in adults (
  <span class="italic">n</span>=3) vs 0.354 (
  <span class="italic">n</span>=8) and 0.360 (
  <span class="italic">n</span>=3), respectively, in 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> on the mainland (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB5" href="#BIO013839TB5">Table 5</a>). This low depth/length ratio is due entirely to a small bill depth in 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> on Anholt (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB4" href="#BIO013839TB4">Table 4</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Overall, the bill's depth/length ratio of 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span>, as averaged across all six islands (juv 0.368; ad 0.366), is slightly lower than the average for mainland conspecifics (juv 0.376; ad 0.381). This is a general deviation on islands in the direction of 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On Gotska Sandön and Bornholm, 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> has proportionately wide bills (width/length ratio=0.400), a deviation toward the bill shape of 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> (width/length ratio=0.425). But the width/length ratio for 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span>, again averaged across the six islands (juv 0.393; ad 0.389), is exactly identical to the average for mainland 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> (juv 0.393; ad 0.389) and very similar to the average ratio taken across 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> (juv 0.396; ad 0.388) (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB5" href="#BIO013839TB5">Table 5</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The depth/width ratio of the bill of 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> is 6.6% lower in juveniles from Anholt (0.895) and 7.8% lower in adults from Gotska Sandön (0.904) than in conspecifics on the Swedish mainland (0.958 for juveniles and 0.980 for adults). These island deviations are in the direction of 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> (0.933).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There are thus occasional differences in body proportions of 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> between some of the islands and the Swedish mainland. But there is no general trend, common to all islands, towards the shape of one or the other of the two absent species. Most of the ratios of 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span>, as averaged across the six islands Gotska Sandön through to Læsø, are almost identical to the corresponding ratios of mainland conspecifics (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB5" href="#BIO013839TB5">Table 5</a>; average ratios in boldface).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In conclusion, the occasional differences in body shape of 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> between some of the islands and the mainland occur variously in the direction of one or the other of the two absent congeners. The lack of consistency between islands suggests the deviations are due to fortuitous founder differences or random drift. But the shape differences could also be the result of evolutionary adaptation in different directions on different islands owing to habitat differences.
 </p>
</sec>
