<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" id="s4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">CONCLUSION</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">None of the alternative explanations is supported, so our 
  <span class="italic">a priori</span> hypothesis is upheld. Because the large size of 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> on the islands is genetically determined, we conclude that it is the result of evolutionary adaptation, due ultimately to the local absence of the larger competitors 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus.</span> Judging by the wide geographical separation of the islands, the large size cannot be the result of a single, local, evolutionary event, followed by dispersal to the other islands. Instead, the size increase must have evolved independently on separate islands after colonization.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The enlarged body size has probably evolved because when 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> are absent, 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> takes over the vacant niche space in the inner tree parts. The takeover is promoted (1) by food in the vacant space (2) and by the absence of competition with the ordinary niche holders. The extended niche space enables 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> to reach high population densities on the islands. Because the food base is widened, competition for food may not increase, but intraspecific interference competition is likely to increase, which strengthens selection for a large body size (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F4" href="#BIO013839F4">Fig. 4</a>). And as indicated by the large size of 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span>, which mostly forage on the thick parts of branches, a large body is better adapted to places where food can be obtained by pecking and tearing in bark and wood (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F4" href="#BIO013839F4">Fig. 4</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In sympatry with 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> on the Swedish mainland, 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> forages predominantly in the outer tree parts. Foraging on the fine and pliant distal twigs in the tree periphery requires frequent hanging underneath branches and many short flights and hovering bouts. For mechanical and aerodynamic reasons a small body size improves agility and manoeuvrability and reduces energy cost of locomotion. Selection therefore favours a small size in 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> on the mainland.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">But when 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> exploits the vacant foraging sites of 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> on the islands, it also adopts their easier foraging techniques and locomotion modes, which reduces demands for manoeuvrability and power output. In addition, after widening its foraging zone in trees, 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> cuts down on its exploitation rate of the canopy periphery, where high manoeuvrability and energy-expensive locomotion modes are required. Selection for a small body size is therefore reduced (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F4" href="#BIO013839F4">Fig. 4</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On the six islands where 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> occurs alone, it is near the average size as calculated across 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span>, 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> in sympatry on the Swedish mainland (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F1" href="#BIO013839F1">Figs 1</a>-
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F3" href="#BIO013839F3">3</a>). So, in the absence of the two larger competitors, 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> has evolved in the direction of the absentees on the six islands and become a medium-sized generalist.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In two other places, 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> coexists with one coniferous forest congener – with 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> on the island of Öland and with 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> on the Danish peninsula Jylland. 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> is larger in both places than on the Swedish mainland. But the size increase is less on Öland and Jylland than on the six islands from which 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> as well as 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> are absent.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The body size of 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> is enlarged in all eight places where it was expected. So here, evolution of local adaptation could be predicted both regarding direction (qualitatively) and the amount of change (quantitatively). And it has taken place independently and in parallel in geographically separated places (repeatability). The large size has evolved within the last 100 years on the four islands Bornholm, Sjælland, Anholt and Læsø because the coniferous forest habitat required by 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> was totally lacking before then.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A corollary of the niche extension and evolutionary size increase in 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> when it is geographically isolated from 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span>, is that when all three coexist, 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> obviously exclude 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> from the inner tree zones, either by virtue of being larger and socially dominant or by reducing food to levels at which it is not profitable for 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> to forage. It leaves 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> to exploit the tree periphery, which requires high manoeuvrability and agility. This keeps up selection for a small body size of 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> on the mainland (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F4" href="#BIO013839F4">Fig. 4</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Predators may play an indirect role in maintaining the small size of mainland 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> in so far as they influence niche partitioning among tits to the effect that 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> forage in the safer inner tree parts from where they drive 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> into the tree periphery where small size is selected for.
 </p>
</sec>
