<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">RESULTS AND DISCUSSION</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Among the three 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> samples from the Swedish mainland, the one from South West (SW) Sweden is the largest and contains 25 juvenile and 11 adult birds. We will use that as a reference against which we contrast measurements from each of the other sampling places.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">First, we compare measurements of 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> from the Swedish mainland with one another and with 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> from the mainland of SW Sweden. Second, we compare 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> from SW Sweden with conspecifics from each of the other 11 capture sites, two of which lie on the Swedish mainland. This comparison shows the degree of variation between the three mainland samples and gives a quick overview of differences between mainland and island birds (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F1" href="#BIO013839F1">Figs 1</a>-
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F3" href="#BIO013839F3">3</a>). 
  <div id="BIO013839F2" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 2.</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>
     <span class="bold">Diagrams showing by how many percent each of 11 size measures of 
      <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> and 
      <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> from SW and SE Sweden exceeds the size of 
      <span class="italic">P. ater</span> in the reference sample from SW Sweden.
     </span> Tarsus refers to tarsus ‘short’. The diagrams are directly comparable to those in 
     <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F3" href="#BIO013839F3">Fig. 3</a>, where the size of 
     <span class="italic">P. ater</span> from each of 11 sampling places is also compared with the 
     <span class="italic">P. ater</span> reference sample from SW Sweden.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="biolopen-4-013839-g2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <div id="BIO013839F3" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 3.</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>
     <span class="bold">Diagrams showing by how many percent each of 11 size measures of 
      <span class="italic">P. ater</span> from 11 sampling places differs from the 
      <span class="italic">P. ater</span> reference sample from SW Sweden.
     </span> Tarsus refers to tarsus ‘short’. 
     <span class="italic">P. ater</span> coexists with 
     <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
     <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> on the Swedish mainland and on the Finnish island of Åland. On the Danish penisnsula Jylland it coexists with 
     <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and on the island of Öland with 
     <span class="italic">P. montanus.</span> But on the six islands Gotska Sandön, Gotland, Bornholm, Sjælland, Anholt and Læsø 
     <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> as well as 
     <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> are totally lacking.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="biolopen-4-013839-g3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Measurements of 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> turn out to be very similar between SW, South East (SE) and South Central (SC) Sweden. Therefore, and because those birds belong to the same cohesive population, we pool the three mainland samples. Each of the nine offshore samples of 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> is then tested statistically against the unified mainland sample (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB2" href="#BIO013839TB2">Tables 2</a>-
  <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB5" href="#BIO013839TB5">5</a>). Finally, we compare the body shape of 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span>, 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> from the Swedish mainland with 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> from each of the six islands where 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> are naturally absent (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB5" href="#BIO013839TB5">Table 5</a>). 
  <div id="BIO013839TB3" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 3.</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>
     <span class="bold">Leg dimensions of 
      <span class="italic">P. ater</span>
     </span>
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="biolopen-4-013839-i3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <div id="BIO013839TB4" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 4.</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>
     <span class="bold">Bill dimensions and tail length of 
      <span class="italic">P. ater</span>
     </span>
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="biolopen-4-013839-i4" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <div id="BIO013839TB5" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 5.</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>
     <span class="bold">Wing loading and proportions of the wing, leg and bill of 
      <span class="italic">P. ater</span>
     </span>
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="biolopen-4-013839-i5" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <sec id="s3a" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Body size of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span>, 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> in sympatry on the Swedish mainland
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Actual measurements of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span>, 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> from the Swedish mainland, and of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> from islands, are shown in 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB2" href="#BIO013839TB2">Tables 2</a>-
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB4" href="#BIO013839TB4">4</a>. And 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F1" href="#BIO013839F1">Fig. 1</a>, inset at top left, shows how three compound measures of the wing, leg and bill of 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> from SW and SE Sweden differ from the reference sample of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> from SW Sweden. Likewise, 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F2" href="#BIO013839F2">Fig. 2</a> shows how each of 11 morphological measurements of 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> from SW and SE Sweden differs from the reference values for 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> in SW Sweden.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> are fairly similar in overall size. But 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> has 7% longer tarsus and 3% longer foot than 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span>. Their bills are equally long, but 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> exceeds the size of 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> by 16% in bill width, 12% in bill depth and 14% in tail length.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Both 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> are considerably larger than 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> from the Swedish mainland. The difference from 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> is statistically highly significant in all measurements except for the depth and width of the bill of 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB2" href="#BIO013839TB2">Tables 2</a>-
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB4" href="#BIO013839TB4">4</a>). Notice that 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F1" href="#BIO013839F1">Figs 1</a> and 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F2" href="#BIO013839F2">2</a> show how much 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> from the Swedish mainland differs from 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> in SW Sweden whereas the actual measurements appear at the bottom of 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB2" href="#BIO013839TB2">Tables 2</a>-
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB4" href="#BIO013839TB4">4</a>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s3b" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Body size of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> from SW Sweden compared with conspecifics from each of 11 other sampling places
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to see how the body size of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> varies between the three mainland samples and whether island birds differ from them, we use the SW Swedish measurements as reference values, against which we contrast data from each of the 11 remaining sampling places. Two of them lie on the Swedish mainland (SC South-Central and SE Sweden), one lies on the Danish mainland Jylland and eight are on different islands.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F1" href="#BIO013839F1">Fig. 1</a> gives a quick overview of the results. The bar diagrams show how much birds at the respective locality differ in linear dimensions from birds in SW Sweden. Each bar shows the difference as averaged across three primary measurements of the wing, leg and bill, respectively.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The difference in wing dimensions, shown by the left bar W, was calculated by first finding the amount, expressed in per cent of the SW Swedish value, by which birds from the respective locality differs from the SW Swedish sample in each of the three wing measurements (wing area)
   <span class="sup">0.5</span>, wing span and hand-wing length. We then took the average value of these three percentages. Similarly, the local deviation from the SW Swedish measurements of the leg, shown by the middle bar L, is the average of the percentage differences in tibiotarsus length, tarsus ‘short’ length and foot length. And the local deviation from the SW Swedish measurements of the bill, shown by the right bar B, is the average of the percentage differences in bill length, width and height.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F3" href="#BIO013839F3">Fig. 3</a> is similar to 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F1" href="#BIO013839F1">Fig. 1</a>. But while each bar in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F1" href="#BIO013839F1">Fig. 1</a> represents the average difference across three measurements, 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F3" href="#BIO013839F3">Fig. 3</a> shows how much each one of 11 morphological measurements of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> from each of 11 sampling places differs from the reference sample from SW Sweden.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The measurements are very similar between the three sampling places on the Swedish mainland (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB2" href="#BIO013839TB2">Tables 2</a>-
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB4" href="#BIO013839TB4">4</a>; 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F1" href="#BIO013839F1">Figs 1</a>, 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F3" href="#BIO013839F3">3</a>). And on the island of Åland, where 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span>, 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus and P. montanus</span> coexist – like on the Swedish mainland – 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> is the same small size as conspecifics on the SW Swedish mainland (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F1" href="#BIO013839F1">Fig. 1</a>, top right; 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F3" href="#BIO013839F3">Fig. 3</a>, left diagram in second row). But on all six islands from which both 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> are absent, 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> is significantly larger in wing, leg and bill dimensions than its conspecifics on the SW Swedish mainland. Compared with conspecifics in SW Sweden, 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> is also larger on the Danish mainland Jylland, where it coexists with 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span>, and on the island of Öland, where it coexists with 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F1" href="#BIO013839F1">Figs 1</a>, 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F3" href="#BIO013839F3">3</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s3c" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Body size of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> in the pooled mainland sample compared with conspecifics from each of nine offshore places
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Among all measurements of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> in the samples from SW, SE and SC Sweden, it is only the body weight of birds in SE Sweden that differs statistically by being about 4.4% lower than in the SW and SC Swedish samples (
   <span class="italic">P</span>&lt;0.02). But because body mass varies with food supply and time of day – as detailed below – a mass difference of this magnitude may not be a reliable measure of overall body size.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Apart from this deviation, there is great homogeneity among all the other measurements of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> from the Swedish mainland (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB2" href="#BIO013839TB2">Tables 2</a>-
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB4" href="#BIO013839TB4">4</a>; 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F3" href="#BIO013839F3">Fig. 3</a>). Therefore, and because mainland birds belong to the same uniform and cohesive population, we added together the samples from SW, SE and SC Sweden into a combined mainland sample consisting of 45 juvenile and 16 adult birds. Each measurement in the pooled mainland sample was obtained by averaging across the three sub-samples, weighted in proportion to their respective size. The nine samples from localities off the Swedish mainland were then tested statistically, one at a time, against this unified mainland sample (Mann–Whitney 
   <span class="italic">U</span>-test). The statistical analyses are based on juvenile birds except for the Gotska Sandön sample, which only contains adults that we compare with adults from the mainland.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This comparison differs from the previous one (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F1" href="#BIO013839F1">Figs 1</a>, 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F3" href="#BIO013839F3">3</a>) insofar as here we contrast each sample collected off the Swedish mainland against the pooled mainland sample rather than against the sub-sample from SW Sweden. The results are reviewed below and shown separately for each measurement in 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB2" href="#BIO013839TB2">Tables 2</a>-
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB4" href="#BIO013839TB4">4</a> and 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F3" href="#BIO013839F3">Fig. 3</a>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s3d" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> in sympatry with 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> on the island of Åland
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The island of Åland is included as a control because it is comparable to the other six islands except that it harbours all three tit species – like the Swedish mainland. Among 12 measurements of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span>, the body mass and tibiotarsus length are significantly larger on Åland than on the Swedish mainland (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB2" href="#BIO013839TB2">Tables 2</a>-
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB4" href="#BIO013839TB4">4</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On the mainland, the body mass averages 9.35 g for juveniles and 9.34 g for adults, whereas juveniles on the Åland island weigh 9.80 g and adults 9.46 g (
   <span class="italic">n</span>=5). This is 0.45 g and 4.8% respectively 0.12 g and 1.3% more than for mainland birds. In general, such small differences in body mass may not be reliable measures of body size because they can be due to different feeding conditions and different times of day for weighing. In a study in Norway, the daily mass increase of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> amounted to 9.8-10.6% (
   <a rid="BIO013839C34" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C34">Haftorn, 1992</a>), which is twice the difference between mainland and Åland birds. As noted above, body mass seems to be decoupled from the other size measures also among 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> from SE Sweden (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F3" href="#BIO013839F3">Fig. 3</a>; 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB2" href="#BIO013839TB2">Tables 2</a>-
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB4" href="#BIO013839TB4">4</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The difference in tibiotarsus length is small. On Åland, the average length is 24.4 mm for juveniles and 23.9 mm for adults (
   <span class="italic">n</span>=5) vs 24.1 mm both for juveniles and adults on the Swedish mainland. So the tibiotarsus is actually shorter in adults on Åland. And wing area, wingspan and bill depth are smaller in juvenile birds on Åland than on the Swedish mainland, whereas the other measurements are very similar between Åland and the Swedish mainland (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F2" href="#BIO013839F2">Fig. 2</a>; 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB2" href="#BIO013839TB2">Tables 2</a>-
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB4" href="#BIO013839TB4">4</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Taken together, the measurements show that 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> is the same small size on Åland as on the Swedish mainland (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB2" href="#BIO013839TB2">Tables 2</a>-
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB4" href="#BIO013839TB4">4</a>; 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F1" href="#BIO013839F1">Figs 1</a>, 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F3" href="#BIO013839F3">3</a>). This is expected since 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> coexists with 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> on Åland – like on the Swedish mainland – entailing similar interspecific competition.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s3e" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> in geographical isolation from 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> on six islands
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> is substantially larger on each of the six islands Gotska Sandön, Gotland, Bornholm, Sjælland, Anholt and Læsø – all of which lack 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatu</span>s and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus –</span> than on the Swedish mainland, where 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> coexists with 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatu</span>s and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus.</span> The amount by which 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> on the islands differs from mainland conspecifics varies between body parts and also between the islands (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F3" href="#BIO013839F3">Fig. 3</a>). The maximum size difference recorded for a single trait between island and mainland first-year birds is 8% for a wing dimension, 10% for a leg dimension and 9% for a bill dimension (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F3" href="#BIO013839F3">Fig. 3</a>; 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB2" href="#BIO013839TB2">Tables 2</a>-
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB4" href="#BIO013839TB4">4</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Each of the six independent island-mainland comparisons involves 12 measures of body size (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB2" href="#BIO013839TB2">Tables 2</a>-
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB4" href="#BIO013839TB4">4</a>; 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F3" href="#BIO013839F3">Fig. 3</a>, showing 11 measurements because tarsus ‘long’ is omitted). Of the resulting 72 comparisons of primary measurements between island and mainland birds, 56 differ in the expected direction at the 0.001 significance level, two at the 0.01 level and six at the 0.05 level, whereas eight comparisons do not reach statistical significance. The latter are body mass, wing area, bill depth and tail length of adult birds on Gotska Sandön; bill depth and tail length of juveniles on Jylland; bill depth of juveniles on Anholt; and tail length of juveniles on Læsø. It is noteworthy that there is not a single local mean measurement of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> that is significantly smaller on any of the six islands than on the Swedish mainland (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB2" href="#BIO013839TB2">Tables 2</a>-
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB4" href="#BIO013839TB4">4</a>; 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F3" href="#BIO013839F3">Fig. 3</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Because each measurement is a measure of body size, the various dimensions of an individual bird are strongly correlated. Taken together, however, the data firmly establish that the overall body size of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> is significantly larger on the islands than on the Swedish mainland. As an additional point, the probability that a size change would occur towards larger birds on all six islands independently, and due to random events only, is 0.5
   <span class="sup">6</span>=0.016, a significant result in itself.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB2" href="#BIO013839TB2">Tables 2</a>-
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB5" href="#BIO013839TB5">5</a> show measurements calculated as means across the six islands Gotska Sandön through to Læsø, all of which entirely lack 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus.</span> Each of these islands has an isolated 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> population of its own, so the means are calculated by giving equal weight to each island.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The bottom of 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB2" href="#BIO013839TB2">Tables 2</a>-
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB5" href="#BIO013839TB5">5</a> shows measurements for 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> from SW and SE Sweden and also mean values across these two species. And the bottom line in 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB2" href="#BIO013839TB2">Tables 2</a>-
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB4" href="#BIO013839TB4">4</a> shows measurements calculated as means across mainland 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span>, 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span>. The reason for calculating average values across 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> as well as across 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span>, 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> in sympatry on the Swedish mainland is that natural selection might drive 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> in those directions on islands where 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> are lacking.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Several of the measurements of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span>, calculated as means across the six islands G. Sandön through to Læsø, are very similar to the three-tit means, calculated across 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span>, 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> in sympatry on the Swedish mainland. The respective means are: 62.9 vs 63.0 mm for the hand-wing; 25.10 vs 25.23 for tibiotarsus; 16.98 vs 17.13 for tarsus ‘short’; 9.94 vs 9.92 for bill length; 3.92 vs 3.92 for bill width; and 3.65 vs 3.73 for bill depth (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB2" href="#BIO013839TB2">Tables 2</a>-
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB4" href="#BIO013839TB4">4</a>). So, on the six islands, from which 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> are totally lacking, 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> has increased in size and is near the mean size as calculated across 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span>, 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> in sympatry on the Swedish mainland.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another study, performed three years after we had completed our fieldwork, compared the size of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> between the island of Gotland and an area near Uppsala on the mainland of east-central Sweden. The only dimension measured was the length of tarsus. It was 5.9% longer in adult males (mean 19.13 mm) and 5.6% longer in adult females (mean 18.72 mm) on the island of Gotland than on the mainland (
   <a rid="BIO013839C5" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C5">Alatalo and Gustafsson, 1988</a>). These results are in good agreement with the differences that we recorded for the ‘long’ tarsus of first-year birds (not separated by sex). In our 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB3" href="#BIO013839TB3">Table 3</a>, the tarsus length of first-year birds on Gotland exceeds that of mainland birds from SW, SE and SC Sweden by 6.0%, 6.6% and 7.1%, respectively.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s3f" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> in sympatry with one competitor in two places
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> co-occurs with 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> on the Danish peninsula Jylland and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> co-occurs with 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> on the island of Öland. But we have no data on the population density of 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> on Jylland or of 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> on Öland, except that 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> occurs scantily on Öland (
   <a rid="BIO013839C64" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C64">SOF, 1990</a>; 
   <a rid="BIO013839C48" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C48">Kullberg and Ekman, 2000</a>). So we do not know how strong interspecific competition that 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> is exposed to in these two places.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the absence of only one of the two larger coniferous forest congeners, 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> is nonetheless larger in both places than on the Swedish mainland where it coexists with both 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F1" href="#BIO013839F1">Figs 1</a>, 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F3" href="#BIO013839F3">3</a>; 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB2" href="#BIO013839TB2">Tables 2</a>-
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB4" href="#BIO013839TB4">4</a>). The comparison of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> from the Swedish mainland with conspecifics from Jylland and Öland involves 12 measures of body size. Of the resulting 24 comparisons, 17 show statistically significant differences in the expected direction, whereas 7 do not. The latter are wing area, bill depth and tail length of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> on Jylland; and body mass, wing area, bill depth and tail length of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> on Öland. But there is not a single local mean measurement of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> that is smaller in any of these two places than on the Swedish mainland (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB2" href="#BIO013839TB2">Tables 2</a>-
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB4" href="#BIO013839TB4">4</a>; 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F3" href="#BIO013839F3">Fig. 3</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Neither in Jylland nor on Öland does the overall size of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> reach the size attained on any of the six islands, from which both 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> are absent. This is as predicted because the niche space of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> is narrower on Öland and Jylland, both places of which offer only one vacant niche – that of one absentee – that may be divided up by the two species present. But on the six islands, where 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> is alone, there are two vacant foraging niches – those of the two absent congeners – that can be added in their entirety to the foraging space of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span>. Inclusion by 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> of the foraging sites of the absentees entails adoption of their less demanding locomotion modes, which relaxes selection for manoeuvrability and a small size.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The probability is 0.5
   <span class="sup">8</span>=0.004 that a size change would occur towards larger birds independently, and at random, on all six islands where 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> is alone, as well as on Jylland and Öland where one competing congener is lacking. And except for the change of body size in the predicted direction in all eight places, where it was expected to happen, also the magnitude of the size increase is as anticipated.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s3g" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Variability</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Small populations tend to show reduced genetic and phenotypic variability due to accidental loss of alleles by genetic drift (
   <a rid="BIO013839C51" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C51">Mayr, 1965</a>; 
   <a rid="BIO013839C26" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C26">Grant and Grant, 2008</a>). The populations studied here differ enormously in size. Anholt is the smallest island and based on the coniferous forest size we estimate its 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> population to be 200 individuals whereas Gotland, which is the largest island, harbours 80,000 (
   <a rid="BIO013839C64" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C64">SOF, 1990</a>) and the Swedish mainland 2 million individuals (
   <a rid="BIO013839C71" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C71">Ulfstrand and Högstedt, 1976</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The coefficient of variation, defined as the standard deviation expressed in per cent of the mean, was calculated for all measurements of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> listed in 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB2" href="#BIO013839TB2">Tables 2</a>-
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB4" href="#BIO013839TB4">4</a>. It mostly lies between 2 and 4%. The variance of measurements in the sample from SW Sweden was used as a reference against which we tested the variance of each of the other samples (variance-ratio 
   <span class="italic">F</span>-test). There is no trend in the size of the coefficient of variation between island and mainland birds or between small and large populations. In particular, the coefficients of variation in the very small population of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> on the island of Anholt are not any different from the large populations on Gotland and the Swedish mainland. So, the small Anholt population seems not to have lost phenotypic variability.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s3h" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Body shape of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span>, 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> from the Swedish mainland compared with 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> from six islands
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Body shape is described here in terms of ratios between various measurements in 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB2" href="#BIO013839TB2">Tables 2</a>-
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB4" href="#BIO013839TB4">4</a>. Seven ratios, defined in 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB5" href="#BIO013839TB5">Table 5</a>, were calculated for each of the 12 samples. We also calculated the average value of each ratio across the three mainland samples from SW, SE and SC Sweden. Because mainland birds belong to the same uniform population, we weighted the sub-samples in relation to their size. But populations on each of the six islands Gotska Sandön through to Læsø are separate entities. Therefore, we calculated the average ratios across these islands by giving equal weight to each island. The average ratios are set in boldface in 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB5" href="#BIO013839TB5">Table 5</a>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the absence of 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> from the islands, 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> might be expected to evolve morphologically in the direction of one or the other of the missing congeners, or towards some average of their respective shapes. Therefore, we also present ratios as averaged across 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> from the Swedish mainland, using data from 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB2" href="#BIO013839TB2">Tables 2</a>-
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB4" href="#BIO013839TB4">4</a> and giving equal weight to each species. These across-species average ratios are set in boldface at the bottom of 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB5" href="#BIO013839TB5">Table 5</a>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">First and foremost, there are only small differences in the shape and proportions of the wing, leg and bill between 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span>, 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> on the Swedish mainland. Therefore, one would not expect any large changes in body proportions of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> in places where 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> are lacking. And overall, the body proportions of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> are rather similar between the islands and the Swedish mainland. However, in a few cases, set out in bold italics in 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB5" href="#BIO013839TB5">Table 5</a> and reviewed below, the shape of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> differs between the islands and the Swedish mainland.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Wing loading is equal to (body weight)/(wing area) and is proportional to 
   <span class="italic">l</span>
   <span class="sup">3</span>/
   <span class="italic">l
    <span class="sup">2</span>
   </span>∝
   <span class="italic">l</span> under geometric similarity, 
   <span class="italic">l</span> being a representative length. So, wing loading is scale dependent and varies in proportion to the linear dimension among different sized animals of the same shape. The wing loading is 4.4% larger in 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 5.5% larger in 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> than in 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> in the pooled mainland sample (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB5" href="#BIO013839TB5">Table 5</a>). But the linear wing dimensions of 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> exceed those of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> by about the same percentages as the wing loading (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F2" href="#BIO013839F2">Fig. 2</a>). Therefore, the higher wing loading in 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> is largely a scale effect of their larger body size. But it is noteworthy that even though 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> is larger on the islands than on the mainland the wing loading is not higher in island birds, so in this respect there is no convergence on 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB5" href="#BIO013839TB5">Table 5</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The proportion that the hand-wing makes up of the wing span is 1% smaller in 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 1.5% smaller in 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> than in mainland 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span>, but it is identical between mainland and island 
   <span class="italic">P. ater.</span> And the wing aspect ratio is similar between 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and mainland 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span>, whereas it is 2.6% smaller in 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> than in mainland 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span>. But the aspect ratio of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span>, as averaged across the six islands, is equal to that of mainland 
   <span class="italic">P. ater.</span> So, wing shape of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> has not changed on the islands.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ratio between tarsus and tibiotarsus is 1–3.3% larger on the islands of Gotska Sandön (ad, 0.776) and Gotland (juv, 0.777) than in mainland conspecifics (ad, 0.767; juv 0.762), so on these islands 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> approaches the leg shape of 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB5" href="#BIO013839TB5">Table 5</a>). But this is not a general trend for the islands; the tarsus/tibiotarsus ratio of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> as averaged across all six islands, from Gotska Sandön through to Læsø, is 0.763 for juveniles (
   <span class="italic">n</span>=91) and 0.767 for adults (
   <span class="italic">n</span>=27). This is in close agreement with the ratios 0.762 and 0.767, respectively, for the unified mainland sample (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB5" href="#BIO013839TB5">Table 5</a>). What is more, the tarsus/tibiotarsus ratio of mainland 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> is similar to the mean ratio taken across 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> in allopatry on the Swedish mainland. Therefore, there should not be any directional selection on leg proportions in 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> when 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> are absent.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The bill is the same length in 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB4" href="#BIO013839TB4">Table 4</a>). But it is stouter in 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span>, being both deeper and wider and in both respects differs from 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> at the 0.001 significance level. As a result, the bill's depth/length and width/length ratios are larger in 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> than in 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span>. In 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> from the Swedish mainland, both ratios are halfway between those of 
   <span class="italic">P montanus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB5" href="#BIO013839TB5">Table 5</a>). So, when each of the depth/length and width/length bill ratios is averaged across 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span>, the mean across-species ratios are 0.376 and 0.396, respectively, which is strikingly similar to the corresponding ratios 0.376 and 0.393 of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> on the mainland (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB5" href="#BIO013839TB5">Table 5</a>). Therefore, there is no obvious direction in which bill shape of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> might be expected to evolve on islands in the absence of 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">But there are a few local deviations in bill shape. On the island of Anholt, the depth/length ratio of the bill of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> stands out by being 6.1% lower in juveniles and 8.1% lower in adults than in mainland conspecifics. In this respect, 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> on Anholt has converged on the bill shape of mainland 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> to the extent that they are almost identical; the bill's depth/length ratio of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> on Anholt is 0.353 in juveniles (
   <span class="italic">n</span>=11) and 0.350 in adults (
   <span class="italic">n</span>=3) vs 0.354 (
   <span class="italic">n</span>=8) and 0.360 (
   <span class="italic">n</span>=3), respectively, in 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> on the mainland (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB5" href="#BIO013839TB5">Table 5</a>). This low depth/length ratio is due entirely to a small bill depth in 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> on Anholt (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB4" href="#BIO013839TB4">Table 4</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Overall, the bill's depth/length ratio of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span>, as averaged across all six islands (juv 0.368; ad 0.366), is slightly lower than the average for mainland conspecifics (juv 0.376; ad 0.381). This is a general deviation on islands in the direction of 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On Gotska Sandön and Bornholm, 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> has proportionately wide bills (width/length ratio=0.400), a deviation toward the bill shape of 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> (width/length ratio=0.425). But the width/length ratio for 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span>, again averaged across the six islands (juv 0.393; ad 0.389), is exactly identical to the average for mainland 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> (juv 0.393; ad 0.389) and very similar to the average ratio taken across 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> (juv 0.396; ad 0.388) (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB5" href="#BIO013839TB5">Table 5</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The depth/width ratio of the bill of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> is 6.6% lower in juveniles from Anholt (0.895) and 7.8% lower in adults from Gotska Sandön (0.904) than in conspecifics on the Swedish mainland (0.958 for juveniles and 0.980 for adults). These island deviations are in the direction of 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> (0.933).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There are thus occasional differences in body proportions of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> between some of the islands and the Swedish mainland. But there is no general trend, common to all islands, towards the shape of one or the other of the two absent species. Most of the ratios of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span>, as averaged across the six islands Gotska Sandön through to Læsø, are almost identical to the corresponding ratios of mainland conspecifics (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB5" href="#BIO013839TB5">Table 5</a>; average ratios in boldface).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In conclusion, the occasional differences in body shape of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> between some of the islands and the mainland occur variously in the direction of one or the other of the two absent congeners. The lack of consistency between islands suggests the deviations are due to fortuitous founder differences or random drift. But the shape differences could also be the result of evolutionary adaptation in different directions on different islands owing to habitat differences.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s3i" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The large body size of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> on islands is genetically determined
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Two cross-fostering experiments have been done to find out whether the large size of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> on the islands has a genetic basis. The switch occurred at the egg-stage and involved entire clutches in both experiments. In the first case, eggs were exchanged between nests on the island of Anholt and nests in an area 50 km east of Gothenburg in south-western Sweden (R.Å.N. and Raimo Neergaard-Thörgersen, unpublished). In the other, eggs were exchanged between nests in the southern part of the island of Gotland and nests in an area near the city of Uppsala in east-central Sweden (
   <a rid="BIO013839C5" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C5">Alatalo and Gustafsson, 1988</a>). Both experiments show conclusively that the enlarged body size of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> on the islands is genetically determined and not due to environmental effects on the phenotype.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s3j" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Adaptation in island 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> in the presence of gene flow
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Body size is determined by several selection forces, some of which act in opposite directions (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F4" href="#BIO013839F4">Fig. 4</a>). The direction and strength of selection are determined by environmental conditions and behaviour and depend on the current body size. When body size has reached its optimal value, the conflicting selection forces balance out. But if conditions are different in a newly colonized area, directional selection sets in and acts to shift body size towards a new optimum. While a trait is in the process of responding to a recent selection force, the gap becomes progressively narrower between the current state and the optimum. But the strength of directional selection diminishes as the phenotype nears its optimal state, which is therefore approached asymptotically and ever more slowly. 
   <div id="BIO013839F4" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 4.</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>
      <span class="bold">Ecological selection forces acting on the body size of 
       <span class="italic">P. ater</span>.
      </span> Open arrows symbolize selection pressures on 
      <span class="italic">P. ater</span> when 
      <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
      <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> are present, solid arrows when they are absent. Arrow length in each pair indicates presumed relative selection strengths in sympatry and allopatry, respectively. Conditions on the left side act to increase body size and they gain in importance in allopatry on the islands. Those on the right side act to reduce body size and they lose significance on the islands. When 
      <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
      <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> are absent, 
      <span class="italic">P. ater</span> takes over the vacant space, which creates a new selection regime. The widened food base permits a higher population density. It probably increases intraspecific, interference competition, which in turn selects for a large body size. And the take-over of foraging sites on the inner parts of branches and on the trunk, normally occupied by 
      <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
      <span class="italic">P. montanus</span>, gives more opportunity for obtaining food by pecking and tearing, which selects for a large size. In sympatry on the mainland, 
      <span class="italic">P. ater</span> forages mainly in the canopy periphery, which requires high manoeuvrability and is expensive in energy. A low body mass improves manoeuvrability and reduces energy costs for locomotion and, in addition, facilitates access to tight spaces in the canopy periphery. The frequent use of outer branch parts by 
      <span class="italic">P. ater</span> on the mainland therefore selects for a small body size. But when 
      <span class="italic">P. ater</span> exploits the foraging sites of the absentees on the islands, it cuts down on its use of the canopy periphery, which relaxes selection for a small body size. Conflicting selection forces therefore cancel out at a larger body size of 
      <span class="italic">P. ater</span> on the islands than on the mainland where it coexists with 
      <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
      <span class="italic">P. montanus</span>.
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="biolopen-4-013839-g4" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Adaptive evolution on the islands will also be slowed by gene flow from the mainland population due to the occasional arrival of immigrants and ensuing interbreeding events. And adaptation comes to an end when the strength of directional selection has dropped to the level where it is offset by the rate of inflow of those genes that are selected against. In the presence of gene flow, adaptation therefore ceases before the optimal state is reached. The higher the rate of gene flow the wider the gap between the attainable character state and the optimal state. For these reasons, the locally optimal body size of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> may not be attained on the islands.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> is a permanent resident the whole year through within its range on the mainland of Norway, Sweden and Finland as well as on the islands. But it occasionally performs irruptive migrations. In the 41-year period from 1973 to 2013, an unusually large autumn irruption occurred in 1975, when 15,515 individuals of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> were recorded on migration at Falsterbo Bird Observatory on the SW-most point of Sweden (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F1" href="#BIO013839F1">Fig. 1</a>). Smaller autumn irruptions occurred in the following years, with bird counts in parentheses: 1982 (518), 1986 (277), 1988 (2175), 1990 (4479), 1991 (1976), 1993 (504), 1996 (129), 2003 (880), 2008 (320) and 2012 (533). In the other years, only a few migrating birds were recorded and in 15 of the 41 years there was not a single record of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> at Falsterbo Bird Observatory, from which these migration counts were obtained.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Judging from ringing data from Scandinavian bird observatories, migrating 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> stay inland of the west and east coastlines of Sweden (
   <a rid="BIO013839C58" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C58">Ottenby Report, 1989</a>). Therefore, and because irruptions are infrequent, gene flow is probably weak to the most isolated islands Gotska Sandön, Gotland, Bornholm, Anholt and Læsø.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s3k" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Selection for a large body size in 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> when 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> are absent
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We will now examine how the absence of 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> from the islands influences niche width and foraging behaviour of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> and the selection acting on it. 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F4" href="#BIO013839F4">Fig. 4</a> shows some ecological factors that are likely to determine the difference in body size of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> between the mainland and islands. We distinguish between forces that select for a large size – acting rightwards in 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F4" href="#BIO013839F4">Fig. 4</a> – and those that select for a small size – acting leftwards – and evaluate their relative strengths on the mainland and the islands.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The population density of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> has been determined on the island of Gotland, where 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> are naturally absent. In the winter months December-February, 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> occurred at 5-15 times higher densities in forests of 
   <span class="italic">Pinus silvestris</span> on Gotland than in forests dominated by 
   <span class="italic">Picea abies</span> on the mainland of southern Sweden (
   <a rid="BIO013839C9" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C9">Alerstam et al., 1974</a>). The high population density of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> on Gotland was confirmed in a later study. In the winter months January-February, there were 90-110 individuals per km
   <span class="sup">2</span> on Gotland vs 20 per km
   <span class="sup">2</span> on the mainland of east-central Sweden, a difference by a factor 5 (Appendix in 
   <a rid="BIO013839C8" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C8">Alatalo et al., 1986</a>). 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> thus compensates numerically for the two absent species on Gotland and reaches a population density that is similar to the combined density of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span>, 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> on the Swedish mainland (
   <a rid="BIO013839C9" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C9">Alerstam et al., 1974</a>; 
   <a rid="BIO013839C29" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C29">Gustafsson, 1988</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On Gotland, 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> has expanded its niche width and exploits the foraging sites used elsewhere by the two absent species (
   <a rid="BIO013839C9" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C9">Alerstam et al., 1974</a>; 
   <a rid="BIO013839C29" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C29">Gustafsson, 1988</a>). And in a mainland study area near the city of Uppsala in east-central Sweden, 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> expanded its foraging niche in a similar way after the number of 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> had been experimentally reduced by more than 50% (
   <a rid="BIO013839C7" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C7">Alatalo et al., 1985</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The niche expansion of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> enlarges its food base so the associated increase in population density need not necessarily strengthen intraspecific competition for food. But the increased population density likely intensifies behavioural interference competition. This, in turn, should select for a large body size (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F4" href="#BIO013839F4">Fig. 4</a>, point 1).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Body size is also related to feeding site selection and locomotor modes during foraging. 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> are specialized to forage on the middle and proximal parts of branches and on tree trunks, and their large size is probably an adaptation for this. There are pronounced differences in feeding site selection and foraging behaviour of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> between, on the one hand, the island of Åland and the Swedish mainland and, on the other hand, the island of Gotland. In coexistence with 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> on the island of Åland and on the mainland (near the city of Uppsala in east-central Sweden), 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> foraged almost exclusively in the needle-carrying parts of pine trees, spending 90% of its foraging time there and 10% on twigs. In allopatry on Gotland, however, 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> spent only 24% among needled twigs, but 29% on needle-free twigs, 40% on thick parts of branches and 7% on the trunk of 
   <span class="italic">Pinus silvestris</span> (Fig. 1 and appendix in 
   <a rid="BIO013839C8" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C8">Alatalo et al., 1986</a>; Fig. 1 in 
   <a rid="BIO013839C29" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C29">Gustafsson, 1988</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A partial niche takeover occurred also in experimental forest plots on the mainland of east-central Sweden. After the density of 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> had been experimentally reduced by more than 50%, 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> and 
   <span class="italic">R. regulus</span> increased their foraging rate in the inner canopy parts, which is the foraging zone of the two population-reduced species (
   <a rid="BIO013839C7" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C7">Alatalo et al., 1985</a>). And an aviary experiment, which tested 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> against each other, showed that when 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> tits were removed, 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> turned to exploiting also the characteristic foraging sites of 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> in the inner tree parts (
   <a rid="BIO013839C6" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C6">Alatalo and Moreno, 1987</a>). In all these cases, 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> shifted from foraging predominantly on the peripheral twigs and needles to foraging also on the middle and basal branch parts and on the trunk.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The increased use of the inner tree regions by 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> when 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> are absent gives more opportunity for obtaining food by pecking and tearing in bark and wood. These activities are favoured by a large body size, which is therefore selected for in 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> on the islands (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F4" href="#BIO013839F4">Fig. 4</a>, point 2).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On the mainland, 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> made frequent short flights in the tree periphery, hovered occasionally and often hung underneath slender and pliant twigs, activities that require good manoeuvrability and are expensive in energy. But on Gotland, it mostly moved by hops on top of branches in an upright position (Appendix in 
   <a rid="BIO013839C8" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C8">Alatalo et al., 1986</a>; Fig. 1 in 
   <a rid="BIO013839C29" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C29">Gustafsson, 1988</a>). The shift to foraging more frequently in the inner parts of trees on Gotland is thus associated with a change to easier and less energy-expensive postures and locomotion modes.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Niche differentiation with respect to body size occurs also at the intraspecific level between different-sized individuals of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span>. In isolation from 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> on Gotland, large individuals of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> often used the inner parts of trees whereas small individuals foraged more in the needle-carrying outer regions (
   <a rid="BIO013839C29" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C29">Gustafsson, 1988</a>). Five size measures – tarsus length, bill length, length of the first secondary wing feather, hand-wing length and tail length – were correlated with body mass, and tarsus length was a particularly reliable measure of body size. The range of size variation was 18.6–20.1 mm for tarsus length and 9.0–11.1 g for body mass (read from Fig. 5B and C in 
   <a rid="BIO013839C29" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C29">Gustafsson, 1988</a>). So, it was within these limited ranges of variation that a body-size-related niche differentiation was observed among 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> on Gotland. This intraspecific differentiation of feeding sites among different-sized individuals of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> mirrors the interspecific body-size-related feeding site differentiation that occurs among 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span>, 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> where they coexist on the Swedish mainland. It emphasizes the tight association between body size and foraging zone in trees.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Flight manoeuvrability and general agility increase with decreasing body size for aerodynamic and mechanical reasons (
   <a rid="BIO013839C10" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C10">Andersson and Norberg, 1981</a>). And the energy cost of locomotion decreases with decreasing body mass. During short flights within trees, birds often do not attain the maximum-range cruising speed at which energy cost per unit distance is minimized. At slower speeds, energy cost goes up more the lower the speed, peaking at hovering (
   <a rid="BIO013839C60" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C60">Pennycuick, 2008</a>). In addition, short flights in tree canopies contain a disproportionately large proportion of energy-expensive manoeuvres, such as take-off and landing and twists and turns for negotiating obstacles in the cluttered canopy space. In an experimental study of 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span>, kept in aviaries that only permitted short flights, the energy cost for flight, measured with the doubly-labelled water technique, was 27–32% higher than that calculated for direct flight at normal cruising speed (
   <a rid="BIO013839C15" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C15">Carlson and Moreno, 1992</a>). So, flight within tree canopies is energetically very expensive.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On the mainland, 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> flies more frequently while foraging than do 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> (
   <a rid="BIO013839C53" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C53">Moreno et al., 1988</a>). To see how that affects energy expenditure, the daily field metabolic rate was measured in 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span>, 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> under natural conditions, using the doubly-labelled water technique. The measurements were made on free-ranging birds when temperatures were below freezing in mid-winter (December-January) in a forest near Uppsala in east-central Sweden. The daily metabolic rate turned out to be a higher multiple of the basal metabolic rate in 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> than in 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus.</span> It was 2.89× BMR for 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> and 2.22× BMR for each of the other two, a difference by a factor 1.3 (
   <a rid="BIO013839C53" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C53">Moreno et al., 1988</a>). The difference is obviously a consequence of the more frequent use of energy-demanding locomotion modes, like flight, by 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On the mainland, small size is therefore particularly important to 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> for keeping down energy costs for locomotion (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F4" href="#BIO013839F4">Fig. 4</a>, point 4). But because a lower proportion of the foraging time is spent in the canopy periphery on the islands, selection for a small body size must be weaker there than on the mainland (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F4" href="#BIO013839F4">Fig. 4</a>, point 3-5). In addition, a small size is favoured more when foraging in the tight spaces in the meshwork of twigs and needles in the periphery of the tree canopy than when foraging in less cluttered spaces near the trunk (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F4" href="#BIO013839F4">Fig. 4</a>, point 5).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We conclude that the evolutionary increase in body size of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> on the islands is due ultimately to the absence of 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span>. It was likely brought about by the combination of intensified selection for a large size, due to increased intraspecific interference competition following niche expansion and population increase, and weakened selection for a small size following a shift to easier foraging modes on the islands (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F4" href="#BIO013839F4">Fig. 4</a>). Other selection forces on body size are discussed under ‘Alternative explanations’. But they act in the opposite direction to the evolutionary change that has actually taken place and therefore cannot explain it. Their effect is obviously overridden by the selection forces reviewed above.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s3l" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Interspecific competition among 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span>, 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">If the large body size of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> has evolved on the islands because there is no competition from 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span>, then its small size in sympatry with them on the mainland must be due to their presence. Based on the literature, we review evidence for interspecific competition.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span>, 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> have similar diet both regarding food items cached in autumn for consumption in winter, as documented in a large study in Norway (
   <a rid="BIO013839C33" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C33">Haftorn, 1956c</a>), and food given to nestlings, as recorded in SW Sweden by automatic photography of parents bringing food to their young (
   <a rid="BIO013839C72" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C72">von Brömssen and Jansson, 1975</a>). And all three species join up in mixed-species foraging flocks in winter, which is conducive to interspecific competition.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The way population density is regulated has been extensively studied in 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> but not in 
   <span class="italic">P. ater.</span> Because the ecology is so similar between these three species, population regulation is probably similar for 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span>. Therefore, we refer to results for 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> in the following. We emphasize field studies done in the Nordic countries because their climate and forest habitat are similar to those of the islands and therefore present similar conditions for population regulation.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Predation by tits causes considerable reduction of their food in winter. In two field experiments in SW Sweden, branches of 
   <span class="italic">Picea abies</span> were enclosed with nets to prevent birds from foraging on them throughout the winter. In one of the experiments, run in the period October to March, the exclosure reduced spider mortality from 57% on unprotected branches to 34% on protected branches, suggesting that birds consumed 23% of the spiders present in autumn (
   <a rid="BIO013839C11" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C11">Askenmo et al., 1977</a>). In the other experiment, the exclosure reduced overwinter mortality of small spiders from 90% on unprotected branches to 75% on protected, indicating that birds consumed 15% of the small spiders present in autumn. For large spiders, mortality was reduced from 85% on unprotected branches to 46% on protected, indicating that birds consumed 39% of the large spiders present in autumn (Table 2 in 
   <a rid="BIO013839C27" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C27">Gunnarsson, 1983</a>). The higher disappearance rate of spiders from unprotected branches was attributed to predation by 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span>, 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span>, 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">R. regulus</span>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Because birds themselves reduce prey density, bird mortality due to starvation acts in a density-dependent way. It has been shown experimentally that energy stress is the main cause of winter mortality among 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span>. After experimental provisioning of extra food in autumn and winter in SW Sweden, winter survival almost doubled during the period November to March, from 39% to 76% for 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and from 45% to 82% for 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> (Table 4 in 
   <a rid="BIO013839C44" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C44">Jansson et al., 1981</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">At the same study site in SW Sweden, population density of 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> was experimentally reduced locally in autumn. For 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span>, winter survival in the low-density experimental population increased to 100% whereas survival rate was 68% by April in a normal-density control population. This outcome demonstrates that winter losses are density-dependent and that there is significant intraspecific competition between flock members (
   <a rid="BIO013839C23" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C23">Ekman et al., 1981</a>). Another study in SW Sweden, based on year-round monitoring of a population of marked individuals of 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> over six years, showed that survival is strongly density-dependent among first-year birds in late winter. Mortality in winter is driven by competition for non-renewable food (
   <a rid="BIO013839C20" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C20">Ekman, 1984</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">Parus cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> are considered to be dominant over 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> and to monopolize their species-characteristic feeding sites in the interior of tree canopies, thus preventing 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> from foraging there (
   <a rid="BIO013839C41" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C41">Hogstad, 1978</a>; 
   <a rid="BIO013839C6" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C6">Alatalo and Moreno, 1987</a>; 
   <a rid="BIO013839C66" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C66">Suhonen et al., 1992</a>
   <a rid="BIO013839C67" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C67">, 1993</a>; 
   <a rid="BIO013839C65" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C65">Suhonen, 1993</a>; but see 
   <a rid="BIO013839C35" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C35">Haftorn, 1993</a>). There is also some overlap in feeding sites between 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span>, 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span>, so in the shared space they reduce each other's food resources directly.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The clearest demonstration that 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> restrict the foraging niche of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> comes from the fact that 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> extends it foraging space in their absence. On the mainland, where all three coexist, 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> forages predominantly on the peripheral twigs and needles, but in the absence of 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> it shifts to foraging also on the middle and basal branch parts and the trunk, places that are normally used by the absentees (see review in the foregoing section on selection for a large body size).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">Regulus regulus</span> occurs together with 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> in coniferous forests on the Swedish mainland as well as on all the islands, so there is no mainland-island difference in competition between the two (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB1" href="#BIO013839TB1">Table 1</a>). They use much the same foraging zones in trees (
   <a rid="BIO013839C33" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C33">Haftorn, 1956c</a>) and overlap in diet. 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> eats arthropods and seeds (
   <a rid="BIO013839C33" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C33">Haftorn, 1956c</a>) whereas 
   <span class="italic">R. regulus</span> only eats arthropods all year round, including very small items like Collembola (
   <a rid="BIO013839C70" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C70">Thaler, 1973</a>; 
   <a rid="BIO013839C42" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C42">Hogstad, 1984</a>). 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> is socially dominant over 
   <span class="italic">R. regulus</span> and often takes over its feeding site by supplanting attacks (R.Å.N., personal observation). 
   <span class="italic">Certhia familiaris</span> occurs in coniferous forest on the mainland and on all the islands except Anholt and Læsø (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB1" href="#BIO013839TB1">Table 1</a>). It forages almost entirely on tree trunks and therefore interferes little with 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In conclusion, food is a limiting factor that brings about population regulation in winter. The process is density-dependent because the rate of food depletion increases with increasing population density and feeds back to the individual in terms of food scarcity. Winter is also the season when 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> occurs together with 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> in mixed-species foraging flocks, which is conducive to interspecific competition. Regardless of whether 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> restrict the foraging space of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> physically, or if they reduce food in their foraging zones to levels at which it is not profitable for 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> to forage, they compete by reducing food accessibility for it. In addition, they reduce food for 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> directly in the overlapping parts of their respective foraging space. Since winter is the season when population regulation mostly takes place, it is also then that selection on behaviour and morphology is the strongest. Because 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> cause 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> to forage predominantly in the tree periphery during winter, interspecific competition maintains selection for a small body size of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> in sympatry on the mainland (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F4" href="#BIO013839F4">Fig. 4</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s3m" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Alternative explanations</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We think that the genetically determined increase in body size of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> on the islands is the result of adaptive evolution in response to the absence of competition from 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span>. But the large size may have come about for other reasons. 
   <a rid="BIO013839C61" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C61">Platt (1964)</a> forcefully advocated the ‘method of multiple working hypotheses', placing focus on finding proof for exclusion. Here, we test 11 alternative hypotheses against available evidence. They are treated in turn below and can all be eliminated.
  </p>
  <sec id="s3m1" class="sec">
   <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1.</span>
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Relict island populations reflecting historically widespread ancestral characteristics</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <span class="italic">P. ater</span> is strictly bound to coniferous forest. But the four islands Bornholm, Sjælland, Anholt and Læsø were not planted with conifers until after 1850. In these recently founded populations, 
    <span class="italic">P. ater</span> is equally large as conspecifics on Gotska Sandön and Gotland, both of which have had primeval coniferous forests since long-ago.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="s3m2" class="sec">
   <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.</span>
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Island 
    <span class="italic">P. ater</span> derived from other populations than those that colonized the Swedish mainland
   </div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In view of the large geographical separation between the islands and their location to the east, south and west of the Swedish mainland, it is unlikely that the islands and the Swedish mainland got their populations from different sources. But most important, there is almost no variation in body size among continental 
    <span class="italic">P. ater</span> over the northern Palearctic (
    <a rid="BIO013839C62" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C62">Snow, 1954</a>, 
    <a rid="BIO013839C63" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C63">1955</a>), so there is no nearby place from which large birds could have been recruited.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="s3m3" class="sec">
   <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.</span>
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Geographical trends or clinal variation in body size</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <span class="italic">P. ater</span> has a continuous distribution across the northern Palearctic and shows great uniformity in body dimensions with little clinal variation (
    <a rid="BIO013839C62" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C62">Snow, 1954</a>, 
    <a rid="BIO013839C63" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C63">1955</a>). So there is no geographical trend that could explain the size difference between island and mainland tits.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="s3m4" class="sec">
   <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.</span>
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Founder effect</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This refers to the reduction of genetic variation that occurs when a population is established by a small number of pioneers. When there are few individuals in a colonizing group, random processes increase the likelihood that the group brings with it a skewed gene sample that is not representative of the parent population. This may contribute to evolutionary divergence.</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <span class="italic">P. ater</span> is sedentary the whole year round but performs irruptive migrations at irregular intervals. The islands were most likely colonized by mainland birds that took part in such irruptions. But the probability is only 0.5
    <span class="sup">8</span>=0.004 that all eight places, from which one or two congeners are absent, were colonized by larger than average-sized mainland birds by chance alone. So random founder events cannot account for the large size of 
    <span class="italic">P. ater</span> in all eight places.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We will now look at the size of present-day migrants of 
    <span class="italic">P. ater.</span> Judging by observations during an autumn irruption in 1990, migrants consist almost exclusively of juveniles. On that occasion, 716 
    <span class="italic">P. ater</span> were netted and ringed at Falsterbo Bird Observatory and all of them were first-year birds (Lennart Karlsson, personal communication).
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The hand-wing and the tarsus of first-year birds on southbound autumn migration were measured by staff ornithologists at the Falsterbo Bird Observatory, who used the measuring technique described in the methods section herein. Hand-wing length of migrants was remarkably similar between samples in different years. The average length was 61.26 mm (s.d. 1.62) for 273 migrating 
    <span class="italic">P. ater</span> measured in September and October 1982-1986 (Göran Walinder, personal communication) and 61.23 mm (s.d. 1.51) for 180 birds measured in September and October 1990 (Lennart Karlsson, personal communication). This gives an overall average of 61.25 mm for migrants. The hand-wing length of resident first-year birds that we measured on the mainland was 60.9 mm in SW Sweden, 61.0 mm in SE Sweden and 61.3 mm in SC Sweden, with an average of 61.0 mm for the pooled mainland sample (
    <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB2" href="#BIO013839TB2">Table 2</a>). Residents in SC Sweden thus had a longer hand-wing than migrants. But the hand-wing in the pooled mainland sample is 0.4% shorter than in migrants (61.0 vs 61.25 mm). By contrast, hand-wing length of island birds exceeds that of mainland residents by up to 4.3% (63.6 on Bornholm vs 61.0 mm on the mainland; 
    <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB2" href="#BIO013839TB2">Table 2</a>).
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The average length of the tarsus was 18.60 mm (s.d. 0.59) in the 180 autumn migrants measured in 1990 (Lennart Karlsson, personal communication). The tarsus length of resident first-year birds that we measured on the mainland was 18.4 mm in SW Sweden, 18.3 mm in SE Sweden and 18.2 mm in SC Sweden (
    <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB3" href="#BIO013839TB3">Table 3</a>), with an overall average of 18.34 mm for mainland birds. So, the tarsus was 1.4% longer in migrants than in mainland residents (18.60 vs 18.34 mm). This is a small difference as compared, for example, with the 6.3% that separate birds on the island of Gotland from mainland residents (19.5 mm vs 18.34; 
    <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB3" href="#BIO013839TB3">Table 3</a>).
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In conclusion, judging by the wing and tarsus measurements of present-day migrants, the islands were not colonized by big immigrants arriving from the mainland without further size change. The size of present-day migrants instead suggests that island colonizers were similar in size to mainland residents and that a size increase came about by local evolutionary adaptation following colonization.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="s3m5" class="sec">
   <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">5.</span>
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Genetic drift</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This is divergence of allele frequencies and associated phenotype traits between separated populations through random processes. It is distinct from any divergence already present due to founder effects. Genetic drift arises from random survival and random allele sampling during reproduction and is more likely to result in accidental loss of alleles the smaller the population. It is distinct from divergence due to local adaptation by natural selection.</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A random change of body size is equally likely in either direction. Therefore, the increased size of 
    <span class="italic">P. ater</span> in all eight places studied has a probability of independent, random occurrence of 0.5
    <span class="sup">8</span>=0.004. In addition to the size changes in the predicted direction, also the magnitude of increase is in accord with predictions. Therefore, genetic drift can be ruled out as a cause for the consistent increase in body size.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="s3m6" class="sec">
   <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">6.</span>
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Inbreeding</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Because populations of 
    <span class="italic">P. ater</span> are smaller on the islands than on the mainland, there is a higher risk of inbreeding on the islands. Inbreeding will tend to increase homozygosity and the expression of recessive deleterious alleles, potentially leading to inbreeding depression and reduced vigour (
    <a rid="BIO013839C24" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C24">Falconer, 1983</a>). If body size were at all affected it would likely shift towards smaller rather than bigger – contrary to the case on the islands. A study of a wild population of another passerine bird, the collared flycatcher 
    <span class="italic">Ficedula albicollis</span>, showed that inbreeding caused a significant reduction in fledgling skeletal size and in post-fledgling juvenile survival (
    <a rid="BIO013839C46" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C46">Kruuk et al., 2002</a>).
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another argument against inbreeding as a cause for the increased size of 
    <span class="italic">P. ater</span> relates to differences in population size between islands. Gotland is the largest island, Anholt the smallest, and the area of coniferous forest on them is 1147 km
    <span class="sup">2</span> and 3.0 km
    <span class="sup">2</span>, respectively (
    <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB6" href="#BIO013839TB6">Table 6</a>). If population size is taken to be proportional to the area of coniferous forest, there would be 400 times more individuals of 
    <span class="italic">P. ater</span> on Gotland than on Anholt. The number is estimated to be about 80,000 on Gotland (
    <a rid="BIO013839C64" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C64">SOF, 1990</a>) so there would be about 200 on Anholt. Another census on Gotland estimated the population density of 
    <span class="italic">P. ater</span> to 90–110 individuals per km
    <span class="sup">2</span> of pine-dominated forest in January-February (Appendix in 
    <a rid="BIO013839C8" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C8">Alatalo et al., 1986</a>). Estimates based on these numbers give similar results, namely 100,000–126,000 individuals on Gotland and 270–330 on Anholt. But although the population is 400 times larger on Gotland than on Anholt, 
    <span class="italic">P. ater</span> is the same size on both islands. 
    <div id="BIO013839TB6" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="table-wrap">
     <span class="label">Table 6.</span>
     <div class="caption">
      <p>
       <span class="bold">Data on isolation, surface area and forest composition for the Scandinavian islands treated in this paper</span>
      </p>
     </div>
     <div xlink:href="biolopen-4-013839-i6" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    </div>
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="s3m7" class="sec">
   <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">7.</span>
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Habitat</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For 
    <span class="italic">P. ater</span>, the absence of 
    <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
    <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> from the islands is the most important habitat difference from the Swedish mainland. Other than that, island habitats are often considered to be impoverished in relation to their mainland counterparts, implying that the abundance and diversity of food items are less on islands (
    <a rid="BIO013839C50" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C50">Lack, 1976</a>). If that were to affect body size, island birds might be smaller than mainland conspecifics due to direct effects on the phenotype during the nestling period, or because of evolutionary adaptation to poor food conditions. But 
    <span class="italic">P. ater</span> is instead larger on the islands.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Island forests might have characteristics that favour a large body size in 
    <span class="italic">P. ater</span>. But forest structure and tree species composition vary considerably between islands and there is no forest feature that is shared by all islands and distinguishes them from the mainland. As an example, the forest is 100% pine 
    <span class="italic">Pinus silvestris</span> on Gotska Sandön, whereas spruce 
    <span class="italic">Picea</span> spp. and 
    <span class="italic">Abies</span> spp. make up 77% of the forests on Bornholm (
    <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB6" href="#BIO013839TB6">Table 6</a>). Yet 
    <span class="italic">P. ater</span> is about the same size on both islands. The possibility that some feature of planted forests on the islands of Bornholm, Anholt and Læsø underlies the large body size is refuted by the fact that 
    <span class="italic">P. ater</span> is as large also on the islands of Gotska Sandön and Gotland, the forests of which are indigenous and natural.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="s3m8" class="sec">
   <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">8.</span>
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the thermoneutral zone of a warm-blooded animal there is no metabolic energy cost for thermoregulation. But below it, metabolic heat must be generated to maintain body temperature. For the same insulation and temperature gradient across the body surface, the rate of heat loss is proportional to body surface area. Among geometrically similar animals, area is proportional to volume
    <span class="sup">2/3</span> so the rate of heat loss from an entire animal increases in proportion to mass
    <span class="sup">2/3</span>. But the rate of heat loss per unit body mass decreases with increasing body size as mass
    <span class="sup">2/3</span>/mass=mass
    <span class="sup">−1/3</span>. So, heat loss per unit body mass is larger the smaller the animal. Selection for reduced mass-specific metabolic costs for thermoregulation in temperate and cold regions therefore favours large body sizes. This is a likely explanation for the intraspecific trend of increasing body size among some warm-blooded vertebrates in colder parts of their distribution range – known as Bergmann's ecogeographical rule (
    <a rid="BIO013839C12" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C12">Bergmann, 1847</a>; 
    <a rid="BIO013839C51" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C51">Mayr, 1965</a>). Another explanation is that the size trend arises because large animals have better fasting ability, which is particularly advantageous in cold and seasonal environments with periods of food scarcity (
    <a rid="BIO013839C54" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C54">Murphy, 1985</a>). Either way, selection for large size must be strongest in winter.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On the islands where 
    <span class="italic">P. ater</span> occurs but 
    <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
    <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> are absent, the winter climate is considerably milder than on the Swedish mainland, except that Gotland is like the mainland (
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F5" href="#BIO013839F5">Fig. 5</a>). If reduction of mass-specific energy costs for thermoregulation in winter were important, mainland birds would be larger than their island conspecifics. But body mass and all linear measurements of 
    <span class="italic">P. ater</span> are smaller on the Swedish mainland than on the islands where 
    <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
    <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> are lacking (
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F1" href="#BIO013839F1">Figs 1</a> and 
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F3" href="#BIO013839F3">3</a>). And on the island of Åland, where all three species coexist, 
    <span class="italic">P. ater</span> is the same small size as on the Swedish mainland even though Åland is the coldest among the islands (except for Gotska Sandön in May) and colder in all seasons than the Swedish mainland (
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F1" href="#BIO013839F1">Figs 1</a>, 
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F3" href="#BIO013839F3">3</a> and 
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F5" href="#BIO013839F5">5</a>). So, climate cannot explain the large size of 
    <span class="italic">P. ater</span> on the islands. 
    <div id="BIO013839F5" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
     <span class="label">Fig. 5.</span>
     <div class="caption">
      <p>
       <span class="bold">Comparisons of mean monthly temperatures at the 12 places where we measured tits.</span> The diagram at top left shows the actual mean monthly temperature in degree centigrade at the reference locality in SW Sweden, averaged over each of two partly overlapping 30-year periods, 1931–1960 and 1951–1980. The other diagrams show local deviations from the mean monthly temperatures recorded in SW Sweden during the period 1931–1960. The vertical bars to the right of the top left diagram show the mean yearly temperature in SW Sweden for the two 30-year periods. Bars to the right of the other diagrams show local deviations from the mean yearly reference temperature in SW Sweden. Temperature was recorded at meteorological stations near the respective sampling place. Data were obtained from The Swedish Meteorological and Hydrological Institute, Norrköping, for the periods 1931–60 and 1951–80; The Danish Meteorological Institute, Copenhagen, for the period 1931–60; and The Finnish Meteorological Institute, Helsinki, regarding the island of Åland for the period 1951–80.
      </p>
     </div>
     <div xlink:href="biolopen-4-013839-g5" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    </div>
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="s3m9" class="sec">
   <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">9.</span>
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Snow cover</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A field study in pine forest 
    <span class="italic">Pinus</span> spp. in the eastern Pyrenees showed that 
    <span class="italic">P. ater</span> foraged mainly in the canopy periphery under snow-free conditions (
    <a rid="BIO013839C14" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C14">Brotons, 1997</a>), just like it does on the Swedish mainland. But when there is snow, the distal branch parts became less accessible. It then shifted to the inner parts of trees, using trunks and thick branches as the main foraging space. This change of foraging sites was associated with a shift to less energy-demanding locomotion modes (
    <a rid="BIO013839C14" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C14">Brotons, 1997</a>).
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Small body size furthers manoeuvrability and cuts costs of the energy-expensive locomotion modes that are required in the canopy periphery. But when snow forces 
    <span class="italic">P. ater</span> to forage on the inner tree parts, where it can use easy locomotion modes, selection for a small body size is relaxed. During the snowy period, the balance between conflicting selection pressures therefore shifts temporarily towards a larger body size (
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F4" href="#BIO013839F4">Fig. 4</a>).
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Swedish mainland and the islands Åland, Gotska Sandön and Gotland have longer snow periods than Bornholm, Sjælland, Anholt and Læsø (
    <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB7" href="#BIO013839TB7">Table 7</a>). A large body size should therefore be more favoured in the former places. But 
    <span class="italic">P. ater</span> is small on the Swedish mainland and the island of Åland, where also 
    <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
    <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> occur, and large on the other islands, all of which lack 
    <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
    <span class="italic">P. montanus</span>. This is contrary to expectations based on the length of the snowy season so differences in snow cover cannot explain the large size of 
    <span class="italic">P. ater</span> on the islands. 
    <div id="BIO013839TB7" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="table-wrap">
     <span class="label">Table 7.</span>
     <div class="caption">
      <p>
       <span class="bold">Distribution of three raptors and one diurnal owl, all of which prey on passerine birds</span>
      </p>
     </div>
     <div xlink:href="biolopen-4-013839-i7" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    </div>
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="s3m10" class="sec">
   <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">10.</span>
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nest holes</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">If nest holes are in short supply, large individuals would get a competitive advantage. At a field site in Belgium, the mean size of 
    <span class="italic">Parus major</span> showed a decreasing trend in the period 1962–1975. This was concomitant with the provision of an abundance of nest boxes. Therefore, the progressive reduction in body size during this period was interpreted to be the result of relaxed competition for nest holes, whereby big individuals lost some of their advantage (
    <a rid="BIO013839C16" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C16">Dhondt et al., 1979</a>). But apart from using tree holes, 
    <span class="italic">P. ater</span> nests readily in holes under tree roots and stones, so it is unlikely that there is a shortage of nest holes either on the mainland or on the islands.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="s3m11" class="sec">
   <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">11.</span>
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Predation</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When tits forage in the canopy periphery, they are exposed to high predation risk, whereas foraging closer to the trunk gives structural protection from raptors and day-hunting owls (
    <a rid="BIO013839C21" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C21">Ekman, 1986</a>; 
    <a rid="BIO013839C47" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C47">Kullberg, 1995</a>; 
    <a rid="BIO013839C25" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C25">Götmark and Post, 1996</a>). Therefore, if predation pressure differs between islands and the mainland, island tits might change their use of foraging zones in trees. And that entails a shift in locomotion mode, which in turn may alter selection on body size.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here follows a review of predation on coniferous forest tits and how predators influence their foraging behaviour and thence the selection on morphology. We focus on raptors and a day-hunting owl whose hunting success depends on where in trees their prey is. Night-hunting owls and nest predators are thus left out.</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A study in SW Sweden found that the sparrowhawk 
    <span class="italic">Accipiter nisus</span> takes few coniferous forest tits in winter but preys more on them in summer (Table 2 in 
    <a rid="BIO013839C20" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C20">Ekman, 1984</a>). Another study, performed in summer in SW Sweden, compared the proportion of different bird species in the diet of 
    <span class="italic">A. nisus</span> with their relative abundance in the local bird community. The hawk took somewhat fewer 
    <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> than expected whereas the proportion of 
    <span class="italic">P. ater</span> and 
    <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> in its diet was much lower than expected from their relative abundance on the hawks' hunting grounds (
    <a rid="BIO013839C25" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C25">Götmark and Post, 1996</a>). 
    <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> and 
    <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> forage in relatively predator-safe tree parts, which may explain their low frequency in the hawk diet. But the still lower predation rate on 
    <span class="italic">P. ater</span> runs counter to expectations based on its use of exposed foraging sites.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The pygmy owl 
    <span class="italic">Glaucidium passerinum</span> hunts by day and is responsible for a considerable proportion of the winter mortality of 
    <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
    <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> in SW Sweden (
    <a rid="BIO013839C23" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C23">Ekman et al., 1981</a>; 
    <a rid="BIO013839C20" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C20">Ekman, 1984</a>, 
    <a rid="BIO013839C21" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C21">1986</a>). In a study area where 
    <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
    <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> were individually colour-banded, the tits were very sedentary in winter and did not leave the territory of their respective flock. Any disappearance from the winter territory in the period November-March was therefore attributed to mortality. Among those that disappeared, 19% of the number of 
    <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 24% of 
    <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> were found – and identified by their rings – in regurgitated pellets in winter roosting holes of 
    <span class="italic">G. passerinum</span> (Table 5 in 
    <a rid="BIO013839C44" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C44">Jansson et al., 1981</a>). These predation rates are probably underestimates because the remains of some prey must have been missed.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When 
    <span class="italic">G. passerinum</span> hunts birds, it strikes from above, launching the attack from perches that are higher up than the focal prey (
    <a rid="BIO013839C47" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C47">Kullberg, 1995</a>). Therefore, predation risk is greater in the low and outer parts of a tree than higher up or in cover from branches and twigs in the inner tree zones (
    <a rid="BIO013839C21" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C21">Ekman, 1986</a>; 
    <a rid="BIO013839C47" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C47">Kullberg, 1995</a>).
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In a study in SW Sweden, the proportion of various bird species in the diet of 
    <span class="italic">G. passerinum</span> was compared with their relative abundance in the local habitat. 
    <span class="italic">P. montanus</span>, which forages near the trunk, was preyed upon about as expected from its relative abundance, whereas 
    <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span>, which forages farther out, was preyed upon more than expected and 
    <span class="italic">P. ater</span> even more so, which is in accord with its use of exposed foraging sites (Table 2 in 
    <a rid="BIO013839C21" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C21">Ekman, 1986</a>). A survey of six field studies in Norway, Sweden, Finland and Russia likewise showed that 
    <span class="italic">G. passerinum</span> preys consistently more heavily on 
    <span class="italic">P. ater</span> and 
    <span class="italic">R. regulus</span> and less on 
    <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
    <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> than expected from their relative abundance in the local bird community (
    <a rid="BIO013839C67" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C67">Suhonen et al., 1993</a>). Empirical results thus confirm that 
    <span class="italic">G. passerinum</span> takes disproportionately many 
    <span class="italic">P. ater</span> – as expected in view of its exposed foraging sites – whereas 
    <span class="italic">A. nisus</span> unexpectedly takes disproportionately few 
    <span class="italic">P. ater</span> (see above; 
    <a rid="BIO013839C25" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C25">Götmark and Post, 1996</a>).
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Predation by 
    <span class="italic">G. passerinum</span> has been shown to determine the choice of foraging sites by tits to various extents depending on the availability of small rodents, which are preferred prey of the owl. In one winter when rodent populations were at a peak level in Finland, voles and shrews 
    <span class="italic">Sorex</span> spp. together made up 98% and birds 2% of the diet of 
    <span class="italic">G. passerinum</span>. In the next winter, the rodent populations had crashed and rodent trap-catches dropped to 0.6% of the value in the previous winter, from 32 to 0.2 captured individuals per 100 trap-nights. At this rodent population low, 
    <span class="italic">G. passerinum</span> switched to eating birds, after which 40% of its winter diet consisted of rodents and shrews while birds made up 60%. Following this huge shift in the owl's diet, 
    <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
    <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> responded behaviourally and foraged less on the outer, exposed regions of spruce trees and more often on the inner parts of branches (
    <a rid="BIO013839C65" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C65">Suhonen, 1993</a>).
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
    <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> are claimed to be socially dominant over 
    <span class="italic">P. ater</span> and to exclude it from their foraging zones, which leaves it to forage in the risky outer canopy (
    <a rid="BIO013839C41" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C41">Hogstad, 1978</a>; 
    <a rid="BIO013839C6" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C6">Alatalo and Moreno, 1987</a>; 
    <a rid="BIO013839C67" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C67">Suhonen et al., 1993</a>; 
    <a rid="BIO013839C65" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C65">Suhonen, 1993</a>). Rank order has been observed to determine feeding site partitioning also at the intraspecific level. In 
    <span class="italic">P. montanus</span>, dominant adults expel subordinate first-year birds from the upper tree regions in winter, leaving them to forage lower in trees where they are more vulnerable to predation (
    <a rid="BIO013839C22" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C22">Ekman and Askenmo, 1984</a>).
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB7" href="#BIO013839TB7">Table 7</a> shows the distribution of potential predators on 
    <span class="italic">P. ater</span>. The hobby 
    <span class="italic">Falco subbuteo</span> is specialised on open-air hunting and the goshawk 
    <span class="italic">Accipiter gentilis</span> mostly takes large prey, so both have little impact on tits. 
    <span class="italic">A. nisus</span> is a breeding resident on the mainland of Denmark, Norway and Sweden and on all islands except Anholt. 
    <span class="italic">G. passerinum</span> is a breeding resident on the mainland of Norway, Sweden and Finland. It has also been recorded on the island of Åland (
    <a rid="BIO013839C37" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C37">Haila, 1981</a>; 
    <a rid="BIO013839C48" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C48">Kullberg and Ekman, 2000</a>), but the population density is low there and its breeding status uncertain (The Finnish Breeding Bird Atlas). It is absent from all the other islands as well as from the Danish mainland Jylland.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The islands have different numbers of resident raptor species (
    <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB7" href="#BIO013839TB7">Table 7</a>). There are three on Gotska Sandön and Gotland, two on Sjælland, one on Bornholm and Læsø and none on Anholt. And yet, 
    <span class="italic">P. ater</span> has increased in size to a similar extent on all six islands (
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F1" href="#BIO013839F1">Figs 1</a> and 
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F3" href="#BIO013839F3">3</a>; 
    <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB2" href="#BIO013839TB2">Tables 2</a>-
    <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB4" href="#BIO013839TB4">4</a>). So, the large size of 
    <span class="italic">P. ater</span> on the islands is not driven by predation. But its body size on the mainland might be influenced indirectly by predators in so far as they affect niche partitioning among tits to the effect that 
    <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
    <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> forage in the safer inner tree regions. By force of their putative dominance, they may expel 
    <span class="italic">P. ater</span> from the inner parts, leaving it to forage in the exposed tree periphery (
    <a rid="BIO013839C41" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C41">Hogstad, 1978</a>; 
    <a rid="BIO013839C6" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C6">Alatalo and Moreno, 1987</a>; 
    <a rid="BIO013839C67" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C67">Suhonen et al., 1993</a>; 
    <a rid="BIO013839C65" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C65">Suhonen, 1993</a>). Once there, it is subject to selection for agility and a small body size.
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
</sec>
