<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s3m" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Alternative explanations</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We think that the genetically determined increase in body size of 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> on the islands is the result of adaptive evolution in response to the absence of competition from 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span>. But the large size may have come about for other reasons. 
  <a rid="BIO013839C61" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C61">Platt (1964)</a> forcefully advocated the ‘method of multiple working hypotheses', placing focus on finding proof for exclusion. Here, we test 11 alternative hypotheses against available evidence. They are treated in turn below and can all be eliminated.
 </p>
 <sec id="s3m1" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1.</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Relict island populations reflecting historically widespread ancestral characteristics</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> is strictly bound to coniferous forest. But the four islands Bornholm, Sjælland, Anholt and Læsø were not planted with conifers until after 1850. In these recently founded populations, 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> is equally large as conspecifics on Gotska Sandön and Gotland, both of which have had primeval coniferous forests since long-ago.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s3m2" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Island 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> derived from other populations than those that colonized the Swedish mainland
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In view of the large geographical separation between the islands and their location to the east, south and west of the Swedish mainland, it is unlikely that the islands and the Swedish mainland got their populations from different sources. But most important, there is almost no variation in body size among continental 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> over the northern Palearctic (
   <a rid="BIO013839C62" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C62">Snow, 1954</a>, 
   <a rid="BIO013839C63" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C63">1955</a>), so there is no nearby place from which large birds could have been recruited.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s3m3" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Geographical trends or clinal variation in body size</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> has a continuous distribution across the northern Palearctic and shows great uniformity in body dimensions with little clinal variation (
   <a rid="BIO013839C62" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C62">Snow, 1954</a>, 
   <a rid="BIO013839C63" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C63">1955</a>). So there is no geographical trend that could explain the size difference between island and mainland tits.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s3m4" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Founder effect</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This refers to the reduction of genetic variation that occurs when a population is established by a small number of pioneers. When there are few individuals in a colonizing group, random processes increase the likelihood that the group brings with it a skewed gene sample that is not representative of the parent population. This may contribute to evolutionary divergence.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> is sedentary the whole year round but performs irruptive migrations at irregular intervals. The islands were most likely colonized by mainland birds that took part in such irruptions. But the probability is only 0.5
   <span class="sup">8</span>=0.004 that all eight places, from which one or two congeners are absent, were colonized by larger than average-sized mainland birds by chance alone. So random founder events cannot account for the large size of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> in all eight places.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We will now look at the size of present-day migrants of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater.</span> Judging by observations during an autumn irruption in 1990, migrants consist almost exclusively of juveniles. On that occasion, 716 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> were netted and ringed at Falsterbo Bird Observatory and all of them were first-year birds (Lennart Karlsson, personal communication).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The hand-wing and the tarsus of first-year birds on southbound autumn migration were measured by staff ornithologists at the Falsterbo Bird Observatory, who used the measuring technique described in the methods section herein. Hand-wing length of migrants was remarkably similar between samples in different years. The average length was 61.26 mm (s.d. 1.62) for 273 migrating 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> measured in September and October 1982-1986 (Göran Walinder, personal communication) and 61.23 mm (s.d. 1.51) for 180 birds measured in September and October 1990 (Lennart Karlsson, personal communication). This gives an overall average of 61.25 mm for migrants. The hand-wing length of resident first-year birds that we measured on the mainland was 60.9 mm in SW Sweden, 61.0 mm in SE Sweden and 61.3 mm in SC Sweden, with an average of 61.0 mm for the pooled mainland sample (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB2" href="#BIO013839TB2">Table 2</a>). Residents in SC Sweden thus had a longer hand-wing than migrants. But the hand-wing in the pooled mainland sample is 0.4% shorter than in migrants (61.0 vs 61.25 mm). By contrast, hand-wing length of island birds exceeds that of mainland residents by up to 4.3% (63.6 on Bornholm vs 61.0 mm on the mainland; 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB2" href="#BIO013839TB2">Table 2</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The average length of the tarsus was 18.60 mm (s.d. 0.59) in the 180 autumn migrants measured in 1990 (Lennart Karlsson, personal communication). The tarsus length of resident first-year birds that we measured on the mainland was 18.4 mm in SW Sweden, 18.3 mm in SE Sweden and 18.2 mm in SC Sweden (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB3" href="#BIO013839TB3">Table 3</a>), with an overall average of 18.34 mm for mainland birds. So, the tarsus was 1.4% longer in migrants than in mainland residents (18.60 vs 18.34 mm). This is a small difference as compared, for example, with the 6.3% that separate birds on the island of Gotland from mainland residents (19.5 mm vs 18.34; 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB3" href="#BIO013839TB3">Table 3</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In conclusion, judging by the wing and tarsus measurements of present-day migrants, the islands were not colonized by big immigrants arriving from the mainland without further size change. The size of present-day migrants instead suggests that island colonizers were similar in size to mainland residents and that a size increase came about by local evolutionary adaptation following colonization.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s3m5" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">5.</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Genetic drift</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This is divergence of allele frequencies and associated phenotype traits between separated populations through random processes. It is distinct from any divergence already present due to founder effects. Genetic drift arises from random survival and random allele sampling during reproduction and is more likely to result in accidental loss of alleles the smaller the population. It is distinct from divergence due to local adaptation by natural selection.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A random change of body size is equally likely in either direction. Therefore, the increased size of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> in all eight places studied has a probability of independent, random occurrence of 0.5
   <span class="sup">8</span>=0.004. In addition to the size changes in the predicted direction, also the magnitude of increase is in accord with predictions. Therefore, genetic drift can be ruled out as a cause for the consistent increase in body size.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s3m6" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">6.</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Inbreeding</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Because populations of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> are smaller on the islands than on the mainland, there is a higher risk of inbreeding on the islands. Inbreeding will tend to increase homozygosity and the expression of recessive deleterious alleles, potentially leading to inbreeding depression and reduced vigour (
   <a rid="BIO013839C24" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C24">Falconer, 1983</a>). If body size were at all affected it would likely shift towards smaller rather than bigger – contrary to the case on the islands. A study of a wild population of another passerine bird, the collared flycatcher 
   <span class="italic">Ficedula albicollis</span>, showed that inbreeding caused a significant reduction in fledgling skeletal size and in post-fledgling juvenile survival (
   <a rid="BIO013839C46" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C46">Kruuk et al., 2002</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another argument against inbreeding as a cause for the increased size of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> relates to differences in population size between islands. Gotland is the largest island, Anholt the smallest, and the area of coniferous forest on them is 1147 km
   <span class="sup">2</span> and 3.0 km
   <span class="sup">2</span>, respectively (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB6" href="#BIO013839TB6">Table 6</a>). If population size is taken to be proportional to the area of coniferous forest, there would be 400 times more individuals of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> on Gotland than on Anholt. The number is estimated to be about 80,000 on Gotland (
   <a rid="BIO013839C64" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C64">SOF, 1990</a>) so there would be about 200 on Anholt. Another census on Gotland estimated the population density of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> to 90–110 individuals per km
   <span class="sup">2</span> of pine-dominated forest in January-February (Appendix in 
   <a rid="BIO013839C8" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C8">Alatalo et al., 1986</a>). Estimates based on these numbers give similar results, namely 100,000–126,000 individuals on Gotland and 270–330 on Anholt. But although the population is 400 times larger on Gotland than on Anholt, 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> is the same size on both islands. 
   <div id="BIO013839TB6" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="table-wrap">
    <span class="label">Table 6.</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>
      <span class="bold">Data on isolation, surface area and forest composition for the Scandinavian islands treated in this paper</span>
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="biolopen-4-013839-i6" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s3m7" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">7.</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Habitat</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span>, the absence of 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> from the islands is the most important habitat difference from the Swedish mainland. Other than that, island habitats are often considered to be impoverished in relation to their mainland counterparts, implying that the abundance and diversity of food items are less on islands (
   <a rid="BIO013839C50" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C50">Lack, 1976</a>). If that were to affect body size, island birds might be smaller than mainland conspecifics due to direct effects on the phenotype during the nestling period, or because of evolutionary adaptation to poor food conditions. But 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> is instead larger on the islands.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Island forests might have characteristics that favour a large body size in 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span>. But forest structure and tree species composition vary considerably between islands and there is no forest feature that is shared by all islands and distinguishes them from the mainland. As an example, the forest is 100% pine 
   <span class="italic">Pinus silvestris</span> on Gotska Sandön, whereas spruce 
   <span class="italic">Picea</span> spp. and 
   <span class="italic">Abies</span> spp. make up 77% of the forests on Bornholm (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB6" href="#BIO013839TB6">Table 6</a>). Yet 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> is about the same size on both islands. The possibility that some feature of planted forests on the islands of Bornholm, Anholt and Læsø underlies the large body size is refuted by the fact that 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> is as large also on the islands of Gotska Sandön and Gotland, the forests of which are indigenous and natural.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s3m8" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">8.</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the thermoneutral zone of a warm-blooded animal there is no metabolic energy cost for thermoregulation. But below it, metabolic heat must be generated to maintain body temperature. For the same insulation and temperature gradient across the body surface, the rate of heat loss is proportional to body surface area. Among geometrically similar animals, area is proportional to volume
   <span class="sup">2/3</span> so the rate of heat loss from an entire animal increases in proportion to mass
   <span class="sup">2/3</span>. But the rate of heat loss per unit body mass decreases with increasing body size as mass
   <span class="sup">2/3</span>/mass=mass
   <span class="sup">−1/3</span>. So, heat loss per unit body mass is larger the smaller the animal. Selection for reduced mass-specific metabolic costs for thermoregulation in temperate and cold regions therefore favours large body sizes. This is a likely explanation for the intraspecific trend of increasing body size among some warm-blooded vertebrates in colder parts of their distribution range – known as Bergmann's ecogeographical rule (
   <a rid="BIO013839C12" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C12">Bergmann, 1847</a>; 
   <a rid="BIO013839C51" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C51">Mayr, 1965</a>). Another explanation is that the size trend arises because large animals have better fasting ability, which is particularly advantageous in cold and seasonal environments with periods of food scarcity (
   <a rid="BIO013839C54" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C54">Murphy, 1985</a>). Either way, selection for large size must be strongest in winter.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On the islands where 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> occurs but 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> are absent, the winter climate is considerably milder than on the Swedish mainland, except that Gotland is like the mainland (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F5" href="#BIO013839F5">Fig. 5</a>). If reduction of mass-specific energy costs for thermoregulation in winter were important, mainland birds would be larger than their island conspecifics. But body mass and all linear measurements of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> are smaller on the Swedish mainland than on the islands where 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> are lacking (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F1" href="#BIO013839F1">Figs 1</a> and 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F3" href="#BIO013839F3">3</a>). And on the island of Åland, where all three species coexist, 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> is the same small size as on the Swedish mainland even though Åland is the coldest among the islands (except for Gotska Sandön in May) and colder in all seasons than the Swedish mainland (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F1" href="#BIO013839F1">Figs 1</a>, 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F3" href="#BIO013839F3">3</a> and 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F5" href="#BIO013839F5">5</a>). So, climate cannot explain the large size of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> on the islands. 
   <div id="BIO013839F5" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 5.</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>
      <span class="bold">Comparisons of mean monthly temperatures at the 12 places where we measured tits.</span> The diagram at top left shows the actual mean monthly temperature in degree centigrade at the reference locality in SW Sweden, averaged over each of two partly overlapping 30-year periods, 1931–1960 and 1951–1980. The other diagrams show local deviations from the mean monthly temperatures recorded in SW Sweden during the period 1931–1960. The vertical bars to the right of the top left diagram show the mean yearly temperature in SW Sweden for the two 30-year periods. Bars to the right of the other diagrams show local deviations from the mean yearly reference temperature in SW Sweden. Temperature was recorded at meteorological stations near the respective sampling place. Data were obtained from The Swedish Meteorological and Hydrological Institute, Norrköping, for the periods 1931–60 and 1951–80; The Danish Meteorological Institute, Copenhagen, for the period 1931–60; and The Finnish Meteorological Institute, Helsinki, regarding the island of Åland for the period 1951–80.
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="biolopen-4-013839-g5" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s3m9" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">9.</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Snow cover</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A field study in pine forest 
   <span class="italic">Pinus</span> spp. in the eastern Pyrenees showed that 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> foraged mainly in the canopy periphery under snow-free conditions (
   <a rid="BIO013839C14" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C14">Brotons, 1997</a>), just like it does on the Swedish mainland. But when there is snow, the distal branch parts became less accessible. It then shifted to the inner parts of trees, using trunks and thick branches as the main foraging space. This change of foraging sites was associated with a shift to less energy-demanding locomotion modes (
   <a rid="BIO013839C14" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C14">Brotons, 1997</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Small body size furthers manoeuvrability and cuts costs of the energy-expensive locomotion modes that are required in the canopy periphery. But when snow forces 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> to forage on the inner tree parts, where it can use easy locomotion modes, selection for a small body size is relaxed. During the snowy period, the balance between conflicting selection pressures therefore shifts temporarily towards a larger body size (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F4" href="#BIO013839F4">Fig. 4</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Swedish mainland and the islands Åland, Gotska Sandön and Gotland have longer snow periods than Bornholm, Sjælland, Anholt and Læsø (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB7" href="#BIO013839TB7">Table 7</a>). A large body size should therefore be more favoured in the former places. But 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> is small on the Swedish mainland and the island of Åland, where also 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> occur, and large on the other islands, all of which lack 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span>. This is contrary to expectations based on the length of the snowy season so differences in snow cover cannot explain the large size of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> on the islands. 
   <div id="BIO013839TB7" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="table-wrap">
    <span class="label">Table 7.</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>
      <span class="bold">Distribution of three raptors and one diurnal owl, all of which prey on passerine birds</span>
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="biolopen-4-013839-i7" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s3m10" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">10.</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nest holes</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">If nest holes are in short supply, large individuals would get a competitive advantage. At a field site in Belgium, the mean size of 
   <span class="italic">Parus major</span> showed a decreasing trend in the period 1962–1975. This was concomitant with the provision of an abundance of nest boxes. Therefore, the progressive reduction in body size during this period was interpreted to be the result of relaxed competition for nest holes, whereby big individuals lost some of their advantage (
   <a rid="BIO013839C16" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C16">Dhondt et al., 1979</a>). But apart from using tree holes, 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> nests readily in holes under tree roots and stones, so it is unlikely that there is a shortage of nest holes either on the mainland or on the islands.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s3m11" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">11.</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Predation</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When tits forage in the canopy periphery, they are exposed to high predation risk, whereas foraging closer to the trunk gives structural protection from raptors and day-hunting owls (
   <a rid="BIO013839C21" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C21">Ekman, 1986</a>; 
   <a rid="BIO013839C47" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C47">Kullberg, 1995</a>; 
   <a rid="BIO013839C25" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C25">Götmark and Post, 1996</a>). Therefore, if predation pressure differs between islands and the mainland, island tits might change their use of foraging zones in trees. And that entails a shift in locomotion mode, which in turn may alter selection on body size.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here follows a review of predation on coniferous forest tits and how predators influence their foraging behaviour and thence the selection on morphology. We focus on raptors and a day-hunting owl whose hunting success depends on where in trees their prey is. Night-hunting owls and nest predators are thus left out.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A study in SW Sweden found that the sparrowhawk 
   <span class="italic">Accipiter nisus</span> takes few coniferous forest tits in winter but preys more on them in summer (Table 2 in 
   <a rid="BIO013839C20" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C20">Ekman, 1984</a>). Another study, performed in summer in SW Sweden, compared the proportion of different bird species in the diet of 
   <span class="italic">A. nisus</span> with their relative abundance in the local bird community. The hawk took somewhat fewer 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> than expected whereas the proportion of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> in its diet was much lower than expected from their relative abundance on the hawks' hunting grounds (
   <a rid="BIO013839C25" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C25">Götmark and Post, 1996</a>). 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> forage in relatively predator-safe tree parts, which may explain their low frequency in the hawk diet. But the still lower predation rate on 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> runs counter to expectations based on its use of exposed foraging sites.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The pygmy owl 
   <span class="italic">Glaucidium passerinum</span> hunts by day and is responsible for a considerable proportion of the winter mortality of 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> in SW Sweden (
   <a rid="BIO013839C23" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C23">Ekman et al., 1981</a>; 
   <a rid="BIO013839C20" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C20">Ekman, 1984</a>, 
   <a rid="BIO013839C21" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C21">1986</a>). In a study area where 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> were individually colour-banded, the tits were very sedentary in winter and did not leave the territory of their respective flock. Any disappearance from the winter territory in the period November-March was therefore attributed to mortality. Among those that disappeared, 19% of the number of 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 24% of 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> were found – and identified by their rings – in regurgitated pellets in winter roosting holes of 
   <span class="italic">G. passerinum</span> (Table 5 in 
   <a rid="BIO013839C44" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C44">Jansson et al., 1981</a>). These predation rates are probably underestimates because the remains of some prey must have been missed.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When 
   <span class="italic">G. passerinum</span> hunts birds, it strikes from above, launching the attack from perches that are higher up than the focal prey (
   <a rid="BIO013839C47" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C47">Kullberg, 1995</a>). Therefore, predation risk is greater in the low and outer parts of a tree than higher up or in cover from branches and twigs in the inner tree zones (
   <a rid="BIO013839C21" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C21">Ekman, 1986</a>; 
   <a rid="BIO013839C47" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C47">Kullberg, 1995</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In a study in SW Sweden, the proportion of various bird species in the diet of 
   <span class="italic">G. passerinum</span> was compared with their relative abundance in the local habitat. 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span>, which forages near the trunk, was preyed upon about as expected from its relative abundance, whereas 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span>, which forages farther out, was preyed upon more than expected and 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> even more so, which is in accord with its use of exposed foraging sites (Table 2 in 
   <a rid="BIO013839C21" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C21">Ekman, 1986</a>). A survey of six field studies in Norway, Sweden, Finland and Russia likewise showed that 
   <span class="italic">G. passerinum</span> preys consistently more heavily on 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> and 
   <span class="italic">R. regulus</span> and less on 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> than expected from their relative abundance in the local bird community (
   <a rid="BIO013839C67" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C67">Suhonen et al., 1993</a>). Empirical results thus confirm that 
   <span class="italic">G. passerinum</span> takes disproportionately many 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> – as expected in view of its exposed foraging sites – whereas 
   <span class="italic">A. nisus</span> unexpectedly takes disproportionately few 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> (see above; 
   <a rid="BIO013839C25" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C25">Götmark and Post, 1996</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Predation by 
   <span class="italic">G. passerinum</span> has been shown to determine the choice of foraging sites by tits to various extents depending on the availability of small rodents, which are preferred prey of the owl. In one winter when rodent populations were at a peak level in Finland, voles and shrews 
   <span class="italic">Sorex</span> spp. together made up 98% and birds 2% of the diet of 
   <span class="italic">G. passerinum</span>. In the next winter, the rodent populations had crashed and rodent trap-catches dropped to 0.6% of the value in the previous winter, from 32 to 0.2 captured individuals per 100 trap-nights. At this rodent population low, 
   <span class="italic">G. passerinum</span> switched to eating birds, after which 40% of its winter diet consisted of rodents and shrews while birds made up 60%. Following this huge shift in the owl's diet, 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> responded behaviourally and foraged less on the outer, exposed regions of spruce trees and more often on the inner parts of branches (
   <a rid="BIO013839C65" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C65">Suhonen, 1993</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> are claimed to be socially dominant over 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> and to exclude it from their foraging zones, which leaves it to forage in the risky outer canopy (
   <a rid="BIO013839C41" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C41">Hogstad, 1978</a>; 
   <a rid="BIO013839C6" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C6">Alatalo and Moreno, 1987</a>; 
   <a rid="BIO013839C67" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C67">Suhonen et al., 1993</a>; 
   <a rid="BIO013839C65" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C65">Suhonen, 1993</a>). Rank order has been observed to determine feeding site partitioning also at the intraspecific level. In 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span>, dominant adults expel subordinate first-year birds from the upper tree regions in winter, leaving them to forage lower in trees where they are more vulnerable to predation (
   <a rid="BIO013839C22" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C22">Ekman and Askenmo, 1984</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB7" href="#BIO013839TB7">Table 7</a> shows the distribution of potential predators on 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span>. The hobby 
   <span class="italic">Falco subbuteo</span> is specialised on open-air hunting and the goshawk 
   <span class="italic">Accipiter gentilis</span> mostly takes large prey, so both have little impact on tits. 
   <span class="italic">A. nisus</span> is a breeding resident on the mainland of Denmark, Norway and Sweden and on all islands except Anholt. 
   <span class="italic">G. passerinum</span> is a breeding resident on the mainland of Norway, Sweden and Finland. It has also been recorded on the island of Åland (
   <a rid="BIO013839C37" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C37">Haila, 1981</a>; 
   <a rid="BIO013839C48" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C48">Kullberg and Ekman, 2000</a>), but the population density is low there and its breeding status uncertain (The Finnish Breeding Bird Atlas). It is absent from all the other islands as well as from the Danish mainland Jylland.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The islands have different numbers of resident raptor species (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB7" href="#BIO013839TB7">Table 7</a>). There are three on Gotska Sandön and Gotland, two on Sjælland, one on Bornholm and Læsø and none on Anholt. And yet, 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> has increased in size to a similar extent on all six islands (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F1" href="#BIO013839F1">Figs 1</a> and 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F3" href="#BIO013839F3">3</a>; 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB2" href="#BIO013839TB2">Tables 2</a>-
   <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB4" href="#BIO013839TB4">4</a>). So, the large size of 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> on the islands is not driven by predation. But its body size on the mainland might be influenced indirectly by predators in so far as they affect niche partitioning among tits to the effect that 
   <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> forage in the safer inner tree regions. By force of their putative dominance, they may expel 
   <span class="italic">P. ater</span> from the inner parts, leaving it to forage in the exposed tree periphery (
   <a rid="BIO013839C41" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C41">Hogstad, 1978</a>; 
   <a rid="BIO013839C6" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C6">Alatalo and Moreno, 1987</a>; 
   <a rid="BIO013839C67" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C67">Suhonen et al., 1993</a>; 
   <a rid="BIO013839C65" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C65">Suhonen, 1993</a>). Once there, it is subject to selection for agility and a small body size.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
