<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s3l" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Interspecific competition among 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span>, 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">If the large body size of 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> has evolved on the islands because there is no competition from 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span>, then its small size in sympatry with them on the mainland must be due to their presence. Based on the literature, we review evidence for interspecific competition.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span>, 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> have similar diet both regarding food items cached in autumn for consumption in winter, as documented in a large study in Norway (
  <a rid="BIO013839C33" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C33">Haftorn, 1956c</a>), and food given to nestlings, as recorded in SW Sweden by automatic photography of parents bringing food to their young (
  <a rid="BIO013839C72" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C72">von Brömssen and Jansson, 1975</a>). And all three species join up in mixed-species foraging flocks in winter, which is conducive to interspecific competition.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The way population density is regulated has been extensively studied in 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> but not in 
  <span class="italic">P. ater.</span> Because the ecology is so similar between these three species, population regulation is probably similar for 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span>. Therefore, we refer to results for 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> in the following. We emphasize field studies done in the Nordic countries because their climate and forest habitat are similar to those of the islands and therefore present similar conditions for population regulation.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Predation by tits causes considerable reduction of their food in winter. In two field experiments in SW Sweden, branches of 
  <span class="italic">Picea abies</span> were enclosed with nets to prevent birds from foraging on them throughout the winter. In one of the experiments, run in the period October to March, the exclosure reduced spider mortality from 57% on unprotected branches to 34% on protected branches, suggesting that birds consumed 23% of the spiders present in autumn (
  <a rid="BIO013839C11" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C11">Askenmo et al., 1977</a>). In the other experiment, the exclosure reduced overwinter mortality of small spiders from 90% on unprotected branches to 75% on protected, indicating that birds consumed 15% of the small spiders present in autumn. For large spiders, mortality was reduced from 85% on unprotected branches to 46% on protected, indicating that birds consumed 39% of the large spiders present in autumn (Table 2 in 
  <a rid="BIO013839C27" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C27">Gunnarsson, 1983</a>). The higher disappearance rate of spiders from unprotected branches was attributed to predation by 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span>, 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span>, 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">R. regulus</span>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Because birds themselves reduce prey density, bird mortality due to starvation acts in a density-dependent way. It has been shown experimentally that energy stress is the main cause of winter mortality among 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span>. After experimental provisioning of extra food in autumn and winter in SW Sweden, winter survival almost doubled during the period November to March, from 39% to 76% for 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and from 45% to 82% for 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> (Table 4 in 
  <a rid="BIO013839C44" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C44">Jansson et al., 1981</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">At the same study site in SW Sweden, population density of 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> was experimentally reduced locally in autumn. For 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span>, winter survival in the low-density experimental population increased to 100% whereas survival rate was 68% by April in a normal-density control population. This outcome demonstrates that winter losses are density-dependent and that there is significant intraspecific competition between flock members (
  <a rid="BIO013839C23" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C23">Ekman et al., 1981</a>). Another study in SW Sweden, based on year-round monitoring of a population of marked individuals of 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> over six years, showed that survival is strongly density-dependent among first-year birds in late winter. Mortality in winter is driven by competition for non-renewable food (
  <a rid="BIO013839C20" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C20">Ekman, 1984</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Parus cristatus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> are considered to be dominant over 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> and to monopolize their species-characteristic feeding sites in the interior of tree canopies, thus preventing 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> from foraging there (
  <a rid="BIO013839C41" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C41">Hogstad, 1978</a>; 
  <a rid="BIO013839C6" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C6">Alatalo and Moreno, 1987</a>; 
  <a rid="BIO013839C66" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C66">Suhonen et al., 1992</a>
  <a rid="BIO013839C67" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C67">, 1993</a>; 
  <a rid="BIO013839C65" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C65">Suhonen, 1993</a>; but see 
  <a rid="BIO013839C35" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C35">Haftorn, 1993</a>). There is also some overlap in feeding sites between 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span>, 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span>, so in the shared space they reduce each other's food resources directly.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The clearest demonstration that 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> restrict the foraging niche of 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> comes from the fact that 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> extends it foraging space in their absence. On the mainland, where all three coexist, 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> forages predominantly on the peripheral twigs and needles, but in the absence of 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> it shifts to foraging also on the middle and basal branch parts and the trunk, places that are normally used by the absentees (see review in the foregoing section on selection for a large body size).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Regulus regulus</span> occurs together with 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> in coniferous forests on the Swedish mainland as well as on all the islands, so there is no mainland-island difference in competition between the two (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB1" href="#BIO013839TB1">Table 1</a>). They use much the same foraging zones in trees (
  <a rid="BIO013839C33" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C33">Haftorn, 1956c</a>) and overlap in diet. 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> eats arthropods and seeds (
  <a rid="BIO013839C33" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C33">Haftorn, 1956c</a>) whereas 
  <span class="italic">R. regulus</span> only eats arthropods all year round, including very small items like Collembola (
  <a rid="BIO013839C70" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C70">Thaler, 1973</a>; 
  <a rid="BIO013839C42" ref-type="bibr" href="#BIO013839C42">Hogstad, 1984</a>). 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> is socially dominant over 
  <span class="italic">R. regulus</span> and often takes over its feeding site by supplanting attacks (R.Å.N., personal observation). 
  <span class="italic">Certhia familiaris</span> occurs in coniferous forest on the mainland and on all the islands except Anholt and Læsø (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="BIO013839TB1" href="#BIO013839TB1">Table 1</a>). It forages almost entirely on tree trunks and therefore interferes little with 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In conclusion, food is a limiting factor that brings about population regulation in winter. The process is density-dependent because the rate of food depletion increases with increasing population density and feeds back to the individual in terms of food scarcity. Winter is also the season when 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> occurs together with 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> in mixed-species foraging flocks, which is conducive to interspecific competition. Regardless of whether 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> restrict the foraging space of 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> physically, or if they reduce food in their foraging zones to levels at which it is not profitable for 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> to forage, they compete by reducing food accessibility for it. In addition, they reduce food for 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> directly in the overlapping parts of their respective foraging space. Since winter is the season when population regulation mostly takes place, it is also then that selection on behaviour and morphology is the strongest. Because 
  <span class="italic">P. cristatus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">P. montanus</span> cause 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> to forage predominantly in the tree periphery during winter, interspecific competition maintains selection for a small body size of 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span> in sympatry on the mainland (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F4" href="#BIO013839F4">Fig. 4</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
