<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s5a" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Measurements taken</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We weighed birds with a 30 g Pesola spring balance, read to the nearest 0.1 g, and used rulers to measure wing span to the nearest 1 mm and hand wing and tail to the nearest 0.5 mm. The other linear measurements were taken with a plastic dial calliper rule, read to the nearest 0.1 mm. Wing area was measured from photographs taken of birds with outstretched wings as described below. We projected an enlarged image onto paper, draw the wing outline and measured wing area with a polar compensating planimeter. We made three planimeter tracings of the same drawing of each individual and calculated the average area.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We collaborated on all fieldwork. But to eliminate variation due to possible differences in measuring technique, one of us made all measurements in the field whereas the other measured all wing areas from photographs. Whenever uncertainty arose how to round off a reading, we counteracted unintentional bias by consistently rounding in the opposite direction to that expected from our working hypothesis.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Body mass</span>: We weighed most birds within one hour of capture. But in a few cases, weighing was delayed for up to two hours due to the handling of a large catch.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Wing area</span>: Wing area is the area of both wings and the portion of body in between as projected onto the wing-chord plane. In flight, the reduced pressure over the wings is retained over the body portion between the wings so it is part of the lift-producing area. We measured wing areas from photographs taken in dorsal view, perpendicular to the wing chord plane, of birds held against a board with a scale. We held the wings by the wrist and extended them moderately as they are judged to be in mid-downstroke. We also rotated the handwings forward to straighten and align the leading edges of the wings and spread the flight feathers evenly but without disrupting their natural backward and ventral curvature.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">(Wing area)
   <span class="sup">0.5</span>
  </span>: Among geometrically similar animals, areas increase as a representative length squared, so areas in different sized animals cannot be directly compared with linear measurements. Therefore, we calculated the square root of the wing area to obtain another linear measure of wing size – in effect, the length of the side of a quadrate with the same area as the wings. The square root of wing area is not listed in any table and is used only to calculate a compound measure of wing linear size for the diagrams in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="BIO013839F1" href="#BIO013839F1">Fig. 1</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Wing span</span>: The bird was placed on its back and the wings were stretched moderately as described under ‘wing area’. Distance was measured from wingtip to wingtip without disrupting the natural ventral and backward curvature of the feathers that form the wingtip.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Hand-wing length</span>: Distance from the wing-bend at the wrist to the wingtip. The wing was folded and the ruler was applied to the wing's ventral side with the bent wrist pressed against the ruler's zero-stop. The maximum hand-wing length was obtained by pressing the primary feathers flat against the ruler to eliminate their ventral curvature and by gently pushing backwards on the wing's leading edge near the alula and moving the feather tips forward to eliminate the lateral curvature.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Wing loading</span>: We calculated wing loading as body weight in Newton divided by wing area in m
  <span class="sup">2</span>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Wing aspect ratio</span>: It is the ratio 
  <span class="italic">B</span>/
  <span class="italic">c</span> between wingspan 
  <span class="italic">B</span> and the mean wing chord 
  <span class="italic">c</span>, and was calculated as wing span squared divided by wing area 
  <span class="italic">S</span>; 
  <span class="italic">B</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span>/
  <span class="italic">S</span>=
  <span class="italic">B</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span>/(
  <span class="italic">B</span>×
  <span class="italic">c</span>)=
  <span class="italic">B</span>/
  <span class="italic">c</span>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Tail length</span>: Distance from root to tip of the tail while it is folded and straightened along the ruler. The ruler's bevelled edge was placed between the tail feathers and the under tail-coverts and pushed gently against the roots of the two central tail feathers.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Tibiotarsus length</span>: Distance from the top of the knee to the ventral side of the tarsometatarsus at the joint between tibiotarsus and tarsometatarsus when the knee and the tibiotarsus-tarsometatarsus joints are set at 90°. Care was taken to align the measurement with the long axis of the tibiotarsus.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Tarsus (=tarsometatarsus) ‘short’ length</span>: Distance from the notch underneath the tibiotarsus-tarsometatarsus joint, when it is bent 90°, to the outer edge of the last complete scale on the dorsal side of tarsomtetatarsus, just before the toes.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Tarsus (=tarsometatarsus) ‘long’ length</span>: Distance from the posterior surface of the tibiotarsus at the tibiotarsus-tarsometatarsus joint, when it is bent 90°, to the dorsal side of the 3rd toe when it is bent 90° backwards relative to the tarsometatarsus. In 
  <span class="italic">P. ater</span>, this distal measuring point coincides with the outer edge of the last complete scale on the dorsal side of the tarsometatarsus, used in the previous measurement. Care was taken to align the measurement with the long axis of the tarsometatarsus.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Foot length</span>: Distance, measured on the dorsal side of the foot, from the edge of the skin at the base of the claw of the middle forward toe (#3) to the edge of the skin at the base of the claw of the hind toe (#1) when the toes are gently stretched forwards and backwards, respectively. The claws are not included in the measurement since they may be worn down to various extents.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Bill length</span>: Length from the bill tip to the frontonasal angle at which the calliper jaw (for measuring inner dimensions) stops when it is gently slid backwards along the bill's culmen. We took a projected measurement parallel to the bill's cutting edge because if one measures obliquely, directly from the bill tip, it is difficult to locate the flat frontonasal angle that is concealed by feathers.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Bill width</span>: Width measured at the middle of the nostrils.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Bill depth</span>: Bill height at the middle of the nostrils measured at 90° to the bill's cutting edge. Care was taken not to press the bill beyond its natural closure.
 </p>
</sec>
