<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The southeast region, which represents the main climate refuge of the MDB fish diversity is already affected by several contemporary impacts. Anthropogenic alterations of flow (regulation and consumptive use), fragmentation (by dams and weirs) and land use intensification (causing pollution and sedimentation) are significant in the southern MDB, but are not restricted to this area alone [
 <xref rid="pone.0225128.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Another challenge to conservation of native fish in the MDB under climate change relates to the high number of introduced fish species in the basin. Although some studies have revealed diminishing impacts of invasive species under climate change [
 <xref rid="pone.0225128.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0225128.ref101" ref-type="bibr">101</xref>], other indicate that future climate may exacerbate the threat posed by invasive species [
 <xref rid="pone.0225128.ref102" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>]. In Australia, introduced stream fish of Victorian streams were predicted to experience both contraction (
 <italic>Salmo trutta</italic> and 
 <italic>Oncorhynchus mykiss</italic>) and expansion (
 <italic>Gambusia holbrooki</italic> and 
 <italic>Misgurnus anguillicaudatus</italic>) of their ranges [
 <xref rid="pone.0225128.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. The MDB shows 11 invasive species (23% of the total), thus it is possible that the functional characteristics of these species may be favorably selected in the future. It is possible that introduced species may increase their dominance in climatic refuges intensifying biotic interactions such as predation and competition, with native species. The difficulty of predicting how interactions among species will be altered under future climate scenarios are reported in several papers (e.g. [
 <xref rid="pone.0225128.ref103" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>]). Thus, further research is needed to assess to what extent invasive species of MDB can spread their ranges considering future environmental conditions.
</p>
