<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Even though the decrease of climatic-environmental suitability and range size does not necessarily imply extinction of a species (see below the importance of physiologic plasticity), it is consensual in conservation biology that a decrease in the extent of occurrence or area of occupancy reflects increasing extinction risk [
 <xref rid="pone.0225128.ref087" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>]. In the face of predicted climate change, the persistence of species in their original ranges will be dependent on the degree of genetic diversity, physiological and phenotypic plasticity [
 <xref rid="pone.0225128.ref088" ref-type="bibr">88</xref>]. In this sense, historic-evolutionary hypothesis explaining diversity gradients postulates that due to the climatic stability of lower latitudes, tropical species evolve to have narrow thermal tolerances and that due to the climatic instability of high latitudes, temperate species evolve to have broader thermal tolerances [
 <xref rid="pone.0225128.ref089" ref-type="bibr">89</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0225128.ref090" ref-type="bibr">90</xref>]. As a consequence, tropical species are likely to be more vulnerable to changes in global climate due their narrow thermal niches [
 <xref rid="pone.0225128.ref091" ref-type="bibr">91</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0225128.ref092" ref-type="bibr">92</xref>]. Because the MDB is a temperate basin, it would be expected high tolerance of fish species to global warming forces. Nonetheless, we found that for many MDB fish species, the upper lethal temperature was lower than future temperature predictions. The fragility of temperate fish facing climate alteration was also pointed out by [
 <xref rid="pone.0225128.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Evaluating plasticity to upper tolerance temperature of fishes, these authors found that species occupying higher latitudes showed no greater acclimatization capacity than those living at lower latitudes, interposing to historic-evolutionary hypothesis.
</p>
