<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Although we did not measure ecological processes linked to ecosystem functioning directly, we can make some predictions. Loss of, or a decline of fish taxa with large body length, as suggested here, may compromise biomass and affect recreational fisheries that generate substantial socio-economic benefits. The larger fish species of the MDB, such as the Murray cod, golden perch, silver perch and freshwater catfish have historically provided an important food source for Aboriginal people and European settlers [
 <xref rid="pone.0225128.ref095" ref-type="bibr">95</xref>], supplying recreational activities and the commercial fish industry. In addition, the potential extirpation of species displaying traits such as catadromy, amphidromy, potamodromy, herbivory-detritivory and omnivory in 2080 and the severe reduction in vertical position non-benthic, and species tolerants to low temperatures (TMIN) under the pessimistic emission scenario warns of potential degradation of ecosystem functioning. The loss of species traits related to movement between distinct habitats implies a reduction in the transfer of energy, biomass and nutrients [
 <xref rid="pone.0225128.ref096" ref-type="bibr">96</xref>]. Despite not being entirely lost from the MDB based on our models, potamodromous fish also suffer a significant decline. The life-cycles of many potamodromous fishes are flow-dependent [
 <xref rid="pone.0225128.ref097" ref-type="bibr">97</xref>]. Forecasts of future declines in rainfall and runoff in MDB [
 <xref rid="pone.0225128.ref098" ref-type="bibr">98</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0225128.ref099" ref-type="bibr">99</xref>], suggest flow events triggering large-scale movements will decline. The loss of the traits herbivorous-detritivorous and omnivorous can alter the trophic structure of stream food webs, leading to cascades that have not been captured by predictions arising from SDMs [
 <xref rid="pone.0225128.ref100" ref-type="bibr">100</xref>].
</p>
