<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">To extend beyond our prior work, we now incorporate the spatial pattern of both temperature and precipitation responses based on an analysis of nine global climate models that have performed idealized simulations examining the individual responses to CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>, CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub>, SO
 <sub class="sub">4</sub>, and BC (Myhre et al., 
 <xref rid="eft2497-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>). Aerosols were increased globally by large factors (5× present day for sulfate and 10× for BC) to obtain statistically significant signals. Responses to localized aerosol perturbations might differ, and hence, here we present only responses to worldwide aerosol changes. All results are interpolated to 1° × 1° horizontal resolution, with the native resolution in the underlying climate models ranging from 2.8° × 2.8° to 1.4° × 1.4°. We assume that the temperature and precipitation responses per unit forcing to other well‐mixed greenhouse gasses (WMGHGs; N
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O and F‐gasses) is similar to the responses to CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> (as is found to be the case for methane). Similarly, we assume the response to other scattering aerosols or aerosol precursors (OC, NH
 <sub class="sub">3</sub>, and the portion of NO
 <sub class="sub">x</sub> that leads to nitrate) is similar to the response to SO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>. Multimodel mean results for the temperature and precipitation impacts of CO and NO
 <sub class="sub">x</sub> emissions via tropospheric ozone and methane are excluded, as these are not available. Based on the IPCC AR5, the net forcing from these two gasses (excluding nitrate‐related impacts) is 0.1 W/m
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>, a small value compared with forcing due to, for example, CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> of 1.7 W/m
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>. Nevertheless, it would be useful to add the impacts of these gasses along with nonmethane volatile organic compounds for completeness. The multimodel mean temperature response patterns are uniformly scaled according to the amplitude of global mean temperature change calculated in the simple model as described in the previous paragraph. Precipitation patterns are also uniformly scaled following the relationship in the climate models between those patterns and global mean temperature for individual forcers.
</p>
