<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Zebrafish (
 <italic class="italic">Danio rerio</italic>) are one of the most widely used laboratory species (
 <xref rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Meyers, 2018</xref>). A wide range of domestication effects has been observed in zebrafish, both between laboratory-strain and wild-caught fish (
 <xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Robison and Rowland, 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref52" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Whiteley 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2011
 </xref>) as well in wild-caught zebrafish after being kept in the laboratory for only nine generations (
 <xref rid="ref48" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Uusi-Heikkilä 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2017
 </xref>). These domestication effects include behavioural (reduced startle response), physiological (increased growth rate) and genetic (genetic changes related to growth and maturation processes) alterations (
 <xref rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Robison and Rowland, 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref48" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Uusi-Heikkilä 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2017
 </xref>). Laboratory zebrafish are able to acclimate to a wide range of temperatures, and under normal holding temperatures (28°C), they have an upper acute thermal tolerance that exceeds 40°C (
 <xref rid="ref7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Cortemeglia and Beitinger, 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Schaefer and Ryan, 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Majhi and Das, 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref32" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Morgan 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2018
 </xref>). This makes it a practical species to address questions within thermal biology, and it has previously been used in such experiments (reviewed in 
 <xref rid="ref26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">López-Olmeda and Sánchez-Vázquez, 2011</xref>). The zebrafish AB-WT laboratory population has been held in a controlled laboratory environment at optimal temperatures (26–28°C) with low thermal variation and few thermal extremes since the 1970s (
 <xref rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Spence 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2008
 </xref>). It could therefore be predicted that laboratory populations, through decades of adaptation to laboratory conditions with no adaptive value for high thermal tolerance, have lost some of their high temperature tolerance. Wild populations, on the other hand, experience daily and seasonally fluctuating temperatures with potentially harmful extreme temperatures (
 <xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Engeszer 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2007
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref44" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Suriyampola 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2016
 </xref>), suggesting that high thermal tolerance is of great adaptive value for wild zebrafish. However, whether there is a difference in thermal tolerance between laboratory-held lines, domesticated lines and wild zebrafish is currently unknown.
</p>
