<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par22">We observed a high degree of individual variation in the capacity to regulate resistance to water loss in our experiments. Individuals that exhibited a high initial 
 <italic>r</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>i</italic>
 </sub> (roughly 7 s cm
 <sup>−1</sup>) maintained a high 
 <italic>r</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>i</italic>
 </sub> throughout the entire experiment, exhibiting limited plasticity. The maintenance of high 
 <italic>r</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>i</italic>
 </sub> was unexpected given that salamanders were maintained in saturated conditions for a month prior to the experiment, and consequently, this upper boundary may be indicative of a physiological limit. At the other end of the spectrum, some individuals began the experiment with a relatively low 
 <italic>r</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>i</italic>
 </sub> (4 s cm
 <sup>−1</sup>) and increased 
 <italic>r</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>i</italic>
 </sub> over the course of the experiment by as much as 68% to the maximum value. Thus, the population consists of individuals that fall across a spectrum of plasticity, which raises intriguing questions about the benefits of plasticity or lack thereof. Low 
 <italic>r</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>i</italic>
 </sub> would predispose individuals to desiccation. However, a low resistance might also increase metabolic scope by promoting greater oxygen uptake
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>
 </sup>. Thus, individuals might benefit from low resistance by supporting oxygen-demanding activities, such as foraging or defending territories. At the other end of the spectrum, limiting plasticity might reduce costs of maintaining sensory pathways
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>
 </sup> or maximal resistance in the face of unpredictable VPDs. The costs and benefits of water loss plasticity might be better understood by exploring these interactions.
</p>
