<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Based on our results, we provide suggestions for invasion management under climate change. Monitoring strategies should be defined and utilised for climate change for IPS, particularly for aquatic plants, trees, and herbs in the biomes of coastal regions or high latitudes (
 <xref rid="ref-67" ref-type="bibr">Petitpierre et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-94" ref-type="bibr">Wang, Wan &amp; Zhang, 2017</xref>). In these ecoregions, climate change could result in a number of potential consequences for IPS in areas with a high invasion potential, such as changing transport and introduction mechanisms, establishment of new IPS in invaded regions, impact of existing IPS on invaded habitats, redistribution of existing IPS, and reduction in effectiveness of control strategies (
 <xref rid="ref-86" ref-type="bibr">Thuiller et al., 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-42" ref-type="bibr">Hellmann et al., 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-23" ref-type="bibr">Cronin et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-30" ref-type="bibr">Early et al., 2016</xref>). 
 <xref rid="ref-30" ref-type="bibr">Early et al. (2016)</xref> have shown that areas with high levels of poverty and low historical levels of invasion may be severely invaded by IPS. These consequences would result in a large potential for IPS to impact regional ecoregions worldwide. Hence, we need to design long-term management plans at the biome scale to create a mitigation strategy for the expansion of IPS in ecoregions due to climate change (
 <xref rid="ref-63" ref-type="bibr">Olson et al., 2001</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-1" ref-type="bibr">Abell et al., 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-30" ref-type="bibr">Early et al., 2016</xref>). We should also develop policies to prevent intentional or accidental introduction or IPS dispersal worldwide (
 <xref rid="ref-71" ref-type="bibr">Powell, Chase &amp; Knight, 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-47" ref-type="bibr">Kalusová et al., 2013</xref>). Considering forest and coastal biomes, we need to create a framework of adaptive management for forest and aquatic IPS under climate change (
 <xref rid="ref-49" ref-type="bibr">Kulhanek, Ricciardi &amp; Leung, 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr">Donaldson et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr">Bajer et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-40" ref-type="bibr">Gillard et al., 2017</xref>). Furthermore, 
 <xref rid="ref-30" ref-type="bibr">Early et al. (2016)</xref> have shown that plant invasion may be a current result of environmental change in economically developing regions. Hence, combined with our results, we need to attach importance to the improvement of early-warning monitoring schemes in the ecoregions with coastal or high latitudes in developing countries (
 <xref rid="ref-30" ref-type="bibr">Early et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-67" ref-type="bibr">Petitpierre et al., 2016</xref>).
</p>
