<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The choice of destination is affected largely by distance from the place of origin (most migration occurs over short distances), availability of jobs and housing, family and social networks, and immigration policies in the new location [
 <xref rid="B40-ijerph-13-00443" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>]. For example, environmental migrants leaving rural areas due to natural disasters may try to find work in local cities [
 <xref rid="B34-ijerph-13-00443" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>]. Furthermore, environmental migrants are more likely to stay within their own countries than they are to migrate abroad [
 <xref rid="B41-ijerph-13-00443" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-ijerph-13-00443" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="B43-ijerph-13-00443" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>]. In both developed and developing countries, migrants after extreme natural events have been observed to remain within national borders and close to their place of origin. For example, in Florida after Hurricane Andrew, 76% of 353,300 displaced residents from Dade County remained within the county, 18% moved within the state, and 6% moved out-of-state ([
 <xref rid="B44-ijerph-13-00443" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>], p. 272). Similarly, a study in India of the Ghaghara floodplain found that the majority of permanent migrants settled just outside the flood zone [
 <xref rid="B45-ijerph-13-00443" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>]. After the Indian Ocean Tsunami in 2004, migration to nearby urban areas was observed in Sri Lanka, Thailand, and Indonesia [
 <xref rid="B46-ijerph-13-00443" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>]. These findings suggest that migration as an adaptive response to natural hazards most often occurs within a very small radius of the migrant’s place of origin, and may tend towards urban areas. However, despite the fact that the majority of migration after natural disasters is internal, most research to-date has focused on international migration [
 <xref rid="B39-ijerph-13-00443" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>]. This highlights the issue of localized migration as one priority for future research. 
</p>
