<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par46" class="p">Temperature was used to parameterize the expression of 
 <italic class="italic">R</italic>
 <sub class="sub">0</sub> in patches environment for understanding the dynamics of malaria transmission and later generate maps for the disease risk areas in Africa. Biting rate, vector competence, adult mortality rate, parasite development rate, eggs laid per adult female per day, egg-to-adult survival probability, and mosquito development rate were expressed as dependent on temperature, hence the parameters help to include a climatic variable into the expression of 
 <italic class="italic">R</italic>
 <sub class="sub">0</sub> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">13</xref>]. Combining these thermal responses constrained from high to low limits into a spatial distribution of temperature values yielded maps showing areas of potential transmission of malaria. The obtained maps of 
 <italic class="italic">R</italic>
 <sub class="sub">0</sub> agree to a certain level with existing malaria risk maps of Africa obtained from an experimental study such as the MARA maps [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" class="xref">42</xref>]. The present results further agree with the spatial distribution map of 
 <italic class="italic">P. falciparum</italic> malaria endemic areas in Africa [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" class="xref">49</xref>]. The model predicted numerous regions with 
 <italic class="italic">R</italic>
 <sub class="sub">0</sub> greater than unity because of the clumping effects of spatial models [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" class="xref">50</xref>]. The accuracy of our model is enshrined in the capacity of reproducing almost all known regions at risk of malaria, which were the same as that identified by various other models [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" class="xref">42</xref>]. The estimates of the basic reproduction number magnitudes for randomly selected points in Africa compared to 
 <italic class="italic">APfEIR</italic> further confirmed the accuracy of the approach used. But the variations between 
 <italic class="italic">APfEIR</italic> and the values of 
 <italic class="italic">R</italic>
 <sub class="sub">0</sub> in endemic areas were substantial due to the short-range heterogeneity used in the computation of 
 <italic class="italic">R</italic>
 <sub class="sub">0</sub> compared to the patchy distribution of the field datasets. Usually, 
 <italic class="italic">APfEIR</italic> are computed with data obtained from disparate health units within the region to characterize the point location, whereas the values of 
 <italic class="italic">R</italic>
 <sub class="sub">0</sub> is estimated based on the exact values of the temperature at point location represented by its geographical coordinates.
</p>
