<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par47" class="p">In literature, several studies have used different approaches to tackle problems similar to the current study. For instance, Craig et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" class="xref">42</xref>] have proposed a “fuzzy logic” model for the distribution of stable malaria transmission in sub-Saharan Africa. However, the model development required detailed information, not always available in all localities of Africa. The study in [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" class="xref">49</xref>] interpolated the probabilities of 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">falciparum</italic> entomological inoculation rate (
 <italic class="italic">PfEIR</italic>), 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">falciparum</italic> basic reproductive number (
 <italic class="italic">PfR</italic>), and 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">falciparum</italic> parasite rate (
 <italic class="italic">PfPR</italic>) to generate the map for each quantity, which were then combined to yield the malaria transmission map. Although the outcome was realistic, the method did not include the dynamics of malaria vectors and parasites. Other studies [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>] used CLIMEX model, a platform designed to infer species responses to environmental conditions and climatic parameters to produce potential distributional maps of disease occurrence. The authors only focused on 
 <italic class="italic">A. gambiae</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">A. arabiensis</italic> distributions to infer malaria transmission, with no consideration of the parasites. Overall, malaria parasite transmission intensity is spatially heterogeneous and this heterogeneity has important implications for risks and age patterns of progression from malaria infection to disease, infirmity, morbidity, and death [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" class="xref">51</xref>]. The present study is among the very first investigations that define the limits of contemporary malaria transmission, using the basic reproduction number derived from a dynamical mathematical model. The authors in [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">14</xref>] used a similar approach but limited the study to expected changes in transmission at the Republic of Tanzania. In addition, the models used by Parham and Michael [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">14</xref>] failed to predict accurately the optimal value of temperature for malaria transmission, thus producing maps with false high magnitude areas of malaria transmission. Studies using approaches similar to what is presented here were applied to map bluetongue virus in the Netherlands [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" class="xref">52</xref>]; to develop a temperature-driven map of the emerging tick vector of Lyme disease 
 <italic class="italic">Ixodes scapularis</italic> in Canada [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" class="xref">53</xref>], and to assess the effect of climate change in the risk of Chagas disease transmission in Colombia [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" class="xref">54</xref>].
</p>
