<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par48" class="p">The link between climate change and vector-borne diseases such as malaria is well established [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" class="xref">55</xref>]. Although other studies highlighted the importance of climate change on the burden of malaria in Africa [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" class="xref">56</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" class="xref">57</xref>], few researches have considered temperature as a paramount climatic factor and used it to predict future changes in malaria transmission. Our findings showed that changes in the magnitude of temperatures are likely to create a shift in the distribution of malaria-endemic areas than to expand its geographic ranges. This finding concurs with the results reported in [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" class="xref">57</xref>]. A similar observation was also reported in studies by [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>]. It is important to note that, in cases where temperature extremes set boundaries on the vectors distributions, climate change might alter the range (in altitude or latitude) of favorable environmental conditions for the malaria vectors and the parasites. We noted that the greatest effect of climate change on malaria is likely to be observed at a temperature equal to 25 °C, corresponding to the favorable conditions for disease transmission. The optimum temperature value for malaria transmission has been estimated based on the vectors and parasites biological characteristics. With species evolution and under certain circumstances, the vectors and parasites could undergo some genetic modifications in order to adapt to current environments with different optimum temperatures. With this hypothesis, the range for the shift of malaria transmission/endemic areas will be less than predicted. In addition to the direct influence of temperature on the biology of vectors and parasites, changing precipitation patterns could also have short- and long-term effects on vector development [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">17</xref>]. A recent analysis of global mean surface precipitation over the period 1901–1995 indicates that precipitation trends vary across Africa. Precipitation appears to be increasing in east Africa but decreasing in western and northern part of the continent [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">17</xref>]. These are common observations that if actualized, may reduce the level of certainty on our findings.
</p>
