<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par24" class="p">Even assuming unlimited dispersal, about half of modeled bumblebee species’ ranges are projected to decline in all future climate scenarios. Large interspecies variation arose because of differences in spatial shifts of species’ climatically suitable range into new areas and the extent to which areas in their current ranges were forecasted to become unsuitable. Range losses were focused in regions that are also strongly disturbed by various anthropogenic activities (e.g. agricultural and developed land). Areas where multiple species expanded (i.e. hotspots) were concentrated in regions poleward of current distributions, where developed or agricultural lands are limited
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" class="xref">62</xref>
 </sup>. The extent of hotspots was largest in areas east of the Rockies where the geographical trajectories of anticipated climate changes are mostly northward
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" class="xref">64</xref>
 </sup>. The relatively uniform topography of eastern regions generates weak climate gradients, so large latitudinal shifts are necessary for species to track changing climatic conditions
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">17</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" class="xref">65</xref>
 </sup>. Comparatively smaller distances must be traveled to track similar climatic changes within mountainous areas
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">13</xref>
 </sup>. Under high or unlimited dispersal, range changes are more accentuated in 2050 than 2070 for some species, but only under strong climate mitigation (RCP2.6). The relatively low losses at most species’ trailing edge of this moderate RCP scenario were compensated more easily at the leading edge in 2070 while losses were not significantly worsened. Species-specific traits, however, ultimately determine species’ capacities to reach newly suitable areas in the future, regardless of environmental or anthropogenic barriers
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">13</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">17</xref>
 </sup>, and may explain variation associated with bumblebees’ realised responses to climate change
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" class="xref">66</xref>
 </sup>. Bumblebees’ ability to reach and persist in new areas, necessary to maintain their range over time, is particularly important within agricultural areas where ecosystem services hold important economic and ecological value for human populations
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">4</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
