<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par29" class="p">Findings support the need for effective mitigation strategies that could benefit multiple species simultaneously, and aim to increase the likelihood of successful colonizations in areas beyond those occupied historically. Our data revealed relatively large and concentrated hotspots overlapping across climate scenarios, supporting broad-scale management plans for multiple bumblebee species. These hotspots include candidate sites where assisted colonisation efforts could be concentrated and would benefit several species
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76" class="xref">76</xref>
 </sup>. Such efforts might help species maintain broader geographical ranges than would otherwise be possible, reducing the prospects of species extinctions and erosion of pollination services associated with rapid climate change
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" class="xref">26</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77" class="xref">77</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78" class="xref">78</xref>
 </sup>. Assisted colonisation precludes introductions of species across biogeographical boundaries
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79" class="xref">79</xref>
 </sup>, avoiding the creation of non-analog ecological communities and should account for risks of introducing novel genotypes of pathogens to new areas. Bumblebees’ high risk of decline under climate change, the relative practicality of translocation, and manageable costs of relocating small numbers of fertilized queens in the spring, together, suggest that assisted colonisation should be evaluated alongside conventional conservation strategies focusing on habitat characteristics
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>
 </sup>. Assisted colonisation remains controversial on ethical grounds and due to potential risks of relocated species becoming locally invasive
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" class="xref">26</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80" class="xref">80</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82" class="xref">82</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
