<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">
 <bold class="bold">The sustained dependency of human society on</bold> hydrocarbons is predicted to increase global near-surface temperatures, particularly across the second half of the twenty-first century (IPCC 
 <xref rid="bib44" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>). Warming will be most pervasive in high-altitude (alpine) and -latitude (Arctic) regions and will be coupled with changing precipitation patterns (Gobiet et al. 
 <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>). Significant climatic changes are already occurring within these environments, reducing the distribution, thickness, and permanency of ice sheets and driving the thinning and retreat of many mountain glaciers (Zemp et al. 
 <xref rid="bib84" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>). Continued retreat will alter the proportional contribution of ice melt, snow melt, and groundwater to proglacial mountain-river systems (Brown et al. 
 <xref rid="bib9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2007</xref>). Each of these water sources has a unique physicochemical signature and flow regime, which influences the assembly of river communities (Milner et al. 
 <xref rid="bib62" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>). Glacier retreat and loss will therefore alter the mosaic of aquatic habitats across glacier floodplains, threatening multiple endemic and rare species that often exist at their tolerance limits (Wrona et al. 
 <xref rid="bib82" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2006</xref>, Brown et al. 
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>, Jacobsen et al. 
 <xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>, Giersch et al. 
 <xref rid="bib35" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>). Wider alterations to the persistence, density, and distribution of species will combine to drive major biological reorganization of mountain-river ecosystems (Brown and Milner 
 <xref rid="bib7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>, Jacobsen et al. 
 <xref rid="bib45" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>).
</p>
