<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par19" class="p">The importance of variation in SIP extends beyond inland and coastal ecosystems. SIP just above Earth’s surface can be estimated for any location and time given knowledge of the optical state of the atmosphere (mostly ozone and clouds) as well as season and latitude (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" class="xref">7</xref>). The reference SIP values from Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" class="xref">1</xref> (100 J m
 <sup class="sup">−2</sup> day
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>) are exceeded year-round only in the tropics, and in the summer only at latitudes &lt;45°. Thus even in the most transparent waters SIP may be very low in higher latitude regions during the winter when sun angle is low, or at times when cloud cover is high. Current climate change scenarios project region-specific changes in cloud cover in the future
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">1</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" class="xref">52</xref>
 </sup> that will affect UV exposure levels. For example, increases in cloud cover at high Northern latitudes will reduce incident UV
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" class="xref">64</xref>
 </sup>. However, for temperate latitudes, UV changes due to cloud changes are expected to be 5% or less by the end of this century
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" class="xref">64</xref>
 </sup>. At the global scale, recovery from ozone depletion is predicted to reduce incident UV by up to 40% in Antarctica, but will have smaller effects outside of the high southern latitudes
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" class="xref">64</xref>
 </sup>. In contrast, climate change induced melting of ice in the Arctic Sea may increase sub-surface exposure to UV by tenfold, and improvements in air quality over populated areas may decrease aerosols and potentially increase incident UV by 10–20% or more
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" class="xref">64</xref>
 </sup>. These changes, along with those affecting water transparency and runoff, will alter the potential for solar UV disinfection of waterborne pathogens in the coming decades. The disproportionally greater increase in human populations in coastal regions (e.g. 39% growth in coastal regions vs. 13% for the overall population in the USA since 1970
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" class="xref">51</xref>
 </sup>) as well as heavy use of inland waters for waste disposal will amplify the potential exposure of humans to contaminated waters. Livestock and wildlife that depend on surface waters are also likely to experience an increase in exposure to waterborne pathogens and infectious diseases, further threatening the ecosystem goods and services provided by inland and coastal surface waters. 
</p>
