<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3" class="p">It is commonly accepted that drought can be grouped into meteorological, agricultural, hydrological and socio-economic drought categories
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">23</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" class="xref">26</xref>
 </sup>. Meteorological drought is defined as precipitation deficit while soil moisture and low river flow are often termed as agricultural drought and hydrological drought, respectively. Because different drought indices measuring various drought types contrast sharply
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" class="xref">2</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">17</xref>
 </sup>, it is important to compare these drought types to understand why their results are different. Previous studies have investigated future changes in drought based on the anomaly of precipitation
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" class="xref">27</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>
 </sup>, soil moisture
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">30</xref>
 </sup> or streamflow/runoff
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" class="xref">31</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" class="xref">32</xref>
 </sup>, separately. To date, investigation of meteorological, hydrological and agricultural drought in a consistent manner is rare
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" class="xref">26</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" class="xref">33</xref>
 </sup>, not to mention its concurrence which could exert more severe effects than any other single drought type in terms of impacts
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" class="xref">34</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" class="xref">35</xref>
 </sup>. Recently, Zhang 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" class="xref">36</xref>
 </sup> has conducted a pioneering work by investigating the change pattern of four types of drought in India and examined drought impacts on wheat yield with a focus on the historical period. What’s more, a single drought event can be characterized by its duration and intensity, while several metrics can be used to measure the probabilistic distribution of droughts in a specific period, e.g., the total occurrences, mean and extreme duration/intensity and etc. Changes in drought with different duration and intensity have distinct implications for drought management and adaptations. Sheffield 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">13</xref>
 </sup> investigated three classes of drought duration (i.e., short-term, medium term, and long-term) but only considering the soil moisture based drought from limited raw climate model simulations. To date, most of previous investigations mainly focused on the mean of droughts, leaving the changes in drought of various types under different categories and the extremes under-investigated.
</p>
