<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>For China, the average SDTR, which is the soil temperature range between day and night, decreased at an average of 0.025 °C/year during the study period due to a slight increase in 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="mm100">
   <mrow>
    <mrow>
     <mi>S</mi>
     <msub>
      <mi>T</mi>
      <mrow>
       <mi>max</mi>
      </mrow>
     </msub>
    </mrow>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> and a substantial increase in 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="mm101">
   <mrow>
    <mrow>
     <mi>S</mi>
     <msub>
      <mi>T</mi>
      <mrow>
       <mi>min</mi>
      </mrow>
     </msub>
    </mrow>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> (0.031 and 0.055 °C/year, respectively) in all seasons at most stations. The annual decrease in SDTR was mainly attributed to a decrease in winter (–0.08 °C/year). The solar duration was positively and strongly related to SDTR, whereas precipitation was negatively associated with SDTR. Based on the significant reductions in SD change and similar spatial patterns between SD and SDTR, we concluded that the decreasing SD was an important cause of the decrease in SDTR. In general, soil temperature changes were consistent with those of air temperature, although the magnitude of their asymmetry affected crop growth. The differences between soil and air temperature were highest in summer (2.76 °C) and smallest in winter (1.55 °C). On average, 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="mm102">
   <mrow>
    <mrow>
     <msub>
      <mi>T</mi>
      <mi>D</mi>
     </msub>
    </mrow>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> decreased by 0.3 °C over the entire period, which was mainly attributed to a substantial change in winter (0.8 °C over 50 years). The asymmetry between soil temperature and air temperature meant agricultural practice plans based on air temperature alone may be severely limited. The difference between soil temperature and air temperature reduces at night. This would facilitate the wintering of perennials in areas near the zero-contour line. These results about asymmetric soil warming are important because it highlights the significance of using soil temperature (versus air temperature) for a reliable estimation of the responses and feedback of ecological soil processes to climate change and agricultural production.
</p>
