<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Indirect effects of rainfall may affect food plant quality through both chemical and morphological changes. The two groups of chemicals measured in this study, glucosinolates and sugars, thus, represent only a very small subset of the full arsenal of traits in plants that can affect the performance of insect herbivores and of which the expression may also change in response to rain. In plants exposed to both rainfall (single daily events) and herbivory, the induction of foliar levels of sinigrin, the dominant GS in 
 <italic>B. nigra</italic>, was strongest (2 fold increase), whereas the induction of sinigrin by either herbivory or rainfall alone was not statistically significant. This result suggests that, in 
 <italic>B. nigra</italic>, rainfall dramatically increased the sensitivity of GS metabolism to herbivory. However, specialist herbivores such as 
 <italic>P. brassicae</italic> and 
 <italic>P. xylostella,</italic> which both have efficient mechanisms to prevent exposure to the toxic GS breakdown products (Winde and Wittstock 
 <xref rid="ecy2819-bib-0048" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>), are generally less affected by changes in GS and potentially other defensive traits specific for brassicaceous plants. This could be the reason that, despite these considerable changes in sinigrin concentrations in response to rainfall, indirect (plant‐mediated) effects of rainfall on these insects were small. We therefore speculate that generalist insect herbivores that are more strongly affected by changes in GS (Gols et al. 
 <xref rid="ecy2819-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>, Jeschke et al. 
 <xref rid="ecy2819-bib-0023" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>) may be more sensitive to such indirect, plant‐mediated effects of rainfall. In the second experiment, in which the frequency (but not duration) of downpours was increased, sinigrin concentrations were high in all plants including those that were not exposed to rain and or herbivory. Sinigrin concentrations reached the same levels as those found in plants with the highest concentrations (&gt;50 μmol/g dry mass) in the first experiment. These concentrations are high in comparison with results previously reported for 
 <italic>B. nigra</italic> (van Dam et al. 
 <xref rid="ecy2819-bib-0045" ref-type="ref">2004</xref>, Gols et al. 
 <xref rid="ecy2819-bib-0016" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>). It is not clear why the concentrations were higher in the second than in the first experiment, but it seemed that the conditions were less favorable for both the plant and the herbivores (on control plants, caterpillars developed faster and were heavier in the first than in the second experiment). The second experiment was conducted in a greenhouse in winter, whereas the first experiment was conducted in a greenhouse in autumn. Even in climate‐controlled greenhouses, conditions, such as the quality and intensity of the artificial light for plant and insect growth, may vary seasonally (Gols et al. 
 <xref rid="ecy2819-bib-0015" ref-type="ref">2007</xref>). It should also be noted that we used a short‐lived annual plant. Such species may be less likely to exhibit strong indirect effects of rainfall or other climate‐related effects than perennial plants, as these events may occur in multiple years causing accumulative effects on host plant quality in perennials.
</p>
