<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The layers of the projected distributions for the 1961–90 and the 2080–99 periods for all the taxonomic groups together and the three taxonomic groups separately were loaded into the software. The assessment of efficiency of current Protected Areas (PAs) was performed in two different ways. The first was a typical minimum set cover problem. We compared the extent (here used as cost measure) of current PAs with the extent of a quasi-optimal solution that minimized number of protected cells while protecting the same mean proportion of each species range. This mean proportion was used as the target in the general analysis, with solutions being restricted to those that fulfilled it (hereinafter designated as minimum set). We conducted a second analysis, in which we gave more weight to single island endemics (SIEs). The ratio between the extent (number of cells protected) of the quasi-optimal solution and of current PAs reflects the efficiency of PAs, with the ratio being “1” if current PAs were as good as the best solution found by PRION and approaching “0” if the PAs occupied the entire island (
 <italic class="italic">i</italic>.
 <italic class="italic">e</italic>. a purely theoretical scenario). Because the software finds a quasi-optimal solution, if the number of current protected cells matches the ones found by the program (
 <italic class="italic">i</italic>.
 <italic class="italic">e</italic>. the ratio is 1) then the current PA’s are as effective as an optimal solution. When this is not the case, and the optimal solution can protect the same proportion of species occupying less number of cells than the current PA’s then the optimal solution is more effective (
 <italic class="italic">i</italic>.
 <italic class="italic">e</italic>. the ratio is 0). The ratio was calculated with the output values for cost from PRION for both the existing PAs and the minimum set solution. The second approach was a typical maximum coverage problem. We compared the average of the proportions of species’ protected ranges with an optimal solution that maximized species coverage with similar costs. The number of protected cells (costs) in the current PAs was used as restriction in PRION (hereinafter designated as maximum coverage). The ratio between the current and the quasi-optimal percentages of targets reached (as single output values given by PRION) reflected the efficiency of current PAs, with the ratio being “1” if current PAs were as good as the best solution found by Prion and “0” if the PAs did not reach any target.
</p>
