<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Our results indicate that, despite drastic predicted changes in climatic conditions, suitable habitats for plant species endemic to the Caatinga semi-arid region will tend to remain within this phytogeographic domain boundaries. Specifically, regardless of the intensity of climate change projections examined here, suitable habitat areas for endemic plant species—with any of the life-history traits we considered—will most likely be reduced and concentrated in the northeasternmost portion of the Caatinga (Figs 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217028.g004" class="xref">4</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217028.g007" class="xref">7</xref>), which is nearest the coast, and therefore least arid. In addition, suitable habitats for species with specialized reproductive strategies, such as obligatory cross-pollination, will be generally reduced more intensely (up to 28%) compared to the analogous areas hosting species with generalist reproductive strategies (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217028.g003" class="xref">Fig 3</xref>). Above and beyond climatic conditions, the long-term viability of plants endemic to the Caatinga will also rely on the persistence of suitable habitat remnants. The Caatinga vegetation is currently reduced to 50% of its original extension due to expansion and intensification of anthropogenic activities. In addition, the remaining Caatinga vegetation, is now distributed across ca. 41,700 remnants mainly represented by forests patches smaller than 500 ha [
 <xref rid="pone.0217028.ref085" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">85</xref>]. These small forest patches are concentrated in the eastern portion of the Caatinga, which according to our results, coincides with areas of suitable climatic conditions for endemic plant species, in both the current and future scenarios. The synergistic combination of climate change and Caatinga habitat loss through rapidly escalating land-use can potentially exacerbate the loss of suitable habitat for endemic plant species, and this is even more intensive for species with specialized reproductive traits. Several key ecological interactions, plant community dynamics, and the maintenance of native biodiversity are therefore particularly threatened in this SDTF, as discussed below.
</p>
