<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Endemic species are usually associated with restricted ranges, small populations, and specialized habitat requirements (with narrow spectrum of conditions and adequate environmental resources) [
 <xref rid="pone.0217028.ref043" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>]. In a global study on extinction risk in endemic species within biodiversity hotspots, habitat specificity was, the most influential variable in the potential loss of 56,000 plant species and 3,700 vertebrate species worldwide [
 <xref rid="pone.0217028.ref044" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>]. In addition to these habitat requirements, the disruption of ecological interactions, such as pollination and seed dispersal, may also be associated with the extinction of endemic plant species, especially those with specialized reproductive strategies [
 <xref rid="pone.0217028.ref033" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>]. Indeed, plant species that strictly depend on pollinators [obligatory cross-pollination (self-incompatible + dioecious) like as 
 <italic class="italic">Apterokarpus gardneri</italic>, Anacardiaceae], which are pollinated by a single pollination vector or by a reduced group of specific pollinators such as bats (
 <italic class="italic">Calliandra aeschynomenoides</italic>, Fabaceae), Sphingid moths, and non-flying vertebrates are more prone to the disruption of these ecological interactions mainly in human modified landscapes in tropical regions (e.g. [
 <xref rid="pone.0217028.ref033" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0217028.ref100" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">100</xref>]). These negative effects of climate change on the distribution of endemic plant species may be intensified due to anthropogenic disturbances. For example, SDTFs have been the historically most preferred regions for agricultural development and human settlements in Meso and South America [
 <xref rid="pone.0217028.ref101" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">101</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0217028.ref104" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">104</xref>]. In Brazil, the Caatinga domain is mainly inhabited by the rural poor who continue to intensively extract forest resources to meet their basic livelihoods [
 <xref rid="pone.0217028.ref085" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">85</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0217028.ref105" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">105</xref>]. Considering forage potential, 
 <italic class="italic">Libidibia ferrea</italic> (jucá) and fruits of 
 <italic class="italic">Spondias tuberosa</italic> (umbuzeiro) are used as feed for goats, sheep and cattle [
 <xref rid="pone.0217028.ref088" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">88</xref>]. Some species such as 
 <italic class="italic">Ziziphus joazeiro</italic> (Juazeiro), 
 <italic class="italic">Poincianella microphylla</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Poincianella pyramidalis</italic> are exploited by the population to produce firewood, charcoal and / or cuttings without any cultivation technique [
 <xref rid="pone.0217028.ref106" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">106</xref>]. 
 <italic class="italic">Poincianella pyramidalis</italic> is commonly used in folk medicine [
 <xref rid="pone.0217028.ref107" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">107</xref>]. Moreover, less than 2% of the Caatinga biome is strictly protected [
 <xref rid="pone.0217028.ref108" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">108</xref>]. Alarmingly, when we overlapped our suitable habitat projections for endemic plant species with the distribution of all protected areas in the Caatinga, we observed few conservation units covering future potential distribution areas, further aggravating the vulnerability of these species (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217028.g002" class="xref">Fig 2</xref>). This in turn may be particularly relevant to the productivity and resilience of the Caatinga [
 <xref rid="pone.0217028.ref109" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">109</xref>]. Anthropogenic activities create barriers that hinder or preclude species movements [
 <xref rid="pone.0217028.ref110" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">110</xref>]. Therefore, the synergistic interaction between climate change and acute or chronic anthropogenic habitat disturbance threatens the persistence, dynamics and functioning of dry tropical forest ecosystems, and their biodiversity (e.g. [
 <xref rid="pone.0217028.ref102" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">102</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0217028.ref111" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">111</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0217028.ref113" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">113</xref>]).
</p>
