<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The malady has increased since the Second World War [
 <xref rid="B6-microorganisms-07-00024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>] and is often reported now in young plants and seedlings, whereas previously, only mature oil palms were infected. The fungus can reduce yields by 50–80% [
 <xref rid="B3-microorganisms-07-00024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>]. Over 50% of palms were infected with 
 <italic class="italic">Ganoderma</italic> in several areas in the Far East decades ago [
 <xref rid="B9-microorganisms-07-00024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>], where the disease was described as very serious. BSR can kill 80% of the stand by the time palms are half way through their economic life span [
 <xref rid="B3-microorganisms-07-00024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>]. Furthermore, expansion of industrial oil palm cultivation and BSR disease began early in Sumatra [
 <xref rid="B8-microorganisms-07-00024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>], a region where 
 <italic class="italic">G. boninense</italic> adaption to the environment is most likely to occur. This region contains the highest levels of disease, implying an association between the length of time of the existence of oil palm and high disease concentrations. The disorder was reported increasingly in inland peninsular Malaysia and Sabah, Malaysia, and in some cases at high levels, whereas before, it had not been detected. BSR was reported increasingly, and at high levels, in oil palm on (i) inland lateritic soils and (ii) peat soils, irrespective of cropping history, when before they were disease-free [
 <xref rid="B10-microorganisms-07-00024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. By the time of replanting (25 years), 40–50% of palms were lost in some fields, with the majority of standing palms showing disease symptoms [
 <xref rid="B11-microorganisms-07-00024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>], whereas levels were low originally. The disease level in Asahan, Indonesia indicated a climate change-related event [
 <xref rid="B12-microorganisms-07-00024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. This information indicates a trend for increasing BSR with projected climate change. However, the climate for growing oil palm is currently optimal [
 <xref rid="B1-microorganisms-07-00024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B3-microorganisms-07-00024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-microorganisms-07-00024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-microorganisms-07-00024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>] and has been so for many decades. The increase in disease previously reported will be from increased virulence of the fungus, rather than a possible increased susceptibility of oil palm due to a less suitable climate. There are procedures that may assist in reducing the future threats caused by BSR [
 <xref rid="B1-microorganisms-07-00024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>] (and see Discussion), although they require testing.
</p>
