<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Concluding remarks</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this study, which had the ultimate aim of incorporating the risks associated with TEs and their thresholds into the development of strategies for global climate risk management, we assessed two major TEs (Arctic summer sea-ice loss and Greenland ice-sheet melting) to determine (i) the probability of passing the thresholds within this century and (ii) the potential impact of the Greenland ice-sheet melting beyond the threshold.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the first part of this study, we estimated the probability of crossing the thresholds under several policy choices, which indicated how policy choices could alter the probability of crossing thresholds within this century. The estimated probabilities for BaU were significantly larger than those for T25 and T20, whereas the estimated probabilities for T15 were considerably lower. Such information could be used to support decision-making. However, the estimated probability in this study is not definitive, because the derived probability depends on several assumptions, as described in the methodology. Therefore, applying different methods of making assumptions or different analytical approaches would help in evaluating the confidence and robustness of the estimated probabilities. For example, a recent study by Screen and Williamson (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">2017</a>) used a different estimation approach and found that the probability of achieving a nearly ice-free Arctic sea would be less than 1/100,000 for a 1.5 °C increase and around 1/3 for a 2 °C increase. It should be also noted that the probability of crossing thresholds after 2100 should be researched in greater detail in the future to offer greater support to decision-making.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the second part of this study, we estimated the global mean sea level rise until the year 3000 using a semi-empirical model assigning three millennial temperature pathways. In addition, we estimated the potential coastal exposure using the estimated sea level.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There was a large gap between the scenarios exceeding the threshold (T25 and T20) and those not exceeding the threshold (T15) in the global total. It should be noted that the results are greatly affected by the assumption that the threshold temperature of the Greenland ice sheet is 1.6 °C. Therefore, the parameters used to describe ice sheets and sea level distribution should be explored further to yield more plausible sea level and exposure estimations on a millennial timescale.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Overall, although our study has presented a framework for probabilistic assessment and added estimates of probabilities of exceeding thresholds while also outlining the potential consequences of exceeding thresholds, enhancing the scientific basis for various TEs and their thresholds through additional research is necessary, because understanding on these parameters is still limited.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To this end, several studies on TEs and their thresholds (e.g., Abe-Ouchi et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">2013</a>; Yamamoto et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">2014</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">2015</a>; Obase et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">2017</a>) were successfully conducted for the ICA-RUS. The growth and reduction of Northern Hemisphere ice sheets over a million-year timescale (Abe-Ouchi et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">2013</a>), and basal melting of the Antarctic ice shelves (Obase et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">2017</a>) and ocean oxygen depletion due to the decomposition of submarine methane hydrates over timescales of 1,000 years or more (Yamamoto et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">2014</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">2015</a>) could be considered as additional TEs for the next research step. Future policy-related research projects similar to ICA-RUS should continue to promote additional basic studies on TEs and their thresholds.
 </p>
</sec>
