<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Probability of exceeding threshold temperatures in the current century</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Exceeding threshold temperatures could have catastrophic impacts. However, existing studies on the impacts of temperature increase seldom consider the threshold behavior of climate systems in their assessments. Difficulties in considering climate system thresholds in impact assessments arise from uncertainties associated with the thresholds, including the possible range of threshold temperatures. However, a probabilistic approach can be used to cope with these uncertainties. Several studies using IAMs have evaluated climate impacts while considering the probability of crossing threshold temperatures (e.g., Hope 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">2006</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">2011</a>; Cai et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">2015</a>; Lontzek et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">2015</a>). Lontzek et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">2015</a>) introduced a threshold module into a stochastic version of the dynamic stochastic integrated climate and economy model, which is an IAM that has been widely used for evaluating the economic impacts of climate change (Watkiss 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">2011</a>). The module’s parameter to set the probability of crossing the threshold temperature was determined by referring to the study of Kriegler et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">2009</a>), which used expert elicitations from 43 experts. Meanwhile, Screen and Williamson (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">2017</a>) assessed the probability of an ice-free state Arctic sea focusing on the temperature targets in the Paris Agreement. These studies provide important insights into the probability of exceeding the thresholds of the climate system. However a framework to estimate the probability of exceeding various thresholds has not yet been established, whereas the probabilities estimated using such a framework can be incorporated into IAMs and the importance of incorporating thresholds has previously been discussed (Lenton and Ciscar 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">2013</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here, we present a framework to execute a probabilistic assessment of exceeding the threshold of the climate system focusing on two TEs, the Greenland ice sheet and Arctic summer sea-ice. Within our framework, uncertainty in the threshold temperatures is represented by probability density functions (PDFs). The parameters of the PDFs are determined based on a literature review, enabling us to obtain the PDF for each TE separately. In this study, temperature increase represents the temperature anomaly with respect to preindustrial levels.</p>
 <sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methodology used to estimate the probability of exceeding the threshold temperatures</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figure 
   <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a> presents the algorithm used to assess the probability of exceeding the threshold temperatures of the TEs. In this algorithm, the uncertainties of the global mean temperature increase and the threshold temperature of the TEs are represented by PDFs. For the two major TEs, we set the PDF and threshold temperature of the two TEs based on the following rationale.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Flow chart of a method for estimating the probability of exceeding the threshold temperature by a target year under different policy choices</p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="11625_2018_536_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e404" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">First, the threshold of Greenland ice-sheet melting is defined as the temperature increase at which the surface mass balance of the Greenland ice sheet becomes negative. It should be noted that it may take hundreds of years to reach a negative mass balance after the temperature increases to the threshold. In the AR5 (IPCC 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">2013</a>), the threshold temperature of the Greenland ice sheet is given as greater than 1 °C (low confidence) and lower than 4 °C (medium confidence). These statements suggest that we can be relatively confident that the threshold of Greenland ice sheet melting is below 4 °C, and also implies that the threshold might be lower, and closer to 1 than 4 °C. Robinson et al. (
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">2012</a>) estimated the threshold temperature to be 1.6 °C with a 95% confidence interval of 0.8–3.2 °C. In addition to the above studies, Leverman et al. (2013) discussed the threshold of abrupt Greenland ice sheet loss to be between 0.8 and 2.2 °C (90% credible interval). Based on these values, we employed a log-normal distribution for the threshold temperature of Greenland ice-sheet melting using 1.6 °C as the best estimate and 1.0–4.0 °C as the 95% confidence interval., This setting of the PDF is consistent with our assumption of a threshold around 1.6 °C with a right-skewed distribution. Second, the threshold of Arctic summer sea-ice loss is the temperature at which the Arctic Ocean is in a nearly ice-free in September, and was determined as follows. Several models have estimated that a largely ice-free Arctic sea in summer would begin around 2 °C above the present temperature (Lenton 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">2012</a>). Massonnet et al. (
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">2012</a>) identified a Coupled Model Intercomparison Project Phase 5 (CMIP5) subset to represent September Arctic sea ice extent, indicating an increase of 1.6–2.1 °C (mean 1.9 °C) from the present period (2.2–2.7 °C and mean 2.5 °C from preindustrial levels) as the annual mean global surface temperature threshold for a nearly ice-free state of the Arctic Ocean in September. Therefore, we set the PDF for the threshold temperature of Arctic summer sea ice of 2.45 °C as the mean and 2.2–2.7 °C as the 68% confidence interval. The mean of 2.45 °C was almost consistent with a mean value of 2.5 °C in the CMIP 5 subset presented in Fig. 12.31e of AR5 (IPCC 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">2013</a>), and did not conflict with the best estimate of ~ 2.0 °C (above present) given by Mahlstein and Knutti (
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">2012</a>). Meanwhile, setting 2.2–2.7 °C as the 68% confidence interval (1.95–2.95 °C as the 95% confidence interval) enabled the possibility of the threshold falling in the range beyond of 2.2–2.7 °C, which should be considered because of the large variabilities of the thresholds in the models presented in Figs. 12.30 and 12.31 of the AR5 (IPCC 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">2013</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To estimate the probability of exceeding the thresholds by the end of this century, we used a set of global mean temperature increase projections conducted as IAM simulations in ICA-RUS. The IAM simulations were performed for several policy choices based on the target temperature at the end of this century. Details of the IAM simulations can be found in Su et al. (
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">2017</a>), who computed four sets of future emission pathways, including T15, T20, and T25. Each emission pathway corresponds to a temperature pathway. These pathways each correspond to a policy target that limits the temperature increase in 2100 to below 1.5, 2.0, and 2.5 °C from preindustrial levels, respectively. The IAM simulations in ICA-RUS assume the existence of a policy-maker who presumes climate sensitivity as 3.65 °C, which yields a 66% probability of achieving the policy target by additionally assuming that climate sensitivity follows a normal distribution with a mean of 3.0 and standard deviation of 1.5 (ICA-RUS report 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">2017</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition to T15, T20, and T25, Su et al. (
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">2017</a>) computed a set of future emission pathways for a business-as-usual (BaU) scenario. The T15, T20, T25, or BaU scenarios were each associated with several future emission pathways (temperature pathways) depending on the actual climate sensitivity, which were set to 1.50, 3.00, 3.65, or 4.00 °C. These settings of climate sensitivities were used because the actual climate sensitivity for policy-making is currently unknown; that is, even though policy-makers assume 3.65 °C as the climate sensitivity, future emission pathways (temperature pathways) could differ according to the discrepancy between the actual climate sensitivity and the climate sensitivity assumed by policy-makers. For this reason, four sets of actual climate sensitivities were assumed for each of the policy choices (i.e., T15, T20, T25, and BaU). Although the IAM simulations in the ICA-RUS were also conducted under three Shared Socioeconomic Pathways (SSPs), we focused on SSP2, which is a middle-of-the-road scenario (O’Neil et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">2014</a>). As a result, our analysis included 16 emission pathways or temperature pathways (i.e., the four temperature goals, including the BaU scenario, multiplied by the four sets of climate sensitivities under SSP2).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figure 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a> shows some of the temperature pathways with threshold ranges of 1.0–4.0 °C for the Greenland ice sheet and 1.95–2.95 °C for Arctic summer sea ice. If the actual climate sensitivity were to differ from the climate sensitivity adopted in a policy, the actual temperature increases at the end of this century would differ from the temperature goal (Su et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">2015</a>). As such, our framework incorporated this uncertainty in the future temperature increase using the IAM simulations for different climate sensitivities.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Relationship between global temperature paths of ICA-RUS and threshold temperatures of 
      <span class="bold">a</span> Arctic summer sea ice and 
      <span class="bold">b</span> Greenland ice sheet. The temperature paths assume that the climate sensitivity assumed by policy maker is 3.65 °C and the climate sensitivity of actual climate is 3.00 °C. The temperature paths were adjusted so that mean temperature increase during 1986–2005 is 0.61 °C from average of 1850–1900 (IPCC 
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">2013</a>)
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="11625_2018_536_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e473" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Using the 16 emission pathways (i.e., 16 temperature pathways) and assumptions of the PDFs of the threshold temperatures, the algorithm in Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a> was executed as follows. First, we estimated the PDFs of the threshold temperature and climate sensitivity (Step 1). The PDF of climate sensitivity was estimated following the assumption used in the ICA-RUS (i.e., climate sensitivity is normally distributed with a mean of 3.0 and standard deviation of 1.5). Then, for each policy choice, we estimated the regression line (Step 2) between the temperature increase in 2100 and actual climate sensitivity (i.e., 1.5, 3.00, 3.65, and 4.5 °C). Scatter plots of the temperature increase in 2100 and actual climate sensitivity suggested that the relationship between the temperature increase in 2100 and actual climate sensitivity could be approximated based on linear regression lines (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>). Therefore, we used the estimated linear regression lines to convert the PDF of climate sensitivity into the PDF of the temperature increase in 2100 (Step 3).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Relationship between the actual climate sensitivities (i.e., actual climate sensitivity = 1.5, 3.0, 3.65, or 4.5 °C) and temperature increase in 2100. The relationship and regression line are shown for the business-as-usual (plus and black line), T15 (triangle and blue line), T20 (circle and red line), and T25 (square and cyan line) scenarios</p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="11625_2018_536_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e493" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It should be noted that, although linear response theory of climate sensitivity suggests that the multiplicative (i.e., two) of climate sensitivity should correspond to the same multiplicative (i.e., two) of temperature increase, such multiplicative features do not appear in Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a> (i.e., a twofold increase in the climate sensitivity from 1.5 to 3.0 °C does not correspond to a twofold temperature increase in 2100). The reason for this response feature of temperature increase against climate sensitivity is due to the setting of the target temperature in the IAM. When the climate sensitivity assumed by the policy is in accordance with the climate sensitivity of the actual climate, the temperature increase obtained from the IAM is almost the same as the policy target temperature, as seen at 
   <span class="italic">x</span> = 3.65 in Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>. However, when the policy assumes a climate sensitivity greater than that of the actual climate, a more stringent effort to reduce emissions is performed in the IAM (Su et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">2015</a>), and accordingly the temperature increase at 2100 is lower than the policy target temperature. Similarly, when policy assumes a lower climate sensitivity than that of the actual climate, the temperature increase at 2100 exceeds the policy target temperature. In other words, because we use the IAM, which controls emissions according to the policy temperature target and policy-maker assumptions regarding climate sensitivity, the temperature increase at 2100 is strongly controlled by both the temperature target at 2100 and by how much the climate sensitivity of the actual climate departs from the climate sensitivity assumed by the policy. As a result, the temperature increase in 2100 does not show a linear response to increasing of climate sensitivity.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Next, we made a joint PDF from the PDFs of the temperature increase at 2100 and the threshold temperature (Step 4). Finally, we integrated this PDF over the domain where the threshold temperature was lower than the temperature increase at 2100 to obtain probability of exceeding the threshold temperature (Step 5).</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results and discussion of the probability of exceeding threshold temperatures</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From the above-described algorithm, we obtained the probabilities of exceeding the threshold temperatures by 2100 (see Step 5 of the algorithm). As examples of how we integrated the joint PDFs to obtain the probabilities of exceeding the threshold, Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>a, b (Arctic summer sea ice under T20 and BaU, respectively) and Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>a, b (Greenland ice sheet under T20 and BaU, respectively) show the joint PDF and the PDFs of the threshold temperature and temperature increase at 2100, respectively. Comparison of Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>a, b (or Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>a, b) shows that BaU has higher probabilities of large temperature increases than T20. Compared with T20, the higher probabilities of larger temperature increases in BaU shift the center of the joint probability density from outside of the integration domain (see Figs. 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>a, 
   <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>a) to inside of the domain (see Figs. 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>b, 
   <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>b), resulting in higher probabilities of exceeding the thresholds under BaU. In fact, the cumulative probabilities of exceeding the thresholds, which are obtained by integrating the domain where the temperature increase is greater than the threshold, confirmed that higher target temperatures result in higher probabilities of exceeding the thresholds (see “
   <a rid="Sec7" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec7">Appendix 1</a>”).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <div id="Fig4" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Probability density functions (PDFs) of the threshold temperature for Arctic summer sea ice (red) and temperature increase (blue) at 2100. The PDFs are shown for 
      <span class="bold">a</span> T20 and 
      <span class="bold">b</span> business as usual. Joint probability density function (green) between the PDFs is shown on the plain spanned by temperature increase and threshold temperature axis. The domain for integration to obtain the probability of exceeding threshold is colored with gray
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="11625_2018_536_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e561" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <div id="Fig5" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 5</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Probability density functions (PDFs) of the threshold temperature for Greenland ice sheet (red) and temperature increase (blue) at 2100. The PDFs are shown for 
      <span class="bold">a</span> T20 and 
      <span class="bold">b</span> business as usual. Joint probability density function (green) between the PDFs is shown on the plain spanned by temperature increase and threshold temperature axis. The domain for integration to obtain the probability of exceeding threshold is colored with gray
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="11625_2018_536_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e579" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Table 
   <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a> presents the probabilities of exceeding the threshold temperatures for Arctic summer sea ice and the Greenland ice sheet (see Step 5 of the algorithm). The probabilities of exceeding the threshold for the Greenland ice sheet were estimated as 24.8 (13.6)% for T15, 44.5 (26.4)% for T20, 62.5 (39.8)% for T25, and 88.1 (77.6)% for BaU, where the number in parentheses is the probability estimated assuming that the PDF of the threshold temperature follows a uniform distribution. The probability using a uniform distribution was also applied here to investigate the sensitivity of the estimated probability against the choice of probability distribution. A uniform distribution was used for this comparative PDF as an alternative assumption. The probabilities of exceeding the threshold for Arctic summer sea ice were estimated as 2.7 (3.0)% for T15, 16.6 (17.1)% for T20, 37.3 (37.5)% for T25, and 82.4 (82.2)% for BaU. Screen and Williamson (
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">2017</a>) estimated that the probability of a nearly ice-free Arctic sea at the end of summer was less than 1/100,000 for a 1.5 °C increase in temperature. Although our estimation showed a slightly higher probability for T15 than that of Screen and Williamson (
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">2017</a>), both studies indicated that the probability of exceeding the threshold temperature for Arctic summer sea ice would be low under T15.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <div id="Tab1" class="table-wrap">
    <span class="label">Table 1</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Probability (%) of exceeding threshold temperature by 2100</p>
    </div>
    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
     <thead>
      <tr>
       <th align="left"/>
       <th align="left">T15</th>
       <th align="left">T20</th>
       <th align="left">T25</th>
       <th align="left">BaU</th>
      </tr>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">Greenland ice sheet</td>
       <td char="(" align="char">24.8 (13.6)</td>
       <td char="(" align="char">44.5 (26.4)</td>
       <td char="(" align="char">60.2 (39.8)</td>
       <td char="(" align="char">88.1 (77.6)</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">Arctic summer sea ice</td>
       <td char="(" align="char">2.7 (3.0)</td>
       <td char="(" align="char">16.6 (17.1)</td>
       <td char="(" align="char">37.3 (37.5)</td>
       <td char="(" align="char">83.4 (82.2)</td>
      </tr>
     </tbody>
    </table>
    <div class="table-wrap-foot">
     <p>The numbers in parenthesis represent the probability estimated by assuming that the probability density function of the threshold temperature exhibits a uniform distribution</p>
     <p>The range of the uniform distribution is 1.0–4.0 for Greenland ice sheet and 1.95–2.95 for Arctic summer sea ice. These ranges are given as the 95% confidence intervals of the log-normal distribution for Greenland ice sheet and normal distribution for Arctic summer sea ice</p>
    </div>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results showed that if the policy target temperature were low, the likelihood of exceeding the threshold for the Greenland ice sheet would be higher than that of Arctic summer sea ice. This was due to our assumption that the lower bound of the threshold for the Greenland ice sheet was lower than that of Arctic summer sea ice. The assumption that the PDF of the Greenland ice sheet was right-skewed also explained the relatively high probability of exceeding the threshold even though the temperature target was low.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">However, under a high temperature increase (i.e., BaU), the probability of crossing the threshold for Arctic summer sea ice would rapidly increase, as indicated by a sudden increase in the probability from 37.3% (T2.5) to 82.4% (BaU). This rapid increase in probability arose because the upper bound of the threshold temperature of Arctic summer sea ice was lower than that of the Greenland ice sheet, even though the lower bound of the threshold temperature of Arctic summer sea ice was higher than that of the Greenland ice sheet. Therefore, the probability of exceeding the threshold of Arctic summer sea ice increases rapidly under high temperature increases. However, it should be noted that these trends in the probability of exceeding thresholds strongly depend on the assumptions of the form of the PDF and range of the confidence interval.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our probabilistic assessment quantitatively showed the variations in the probability of exceeding thresholds according to policy target temperature. By placing assumptions on climate sensitivity and tipping points, this computation suggested that identifying the lower bound of the threshold and narrowing the uncertainty range of the threshold, as well as identifying their PDFs could greatly improve the confidence of the estimated probability of exceeding the threshold temperature.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It should be noted that the probabilities of exceeding thresholds were derived from several assumptions. For instance, we assumed a log-normal distribution for the Greenland ice sheet and a normal distribution for the Arctic summer sea ice, despite the fact that the probability distributions for those thresholds remain unknown. Thereby, a sensitivity analysis of the estimated probabilities was performed using a uniform distribution as the PDF of tipping points. The ranges of uniform distribution for the Greenland ice sheet and Arctic summer sea ice were set as (1.0–4.0) and (1.95–2.95), respectively. The sensitivity analysis (see the numbers in parenthesis in Table 
   <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>) suggested that the probabilities varied according to the choice of PDFs. Therefore, it is crucial to keep updating the PDFs and threshold ranges to enhance the reliability of the assessed probabilities of exceeding thresholds. Moreover, further advancement in scientific understanding of climate sensitivity is also vitally important, because previous studies employed various PDFs to fit climate sensitivity (e.g., Hare and Meinshausen 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">2006</a>; Annan and Hargreaves 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">2011</a>) and the likely range of climate sensitivity given in AR5 (IPCC 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">2013</a>) is still wide (i.e., 1.5–4.5).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition, the meaning of “exceeding thresholds” should be interpreted carefully. Passing the threshold of the Greenland ice sheet does not mean that it reaches the point of no return; if the temperature reaches only slightly above the threshold and then decreases below the threshold within the transition time, the surface mass balance of the Greenland ice sheet could become positive, although it might not recover to the original state observed before crossing the threshold (Robinson et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">2012</a>). Passing the threshold of Arctic summer sea ice indicates a nearly ice-free state of Arctic Ocean in September and does not necessarily mean that the climate system of the Arctic Ocean has passed into a different phase; as described in AR5 (IPCC 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">2013</a>), although sudden loss of Arctic summer sea ice was indicated in some climate projections (Holland et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">2006</a>; Vavrus et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">2012</a>; Döscher and Koenigk 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">2013</a>), those projections are not necessarily associated with the existence of a tipping point to another stable state or irreversible process (Amstrup et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2010</a>; Lenton 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">2012</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
