<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The entire study area encompasses an area of about 1900 km
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>, of which the largest part is located in the Netherlands (∼1500 km
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>). The Dommel River has a total length of 146 km and runs from its source in the Kempen region to its confluence with the Meuse close to s’-Hertogenbosch, located downstream of Eindhoven (De Jonge et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">2008</xref>) (see Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>). The Dommel catchment consists of a natural system of brooks and streams, extended with a network of ditches and tile drainage that have been installed for agricultural purposes in the nineteenth and twentieth century (Visser et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" class="xref">2012</xref>). In addition, water levels in the Dommel catchment are controlled by the artificial supply of water from the Meuse River via the Zuid-Willemsvaart, Wilhelmina, Beatrix, and Eindhoven canals during dry periods in order to prevent agricultural damages (Vroege and Hoijtink 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" class="xref">2013</xref>). In the Dommel catchment, elevation ranges from 80 m a.s.l. (above sea level) at the Kempen Plateau to 2 m a.s.l. close to the Dommel/Meuse confluence. The region experiences a humid and temperate climate with a mean temperature of 10.3 °C and a mean annual precipitation of 750 mm (Eindhoven meteorological station) (KNMI 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" class="xref">2011</xref>). The prevailing soil types in the Dommel catchment are podzols (De Bakker and Schelling 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">1989</xref>). Geologically, the Dommel catchment can be divided into two regions: the 
 <italic class="italic">Campine High</italic> in the southwest and the 
 <italic class="italic">Roer Valley Graben</italic> in the northeast. The Roer Valley Graben is a region of active tectonic subsidence, bounded by the Feldbiss Fault (southwest) and the Peel Boundary Fault (northeast) (Schokker 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" class="xref">2003</xref>; Petelet-Giraud et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" class="xref">2009</xref>). The upper geological unit in the Roer Valley Graben is the Late Pleistocene/Holocene Boxtel Formation characterized by sandy deposits alternated with thin loam and peat layers. The Boxtel Formation and the Middle-Pleistocene Beegden Formation belong to the upper aquifer in the Roer Valley Graben (i.e., with a thickness of approximately 100 m). The upper geological unit at the Campine High is the Middle-Pleistocene Sterksel Formation, which is characterized by coarse-grained fluvial deposits from the Rhine River. This formation belongs to the upper aquifer at the Campine High (i.e., with a thickness of 10–20 m). The underlying formations are (with increasing age) Early-Pleistocene Stamproy Formation, Early-Pleistocene Waalre Formation, Early-Pleistocene Maassluis Formation, Pliocene Kiezeloöliet Formation, Pliocene Oosterhout Formation, and the Miocene Breda Formation (De Mulder et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">2003</xref>; Schokker 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" class="xref">2003</xref>).
</p>
