<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div id="ece34501-abs-0001" class="abstract" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <div class="title">Abstract</div>
 <p>The humphead wrasse (
  <span class="italic">Cheilinus undulatus</span>) and bumphead parrotfish (
  <span class="italic">Bolbometopon muricatum</span>) are two of the largest, most iconic fishes of Indo‐Pacific coral reefs. Both species form prized components of subsistence and commercial fisheries and are vulnerable to overfishing. 
  <span class="italic">C. undulatus</span> is listed as Endangered and 
  <span class="italic">B. muricatum</span> as Vulnerable on the 
  <span style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">IUCN</span> Red List of Threatened Species. We investigated how night spearfishing pressure and habitat associations affected both species in a relatively lightly exploited setting; the Kia fishing grounds, Isabel Province, Solomon Islands. We used fisheries‐independent data from underwater visual census surveys and negative binomial models to estimate abundances of adult 
  <span class="italic">C. undulatus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">B. muricatum</span> as a function of spearfishing pressure and reef strata. Our results showed that, in Kia, night spearfishing pressure from free divers had no measurable effect on 
  <span class="italic">C. undulatus</span> abundances, but abundances of 
  <span class="italic">B. muricatum</span> were 3.6 times lower in areas of high spearfishing pressure, after accounting for natural variations due to habitat preferences. It is likely the species’ different nocturnal aggregation behaviors, combined with the fishers’ use of night spearfishing by spot‐checking underpin these species’ varying susceptibility. Our study highlights that 
  <span class="italic">B. muricatum</span> is extremely susceptible to night spearfishing; however, we do not intend to draw conservation attention away from 
  <span class="italic">C. undulatus</span>. Our data relate only to the Kia fishing grounds, where human population density is low, the spot‐checking strategy is effective for reliably spearing large numbers of fish, particularly 
  <span class="italic">B. muricatum</span>, and fisheries have only recently begun to be commercialized; such conditions are increasingly rare. Instead, we recommend that regional managers assess the state of their fisheries and the dynamics affecting the vulnerability of the fishes to fishing pressure based on local‐scale, fisheries‐independent data, where resources permit.
 </p>
</div>
