<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="P81" class="p">Currently, flux-based metrics are not characterized in the TOAR database, but are discussed in this section for completeness. The flux-based metric is described as: 
 <list list-type="bullet" id="L12" class="list">
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="P82" class="p">The accumulated Phytotoxic Ozone Dose (i.e., the accumulated stomatal flux) of ozone above a flux threshold of Y (POD
    <sub class="sub">Y</sub>). The POD
    <sub class="sub">Y</sub> is calculated for the appropriate time-window as the sum over time of the differences between hourly mean values of ozone stomatal flux (
    <italic class="italic">F</italic>
    <sub class="sub">
     <italic class="italic">st</italic>
    </sub>) and Y nmol m
    <sup class="sup">–2</sup> PLA s
    <sup class="sup">–1</sup> for the peri ods when 
    <italic class="italic">F</italic>
    <sub class="sub">
     <italic class="italic">st</italic>
    </sub> exceeds Y during daylight hours, where PLA is defined as projected leaf area, or, the one-sided area of a leaf perpendicular to the incoming radiation. The DO
    <sub class="sub">3</sub>SE model (
    <xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Emberson et al., 2000</xref>) was adopted by CLRTAP for calculating the accumulated stomatal flux of ozone from hourly values of ozone, together with the following stomatal conductance modifying factors: temperature, vapor pressure deficit (VPD), light (irradiance), soil water potential (SWP) or plant available water (PAW), ozone value, and plant development stage (phenology). The Y threshold varies between species as do the parameterizations for each of the flux modifying factors. Two types of POD
    <sub class="sub">Y</sub> model exist: POD
    <sub class="sub">Y</sub>IAM which has a simplified parameterization and is suitable for large-scale integrated assessment, and POD
    <sub class="sub">Y</sub>SPEC, species-specific parameterization of the flux model. Local and regional parameterizations have been defined for POD
    <sub class="sub">Y</sub>SPEC and POD
    <sub class="sub">Y</sub>IAM in 
    <xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">CLRTAP (2017)</xref> for a range of crops, tree and grassland species/species groups and used to define 21 critical levels, above which negative effects of ozone on crop yield, biodiversity and tree growth are expected. Further information can be found in summary in 
    <xref rid="R137" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Mills et al. (2011b)</xref>, and in more detail including response functions in 
    <xref rid="R65" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Grünhage et al. (2012)</xref> for wheat, Gonzalez et al. (2014) for tomato, and 
    <xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Büker et al. (2015)</xref> for tree species. The POD
    <sub class="sub">Y</sub> model has also been applied in China to derive flux-effect relationships for wheat (
    <xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Feng et al., 2012</xref>) and poplar (
    <xref rid="R86" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hu et al., 2015</xref>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
