<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par24" class="p">The gross storage capacity (billion cubic meters: BCM) of the reservoirs, height (m), total installed capacity (MW) of the dams, and reservoir storage (2002–2014 period) were obtained from India WRIS (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.india-wris.nrsc.gov.in" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.india-wris.nrsc.gov.in</ext-link>) (Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S1</xref>). The variation in the storage of the reservoirs is governed by the inflow from the upstream catchment area and outflow from the reservoir to meet the purpose of the dams (hydropower generation, irrigation, and other water demands). Inflow to the reservoir is primarily influenced by the precipitation over the catchment area (Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S13</xref>). The seasonal storage variation was used to determine the operation year for each reservoir, which starts from September (once the monsoon season is over), based on the criteria that the reservoir begins releasing water from this month
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">12</xref>
 </sup>. The simulated streamflow was fed to a reservoir as inflow and the other parameters of the dam to estimate the monthly release were obtained using the Eq. (
 <xref rid="Equ1" ref-type="" class="xref">1</xref>). Two conditions were enforced while using the method:
 <list list-type="alpha-lower" class="list">
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par25" class="p">The minimum monthly release was set as 10% of the monthly inflow to the reservoir, and</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par26" class="p">As mentioned in Liu 
    <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
    <sup class="sup">
     <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">5</xref>
    </sup>, a minimum of 10% of the total capacity of reservoirs is maintained.
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
