<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The present study investigates the impact of incoming shortwave radiation, incoming longwave radiation, soil moisture, and albedo on the interannual variability and multidecadal trend of monthly means of daily maximum near‐surface air temperature using stepwise multiple linear regression. The four considered variables can explain 79% of interannual temperature variability and 99% of multidecadal temperature trend on land (Figures 
 <xref rid="grl57416-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref>a and 
 <xref rid="grl57416-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref>b and 
 <xref rid="grl57416-supinf-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">supporting information</xref> Figures 
 <xref rid="grl57416-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S2</xref>a and 
 <xref rid="grl57416-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S2</xref>b). While radiation is an essential variable over almost all land area, land surface conditions have a pronounced impact on temperature variability and trend in some confined regions (Figures 
 <xref rid="grl57416-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="grl57416-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref>c–
 <xref rid="grl57416-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref>f, 
 <xref rid="grl57416-supinf-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">supporting information</xref> Figures S1 and 
 <xref rid="grl57416-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S2</xref>). This is also reflected in the effect that typical variations of the explanatory variables have on interannual temperature variability (Figure 
 <xref rid="grl57416-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3</xref>, left columns). Splitting the multidecadal temperature trend into its different contributions (Figure 
 <xref rid="grl57416-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3</xref>, right columns) reveals that incoming longwave radiation contributes homogeneously to the warming trend, while the effect of incoming shortwave radiation, soil moisture, and albedo exhibits more spatial variations and is opposing the trend in some regions.
</p>
