<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The quantification of among‐tree variability and an analytical zooming in, below the population level, has long been stressed to be important (Carrer, 
 <xref rid="ece33290-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>; Graumlich, 
 <xref rid="ece33290-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1991</xref>; Vanoni et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33290-bib-0091" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>), but has hitherto been neglected in the analysis of climate–growth relationships. In other studies, temperatures of many and quite different months were found to be related to population mean growth across tree species at treeline in the European Alps, even with large differences for single species. Still, there is a stronger tendency of larch growth to be determined by temperatures over longer periods in the current year as well as in the year preceding growth ring formation (King, Fonti, Nievergelt, Büntgen, &amp; Frank, 
 <xref rid="ece33290-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>) compared to other species at treeline in the Alps. Based on “classical” correlation analyses, growth of Swiss stone pine and mountain pine, for example, tends to be explained by mean temperatures of only 1 or 2 months or summer seasonal means (Carrer et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33290-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1998</xref>; Lenz et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33290-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Oberhuber et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33290-bib-0076" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>). These findings are partly supported by our results, showing larch at Bosco/Gurin to include the largest number of monthly temperature variables in the LMM (Figure 
 <xref rid="ece33290-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3</xref>). However, our use of an information‐theoretic model selection of LMMs resulted in a substantially higher number of significant covariates also for spruce, Swiss stone pine, and mountain pine. This can largely be ascribed to the capacity of LMMs to explain not only a mean population signal, but also to account for among‐tree variability in the estimation of relevant covariates by employing tree‐specific random effects.
</p>
