<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The species‐ and site‐specific temperature–growth LMMs showed common patterns, but also slightly differing findings. The fixed effects exhibited clear seasonal periods for larch and spruce growth at both sites, but somewhat less clear patterns for Swiss stone pine and mountain pine (Figure 
 <xref rid="ece33290-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3</xref>). Still, all LMMs yielded a strong positive effect of temperature in June/July (larch, spruce) and May/July (Swiss stone pine, mountain pine), forming periods of strong positive effects of summer temperature regardless of tree species and site. This generally agrees with previous studies using correlation analyses (Carrer et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33290-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1998</xref>; Graumlich, 
 <xref rid="ece33290-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1991</xref>; King, Gugerli, Fonti, &amp; Frank, 
 <xref rid="ece33290-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Kirdyanov et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33290-bib-0057" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2003</xref>; Oberhuber et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33290-bib-0076" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>). Growth of Swiss stone pine and mountain pine does not seem to be driven by temperatures during a continuous period of summer months, as for both species the positive effects of May and July were interrupted by weak negative effects in June. In their study on mountain pine, Lenz et al. (
 <xref rid="ece33290-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>) explained this pattern with temperatures early in the growing season to determine the width of the cambium and therefore to be the main determinant of ring width. Temperatures later in the growing season were assumed to determine the earlywood–latewood ratio. Given the similar pattern in our study, this explanation may also apply to Swiss stone pine, but with a somewhat higher impact of cambium formation on ring width than the earlywood–latewood ratio. For all species and sites, the random effects of these months exhibited low standard deviations relative to the fixed effects, thus indicating low among‐tree variability and the high importance of summer temperatures for synchronizing tree growth at treeline, regardless of tree characteristics and other abiotic growth modulators.
</p>
