<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We fit linear and quadratic ordinary least squares regression models between seasonal precipitation (predictor variable) and the detrended growth index (response variable). Response functions were calculated from 1895 (the start of the PRISM precipitation estimates) through the ending year of tree-ring measurements, which varied by site but was never earlier than 1970. Any sites where the slope of the linear model was negative or not significantly different from zero, when controlling the false discovery rate at α
 <sub class="sub">global</sub> = 0.05 (
 <xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">46</italic>
 </xref>), were deemed to be not influenced by precipitation during that season. For the remaining sites, we selected the best model using the Akaike information criterion (AIC) (
 <xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">47</italic>
 </xref>), which penalizes the quadratic models for the additional parameter. Sites where AIC
 <sub class="sub">linear</sub> ≤ AIC
 <sub class="sub">quadratic</sub> (i.e., where the linear model outperformed the quadratic model) responded “symmetrically” to precipitation (
 <xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">12</italic>
 </xref>). Sites where AIC
 <sub class="sub">quadratic</sub> &lt; AIC
 <sub class="sub">linear</sub> (i.e., where the quadratic model outperformed the linear model) responded “asymmetrically” to precipitation. These were further subdivided into “negative asymmetric” relationships (concave-down curves in which increasing precipitation has diminishing returns for growth) and “positive asymmetric” relationships (concave-up curves in which increasing precipitation has increasing returns for growth) (
 <xref rid="F2" ref-type="fig" class="xref">Fig. 2E</xref>). Because the 6-month cool/warm-season distinction may partly mask subseasonal growth responses of some species and regions, we also conducted the same analyses using seasonal precipitation totals in the traditional 3-month meteorological seasons starting with autumn (September to November) before the year of growth through summer (June to August) during the year of growth.
</p>
