<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="gcb13152-sec-0007" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <sec id="gcb13152-sec-0008" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Limitations</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results presented here are dependent on the ability of the models used to represent the observed natural variability. Global‐scale information on variability derived from satellite data is only available for SST and chlorophyll concentration (and derived products, such as PP). Overall, the models represent the natural variability in SST very well, although it is underestimated in the Arctic (Fig. S4). For chlorophyll, observed variability is generally larger than modelled in the coastal and polar regions (Fig. S5). Typically, modelled variability is lower than observed variability, particularly in biogeochemical parameters (e.g. Cadule 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb13152-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb13152-bib-0004">2010</a>; Laepple &amp; Huybers, 
   <a rid="gcb13152-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb13152-bib-0018">2014</a>). Generally, we find a similar pattern, although with some exceptions such as chlorophyll in the oligotrophic gyres in the HadGEM models (see Fig. S5). Increased levels of variability would result in weaker signal to noise ratio, and thus longer 
   <span class="italic">n*</span>. Note also that the observations do not represent purely natural variability as they contain responses to both natural and anthropogenic forcing. The modelled spatial footprints are similar to those calculated from observed SST and chlorophyll (Fig. S6, compare to Fig. 
   <a rid="gcb13152-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#gcb13152-fig-0003">3</a>b, f). For SST, the pattern and shape of the footprints are very similar in observations and models, although they are slightly larger in the observations so that 18% of the ocean is covered by BGC‐SOs (13% for models). In chlorophyll, results are mixed with the size, shape and isotropy of the footprints being similar in observations and models for some BGC‐SOs, for example BATS and PAP, but not in others, for example OOI‐Argentine. Both observations and models suggest that 12% of the ocean is represented by BGC‐SOs for chlorophyll, although the distribution of coverage is slightly different.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The size and shape of the footprints is also dependent on our definition of ‘representative’, which takes into account the mean and variability of time series. For some studies, other metrics of representativeness will be more appropriate and the size of the footprints would thus change accordingly. Additionally, we test repeatedly for statistical significance. At the 5% critical level chosen here, 1 in 20 regressions will produce a ‘false positive’ (i.e. significant when no correlation is actually present), and therefore footprints may in reality be smaller than shown here. Finally, the relatively coarse resolution of the models excludes (sub)‐mesoscale variability which will act to reduce the size of the footprints.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In our analysis, we test only for linear trends by using a generalized least squares approach. In reality, trends may be nonlinear. We tested whether our linear fits are reasonable by verifying the underlying assumptions that the residuals are AR(1) and normally distributed with a constant variance and found that the majority (~66%) of calculated trends meet these assumptions. Furthermore, even though the linear trends estimated using generalized least squares seem reasonable to estimate 
   <span class="italic">n*</span> in most cases, using different trend detection techniques based on nonparametric statistics or Bayesian approaches (e.g. Chandler &amp; Scott, 
   <a rid="gcb13152-bib-0005" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb13152-bib-0005">2011</a>) may result in different estimates of 
   <span class="italic">n*</span>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Finally, the coarse spatial resolution (1°) of the models (i.e. mesoscale variability is not simulated) and the potential underestimation of temporal variability in the models imply that our results are likely to be a ‘best case’ scenario. In reality, the footprints are likely to be smaller than estimated here, due to unresolved mesoscale variability; similarly, 
   <span class="italic">n*</span> is likely to be longer than estimated here, due to unresolved temporal variability.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="gcb13152-sec-0009" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Time and space scales of observation</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The analysis presented here quantifies the time and space scales over which biogeochemical observations need to be made to detect climate change trends, and makes a preliminary assessment of whether the current BGC‐SO network meets those requirements. In general, SST and pH are most rapidly detectable (
   <span class="italic">n*</span> ~15 years). These variables respond directly to increasing atmospheric CO
   <sub>2</sub> concentration, resulting in strong trends. In addition, natural variability is relatively low in SST and pH, particularly in low latitudes. Note however that pH can be very variable in coastal regions (Duarte 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb13152-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb13152-bib-0009">2013</a>) which are not resolved in these global models.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In keeping with our previous work (Henson 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb13152-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb13152-bib-0013">2010</a>), we find that chlorophyll and PP require longer time series to detect trends (
   <span class="italic">n*</span> ~32 years). A key question arising from the earlier work was whether climate change‐driven trends could be more rapidly detectable in other biogeochemical variables. Here, we find that the answer is generally ‘no’ (except for pH), with oxygen and nitrate concentration, export and nondiatom PP all requiring time series &gt;25 years in length (global median; Table 
   <a rid="gcb13152-tbl-0001" ref-type="table-wrap" href="#gcb13152-tbl-0001">1</a>). There are however clear regional differences, with the equatorial Atlantic, Benguela and Arabian Sea requiring fewer years of data to distinguish a trend. In contrast, in parts of the Southern Ocean and Northeast Pacific, detecting trends requires very long records and in some cases changes are nondetectable in the 95 year timescale of the simulations used here. These results are in contrast with the hypothesis that ecosystems can ‘integrate’ the environmental conditions that they experience, improving the signal to noise ratio and permitting detection of weak climate change‐driven trends (Taylor 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb13152-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb13152-bib-0025">2002</a>). Instead we find that detection time is shorter for environmental forcing factors than for the ecosystem response.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">According to our analysis, some BGC‐SOs have been in operation sufficiently long that climate change trends in some variables should be detectable (Table S2). For example, ALOHA was established in 1988 (~27 years ago at the time of writing) and so climate change trends may now be detectable in their records in all parameters except chlorophyll concentration. Indeed, trends have been identified in pH, PP, SST, chlorophyll concentration and nitrate at ALOHA (Saba 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb13152-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb13152-bib-0023">2010</a>; Kim 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb13152-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb13152-bib-0016">2014</a>). The presence of a statistically significant trend in chlorophyll at ALOHA is inconsistent with our estimate of 
   <span class="italic">n*</span>, implying that the observed trend should not yet be ascribed to climate change (or that the modelled 
   <span class="italic">n*</span> is an overestimate, see 
   <a rid="gcb13152-sec-0008" ref-type="sec" href="#gcb13152-sec-0008">Limitations</a> section). Other stations need to be in operation for some years more, for example PAP where, although trends in pH may be detectable after 14 years of operation, other variables require ~25 years of data. With some exceptions, the current network of BGC‐SOs has not been in operation sufficiently long to detect climate change‐driven trends.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An analysis of the SST and pH data collected at BATS illustrates how the 
   <span class="italic">n*</span> estimates presented in Table S2 and Fig. 
   <a rid="gcb13152-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#gcb13152-fig-0001">1</a> can be applied to 
   <span class="italic">in situ</span> time series. At BATS, our analysis suggests that ~15 years of data are needed to distinguish a long‐term trend in pH from background variability (Table S2). We split the observed pH time series (Bates 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb13152-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb13152-bib-0001">2012</a> and N. Bates, personal communication) into overlapping 10 and 15 year chunks and tested for trends by applying Eqn 
   <a rid="gcb13152-disp-0001" ref-type="disp-formula" href="#gcb13152-disp-0001">(1)</a>. Time series as short as 10 years evince statistically significant trends for most periods, however our analysis suggests that, with an estimated 
   <span class="italic">n*</span> of 15 years, it would be ill‐advised to unequivocally attribute the trend in a 10 year time series to climate change. For 15 year time series, all periods show a statistically significant trend which is likely a genuine long‐term trend. For the whole time series of 30 years, the trend is −0.002 units, which is statistically significant at the 95% level. As the length of the complete time series far exceeds the 
   <span class="italic">n*</span> suggested by our analysis, this trend is highly likely to be climate change‐driven.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the SST time series at BATS, we find that 
   <span class="italic">n*</span> is ~11.5 years (Table S2). Splitting the time series into 10 year pieces, a statistically significant trend is found for the period 1987–1996 (but not for other 10 year chunks). Our analysis suggests that this is unlikely to be a long‐term trend as the time series is shorter than the estimated 
   <span class="italic">n*</span>. Indeed, increasing the length of the time series chunks to 11 years yields the result that the trend in the period 1987–1997 is only just statistically significant at the 95% level. Adding another year of data (forming 12 year pieces) results in the trend for the period 1987–1998 becoming nonsignificant. This result matches exactly with our analysis: that any apparent trend in SST in a dataset shorter than 
   <span class="italic">n*</span> (in this case 11.5 years) is unlikely to be due to climate change forcing, but instead is likely to be an artefact associated with natural variability dominating the short time series. For the entire BATS SST time series, there is no statistically significant trend. As the dataset is substantially longer than our estimated 
   <span class="italic">n*</span>, it is likely that if a climate change‐driven trend were present it would be detectable, suggesting that anthropogenic forcing of SST at BATS is not yet distinguishable from natural variability.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Complementary to estimates of the timescales over which observations need to be made is the consideration of the spatial scales required to ensure adequate representation of ocean conditions. Our results demonstrate that the spatial footprint for SST, pH and nitrate is larger than for biogeochemical variables such as PP. As such, the current network of BGC‐SOs are representative of ~15% of the ocean for pH, but only 9% for thermocline oxygen concentration (Table 
   <a rid="gcb13152-tbl-0001" ref-type="table-wrap" href="#gcb13152-tbl-0001">1</a>). For some of the variables considered here there are plentiful alternative sources of data, such as satellite‐derived SST and chlorophyll which ensure global‐scale coverage of surface conditions ensuring that data availability is unlikely to limit trend detection. In addition, platforms such as Argo and bio‐Argo floats, gliders and other autonomous vehicles can provide depth‐resolved data on temperature, chlorophyll, oxygen etc. Therefore for these variables, our calculations underestimate the proportion of ocean represented by current observations. However, variables such as carbon export or phytoplankton functional type‐specific PP are currently not routinely derived from autonomous platforms, so that ship‐serviced BGC‐SOs are the primary source of data.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The current observing network results in substantial regions of the ocean which are not represented by any BGC‐SO. The Arctic and the majority of the Southern Hemisphere are particularly poorly covered. Some of these areas overlap with regions where trends are likely to be rapidly detectable (Fig. 
   <a rid="gcb13152-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#gcb13152-fig-0002">2</a>b), implying that timely detection of climate change‐driven trends in ocean biogeochemistry may be jeopardized by the sparsity of the observations in these areas.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Other regions, notably the west coast of the USA, are represented by multiple BGC‐SOs. One may ask therefore whether some stations could be cut without loss of information for climate change detection. However, it should be noted that the global models used here are relatively coarse resolution (1 × 1°). In addition, this analysis focuses only on the requirements for climate change detection, whereas BGC‐SOs serve many other purposes. Spatial variability will occur on scales smaller than the model resolution, which may be relevant for the primary goals of a BGC‐SO. For example in the case of CALCOFI, a primary goal is fisheries assessment, for which higher spatial resolution sampling is likely to be necessary than for climate trend detection.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="gcb13152-sec-0010" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Implications for ocean observatories</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results allow an initial assessment of the adequacy of the current BGC‐SO network for climate change trend detection, in terms of space and time scale considerations. In many cases, long running SOs are close to having sufficiently long time series to distinguish climate change‐driven trends from background natural variability, for example ALOHA (Table S2). However, these well‐established SOs provide only limited spatial coverage (Fig. 
   <a rid="gcb13152-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#gcb13152-fig-0003">3</a>). Several of the BGC‐SOs considered here are relatively new or still in the planning stages and so, although some of them fill in gaps in the spatial coverage of the network, they may require decades more data before a climate change trend can be detected.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">If the opportunity arose to design a new ocean observatory, with the primary goal of detecting climate change trends, the optimal location would be in a region of large spatial length scales and rapidly detectable trends (ignoring logistical issues). As an example, the size of the footprint for chlorophyll concentration calculated at every grid point (in the same way as for individual BGC‐SOs, see 
   <a rid="gcb13152-sec-0002" ref-type="sec" href="#gcb13152-sec-0002">Materials and methods</a>) is plotted in Fig. 
   <a rid="gcb13152-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#gcb13152-fig-0004">4</a>. Largest footprints for chlorophyll are located in the equatorial Pacific and Indian Oceans, and parts of the Southern Ocean. In the case of the equatorial regions, these also overlap with areas of relatively short 
   <span class="italic">n*</span> (&lt;35 years), marked with a black contour in Fig. 
   <a rid="gcb13152-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#gcb13152-fig-0004">4</a>. None of the existing BGC‐SOs are located within these optimal trend detection regions.
  </p>
  <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="gcb13152-fig-0004" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Figure 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Size of footprint (10
     <span class="sup">6</span> km
     <span class="sup">2</span>) for chlorophyll time series calculated at every grid point, where the footprint is defined as pixels that have similar mean and variability (see 
     <a rid="gcb13152-sec-0002" ref-type="sec" href="#gcb13152-sec-0002">Materials and methods</a>). Black contour marks where the footprint is relatively large (&gt;7 × 10
     <span class="sup">6</span> km
     <span class="sup">2</span>) and 
     <span class="italic">n*</span> is relatively short (&lt;35 years). White stars mark locations of 
     <span style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">BGC</span>‐
     <span style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">SO</span>s.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div id="nlm-graphic-7" xlink:href="GCB-22-1561-g004" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although existing BGC‐SOs may not necessarily be in an ideal location if the primary aim is detecting climate change, for the well‐established stations little is to be gained from relocating them. Generally, 
   <span class="italic">n*</span> is &gt;20 years (except for SST and pH), so if &gt;20 years of data have already been collected, then in most cases more than half the required time series to detect climate change is already in hand (and in some cases much more than half). Importantly, some BGC‐SOs do not have climate change detection as a primary goal, focusing instead on process understanding. In these cases, the discussion presented here of time and space scales is of less relevance.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results suggest that the current network of BGC‐SOs is, in some cases, adequate to assess climate change trends at the local scale. Some BGC‐SOs may already have, or will soon have, sufficiently long time series to detect climate change‐driven trends. Care, however, needs to be taken when calculating trends. Autocorrelation, which is prevalent in geophysical time series, can lead to the detection of spurious trends if not accounted for, particularly when using short time series (Wunsch, 
   <a rid="gcb13152-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb13152-bib-0029">1999</a>). In addition, any ‘interventions’ in the time series, such as due to changes in sampling methodology or instrumentation, gaps in the dataset, relocation of sampling site etc., will tend to increase the number of years of data needed to detect a trend as the intervention effect must then be estimated and accounted for (Beaulieu 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb13152-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb13152-bib-0002">2013</a>). Finally, careful choice of the appropriate statistical model to fit to the data must be made as trends may not be linear.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">At the global scale, the existing BGC‐SO network is representative of 9–15% of the ocean (Table 
   <a rid="gcb13152-tbl-0001" ref-type="table-wrap" href="#gcb13152-tbl-0001">1</a>). Clearly in order for large‐scale biogeochemical trends to be characterized, the BGC‐SOs must be augmented with additional data. Our analysis makes clear that continued satellite‐derived observations are essential due to their global coverage, but also that ongoing support of existing BGC‐SOs and more rapid development of autonomous methods, including the bio‐Argo network, would be beneficial. Currently ~200 bio‐Argo floats have been deployed, emphasizing that concerted international effort on the scale of the original Argo programme is required to achieve coverage on time and space scales suitable for climate change detection. The biological and biogeochemical properties that can be measured by bio‐Argo floats and other autonomous methods are currently limited, in particular when sensors are large or have high power requirements, or where sample collection is necessary. The network of ocean observatories will therefore still need to be maintained into the future. However, targeted deployment strategies could be used to sample regions with particularly poor data coverage, large spatial footprints and short detection times. The preliminary assessment carried out here could be developed into a full Observing System Simulation Experiment (e.g. Majkut 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
   <a rid="gcb13152-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb13152-bib-0020">2014</a>) to strategically optimize the observing network to ensure maximum effect for minimum effort.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
