<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="gcb13152-sec-0010" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Implications for ocean observatories</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results allow an initial assessment of the adequacy of the current BGC‐SO network for climate change trend detection, in terms of space and time scale considerations. In many cases, long running SOs are close to having sufficiently long time series to distinguish climate change‐driven trends from background natural variability, for example ALOHA (Table S2). However, these well‐established SOs provide only limited spatial coverage (Fig. 
  <a rid="gcb13152-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#gcb13152-fig-0003">3</a>). Several of the BGC‐SOs considered here are relatively new or still in the planning stages and so, although some of them fill in gaps in the spatial coverage of the network, they may require decades more data before a climate change trend can be detected.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">If the opportunity arose to design a new ocean observatory, with the primary goal of detecting climate change trends, the optimal location would be in a region of large spatial length scales and rapidly detectable trends (ignoring logistical issues). As an example, the size of the footprint for chlorophyll concentration calculated at every grid point (in the same way as for individual BGC‐SOs, see 
  <a rid="gcb13152-sec-0002" ref-type="sec" href="#gcb13152-sec-0002">Materials and methods</a>) is plotted in Fig. 
  <a rid="gcb13152-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#gcb13152-fig-0004">4</a>. Largest footprints for chlorophyll are located in the equatorial Pacific and Indian Oceans, and parts of the Southern Ocean. In the case of the equatorial regions, these also overlap with areas of relatively short 
  <span class="italic">n*</span> (&lt;35 years), marked with a black contour in Fig. 
  <a rid="gcb13152-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#gcb13152-fig-0004">4</a>. None of the existing BGC‐SOs are located within these optimal trend detection regions.
 </p>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="gcb13152-fig-0004" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 4</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Size of footprint (10
    <span class="sup">6</span> km
    <span class="sup">2</span>) for chlorophyll time series calculated at every grid point, where the footprint is defined as pixels that have similar mean and variability (see 
    <a rid="gcb13152-sec-0002" ref-type="sec" href="#gcb13152-sec-0002">Materials and methods</a>). Black contour marks where the footprint is relatively large (&gt;7 × 10
    <span class="sup">6</span> km
    <span class="sup">2</span>) and 
    <span class="italic">n*</span> is relatively short (&lt;35 years). White stars mark locations of 
    <span style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">BGC</span>‐
    <span style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">SO</span>s.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-7" xlink:href="GCB-22-1561-g004" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although existing BGC‐SOs may not necessarily be in an ideal location if the primary aim is detecting climate change, for the well‐established stations little is to be gained from relocating them. Generally, 
  <span class="italic">n*</span> is &gt;20 years (except for SST and pH), so if &gt;20 years of data have already been collected, then in most cases more than half the required time series to detect climate change is already in hand (and in some cases much more than half). Importantly, some BGC‐SOs do not have climate change detection as a primary goal, focusing instead on process understanding. In these cases, the discussion presented here of time and space scales is of less relevance.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results suggest that the current network of BGC‐SOs is, in some cases, adequate to assess climate change trends at the local scale. Some BGC‐SOs may already have, or will soon have, sufficiently long time series to detect climate change‐driven trends. Care, however, needs to be taken when calculating trends. Autocorrelation, which is prevalent in geophysical time series, can lead to the detection of spurious trends if not accounted for, particularly when using short time series (Wunsch, 
  <a rid="gcb13152-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb13152-bib-0029">1999</a>). In addition, any ‘interventions’ in the time series, such as due to changes in sampling methodology or instrumentation, gaps in the dataset, relocation of sampling site etc., will tend to increase the number of years of data needed to detect a trend as the intervention effect must then be estimated and accounted for (Beaulieu 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb13152-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb13152-bib-0002">2013</a>). Finally, careful choice of the appropriate statistical model to fit to the data must be made as trends may not be linear.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">At the global scale, the existing BGC‐SO network is representative of 9–15% of the ocean (Table 
  <a rid="gcb13152-tbl-0001" ref-type="table-wrap" href="#gcb13152-tbl-0001">1</a>). Clearly in order for large‐scale biogeochemical trends to be characterized, the BGC‐SOs must be augmented with additional data. Our analysis makes clear that continued satellite‐derived observations are essential due to their global coverage, but also that ongoing support of existing BGC‐SOs and more rapid development of autonomous methods, including the bio‐Argo network, would be beneficial. Currently ~200 bio‐Argo floats have been deployed, emphasizing that concerted international effort on the scale of the original Argo programme is required to achieve coverage on time and space scales suitable for climate change detection. The biological and biogeochemical properties that can be measured by bio‐Argo floats and other autonomous methods are currently limited, in particular when sensors are large or have high power requirements, or where sample collection is necessary. The network of ocean observatories will therefore still need to be maintained into the future. However, targeted deployment strategies could be used to sample regions with particularly poor data coverage, large spatial footprints and short detection times. The preliminary assessment carried out here could be developed into a full Observing System Simulation Experiment (e.g. Majkut 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>., 
  <a rid="gcb13152-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" href="#gcb13152-bib-0020">2014</a>) to strategically optimize the observing network to ensure maximum effect for minimum effort.
 </p>
</sec>
