<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Clock</span> gene
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For initial PCR tests, we used the primer pairs from Johnsen et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b54" href="#b54">2007</a>), to amplify the variable region of the 
  <span class="italic">Clock</span> gene locus (corresponding to the human 
  <span class="italic">Clock</span> gene exon 20; Steeves et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b92" href="#b92">1999</a>) with the following settings: initial denaturation at 94°C for 2 min, then 35 cycles of 94°C for 30 sec, 58°C for 30 sec, 72°C for 1 min and a final extension at 72°C for 7 min. In order to verify PCR products, a subset of 37 fragments was sequenced from Dutch and Spanish samples with 25 cycles of 96°C for 10 sec, 50°C for 5 sec, and 60°C for 4 min. Finally, the 
  <span class="italic">Clock</span> gene locus of pied flycatchers was screened for length polymorphism by PCR amplification and electrophoresis using an automatic DNA sequencer. PCR was conducted with an Alexa647 labeled forward primer 5′TGGAGCGGTAATGGTACCAAGTA 3′ and the reverse primer 5′ TCAGCTGTGACTGAGCTGGCT 3′ (Johnsen et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b54" href="#b54">2007</a>) with a final concentration of 0.2 μM each. We applied the same PCR conditions and detection methods as described for the microsatellites, except that PCR products from recent samples were diluted 1:10 to 1:100 before electrophoresis.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Museum samples for which we could not perform at least two replicates with concordant results for each marker (control region, microsatellites, and 
  <span class="italic">Clock</span> gene), or which were genotyped with less than eight of ten microsatellites, were discarded from further analyses. Swedish pied flycatchers collected on Öland are likely to be migrants heading to northern Sweden (Fransson and Hall-Karlsson 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b32" href="#b32">2008</a>). As we could not rule out that they also may migrate to Finland or Norway, we reanalyzed our data excluding these specimens. The exclusion of all potential migrants from Swedish populations did not alter the main picture, and therefore, we report results based on the complete data set.
 </p>
</sec>
