<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Non-neutral genetic differentiation</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Altogether, 275 pied flycatchers, belonging to nine different populations (geographical and temporal), were genotyped for length variation at the poly-Q locus of the 
  <span class="italic">Clock</span> gene. We identified five length variants ranging from 193 bp (10 poly-Q repeats) to 205 bp (14 poly-Q repeats). At least three different alleles were found in each population, and all five alleles were detected in the current Dutch as well as in the historic German population. No pied flycatcher population exhibited private alleles. However, allele 205 was only found once in a historic German sample and in one recent sample from the Netherlands, and allele 193 was not found in extant Norwegian and Swedish samples. The remaining alleles were found in all populations with allele 199 being much more abundant in all populations than the other two. The observed heterozygosity (
  <span class="italic">H</span>
  <sub>o</sub>) was consistent over the populations and ranged from 0.400 to 0.563 (Table 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="tbl1" href="#tbl1">1</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Pairwise comparisons among all populations yielded 
  <span class="italic">F</span>
  <sub>st</sub>-values ranging from zero to 0.0174. Only the pairwise comparison between the recent populations from the Netherlands and Spain showed low (
  <span class="italic">F</span>
  <sub>ST</sub>-value = 0.0174), but significant differentiation at the 
  <span class="italic">Clock</span> gene locus (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1" href="#SD1">Table S3</a>). The overall genetic differentiation index F
  <sub>st</sub> was zero. Results from AMOVA highlight that no variation was found among populations, but 100% of the variation is explained by variation within the populations.
 </p>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Poly-Q variation: Sex bias</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A subset of 205 samples was further analyzed for sex-specific differentiation at the poly-Q locus. GLM analysis performed in STATISTICA yielded no significant differences between geographical regions (
   <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.54) nor any interaction of population x gender (
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SD1" href="#SD1">Table S4</a>). Forty-two pied flycatcher individuals from the Spanish nest box population were tested for a correlation between laying dates (males were assigned the laying date of their mated female) and poly-Q genotype variation. We did not find any association of the two parameters for either females (
   <span class="italic">N</span> = 26; 
   <span class="italic">r</span> = −0.022) or males (
   <span class="italic">N</span> = 16; 
   <span class="italic">r</span> = 0.051).
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
