<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Global climate change has altered the phenology and distribution of many plant and animal species, resulting in mistiming such as disturbed ecological interactions across trophic levels (
  <span class="italic">i.e.,</span> predator prey or host parasite relationships) (review e. g., Parmesan 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b79" href="#b79">2006</a>; Gienapp et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b33" href="#b33">2008</a>; Hansen et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b44" href="#b44">2012</a>). In particular, global warming is an important driving force for rapid adaptive changes of migration and breeding phenology in migrating birds (Cotton 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b18" href="#b18">2003</a>; Gordo 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b37" href="#b37">2007</a>; Both 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b5" href="#b5">2010</a>; Gullett et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b39" href="#b39">2013</a>) as well as for local or regional demographic changes (Both et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b10" href="#b10">2010</a>). Stronger declines in population sizes of long-distance migrants have been observed in those populations that have suffered from climate-change-induced mistiming, as the synchrony between the birds and their food (e.g., bird laying dates and caterpillar abundances) has been distorted (Visser and Both 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b97" href="#b97">2005</a>). However, such population declines are more pronounced in Western Europe, where the rate of spring warming is higher than in northern Europe (Visser et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b98" href="#b98">2003</a>; Both et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b8" href="#b8">2004</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b10" href="#b10">2010</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The pied flycatcher (
  <span class="italic">Ficedula hypoleuca</span>) is a long-distance migrating passerine that has undergone remarkable changes in life-history traits in response to climate change (Fig. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" href="#fig01">1</a>). Over the last two decades, this species has shifted toward earlier laying dates in response to increased local temperatures (Both et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b8" href="#b8">2004</a>; Laaksonen et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b57" href="#b57">2006</a>) particularly in local Dutch populations with early caterpillar food peaks (Both and Visser 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b7" href="#b7">2005</a>). Despite the advancement in laying dates, this temporal shift has been insufficient to compensate costs associated with the earlier development of prey species. In areas with a late food peak, there was only a weak population decline of about 10%, while in habitats with an early food peak, such as oak forests, populations declined up to 90% (Both et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b9" href="#b9">2006</a>). These dramatic regional changes in population sizes might have a measurable effect on genetic diversity over time. To date, the manifold studies on the pied flycatcher genome were mainly concerned with differential selective pressures on autosomal and z-linked markers (Sætre et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b88" href="#b88">2001</a>; Ellegren et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b26" href="#b26">2012</a>; Hogner et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b53" href="#b53">2012</a>; Backström et al.
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b1" href="#b1">2013</a>) and on candidate genes encoding for plumage coloration (Lehtonen et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b61" href="#b61">2012</a>), while the timely aspect of very recent demographic changes was rather neglected. In order to document such changes, it is possible to utilize biological archives, such as museum collections, for genetic analyses if no long-term data sets are available (Wandeler et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b100" href="#b100">2007</a>; Ramakrishnan and Hadly 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b86" href="#b86">2009</a>). In a number of seminal studies, museum collections have been used to document, for example, the loss of genetic diversity in endangered species, the level of anthropogenic influences on population sizes and connectivity, range shifts, cryptic introductions as well as genetic introgression (e.g., Nystrom et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b75" href="#b75">2006</a>; Hekkala et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b49" href="#b49">2011</a>; Mende and Hundsdörfer 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b68" href="#b68">2013</a>). However, most of these studies have focused on temporal changes in genetic variation in neutral genetic markers, whereas only a few have examined the genetic variation in candidate genes (e.g., Hartley et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b47" href="#b47">2006</a>). Although recent environmental and global climate changes are in the focus of current biodiversity and evolutionary research (Reusch and Wood 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b87" href="#b87">2007</a>), only a few studies have compared individuals from museum collections and current populations to assess the genetic response of populations to temperature (Hadly et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b42" href="#b42">2004</a>; Balanya et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b2" href="#b2">2006</a>; Nielsen and Bekkevold 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b74" href="#b74">2012</a>).
 </p>
 <div id="fig01" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Pied flycatcher (
    <span class="italic">Ficedula hypoleuca</span>), male carrying caterpillar as nestling food (photo: Carlos Gutiérrez-Espósito). During recent decades, western European populations have strongly declined due to climate-induced changes to earlier food peaks in oak forest habitats.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="ece30003-4799-f1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here, we studied variation in selectively neutral mitochondrial and nuclear loci as well as one candidate gene in several current and historic European pied flycatcher populations, to test for potential effects of global climate change on the genetic architecture of populations. Sampling sites covered a large part of the species' breeding range, from Spain in the south to Germany, the Netherlands, and to Scandinavia in the north. First, we estimated the genetic variation in recent populations, and secondly, we compared current and historic samples, expecting stronger changes of genetic diversity over time in Dutch populations which underwent a more steep decline (Both et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b10" href="#b10">2010</a>) than the more stable populations of Eastern Germany and Sweden (Steffens et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b93" href="#b93">1998</a>; Flade and Schwarz 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b30" href="#b30">2004</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our third aim was to unravel patterns of natural selection caused by climate change. To this end, we also considered non-neutral genetic variation in a candidate gene approach. Based on the assumption that genes which are known to mediate behavior in one species are likely to mediate comparable behaviors in other species (Fitzpatrick et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b29" href="#b29">2005</a>), we have chosen a putative non-neutral candidate locus related to temperature-dependent breeding behavior. The 
  <span class="italic">Clock</span> gene locus belongs to a group of regulatory genes of the circadian clock in a wide range of invertebrate and vertebrate organisms (Yoshimura et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b156" href="#b156">2000</a>; Helfer et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b154" href="#b154">2006</a>; Zanquetta et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b103" href="#b103">2010</a>). Variation in 
  <span class="italic">Clock</span> genotypes is characterized by allele length polymorphism in the poly-Q region and was shown to change gradually along latitudinal clines in vertebrate model species (O'Malley and Banks 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b77" href="#b77">2008</a>; O'Malley 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b76" href="#b76">2010</a>). Also in some passerine birds, 
  <span class="italic">Clock</span> gene poly-Q length variation is associated with latitude of breeding site (Johnsen et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b54" href="#b54">2007</a>), breeding phenology (Liedvogel et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b64" href="#b64">2009</a>; Caprioli et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b14" href="#b14">2012</a>) and even with fitness-related traits such as clutch size (Dor et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b22" href="#b22">2012</a>) or timing and distance of juvenile dispersal (Charkarov et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b15" href="#b15">2013</a>). Despite of some counterevidence of such adaptive variation in other bird species (Liedvogel and Sheldon 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b63" href="#b63">2010</a>; Dor et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b21" href="#b21">2011</a>), the 
  <span class="italic">Clock</span> gene locus is currently suggested to be a component of a “migratory gene package” that controls physiological adaptations associated with a number of migratory behavioral traits (Liedvogel et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b65" href="#b65">2011</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We therefore expected that the 
  <span class="italic">Clock</span> gene underlies natural selection in our model organism particularly in those populations which are subjected to strong environmental or demographic changes driven by global warming. Specifically, we expected (i) geographical differences and (ii) differences over time in populations where breeding phenology has changed but less differentiation over time where breeding phenology did not change.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fourthly, if global climate change had a significant effect on natural populations of pied flycatchers, we expected genetic differences over time to be as large as, or even larger than those among local populations (within a given time period). Directional selection may cause the overall loss of genetic variation, resulting in fewer haplotypes and alleles or other indices of molecular diversity. An even stronger effect is expected (given that populations are reasonably isolated) in fitness-related genes, such as genes responding to environmental cues determined directly (temperature) or indirectly (food availability) by global climate changes, for example, the 
  <span class="italic">Clock</span> gene. Natural selection may alter gene frequencies even in short time periods, resulting in higher genetic differentiation at candidate loci than at neutral loci. In this study, we tested this hypothesis by comparing spatial and temporal differentiation in mitochondrial DNA, microsatellite loci, and a candidate gene (
  <span class="italic">Clock</span> gene).
 </p>
</sec>
