<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Spatial genetic differentiation in neutral markers</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In general, the low degree of genetic population structuring of bird species (Crochet 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b20" href="#b20">2000</a>) mainly originates from historic processes, in particular cases of rapid range expansions (in the pied flycatcher: Backström et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b1" href="#b1">2013</a>; in tits: Kvist et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b55" href="#b55">2002</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b56" href="#b56">2003</a>). Spatial differentiation patterns driven by dispersal strongly contrast to those driven by vicariance (for birds see Voelker 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b99" href="#b99">1999</a>; Zink et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b104" href="#b104">2000</a>). The extant distribution of western Palearctic 
  <span class="italic">Ficedula</span> flycatcher species has been largely shaped by historic processes such as Pleistocene range fragmentation (for significant East-West subdivision of other Eurasian bird species see Haring et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b45" href="#b45">2007</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b46" href="#b46">2012</a>; Zink et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b105" href="#b105">2008</a>). Their present distribution includes secondary overlap and hybrid zones (Sætre et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b88" href="#b88">2001</a>; Hogner et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b53" href="#b53">2012</a>) as well as significant population subdivision in pied flycatchers with respect to Iberian populations (this study; Lehtonen et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b60" href="#b60">2009</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b61" href="#b61">2012</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The geographical differentiation among extant European pied flycatcher populations in mitochondrial DNA (
  <span class="italic">F</span>
  <sub>st</sub> = 0.34) and nuclear loci matches well the findings by Haavie et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b41" href="#b41">2000</a>). The significant differentiation of populations from the Iberian Peninsula versus the Central and Northern European populations is strongly corroborated by both neutral marker systems (compare also Haavie et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b41" href="#b41">2000</a>; Lehtonen et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b60" href="#b60">2009</a>; however, no confirmation of that pattern from an autosomal marker set in Backström et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b1" href="#b1">2013</a>). Similar phylogeographic patterns have been described for other species, such as Iberian and central/northern European chiffchaffs, 
  <span class="italic">Phylloscopus ibericus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">P. collybita</span> (Helbig et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b50" href="#b50">1996</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b51" href="#b51">2001</a>) and green woodpeckers 
  <span class="italic">Picus viridis</span> (Pons et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b83" href="#b83">2011</a>). Even within the northwestern breeding range of the pied flycatcher shared haplotypes and alleles as well as 
  <span class="italic">F</span>
  <sub>st</sub> statistics suggest some minor but not unequivocal differentiation of the Dutch and German populations against those from Scandinavia. These findings are in concordance with results of Lehtonen et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b60" href="#b60">2009</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The large discrepancies in intraspecific variation between nuclear and mitochondrial markers (such as a 10-fold lower fixation index of microsatellite alleles compared with mtDNA haplotypes) could be related to differences in rate and patterns of mutations (Haavie et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b41" href="#b41">2000</a>; Ballard and Rand 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b3" href="#b3">2005</a>). This discrepancy has also been documented for Swedish pied flycatcher populations (Tegelström et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b95" href="#b95">1990</a>) and might be explained by gender-biased gene flow and dispersal (Prugnolle and de Meeus 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b85" href="#b85">2002</a>; Hedrick 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b48" href="#b48">2007</a>). The slight geographical structure in mtDNA across Central Europe would suggest female-biased dispersal, which is consistent with the general observation that in passerines (including pied flycatchers), dispersal is female-biased (Clarke et al.
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b16" href="#b16">1997</a>; Winkel and Hudde 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b102" href="#b102">2001</a>; Eeva et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b25" href="#b25">2008</a>). However, long-distance dispersal of pied flycatchers between the UK and the Netherlands seemed to be biased more by males than females (Both et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b11" href="#b11">2012</a>), and these relatively rare long-distance dispersal events could profoundly affect genetic structure.
 </p>
</sec>
