<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analysis</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Samples were assigned to groups according to their geographical origin. Dutch, German, and Swedish samples were subdivided into extant and historic samples and Spanish, Finish, and Norwegian samples were classified as three further recent populations only, because no historic sampling was available from these regions. On the temporal scale, we had a considerable sampling gap in the 1980s (from 1977 to 1995), and therefore, we labeled all samples collected before 1977 as “historic” or “museum samples” (
  <span class="italic">N</span> = 110) and those samples taken after 1995 as “extant” or “recent” (
  <span class="italic">N</span> = 201). This temporal division coincides with the first observations of decline in pied flycatcher populations in the Netherlands in the mid-1980s, as well as with a general decline of forest-dwelling long-distance migrants during the same time (Both et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b10" href="#b10">2010</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Control region sequences as well as 
  <span class="italic">Clock</span> gene sequences were aligned with BioEdit 7.0.9.0 (Hall 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b43" href="#b43">1999</a>) and verified by eye. Nucleotide and haplotype diversities for the control region were calculated with the program DnaSP 5.10 (Librado and Rozas 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b62" href="#b62">2009</a>). The allelic richness for microsatellite loci and unbiased estimators of 
  <span class="italic">F</span>
  <sub>st</sub> (e.g., G′′
  <sub>ST</sub>) for microsatellite loci and the 
  <span class="italic">Clock</span> gene and Φ
  <sub>ST</sub> for mtDNA were evaluated with GenAlEx ver. 6.5 (Meirmans and Hedrick 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b67" href="#b67">2011</a>; Peakall and Smouse 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b155" href="#b155">2012</a>). Private haplotypes, private alleles, observed heterozygosity (
  <span class="italic">H</span>
  <sub>o</sub>) for microsatellite loci and the 
  <span class="italic">Clock</span> gene were estimated using Arlequin 3.5.1.2 (Excoffier and Lischer 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b28" href="#b28">2010</a>). Genetic differentiation among populations (
  <span class="italic">F</span>
  <sub>st</sub>) for neutral and non-neutral markers was also calculated with Arlequin 3.5.1.2. (Excoffier and Lischer 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b28" href="#b28">2010</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ten microsatellite loci were tested with MICRO-CHECKER 2.2.3 (van Oosterhout et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b78" href="#b78">2004</a>), using 1000 randomizations and a 95% confidence interval, for genotyping errors due to stuttering, large allelic dropout, and null alleles.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to investigate the phylogeographic relationships among haplotypes, we constructed networks with the program Network 4.6.0.0. (Bandelt et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b4" href="#b4">1999</a>; Forster et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b31" href="#b31">2001</a>; Polzin and Daneshmand 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b82" href="#b82">2003</a>). The median-joining method with transversions weighted three times more than transitions was used to build a network. Both the network and the alignment were cross-checked for any kind of sequencing artifacts, particularly with respect to the historic sampling. Amplification errors can be detected by an increased frequency of unique tip haplotypes (occurring in single individuals) mostly characterized by C to T substitutions in the network representing historic museum specimens (Stiller et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b94" href="#b94">2006</a>; Sefc et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b90" href="#b90">2007</a>). For graphical illustration, we chose the “frequency one criterion”, which excludes unique haplotypes, and the star contraction algorithm in order to simplify the network.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The model-based clustering method structure by Prichard et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b84" href="#b84">2000</a>) was used to infer the number of clusters (K) of individuals based on microsatellite data. Simulations were run assuming the admixture model with correlated allele frequencies and using the sampling location as prior. Ten independent runs, with ten replicates for each K (1–10), were performed with a 500,000 burn-in period followed by 500,000 MCMC repeats after burn-in. To find the true value of K, we performed the K-statistic (Prichard et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b84" href="#b84">2000</a>). The results were compared with K estimates based on the method by Evanno et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b27" href="#b27">2005</a>) as implemented in STRUCTURE HARVESTER (Earl and vonHoldt 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b23" href="#b23">2011</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to analyze the relationship between poly-Q genotypic variation and geographical origin, gender, and laying date (General linear model (GLM) in STATISTICA (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b91" href="#b91">2010</a>)), we defined poly-Q genotypes as the sum of the poly-Q repeats of both alleles, as it has been shown that females (unlike males) with fewer Q repeats tend to breed earlier in the season (Liedvogel et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b64" href="#b64">2009</a>). Associations between pairwise population differentiations (G′′
  <sub>ST</sub>) based on mitochondrial and microsatellite loci as well as microsatellite loci and the 
  <span class="italic">Clock</span> gene locus were tested using a Mantel test (Peakall and Smouse 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b80" href="#b80">2006</a>; GENALEX version 6 and 6.5).
 </p>
</sec>
