<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="F1" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
 <label class="label">Fig. 1</label>
 <caption class="caption">
  <title class="title">Major river basins and projected climate change in Jordan.</title>
  <p class="p">(
   <bold class="bold">A</bold>) Map of Jordan with the major surface water basins color-coded according to the regional basin groups they belong to and locations of the major cities, reservoirs, and stream gauges. (
   <bold class="bold">B</bold>) Temperature deviation from the baseline period average for RCP4.5 and RCP8.5 scenarios. The gray shaded area represents the baseline period (1981–2010). Although Jordan is expected to experience an increase of 2°C in the annual average temperature by 2071–2100 under RCP4.5, a significant increase of 4.5°C is expected under RCP8.5. (
   <bold class="bold">C</bold>) Annual precipitation (essentially the same as the winter precipitation because summers are devoid of rainfall) deviation from the baseline period average under RCP8.5. Any deviation that falls below the −1 SD level from the average is considered to indicate a dry year, as represented by the red shaded area. If, for a given year, the annual average precipitation falls below the −2 SD level, then it is considered to be an extremely dry year. The plotted time series include the bias-corrected precipitation simulations for the three chosen climate models (HadGEM, ECHAM, and IPSL) for 1981–2100 and the observed precipitation (1981–2015). The distribution mapping–based bias correction for the climate simulations was based on the observations during the baseline period (1981–2010). The verification period (2011–2015) is a comparison between bias-corrected climate simulations and the observed precipitation post-baseline period. (
   <bold class="bold">D</bold>) Annual precipitation deviation from the baseline period average for RCP4.5.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="1700581-F1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
