<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">This study used the GCMs ensemble to analyze the regional heat-stress changes for the national pledged emission reduction scenarios under the Paris Agreement and also compared the heat stress results with the 1.5 °C and 2 °C global target scenarios. The response of regional heat stress to different emission scenarios has large differences. The primary research results are summarized as follows:
 <list list-type="order" class="list">
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">With the combination of temperature and humidity under climate change, heat stress intensity in the middle- and low-latitude regions will increase significantly. Under the delayed mitigation scenario, by the end of the 21st century, eastern China, South Asia, the Amazon, western Africa, the eastern United States, northern Australia, and other regions will be particularly vulnerable to heat stress; among them, South Asia, eastern China, and the Amazon are the most vulnerable. While under the INDC continuous mitigation efforts, the wet-bulb temperature of these three regions would decrease 1–2 °C in 2070–2100. Under the 1.5 °C and 2 °C global target scenarios, the predicted wet-bulb temperature of most regions, according to the majority of the models is below 29 °C.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">The frequency of exposure to the dangerous wet-bulb temperature threshold (which may severely affect human labor productivity) also potentially increases. In particular, the heat-stress exposure duration is the longest along the India-Pakistan border region of South Asia, and temperatures exceeding 30 °C and 32 °C during the period 2070–2100 are expected to occur more than 40 days and several to ten days per year, respectively (under the delayed mitigation scenario). Continuous mitigation efforts (compared to the delayed mitigation scenario) can significantly shorten the days and hours of heat exposure in India, but compared with the 1.5 °C and 2 °C global target scenarios, continuous mitigation efforts may still lead to higher exposure risks of heat stress.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">Populations exposed to dangerous wet-bulb temperatures are expected to continue to increase with climate change. More active mitigation policies could reduce population exposure (to wet-bulb temperatures greater than 30–32 °C) by approximately one order of magnitude (pursuing the INDC continuous mitigation scenario versus the delayed mitigation scenario), and half to one order of magnitude (the 2 °C global target scenario versus the INDC continuous mitigation scenario). Given the dramatic increase in the number of people worldwide who may be exposed to dangerous heat stress, failure to take proactive mitigation and adaptation measures in the future will likely result in greater economic losses and increased heat-related mortality.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
