<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Given these potential environmental controls on ticks and tick-borne disease, there have been many efforts to find the set of environmental factors that best explains the current distribution of ticks (or of tick-borne disease). Then, assuming that those conditions represent the full range of suitable habitat, projections of this set of conditions in the future are used to estimate the future distributions of ticks or disease. This approach is largely phenomenological, in that environmental factors are selected based on correlations between those factors and the presence (or less commonly, the abundance) of ticks or of tick-borne disease. In an important early example of this approach Brownstein 
 <italic class="italic">et al.</italic> [
 <xref rid="RSTB20140051C72" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">72</xref>] modelled habitat suitability for 
 <italic class="italic">I. scapularis</italic> in the USA. The authors used a tick distribution map [
 <xref rid="RSTB20140051C73" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">73</xref>] to discriminate locations with from those without 
 <italic class="italic">I. scapularis</italic>. They used 16 climatic variables in a remote sensing dataset—the mean, minimum, maximum and standard deviation of four monthly ground temperatures—to create a climate envelope of suitability. The resulting habitat suitability map predicted modest westward expansion but little northern expansion of tick populations with climate change. In marked contrast, a climate envelope model of Lyme disease cases by Ashley &amp; Meentemeyer [
 <xref rid="RSTB20140051C74" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">74</xref>], based only on spring temperature, precipitation and soil moisture, predicted that vast areas of the eastern and midwestern United States outside the current range were suitable for invasion by Lyme disease. As is often the case with such phenomenological models, however, the important predictor variables can be chosen arbitrarily and are often hard to interpret biologically. For example, the potential for winter, autumn and summer variables to delimit ticks and tick-borne disease was not considered by Ashley &amp; Meentemeyer [
 <xref rid="RSTB20140051C74" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">74</xref>]. In the Brownstein 
 <italic class="italic">et al.</italic> [
 <xref rid="RSTB20140051C72" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">72</xref>] study, the best predictor of tick habitat suitability was minimum winter temperature, but the relationship was a fourth-order polynomial that has no obvious biological interpretation. It is also far from clear if such statistical associations can be expected to hold in the future or even new datasets. Only recently have climatic variables been considered together with factors like habitat fragmentation and host abundances [
 <xref rid="RSTB20140051C34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSTB20140051C75" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">75</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSTB20140051C76" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">76</xref>].
</p>
