<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Notably, non-Hispanic blacks were less likely to own an AC even when adjusting for household income, suggesting that lack of financial resources is not the only cause of lower AC ownership among this group. Similar disparities for black Americans that cannot be fully explained by income are also seen for a variety of health outcomes (including early death rates, diabetes and obesity, hypertension) [
 <xref rid="B21-ijerph-15-01433" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>], as well as economic and educational outcomes [
 <xref rid="B22-ijerph-15-01433" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>]. The results may be indicative of the “pernicious effects of race-based discrimination” [
 <xref rid="B21-ijerph-15-01433" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>], which limits access to resources and services, as well as opportunities for social mobility [
 <xref rid="B23-ijerph-15-01433" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>]. Traditional measures of SES are not equivalent across race because, for example, compared to whites, blacks may have less purchasing power because the costs of goods and services are higher in black communities [
 <xref rid="B24-ijerph-15-01433" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>]. Traditionally disadvantaged groups may be more likely to live in buildings that do not have wiring conducive to AC installation, although building wiring was not cited as a main reason for not owning AC in the 2011 survey among all New Yorkers. There may be other explanations for how economic and structural racism impact AC access. Further qualitative research is needed to better understand these disparities and sharpen interventions to address root causes [
 <xref rid="B25-ijerph-15-01433" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. It is also important to note that other factors, including cultural/religious [
 <xref rid="B26-ijerph-15-01433" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>] and occupational [
 <xref rid="B27-ijerph-15-01433" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>], have also been shown to contribute to heat-related vulnerability.
</p>
