<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Climate change is already negatively impacting many taxa—including global fisheries that are critical food resources for a growing human population (Free et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35277-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2019</xref>; Pacifici et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35277-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>). Consequently, climate change is anticipated to be one of the most significant drivers of ecological and societal change in the coming century (Lawler et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35277-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>). For freshwater coastal wetlands, accelerated sea level rise and saltwater intrusion have been the focal points of climate change research and management planning (Osland et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35277-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). However, tropical cyclonic storms (hurricanes) also pose a formidable threat to coastal ecosystems. Since the 1970s, both frequency and intensity of the strongest North Atlantic tropical cyclones have increased (Bhatia et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35277-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2019</xref>; Hartmann et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35277-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). Current climate change models (e.g., the CMIP3–A1B scenario and the CMIP5‐early and late 21st century scenarios) predict fewer Atlantic tropical storms in warmer climates and an increase in the frequency of the most intense hurricanes (Categories 4 and 5), although this predicted increased frequency varies among models (i.e., a substantially increased frequency is predicted for Categories 4 and 5 hurricanes using the CMIP3 model, but smaller increases are projected using the CMIP5‐early and CMIP5‐late models; Knutson et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35277-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). This projected escalation of catastrophic hurricanes is an unprecedented challenge for conservation and management of imperiled species that inhabit coastal ecosystems.
</p>
