<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In winter, approximately one in four potential colonizations would need to occur, on average, to exceed potential extirpations, making national parks more likely to see an increase in species richness in a changing climate in winter than in summer (when seven of ten potential colonizations would need to occur). This may be because winter cold is more of a limiting physiological factor on species distributions [
 <xref rid="pone.0190557.ref018" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>] than summer heat [
 <xref rid="pone.0190557.ref048" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>], allowing more colonizations in winter as temperatures increase. Winter months have experienced greater changes in climate (primarily warming temperatures) than summer months [
 <xref rid="pone.0190557.ref049" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>] and birds have responded by shifting their wintering distributions north [
 <xref rid="pone.0190557.ref050" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>]. Higher proportions of species showed northward shifts in winter (58%, [
 <xref rid="pone.0190557.ref050" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>]) than summer (23%, [
 <xref rid="pone.0190557.ref019" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>]), with warm-adapted species increasingly dominating wintering landbird communities [
 <xref rid="pone.0190557.ref018" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>]. Migratory species that are already present in summer are perhaps the most likely candidates for winter colonization. Climate change has also already resulted in shorter migration distances for some species [
 <xref rid="pone.0190557.ref051" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">51</xref>]. The presence of a species throughout the winter months may result from partial migration strategies, in which individuals cease to migrate, or from chain migration patterns, where individuals from elsewhere in the distribution replace breeding individuals during winter [
 <xref rid="pone.0190557.ref052" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>]. Or, complete residency could result if selective pressures for shortened migration persist as expected under climate change [
 <xref rid="pone.0190557.ref053" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">53</xref>].
</p>
