<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">To support the IPCC, the international climate research community has participated in a comparison project titled the “Coupled Model Intercomparison Project 5 (CMIP5)” [
 <xref rid="pone.0132326.ref001" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>]. Within this framework, coordinated experiments using climate and earth system models have been organized to research and answer questions on the mechanisms and properties of climate change. The Fifth IPCC Assessment Report (AR5) was published on September 30, 2013 [
 <xref rid="pone.0132326.ref001" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>]. It defined a new set of scenarios to take account of the rising complexity of model calculations and to analyze the effects of different political measures. The Representative Concentration Pathways (RCPs) represent the full bandwidth of possible future emission trajectories. Four RCPs (i.e., RCP2.6, RCP4.5, RCP6.0, and RCP8.5) were coded according to a possible range of radiative forcing values in the year 2100 relative to preindustrial values (+2.6, +4.5, +6.0, and +8.5 W•m
 <sup class="sup">-2</sup>, respectively) [
 <xref rid="pone.0132326.ref020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. The extreme weather variations will pose greater influence to geographical distribution pattern and its temporal and spatial variation of plant. So we selected climate variables for simulation in four climate change scenario/year combinations: RCP2.6–2050 (average for the years 2041–2060 under scenario RCP2.6), RCP2.6–2070 (average for the years 2061–2080 under the scenario RCP2.6), RCP8.5–2050 (average for the years 2061–2080 under the scenario RCP8.5), and RCP8.5–2070 (average for the years 2061–2080 under the scenario RCP8.5), these data all with better representation. The CMIP5-derived future climate scenario data that we used were coded (as BCC-CSM1-1) and generated by the Beijing Climate Center (
 <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cmdp.ncc.cma.gov.cn/en/" class="ext-link" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://cmdp.ncc.cma.gov.cn/en/</span>). Our four selected future climate data sets were downloaded from the World Climate Database (
 <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.worldclim.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.worldclim.org/</span>) [
 <xref rid="pone.0132326.ref018" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>]. Currently only meteorological data (we selected 8 in our study) under future scenario are available for related studies. The 10 environmental parameters (SC, SpH, GDD, FRS, WET, VAP and 4 UV-B radiation parameters) were remained unchanged for the following analyses of SDM projection under future climate conditions.
</p>
