<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The global change that the biosphere will face in the next decades is not limited to climate change. Indeed, fragmentation and reduced habitat quality are other global change drivers 
 <bold class="bold">[
  <xref rid="pone.0218160.ref070" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">70</xref>]
 </bold> that will play a very important role in the fate of plant populations and communities in Mediterranean climates. The different climate change scenarios studied here were established according to the four RCP conditions. As there are important differences in the assumptions for these four scenarios, it is not surprising that considerable variation was obtained in the output data for each climate change scenario. We also studied the evolution of bioclimatic suitability values taken at sites were 
 <italic class="italic">G</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">bermejoi</italic> is currently found. Under RCP 2.6 conditions, the bioclimatic suitability for 
 <italic class="italic">G</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">bermejoi</italic> at its current locations seems to improve noticeably. This might be due to the proposed increase in the minimum temperatures in the coldest month (Bio 6) under this scenario by 2050, remaining at that level until 2070. This could be particularly relevant as the median temperature moves from negative to positive values, probably diminishing the risk of freezing during the winter. The rainfall during the driest month (Bio 14) is also proposed to decrease, yet the median values remain above 10 mm in 2050 (11 mm) increasing again in 2070 (12 mm), which seems to be suitable for this plant to survive under these climatic conditions. According to our models this plant could be capable of dealing with this situation and thus, the models show that at most of the sites where 
 <italic class="italic">G</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">bermejoi</italic> is currently found, bioclimatic suitability will be enhanced by 2050 and it will remain stable until 2070.
</p>
