<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The role of factors in the middle ring deserves additional elaboration focused specifically on climate change: 
 <list list-type="order">
  <list-item>
   <p>
    <bold>Health status and vulnerabilities:</bold> As noted above, adverse population health impacts associated with climate change can, by extension, affect social stability and human well-being (
    <xref rid="c91" ref-type="bibr">Smith et al. 2014</xref>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>
    <bold>Public health and health systems:</bold> Well-functioning health systems play a critical role in anticipating, identifying, communicating, and addressing emerging health issues. Health systems that adaptively manage climate change, targeting resources toward populations most likely to be affected by climate-related hazards, are likely to reduce the risks of related health harms (
    <xref rid="c34" ref-type="bibr">Ebi 2011</xref>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>
    <bold>Human capital:</bold> Educational attainment can affect employment opportunities and decision-making capacity (
    <xref rid="c72" ref-type="bibr">Muttarak and Lutz 2014</xref>), which in turn can influence decisions around migration and adaptation to climate change (
    <xref rid="c98" ref-type="bibr">Van der Land and Hummel 2013</xref>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>
    <bold>Demography:</bold> Demographic conditions can increase the risk of social unrest. Most commonly discussed in the literature are the effects of “youth bulges,” in which young men, who are often socially and economically marginalized, are a disproportionate share of the population, increasing the risk of conflict (
    <xref rid="c96" ref-type="bibr">Urdal 2006</xref>) and of transitions to less democratic forms of governance (
    <xref rid="c105" ref-type="bibr">Weber 2013</xref>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>
    <bold>Dependence on natural resources:</bold> Livelihood dependence on natural resources and ecosystem services likely to be harmed by climate change can increase vulnerability and place societies at greater risk of instability (
    <xref rid="c3" ref-type="bibr">Adger 2000</xref>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>
    <bold>Inequality:</bold> Social and economic inequality, particularly between established ethnic or other established groups within countries, can increase the risk of conflict (
    <xref rid="c77" ref-type="bibr">Østby 2008</xref>). Elite capture of natural resources, ecosystem services, and political power can breed social and economic resentment, increasing the risk of instability (
    <xref rid="c100" ref-type="bibr">Verhoeven 2011</xref>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>
    <bold>Poverty/standard of living:</bold> Poverty affects the resources individuals have to migrate or otherwise adapt their livelihoods when shocks and stresses occur (
    <xref rid="c43" ref-type="bibr">Government Office for Science 2011</xref>). Many millions of people around the world have incomes just above the poverty line, and unexpected events (including climate shocks) can push these populations into poverty, increasing the risk of social instability (
    <xref rid="c47" ref-type="bibr">Hallegatte et al. 2016</xref>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>
    <bold>Resource availability:</bold> Availability of natural resources, such as fresh water, can affect vulnerability to climate shocks and social instability (
    <xref rid="c24" ref-type="bibr">Busby et al. 2014</xref>; 
    <xref rid="c4" ref-type="bibr">Almer et al. 2017</xref>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>
    <bold>Governance quality and institutional capacity:</bold> Metrics of governance quality (e.g. corruption, rule of law, emphasis on equity) are associated with health outcomes (
    <xref rid="c60" ref-type="bibr">Kickbush and Gleicher 2012</xref>). Institutional capacity, i.e., the ability of governments and related social actors to respond to public needs and provide quality services, such as education, defense, and infrastructure, can affect social stability (
    <xref rid="c49" ref-type="bibr">Hendrix 2010</xref>). Effective provision of social welfare services in particular can reduce the risk of social unrest (
    <xref rid="c93" ref-type="bibr">Taydas and Peksen 2012</xref>). As these concepts are somewhat abstract, political scientists often use indexes to operationalize them in models. Political participation and institutional structure and quality are measured using either objective measures, expert judgments, or both (see 
    <xref rid="t2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref> for examples).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>
    <bold>Institutional interconnectedness:</bold> We consider institutional interconnectedness as the number and quality of interlinkages between state and nonstate institutions in different countries. These relationships can influence collective action capacity to address climate-related challenges. Although difficult to measure quantitatively, intersectoral coordination can help more effectively address shocks and stresses, particularly in the health sector (
    <xref rid="c15" ref-type="bibr">Bowen and Ebi 2015</xref>). Collaboration between different states can also support effective responses (
    <xref rid="c23" ref-type="bibr">Bulkeley et al. 2012</xref>; 
    <xref rid="c39" ref-type="bibr">Fünfgeld 2015</xref>). States with poor relationships or frameworks for dealing with interstate environmental challenges may be at greater risk of conflict (
    <xref rid="c30" ref-type="bibr">De Stefano et al. 2012</xref>). This concept can also be operationalized through indexes, such as those measuring trade agreements, foreign investment, treaty membership, and other indicators of international interdependence.
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
