<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Lastly, national adaptation plans may take different forms to suit different country contexts and institutional arrangements, and may be undertaken within and by a particular agency or sector, through the formation of a cross-cutting working group or committee, or by external bodies [
 <xref rid="B53-ijerph-13-00889" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">53</xref>]. National adaptation plans may be comprehensive (e.g., France’s 
 <italic class="italic">Plan national d’adaptation au changement climatique</italic> (national climate change adaptation plan) [
 <xref rid="B104-ijerph-13-00889" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">104</xref>], the UK’s National Adaptation Programme [
 <xref rid="B103-ijerph-13-00889" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">103</xref>]) or sector-specific (e.g., US Department of Health and Human Services Climate Adaptation Plan [
 <xref rid="B96-ijerph-13-00889" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">96</xref>]). This distinction is important in ensuring health issues are sufficiently included in comprehensive plans which are typically coordinated by environment or natural resources ministries [
 <xref rid="B87-ijerph-13-00889" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">87</xref>], and that horizontal coordination is incorporated into sectoral plans. As with vertical coordination, preparing a jurisdictionally appropriate national adaptation plan is particularly challenging in federal, decentralized countries, where sub-national governments may be responsible for health. In federal contexts an adaptation plan may thus be broad rather than very specific. The US’s Department of Health and Human Services, for example, does not steer sub-national adaptation in its adaptation plan, but outlines how the Department will adapt its own activities and work with other agencies and sub-national governments [
 <xref rid="B96-ijerph-13-00889" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">96</xref>]. Belgium has taken another approach to national adaptation planning in a federal, decentralized context, where the National Climate Commission (comprised of representatives from all government levels) will use the federal and regional government adaptation plans as a basis for a future national adaptation plan, thereby using national adaptation planning as a tool to engage sub-national governments [
 <xref rid="B52-ijerph-13-00889" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>,
 <xref rid="B91-ijerph-13-00889" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">91</xref>,
 <xref rid="B111-ijerph-13-00889" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">111</xref>].
</p>
