<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Consideration of step-by-step adaptation pathways</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Thus far we have developed adaptation pathways to maintain current yields as the timely case and prioritized cases, and we have discussed the effects of climate-change uncertainties, adaptation strategies, and emissions scenarios on the adaptation pathways. Here we look at them from the viewpoint of performing a series of adaptation processes. In the cases examined above, we assumed that a large amount of adaptation could be promptly implemented within a decade. However, we must consider the feasible rate of adaptation, because planned adaptation requires both significant investment and substantial time to be developed. We should also consider the lead time to implement an adaptation, which means the time lag between the planning and the implementation of adaptation. Here we consider step-by-step adaptation pathways, which are those described by gradual implementation of the adaptation and considering a lead time to implement an adaptation. In this case, full adaptation would not be achieved immediately under an abrupt climate change, such that adaptation forecasts will become important. In the following, we discuss the advantage of forecasting necessary adaptations.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">If no forecast is conducted (i.e., adaptation to be implemented in the next decade is determined by the yield change in the current decade) and the amount of adaptation implemented is limited to one level per decade each for irrigation and crop variety, the adaptation pathways without prioritization result in the red dashed lines in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f1" href="#f1">Figs 1</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f2" href="#f2">2</a> (referred to as “Non-forecast” in the figures), under the MIROC-ESM projection. In India, Germany, and Pakistan, in which a large amount of adaptation (multiple increments of levels) is required over a short period in the timely case, a substantial yield decrease occurs in the non-forecast case; the negative impact of not forecasting is remarkable. However, the decreases in yield could be moderated if forecasts of 10 yr ahead were conducted (see Methods), even if the amount of adaptation implemented is limited (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f5" href="#f5">Fig. 5</a>; 10-yr-forecast case). If a forecast to 20 yr ahead is available, further yield decreases may be moderated. In India, forecasting to 20 yr ahead could achieve a yield comparable to that in the timely case without implementing a high level of adaptation in a short period (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f5" href="#f5">Fig. 5</a>; 20-yr-forecast case).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The efficacy of forecast is obvious in all nine countries and in all models and ensemble runs (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f6" href="#f6">Fig. 6</a>). In China and Canada, the 10-yr-forecast case is nearly equal to the timely case in the multi-projection average of accumulated yield decrease during the 21st century (the 2010 s to 2090 s); the yield decrease from the current level could be avoided by forecasting 10 yr ahead. Even in India and Pakistan, the yield decrease could be moderated by forecasts. Therefore, forecasting the adaptation necessary in the future is important to achieve the benefit of the adaptation; in other words, the negative impacts of climate change could be moderated by implementing adaptations steadily according to forecasts of the necessary future adaptations, as compared to missing the appropriate timing to implement adaptations.
 </p>
</sec>
