<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Uppards is expected to be inundated at an accelerating rate compared to the semi-protected Tangier, while Goose, the smallest of the Tangier Islands, is predicted to be entirely inundated by 2038. South of the seawall, Tangier will experience significant land loss. The projection indicates it is very likely that the sand spit, which provides some protection against incoming wave energy from the south, will be lost. Tidal creeks winding through the islands will widen significantly, encroaching into the upland ridges. Most of Uppards is predicted to be inundated by 2063, reducing the protection provided to the Town of Tangier. Tangier subsides and is split into three by widening of several large tidal creeks, with continued loss of land expected to occur at all margins of the island except the western shore. By 2113, Uppards Island is predicted to be lost with the possible exception of one small area in its south-central region. A small sub-islet to the east, where there was dredged material placement activity that elevated a significant portion to uplands, is predicted to persist, though reduced in size and elevation. Tangier Island has been split into three sub-islets centered on the three upland ridges (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f3" href="#f3">Fig. 3</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Regarding the future of the Town of Tangier, except small portions of each ridge (&lt;10%), the remaining upland is at a mean of +1.2 m PMSL. Based on projected rates of land loss and RSLR, the town will be uninhabitable in less than 100 years (likely by 2063) and all current uplands, with the possible exception of the three small higher areas (&lt;10% of current uplands), will be converted to a mix of intertidal and high estuarine marsh.</p>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Value of Ecosystem Services Lost</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Under the mid-range RSLR scenario, we expect the Tangier Islands to lose land at an exponential rate (
   <span class="italic">y</span> = 2
   <span class="italic">e</span>+16
   <span class="italic">e</span>
   <span class="sup">−0.016x</span>, 
   <span class="italic">r</span>
   <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.99). By 2063, 174.53 HA of wetlands (ecological services estimated value: 1.75 million USD yr
   <span class="sup">−1</span> will be lost. By 2113, 254.41 HA will be lost, (valued at 2.54 million USD yr
   <span class="sup">−1</span>). The loss of Uppards will lead to the loss of approximately 150 HA of SAV by 2113, (ecological services valued at 3.0 million USD yr
   <span class="sup">−1</span>). Bird nesting will decline, accelerating the decline of these species
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b25" href="#b25">25</a>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Recommended Plan for the Tangier Islands</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Tangier Islands have less than 100 years before they are lost to a combination of RSLR and storm surge-induced erosion. A segmented breakwater system would provide physical protection (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="f5" href="#f5">Fig. 5</a>). These breakwaters would be built offshore to permit construction of a sand beach/dune system along the western shore between the breakwaters and existing shoreline. The dunes would catch wind-borne sediment as well as supply inorganic sediment to the island during storms strong enough to blow some of the dune sand over the island. Along the eastern shore, breakwaters would be built.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Since 1850, five former upland ridges on Uppards and Tangier have become low-lying marsh. These would be restored using dredged sand. These ridges, restored to a height of 2–3 m above the current 2013 spring high tide, could be planted with loblolly pines (
   <span class="italic">Pinus taeda</span>). Pines and other woody vegetation will supply organic material to the ridges and the rest of the island, help maintain elevation, and serve as seabird nesting habitat. Spray dredging could be used to help maintain the elevation of uninhabited portions of the islands. Fertilization of the wetlands should also be considered, to increase the rate of organic material deposition where wetlands cannot be reached by spray dredging. The approximate costs of initial construction of the breakwaters, beach, dunes and ridges would be approximately 20–30 million USD. If no action is taken, significant wildlife habitat will be lost, as well as the culturally-unique Town of Tangier, the last offshore fishing community in Virginia waters of Chesapeake Bay.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
