<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Finally, juvenile survival rates were lower than adult survival rates in both species. This confirmed results of other studies investigating age class‐specific survival in bats (Culina et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35292-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>; Sendor &amp; Simon, 
 <xref rid="ece35292-bib-0046" ref-type="ref">2003</xref>) and underlines the importance of adult survival in long‐lived species, including bats, for population stability (Fleischer et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35292-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>; Gaillard &amp; Yoccoz, 
 <xref rid="ece35292-bib-0014" ref-type="ref">2003</xref>; Péron et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35292-bib-0038" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>). The difference between juvenile and adult survival was more pronounced in Daubenton's bats than Natterer's bats. Compared with other studies, however, the reduction in survival in juveniles was moderate in our study. Culina and co‐authors report a juvenile survival probability over winter of about 0.4 in Daubenton's bats (Culina et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35292-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>), whereas in our study it was estimated to be about 0.66. Potential explanations for this high difference in juvenile winter survival in the two studies might be either population‐specific effects on juvenile survival or differences in the methods of analyses. Culina et al. (
 <xref rid="ece35292-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>) investigated winter survival based on summer roosts and we investigated seasonal survival at a hibernaculum. Our estimated rates for juvenile winter survival might have been higher than the rates found by Culina et al. (
 <xref rid="ece35292-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>) because we only included those juveniles that arrived at the hibernaculum. Thus, our estimates did not consider the juvenile stage between becoming volant and first migration to the wintering site which presumably are associated with a high mortality risk. To distinguish between those possible causes, individual‐based long‐term data sets monitoring individual bats over their life time at their summer roosts and hibernaculum are required.
</p>
