<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Because our analysis is motivated, in part, by a desire to develop mechanistic and general approaches to predict endotherm ranges, we discuss the limited viability of using metabolic constraints to predict warm range boundaries. We omit a full analysis of warm range boundaries because we estimated that 61% and 45% of mammal and bird species with unconstrained warm range boundaries, respectively, do not experience 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>
 <sub class="sub">max</sub> values exceeding their 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>
 <sub class="sub">uc</sub>. We note that these values are likely an overestimate because they do not account for heat associated with solar radiation or heat extremes, but they do suggest a greater viability for using metabolic constraints to project cold range boundaries. Our estimates of metabolic expansibility at the warm range boundary (for species with 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>
 <sub class="sub">max</sub> &gt; 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>
 <sub class="sub">uc</sub>, following methodology for ME
 <sub class="sub">CRB</sub>) approximate 1 (Figure 
 <xref rid="ece34537-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S2</xref>), highlighting the physiological challenges of heat dissipation (Weathers, 
 <xref rid="ece34537-bib-0060" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1981</xref>). At warm range boundaries, the capacity for evaporative cooling may be more limiting than the associated metabolic costs and minimal endogenous heating is favored (McKechnie, Whitfield, et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34537-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>; Tieleman &amp; Williams, 
 <xref rid="ece34537-bib-0056" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2000</xref>). Evaporative cooling poses a risk of dehydration in response to short term heat stress (McKechnie, Hockey, &amp; Wolf, 
 <xref rid="ece34537-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>) and presents a challenge for longer term water balances (Kearney et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34537-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). Additionally, other biotic factors such as species interactions and resource or habitat constraints often constrain warm range boundaries (Sexton, McIntyre, Angert, &amp; Rice, 
 <xref rid="ece34537-bib-0051" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>). Range contractions at warm range boundaries may primarily result from indirect effects (e.g., species’ interactions), which often predominate in climate change responses (Tylianakis, Didham, Bascompte, &amp; Wardle, 
 <xref rid="ece34537-bib-0058" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>; Walther, 
 <xref rid="ece34537-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>).
</p>
