<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s0005" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data</div>
 <p id="p0030" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The West African Sahel is defined as the sub-Saharan region that stretches from the western coasts of Senegal to the Central-Eastern edges of Chad between 10°N to 18°N. Observed daily rainfall records, of ordinary raingauges, weighing bucket and tipping bucket gauges
  <span class="italic">,</span> were provided by the meteorological services and agencies of the WASCAL member countries (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wascal.org" id="ir0020" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.wascal.org</span>) following specific data sharing policies 
  <a rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib1">[1]</a>. This database was complemented by daily measurements from the Global Historical Climatology Network 
  <a rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib2">[2]</a> and the AMMA database (African Monsoon Multidisciplinary Analysis 
  <a rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib3">[3]</a>). The daily rainfall time series (1960–2010) from synoptic, climate, agro-meteorological, and rainfall stations are assessed for quality and consistency before extreme values are extracted. This was achieved by checking erroneous measurement values (e.g., negative precipitation, temporal sequences with the same measurement value), dates and coordinates. The generation of multiple data plots enabled a comprehensive visual inspection of each time series. In combination with local meteorological knowledge and experience, the outliers, mostly caused by data entry typesetting errors, are identified and deleted 
  <a rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib4">[4]</a>. Daily rainfall records are not interpolated when records are missing. Only the 72 longest time series, from different rain gauge types well-spread over the study area (
  <a rid="f0005" ref-type="fig" href="#f0005">Fig. 1</a>), were selected to extract the datasets of daily rainfall extremes above the 90th, 95th, and 99th percentiles of each rainy season.
  <div id="f0005" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Spatial distribution of locations where different rain gauge types are recording extreme rainfall events in the West African Sahel.</p>
   </div>
   <span id="at0005" class="alt-text">Fig. 1</span>
   <div xlink:href="gr1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="p0035" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The data is stored as (1) 
  <span class="italic">SahelRainfallR99P</span> (for the 99th percentile rainfall values), (2) 
  <span class="italic">SahelRainfallR95P</span> (for the 95th percentile rainfall values) and (3) 
  <span class="italic">SahelRainfallR90P</span> (for the 90th percentile rainfall values) with the following header:
  <div list-type="simple" id="li0020" class="list">
   <div id="u0020" class="list-item">
    <span class="label">–</span>
    <p id="p0040">lon: Longitude</p>
   </div>
   <div id="u0025" class="list-item">
    <span class="label">–</span>
    <p id="p0045">lat: Latitude</p>
   </div>
   <div id="u0030" class="list-item">
    <span class="label">–</span>
    <p id="p0050">year: Year of data record</p>
   </div>
   <div id="u0035" class="list-item">
    <span class="label">–</span>
    <p id="p0055">doy: Day-of-year or Julian day of a calendar year (starting from 01-January)</p>
   </div>
   <div id="u0040" class="list-item">
    <span class="label">–</span>
    <p id="p0060">woy: Week-of-year or week number of a calendar year (starting from 01-January)</p>
   </div>
   <div id="u0045" class="list-item">
    <span class="label">–</span>
    <p id="p0065">int: Daily accumulated rainfall amount (mm/day)</p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="p0070" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The files are ASCII tab-delimited text (.txt) and missing values are tagged with “
  <span class="bold">NA</span>”
 </p>
 <p id="p0075" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This is a derived product (DP), publicly available with this data article as part of the study presented by Salack et at. 
  <a rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib1">[1]</a>. The data is in line with WASCAL׳s “3rd party data sharing policy” signed by the member countries of WASCAL during the establishment of new transboundary climate and hydro-meteorological observatories 
  <a rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib1">[1]</a>, 
  <a rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib5">[5]</a>. Complementary and up to date time series for this dataset can be taken from the WASCAL data infrastructure (WADI) geoportal 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://wascal-dataportal.org/wascal_searchportal2/" id="ir0025" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://wascal-dataportal.org/wascal_searchportal2/</span>.
 </p>
</sec>
