<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Ideally, the modelling area should include the vast majority of the range of climatic conditions experienced by a species (
 <xref rid="ref-6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Barbet-Massin, Thuiller &amp; Jiguet</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref-6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>), including the range of projected climatic conditions according to scenarios of climate change in the study area. Covering the full distribution range of a species is not always possible and so, in preliminary analyses, we verified gaps in climate coverage for each species by comparing the modelling area with Little’s range, which is assumed to cover an entire species range in North America (
 <xref rid="ref-57" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Little Jr</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref-57" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1971</xref>). There were minimal or no gap in temperature coverage for sugar maple (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp-3" class="xref">Fig. S1A</xref>), yellow birch (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp-4" class="xref">Fig. S2A</xref>), and balsam fir (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp-5" class="xref">Fig. S3A</xref> ; coverage of 100%, 100%, and 97% of the temperature range respectively). Temperature coverage was 70% for white birch (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp-6" class="xref">Fig. S4A</xref>) and 61% for black spruce (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp-7" class="xref">Fig. S5A</xref>), but the gaps were for colder temperatures that are not characteristic of the projected climate trends in the study area (+1.9 °C to +8 °C; Ouranos 2015). Precipitation coverage was 98% for both sugar maple (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp-3" class="xref">Fig. S1B</xref>) and yellow birch (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp-4" class="xref">Fig. S2B</xref>), and 70% for balsam fir (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp-5" class="xref">Fig. S3B</xref>). The gaps for white birch (35%; 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp-6" class="xref">Fig. S4B</xref>) and black spruce (31%; 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp-7" class="xref">Fig. S5B</xref>) were towards drier annual climates that are also not characteristic of the projected climate trends in the study area (precipitations +3% to +26%; 
 <xref rid="ref-72" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ouranos</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref-72" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>).
</p>
