<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div id="Fig5" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <span class="label">Fig. 5</span>
 <div class="caption">
  <p>Stabilising effect of GIA on ice dynamics. 
   <span class="bold">a</span> The grounding line is the location where the ice sheet begins to float. Flux across the grounding line (
   <span class="italic">q</span>
   <sub>1</sub>) depends on ice thickness at the grounding line (
   <span class="italic">h</span>
   <sub>1</sub>). The position of the grounding line also depends on water depth at the grounding line (
   <span class="italic">d</span>
   <sub>1</sub>), the density of ice (
   <span class="italic">ρ</span>
   <sub>i</sub>), and the density of seawater (
   <span class="italic">ρ</span>
   <sub>w</sub>). 
   <span class="bold">b</span> Before GIA feedbacks: on a reverse bed slope grounding line retreats into deeper water (red arrow) due to, e.g., a reduction in ice shelf buttressing. Increase in ice thickness at the grounding line (
   <span class="italic">h</span>
   <sub>2</sub> &gt; 
   <span class="italic">h</span>
   <sub>1</sub>) results in an increase in ice flux across the grounding line (
   <span class="italic">q</span>
   <sub>2</sub> &gt; 
   <span class="italic">q</span>
   <sub>1</sub>). If ice input from upstream does not increase then the ice sheet thins, triggering further grounding line retreat. 
   <span class="bold">c</span> After GIA feedbacks: following grounding line retreat, grounded ice loss triggers land uplift and sea surface lowering. The resulting decrease in water depth and hence ice thickness (
   <span class="italic">h</span>
   <sub>3</sub> &lt; 
   <span class="italic">h</span>
   <sub>2</sub>) at the grounding line results in a decrease in ice flux across the grounding line (
   <span class="italic">q</span>
   <sub>3</sub> &lt; 
   <span class="italic">q</span>
   <sub>2</sub>), which acts to stabilise the position of the grounding line. Initial configurations shown by dashed lines, new configurations shown by solid lines
  </p>
 </div>
 <div xlink:href="41467_2018_8068_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e1164" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</div>
