<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="introduction" id="S1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate change poses unprecedented global challenges for the living beings and living systems of this planet. The risks to human health, public health, and the natural environment are numerous and include major disruptions to social and economic systems (
  <a rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1">1</a>–
  <a rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5">5</a>). Likewise, climate change is an overarching social justice and human rights issue (
  <a rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6">6</a>, 
  <a rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7">7</a>). The negative consequences of climate change are projected to increase in severity (
  <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">8</a>). While greenhouse gas emissions continue to climb, scientists advocate the urgency of reducing emissions along with the associated carbon storage to restore and balance the global climate system – with the additional goal of minimizing irreversible climate change (
  <a rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1">1</a>, 
  <a rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9">9</a>, 
  <a rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10">10</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A burgeoning array of interdisciplinary data implicates food from animal sources in greenhouse gas emissions, increased resource consumption, and environmental degradation (
  <a rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11">11</a>–
  <a rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26">26</a>). Ruminants, particularly beef cattle, demonstrate greater environmental burdens than other animals (
  <a rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18">18</a>, 
  <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">20</a>, 
  <a rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27">27</a>, 
  <a rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28">28</a>). Other studies indicate that plant-based diets and reducing animal product consumption are effective options in ameliorating environmental degradation, decreasing greenhouse gas emissions, and minimizing resource consumption (
  <a rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11">11</a>–
  <a rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28">28</a>). Attaining climate mitigation targets may not be possible without reductions in animal product consumption (
  <a rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29">29</a>, 
  <a rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30">30</a>). Additionally, the Academy of Nutrition and Dietetics recognizes that well-planned plant-based diets are nutritionally sound throughout the entire lifecycle (
  <a rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31">31</a>), and are associated with reduced chronic disease morbidity and mortality (
  <a rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25">25</a>, 
  <a rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32">32</a>, 
  <a rid="B33" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33">33</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There is a growing body of literature regarding concern for climate change among allied health and public health providers. In their survey of United States public health nurses (
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 786), Polivka and colleagues found that 75% of respondents agreed that humans are severely abusing the environment (
  <a rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34">34</a>). Half of the respondents agreed that their nursing department had an obligation to address the health impacts of climate change (
  <a rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34">34</a>). Most disagreed with the statement that their nursing division was prepared to address the health-related impacts of climate change (
  <a rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34">34</a>). Truckner surveyed health care providers who were members of the Wilderness Medical Society concerning awareness and beliefs about human-induced environmental degradation (HIED) (
  <a rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35">35</a>). Of the 658 respondents, 86% were physicians involved in emergency and primary care medicine while one respondent was a registered dietitian (
  <a rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35">35</a>). Eighty percent of respondents believed that HIED had directly and adversely affected patients, but 93% reported that they do not distribute information about the adverse health effects of HIED to patients (
  <a rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35">35</a>). A recent survey of African-American physicians with 284 respondents found that while 88% of respondents agree that climate change is directly relevant to patient care, 71% of respondents do not know how to approach the issue with patients (
  <a rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36">36</a>). Finally, in a survey of local public health department directors in the United States (
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 217), 34% report that they have programs to increase the consumption of local, organic, and plant-based foods, while 54% do not have and/or are not planning to address the role of food in climate change mitigation activities (
  <a rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37">37</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Registered dietitians are well positioned to educate patients, the public, allied healthcare providers, and interdisciplinary colleagues about food choices that can minimize environmental degradation. With a unique skill set that is applied across a variety of settings and institutions, dietitians can take a major leadership role in promoting diet-related climate change mitigation actions while capitalizing on the health benefits of promoting plant-based diets for chronic disease prevention and amelioration (
  <a rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18">18</a>, 
  <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">22</a>, 
  <a rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38">38</a>, 
  <a rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39">39</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Within the dietetics profession, there has been a growing awareness of the relationship between food systems and impact on the natural environment (
  <a rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40">40</a>, 
  <a rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41">41</a>). However, it is unclear how many registered dietitians in the United States are aware of the connection between diet and climate change and take action to mitigate climate change in their professional practice. Thus, the purpose of this research study was to provide a quantitative account of registered dietitians’ beliefs and concerns about climate change; determine registered dietitians’ involvement in climate change mitigation activities; and understand if a relationship exists (if at all) among (a) practice behaviors, (b) concern for climate change, (c) personal dietary behaviors, and (d) demographic variables.
 </p>
</sec>
