<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="P33" class="p">Controlled human exposure studies that explore induced decrements in lung function indicate that the higher ozone concentrations should carry greater weight than the moderate and lower concentrations (
 <xref rid="R72" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hazucha and Lefohn, 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="R111" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lefohn et al., 2010b</xref>). Such studies vary the (1) intensity, duration and frequency of exercise from light to very heavy load on a treadmill or a bicycle ergometer to increased minute ventilation, (2) duration of exposures over 6.6-h and 8-h periods, and (3) application of varying hour-by-hour concentrations versus constant concentrations. In the 1980s and early 1990s, US EPA investigators published the initial studies on the effects of 6.6-h exposures on healthy humans (
 <xref rid="R51" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Folinsbee et al., 1988</xref>; 
 <xref rid="R83" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Horstman et al., 1990</xref>). In 1992, the first 8-h exposure study of ozone on lung function comparing the results using a constant concentration and variable concentration profile that mimicked typical diurnal patterns existing under ambient conditions was published (
 <xref rid="R70" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hazucha et al., 1992</xref>). Both the constant and the variable concentration regimes used the same effective dose although the variable regime included exposure to high hourly average ozone concentrations. Compared to the square-wave exposure profile, the hourly lung function decrements in pulmonary function of subjects exposed to the variable concentration regime were substantially greater one hour after the peak exposure, with the conclusion that the higher concentrations should be weighted more than the mid-and low-level values. Several later studies (
 <xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Adams 2003</xref>, 
 <xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2006a</xref>, 
 <xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2006b</xref>) employing either variable (continually changing) or stepwise (increasing or decreasing from one hour to the next) exposure profiles confirmed the results reported by 
 <xref rid="R70" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hazucha et al. (1992)</xref>. These studies showed that equivalent doses (varying versus constant exposures) produced different responses which depended on the applied hourly ozone concentration pattern.
</p>
