<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">A primary goal of this study is to evaluate how some widely used E
 <sub class="sub">0</sub> formulations differ in their estimation of E
 <sub class="sub">0</sub>, including in its spatial and temporal variabilities and trends under climate change. Furthermore, we also investigate how different choices of parameters and temporal scale of input data for a specific formulation affect E
 <sub class="sub">0</sub> estimation and future trends. Previous studies have done cross-comparisons of different E
 <sub class="sub">0</sub> formulations (e.g., [
 <xref rid="pone.0174045.ref001" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0174045.ref057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0174045.ref060" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">60</xref>]), but only a few studies (e.g., [
 <xref rid="pone.0174045.ref061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">61</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0174045.ref062" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">62</xref>]) have examined the importance of methodological choices for drought risk assessment at regional scales under climate change scenarios, in particular for the CONUS. For example, Sheffield et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0174045.ref001" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>] found that 20
 <sup class="sup">th</sup> century global drying trends differ between temperature- and physically based E
 <sub class="sub">0</sub> estimation methods. A more exhaustive comparison including several E
 <sub class="sub">0</sub> formulations, choices of parameter estimations, and drought metrics is needed for regional application in drought analyses. Here we compare such uncertainties coming from the methodological choices to estimate E
 <sub class="sub">0</sub> (use of different formulations and input data), and selection of GCM output for the CONUS (see 
 <xref rid="pone.0174045.t001" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref>). Another focus of this study is how “standardized” drought indices are affected by different methodological choices. Standardized drought indices are widely used operationally because they allow comparisons of drought conditions across space and time (e.g., [
 <xref rid="pone.0174045.ref063" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">63</xref>]). E
 <sub class="sub">0</sub> is central to the calculation of a variety of commonly used drought indices, which include the formerly mentioned Aridity Index, the Palmer Drought Severity Index (PDSI; [
 <xref rid="pone.0174045.ref064" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">64</xref>]), the Standardized Precipitation Evapotranspiration Index (SPEI; [
 <xref rid="pone.0174045.ref065" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">65</xref>]), and the recently developed Evaporative Demand Drought Index (EDDI; [
 <xref rid="pone.0174045.ref036" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0174045.ref066" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">66</xref>]). Differences in the estimation of E
 <sub class="sub">0</sub> from different methodologies will affect how these metrics represent the magnitude, duration, and the spatial extent of drought in the historical climate and in projections of future drought (e.g., [
 <xref rid="pone.0174045.ref001" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>]). Therefore, we also evaluate how future trends in standardized E
 <sub class="sub">0</sub> anomalies and trends in standardized drought indices like SPEI and EDDI are sensitive to methodological and GCM choices made when estimating E
 <sub class="sub">0</sub>. This is crucial because ecologists and natural resource managers have a wide variety of methods and GCM datasets to choose from, but generally rely on limited guidance in the literature as to how sensitive their findings could be to these choices. This paper addresses this problem by comparing different methodologies for E
 <sub class="sub">0</sub> estimation, two drought indicators (EDDI and SPEI), and investigating their impacts on present and future droughts conditions at regional scales within the CONUS.
</p>
