<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece31645-sec-0002" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When will Range‐edge Populations be Important?</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Many predictions of how the geographic ranges of species will shift as a result of climate change are based on models that incorporate only a single summary climate variable such as mean annual temperature or total annual precipitation (TAP; Zimmermann et al. 
  <a rid="ece31645-bib-0074" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31645-bib-0074">2009</a>). Under these predictions, a best‐case scenario is one in which species do not suffer from any sort of dispersal limitation and local populations track changing climates perfectly through time and space (Fig. 
  <a rid="ece31645-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#ece31645-fig-0001">1</a>A). However, such a scenario is clearly over‐simplified and unrealistic, as supported by the observation that the distributional shifts of many species' lag well behind concurrent climate shifts (Chen et al. 
  <a rid="ece31645-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31645-bib-0010">2011</a>). One explanation for the observed lag in species' distributional shifts is that many species do not respond to just one measure of climate, but rather to multiple facets of climate including climatic extremes and variability (Zimmermann et al. 
  <a rid="ece31645-bib-0074" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31645-bib-0074">2009</a>). Furthermore, within species, local populations may respond differently to changes in climate depending on the degree of local adaptation and the characteristics of the local environment. Understanding how species and local populations respond to various aspects of climate change (e.g., changes in means vs. variation of climate variables) will greatly improve our ability to predict species' persistence under climate change.
 </p>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece31645-fig-0001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Conceptual models of distributional range shifts of locally‐adapted range‐edge populations during climate change.</p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-3" xlink:href="ECE3-5-4315-g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">At the individual species level, when equilibrium climatic conditions are experienced, climate is commonly most suitable toward the center of the species' range and less suitable, or harsher, toward the range edges (Brown 
  <a rid="ece31645-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31645-bib-0006">1984</a>). Range‐edge populations are often portrayed as being at their physiological limits because they are thought to be located at the edges of a species' climatic niche (MacArthur 
  <a rid="ece31645-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31645-bib-0047">1972</a>) even though harsh climate at one species' range edge may be considered benign by another species. From the species' perspective, range‐edge climates are considered harsher than climate at the species' core as a result of an increased frequency and severity of extreme climate events, such as droughts, heat waves, or freezing episodes (Hoffman and Parsons 
  <a rid="ece31645-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31645-bib-0031">1997</a>; Gaston 
  <a rid="ece31645-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31645-bib-0020">2003</a>). These extreme climate events can play a strong role in determining the demographics and fitness of individuals and local populations (Gutschick and BassiriRad 
  <a rid="ece31645-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31645-bib-0024">2003</a>; Jentsch et al. 
  <a rid="ece31645-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31645-bib-0035">2007</a>; Lynch et al. 
  <a rid="ece31645-bib-0046" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31645-bib-0046">2014</a>). There is also strong evidence that populations distributed across climatic gradients commonly show high levels of local adaptation, especially in tree species (Savolainen et al. 
  <a rid="ece31645-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31645-bib-0062">2007</a>; Aitken et al. 
  <a rid="ece31645-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31645-bib-0001">2008</a>; Leimu and Fischer 
  <a rid="ece31645-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31645-bib-0043">2008</a>; Hereford 
  <a rid="ece31645-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31645-bib-0028">2009</a>; Alberto et al. 
  <a rid="ece31645-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31645-bib-0002">2013</a>). Localized range‐edge populations are therefore likely to maintain specialized genotypes that are particularly well‐adapted to the harsh or extreme climates that they experience.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">If extreme climate events become more common as is often predicted (Kodra et al. 
  <a rid="ece31645-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31645-bib-0039">2011</a>; Dai 
  <a rid="ece31645-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31645-bib-0013">2013</a>; Trenberth et al. 
  <a rid="ece31645-bib-0068" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31645-bib-0068">2014</a>), then range‐edge populations may have a fitness advantage (e.g., higher rates of survival) relative to the more central conspecific populations that are less tolerant of these events (Gutschick and BassiriRad 
  <a rid="ece31645-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31645-bib-0024">2003</a>). According to this hypothesis, locally‐adapted range‐edge populations at both the leading and trailing range edges are predicted to expand their distributions and become increasingly abundant throughout species' ranges in the future (Fig. 
  <a rid="ece31645-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#ece31645-fig-0001">1</a>B–D). However, some geographic areas where many species' range‐edges converge (e.g., ecotones) may also be disproportionally affected by anthropogenic habitat disturbances relative to core populations. Therefore, range‐edge populations and their unique genotypes could be lost, reducing the ability of a species to rapidly colonize new climatically suitable habitats.
 </p>
</sec>
