<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Broadly, uncertainty in climate projections arises from three sources: uncertainty in future climate forcing, in the climate system response to that forcing (i.e. the change in climate) and in the actual realization of climate for a particular time window, which is subject to internal variability. The nature of these uncertainties is very different (e.g. [
 <xref rid="RSPA20190013C23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>]). The first depends primarily on human actions and is called the scenario, and the projections are normally made conditional on the scenario. The second is what is known as an 
 <italic class="italic">epistemic</italic> uncertainty; there is only one truth, but we do not know what it is. The third is what is known as an 
 <italic class="italic">aleatoric</italic> uncertainty; there is a random element to what will occur, whose probability is known to some extent. Any discussion of climate risk must address the central fact that the nature of the second and third uncertainties is fundamentally different. This is especially important for circulation-related aspects of climate change at the regional scale, for which these two sources of uncertainty tend to dominate the overall uncertainty (see [
 <xref rid="RSPA20190013C24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>] for regional precipitation changes). Yet, it is standard practice in climate science to mingle the two sources of uncertainty together, e.g. in the multi-model ensembles (with one realization taken from each model) that are in such widespread use [
 <xref rid="RSPA20190013C2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. In such ensembles, the differences between the individual model projections include both the systematic differences between different model climates (epistemic) and the random differences that arise from the limited sampling of internal variability (aleatoric). Since only the latter possess an underlying probability distribution, this poses challenges in interpretation [
 <xref rid="RSPA20190013C25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>].
</p>
