<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Blood Sample Collection</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A detailed blood sampling scheme is described in Mäkinen et al. (forthcoming) but briefly, birds were divided in two sampling groups representing both temperature treatments and selection lines (see above). Blood was sampled every other week from each individual between January and July. Every pair was sampled within 10 min after capture and then put back in their climate-controlled aviary. During a sampling day, birds (
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 36) were sampled between 8:30 AM and 14:30 PM. Individual birds were randomized by treatment and line to three sampling groups and individuals were sampled around the same time of day every time they were blood sampled. Red blood cells were separated from plasma by centrifuging at 14,000 rpm for 10 min and were stored in Queens buffer at room temperature until being processed. This treatment is sufficient to enrich the sample for red blood cells as the ratio between white to red blood cells in a whole blood sample is normally 1:800 (
  <a rid="evz044-B74" ref-type="bibr" href="#evz044-B74">Vinkler et al. 2010</a>). For the analysis, four time points were chosen based on realized first egg lay dates of the females as described in Mäkinen et al. (forthcoming): 1) the day when day light length &gt;12 h (time point 1), 2) the day when 25% of the females from the warm environment had initiated laying (time point 2), 3) the day when 25% and 50% of the females from the cold and warm environment respectively had initiated laying (time point 3), and 4) the day when 50% of the females from the cold treatment had initiated laying. As our chosen time points did not always coincide with the days of blood sampling scheme, we chose blood samples that were sampled closest to (±7 days) the four chosen time points. This resulted in a total of 63 samples, because we were unable to take one blood sample for time point 4, because one female (warm treatment) was incubating her eggs during the sampling.
 </p>
</sec>
