<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Genomic Locations and Gene Annotation</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As expected, there was a positive correlation between the number of analyzed CpG sites (corrected for chromosome length) and GC content of the chromosome (
  <span class="italic">r</span> = 0.84, df = 32, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.01, 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1" href="#sup1">supplementary fig. S5</a>
  <span class="italic">A</span>, 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1" href="#sup1">Supplementary Material</a> online). This is reflected also in the numbers of time-dependent sites in the different chromosomes. Chromosomes 25LG1 and 25LG2 have the largest number of CpG sites assigned to them in relation to their size (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1" href="#sup1">supplementary fig. S5</a>
  <span class="italic">B</span>, 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1" href="#sup1">Supplementary Material</a> online) as the GC content of these chromosomes is the highest in the whole Great tit genome (
  <a rid="evz044-B25" ref-type="bibr" href="#evz044-B25">Laine et al. 2016</a>). Similarly, GC content is slightly higher also in chromosomes 26, 27, and 28 and LGE22 compared with the other chromosomes (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1" href="#sup1">supplementary fig. S4</a>
  <span class="italic">A</span>, 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1" href="#sup1">Supplementary Material</a> online). This pattern of high GC content is typical for the great tit microchromosomes. In the mitochondria, we observed five sites and these were all time dependent and intragenic (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1" href="#sup1">supplementary table S3</a>, 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1" href="#sup1">Supplementary Material</a> online).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Most of the analyzed CpG sites were intronic (24.8%), whereas for TSS, exon, intergenic, and promoter, the proportions were quite similar (18.3%, 17.3%, 17.4%, and 22.1%, respectively). Methylation levels in the different genomic regions also differed significantly (Wilcox test, see 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1" href="#sup1">supplementary table S5</a>, 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1" href="#sup1">Supplementary Material</a> online) and methylation levels were highest in exons and intergenic regions (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1" href="#sup1">supplementary fig. S6</a>, 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1" href="#sup1">Supplementary Material</a> online). The proportions of the genomic regions within time-independent CpG sites are similar to the genomic regions for all analyzed data set with 19.45%, 17.1%, 16.5%, 24.6%, and 22.2% for TSS, exon, intergenic, intron, and promoter, respectively. For the time dependent and time dependent with treatment effect the corresponding values are 7.4%, 18.6%, 25.3%, 27.0%, and 21.6% and 4.3%, 20.6%, 28.7%, 26.8%, and 19.5%, respectively, for TSS, exon, intergenic, intron, and promoter. Methylation levels were higher for CpG sites classified as time dependent with treatment effect (
  <a rid="evz044-T2" ref-type="table" href="#evz044-T2">table 2</a>) and this was also seen when splitting the CpG sites based on genomic location and model (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1" href="#sup1">supplementary fig. S7</a>, 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1" href="#sup1">Supplementary Material</a> online). In addition, methylation levels did not differ between the treatments for sites classified as time dependent or time independent, whereas levels differed for sites classified as the time dependent with treatment effect as expected (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1" href="#sup1">supplementary fig. S7</a>, 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1" href="#sup1">Supplementary Material</a> online).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There were differences between genomic regions of the time-dependent CpG sites (47,922 in 
  <a rid="evz044-T2" ref-type="table" href="#evz044-T2">table 2</a>.) and the time-independent sites. The number of sites annotated to TSS is lower in time-dependent sites (both without or with treatment), whereas more sites are annotated to exon or intergenic regions in the time-dependent class, especially for time-dependent treatment (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="evz044-F4" href="#evz044-F4">fig. 4</a>, Pearson’s chi-square test, df = 8, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.001). 
 </p>
 <div id="evz044-F4" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">
   <span class="sc">Fig</span>. 4.
  </span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>—Genomic regions of CpG sites in the time-independent and the two time-dependent classes. Colors represent the different genomic locations based on annotation of the 
    <span class="italic">Parus major</span> genome v1.1.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="evz044f4" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">CpG sites classified as time dependent (with or without treatment) overlapped 41% of the annotated genes in 
  <span class="italic">Parus major</span> v1.1 genome; that is, 53% of the genes which were used in the analysis (i.e., the reference set, 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1" href="#sup1">supplementary table S4</a>, 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1" href="#sup1">Supplementary Material</a> online, considering promoter, TSS, and gene body). Genes had on average 15.00 CpG sites assigned to them (SD = 14.12) and typically included CpG sites classified as both time dependent and time dependent with treatment effect (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1" href="#sup1">supplementary table S4</a>, 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1" href="#sup1">Supplementary Material</a> online).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Functional analysis, which is grouping genes based on GO-term enrichment (BH corrected 
  <span class="italic">P</span> value &lt;0.05), for time-dependent classified genes identified 106 functional groups mainly involved in regulation and development of different tissue types (supplementary tables S6, 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1" href="#sup1">Supplementary Material</a> online), whereas for time-dependent treatment classified genes, there were six functional groups identified and these were involved in chromatin modification related functions (GO:0042800 and GO:0048188) as well as transcriptional coactivation (GO:0001223, 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1" href="#sup1">supplementary table S7</a>, 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1" href="#sup1">Supplementary Material</a> online). In the time-dependent genes, we identified specific GO-terms not only for developmental functions in different tissues but also for energy balance and reproductive system development (GO:0003006, GO:0048608, GO:0061458, GO:2000243, GO:0008406, GO:0045137, and GO:0046660). Genes underlying these latter GO-terms as well as GO-terms in the six groups from the time dependent with treatment-specific trajectories can be regarded as potential candidates for timing of breeding in the great tit (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1" href="#sup1">supplementary tables S6 and S7</a>, 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1" href="#sup1">Supplementary Material</a> online).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When looking at genes in more detail, we found that 
  <span class="italic">DIO2</span>, a candidate gene for timing of reproduction in the great tit (
  <a rid="evz044-B46" ref-type="bibr" href="#evz044-B46">Perfito et al. 2012</a>), showed temporal change in DNA methylation. Two out of the eight CpG sites observed in this gene in our data set were classified as time dependent (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1" href="#sup1">supplementary table S4</a>, 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1" href="#sup1">Supplementary Material</a> online). These sites are located in the first exon of the gene (UTR). The overall methylation level of the eight sites in 
  <span class="italic">DIO2</span> have mean methylation level of 2.4% (SD = 1.5%), and the nonlinear change over time is low in general (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1" href="#sup1">supplementary fig. S8</a>, 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1" href="#sup1">Supplementary Material</a> online). One of the new potential candidate genes identified with the GO analysis, 
  <span class="italic">RORA</span> (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1" href="#sup1">supplementary table S7</a>, 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1" href="#sup1">Supplementary Material</a> online, group 1), exhibits a site-specific methylation pattern, which also differs between the treatment groups across time (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1" href="#sup1">supplementary fig. S9</a>, 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1" href="#sup1">Supplementary Material</a> online). It has 30 CpG sites associated to it of which three are time dependent and nine time dependent with treatment. All the sites are located in introns. In contrast to 
  <span class="italic">DIO2</span>, methylation levels in 
  <span class="italic">RORA</span> are higher for the methylated sites (mean = 23.6%, SD = 27.2%) making the difference between methylated and nonmethylated sites more evident than in 
  <span class="italic">DIO2</span>. Both of these genes also indicate linear and nonlinear changes across time.
 </p>
</sec>
