<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece31645-sec-0007" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Caveats, Applications, and Future Directions</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">During future climate change, extreme climatic events will become more frequent and severe across large geographic areas, significantly affecting the ability of many species to persist into the future (Zimmermann et al. 
  <a rid="ece31645-bib-0074" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31645-bib-0074">2009</a>; Reyer et al. 
  <a rid="ece31645-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31645-bib-0059">2013</a>). In addition, asynchronous rates of change in different climate variables will result in novel climates being introduced throughout the globe (Williams et al. 
  <a rid="ece31645-bib-0072" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31645-bib-0072">2007</a>). Using relatively simple conceptual models and empirical analyses, we highlight how locally‐adapted populations occurring at tree species range edges are perhaps the best suited to survive extreme climate events and persist under future novel climates. We also discuss and show how large‐scale habitat disturbances are removing unique range‐edge populations, predominantly at ecotones, potentially hindering species' abilities to respond to climate change.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our models and predictions have some notable caveats. We focused on just two main forested systems, treelines and the southeast Amazon, as these biome boundaries are exemplary of areas with high species range edge convergence coupled with large‐scale anthropogenic disturbance. Notably, our arguments concerning latitudinal and alpine treelines would be greatly improved by further detail concerning the rates and patterns of deforestation at these ecotones. Regardless, we chose these two systems to underline the main points of our models, which were designed to show that human disturbances often can and do remove important range edge populations. Species range edges can occur anywhere across globe and not only at major biogeographic boundaries. Therefore, the application of our conceptual models at the species level will depend on the local intensity of land‐use change and the removal of edge as opposed to more core populations, which will vary depending on the geographic region and species in question.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We also did not explicitly incorporate the phenotypic responses of local genotypes. We believe that this is justified due to the unprecedented magnitude and pace of current climate change which will quickly introduce novel environmental conditions that are likely to be beyond what species can tolerate through plastic responses and acclimation (Jump and Peñuelas 
  <a rid="ece31645-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31645-bib-0036">2005</a>; Valladares et al. 
  <a rid="ece31645-bib-0070" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31645-bib-0070">2007</a>). Plasticity itself is an evolvable trait, but adaptive plasticity is most likely to evolve when cues reliably predict environmental conditions (van Kleunen and Fischer 
  <a rid="ece31645-bib-0038" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31645-bib-0038">2005</a>; Nicotra et al. 
  <a rid="ece31645-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31645-bib-0053">2010</a>). Given the current pace of climate change and that environmental cues may become progressively unreliable and environmental conditions unpredictable, rapid evolutionary responses of plasticity and other traits are unlikely in organisms such as trees that are long‐lived and have long generation times (van Kleunen and Fischer 
  <a rid="ece31645-bib-0038" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31645-bib-0038">2005</a>; Hanski 
  <a rid="ece31645-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31645-bib-0027">2012</a>; Merilä 
  <a rid="ece31645-bib-0051" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31645-bib-0051">2012</a>). Although rapid adaptation can occur over a surprisingly small number of generations, the long generation times in trees means that any adaptive responses to climate change will likely lag behind changes in climate (Jump and Peñuelas 
  <a rid="ece31645-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31645-bib-0036">2005</a>; Quintero and Wiens 
  <a rid="ece31645-bib-0057" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31645-bib-0057">2013</a>). As such, we limit our discussion to the beneficial traits currently expressed by locally‐adapted genotypes and we do not specifically address adaptive phenotypic plasticity or microevolutionary processes.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We give special attention to the responses of locally‐adapted range‐edge populations to only temperature and precipitation as these two variables are often found to be the most important abiotic determinants of range limits in trees (Cahill et al. 
  <a rid="ece31645-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31645-bib-0008">2014</a>). Under future climate scenarios, it is likely that the relative importance of range‐edge populations to total species' persistence will increase dramatically. However, other abiotic factors (e.g., additional climatic factors, soil conditions) and biotic factors (e.g., herbivory rates, competition) will also likely influence species' responses to climate change. With rapid advancements in the breadth and complexity of predictive tools, we should begin to incorporate both climatic and nonclimatic factors into our conceptual models to create more realistic and accurate predictions of species shifts under future climates (Svenning et al. 
  <a rid="ece31645-bib-0067" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31645-bib-0067">2014</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Theoretical efforts toward predicting where and when local adaptations occur in wild populations have seen great advances over the past decades (Merilä 
  <a rid="ece31645-bib-0051" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31645-bib-0051">2012</a>). However, empirical evidence often contradicts theory and shows large variations in where and when local adaptations occur (Sagarin et al. 
  <a rid="ece31645-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31645-bib-0061">2006</a>; Bridle and Vines 
  <a rid="ece31645-bib-0005" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31645-bib-0005">2007</a>). In order to understand and conserve important range edge populations, we must first identify the populations within species' ranges that hold genotypes that may be beneficial under future climate (e.g., see Fitzpatrick and Keller 
  <a rid="ece31645-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31645-bib-0019">2015</a>). Future research into identification and genetic mapping of entire species' ranges has large implications for ecosystem function and persistence under future climates.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Specific focus should be given to identifying the traits within locally‐adapted populations that are predicted to become more important under future climate conditions (e.g., heat and drought tolerance). Identifying the responsible genetic controls of these traits will aid in conservation efforts and advance our ability to accurately forecast where and when locally‐adapted range‐edge populations will be important determinants of species persistence. Even in well‐studied traits, such as cold temperature adaptation in northern hemisphere trees, we still have a relatively basic understanding of how specific genes control phenotypic expression and how genes are linked or interact (Howe et al. 
  <a rid="ece31645-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31645-bib-0033">2003</a>; Savolainen et al. 
  <a rid="ece31645-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31645-bib-0062">2007</a>). Without knowing the constraints to heritable variation in traits under selection, we are unable to make accurate predictions about rapid evolutionary adaptation in populations.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The recent and rapid advances in molecular techniques may allow for the disentangling of genetic controls on beneficial traits and allow researchers to weigh the importance of range shifts versus rapid evolutionary adaptation in a timeframe relevant for contemporary climate change. Work of this nature should focus on intraspecific population genetics across a wide variety of taxa and functional groups that exhibit different life history strategies. Efforts such as these will greatly increase our ability to predict species' range shifts and extinctions and therefore help to most effectively focus the limited resources available for conservation.</p>
</sec>
