<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Temperature can have a strong influence on physiology and metabolic rate (Bennett &amp; Dawson, 
 <xref rid="ece34006-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1976</xref>; Hochachka &amp; Somero, 
 <xref rid="ece34006-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1973</xref>), and can affect numerous life‐history traits including maintenance, growth rate, reproduction, and development (Angilletta, 
 <xref rid="ece34006-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>; Angilletta, Niewiarowski, &amp; Navas, 
 <xref rid="ece34006-bib-0005" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2002</xref>; Huey &amp; Stevenson, 
 <xref rid="ece34006-bib-0044" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1979</xref>). To test for an acclimation response to temperature in ectotherms, differences in oxygen consumption (standard metabolic rate, SMR) can be compared for individuals acclimated at lower and higher temperatures (Feder, 
 <xref rid="ece34006-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1978</xref>; Fitzpatrick, 
 <xref rid="ece34006-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1973</xref>; Fitzpatrick &amp; Atebara, 
 <xref rid="ece34006-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1974</xref>). As oxygen uptake is a proxy for ATP demand, changes in SMR can indicate changing energy needs and the health of an individual. After short‐term exposure to a warmer temperature, species with acclimation ability should maintain or slightly increase SMR, indicating a positive response shift in physiology (Feder, 
 <xref rid="ece34006-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1978</xref>; Hillman, Withers, Drewes, &amp; Hillyard, 
 <xref rid="ece34006-bib-0038" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>). The ability for individuals to reduce or negate the energetic stresses on metabolism, and to remain active at higher temperatures, could lead to the acquisition of greater resources, increased mating opportunities, and expanded distributions (Bernardo, Ossola, Spotila, &amp; Crandall, 
 <xref rid="ece34006-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>; Feder, 
 <xref rid="ece34006-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1976</xref>; Hillman et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34006-bib-0038" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>). A drop in metabolic rate (i.e., metabolic depression) at higher temperatures could indicate physiological stress, and without acclimation, the survivorship and fitness of individuals could be profoundly reduced during rapid or prolonged changes in temperature (Bernardo &amp; Spotila, 
 <xref rid="ece34006-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>).
</p>
