<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par2" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Earth’s climate has three states: no ice caps (such as believed to have occurred during the warm Mesozoic), partial ice caps (as the present period of glacial and interglacials during the Pleistocene and Holocene), and an Earth completely covered in ice and snow called Snowball Earth. Earth is believed to have been in and out of the Snowball-Earth state during at least two periods, the NeoProterozoic Cryogenian Period (720–635 million years ago)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span> and the PaleoProterozoic glaciation (2.45–2.2 billion years ago)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The PaleoProterozoic glaciation occurred during a period of climatic change on Earth. To compensate for the Sun being about 19% weaker than present during the PaleoProterozoic
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>
  </span>, higher concentrations of greenhouse gases, such as carbon dioxide, methane, and water vapor, must have been present in the atmosphere to maintain a temperate climate
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>
  </span>. For example, atmospheric methane concentrations were perhaps as much as 1000 times that of the present due to methanogenic archaea. Atmospheric oxygen concentration was increasing rapidly as a result of oxygen production by photosynthetic bacteria exceeding the sinks of oxygen
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span>. With the increasing oxygenation of Earth, methane reacted with the oxygen, producing carbon dioxide and water vapor. These bacteria would have been a sink for the carbon dioxide, as well. In addition, weathering of fresh basaltic surfaces from rifting of the supercontinent would have reduced the amount of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
  </span>. As carbon dioxide and water vapor are less powerful greenhouse gases compared to methane, this weakened the Earth’s greenhouse, possibly leading to Snowball Earth
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Earth may have slipped in and out of glacial episodes three or four times during the PaleoProterozoic, culminating in the Makganyene Snowball Earth episode at about 2.3–2.2 billion years
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span>. The evidence of cap carbonates at the end of some these glacial episodes suggests one reason for these cycles may be the emission of a large amount of carbon dioxide, perhaps from underwater volcanism, and an enhanced greenhouse effect that led to the end of Snowball Earth
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
  </span>. But, greenhouse gas concentrations are not the only control on Earth’s climate.
 </p>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition to changes in the atmosphere during this period, the Earth’s continents came together in what was perhaps the first supercontinent, although paleogeographical reconstructions are necessarily uncertain given its age
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>
  </span>. Collisions between various continents had produced mountain ranges
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span>. Erosion of the mountains by precipitation would reduce atmospheric carbon dioxide, further weakening the greenhouse effect
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
  </span>. Thus, mountain formation due to continent–continent collisions during supercontinent assembly may also have led to fluctuations in the atmospheric greenhouse. Weathering affecting the atmospheric carbon dioxide concentration is not the only effect on the climate. The direct effect of the topography by changing the atmospheric circulation may have favored or inhibited the potential for the Earth to enter a snowball state. For example, the effect of the mountains at higher latitudes may have had a different impact on the Snowball Earth than mountains at lower latitudes. Such sensitivities have not been investigated previously for the PaleoProterozoic glaciation or any other Snowball Earth period. Given the uncertainties in the reconstruction of the continents and their mountains, exploration of these sensitivities may shed light on the conditions likely responsible for the glaciations.
 </p>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here we present a series of paleoclimate model simulations to examine some of the sensitivities that affect the onset of Snowball Earth. The model is a coupled atmosphere–ocean climate model
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
  </span> that has simulated Snowball Earths previously
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span>. We consider an idealized supercontinent centered on the equator (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). We perform a series of 49 simulations varying the atmospheric greenhouse gas concentration and latitudes of west–east-oriented mountain ranges, keeping all other components of the model fixed. We choose to fix carbon dioxide at 10,000 ppm and vary methane concentrations from 1 to 100 ppmv to regulate the magnitude of the greenhouse effect on Earth. Two mountain ranges are centered at various latitudes: ±10° (M10), ±20° (M20), ±30° (M30), ±40° (M40), and ±50° (M50), with one simulation having one mountain range on the equator (M0) and one simulation having no mountains at all (FLAT) (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). Mountain ranges are 3 km high, 1550 km wide, and extend from the west to east coasts of the continent. Although the design of these simulations were meant to idealise the supercontinent and not represent any particular reconstruction, at least one paleoclimate reconstruction
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
  </span> suggests that there might have been an orogeny at the equator, which would have been similar to simulation M0. Each simulation ran for 400 years by which the latitude of sea-ice extent reached an equilibrium, either at a latitude greater than about ±30° or at the equator (i.e., Snowball Earth). As in previous modelling studies using this model, if sea ice forms within about 25° latitude of the equator, then the climate ultimately proceeds to a Snowball-Earth state, and intermediate latitudes of maximum sea-ice extent do not form
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span>. In reality however, this latitude may be lower because of the omission of sea-ice dynamics in the model
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
  </span>.
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Terrain heights for simulations varying the latitudes of mountain ranges. Colors indicate the terrain elevation, with a maximum terrain height of 3 km.</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_38839_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e403" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
