<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec14" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p id="Par76" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this study, we examined the prevalence of burnout among pediatric residents as well as the correlation between burnout subscales, personal characteristics, related factors in the educational climate and work-related quality of life in a non-Western context. Although, none of the pediatric residents had high burnout levels in 
  <span class="italic">all three</span> domains, seven (17%) showed high levels in two out of three conditions studied (emotional exhaustion, level of depersonalization and perceived low personal accomplishment). Results from the survey showed that emotional exhaustion and educational climate were correlated with work-related quality of life. In the interviews, the main themes related to burnout were inappropriate tasks, teachers and teaching styles, the perception of knowledge insecurity relating to task performance, time dimensions, life crisis during training, role expectations and work allocation clarity, and facilities such as accommodation.
 </p>
 <sec id="Sec15" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Prevalence of burnout among pediatric residents</div>
  <p id="Par77" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A striking finding of the quantitative study was that none of pediatric residents had high burnout levels in all three domains. The explanation of this difference could be the diversity of educational climates between institutions or the social desirability, as our study was confidential but not anonymous. However, seven of the participants in our study with warning signals regarding burnout, reported high scores on two out of the three factors: high emotional exhaustion, high depersonalisation and low personal accomplishment. A correlation between burnout subscales, educational climate and work-related quality of life among pediatric residents in the previous studies, was confirmed in our study [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec16" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Factors associated with burnout level</div>
  <p id="Par78" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another finding of our study was a correlation between total quality of life and emotional exhaustion. The characteristics of residents in our study demonstrated no relationship with any of the subscales of the burnout level. This is in line with previous findings Llera and Durante that demographic factors do not relate to at-risk residents [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>]. However, this contrasts with findings in a study by Shanafelt et al. who identified being older and being married were related to a lower risk for burnout [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>]. These differences might be explained from the context of Thai pediatric residents who are almost all of similar age, gender (female) and marital status (single).
  </p>
  <p id="Par79" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Moreover, the burnout subscales level of pediatric residents was not related to the overall medical educational environment. This is in line with the study of Meriläinenaetal. that reported no relationship between the teaching-learning model of environment and burnout [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>]. Alternatively, Dyrbye et al. discovered that some learning environment factors were associated with medical students’ burnout, but these factors were not included in the PHEEM questionnaire [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>]. In Western countries, factors contributing to burnout were job satisfaction, stress and control at work, working conditions, and home-work interface [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>], while this study added in a non-Western setting, the importance of inappropriate tasks, teachers and teaching styles (including unsafe environment), the perception of knowledge insecurity to perform some tasks, time dimensions, and life crisis occurring during training. These findings thus underscore that differences in factors contributing to burnout exist between different cultures.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec17" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Educational environment and work-related quality of life</div>
  <p id="Par80" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Noteworthy is that a strong association between educational environment and work-related quality of life was found. A learning climate designed to promote resident’s autonomy might benefit resident’s work-related quality of life. Perception of a good teaching climate showed a positive relationship with employee engagement, a moderate association with control at work, general well-being, job and career satisfaction and working conditions, and a negative correlation for stress at work. In conclusion, educational climate had effects not only on residents wellbeing but also on stress at work. Thai clinical teachers and curriculum developers, therefore, need to pay more attention to the effect of educational climate rather than focusing on students learning only. Social support showed a significant correlation with all subscales of work related quality of life, except for stress at work. One possible interpretation is that social support in Thai context could improve the residents’ quality of life but is not likely to reduce the stress level at work. Social support in the workplace in the Thai context seems to be lacking at this moment. Nevertheless, social support in the Thai context should be considered as important for residents wellbeing and would, consequently, needs more attention. Further evidence for this is found in a study among internal medicine and pediatric residents in U.S., where loneliness was associated with burnout, sense of personal accomplishment was associated with greater network centrality [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>], and interpersonal relationship was related to burnout [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>].
  </p>
  <p id="Par81" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The PHEEM questionnaire did not provide detailed information regarding burnout or stress at work and the improvement of the educational environment. The only item of PHEEM with an average score lower than two out of five in the social support subscale was ‘there are adequate catering facilities when I am on call’. However, the qualitative study identified some details of work and workloads, roles and relationships with other professions, learning atmosphere, research conduction, teachers’ responses, accommodation and restaurants, not included in the PHEEM. These issues are especially important for the residents training programme in Thailand.</p>
  <p id="Par82" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A study by Tsai et al. used a new instrument to investigate the relationship between the clinical learning environment and mental distress among post graduate medical students in Taiwan, because of the socio-culture differences between Taiwan and Western countries [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>]. Unfortunately, this instrument was not validated or tested in other socio-cultural contexts, while PHEEM is currently used in many countries such as UK, Canada, Ireland, China, Indonesia, Malaysia, Norway, Sweden, Brazil, the West Indies and the Yemen [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>]. The PHEEM, assessing the educational environment, might not be the most suitable tool to assess the stress and resident training environment context in Thailand. Therefore, a new, more valid, questionnaire should be developed to assess the educational environment in the context of non-Western medical education.
  </p>
  <p id="Par83" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The qualitative data also indicated that changes to the educational environment are necessary to lower the risk of burnout. For example, a medical service system that promotes collaboration, is user friendly and decreases unnecessary work, might facilitate the work of residents and lower the levels of exhaustion. Moreover, a predictable or routine time schedule for working and learning on the wards was preferred by the residents. The teaching schedule should fit with the flow of work during the day and also not disturb residents’ personal time. This finding was similar to U.S. pediatric residents reporting that time demands contributed to burnout [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>]. In addition, the role and work allocation should be clarified and properly scheduled to fit with the learning process and minimize learning disturbances at the workplace. Lastly, this study suggested that considering adopting different teaching styles and methods such as constructive feedback, investing time and effort in interventions contributing to a safe learning climate and paying attention to a faculty mistreatment which could contribute to medical students burnout. Further studies focusing on teaching styles, safe learning climate and mistreatment in a non-Western context are needed. Also the provision of improved faculty development programmes might enhance teaching, assessment and curriculum design and might require institutional policies supporting the programme [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec18" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Strengths and limitations of the study</div>
  <p id="Par84" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The strength of this study is the mixed method design, combining quantitative and qualitative methodologies, which facilitates in-depth information gathering on the related factors of burnout and also exploration of other factors included in the quantitative part. This study also has limitation such as the small sample size, setting limitations to multivariate analysis. Also, the relationship between researchers and participants requires consideration. Although participants were informed that the data was confidential, they might not be comfortable to reveal negative information or may have given socially and culturally desirable answers. Moreover, this exploratory study was conducted in only one hospital, which might limit its generalizability to other settings. Further studies will be needed.</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
