<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec16" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Factors associated with burnout level</div>
 <p id="Par78" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another finding of our study was a correlation between total quality of life and emotional exhaustion. The characteristics of residents in our study demonstrated no relationship with any of the subscales of the burnout level. This is in line with previous findings Llera and Durante that demographic factors do not relate to at-risk residents [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>]. However, this contrasts with findings in a study by Shanafelt et al. who identified being older and being married were related to a lower risk for burnout [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>]. These differences might be explained from the context of Thai pediatric residents who are almost all of similar age, gender (female) and marital status (single).
 </p>
 <p id="Par79" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Moreover, the burnout subscales level of pediatric residents was not related to the overall medical educational environment. This is in line with the study of Meriläinenaetal. that reported no relationship between the teaching-learning model of environment and burnout [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>]. Alternatively, Dyrbye et al. discovered that some learning environment factors were associated with medical students’ burnout, but these factors were not included in the PHEEM questionnaire [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>]. In Western countries, factors contributing to burnout were job satisfaction, stress and control at work, working conditions, and home-work interface [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>], while this study added in a non-Western setting, the importance of inappropriate tasks, teachers and teaching styles (including unsafe environment), the perception of knowledge insecurity to perform some tasks, time dimensions, and life crisis occurring during training. These findings thus underscore that differences in factors contributing to burnout exist between different cultures.
 </p>
</sec>
