<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec13" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Qualitative part, individual interviews</div>
 <p id="Par44" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Six out of the seven residents who met the inclusion criteria of scores on burnout subscales participated in the interviews. Three were first year residents and one was a third-year resident; one participant was male. Factors in educational climate and work-related quality of life were explored in depth to find a relationship with risk of burnout. The following themes which residents perceived to relate to risk of burnout emerged from the qualitative data analysis of the individual interviews:
  <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
   <div class="list-item">
    <p id="Par45">Educational climate
     <div list-type="order" class="list">
      <div class="list-item">
       <p id="Par46">Inappropriate tasks</p>
      </div>
     </div>
    </p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par47" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Residents reported execution of undesired tasks such as unnecessary or useless work which contributed to exhaustion.</p>
 <p id="Par48" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div class="disp-quote">
   <p id="Par49">
    <span class="italic">“When I rotated to a busier hospital outside my institute, I felt less exhausted, even though the number of patients under my responsibility increased. The unnecessary paper work and rule restrictions in that hospital were less than in my institute.” (Female, 3rd year resident)</span>
   </p>
  </div>
  <div list-type="simple" class="list">
   <div class="list-item">
    <span class="label">2.</span>
    <p id="Par50">Teachers, teaching styles, and role as a teacher</p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par51" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Residents reported stress during various learning activities such as in a conference, or during ward rounds. The stress, in residents’ perception, came from, teacher’s styles, and unsafe atmosphere of some learning activities.</p>
 <p id="Par52" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Constructive feedback from teachers is crucial for learners to achieve personal or teaching programme-related objectives. Residents prefer teachers who do not to display aggressive verbal communication or give negative emotional responses in public.</p>
 <p id="Par53" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div class="disp-quote">
   <p id="Par54">
    <span class="italic">“I felt pressure in the morning conference as I did not have sufficient time to prepare my case report. Sometimes I can’t answer the question, but the teacher still keeps asking more and more questions. I have nothing further to say and I feel stressed.” (Female, 3rd year resident)</span>
   </p>
  </div>Residents’ roles as teachers to medical students was perceived as one of the stress burdens as they were expected to spend extra time to teach. Also, evaluation of their teaching at the end of rotation caused them stress and lowers their motivation to guide younger colleagues.
  <div list-type="simple" class="list">
   <div class="list-item">
    <span class="label">3.</span>
    <p id="Par55">Knowledge insecurity to perform tasks</p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par56" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although senior residents and attending staff were available to provide support, they sometimes felt insecure in their knowledge and felt a gap regarding patient care and consequently lacked the confidence to teach the students.</p>
 <p id="Par57" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div class="disp-quote">
   <p id="Par58">
    <span class="italic">“I can’t understand and catch up with the conversations during ward rounds with the Senior Resident and supervisors. I feel that I have insufficient knowledge.” (Female, 1st year resident)</span>
   </p>
  </div>
  <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
   <div class="list-item">
    <p id="Par59">Work-related quality of life
     <div list-type="order" class="list">
      <div class="list-item">
       <p id="Par60">The time dimension</p>
      </div>
     </div>
    </p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par61" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Residents reported that extra personal time, in addition to duty hours, spent on ward rounds or other work related activities contributed to burnout.</p>
 <p id="Par62" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div class="disp-quote">
   <p id="Par63">“When I have limited personal time, I feel exhausted. I cannot remember things and this decreases my learning motivation.” (Female, 1st year resident)</p>
  </div>
  <div list-type="simple" class="list">
   <div class="list-item">
    <span class="label">2.</span>
    <p id="Par64">Life crisis during training and home-work unbalance</p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par65" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Limitation of personal time could have an effect on the personal life of residents, especially when critical life events occurred in their private lives.</p>
 <p id="Par66" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div class="disp-quote">
   <p id="Par67">
    <span class="italic">“Before my mother passed away, I had no time to say goodbye to her. I spent my time taking care of other children instead of talking to my mother when she could communicate with me.” (Female, 2nd year resident)</span>
   </p>
  </div>
  <div list-type="simple" class="list">
   <div class="list-item">
    <span class="label">3.</span>
    <p id="Par68">Physical environment and facilities</p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par69" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Some residents perceived the need for more and better facilities such as more dormitories and a better quality of available restaurants after office hours, instead of fast food and convenience stores. It was seen as is a way to pursuit wellbeing. Also, residents want more dormitories in the hospital, in order to create more time in the hospital in the already busy mornings.</p>
 <p id="Par70" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div class="disp-quote">
   <p id="Par71">
    <span class="italic">“I don’t live inside the hospital, I have to travel from the hospital to my home every day. I always feel exhausted.” (Female, 2nd year resident) “It would be nice to have a place to stay near the hospital, so I don’t have to waste my time in the traffic.” (Female, 3rd year resident)</span>
   </p>
  </div>
  <div list-type="simple" class="list">
   <div class="list-item">
    <span class="label">4.</span>
    <p id="Par72">Role and work allocation clarity</p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par73" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Some work was not clearly allocated, so unexpected workload or repetitive work occurred.</p>
 <p id="Par74" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div class="disp-quote">
   <p id="Par75">“
    <span class="italic">New patients arrive on the ward at the beginning of night shifts around 5pm. Sometimes the Chief Resident assigns the resident on the ward to assess and care for the patient, instead of the resident on the night shift. Thus, the resident on the ward finishes work late and the resident on the night shift also cares for the patient simultaneously.” (Female, 1st year resident)</span>
   </p>
  </div>In summary, the qualitative part explicated some important factors in the educational climate, such as inappropriate tasks, teaching styles and also work-related quality of life in pediatric residents’ perception, such as spending extra personal time on work-related activities, and life crisis which relate to risk of burnout.
 </p>
</sec>
