<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Quantitative phase, surveys</div>
 <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The first phase employed a quantitative cross-sectional survey which included background variables, measurements of burnout, the perceived learning environment, and work-related quality of life. The following background-characteristics were measured: age, gender, year of training, marital status, responsibility for the family’s or own financial burden, sleep hours/night, study time hours/week, non-academic leisure time hours/week.</p>
 <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Burnout was measured with the Maslach Burnout Inventory (MBI) - Health service survey, an internationally acknowledged and validated instrument [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>]. The MBI is a standard 22-item questionnaire (7-point Likert scale). The instrument consists of three sections which measures levels of a) emotional exhaustion, b) depersonalisation and c) personal accomplishment [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>]. The MBI has previously been translated into Thai and tested for reliability. Cronbach’s alpha coefficients for the sections were 0.92, 0.66 and 0.65, respectively [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par31" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Learning environment was measured with the Postgraduate Hospital Educational Environmental Measure (PHEEM) questionnaire. This questionnaire consists of 40 items, divided into three sections: a) autonomy, b) teaching, and c) social support (5-point Likert scale, ranging from 4 = strongly agree to 0 = strongly disagree). The original instrument, tested in the UK, had a Cronbach’s alpha reliability of 0.91 [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>]. Translation into the Thai language was done by an experienced translator in the medical field and then back-translated to English by another experienced translator, leading to further refinement into the Thai language. The original English questionnaire was then analyzed for degree of agreement with the back-translation and rated by three faculty medical instructors from the paediatric department. Kappa’s agreement scores ranged between 0.61–0.80 and were confirmed as substantial at 80–95% of agreement.
 </p>
 <p id="Par32" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Work-related Quality of life was measured with the Work-Related Quality of Life scale (WRQoL), a 23-item psychometric scale divided into six subscales of factors contributing to quality of life: Job and Career Satisfaction (JCS), General Well-Being (GWB), Stress at Work (SAW), Control at Work (CAW), Home-Work Interface (HWI) and Working Conditions (WCS). The questionnaire is composed of 5-point Likert scale items (1 = strongly disagree; 5 = strongly agree). Its reliability (Cronbach’s alpha of 0.75–0.86) were verified among medical personnel in the United Kingdom [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>]. We used the Thai-translated and validated 34item WRQoL version 2 with 7 sub-scales (Job and Career Satisfaction (JCS), General Well-Being (GWB), Stress at Work (SAW), Control at Work (CAW), Home-Work Interface (HWI) and Working Conditions (WCS) and employee engagement (EET)), which had a content validity index of the scale of 0.97. Overall Cronbach’s alpha was 0.93 with good test-retest reliabilityof0.892 [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par33" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The three surveys (110 items) were distributed in written format among all 42 pediatric residents across all years of training, also inviting them to later participate in interviews.</p>
</sec>
