<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Quantitative part, surveys</div>
 <p id="Par38" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Forty-two paediatric residents were invited to participate with a 97% response rate (one refused to participate); 75% of respondents were female. The distribution of responding residents over years 1, 2 and 3 was 15 (36%), 14 (33%) and 12 (29%) respectively (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>).
  <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Distribution of residents participated in the study in all year</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="12909_2019_1687_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par39" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The MBI questionnaire identified 7 residents (17%) perceiving high emotional exhaustion, five (12%) showed high depersonalization and 12 (29%) perceived low personal achievement. None of the residents experienced burnout with high levels of both emotional exhaustion and depersonalization and a low level of personal achievement. However, residents who met 2 of 3 criteria of burnout were able to provide information related to burnout.</p>
 <p id="Par40" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Postgraduate Hospital Educational Environmental Measure (PHEEM) revealed that most of the residents (88%) had a positive perception of their role autonomy. For the perception of teaching, 51% gave scores for teaching between 31 and 45 indicating that the teaching activities might need some improvement. For the social support dimension, 85% thought that there were more pros than cons. The average score of PHEEM was 112.7 (SD = 11.2, range 79–134), indicating a rather positive educational environment, but with room for improvement.</p>
 <p id="Par41" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Only 5 (out of 41participants, 12%) reported a good quality of life, while the majority of residents (88%) reported a moderate level of overall work-related quality of life. About 10% of residents reported a low level of employee engagement, poor home-work interface and low general well-being. More than 50% (56%) of residents experienced moderate levels of stress at work and 68% had a negative work-family interface. Also, 54% of the residents were fully satisfied with the work conditions.</p>
</sec>
