<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par18" class="p">To analyze abalone growth and mortality data, we used the Linear mixed-effects model (LMM) and the Generalized linear mixed model (GLMM, binomial family link) with a random error component—i.e., initial size of abalone and Vexar cages nested in steel wire cages respectively—to determine if these random factors had a significant effect on the model assessment of growth and mortality. For growth, we evaluated the mean change in shell length relative to the Year and Location and Depth as fixed factors and as an initial investigation into possible differential response in biological performance. However, our main goal was to determine if changes in temperature and dissolved oxygen (or their interaction) had a differential effect on growth and survivorship. Thus, the individual change in shell length was also used to evaluate growth as a function of temperature and dissolved oxygen exposure (TI and OI) experienced over the total experimental period. For this analysis, both TI and OI were defined as a continuous factor and compared as independent factors and as interactions—i.e., TI × OI. Changes in the shell length were weighted by the number of surviving abalone in each compartment at the end of 8-week deployment. To assess abalone mortality, we evaluated the weekly proportional mortality relative to the sum of the TI and OI experienced up to each weekly census. The weekly proportion of dead versus live abalone were weighted by the total number of remaining abalone in the previous week’s census. Both TI and OI were defined as independent and continuous factors—i.e., TI × OI. We visually assessed all model fits by examining the residuals versus fitted values and did not see any over dispersion (Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S3</xref>). To test the significance of the comparisons in the LME models, we used analysis of variance with the Kenward-Roger approximation for degrees of freedom. To test whether the proportion of non-viable hemocytes sampled from the juvenile abalone exposed to temperature ramps was significantly different from the juvenile abalone exposed to ambient temperature conditions, we used GLMM with the sampling point as a random factor. The non-viable hemocyte data were weighted by the total number of cells counted. Multiple comparisons of mean non-viable hemocytes among treatment groups were evaluated using the Tukey post hoc test. Differences in the proportion of total inactive animals between temperature treatment and ambient groups were assessed, at each sampling point, using Chi-square tests. All analysis was done in RStudio (RStudio Inc., 2016) using the packages “lme4”, “glmm”, ‘lmerTest’, and “MASS”.
</p>
