<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec4dot3-ijerph-16-02999" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.3. Characteristics of Soil N
  <sub>2</sub>O Emissions from LF, PF, and BF
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Soil nitrification and denitrification are two important links in the nitrogen cycle of ecosystems and form an important source of atmospheric N
  <sub>2</sub>O. The monitoring results showed that N
  <sub>2</sub>O fluxes of the three forest types were all sources of emissions. In June (during the growing season), soil N
  <sub>2</sub>O fluxes showed peak emission periods. Thomas et al. [
  <a rid="B51-ijerph-16-02999" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51-ijerph-16-02999">51</a>] also reached a similar conclusion. The main reason may be that the outer surface of the soil particles is covered by an ice layer and the inner layer is wrapped with a tightly bound liquid water film, which forms a better anaerobic environment and remains high active nutrients after the soil completely frozen in winter [
  <a rid="B52-ijerph-16-02999" ref-type="bibr" href="#B52-ijerph-16-02999">52</a>]. The anaerobic environment provides a good place for denitrification to produce N
  <sub>2</sub>O, which is sequestered by the frozen soil [
  <a rid="B53-ijerph-16-02999" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53-ijerph-16-02999">53</a>]. The N
  <sub>2</sub>O enclosed in the soil is burst out into the atmosphere after thawing. In summer, plants grow vigorously and absorb a large amount of nitrogen. Competition between vegetation and microbes causes soil microbes to utilize substrate reduction, and frequent rainfall during the summer causes the shallow soil to alternate between wet and dry conditions, all of which affects the soil N
  <sub>2</sub>O emission rate [
  <a rid="B54-ijerph-16-02999" ref-type="bibr" href="#B54-ijerph-16-02999">54</a>]. Permafrost soils, which are characterized by cold temperatures, have low net N mineralization rates and availability of mineral nitrogen [
  <a rid="B36-ijerph-16-02999" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36-ijerph-16-02999">36</a>]. Consequently, the available nitrogen in the soil (predominantly ammonium nitrogen and nitrate nitrogen) is poor in the forests of northern China [
  <a rid="B55-ijerph-16-02999" ref-type="bibr" href="#B55-ijerph-16-02999">55</a>]. This study found that PF soil N
  <sub>2</sub>O fluxes were higher than LF and BF. The available nitrogen (NH
  <sub>4</sub>
  <span class="sup">+</span>-N and NO
  <sub>3</sub>
  <span class="sup">−</span>-N) contents of different forest types showed that BF was significantly higher than both PF and LF (
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.05), and the NH
  <sub>4</sub>
  <span class="sup">+</span>-N content was significantly higher than the NO
  <sub>3</sub>
  <span class="sup">−</span>-N content (
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0. 05) (
  <a rid="ijerph-16-02999-t001" ref-type="table" href="#ijerph-16-02999-t001">Table 1</a>). Therefore, denitrification may be the main source of soil N
  <sub>2</sub>O fluxes in this region. However, BF soil pH was significantly lower than LF and PF (
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.05) (
  <a rid="ijerph-16-02999-t001" ref-type="table" href="#ijerph-16-02999-t001">Table 1</a>). According to Struwe et al. [
  <a rid="B56-ijerph-16-02999" ref-type="bibr" href="#B56-ijerph-16-02999">56</a>], the optimal pH range for denitrification in soil is between 6 and 8. Soil denitrification is inhibited under acidic conditions and the rate of denitrification decreases with increasing soil acidity. Therefore, the N
  <sub>2</sub>O emission rate of LF was lower than that of PF and BF. Our study found that the temperature sensitivity of N
  <sub>2</sub>O in LF, PF, and BF were 2.23, 1.82, and 1.49, respectively, and LF soil N
  <sub>2</sub>O responded most to temperature rise. However, the difference of N
  <sub>2</sub>O fluxes between the three forest types were not significant, and the forest type was not the main factor affecting soil N
  <sub>2</sub>O fluxes.
 </p>
</sec>
