<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The analysis of leaf gas exchange is an important method to detect the biochemical and stomatal mechanisms of leaves in response to environmental changes. In this study, the change of gas exchange parameters revealed that, although the 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>
 <sub class="sub">n</sub> and 
 <italic class="italic">G</italic>
 <sub class="sub">s</sub> were significantly affected by both the temperature and water availability treatments (
 <italic class="italic">p</italic> &lt; 0.01), no corresponding differences in the 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>
 <sub class="sub">i</sub> were detected (
 <italic class="italic">p</italic> &gt; 0.05). Thus, the S. 
 <italic class="italic">baicalensis</italic> grown at different temperatures and with different levels of water availability had the same intercellular CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> concentration for photosynthesis
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b37" class="xref">37</xref>. Furthermore, the 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>
 <sub class="sub">i</sub>/
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>
 <sub class="sub">a</sub> ratio is a useful and effective index to evaluate the stomatal acclimation, and a change in the index directly reflects any changes in the relationship between the capacity for CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> fixation and the 
 <italic class="italic">G</italic>
 <sub class="sub">s</sub>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b38" class="xref">38</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b39" class="xref">39</xref>. If the stomata acclimated to changes in the environment independently, then the 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>
 <sub class="sub">i</sub>/
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>
 <sub class="sub">a</sub> would change. In our study, the 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>
 <sub class="sub">i</sub>/
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>
 <sub class="sub">a</sub> did not change significantly among the temperature and water treatments (
 <italic class="italic">p</italic> &gt; 0.05). Because the values of 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>
 <sub class="sub">i</sub> and 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>
 <sub class="sub">i</sub>/
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>
 <sub class="sub">a</sub> were unaffected by the different temperature and moisture treatments, the nonstomatal limitation was likely the primary mechanism for the regulation of photosynthesis in S. 
 <italic class="italic">baicalensis</italic>, which was a conclusion that was similar to that of a study on transgenic tobacco
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b40" class="xref">40</xref>.
</p>
