<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">High temperatures inhibit the growth of plants and increase the respiration, which requires the plants to fix more carbon to sustain life. Based on previous reports, a temperature above 35 °C drastically limits photosynthesis by reducing the activity of Rubisco
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b42" class="xref">42</xref>. However, when plants are exposed to a long-term change in temperature, the acclimation of the photosynthetic apparatus possible occurs. By changing the optimum temperature for photosynthesis, photosynthesis can remain highly efficient at the new growth temperature
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27" class="xref">27</xref>. Niu 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b43" class="xref">43</xref>, for the species in a temperate steppe of northern China, found that elevated temperature increased the 
 <italic class="italic">V</italic>
 <sub class="sub">cmax</sub> and the 
 <italic class="italic">J</italic>
 <sub class="sub">max</sub> in the C3-grasses and the carboxylation efficiency (CE) and the CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>-saturated photosynthetic rate (
 <italic class="italic">A</italic>
 <sub class="sub">sat</sub>) in the C4-grass, which indicated that photosynthesis had acclimated to the elevated temperature. However, in our study, the effect of elevated temperature on the photosynthetic capacity was primarily caused by changes in the 
 <italic class="italic">V</italic>
 <sub class="sub">cmax</sub> (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4" class="xref">Fig. 4</xref>), which indicated that the effect of elevated temperature on the photosynthetic capacity of S. 
 <italic class="italic">baicalensis</italic> was primarily caused by the reduction in the activation of Rubisco. This result was different from those that were found by other researchers, which could be explained by different plant species have different abilities to acclimate to a changing temperature. For cool-climate species (e.g., turnips, lamb’s-quarters, barley and broadbean), Bunce
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b44" class="xref">44</xref> found that the 
 <italic class="italic">V</italic>
 <sub class="sub">cmax</sub> and the 
 <italic class="italic">J</italic>
 <sub class="sub">max</sub> were much higher for leaves grown at a cooler temperature than for those grown at a warmer temperature. The S. 
 <italic class="italic">baicalensis</italic> grows in the high latitude regions of northern China and is highly acclimated to cooler temperatures. When the temperature was increased, the high temperature reduced 
 <italic class="italic">V</italic>
 <sub class="sub">cmax</sub> and resulted in the photosynthetic downregulation of S. 
 <italic class="italic">baicalensis</italic>.
</p>
