<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 39.96?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5841656</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0192642</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-17-04038</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Earth Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Atmospheric Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Climatology</subject><subj-group><subject>Climate Change</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Agriculture</subject><subj-group><subject>Crop Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Crops</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Agriculture</subject><subj-group><subject>Agricultural Methods</subject><subj-group><subject>Agricultural Irrigation</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Ecology and Environmental Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Natural Resources</subject><subj-group><subject>Water Resources</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Earth Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Geography</subject><subj-group><subject>Physical Geography</subject><subj-group><subject>Watersheds</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Earth Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Seasons</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Biology and Life Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Agriculture</subject><subj-group><subject>Crop Science</subject><subj-group><subject>Crops</subject><subj-group><subject>Cereal Crops</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v3"><subject>Earth Sciences</subject><subj-group><subject>Hydrology</subject><subj-group><subject>Surface Water</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Impacts of climate change on cropping patterns in a tropical, sub-humid watershed</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Impacts of climate change on cropping patterns</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id authenticated="true" contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1670-3451</contrib-id><name><surname>Duku</surname><given-names>Confidence</given-names></name><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Conceptualization</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Data curation</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Formal analysis</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Investigation</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Methodology</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Validation</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Visualization</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Writing &#x02013; original draft</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor001">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Zwart</surname><given-names>Sander J.</given-names></name><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Conceptualization</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Supervision</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff003"><sup>3</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hein</surname><given-names>Lars</given-names></name><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Conceptualization</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Methodology</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Supervision</role><role content-type="http://credit.casrai.org/">Writing &#x02013; review &#x00026; editing</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff001"><label>1</label>
<addr-line>Environmental Systems Analysis Group, Wageningen University, Wageningen, The Netherlands</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff002"><label>2</label>
<addr-line>Africa Rice Center (AfricaRice), Cotonou, Benin</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff003"><label>3</label>
<addr-line>Faculty of Geo-Information Science and Earth Observation (ITC), University of Twente, Enschede, The Netherlands</addr-line></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Subudhi</surname><given-names>Prasanta K.</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1"><addr-line>Louisiana State University College of Agriculture, UNITED STATES</addr-line></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="COI-statement" id="coi001"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>confidence.duku@wur.nl</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>7</day><month>3</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>13</volume><issue>3</issue><elocation-id>e0192642</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>31</day><month>1</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>26</day><month>1</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2018 Duku et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Duku et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:href="pone.0192642.pdf"/><abstract><p>In recent decades, there have been substantial increases in crop production in sub-Saharan Africa (SSA) as a result of higher yields, increased cropping intensity, expansion of irrigated cropping systems, and rainfed cropland expansion. Yet, to date much of the research focus of the impact of climate change on crop production in the coming decades has been on crop yield responses. In this study, we analyse the impact of climate change on the potential for increasing rainfed cropping intensity through sequential cropping and irrigation expansion in central Benin. Our approach combines hydrological modelling and scenario analysis involving two Representative Concentration Pathways (RCPs), two water-use scenarios for the watershed based on the Shared Socioeconomic Pathways (SSPs), and environmental water requirements leading to sustained streamflow. Our analyses show that in Benin, warmer temperatures will severely limit crop production increases achieved through the expansion of sequential cropping. Depending on the climate change scenario, between 50% and 95% of cultivated areas that can currently support sequential cropping or will need to revert to single cropping. The results also show that the irrigation potential of the watershed will be at least halved by mid-century in all scenario combinations. Given the urgent need to increase crop production to meet the demands of a growing population in SSA, our study outlines challenges and the need for planned development that need to be overcome to improve food security in the coming decades.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This research was conducted at Wageningen University as part of the project &#x0201c;Realizing the agricultural potential of inland valley lowlands in sub-Saharan Africa while maintaining their environmental services&#x0201d; (RAP-IV). The project is implemented by the Africa Rice Center and its national partners and is funded by the European Commission through the International Fund for Agricultural Development (IFAD).</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="8"/><table-count count="4"/><page-count count="21"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>Data are freely available from the following institutional data access for researchers who meet the criteria. 1. IMPETUS Project (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://geonetwork.impetus.uni-koeln.de/srv/en/main.home">http://geonetwork.impetus.uni-koeln.de/srv/en/main.home</ext-link>); 2. AMMA-CATCH (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bd.amma-catch.org/main.jsf">http://bd.amma-catch.org/main.jsf</ext-link>); 3. CCAFS (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gisweb.ciat.cgiar.org/MarkSimGCM/">http://gisweb.ciat.cgiar.org/MarkSimGCM/</ext-link>).</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><title>Data Availability</title><p>Data are freely available from the following institutional data access for researchers who meet the criteria. 1. IMPETUS Project (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://geonetwork.impetus.uni-koeln.de/srv/en/main.home">http://geonetwork.impetus.uni-koeln.de/srv/en/main.home</ext-link>); 2. AMMA-CATCH (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bd.amma-catch.org/main.jsf">http://bd.amma-catch.org/main.jsf</ext-link>); 3. CCAFS (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gisweb.ciat.cgiar.org/MarkSimGCM/">http://gisweb.ciat.cgiar.org/MarkSimGCM/</ext-link>).</p></notes></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001"><title>Introduction</title><p>Increasing crop production in sub-Saharan Africa (SSA) is urgently needed. The population of the region is projected to double by 2050 compared to 2015 [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. About 97% of current cropland area is under rainfed cultivation [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>] and current productivity levels for major food crops, which are the lowest in the world, are inadequate to meet the projected food demand [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. To meet the food demand of a growing population several options for increasing crop production must be harnessed. These include amongst others crop intensification in rainfed systems to produce higher yields and/or increased cropping frequency, expansion of irrigated area and rainfed cropland expansion. Over the past decades, higher yields, increased cropping frequency (i.e. sequential cropping and intercropping) and cropland expansion have accounted for an estimated 38%, 31% and 31% respectively of the recorded increases in crop production in SSA [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>].</p><p>In the coming decades, climate change will affect these various options for increasing crop production. West Africa in particular has been identified as a regional hotspot of climate change with climate departure from historical variability projected to occur faster than the global average [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. Changes in precipitation and temperature will pose serious risks to crop production systems and food security in general [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref007" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>]. Several studies have examined the impact of climate change on crop yields in SSA. For example, in Benin, reduced rainfall and increased rainfall variability is likely to result in yield reductions in maize and yam [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>] and, in Niger, climate change will reduce millet production between 11% to 26% by 2025 [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. A variety of mechanisms drive impacts of climate change on crop yields. For example, in Tanzania, climate change is likely to intensify rice diseases such as bacterial leaf blight leading to greater yield losses [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. Climate change will also affect irrigated agriculture in the Sahel region where, yields of irrigated rice systems are projected to decline by up to 45% by the 2070s [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Across SSA, aggregated mean yields for major food crops are forecasted to decrease by 6% to 24% by the end of this century [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. However, focussing on crop yield responses alone underestimates the impact of climate change on agriculture in SSA. For example, in a key agricultural region in Brazil, analyses of the sensitivities of crop yields, cropping frequency and cropping area to inter-annual climate variability showed that about 70% of the total change in agricultural output in the region could be attributed to changes in cropping frequency and/or cropping area [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. In SSA, to date, information on the likely impacts of climate change on 1) rainfed cropping frequency in cultivated areas; 2) potential arable land; and 3) the irrigation potential are rare.</p><p>In SSA, sequential cropping in rainfed areas has been one of the ways of increasing crop yields (in addition to intercropping) and involves cultivation of two or more crops on the same field after each other or with overlapping growing periods (relay cropping) [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Already, sequential cropping in rainfed systems large parts of SSA is constrained by the length of growing period, high labour intensity, lack of knowledge and lack of market access [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. In the coming decades, detailed information on how climate change will affect sequential cropping in both cultivated areas and in potential arable areas will be vital to reduce agricultural vulnerability to climate change.</p><p>In addition to cropping frequency, increased application of irrigation water is vital to boosting crop production and meeting the food demand of a growing population in SSA [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0192642.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Investments in irrigation are therefore increasing and irrigation water withdrawals in SSA are expected to increase from 96 km<sup>3</sup> (2005 estimate) to 133 km<sup>3</sup> per annum by 2050 [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. However, changes in precipitation and temperature are not only likely to affect water availability for irrigation but also irrigation water requirements of major food crops in SSA. Furthermore, population growth and socioeconomic development are also likely to increase water demand and hence increase competition for water use. Hence, to support agricultural development and planning, there is a need for detailed information on how climate change and socioeconomic development will jointly affect irrigation potential. Yet, despite numerous studies examining the impact of climate change on water resources in general [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], studies specifically examining the impacts on the capacity to support irrigation expansion are rare in SSA.</p><p>Therefore, to provide a better understanding of the varied impacts of climate change on opportunities for increasing crop production, we examine three potential options for increasing crop production in a large sub-humid tropical watershed in central Benin, the Upper Ou&#x000e9;m&#x000e9; watershed. First, we analyse the impact of climate change on the potential for increasing rainfed cropping frequency through sequential cropping in cultivated areas. Second, we analyse the impact of climate change on the suitability of potential arable land areas for rainfed sequential cropping. Finally, we analyse the combined impacts of climate change and socioeconomic development on the potential for irrigation expansion in the watershed taking into account household water demand and riverine environmental flow requirements, which are the two major non-agricultural water uses in the watershed. Our approach combines hydrological modelling and scenario analysis involving two contrasting Representative Concentration Pathways (RCPs), two water-use scenarios for the watershed based on the Shared Socioeconomic Pathways (SSPs), and environmental water requirements leading to sustained water flows in the Upper Ou&#x000e9;m&#x000e9; river network.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec002"><title>Methods</title><sec id="sec003"><title>Study area</title><p>The Upper Ou&#x000e9;m&#x000e9; watershed in central Benin covers an area of approximately 14,500 km<sup>2</sup> with an estimated population of about 510,000 people [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0192642.g001">Fig 1</xref>). It is located in the sub-humid tropical zone and is characterized by a unimodal rainfall season from May to October with about 1250 mm of precipitation per year. In general, Benin is affected by a seasonal alteration of cool and humid monsoon air mass (originating from the Gulf of Guinea), and hot, dry and dusty Saharan air mass [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Rainfall anomalies in Benin and West Africa in general have been associated with the northward or southward position of the Inter-Tropical Convergence Zone and the associated low and upper level jet streams [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. The natural vegetation of the watershed is a mosaic of savannah woodland and small forest islands. Smallholder rainfed agriculture is the major economic activity. Maize, rice, yam, cassava, sorghum and millet are the most important food crops, with cotton being the major cash crop. The cropping intensity of these staple crops is 1.5 [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>], indicating that a substantial portion of land either devoted to these crops or other crops is harvested twice per year. The irrigation sector is poorly developed and the lack of irrigation water during the dry season is a major problem for many farmers [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. Pastoral communities from neighbouring countries such as Nigeria often migrate to this study area, especially for grazing in the dry season when water and food resources are scarce in the less humid zones of the Upper Ou&#x000e9;m&#x000e9; to the north [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>].</p><fig id="pone.0192642.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0192642.g001</object-id><label>Fig 1</label><caption><title>Land cover of the Upper Ou&#x000e9;m&#x000e9; watershed showing current cropland areas.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0192642.g001"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec004"><title>Modelling the hydrological response of the watershed</title><p>To simulate the hydrological response of the watershed under current and future climate conditions, we used a modified Soil and Water Assessment Tool (SWAT), which had been reconfigured with a grid-based landscape discretization [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>] and further enhanced to simulate water flow across the discretized landscape units [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0192642.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. The SWAT model in general is a spatially explicit, physical, ecohydrological model that simulates the impact of land use and land management practices on water, sediments and agricultural chemicals in large complex watersheds with varying soils, land use and management conditions over several years [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0192642.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. The reconfiguration to a grid-based landscape discretization scheme [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0192642.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>] from the standard Hydrological Response Units (HRUs), enhances the spatial detail and accuracy of simulated hydrological processes [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Furthermore, a landscape routing sub-model was incorporated to enhance the spatial interaction between discretized landscape units and allowed for the simulation of surface water, lateral and groundwater flow interactions across these units. Detailed information about the grid-based SWAT landscape model description can be found in Rathjens et al. [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>] and Arnold et al. [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>].</p><p>The grid-based SWAT landscape model used in the present study to simulate hydrological response of the watershed under current climatic and future climatic conditions had been set up, calibrated and validated in Duku et al. [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. The input data used to set up the model are presented in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0192642.t001">Table 1</xref>. The Soil Conservation Service curve number approach was used to model surface runoff and the daily curve number value was calculated as a function of plant evapotranspiration [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] and potential evapotranspiration was modelled with the Hargreaves method [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. The model was calibrated and validated using daily observed streamflow data from 11 monitoring stations within the watershed (See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0192642.s001">S1 File</xref>) [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Calibration was mostly from 2001 to 2007 and validation was from 2008 to 2011. Calibration and validation of the model was carried out using the Sequential Uncertainty Fitting (SUFI-2) optimization algorithm of the SWAT Calibration and Uncertainty Program [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0192642.s001">S1 File</xref> for the calibrated parameter values (Table A), graphical (Figure A) and statistical results (Table B) of model calibration and validation.</p><table-wrap id="pone.0192642.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0192642.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Description of spatial input data of the Upper Ou&#x000e9;m&#x000e9; watershed for the SWAT landscape model.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0192642.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0192642.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Data type</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Description</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Resolution</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Source</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Topography</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASTER Digital Elevation Model (DEM)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30m</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NASA</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Land use/ land cover</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Classified LANDSAT-7 ETM+ image</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28.5m</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IMPETUS [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soil types</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soil map and associated parameters derived from geological maps and field surveys</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:200,000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IMPETUS [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Precipitation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gridded daily precipitation data (1999 to 2012)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25km</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AMMA-CATCH [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Temperature</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gridded monthly average minimum and maximum temperatures (1999 to 2012)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50km</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CRU TS 3.21 [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Household water consumption</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Groundwater and surface water extractions</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">(village level)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IMPETUS [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t001fn001"><p>- NASA is the National Aeronautics and Space Administration of the United States</p></fn><fn id="t001fn002"><p>- IMPETUS is Integrated Approach to Efficient Management of Scarce Water Resources in West Africa</p></fn><fn id="t001fn003"><p>- AMMA-CATCH is the African Monsoon and Multidisciplinary Analysis&#x02013;Coupling the Tropical Atmosphere and the Hydrological Cycle</p></fn><fn id="t001fn004"><p>- CRU TS is the Climate Research Unit Time Series datasets.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec005"><title>Climate change and socioeconomic pathways</title><p>For the present study, simulations involving daily time-steps were undertaken for the period from 2003 to 2012. This represented the current climatic conditions henceforth referred to as the baseline conditions. To simulate the hydrological response of the watershed under future climate scenarios, climate data (precipitation and temperature) projected under two contrasting Representative Concentration Pathways (RCPs) were utilized. RCPs encompass four greenhouse gas concentration trajectories adopted by the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change and supersedes the Special Report on Emissions Scenarios projections [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. For the present study, precipitation and temperature data projected under RCP2.6 and RCP8.5 for different time-periods were used for SWAT simulation (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0192642.t002">Table 2</xref>). The RCP2.6 scenario is an emission pathway that leads to the lowest concentration levels of atmospheric greenhouse gases [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0192642.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. It represents a peak in greenhouse gas emissions by 2050 followed by a consistent decline throughout the rest of this century. It is the pathway needed to realize the targets set during the twenty-first Conference of Parties of the UN Framework Convention on Climate Change, i.e. keep mean global warming to within 2&#x000b0;C above pre-industrial levels. The RCP8.5 scenario, on the other hand, is characterized by increasing greenhouse gas emissions leading to the highest concentration of atmospheric greenhouse gases by the end of this century [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0192642.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>]. It is representative of the business-as-usual scenario, i.e. a continued increase in greenhouse gas emissions.</p><table-wrap id="pone.0192642.t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0192642.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Changes in annual precipitation totals and average temperature in future climate scenarios compared to baseline scenario.</title><p>The average temperature in baseline is 27.4&#x000b0;C.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0192642.t002g" xlink:href="pone.0192642.t002"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scenario and time period</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Watershed-wide average annual precipitation total (mm/yr)</th><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Watershed-wide change in average temperature (&#x000b0;C)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baseline</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1240</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RCP2.6 2040s</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1180</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RCP2.6 2090s</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1160</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.6</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RCP8.5 2040s</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1180</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">RCP8.5 2090s</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1145</td><td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap><p>For simulations under climate-change scenarios, we obtained downscaled monthly precipitation totals, and maximum and minimum temperature data projected under RCP2.6 and RCP8.5; and for two time-periods i.e. 2041&#x02013;2050 (2040s) and 2091&#x02013;2100 (2090s). Daily precipitation and temperature data are the outputs of multi-model ensemble of 17 General Circulation Models (GCMs) (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0192642.s002">S2 File</xref>) and were obtained from the MarkSimGCM geoportal (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gisweb.ciat.cgiar.org/MarkSimGCM/">http://gisweb.ciat.cgiar.org/MarkSimGCM/</ext-link>) [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. The MarkSimGCM geoportal is part of the Consultative Group for International Agricultural Research (CGIAR) research program on Climate Change Agriculture and Food Security (CCAFS). In MarkSimGCM, fifth-order polynomials are fit to climate anomalies between the baseline [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>] and each GCM future climate prediction. Cubic convolutions are then used to interpolate to smaller grids of about 1 km resolution. These intra-GCM differences are then added to the baseline data to provide monthly averaged climate data at each grid cell [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. To produce multi-model ensemble data drawing from all 17 GCMs, the polynomial functions that were fitted to each individual GCM were averaged and not the climate data produced by the GCMs, which would have led to a progressive dilution of the variance as more GCM models were added. A detailed description of the downscaling and bias correction approach can be found in [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>].</p><p>To generate the daily time-series of climate data needed to run the SWAT model, we used the change factor approach [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0192642.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0192642.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. The change factor approach involves the calculation of the relative changes in monthly precipitation and the absolute changes in temperature between the multi-model GCM data and the baseline climate data for each time period (i.e. 2040s and 2090s) under each RCP scenario [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. The change factors were calculated separately for each of the 44 subwatersheds of the Upper Ou&#x000e9;m&#x000e9; watershed (the SWAT model assigns one climate station to each subwatershed based on the nearest neighbour) [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. The calculated changes were used to perturb the baseline climate observations in the calibrated and validated grid-based SWAT landscape model. In simulating watershed hydrology under each RCP scenario, the effect of increased atmospheric carbon dioxide concentration was not taken into account. We discuss the implications of excluding increasing atmospheric carbon dioxide in Section 4.</p><p>In addition to the RCPs, we developed water-use scenarios in line with the qualitative narratives of the Shared Socioeconomic Pathway (SSP) [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0192642.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>] for the calculation of irrigation potentials (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0192642.g002">Fig 2</xref>). The SSPs are a set of alternative reference assumptions about future socioeconomic development in the absence of climate policies. The SSP1 scenario depicts a development pathway characterised by rapid economic development especially in low-income countries leading to rapid technological development, increased resource use efficiency and low population growth whereas SSP3 represents a scenario with slow economic growth, slow technological development, low resource use efficiency and rapid population growth. In this study, each SSP was characterized by three variables; population growth, irrigation efficiency, and per capita domestic water use (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0192642.t003">Table 3</xref>). Estimates of population projections in the watershed under each SSP for different time-periods were computed from Jones et al. [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. Data on irrigation efficiency was obtained from Hanasaki et al. [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>] and had been derived from the qualitative narrative of each SSP. Finally, we derived estimates of per capita domestic water use in our study area based on the qualitative narratives of each SSP and data from FAO [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>].</p><fig id="pone.0192642.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0192642.g002</object-id><label>Fig 2</label><caption><title>Schematic diagram of the modelling aproach.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0192642.g002"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone.0192642.t003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0192642.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Characterization of water-use scenarios in line with the qualitative storylines of the Shared Socioeconomic Pathways (SSPs).</title><p>Current population in the watershed is about 510,000 [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Values of irrigation efficiency are based on [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>].</p></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0192642.t003g" xlink:href="pone.0192642.t003"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Baseline water-use</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">2040s</th><th align="center" colspan="2" rowspan="1">2090s</th></tr><tr><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SSP1</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SSP3</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SSP1</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SSP3</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Irrigation efficiency</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn002">*</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.52</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Population growth (%)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn001"><sup><bold>a</bold></sup></xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">101</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">156</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">114</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">285</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Per capita domestic water use (L day<sup>-1</sup>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t003fn003">**</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t003fn001"><p><bold>a</bold> Percentage increase in population with 2010 as the base year. For the 2040s and 2090s decades, the projected population of the years 2050 and 2100 respectively were used.</p></fn><fn id="t003fn002"><p>* indicates values of irrigation efficiency under baseline conditions obtained from [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>].</p></fn><fn id="t003fn003"><p>** indicates per capita domestic water use under baseline conditions obtained from [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0192642.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. Per capita domestic water use was derived from [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>] and the qualitative storyline of each SSP scenario.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec006"><title>Modelling meteorological drought</title><p>We characterised meteorological drought conditions under each RCP scenario using the Standardized Precipitation Evapotranspiration Index (SPEI) [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. The SPEI methodology estimates the severity and frequency of meteorological drought by accounting for changes in evapotranspiration demand caused by changes in temperature in addition to precipitation. It is based on a probability distribution fitted to a time-series of the difference between monthly precipitation and potential evapotranspiration (i.e. climatic water balance) aggregated over different time-scales using a moving window (e.g. 3-month, 6-month etc.). This probability distribution is transformed to the cumulative distribution function of the standard normal distribution (with a mean of 0 and standard deviation of 1). In this study, the regional (i.e. average over the entire watershed) monthly precipitation and potential evapotranspiration time-series were used. Potential evapotranspiration was computed using the Hargreaves method [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>]. The sequences of climatic water balance in the baseline and for the 2040s and 2090s in each RCP scenario were used to compute the 6-month (seasonal drought) and 12-month (annual drought) SPEIs.</p></sec><sec id="sec007"><title>Modelling length of growing period</title><p>The length of growing period (LGP) indicates the potential for rainfed crop production. We modelled the LGP as the number of days in a year in which moisture supply (i.e. the sum of daily precipitation and plant available soil water content) was equal to or exceeded potential evapotranspiration and temperature was above 5&#x000b0;C (e.g. [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]). The basic concept according to the heat unit theory [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0192642.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>] is that plant growth and development will only occur if the temperature exceeds some minimum threshold. For our study area, which is located in tropical lowlands, the year round minimum daily temperature always exceeds 5&#x000b0;C. Hence, the limiting factor in the computation of LGP was moisture supply. The SWAT model was used to simulate daily soil moisture content for the computation of LGP. The computed LGPs were then used together with the criteria in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0192642.t004">Table 4</xref>, to delineate single, relay and double cropping zones under each climate change scenario. The criteria in <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0192642.t002">Table 2</xref> is based on the Agro-Ecological Zone methodology [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. Sequential cropping zones delineated in this study do not involve the cultivation of wetland rice, which covers less than 1% of the study area.</p><table-wrap id="pone.0192642.t004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0192642.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Criteria for delineation of potential rainfed sequential cropping zones under rainfed conditions [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>].</title><p>Sequential cropping zones are disaggregated into relay and double cropping zones.</p></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0192642.t004g" xlink:href="pone.0192642.t004"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cropping zones</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Length of growing period (days)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Accumulated temperature above 5&#x000b0;C over the growing period</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Accumulated temperature above 10&#x000b0;C over the growing period</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Single cropping</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265; 120</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Relay cropping<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn001"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265; 200</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265; 3200</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265; 2700</td></tr><tr><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Double cropping<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="t004fn001"><sup>a</sup></xref></td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265; 240</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265; 4000</td><td align="justify" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02265; 3200</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t004fn001"><p>a In double cropping zones, there can be cultivation of two or more crops on the same field after each other whereas in relay cropping zones this involves overlapping growing periods between the two crops</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec008"><title>Modelling streamflow drought</title><p>Streamflow droughts affect the availability of water for irrigation and other consumptive purposes. We used two approaches to compute streamflow droughts; the Standardised Streamflow Index (SSI) [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0192642.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>] and Severity-Duration-Frequency curves (SDF) [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. The SSI approach is similar to the SPEI methodology, however, in this case a non-parametric probability distribution was fitted to the time-series of monthly streamflow totals simulated at the watershed outlet [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0192642.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. Unlike the SSI approach, the SDF approach involved daily streamflow simulated at the watershed outlet and streamflow droughts occurred when streamflow was below a specified threshold for at least a specific period of time (e.g. [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0192642.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]). We used the environmental water requirements of the river as the threshold level. The environmental water requirement is critical for sustaining the natural functioning of riverine ecosystems during periods of high flow in the wet season and low flow in the dry season. We defined the environmental water requirements separately for each month as the streamflow value with a 75% exceedance frequency (Q75) [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>]. We estimated these threshold levels based on flow duration curves under baseline climatic conditions. For example, the Q75 value of the month of August was 138 m<sup>3</sup>s<sup>-1</sup> whereas the value in November was 22 m<sup>3</sup>s<sup>-1</sup>. See <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0192642.s003">S3 File</xref> for a detailed description of the SDF approach.</p></sec><sec id="sec009"><title>Modelling irrigation potential</title><p>We estimated the irrigation potential from a water resources perspective i.e. assuming surface water availability was the major limiting factor [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. We created a matrix of RCPs and SSPs, where each RCP was characterized by 1) the simulated total streamflow in excess of the Q75 threshold level and 2) potential evapotranspiration (crop water demand); and each SSP was characterized by 1) irrigation efficiency, 2) population growth and 3) per capita domestic water use (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0192642.t003">Table 3</xref>). Irrigation potential (in hectares) was computed as the quotient between total volume of streamflow available and irrigation water requirement [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. The volume of streamflow available for irrigation was computed using <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0192642.e001">Eq 1</xref>. The total irrigation water requirement was computed as the quotient between crop water demand (using rice as a proxy crop) and irrigation efficiency. We used rice as a proxy crop for crop water demand because rice is the most commonly irrigated crop in Benin. Furthermore, land-use data with the required level of detail to distinguish between different crops in croplands are currently unavailable. Obtaining such information is complicated by the small plot sizes and cropping patterns varying from year to year. We discuss the implication of the use of rice as a proxy crop for water demand in Sect. 4,.
<disp-formula id="pone.0192642.e001"><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="pone.0192642.e001.jpg" id="pone.0192642.e001g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" orientation="portrait"/><mml:math id="M1"><mml:mrow><mml:mi>W</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo stretchy="false">[</mml:mo><mml:mstyle displaystyle="false"><mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02211;</mml:mo><mml:mi>i</mml:mi></mml:msub></mml:mstyle><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mi>V</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:msub><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mi>Q</mml:mi><mml:mn>75</mml:mn></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="false">]</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mo>(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi>D</mml:mi><mml:mo>&#x000d7;</mml:mo><mml:mi>P</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo>)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:mrow></mml:math></alternatives><label>(1)</label></disp-formula>
where W is total annual volume of streamflow available for irrigation (m<sup>3</sup> yr<sup>-1</sup>); V<sub>t</sub> is total monthly volume of streamflow at month i (m<sup>3</sup>); Q75 is environmental flow requirement of month i (m<sup>3</sup>); D is per capita domestic use (m<sup>3</sup> person<sup>-1</sup> yr<sup>-1</sup>); P is total watershed population.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec010"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec011"><title>Present and projected patterns of meteorological drought</title><p>SPEI values are the number of standard deviations by which the anomaly in climatic water balance deviates from the long-term mean. Our SPEI analyses clearly show a substantial shift from relatively wetter climatic conditions under the baseline to increasingly drier climatic conditions under both RCP2.6 and RCP8.5 scenarios (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0192642.g003">Fig 3</xref>). Not only will the probability of occurrence of seasonal drought (6-month SPEI) increase under both RCP2.6 and RCP8.5 but annual droughts (12-month SPEI) will increase as well.</p><fig id="pone.0192642.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0192642.g003</object-id><label>Fig 3</label><caption><title>Probability density plots of 6-month and 12-month Standardized Precipitation Evapotranspiration Index (SPEI) derived under baseline climate conditions (2003&#x02013;2012) and under two future climate scenarios.</title><p>SPEI values &#x0003c; 0 represent meteorological drought and the greater the absolute value, the higher the severity. SPEI values &#x0003e; 0 represent wetter than normal conditions.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0192642.g003"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec012"><title>Impact of climate change on rainfed production potential</title><p>Our analyses show that a watershed-wide average of between 15 and 30 growing days will be lost depending on the climate change scenario. Despite the loss of growing days, cultivated and uncultivated areas that currently are used for single cropping or can support it will still be suitable depending on the type of crop cultivated. However, substantial areas of hitherto rainfed sequential areas will only be suitable for single cropping (Figs <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0192642.g004">4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0192642.g005">5</xref>). Depending on the climate change scenario, between 50% (30,000 ha) and 95% (57,000 ha) of cultivated areas that are currently used for rainfed sequential cropping or can support it will only be suitable for single cropping (Figs <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0192642.g004">4</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0192642.g005">5</xref>). In currently uncultivated areas, between 10% and 60% of the areas where rainfed sequential cropping is currently feasible will only be suitable for single cropping. Currently over 90% of areas that can support sequential cropping in the watershed, i.e. over 570,000 ha, are not under cultivation and lie mainly in the forested south-western part of the watershed (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0192642.g004">Fig 4</xref>). In the coming decades and especially under RCP2.6, a large part of these areas will still be able to support sequential cropping albeit with either a loss or shortening of the fallow period (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0192642.g005">Fig 5</xref>). Adequate soil and nutrient management will then be required to increase productivity.</p><fig id="pone.0192642.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0192642.g004</object-id><label>Fig 4</label><caption><title>The cropping zones in the watershed under baseline climatic conditions and RCP scenarios.</title><p>Sequential cropping zones have been disaggregated into full double cropping and relay cropping zones. These zones indicate the areas where water availability is sufficient to permit different cropping systems.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0192642.g004"/></fig><fig id="pone.0192642.g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0192642.g005</object-id><label>Fig 5</label><caption><title>Proportion of cultivated and potential arable areas suitable for sequential and single cropping under different RCP scenarios in the watershed.</title><p>The total cultivated areas in the watershed are 150,000 ha and the potential arable land area is about 1.3 million ha.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0192642.g005"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec013"><title>Impact of climate change on streamflow drought</title><p>Our SDF and SSI analyses show that climate change will increase the severity, duration and frequency of streamflow droughts (Figs <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0192642.g006">6</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0192642.g007">7</xref>). For example, a streamflow drought event with 120 days duration and a total deficit volume of about 50 million m<sup>3</sup> water in the watershed is estimated to occur once every 50 years (return period) under baseline climatic conditions. However, in the 2040s, these return periods are projected to be 18 years and 13 years under the RCP 2.6 and RCP 8.5 scenarios respectively (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0192642.g006">Fig 6</xref>). Increasing severity, duration and frequency of streamflow drought affects the availability of water for household consumption, riverine ecosystem requirements and irrigation. In addition to population growth, streamflow droughts will increase competition for water resources (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0192642.g008">Fig 8</xref>). In this study, because we prioritized household water demand and riverine ecosystem requirements over irrigation, streamflow droughts substantially reduce the irrigation potential of the watershed.</p><fig id="pone.0192642.g006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0192642.g006</object-id><label>Fig 6</label><caption><title>Contour plots showing severity-duration-frequency relationships of streamflow droughts in the Upper Ou&#x000e9;m&#x000e9; watershed under baseline climatic conditions (2003&#x02013;2012) and two RCP scenarios.</title><p>Contour plots were derived using daily streamflow simulated at the watershed outlet.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0192642.g006"/></fig><fig id="pone.0192642.g007" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0192642.g007</object-id><label>Fig 7</label><caption><title>Probability density plots of 6-month and 12-month Standardized Streamflow Index (SSI) derived under baseline climatic conditions and under RCP scenarios.</title><p>SSI values &#x0003c; 0 represent streamflow drought and the greater the absolute value, the higher the severity. SSI values &#x0003e; 0 represent higher streamflow.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0192642.g007"/></fig><fig id="pone.0192642.g008" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0192642.g008</object-id><label>Fig 8</label><caption><title>Irrigation potential (ha) in the Upper Ou&#x000e9;m&#x000e9; watershed under current and future climate and water-use scenarios.</title><p>Superscript <sup>a</sup> indicates that irrigation potential estimates represent the 2040s under the SSPs and baseline climate. For 2090s, irrigation potential under baseline climate and SSP1 was 36,100 ha whereas it was 26,900 ha under baseline climate and SSP3.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0192642.g008"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec014"><title>Impact of climate change and socioeconomic development on irrigation potential</title><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0192642.g008">Fig 8</xref> shows the irrigation potential of the watershed under different combinations of climate change based on RCPs and socioeconomic development based on SSPs. It shows that the irrigation potential is likely to be at least halved under all combinations of future climatic conditions based on RCPs and socioeconomic development based on SSPs. This can be mainly attributed to reduced precipitation and increased temperature resulting in reduced water availability for irrigation and increased irrigation water requirements. Even though increased irrigation efficiency under SSP1 compared to current conditions may reduce the irrigation intensity, this reduction cannot completely offset the effects of climate change and to a lesser extent population growth.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec015"><title>Discussion</title><p>In this study, we used multi-model ensemble climate data projected by 17 GCMs for simulation. In using multi-model ensemble data, extreme climatic values projected by individual GCMs are smoothed. To maintain the climate extremes, climate data from individual GCMs with divergent climatic trajectories can be used. However, in West Africa, where these projections are highly uncertain especially for precipitation, and there is a large spread across various GCMs [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0192642.ref068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>], using climate data projected by individual GCMs may not address the structural uncertainties and independent simulation errors in these models. In these situations, multi-model ensemble data are highly recommended and have been widely used [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. The multi-model ensemble approach have been reported to outperform individual ensemble members in hindcasting studies and thus provide an improved &#x02018;best estimate&#x02019; forecast [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>]. Lambert et al. [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>] showed that simulations of multi-model ensemble data of precipitation, temperature, and pressure of current climate are generally closer to observed distributions, as measured by mean squared differences, correlations, and variance ratios, than the results of any particular model. Yira et al. [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>] show that as a result of the high uncertainties in precipitation projections in West Africa, a larger ensemble of climate projections is required to estimate the impacts of climate change on water resources accurately. Giorig et al. [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref072" ref-type="bibr">72</xref>] suggest that as a result of these uncertainties, a minimum of four to five multi-model ensemble is needed to obtain robust regional precipitation change estimates.</p><p>We also used the scenario matrix approach [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>] to analyse the impacts of climate change based on RCPs and socioeconomic development based on SSPs on the irrigation potential of the watershed. It has been pointed out that the radiative forcing projected under some RCPs may be inconsistent with the socioeconomic assumptions described in some SSPs i.e. certain SSPs may not produce the level of greenhouse gas emissions needed to achieve the level of radiative forcing in certain RCPs. However, such inconsistencies occur only at the global scale of analysis. At the local and regional scales, all possible combinations of RCPs and SSPs may be possible. Because 1) the global-average level of radiative forcing described in each RCP may differ from those at the local and regional scales due to a number of factors, including land-use change and air pollutant concentrations [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>]; 2) SSPs are developed as hypothetical cases without new climate policy interventions (mitigation and adaptation) and without being influenced by future climate change [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0192642.ref073" ref-type="bibr">73</xref>].</p><p>In our analysis, we used the same land-cover and soil parameters for simulation of the watershed hydrology under both current and future climatic conditions. This is one of the main sources of uncertainty in our study. Land-cover dynamics affect actual evapotranspiration and together with soil properties influence the partitioning of rainfall into overland flow and soil infiltration. Incorporating plausible land-use changes could impact on our analyses in a variety of ways and the net effect on streamflow depends on the types and extent of land-use changes. For example, conversion of forests and woodlands for crop cultivation reduces dry season streamflow and consequently water available for irrigation [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. Nevertheless, by maintaining these watershed characteristics constant, we were able to isolate the impacts of climate change on watershed hydrology from the impacts of plausible land-use changes. We excluded the effects of elevated atmospheric carbon dioxide under future climatic conditions in our analysis, which is another source of uncertainty. The effect of changes in atmospheric carbon dioxide on watershed hydrology is incorporated in the SWAT model through a modification of the Penman-Monteith equation for computing potential evapotranspiration [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. In this study, however, we used the Hargreaves equation [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] to compute potential evapotranspiration because of inadequate data to apply the Penman-Monteith equation. Elevated atmospheric carbon dioxide has countervailing effects on the transpiration rate of vegetation cover. On one hand, it reduces transpiration rate by reducing leaf stomatal conductance [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0192642.ref074" ref-type="bibr">74</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0192642.ref075" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>]. On the other hand, it increases transpiration rate by stimulating plant growth [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0192642.ref075" ref-type="bibr">75</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0192642.ref076" ref-type="bibr">76</xref>]. Their net effect on the magnitude and seasonality of the components of the hydrological cycle depends on local weather conditions and vegetation characteristics. For example, in forested watersheds of the northern Coastal Ranges and Sierra Nevada mountain range in California, research has shown that elevated carbon dioxide concentrations reduced evapotranspiration by around 3% and consequently increased streamflow [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>]. More research, however, is needed on the net effect in the sub-humid tropics of West Africa dominated by woodland savannah.</p><p>In this study, we computed irrigation potential from a water resources perspective, i.e. assuming water availability was the only limiting factor for irrigation and all other socioeconomic, biophysical and technological factors were non-limiting. The irrigation potential reported in this study, therefore, is the maximum irrigable land area because, in practice, other physical and socioeconomic factors will be constraining. Our approach reflects the fact that renewable water resources that are adequate for irrigating a given amount of land today may not be so in the future as a result of climate change. Moreover, unlike water availability, many other limitations may be overcome in the future depending on the socioeconomic development pathway. Hence, analysing the impact of climate change on maximum irrigable land area from a water resources perspective is instructive and important for long-term irrigation development planning. Our irrigation potential estimates were computed using rice as a proxy crop for crop water demand. Rice is currently the only staple crop grown on irrigated fields in the watershed. Compared to other crops, rice has a relatively high water demand especially if measured on a per hectare basis (as opposed to a per kg of produce basis). Hence for other crops, our approach underestimates the irrigation potential. Our model can be adapted in a relatively simple way to assess the amount of other crops that can be irrigated.</p><p>In rainfed production systems that are characteristic of the watershed and SSA in general, crop growth and yield are closely related to the LGP. Across SSA, inadequate LGP is one of the major constraints to establishing rainfed sequential cropping systems. In this study, we have demonstrated that increasing drought risk due to climate change will considerably reduce the LGP across the study area. Due to the reduction in LGP, substantial areas in both cultivated and uncultivated areas hitherto suitable for rainfed sequential cropping will revert to single cropping. Cultivated and uncultivated areas that can currently support single cropping will still be suitable in the coming decades. However, the number of crops that can be cultivated (especially long-cycle crops such as cassava and yam) will be limited as a result of the shortening of the LGP. Our analyses show that currently about 60,000ha (40%) of cultivated areas in the study area are suitable for sequential cropping (including relay cropping). It is difficult to ascertain if all of these areas are actually used for sequential cropping due to inadequate data. However, the average cropping intensity of staple crops such as maize, yam, cassava and sorghum in the study area is 1.5, i.e. the harvested area is one and a half times greater than the physical area devoted to the cultivation of each crop [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>]. This can be attributed to both sequential cropping and intercropping. If all 60,000ha of suitable sequential cropping areas in cultivated areas are currently used for sequential cropping, then in the coming decades, farmers will have to shift to either single cropping systems or adopt crop cultivars with shorter growing periods. To a degree, the impact on crop production may be mitigated by agronomy including breeding of drought resistant varieties. If, however, a substantial portion is only used for single cropping, then climate change will severely limit such opportunities for increasing crop production. In both situations, substantial reductions in sequential cropping areas may result in relatively greater rainfed cropland expansion to make up for lost opportunities to increase crop production.</p><p>Over 90% of the total suitable sequential cropping area is currently not under cultivation and lies in the forested south-western part of the watershed. In these areas, the higher soil water-holding capacity allows for relatively longer LGPs and the impact of climate change is relatively less. However, most of these potentially suitable sequential cropping areas are presently either forested or are woodland savannahs. The forested areas are essential for biodiversity conservation, wood resources, water flow regulation, carbon sequestration etc. and the woodland savannah areas provide grazing opportunities for livestock. Particularly during the dry season, pastoral communities from other parts of Benin and neighbouring countries, such as Nigeria, often migrate here for grazing [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref030" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. Nevertheless, it is likely that forested and woodland savannah areas will be increasingly under pressure from land use change in the coming decades. Among others, this may cause tensions between pastoralists traditionally using the areas for grazing and new settlers. Land use changes in the Upper Ou&#x000e9;m&#x000e9; watershed are also likely to affect population growth and per capita water use. These feedbacks are, however, not included in the present study and it would be very challenging to do so in the scope of one paper.</p><p>In Benin, the total actual land area equipped for irrigation is only 23,000ha [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref077" ref-type="bibr">77</xref>]. In our study area, irrigation is almost non-existent. The lack of irrigation water during the dry season has been a major problem for many farmers [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0192642.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>]. To sufficiently increase crop production in the coming decades, irrigation will have to play a crucial role and is a pathway that has been proposed for other parts of SSA [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0192642.ref078" ref-type="bibr">78</xref>]. Under current climatic conditions, there is considerable potential for irrigation expansion. A maximum land area of 27,000ha can be irrigated even after household water demands and environmental water requirements have been implemented. However, our study has shown that future opportunities for irrigation expansion will be heavily constrained by increased severity, frequency and duration of streamflow droughts. Streamflow droughts coupled with increased household water-use due to population growth and socioeconomic development will result in increased competition for surface-water resources. Where household and environmental water requirements are prioritized over irrigation as in this study, streamflow droughts will substantially reduce the irrigation potential of the watershed. Potential cropland expansion into currently forested areas will also affect seasonal distribution of streamflow further reducing irrigation opportunities especially in the critical dry season [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. Deforestation tends to increase peak flow in the wet season and reduce baseflow in the dry season.</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec016"><title>Conclusion</title><p>In this study, we have shown that, in addition to crop yield responses, climate change will affect other options that have been used to increase crop production in recent decades in SSA i.e. rainfed sequential cropping, rainfed cropland expansion and irrigation expansion. Currently, about 41% of cultivated areas in the Upper Ou&#x000e9;m&#x000e9; watershed are either used for rainfed sequential cropping or can support it. However, by 2050 this will decrease to between 2% and 16% depending on the climate change scenario. Farmers will therefore have to shift to single cropping systems or adopt improved agronomic practices including drought-resistant and short-cycle cultivars. Farmers may also be driven to expand to hitherto uncultivated areas to make up for lost opportunities to increase crop production. In the Upper Ou&#x000e9;m&#x000e9; watershed, over 90% of the land area that can support rainfed cropping is not currently under cultivation and largely consists of forest and woodland savannah. This situation is unlike other parts of Benin where the availability of currently uncultivated land is much lower. A large part of these potential arable lands will still be able to support rainfed sequential cropping in the coming decades despite the loss of between 15 and 30 growing days due to their relatively higher soil moisture storage. If these areas are to be used for rainfed sequential cropping, then fallow periods will have to be shortened or lost completely and improved soil and nutrient management will be needed to increase productivity. However, in a previous paper, Duku et al. [<xref rid="pone.0192642.ref067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>], we showed that the conversion of forested and woodland savannah areas to cropland will have negative feedbacks on water availability for irrigation. In the present study, we have shown that even if there is no change in forest cover, at least 50% of irrigation potential will be lost in the coming decades due to climate change. Forest and woodland areas, therefore, will be needed to regulate water flows and increase dry season streamflow in addition to the provision of other ecosystem services. Our paper shows the importance of using an integrated approach to rural development planning, where climate change can be expected to have multiple, major implications on cropping systems and resilience for climate change depends upon maintaining overall landscape integrity including areas that regulate water flows.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec017"><title>Supporting information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0192642.s001"><label>S1 File</label><caption><p>Supporting information document contains Table B (Calibrated parameter values of the SWAT landscape model); and Table B and Figure A (SWAT calibration and validation results).</p><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0192642.s001.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0192642.s002"><label>S2 File</label><caption><p>Supporting information document contains Table A listing the general circulation models used in the study.</p><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0192642.s002.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0192642.s003"><label>S3 File</label><caption><p>Supporting information document contains severity-duration-frequency methodology for modelling streamflow droughts and Table D which shows the goodness of fit of marginal distributions.</p><p>(DOCX)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0192642.s003.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>This research was conducted at Wageningen University as part of the project &#x0201c;Realizing the agricultural potential of inland valley lowlands in sub-Saharan Africa while maintaining their environmental services&#x0201d; (RAP-IV). The project is implemented by the Africa Rice Center and its national partners and is funded by the European Commission through the International Fund for Agricultural Development (IFAD). We thank Rik Leemans for his invaluable comments on an earlier version of this manuscript.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0192642.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>UN</collab>. <chapter-title>World Population Prospects: The 2015 Revision, Key Findings and Advance Tables</chapter-title>
<publisher-loc>New York, USA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Department of Economic and Social Affairs, Population Division, United Nations</publisher-name>, <year>2015</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>You</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ringler</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wood-Sichra</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>What is the irrigation potential for Africa? A combined biophysical and socioeconomic approach</article-title>. <source>Food Policy</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>36</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>770</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>82</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.foodpol.2011.09.001">10.1016/j.foodpol.2011.09.001</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Alexandratos</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bruinsma</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>World agriculture towards 2030/2050: the 2012 revision</chapter-title>
<publisher-loc>Rome, Italy</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>FAO</publisher-name>, <year>2012</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Diffenbaugh</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Giorgi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>. <article-title>Climate change hotspots in the CMIP5 global climate model ensemble</article-title>. <source>Clim Change</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>114</volume>(<issue>3&#x02013;4</issue>):<fpage>813</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>22</lpage>. Epub 2012/01/10. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10584-012-0570-x">10.1007/s10584-012-0570-x</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMCPMC3765072.<?supplied-pmid 24014154?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24014154</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>IPCC</collab>. <chapter-title>Climate Change 2013: The Physical Science Basis. Contribution of Working Group I to the Fifth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change</chapter-title> In: <name><surname>Stocker</surname><given-names>TF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Qin</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Plattner</surname><given-names>G-K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tignor</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Boschung</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>, editors. <publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK and New York, NY, USA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>; <year>2013</year> p. <fpage>1535</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mora</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Frazier</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Longman</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dacks</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Walton</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tong</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>The projected timing of climate departure from recent variability</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>502</volume>(<issue>7470</issue>):<fpage>183</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>. Epub 2013/10/11. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nature12540">10.1038/nature12540</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 24108050?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24108050</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>von Braun</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Climate change impacts on global food security</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>341</volume>(<issue>6145</issue>):<fpage>508</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>13</lpage>. Epub 2013/08/03. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1126/science.1239402">10.1126/science.1239402</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 23908229?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23908229</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Niang</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ruppel</surname><given-names>OC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Abdrabo</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Essel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lennard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Padgham</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<chapter-title>Africa</chapter-title> In: <name><surname>Barros</surname><given-names>VR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>CB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dokken</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mastrandrea</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mach</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bilir</surname><given-names>TE</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>, editors. <source>Climate Change 2014: Impacts, Adaptation, and Vulnerability Part B</source>: <publisher-name>Regional Aspects Contribution of Working Group II to the Fifth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK and New York, NY, USA</publisher-loc><year>2014</year> p. <fpage>1199</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>265</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gornall</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Betts</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Camp</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Willett</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Implications of climate change for agricultural productivity in the early twenty-first century</article-title>. <source>Philosophical transactions of the Royal Society of London Series B, Biological sciences</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>365</volume>(<issue>1554</issue>):<fpage>2973</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>89</lpage>. Epub 2010/08/18. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1098/rstb.2010.0158">10.1098/rstb.2010.0158</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC2935125.<?supplied-pmid 20713397?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20713397</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Roudier</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sultan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Quirion</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>The impact of future climate change on West African crop yields: What does the recent literature say?</article-title>
<source>Global Environmental Change</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>1073</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>83</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gloenvcha.2011.04.007">10.1016/j.gloenvcha.2011.04.007</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sonneveld</surname><given-names>BGJS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Keyzer</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Adegbola</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pande</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>The Impact of Climate Change on Crop Production in West Africa: An Assessment for the Oueme River Basin in Benin</article-title>. <source>Water Resources Management</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>26</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>553</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>79</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11269-011-9931-x">10.1007/s11269-011-9931-x</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ben Mohamed</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>van Duivenbooden</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Abdoussallam</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Impact of Climate Change on Agricultural Production in the Sahel&#x02013;Part 1. Methodological Approach and Case Study for Millet in Niger</article-title>. <source>Climatic Change</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>54</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>327</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>48</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1023/a:1016189605188">10.1023/a:1016189605188</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Duku</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sparks</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zwart</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Spatial modelling of rice yield losses in Tanzania due to bacterial leaf blight and leaf blast in a changing climate</article-title>. <source>Climatic Change</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>135</volume>(<issue>3&#x02013;4</issue>):<fpage>569</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>83</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10584-015-1580-2">10.1007/s10584-015-1580-2</ext-link>.</comment> WOS:000375466700015.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Van Oort</surname><given-names>PAJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zwart</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Impacts of climate change on rice production in Africa and causes of simulated yield changes</article-title>. <source>Global Change Biol</source>. <year>2017</year>;Accepted.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Waha</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Muller</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bondeau</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dietrich</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kurukulasuriya</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Heinke</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Adaptation to climate change through the choice of cropping system and sowing date in sub-Saharan Africa</article-title>. <source>Global Environmental Change-Human and Policy Dimensions</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>130</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>43</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gloenvcha.2012.11.001">10.1016/j.gloenvcha.2012.11.001</ext-link>.</comment> WOS:000315617200013.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cohn</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>VanWey</surname><given-names>LK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Spera</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mustard</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name>. <article-title>Cropping frequency and area response to climate variability can exceed yield response</article-title>. <source>Nature Climate Change</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>6</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>601</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/Nclimate2934">10.1038/Nclimate2934</ext-link>.</comment> WOS:000376500600015.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Francis</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Multiple cropping systems</chapter-title> No. 631.58 M961. <publisher-loc>New York, USA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Macmillan</publisher-name>; <year>1986</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Burney</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Woltering</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Naylor</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pasternak</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>. <article-title>Solar-powered drip irrigation enhances food security in the Sudano-Sahel</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>107</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1848</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>53</lpage>. Epub 2010/01/19. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.0909678107">10.1073/pnas.0909678107</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMCPMC2806882.<?supplied-pmid 20080616?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20080616</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>FAO</collab>. <chapter-title>Water and the rural poor: Interventions for improving livelihoods in sub-Saharan Africa</chapter-title>
<publisher-loc>Rome, Italy</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Food and Agriculture Organization</publisher-name>, <year>2008</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Nkhata</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Does irrigation have an impact on food security and poverty: Evidence from Bwanje Valley Irrigation Scheme in Malawi</chapter-title>
<publisher-loc>Washington D.C., U.S.A</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>International Food Policy Research Institute (IFPRI)</publisher-name>, <year>2014</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Karambiri</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Galiano</surname><given-names>SGG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Giraldo</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yacouba</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ibrahim</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Barbier</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Assessing the impact of climate variability and climate change on runoff in West Africa: the case of Senegal and Nakambe River basins</article-title>. <source>Atmospheric Science Letters</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>1</issue>):<fpage>109</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>15</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1002/asl.317">10.1002/asl.317</ext-link>.</comment> WOS:000287816700018.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hollermann</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Giertz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Diekkruger</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>. <article-title>Benin 2025-Balancing Future Water Availability and Demand Using the WEAP 'Water Evaluation and Planning' System</article-title>. <source>Water Resources Management</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>24</volume>(<issue>13</issue>):<fpage>3591</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>613</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s11269-010-9622-z">10.1007/s11269-010-9622-z</ext-link>.</comment> WOS:000281742000015.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Faramarzi</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Abbaspour</surname><given-names>KC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vaghefi</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Farzaneh</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zehnder</surname><given-names>AJB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Srinivasan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Modeling impacts of climate change on freshwater availability in Africa</article-title>. <source>J Hydrol</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>480</volume>:<fpage>85</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>101</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhydrol.2012.12.016">10.1016/j.jhydrol.2012.12.016</ext-link>.</comment> WOS:000315008300008.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mahe</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lienou</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Descroix</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bamba</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Paturel</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Laraque</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>The rivers of Africa: witness of climate change and human impact on the environment</article-title>. <source>Hydrological Processes</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>27</volume>(<issue>15</issue>):<fpage>2105</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1002/hyp.9813">10.1002/hyp.9813</ext-link>.</comment> WOS:000325218100002.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>World Bank</collab>. <chapter-title>Turn Down the Heat: Climate Extremes, Regional Impacts, and the Case for Resilience. A report for the World Bank by the Potsdam Institute for Climate Impact Research and Climate Analytics</chapter-title>
<publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>: <collab>World Bank</collab>, <year>2013</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Bright</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Coleman</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Urban</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>LandScan 2010. digital raster data</chapter-title>
<publisher-loc>Oak Ridge, TN</publisher-loc>: <collab>Oak Ridge National Laboratory</collab>; <year>2011</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Fink</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Atmosphere</chapter-title> In: <name><surname>Speth</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Christoph</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Diekkr&#x000fc;ger</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, editors. <source>Impacts of Global Change on the Hydrological Cycle in West and Northwest Africa</source>. <publisher-loc>Berlin, Heidelberg</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Springer Berlin Heidelberg</publisher-name>; <year>2010</year> p. <fpage>132</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>63</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">You L, Wood-Sichra U, Fritz S, Guo Z, See L, Koo J. Spatial Production Allocation Model (SPAM) 2005 v2.0 2014 [November 7, 2016. Available from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mapspam.info">http://mapspam.info</ext-link>].</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Giertz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Steup</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schonbrodt</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Use and Constraints on the Use of Inland Valley Ecosystems in Central Benin: Results from an Inland Valley Survey</article-title>. <source>Erdkunde</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>66</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>239</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>53</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.3112/erdkunde.2012.03.04">10.3112/erdkunde.2012.03.04</ext-link>.</comment> WOS:000310494800004.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Judex</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thamm</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>IMPETUS Atlas Benin. Research Results 2000&#x02013;2007</chapter-title>, <edition>3rd ed.</edition>
<publisher-name>Department of Geography, University of Bonn</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Germany</publisher-loc>, <year>2008</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rathjens</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oppelt</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>. <article-title>SWATgrid: An interface for setting up SWAT in a grid-based discretization scheme</article-title>. <source>Computers &#x00026; Geosciences</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>161</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cageo.2011.11.004">10.1016/j.cageo.2011.11.004</ext-link>.</comment> WOS:000306771100019.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Volk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bosch</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name>. <article-title>Assessment of Different Representations of Spatial Variability on SWAT Model Performance</article-title>. <source>Transactions of the ASABE</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>53</volume>(<issue>5</issue>):<fpage>1433</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>43</lpage>. WOS:000284818500007.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rathjens</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oppelt</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bosch</surname><given-names>DD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Volk</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Development of a grid-based version of the SWAT landscape model</article-title>. <source>Hydrological Processes</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>900</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1002/hyp.10197">10.1002/hyp.10197</ext-link>.</comment> WOS:000350548100007.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Neitsch</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kiniry</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Soil and Water Assessment Tool, Theoretical Documentation</chapter-title>
<publisher-name>Grassland, Soil and Water Research Laboratory</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Temple, TX, USA</publisher-loc>, <year>2009</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gassman</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reyes</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Green</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>. <article-title>The Soil and Water Assessment Tool: Historical development, applications, and future research directions</article-title>. <source>Transactions of the ASABE</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>50</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1211</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>50</lpage>. WOS:000249466000012.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rathjens</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Oppelt</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>. <article-title>SWAT model calibration of a grid-based setup</article-title>. <source>Advances in Geosciences</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>32</volume>:<fpage>55</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>61</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.5194/adgeo-32-55-2012">10.5194/adgeo-32-55-2012</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Duku</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rathjens</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zwart</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hein</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>Towards ecosystem accounting: a comprehensive approach to modelling multiple hydrological ecosystem services</article-title>. <source>Hydrology and Earth System Sciences</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>10</issue>):<fpage>4377</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>96</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.5194/hess-19-4377-2015">10.5194/hess-19-4377-2015</ext-link>.</comment> WOS:000364327800022.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hargreaves</surname><given-names>GL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hargreaves</surname><given-names>GH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Riley</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Agricultural Benefits for Senegal River Basin</article-title>. <source>Journal of Irrigation and Drainage Engineering-ASCE</source>. <year>1985</year>;<volume>111</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>113</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>24</lpage>. WOS:A1985AJV6800002.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Abbaspour</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Reichert</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vejdani</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Haghighat</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Srinivasan</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>SWAT-CUP, SWAT Calibration and Uncertainty programs</chapter-title>
<publisher-name>Swiss Federal Institute of Aquatic Science and Technology (EAWAG)</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Zurich, Switzerland</publisher-loc>
<year>2008</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">AMMA-CATCH. AMMA-CATCH Observatory 2014 [(last access: 28 May 2014)]. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://bd.amma-catch.org/amma-catch2/main.jsf">http://bd.amma-catch.org/amma-catch2/main.jsf</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>CRU TS3.21: Climatic Research Unit (CRU) Time-Series (TS) Version 3.21 of High Resolution Gridded Data of Month-by-month Variation in Climate (Jan. 1901&#x02014;Dec. 2012)</chapter-title>
<publisher-name>NCAS British Atmospheric Data Centre: University of East Anglia Climatic Research Unit (CRU)</publisher-name>; <year>2013</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Babiker</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brinkman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Calvo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Edmonds</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<chapter-title>Towards New Scenarios for the Analysis of Emissions: Climate Change, Impacts and Response Strategies</chapter-title>
<publisher-name>Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change Secretariat (IPCC)</publisher-name>; <year>2008</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Edmonds</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hibbard</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Manning</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rose</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>van Vuuren</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>The next generation of scenarios for climate change research and assessment</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>463</volume>(<issue>7282</issue>):<fpage>747</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>56</lpage>. Epub 2010/02/12. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/nature08823">10.1038/nature08823</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 20148028?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20148028</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thornton</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name>. <article-title>Generating downscaled weather data from a suite of climate models for agricultural modelling applications</article-title>. <source>Agricultural Systems</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>114</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.agsy.2012.08.002">10.1016/j.agsy.2012.08.002</ext-link>.</comment> WOS:000312178100001.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hijmans</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Parra</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jarvis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Very high resolution interpolated climate surfaces for global land areas</article-title>. <source>International Journal of Climatology</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>25</volume>(<issue>15</issue>):<fpage>1965</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>78</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1002/joc.1276">10.1002/joc.1276</ext-link>.</comment> WOS:000234519700002.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ficklin</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Assessment of climate change impacts on hydrology and water quality with a watershed modeling approach</article-title>. <source>The Science of the total environment</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>450-451</volume>(<issue>451</issue>):<fpage>72</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>82</lpage>. Epub 2013/03/08. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2013.02.004">10.1016/j.scitotenv.2013.02.004</ext-link></comment> .<?supplied-pmid 23467178?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23467178</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref047"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Anandhi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Frei</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pierson</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schneiderman</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zion</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lounsbury</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Examination of change factor methodologies for climate change impact assessment</article-title>. <source>Water Resour Res</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>47</volume>(<issue>3</issue>). Artn W03501 <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1029/2010wr009104">10.1029/2010wr009104</ext-link>.</comment> WOS:000288083200001.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref048"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Diaz-Nieto</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wilby</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name>. <article-title>A comparison of statistical downscaling and climate change factor methods: Impacts on low flows in the River Thames, United Kingdom</article-title>. <source>Climatic Change</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>69</volume>(<issue>2&#x02013;3</issue>):<fpage>245</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>68</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10584-005-1157-6">10.1007/s10584-005-1157-6</ext-link>.</comment> WOS:000228882000004.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref049"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>O&#x02019;Neill</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kriegler</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Riahi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ebi</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hallegatte</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>A new scenario framework for climate change research: the concept of shared socioeconomic pathways</article-title>. <source>Climatic Change</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>122</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>387</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>400</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10584-013-0905-2">10.1007/s10584-013-0905-2</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref050"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kriegler</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>O'Neill</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hallegatte</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kram</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lempert</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>The need for and use of socio-economic scenarios for climate change analysis: A new approach based on shared socio-economic pathways</article-title>. <source>Global Environmental Change-Human and Policy Dimensions</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>22</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>807</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>22</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gloenvcha.2012.05.005">10.1016/j.gloenvcha.2012.05.005</ext-link>.</comment> WOS:000309788000002.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref051"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>O'Neill</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name>. <article-title>Spatially explicit global population scenarios consistent with the Shared Socioeconomic Pathways</article-title>. <source>Environmental Research Letters</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>11</volume>(<issue>8</issue>):<fpage>084003</fpage> Artn 084003 <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1088/1748-9326/11/8/084003">10.1088/1748-9326/11/8/084003</ext-link>.</comment> WOS:000381828300004.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref052"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hanasaki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fujimori</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yamamoto</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yoshikawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Masaki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hijioka</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>A global water scarcity assessment under Shared Socio-economic Pathways &#x00026;ndash; Part 1: Water use</article-title>. <source>Hydrology and Earth System Sciences</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>2375</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>91</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.5194/hess-17-2375-2013">10.5194/hess-17-2375-2013</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref053"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>FAO</collab>. <chapter-title>Rural structures in the tropics</chapter-title>
<publisher-name>Design and development</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>Rome, Italy</publisher-loc>: <year>2011</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref054"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>FAO</collab>. <chapter-title>Irrigation potential in Africa. a basin approach</chapter-title>
<publisher-loc>Rome, Italy</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>Food and Agriculture Organization of United Nations, Land and Water Development Division</publisher-name>, <year>1997</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref055"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hadjer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schopp</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Water consumption embedded in its social context, north-western Benin</article-title>. <source>Physics and Chemistry of the Earth</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>30</volume>(<issue>6&#x02013;7</issue>):<fpage>357</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>64</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.pce.2005.06.014">10.1016/j.pce.2005.06.014</ext-link>.</comment> WOS:000232249600005.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref056"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">INSAE. Troisi&#x000e8;me Recensement G&#x000e9;n&#x000e9;ral de la Population et de l&#x02019;Habitation. Cotonou, Benin: 2003.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref057"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vicente-Serrano</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Begueria</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lopez-Moreno</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name>. <article-title>A Multiscalar Drought Index Sensitive to Global Warming: The Standardized Precipitation Evapotranspiration Index</article-title>. <source>Journal of Climate</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>23</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1696</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>718</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1175/2009JCLI2909.1">10.1175/2009JCLI2909.1</ext-link>.</comment> WOS:000276505500005.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref058"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>PG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thornton</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name>. <article-title>Croppers to livestock keepers: livelihood transitions to 2050 in Africa due to climate change</article-title>. <source>Environmental Science &#x00026; Policy</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>12</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>427</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>37</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envsci.2008.08.006">10.1016/j.envsci.2008.08.006</ext-link>.</comment> WOS:000267515300006.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref059"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Phillips</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>. <article-title>Heat summation theory as applied to canning crops</article-title>. <source>The Canner</source>. <year>1950</year>;<volume>27</volume>:<fpage>13</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref060"><label>60</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Barnard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Heat units as a measure of canning crop maturity</article-title>. <source>The Canner</source>. <year>1948</year>;<volume>106</volume>(<issue>16</issue>):<fpage>28</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref061"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>IIASA, FAO</collab>. <chapter-title>Global Agro-ecological Zones (GAEZ v3.0)</chapter-title>
<publisher-name>IIASA, Laxenburg, Austria and FAO</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Rome, Italy</publisher-loc>, <year>2012</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref062"><label>62</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Farahmand</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>AghaKouchak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>A generalized framework for deriving nonparametric standardized drought indicators</article-title>. <source>Advances in Water Resources</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>76</volume>:<fpage>140</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1152/ajplegacy.1975.229.3.570">10.1152/ajplegacy.1975.229.3.570</ext-link></comment> . WOS:000349673500012.<?supplied-pmid 10.1016/j.advwatres.2014.11.012?></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref063"><label>63</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hao</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>AghaKouchak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nakhjiri</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Farahmand</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>Global integrated drought monitoring and prediction system</article-title>. <source>Scientific Data</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>1</volume>:<fpage>140001</fpage> Epub 2014/01/01. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1038/sdata.2014.1">10.1038/sdata.2014.1</ext-link></comment> ; PubMed Central PMCID: PMC4322588.<?supplied-pmid 25977759?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25977759</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref064"><label>64</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Shiau</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nadaraiah</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Assessment of hydrological droughts for the Yellow River, China, using copulas</article-title>. <source>Hydrological Processes</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>16</issue>):<fpage>2157</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>63</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1002/hyp.6400">10.1002/hyp.6400</ext-link>.</comment> WOS:000248632400008.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref065"><label>65</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Van Loon</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ploum</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Parajka</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fleig</surname><given-names>AK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Garnier</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Laaha</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Hydrological drought types in cold climates: quantitative analysis of causing factors and qualitative survey of impacts</article-title>. <source>Hydrology and Earth System Sciences</source>. <year>2015</year>;<volume>19</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>1993</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2016</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.5194/hess-19-1993-2015">10.5194/hess-19-1993-2015</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref066"><label>66</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Smakhtin</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Revenga</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Doll</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>A pilot global assessment of environmental water requirements and scarcity</article-title>. <source>Water International</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>29</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>307</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>17</lpage>. WOS:000234618500006.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref067"><label>67</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Duku</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zwart</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hein</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>. <article-title>Modelling the forest and woodland-irrigation nexus in tropical Africa: A case study in Benin</article-title>. <source>Agriculture Ecosystems &#x00026; Environment</source>. <year>2016</year>;<volume>230</volume>:<fpage>105</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>15</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1016/j.agee.2016.06.001">10.1016/j.agee.2016.06.001</ext-link>.</comment> WOS:000381834500012.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref068"><label>68</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rowell</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>. <article-title>Sources of uncertainty in future changes in local precipitation</article-title>. <source>Climate Dynamics</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>39</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>1929</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>50</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s00382-011-1210-2">10.1007/s00382-011-1210-2</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref069"><label>69</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Randall</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wood</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bony</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Colman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fichefet</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fyfe</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<chapter-title>Climate models and their evaluation</chapter-title>
<source>Climate change 2007</source>: <publisher-name>The physical science basis Contribution of Working Group I to the Fourth Assessment Report of the IPCC (FAR): Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>; <year>2007</year> p. <fpage>589</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>662</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref070"><label>70</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lambert</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Boer</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>CMIP1 evaluation and intercomparison of coupled climate models</article-title>. <source>Climate Dynamics</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>17</volume>(<issue>2&#x02013;3</issue>):<fpage>83</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>106</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1007/Pl00013736">10.1007/Pl00013736</ext-link>.</comment> WOS:000166407500001.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref071"><label>71</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Yira</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Diekkr&#x000fc;ger</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Steup</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bossa</surname><given-names>AY</given-names></name>. <article-title>Impact of climate change on hydrological conditions in a tropical West African catchment using an ensemble of climate simulations</article-title>. <source>Hydrol Earth Syst Sci</source>. <year>2017</year>;<volume>21</volume>(<issue>4</issue>):<fpage>2143</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>61</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.5194/hess-21-2143-2017">10.5194/hess-21-2143-2017</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref072"><label>72</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Giorgi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Coppola</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>. <article-title>Does the model regional bias affect the projected regional climate change? An analysis of global model projections</article-title>. <source>Climatic Change</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>100</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>787</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>95</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref073"><label>73</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>van Vuuren</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kriegler</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>O&#x02019;Neill</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ebi</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Riahi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carter</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>A new scenario framework for Climate Change Research: scenario matrix architecture</article-title>. <source>Climatic Change</source>. <year>2014</year>;<volume>122</volume>(<issue>3</issue>):<fpage>373</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>86</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s10584-013-0906-1">10.1007/s10584-013-0906-1</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref074"><label>74</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Medlyn</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>CVM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Broadmeadow</surname><given-names>MSJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ceulemans</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>De Angelis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Forstreuter</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Stomatal conductance of forest species after long-term exposure to elevated CO2 concentration: a synthesis</article-title>. <source>New Phytologist</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>149</volume>(<issue>2</issue>):<fpage>247</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>64</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1046/j.1469-8137.2001.00028.x">10.1046/j.1469-8137.2001.00028.x</ext-link>.</comment> WOS:000166890800010.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref075"><label>75</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wand</surname><given-names>SJE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Midgley</surname><given-names>GF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Curtis</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Responses of wild C4 and C3 grass (Poaceae) species to elevated atmospheric CO2 concentration: a meta-analytic test of current theories and perceptions</article-title>. <source>Global Change Biology</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>6</issue>):<fpage>723</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>41</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1046/j.1365-2486.1999.00265.x">10.1046/j.1365-2486.1999.00265.x</ext-link>.</comment> WOS:000081655000009.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref076"><label>76</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pritchard</surname><given-names>SG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>HH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Prior</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name>. <article-title>Elevated CO2 and plant structure: a review</article-title>. <source>Global Change Biology</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>5</volume>(<issue>7</issue>):<fpage>807</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>37</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.org/10.1046/j.1365-2486.1999.00268.x">10.1046/j.1365-2486.1999.00268.x</ext-link>.</comment> WOS:000082646900006.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref077"><label>77</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><collab>FAO</collab>. <chapter-title>AQUASTAT Main Database</chapter-title>
<publisher-name>Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations</publisher-name>; <year>2016</year>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0192642.ref078"><label>78</label><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Dillon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <chapter-title>Access to irrigation and the escape from poverty: Evidence from northern Mali</chapter-title>
<publisher-loc>Washington DC, USA</publisher-loc>: <publisher-name>International Food Policy Research Institute</publisher-name>, <year>2008</year>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>