<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par6" class="p">Here, we used a spatially explicit individual based model to simulate a coral community which is influenced by the presence of macroalgae, mechanical disturbance events and temperature. We concentrated on 3 important traits in corals: (i) 
 <italic class="italic">Growth rate</italic>, which influences the speed at which a coral is able to colonize an area; (ii) 
 <italic class="italic">Tolerance to thermal stress</italic>, which reduces the mortality associated with extreme thermal events (i.e. bleaching), and (iii) 
 <italic class="italic">Competitiveness with neighbours</italic>, which enables coral colonies to maintain space on a reef and even colonize new ground at the expense of an inferior neighbour when coral cover is high. We populated the model with an array of massive and branching species with different combinations of these three traits, in which pairs of species, one of each morphology, share the same trait combinations (see Methods: Simulations; Appendix, Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S1</xref>). To represent the respective position of each species in trait space we apply the triangle approach originally developed by Grime
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>
 </sup> for terrestrial plants (Appendix 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">1</xref>: Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S2</xref>). Each array consisted of 20 species and each simulation run consisted of multiple replications of 10 different initial coral community distributions, whose results were combined for analysis. Thus the initial number of species in each simulated scenario was 200 species. Community dynamics were simulated over 90 years. We used these model simulations to explore the influence of key environmental parameters on coral cover and community composition (Appendix 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">1</xref>: Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S2</xref>). Furthermore, we set out to identify the trait combination(s) that will enable coral species of each growth form to be ‘successful’ (‘winners’ 
 <italic class="italic">sensu</italic> Loya 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">30</xref>
 </sup>) under future temperature conditions predicted by climate change scenarios.
</p>
