<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec013" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Controversies in curricula</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Manitoba’s science curriculum, which is among the oldest in Canada (dating from 2001), displayed a tendency to depart from the scientific consensus. For instance, specific learning objectives moderated the idea of anthropogenic climate change, saying that the climate “can be influenced” by humans [
  <a rid="pone.0218305.ref057" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref057">57</a>] rather than describing humans as the major driver of current climate change. But divergence from scientific understanding was much more pronounced in supplementary materials in Manitoba’s curriculum, which recommended reading material produced by “Friends of Science”, an organization described as opposing the IPCC understanding of climate change [
  <a rid="pone.0218305.ref058" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref058">58</a>]. The curriculum document adds, “It should be noted that there is significantly polarized debate on the issue among scientists. Students should be justifiably cautious about accepting unsubstantiated claims about global warming” [
  <a rid="pone.0218305.ref058" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref058">58</a>]. This is particularly concerning given that there actually is no polarized debate in the scientific community [
  <a rid="pone.0218305.ref017" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref017">17</a>]. Furthermore, individuals who hold the misconception that there is widespread disagreement amongst scientists on this issue are less likely to support policies to mitigate climate change [
  <a rid="pone.0218305.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref039">39</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Manitoba was not the only province with curriculum documents conveying disagreement amongst the scientific community (
  <a rid="pone.0218305.t003" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0218305.t003">Table 3</a>). The supporting documentation for both Newfoundland and Prince Edward Island undermine the notion of a scientific consensus, suggesting that debate should be encouraged amongst students on the cause of current climate change. This raises the question of how climate change is best taught, and whether debate on the biophysical existence and anthropogenic cause of warming should encouraged on the issue, as it may lead students to incorrectly conclude that there remains scientific disagreement on these topics.
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0218305.t003" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0218305.t003</span>
  <span class="label">Table 3</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Statements in curriculum documents that oppose the scientific consensus on anthropogenic climate change.</div>
  </div>
  <div class="alternatives">
   <div id="pone.0218305.t003g" xlink:href="pone.0218305.t003" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <colgroup span="1">
     <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
     <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
    </colgroup>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
       <span class="bold">Manitoba</span>
      </td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">“It is important for students to conduct research that is fair and representative of alternative, and viable, scientific viewpoints on such a vital issue. Students should research climate science, as articulated by organizations such as The Friends of Science—Providing Insight into Climate Science (see &lt;
       <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.friendsofscience.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.friendsofscience.org/</span>&gt;). This large, international community of climate scientists, for instance, holds views quite contrary to what has been supported by Environment Canada and the United Nations’ (UN) Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) over the past decade … Students could role-play disparate points of view within the climate science community.” [
       <a rid="pone.0218305.ref058" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref058">58</a>] “A discussion of the merits and shortcomings of the scientific community’s research agenda into the anthropogenic CO
       <sub>2</sub> contribution to potential global warming could be conducted in relation to this topic. It should be noted that there is significantly polarized debate on the issue among scientists. Students should be justifiably cautious about accepting unsubstantiated claims about global warming. This issue provides an opportunity to engage students in the patterns of behaviour that occur within science during what can be termed a “crisis” situation.” [
       <a rid="pone.0218305.ref058" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref058">58</a>]
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
       <span class="bold">Newfoundland and Labrador + Prince Edward Island</span>
      </td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">“Teachers should ensure that students understand that there are contradictory viewpoints to this issue. Students may have seen Al Gore’s movie “An Inconvenient Trust [
       <span class="italic">sic</span>]” which explains the anthropogenic side of the story. Teachers should ensure that students know that there may be a natural cyclic event on Earth causing global warming. Some sources include volcanic activity, ocean currents, solar variability, Earth’s orbit and tilt, plate tectonics and biological evolution.” [
       <a rid="pone.0218305.ref059" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref059">59</a>] “Not all scientists agree on the science surrounding climate change. Some scientists are skeptical and believe that climate change is a natural, cyclic process. Research and try to find opposing arguments to climate change. Take one side of the issue and debate it with another student with an opposing viewpoint.” [
       <a rid="pone.0218305.ref059" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref059">59</a>] and [
       <a rid="pone.0218305.ref060" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref060">60</a>]
      </td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
  </div>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While some provinces (and textbooks) suggest teaching the existence of human-caused climate warming (“It’s Us”) as a debate, few are teaching the scientific consensus of the current human-caused climate warming. Only one province (Saskatchewan) covered the core teaching topic “Experts agree”, and only in a non-mandatory course (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0218305.g001" href="#pone.0218305.g001">Fig 1</a>). The “We can fix it” topic was also sparsely covered, with only five provinces addressing this concept in their objectives. But the way in which “We can fix it” is covered is also an area of interest. For instance, some provincial curricula suggest individual actions that would lead to climate change mitigation [
  <a rid="pone.0218305.ref061" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref061">61</a>], largely focusing on energy efficiency and recycling, while others discuss the political steps that can be taken [
  <a rid="pone.0218305.ref059" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref059">59</a>]. But no province connects these two things–i.e., how can an individual contribute to political or structural changes. Some textbooks fill these gaps, discussing both the meaning [
  <a rid="pone.0218305.ref062" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref062">62</a>] and existence of scientific consensus [
  <a rid="pone.0218305.ref063" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref063">63</a>], as well as prompting students to participate in political processes: “Make a list of five ways you can reduce your personal impact on climate change and three ways you can influence corporate and/or governmental action of climate change” [
  <a rid="pone.0218305.ref064" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0218305.ref064">64</a>]. So even with little prompting from the curriculum, some textbooks encourage positive personal and political participation regarding climate change.
 </p>
</sec>
