<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The respondents mentioned that apart from tilling the land before rainfall they also store water for agricultural purposes by building temporary walls around riverbanks. When the river dries up they are then able to sustain their crops through irrigation from riverbank wells. Generally, the respondents demonstrated that even though climate change had numerous impacts on their livelihoods, they equally had workable strategies. It was discovered that these strategies were unique and have been sustained for a long time. The view that Afrocentricity implies that Africans should be studied from their own worldview is largely upheld on this aspect. The uniqueness of the strategies employed by community members necessitates this study to be informed by Afrocentricity. In a study by Nkomwaa et al. (
 <xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>) on IKS and climate change adaptation strategies in agriculture in the Chagaka area, Malawi, farmers have always utilised a variety of traditional aspects in order to enhance their farming practices. Also, Gyampoh et al. (
 <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>) observed that rural communities that are vulnerable to climate change have strong adaptive capacities. Adapting to drought, scarcity of rain and decreased production of crops is accomplished through community-based measures to sustain human livelihoods (Gyampoh et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>). In the current study, most farmers reported that they changed crop types from maize to sorghum and millet in order to cope with climate change. This is in line with a study conducted in Pakistan by Abid et al. (
 <xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>) which shows that farmers opted to change crop types because of an incidence of heavy pest and insect attacks, soil problems and extreme temperature events. Some farmers reported that they had replaced cotton crops with maize crops since 2010 because of cotton’s susceptibility to heavy pest attacks and changing weather conditions (Abid et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>). Even though subsistence farmers have always adopted adaptive strategies to some of these changes over the years, effective adaptation strategies should be aimed at securing communities’ well-being in the face of climatic changes (Somah 
 <xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>).
</p>
