<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The main focus on thermoregulatory sweating in children is typically whole-body sweating, with a paucity of data regarding RSR. Regional SRs are widely recognized in adults [
 <xref rid="B102-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">102</xref>,
 <xref rid="B103-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">103</xref>,
 <xref rid="B104-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">104</xref>,
 <xref rid="B105-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">105</xref>,
 <xref rid="B106-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">106</xref>], with differences in children depending on maturational stage [
 <xref rid="B34-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. This was observed by Shibasaki and colleagues [
 <xref rid="B34-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] following passive heating of prepubertal boys (7–11 years) and young men (21–25 years) via lower leg immersion in a 42 °C water bath for 60 min. RSRs varied, with some sites significantly higher than adults (forearm), some significantly lower (chest, thigh during latter 30 minutes only), and others showing no differences (back) between groups. The sweating threshold (
 <italic>T
  <sub>b</sub>
 </italic>) was slightly higher in boys, albeit nonsignificant (
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.10), regardless of body region. Heat-activated sweat gland density (HASG) was higher in boys at all sites, but this is not surprising given their developmental stage and smaller body size and surface area. The authors suggest regional variation in sweating associated with maturational stage and argue a peripheral ‘underdevelopment’ at the level of the sweat gland versus central drive [
 <xref rid="B34-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. This highlights the necessity for measuring RSR at multiple sites and the need for more detailed regional sweating data in children and adolescents at varying maturational stages. Notably, ambient conditions were 25 °C, 45% rh, providing a favorable temperature gradient for dry heat losses on which children typically rely more heavily. The authors focus on sweating in relation to maturational age, but other heat loss mechanisms should be considered. Despite lower RSR, change in 
 <italic>T
  <sub>re</sub>
 </italic> did not differ between groups, indicating that prepubertal boys could adequately thermoregulate under mild to moderate passive heat stress in the specified conditions, relying on differing mechanisms and perhaps displaying greater efficiency.
</p>
