<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2f" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate change scenarios</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We generated extrapolations of projected dengue risk based on our fitted GAM parameters for the years 2030, 2050 and 2080, under the A1B, A2 and B1 climate change scenarios. The storylines behind these scenarios are described in detail elsewhere 
  <a rid="pntd.0002503-IPCC1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pntd.0002503-IPCC1">[12]</a>. Briefly, the A1B scenario relates to a future with very rapid economic growth, global population peaking in mid-century, and the introduction of more efficient technologies with a balance in energy-sources-related technological change 
  <a rid="pntd.0002503-IPCC1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pntd.0002503-IPCC1">[12]</a>. The A2 scenario describes a future with a continuously increasing global population, economic development regionally oriented, and a slower and fragmented per capita economic growth and technological change than other scenarios 
  <a rid="pntd.0002503-IPCC1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pntd.0002503-IPCC1">[12]</a>. Lastly, the B1 scenario considers a similar global population growth as the A1B, but with an economic structure towards a service and information economy, reductions in material intensity, and the introduction of clean and resource-efficient technologies 
  <a rid="pntd.0002503-IPCC1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pntd.0002503-IPCC1">[12]</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We retrieved province-specific temperature and precipitation ensemble outputs of multiple models (relative to the base period climatology of 1970–1999) from the website of the Mexican National Institute of Ecology for the years 2030, 2050 and 2080. The methodology and outputs of these ensembles have been described by Magaña and Caetano 
  <a rid="pntd.0002503-Magaa1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pntd.0002503-Magaa1">[36]</a>. Briefly, the three scenarios (A1B, A2, and B1) describe rising temperature at an increasing rate all over the country. The north-west region is the most greatly affected by temperature at the end of the century 
  <a rid="pntd.0002503-Magaa1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pntd.0002503-Magaa1">[36]</a>. In these scenarios, changes in precipitation are be very irregular; though they agree that decreases are expected mainly in the north and north-west, followed by the Yucatán Peninsula and central Mexico 
  <a rid="pntd.0002503-Magaa1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pntd.0002503-Magaa1">[36]</a>. Changes in both temperature and precipitation are expected to be greater under the A2 scenario (high emissions) followed by the A1B and B1 
  <a rid="pntd.0002503-Magaa1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pntd.0002503-Magaa1">[36]</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To conduct our estimations, we used future projections of climate holding all the other driving forces constant (fixed to the baseline year 2000) to isolate the effects of climate on dengue. While our model is robust to the confounding effects of observed and un-observed non-climatic factors, these projections are not predictions of the future but rather aim to show the potential impact of climate change on dengue incidence whilst keeping the other driving forces constant.</p>
</sec>
