<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="methods" id="s2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec id="s2a" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Dengue data</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Province-specific monthly reports of laboratory confirmed dengue cases were collected from the Mexican National System of Epidemiologic Surveillance 
   <a rid="pntd.0002503-CENAVECE1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pntd.0002503-CENAVECE1">[22]</a> for the period 1985—2007 (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pntd-0002503-g001" href="#pntd-0002503-g001">Figure 1</a>). Dengue and severe dengue cases were aggregated because they correspond to different presentations of the disease.
  </p>
  <div id="pntd-0002503-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pntd.0002503.g001</span>
   <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <div class="title">Time series of average monthly dengue incidence in Mexico (cases/100,000 people) over the period January 1985 to December 2007.</div>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="pntd.0002503.g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2b" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Weather data</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We obtained the province-specific monthly mean values of minimum temperature, average maximum temperature and monthly accumulated precipitation from the Mexican National Meteorological Service for each province for the period 1971—2007. These monthly mean values were computed using province-specific observations from all available meteorological stations across Mexico. The network of meteorological stations from the National Meteorological Service consists of over 2,000 stations distributed across the whole country. The frequency and duration of rainy events were not considered as such information was not available from the National Meteorological Service. We preferred station data over satellite data because meteorological stations seem to provide more reliable information about the conditions (particularly rainfall) of an area than do satellites 
   <a rid="pntd.0002503-Mendelsohn1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pntd.0002503-Mendelsohn1">[23]</a>, 
   <a rid="pntd.0002503-Ceccato1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pntd.0002503-Ceccato1">[24]</a>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Because the modulating effects of the climate system on vector populations do not immediately result in changes on dengue transmission, we specified meteorological variables within biologically and physically plausible time lags based on literature reports in Mexico (for example, references 
   <a rid="pntd.0002503-ColnGonzlez1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pntd.0002503-ColnGonzlez1">[25]</a>, 
   <a rid="pntd.0002503-Brunkard1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pntd.0002503-Brunkard1">[26]</a>, 
   <a rid="pntd.0002503-HurtadoDaz1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pntd.0002503-HurtadoDaz1">[27]</a>), and considering the delays in laboratory confirmation of suspected cases and their reporting. Optimal lags for the climatic variables comprised monthly average minimum temperature, average monthly maximum temperature and accumulated monthly precipitation lagged one and two months. Due to significant autocorrelation between the lags of these variables (Spearman's rank rho 0.7), we created new variables (Tmin
   <sub>1∶2</sub>, Tmax
   <sub>1∶2</sub>, and Precipitation
   <sub>1∶2</sub>) taking the mean of the values of the two optimal lags.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2c" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Socioeconomic data</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Provincial population data were retrieved from the National Institute of Statistics and Geography (INEGI) 
   <a rid="pntd.0002503-INEGI1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pntd.0002503-INEGI1">[28]</a> for 1990, 1995, 2000 and 2005. The proportion of the population with access to piped water was also obtained from INEGI for 1990, 2000, 2005 and 2010. The share of the population living in urban areas (urbanisation) was obtained from the Chamber of Deputies 
   <a rid="pntd.0002503-CEFP1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pntd.0002503-CEFP1">[29]</a> for 1980, 1990, 1995, 2000 and 2004. Intervening years for these variables were estimated using linear interpolation. Yearly GDP per capita was obtained from the World Bank for the whole period of study. These data were then deflated at constant 2003 values. GDP data were originally aggregated at the national level. To obtain province-specific GDP estimates we assumed that the proportion of the national GDP for each province was the same as that for which GDP information were available (1993–2005) from INEGI. Thus, the province-specific proportion of GDP for the period 1985–1993 was assumed to be the same than that observed in 1993 on the INEGI data. Proportions for the subsequent years were assumed to be the same as in the INEGI data.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2d" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate change data</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To project the potential impact of climate change on dengue (with Monte Carlo 95% confidence intervals), we retrieved province-specific historical values (relative to the 1970—1999 climatology) and projected changes for the years 2030, 2050 and 2080 under three climate change scenarios (A1B, A2 and B1) for monthly mean temperature and precipitation from the National Institute of Ecology 
   <a rid="pntd.0002503-INE1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pntd.0002503-INE1">[30]</a> using the coordinates of the centroids of each province. The coordinates of the centroids were obtained using the standard ‘coordinates’ routine within the ‘sp’ package for R 
   <a rid="pntd.0002503-R1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pntd.0002503-R1">[31]</a> and a digital map of Mexico. Average monthly minimum temperature, maximum temperature and precipitation were estimated as the monthly averages of the baseline period based on the observational data obtained from the Mexican National Meteorological Service. To generate new temperature values for each scenario, we added the corresponding projected changes to the historical values. Precipitation was rescaled multiplying the historical value by the corresponding projected percentage of variation. Average minimum and maximum temperature, and accumulated precipitation values (historical and projected) lagged 1 and 2 months were then used for the climate change projections.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2e" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">GAM analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We specified the expected number of dengue cases during month 
   <span class="italic">t</span> and province 
   <span class="italic">i</span> as:
   <div id="pntd.0002503.e001" class="disp-formula">
    <div xlink:href="pntd.0002503.e001.jpg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    <span class="label">(1)</span>
   </div>where 
   <span class="italic">g</span>(.) is a log link function of the expectation 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>
   <sub>it</sub>≡
   <span class="italic">E</span>(
   <span class="italic">Y
    <sub>it</sub>
   </span>), with 
   <span class="italic">Y
    <sub>it</sub>
   </span> as the series of dengue counts. 
   <span class="italic">X
    <sub>jit</sub>
   </span> denotes the 
   <span class="italic">j</span>-th meteorological variables, 
   <span class="italic">s
    <sub>j</sub>
   </span>(.) and 
   <span class="italic">s
    <sub>1</sub>
   </span>(.) are smooth functions for the meteorological variables and the time trend defined via penalized cubic regressions splines; 
   <span class="italic">Z
    <sub>kit</sub>
   </span> denotes the 
   <span class="italic">k</span>-th socio-economic variables (GDP per capita, proportion of people living in urban areas, proportion of people with access to piped water) which enter the model linearly; 
   <span class="italic">d
    <sub>i</sub>
   </span> are province-specific fixed effects 
   <a rid="pntd.0002503-Johnston1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pntd.0002503-Johnston1">[32]</a> to capture the effects of potential unobserved confounders (e.g. social behaviour) in the model. Log(
   <span class="italic">ξ
    <sub>it</sub>
   </span>) indicates the logarithm of the population/month at risk included as an offset variable. This offset variable standardises dengue occurrence by population to compute estimations on the incidence rate rather than on the total number of dengue cases. To account for possible over-dispersion, we allowed the scale parameter to be different from the mean 
   <a rid="pntd.0002503-Cameron1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pntd.0002503-Cameron1">[33]</a>. This led to a quasi-maximum likelihood Poisson model, which is the standard consistent estimator for count variables 
   <a rid="pntd.0002503-Wooldridge1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pntd.0002503-Wooldridge1">[34]</a>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The province-specific fixed effects control for province-specific omitted variable bias and un-modelled confounders such as social behaviour. The smooth function of time controls for long-term trends and seasonality that could arise from non-climatic factors such as resistance of the vector to insecticides, changes in the diagnostic techniques, holidays and seasonal water storage practices. To ensure the robustness of our results, we tested other specifications to account for long-term and seasonal trends including: 0,1 categorical variables for each year and for each season for the period, categorical variables for each year with a sinusoidal term for seasonal trends, and a linear trend with a sinusoidal term for seasonal trends. As is the case of the smooth function for time, our categorical variables account for long-term and seasonal changes that could happen as a consequence of confounding non-climatic factors such as seasonal water storage or year-specific disruptions in the public health systems. Estimations were conducted using the ‘mgcv’ package 
   <a rid="pntd.0002503-Wood1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pntd.0002503-Wood1">[21]</a> for R version 2.12.0 
   <a rid="pntd.0002503-R1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pntd.0002503-R1">[31]</a>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The smooth functions are represented by regression splines, which can be written as linear-combinations of known basis functions of the regressors.
   <div id="pntd.0002503.e002" class="disp-formula">
    <div xlink:href="pntd.0002503.e002.jpg" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    <span class="label">(2)</span>
   </div>where 
   <span class="italic">b
    <sub>l</sub>
   </span>(.) denotes the basis functions and 
   <span class="italic">δ
    <sub>l</sub>
   </span> the parameters to be estimated. The number of basis functions 
   <span class="italic">q</span> determines the maximum possible flexibility of the relation between 
   <span class="italic">X
    <sub>jit</sub>
   </span> and 
   <span class="italic">g</span>(
   <span class="italic">μ
    <sub>it</sub>
   </span>) (see 
   <a ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pntd.0002503.e001" href="#pntd.0002503.e001">Equation 1</a>); the greater the value of 
   <span class="italic">q</span>, the more flexible is the estimated effect. Here, we used Cubic Regression Splines (CRS) in which the basis functions 
   <span class="italic">b
    <sub>l</sub>
   </span>(.) are constructed by dividing the range of values of the independent variable into segments separated by knots. A local cubic regression is fitted to each segment. The continuity and smoothness at the knots is ensured imposing conditions on the first and second-order derivatives 
   <a rid="pntd.0002503-Keele1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pntd.0002503-Keele1">[35]</a>. Our estimation method, implemented via Penalized Iteratively Reweighted Least Squares (P-IRLS) is designed to automatically reduce the nonlinearities not supported by the data to simple linear forms 
   <a rid="pntd.0002503-Wood1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pntd.0002503-Wood1">[21]</a>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2f" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate change scenarios</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We generated extrapolations of projected dengue risk based on our fitted GAM parameters for the years 2030, 2050 and 2080, under the A1B, A2 and B1 climate change scenarios. The storylines behind these scenarios are described in detail elsewhere 
   <a rid="pntd.0002503-IPCC1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pntd.0002503-IPCC1">[12]</a>. Briefly, the A1B scenario relates to a future with very rapid economic growth, global population peaking in mid-century, and the introduction of more efficient technologies with a balance in energy-sources-related technological change 
   <a rid="pntd.0002503-IPCC1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pntd.0002503-IPCC1">[12]</a>. The A2 scenario describes a future with a continuously increasing global population, economic development regionally oriented, and a slower and fragmented per capita economic growth and technological change than other scenarios 
   <a rid="pntd.0002503-IPCC1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pntd.0002503-IPCC1">[12]</a>. Lastly, the B1 scenario considers a similar global population growth as the A1B, but with an economic structure towards a service and information economy, reductions in material intensity, and the introduction of clean and resource-efficient technologies 
   <a rid="pntd.0002503-IPCC1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pntd.0002503-IPCC1">[12]</a>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We retrieved province-specific temperature and precipitation ensemble outputs of multiple models (relative to the base period climatology of 1970–1999) from the website of the Mexican National Institute of Ecology for the years 2030, 2050 and 2080. The methodology and outputs of these ensembles have been described by Magaña and Caetano 
   <a rid="pntd.0002503-Magaa1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pntd.0002503-Magaa1">[36]</a>. Briefly, the three scenarios (A1B, A2, and B1) describe rising temperature at an increasing rate all over the country. The north-west region is the most greatly affected by temperature at the end of the century 
   <a rid="pntd.0002503-Magaa1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pntd.0002503-Magaa1">[36]</a>. In these scenarios, changes in precipitation are be very irregular; though they agree that decreases are expected mainly in the north and north-west, followed by the Yucatán Peninsula and central Mexico 
   <a rid="pntd.0002503-Magaa1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pntd.0002503-Magaa1">[36]</a>. Changes in both temperature and precipitation are expected to be greater under the A2 scenario (high emissions) followed by the A1B and B1 
   <a rid="pntd.0002503-Magaa1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pntd.0002503-Magaa1">[36]</a>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To conduct our estimations, we used future projections of climate holding all the other driving forces constant (fixed to the baseline year 2000) to isolate the effects of climate on dengue. While our model is robust to the confounding effects of observed and un-observed non-climatic factors, these projections are not predictions of the future but rather aim to show the potential impact of climate change on dengue incidence whilst keeping the other driving forces constant.</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
