<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Empirical ecological networks are known to display two non-random structural patterns. One is nested architecture (
 <italic class="italic">nestedness</italic>) [
 <xref rid="pone.0157929.ref010" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>], a hierarchical structure in which the interaction pairs of a specialist species are included in those of another (generalist) species. The other is modular structure (
 <italic class="italic">modularity</italic>) [
 <xref rid="pone.0157929.ref011" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>], a compartmentalized structure in which a number of dense sub-networks (modules) are weakly interconnected. Modularity is also a significant property of biological systems [
 <xref rid="pone.0157929.ref012" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>], such as signaling [
 <xref rid="pone.0157929.ref013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>] and metabolic [
 <xref rid="pone.0157929.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0157929.ref016" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>] networks. Although these two structural patterns generally correlate with each other, the direction and magnitude of the correlation differ depending on network type and the level of connectedness (connectance or graph density); thus, these structural patterns provide complementary information on how interactions are organized in communities [
 <xref rid="pone.0157929.ref017" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. The degree of nestedness and modularity vary between antagonistic networks (e.g., food webs) and mutualistic networks (e.g., plant–pollinator networks); the modularity of mutualistic networks is typically lower than that of antagonistic networks, whereas the nestedness of mutualistic networks is generally higher than that of antagonistic networks [
 <xref rid="pone.0157929.ref005" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0157929.ref010" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. Furthermore, studies have shown that nestedness and modularity influence ecosystem dynamics; in particular, nestedness plays important roles in increasing mutualistic-network stability [
 <xref rid="pone.0157929.ref018" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0157929.ref022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>]. Moreover, Thébault and Fontaine [
 <xref rid="pone.0157929.ref005" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>] demonstrated that both nestedness and modularity influence ecosystem stability (i.e., persistence and resilience against perturbations). The contributions of nestedness and modularity to ecosystem stability differ between mutualistic and antagonistic networks, in that increasing nestedness and/or decreasing modularity enhance the stability of mutualistic networks but reduce the stability of antagonistic networks (i.e., food webs).
</p>
