<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Management and conservation implications</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Mediterranean has been exploited for centuries, suffering the impacts of continuous and multiple anthropogenic pressures
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b19" href="#b19">19</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b80" href="#b80">80</a>. Because of increasing signs of deteriorations and degradations at species-, community- and ecosystem levels
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b19" href="#b19">19</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b39" href="#b39">39</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b80" href="#b80">80</a>, evidenced as well by this study, the basin is now of particular concern, and is a clear candidate for management actions to halt further decline and increase the sustainable use of marine resources
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b74" href="#b74">74</a>. Hindcasting analyses, as performed in this study, allow assessing historical changes in the ecosystem and in its marine resources, and are necessary pieces of the tool kit needed to support management and conservation processes.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Yet, to move towards better information to support regional policy and conservation plans, several additional steps should be developed in the near future.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">First, spatial-temporal analyses able to identify spatial patterns that can directly assist spatial management actions (e.g., by prioritizing specific areas of concern), and facilitate the communication between scientists and policy makers, environmental managers, conservationists and the general public
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b80" href="#b80">80</a> are needed to contribute to the recent Maritime Spatial Planning Directive (MSPD) of the European Commission
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b81" href="#b81">81</a>. A first attempt has been made in a recent study by Liquete 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b82" href="#b82">82</a>, which assessed the delivery of five marine ecosystem services for the whole Mediterranean basin using several modelling approaches, both in time and space. However, as pointed out by these authors, more work is needed to be able to support management decisions.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Second, the integration of additional human stressors (e.g., aquaculture, invasive species, water warming, acidification, pollution, habitat degradation) as driving forces of species dynamics is needed to increase the reliability of this modelling exercise since marine ecosystems are impacted by simultaneous cumulative threats
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b19" href="#b19">19</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b80" href="#b80">80</a>. Currently the recent MSPD, which include the EU’s Blue Growth Strategy
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b83" href="#b83">83</a> that supports sustainable growth in emergent marine sectors (e.g., aquaculture, coastal tourism, marine energies), is expected to impose further pressures on the Mediterranean Sea
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b19" href="#b19">19</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b84" href="#b84">84</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Third, the development of forecast scenarios, including different future management actions, is crucial for the implementation of management plans. Future scenarios should follow the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) projections on climate-induced changes in sea surface temperature. They should also consider the relevant elements of the Common Fisheries Policy (CFP) on commercially important stocks to exploit them at Maximum Sustainable Yield (MSY) levels and the reduction of fishing effort needed to develop effective and appropriate policy and conservation plans in the region
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b39" href="#b39">39</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b56" href="#b56">56</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition, this work emphasizes the need to use end-to-end modelling approaches as strategic tools for an explicit support to the decision-making process. Several end-to-end (E2E) models have now been developed
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b22" href="#b22">22</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b23" href="#b23">23</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b61" href="#b61">61</a> to capture the feedbacks and multi-scale interactions that drive ecosystems dynamics with the goal of guiding responsible resource management decisions. As pointed out by Fulton
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b85" href="#b85">85</a>, there is no “one best E2E model”, on the contrary, a suite of tools should be considered given that such approaches are normally used to address questions at a scale where there is still a lot of uncertainty about how systems function. Our study advanced in this direction using results of complementary models together.
 </p>
</sec>
