<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Model assumptions and limitations</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Modelling the Mediterranean Sea ecosystem is a challenging task, not only because of the complex dynamics that characterize this Large Marine Ecosystem (e.g., differences in environmental and biological features), but also because of the difficulties of gathering and integrating regional data
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b24" href="#b24">24</a>. Several gaps have been already identified and described in a previous work of Piroddi 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b24" href="#b24">24</a> which identified the lack of trophic information with a temporal dimension, the limited information on biomass of different species (especially of those non-commercially important species and deep-sea organisms), and the lack of reliable catch data and fishing effort. The absence of time series of seagrass productivity at regional scale is another constraint. Assessing the role and contribution of seagrass productivity on the overall marine primary productivity is critically important for understanding how changes in seagrass growth rates might impact the different compartments of an ecosystem
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b86" href="#b86">86</a>. In addition, the lack of historical data series (particularly between 1950 s and 1970 s), and the problems with data accessibility limit the potential resolution of modelling studies and the development of robust EBM approaches
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b24" href="#b24">24</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b74" href="#b74">74</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b87" href="#b87">87</a>. Therefore, more efforts should be dedicated to improve data collection and quality, and to make data better accessible for the region.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study includes the best available regional data (see 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">Supplementary Information</a>) and highlights, when necessary, gaps and difficulties encountered in the modelling process (see below). To account for the uncertainty around the model parameters, we applied a Monte Carlo routine to evaluate model outputs sensitivity (in our case for biomasses and model derived indicators) to data uncertainty. Considering data uncertainty in model development is critical if the purpose of modelling is to inform policy/management processes
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b6" href="#b6">6</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b27" href="#b27">27</a>. Still, the majority of available modelling tools lack an approach to take uncertainty of modelled data (both input and output) into account
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b8" href="#b8">8</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b88" href="#b88">88</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although some time series were not always well replicated and uncertainty analyses can be improved as higher quality data becomes available, our modelling exercise reproduced several surveyed datasets in a satisfactory way and, as such, it is to date the best available representation of historical trends for the Mediterranean Sea as a whole, and a first step towards the integrated and historical understanding of this complex ecosystem.</p>
</sec>
