<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Over the PILM (850‐1849), we found that the global terrestrial ecosystem carbon balance remained close to an equilibrium, with global NBP being close to zero at centennial timescales, which is mostly in agreement with estimates based on atmospheric 
 <sup class="sup">13</sup>C in CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>, which suggest a very small increase of only about 30 Pg C/ka between AD 755 and 1850 in land pools (Bauska et al., 
 <xref rid="jame20902-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). This equilibrium was preserved mainly because the carbon turnover rate of the global terrestrial ecosystem was not significantly reduced or enhanced from natural climate variability and external forcings for the PILM (Figure 
 <xref rid="jame20902-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3</xref>). Based on our theoretical framework for the variance of key components of the C cycle at different time‐scales (equations 
 <xref rid="jame20902-disp-0001" ref-type="disp-formula" class="xref">(1)</xref> and 
 <xref rid="jame20902-disp-0002" ref-type="disp-formula" class="xref">(2)</xref>; Figure 
 <xref rid="jame20902-fig-0009" ref-type="fig" class="xref">9</xref>a; Zhang et al., 
 <xref rid="jame20902-bib-0077" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2018</xref>), the CESM‐LME modeling results show the preindustrial dynamics of terrestrial carbon cycle; in particular, it was seen that variation in the terrestrial net C balance (i.e., NBP) is dominated by fluctuations in C input (i.e., NPP) on the interannual to decadal timescales, while the influence from output fluxes (i.e., RH+D) tends to increase with increasing period and becomes dominant at centennial timescales (100‐1,000 years). The D flux contributes relatively little to variability in NBP on centennial timescales, which mostly arose from early anthropogenic land use change. When the ecosystem C turnover remains steady on centennial timescales, variability in RH is mostly driven by variation in NPP via the contribution of plant litter carbon to the soil C pool.
</p>
