<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par20" class="p">These results did not include economic considerations, which could reduce the mitigation potential [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>] but do include estimates of transportation distances for the bioenergy scenario. Although beyond the scope of the current analyses, economic and socio-economic analyses should also be addressed to understand potential barriers to implementation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">6</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>]. Mitigation scenarios levels were considered to be feasible, but there are uncertainties about technical feasibility, regulatory barriers, and market barriers that were not considered. Forests provide a range of services and co-benefits, and forest managers are required to manage for multiple objectives, some of which could come into conflict with mitigation objectives and could limit the level of mitigation scenario implementation [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">30</xref>]. The mitigation scenarios considered in this analysis focused on harvesting activities, residue management and wood use, and did not consider activities which would impact growth and yield. Additional activities could be undertaken to enhance future growth which would enhance the forest sequestration potential [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">5</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>]. The 
 <italic class="italic">Higher Utilization</italic> scenario assumed that the same product mix could be achieved with the 5% incremental utilization rate, i.e. incremental harvest from a stand, although the incremental harvest could be of lower quality and produce more short-lived wood commodities. On the other hand, technological advances in building materials such as cross-laminated timber and other composite materials such as oriented strand board are enabling higher utilization rates.
</p>
