<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec1-ijerph-12-14994" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1. Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Public perceptions of climate change risk have primarily been explained by political and cultural worldviews, awareness of physical changes in the environment, and understanding of the scientific evidence [
  <a rid="B1-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-ijerph-12-14994">1</a>,
  <a rid="B2-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-ijerph-12-14994">2</a>]; the role of vulnerability in shaping people’s assessment of the threat has been less studied [
  <a rid="B3-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3-ijerph-12-14994">3</a>]. Indeed, whether vulnerability specifically due to health status influences individuals’ perceptions of their climate change risks has been little explored [
  <a rid="B2-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-ijerph-12-14994">2</a>], but is particularly of relevance for climate adaptation planning. Public health organizations have shown an increasing interest in communicating with vulnerable populations in order to promote successful adaptation strategies for these health threats [
  <a rid="B4-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-ijerph-12-14994">4</a>]. Indeed, the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC) established a Climate and Health Program in 2009 [
  <a rid="B5-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-ijerph-12-14994">5</a>]. Maryland participates in the CDC Climate-Ready States and Cities Initiative in which it is tasked with assessing state health vulnerabilities and potential interventions, developing and implementing a climate and health plan, and conducting ongoing activity evaluation.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate change both directly and indirectly affects human health [
  <a rid="B6-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6-ijerph-12-14994">6</a>,
  <a rid="B7-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-ijerph-12-14994">7</a>]. Direct impacts result in human injuries; illnesses and deaths related to extreme weather events and changes in weather patterns; rises in infectious diseases due to changes in vector-pathogen relations; and increased disease burdens from declines in water and air quality. Indirect impacts include impaired food security and nutrition as a result of changes in crop yields, as well as displacement and loss of livelihoods leading to negative health effects.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate change vulnerability represents the propensity to be adversely affected under these conditions of risk and can be deconstructed into three components: sensitivity, exposure, and the capacity to adapt [
  <a rid="B7-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-ijerph-12-14994">7</a>]. Populations vary in degree of vulnerability depending on these factors. Those with higher sensitivity include women, children, the elderly, and those with chronic illnesses and disability. Those in urban heat islands, floodplains, and coastal communities are at greater exposure, and socioeconomically disadvantaged groups may have both greater exposure and less capacity for adaptation [
  <a rid="B6-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6-ijerph-12-14994">6</a>,
  <a rid="B8-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8-ijerph-12-14994">8</a>,
  <a rid="B9-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9-ijerph-12-14994">9</a>,
  <a rid="B10-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10-ijerph-12-14994">10</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In 2014, a majority of Marylanders recognized that people with medical conditions (59%) and the elderly (55%) are very vulnerable to the potential health impacts of climate change; they were less likely to identify young children and people with low incomes as very vulnerable (42% and 36%, respectively) [
  <a rid="B11-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-ijerph-12-14994">11</a>]. Moreover, Marylanders were more likely to say that people in the United States generally are “very vulnerable” to the health effects of climate change (31%) or even people in Maryland (21%), than they themselves (11%) or those in their households (13%).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Public awareness and knowledge of climate health risks are an important component of climate adaptation [
  <a rid="B12-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12-ijerph-12-14994">12</a>,
  <a rid="B13-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13-ijerph-12-14994">13</a>]. Nevertheless, there has been little research on people’s perceptions of health risks from climate change either in the United States or abroad [
  <a rid="B14-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14-ijerph-12-14994">14</a>,
  <a rid="B15-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-ijerph-12-14994">15</a>,
  <a rid="B16-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16-ijerph-12-14994">16</a>,
  <a rid="B17-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17-ijerph-12-14994">17</a>,
  <a rid="B18-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-ijerph-12-14994">18</a>]. Surveys from the United States, Canada and Malta that assessed public understanding of the links between climate change and human health have found that less than half of American respondents believe that they themselves are at risk from climate impacts [
  <a rid="B18-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-ijerph-12-14994">18</a>,
  <a rid="B19-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-ijerph-12-14994">19</a>]; conversely, rates of concerned respondents are higher in Canada and Malta [
  <a rid="B19-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-ijerph-12-14994">19</a>]. The frequency of cited health impacts is greater for multiple choice responses or specific prompts than open-ended questions [
  <a rid="B14-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14-ijerph-12-14994">14</a>,
  <a rid="B18-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-ijerph-12-14994">18</a>,
  <a rid="B19-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-ijerph-12-14994">19</a>]. This suggests that although people believe climate change will cause declines in public health, it is not a highly salient issue.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The feeling of being at risk has long been known to be influenced by social vulnerability, especially gender and race [
  <a rid="B20-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-ijerph-12-14994">20</a>,
  <a rid="B21-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21-ijerph-12-14994">21</a>]. Previous research has operationalized social vulnerability as a combination of perceived social and economic discrimination, poor health, and reduced access to medical care [
  <a rid="B22-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-ijerph-12-14994">22</a>]. Most studies on the relationship between vulnerability and climate change risk perceptions have focused on the physical environment instead: direct experience of changes in weather and climate, and exposure to hazards based on location and current or projected conditions [
  <a rid="B3-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3-ijerph-12-14994">3</a>,
  <a rid="B23-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-ijerph-12-14994">23</a>]. Moreover, the results at times have been conflicting. Personal experiences of flood events and higher temperatures have been correlated with higher risk perceptions of climate change [
  <a rid="B24-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-ijerph-12-14994">24</a>,
  <a rid="B25-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25-ijerph-12-14994">25</a>], though not consistently [
  <a rid="B26-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26-ijerph-12-14994">26</a>,
  <a rid="B27-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27-ijerph-12-14994">27</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To our knowledge, the influence of health susceptibility on personal and household perceptions of climate change health risk has not been studied, particularly in combination with two of the most common climate impacts that vulnerable communities in the United States are likely to face: extreme heat in urban areas, and flooding [
  <a rid="B10-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10-ijerph-12-14994">10</a>]. In this study we hypothesize, based on previous literature, that general health risk perceptions, political ideology, and climate beliefs will strongly predict perceptions of climate change as a personal and household health threat. Furthermore, we pose two research questions:
  <div list-type="simple" class="list">
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>RQ
     <sub>1</sub>: Do measures of social vulnerability and health susceptibility explain unique variance in perceived vulnerability to the health effects of climate change above and beyond other known covariates?
    </p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>RQ
     <sub>2</sub>: Do measures of exposure to risk of flooding and urban heat explain unique variance in perceived vulnerability to the health effects of climate change above and beyond other known covariates?
    </p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To investigate the relationship between perceptions of personal and household climate health risk and vulnerability due to social status, health, and location, we employ data from a mail survey of more than 2000 Maryland residents. These results are paired with secondary data sources for 100-year floodplain designations and urban 
  <span class="italic">versus</span> rural locations as a proxy for higher temperatures due to heat island effects.
 </p>
</sec>
