<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec4-ijerph-12-14994" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4. Conclusions</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study finds that some populations at higher risk for health impacts associated with climate change, and greater exposure, already see themselves as more vulnerable than members of the public at large. Having one or more chronic medical conditions, being a member of a community of color (African American/black, Hispanic/Latino), location in a floodplain, and having less income are significant predictors of higher risk perceptions; being female is of near significance. This result aligns with previous research that has found that vulnerable members of society feel at greater risk to environmental threats [
  <a rid="B20-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-ijerph-12-14994">20</a>,
  <a rid="B21-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21-ijerph-12-14994">21</a>]. Indeed, those most at risk from climate change are generally those who are susceptible to any number of environmental and societal harms. Yet the finding is surprising for two reasons: (1) the effects of climate change are arguably more abstract and long-term compared to the more visible and immediate environmental hazards, such as natural disasters, chemical manufacturing, and nuclear power, which have been the focus of other studies; and (2) the effect of being vulnerable to climate health impacts remained identifiable, even when general health risk perceptions were held constant.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A cursory interpretation of current audiences developed to explain climate change beliefs, risk perceptions, and policy support would suggest that people who are most socially vulnerable are those who are also most unsure about the effects of climate change [
  <a rid="B46-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46-ijerph-12-14994">46</a>]. This study shows the need for a more nuanced understanding of that relationship. Some of the audiences most vulnerable to the health effects of climate change are less likely to say that they do not know whether they are vulnerable: women, African Americans; Hispanics and Latinos; and those with chronic disease or disability. At the same time, people who are higher income and education, with more knowledge of the health effects of climate change in Maryland—qualities typically related to lower social vulnerability—are also less likely to say that they don’t know.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Climate beliefs.</span> Our covariates, political ideology and general health risk perceptions, represent heuristics that influence people’s perceptions of vulnerability to the health effects of climate change, and in this case explained half (49%) of the explained variance. But cognitive factors—beliefs—explained another 45%. Climate change belief certainty and information about the potential health effects of climate change in Maryland were two of the largest standardized coefficients, along with general health risk perceptions. Education—considered under social vulnerability factors—also was a significant predictor of vulnerability beliefs, again demonstrating the importance of knowledge and information, though not in a direction that supports the social vulnerability thesis. Knowledge has been shown repeatedly to be a key component of perceptions of climate risk and even behavior [
  <a rid="B2-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-ijerph-12-14994">2</a>,
  <a rid="B51-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51-ijerph-12-14994">51</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Social vulnerability and health susceptibility.</span> The demographic and medical condition indicators of social vulnerability and health added 4% of explanatory power to the model. Being African-American was the characteristic of social vulnerability that most strongly influenced climate health risk perceptions. This aligns with previous research demonstrating substantial differences in risk perceptions between whites and non-whites, and especially white males and non-white females [
  <a rid="B21-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21-ijerph-12-14994">21</a>,
  <a rid="B22-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-ijerph-12-14994">22</a>]. Being of Hispanic or Latino ethnicity also was a significant predictor, as was being female, lower income and health-impaired from chronic disease or disability within the household. All of these conditions potentially describe conditions of perceived scarcity—monetary, health, security—that have been hypothesized to fundamentally affect people’s attention to risk and their subsequent decision-making [
  <a rid="B52-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B52-ijerph-12-14994">52</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Being elderly did not affect climate health risk perceptions, although the elderly are at particular risk from extreme heat [
  <a rid="B53-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53-ijerph-12-14994">53</a>]. Public opinion polls have shown few differences in age on climate change beliefs and risk perceptions; the elderly appear mildly less concerned than middle-aged populations [
  <a rid="B54-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B54-ijerph-12-14994">54</a>]. Previous work has shown that health risk perceptions of older people are elevated for conditions to which they believe they are particularly prone, such as cancer [
  <a rid="B55-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B55-ijerph-12-14994">55</a>]. Climate change-related health impacts may seem to be too far removed in the future for the elderly to find them of personal concern.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Exposure.</span> Both of the exposure variables—location in a floodplain or in an urban area (as a proxy for heat island effects)—accounted for only 2% of the variance in the final model. Location in a floodplain was a significant predictor, while urban location was not. While we did not measure experienced flood events or extreme heat, this result resembles the findings by Goebbert and colleagues that people’s perceptions of flooding are more likely to be accurate than their recollection of temperature, which is heavily influenced by the politicization of “global warming” [
  <a rid="B56-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B56-ijerph-12-14994">56</a>]. Other studies have found that people can make accurate judgments about temperature [
  <a rid="B57-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B57-ijerph-12-14994">57</a>]. The proxy nature of our variable—urban location—may have limited our ability to detect this effect.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Limitations.</span> The strengths of this study are in the sample’s wide representation of political beliefs and its use of secondary data in combination with survey responses. However, surveys often do not sufficiently reach individuals who are at higher levels of vulnerability [
  <a rid="B58-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B58-ijerph-12-14994">58</a>], and respondents are more likely to be civically engaged than those who do not participate [
  <a rid="B32-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32-ijerph-12-14994">32</a>]. These conditions reflect the limitations of this study as well. Moreover, the ecology of vulnerability is complex and threat-specific; the measures in this study reflect only broad indicators. The factors for extreme heat vulnerability among the socially vulnerable have been recently explored in detail, calling attention to the importance of social and environmental conditions as well as individual characteristics [
  <a rid="B53-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53-ijerph-12-14994">53</a>,
  <a rid="B59-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B59-ijerph-12-14994">59</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We speculate that something about the qualities of being vulnerable—due to social, health or location circumstance—makes people more concerned about climate change’s health effects to themselves and their households above and beyond their risk perceptions of flu epidemics, air pollution, chemicals, and polluted water. One possibility is that the amorphous and outsized nature of climate change’s threat—the level to which its effects are both unknown and highly dreaded [
  <a rid="B60-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B60-ijerph-12-14994">60</a>]—makes it distinct from other environmental threats, especially for people who already feel at risk. Further research should explore this hypothesis with these audiences because of the possibility that fear responses may impinge on successful adaptation efforts [
  <a rid="B61-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B61-ijerph-12-14994">61</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Even so, climate change beliefs—including respondents’ ability to identify localized effects of climate change on health—account for more of the variance in the public’s health risk perceptions than do vulnerability factors. This presents a dilemma to communicators as it suggests that while information about the risks of climate change can be valuable, when these messages are targeting vulnerable populations, their heightened sense of risk may cause these messages to backfire. In these groups, messages should perhaps instead focus on specific actions that can be taken to contribute to their sense of control over their health outcomes [
  <a rid="B61-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B61-ijerph-12-14994">61</a>]. The climate change health narratives provided by Ebi and colleagues may be one such approach [
  <a rid="B62-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B62-ijerph-12-14994">62</a>]. If the combination of dread and unknown risk is what makes climate change feel more risky than other environmental threats to these audiences, making the effects more “knowable” and within control may alleviate that fear.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As climate change health impacts, and the need for adaptive public health responses, increase, so too will the need to assist populations of increased vulnerability. Understanding how these groups interpret risks is more important than ever. We note that the effect sizes for indicators of vulnerability are comparatively small compared to those variables that receive more research interest in climate change social science. This suggests that their practical relevance may be limited, but surveys and public health communication often are challenged to reach individuals who are at increased vulnerability [
  <a rid="B58-ijerph-12-14994" ref-type="bibr" href="#B58-ijerph-12-14994">58</a>], so even a small effect may have important policy implications.
 </p>
</sec>
