<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The variability of the AML projections was disaggregated into three major components and the uncertainty originating from, 1) the different climate projections, 2) the inter-annual variability of the weather, and 3) the different milk loss calculation methods. These were estimated by using the coefficient of variation of the AML values. Despite the considerable inter-annual variability of the AML as well as the large differences between the climate projections, the variety of the calculation methods may introduce even larger uncertainty in the milk loss projections for the future. This finding is in line with previous climate change impact assessments. Inter-annual variability was predicted to increase slightly at higher temperatures (toward the end of the century) but this effect was generally less than inter-model variability [
 <xref rid="pone.0197076.ref059" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">59</xref>]. Model differences introduced more uncertainty in the climate change impact projections than the differences caused by the climate projections [
 <xref rid="pone.0197076.ref060" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">60</xref>]. This finding emphasizes the importance of using multi-model ensembles in order to provide robust projections [
 <xref rid="pone.0197076.ref061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">61</xref>]. Though they investigated global maize production, Bassu et al (2014) reported that only an ensemble of at least 8–10 models was able to simulate absolute yields accurately [
 <xref rid="pone.0197076.ref059" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">59</xref>]. Here we demonstrate that for the South-East of England (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0197076.g004" class="xref">Fig 4</xref>) this uncertainty was introduced by the selection of the daily or sub-daily AML calculation methods, where the sub-daily methods over-predicted heat stress days. Indeed, for current South-East of England conditions, the sub-daily methods predict 39 days of heat stress, while the daily step methods estimate 9 days (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0197076.g004" class="xref">Fig 4</xref>). The latter is perhaps closer to current British conditions, where heat stress is not generally considered a major issue.
</p>
