<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The malaria transmission cycle is a complex system with multiple non-linear and often interacting variables of climate change, environmental, biological and socio-economic influences thus, conceptualizing such a system is challenging. The cross-impact multiplication method (CIMM) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" class="xref">51</xref>] was used to undertake a structural analysis. The structural analysis method revealed key system components and interactions from a candidate set identified from the literature review and expert consultations and followed a four-step iterative process:
 <list list-type="alpha-lower" class="list">
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">Compilation of a candidate set of key variables from the literature review and expert consultations;</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">Description of the relationships between variables based on contextual knowledge and expert opinion. The degree of influence between variables was rated 0 if there was no evidence of 
    <italic class="italic">direct influence</italic> between two variables. Otherwise, the strength of the relationship was rated 1(low), 2 (medium), 3 (high) or 4 (potential);
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">Identification of key variables using the CIMM approach which calculates the intensity of influence and dependency between variables; and</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">The CIMM approach was also used to identify the relationships between the identified variables of the system through an analysis of the impact matrix by generating a map of direct influence, which separates the variables into four types according to degree of influence: (i) influential variables, which influence the system, but are not dependent on other variables; (ii) relay variables, which influence the system and are dependent on influential variables; (iii) dependent variables, which represent the system’s output variables and; (iv) autonomous variables, which are neither influential nor dependent and may or may not significantly affect the system depending on the strength of their relationships.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
