<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In responding to climate change impacts, many least developed countries including Malawi have developed policies and strategies to address climate change–related risks. Examples include National Adaptation Programmes of Actions (NAPAs) that provide a framework of adaptation programmes to ensure rural livelihoods security (Brown 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>:1–40; Government of Malawi 
 <xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2006</xref>:1-45; IPCC 
 <xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>:151). However, these NAPAs are inadequately designed and implemented (Brown 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>:1–40; Joshua, Jalloh &amp; Hachigonta 
 <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>:9). Additionally, National Adaptation Programmes have low local relevance. Climate change impacts can have spatial variations even within one country because of variations in vulnerability context as well as adaptive capacity. This article argues that effective adaptation can occur if interventions fit specific local conditions. Such interventions should therefore ideally be based on location-specific impacts of climate change, involving meaningful participation (that can influence decision making) of local stakeholders and are locally generated. ’Locally generated adaptation approaches and active participation of local actors bring relevance to climate change adaptation programmes’ (Joshua 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>:9). It is widely accepted that vulnerable communities have developed various adaptation strategies (Adger 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2003</xref>:179–195; IPCC 
 <xref rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>:151; Tompkins 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>:627). Such coping and adaptation strategies are also linked to a very large extent with their perceptions on climate change and its impacts (Kihupi, Chingonikaya &amp; Mahonge 
 <xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>:137–147). The strategies include changes in farming calendar, crop varieties and integration of crop and livestock diversification (Action Aid 
 <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2006</xref>:1–8). However, many rural communities in sub-Saharan Africa have faced challenges in selecting appropriate adaptation strategies in response to climate change impacts including high interannual rainfall variability and unpredictability of rainfall patterns. In the Sahel region, such strategies include adoption of drought-tolerant crops such as sorghum, staggered sowing and use of hand-dug well for irrigation during prolonged drought periods. However, it was noted that the farmers in the Sahel were often not aware of the overall scale of climate change and that their adaptation practices may not be very effective with current climate change impacts, thereby threatening their ability to sustain their family’s livelihood (Deutsche Gesellschaft für Internationale Zusammenarbeit 
 <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>:46). In semi-arid areas of Tanzania, community-based adaptation strategies included fast-maturing crop varieties, buying supplementary foods, increasing wetland cultivation and livestock keeping, water harvesting, practicing mixed cropping and increased emphasis on small stocks (Kangalawe &amp; Lyimo 
 <xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>:266–278). The study by Kangalawe and Lyimo (
 <xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>:266–278) observed that the vulnerable communities often implemented these adaptation strategies on an ad hoc basis with limited planning. In addition, they further observed that despite their strong potential, if well implemented, there is need for investigating their complementarity as none of these can single-handedly be successful in the adaptation process. Just as in the case of the Sahel, a lack of information, education and a communication strategy on climate change issues affecting rural community livelihoods in the semi-arid areas of Tanzania were also highlighted. This also remains a key policy challenge in many developing countries. The study therefore attempts to address some of these gaps.
</p>
