<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" class="supplementary-material">
 <p class="p">Supplementary material for this article is available at 
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://advances.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/5/8/eaax1396/DC1" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://advances.sciencemag.org/cgi/content/full/5/8/eaax1396/DC1</ext-link>
 </p>
 <p class="p">Fig. S1. Five-year moving average of VPD.</p>
 <p class="p">Fig. S2. Spatial distributions of the difference of VPD trends (kPa year
  <sup class="sup">−1</sup>) before and after TP years.
 </p>
 <p class="p">Fig. S3. Spatial pattern of VPD changes between 1982–1986 and 2011–2015 derived from CRU dataset.</p>
 <p class="p">Fig. S4. Interannual variability of SVP (red dots and lines), AVP (green dots and lines), and air temperature (
  <italic class="italic">T</italic>
  <sub class="sub">a</sub>; blue dots and lines) derived from four datasets.
 </p>
 <p class="p">Fig. S5. Global mean LAI and linear trends during 1982–2015.</p>
 <p class="p">Fig. S6. Differences of LAI trends over the globally vegetated areas between before and after TP years.</p>
 <p class="p">Fig. S7. Model validation of random forest models for simulating NDVI.</p>
 <p class="p">Fig. S8. Environmental regulations on long-term changes of global NDVI.</p>
 <p class="p">Fig. S9. Correlations of LUE and VPD at the different temperature ranges taking DE-Tha site as an example.</p>
 <p class="p">Fig. S10. Correlations between VPD and tree-ring width.</p>
 <p class="p">Fig. S11. Comparison on changes of global mean GPP trend simulated by ecosystem models.</p>
 <p class="p">Fig. S12. Projected future changes in VPD.</p>
 <p class="p">Fig. S13. Validation of EC-LUE model.</p>
 <p class="p">Table S1. Climate and satellite datasets used in this study.</p>
 <p class="p">Table S2. Responses of GPP simulated by EC-LUE, MODIS, and TRENDY models to climate variables, satellite-based NDVI and fPAR, and atmospheric CO
  <sub class="sub">2</sub> concentration.
 </p>
 <p class="p">Table S3. Name, location, and durations of the study EC sites used for revised EC-LUE model calibration and validation.</p>
 <p class="p">Table S4. Correlations between VPD and LUE at different temperature ranges.</p>
 <p class="p">Table S5. CMIP5 models used to estimate VPD from 1850 to 2100.</p>
 <p class="p">Table S6. Correlation matrixes for global VPD simulated by the six CMIP5 ESMs and four historical datasets (CRU, ERA-Interim, HadISDH, and MERRA).</p>
 <p class="p">Table S7. Model parameters of EC-LUE for different vegetation types.</p>
</supplementary-material>
