<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">For adaptive capacity (the ability of systems, institutions, people, and other organisms to adjust to potential damage, to take advantage of opportunities or to respond to consequences [
 <xref rid="pone.0190808.ref059" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">59</xref>]), the main focus was governance and social capital. Governance and local institutions are considered essential to reducing vulnerability and enhancing adaptation at the local level, since they help to shape the risks associated with climate impacts and to define the degree to which individuals will respond to the impact, including the collective scope [
 <xref rid="pone.0190808.ref060" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">60</xref>]. This aspect was evaluated by 1) the municipal competence to promote economic development in key areas such as health, education and employment, with regards to quality and access, and whose performance has been measured since 2008 by the FIRJAN Municipal Development Index; and 2) the presence of public institutions of security, risk management and health that could provide support and actions to reduce harm in the face of the expected negative impacts of climate change. As for social capital, its ability to increase the resilience of populations is well known, either through the proximity of different groups, closer ties between individuals who share a social identity or through networks of trust that are established between the different levels of authority [
 <xref rid="pone.0190808.ref061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">61</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0190808.ref063" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">63</xref>]. For this, a proxy measure for the possibility of citizen participation in the political process was used, namely the representation on councils or consortia. The variables used here are inversely related to vulnerability, since municipalities with better levels of governance and socio-institutional arrangements are better able to deal with climate impacts, thus reducing vulnerability.
</p>
