<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The estimated global NBP since the 1960s (from modeling and carbon inventories) shows significant influences of both natural variability and anthropogenic forcings, as can be seen in the long‐term trend and the residual variability (e.g., Piao et al., 
 <xref rid="jame20902-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Schimel et al., 
 <xref rid="jame20902-bib-0060" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Shevliakova et al., 
 <xref rid="jame20902-bib-0064" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Zhang et al., 
 <xref rid="jame20902-bib-0077" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2018</xref>). One complicating factor is that the superposition of natural and anthropogenic influences on the terrestrial carbon cycle makes it difficult to disentangle those two influences, and the more readily available instrumental observations and model simulations over the last 100 years are too short to draw strong conclusions on multidecadal and longer‐term variability (Lehner et al., 
 <xref rid="jame20902-bib-0045" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). Therefore, there is a need to study the causes of variability in global NBP under the climate state without the strong anthropogenic forcings (i.e., the background climate state). During the 1,000 years ending in 1850, the variability of NBP was governed by internal variability of carbon uptake and losses and their responses to natural external forcings (e.g., volcanic eruptions and solar activity) with a limited contribution of early land‐use change to CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> and CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> (Ferretti et al., 
 <xref rid="jame20902-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2005</xref>; MacFarling Meure et al., 
 <xref rid="jame20902-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>). The preindustrial last millennium (PILM, 850‐1849) thus constitutes a test‐bed to characterize multiannual timescales of variability in global NBP and its driving mechanisms without the complications of anthropogenic influences. This allows us to study the timescale‐dependent response of the land carbon cycle to natural climate variability and external natural forcings, and how they together influenced the long‐term variability of atmospheric CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> levels in the past 1,000 years.
</p>
