<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">This mode of security politics is arguably more readily recognizable in the climate policy domain than the modes of either international conflict or securitization. Climate change as an ‘emergency’ is in a way a curious idea given the slow and long-term nature of the issue. Risk management involving reducing emissions of greenhouse gasses tackles the root cause of climate change, while adaptation tackles vulnerabilities. Mitigation is a risk-security policy since it seeks to alter the conditions that facilitate what is considered directly dangerous, such as extreme weather events. Adaptation limits underlying exposure to danger through ‘enhanced preparedness and resilience’ (
 <xref rid="bibr79-0967010617704142" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Oels, 2013</xref>: 25). This means that climate politics reaches into myriad fora and in some ways changes or expands the scope of governance of societies. For Foucauldian scholars, climate politics has even fostered a form of carbon ‘governmentality’: the regimenting and cataloguing of activities, people, and substances for climate purposes bringing a new dimension of life under governmental control and generating new subjectivities and units such as carbon footprints (see, for example, 
 <xref rid="bibr101-0967010617704142" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Stripple and Bulkeley, 2013</xref>). The very emergence of climate change as a space amenable to governance was in turn dependent upon the emergence of earth systems sciences (
 <xref rid="bibr62-0967010617704142" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lövbrand et al., 2009</xref>) and the gradual development of a ‘vast machine’ of climate measurement and calculation in the form of ice-core drills, satellites, indexes, models, academic disciplines, and national and global institutions (
 <xref rid="bibr29-0967010617704142" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Corry, 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bibr37-0967010617704142" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Edwards, 2010</xref>).
</p>
