<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2dot1-animals-09-00141" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1. Study Area</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The studies were undertaken in a lowland area of central Poland in the area of the Experimental Forest Station of Warsaw University of Life Sciences in the vicinity of Rogów village (51° 49’ 17,98 N, 19° 53’ 54, 15 E). This region is affected by the mild oceanic climate of Western Europe and the harsh and dry continental climate of Eastern Europe and Asia. The duration of the growing season is approximately 210 days; the total precipitation is 600 mm per year; and the mean ambient temperature ranges from –4°C in January to +18°C in July. The study area comprised ca. 105 km
  <span class="sup">2</span> of field and forest mosaic. Forests accounted for 25% of the area (approx. 2400 ha) and formed seven complexes (70–1000 ha) (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="animals-09-00141-f001" href="#animals-09-00141-f001">Figure 1</a>). The remaining area included arable lands (59%), orchards (5%), grasslands (5%), and scattered buildings [
  <a rid="B33-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33-animals-09-00141">33</a>]. Most of the forests (83% of their area) grew on rich, moderately moist soil. The main forest-forming species was Scots pine, 
  <span class="italic">Pinus sylvestris</span>, but its share has dropped in the last decades as the species structure of stands has adjusted to habitat types. On the contrary, the share of larch 
  <span class="italic">Larix</span> spp. and broadleaved species rose. Also, the share of older stands, which are best for goshawks to build their nests, has increased in recent decades (
  <a rid="animals-09-00141-t001" ref-type="table" href="#animals-09-00141-t001">Table 1</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The mean stand age and stand volume has increased in recent decades, and in January 2009, it reached 71 years and 281 m
  <span class="sup">3</span>/ha, as compared to 51 years and 213 m
  <span class="sup">3</span>/ha in 1978. The annual harvest in the years 2014–2017 was rather low (4.9 m
  <span class="sup">3</span>/ha) [
  <a rid="B34-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34-animals-09-00141">34</a>]. 
 </p>
</sec>
