<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2dot2-animals-09-00141" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2. Inventory of Goshawk Population and Measurements of Nesting Trees</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Each year (2011–2018, January–March), all known nests were visited in all seven forest complexes. Courtship displays, as well as the presence of single birds, were noted. From the beginning of April to early May, newly built nests were searched by two people equipped with binoculars (10 × 42) and handheld transceivers, walking 50–200 m apart, depending on the stand type and age and visibility. All stands, except areas with newly planted trees and sapling stands, were searched. After the breeding season (in autumn), areas where nests might have been missed (i.e., where calls of adult or young birds were heard during the breeding season) were checked again. All nests that were located were recorded on the map of stands (1:10,000) and recorded on a GPS receiver (Garmin 62sc, Garmin 62sc, Garmin International, Inc., Olathe, KS).</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All occupied nests were visited in June and July to estimate the number of fledglings. The reasons for brood loss were determined when possible. The criteria for breeding were similar to the previous periods (1982–1992 and 2001–2003) and were as follow: (i) mating behavior (calls and flights of two birds) in the vicinity of a new/rebuilt nest, (ii) incubating a female on a nest/remnants of goshawk eggs below the new/rebuilt nests, and (iii) the presence of chicks and fledglings on the/next to the nest or their remnants in the vicinity of a nesting tree. On this basis, we calculated the number of nesting attempts per one nest, i.e., the number of breeding cases divided by the number of nests used for breeding. The breeding success (percent of pairs that successfully produced at least one fledgling as referred to all breeding pairs) and the number of fledglings were calculated, both for successful pairs and for all known breeding pairs.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Measurements of the nesting trees were completed in November and December. The tree species were determined, and the height of the nest placement and the tree diameter at a 1.3 m height were measured. The altimeter SILVA Clino Master, Spencer Loggers Tape, and caliper Haglof Mantax Precision were used.</p>
</sec>
