<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2dot3-animals-09-00141" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3. Diet Composition</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Diet composition was assessed on the basis of an analysis of the plucking remains, pellets, and other prey remains and were collected on average every two weeks (from April to July) in the vicinity of nests (50 m radius). For each nest, we pooled all prey remains collected during the visits in one breeding season. In the laboratory, prey remains were systematically assigned with the aid of keys [
  <a rid="B35-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35-animals-09-00141">35</a>,
  <a rid="B36-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36-animals-09-00141">36</a>,
  <a rid="B37-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37-animals-09-00141">37</a>,
  <a rid="B38-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38-animals-09-00141">38</a>,
  <a rid="B39-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39-animals-09-00141">39</a>]. Furthermore, collections of feathers and skulls were used for comparison. In some cases, a histological analysis of the hair was performed [
  <a rid="B40-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40-animals-09-00141">40</a>]. Bird presence was detected mostly on the basis of feathers from plucking sites, while pellets were used mainly to detect other prey. We tried to avoid the double counting of prey detected with the two methods at one nest, i.e., we counted birds from pellets only in cases when we found bird remnants (mainly skulls) of species that were not detected on the basis of feathers from plucking sites. The mean prey body mass was adopted on the basis of the literature [
  <a rid="B35-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35-animals-09-00141">35</a>,
  <a rid="B41-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41-animals-09-00141">41</a>,
  <a rid="B42-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42-animals-09-00141">42</a>,
  <a rid="B43-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43-animals-09-00141">43</a>], and the body mass of small rodents was assessed during live-trapping undertaken every year in the same study area [
  <a rid="B44-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44-animals-09-00141">44</a>]. For bigger animals (assumingly eaten as carrion), the mean daily food requirement (200 g) was adopted as consumed biomass, while for insects, 1 g was adopted as a body mass for all species. The diet composition was presented as the share of a given taxon in a total number of prey items or consumed biomass. 
 </p>
</sec>
