<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec4-animals-09-00141" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4. Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our study showed that the goshawk population decrease observed in central Poland in the last few years (2011–2018) was combined with a forced diet shift, as a response to changes in anthropogenic prey (poultry and domestic pigeons) availability. A high share of such food was typical for central Poland populations of the species in the 1980s; for instance, in Kampinos National Park, domestic pigeons and poultry accounted for 55% of prey items [
  <a rid="B58-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B58-animals-09-00141">58</a>]. Studies done in natural forest complexes in northeastern Poland showed a much lower share of anthropogenic food or its absence; instead, birds preyed mainly on jays, thrushes 
  <span class="italic">Turdus</span> spp., and woodpeckers [
  <a rid="B42-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42-animals-09-00141">42</a>,
  <a rid="B59-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B59-animals-09-00141">59</a>]. However, the density of goshawks in such habitats was much lower (in the Białowieża Primeval Forest, it was 10.8 pairs/100 km
  <span class="sup">2</span>, [
  <a rid="B42-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42-animals-09-00141">42</a>]) than originally recorded in our study area in the 1980s [
  <a rid="B19-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-animals-09-00141">19</a>]). Domestic pigeons were also an important food source for these birds in northwestern Spain (2008–2011), accounting for 17% of prey and 25% of the consumed biomass [
  <a rid="B60-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B60-animals-09-00141">60</a>]. Similar in our case, when the availability of domestic pigeons dropped (by 71% between 1983 and 2012, [
  <a rid="B60-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B60-animals-09-00141">60</a>]), a decrease in their share in the goshawk diet and an increase in the consumption of jays was recorded. However, even afterward this shift, the population density was very high at 15.8 nesting territories/100 km
  <span class="sup">2</span> [
  <a rid="B21-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21-animals-09-00141">21</a>]. The goshawk diet can vary, although it is usually bird-dominated, with medium-sized birds such as thrushes, pigeons, and corvids (i.e., rooks and jays) playing an important role [
  <a rid="B27-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27-animals-09-00141">27</a>,
  <a rid="B49-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49-animals-09-00141">49</a>,
  <a rid="B50-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B50-animals-09-00141">50</a>,
  <a rid="B51-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51-animals-09-00141">51</a>]. The regional variety can be recorded; for example, in the diet of goshawks from the Iberian Peninsula reptiles are frequently consumed [
  <a rid="B46-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46-animals-09-00141">46</a>,
  <a rid="B60-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B60-animals-09-00141">60</a>]. Goshawks may prey on medium-sized mammals when they are abundant. In Gotland, a Baltic island, goshawks preyed mainly on rabbits, corvids, and thrushes, where rabbits were available in high density. With a low rabbit density, goshawks preyed on corvids, thrushes, and other birds, but the rabbit share was negligible. In the low rabbit abundance area, the density of goshawk was twice as low [
  <a rid="B61-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B61-animals-09-00141">61</a>]. Similarly, in northeastern Spain, the food base for goshawks were European rabbits and red-legged partridge 
  <span class="italic">Alectoris rufa</span>, while domestic pigeons accounted for only a small share of prey items. When the rabbit population crashed, goshawks preyed more intensively on the red-legged partridge [
  <a rid="B46-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46-animals-09-00141">46</a>]. In boreal forest, goshawks prey mainly on forest grouses and mountain hare 
  <span class="italic">Lepus timidus</span> [
  <a rid="B28-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-animals-09-00141">28</a>,
  <a rid="B47-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B47-animals-09-00141">47</a>,
  <a rid="B62-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B62-animals-09-00141">62</a>]. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To our knowledge, only in our study area in the 1980s was such a high share of poultry recorded [
  <a rid="B23-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-animals-09-00141">23</a>]. This was probably due to a specific situation in farming at this time. During the communist years in Poland (1945–1989), people suffered from a shortage of food, mainly meat. Central (state-governed) food production was insufficient, while individual farmers could not legally sell their products and instead were obliged to sell them to state purchase points. Meat (in any form) was hardly available in shops, and to buy it, special tokens were needed. Illegal meat trading was severely punished (in extreme cases with the threat of the death penalty). In this situation, people living on farmland (and to some extent in cities) kept poultry (mainly hens), rabbits, and pigeons as a source of meat (breeding of these species for personal use was not limited or controlled). The breeding of race or fancy pigeons was also a popular hobby. Most farms kept a flock of hens, while in each village, a few large pigeon lofts were present. Birds (during the daytime) wandered/flew around farmsteads unprotected from raptors. As a result, they became a staple food for goshawks in farmland areas [
  <a rid="B23-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-animals-09-00141">23</a>,
  <a rid="B58-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B58-animals-09-00141">58</a>]. The situation changed after 1989, when the communist regime collapsed and the food supply became unlimited. As a result, poultry or pigeon production became less important. Small-scale poultry farming was replaced by industrial chicken houses, with thousands of birds, yet these were completely unavailable to goshawks. Additionally, the bird flu outbreak in the years 2006–2007 resulted in strict procedures around domestic bird keeping, in which birds were required to stay in enclosures with no contact with wild birds. Moreover, in the last 30 years, many farms were abandoned (with people migrating to cities) as farmers often found employment elsewhere and some of the farmsteads are used as summer houses now. These factors all resulted in a sharp decrease in food availability for goshawks. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although in the previous study periods no monitoring of availability of anthropogenic food was conducted, small-scale poultry and pigeon farming was very popular and did not seem to decrease [
  <a rid="B19-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-animals-09-00141">19</a>]. At the same time, goshawks were persecuted by farmers who perceived them as pests and tried to limit their population illegally (i.e., by cutting nesting trees, bird trapping, and shooting). For example, in Kampinos National Park near the study area in central Poland, up to 20% of nests were damaged each year [
  <a rid="B63-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B63-animals-09-00141">63</a>]. Ornithologists claimed that this persecution was a severe threat which may lead to the extinction of local populations [
  <a rid="B4-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-animals-09-00141">4</a>]. Nevertheless, in our study area, this could not have been very efficient given the high reproductive success of the population at that time [
  <a rid="B19-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-animals-09-00141">19</a>]. The population decrease observed in 2001–2003 coincided with socioeconomic changes in the Polish farmlands (and the consequent decreased availability of anthropogenic food); however, a limited access to supplementary foods (i.e., small game) could also have played a role. As it was shown earlier, goshawks can adapt to prey availability changes by switching to alternative food sources [
  <a rid="B46-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46-animals-09-00141">46</a>,
  <a rid="B60-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B60-animals-09-00141">60</a>,
  <a rid="B61-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B61-animals-09-00141">61</a>]. In the case of our study area, however, the possibility of doing so was limited. In the last two decades a sharp increase in red fox 
  <span class="italic">Vulpes vulpes</span> numbers was recorded in central Poland [
  <a rid="B64-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B64-animals-09-00141">64</a>] and across the whole country [
  <a rid="B65-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B65-animals-09-00141">65</a>]. This resulted in a crash of small game abundance, related also to agriculture intensification [
  <a rid="B30-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30-animals-09-00141">30</a>,
  <a rid="B56-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B56-animals-09-00141">56</a>,
  <a rid="B66-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B66-animals-09-00141">66</a>]. As a result, goshawks lost their potential alternative prey source (i.e., pheasant, grey partridge, brown hare, and European rabbit). In central Poland, there are no forest grouses (i.e., western capercaillie 
  <span class="italic">Tetrao urogallus</span>, black grouse 
  <span class="italic">Tetrao tetrix</span>, and hazel grouse 
  <span class="italic">Tetrastes bonasia</span>) which contribute to a food base for goshawks in northern Europe [
  <a rid="B48-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B48-animals-09-00141">48</a>,
  <a rid="B62-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B62-animals-09-00141">62</a>,
  <a rid="B67-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B67-animals-09-00141">67</a>]. As our study showed, the density of other alternative prey (i.e., most corvid species) was relatively low. Instead, goshawks preyed more heavily on jays and wood pigeons, whose abundance rose in the last decades across the whole of Poland [
  <a rid="B12-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12-animals-09-00141">12</a>]. It seems that farmers have now stopped persecuting goshawks, as we recorded no cases of nesting tree cutting, yet this has not counterbalanced the food base loss. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Additionally, predators do not seem to be the reason for the goshawk population decrease, as occurred in northeastern USA [
  <a rid="B28-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-animals-09-00141">28</a>]. Goshawks may be killed by martens (
  <span class="italic">Martes foina</span> and 
  <span class="italic">M. martes</span>); however, their abundance in the study area was stable over the last 40 years [
  <a rid="B44-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44-animals-09-00141">44</a>], and we detected no such cases in the last study period (2011–2018). Another potential threat may be predation from the white-tailed eagle (
  <span class="italic">Haliaeetus albicilla</span>), two pairs of which nested in the study area [
  <a rid="B68-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B68-animals-09-00141">68</a>], yet interactions between the two species were never recorded in our study. All identified reasons for the brood loss were connected to unfavourable weather conditions (nest falling down due to heavy winds or a heavy snowfall during below zero (°C) temperatures in April/May). According to some authors, the forest management practices may affect goshawk population negatively [
  <a rid="B6-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6-animals-09-00141">6</a>,
  <a rid="B15-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-animals-09-00141">15</a>,
  <a rid="B16-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16-animals-09-00141">16</a>,
  <a rid="B69-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B69-animals-09-00141">69</a>,
  <a rid="B70-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B70-animals-09-00141">70</a>], yet others have shown that goshawks can successfully nest in managed forests [
  <a rid="B45-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B45-animals-09-00141">45</a>], artificial intensive forest plantations [
  <a rid="B71-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B71-animals-09-00141">71</a>], or even in urbanized areas [
  <a rid="B72-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B72-animals-09-00141">72</a>]. However, the forests in our study area have undergone rather positive changes in the last 40 years: The forest cover has remained stable (or even increased slightly due to land abandonment and natural succession as a result of changes in farming practices after 1989) and increased in the mean age of stands as determined by the share of stands in the highest class ages. In the 2011–2018 period, a nesting tree was cut down by foresters only once, and it happened outside of the breeding season. In spring, the affected birds built a new nest 100 m further away and bred successfully. A factor that should be noted is that the number of breeding attempts per one nest was higher than in the 1980s, which indicates that disturbances from local farmers or foresters are probably lower now. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The birds we studied appear to have adapted to changes in the forest structure. In the second half of the XIX and in the beginning of the XX century, mainly Scots pine was planted in rich forest habitats in the forests in our study area, as it was the most profitable species. In the last 40 years, a systematic decrease in the share of this species in stands as a result of stand reconstruction has been recorded [
  <a rid="B73-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B73-animals-09-00141">73</a>]. As a result, goshawks built their nests on larches more frequently, while pines were chosen less frequently than in the 1980s. With the higher mean stand age birds could place their nests higher and on trees that are older and larger in diameter. As such, trees (especially larch) give a more solid base for the nest; this may be the other reason for a given nest being used for a longer period of time than in the 1980s.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The breeding parameters used in this study were similar to those obtained for farmland of western Poland (2001–2002), where the mean number of juveniles per breeding pair was 1.4 and per successful pair was 2.0 and the breeding success was 72% [
  <a rid="B20-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-animals-09-00141">20</a>]. Similar results come from north Wisconsin in the USA; the mean number of young fledged per active nest was 1.6 and per successful nest was 2.1, and the breeding success was 73% [
  <a rid="B28-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-animals-09-00141">28</a>]. In northeastern Poland in the Białowieża Primeval Forest, productivity was low at just 1.1 juveniles per breeding pair [
  <a rid="B74-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B74-animals-09-00141">74</a>]. In the more transformed habitat of the Augustów Primeval Forest, the breeding parameters were much higher: 1.9 juveniles per breeding pair and 2.7 per successful pair [
  <a rid="B59-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B59-animals-09-00141">59</a>]. Nevertheless, the highest productivity per successful pair was recorded in central Poland in Kampinos National Park, where the birds produced on average 3.3 juveniles [
  <a rid="B63-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B63-animals-09-00141">63</a>], in a population feeding heavily on domestic pigeons [
  <a rid="B58-animals-09-00141" ref-type="bibr" href="#B58-animals-09-00141">58</a>]. 
 </p>
</sec>
