<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec0010" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <p id="par0460" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This frame of reference is structured following the framework of 
  <a rid="bib0135" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0135">Bull et al. (2015)</a> who demonstrated the approach in the context of biodiversity offsets for the residual ecological impacts of oil and gas extraction in Uzbekistan. We adapted the framework slightly to fit the case study, e.g. we focused on a species target, not a habitat target.
 </p>
 <sec id="sec0015" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Brief recent history</div>
  <p id="par0465" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">First, we took a historical perspective and compiled the key institutional, social, economic and environmental events in the recent history of Bangladesh. We selected these events according to their potential direct or indirect relevance to the hilsa fishery, which we established through literature review and key informant interviews (
   <a rid="bib0085" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0085">Bladon, 2016</a>). The resultant figure (
   <a rid="fig0005" ref-type="fig" href="#fig0005">Fig. 1</a>) provides a timeline that can be used for reference throughout the results section. 
   <a rid="bib0135" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0135">Bull et al. (2015)</a> set the context of their frame of reference with 100 years of history, since this is approximately how long Uzbekistan had existed as a defined international entity. We therefore restricted our analysis of Bangladesh to the years since its independence in 1971 – approximately 50 years of history.
   <div id="fig0005" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Timeline of key institutional, social, economic, and environmental events in the recent history of Bangladesh classified by potential direct and indirect relevance for hilsa. BFDC = Bangladesh Fisheries Development Corporation; BFRI = Bangladesh Fisheries Research Institute; BNP = Bangladesh Nationalist Party; HFMAP = Hilsa Fishery Management Action Plan; BOBLME = Bay of Bengal Large Marine Ecosystem; IIED = International Institute for Environment and Development; BCCSAP = Bangladesh Climate Change Strategy and Action Plan. Cyclones, famines and other natural disasters are not presented here because of their high frequency. Extra details can be found in mmc2 (in Supplementary material).</p>
    </div>
    <span id="at0005" class="alt-text">Fig. 1</span>
    <div xlink:href="gr1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec0020" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Frame of reference</div>
  <p id="par0470" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To develop the frame of reference, we explicitly considered trends in potential physical, social, economic, and institutional drivers of ecological change in the hilsa fishery, before exploring trends in hilsa abundance and distribution – scanning the available literature and analysing secondary data compiled from published literature, online sources, and collaborators at the Bangladesh Department of Fisheries (DoF). This allowed us to establish a current baseline for the hilsa fishery, structured by each of the four categories in our framework and presented in the context of historical change over the last 50 years.</p>
  <p id="par0475" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on expectations formed through this analysis, we developed a conceptual map of the potential interactions between these drivers, within and between categories. We outlined the key expected interactions between hilsa and drivers of change (i.e. those most relevant to the sustainability of the hilsa fishery) and created two potential counterfactuals, consisting of projections based on these trends and interactions. Together, the baseline and counterfactuals form the frame of reference. Various potential counterfactuals could be projected from the trends presented in this study. We chose two feasible extremes to illustrate the range of potential outcomes, representing the ‘most desirable’ and ‘least desirable’ scenarios from the perspective of the sustainability of the fishery. Although this entailed making an implicit value judgement about what is and is not desirable for the hilsa fishery, it also allowed us to make our assumptions explicit. We interrogated the differences between the two potential counterfactuals to identify outstanding areas of uncertainty and their associated management implications. Finally, we highlighted information needs to improve the robustness of the frame of reference as a tool for action and intervention evaluation.</p>
  <sec id="sec0025" class="sec">
   <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2.1</span>
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Selection of potential drivers of change</div>
   <p id="par0480" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on our understanding of hilsa biology, and that of similar species, we identified factors that are known to or would be expected to a) directly affect hilsa populations, and b) indirectly affect hilsa populations. This selection process relied on extensive literature review and interviews with key stakeholders (
    <a rid="bib0085" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0085">Bladon, 2016</a>). For each potential driver, we reviewed the literature and assessed secondary datasets for trends, conducting statistical analysis where possible. Here we provide a brief justification for selection of drivers in each category.
   </p>
   <sec id="sec0030" class="sec">
    <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2.1.1</span>
    <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Physical drivers</div>
    <p id="par0485" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The life history of hilsa is known to be influenced by environmental conditions including water salinity, turbidity, flow, temperature, pH, dissolved O
     <span class="sup">2</span>, and phytoplankton availability (
     <a rid="bib0020" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0020">Ahsan et al., 2014</a>; 
     <a rid="bib0450" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0450">Rahman et al., 2012a</a>). We therefore identified key physical drivers that have been linked to general fish abundance and distribution, to changes in those environmental conditions, or directly to the abundance and distribution of hilsa. These drivers were: climate change, water diversion activities, forest cover, and pollution (see mmc1 in Supplementary material).
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec id="sec0035" class="sec">
    <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2.1.2</span>
    <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Social drivers</div>
    <p id="par0490" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We identified human population and poverty to be drivers of change in the hilsa fishery (see mmc1 in Supplementary material). Human population size influences the extent of fishing pressure in Bangladesh, because capture fisheries are essential for livelihood support and food security (
     <a rid="bib0070" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0070">Belton et al., 2014</a>; 
     <a rid="bib0195" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0195">FAO, 2014</a>). Human population size also influences the extent of development and infrastructure, including agriculture and aquaculture, which place pressure on hilsa habitat (
     <a rid="bib0110" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0110">BOBLME, 2011</a>). In hilsa fishing areas, low income is associated with fishing juvenile hilsa (known in Bangladesh as 
     <span class="italic">jatka</span>) and with strong fishing dependence, which is characterised by illegal fishing and lack of other livelihood activities (
     <a rid="bib0100" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0100">Bladon et al., 2018</a>).
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec id="sec0040" class="sec">
    <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2.1.3</span>
    <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Economic drivers</div>
    <p id="par0495" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We identified the primary economic activities in Bangladesh, and those which are fast-growing or being explored, and assessed trends in these activities. All of these activities are relevant to the hilsa fishery through the impacts of livelihood availability and wealth on fishing pressure (
     <a rid="bib0100" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0100">Bladon et al., 2018</a>). Some of them also have direct or indirect environmental impacts on hilsa populations: agriculture and aquaculture can affect hilsa habitat through eutrophication (
     <a rid="bib0110" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0110">BOBLME, 2011</a>): factories can contaminate rivers (
     <a rid="bib0325" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0325">Karn and Harada, 2001</a>); and mechanised vessels, shipbuilding, ship breaking, and oil and gas extractive industries can pollute coastal waters (
     <a rid="bib0150" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0150">Chowdhury et al., 2017</a>; 
     <a rid="bib0275" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0275">Hossain et al., 2016</a>). Because of the direct impact of exploitation on hilsa abundance, we focused largely on bioeconomic trends in the fishing industry, looking for trends in commercial catch per unit effort (CPUE) and economic value in the hilsa fishery.
    </p>
   </sec>
   <sec id="sec0045" class="sec">
    <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2.1.4</span>
    <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Institutional drivers</div>
    <p id="par0500" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The effectiveness of fisheries management is a crucial determinant of sustainable fisheries. Management effectiveness depends on a range of factors, including: a robust scientific basis for management recommendations, transparency in turning recommendations into policy, and capacity to enforce and ensure compliance with regulations. We reviewed the current national institutional and legislative context of fisheries management, exploring how it has changed in recent history, with a focus on hilsa fishery management. We also evaluated the current institutional framework, with respect to scientific rigor, capacity, and transparency.</p>
   </sec>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec0050" class="sec">
   <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2.2</span>
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hilsa trends</div>
   <p id="par0505" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although categorised as a species of least concern (
    <a rid="bib0210" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0210">Freyhof, 2014</a>), hilsa – like many other shads – are poorly understood, particularly in their marine phase (
    <a rid="bib0085" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0085">Bladon, 2016</a>). We explored trends in abundance and distribution of hilsa by compiling all available information on the key rates that partially determine this abundance and distribution (movement, reproduction, growth, and mortality). We also explored trends in stock status; due to data limitations, no reliable stock assessments have been conducted in Bangladesh waters, but we reviewed the available information. We included official national catch statistics (and CPUE, where available), which can be useful indicators of abundance when other data are sparse (
    <a rid="bib0415" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib0415">Pauly, 2013</a>).
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
</sec>
