<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par10">Our study presents the first comprehensive and broad-scale quantitative test of the ‘cul-de-sac’ hypothesis
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>
 </sup>, which predicts that viviparous species are more vulnerable to extinctions as climate warming progressively shrinks the cold regions they are adapted to
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>
 </sup>. Our findings across three highly-diverse lizard radiations support the effects that parity modes are expected to exert on the patterns of elevational shifts projected for these organisms as climate warms up (whereas, no such differences were observed for direction of shifts in range centroids). Specifically, our findings revealed that the prediction strongly holds for alterations in elevational distributions, where viviparous species combined experience greater elevational shifts relative to oviparous species (see Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1d</xref>). These elevational displacements observed in viviparous species were stronger in 
 <italic>Phymaturus</italic> (strictly viviparous), suggesting the potential for greater magnitudes of demographic impacts, and potentially extinction risks faced by these lizards under the ongoing climate trends
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>
 </sup>. Importantly, our findings also suggest that as the degrees of emissions of greenhouse gases increase, the extent of spatial overlap between oviparous and viviparous reproducers will increase, thus leading to the predicted scenarios of novel forms of competition between oviparous and viviparous species
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>
 </sup>. Collectively, therefore, our study reinforces the need to add the life-history dimension to the search for factors that trigger mechanisms underlying biodiversity alterations caused by increased anthropogenic climate change
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>
 </sup>. It also adds a further component to the sustained efforts to establish the combination of factors that define the ‘profile’ (i.e., shared combinations of traits) of species that have entered a current phase of extinction risk (or, on the other hand, of species which have seen their populations remain stable or even increase) as a result of environmental alterations.
</p>
