<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The climatic suitability index accounted for the effects of light, temperature and precipitation on the growth and development of the potato. As the climate changed, zones suitable for potato cultivation shifted. For farmers and advisors, it was critically important to understand these changes in order to develop short-term and long-term adaptation strategies with limited resources [
 <xref rid="pone.0203538.ref020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0203538.ref037" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>]. In this study, we found that the middle suitability cropping areas and high suitability cropping areas for potato over the past 50 years receded in northwest China and north China, respectively. Furthermore, the high suitability cropping areas expanded in northeast China, mainly because potatoes belonged to the cool season crops. However, increased heat and reduced water resources caused by climate warming in northwest and north China had negative effects on the distribution of areas suitable for potato planting. These results were consistent with a number of previous studies [
 <xref rid="pone.0203538.ref018" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0203538.ref021" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0203538.ref038" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>]. For example, Wang et al [
 <xref rid="pone.0203538.ref018" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>] found that the areas suitable for the potato in northwest China would move northward and recede as a result of climate change in the future. Zhao et al [
 <xref rid="pone.0203538.ref021" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>] pointed out that the key meteorological factors affecting potato yield in northern China was diurnal temperature range, radiation, precipitation and reference crop evapotranspiration based on daily climate variables obtained from 607 meteorological stations from 1961 to 2014 and detailed field experimental data, which would have an impact on the planting distribution of potato. Tang et al [
 <xref rid="pone.0203538.ref038" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>] indicated that variation in potato yield in North China correlated significantly with variation in growing-season effective precipitation, as well as variation in the ratio of precipitation to potential evapotranspiration during the tuberization stage, but not with variation in growing-season total precipitation. Thus, the impact of climate warming and drying in North China had negative effects on the distribution of areas suitable for potato planting.
</p>
