<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Situated in the Caucasus mountain ranges, Georgia is known for its high plant biodiversity and endemism. The flora of Georgia encompasses about 4,400 native species of vascular plants and 380 non‐native plant species, from which 16 are classified as invasive (Kikodze et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34005-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>). Approximately 21% of the Georgian flora is endemic to the Caucasus region, 278 of them being strictly endemic to Georgia (Gagnidze et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34005-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2002</xref>; Solomon et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34005-bib-0056" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). This high biodiversity is recognized by the national protection of 43 areas in Georgia, which follow the IUCN guidelines (Dudley, 
 <xref rid="ece34005-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>) and are general indicators of high biodiversity. While PAs are in general indicators of high biodiversity, those areas are not necessarily encompassing high plant endemism or endangered species (i.e., critically endangered, endangered, and vulnerable following IUCN guidelines; Dudley, 
 <xref rid="ece34005-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>), as it was shown for Armenia (Fayvush, Tamanyan, Kalashyan, &amp; Vitek, 
 <xref rid="ece34005-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). Fayvush et al. (
 <xref rid="ece34005-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>) showed that the protected natural areas of Armenia are missing important hotspots of plant endemism and even fail to preserve adequately half of the plants under categories Critically endangered (CR), endangered (EN), and vulnerable (VU) by IUCN classification. Countries with high biodiversity and a high number of strictly endemic and subendemic plant species, such as Georgia (Gagnidze et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34005-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2002</xref>; Solomon et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34005-bib-0056" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>), have an international responsibility to protect them adequately (see Convention on Biological Diversity: 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cbd.int/convention/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.cbd.int/convention/</ext-link>). Due to the high conservation value of endemic species and their susceptibility to IAPs and climate changes (e.g., Li et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34005-bib-0515" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Barrett &amp; Yates, 
 <xref rid="ece34005-bib-0500" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Urban, 
 <xref rid="ece34005-bib-0524" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Zhang et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34005-bib-0528" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>), areas of high plant endemism should be considered for the assessment of future impacts on endemic plant species in AHCV. In addition, reconciling potential inconsistencies between the distribution of PAs and areas of high endemic/endangered species richness would lead to a better prediction of AHCV and conflict zones between IAPs and AHCV.
</p>
