<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Studies projecting species’ distributions under climate change generally predict altered patterns of broad‐scale species richness (e.g., Jones &amp; Cheung, 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Luo, Jiang, &amp; Tang, 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Molinos et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>) as a response of the poleward latitudinal and/or upward altitudinal range shifts of the species (Araújo, Thuiller, &amp; Pearson, 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0005" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>; Chen, Hill, Ohlemüller, Roy, &amp; Thomas, 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>). Therefore, it follows that low latitude regions are expected to lose in species richness, whereas high latitude regions have the opposite predictions, i.e. to gain in species richness (Jones &amp; Cheung, 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Molinos et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). As stated in the last paragraph, the richness gradients for the baseline climate documented here for both hotspots are broadly congruent with previous studies. Nonetheless, the climate change is not expected to cause deep changes in the spatial configuration of anuran richness in both hotspots, a prediction already documented for amphibians in the AF (Loyola et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). This is somewhat expected due to the small climatic gradient of the present study compared to global‐scale studies that have found evident patterns of latitudinal changes in species richness (Jones &amp; Cheung, 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). Most of the AF grids are presumed to lose species, as already documented by Loyola et al. (
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>), but even the higher rates of losses in the southeastern grids do not change the fact that, presumably, this will still be the richest region of anurans in the hotspot. A combination of potential mechanisms is argued to explain the highest AF anuran richness in the southeastern Brazil close to the Atlantic coast, such as the high humidity levels of the region (da Silva et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>; Vasconcelos et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0063" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>) and the rough topography that may had promoted higher rates of allopatric speciation in the region (Haddad &amp; Prado, 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2005</xref>).
</p>
