<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">On the other hand, although most CER grids are expected to lose species, most of the northeastern grids are expected to gain in species. These gains are a probable reflection of the expansion of common/widespread species since these grids have high beta diversity in the baseline climate, but the future climate change predictions evidence a homogenization of the anuran composition in this region (Figures 
 <xref rid="ece34357-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3</xref> and 
 <xref rid="ece34357-fig-0006" ref-type="fig" class="xref">6</xref>; see complete discussion regarding beta diversity ahead). Although biodiversity losses are the main consequences regarding the human activity worldwide, biodiversity gains over some time period have also occurred in different regions of the world (Primack et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2018</xref> and references therein). Our results highlight the probable occurrence of biodiversity gains in northeastern CER as a response to climate change, which therefore reinforces the value of considering this phenomenon to assist conservationists on effective practices to deal with higher rates of species replacement and maintenance of ecosystem processes and services (Primack et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2018</xref>). All in all, the climate change is not predicted to change the fact that the highest anuran richness in CER is found in the southern rim of the hotspot, but a considerable species loss is expected in the western and southwestern areas with current moderately‐to‐high richness. This region is in contact with the lowlands of the Pantanal floodplain, the largest contiguous extent of this habitat type on Earth that had been recently predicted to have no climatically suitable areas by 2050 for four generalist treefrogs as a consequence of the climate change effects (Vasconcelos &amp; Nascimento, 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>).
</p>
