<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We found that a homogenization of the anuran fauna along the CER extent is presumed in future climate change scenarios compared to the baseline climate. Hence, the turnover and nestedness components decrease in importance for future predictions for the sake of the homogenization of the anuran fauna by 2050 and 2070. Although species loss is an important driver of the temporal change in species composition, it is their interaction with the arrival of new species that ultimately drives the beta diversity changes of communities across time (Molinos et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). Then, the higher rates of species gain in the CER compared to the AF, mainly located in the northeastern CER, might be responsible for the lower dissimilarity values of beta diversity in this hotspot by 2050 and 2070. Congruently, most of the grid cells with species gains under the climate change scenarios (Figure 
 <xref rid="ece34357-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3</xref>) are the same ones predicted to have high beta diversity in the baseline climate, but not anymore in the future climate change scenarios (see Figures 
 <xref rid="ece34357-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3</xref> and 
 <xref rid="ece34357-fig-0006" ref-type="fig" class="xref">6</xref>), thus evidencing the range expansion of some species in this region. From a conservation point of view, different strategies might be considered in the CER from current to future actions considering the dynamic changes of the beta diversity distribution. Sites having unusual combination of species (i.e., grid cells with high beta diversity) are presumed to decrease in the northeastern region of the CER in future climate change scenarios, whereas a wider area of high beta diversity is expected by 2050 and 2070 in the southeast/southwest. Hence, a gradual decrease in conservation efforts in northern/northeastern areas of CER should be compensated by higher conservation efforts across time in the southeastern/southwestern region of the hotspot (e.g., Figure 
 <xref rid="ece34357-fig-0006" ref-type="fig" class="xref">6</xref> may help decision‐makers to select specific and/or establish new conservation units, as well as establishing corridors between current and future predicted areas of high beta diversity; Socolar et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>).
</p>
