<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par7" class="p">In our bibliometric analysis, we have investigated the lifework of Keeling from a quantitative (bibliometric) perspective. The bibliometric analysis has been performed in several steps by using different databases: 
 <list list-type="order" class="list">
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par8" class="p">In a first step, the profile of his publication history and the impact of his publications have been looked at. These analyses are based on Web of Science (WoS, Clarivate Analytics) data. We have searched for Keeling’s scientific publications and found 79 papers published between 1953 and 2004 (one paper appeared 2011, six years after his death). Is seems that Keeling always used his first and middle name initials—no relevant papers authored by C. Keeling could be found. Based on the publication set of 79 papers, we have established the WoS citation report.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par9" class="p">In a second step, we broadened the perspective and analyzed whether slow reception (compared to the classical citation time pattern with a maximum of impact about three years after publication) and under-citedness are specific for Keeling’s papers or reflect general patterns of certain climate change papers. As in step 1, we used WoS data for this analysis.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par10" class="p">In a third step, we focused on publications dealing with the measurement of the CO
    <sub class="sub">2</sub> concentration in the earth’s atmosphere only and investigated Keeling’s citation impact on the field. The analysis is based on the search and retrieval functions of the databases offered by Chemical Abstracts Service (CAS), a division of the American Chemical Society (ACS). The CAS literature database (CAplus
    <sup class="sup">SM</sup>) covers scientific publications and patents since around the early 1800’s (including the references cited therein since the publication year 1996 of the database records). The CAS chemical substance database (CAS REGISTRY
    <sup class="sup">SM</sup>) contains all chemical species mentioned within disclosures in chemistry and related fields, identified and registered by the CAS Registry system. All compound records are associated with a unique CAS Registry Number
    <sup class="sup">®</sup> (CAS RN
    <sup class="sup">®</sup>). Both databases are connected to each other via the CAS RN. The coverage and indexing of these subject specific databases are optimized in particular for searching literature dealing with chemical processes like the analysis of compounds.
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
