<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The Grand River Grasslands (GRG) of Ringgold County, Iowa, and Harrison County, Missouri, is a 28,000 hectare conservation priority area comprised mostly of privately owned farms and ranches (Delaney et al., 
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>; Figure 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" class="xref">1</xref>). It has been identified as the best known opportunity to restore a functional tallgrass prairie system in the entire Central Tallgrass Prairie ecoregion (The Nature Conservancy, 
 <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2008</xref>). This Conservation Opportunity Area supports a diversity of grassland wildlife of conservation concern, including northern prairie skinks (
 <italic class="italic">Plestiodon septentrionalis</italic>), regal fritillary butterflies (
 <italic class="italic">Speyeria idalia</italic>), and grassland birds [(Greater Prairie-Chickens (
 <italic class="italic">Tympanuchus cupido</italic>), Henslow's Sparrows (
 <italic class="italic">Ammodramus henslowii</italic>), Dickcissels (
 <italic class="italic">Spiza americana</italic>), Bobolinks (
 <italic class="italic">Dolichonyx oryzivorus</italic>), Northern Harriers (
 <italic class="italic">Circus cyaneus</italic>)]. We obtained occurrence records of plant species in the GRG from Whittaker plot surveys conducted in 11 experimental pastures in Iowa and one in Missouri during May-August 2011 and 2012. Methodologies are described in McGranahan et al. (
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>). We used a total of 33 plant species common to these pastures, including native and exotic warm-season and cool-season grasses, forbs, and woody species (Table 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1" class="xref">S1</xref>). Occurrence records for each county in Iowa and one county in Missouri were obtained from The Biota of North America (BONAP), 
 <italic class="italic">North American Plant Atlas</italic> (Kartesz, 
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>).
</p>
