<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Tracer ventilation intimately linked to jet dynamics</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The different states of tracer ventilation are intimately linked to changes in jet dynamics, best explained using time-mean hydrographic sections across the Kerguelen jet, as shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Fig. 5</a> for the green transect in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Fig. 1A</a>. The time-mean ocean properties in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Fig. 5</a> are zonal velocity (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Fig. 5</a>, A to C), stratification (shown as buoyancy frequency; 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Fig. 5</a>, D to F), and salinity (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Fig. 5</a>, G to I) for wind stresses of 0.5*τ (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Fig. 5</a>, A, D, and G), τ (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Fig. 5</a>, B, E, and H), and 2*τ (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Fig. 5</a>, C, F, and I). The black feature in these panels is the northern edge of the KP, white contours mark isopycnal surfaces, and the approximate location of the bottom of the SML is shown by the green line. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Figure 5</a> (J to L) shows a horizontal section of stratification at a depth of 120 m (which is approximately the depth of the SML) for the same perturbation experiments. The red patch in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Fig. 5H</a> highlights a region of convection. Additional insight is gained from the transient behavior of the jet, shown on a Hovmöller diagram of zonal velocities at the ocean surface for wind stresses of 0.5*τ (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Fig. 5M</a>), τ (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Fig. 5N</a>), and 2*τ (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Fig. 5O</a>). The abrupt change in jet dynamics occurs at a critical point between wind stresses of τ and 2*τ (at approximately a wind stress of 1.25*τ, which will become evident below). Beyond the critical point, the Kerguelen jet suddenly accelerates, westward jets appear at its flanks (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Fig. 5</a>, A, D, and G), and, as seen in the Hovmöller diagram, the Kerguelen jet becomes more steady, locked in latitude, and smaller length scales appear (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Fig. 5</a>, M to O). While an increase in wind stress from 0.5*τ to τ leads to a decrease in stratification across the base of the SML across the Kerguelen jet (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Fig. 5</a>, B and E), it is only when the wind stress increases to 2*τ that convection across the base of the SML occurs, resulting in the ventilation of fresh (that is, low salinity) surface waters, known as AASW, into AAIW (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Fig. 5</a>, C, F, and I), consistent with the ventilation of the passive tracer shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F4" href="#F4">Fig. 4</a>.
 </p>
 <div id="F5" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 5</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Hydrographic sections across the Kerguelen jet.</div>
   <p>Colors show vertical sections along the green transect in 
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Fig. 1A</a> of time-mean (
    <span class="bold">A</span>, 
    <span class="bold">D</span>, and 
    <span class="bold">G</span>) zonal velocity (meters per second), (
    <span class="bold">B</span>, 
    <span class="bold">E</span>, and 
    <span class="bold">H</span>) buoyancy frequency (per second), and (
    <span class="bold">C</span>, 
    <span class="bold">F</span>, and 
    <span class="bold">I</span>) salinity (psu), for the perturbation experiments with wind stresses of (A to C) 0.5*τ, (D to F) τ, and (G to I) 2*τ. White contours are time-mean isopycnals, and the green line is the time-mean mixed layer depth. The black feature is the northern slope of the KP. The red patch in (H) marks a region of time-mean convection. Horizontal sections of time-mean buoyancy frequency (per second) on a log
    <sub>10</sub> scale at a depth of 120 m, chosen to represent the depth of the base of the SML, for the perturbation experiments with wind stresses of (
    <span class="bold">J</span>) 0.5*τ, (
    <span class="bold">K</span>) τ, and (
    <span class="bold">L</span>) 2*τ. Hovmöller diagrams of zonal surface velocities along the green transect in 
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Fig. 1</a> for (
    <span class="bold">M</span>) 0.5*τ, (
    <span class="bold">N</span>) τ, and (
    <span class="bold">O</span>) 2*τ.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="aao4719-F5" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This change in jet dynamics—ignoring their effect on ventilation for a moment—can be understood in more detail from 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F6" href="#F6">Fig. 6</a>. Shown are time and zonal means, averaged between 66°E and 70°E, of vertical profiles of zonal velocities in the jet’s core (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F6" href="#F6">Fig. 6A</a>, solid lines) and its northern flank (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F6" href="#F6">Fig. 6A</a>, dashed lines), depth-mean zonal velocities (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F6" href="#F6">Fig. 6B</a>), depth-mean EKE (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F6" href="#F6">Fig. 6C</a>), and the cross-jet potential vorticity gradient (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F6" href="#F6">Fig. 6D</a>). The potential vorticity gradient is a metric that is closely associated with the stability properties of a jet. A zero crossing in the potential vorticity gradient is associated with the necessary condition for the instability of the jet. The potential vorticity gradient used here is defined as β* = β − 
  <span class="italic">U</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">yy</span>
  </sub> and hence includes a contribution from Earth’s rotation (β 
  <span class="italic">= f</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">y</span>
  </sub>, where 
  <span class="italic">f</span> is the Coriolis parameter and 
  <span class="italic">y</span> is latitude) and the meridional shear of the jet’s depth-mean flow (
  <span class="italic">U</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">yy</span>
  </sub>), and is a proxy for the jet’s barotropic stability properties (
  <a rid="R28" ref-type="bibr" href="#R28">
   <span class="italic">28</span>
  </a>). In particular, the jet can become barotropically unstable when the stabilizing effect due to Earth’s rotation is counteracted by the horizontal shear of the jet. Note that the topographic influence on the potential vorticity gradient is ignored here since it is not clear at which length scales topography affects jet dynamics.
 </p>
 <div id="F6" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 6</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Dynamics of the Kerguelen jet.</div>
   <p>Jet properties are time- and zonal-mean values calculated between 66°E and 70°E. (
    <span class="bold">A</span>) Solid lines represent vertical profiles of zonal velocities in the core [at 45°S; solid gray line in (B) to (D)] of the eastward jet. Dashed lines represent vertical profiles of zonal velocities at the northern flank [at 43°S; dashed gray line in (B) to (D)] of the jet. (
    <span class="bold">B</span>) Depth-mean zonal velocities across the jet. (
    <span class="bold">C</span>) Depth mean EKE across the jet. (
    <span class="bold">D</span>) Smoothed potential vorticity (PV) gradient β* = β − 
    <span class="italic">U</span>
    <sub>
     <span class="italic">yy</span>
    </sub>, where β is the meridional gradient of the Coriolis force and 
    <span class="italic">U</span>
    <sub>
     <span class="italic">yy</span>
    </sub> is the meridional shear of the depth-mean zonal velocity. Colors represent the different wind perturbation experiments shown in 
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Fig. 1B</a>.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="aao4719-F6" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The change in jet dynamics shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Figs. 5</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F6" href="#F6">6</a> can be interpreted as follows. For a wind stress of 0.5*τ, the jet core has near-zero bottom velocities (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F6" href="#F6">Fig. 6A</a>, blue line) and its potential vorticity gradient is positive everywhere across the jet (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F6" href="#F6">Fig. 6C</a>, blue line). For this state, an increase in wind stress to τ leads to an increase in the jet’s vertical shear (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F6" href="#F6">Fig. 6A</a>) and, consequently, an increase in its baroclinic instability with an associated increase in EKE (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F6" href="#F6">Fig. 6C</a>). At the critical point, the potential vorticity gradient approaches zero at its southern flank (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F6" href="#F6">Fig. 6D</a>), with a zero crossing of the potential vorticity gradient being the necessary condition for the barotropic instability of the jet (
  <a rid="R29" ref-type="bibr" href="#R29">
   <span class="italic">29</span>
  </a>). Once the wind stress further increases, the jet abruptly reorganizes its structure to equilibrate its eddy instabilities through modification of its mean structure by eddy fluxes (
  <a rid="R30" ref-type="bibr" href="#R30">
   <span class="italic">30</span>
  </a>). As a consequence, the eastward jet core significantly accelerates while its flanks develop two westward jets, leading to a large increase in the jet’s lateral shear (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Figs. 5</a>, G and L, and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F6" href="#F6">6</a>, A and B). This jet structure is now associated with a large positive potential vorticity gradient across the jet’s core and negative potential vorticity gradients across both of its flanks (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F6" href="#F6">Fig. 6D</a>). Beyond the critical point, a further increase in wind stress results in the acceleration of the jet core’s depth-mean velocities and, subsequently, a further increase in the jet’s lateral shear while keeping its vertical shear near constant (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F6" href="#F6">Fig. 6</a>, A and B). At the critical point, the jet dynamics therefore abruptly change from that of a baroclinic jet, in which the jet’s vertical shear increases as the jet is accelerated, to that of a barotropic jet, in which the jet’s lateral shear increases as the jet is accelerated. This strong lateral shear is known to be able to suppress baroclinic instability, a process known as the barotropic governor (
  <a rid="R31" ref-type="bibr" href="#R31">
   <span class="italic">31</span>
  </a>), which explains why this jet can sustain such steep isopycnals without becoming unstable. The effects of jet dynamics on baroclinic instability and, hence, EKE can be used to find the critical point at which jet dynamics abruptly change. From 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Fig. 5C</a>, it is apparent that EKE adjacent to the jet increases from a wind stress of 0.5*τ to 1.25*τ, reaches a maximum of 1.25*τ, and then decreases with further increases in wind stress. This is particularly evident in the region where the shear between the eastward jet core and its westward jets at its flanks becomes largest due to the barotropic governor increasingly suppressing baroclinic instability. For the Kerguelen jet, the critical point occurs for a wind stress increase of 25%.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the Southern Ocean, strong westerly winds prevail and hence blow into the direction of the jets, a scenario usually referred to as “down-front winds” (
  <a rid="R32" ref-type="bibr" href="#R32">
   <span class="italic">32</span>
  </a>). These down-front winds lead to Ekman advection of buoyancy across the jet. Depending on the lateral gradients of buoyancy and momentum across the jet, the Ekman advection of buoyancy can lead to convection across the base of the SML (
  <a rid="R32" ref-type="bibr" href="#R32">
   <span class="italic">32</span>
  </a>). As evident from vertical sections of stratification across the Kerguelen jet (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Fig. 5</a>, B, E, and H), increasing winds erode the stratification across the base of the SML across all perturbation experiments, but it is only beyond the critical point, where the jet changes from baroclinic to barotropic, that this reduction in stratification is sufficient to lead to convection across the base of the SML [
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Fig. 5</a>, B, E, and H; note that the mixed layer depth in the jet (~400 m in the case of 2*τ) is much deeper than the boundary layer parameterized by KPP (K-profile parameterization) for the same region (~100 m in the case of 2*τ) and hence is not a numerical artifact due to the choice of this parameterization scheme (Materials and Methods)]. This convection allows the passive tracer (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F4" href="#F4">Fig. 4</a>, C and F) and AASW (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Fig. 5I</a>) to ventilate AAIW along the jet. As evident from 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Fig. 5</a> (J to L), which shows a horizontal section of stratification at the base of the mixed layer at a depth of 120 m, convection across the base of the SML is confined to the core of the jet, that is, regions where lateral gradients of buoyancy and momentum are largest. These results therefore point toward the possibility of the abrupt reorganization from a baroclinic to a barotropic jet and the associated increase in the lateral gradients of buoyancy and momentum, which is a prerequisite for the ventilation of AAIW along the jet.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The role of jet dynamics in Southern Ocean ventilation can be summarized as follows. Because of the interaction of the Southern Ocean’s background mean flow with topography, strong jets appear adjacent to this topography, such as the Kerguelen jet discussed here. For the example of the Kerguelen jet, an increase in winds of up to 1.25*τ leads to an increase in the jet’s vertical shear, which is associated with an increase in EKE due to baroclinic instability in both the jet and the associated storm track. The consequence of this increase in storm track intensity is a change from no tracer ventilation (0.5*τ) to the tracer being ventilated into a deep SML (0.75*τ to 1.25*τ). Once the wind stress increases beyond the critical point at 1.25*τ, the jet abruptly changes its structure to a barotropic jet with westward jets at its flanks, increasing its lateral shear and hence suppressing baroclinic instability due to an effect known as the barotropic governor. Because of the emerging barotropic governor, a further increase in winds leads to a decrease in EKE and increasingly steep isopycnal surfaces. This abrupt increase in cross-jet gradients of buoyancy and momentum, combined with down-front winds, leads to convection across the base of the SML. This convection across the base of the mixed layer, combined with the steep isopycnal surfaces across the jet, leads to the ventilation of AAIW along the jet.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While the model experiments shown here resolve mesoscale turbulence with length scales of the order of 10 to 100 km and Rossby numbers of 
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <sub>o</sub> = ζ
  <span class="italic">/f</span> &lt;&lt; 1 (where ζ 
  <span class="italic">= v</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">x</span>
  </sub> − 
  <span class="italic">u</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">y</span>
  </sub> is the relative vorticity and 
  <span class="italic">f</span> is the planetary vorticity), these model experiments barely resolve submesoscale turbulence with length scales of the order of 1 to 10 km and Rossby numbers of 
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <sub>o</sub> = 
  <span class="italic">O</span>(1). Nevertheless, it is the submesoscale turbulence, which is associated with strong vertical velocities, that is thought to dominate tracer ventilation (
  <a rid="R33" ref-type="bibr" href="#R33">
   <span class="italic">33</span>
  </a>). An insight into how the dynamics presented here could affect submesoscale turbulence and hence tracer ventilation can be gained from snapshots of Rossby numbers for the different perturbation experiments (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F7" href="#F7">Fig. 7</a>). For a wind stress of 0.5*τ, the Rossby number 
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <sub>o</sub> &lt;&lt; 1 (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F7" href="#F7">Fig. 7A</a>), and no tracer ventilation occurs. For a wind stress of τ, the Rossby number 
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <sub>o</sub> increases predominantly in the storm track downstream of topography (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F7" href="#F7">Fig. 7B</a>), consistent with tracer ventilation occurring in this region. For a wind stress of 2*τ, the cross-jet gradients of buoyancy and momentum abruptly increase. This increase in cross-jet buoyancy gradient energizes submesoscale turbulence (
  <a rid="R33" ref-type="bibr" href="#R33">
   <span class="italic">33</span>
  </a>), which is consistent with Rossby numbers abruptly increasing to 
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <sub>o</sub> = 
  <span class="italic">O</span>(1) adjacent to the Kerguelen jet (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F7" href="#F7">Fig. 7C</a>). If submesoscale turbulence were resolved, then the ventilation of the tracer would very likely substantially increase in regions of 
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <sub>o</sub> = 
  <span class="italic">O</span>(1).
 </p>
 <div id="F7" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 7</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">The dependence of Rossby numbers on wind stress.</div>
   <p>Rossby numbers 
    <span class="italic">R</span>
    <sub>o</sub> = ζ
    <span class="italic">/f</span>, where ζ = 
    <span class="italic">v</span>
    <sub>
     <span class="italic">x</span>
    </sub> − 
    <span class="italic">u</span>
    <sub>
     <span class="italic">y</span>
    </sub> is the relative vorticity and 
    <span class="italic">f</span> is the planetary vorticity, at the ocean surface for (
    <span class="bold">A</span>) 0.5*τ, (
    <span class="bold">B</span>) τ, and (
    <span class="bold">C</span>) 2*τ.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="aao4719-F7" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
