<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ocean model configuration</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ocean model used was the Massachusetts Institute of Technology general circulation model (MITgcm) (
  <a rid="R46" ref-type="bibr" href="#R46">
   <span class="italic">46</span>
  </a>). It uses depth coordinates, partially filled cells for the bathymetry, a quadratic bottom drag coefficient of 0.0025, a nonlinear equation of state (
  <a rid="R47" ref-type="bibr" href="#R47">
   <span class="italic">47</span>
  </a>), a seventh-order advection scheme, and the K-profile parameterization (
  <a rid="R48" ref-type="bibr" href="#R48">
   <span class="italic">48</span>
  </a>). The model domain ranged from 57° to 129°E in longitude and 70° to 35°S in latitude and hence included the steep topography associated with the KP and the SEIR. The horizontal grid spacing was 1/20°, which converts to a zonal grid spacing of ~4.5 km at the northern boundary and ~1.9 km at the southern boundary, with a meridional grid spacing of ~5.6 km. The vertical resolution was resolved by 150 layers, ranging from 10 m thickness at the surface to 50 m thickness at depth.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The model topography was taken from the 1-min-resolution Shuttle Radar Topographic Mission (
  <a rid="R49" ref-type="bibr" href="#R49">
   <span class="italic">49</span>
  </a>) with a maximum depth of 5000 m. The model domain was made periodic in the east-west direction, and the topography was interpolated over 4° bands at its eastern and western bands to avoid discontinuities. The northern boundary was relaxed over a 1°-wide sponge layer with a relaxation time of 4 days to annually and zonally averaged climatological fields taken from year 2005 of the Southern Ocean State Estimate (
  <a rid="R50" ref-type="bibr" href="#R50">
   <span class="italic">50</span>
  </a>). At the ocean surface, the model was forced to the annually and zonally averaged sea-surface temperature (which was restored with a relaxation time of 15 days), freshwater fluxes, and wind forcing from the Southern Ocean State Estimate. The Southern Ocean MOC was calculated using the MITgcm’s layer package (
  <a rid="R51" ref-type="bibr" href="#R51">
   <span class="italic">51</span>
  </a>), with the maximum value being determined for all regions south of the sponge layer. For this reference experiment, the total zonal transport was equal to 155 Sverdrup (1 Sverdrup = 10
  <span class="sup">6</span> m
  <span class="sup">3</span> s
  <span class="sup">−1</span>), which was close to the observed value of the transport estimated in Drake Passage of 173.3 Sverdrup (
  <a rid="R52" ref-type="bibr" href="#R52">
   <span class="italic">52</span>
  </a>). A more detailed comparison of this model configuration with observations can be found elsewhere (
  <a rid="R53" ref-type="bibr" href="#R53">
   <span class="italic">53</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R54" ref-type="bibr" href="#R54">
   <span class="italic">54</span>
  </a>).
 </p>
</sec>
