<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Interplay Among Team Emergent States</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Each of these four emergent states contributes significantly to team learning. However, they have usually been studied in isolation from each other. There are two reasons to be concerned about this. The first is that when it comes to the levels of team states, it is not always “more is better.” For example, high levels of cohesion have detrimental effects due to increased pressure for conformity (
  <a rid="B69" ref-type="bibr" href="#B69">Lott and Lott, 1965</a>; 
  <a rid="B45" ref-type="bibr" href="#B45">Hackman, 1976</a>). Alternately, if team members believe 
  <span class="italic">too</span> strongly in their ability to accomplish a task (efficacy), theory suggests that they can succumb to overconfidence and complacency (
  <a rid="B42" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42">Gist, 1987</a>). They tend to make poorer decisions by taking uncalculated risks, spending less time on information-processing activities, and rejecting negative feedback (
  <a rid="B100" ref-type="bibr" href="#B100">Whyte, 1998</a>). While such curvilinear relationships have not been investigated with respect to psychological safety, it would not be hard to imagine a team where effectiveness suffers because mistakes are so welcome. Similarly, there are contexts where performance orientation is more appropriate (
  <a rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1">Alexander and Van Knippenberg, 2014</a>). The bottom line is that each emergent state has an optimum setting that may change with task and context.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This leads to the second point, efforts to influence one state may affect the utility of the others. For example, moderate level of team efficacy is recommended for teams to engage in learning behaviors that enhance performance (e.g., 
  <a rid="B93" ref-type="bibr" href="#B93">Tasa and Whyte, 2005</a>), unless they monitor their goal closely—then, high level of team efficacy is beneficial (
  <a rid="B84" ref-type="bibr" href="#B84">Rapp et al., 2014</a>). Such contingencies mean that beneficial effects of one state might be counteracted by negative effects on another. It would explain why some researchers find a positive relationship between cohesion and team learning (e.g., 
  <a rid="B87" ref-type="bibr" href="#B87">Schippers et al., 2008</a>), and others find no relationship (e.g., 
  <a rid="B94" ref-type="bibr" href="#B94">van Ginkel and van Knippenberg, 2008</a>). What is unknown is whether some attempts to increase cohesion might not cancel out the benefits by also increasing a negative effects like groupthink (
  <a rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" href="#B55">Janis, 1972</a>). The bottom line is that if team emergent states affect each other, then research needs to address how to manage an equilibrium among them in order to maximize positive behaviors and outcomes such as learning in teams. We lack such an understanding of how the four team emergent states 
  <span class="italic">collectively</span> influence team learning.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Research on the dynamics of teams is still in its infancy (
  <a rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9">Bowers et al., 2017</a>), and conceptual work must therefore take a step forward and develop more dynamic models of team learning (
  <a rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7">Bell et al., 2012</a>). Inertia is a foundation for dynamics – without inertia there is no way for the past to influence the future (
  <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">Cronin and Vancouver, 2018</a>). Above we have discussed why each emergent state could exhibit inertia. Yet to truly understand the 
  <span class="italic">dynamics</span> of TLC, we must consider the feedback loops within the system. That is, how the change to emergent states produced by some leadership action may set into motion a causal chain that loops back to perpetuate or even reinforce the current conditions. Such feedback loops can diminish the intended effect of leaders’ actions or even worsen the problem via unintended consequences. What leaders really need to do is to promote virtuous cycles within the system. In all cases, one cannot control a system by focusing only on one part of it (i.e., one emergent state).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To be clear, when we discuss feedback, we are talking about circular chains of causality (
  <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">Cronin and Vancouver, 2018</a>). Feedback loops are what 
  <a rid="B71" ref-type="bibr" href="#B71">Marks et al. (2001)</a> and others (e.g., 
  <a rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" href="#B54">Ilgen et al., 2005</a>) have recognized as inherent in teams: An “output” at time 1 becomes the “input” at time 2. Such feedback is how non-linear growth and change can continue within a system even after a leadership action (or any other process intended to affect the team) has stopped. Feedback when coupled with inertia is also how systems as a whole resist change. To articulate how to control systems with inertia and feedback, it is often helpful to model them as 
  <span class="italic">stock and flow systems</span> (
  <a rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40">Forrester, 1968</a>). A stock is like a tank that maintains its water level over time unless it is filled or emptied. Thus it has inertia like other emergent states. But importantly, the stock and flow structure highlights that what causes TLC to increase may not be what causes it to decrease—the inflow to TLC can represent a different set of processes or actions from the outflow (
  <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">Cronin and Vancouver, 2018</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This decoupling of inflows from outflows allows for greater prediction and control of TLC both within and between emergent states. For example, efficacy opens the inflow to TLC, for example, by increasing the motivation to perform. Yet after a certain point, efficacy might also open the outflow to TLC as well, albeit through a different process such as the discarding of new knowledge (i.e., “our way works, why would we change it?”). Such a characterization still fits with the conceptualization of efficacy, but it suggests that to control the system a leader should focus on counteracting the tendency to ignore new knowledge. The broader point is that the emergent states act as a collective to alter the inflow and outflow to TLC.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The systems view implies that to truly understand how leadership can manage TLC, research must conduct studies that will simultaneously monitor the equilibration among the different emergent states. To use another analogy, consider a vegetable garden. To achieve the highest yield, the gardener must balance soil quality, sunlight, watering, and pest control. The relative levels of all these factors in concert determine the garden’s potential to produce a healthy crop. Moreover, addressing one factor might influence another (e.g., using pesticides might impair soil quality). Further, the relationships are not linear: Some watering is needed, but not too much, and this also depends on the amount of sunshine. TLC is like the yield of the garden. It represents the team’s potential to learn effectively, based on the current levels of the important factors that support or inhibit team learning. In many ways, leaders must be capable gardeners.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Figure 1</a> provides a more graphical illustration of the kinds of questions a systems view would warrant, and why these would be useful. The bottom of 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Figure 1</a> shows the stock of TLC with a single inflow and a single outflow, the arrows with hourglass symbols. Based on what we know about team learning, the inflow would represent experimentation and reflection processes (those that increase knowledge), while the outflow might represent forgetting and discounting processes (those that reject new knowledge). The emergent states are represented above the inflow and outflow arrows, and these have the capacity to influence each other as well as to open or close the flows. For simplicity, let us focus on psychological safety, and let us further assume that leaders are going to attempt to increase psychological safety through policy about the importance of always speaking up. The direct effect (represented by the bold arrow to the TLC inflow) should increase the rate of speaking up, which will encourage others in the team to do so as well, thus increasing the stock of TLC. Such an immediate effect can be tested and verified, but if one ignores the longer term effects, the understanding of the utility of this policy is incomplete.
 </p>
 <div id="F1" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">FIGURE 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Dynamic model of team learning climate. Note that this model conforms to systems dynamics modeling conventions (
    <a rid="B92" ref-type="bibr" href="#B92">Sterman, 2000</a>). Boxed variables are stocks, and the hourglass shapes are flows. Cloud shapes represent factors exogenous to the model. Causal influence arrows are all directional, and denote either positive (blue) or negative (red) relationships. Arrows with “||” on the stem denote delayed influence (e.g., it may take time before goal orientation starts to influence the team learning inflow).
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="fpsyg-10-01441-g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For one thing, thinking about the growth of TLC over time leads one to realize that it would not be reasonable to expect that psychological safety will increase TLC forever. There is likely to be some control function, possibly emanating from the limits on psychological safety itself, that could eventually cause diminishing returns on the accumulation of TLC. We might conjecture that people will get used to the policy of speaking up, and thus its influence on behavior will fade over time as it becomes taken for granted. Alternately, after a certain point, psychological safety may start to decrease TLC if teammates feel no need to consider their ideas before voicing them; it may lead to a kind of information overload. This kind of influence is represented by the arrow from psychological safety to the outflow of TLC, and may only emerge after psychological safety grows to a certain point, which is why there is a delay mark (||) on the arrow.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As we discussed above, psychological safety can affect or be affected by the other states as well (
  <a rid="B51" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51">Harvey et al., in press</a>). These would be represented by the other curved arrow in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Figure 1</a>. Perhaps more important is that such effects can be delayed and can have second and even third order effects on TLC (i.e., the effect of psychological safety on TLC goes through two or three pathways). Consider first that while psychological safety can increase cohesion, as cohesion grows beyond a certain point it may increase conformity pressures which loopback to limit psychological safety (
  <a rid="B56" ref-type="bibr" href="#B56">Kahn, 1990</a>; 
  <a rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31">Edmondson, 2018</a>). This is a balancing loop (denoted by B). This would be another way that the impact of the policy that encourages speaking up might fade over time (as cohesion grows).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sometimes the second order effects are harder to identify. Psychological safety may lead to increased efficacy, and as we discussed above, this might lead to overconfidence that decreases TLC as team members reject new knowledge (
  <a rid="B84" ref-type="bibr" href="#B84">Rapp et al., 2014</a>). This effect might also be delayed (represented by the two perpendicular lines on the arrow) because efficacy takes time to grow. However, once the effect of overconfidence surfaces and TLC starts to decrease, it may cause leaders to try to further increase psychological safety. Yet this will not fix the problem, and because of the delay between the change to psychological safety and the effect of overconfidence, leaders might overlook efficacy as the cause of the problem.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As the feedback loops get longer and causes and effects become more distal in time, the potential for perverse outcomes increases. Continuing with our example, if psychological safety improves efficacy, it might eventually change the goal orientation to a performance one (especially if performance is rewarded and the team gets used to “winning”). This is a second order effect that might produce the third order effect whereby performance orientation reduces the willingness to experiment and possibly fail, thus shutting the TLC inflow.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The important point about a systems view is that all of these things may co-occur. Thus, while initially psychological safety is a boon to TLC, over time its influence becomes more limited because of increased cohesion, and possibly even detrimental if the dark side of efficacy and goal orientation takes over. Managing this system thus requires managing all four emergent states, not just one.</p>
</sec>
