<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Team emergent states are defined in terms of beliefs that team members hold about the team’s goals, team member abilities, and interpersonal norms. They emerge early after team formation and continue to develop over time as the team’s work unfolds (
  <a rid="B71" ref-type="bibr" href="#B71">Marks et al., 2001</a>; 
  <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">Cronin et al., 2011</a>; 
  <a rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35">Edmondson and Harvey, 2018</a>). They tend to stabilize as beliefs become relatively coherent across team members (
  <a rid="B61" ref-type="bibr" href="#B61">Kozlowski and Chao, 2012</a>), ultimately guiding behaviors within the team (e.g., 
  <a rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28">Edmondson, 1999</a>). Yet their emergence is described as dynamic because they form in response to experiences and observations of team member interactions, and these experiences and observations both shape and are shaped by the accumulating beliefs. We know a fair amount about what makes particular team states emerge, and how team leadership can influence such emergence (e.g., 
  <a rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34">Edmondson and Harvey, 2017</a>), but we know significantly less about the feedback among team states when they are linked as a system, and what this means for team leadership seeking to control that system.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this paper, we focus on team learning because it is one of the most critical team processes, and team leaders have significant impact on creating conditions that support it (
  <a rid="B59" ref-type="bibr" href="#B59">Koeslag-Kreunen et al., 2018</a>). We draw from 
  <a rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7">Bell et al. (2012)</a> to consider four key emergent states for team learning, namely psychological safety, goal orientation, cohesion, and efficacy, and we argue that collectively these states bring about the team’s learning climate (TLC). We conceptualize TLC as a capacity that rises and falls as a joint function of the psychological safety, goal orientation, cohesion, and efficacy that exist in the team. If the four emergent states can increase or decrease the level of TLC, then collectively TLC can be conceptualized as a control system (cf. 
  <a rid="B95" ref-type="bibr" href="#B95">Vancouver, 2005</a>). If the level in any one component of the system (e.g., cohesion) affects but is also affected by other components (e.g., psychological safety), then there is feedback in this system. If the levels of a component can persist over time, then there is inertia. It is these two conditions that make a system dynamic (
  <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">Cronin and Vancouver, 2018</a>), and dynamics increase the challenge of maintaining control of a system (
  <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">Cronin et al., 2009</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Because leadership activities may influence multiple team emergent states at once, it is fundamental to take a systems view (
  <a rid="B92" ref-type="bibr" href="#B92">Sterman, 2000</a>) of how the various states affect the rates of increase and decrease to TLC. It is when leaders are conscious of their influence on emergent states as a system that they come to realize that their interventions can simultaneously affect the various parts of the system in distinct ways (
  <a rid="B89" ref-type="bibr" href="#B89">Shuffler et al., 2018</a>), or that their interventions can have little impact because of the inertia found in the system (
  <a rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39">Ericksen and Dyer, 2004</a>). A focus on one particular emergent state to the exclusion of others is often why practices intended to help wind up being net negative (
  <a rid="B92" ref-type="bibr" href="#B92">Sterman, 2000</a>). Leaders can overlook the side effects that would be visible had they taken a broader view of the entire system. This is particularly important in teams because most teams encounter turbulences, and it is during turbulences that their leaders intervene. It is also during such times that a leader’s focus can narrow (
  <a rid="B91" ref-type="bibr" href="#B91">Staw et al., 1981</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The systems view helps further elaborate on the leadership function of team monitoring. Functional leadership doesn’t prescribe individual traits to good or bad leaders, but rather informs on the interventions required to satisfy team needs. The core idea is not to emphasize “what leaders should do” but rather “what needs to be done for effective performance” (
  <a rid="B48" ref-type="bibr" href="#B48">Hackman and Walton, 1986</a>, p. 77). From this perspective, team leadership is about identifying and solving problems with the aim of ensuring team effectiveness. Team monitoring is a key leadership function that refers to examining a team’s internal activity, progress toward the achievement of the team task, and its environment (
  <a rid="B78" ref-type="bibr" href="#B78">Morgeson et al., 2010</a>). While some studies have examined the relationship between team monitoring and team learning—e.g., both 
  <a rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23">De Jong and Elfring (2010)</a> and 
  <a rid="B81" ref-type="bibr" href="#B81">Otte et al. (2017)</a> have shown the positive and significant relation between team monitoring and team reflexivity (reflexivity is a learning process)—the emergent states described as part of TLC have not been considered in any of these studies. Our systems approach helps provide an understanding of how team states influence TLC, and how TLC can be effectively controlled over time. Thus monitoring TLC is better understood when we view teams as systems where inertia and feedback inform leadership.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Specifically, we propose that 
  <span class="italic">team state monitoring</span> is a key leadership function that encompasses the routine evaluation of how a team evolves to identify and correct dysfunctional imbalances in a collection of team states. Because we take a systems view of team emergent states’ development, we not only focus on how changes to one state might propagate throughout the system, we also consider the unintended consequences that can be created as leaders attempt to manage these states. We argue that monitoring is effectively the means to manage TLC over time, but such monitoring can be myopic and lead to actions that enhance one part of the system while degrading others. It can be beneficial, however, when leaders take a systems view.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the sections that follow, we review the literature on team emergent states and team learning to develop a systems view of TLC. Then, we operationalize this view through a vignette that helps illustrate why it matters for team leadership before deepening the notion of team monitoring as a leadership function. This takes us to a discussion of team state monitoring and its implications for team research and leadership practice.</p>
</sec>
