<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Our results indicate that harvest at a level designed to meet management objectives (i) and (ii) can mitigate the risk of accelerating population declines caused by habitat loss due to climate change. This requires that climate change affects populations primarily through density‐dependent mechanisms (e.g. Lunn 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="jpe12864-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>) or that management intervals are short enough to respond to potential density‐independent reductions in 
 <italic class="italic">r</italic>
 <sub class="sub">MNPL</sub> (alternatively, that within‐interval reductions in 
 <italic class="italic">r</italic>
 <sub class="sub">MNPL</sub> are considered when deriving values of 
 <italic class="italic">F</italic>
 <sub class="sub">O</sub>). The proposed state‐dependent framework implements harvest as a fraction of current population size, which is a more robust strategy than fixed‐level harvest (Quinn &amp; Deriso 
 <xref rid="jpe12864-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1999</xref>). A consequence of this approach is that, if populations are declining due to declining 
 <italic class="italic">K</italic>, the calculated harvest level will decline as well. Our analyses suggest that the following considerations also may be important if environmental conditions are deteriorating rapidly: (i) obtaining improved population data and shortening the management interval, and (ii) reducing all human impacts, including harvest, when pre‐determined thresholds for population status are crossed (noting that, for polar bears, different types of human‐caused removals are interrelated such that defence kills may increase when subsistence harvest is decreased). Threshold harvest rules, under which there is no harvest below a lower limit on population size, can be an effective method of minimizing harvest risks while maintaining the opportunity for future use if populations rebound (Lande, Saether &amp; Engen 
 <xref rid="jpe12864-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1997</xref>). Although our example focuses on the subsistence harvest of polar bears, the methods presented here could be applied to other management issues (e.g. reproductive failure due to disturbance) or species and integrated with decision analysis tools to optimize trade‐offs in conservation planning (e.g. Williams &amp; Johnson 
 <xref rid="jpe12864-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>).
</p>
