<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="methods" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Great tit captures and handling</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A total of 311 nestboxes were installed in temperate broadleaf, mixed forests throughout the Canton of Vaud in western Switzerland. Adult great tits (
   <span class="italic">Parus major</span>) were trapped in their nestboxes during three consecutive breeding seasons (2009-2011) by using door traps mounted inside the nestboxes when their nestlings were twelve days old. Body mass was measured to the nearest 0.1 g. A 30 
   <span class="italic">μ</span>l blood sample was taken by brachial venapuncture, and collected in lithium-heparin lined Microvettes 
   <span class="sup">
    <span class="italic">â“‡</span>
   </span> (CB 300 LH, Sarstedt, Germany). Only birds captured in more than one season were considered for this study (n = 55). All birds were captured under license from the Swiss Federal Office for the Environment (number F044-0799), and in accordance with the Cantonal Veterinary Authorities of the Canton de Vaud, Switzerland (authorization number 1730).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Molecular analyses</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">DNA was extracted from blood using the DNeasy tissue extraction kit (QIAGEN) according to the manufacturer’s protocol for purification of DNA from blood using the BioSprint 96. After DNA extraction a nested PCR refined by Waldenström 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>[
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B36" href="#B36">36</a>] from the original protocol made by Bensch 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>[
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B14" href="#B14">14</a>] was performed on all samples. The full method is described in [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B37" href="#B37">37</a>] with the following modifications: The PCR cycle profile included an initial denaturation at 94°C for 3 minutes followed by 20 cycles of 94°C for 30 s; 50°C for 30 s; 72°C for 45 s, and with a final extension at 72°C for 10 min. The final PCR amplification was run for 35 cycles with the same thermal profile as described here. For 
   <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span> amplification, initial primers HaemNFI and HaemNR3 and nested primers HaemFL and HaemR2L (amplifying a 480 bp 
   <span class="italic">Cyt b</span> fragment) were used [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B38" href="#B38">38</a>] with the same thermal profile and procedure as described. Reactions were run on a Veriti 96 Well Thermal Cycler (Applied Biosystems). Distilled RNAse-free water was used as a negative control and one negative control was inserted for every nine samples tested. Genomic DNA from individuals with known malarial infections were used as positive control. Nested PCR products were separated on 2% agarose gels containing ethidium bromide and a sample deemed positive if a fragment of approximately 500 bp was present when the gel was viewed under a UV light.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nested PCR products were purified using the Wizard SV Gel and PCR Clean-Up System (Promega) using the manufacturer’s protocol for DNA purification by centrifugation. Purified PCR products were sequenced in both directions using the primers HaemF and HaemR2 for 
   <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span> and 
   <span class="italic">Haemoproteus</span> and primers HaemFL and HaemR2L for 
   <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span> with a dye terminator cycle sequencing (BigDye 
   <span class="sup">
    <span class="italic">â“‡</span>
   </span> v3.1) reaction and electrophoresis was carried out on an ABI Prism 3100 sequencer (Perkin Elmer, Norwalk, CT). The sequences were assembled and edited using CodonCode Aligner (CodonCode Corporation). Sequences were then identified by performing a local BLAST search with the MalAvi database [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B2" href="#B2">2</a>]. All 
   <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span> and 
   <span class="italic">Haemoproteus</span> sequences could be identified (or characterised as multiple infections), while 3.5% of 
   <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span> samples were unidentifiable after sequencing due to poor DNA quality resulting in unreadable chromatographs. Similarly, identification of lineages involved in multiple infections were not possible (38.9% of infected birds suffered multiple 
   <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span> infections, while 3.7% suffered multiple 
   <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span> / 
   <span class="italic">Haemoproteus</span> infections).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span> and 
   <span class="italic">Haemoproteus</span> parasite quantification was achieved using a real-time quantitative PCR (qPCR) assay described in [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B37" href="#B37">37</a>] but using a parasite 
   <span class="italic">Cyt b</span> TaqMan probe (CY3-CYTb-BHQ2: 5’-CCTTTAGGGTATGATACAGC-3’) and a host 18S rRNA probe (FAM-18S-BHQ1: 5’-AACCTCGAGCCGATCGCACG-3’), and calculated in the following manner: Firstly, parasite and host DNA quantity present in a sample was calculated by the equation
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <div id="bmcM1" class="disp-formula">
    <span class="label">(1)</span>
    <div id="M1" name="1475-2875-12-40-i1" overflow="scroll" class="math">
     <span class="mi">α</span>
     <span class="mo">=</span>
     <span class="mn">1</span>
     <div class="msup">
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mn">0</span>
      </div>
      <div class="mrow">
       <div class="mfrac">
        <div class="mrow">
         <span class="mn">1</span>
        </div>
        <div class="mrow">
         <span class="mi">m</span>
         <span class="mo">(</span>
         <span class="mo">△</span>
         <span mathvariant="italic" class="mtext">Ct</span>
         <span class="mo">)</span>
        </div>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Where 
   <span class="italic">α</span> represents the DNA quantity in the sample; m represents the slope of the standard curve; and △Ct is the difference between the mean Ct value of the sample and the intercept of the standard curve. Ct (or threshold cycle) is the fractional cycle number at which the fluorescence is detected to significantly surpass the threshold. This equation then gives a relative quantification value for parasitaemia relative to a standard sample used. Relative parasite density relative to host (R 
   <span class="italic">α</span>) was then calculated by the equation 
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <div id="bmcM2" class="disp-formula">
    <span class="label">(2)</span>
    <div id="M2" name="1475-2875-12-40-i2" overflow="scroll" class="math">
     <span class="mi">Rα</span>
     <span class="mo">=</span>
     <div class="mfrac">
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mi">α</span>
       <span class="mo">(</span>
       <span mathvariant="italic" class="mtext">parasite</span>
       <span class="mo">)</span>
      </div>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mi">α</span>
       <span class="mo">(</span>
       <span mathvariant="italic" class="mtext">host</span>
       <span class="mo">)</span>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As a result of the exponential relationship between Ct and R 
   <span class="italic">α</span>, the log
   <sub>10</sub> of R 
   <span class="italic">α</span> was used to linearize this relationship. Parasitaemia is, therefore, unitless. The same reference sample was used for all qPCR standard curves and the efficiency of each qPCR run is taken into account during the calculation, therefore, parasitaemia values for samples collected in different years are directly comparable.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cloning of multiple infections</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cloning was performed on a randomly chosen subset of ten samples containing multiple double peaks when DNA chromatographs were viewed. This was done to verify that the double peaks observed indicated multiple infections of parasites within a single host or due to problems like amplification errors arising from sequencing. Cloning was performed using the pGEM 
   <span class="sup">
    <span class="italic">â“‡</span>
   </span>-T Easy Vector System (Promega) according to the manufacturer’s protocol. Ligation reactions were set up using purified PCR products and cultures of transformed high efficiency competent cells were plated onto LB/ampicillin/IPTG/X-Gal plates. Eight positive colonies were selected at random from every cloned sample. Inserts of positive colonies were sequenced using the SP6 and T7 Promoter Primers (Promega). Due to the cloning procedure being prone to introducing artificial mutations, only lineages that were detected in two or more separate colonies from each sample were considered as lineages involved in co-infection. Cloning confirmed that the double peaks on DNA chromatographs indicated infection with multiple lineages at the same time within a single host.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analyses</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The analyses were performed with the freeware R-Cran Project [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B39" href="#B39">39</a>]. A Fisher’s exact test was performed to determine differences in the frequency of lineage identity changes and infection status (infected vs. uninfected) changes between 
   <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span>, 
   <span class="italic">Haemoproteus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span> infections in recaptured individuals. Parasitaemia data were log transformed to achieve normality. A Welch two-sample t-test was used to assess the difference in parasitaemia between the two most prevalent 
   <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span> lineages, SW2 (
   <span class="italic">P. polare</span>) and SGS1 (
   <span class="italic">P. relictum</span>), as sample sizes for other recorded lineages were too low to be considered. Paired t-tests were performed to determine whether an individual’s parasitaemia changed between years of capture. Linear mixed models (lmer) in the lme4 package [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B40" href="#B40">40</a>] were performed on parasitaemia data to determine whether there is a relationship between concurrent infection with 
   <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span> and 
   <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span> parasitaemia. 
   <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span> parasitaemia was considered as response variable with bird identity and year of capture as random factors and 
   <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span> infection as fixed effect. To assess the virulence (i.e. affect on host body mass) of co-infection, linear mixed models were performed on a subset of data containing only occurrences of lineage SGS1 (n = 83) and considering 
   <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span> infections as presence or absence values only. Body mass was considered as response variable with bird identity as random factor and sex and 
   <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span> infection as fixed effects. Likelihood ratio tests (LRT) were used to compare “goodness of fit” between models containing and excluding the fixed effect of interest. Probability values of 
   <span class="italic">p</span> ≤ 0.05 were considered significant.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
