<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We designed two experiments to assess how Global Climate Change (GCC) modulates the effects of abiotic and biotic variables on the ecophysiological performance of 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">quitensis</italic>. The consequences of the changes in current and future environmental conditions on plant photochemical performance were examined in growth chambers with an automatic system of air cooling (Model: LTJ300LY; Tianyi Cool, China), while the effects of abiotic variation were evaluated through a field experiment. In order to establish the “current environmental conditions” (control treatment) for these, we used both published and contemporary field data. These data were then used to define the “future environmental conditions” treatment, through modifying the current conditions based on the most recent global change predictions and models [
 <xref rid="pone.0164844.ref009" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0164844.ref012" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. First, we selected a temperature of 4°C as control (current environmental temperature). This temperature was chosen because it represents an intermediate value between the King George Island (5°C) and the Antarctic Peninsula (3°C, 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.worldclime.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.worldclime.org</ext-link>) over their growing seasons (from December to February). Current global and regional climate models predict average annual temperature increases of 2–4.5°C [
 <xref rid="pone.0164844.ref012" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0164844.ref044" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>] over the next century in Antarctica [
 <xref rid="pone.0164844.ref009" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0164844.ref011" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>]. Thus, incubation temperature was increased by 3°C in our “future conditions” experiments.
</p>
