<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The abrupt, significant decrease in precipitation obtained by the model calculations could apply to the paleoclimate because the distribution and amounts of precipitation in the late Cretaceous do not differ substantially from those of the present day
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b41" class="xref">41</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b42" class="xref">42</xref> (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3" class="xref">Fig. 3</xref>). In the 15°N to 15°S region for the 500-Tg, 1500-Tg, and 2600-Tg ejection cases, annual mean precipitation over the land decreased by 75% (to 1.1 mm/day), 93% (0.3 mm/day), and 94% (0.3 mm/day), which lasted for 1.5, 2.5, and 3.5 years, respectively (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3" class="xref">Fig. 3</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="t1" class="xref">Table 1</xref>). The low precipitation, similar to that of the Sahara Desert, occurred in all areas over the land in the 15°N to 15°S region for the 1500-Tg and 2600-Tg BC ejection scenarios (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4" class="xref">Fig. 4</xref>), suggesting desert-like precipitation conditions over those areas after the impact. Soil moisture near the surface decreased by up to 40% for the 500-Tg ejection scenario and 50% for the 1500-Tg and 2600-Tg ejection scenarios in the equatorial zone (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3" class="xref">Fig. 3</xref>), which may have caused significant damage to the tropical herbaceous and broad-leaved vegetation, except for tropical broad-leaved evergreens
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b45" class="xref">45</xref>, leading to further loss of soil moisture and vegetation. The decreasing cover and size of vegetation patches resulted in further losses of soil and water, which led to further vegetation loss
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b62" class="xref">62</xref>. The herbivorous dinosaurs ate the decreased number of plants, resulting in the disappearance of vegetal food, similar to overgrazing leading to desertification today
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b63" class="xref">63</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b64" class="xref">64</xref>, which could have led to the extinction of the dinosaurs. Survival of freshwater-dwelling vertebrates such as crocodilians is dependent the availability of food, such as birds, mammals, fish, reptiles (turtles, snakes), amphibians, and macroinvertebrates and the base of the food webs being plant detritus
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6" class="xref">6</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b65" class="xref">65</xref>. The riverine communities could have survived because their organic carbon was derived from detritus
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6" class="xref">6</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b65" class="xref">65</xref> and water sourced from the middle latitudes had sufficient precipitation.
</p>
