<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The family life in species with parental care typically creates a social environment in which traits such as offspring begging and parental feeding that are expressed by one family member exert a selective pressure on the trait expression in another family member. As a result, these traits should ultimately become genetically correlated 
  <a rid="pone.0070463-Wolf1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0070463-Wolf1">[1]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0070463-Klliker3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0070463-Klliker3">[15]</a>. Such genetic correlations are expected to be positive when parents control the level of parental provisioning and selection predominantly acts on offspring begging and vice versa in case of a negative correlation. Our experimental evidence is consistent with these theoretical predictions, suggesting that parents control feeding, which is further supported by our results on the stabilizing costs.
 </p>
 <sec id="s4a" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Covariation between offspring begging and parental feeding</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We found evidence for a positive and significant phenotypic covariation between offspring begging and parental feeding levels, the latter was estimated via the mean nestling growth rates of the foster nestlings parents reared. Thus, we were able to confirm the existence of a positive covariation between offspring begging and parental feeding, as has recently been reported in canaries 
   <a rid="pone.0070463-Hinde2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0070463-Hinde2">[16]</a>. This adds to the evidence and importance of the previous findings, even more so since we used a slightly different experimental design 
   <a rid="pone.0070463-Kelly1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0070463-Kelly1">[39]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0070463-Parker1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0070463-Parker1">[40]</a>. The positive phenotypic correlation may represent a truly genetic correlation 
   <a rid="pone.0070463-Curley1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0070463-Curley1">[4]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0070463-Hager1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0070463-Hager1">[17]</a>, but we cannot rule out that environmental factors before cross-fostering contribute to this relationship. In birds, prime candidates for generating such phenotypic covariation are effects that act via maternally derived egg components. Maternally derived steroid hormones in the yolk of bird eggs have been shown to modulate offspring begging behaviour in a number of bird species including canaries (e.g. 
   <a rid="pone.0070463-Schwabl1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0070463-Schwabl1">[41]</a>, reviewed in 
   <a rid="pone.0070463-Groothuis1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0070463-Groothuis1">[42]</a> but see e.g. 
   <a rid="pone.0070463-Mller1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0070463-Mller1">[35]</a>). Maternal yolk carotenoids transferred into the egg yolks may be another candidate to match offspring demand to parental feeding (e.g. 
   <a rid="pone.0070463-Biard1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0070463-Biard1">[43]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0070463-Helfenstein1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0070463-Helfenstein1">[44]</a>). Our experimental design, however, does not enable us to estimate the relative contributions of genes and other prenatally acting factors any further.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Even though we were able to confirm the outcome of a previous study, indirect measures of parental care were used, as the parental feeding levels were estimated via the growth pattern of the foster nestlings 
   <a rid="pone.0070463-Hinde2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0070463-Hinde2">[16]</a>. Thus, it remained to be shown whether these traits correlate at the behavioural level, which will also allow testing whether this relationship differs between males and females. We indeed found a significant relationship between the actual rate of parental feeding (to foster nestlings) and offspring begging, with no evidence for a sex specific pattern (but see 
   <a rid="pone.0070463-Klliker2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0070463-Klliker2">[10]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0070463-Hager1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0070463-Hager1">[17]</a>). However, the power to detect sex specific relationships on the behavioural level is likely to be lower as the rate of parental feeding is based on fewer feeding visits as it considers only one sex.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">However, the observed covariation indicates that the previously established (indirect) relationship also holds at the behavioural level. But this was only the case when considering the begging intensity at the highest level of food deprivation (after 90 min) as response variable. The reasons for this may be multifold:</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Offspring growth may in general represent a more robust measure for parental feeding, as it integrates the parental feeding over a period of 13 days. In contrast, parental feeding rates were recorded during 2 h sessions on a particular day, which is obviously a much shorter timeframe. Yet, offspring growth integrates not only a much larger timeframe, but also other aspects such as the parental responsiveness to (changes in) nestlings' food demand, while we control for variation in hunger level during the measurement of parental feeding by standardizing the satiation of the nestlings. Thus, there may be no covariation between offspring begging and actual number of dips at a certain hunger level, but with parental responsiveness to offspring needs 
   <a rid="pone.0070463-Klliker2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0070463-Klliker2">[10]</a>. This may be less well captured in our measure of parental feeding during a standardized 2 h observation. Experimental designs in which changes in begging demands are implemented, for instance by changing the brood size or using playbacks of begging nestlings (sensu 
   <a rid="pone.0070463-Klliker2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0070463-Klliker2">[10]</a>) could provide useful insights in this respect.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The standardization of both the begging and the parental feeding may also explain why we only find covariation between parental feeding and begging at the highest level of food deprivation. Before the parental feeding behaviour was recorded, nestlings were food deprived, and in contrast to the begging trial, in this case they were not satiated. Furthermore, parents need to pre-digest the food before feeding the nestlings (which can take up to 14 min from the time new food is introduced into the cage, N. Estramil pers. observ.), increasing once more the period of food deprivation. Finally, the begging intensity may have been higher at a given hunger level due to the presence of siblings in the nest. The begging intensity of nestlings during the video-recordings was, therefore, likely comparable to the level of nestlings, which were food deprived for 90 min. Thus, parental feeding may covary with offspring behaviour, when both are measured at similar hunger levels suggesting a close match between offspring demand and the rate of parental feeding.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s4b" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Costs to parents and offspring</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We investigated potential consequences of a mismatch between parental feeding and offspring begging on the basis of a reciprocal cross-fostering design. Our results suggest that parents control the amount of resources that are provided and that the costs of a mismatch are paid by the offspring:</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Firstly, the difference in begging behaviour between foster and focal nestlings did not affect the future reproductive investment of the mothers, neither in terms of total clutch mass or total number of laid eggs within and across years. This is in contrast with a previous study by Hinde and colleagues 
   <a rid="pone.0070463-Hinde1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0070463-Hinde1">[6]</a> showing that canary females that raised more demanding nestlings than their own laid fewer eggs in the following year, while the opposite was true for females that raised less demanding foster nestlings. These differences may relate to slightly different experimental designs. The breeding design of Hinde and colleagues 
   <a rid="pone.0070463-Hinde1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0070463-Hinde1">[6]</a> was more demanding, with females raising two broods in the first year and laying eggs in the second year of study. Furthermore, the focal nestlings in the previous study were raised by their own parents, while we applied a reciprocal cross-fostering. This may become relevant if the foster parents would influence the begging behaviour of the focal nestlings, which should be taken into account when interpreting the data. The reciprocal design may then lead to smaller differences within dyads. But this remains speculative, and it will require further studies to estimate the potential fitness costs for parents under a number of different conditions. As pointed out above, there is still a lack of studies investigating the costs that may stabilize coadaptation.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Secondly, the growth rate of the focal brood did not vary with the difference in begging intensity between foster and focal brood. Thus, offspring begging at a lower level than the biological nestlings benefited from the higher generosity of their foster parents, while offspring begging more vigorously than the biological nestlings were unable to extract sufficient resources to reach a higher growth rate than low begging nestlings. In fact, they may have been able to obtain slightly more food than the parents initially intended. However, these benefits may vanish due to the costs of begging (e.g. 
   <a rid="pone.0070463-Kilner4" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0070463-Kilner4">[26]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0070463-Noguera1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0070463-Noguera1">[45]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0070463-MorenoRueda1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0070463-MorenoRueda1">[46]</a>). The lack of long-lasting effects of the difference in begging on the clutch size and clutch mass of the daughters in the subsequent year further supports this argumentation
   <span class="monospace">. </span>Alternatively, the difference in begging intensity may be too small to have long-lasting consequences (but see 
   <a rid="pone.0070463-Hinde1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0070463-Hinde1">[6]</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Thirdly, daughters suffered from a mismatch between offspring begging and parental feeding in terms of future fecundity. We found a marginally non-significant tendency for a relationship between differences in parental feeding rates ( =  when using the growth rate as a proxy) between foster and focal parents and the future reproductive investment of the daughters. This implies that daughters made a smaller reproductive investment when they were raised by foster parents that were less generous than their biological parents and larger investment when raised by more generous parents. The most likely explanation for this are costs from (unrewarded) high levels of begging, given that there were no direct costs in terms of reduced growth rate (see above). Thus the possibilities to demand additional resources from the parents appear to be limited for the offspring, while the costs of changes in begging demand were smaller for parents than in a previous study 
   <a rid="pone.0070463-Hinde1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0070463-Hinde1">[6]</a>. Yet, this is also the first study to measure the costs to mothers and daughters in the same currency (clutch mass/size) within the same experiment, which facilitates the comparison between mothers and daughters. These results show that daughters' investment tend to be more affected by changes in parental feeding than their mothers by changes in begging demands, both suggesting that parents do have the control over feeding rates 
   <a rid="pone.0070463-Hinde1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0070463-Hinde1">[6]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0070463-Klliker3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0070463-Klliker3">[15]</a>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In general, our results provide evidence for covariation between offspring begging and parental feeding at the behavioural level and suggest that parents control the feeding rates. These findings may also be taken as evidence for a resolved conflict dictated by selection acting more strongly on offspring begging 
   <a rid="pone.0070463-Klliker3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0070463-Klliker3">[15]</a>. However, we did not find direct antagonistic fitness consequences 
   <a rid="pone.0070463-Kilner1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0070463-Kilner1">[7]</a>. Conversely, parents may be too powerful for the offspring to manipulate feeding and therefore, this conflict will never emerge at the phenotypic level 
   <a rid="pone.0070463-Kilner1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0070463-Kilner1">[7]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0070463-Mock3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0070463-Mock3">[47]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0070463-Alexander1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0070463-Alexander1">[48]</a>. More detailed empirical studies on parent-offspring interactions and the fitness costs to both counterparts will be necessary to understand how this covariation is maintained.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
