<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s3d" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Costs of the cross-fostering for offspring</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There was no effect of the difference in begging between foster and focal nestlings on the growth rate of focal nestlings (LM, 
  <span class="italic">F
   <sub>1,32</sub>
  </span> = 1.76, 
  <span class="italic">r
   <span class="sup">2</span>
  </span> = 0.02, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.19, 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0070463-g003" href="#pone-0070463-g003">Figure 3</a>). This was also the case when using only the daughters in the analysis (LM, 
  <span class="italic">F
   <sub>1,18</sub>
  </span> = 0.33, 
  <span class="italic">r
   <span class="sup">2</span>
  </span> = 0.02, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.57). The difference in begging demands did not have significant long-lasting effect on the clutch size (GLM, 
  <span class="italic">z
   <sub>24</sub>
  </span> = 0.01, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.99) or clutch mass (LM, 
  <span class="italic">F
   <sub>1,24</sub>
  </span> = 1.04, 
  <span class="italic">r
   <span class="sup">2</span>
  </span> = 0.042, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.32) laid by the daughters in their first breeding season. However, the clutch mass of the daughters tended to be affected by the difference in parental feeding rates between foster and focal parents, when using the difference in growth rate between foster and focal nestlings as a proxy of changes in parental feeding rate (
  <span class="italic">F
   <sub>1,24</sub>
  </span> = 4.10, 
  <span class="italic">r
   <span class="sup">2</span>
  </span> = 0.11, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.054, 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0070463-g004" href="#pone-0070463-g004">Figure 4A</a>). This indicates that daughters tend to lay heavier clutches when they are raised by foster parents feeding at higher rates than focal parents and vice versa. However, no such tendency was observed when using the difference in number of dips between foster and focal parents as explanatory variable (
  <span class="italic">F
   <sub>1,24</sub>
  </span> = 0.66, 
  <span class="italic">r
   <span class="sup">2</span>
  </span> = 0.01, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.43, 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0070463-g004" href="#pone-0070463-g004">Figure 4B</a>). The clutch size of daughters was not significantly affected by the difference in growth rate between foster and focal nestlings ( =  proxy of changes in parental feeding rate) (GLM, 
  <span class="italic">z
   <sub>24</sub>
  </span> = 0.35, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.73) or by the difference in number of dips between foster and focal parents (
  <span class="italic">z
   <sub>24</sub>
  </span> = −0.24, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.81).
 </p>
 <div id="pone-0070463-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0070463.g003</span>
  <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Changes in begging demands and their effects on offspring growth.</div>
   <p>The difference in mean brood begging intensities between foster and focal broods measured after 90 min of food deprivation had no significant effect on the growth rate of the focal nestlings.</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0070463.g003" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <div id="pone-0070463-g004" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0070463.g004</span>
  <span class="label">Figure 4</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Consequences of a change in parental feeding behaviour on the reproductive investment of the daughters.</div>
   <p>The total clutch mass (2011) of the daughters tended to be affected by (A) the difference in growth rate between foster and focal nestlings (2010), but not by (B) the difference in feeding rate ( = total number of dips given during a 2 h video session) between foster and focal parents (2010).</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0070463.g004" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
