<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s3a" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Covariation between offspring begging and parental feeding rate</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There was no significant relationship between the begging intensity of focal nestlings and the total number of dips given by the focal ( =  biological) parents to foster nestlings (LMM, 
  <span class="italic">F
   <sub>1,15</sub>
  </span> = 0.64, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.44, 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0070463-g001" href="#pone-0070463-g001">Figure 1A</a>). Nor was there such a relationship between the begging intensity of focal nestlings and the total number of dips given by their foster parents (
  <span class="italic">F
   <sub>1,15</sub>
  </span> = 1.03, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.33). Removing the term “total number of dips given by foster parents”, which was included to control for the effect of the feeding rates of the foster parents on the begging of the focal nestlings, made little difference to the results (
  <span class="italic">F
   <sub>1,16</sub>
  </span> = 1.12, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.31). However, when using the begging intensity after 90 min of food deprivation (maximum begging level) as the only response variable, we found a positive and significant covariation between the begging intensity of the focal nestlings and the total number of dips given by their biological parents (
  <span class="italic">F
   <sub>1,15</sub>
  </span> = 4.9, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.043).
 </p>
 <div id="pone-0070463-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0070463.g001</span>
  <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Relationship between begging intensity and parental feeding.</div>
   <p>The mean brood begging intensity of focal nestlings after 60 (grey) and 90 (black) minutes of food deprivation did not covary significantly with (A) the feeding rate of the focal parents ( =  the total number of dips given by the focal parents to their foster nestlings during a 2 h video session), but with (B) the mean growth rate of the foster nestlings ( = proxy of the intensity of parental feeding of the focal parents).</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0070463.g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">No significant relationship was found between the begging intensity of focal nestlings and the total number of dips given by the focal father (
  <span class="italic">F
   <sub>1,15</sub>
  </span> = 0.36, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.56) nor with the foster father (
  <span class="italic">F
   <sub>1, 15</sub>
  </span> = 0.15, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.71). Removing the term “total number of dips given by the foster father” made little difference to the results (
  <span class="italic">F
   <sub>1,16</sub>
  </span> = 0.36, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.56). A lack of covariation was also observed between the begging intensity of focal nestlings and the total number of dips given by the focal mother (
  <span class="italic">F
   <sub>1,15</sub>
  </span> = 0.03, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.87) and the foster mother (
  <span class="italic">F
   <sub>1,15</sub>
  </span> = 2.15, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.16). Removing the term “total number of dips given by the foster mother” made little difference to the results (
  <span class="italic">F
   <sub>1,16</sub>
  </span> = 0.25, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.62).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Similarly, we did not find evidence for covariation between the begging intensity of focal nestlings at 90 min of food deprivation and the feeding rate of each parent (focal father: 
  <span class="italic">F
   <sub>1,15</sub>
  </span> = 2.2, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.16; focal mother: 
  <span class="italic">F
   <sub>1,15</sub>
  </span> = 0.02, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.89). Removing the term “total number of dips given by the foster father” and “total number of dips given by the foster mother”, respectively, made little difference to the results.
 </p>
</sec>
