<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2d" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Offspring begging intensity</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Begging tests were performed on day five after hatching, when the nestlings still do not show a fear response, following a previously established protocol 
  <a rid="pone.0070463-Hinde2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0070463-Hinde2">[16]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0070463-Goodship1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0070463-Goodship1">[33]</a> with slight modifications. Briefly, before testing, each focal nest was removed from its cage and all nestlings were fed until satiation with Orlux Handmix (Orlux Versele, Laga Belgium). We selected two intermediate nestlings per nest, and placed each of them individually in a wooden test box (10*10*13 cm
  <span class="sup">3</span>) and returned the nest with the remaining nestlings to their original cage. We completely removed the food from the cage 15 min before starting each trial to ensure that the remaining nestlings were not fed while focal nestlings were tested. Each wooden box had two lids, enabling us to open the top and the upper half of the front section of the box when testing. Each box was filled with expanded polystyrene in the lower half. This filling had a central hole (2 cm diameter, 1.5 cm deep) where the nestling was placed. Once a nestling was placed in the central hole, the lids were closed. Each box was moved to a heated climate room (29–30°C) and placed on a separate table (since the vibrations of tapping and the light and vibration stimulus when opening a given box - rather than the (very soft) begging calls of other tests elicit begging, NE pers. observation). After 60 min of food deprivation, the box was opened and we immediately tapped the box three times with an iron bar (21 cm, 51.63 g). Each nestling received, therefore, sound and light stimuli once the box was opened. The begging behaviour of all nestlings was video recorded using Sony video cameras (DCR-SX 30). Each trial ended after five seconds without begging. We closed the boxes and repeated the begging test 30 min later (90 min of food deprivation). In most cases, a maximum of eight nestlings were tested at one time. After testing, we returned the nestlings to their original cage, fed all nestlings until satiation with Orlux Handmix and placed the food back in the cage. Videos were analysed using Windows media player. Nestling begging intensity after 60 and 90 min of food deprivation was estimated by giving a score every second (0 =  not begging; 1 =  gape open; 2 =  gape open, head back; 3 =  gape open, head back and neck stretched; 4 =  as in 3 plus back vertical) and summing up all the scores over the time period, according to 
  <a rid="pone.0070463-Kilner4" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0070463-Kilner4">[26]</a>.
 </p>
</sec>
