<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2g" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analyses</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Shapiro-Wilk and Bartlett tests were used to analyse the normality and homogeneity of variance, respectively. We tested for a relationship between offspring begging and the actual parental feeding rate of both parents by using a linear mixed model. In this case, mean brood begging intensity of focal nestlings was used as response variable and the total number of dips given by focal and foster parents as covariates. Mean brood begging represents the average value of two nestlings per nest, except in two cases where only a single nestling could be included, and forms a repeated measurement (after 60 and 90 min of food deprivation). Nest identity and dyads were used as random effects with nest identity being nested in dyads. The feeding behaviour of foster parents was included to control for its effect on the begging levels of focal nestlings. Since nestlings were more responsive after 90 min of food deprivation, we applied a similar test by using begging intensity of nestlings at 90 min as the only response variable.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We repeated these analyses (i.e. either by using the begging intensity at 60 and 90 min as repeated measurements or only 90 min) using the total number of dips given by male and females, separately.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A similar linear mixed model was applied to test for a relationship between offspring begging and growth rate ( =  proxy of the parental feeding behaviour) with mean brood begging intensity of focal nestlings (after 60 and 90 min of food deprivation) as response variable and mean growth rate of foster nestlings as covariate. In this case, the mean growth rate of focal nestlings was kept to control for the effect of parental feeding of their foster parents on their begging levels.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Begging at 90 min of food deprivation was used as an estimate for the maximum begging levels for the analyses of parental reproductive costs and offspring growth costs. Differences in begging intensities between focal and foster nestlings indicate changes in demand. Therefore, we applied multiple linear regressions to test whether changes in nestling demands had an effect on the investment of the parents (mothers) in subsequent clutches. Total clutch mass of the second or the third clutch respectively, was used as a dependent variable whereas the difference in begging intensity and the total number of eggs laid in the first clutch were used as covariates, in order to control for intrinsic variation in egg size/egg mass.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Similarly, we applied a generalized linear model (Poisson distribution) by using either the total number of eggs laid in the second or the third clutch as the dependent variable and begging intensity differences and total number of eggs laid in the first clutch as covariates. In two nests, data were only available for clutch size but not for clutch mass.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To test whether focal nestlings pay a cost of begging at a different rate than foster nestlings, we used a simple linear regression with growth rate as the response variable and changes in begging demands as the explanatory variable. We repeated this analysis for the daughters, only. We also applied a simple linear regression to test whether the clutch mass of daughters was affected by changes in begging demands and a generalized linear model (Poisson distribution) to test for this effect on clutch size. No covariation would be expected under stabilizing selection and parental control, if parents do not increase their feeding rate when exposed to more demanding nestlings.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The effect of parental feeding changes on the future investment of the daughters was tested by applying a simple linear regression with total clutch mass laid in 2011 as a response variable. Either the difference in number of dips given by foster and focal parents during the 2 h video recordings or the difference in growth rate between the foster and focal nestlings was used as a covariate. A similar test was applied with clutch size laid in 2011 as response variable (generalized linear model, Poisson distribution).</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We use a top-down strategy to obtain the minimal. We use a top-down strategy to obtain the minimal model, starting with the model that contains all fixed explanatory variables and their interactions. When applying nested models, the random structures were compared by using restricted maximum likelihood (REML) estimators while the optimal fixed structure was obtained by using maximum likelihood (ML), as described in 
  <a rid="pone.0070463-Zuur1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0070463-Zuur1">[38]</a>. All reported statistical tests were two-tailed and executed in R, version 2.10.1 (R development core team 2009; 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.r-project.org" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.r-project.org</span>). The alpha value was 0.05.
 </p>
</sec>
