<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>An additional consequence of climate change to amphibians could be local population declines or extirpations [
 <xref rid="pone.0222097.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0222097.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0222097.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. Perhaps not surprisingly, the dominant predictor for the number of returning spotted salamanders was precipitation during the migration period, which has long been recognized as the primary stimulant for initiating migrations in ambystomatid salamanders [
 <xref rid="pone.0222097.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0222097.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0222097.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. Reduced springtime precipitation from climate change would likely reduce the number of migrating adults due to insufficient migratory cues and conditions, whereas reduced precipitation during the dry season (i.e., summer) could affect population size through larval desiccation if ponds dry early [
 <xref rid="pone.0222097.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0222097.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. In fact, the influence of migration period precipitation in the two-year time-lag analyses suggests an important link between migrant abundance and recruitment that affects future abundance (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0222097.s002">S2 Fig</xref>). Once again though, we observed no trends related to precipitation that led to obvious long-term changes in population size (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0222097.g002">Fig 2A and 2B</xref>). Finally, climate warming can also have positive effects on population size [
 <xref rid="pone.0222097.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>], and we observed a potential link between summer warming and increased male abundance across our study period (
 <xref rid="pone.0222097.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Climate change models in our study region predict increased precipitation for all seasons [
 <xref rid="pone.0222097.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], and while this could have an overall benefit to the species by further increasing population sizes, it may also contribute to a larger skew in sex ratios.
</p>
