<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The responsiveness of different amphibian species or populations to a changing climate will depend on how a variety of species-specific characteristics determine individual sensitivity and adaptability to climate change. Certain populations may be at higher risk depending upon their geographical position within the species distribution (i.e., a climatic extreme; [
 <xref rid="pone.0222097.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]), as well as their total range sizes. Spotted salamanders have a large range size across most of eastern North America and this population does not lie at a distributional limit; both of which may make them less susceptible to climatic changes than species with smaller range sizes [
 <xref rid="pone.0222097.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. With respect to phenology, changes in migration timing will depend on seasonal differences in climate change, such as whether climate warming occurs for autumn versus spring migrants (e.g., [
 <xref rid="pone.0222097.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]). From an eco-physiological perspective, pond-breeding ambystomatids might be less susceptible to climate change than stream-dwelling, plethodontid salamanders because the latter are lungless and particularly sensitive to changes in moisture and temperature. Species and populations at higher elevations are also more susceptible to range contractions and extirpations than those at lower elevations [
 <xref rid="pone.0222097.ref064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. Indeed, documented climate change impacts on high elevation plethodontids have been more dramatic than that of ambystomatids [
 <xref rid="pone.0222097.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0222097.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0222097.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0222097.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Different species will also vary in their susceptibility to indirect effects of climate change from other stressors, such as susceptibility to infectious diseases [
 <xref rid="pone.0222097.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0222097.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0222097.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0222097.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Even within the same habitats, some species will be more vulnerable to this interaction whereas others serve mainly as vectors and are only weakly affected [
 <xref rid="pone.0222097.ref029" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>].
</p>
