<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Estimating thermal niche (and potential distribution) using distribution and climatic data</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For each of the taxa we compiled georeferenced distributional data from our own records, specialized publications and other unpublished information to estimate the extremes of the climatic conditions within their entire ranges. To characterise current thermal niches we used the mean annual temperature from the entire study area at 0.08 degree spatial resolution cells from WORLDCLIM version 1.3 (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.worldclim.org" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.worldclim.org</span>)
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b42" href="#b42">42</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To compute the bioclimatic models, we first estimated for each species the temperature in the observed presence localities (i.e. the estimated temperature of the cave), and then calculated the extreme climatic values for their whole range. Then, assuming that temperature is the most important factor to characterise their climatic niche and that these recorded occurrences are representative of the full climatic conditions in which the species may survive and reproduce, we used these extreme values to derive a distributional hypothesis on the areas with climatically (thermal) suitable conditions (considered here as the potential distribution)
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b7" href="#b7">7</a>. Basically, all grid cells with climatic values falling within the mentioned range were designated as suitable, and all cells outside it as unsuitable. We use this “bioclimatic envelope” procedure to be conservative, as it is an established procedure directed at maximizing the capacity to represent geographically the potential distribution of species niches when they are only based on distributional data
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b43" href="#b43">43</a>.
 </p>
</sec>
