<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">For analyzing the change in seasonality of climate variables in response to different surface conditions, we focus on 9 of the 26 subcontinental regions defined in the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change Special report on Managing the Risks of Extreme Events and Disasters to Advance Climate Change Adaptation (SREX; Seneviratne et al., 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-bib-0078" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). While there is substantial spatial variability in climate variables within these large domains, these regions are widely used for comparing the response of climatic variables to various external forcings (e.g., Greve et al., 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-bib-0030" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2018</xref>; Hirsch et al., 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>; Kharin et al., 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-bib-0038" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2018</xref>; Seneviratne et al., 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-bib-0078" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>; Thiery et al., 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-bib-0082" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>), providing a standard set of domains for future comparisons across models. The boundaries of these nine regions—Central America/Mexico (CAM), Central Asia (CAS), Central Europe (CEU), Central North America (CNA), East Asia (EAS), South Europe/Mediterranean (MED), South Asia (SAS), Tibetan Plateau (TIB), and West Asia (WAS)—are shown in Figure 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>. These are the subset of regions that have relatively high modern‐day irrigation rates and are characterized by intensive agricultural production (Figures 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>a and 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>b). The exception is TIB, which is included due to its proximity to the heavily irrigated regions in Asia. The seasonal cycle of irrigation requirements in the IrrigatedCrops scenario along with the LAI in the NatVeg and Crops scenarios in each region is shown in Figure 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>c. We calculate area‐weighted averages of surface temperature and precipitation over land within these regions.
</p>
