<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The land surface properties and irrigation rates of these regions are summarized in Table 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-tbl-0001" ref-type="table" class="xref">1</xref>. The average cropped fraction across the nine SREX regions varies from 0.45 over WAS to 0.72 over CNA (Figure 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S1</xref> and Table 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-tbl-0001" ref-type="table" class="xref">1</xref>). Although crops replace a variety of vegetation types, crops lower the average vegetation heights over all the study regions (Table 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-tbl-0001" ref-type="table" class="xref">1</xref>), with implications for reduced roughness lengths. Across the nine SREX regions, the model LAI—an indicator of plant growth—is higher for crops relative to natural vegetation (Figure 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>a and Table 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-tbl-0001" ref-type="table" class="xref">1</xref>). The LAI typically peaks during the boreal summer season, except in SAS and CAM, where the peak LAI occurs in the fall season (Figure 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>c). Irrigation rates vary substantially between these regions, with the heaviest rates over SAS (Figure 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>b and Table 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-tbl-0001" ref-type="table" class="xref">1</xref>). Within these regions, there is considerable variation in the seasonal cycle of irrigation requirements (Figure 
 <xref rid="jgrd55039-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>c). For instance, the peak irrigation in SAS occurs during the premonsoon and early‐monsoon season, whereas the peak in other regions occurs during the primary growing season of June–September. Because irrigation is applied in most months of the year and crop growth in some regions peaks following the boreal summer season, the climatic responses to these forcings (i.e., land cover change and applied irrigation) could extend to multiple seasons beyond the primary growing season.
</p>
