<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Under the high emission scenario (RCP 8.5), little auk energy requirements should decrease during the twenty-first century within their current core wintering areas (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS171883F4" class="xref">figure 4</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="RSOS171883TB2" class="xref">table 2</xref>). Under the low emission scenario (RCP 2.6), their energy requirements are predicted to decrease only in January (
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="RSOS171883TB2" class="xref">table 2</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS171883F4" class="xref">figure 4</xref>). The RCP 2.6 represents a high mitigation scenario that aims to keep global warming to less than 2°C above pre-industrial temperatures [
 <xref rid="RSOS171883C7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>]. A decrease in energy requirements during winter is therefore likely for little auks, and could be beneficial for them as well as for other wintering seabirds. In order to anticipate the future distributions of wintering migrants, it is also necessary to know how their prey will react to ongoing environmental changes, and two scenarios can be considered: (1) if prey biomass remains constant, winter visitors could stay in their current wintering areas, especially if those become energetically more profitable, due to climate warming. However, (2) if prey abundance decreases in this area, they may have to move to follow their current prey distribution and/or target different prey species. It is therefore imperative to understand whether little auk wintering areas off Newfoundland will remain highly productive during winter, thereby supporting scenario (1), or if changes in ocean circulation may modify primary productivity and associated food webs. Higher temperatures are known to favour smaller zooplankton species [
 <xref rid="RSOS171883C58" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">58</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSOS171883C59" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">59</xref>]. Therefore, prey biomass has to be maintained to sustain the rest of the food web, including migratory bird populations. Yet, over the past 40 years, a decrease in total zooplankton biomass has been observed in the Northeast Atlantic and the same phenomenon is predicted to occur in the Northwest Atlantic [
 <xref rid="RSOS171883C60" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">60</xref>].
</p>
