<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par21" class="p">The impact of climate change and human activities on the grassland NPP in the TRHR. The results of this study demonstrate that precipitation and temperature are the most important climatic factors driving changes in grassland NPP within the TRHR. Previous studies have also recovered similar results and have shown that increased temperature and precipitation are the key factors influencing grassland vegetation growth since the underlying mechanism is significantly increased growing season length
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">17</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" class="xref">53</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" class="xref">55</xref>
 </sup>. This analysis also shows that although a ‘warm and moist’ climate trend has been beneficial to increasing grassland NPP, the rate at which this has risen has been faster in relatively drier and warmer regions. This result may be due to the main climatic features of the TRHR; because of the harsh alpine-subalpine environment in this area, total annual precipitation and mean annual temperature remain low during the grassland growth period. This means that although precipitation and temperature are factors that limit plant growth, the spatiotemporal distribution of grassland NPP in the TRHR is nevertheless strongly correlated with both these variables. At the same time, as solar radiation is another key factor determining plant photosynthesis, vegetation growth in small watersheds that are characterized by relatively abundant rainfall and low altitude will also be limited by this variable
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" class="xref">56</xref>
 </sup>. A decreased level of solar radiation induced by enhanced precipitation may therefore mitigate the otherwise positive effect of this variable on plant growth; in other words, precipitation and temperature are more beneficial in smaller watershed with lower levels of rainfall and favorable temperatures.
</p>
