<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par22" class="p">Previous studies have also shown that human activities, including anthropogenic changes to grassland cover, cause major disturbances to alpine grassland ecosystems
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" class="xref">43</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" class="xref">57</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" class="xref">59</xref>
 </sup>. Indeed, since the 1990s, an economic boom in this region has rapidly increased the population level within the TRHR (Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S4</xref>). Grassland ecosystems have therefore evolved as a consequence of frequent disturbances
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" class="xref">60</xref>
 </sup>, especially in middle and eastern areas of the TRHR where intensive human activities have resulted in the over-exploitation of grassland resources
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">1</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" class="xref">61</xref>
 </sup>. The results of this study suggest that economic development and human population growth across the TRHR may have had a negative impact on grassland NPP, while meat production has the opposite effect. These changes might be due to GDP growth (Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S4</xref>) while increases in population can lead to the conversion of grasslands to cropland and construction land; although these influences will result in degraded grassland
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" class="xref">62</xref>
 </sup>, an increasing level of meat production might also encourage herdsmen to pay more attention to grassland management and thus could promote the NPP of these ecosystems
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" class="xref">63</xref>
 </sup>. We have also demonstrated that the negative effects caused by human activities are significantly moderated by grassland percentage area; the limitations that result from climatic and topographic conditions mean that human activities within the TRHR are concentrated in central and eastern smaller watersheds which are rich in grassland resources. As these smaller watersheds are therefore subject to more pressure from human activities, the results of this study also support the widespread view that economic development and population levels both harm alpine grassland ecosystems.
</p>
