<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In Amazonia, as elsewhere, climate change is a potential leading driver of changes to the ecosystem. During the last few decades, the climate of Amazonia has become more extreme—the length of the dry season and its intensity have increased, while precipitation has become more intense during the wet season (Gloor et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14413-bib-0055" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>; Hilker et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14413-bib-0057" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>). Extreme climate events in recent years include the three strong droughts within a decade (Erfanian, Wang, &amp; Fomenko, 
 <xref rid="gcb14413-bib-0035" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>; Jiménez‐Muñoz et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14413-bib-0060" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>; Lewis, Brando, Phillips, Van Der Heijden, &amp; Nepstad, 
 <xref rid="gcb14413-bib-0068" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>; Marengo, Tomasella, Alves, Soares, &amp; Rodriguez, 
 <xref rid="gcb14413-bib-0077" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>; Marengo et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14413-bib-0076" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>) and several large‐scale episodes of extreme rainfall (Espinoza et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14413-bib-0036" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>; Marengo &amp; Espinoza, 
 <xref rid="gcb14413-bib-0075" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>). In addition to the repeated drought events, precipitation has declined in the south and south east of the basin (25% reduction in rainfall between 2000 and 2012) (Hilker et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14413-bib-0057" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>) and higher temperatures are likely to have intensified seasonal evaporative stress across the basin (Jiménez‐Muñoz, Sobrino, Mattar, &amp; Malhi, 
 <xref rid="gcb14413-bib-0061" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>). These changes are consistent with model‐based predictions (Duffy, Brando, Asner, &amp; Field, 
 <xref rid="gcb14413-bib-0029" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>), implying that the Amazon may already have entered a new regime of a hotter, more variable climate. The forest has clearly responded to these recent fluctuations in climate—for example, tree mortality rates increased markedly during and after drought events causing at least temporary losses of standing biomass (Brienen et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14413-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>; Feldpausch et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14413-bib-0046" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>; Phillips et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14413-bib-0092" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>; Zuleta, Duque, Cardenas, Muller‐Landau, &amp; Davies, 
 <xref rid="gcb14413-bib-0118" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). The 2010 drought also impacted on the basin‐wide exchange of carbon dioxide between the vegetation and the atmosphere, with the vegetation becoming a net source of CO
 <sub>2</sub> during 2010 (Gatti et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14413-bib-0052" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>).
</p>
