<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Forging a Superordinate Identity to Reduce Intergroup Environmental Conflict</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conflict between groups on environmental issues has the potential to impede progress on addressing these issues. As we outlined above, intergroup conflict reinforces the boundaries between groups so that group members relate more to each other as group members, and are therefore more likely to exhibit ingroup-favoring attitudes and behaviors. When thought of in this way it is easy to see how this type of intergroup context can stand in the way of developing bi-partisan climate change policy, or sustainable resource allocation that benefits the environment as well as other stakeholders.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One way that negative intergroup relations could be transformed is through forging a more inclusive superordinate identity that encompasses conflicting subgroups (
  <a rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37">Gaertner et al., 1993</a>; 
  <a rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36">Gaertner and Dovidio, 2000</a>; 
  <a rid="B65" ref-type="bibr" href="#B65">Opotow and Brook, 2003</a>). Focusing sub-group members on a higher order, superordinate group identity helps to shift the context from one of ‘them’ and ‘us’ to ‘we’. Past research has shown that this strategy can reduce prejudice and discrimination (
  <a rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36">Gaertner and Dovidio, 2000</a>) because outgroup members are now part of the ingroup and are therefore accorded the benefits of ingroup membership. 
  <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">Batalha and Reynolds (2012)</a> highlight the importance of superordinate identity as a way to develop more effective global negotiations around climate change mitigation. Drawing on the Actualizing Social and Personal Identity Resources model (ASPIRe model; 
  <a rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39">Haslam et al., 2003</a>), they argue that negotiations may be more effective if subgroups are formed that reflect the mutual concerns and interests of like-minded nations and that these subgroups then work together to forge a superordinate framework. The ASPIRe model provides a process for forming superordinate identity beginning with identifying the current social identities that people use to define themselves, followed by the formation of subgroups and the articulation of subgroup goals. The final steps involve the overarching organizational group—incorporating all subgroups—formulating superordinate group goals that inform subsequent action. More broadly, the social identity literature suggests that conditions for making a group such as a superordinate identity ‘real’ are accessibility of the identity, fit (as discussed in section “The Fluidity of Social Identity”), and entitativity (i.e., a combination of interdependence, common fate, physical proximity, similarity; 
  <a rid="B63" ref-type="bibr" href="#B63">Oakes et al., 1991</a>; 
  <a rid="B80" ref-type="bibr" href="#B80">Sherman et al., 1999</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a rid="B73" ref-type="bibr" href="#B73">Samuelson et al. (2003)</a> also provide a concrete example of how conflict between stakeholders over watershed restoration efforts can be transformed through forging a new superordinate identity. The formation of the San Antonio Watershed Council involved bringing a variety of stakeholders together in a structured communication setting that allowed collaborative learning. The formation of the new group identity allowed stakeholders from different subgroups who came with opposing positions to reach consensus and develop a set of recommendations to improve the quality of the watershed.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Forging a superordinate identity, though, should not entail group members losing or negating their subgroup identity. In fact, research has shown that there are greater reductions in intergroup bias when people identify with both their subgroup and a superordinate group simultaneously (
  <a rid="B45" ref-type="bibr" href="#B45">Hornsey and Hogg, 2000a</a>,
  <a rid="B46" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46">b</a>). In the context of intergroup environmental conflicts, 
  <a rid="B65" ref-type="bibr" href="#B65">Opotow and Brook (2003)</a> argue that retaining subgroup identities can allow the positive attitudes that can develop because of shared superordinate group identity to generalize to the broader subgroup. For example, in the context of the conflict relating to fracking of coal seam gas in Australia, the Lock the Gate Alliance includes farmers and environmentalists, groups that are usually not in alliance. To the extent that Lock the Gate members retain their subgroup identities, this makes it more likely that farmers and environmentalists can develop more positive, nuanced and less stereotypical impressions of each other’s groups. Preserving subgroup identities also reduces the risk that subgroup identities are threatened (
  <a rid="B45" ref-type="bibr" href="#B45">Hornsey and Hogg, 2000a</a>) and allows an appreciation of the distinctiveness of subgroup identities such as the expertise and experiences of specific subgroups (
  <a rid="B65" ref-type="bibr" href="#B65">Opotow and Brook, 2003</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
