<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Influence of Intergroup Conflict</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As we noted previously, negative and competitive intergroup relations may arise when ingroup members perceive illegitimate status differences between their own group and other relevant outgroups (
  <a rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10">Branscombe et al., 1999</a>; 
  <a rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25">Ellemers et al., 2002</a>). In addition to climate change, many other environmental issues are marked by just this type of context: the issues are highly contested and often involve the imposition of regulations and decisions by powerful outgroups. Examples include the imposition of environmental regulation on farmers; water allocation decisions that trade-off between water for the environment, agriculture, and the community; or the conflict between groups over fracking of coal seam gas. These latter contexts are often seen as ‘David and Goliath’ situations where mining companies and government agencies are perceived to be powerful agents who propagate unilateral decisions. Although social identity theory does not argue that all intergroup contexts lead to ingroup bias and outgroup derogation, the power differences and perceived illegitimacy that flows from these types of contexts can lead ingroup members to perceive the decisions as unfair and to resist them. A study by 
  <a rid="B33" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33">Fielding et al. (2008b)</a>, for example, showed that when rural landholders perceived more negative relations between rural and urban Australia (with urban Australia the site of government who develop regulation that impacts on rural landholders) they had lower intentions to manage their riparian zones.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When people come into conflict over environmental issues or resources, their social identities come to the fore. People stereotype each other in ingroup-favoring ways (e.g., “we are the defenders of the environment, they are the destroyers”) and outgroup members are denigrated and can be morally excluded from the scope of justice (
  <a rid="B66" ref-type="bibr" href="#B66">Opotow and Weiss, 2000</a>; 
  <a rid="B65" ref-type="bibr" href="#B65">Opotow and Brook, 2003</a>). Research by 
  <a rid="B65" ref-type="bibr" href="#B65">Opotow and Brook (2003)</a> provides evidence of these processes in the context of environmental protection regulation. When a threatened species act was introduced, ranchers and environmentalists came into conflict. The ranchers viewed the threatened species as insignificant, and characterized non-ranchers as inexperienced, irresponsible, and the cause of the problem. In contrast, ranchers viewed themselves as stewards of the environment who made fair environmental decisions. Despite their espoused environmental stewardship, ranchers were wary of government regulation to protect wildlife, a stance that reinforces environmentalists’ notions that ranchers are anti-environment.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Interestingly, some environmental issues can give rise to emergent group identities that center around strongly held positions [i.e., opinion-based groups (
  <a rid="B60" ref-type="bibr" href="#B60">McGarty et al., 2009</a>)]. For example, 
  <a rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9">Bliuc et al. (2015)</a> found that U.S. respondents saw their position as a climate “believer” or “skeptic” as distinct social identities in their own right, and that they perceived each other through a hostile intergroup lens. When political affiliation overlaps with these opinion-based identities, identity faultlines can emerge that make objective appraisals of evidence psychologically implausible. Another example of conflict giving rise to emergent social identities is the conflict that has arisen over fracking of coal seam gas in Australia. Unlikely alliances have emerged between environmental group members, farmers, conservative politicians, and media presenters who oppose fracking, with government agencies and mining companies perceived as the salient outgroup (
  <a rid="B48" ref-type="bibr" href="#B48">Hutton, 2012</a>; 
  <a rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16">Colvin et al., 2015b</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There are important consequences of these identities that emerge out of environmental conflict. The alignment of climate change attitudes with political party identity lends an intense and competitive intergroup dynamic to what should be even-handed discussions about science and truth. When framed within an entrenched intergroup context, solutions advanced by one political party are likely to be dismissed by political opponents simply because they emanate from the outgroup. Similarly, in relation to the ‘Lock the gate’ movement, the emergent social identity becomes a short cut for deciding whether someone is friend or foe and whether to attend to or trust information from them. To the extent that information comes from people, who are perceived to be aligned with the outgroup, ingroup members are more likely to dismiss it regardless of its veracity (
  <a rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1">Abrams et al., 1990</a>; 
  <a rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" href="#B55">Mackie and Queller, 2000</a>; 
  <a rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26">Esposo et al., 2013</a>). In this way intergroup distinctions become entrenched and the potential to reach compromise or develop viable solutions becomes less likely.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although intergroup conflict can stymy progress on environmental issues, it should be noted that a degree of intergroup conflict is inevitable when pushing for social change, and that the alternative to conflict is often an unhealthy stasis. The social identity model of collective action (SIMCA; 
  <a rid="B99" ref-type="bibr" href="#B99">van Zomeren et al., 2008</a>) highlights the fact that collective action is an important precursor for change, and that willingness to engage in collective action is partly driven by identification with social groups. In their meta-analysis of the collective action literature, 
  <a rid="B99" ref-type="bibr" href="#B99">van Zomeren et al. (2008)</a> showed that stronger social identifications were associated with greater willingness to engage in collective action, and that this was particularly the case when identification was measured with respect to a disadvantaged group or a social movement (so-called “politicized” identities). Other research demonstrates that group identification is positively associated with the belief that the group can be effective in reaching its collective goals (
  <a rid="B98" ref-type="bibr" href="#B98">van Zomeren et al., 2010</a>), suggesting a virtuous cycle of identification leading to action leading to positive change leading back to identification.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Of course, reality is more complex than this: whether or not collective action readiness is viewed as positive and legitimate will likely depend on the type of collective action (whether it is violent or non-violent; whether it involves trade-offs with economic goals, etc.). Furthermore, although environmental collective action often involves a range of people from many walks of life, research has shown that people hold negative stereotypes of environmentalists as militant, aggressive, unconventional, and eccentric (
  <a rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7">Bashir et al., 2013</a>). 
  <a rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7">Bashir et al. (2013)</a> showed that participants had lower pro-environmental intentions when they were exposed to an article promoting environmental sustainability written by a journalist who was a typical environmentalist (i.e., a person who organizes rallies to protest harmful chemicals) than one who was an atypical environmentalist. With this in mind it is easy to see how messages that emanate from environmental groups that are perceived to be extreme may gain little traction with the broader populace and could even polarize people away from support for important environmental issues (
  <a rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9">Bliuc et al., 2015</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
