<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s6" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Features of the Trends in Cumulative RF.</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our calculations show the impact of the offsetting effects of the GHG emissions and aerosol emissions. As noted in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" href="#fig01">Fig. 1</a>, the difference between the RF with and without aerosols is roughly 1 W m
  <span class="sup">−2</span>. This contribution, which has significantly offset the GHG contributions in many regions, can change markedly as air quality is improved, which is important for health benefits now as well as in the future. In the past, net RF has rapidly increased for North America, the Pacific region, and Europe. China is just recently “breaking out” as its emissions are not increasing exponentially, and measures are being taken to control air pollution. Accelerating emissions are required for aerosol cooling to continue to offset the warming by long-lived GHGs. The accelerating emissions are tied to both economic growths and any controls that are placed due to air quality. India is starting to consider air-quality deterioration and its aerosol emissions are unlikely to continue to accelerate indefinitely. Therefore, one should expect that India would also break out to positive cumulative RF in the next decade or two. Of course, avoiding this pattern could be one of the goals of other regions.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the future, other regions may experience rapid growth in their contributions to net RF as air quality is improved. Indeed, if all emissions (including GHGs) ceased in 2017, global net RF would be larger than today for 15–20 y until GHG concentrations decayed enough to offset the roughly −1 W m
  <span class="sup">−2</span> of aerosol forcing (
  <a rid="r33" ref-type="bibr" href="#r33">33</a>). How could the rest of the world avoid the temporary cancellation/huge commitment scenario followed by North America, Europe, and China? In the absence of large-scale removal of CO
  <sub>2</sub> from the atmosphere, avoiding the commitment would require a transition to low-GHG emissions before the exponential growth/high-pollution pattern rather than first using a high-GHG economy and then transitioning away from GHGs.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One of the differences between cumulative RF and either ocean heat content or temperature change is the inclusion in cumulative RF of the energy represented by 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="i5" class="math">
    <div class="mrow">
     <div displaystyle="true" class="mstyle">
      <span class="mo">∫</span>
     </div>
     <span class="mi">λ</span>
     <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">Δ</span>
     <span class="mi">T</span>
     <span class="mi">d</span>
     <span class="mi">t</span>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div> term. This term represents the energy that maintained/maintains the Earth at a warmer temperature. The regional contributions to global temperature in, for example, 2100, consider only the temperature in 2100, not keeping the Earth warmer between now and 2100. Because it takes into account the energy needed to maintain a warmer Earth, the cumulative RF may be a useful and appropriate measure of future commitments. On the other hand, the temperature is more closely related to impacts of climate change than cumulative RF. The same considerations apply to GTP and GWP metrics: GTP is more closely related to climate impacts but GWP calculations are simpler and more certain.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The relative contributions of different regions and nations to the forcing of climate change depends more strongly on what is included in the comparison and the time frames of the examination rather than whether the metric is cumulative RF, temperature change, or ocean heat content. This result is analogous to the calculation of GWPs for individual climate forcing agents: The time horizon chosen for the GWP is generally more important than other details of the way the GWP is defined. One should not minimize the importance of the metric: Even a few percentage points in a global contribution might have large economic consequences. But, the time frame of the comparison (e.g., now, 2100, or some other time horizon) and the inclusion or exclusion of future RF from GHGs already in the atmosphere are much more important to regional contributions than the specific metric used to compare various regions.</p>
</sec>
