<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Other Metrics of Future Contributions.</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">Fig. 2</a> shows that considering only today’s RF can be misleading because the commitment to future RF from GHGs already in the atmosphere exceeds the net cumulative forcing to date. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3</a> shows several metrics (cumulative RF, ocean heat content and temperature) of the regional contributions to today’s and future climate forcing. (The details of this calculation are given in 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1813951115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>
  </span>.) The regions are shown as percentages of the global total because that minimizes, although does not entirely eliminate, the dependence on overall climate sensitivity. The solid black bars in the 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3</a> (
  <span class="italic">Top</span>) are equivalent to the solid black bars in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">Fig. 2</a>.
 </p>
 <div id="fig03" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 3.</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Metrics of regional contributions to climate forcing now and in 2100. Shown are the estimated contributions to cumulative RF, ocean heat content, and temperature for today or 2100 under various scenarios.</p>
  </div>
  <div id="gra3" xlink:href="pnas.1813951115fig03" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The “no emissions after 2017” (second panel from the top) in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3</a> is not intended as a realistic scenario but instead shows future commitment already baked in due to past emissions. The bottom two panels show calculations based on the widely used scenarios presented in the IPCC reports, i.e., the RCPs. Here we explore the future under two commonly used RCPs––RCP 8.5 when the forcing in 2100 would be 8.5 W m
  <span class="sup">−2</span> [the so-called “business as usual” scenario] (
  <a rid="r16" ref-type="bibr" href="#r16">16</a>), and RCP-2.6 when the forcing in 2100 would be 2.6 W m
  <span class="sup">−2</span>, which would require major controls in place (
  <a rid="r31" ref-type="bibr" href="#r31">31</a>). One simple message that emerges in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3</a> is that the contribution of North America is the largest to date, irrespective of the metric used. North America’s contribution remains roughly the same, except for the RCP 8.5 scenario where China contributes slightly more than North America by 2100.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Some other general conclusions about regional contributions can be seen by examining the contribution from China in the various panels. China provides a good example because it has large and rapidly changing emissions (
  <a rid="r32" ref-type="bibr" href="#r32">32</a>) rather than any special feature of its mix of emissions. In 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3</a>, China’s percentage of the global total varies much more from the top to bottom panels than it does for various metrics within each panel. Considering the top two panels, there is a very large change in China’s contribution if only current conditions are considered or if future commitments are included, but the various bars for China are not all that different within each comparison. Considering the bottom two panels for China, the scenario for future emissions matters much more than which metric is used to measure the regional contributions.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The choice of metric to measure regional contributions is more important for 2017 (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3</a>, 
  <span class="italic">Top</span>) than commitments to 2100 (second from top). Again, using China as an example, the choice of metric can make about a factor of 2 change to its contribution to 2017 climate but only a modest change to its contribution to 2100. The reason is that the metrics respond differently to short-lived climate forcing, especially aerosols, which have a shorter lifetime than any of the GHGs. In contrast, for percentage contributions to the commitment to climate forcing it hardly matters which metric is used. Even by 2100––less than 100 y from now––most of the already committed climate forcing is from one species, CO
  <sub>2</sub>. In that case, and further into the future, the choice of metric becomes less important than it is for estimating contributions in the present (
  <a rid="r4" ref-type="bibr" href="#r4">4</a>). Beyond 2100, most of the committed forcing is from CO
  <sub>2</sub> so the percentage contributions of various regions to cumulative forcing past 2100 is fairly similar to their percentage contributions to cumulative CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Overall, 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3</a> shows that the percentage contribution of each region to the global climate is strongly affected by two factors: the pattern of economic development (e.g., RCP 2.6 or 8.5), and by how commitments to future RF are included. The latter is analogous to the known dependence of GWPs on the time horizon used to calculate GWP. In contrast, the choice of climate variable is less important to the percentage contributions by different regions.
 </p>
</sec>
