<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Under our future projections of amplified drought-conditioned temperature shifts in the southern United States, the occurrence of concurrent extremes will likely increase and exacerbate the impacts anticipated from individual extremes. This is exceedingly important as dry lands are becoming more widespread under climate change, which will widen the documented temperature impact (
 <xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">30</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">31</italic>
 </xref>). In addition, these conditional temperature shifts will compound on the increased probability of more extreme, warm events in projected pathways of climate warming (
 <xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">32</italic>
 </xref>). We anticipate severe socioeconomic consequences to accompany these drought-conditioned temperature shifts. The consequences may include disruptions of local and global food systems, damages to public health and quality of life, and the expansion of areas vulnerable to concurrent extremes (
 <xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">33</italic>
 </xref>). Society can respond to these observed and projected concurrent events by studying the effects of these natural threats and improving the resilience of our systems to these threats. Future studies should focus on the ramifications of these temperature shifts to quantify projected risks on population health, food supply, and infrastructure. From these studies, we can propose changes in urban development and settlement patterns to reduce population exposure to extremes, improve agricultural cultivation and trade, and adapt building infrastructure to the changing climate—all responses that can alleviate the negative impacts of these intensifying extremes (
 <xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">33</italic>
 </xref>).
</p>
