<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3" class="p">Soils in the northern permafrost region contain ~1300 ± 300 Pg of soil organic carbon (SOC)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">1</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">3</xref>
 </sup>, more than one-third of the global total SOC
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">4</xref>
 </sup>, formed under cold climates with limited decomposition. Carbon release from this large pool due to warming-induced thawing and acceleration of microbial decomposition may act as an important positive feedback to climate change, but the magnitude and timing of this carbon release remains uncertain
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">3</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">5</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>
 </sup>. Model estimates of changes in permafrost extent and carbon stocks vary widely for the recent decades
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">8</xref>
 </sup> as well as for future scenarios
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">9</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>
 </sup>, partly because different representations of soil thermodynamics lead to different soil temperature responses to air temperature changes. For the ground surface, the energy budget is composed of net radiation, sensible heat, latent heat from evapotranspiration, and heat flux into and out of the ground. On the other hand, below the surface, thermal dynamics is dominated by heat conduction
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">11</xref>
 </sup> driven by surface soil temperature variations, and also affected by latent heat released or absorbed during soil water phase changes which can be important for wet soils in permafrost regions
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">12</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
