<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par6" class="p">Here we infer 
 <italic class="italic">D</italic> from two large data sets of depth-specific soil temperature measurements, the Russian Historical Soil Temperature Data
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">23</xref>
 </sup> (hereafter RHST) and the International Polar Year Thermal State of Permafrost
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">24</xref>
 </sup> (hereafter IPY), at 274 locations that spread throughout Russia and North America including permafrost and non-permafrost regions (Supplementary Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">1</xref>). A key requirement for Eqs. (
 <xref rid="Equ4" ref-type="" class="xref">4</xref>) and (
 <xref rid="Equ5" ref-type="" class="xref">5</xref>) to be valid for inferring 
 <italic class="italic">D</italic> using real-world soil temperature profiles is that non-conductive processes, like the latent heat associated with soil freezing, have minor impacts on the heat budget of soils at seasonal-cycle time-scale. Therefore, we examined the shape of temperature profiles at each site and selected only the sites where monthly temperature oscillations conform to sinusoidal functions, that is, to the solution (Eq. [
 <xref rid="Equ4" ref-type="" class="xref">4</xref>]) of heat conduction (see detailed data processing and discussion in Methods). After this data-filtering, 184 sites were retained. The calculated 
 <italic class="italic">D</italic> value using Eq. [
 <xref rid="Equ5" ref-type="" class="xref">5</xref>] can approximately represent the thermal diffusivity for the bulk soil in the corresponding depth interval at those selected sites. Then, we searched for emerging relationships between the observation-derived 
 <italic class="italic">D</italic> values and a suite of soil properties extracted from broad-scale soil maps, in order to identify the dominant factors that control 
 <italic class="italic">D</italic> and subsequently the propagation of temperature waves from ground surface to deeper soils. We find that SOC is the strongest predictor to explain the variability of 
 <italic class="italic">D</italic> among sites. Using the same method to calculate 
 <italic class="italic">D</italic> from CMIP5 model outputs, we find that the different parameterization of 
 <italic class="italic">D</italic> in these models dominates their large-scale performance in simulating today’s permafrost extent. Further with a land surface model, we show that the thermal insulation of SOC increases modelled present-day permafrost carbon stock (0–3 m depth) by 39% ( + 230 Pg C) and permafrost area by 33% (+3.4 million km
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>), increasing agreement with broad-scale observational data. These findings demonstrate the need to explicitly represent the coupling between SOC and soil thermal dynamics in models that are utilized to project future permafrost changes.
</p>
