<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Transmission by 
 <italic class="italic">I. ricinus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">I. persulcatus</italic> ticks of TBEV to wildlife hosts typically results in short-term infection that might not be disseminated beyond the site of the tick bite. As a consequence, the transmission cycle of TBEV appears to rely largely on simultaneous feeding (co-feeding) by infected nymphs and uninfected larvae in close proximity on the host's body [
 <xref rid="RSTB20140051C116" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">116</xref>]. For TBEV to be maintained in an enzootic cycle that can result in zoonotic transmission, it is often assumed that some degree of synchrony in the seasonal questing activity of larval and nymphal ticks is therefore necessary [
 <xref rid="RSTB20140051C117" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">117</xref>], a view supported by the large contribution of co-feeding transmission to 
 <italic class="italic">R</italic>
 <sub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">0</sub> in an NGM model [
 <xref rid="RSTB20140051C91" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">91</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSTB20140051C92" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">92</xref>]. An NGM model of Powassan virus, a close relative of TBEV, that explicitly included the overlap between larval and nymphal feeding, suggests that climatic factors that reduce their synchrony will reduce enzootic transmission, although modest vertical transmission might still maintain the virus populations [
 <xref rid="RSTB20140051C93" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">93</xref>]. Kurtenbach 
 <italic class="italic">et al.</italic> [
 <xref rid="RSTB20140051C108" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">108</xref>] suggested that, like other pathogens that cause only short-lived infections in reservoir hosts, TBEV maintenance might be facilitated by milder climates that permit extended host-seeking activity of both larvae and nymphs, which should result in seasonal overlap and co-feeding. It stands to reason that climate changes that reduce temporal overlap between larval and nymphal feeding would reduce the risk of TBE. Long-term studies will be necessary to evaluate this expectation.
</p>
