<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par55" class="p">
 <italic class="italic">Challenge 2: Enhancing the application of technological mitigation options.</italic> For this analysis, a limited set of specific technological (i.e. technical and management-based) GHG mitigation options has been introduced into the modelling approach. In our mitigation scenario, almost all EU crop production would potentially use the provided mitigation options in 2030. On the other hand, based on the included set of options, the impact of a change in livestock production management and technology on overall EU agriculture emissions tends to be rather limited. As a consequence, the largest part of the required GHG reduction is realized by a quantitative adjustment of production (herd size, yield and cultivated hectares). A similar result is likely at global level if the mitigation targets were implemented worldwide. It has to be noted that the modelled set of technologies does not include all available technical and management-based mitigation options (e.g. feed additives to reduce methane emissions from enteric fermentation or genetic improvements steered to increasing milk yields of dairy cows are not modelled). Taking more options into consideration and assuming a wider applicability, say due to additional farm structure change or accelerated technological maturation, could potentially downscale any negative impacts on the EU’s agricultural production and trade in our scenario (see, e.g. Witzke et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" class="xref">2014</xref>). The importance of technical and management-based options for the mitigation of agricultural emissions is also indicated in the international literature and seems to have particularly great potential for emissions reduction in developing countries (Henderson et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">2017</xref>; Hristov et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">2013</xref>; Smith et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" class="xref">2007</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" class="xref">2014</xref>). However, it might need specific incentives and support measures (e.g. investment support or training) to trigger and facilitate the implementation of mitigation technologies both within and outside the EU. Moreover, regarding the latter technology transfer may play an important role for emission mitigation, specifically for developing countries (Tilman et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" class="xref">2011</xref>; Somanathan et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">2014</xref>; Stavins et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" class="xref">2014</xref>).
</p>
