<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The cores used in this study were from the collection of Liu et al. (
 <xref rid="ece33836-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>) in 2011, by SCUBA divers using a push core with a 6 cm internal diameter. Four replicate cores were taken at each site to enable a range of different parameters to be analyzed. The purpose of the study by Liu et al. (
 <xref rid="ece33836-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>) was to investigate the impact of pearl farming on the sediment quality; hence, they chose one contrasting reference site 1.5 km away from the pearl aquaculture area (Figure 
 <xref rid="ece33836-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>c; reference site: 16°32′S, 122°59′E; water depth: 9.8 m). In this study, one of the cores (106 cm long) from the reference site was used for biomarker analyses (TEX
 <sub class="sub">86</sub>, long‐chain 
 <italic class="italic">n</italic>‐alkanes, brassicasterol, and dinosterol). These biomarkers were not used in the previous study of Liu et al. (
 <xref rid="ece33836-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>), as they focused on the analysis of chronology and geochemical parameters (organic matter, carbon and nitrogen isotopes, biogenic silica) to examine whether aquaculture had induced any change in the sediment over time. The replicate core used in this study had a similar sediment texture compared to other cores at the reference site, and the median grain size (d
 <sub class="sub">50</sub>) between replicate cores was significantly correlated at a 95% confidence level (Liu et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33836-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). The core we used covered a time span of approximately 1916–2011, according to the dating result (sedimentation rate: 1.11 cm/year) in Liu et al. (
 <xref rid="ece33836-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). This study focused on the data variations for the period 1940–2011, matching the observational data from Australian Bureau of Meteorology.
</p>
