<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par19" class="p">Our analysis of the multi-model mean by design emphasizes the externally forced response and leads us to propose the following indirect attribution argument for Sahelian climate change, past and future. In the second half of the twentieth century, as global dimming (Stanhill and Cohen 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" class="xref">2001</xref>; Liepert 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" class="xref">2002</xref>) opposed global warming in the northern hemisphere, a unique combination of anthropogenic emissions contributed to the late twentieth century drying of the Sahel through their effect on sea surface temperatures: aerosols by cooling the North Atlantic and greenhouse gases by warming the tropical oceans, especially the Indian Ocean. Warming of the global tropical oceans “upped the ante” for deep convection (Chou and Neelin 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">2004</xref>; Held et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" class="xref">2005</xref>), while the absence of warming in the North Atlantic reduced the moisture supply to the monsoon and thus its  potential to meet the “upped ante” and to trigger vertical instability (Giannini et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">2008</xref>). Our argument is distinct from others previously proposed, which attributed late twentieth century Sahel drought solely to aerosols, whether through cooling of the North Atlantic or of the entire northern hemisphere (Rotstayn and Lohmann 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" class="xref">2002</xref>; Kawase et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" class="xref">2010</xref>; Ackerley et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">2011</xref>; Booth et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">2012</xref>; Hwang et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">2013</xref>
 <italic class="italic">;</italic> Park et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" class="xref">2015</xref>; Wang et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" class="xref">2016</xref>), in three ways. First of all, we argue for an 
 <italic class="italic">indirect effect</italic> of anthropogenic emissions, i.e., mediated by sea surface temperatures. Linking emissions to Sahel rainfall through SSTs has the added advantage that it allows the synthesis in a single physical explanation of 
 <italic class="italic">natural</italic> variability and 
 <italic class="italic">anthropogenic</italic> change. Secondly, our argument is not about the role of interhemispheric gradients in SST shifting the latitudinal location of the Intertropical Convergence Zone and by extension rainfall in the Sahel. Rather, it is about 
 <italic class="italic">quasi-equilibrium in convection</italic> as the world warms. The observed late twentieth century drying of the Sahel was more profound—longer lasting and of greater amplitude—than, e.g., the early twentieth century drought around 1910, despite the North Atlantic being cooler during the early period. This observation justifies the search for additional factors in drought, which we identify in greenhouse gas-induced tropical warming, which in the twentieth century occurred simultaneously with North Atlantic cooling. Therefore, thirdly, we argue for the 
 <italic class="italic">combined drying effect</italic> of the two contrasting anthropogenic influences in twentieth century: drought was not caused by aerosols alone or by the cooling of the North Atlantic alone. Neither could it have been caused by greenhouse gases alone, as is made evident in simulations which include only the latter forcing (Biasutti 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">2013</xref>; Dong and Sutton 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">2015</xref>; Gaetani et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" class="xref">2017</xref>; Hill et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">2017</xref>). Rather, drought resulted from the combination of aerosols and greenhouse gases. One influence cooled and reduced the moisture supply, while the other, warming, raised the threshold for convection—a double jeopardy. In the twenty-first century, external influence is dominated by GHG-induced warming, of both the North Atlantic and global tropical oceans. NARI, their difference, tends to zero, leaving all response to external forcing to be explained by their sum.
</p>
