<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par20" class="p">SVD rotation of the original predictors to their weighted sum and difference and the relative sizes of their regression coefficients (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" class="xref">2</xref>) expose the near-orthogonality of the twentieth and twenty-first centuries in the response of SSTs and rainfall to external forcing. The oceans’ translation of external forcing of predominantly anthropogenic nature leads to contrasting but not inconsistent outcomes in the past and the future. Late twentieth century drying and twenty-first century projections of wetting are consistent with different balances in the influences of aerosol and greenhouse gas emissions on regional energy and moisture budgets, underlined by one coherent physical explanation rooted in the dynamics of quasi-equilibrium in convection. The fact that emissions need to be considered holistically, not additively, explains how it is possible that while anthropogenic warming had a role in past drought, continued warming in the twenty-first century gives rise to a strengthening of the monsoon. As aerosol emissions have abated, especially around the North Atlantic, it is the combination of warmings of both North Atlantic and global tropical oceans that explains the strengthening of the monsoon: the upped ante can now be met. This situation is consistent with understanding of monsoon response to warming on paleoclimate time scales: when the ocean warms enough to contribute to an “upped ante” with increased moisture supply but not enough to shift the favored locus of convection from land to ocean (Chou et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">2001</xref>), it reinforces the monsoon, as is the case for West Africa (Braconnot et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">2012</xref>). With the usual caveats related to uncertainty in multi-model mean projections, that further warming may result in wetting of the Sahel is a conclusion worth reinforcing, in equal parts because it has gained in coherence between CMIP3 and CMIP5 (Biasutti 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">2013</xref>), and because the recovery of the rains is being experienced on the ground, in a fashion that is remarkably consistent with expectation from anthropogenic warming (West et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" class="xref">2008</xref>; Lodoun et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">2013</xref>).
</p>
