<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>However, the meteorological and hydrological processes that drive flooding from land and sea are, to a certain extent, related. The co-occurrence or close succession of a heavy precipitation event and a storm surge is driven by deep low-pressure systems (
 <xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>1</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>2</italic>
 </xref>). Although heavy precipitation alone can be caused by convection without intense cyclonic activity (
 <xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>8</italic>
 </xref>), the latter is also a precondition for storm surges (
 <xref rid="F1" ref-type="fig">Fig. 1</xref>). Intense cyclones drive storm surges through strong winds pushing water toward the coast and the barometric pressure effect (
 <xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>3</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>9</italic>
 </xref>). CF can be caused by several mechanisms (
 <xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>2</italic>
 </xref>). A storm surge can block or slow down the precipitation drainage into the sea (
 <xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>3</italic>
 </xref>), causing flooding along the coast (
 <xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>2</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>6</italic>
 </xref>). Runoff from a river may require a certain time to drain into the sea such that precipitation may have to occur well before the storm surge. Similarly, flood levels of a storm surge may be amplified by any relevant amount of precipitation (
 <xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>2</italic>
 </xref>). Last, a flood may occur when precipitation falls on wet soil that is saturated by a preceding storm surge. The relative importance of these mechanisms in a particular location depends on both the local climate and topography (
 <xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>2</italic>
 </xref>), but all of the above implies that storm surges and extreme precipitation runoff are often not independent phenomena. Therefore, ignoring their dependence may substantially underestimate the resulting CF risk (
 <xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>2</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>3</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>6</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>10</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>11</italic>
 </xref>).
</p>
