<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par42" class="p">Sea temperature, sea ice duration, iceberg disturbance, melt water run-off and plankton blooms are all rapidly changing in the polar-regions [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">8</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">14</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">23</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" class="xref">63</xref>]. It is, therefore, important to understand the key factors that will determine the structure of soft sediment communities into the future [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" class="xref">64</xref>]. The results of this study suggest that increased sedimentation from melting glaciers may be the biggest impact of current climate change on soft sediment communities [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">8</xref>]. Previous studies of Antarctic shallow water sedimentary meiofauna have concentrated on areas of rapid glacier retreat with the aim of understanding re-colonisation processes [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">20</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">22</xref>]. These suggest that the microfauna may respond more slowly than the more mobile macrofauna [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" class="xref">19</xref>]. Thus studies such as the one described here, where sediment communities are described across all size classes of organism (from macro- to microfauna) are vital to understanding not only community structure, but also ecosystem functioning and trophic interactions. One particular issue that needs to be addressed in the future is the correlation between species composition, energy transfer and nutrient cycling, as this has far-reaching implications for the wider benthic ecosystem and bentho-pelagic coupling. The meio- and microfauna in sediments can only be efficiently characterised using molecular methods. Metabarcoding provides a catalogue of species, but not their functions, whereas often with the megafauna there is at least rudimentary knowledge of the feeding modes (primary consumer, secondary consumer, carnivore, scavenger, detritivore, etc.) and therefore a basic classification within the food web. In the future these molecular types of studies need to be more closely linked to genomic shotgun sequencing and transcriptomic approaches to evaluate active biochemical processes in the sediment and identify the species responsible for them. This will significantly aid in our understanding of the functional roles of the various community components present in these poorly studied environments, and their potential responses to future climate change.
</p>
