<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par37" class="p">These dominance differences and also the differences between coves revealed by the two techniques may be due to several reasons. The main one is obviously size selection, as suction sampling only collected organisms larger than 1 mm in size, which almost certainly accounts for the dominance of bivalves, particularly 
 <italic class="italic">Altenaeum charcoti</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Aequiyoldia eightsi.</italic> The vast majority of nematodes and crustaceans are too small to be sampled by the suction sampler but will be picked up by metabarcoding. However, the other major factor is the potential destruction of fragile or soft bodied species during the collection for morphotaxonomy, particularly nematodes and Platyhelminthes. Metabarcoding would identify these taxa as present, even if individuals were lethally damaged and unrecognizable as whole animals. eDNA samples include traces of animals, such as mucus trails, faeces, decaying tissue in the sediment and early life history stages that can be detected at the molecular level, even if not physically observed in the sample. In spite of these differences, some taxa were common to both techniques and the results of both techniques validated the overall higher taxonomic diversity in South Cove than Hangar Cove and a similar level of difference between the coves. The combined data of the current study, coupled with the high numbers of unique taxa, indicate that regional biodiversity (β-diversity) is high. They also emphasize the utility of combining different techniques to gain a more complete picture of overall biodiversity in soft sediments, particularly for the soft bodied microfauna [cf. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" class="xref">44</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" class="xref">50</xref>]. Overall both approaches proved to be quite complementary where the 18S rRNA gene allowed to assess general ecological patterns at higher taxonomic rankings like family or genus level but it also served as an auxiliary tool in this study, where information on morphological characteristics was available and also an additional marker such as the COI gene provided species-level resolution. Further to this, the eDNA approach also revealed high numbers of unassigned taxa (NAs) mainly reflecting the poor existing reference databases for Antarctic species [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" class="xref">51</xref>]. Additionally, the 18S marker is well known to have a poor species-level resolution mainly due to being highly conservative [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" class="xref">52</xref>]. Consequently some assignments will likely be assigned to non-polar species, which will significantly decrease the accuracy and number of the taxonomic assignments.
</p>
