<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-plants-08-00271" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1. Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Global climate change causes non-uniform warming, with faster and stronger warming in high latitudes and altitudes where tundra exists [
  <a rid="B1-plants-08-00271" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-plants-08-00271">1</a>]. Tundra develops at low temperatures, and air warming will affect many other environmental factors such as moisture and nutrient availability, and thus directly or/and indirectly influences eco-physiological functions of plants [
  <a rid="B2-plants-08-00271" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-plants-08-00271">2</a>]. Even a relatively small increase in temperature has caused strong responses of plants in the tundra ecosystem [
  <a rid="B3-plants-08-00271" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3-plants-08-00271">3</a>,
  <a rid="B4-plants-08-00271" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-plants-08-00271">4</a>]. It has been expected that present and future warming could lead to pronounced effects on tundra plants. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Many studies have reported phenology [
  <a rid="B5-plants-08-00271" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-plants-08-00271">5</a>], shrub expansion [
  <a rid="B6-plants-08-00271" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6-plants-08-00271">6</a>], growth [
  <a rid="B7-plants-08-00271" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-plants-08-00271">7</a>,
  <a rid="B8-plants-08-00271" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8-plants-08-00271">8</a>], gas exchange [
  <a rid="B9-plants-08-00271" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9-plants-08-00271">9</a>], morphological changes [
  <a rid="B10-plants-08-00271" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10-plants-08-00271">10</a>], and anatomical changes [
  <a rid="B11-plants-08-00271" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-plants-08-00271">11</a>] in tundra plants in response to warming. Among these changes, the photosynthetic adjustment was found to be relatively rapid and sensitive to warming, while alterations in leaf morphology and anatomy showed adaptive responses to long-term warming.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Low temperature is one of the most important limiting factors determining the growth of alpine and tundra vegetation. Generally, photosynthesis increases with increasing leaf temperature until temperature reaches an optimum [
  <a rid="B12-plants-08-00271" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12-plants-08-00271">12</a>]. Therefore, the positive effect of warming on photosynthesis is expected for vegetation growing in the tundra. It has been widely reported that warming has increased photosynthetic carbon uptake for arctic tundra vegetation [
  <a rid="B13-plants-08-00271" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13-plants-08-00271">13</a>,
  <a rid="B14-plants-08-00271" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14-plants-08-00271">14</a>,
  <a rid="B15-plants-08-00271" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-plants-08-00271">15</a>,
  <a rid="B16-plants-08-00271" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16-plants-08-00271">16</a>]. However, the magnitude and direction of photosynthetic responses of tundra plants to warming differ greatly with species. In-situ warming (+1.4 °C, 3 years) in the Antarctic has promoted photosynthetic assimilation in 
  <span class="italic">Colobanthus quitensis</span> but not in 
  <span class="italic">Deschampsia antarctica</span> [
  <a rid="B17-plants-08-00271" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17-plants-08-00271">17</a>]. The photosynthetic rate of 
  <span class="italic">Picea glauca</span> was 41% greater in OTCs (+1.8 °C warming, three growing seasons) compared to that in the controls [
  <a rid="B18-plants-08-00271" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-plants-08-00271">18</a>]. Knowledge of species-specific responses to warming can help to better understand and predict future changes in cover, abundance, distribution and adaptation of tundra plants in a changing world. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Warming has been shown to induce morphological and anatomical changes in plants grown in a variety of environments including tundra. Long-term warming (+1~2 °C, 16 years) has increased leaf size and plant height but decreased specific leaf area in 
  <span class="italic">Cassiope tetragona</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Salix arctica</span> in Canadian High Arctic tundra [
  <a rid="B19-plants-08-00271" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-plants-08-00271">19</a>]. Increased temperature (+1 °C, one growing season) has resulted in thinner leaves due to thinner epidermis, palisade and spongy layers in 
  <span class="italic">Populus tremula</span> [
  <a rid="B20-plants-08-00271" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-plants-08-00271">20</a>]. Warming has decreased the palisade-spongy ratio in 
  <span class="italic">C. tetragona</span> (subarctic, +3~4 °C, 23 growing seasons) and 
  <span class="italic">Empetrum nigrum</span> (Greenland tundra, +2.7 °C, two growing seasons) but has increased the thickness of the epidermis in 
  <span class="italic">C. tetragona</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Betula nana</span> (Greenland tundra, +2.7 °C, two growing seasons) [
  <a rid="B11-plants-08-00271" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-plants-08-00271">11</a>,
  <a rid="B21-plants-08-00271" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21-plants-08-00271">21</a>]. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Leaf anatomy showed acclimation to long-term warming. For example, Hartikainen et al. found that leaf anatomy can respond sensitively to short-term warming, but Schollert et al. showed no alterations of leaf anatomy to long-term warming [
  <a rid="B11-plants-08-00271" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-plants-08-00271">11</a>,
  <a rid="B20-plants-08-00271" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-plants-08-00271">20</a>]. The alterations in leaf anatomy can then affect photosynthetic gas exchange. For instance, increased leaf thickness and epidermis could be beneficial for water deficit and thus influence leaf physiology, and changes in palisade-spongy tissue ratio will change photosynthetic potential because palisade tissue has more chloroplasts [
  <a rid="B21-plants-08-00271" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21-plants-08-00271">21</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To better understand and predict tundra species and ecosystem responses to future warming, we studied leaf photosynthesis, morphology and anatomy of three dominant tundra shrubs (
  <span class="italic">Dryas octopetala var. asiatica</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Vaccinium uliginosum</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Rhododendron confertissimum</span>) which have been artificially warmed by OTCs in situ on the Changbai Mountain tundra for 7 years. We hypothesized that a continuous 7 years of warming would stimulate photosynthesis at the individual scale, but with different magnitudes for different species. The changes in morphology and anatomy would benefit to improve photosynthesis. Therefore, we expected some species with higher responses in photosynthesis and/or morphology and/or anatomy to have competitive advantages over the other species.
 </p>
</sec>
