<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Females are the dispersive sex in 
 <italic class="italic">P. aegeria</italic> responsible for between-population exchange and colonization
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27" class="xref">27</xref>. Female flight performance can be traded-off against life-history traits like fecundity
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17" class="xref">17</xref> and longevity (but in an ecotype-specific way
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20" class="xref">20</xref>). Males and females differ in flight pattern corresponding to different flight performances and energetic needs
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27" class="xref">27</xref>. In another butterfly, the relationship between FMR and flight duration was indeed positive in females, but not in males
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28" class="xref">28</xref>. So, northern females are predicted to have stronger performances for flight endurance and corresponding FMR compared to southern ones as they have to deal with a reduced time budget to spread their eggs across suitable host plants. Hence, northern females should be more mobile compared to southern conspecifics
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29" class="xref">29</xref>, but under the assumption of local adaptation, mobility may be compromised when reared under cooler conditions for southern individuals and warmer conditions for northern individuals. However, predictions are different for males. At low ambient temperatures, males principally adopt a territorial perching strategy, while they adopt a patrolling, searching strategy with longer periods of flight when ambient temperature is highest
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30" class="xref">30</xref>. Both behavioural strategies require different flight patterns
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31" class="xref">31</xref>; flight endurance, as measured here in a flight mill, better reflect flight performance during patrolling rather than for territorial perching, which principally relies on acceleration and maneuverability
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27" class="xref">27</xref>. Assuming higher specialization on perching in the north and in cooler woodland habitat compared to warmer agricultural habitat, we consequently predict lower flight endurance in the north, and particularly so in the woodland ecotype.
</p>
