<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Many predictions have been made concerning the likely impact of climatic change on forest tree species (e.g., 
 <xref rid="ref-64" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Zimmermann et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Cheaib et al., 2012</xref>). However, there are gaps in our knowledge concerning the contribution of differences in sensitivity to climate change between species, taking into account the pattern of genetic differentiation between populations within species. Large-scale shifts in growing conditions triggered by rapid climate change lead to changes in growth rate and shifts in species habitats during the lifetime of tree populations. Field studies are therefore required to clarify the role of genetic differentiation in these processes. Common garden data (provenance tests) for forest tree species have shown that broadly distributed forest tree species form genetically specialized populations, each of which is assumed to be optimally or almost optimally adapted to only a portion of the climatic niche occupied by the species as a whole (
 <xref rid="ref-39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Morgenstern, 1996</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-43" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Rehfeldt et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-47" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Sáenz-Romero et al., 2017</xref>). Given the general shortage of field-based data concerning genetic adaptation, common gardens may provide useful information (
 <xref rid="ref-33" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Mátyás, 1994</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-37" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Mátyás, Nagy &amp; Újvári-Jármay, 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-35" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Mátyás et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Leites et al., 2012a</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Leites et al., 2012b</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-43" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Rehfeldt et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-47" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Sáenz-Romero et al., 2017</xref>), even though their datasets are mostly imperfect, for biological, technical and conceptual reasons. These common gardens were set up for other purposes, principally for identifying the best provenances for plantation programs, as genecological perspectives and estimation of the impact of climate change had not yet become relevant at the time of planting. However, the transplantation of populations into common gardens may be interpreted as mimicking climatic change, and the impact of such change can be characterized by climatic transfer distance (ecodistance, 
 <italic class="italic">sensu</italic>
 <xref rid="ref-33" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Mátyás, 1994</xref>). The term “ecodistance” is defined as the difference between the investigated, ecologically relevant variables (in this case, climate) at the test site and at the population provenance (origin). Here, we revisit forest tree provenance tests originally designed decades ago for purposes other than predicting the impact of climate change. These data provide a unique opportunity to measure the response of trees in relation to ecodistance. If we substitute climatic space for time, we can use these data to anticipate the effects of ongoing climatic change on trees.
</p>
