<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Comparisons with ice core records</div>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">BC deposited on glaciers and recovered in ice cores can be used to infer the relative change in atmospheric total BC concentrations that occurred between the PI and the PD
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span>. Here we evaluate NH changes in BC concentrations in each dataset. We compare modelled PD/PI BC atmospheric concentration ratios (see Methods, Supplementary Figure 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">5</a>) to measured BC ice core ratios at four ice core locations: two in Greenland, and one in each of North America and Europe (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>). To minimise the large uncertainties associated with the absolute deposition
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
  </span>, we analysed only the ratio of PI to PD BC in the cores, assuming that trends can be more accurately modelled than absolute values. Our hypothesis is that a modelled PD/PI ratio that is higher than measured indicates that PI emissions are too low in the model compared to the PD. Although absolute BC deposition is uncertain
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
  </span> (see later discussion) we assume that the controlling factor in the PD/PI ratio across multiple independent sites will be the trend in emissions. Together these ice core records provide an estimate of how fire emissions have changed within, or downwind of, NH regions of intensive land use and land cover change over the last 200 years
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
  </span>.
  <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Present-day/pre-industrial ratio in ice core and modelled black carbon concentrations. Shown are two Greenland sites (D4 and NM), one North American site at Wyoming (WY), and one Swiss Alps site at Colle Gnifetti (CG). Bias factor in the present-day/pre-industrial (PD/PI) ratio for each modelled fire emission scenario (D4: red bars, NM: gold bars, WY: black bars, CG: blue bars). For model M and observation O the symmetric bias factor was calculated as: For M &gt; O: (M/O)–1; For O &gt; M: –(O/M) + 1. The AeroCom bias factor at the WY site is off the scale and shown as an arrow with its bias factor given. Measured PD/PI values shown as horizontal bars (±standard error of the mean bound Greenland estimates, see Methods) with the model simulations PD/PI ratio shown as dots (D4: red, NM: gold, WY: black, CG: blue). The WY and CG modelled ratio changes are scaled by a factor of 1.6 (1.2–2.0 in bias factor panel) and 2.0 (1.5–2.5 in bias factor panel) respectively to account for the change in BC concentration emissions near the site between the period of the PD measurement and the modelled concentration (see Methods). The AeroCom and CMIP6 changes at the WY and CG sites are off the scale and shown as open circles with the PD/PI ratio given</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2018_5592_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e676" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Overall (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>), global aerosol model simulations of the PD/PI ratio in BC concentrations using LMfire and SIMFIRE-BLAZE fire emissions are in closer agreement with ice core measurements than the global aerosol model simulation which uses the CMIP6 fire emissions dataset, although CMIP6 is an important improvement on the AeroCom dataset.
 </p>
 <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In Greenland the ice core BC in the PI is derived from wildland fires
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
  </span> transported from boreal North America
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>
  </span>, while in the PD it will also contain large amounts of BC from industrial activity
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
  </span>. Figure 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a> compares the aerosol model with the PD/PI ratio in ice core BC concentrations from the D4 core (2713 m above sea level) in central Greenland
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
  </span> and the NEEM core (2480 m above sea level) in northern Greenland
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>
  </span>. Using AeroCom emissions in the aerosol model results in a PD/PI atmospheric BC ratio that is a factor 2.2–3.1 higher at NEEM and a factor 5.6–8.6 higher at D4 than the measured BC ratio in the ice. These ratios suggest that assuming a positive relationship between human population density and fire occurrence results in PI fire emissions that are too low. Using CMIP6 emissions results in a PD/PI BC ratio that is a factor of 1.3–1.9 higher at NEEM and a factor of 2.9–4.5 higher at D4 than the measured BC ratio. Using LMfire emissions results in a PD/PI BC ratio that is a factor 1.7–2.4 lower at NEEM and between a factor of 1.3 higher and a factor of 1.1 lower at D4, while using SIMFIRE-BLAZE emissions results in a PD/PI BC ratio that is between a factor of 1.0–1.5 higher at NEEM and a factor of 2.0–3.1 higher at D4, than the measured BC ratio.
 </p>
 <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the Wyoming ice core
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>, which is 4100 m above sea level (see Methods), measured PD (1970–1979) BC concentrations are 37% lower than in the PI (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>). However, North American industrial BC emissions have been decreasing significantly since 1970
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>
  </span>, so to compare with our model simulation in 2000 we scale the model PD concentrations by a factor of 1.6 ± 0.4 in line with the CMIP6 changes in anthropogenic emissions, and the uncertainty, over this period (see Methods). The global aerosol model with AeroCom fire emissions results in a PD/PI BC ratio at the altitude of the measurement site that is a factor 21.2 (15.7–26.2) larger than the measured ratio in the ice core (0.6), again consistent with the hypothesis of fire emissions being too low in the PI with a positive scaling of fire occurrence with population density. Using CMIP6 emissions results in a PD/PI ratio that is a factor of 11.5 (8.5–14.2) higher than the measured BC ratio. Using LMfire emissions results in a PD/PI BC ratio that is a factor 1.2 (1.0–1.6) lower than measured, while using SIMFIRE-BLAZE emissions results in a PD/PI BC ratio that is 2.2 (1.6–2.7) higher than measured. Aerosol model results using fire model estimates of PI fire emissions are much closer to the measured PI to PD change in BC concentrations than the aerosol model results using the AeroCom and CMIP6 datasets, which predict far larger increases in BC from PI to PD.
 </p>
 <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the Colle Gnifetti ice core in the Swiss Alps, which is 4450 m above sea level
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>
  </span> (see Methods), BC concentrations averaged for 1950-to-1980 are a factor of 2.9 higher than in 1750 (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>). Total BC concentrations at this site are significantly higher in the PD than in the PI due to additional industrial emissions that are not present in the PI. Similarly to North America, European industrial BC emissions have been decreasing significantly since 1960
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>
  </span>. In Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a> we account for this known change by increasing the global aerosol model PD concentrations of BC by a factor of 2.0 ± 0.5 (see Methods). The global aerosol model with AeroCom fire emissions results in a PD/PI BC ratio, at the altitude of the measurement site, that is a factor 4.1 (3.1–5.2) larger than the PD/PI BC ratio recorded in the ice core; again, consistent with AeroCom PI emissions being too low. Using CMIP6 emissions results in a PD/PI ratio that is a factor of 2.7 (2.0–3.3) higher. Using LMfire emissions results in a PD/PI BC ratio that is a factor 1.6 (1.3–2.2) lower than the ratio recorded in the ice core, while using SIMFIRE-BLAZE emissions results in a PD/PI BC ratio that is 1.3 (1.0–1.6) higher than the ratio recorded in the ice core.
 </p>
 <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Due to the short atmospheric lifetimes of aerosol and soluble gases, ice cores store local-to-hemispheric-scale changes and contain many uncertainties as a proxy for fire emissions (see Methods). Nevertheless, we find that the changes in BC recorded in ice cores at four sites in very different environments are inconsistent with the assumption that fire emissions were significantly lower in the PI than in the PD, especially over North America and Europe. Compared to using fire emissions from the CMIP6 dataset, incorporating fire model emissions within the aerosol model results in closer agreement with the measured PD/PI ratio of total BC.</p>
</sec>
