<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The global occurrence of wildfire and biomass burning in the modern world is controlled by a combination of climate and human activity
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span>. The present-day (PD) pattern of fire (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>) is relatively well understood based on global satellite measurements of burned area
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span>. However, despite the importance of fire in the climate system in the past and present
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span>, current understanding of fire occurrence in the late pre-industrial Holocene (PI) is limited
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
  </span>. Analyses of ice core records, charcoal measured in lake and marine sediments, and tree-rings suggest that fire activity varied considerably over the last 500 years, but that generally fire occurrence increased to a peak around 1850 CE before declining to PD levels
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>
  </span>. Paleoenvironmental archives therefore suggest that PI fire activity was similar to PD activity, if not higher (Supplementary Figures 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a> and 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2</a> and Supplementary Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>). This runs contrary to existing ideas about the pristine nature of the Earth system in the PI, which is embodied in both the AeroCom 1750
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span> and the Coupled Model Intercomparison Project (CMIP) phase 5 and 6 aerosol emission datasets
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span>.
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Fire carbonaceous aerosol emissions. 
     <span class="bold">a</span> Pre-industrial (PI) and present-day (PD) carbonaceous fire emissions (sum of black and organic carbon) as a function of latitude. PI fire emissions derived from four fire datasets: LMfire, SIMFIRE-BLAZE, CMIP6 and AeroCom. PD fire emissions are from the CMIP6 dataset. The range around LMfire represents a plausible range in the natural variability of PI fire emissions derived from the maximum and minimum in fire emissions from the four distinct decadal mean fire climatologies. Seasonal PI carbonaceous aerosol emission maps are shown in Supplementary Figure 
     <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">4</a>. 
     <span class="bold">b</span> Black carbon emissions for PD from five datasets: LMfire, SIMFIRE-BLAZE, GFED4, GFAS and FINN (mean of 2003–2012 for all except LMfire which is the mean over 1991–2000). Shaded area represents the minimum and maximum in decadal emissions from within all three observation datasets
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2018_5592_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e449" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It has been widely assumed in global climate models that aerosol emissions from fires in the PI were lower than in the PD
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span>, based on a misconception that total fire emissions have increased with human population density
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
  </span>. Globally, most fire ignitions are caused by humans
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span>, which makes a positive scaling of total burned area, and hence total fire emissions, with human population density logical at first. However, recent analysis of global fire occurrence shows that, at a global scale, burned area declines with increasing population density
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
  </span> due to land use change
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>
  </span>. For example, observationally based estimates of burned area over the last few decades suggest a global decline of 1–2% per year
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
  </span>, with a maximum of 3–6% per year regional decline in Europe and Australia/New Zealand
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>
  </span>. On longer timescales Mallek et al.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
  </span> suggest that PD (1984–2009) burned area is just 14% of PI (1500–1850) burned area in California, and Arora and Melton
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
  </span> suggest an overall global decline of 25–30% in burned area since the PI. This decline in fire is a result of human activity: e.g., passive fire suppression from landscape fragmentation limits the spread of fires
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>
  </span>, while active fire suppression management and legislation aimed to improve air quality offset any potential anthropogenic increase in accidental fire ignitions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>
  </span>. Therefore, advances in global fire modelling
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>
  </span> suggest a significantly different pattern of fire occurrence under PI conditions (modelled PI burned area estimates: Supplementary Figure 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">3</a>), with consequently higher aerosol emissions than previously estimated.
 </p>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A large number of global fire models exist, of which six contributed to the creation of historical fire emissions in the CMIP6 dataset
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span>. However, most fire models still assume an overall positive relationship between human population and fire
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>
  </span> so they do not capture the observed human-driven decline in burned area, and hence fire emissions, over the last decades
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>
  </span>. Therefore, CMIP6 probably underestimates PI fire emissions.
 </p>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here we use two fire models driven by distinct philosophies of the relationship between humans and fire to simulate a range of PI fire emissions which are consistent with current knowledge of how humans influence global fire occurrence, as well as representing the uncertainty in anthropogenic land cover and land use change from the PI to the PD (see Methods). Emissions in the two fire models are much greater than in the AeroCom and CMIP6 PI datasets and are more in line with the trends predicted from paleofire proxy records. When used in a global aerosol model, the fire models result in a substantial reduction in the magnitude of anthropogenic aerosol forcing over the Industrial Era compared to the CMIP6 fire emission scenario; which has not been accounted for in climate models.</p>
</sec>
