<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec14" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">LPJ-LMfire fire model description</div>
 <p id="Par35" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The LPJ-LMfire model
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" href="#CR64">64</a>
  </span> includes processes to simulate natural wildfires from lightning ignition and a unique representation of fire generated by both agricultural and pastoral societies. To run LMfire we combined climatological mean climate fields that provide a high-spatial-resolution baseline, with detrended, interpolated climate anomalies from reanalysis simulations that provide interannual variability. The original datasets used to drive the model are described in Table 3 of Pfeiffer et al.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span>; here we describe the process that were used to prepare the interannually variable climate driver input files.
 </p>
 <p id="Par36" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A 20th Century Reanalysis
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" href="#CR65">65</a>
  </span> is used to impose interannual variability in our simulations in several steps. First, we prepared monthly anomalies relative to the period 1961–1990 for: mean temperature, diurnal temperature range, total precipitation, number of days with precipitation, cloud cover, wind speed, and convective-available potential energy (CAPE). These monthly anomalies are then detrended using a robust loess regression filter
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">66</a>
  </span> with a bandwidth of 30 years. Next, we interpolated the detrended anomalies for each meteorological variable to 0.5° spatial resolution. Next, a climate driver dataset was generated from a 1080-year climate dataset by dividing the 140-year detrended climate anomalies into twelve 30-year blocks at 10-year intervals. Anomalies were then sampled using a pseudo-random scheme where once a block was chosen it was not selected again until all of the other remaining blocks have been selected. In order to generate a 1080-year timeseries 36 blocks were selected, i.e., each block was used three times but appeared in a different order each time. Finally, each anomaly timeseries was added to its complementary baseline climatological mean climate field, and used the resulting 1080-year (12960-month) climate data input file to run LMfire. For the PI simulation in LMfire, we used only the last 150 years of this model run, i.e., years 931–1080, as this is the period where all of the model pools are considered to be in equilibrium, although we acknowledge that the actual state of the terrestrial biosphere in the late preindustrial Holocene may have been far from equilibrium in many regions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" href="#CR67">67</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" href="#CR68">68</a>
  </span>. Atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub> concentrations were set to 1770 levels for the duration of this simulation.
 </p>
 <p id="Par37" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the LMfire PI simulation, land use is prescribed from the KK10 scenario
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" href="#CR67">67</a>
  </span> for the year 1770. The managed burning routine of the fire module
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span> defines that 50% of the litter on 20% of the used land (cropland and pasture) is burned annually. As the seasonality of burning on used land is not well known at global scale, fire emissions are partitioned evenly across all snow-free days of the year with mean temperature above 0 °C. In reality, most biomass burning on used land probably occurred during certain periods of the year, e.g., after harvest, but it is currently beyond the capability of any global land use scenario to prescribe these periods.
 </p>
 <p id="Par38" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To perform a PD simulation with LMfire, we made a transient model simulation for the period 1701–2000 driven by the synthetic climate timeseries described above, transient land use, and reconstructed and measured atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub> concentrations. Land use was provided by merging KK10, which ends in 1850, to the Hundred Year Database for Integrated Environmental Assessments (HYDE) dataset following the protocol described in Kaplan et al.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" href="#CR68">68</a>
  </span>. The LMfire PD results presented here represent the mean over the period 1991–2000.
 </p>
 <p id="Par39" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Modern agricultural practices and legislation to protect air quality mean that in some parts of the world intentional burning of used land is currently rare. To account for this in the PD simulation, we set the burning-on-used-land factor described above to not exceed the observed burned area fraction in the JR12 burned area dataset
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" href="#CR69">69</a>
  </span>, which leads to burning on used land at PD to be effectively zero in large parts of North America and Europe.
 </p>
 <p id="Par40" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although passive fire suppression as a result of land use is included in this simulation following Pfeiffer et al.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span>, and burning on used land is largely eliminated in many parts of the world, the PD simulation of LMfire still overestimates mean annual burned area in parts of the world, notably in the western United States, southern Europe, and the Middle East. Because these are PD regions known to be subject to large-scale industrial fire suppression efforts, we accounted for this fire suppression by further correcting the LMfire output in a model postprocessing step. To identify regions affected by potential model bias, we compared modelled burned area with GFED4s at the level of GFED regions, with Europe further subdivided into North and South at 45° N (Supplementary Figure 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">9</a>). Within those regions where the discrepancy between modelled and observed burned area was ≥90%, i.e., the USA, southern Europe, and Middle East, we assumed that the primary reason for the discrepancy was active fire suppression. To correct this model PD bias in these regions, we scaled the modelled BC emissions by the ratio of GFED4s observed to LMfire modelled burned area calculated at the GFED regional level. This resulted in a slightly &lt;10% decrease to the global BC annual emission flux. In all other regions, we used modelled BC emissions without bias correction because the discrepancy was smaller and we could not justify industrial fire suppression as being the potential primary cause of model-data mismatch. The primary region where simulated burned area remains overestimated by LMfire is in the tropical seasonal forests of South America. This is both a region of rapid land use change over recent decades where anthropogenic influences on burning may not be well captured in the PD LMfire simulation, and where it has already been identified
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span> as a place where the process representation of fire could be improved in the LMfire model.
 </p>
 <p id="Par41" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In all three GFED regions (encompassing the USA and Mediterranean) where PD LMfire emissions were scaled, the scaling reflects a modern-day fire suppression practice driven largely by technologies and ideologies that were not present in 1750. For example, in the PD US &gt; 99.5% fires are actively suppressed
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span>, and due to this the USA underwent reductions in annual burned area over the 20th Century of over 80% from &gt;40 m ha in late 1920s to ≤5 m ha in the early 2000s (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fao.org/docrep/010/ai412e/AI412E06.htm" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.fao.org/docrep/010/ai412e/AI412E06.htm</span>)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" href="#CR70">70</a>
  </span>. We therefore assume that a similar small (&lt;10% global emission reduction) PI bias correction is not required here. This does however highlight once more that fire models should aim to move beyond present-day optimisations
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>
  </span> by incorporating more paleofire data.
 </p>
 <p id="Par42" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Differences in fire emissions within boreal regions between LMfire and GFED4s are in part due to the longer simulation time within LMfire (150 years) compared to satellite measurements, resulting in fires being simulated in the model that are not represented in the satellite record used to construct the GFED4s emission dataset. In particular, the wide range of fire regimes within the Arctic tundra leads to fire return periods of between decades to millennia
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71" href="#CR71">71</a>
  </span>. Many high latitude fires are therefore unaccounted for in fire emission datasets
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72" href="#CR72">72</a>
  </span>, including the CMIP6 and SIMFIRE-BLAZE datasets presented here, but can occur within LMfire. Other differences include assumptions about fuel load, combustion completeness, emission factors, permafrost, PD fire suppression and increased post-harvest agricultural burning in the PI that is not present in the PD due to land use change practices. Within semi-arid regions LMfire predicts a shorter fire return interval
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span> than suggested by recent studies
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73" href="#CR73">73</a>
  </span>, however total emissions from these regions are generally low, and therefore less important for climate, due to the sparse vegetation cover within them
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par43" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To test the sensitivity of PI fire emission estimates to natural climate variability the 150-year emission dataset of LMfire was partitioned into 15 decadal mean fire climatologies, each representing a plausible PI fire landscape. As tropical and extra-tropical fires belong to distinct regimes with different characteristics, four different scenarios (Supplementary Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2</a>) based on the maximum and minimum emissions from each were selected. These four scenarios were then used to generate the uncertainty range in estimates of LMfire emissions in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a> and the range in radiative forcing calculations in Supplementary Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2</a>.
 </p>
</sec>
