<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Uncertainties and future directions</div>
 <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Several lines of evidence, aside from more realistic fire models, point to PI fire emissions being greater than previously assumed: ice core records of the PI to PD change in BC at several independent sites in different environments; ice-core records of tracers of fire activity; recent analyses of fire occurrence revealing declining burned area with increasing population density (e.g., refs. 
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
  </span>); and indirect evidence from the charcoal record and tree-rings. Nevertheless, evidence to support new model estimates currently contains many uncertainties, including: the modelling of aerosol deposition on snow, in particular the extent to which models can simulate trends even if absolute deposition is very uncertain; the ability to simulate deposition to high-altitude sites using low-resolution models; the extent to which deposition scales with emissions and concentrations on a long-term mean; the effect of PI to PD changes in aerosol processing, atmospheric circulation and precipitation patterns; uncertainties in the different records of fire emissions themselves; uncertainty in land cover and land use change over the industrial period, and how this translates to uncertainty in aerosol emission and deposition rates; uncertainty in the impacts of European colonisation on fire regimes influenced by aboriginal land use practices; uncertainty in fire emission factors, which also may have been different in the PI environment; spatial and temporal variability in fire emissions, including the fire return interval, and how this affects the optimum length of model simulations; and the uncertainty in a single model analysis. These are clear tasks for future research to help reduce uncertainty in PI to PD changes in fire emissions, as well as the associated uncertainty in radiative forcing estimates over the Industrial Era, noting that any future constraints are not automatically equivalent within each time-period.
 </p>
 <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results highlight the importance of developing a much deeper understanding of how fires evolved over the industrial period, especially since global fire models have mostly been evaluated against PD data
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>
  </span>. The exponential increase in human population over the Industrial Era has restructured the fire landscape on all inhabited continents and created a permanent change in the energy balance of the atmosphere that has not been fully accounted for in climate models. Furthermore, it is highly likely that models participating in CMIP6 would simulate smaller anthropogenic aerosol radiative forcings over the industrial period if they used higher PI fire emissions.
 </p>
 <p id="Par31" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The climate impacts of fires will also extend beyond changes in aerosol emissions, and includes many other important processes
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span> such as changes in CO
  <sub>2</sub> exchange, surface albedo, ozone and methane concentrations, as well as other smoke-induced adjustments to clouds and regional meteorology that were not explored here. These factors could amplify or attenuate the effects we have simulated here. A reduction in the uncertainties in unobservable PI aerosol concentrations
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">59</a>
  </span>, including but not limited to fire emissions investigated within this study, will best be achieved through a multi-disciplinary approach, including contributions from Earth system modelling, palaeontology, geology, anthropology and archaeology.
 </p>
</sec>
