<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Here I focus on the interactive effects of competition and dispersal. Biotic interactions and dispersal capacity are increasingly acknowledged as factors that can influence species responses to climate change [
 <xref rid="pone.0177778.ref006" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0177778.ref009" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0177778.ref012" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. Species grow, reproduce and disperse in landscapes filled with potential competitors. When environmental conditions change, species interactions [
 <xref rid="pone.0177778.ref005" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0177778.ref012" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>] and species-specific dispersal capacity [
 <xref rid="pone.0177778.ref009" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>] mediate the ability of species to track their moving niches. Competition from resident species, for example, may pose resistance to colonisation of species that undergo a range shift [
 <xref rid="pone.0177778.ref011" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0177778.ref020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. Dispersal dynamics can either maintain populations in habitat that is no longer suitable (source-sink dynamics; [
 <xref rid="pone.0177778.ref021" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>]), or prevent spread to habitat that becomes suitable but that cannot be reached (dispersal limitation; [
 <xref rid="pone.0177778.ref022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0177778.ref024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>]). Modellers most often assume no dispersal or universal dispersal during range shifts, irrespective of species differences or spatial distance, but assumptions about dispersal significantly affect model predictions of biodiversity loss [
 <xref rid="pone.0177778.ref006" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>]. Using a trait-based simulation model, Urban et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0177778.ref011" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>] explored the effect of interspecific differences in dispersal capacity on diversity patterns in communities of competing species under climate change. They showed that increasing the differences between species in dispersal capacity resulted in higher predicted extinction risk. This effect was not only due to direct extinction of species with low dispersal capacity that were unable to track their climatic niche, but also due to an interaction with competition: better dispersers tracked changing climates better and then out-competed poorer dispersers.
</p>
