<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3. Results </div>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1. Summary of Findings from the Literature Review that Supported Indicator Development </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Efforts to enhance emergency management systems, strengthen health care services and actions aimed at climate-proofing and greening operations can help build resiliency of health care facilities to climate change impacts [
   <a rid="B4-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-ijerph-11-13097">4</a>,
   <a rid="B7-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-ijerph-11-13097">7</a>,
   <a rid="B25-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25-ijerph-11-13097">25</a>,
   <a rid="B32-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32-ijerph-11-13097">32</a>,
   <a rid="B33-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33-ijerph-11-13097">33</a>]. Effective practices as they pertain to these areas are described below.
  </p>
  <sec class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1.1. Emergency Management and Strengthening Health Care Services</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Robust emergency management and health care strengthening programs that include measures to prevent, prepare for, respond to and recover from extreme weather events or public health emergencies increase resilience to climate change [
    <a rid="B31-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31-ijerph-11-13097">31</a>,
    <a rid="B32-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32-ijerph-11-13097">32</a>,
    <a rid="B34-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34-ijerph-11-13097">34</a>]. Standard emergency management approaches, such as all-hazards programs need to be modified to incorporate observed and projected alterations in the frequency, intensity and duration of extreme events to increase preparedness [
    <a rid="B32-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32-ijerph-11-13097">32</a>]. Managing risks from climate change (such as extreme weather) requires health care facilities to regularly undertake risk assessments that integrate current climate variability and future climate change [
    <a rid="B24-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-ijerph-11-13097">24</a>] to support effective forward planning [
    <a rid="B31-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31-ijerph-11-13097">31</a>,
    <a rid="B35-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35-ijerph-11-13097">35</a>]. In regions found to be vulnerable to climate hazards such as floods or storm surges, adaptation efforts to increase the safety of buildings and protection of critical equipment can increase resilience [
    <a rid="B24-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-ijerph-11-13097">24</a>] as can efforts to prepare for patient surges and associated pressures. 
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To anticipate increased health care demands and prepare accordingly, information on climate change and health vulnerabilities at the community level can be used [
    <a rid="B2-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-ijerph-11-13097">2</a>]. In many urban communities in Canada, climate change will contribute to poor air quality (e.g., from wildfire smoke, smog, allergens) that can lead to increased hospital cases of asthma, COPD, acute bronchitis, chest pain and other cardio-respiratory illnesses [
    <a rid="B3-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3-ijerph-11-13097">3</a>,
    <a rid="B36-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36-ijerph-11-13097">36</a>]. Early warning systems can help increase preparedness to support the delivery of care. Health care facilities can benefit by being linked to weather alert and warning systems [
    <a rid="B37-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37-ijerph-11-13097">37</a>] such as heat alert and response systems (HARS) [
    <a rid="B34-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34-ijerph-11-13097">34</a>]; air quality alerts [
    <a rid="B38-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38-ijerph-11-13097">38</a>]; boiled water advisories and critical service disruption notifications to better anticipate increases in hospital visits. Many communities in Canada have adopted HARS to notify vulnerable groups, the general public and health care and community services of impending extreme heat events and to provide information on how people can protect themselves from heat-health impacts [
    <a rid="B39-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39-ijerph-11-13097">39</a>]. Such systems can help health care facilities be more prepared for increased heat-related hospital visits.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Increasing mortality from heatwaves and other extreme weather events, changes in the geographic range and incidence of climate-sensitive infectious diseases, increasing morbidity and mortality from poor air quality and other health impacts will require modification of current public health programs and training of health care providers to be prepared for patients presenting with currently unexpected climate-sensitive health outcomes [
    <a rid="B40-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40-ijerph-11-13097">40</a>]. As such, training programs could be enhanced to ensure adequate protection and care of patients with specialized needs (e.g., infants and children) [
    <a rid="B41-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41-ijerph-11-13097">41</a>]. Furthermore, information on range expansion of specific diseases acquired through national and regional assessments can be used to inform rapid testing, diagnosis, treatment and surveillance of diseases to protect health [
    <a rid="B24-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-ijerph-11-13097">24</a>]. Climate-induced range expansion of the deer tick that harbors Lyme disease is occurring rapidly in Canada [
    <a rid="B42-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42-ijerph-11-13097">42</a>,
    <a rid="B43-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43-ijerph-11-13097">43</a>,
    <a rid="B44-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44-ijerph-11-13097">44</a>] and warmer weather and more precipitation events may increase the abundance of mosquito species that carry West Nile Virus [
    <a rid="B45-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B45-ijerph-11-13097">45</a>,
    <a rid="B46-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46-ijerph-11-13097">46</a>].
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Once health care facilities have a better understanding of risks in their area, officials can create new or enhance existing protocols to improve risk management. For example, health care facilities in areas vulnerable to extreme heat should develop plans and protocols to guide actions that need to be taken during an extreme heat event (see 
    <a ref-type="table" rid="ijerph-11-13097-t003" href="#ijerph-11-13097-t003">Table 3</a>) [
    <a rid="B39-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39-ijerph-11-13097">39</a>].
   </p>
   <div id="ijerph-11-13097-t003" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <span pub-id-type="pii" class="object-id">ijerph-11-13097-t003_Table 3</span>
    <span class="label">Table 3</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Health care facility protocol for ensuring the health and safety of patients during extreme heat events.</p>
    </div>
    <table frame="hsides" rules="all" style="border:solid thin">
     <tbody>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" valign="middle" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <div list-type="simple" class="list">
         <div class="list-item">
          <span class="label">○</span>
          <p>Develop emergency surge procedure to ensure adequate capacity and personnel</p>
         </div>
         <div class="list-item">
          <span class="label">○</span>
          <p>Protect staff from heat illness and provide adequate work rest cycles </p>
         </div>
         <div class="list-item">
          <span class="label">○</span>
          <p>Follow regional requirements to keep the facility cool and comfortable</p>
         </div>
         <div class="list-item">
          <span class="label">○</span>
          <p>Evacuate rooms if extremely high temperature occurs (case by case basis)</p>
         </div>
         <div class="list-item">
          <span class="label">○</span>
          <p>Ensure cooling supplies are available for your patients and residents</p>
         </div>
         <div class="list-item">
          <span class="label">○</span>
          <p>Provide cooling areas</p>
         </div>
         <div class="list-item">
          <span class="label">○</span>
          <p>Keep medications cool</p>
         </div>
         <div class="list-item">
          <span class="label">○</span>
          <p>Ensure meals have high water content and that spoiled food is discarded</p>
         </div>
         <div class="list-item">
          <span class="label">○</span>
          <p>Review clinical management of patients and residents most at risk either due to reduced mobility, chronic illnesses, use of certain medications, social isolation, inadequate housing or environmental factors</p>
         </div>
         <div class="list-item">
          <span class="label">○</span>
          <p>Increase frequency of patient observations, especially those at high risk, and advise staff to closely monitor early indicators of heat illnesses and initiate appropriate treatment</p>
         </div>
         <div class="list-item">
          <span class="label">○</span>
          <p>Consider outdoor temperatures when planning group activities</p>
         </div>
        </div>
       </td>
      </tr>
     </tbody>
    </table>
   </div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Logisticians should be cognizant that more extreme weather events can increase risks of flooding at supply warehouses, damage to storage facilities, and disruption of communication lines and transportation [
    <a rid="B25-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25-ijerph-11-13097">25</a>] and therefore diversify suppliers and develop plans accordingly. Emergency preparedness programs could also enhance contingency plans for timely delivery of medical supplies and establish mutual aid agreements with other health care facilities to be resilient in emergencies where resources are limited [
    <a rid="B33-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33-ijerph-11-13097">33</a>].
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Efforts to support community resilience to climate change should be implemented in addition to regular health care facility risk management processes. Some communities are undertaking climate change and health vulnerability assessments [
    <a rid="B47-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B47-ijerph-11-13097">47</a>]; health care facility officials can participate in these efforts to support the identification of community level vulnerabilities and contribute to better estimates of health system adaptive capacity. Health care facilities also could participate in disaster risk management exercises to promote coordination and collaboration during a real event. Real time reporting of climate-sensitive health outcomes can help public health agencies take action to prevent public health emergencies [
    <a rid="B48-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B48-ijerph-11-13097">48</a>,
    <a rid="B49-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49-ijerph-11-13097">49</a>]. Syndromic surveillance of health outcomes attributable to extreme heat or other climate hazards using hospital visits or other health information systems (e.g., health help lines, clinician visits) can support public health programs such as monitoring and providing early warning of impacts, informing and improving the public health response to climate hazards. It also provides a source of morbidity data to use in the process of continually assessing, evaluating and improving health programs [
    <a rid="B18-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-ijerph-11-13097">18</a>,
    <a rid="B49-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49-ijerph-11-13097">49</a>]. As one example, the British Columbia Centre for Disease Control is involved in efforts to link health care facility syndromic surveillance with air quality issues from wildfire smoke and extreme heat events. The system will better equip public health officials with information needed to target key vulnerable groups.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1.2. Climate-Proofing and Greening Operations</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Most infrastructure was built under the assumption that the weather in the next few decades will be similar to the weather today. As a result, some critical infrastructure, such as health care facilities are located in flood plains and along coastal regions that are at risk of inundation [
    <a rid="B40-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40-ijerph-11-13097">40</a>]. As such, health care facilities may need to take steps to make infrastructure more resilient to climate change. Robust facility structural elements (e.g., roofs, doors, windows) and non-structural components (e.g., computers, diagnostic equipment, HVAC systems, back-up generators) need to be able to withstand extreme weather events that may cause acute or gradual damage, and/or may need to be moved above possible floodwaters. Regular maintenance, prioritizing replacement of old equipment and use of new and emerging technologies to mitigate the effects of such events can reduce vulnerability [
    <a rid="B14-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14-ijerph-11-13097">14</a>,
    <a rid="B50-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B50-ijerph-11-13097">50</a>]. For example, health care facilities in drought prone regions that may be vulnerable to future water shortages can install storm water collection systems, design landscapes with drought resistant native plants, and conserve water by using appropriate low flow taps, nozzles and toilets. Health care facilities can increase their resiliency to extreme heat events by installing devices and equipment for monitoring indoor temperatures, cooling existing buildings and outdoor spaces, blocking direct sun, and increasing air flow and reducing humidity [
    <a rid="B39-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39-ijerph-11-13097">39</a>,
    <a rid="B50-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B50-ijerph-11-13097">50</a>]. In addition, encouraging sustainability practices, such as turning off equipment when not in use, has shown to be a cost effective [
    <a rid="B28-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-ijerph-11-13097">28</a>].
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Energy supply systems in many communities are vulnerable to more frequent and severe extreme weather events and other pressures such as increased demand from population growth. Back-up power sources and strategies to deal with long lasting electricity disruptions will better prepare health care facilities for emergencies and disasters. In addition to disrupting patient care, power-outages can affect patient identification and records, access to clinical care, the demand for services, communication systems, and transportation to and from the health care facilities [
    <a rid="B14-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14-ijerph-11-13097">14</a>,
    <a rid="B16-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16-ijerph-11-13097">16</a>] and increase risks of infectious diseases [
    <a rid="B51-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51-ijerph-11-13097">51</a>]. Back-up generators should be tested and protected to ensure they are functional in an extreme weather event [
    <a rid="B35-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35-ijerph-11-13097">35</a>] and use of combined heat and power systems as a replacement for back-up generators should be evaluated. In cases where power is limited during disruptions, electricity should be re-directed to clinical areas to meet needs of vulnerable patients [
    <a rid="B14-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14-ijerph-11-13097">14</a>]. Plans and protocols for managing outcomes of power-outages, such as mandatory evacuation, should be developed, reviewed, and tested regularly to ensure that effective measures are in place to continue to provide high quality health care when electricity is limited.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Greening initiatives which invest in energy efficient solutions can help mitigate greenhouse gas emissions, and reduce health care facility costs and vulnerability to power disruptions [
    <a rid="B52-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B52-ijerph-11-13097">52</a>,
    <a rid="B53-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53-ijerph-11-13097">53</a>]. Health care facilities can improve energy efficiency and save energy costs by using low energy lighting, boilers and electrical systems, increasing reliance on natural ventilation, promoting active transportation and the use of energy efficient vehicles, providing distant counseling services and using green procurement (e.g., purchasing local food) [
    <a rid="B5-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-ijerph-11-13097">5</a>,
    <a rid="B6-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6-ijerph-11-13097">6</a>,
    <a rid="B7-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-ijerph-11-13097">7</a>,
    <a rid="B24-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-ijerph-11-13097">24</a>,
    <a rid="B54-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B54-ijerph-11-13097">54</a>]. E-health, which includes electronic methods of information exchange among health care professionals and patients (e.g., use of email delivery of diagnostic results), can help reduce greenhouse gas emissions from patient commuters; however, backup plans should be developed to address unreliable power or energy supplies [
    <a rid="B55-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B55-ijerph-11-13097">55</a>]. Greening health care facility properties (e.g., planting trees, grass and gardens) offers multiple health co-benefits such as the provision of natural shade for patients, staff and visitors during extreme heat events, reduced risk of facility flooding through the creation of natural flood water infiltration and the improvement of air quality by filtering pollutants [
    <a rid="B28-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-ijerph-11-13097">28</a>]. Installation of high performance windows and exceeding minimum insulation requirements can also improve energy efficiency and enhance the comfort and safety of patients during extreme temperature events [
    <a rid="B56-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B56-ijerph-11-13097">56</a>].
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2. Results from the Interviews</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Checklists were completed for all pilot health care facilities and interview respondents provided feedback based on questions posed during interviews. Health care facility officials indicated that the tool was useful, particularly in informing where efforts were needed to strengthen emergency management and health care services activities and partnerships, make infrastructure more robust and increase awareness of the need to be more sustainable. Because many of the questions focused on emergency management and health care services activities that are already standard practice, it was suggested that the tool may be more useful for health care facilities with fewer resources or those where officials have less experience with major events or emergencies. There was consensus that the checklist reinforces the need for robust emergency management measures in a changing climate. Interviewees noted that the checklist could be valuable component to existing risk management processes (e.g., enhancing existing Hazard Risk Vulnerability Assessment tools). The checklist was useful in helping to identify risks from gradual weather changes such as degradation of infrastructure and an increasing number of people vulnerable to climate-related impacts and in need of health care (e.g., ageing population combined with greater exposure to climate-related hazards).</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Interviewees stated that the checklist is a helpful resource to inform planning. By revealing preparedness gaps and areas where improvement may be needed, the checklist provides evidence for action to reduce current and future climate-related risks. As one example, interviewees indicated that health care facilities use off site warehouses for supply storage. The location and number of warehouses may change over time as well as transportation routes to access supplies. These factors should be taken into account during contingency planning since more extreme weather could damage warehouses or reduce access to supplies during extreme weather. Some mentioned that the facility will likely need to move back-up generators or install new chillers and cooling towers. Respondents indicated that the checklist helps identify the types of emergency responses that may become more common in a changing climate; for example, there may be more evacuations needed with increased floods. The checklist raised awareness of potential cost-savings actions such as installation of new energy efficient systems, water conservation methods and better infrastructure that can withstand extreme weather. A few questions in the assessment checklist inquired about the status of surveillance and monitoring of climate-attributable health outcomes. Respondents indicated that this is a lead responsibility of public health departments but that health care facilities could support surveillance and monitoring activities if resources and guidance were available.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Interviewees provided a number of recommendations to improve the tool. Many respondents suggested that information on climate change risks in different regions of Canada and implications for health care facilities be provided as context prior to completing the checklist. Many respondents indicated that the checklist does a good job in identifying gaps and needs, but that more information is needed on how to be more resilient. A best practices resource was suggested as one way to help inform resiliency measures as well as sharing lessons learned with other health care facilities. Those who were in charge of completing the assessment checklist indicated that it took a long time to fill out because many different people needed to be consulted. As a solution, it was suggested that the checklist be completed as a group of knowledgeable individuals with senior level responsibility in managing emergencies, facility operations (e.g., HVAC systems), supply chain management and health care services and that one person facilitate the group meeting. It was suggested also that the checklist be available online and formatted to include scoring. This would help speed up the process of filling out the checklist and enable progress to be tracked over time. It was recommended that a comments field should be included after each question to provide further information as needed. Interviewees noted that it will be challenging to get resources for improvements that may be needed. As such, it was suggested that preparing for climate change and providing access to resources be part of health care facility standards nationally or provincially. 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="ijerph-11-13097-t004" href="#ijerph-11-13097-t004">Table 4</a> lists some of the key recommendations from respondents.
  </p>
  <div id="ijerph-11-13097-t004" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span pub-id-type="pii" class="object-id">ijerph-11-13097-t004_Table 4</span>
   <span class="label">Table 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Suggestions from interviewees on how to improve the tool.</p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="all" style="border:solid thin">
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
       <span class="bold">
        <span class="underline">Improving Value of the Tool</span>
       </span>
       <div list-type="order" class="list">
        <div class="list-item">
         <p>Shorten the tool by eliminating repetitive questions</p>
        </div>
        <div class="list-item">
         <p>Provide more detail to increase value of some questions</p>
        </div>
        <div class="list-item">
         <p>Make questions less wordy and more concise</p>
        </div>
        <div class="list-item">
         <p>Include comments field after each question</p>
        </div>
        <div class="list-item">
         <p>Include column to indicate if other stakeholders have primary role</p>
        </div>
        <div class="list-item">
         <p>Re-structure the tool to improve categorization of topics </p>
        </div>
        <div class="list-item">
         <p>Distinguish between current and future risks </p>
        </div>
        <div class="list-item">
         <p>Distinguish between acute impacts and gradual impacts </p>
        </div>
        <div class="list-item">
         <p>Include best practicesInclude scenarios to provide more context on climate impacts</p>
        </div>
       </div>
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
       <span class="bold">
        <span class="underline">Packaging the Tool</span>
       </span>
       <div list-type="order" class="list">
        <div class="list-item">
         <p>Promote use of the tool as a complimentary exercise to build on regular management activities </p>
        </div>
        <div class="list-item">
         <p>Improve information about how the tool will benefit stakeholders</p>
        </div>
        <div class="list-item">
         <p>Make the tool available electronically and include scoring</p>
        </div>
        <div class="list-item">
         <p>Include resources and additional tools to help fill identified gaps</p>
        </div>
        <div class="list-item">
         <p>Consider including a power-point presentation as a facilitator’s guide </p>
        </div>
        <div class="list-item">
         <p>Ensure that objectives are clear (
          <span class="italic">i.e</span>., intrinsic use only, intended use for planning)
         </p>
        </div>
        <div class="list-item">
         <p>Present tool as a team exercise and suggest one lead to facilitate the process of completing the checklist</p>
        </div>
        <div class="list-item">
         <p>Indicate that the tool is a working document and can be an iterative process in the long-term</p>
        </div>
        <div class="list-item">
         <p>Ensure tool is applicable to hospitals, health authorities and other government stakeholders</p>
        </div>
        <div class="list-item">
         <p>Consider expanding applicability to other health care institutions (e.g., senior care homes)</p>
        </div>
       </div>
      </td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
  </div>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.3. Description of the Final Health Care Facility Toolkit </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The health care facility resiliency toolkit includes an assessment checklist, a facilitator’s guide and a resource guidebook. The checklist has 82 questions within four broad areas: general information (n = 4), assessing climate-related risks (n = 19), risk management (n = 45) and building capacity to adapt to climate change (n = 14). The checklist provides a qualitative assessment of resiliency by posing questions with possible responses of “Yes”, “No”, “Somewhat, Sometimes”, “I don’t know” or “Not Applicable”. All questions include a comments box where other pertinent information, such as gaps in knowledge and data, roles and responsibilities and status of activities can be recorded and updated during future assessments. The facilitator’s guide and the resource guide were developed in response to feedback received during pilot testing of the draft toolkit. The facilitator’s guide provides background information on climate change risks to health care facilities in Canada and instructions for health care facility officials to aid in completion of the checklist. The resource guidebook includes information highlighting effective measures that can be taken to reduce risks to the facility from climate change. The toolkit is available for download at 
   <span xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="http://greenhealthcare.ca/climateresilienthealthcare/" class="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://greenhealthcare.ca/climateresilienthealthcare/</span>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The resource guidebook provides helpful resources for health care facilities to increase understanding of climate change and health risks and actions to increase resiliency. In Canada, resources are available to increase awareness of climate change risks to the health care sector. In 2008, Health Canada released a report entitled: “
   <span class="italic">Human Health in a Changing Climate: A Canadian Assessment of Vulnerabilities and Adaptive Capacity</span>” which provides information for Canadians and health authorities on climate change and health risks as well as the adaptive capacity of the health sector in Canada to manage risks [
   <a rid="B2-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-ijerph-11-13097">2</a>]. A Government of Canada climate change impacts and adaptation assessment, released in 2014, provides updated information on climate change and health challenges in urban, rural, coastal and northern communities and innovative adaptation measures available to health sector decision makers [
   <a rid="B3-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3-ijerph-11-13097">3</a>]. The Canadian Coalition for Green Health Care provides information to help hospital officials reduce the environmental footprint of their facility and mitigate greenhouse gases [
   <a rid="B56-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B56-ijerph-11-13097">56</a>]. Internationally, the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change produces regular assessment reports [
   <a rid="B57-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B57-ijerph-11-13097">57</a>] and special reports (e.g., Managing the Risks of Extreme Events and Disasters to Advance Climate Change Adaptation: a Special Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change) that includes information on climate change risks to human health. The WHO has published information about climate change and health related risks for a number of areas including extreme heat [
   <a rid="B58-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B58-ijerph-11-13097">58</a>], flooding, economic valuation, gender implications [
   <a rid="B59-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B59-ijerph-11-13097">59</a>] and innovative ways to reduce risks, for example, by linking climate services with emergency management and health care services [
   <a rid="B60-ijerph-11-13097" ref-type="bibr" href="#B60-ijerph-11-13097">60</a>]. Links to these resources and others are provided in the resource guidebook to facilitate its application and subsequent use to increase climate resiliency in health care facilities. Completion of the assessment checklist by a health care facility provides information on the degree to which that facility is resilient to current climate variability and future climate change based upon the indicators presented above. Identification of important gaps related to emergency management and health care services, greening of operations or supply procurement and management may be used by hospital officials to inform the implementation of needed adaptations.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
