<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Community-based adaptation is helpful in reducing the vulnerability as well as improving the resilience of the local people to climatic variability and change. Even though subsistence farmers have always adopted adaptive strategies to some of these changes over the years, effective adaptation strategies should be aimed at securing their well-being in the face of climatic changes (Somah 
 <xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>). Nhemachena and Hassan (
 <xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2007</xref>) argue that the climate is already changing, to such an extent that adaptation is critical and of concern in developing countries, particularly in Africa where vulnerability is high. Mitigation plans may be implemented, but they would not be sufficient enough to avoid changes in the global climate, hence the importance of adaptation (Akoh et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>:24). Furthermore, Gbetibouo (
 <xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2008</xref>:1) states that the ‘extent to which the adverse impacts of climate change are felt depend on the extent of adaptation; without adaptation, climate change would be detrimental’. The Assessments of Impact and Adaptations to Climate Change (AIACC) project that was undertaken in various regions of Africa, Asia, Central and South America, the Caribbean and the Indian and Pacific Oceans found that overall there was an adaptation deficit, which is likely to be widened because of climate change (Leary et al. 
 <xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2007</xref>). ‘Adapting to climate change will entail adjustments and changes at every level, from community to national and international levels’ (UNFCCC 
 <xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2007</xref>:29). Burton, Smith and Lenhart (
 <xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1998</xref>) are of the view that adaptation can take different forms depending on the action taken in response to the external threat. This implies that if the action is taken before the threat, the adaptation is preventive; and if the action is taken during the time of the threat, the adaptation is gradual and short term. Correspondingly, if the action is taken after the threat, the adaptation is reactive or corrective.
</p>
