<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Background</div>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Environmental hypoxia—the decreased partial pressure of oxygen—and cold temperature are key drivers in the evolution of high elevation adaptations in montane organisms [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>]. In particular, birds that undertake elevational migrations are exposed to considerable seasonal fluctuations in hypoxia levels and temperature across the year. Therefore elevational migrants must evolve physiological strategies to regulate haemoglobin (hereafter Hb) concentration, an important measure of blood oxygen-carrying capacity [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>], as they move between elevations. High intensity infections with avian ectoparasites and haemoparasites have been shown to lower the oxygen-carrying capacity of their hosts by reducing Hb levels through direct consumption or destruction of red blood cells, often leading to anaemia [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>]. Thus the capacity to regulate Hb concentration and cope with hypoxia can be significantly compromised by haemoparasite infection in elevational migrants which are at increased risk of infection due to the following several factors. Elevational migrants tend to encounter more parasites as they are exposed to high prevalence areas at low elevations with optimal climatic conditions for parasite transmission (e.g. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>]), have increased physiological demands incurred due to changes in immune conditions during migration ([
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>] but see [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>]), have a relapse of chronic infections prior to or during the journey [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>], and have increased risk of exposure due to host aggregation during migration or at the wintering sites [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>]. Given the physiological strategies and life-history characteristics, high intensity parasite infections could be especially costly in hypoxic environments for montane birds. Recent evidence suggests that Hb is a more reliable indicator of host response to parasitism than lowered haematocrit (Hct, total red blood cell volume), due to the commonly observed occurrence of erythropoiesis in parasitized hosts [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>]. In birds, regenerative or haemolytic anaemia leads to increased erythropoiesis that is rapid production of immature red blood cells stimulated by hypoxia and yet showing normal Hct, despite a substantial parasite load (intensity). To date, only a few studies have compared association between Hb levels and ectoparasite load [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>] and haemoparasites [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>], and these have only been in juvenile altricial birds [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Avian haemosporidians (Apicomplexa: Haemosporida; 
  <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span> and other related genera 
  <span class="italic">Haemoproteus</span> spp. and 
  <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span> spp.; henceforth referred to as ‘avian malaria’) are vector-borne blood parasites that place significant selective pressure on their host populations by reducing reproductive success [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>], immune response [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>], and chronic-infection driven fitness [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>]. Increased parasite intensities can have negative effects on bird populations by reducing growth [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>] and causing higher mortality and/or lower birth rates [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The temporal and spatial dynamics, and epidemiology of avian malaria are strongly governed by ecological (season, habitat quality, elevation) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>], demographical (host and vector density) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>], and environmental factors (temperature, precipitation) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>]. Seasonal variation in ambient temperature, influences host condition through an increase in energy demands [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>], leading to stress, and thereby increasing susceptibility to infection [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>]. In addition, host and vector abundance govern the frequency-dependent transmission of the pathogens [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>]. Cosgrove et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>] showed a marked seasonality in 
  <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span> transmission in temperate environments, which appears to result in zero prevalence estimates in winters. This is in stark contrast to the tropics where there is a lack of seasonal variation in 
  <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span> spp. prevalence in birds despite a strong correlation between mosquito abundance and temperature [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>]. Given these seasonal effects, the role of avian haemosporidians on their host has mainly been examined in the breeding season where the spring–summer emergence of parasitemia in avian hosts coincides with a high allocation of energy in reproduction, and high levels of corticosterone in the blood. However, the impact of parasite infection in the non-breeding season has largely remained neglected but see [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>]. Furthermore, climate change is likely to facilitate expanding geographic range of 
  <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span> species with an increase in the transmission window in habitats that are currently too cool to sustain vector populations and parasite development.
 </p>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The western Himalayan bird community provides a unique opportunity to understand the interplay between hypoxia and blood parasite intensity. In this montane system, birds exhibit two migration strategies; species are either year-round high elevation residents (sedentary) or seasonal elevational migrants. Elevational migrants winter at low elevations or in the plains (≤ 1500 m above sea level; a.s.l.) and move to breeding grounds at higher elevations (2600–4000 m a.s.l. or even higher) during the summer season [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>]. In the wintering grounds, resident birds may act as reservoirs for blood parasites, increasing the risk of infection for migrants. Elevational migrants thus, encounter a more diverse fauna of parasites compared with sedentary species. Barve et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>] showed that high elevation residents regulate Hb by having high mean cell haemoglobin concentration (MCHC), while elevational migrants adjust their Hb through fluctuation in Hct as they move between high and low elevations. The degree to which elevation and blood parasites influence Hb levels across elevational migrants and resident birds has remained unexplored and can have important implications for the ecology of parasites and montane birds. Given that thermal conditions and suitable vectors are present to transmit and maintain the infection, such migrants can form an effective bridge for parasites between the wintering and breeding grounds. Hence, this increases the risk of infection to naïve resident birds at high elevations which might not have evolved to cope with decreased Hb levels as a result of parasite infection. Additionally, elevational migrants are exposed to hypoxia for a relatively short period compared to their high elevation resident counterparts. Therefore, an examination of Hb concentration and haemosporidians infections in resident and migrant species can reveal whether physiological stress and haemolytic anaemia might be more detrimental to high elevation residents, with more haemoglobin lost with the haemolysis of each red blood cell, exacerbating physiological stress across a large elevational gradient.
 </p>
 <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this study we examined the infection status and infection intensity of three parasite genera 
  <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Haemoproteus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span> in 18 Himalayan avian species which differ in their migration strategies, and their erythropoietic response to hypoxia. We predicted that: (i) seasonal variation in probability of infection and infection intensity will be higher in elevational migrants than their resident counterparts; (ii) infection status and infection intensity will show a negative relationship with Hct and Hb levels; and (iii) high infection intensity and low Hb levels will be associated with elevational migrants as they are likely to experience more chronic hypoxia in the breeding season than high elevation residents.
 </p>
</sec>
