<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study site, avian blood sampling and physiological parameters</div>
  <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The bird blood sampling was conducted in the non-breeding season (January–March) and breeding season (April–May) in Kedarnath Wildlife Division, Uttarakhand, India. We selected 18 species of passerine birds based on their abundance and diversity across seven elevations: 1000, 1500 (low), 2100 (mid), 2650, 2800, 3000 and 3200 m (high) a.s.l. as mentioned in Barve et al. [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>] (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>a, Additional file 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>: Table S1).
   <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>
      <span class="bold">a</span> Phylogenetic relationships among bird species used in the analysis following [
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>]. Elevational distributions are from Dixit et al. [
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>] and Rasmussen and Anderton [
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>]. Dotted vertical lines represent sampling locations. Horizontal solid lines represent species breeding elevational distribution and dashed lines represent species winter distribution (elevation in metres) of resident (red) and elevational migrant (black) species. Coloured boxes on the left margin denote taxonomic families used in the analysis. Species codes (from top): PX (
      <span class="italic">Parus xanthogenys</span>, n = 9), PM (
      <span class="italic">Parus monticolus</span>, n = 115), PC (
      <span class="italic">Parus cinereus</span>, n = 24), GV (
      <span class="italic">Garrulax variegatum</span>, n = 29), GE (
      <span class="italic">Garrulax erythrocephalus</span>, n = 64), GA (
      <span class="italic">Garrulax albogularis</span>, n = 30), SW (
      <span class="italic">Seicercus whistleri</span>, n = 10), PR (
      <span class="italic">Phylloscopus reguloides</span>, n = 27), PXN (
      <span class="italic">Phylloscopus xanthoschistos</span>, n = 83), PMC (
      <span class="italic">Phylloscopus maculippenis</span>, n = 11), AC (
      <span class="italic">Aegithalos concinnus</span>, n = 41), TB (
      <span class="italic">Turdus boulboul</span>, n = 8), MC (
      <span class="italic">Myophonus caeruleus</span>, n = 43), FS (
      <span class="italic">Ficedula superciliaris</span>, n = 6), FST (
      <span class="italic">Ficedula strophiata </span>= n=14), PF (
      <span class="italic">Phoenicurus frontalis</span>, n = 15), TR (
      <span class="italic">Tarsiger rufilatus</span>, n = 24), PD (
      <span class="italic">Passer domesticus</span>, n = 20). Bird illustrations were reproduced from Handbook of the Birds of the World Alive [
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78" href="#CR78">78</a>]. 
      <span class="bold">b</span> Total parasite intensity decrease with increase in elevation (m). Parasite intensity increases with mid-elevation in non-breeding season. Intensity: 1 = submicrocopic; 2 = low; 3 = medium; 4 = high; 5 = very high; H = 
      <span class="italic">Haemoproteus</span>, L = 
      <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span>, P = 
      <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span>, H, L = 
      <span class="italic">Haemoproteus</span> and 
      <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span> co-infections, P, L = 
      <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span> and 
      <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span> co-infections. 
      <span class="bold">c</span> Hct is negatively correlated with total parasite intensity. 
      <span class="bold">d</span> Hb is negatively correlated with parasite intensity. H, L = 
      <span class="italic">Haemoproteus</span> and 
      <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span> co-infections, P, L = 
      <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span> and 
      <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span> co-infections
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="12898_2018_171_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">At each sampling site, 6–12 mist nets were set up in high bird activity locations. Each bird caught was identified and ringed with a numbered metal ring. Bird blood from the sub-brachial wing vein (never exceeding 1% of the individual’s body weight) was collected in SET Buffer (20–40 μL in 500 μL buffer 0.15 M NaCl, 0.05 M Tris, M EDTA, pH 8.0) or FTA cards (Whatman) for molecular analyses. Captured individuals were released at the site immediately after processing. In addition, for each blood sample, the concentration of Hb was determined using a portable HemoCue Hb 201+ photometer (HemoCue Hb, Ängelholm, Sweden). In this study we measured Hb for 18 bird species and obtained 286 samples in the breeding season and 287 in the non-breeding season (Additional file 
   <a rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM2">2</a>: Table S2 and Fig. S1 for summary of bird species with infection status and Hb values).
  </p>
  <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Whenever a sufficient sample (20–30 μL) was available, we also measured Hct (n = 245; Additional file 
   <a rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM2">2</a>: Table S2) for the same samples, using a Zipocrit Portable Centrifuge (LW Scientific Inc., Lawrenceville, GA, USA) with a spin time of 5 min. Both Hb and Hct measurements were highly repeatable within this study [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>].
  </p>
  <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition, for the 2014–2015 bird sampling in the breeding season (April–May), thin blood smears were prepared on glass slides to identify whether infections exhibited parasite gametocytes, which would indicate that elevational migrants act as ‘true’ hosts for that particular parasite strain [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>]. The smears were air-dried, fixed in 100% methanol and stained with Giemsa.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Infection status and intensity estimation</div>
  <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">DNA extractions were conducted using the phenol chloroform extraction method [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>]. The presence of 
   <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span>, 
   <span class="italic">Haemoproteus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span> was assessed using parasite-specific primers designed to amplify partial fragments the cytochrome 
   <span class="italic">b</span> (cyt-
   <span class="italic">b</span>) gene using nested PCR protocol [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>]. Each plate run included a parasite positive control and also a negative control (water instead of template DNA) to examine for any potential contamination. We screened all parasite negative samples for bird DNA (for cyt-
   <span class="italic">b</span> gene) following Dumbacher et al. [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>]. The resulting PCR products were then sequenced in both directions. Sequences were assembled, aligned and edited using SEQUENCHER version 5.2 (Genecodes Corp., Ann Arbor, MI, USA). We then identified sequences to genus using their closest sequence matches in the GenBank or MalAvi databases [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>]. For each positive PCR product (without blood smear in non-breeding season; January–March), parasite intensities were calculated as relative quantification values (RQ) as follows. We performed two quantitative PCRs (qPCR): one targeting the 18sRNA gene of avian haemosporidians following Ishtiaq et al. [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>], and the other targeting the 18sRNA gene of the bird (as described in [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>]). RQ can be interpreted as the fold-amount of the target gene (parasite 18s rDNA) with respect to the amount of the reference gene (Bird18s rDNA) and was calculated as 2
   <span class="sup">−(Ct18s parasite−Ct18s Bird)</span> where Ct represents the number of PCR cycles at which fluorescence was first detected as statistically significant above the baseline, which is inversely correlated with the initial amount of DNA in a sample. Each DNA sample was run in duplicate and the average values were used for further analysis. For samples run on different plates we used one reference sample common to all plates. We ran all samples, including the inter run calibrator (IRC), in duplicate. Runs were validated only if the non-template control (NTC) and the negative control did not exhibit fluorescence curves that crossed the threshold line, and the positive control gave a fluorescence curve that crossed the threshold line within 38 cycles (Ct ≤ 38). Following each run, we examined the results to ensure that replicates had similar Ct values and melting peaks. We validated intensity data against microscopy by including positive samples which had corresponding blood smear to calculate intensity. These results showed a good correspondence between parasitemia estimated by qPCR and microscopy [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>] which allowed us to compare intensity results using qPCR and traditional microscopy techniques. Similar results have been reported in other studies (e.g. [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>]). For convenience, RQ values were log transformed into intensity categories so it can be combined with the data with intensities scored on smears (see below). For example, assuming that in one microscopic field is 300–400 erythrocytes, then: ++++ should be more than approx. 3% (in percentage; 3 of 10 erythrocytes are infected); +++ should be about 0.3–1.3%, ++ should be about 0.03–0.2%, + should be about 0.003–0.02%. So, qPCR values (host/parasite ratio) of 1.796519336 were considered as +++; 0.011073119 + 0.064422307 ++. This way we generated intensity data for all samples ranging from submicroscopic, low (+), medium (++), high (+++) to very high (++++) intensity.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Light microscopy</div>
  <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Blood smears were examined for the presence of infected blood cells and gametocytes following Godfrey et al. [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>]. Briefly, all slides were first examined at low magnification (500×) for approximately 100 fields and then at least 100 fields were studied at high magnification (1000×) using an oil immersion lens (taking into account the 10× contribution from the ocular combined with objectives of the magnification reported). The intensity of infection was recorded as per the following criteria: low (+); 1–10 parasites per 100 thin film fields, medium (++); 11–100 parasites per 100 thin film fields, high (+++); 1–10 parasites in one thin film field and very high (++++); more than 10 parasites in one thin film field.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Modelling disease risk in Hb compromised species</div>
  <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For comparison of infection status across three parasite genera, we carried out four distinct analyses. We classified each sampled species as either an elevational migrant (EM status = 1) where almost all individuals migrate to significantly lower elevations or as sedentary (EM status = 0) were species that are consistently found in their breeding range in the winter in our study site. Information on elevational movement and distribution was obtained from a field survey [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>] in our study site and Rasmussen and Anderton [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>]. The first analysis consisted of generalized linear mixed models (GLMMs, function glmer in lme4; Bates et al. [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>]) to assess whether individual infection status with 
   <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span>, 
   <span class="italic">Haemoproteus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span> was influenced by elevation, bird migration strategy and season, as fixed effects, and bird taxonomy (species nested in genus and genus nested in family) as a random effect. All models were specified with a binomial error distribution and logit link function. The significance of fixed effects was evaluated with Wald’s χ
   <span class="sup">2</span>-tests [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>].
  </p>
  <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the second analysis, we used a linear mixed effect models to assess differences in infection intensity of the three parasite genera (
   <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span>, 
   <span class="italic">Haemoproteu</span>s and 
   <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span>) with elevation, season and migration status as fixed effects, and bird species as a random effect. For the intensity data, we used only positive samples with microscopy and qPCR methods. We further analysed the relationship between infection status and parasite intensity with Hct sampled across species. Owing to limited data, Hct was not analysed for migration strategies and season. Finally, we sought to tease apart the effects of migration status, parasite intensity, elevation, and season, on Hb levels. In order to investigate factors relating to Hb (at a variety of complexities/scales), we constructed predictive regression models using the linear mixed-effects kinship model fit by maximum likelihood (lmekin) within the “coxme” package [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>]. For each model, we controlled for phylogenetic effects by including a phylogenetic correlation matrix as a random effect using the “ape” package [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>]. The phylogenetic correlation matrix was derived from a phylogeny constructed from information by Jetz et al. [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>]. All data was checked for normality and corrected for over-dispersion as required.
  </p>
  <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Prior to running predictive models, correlations between predictor variables were assessed to test for collinearity using correlation matrices and simple linear models generated for each pairwise combination of predictors. There was a significant positive relationship between Hb and elevation in both elevational migrants (R
   <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.24, 
   <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.001) and residents (R
   <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.16, 
   <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.001; [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>]). We used intensity as an interactive term in all models since infection intensity can vary with time, seasons, age and sex [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>] and showed a negative association with Hb levels (see below). All other pairwise comparisons yielded absolute correlation values and variance explained by linear models (adjusted R
   <span class="sup">2</span>) of &lt; 0.5, indicating no issues of collinearity, so all predictors were retained.
  </p>
  <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Using data for 15 species in summer and nine species in winter (18 species in total), we fitted 18 linear mixed models separately for 
   <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span>, 
   <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span>, 
   <span class="italic">Haemoproteus</span>, mixed infections and total infected birds. We used AIC-based multi-model inference to identify well-supported statistical models that describe the relationships between Hb and biological parameters relevant to elevational distribution, such as (i) infection intensity, (ii) elevation (low, mid, high), (iii) EM status (1 = elevational migrants, 0 = resident species), (iv) season (breeding = 1, nonbreeding = 0), as fixed effects. In all cases, bird species was included as a random effect. The models were written based on variables that were ecologically relevant to hypoxia physiology (Additional file 
   <a rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM3">3</a>: Table S3) and model selection was done using the MuMIn package [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>].
  </p>
  <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used the Akaike Information Criteria (AIC; see [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>]), to select the best-fit model. We generated a set of 18 candidate models (including global model and single predictor models) which were ranked by AICc (Additional file 
   <a rid="MOESM3" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM3">3</a>: Table S3). Models with a difference (ΔAICc) of ≤ 2 are as parsimonious as the best-fit model (lowest AICc), and is considered strong evidence that the quality of the candidate models differ from one another [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>]. Relative importance of the traits was assessed and model-averaged estimates were derived to account for model uncertainty [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>]. We used a model-averaging approach to check the validity of the top-ranking model in each case, only including models with ΔAICc &lt; 2 [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>]. The relative importance (RI) of each parameter after model-averaging, was calculated by summing 
   <span class="italic">wi</span> across all models in which the parameter was present. Analyses were conducted in R v. 3.0.1 [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
