<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p id="Par31" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This is the first study which links interspecific variation in migratory strategies, variation in erythropoietic responses to hypoxia and parasite infection and intensity across an elevational gradient. Our current understanding of the seasonality and epidemiology of the avian haemosporidian community has been largely derived from studies conducted in the breeding season in temperate regions, when parasite infections peak in spring and summer with an increase in vector activity [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>]. Our study on western Himalayan birds shows that parasites persist in winters and infections are higher in intensity in the non-breeding season. We also demonstrate that high parasite intensity has a negative influence on both Hb and Hct suggesting a role of haemosporidian infections in impacting hypoxic stress in high elevation Himalayan birds.
 </p>
 <sec id="Sec11" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Seasonal variation in parasite intensity and infection status</div>
  <p id="Par32" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The presence of parasitemia throughout our study period (January–May; 2014–2015) suggests various underlying mechanisms; (i) the continued presence of all three parasite genera in medium to high intensity during the non-breeding season, highlighting the environmental stress in winters which likely induces a relapse of the previous year’s infections [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>]; (ii) scarcity of food in highly seasonal habitats like the Himalayas (e.g. [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>]), which directly affects body condition [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>], and is often reflected in high levels of infection intensity in winters. Migrant birds generally have poorer condition in winters compared to summer [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>] and body condition can deteriorate with high intensity infections [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>]. In addition, Hb declines with haemosporidian infections [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>], and a lower Hb with high intensity infections mainly driven by 
   <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span> spp. in the non-breeding season, would reflect a seasonal decline in trophic conditions. High intensity infections in elevational migrants in winter is thus an important finding, which has important implications for seasonal disease dynamics with the potential for carryover effects to the breeding season. Many elevational migrants sampled at high elevations during the breeding season were infected with submicroscopic infections.
  </p>
  <p id="Par33" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Dunn et al. [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>] showed high incidence of 
   <span class="italic">Haemoproteus</span> spp. in the non-breeding season, however, at low intensity. In our study, total parasite intensity was high in the non-breeding season. 
   <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span> spp. intensity showed no variation across seasons which is likely to be chronic stages of infections, whereas 
   <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span> spp. showed high intensity in the non-breeding season regardless of bird migration status, which can be classified either as chronic or relapses. These findings have important implications for over-winter ecology of 
   <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span> spp. in elevational migrants. Nonetheless, the total parasite intensity showed a significant decrease with elevation despite no change in parasite infection status with elevation. Temperature is a key driver of haematophagous arthropod vectors and parasite life-history traits that combine to determine transmission intensity. Even though the probability of infection with three parasite genera at these sites is variable, the sampling sites were selected primarily to illustrate the contrasting thermal environments that can exist across relatively small spatial scales within a region. Our sampling sites vary in elevation (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>a) and have marked differences in mean temperatures and diurnal temperature ranges, and thus have divergent effects on parasite development and persistence at a population level [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>]. The daily temperatures in the low elevation sites during the non-breeding season were warmer (10–25 °C) than mid to high elevation sites (4–10 °C; FI unpub. data) which suggests that low elevations have optimal conditions and lack any thermal constraints for the parasites and this probably allows the parasites to be present in the blood stream during non-breeding season. This would imply an ongoing transmission at the low elevation during winter as long as potential vector species are present, whereas at colder higher elevation sites, parasites withdraw from the blood stream until the ideal conditions appear.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec12" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Effect of parasite intensity on Hct and Hb</div>
  <p id="Par34" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In western Himalayan birds, high Hb levels were strongly associated high elevation, and the breeding season where elevational migrants are likely to experience chronic hypoxia (potentially compounded by increased energetic demands) [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>]. In our linear mixed model analyses to examine factors influencing Hb levels in parasite-specific infected bird models, parasite intensity was selected as an important predictor in mixed infection birds, however, parasite intensity showed negative significant effect in 
   <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span> infected birds with confidence intervals for the parameter estimates included zero, so there was little evidence that 
   <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span> parasite had any effect on Hb levels. These results are consistent with other studies that report negative effects of parasite intensity on haemoglobin concentration in birds [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">59</a>]; whereas some studies report no effect of parasite intensity on Hb levels [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">60</a>]. Based on a recent experimental study, even low intensity chronic infection influences physiology and fitness of hosts [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">61</a>]. Therefore, measurement of parasite intensity is important rather than relying only on infection status in evaluating the role of infections on host fitness and physiology.
  </p>
  <p id="Par35" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Whilst the prevalence estimates of haemosporidians are snapshots in time and space [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" href="#CR62">62</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">63</a>], our findings are important from physiological as well as ecological perspectives. Previous studies have shown that there is a correlation between parasite intensity and the severity of human malarial infections-high parasite intensity is correlated with high mortality rates [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" href="#CR64">64</a>]. It is quite possible that high intensity blood parasite infections are pathogenic to elevational migrants and lead to excessive haemolysis of parasitized erythrocytes in malaria infection, and may lead to anaemia (e.g. [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" href="#CR65">65</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">66</a>]). This is further supported by the low frequency of very high intensity parasite infections in high elevation sites. Many elevational migrants were detected with submicroscopic infection (detected by PCR but not by microscopy and this implies absence of infective parasite stage—gametocytes) in high elevation environments in peak breeding season despite being found in medium or high intensity at low elevations. These findings are in stark contrast with other studies in temperate regions where the majority of the birds with latent infections (birds infected during the prior breeding season) return to the breeding grounds and experience an increase in parasite blood stages—relapse [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" href="#CR67">67</a>]. Parasite intensity in 
   <span class="italic">Plasmodium falciparum</span> often shows a clear trend of decreasing with decreasing transmission intensity [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" href="#CR68">68</a>] and our finding implies that elevation can be a proxy for transmission intensity in avian haemosporidians, highlighting that studies should not only rely on prevalence based models as intensity drives the transmission intensity in high elevation sites and the combination of molecular tools and microscopy is critical in assessing parasite load. While we quantified relative intensity across Himalayan birds, one of the limitations of using mix intensity data—by converting qPCR values into intensity categories as scored on smears—meant loss of quantitative information which would have provided better resolution. Our estimates could be compromised for genus level intensity in few co-infected birds as qPCR primers amplify all three parasite genera successfully [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>]. Nonetheless, our parasite intensity estimates from qPCR and microscopy techniques were comparable as we screened all samples using nested PCR protocols [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>].
  </p>
  <p id="Par36" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Similarly, Hct, an important predictor of blood oxygen transport in elevational migrants, showed a negative effect with overall parasite intensity suggesting that the infections with haemosporidians lowers haematocrit. A recent field study of wild red-winged blackbirds population demonstrated that birds with higher 
   <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span> and 
   <span class="italic">Haemoproteus</span> parasitemia have lower hematocrit and a higher rate of red blood cell production [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">61</a>]. The probability of 
   <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span> infection showed a slight increase with Hct, probably as a result of upregulation of erythrocyte production, although, this warrants further investigation. 
   <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span> remained absent in high elevation environments in resident birds and showed distinctly low prevalence in migrant populations. Given that all infections in our study are identified at the parasite genus level and we have not been able to detect differences in pathogenicity within a genus, the pathogenicity could be related to specific parasite lineages which could in turn have a variable effect [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" href="#CR69">69</a>]. In general, 
   <span class="italic">Haemoproteus</span> has lower pathogenicity on its host than 
   <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span> [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" href="#CR70">70</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72" href="#CR72">72</a>]. It is possible that 
   <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span> infections are pathogenic to high elevation residents, which is reflected by low incidence at high elevations (but see below). Finally, some host species may be more susceptible to infection than others, and the species chosen for this study may have co-evolved with 
   <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span> spp. parasites becoming resistant to them [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73" href="#CR73">73</a>], a factor that probably explains the generally high prevalence of this parasite genus in western Himalayan birds. The high prevalence of 
   <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span> spp. throughout the elevational gradient is in contrast with other studies (e.g. [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74" href="#CR74">74</a>]) where 
   <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span> showed an association with high elevation rather than in adjacent lowlands. In our western Himalayan system, there was no difference in infection status but intensity showed a sharp decline across the elevational gradient which points towards the role of high intensity infections lowering Hct and Hb levels at high elevations.
  </p>
  <p id="Par37" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From an ecological perspective, climate change increases the risk of malaria in many birds [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75" href="#CR75">75</a>]. In addition to rising mean temperatures, diurnal fluctuations in temperature have also been shown to affect the rate of parasite development [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76" href="#CR76">76</a>] and range expansion, or allows a longer breeding season for arthropod vectors, both of which can alter transmission rates of malaria parasites. The relatively low prevalence of 
   <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span> in high elevation environments could be attributed to micro-climatic differences governing the vector populations between low and high elevations and therefore influencing the spread of the disease across elevational gradients. The high elevation Himalayan bird community may not generally be exposed to vectors and parasites throughout the year—
   <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span> transmission is restricted by thermal constraints and distribution of potential vectors [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>], and 
   <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span> spp. was not found in the resident birds in the high elevation sites and was limited to the elevational migrants. With rising temperature predicted by imminent climate warming [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77" href="#CR77">77</a>], and the subsequent range expansion of mosquito species and 
   <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span> spp. parasites to high elevations, this might pose significant risks to naïve bird populations (e.g. Hawaii islands; [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71" href="#CR71">71</a>]).
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
