<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Infection status and intensity estimation</div>
 <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">DNA extractions were conducted using the phenol chloroform extraction method [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>]. The presence of 
  <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Haemoproteus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span> was assessed using parasite-specific primers designed to amplify partial fragments the cytochrome 
  <span class="italic">b</span> (cyt-
  <span class="italic">b</span>) gene using nested PCR protocol [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>]. Each plate run included a parasite positive control and also a negative control (water instead of template DNA) to examine for any potential contamination. We screened all parasite negative samples for bird DNA (for cyt-
  <span class="italic">b</span> gene) following Dumbacher et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>]. The resulting PCR products were then sequenced in both directions. Sequences were assembled, aligned and edited using SEQUENCHER version 5.2 (Genecodes Corp., Ann Arbor, MI, USA). We then identified sequences to genus using their closest sequence matches in the GenBank or MalAvi databases [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>]. For each positive PCR product (without blood smear in non-breeding season; January–March), parasite intensities were calculated as relative quantification values (RQ) as follows. We performed two quantitative PCRs (qPCR): one targeting the 18sRNA gene of avian haemosporidians following Ishtiaq et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>], and the other targeting the 18sRNA gene of the bird (as described in [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>]). RQ can be interpreted as the fold-amount of the target gene (parasite 18s rDNA) with respect to the amount of the reference gene (Bird18s rDNA) and was calculated as 2
  <span class="sup">−(Ct18s parasite−Ct18s Bird)</span> where Ct represents the number of PCR cycles at which fluorescence was first detected as statistically significant above the baseline, which is inversely correlated with the initial amount of DNA in a sample. Each DNA sample was run in duplicate and the average values were used for further analysis. For samples run on different plates we used one reference sample common to all plates. We ran all samples, including the inter run calibrator (IRC), in duplicate. Runs were validated only if the non-template control (NTC) and the negative control did not exhibit fluorescence curves that crossed the threshold line, and the positive control gave a fluorescence curve that crossed the threshold line within 38 cycles (Ct ≤ 38). Following each run, we examined the results to ensure that replicates had similar Ct values and melting peaks. We validated intensity data against microscopy by including positive samples which had corresponding blood smear to calculate intensity. These results showed a good correspondence between parasitemia estimated by qPCR and microscopy [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>] which allowed us to compare intensity results using qPCR and traditional microscopy techniques. Similar results have been reported in other studies (e.g. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>]). For convenience, RQ values were log transformed into intensity categories so it can be combined with the data with intensities scored on smears (see below). For example, assuming that in one microscopic field is 300–400 erythrocytes, then: ++++ should be more than approx. 3% (in percentage; 3 of 10 erythrocytes are infected); +++ should be about 0.3–1.3%, ++ should be about 0.03–0.2%, + should be about 0.003–0.02%. So, qPCR values (host/parasite ratio) of 1.796519336 were considered as +++; 0.011073119 + 0.064422307 ++. This way we generated intensity data for all samples ranging from submicroscopic, low (+), medium (++), high (+++) to very high (++++) intensity.
 </p>
</sec>
