<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec11" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Seasonal variation in parasite intensity and infection status</div>
 <p id="Par32" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The presence of parasitemia throughout our study period (January–May; 2014–2015) suggests various underlying mechanisms; (i) the continued presence of all three parasite genera in medium to high intensity during the non-breeding season, highlighting the environmental stress in winters which likely induces a relapse of the previous year’s infections [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>]; (ii) scarcity of food in highly seasonal habitats like the Himalayas (e.g. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>]), which directly affects body condition [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>], and is often reflected in high levels of infection intensity in winters. Migrant birds generally have poorer condition in winters compared to summer [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>] and body condition can deteriorate with high intensity infections [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>]. In addition, Hb declines with haemosporidian infections [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>], and a lower Hb with high intensity infections mainly driven by 
  <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span> spp. in the non-breeding season, would reflect a seasonal decline in trophic conditions. High intensity infections in elevational migrants in winter is thus an important finding, which has important implications for seasonal disease dynamics with the potential for carryover effects to the breeding season. Many elevational migrants sampled at high elevations during the breeding season were infected with submicroscopic infections.
 </p>
 <p id="Par33" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Dunn et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>] showed high incidence of 
  <span class="italic">Haemoproteus</span> spp. in the non-breeding season, however, at low intensity. In our study, total parasite intensity was high in the non-breeding season. 
  <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span> spp. intensity showed no variation across seasons which is likely to be chronic stages of infections, whereas 
  <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span> spp. showed high intensity in the non-breeding season regardless of bird migration status, which can be classified either as chronic or relapses. These findings have important implications for over-winter ecology of 
  <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span> spp. in elevational migrants. Nonetheless, the total parasite intensity showed a significant decrease with elevation despite no change in parasite infection status with elevation. Temperature is a key driver of haematophagous arthropod vectors and parasite life-history traits that combine to determine transmission intensity. Even though the probability of infection with three parasite genera at these sites is variable, the sampling sites were selected primarily to illustrate the contrasting thermal environments that can exist across relatively small spatial scales within a region. Our sampling sites vary in elevation (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>a) and have marked differences in mean temperatures and diurnal temperature ranges, and thus have divergent effects on parasite development and persistence at a population level [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>]. The daily temperatures in the low elevation sites during the non-breeding season were warmer (10–25 °C) than mid to high elevation sites (4–10 °C; FI unpub. data) which suggests that low elevations have optimal conditions and lack any thermal constraints for the parasites and this probably allows the parasites to be present in the blood stream during non-breeding season. This would imply an ongoing transmission at the low elevation during winter as long as potential vector species are present, whereas at colder higher elevation sites, parasites withdraw from the blood stream until the ideal conditions appear.
 </p>
</sec>
