<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study site, avian blood sampling and physiological parameters</div>
 <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The bird blood sampling was conducted in the non-breeding season (January–March) and breeding season (April–May) in Kedarnath Wildlife Division, Uttarakhand, India. We selected 18 species of passerine birds based on their abundance and diversity across seven elevations: 1000, 1500 (low), 2100 (mid), 2650, 2800, 3000 and 3200 m (high) a.s.l. as mentioned in Barve et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>] (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>a, Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>: Table S1).
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>
     <span class="bold">a</span> Phylogenetic relationships among bird species used in the analysis following [
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>]. Elevational distributions are from Dixit et al. [
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>] and Rasmussen and Anderton [
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>]. Dotted vertical lines represent sampling locations. Horizontal solid lines represent species breeding elevational distribution and dashed lines represent species winter distribution (elevation in metres) of resident (red) and elevational migrant (black) species. Coloured boxes on the left margin denote taxonomic families used in the analysis. Species codes (from top): PX (
     <span class="italic">Parus xanthogenys</span>, n = 9), PM (
     <span class="italic">Parus monticolus</span>, n = 115), PC (
     <span class="italic">Parus cinereus</span>, n = 24), GV (
     <span class="italic">Garrulax variegatum</span>, n = 29), GE (
     <span class="italic">Garrulax erythrocephalus</span>, n = 64), GA (
     <span class="italic">Garrulax albogularis</span>, n = 30), SW (
     <span class="italic">Seicercus whistleri</span>, n = 10), PR (
     <span class="italic">Phylloscopus reguloides</span>, n = 27), PXN (
     <span class="italic">Phylloscopus xanthoschistos</span>, n = 83), PMC (
     <span class="italic">Phylloscopus maculippenis</span>, n = 11), AC (
     <span class="italic">Aegithalos concinnus</span>, n = 41), TB (
     <span class="italic">Turdus boulboul</span>, n = 8), MC (
     <span class="italic">Myophonus caeruleus</span>, n = 43), FS (
     <span class="italic">Ficedula superciliaris</span>, n = 6), FST (
     <span class="italic">Ficedula strophiata </span>= n=14), PF (
     <span class="italic">Phoenicurus frontalis</span>, n = 15), TR (
     <span class="italic">Tarsiger rufilatus</span>, n = 24), PD (
     <span class="italic">Passer domesticus</span>, n = 20). Bird illustrations were reproduced from Handbook of the Birds of the World Alive [
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78" href="#CR78">78</a>]. 
     <span class="bold">b</span> Total parasite intensity decrease with increase in elevation (m). Parasite intensity increases with mid-elevation in non-breeding season. Intensity: 1 = submicrocopic; 2 = low; 3 = medium; 4 = high; 5 = very high; H = 
     <span class="italic">Haemoproteus</span>, L = 
     <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span>, P = 
     <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span>, H, L = 
     <span class="italic">Haemoproteus</span> and 
     <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span> co-infections, P, L = 
     <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span> and 
     <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span> co-infections. 
     <span class="bold">c</span> Hct is negatively correlated with total parasite intensity. 
     <span class="bold">d</span> Hb is negatively correlated with parasite intensity. H, L = 
     <span class="italic">Haemoproteus</span> and 
     <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span> co-infections, P, L = 
     <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span> and 
     <span class="italic">Leucocytozoon</span> co-infections
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="12898_2018_171_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">At each sampling site, 6–12 mist nets were set up in high bird activity locations. Each bird caught was identified and ringed with a numbered metal ring. Bird blood from the sub-brachial wing vein (never exceeding 1% of the individual’s body weight) was collected in SET Buffer (20–40 μL in 500 μL buffer 0.15 M NaCl, 0.05 M Tris, M EDTA, pH 8.0) or FTA cards (Whatman) for molecular analyses. Captured individuals were released at the site immediately after processing. In addition, for each blood sample, the concentration of Hb was determined using a portable HemoCue Hb 201+ photometer (HemoCue Hb, Ängelholm, Sweden). In this study we measured Hb for 18 bird species and obtained 286 samples in the breeding season and 287 in the non-breeding season (Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM2">2</a>: Table S2 and Fig. S1 for summary of bird species with infection status and Hb values).
 </p>
 <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Whenever a sufficient sample (20–30 μL) was available, we also measured Hct (n = 245; Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM2">2</a>: Table S2) for the same samples, using a Zipocrit Portable Centrifuge (LW Scientific Inc., Lawrenceville, GA, USA) with a spin time of 5 min. Both Hb and Hct measurements were highly repeatable within this study [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition, for the 2014–2015 bird sampling in the breeding season (April–May), thin blood smears were prepared on glass slides to identify whether infections exhibited parasite gametocytes, which would indicate that elevational migrants act as ‘true’ hosts for that particular parasite strain [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>]. The smears were air-dried, fixed in 100% methanol and stained with Giemsa.
 </p>
</sec>
