<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Contributions to ambient and population-weighted PM
  <sub>2.5</sub>
 </div>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Due to the rapid transition of cooking and heating energy from solid fuels towards clean fuels and electricity, as well as a rapid urbanization, most air pollutant emissions from the rural residential sector have been reduced over the last two decades; however, this sector remains a significant source of many air pollutants, contributing 39% and 46% of the total emissions of BC and organic carbon (OC) in 2012, respectively
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span>. Based on the results of atmospheric chemical transport modelling (see Method), in 2012, the increment contributed by rural residential emissions to the national annual mean ambient PM
  <sub>2.5</sub> concentration was 5.4 ± 6.1 μg/m
  <span class="sup">3</span> with high spatial variations. This value corresponds to a relative contribution of one-third (33 ± 17%) of the total PM
  <sub>2.5</sub> concentration in ambient air originating from all anthropogenic emission sources including power generation, industry, and transportation.
 </p>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Because of uneven population distribution, the population-weighted concentration (PWC) was different from the air quality concentration. The contribution from rural residential emissions to the annual mean PWC was 14 ± 10 μg/m
  <span class="sup">3</span>, accounting for 21 ± 14% of the total PWC from all sources. The national average rural residential source associated PWC (14 µg/m
  <span class="sup">3</span>) was almost three times the average ambient PM
  <sub>2.5</sub> concentration attributable to rural residential emissions (5.4 µg/m
  <span class="sup">3</span>). Since the National Grade-I standard
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
  </span>, equal to the Interim Target-1 level set by the World Health Organization (WHO)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span>, for the annual mean ambient PM
  <sub>2.5</sub> is 35 μg/m
  <span class="sup">3</span>, the contribution from the rural residential sector cannot be ignored in the overall mitigation strategy for combating severe air pollution.
 </p>
</sec>
