<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Emission data</div>
 <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The emission inventories of CO
  <sub>2</sub> and major air pollutants, including SO
  <sub>2</sub>, CO, PM
  <sub>2.5</sub>, PM
  <sub>10</sub>, BC, OC, NOx, and NH
  <sub>3</sub>, from rural residential and other sources with 0.1° × 0.1° spatial and daily temporal resolutions for 1992, 2002, 2007, and 2012 were sourced from 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://inventory.pku.edu.cn" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://inventory.pku.edu.cn</span>, which was updated recently to include the latest information on the rural residential energy transition, population growth, and urbanization
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span>. Air pollutant emissions for the rural residential sector were mainly based on two recently updated databases. A new energy database was established based on a rural residential energy survey that covered detailed energy use activities, including staple food cooking, side dish preparation, water boiling, animal feed heating, and space heating for more than 34,400 households and daily biomass fuel consumption quantities for more than 1600 households
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span>. The rural residential energy database covered detailed information on various energy types including coal, honeycomb briquette, straw, corncob, fuelwood, brushwood, charcoal, LPG, biogas, and electricity. The emission factor database was re-compiled based on carefully screened data from published studies conducted in China. For CO
  <sub>2</sub> emission calculation, all crop residues were considered carbon neutral, and for fuelwood, the non-renewable fractions for all individual provinces in China were sourced from the literature
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
  </span>. The VOC emissions were obtained from the EDGAR-HTAP dataset
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
</sec>
