<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec13" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Uncertainty analysis</div>
 <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A Monte Carlo simulation (1000 times) was conducted to characterize the uncertainty of the estimated health impacts. The results reflect the influences of both the exposure level and the dose-response relationship including slope and nonlinearity. Because of the heavy computation load, a Monte Carlo simulation could not be conducted for the transport modelling. According to the results from a previous research the variation of PM
  <sub>2.5</sub> concentrations is similar to that of primary PM
  <sub>2.5</sub> emissions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>
  </span>, which was close to 10% in China
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span>. Therefore, for each grid, a 10% uncertainty in air PM
  <sub>2.5</sub> was assumed and used in the uncertainty analysis for the health impact assessment. The sensitivity analysis (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">10</a>) showed that differences in estimated premature deaths with the assumed grid PM
  <sub>2.5</sub> concentration uncertainties at 10%, 15%, and 25% were within 1%, indicating that the overall uncertainty in health outcomes was affected largely by dose-response functions compared with the uncertainty in PM
  <sub>2.5</sub> concentration
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">60</a>
  </span>. The uncertainties of estimated health impacts were calculated based on the given distribution of parameters from the GEMM
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>
  </span>, by applying a 1000-run Monte Carlo simulation. The variations derived from the Monte Carlo simulation are strongly associated with the nonlinearity of the dose-response relationship. The importance of the dose-response relationship for uncertainty has been previously reported
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">60</a>
  </span>. The results are presented at a 95% uncertainty interval (which ranges between the 2.5th and 97.5th percentiles).
 </p>
</sec>
