<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Perceived internal efficacy was measured by adapting established measures of internal political efficacy [
 <xref rid="pone.0157658.ref030" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0157658.ref039" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>] to the specific context of climate change. Previous research found that items assessing citizens’ perceived understanding of political issues, their sense of being well-informed about politics, and their feeling of being well-qualified to participate in politics together perform as a valid and reliable measure of internal efficacy [
 <xref rid="pone.0157658.ref030" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0157658.ref039" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>]. We directly adapted these items to the issue of climate change and also included additional items to help further capture one’s perceived ability to understand and participate in politics in the context of climate change. Given that climate change is both a scientific and political issue, internal political efficacy in the realm of climate change requires confidence in one’s understanding of politics in general, one’s understanding of politics as it applies to climate change specifically, and one’s understanding of climate change itself, as well as in one’s ability to effectively participate on the issue of climate change. Thus, we asked participants how much they agreed or disagreed with the following statements: 1) “I think that I am as well informed about politics and government as most people,” 2) “I think that I know as much about the politics surrounding climate change as most people,” 3) “I think that I am as well informed about government policies that could address climate change as most people,”4) “I consider myself to be well qualified to participate in politics related to climate change,” 5) “I feel that I have a pretty good understanding of climate change,” and 6) “I feel confident that, if I wanted to, I would have the ability to contact a government official about climate change.” Each item was rated on a 7-point scale that ranged from strongly disagree (1) to strongly agree (7). The respective answers were then averaged into a single internal efficacy scale (Cronbach’s alpha = .92, M = 4.48, SD = 1.38).
</p>
