<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="P22" class="p">We estimate the economic value of projected health impacts based on recommendations in federal guidance for economic analyses (
 <xref rid="R66" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">U.S. EPA, 2014</xref>) and valuation functions included in the BenMAP-CE model. Such economic analyses consider the “willingness to pay” of individuals, which accounts for the amounts individuals are willing to pay for small reductions in mortality risk (“Value of Statistical Life (VSL)”) and the changes in VSL over time as real income grows (“income elasticity” of willingness to pay). For mortality endpoints, the EPA’s Guidelines for Preparing Economic Analyses recommends a VSL of $7.9 million (2008$) based on 1990 incomes (
 <xref rid="R66" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">U.S. EPA, 2014</xref>). To create a VSL using 2015$ and based on 2010 incomes, the standard value was adjusted for inflation and income growth based on the approach described in EPA’s BenMAP-CE model and its documentation (
 <xref rid="R70" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">U.S. EPA, 2018a</xref>, 
 <xref rid="R71" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2018b</xref>). The resulting value, $9.7 million for 2010 (2015$), was adjusted to future years by assuming an income (gross domestic product per capita) elasticity of VSL of 0.4. Projections of U.S. population change are described in 
 <xref rid="S7" ref-type="sec" class="xref">section 2.3.2</xref>, and the Emissions Predictions and Policy Analysis model (version 6; 
 <xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Chen et al., 2015</xref>) was run to generate a projection of economic growth. Applying this standard approach yields the following VSL values: $11.0 million in 2030, $12.4 million in 2050, $13.8 million in 2070, and $15.2 million in 2090 (in undiscounted 2015$). As more recent literature favors a higher estimate of income elasticity of VSL (see 
 <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">supporting information</xref>), we also perform a sensitivity test using an elasticity of 1.0, reflecting proportional growth in VSL with gross domestic product per capita. Using an elasticity of 1.0 compared with 0.4, our estimated costs associated with the mortality burdens are 16% higher in 2030 and 87% higher in 2090 (
 <xref rid="SD1" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">Table S7</xref>). The sensitivity analysis suggests that our valuation of the mortality endpoints may be conservative.
</p>
