<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2a" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Roost selection experiment</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All procedures were conducted under Manitoba Conservation and Ontario Ministry of Natural Resources permits and approved by the University of Winnipeg Animal Care Committee. Between 28 April and 5 May 2013, 32 adult male little brown bats (hereafter, ‘infected’) were captured from two WNS-positive mines &lt;90 km apart near Renfrew, Ontario (45.47°N, 76.68°W) and Gatineau, Québec (45.48°N, 75.65°W), Canada. These bats were used in several studies examining the recovery phase from WNS and, of these individuals, 11 were available for use in the present study. At the time of capture, bats were weighed (CS200 portable scale; Ohaus Corporation, Pine Brook, NJ, USA, accuracy ±0.1 g), and their forearm length was measured using digital callipers (digital caliper; Mastercraft, Vonore, TN, USA). All bats were outfitted with temperature dataloggers (DS1922L-F5 Thermochron iButton; Maxim, San Jose, CA, USA) modified to reduce mass following 
  <a rid="COV070C35" ref-type="bibr" href="#COV070C35">Lovegrove (2009</a>) and 
  <a rid="COV070C44" ref-type="bibr" href="#COV070C44">Reeder 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span> (2012
  </a>). Temperature dataloggers were attached in the interscapular region using a latex-based adhesive (Osto-Bond; Montreal Ostomy Centre, Vaudreuil-Dorion, QC, Canada), and a unique symbol was marked on each datalogger for easy identification of individuals. The dataloggers were used for another study to record 
  <span class="italic">T</span>
  <sub>b</sub> during late winter and early spring, and datalogger memories were full by the time our behavioural experiment began. However, we did not remove them from bats before our experiment in order to reduce handling stress. Thus, no 
  <span class="italic">T</span>
  <sub>b</sub> data are reported in this paper. Bats were held in cloth bags inside hepa-filtered animal carriers stored in a temperature-controlled cabinet for transport to the University of Winnipeg. Bats were later banded with a uniquely numbered, lipped aluminum forearm band (Porzana Ltd, Icklesham, East Sussex, UK).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On 28 May 2013, 39 male little brown bats (hereafter, ‘control’) were captured from a WNS-negative cave in the northern-interlake region of Manitoba, Canada (53.20°N, 99.30°W). Of these individuals, 26 were available for this study. Bats were tagged and placed in cloth bags suspended in a plug-in ventilated cooler for transport to the University of Winnipeg. Morphometric measurements were obtained as described for infected bats. Bats from both the infected and control groups were housed over the summer until the beginning of hibernation on 11 October 2013. We confirmed the infection status of all individuals from both infected (all individuals were positive for 
  <span class="italic">P. destructans</span>) and control (all individuals were negative) groups via quantitative PCR conducted at the Center for Microbial Genetics and Genomics at Northern Arizona University (
  <a rid="COV070C33" ref-type="bibr" href="#COV070C33">Lorch 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2010
  </a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The holding room was maintained at 18°C and 60% relative humidity, and lights were set for a natural spring photoperiod (light:dark = 11:13 h) with a graduated transition from lights on to lights off. Infected and control bats were housed in separate but identical flight cages 2.24 m
  <span class="sup">2</span> long × 1.01 m wide × 2.42 m high. Separate cages eliminated the possibility of infection of control bats because 
  <span class="italic">P. destructans</span> does not spread without physical contact in the laboratory (
  <a rid="COV070C33" ref-type="bibr" href="#COV070C33">Lorch 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>., 2010
  </a>). Each flight cage was equipped with two custom-built single-chambered bat houses (44 cm × 6.3 cm × 60 cm). The back of one bat house in each cage was lined with an electrical heating coil (Exoterra Temperature Heating Cable, 12 V; Rolf C. Hagen Group, Mansfield, MA, USA) controlled using an electronic temperature controller set to 30°C (Ranco Nema 4× Electircal Temperature Control; Invensys, Plain City, OH, USA), slightly below the lower critical temperature for little brown bats (i.e. 32°C; 
  <a rid="COV070C49" ref-type="bibr" href="#COV070C49">Stones and Wiebers, 1965</a>; 
  <a rid="COV070C48" ref-type="bibr" href="#COV070C48">Speakman and Thomas, 2003</a>). In the infected flight cage, the heated bat house was mounted on 7 May 2013, whereas the unheated bat house was provided on 21 May 2013 because it was not yet available when infected bats were collected. In the flight cage housing control bats, both the heated and unheated bat houses were installed on 21 May 2013. Throughout captivity, bats were provided with mealworms (
  <span class="italic">Tenebrio molitor</span>) and water 
  <span class="italic">ad libitum</span> on tables in the centre of each flight cage. Bats were collected from inside bat houses for weighing about every 2 days. Between 9 June and 31 July 2013, while collecting bats for these weighing sessions, we recorded the number of bats in each type of bat house in each flight cage.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although they are among the species most affected by WNS and, therefore, important to study, little brown bats are difficult to maintain in captivity during the active season (
  <a rid="COV070C32" ref-type="bibr" href="#COV070C32">Lollar, 2010</a>). Between 3 May 2013 and 28 July 2013, some infected (
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 2) and control bats (
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 17) exhibited abnormal behaviour, including impaired and weakened gait, inability to fly, lack of feeding, and a decline in body mass. Bats exhibiting these symptoms were isolated in smaller nylon mesh cages (20.3 cm × 20.9 cm × 24.1 cm) to improve access to food and water and facilitate monitoring. If their condition continued to decline, as indicated by a loss of &gt;5% body mass, they were anaesthetized using isoflurane in oxygen (5%) and euthanized via CO
  <sub>2</sub> asphyxiation. Pathology showed no bacterial or viral infection, and bats did not exhibit signs of fatty liver syndrome, which can cause the behavioural patterns we observed in captive bats as a combined result of excess food consumption and stress (
  <a rid="COV070C32" ref-type="bibr" href="#COV070C32">Lollar, 2010</a>; 
  <a rid="COV070C3" ref-type="bibr" href="#COV070C3">Olsson and Barnard, 2009</a>). In addition to this unidentified problem, between 23 July and 31 July 2013 two bats were isolated for lower abdominal swelling that turned out to be a bacterial infection caused by 
  <span class="italic">Proteus morganii</span>. Therefore, all bats were given an oral administration of enrofloxacin (0.1 mL day
  <span class="sup">−1</span>) and cefazolin (0.1 mL day
  <span class="sup">−1</span>). These challenges led to fluctuating numbers of bats in each cage as individuals were moved between the flight cage and isolation, and a gradual decline in numbers in each flight cage as bats were removed from the study (
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 8 bats per group by the end of the study). As a result of these fluctuating numbers, we quantified roosting preferences as the proportion of bats in each flight cage found roosting in the heated vs. unheated houses during the times when we captured bats for weighing.
 </p>
</sec>
