<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Recently, studies have begun to incorporate natural cycles within climate variables, such as O
 <sub>2</sub>, CO
 <sub>2</sub> or temperature. In the only study to date to attempt to investigate the effect of diel cycles of CO
 <sub>2</sub> on fish anti-predator performance (
 <xref rid="ref87" ref-type="bibr">Jarrold and Munday, 2018</xref>), the escape response to a startle stimulus of juvenile damselfish (
 <italic>Acanthochromis polyacanthus</italic>) was examined. Fish were reared for 11 weeks in two stable (450 and 1000 μatm) and two diel-cycling elevated CO
 <sub>2</sub> treatments (1000 ± 300 and 1000 ± 500 μatm) at both current-day (29°C) and projected future temperatures (31°C). No interaction between CO
 <sub>2</sub> and temperature for any performance characteristics was found, though survival was affected. Survival was lower in the two cycling CO
 <sub>2</sub> treatments at 31°C compared with 29°C, but did not differ between temperatures in the two stable CO
 <sub>2</sub> treatments. While temperature had significant independent effects on escape performance traits, there was no effect of stable or cycling CO
 <sub>2</sub> levels nor was there an interaction between temperature and CO
 <sub>2</sub>.These findings support the idea that water temperature, confined within realistic near-future projections, has the greatest impact on escape performance compared to elevated CO
 <sub>2</sub> (
 <xref rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr">Allan 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2017
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref87" ref-type="bibr">Jarrold and Munday, 2018</xref>). Other stressors, such as dissolved oxygen can also display major diel fluctuations (e.g. 
 <xref rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr">Domenici 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007a
 </xref>) and these are yet to be incorporated into experiments. Although experiments that incorporate cycles in more than one stressor have yet to be undertaken, these will be important as diel temperature cycles peak during the daylight hours, while diel CO
 <sub>2</sub> cycles peak at night, and oxygen levels tend to be lowest at dawn. These diel patterns may complicate predictions about how they interact to affect fish performance.
</p>
