<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par2" class="p">Hurricanes are one of the most devastating and costly natural disasters to befall the United States coastal regions
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">1</xref>
 </sup>. They account for about 20% of the total billion dollars weather and climate related disasters and over 50% of the total loss in the U.S.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">1</xref>
 </sup>. Previous studies
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" class="xref">2</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">3</xref>
 </sup> have shown that there has been increased destruction associated with Atlantic hurricanes in the past few decades. How human activity may contribute to hurricane intensity change in the future, particularly landfalling hurricanes, is thus an extremely urgent question for society at large. The longer-term change in hurricane intensity in the observational record, however, is somewhat uncertain
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">4</xref>
 </sup>. The uncertainty is partly due to the lack of long reliable historical hurricane data
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">5</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">6</xref>
 </sup>, and partly due to the large natural multidecadal variability in the North Atlantic sea surface temperatures (SST) that are known to affect hurricane activity in the tropical Atlantic
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">8</xref>
 </sup>. Large scale environmental variables, such as SST and vertical wind shear (VWS), are often used as a proxy for hurricane potential intensity (PI)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">9</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>
 </sup> and genesis
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">11</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">13</xref>
 </sup>, respectively. The VWS, defined as the magnitude of the vector wind difference between the upper (200 hPa) and lower (850 hPa) troposphere, is well known to affect hurricane activity on various time-scales, with weak VWS favorable for hurricane convective organization and intensification
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">14</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>
 </sup>. A recent study
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">17</xref>
 </sup> noted that hurricane intensification rates near the U.S. southeast coast were suppressed in recent decades due to enhanced VWS. That study, as well as previous studies
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">18</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" class="xref">19</xref>
 </sup>, further noted that there is a large decadal variation in the dominant mode of VWS, which is characterized by a dipole spatial pattern with one node along the U.S. East Coast and one in the tropical North Atlantic, or the hurricane main development region (MDR)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">17</xref>
 </sup>. The dipole structure also exists in the SST pattern, with slightly weaker warming in the region of increased VWS and stronger warming in the MDR. During the phase when the tropical Atlantic experiences weak VWS and warm SST, and thus greater hurricane activity in the MDR region, the U.S. coast is shielded from strong landfalling hurricanes due to the strong VWS and weak SST warming along the coastal regions. Thus the dipole mode provides a protective barrier to the U.S. East Coast when hurricanes are particularly active and strong in the tropical Atlantic MDR, which seems to be the case in recent decades. It is not clear, however, whether the dipole pattern and the related recent increases in VWS along the U.S. East Coast are driven entirely by natural decadal variability, or there may be contributions from anthropogenic forcing.
</p>
