<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Human malaria is caused by five species of plasmodium parasites and is transmitted by female 
 <italic class="italic">Anopheles</italic> mosquitoes. The tropical form, 
 <italic class="italic">Plasmodium falciparum</italic>, causes the most severe clinical form of malaria and is widespread in the tropics and sub‐Saharan Africa, causing about 90% of global malaria cases.
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" class="xref">34</xref> The more temperate form, 
 <italic class="italic">Plasmodium vivax</italic>, used to be prevalent in Europe, but control measures such as drainage of marshes and spraying of dichlorodiphenyltrichloroethane (DDT) led to its disappearance following World War II. Overall, 
 <italic class="italic">Anopheles</italic> mosquitoes need adequate rainfall to create breeding sites that will not dry up or wash away over a 9–12 day period. Replication of the parasite within the mosquito vector requires a minimum air temperature of about 15–16 °C for 
 <italic class="italic">P. vivax</italic> and 19–20 °C for 
 <italic class="italic">P. falciparum</italic>.
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" class="xref">35</xref>, 
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" class="xref">36</xref> Increased temperatures that are close to the upper limit for vector and pathogen survival (roughly about 35–37 °C) tend to reduce transmission, while increased variation in daily temperatures near the lower limit tends to increase transmission.
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" class="xref">35</xref>, 
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" class="xref">37</xref>, 
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0038" ref-type="ref" class="xref">38</xref> Precipitation creates adequate vector breeding sites, and the relationship between temperature, rainfall, and malaria is also highly vector‐specific.
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" class="xref">24</xref>, 
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" class="xref">39</xref>
</p>
