<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Economic development and the implementation of stringent control and intervention measures have driven a large global decrease in the spatial distribution and endemicity of the disease over the past century. This is despite rising global temperatures,
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" class="xref">40</xref>, 
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" class="xref">41</xref> thanks to significant funding efforts to control and reduce malaria burden. Current malaria interventions have the ultimate goal of malaria elimination, but are unlikely to be capable of eradicating the disease completely in all regions of Africa, even in current climate conditions.
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" class="xref">42</xref> The number of reported human infections with 
 <italic class="italic">P. falciparum</italic> is increasing in tropical highland regions across the globe, for example, in Eastern Africa,
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" class="xref">24</xref>, 
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" class="xref">25</xref>, 
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" class="xref">43</xref>, 
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0044" ref-type="ref" class="xref">44</xref>, 
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0045" ref-type="ref" class="xref">45</xref>, 
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0046" ref-type="ref" class="xref">46</xref> Nepal,
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" class="xref">47</xref>, 
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0048" ref-type="ref" class="xref">48</xref>, 
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" class="xref">49</xref>, 
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0050" ref-type="ref" class="xref">50</xref> and Colombia.
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" class="xref">43</xref> Competent malaria vectors have also recently been found at higher altitudes.
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" class="xref">47</xref>, 
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" class="xref">49</xref>, 
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0051" ref-type="ref" class="xref">51</xref>, 
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" class="xref">52</xref>, 
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" class="xref">53</xref>, 
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" class="xref">54</xref>This has serious implications for indigenous highland human populations that usually lack protective immunity and are more vulnerable to severe malaria morbidity and mortality. The extraordinary biological complexity of the malaria parasite has hindered the development of effective vaccines, even though it is well known that transmission‐blocking antiparasite immune responses exist. RTS,S/AS01 is the most advanced malaria vaccine candidate currently in development, and is due to be rolled out in trials in three African countries in 2018.
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" class="xref">55</xref>
</p>
