<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The distinctive geographic environment of the world highest plateau—Tibetan Plateau (with an average elevation of over 4000 m above sea level) makes its carbon cycle be strongly sensitive to climate variation and environmental change [
  <a rid="pone.0215261.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215261.ref001">1</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0215261.ref003" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215261.ref003">3</a>]. The Plateau covers a vast area of alpine vegetation and has a large reservoir of organic carbon in the permafrost soil, and it has been reported as a significant terrestrial carbon sink for recent decades due largely to warming and CO
  <sub>2</sub> fertilization [
  <a rid="pone.0215261.ref003" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215261.ref003">3</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0215261.ref005" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215261.ref005">5</a>]. The Plateau has undergone significant warming during the last decades. Increasing temperatures have been reported to prolong growing season lengths [
  <a rid="pone.0215261.ref006" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215261.ref006">6</a>], metabolic rates, and the productivity and distribution [
  <a rid="pone.0215261.ref007" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215261.ref007">7</a>] of vegetation at the Plateau and high latitude areas [
  <a rid="pone.0215261.ref008" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215261.ref008">8</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0215261.ref010" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215261.ref010">10</a>]. Furthermore, the fate of soil organic carbon (SOC) is controlled by the complex processes involving accumulation of carbon input by plant production and loss through microbial decomposition. Warming may also suppress plant growth by increasing evapotranspiration [
  <a rid="pone.0215261.ref011" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215261.ref011">11</a>] and induce the soil carbon loss through enhanced Rh [
  <a rid="pone.0215261.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215261.ref012">12</a>]. Thus the carbon fluxes can be amplified by increased carbon emissions from thawing permafrost [
  <a rid="pone.0215261.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215261.ref013">13</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0215261.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215261.ref014">14</a>]. Schaphoff et al. [
  <a rid="pone.0215261.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215261.ref015">15</a>] revealed that warming contributed to the net uptake of carbon in the permafrost zone in previous decades because carbon uptake by vegetation increased at a faster rate than that released from soil. Furthermore, increasing the atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub> concentrations tends to stimulate photosynthesis and reduce water loss [
  <a rid="pone.0215261.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215261.ref016">16</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0215261.ref017" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215261.ref017">17</a>], which is likely to offset the adverse effects of climate change.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The temperature on the Tibetan Plateau increased with a linear trend of 0.2°C/decade during the past five decades [
  <a rid="pone.0215261.ref018" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215261.ref018">18</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0215261.ref019" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215261.ref019">19</a>] and is projected to continue warming in the future under different representative concentration pathways (RCPs) [
  <a rid="pone.0215261.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215261.ref020">20</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0215261.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215261.ref021">21</a>]. Although there has been several studies on the carbon cycle and climate change associated with the elevated CO
  <sub>2</sub> on the Tibetan Plateau for historical research and sensitivity analysis [
  <a rid="pone.0215261.ref002" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215261.ref002">2</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0215261.ref003" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215261.ref003">3</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0215261.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215261.ref020">20</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0215261.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215261.ref022">22</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0215261.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215261.ref023">23</a>], there is still a lack of studies on the carbon dynamic projections under different RCPs on the Plateau. Temperature has been reported as the critical determinant of carbon exchange in alpine ecosystems [
  <a rid="pone.0215261.ref024" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215261.ref024">24</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0215261.ref025" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215261.ref025">25</a>]. The warming had prolonged the alpine plant phenology [
  <a rid="pone.0215261.ref026" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215261.ref026">26</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0215261.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215261.ref028">28</a>] and promoted the vegetation productivity [
  <a rid="pone.0215261.ref003" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215261.ref003">3</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0215261.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215261.ref029">29</a>], and consequently enhanced carbon inputs into the soil, offseting the carbon release from thawing permafrost in the Tibetan Plateau [
  <a rid="pone.0215261.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215261.ref004">4</a>]. The vegetation production on Tibetan Plateau was projected to increase under future climate scenarios [
  <a rid="pone.0215261.ref007" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215261.ref007">7</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0215261.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215261.ref030">30</a>]. The results of field experiments, however, have shown some opposite responses of vegetation productivity to warming, which varied among regions [
  <a rid="pone.0215261.ref031" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215261.ref031">31</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0215261.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215261.ref033">33</a>]. Ganjurjav et al. [
  <a rid="pone.0215261.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215261.ref034">34</a>] found that the aboveground net primary production (NPP) was significantly stimulated in an alpine meadow under experimental warming, whereas it decreased in an alpine steppe due to warming-induced drought. Furthermore, there are situations that the climatic warming stimulated the ecosystem respiration more than NPP, which potentially led to loss of soil carbon in the Tibetan Plateau [
  <a rid="pone.0215261.ref018" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215261.ref018">18</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0215261.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215261.ref022">22</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0215261.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215261.ref030">30</a>]. This discrepant responses of NPP and heterotrophic respiration (Rh) to the climatic warming in the Tibetan Plateau might be quite different from that in the northern high-latitude permafrost zones [
  <a rid="pone.0215261.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215261.ref015">15</a>], where warming increased NPP more than Rh. In previous historical period modeling studies [
  <a rid="pone.0215261.ref003" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215261.ref003">3</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0215261.ref005" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215261.ref005">5</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0215261.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215261.ref035">35</a>], a net carbon sink has been estimated for the Tibetan Plateau grassland for the 20th century, albeit with variability in absolute value of 11.8 ~ 29.8 Tg C yr
  <span class="sup">-1</span>. Based on a field experiment in the Tibetan Plateau alpine meadow, Zhu et al. [
  <a rid="pone.0215261.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215261.ref036">36</a>] found that warming caused a seasonal shift in ecosystem carbon exchange but had little impact on net carbon uptake. However, the direction and magnitude of carbon fluxes responses to climate change and elevated CO
  <sub>2</sub> concentration under future climate scenarios in the Tibetan Plateau grassland remains uncertain. Thus, quantifying the influence of the future climatic change on the carbon exchange in alpine ecosystems in the Tibetan Plateau will promote our understanding of the mechanisms in the climate-carbon cycle feedbacks.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this study, we used an onsite calibrated and validated process-based model, CENTURY, to explore the responses of three important carbon cycle indicators, namely NPP, Rh and net ecosystem production (NEP), to future climate change projections on alpine grasslands of the Tibetan Plateau. The representative concentration pathways (RCP) scenarios of the climate change projections under the framework of the Coupled Model Intercomparison Project Phase 5 (CMIP5) vary in their total radiative forcing increase by 2100 [
  <a rid="pone.0215261.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215261.ref037">37</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0215261.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215261.ref038">38</a>]. Three different RCP scenarios (i.e., RCP2.6, RCP4.5, and RCP8.5) were applied in this study. The objectives of this paper are: (1) to predict the trends and differences in the ecosystem carbon cycle components in alpine grasslands under RCP scenarios during the 21st century; and (2) to differentiate the contributions of the changing climate variables (temperature and precipitation) and elevated CO
  <sub>2</sub> on the future carbon budget on the Tibetan Plateau grasslands.
 </p>
</sec>
