<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Based on simulations from 32 GCMs models and their ensemble, we examined changes in extreme high-temperature events in CA under global INDC scenarios and further compared the results with those of the 2.0 °C/1.5 °C warming targets. Our primary conclusions are as follows:
 <list list-type="simple" class="list">
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <label class="label">(1)</label>
   <p class="p">The SAT in CA will increase by approximately 2.3 °C, 3.0 °C, and 4.8 °C above the preindustrial level under the 1.5 °C, 2.0 °C, and INDC scenarios, with a higher warming rate than the global mean. Larger warming magnitudes will occur in high-latitude areas and the Pamir Mountains. The amplitudes of the PRs of extreme high temperatures will increase much more than those of the mild high temperatures.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <label class="label">(2)</label>
   <p class="p">Extreme high-temperature events will become more intense, more frequent, and longer-lasting with the enhancement of global warming. The increasing amplitude of the intensity is relatively uniform among CA, while the duration of HWs will increase more in low-altitude areas. The nighttime heat extremes will increase more than the daytime hot extremes (with respect to the frequency index and PR). Record-breaking high-temperature events will be more frequent, and the population/area fraction will linearly increase with the global mean warming.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <label class="label">(3)</label>
   <p class="p">Compared with the INDC scenario, the lower warming of the 2.0 °C/1.5 °C target scenarios will help to avoid approximately 44–61%/65–80% of the increase in extreme temperature events in terms of the intensity, frequency, and duration in CA. All the subregions would experience such a remarkable impact reduction, although the magnitudes would slightly differ.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
