<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The climatic conditions of different seasons and regions cause varying effects on the bioclimatology of different plants (Menzel et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83" class="xref">2001</xref>). For example, the higher winter temperatures at middle latitudes cause most plants to blossom and sprout earlier (Sparkes et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR119" class="xref">1997</xref>). At middle and high latitudes, the end of growth periods and the beginning of dormant periods of most plants are primarily influenced by the shorter days and temperature conditions of late summer (Heide 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" class="xref">1974</xref>; Wareing 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR130" class="xref">1956</xref>). Subsequently, the low temperature of the following winter breaks plant dormancy (Fuchigami et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" class="xref">1982</xref>; Perry 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97" class="xref">1971</xref>; Vegis 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR126" class="xref">1964</xref>). Fluctuating temperatures break plant dormancy more effectively than constant temperatures do (Campbell and Sugano 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">1975</xref>; Hänninen 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" class="xref">1990</xref>; Murray et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88" class="xref">1989</xref>). However for some plants, fluctuating and constant temperatures have the same effect (Myking 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88" class="xref">1997</xref>). Phenological variations during plant growth periods are primarily affected by accumulated temperature (Peñuelas and Filella 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96" class="xref">2001</xref>). However, selecting the initial temperature for calculating accumulated temperature has been a major difficulty in bioclimatology because it may differ substantially in plants of the same species when influenced by varying environmental factors (Heide 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" class="xref">1993</xref>; Murray et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88" class="xref">1989</xref>). This difference severely affects the precision and prediction accuracy in research regarding plant growth bioclimatology. Despite the differences, 5 °C is commonly used as the initial temperature for calculating the accumulated temperature of plants (Cannell and Smith 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">1986</xref>; Cannell et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">1985</xref>; Kellomäki et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" class="xref">1995</xref>; Murray et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88" class="xref">1989</xref>).
</p>
