<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fn-group class="fn-group">
 <fn fn-type="abbr" class="fn">
  <p class="p">Abbreviations: 1st-L ABL = first-line ambulance, 1st-L H = first-line hospital, 2nd-L ABL = second-line ambulance, 2nd-L H = second-line hospital, 3rd-L ABL = third-line ambulance, 3rd-L H = third-line hospital, app. DE
   <sub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">max</sub> = apparent maximum DE, approximate real-life situations for calculations, app. DE
   <sub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">min</sub> = apparent minimum DE, approximate real-life situations for calculations, app. TE
   <sub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">max</sub> = apparent maximum TE, approximate real-life situations for calculations, app. TE
   <sub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">min</sub> = apparent minimum TE, approximate real-life situations for calculations, D
   <sub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">CM</sub> = EMS total transportation distance in the conventional method, DE = distance efficiency, DE
   <sub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">max</sub> = maximum DE, random selection of transportation to hospitals, DE
   <sub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">min</sub> = minimum DE, random selection of transportation to hospitals, D
   <sub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">SM</sub> = EMS total transportation distance in the sequential-conveyance method, ED = emergency department, EMS = emergency medical service, GIS = geographic information system, MCI = mass-casualty incidence, MEMC = mobile emergency medical center, p = number of nonpatients, PR = patient ratio, q = number of patients, R
   <sub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">n</sub> = refuges, where subscript n indicates each individual refuge, T
   <sub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">CM</sub> = EMS total transportation time in the conventional method, TE = time efficiency, TE
   <sub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">max</sub> = maximum TE, random selection of transportation to hospitals, TE
   <sub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">min</sub> = minimum TE, random selection of transportation to hospitals, T
   <sub xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">SM</sub> = EMS total transportation time in the sequential-conveyance method, X = Xiaolin village.
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="conflict" class="fn">
  <p class="p">The authors have no funding and conflicts of interest to disclose.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn fn-type="supplementary-material" class="fn">
  <p class="p">Supplemental digital content is available for this article. Direct URL citations appear in the printed text and are provided in the HTML and PDF versions of this article on the journal's Website (
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.md-journal.com" class="ext-link" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.md-journal.com</span>).
  </p>
 </fn>
</fn-group>
