<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="pone.0218160.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
 <object-id pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0218160.g002</object-id>
 <label class="label">Fig 2</label>
 <caption class="caption">
  <title class="title">Habitat suitability predicted by the MaxEnt models for 
   <italic class="italic">G</italic>. 
   <italic class="italic">bermejoi</italic> under the RCP 2.6 scenario.
  </title>
  <p class="p">Habitat suitability map for the current climatic conditions (A), those predicted for 2050 (B) and those for 2070 (C). (D) Habitat suitability values in the current climatic conditions (R software standard box-plot), and under those predicted for 2050 and 2070, measured at the sites where this taxon is currently found. In E, F and G, we show the bioclimatic suitability values for the sites where 
   <italic class="italic">G</italic>. 
   <italic class="italic">bermejoi</italic> is currently found. To aid interpretation of these maps, a color code was used to express the different intervals of habitat suitability. (H) These box-plots show the evolution of the values for the Bio 6 variable (the minimum temperature in the coldest month) measured at the sites where 
   <italic class="italic">G</italic>. 
   <italic class="italic">bermejoi</italic> is currently found. The bioclimatic suitability was also measured at each location with gypsum soil indicated by the presence of 
   <italic class="italic">O</italic>. 
   <italic class="italic">tridentata</italic>. These values are shown for the current climatic conditions, and the conditions predicted for 2050 and 2070, in maps I, J and K, respectively. (L) These box-plots are similar to those in (H) but for the values of the Bio 14 variable (precipitation in the driest month), also measured at the locations where 
   <italic class="italic">G</italic>. 
   <italic class="italic">bermejoi</italic> is currently found.
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="pone.0218160.g002" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
