<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An Evolutionary-Cognitive Perspective on Attempts to Compensate for Unsustainable Behavior</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Problems associated with social interaction and various forms of social exchange have been particularly important to master for successful adaptation. Consequently, rules governing social exchange has shaped human cognition, heuristics, biases, and reasoning abilities (
  <a rid="B3" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3">Cosmides, 1989</a>; 
  <a rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32">Tooby and Cosmides, 1996</a>; 
  <a rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12">Hoffman et al., 1998</a>; 
  <a rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19">Kiyonari et al., 2000</a>; 
  <a rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36">Yamagishi et al., 2007</a>; 
  <a rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4">Cosmides et al., 2010</a>). One aspect that might be particularly important, for our purpose here, is the rules governing the balance between giving and receiving favors. People expect reciprocity in interpersonal relationships – when they give something, they generally expect something in return, and when they get something they feel obliged to return the favor. Lack of balance in give-and-receive transactions of a relationship makes people sad and compromises health and wellbeing (
  <a rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1">Buunk and Schaufeli, 1999</a>). Neglecting the balance in a relationship by receiving more than one gives can lead to shame and guilt, and giving more than one receives can lead to anger. However, the balance can be restored when the one in debt do what is necessary to compensate for past transgressions (
  <a rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35">Xu et al., 2011</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Because of the importance of social exchange during human evolution, natural selection has shaped human cognition to compute and seek balance in social exchange efficiently. Specifically, natural selection has made this kind of moral accounting important, and formed a balancing heuristic that simplifies cognition concerning interpersonal cooperation by calculating the balance in social transactions. This balancing heuristic still influences the way people think today. For example, people often take action to maintain balance between “good” and “bad” deeds – actions that can be observed in human moral decision-making (
  <a rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27">Sachdeva et al., 2009</a>). Morally righteous and unrighteous decisions appear to be mentally accounted for as if they balance each other out. For example, prior good deeds can “license” latter choices of a more self-indulgent character (
  <a rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17">Khan and Dhar, 2006</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Moral accounting and balance seeking behavior not only apply to social relationships, they seem to apply to environmental issues as well. Some people are more likely to cheat and steal after purchasing “eco-friendly” products (
  <a rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24">Mazar and Zhong, 2010</a>), probably because they feel licensed to do so since they morally account the “eco-friendly” choice as a “good” deed. Moral licensing has also been observed in the context of cooperation for the good of the environment (
  <a rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27">Sachdeva et al., 2009</a>). When people are reminded of deeds they have done that they know were harmful to the environment, they might be left with a feeling of “eco-guilt” (
  <a rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23">Mallett, 2012</a>). People who experience eco-guilt seek pro-environmental actions to compensate for this guilt and restore balance. In their search for such a balance, people are inclined to believe in “quick-fixes,” because they want to re-establish the moral balance and escape the guilt as quickly and easily as possible. In the same way that cognitive dissonance may make people change their attitudes to reduce inconsistencies between attitudes and behavior, people may also change their evaluation of past environmentally burdening behaviors and future environmentally friendly behaviors to restore the balance in their relationship with the environment. For instance, people are more likely to sign a petition addressing environmental issues after viewing evidence of human-caused environmental damage (
  <a rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26">Rees et al., 2015</a>). Hence, the balancing heuristic of the moral accounting seems to have been generalized to human-climate interactions although such interactions are evolutionary novel.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In social exchange, allowing give-and-take transactions to balance each other out works well to maintain well-functioning cooperation. However, the same balancing rule is not appropriate to apply to “environmentally friendly” and “harmful” behavior. When people experience a negative imbalance from having done something harmful to the environment, they may actively seek an opportunity to do something good for the environment to restore the balance. However, the environment is a complex system of processes that does not respond like a person in a reciprocal relationship. Also, and foremost, environmentally harmful behavior can neither be compensated for, restored nor undone. While the tension in a relationship, caused by a harmful action to another person, can be restored by compensation without leaving permanent changes in either person, harmful actions on the environment have permanent consequences. Flying adds to an individual’s total environmental burden, no matter how many meat free Mondays that individual has. Still, “compensatory green beliefs” are widespread in the general population (
  <a rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16">Kaklamanou et al., 2015</a>). The balancing heuristic may make people purchase more “eco-labeled” food in order to do something good for the environment, but the best thing for the environment would of course be to consume less overall. Consuming more of something is never the best way to reduce one’s own environmental impact, even if the produce is marketed as “environmentally friendly.” In the same spirit, attempts to cancel the guilt from “harmful” deeds, by avoiding taking too hot showers, or driving vehicles that run on “sustainable fuel” might make people feel good about themselves. However, the behavior can cause even more harm to the environment, if showers instead go on for longer and people take the car to work more often (cf. rebound effects; 
  <a rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2">Chitnis et al., 2013</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The balancing heuristic is not only applied when people reason about their own behavior and choices – it also generalizes to items and objects. When so-called “environmentally friendly” items are added to a set of “conventional” items, people believe the environmental impact of the whole set is reduced. For instance, people intuitively think the environmental burden of a hamburger and an “organic” apple in combination is lower than the environmental burden of the hamburger alone (
  <a rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10">Gorissen and Weijters, 2016</a>). People mentally account for the “environmentally friendly” and the more “harmful” objects as if the objects balance each other out rather than sum up together (
  <a rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13">Holmgren et al., 2018a</a>,
  <a rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14">b</a>). This averaging principle leads to quantity insensitivity with regard to the amount of “environmentally friendly” objects in the set. For example, people tend to think that the environmental burden of a car pool remains the same when hybrid cars are added to the pool, as if numbers do not matter as long as the cars are seemingly friendly to the environment (
  <a rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18">Kim and Schuldt, 2018</a>). One interpretation of this is that the balancing heuristic makes people think that the climate friendlier objects compensate for the more harmful ones, in the same manner as it does for evaluations of people’s own deeds.
 </p>
</sec>
