<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec013" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Calibration of the model</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To begin the calibration process, the model was initially run with only the chlorophyll 
  <span class="italic">a</span> time series forcing primary producer groups. In this case, the model failed to recreate the documented trends of biomass for all species for which time series were available, except for 
  <span class="italic">C</span>. 
  <span class="italic">gunnari</span>. Forcing functions were then applied to specific predator-prey interactions to influence the prey’s vulnerability to predation, the predator’s search rate, or the size of the area where prey are vunerable to predation (i.e., the foraging arena). This type of forcing was applied in Ecosim without the use of response curves. Choices of which time series were applied as forcing functions to each predator-prey interaction were influenced by hunting strategies documented in the diet studies used to build the diet matrix. For example, gentoo penguins forage in near shore environments [
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref067" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref067">67</a>] and have been increasing in abundance as seaice has declined [
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref017" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref017">17</a>]. This suggests that gentoo penguins are more successful foragers in open water conditions. Thus we used the open water environmental driver to force predator-prey interactions between gentoo penguins and on-shelf fish and krill. This application made those prey items more vulnerable to gentoo predation where open water was more prevalent.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Model fit was measured by sums of the squared differences (SS) between simulation results and biomass time series for the eight monitored species, where a smaller SS indicates a better fit. If applying a forcing function to a specific predator prey interaction did not improve the fit, or otherwise help the model recreate trends documented in the time series, that function was no longer applied to that foraging interaction. To improve model fit for large krill and 
  <span class="italic">G</span>. 
  <span class="italic">gibberifrons</span>, we used our sea-ice index to directly drive the biomasses of both species. We evaluated two curves for each species and retained the curve that resulted in the lowest total sum of squares. Once the model was able to recreate the trends of biomass as documented in the time-series data, and each group-specifc SS had been minimized, the model was considered calibrated.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used the Monte Carlo (MC) routine provided within EwE [
  <a rid="pone.0214814.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0214814.ref020">20</a>] to assess model sensitivity. The MC routine randomly selects initial values of the input parameters (Biomass, P/B, and EE) for all model groups using a coefficient of variation (C.V.) of 0.1 and computes the total sum of squares using these new input values. The degree of difference in the sum of squares between the user-specified model, and randomly selected runs is used to infer sensitivity to small changes in input parameters. We ran 200 MC simulation trials to assess sensitivity.
 </p>
</sec>
