<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Early studies suggested that warmer conditions are drivers of mosquito abundance [
 <xref rid="pone.0163863.ref043" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0163863.ref045" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>]; however, other studies suggested a delay in the start of the breeding season of 
 <italic class="italic">Cx</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">quinquefasciatus</italic> in sites presenting a dry and hot spring and summer, but extensions in the season with fall rains and higher temperatures [
 <xref rid="pone.0163863.ref046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>]. Our prediction suggested suitability of occurrence of 
 <italic class="italic">Cx</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">quinquefasciatus</italic> in regions with lower temperatures than in tropical and subtropical regions. Generally, 
 <italic class="italic">Cx</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">quinquefasciatus</italic> is likely to experience decreased survival as a result of elevated temperatures [
 <xref rid="pone.0163863.ref047" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>]. A previous study showed a tripling in rates of development, fecundity, and feeding with higher temperature [
 <xref rid="pone.0163863.ref047" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>]. Although climate change likely will affect the biology of 
 <italic class="italic">Cx</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">quinquefasciatus</italic> directly, distributional changes in response to elevated temperatures will likely be manifested. Climate change can thus trigger changes in the distributional patterns of 
 <italic class="italic">Cx</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">quinquefasciatus</italic>, but these changes will be strongly dependent on the location and timing of climate changes [
 <xref rid="pone.0163863.ref046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>]. Other environmental effects are on survival, reproductive rate, and vectorial capacity to transmit pathogens; for example, higher temperatures increase pathogen proliferation, and therefore vector competence [
 <xref rid="pone.0163863.ref027" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0163863.ref048" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0163863.ref049" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>].
</p>
