<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We modeled landscape dynamics using probabilistic state-and-transition simulation models (STSMs, [
 <xref rid="pone.0209490.ref027" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>]) previously developed through the Integrated Landscape Assessment Project [
 <xref rid="pone.0209490.ref050" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>]. With STSMs, a continuum of conditions is typically grouped into discrete classes known as states. Transitions, representing agents of change in a STSM, link modeled states to each other. An individual state can have multiple transitions, where each transition can result in a different condition, or end state (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0209490.g002" class="xref">Fig 2</xref>). Following [
 <xref rid="pone.0209490.ref029" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0209490.ref050" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>], we represented current forest structure and species information in our STSMS using a consistent ruleset based on dominant tree cover species, tree diameter, percent canopy cover, and canopy layers. Post-disturbance conditions were also included, representing surviving live trees of specific diameter ranges in addition to standing snags and downed wood. The number of states within our STSMs varied from seven to ~40 depending on vegetation type (models can be accessed through DRYAD). States were connected through transitions representing natural disturbances or succession. Primary stand-replacing disturbances in the model were episodic wind events and wildfire. Wind events were restricted to low and mid-elevation forests near the coast and occurred every 35 years, on average, based on the frequency of past events since the 1880s [
 <xref rid="pone.0209490.ref008" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. We developed wildfire estimates of fire rotations from the literature, assuming a predominantly stand-replacing fire regime in all forest zones other than the Douglas-fir zone, which we characterized as a mixed-severity fire regime [
 <xref rid="pone.0209490.ref008" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0209490.ref035" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>].
</p>
