<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">One of the first published approaches tackling GCM model selection with formal criteria stems from Smith and Hulme (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" class="xref">1998</xref>). They propose several criteria such as vintage (considering the latest generation of climate simulations only), resolution (the higher the resolution, the better), validity (model performance in the past), and representativeness (picking simulations from the high and low end of the range of climate change signals of temperature and precipitation to obtain a representative sub-sample). This method has been adopted by the IPCC guidelines for climate scenarios (IPCC-TGICA 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">2007</xref>). Such a selection of GCMs has been applied by e.g. Murdock and Spittlehouse (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">2011</xref>) focusing on the region of British Columbia by analyzing the models based on the spread of change in temperature and precipitation. A discussion of sub-selecting climate simulations for hydrology studies has been published by Salathe et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">2007</xref>). They propose sampling driving climate simulations by considering the projected model spread for hydrology-relevant parameters (temperature and precipitation change) to find groups of similar simulations and selecting representative climate models. A generalization to a multivariate setup has recently been presented by Cannon (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">2015</xref>). His proposed method maximizes model diversity by selecting the most extreme simulations. All those studies have a non-probability sampling scheme in common: instead of assigning probabilities to the simulations and sampling them randomly, the selection is based on qualitative characteristics which are relevant for the researcher (Mays and Pope 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">1995</xref>). The aim is to maximize diversity of these characteristics.
</p>
