<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec021" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Concluding remarks</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study was conducted with the objective of capturing internal dynamic behaviors which influence the long-term resilience of civil infrastructure systems in the presence of external stressors. The proposed framework characterizes the object of study (a water distribution network) as a complex system and offers a multi-agent simulation (MAS) model to quantify its components, dynamic processes, and external stressors acting on it. The output of the model depicts the performance regime of the system over an extended horizon which enables the detection of regime shifts to evaluate the long-term resilience.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Different performance regimes were observed in response to changes in the renewal decision-making process of the administrative agency, which is an expected outcome owing to the fact that availability of funding is a function of revenue, which in turn depends on the demand generated by the user population. The model also identified tipping points in the performance regime when specific renewal strategy targets were adopted by the administrative agency. For instance, when a renewal strategy of average condition controlling at 45 was adopted in conjunction with a capital improvement fund of $15 Million, the infrastructure satisfied the target by exhibiting long-term performance. Any decrease to the fund however, caused a regime shift if the agency continued to maintain the same strategy target. These results show that the performance regime of an infrastructure system is shaped by its internal dynamics, which reinforces the premise that changes in internal dynamics would lead to regime shifts in long-term behavior of the system. The model also adequately captured the long-term response of infrastructure when subjected to external stressors. For instance, a positive correlation between decline in user population and the long-term service reliability of the infrastructure was observed. The model showed that a price hike of 4% annually would maintain the service reliability of the case study water distribution infrastructure system in a stable state, despite changes to its user population.</p>
</sec>
