<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec019" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Internal dynamics and performance regime</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The simulation model was used to examine how infrastructure dynamics shape performance regimes. To this end, the effect of renewal strategies (as an element affecting infrastructure dynamics) on the performance regime of the network was evaluated. Two renewal strategies (i.e., condition and break control) were considered. For each renewal strategy, different required performance targets and capital improvement funding levels were assessed. In total, 25 scenarios were simulated, where each scenario represents a unique state of infrastructure dynamics in the case study. In this analysis, resilience is determined based on detection of regime shifts in the stable state of performance in the system. Different performance measures could be used for assessing possible regime shifts. In this set of analysis, the network average condition was selected among the network performance measures for two reasons: first, the network average condition collectively represents the physical state of the pipes in the network; second, most of the network performance measures such as leakage, breakage, and service reliability, either directly or indirectly, are affected by the network average condition. Accordingly, resilience of the system is analyzed based on regime shifts in the long-term average condition of the network.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0207674.g008" href="#pone.0207674.g008">Fig 8</a> shows network average conditions plotted over a 100-year horizon under 1% population growth rate for all the scenarios. In 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0207674.g008" href="#pone.0207674.g008">Fig 8</a>, each column represents a certain renewal strategy and each row represents a certain level of capital improvement fund (
  <span class="italic">CIF</span>). As can see in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0207674.g008" href="#pone.0207674.g008">Fig 8</a>, the state of infrastructure dynamics in each scenario leads to a certain regime in the performance of the network. For example, under scenarios A1-A4, the behavior (regime) of the network performance follows a similar trend; however, under scenario A5, the dynamics of the system changes (because of change in renewal strategy target), and hence the infrastructure performance changes.
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0207674.g008" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0207674.g008</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 8</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Modeling regimes of network average condition under various scenarios.</div>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0207674.g008" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This change in the performance regime of infrastructure is a significant phenomenon and can be characterized as a critical point or tipping point. Critical or tipping points represent values related to the internal dynamics of infrastructure or external stressor, in which a small change in the parameter value leads to a significant change in the performance of infrastructure. For example, 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0207674.g008" href="#pone.0207674.g008">Fig 8</a> shows that under a fix capital improvement funding (e.g., $20 Million), a change in the renewal strategy from condition control to break control will lead to a shift in the performance regime of the network (compare scenarios C1-C3 with C4-C5). Under each renewal strategy, there is a certain value of capital improvement funding that leads the infrastructure system to a resilient behavior (i.e., the network meets the desired target with a stable regime). This value, accordingly, is specified as a tipping or critical point. For instance, under the renewal strategies of controlling average condition at 40, 45, and 50, any capital improvement funding below $25 million, $20 million, and $15 million, respectively, wouldn’t lead the system to a resilient behavior (compare D1 with C1, C2 with B2, and B3 with A3). These results show that internal dynamics shape the performance regime of infrastructure and how the changes in these internal dynamics affect the long-term performance regimes and cause the regime shifts.
 </p>
</sec>
