<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec017" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Simulation experiments</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">After using different internal verification and external validation techniques to ensure the model quality, the simulation model was used for building various experiments based on all possible scenarios. Various simulation experiments were conducted through the change of model input parameter values and logics in the computational model. The possible scenarios were established based on different combinations of the input variables (parameters) in the model, shown in 
  <a rid="pone.0207674.t001" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0207674.t001">Table 1</a>. The combinations of these scenarios reflect changes in population growth rate, capital improvement fund level, water price hike, renewal strategy, and strategy target. Since network break frequency is modeled as a stochastic Poisson process, one thousand runs of Monte-Carlo experiments were conducted to determine the mean value of the model output parameters (e.g., service reliability) under each specific scenario.
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0207674.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0207674.t001</span>
  <span class="label">Table 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Model input variables.</div>
  </div>
  <div class="alternatives">
   <div id="pone.0207674.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0207674.t001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <colgroup span="1">
     <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
     <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
    </colgroup>
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Input Variable</th>
      <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable Value(s)</th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Base Population</td>
      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">113,000</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number of Households</td>
      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60,000</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Population Change Rate (%)</td>
      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">-2, -1.5, -1, -0.5, 0, 0.5, 1, 1.5, 2</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pipeline Renewal Strategy</td>
      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1. Regular Renewal
       <span class="break"/>2. Controlling Network Average Condition at 40, 45, and 50
       <span class="break"/>3. Controlling Average Break Frequency at 20, and 25
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Initial Water Price ($/gallon)</td>
      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Water Price Hike Rate (%)</td>
      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0, 4, 8</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Capital Improvement Fund ($ Million)</td>
      <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0, 10, 15, 20, 25, 30</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
  </div>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Two sets of simulation experiments were conducted to evaluate the long-term resilience of the water distribution infrastructure system. First, the impacts of decision and physical infrastructure attributes were examined in order to explore the significant attributes and their critical threshold value that could lead to the occurrence of tipping point behaviors. To this end, time-series results related to the network average condition were visualized to investigate the existence of non-linear increase or decline trends in the simulated long-term performance measure. Accordingly, the threshold values related to decision and infrastructure attributes (e.g., level of capital improvement funding and desired network average condition), at which the steady state of infrastructure performance is disrupted were examined as tipping points. The results related to regime shifts and tipping points were used to evaluate the long-term resilience of the case study network under different adaptation strategy scenarios (i.e., funding allocation and renewal strategies). Second, the impacts of population changes and funding fluctuations on the network performance parameters and its ultimate effects on network service reliability over the analysis period (i.e., 100 years) were investigated. To this end, the mean values of the infrastructure service reliability were plotted against different values of population change rate and capital improvement funding level to visually examine the occurrence of shifts in the service reliability performance of the infrastructure system. Accordingly, the occurrence of regime shifts and tipping points were detected and used to analyze the sensitivity of long-term infrastructure system performance to external stressors.</p>
</sec>
