<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec004" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">External stressors</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">External stressors can be chronic or acute in nature. Chronic stressors are gradual, low impact-high probability events that are caused by changes in the internal feedback processes and the external environment. Acute stressors are abrupt, high impact-low probability events that are mainly caused by extreme events. Both chronic (e.g. accelerated erosion due to climate change) and acute stressors (e.g. flooding) affect the dynamics of the infrastructure and as a consequence, its resilience. For instance, climate change (chronic stressor) is a major driver of changes in the socio-environmental conditions surrounding civil infrastructure [
  <a rid="pone.0207674.ref025" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207674.ref025">25</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0207674.ref026" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207674.ref026">26</a>]. Climate change impacts the sustainability and resilience of civil infrastructure in various ways such as (i) changes in temperature and precipitation which affect the erosion of the networks; (ii) population displacement which affects the demand on the networks; (iii) changes in the priorities of agencies which affects allocation of resources; and (iv) increased frequency and magnitude of extreme events (e.g. floods), leading to greater exposure of the networks to risks [
  <a rid="pone.0207674.ref027" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207674.ref027">27</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0207674.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207674.ref028">28</a>]. Hence, changes in decision and physical infrastructure attributes and relationship would change the sensitivity of civil infrastructure system to external stressors. The Threshold values of these attributes at which the sensitivity of infrastructure system to stressors varies can be examined as tipping points. Tipping points occur in complex systems when “a small smooth change made to the parameter values of a system causes a sudden qualitative or topological change in its behavior”. The parameter value at which state transition occurs is referred to as the tipping point or threshold point. Understanding tipping points is essential in describing long-term resilience in complex systems. In the context of civil infrastructure system resilience, regime shifts describe the extent to which the infrastructure system performance regime is sensitive to changes in external stressors magnitudes (e.g., population growth rate). On the other hand, tipping points, explain the critical values related to decision and physical infrastructure attributes (e.g., funding level and network age) that drastically increase or decrease the infrastructure system sensitivity to a certain scenario and stressor magnitude.
 </p>
</sec>
