<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec006" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Performance regime shifts</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The performance regime of infrastructure is defined as the steady state related to the system’s performance, which is maintained by internal dynamics associated with the interactions between human actors and physical infrastructure affected by different stressors. A regime is a characteristic behavior of a system which is maintained by mutually reinforced processes or internal dynamics [
  <a rid="pone.0207674.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207674.ref023">23</a>]. A change of regime (regime shift) occurs when a change in an internal process (dynamics) or external disturbance triggers a completely different system performance behavior [
  <a rid="pone.0207674.ref019" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207674.ref019">19</a>]. Regime shifts are large, abrupt, persistent changes in the performance behavior of a system [
  <a rid="pone.0207674.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207674.ref030">30</a>]. The regime shifts occur at tipping points (critical points), where an external stressor interrupts the steady state of the system performance. Evaluation of performance regime shifts is critical for long-term decision-making. Due to significant physical and institutional inertia that is prevalent in civil infrastructure, undesirable performance regime shifts are very difficult to reverse. Identification and adoption of the critical points would facilitate early detection of regime shifts, prior to their occurrence. The occurrence of shifts in the performance regime of an infrastructure system can be detected using different methods such as (i) plotting mean and standard deviation values of the system performance parameters against socio-environmental parameters (e.g. population change, temperature change, and level of funding); and (ii) using time-series data related to different system performance measures in non-parametric methods. To this end, a visual investigation of system performance parameter values under different scenarios can be conducted to identify the non-linear trends and long-term regime shifts.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the next step of this study, a dynamic (time-dependent) multi-agent simulation model was created and validated to capture and explain the complex dynamics of stressor-human-infrastructure nexus. The elements of the multi-agent model are explained in the following section.</p>
</sec>
