<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec009" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Physical network degradation</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The physical condition of an infrastructure asset denotes its structural capacity and ability to withstand different types of stressors. On the other hand, the functionality of infrastructure indicates its ability to serve its intended function at the desired level of service. The approach to modeling the mechanisms of physical degradation varies for different infrastructure (e.g., roadways vs. water systems) [
  <a rid="pone.0207674.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207674.ref039">39</a>]. However, the modeling of infrastructure degradation essentially involves identifying indicators of physical and functional conditions of an asset and then integrating them into a unified performance measure [
  <a rid="pone.0207674.ref040" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207674.ref040">40</a>]. A unified performance measure quantifies the state of an infrastructure asset at any given time based on variables such as design characteristics of the asset, asset’s age, ambient climate, and service load of the asset in that period [
  <a rid="pone.0207674.ref040" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207674.ref040">40</a>]. Typical physical attributes of a water distribution network are pipeline age, materials used, length of pipes, fluid pressure and flow rate. The deterioration of physical assets in a network decreases the reliability of the infrastructure and affects the system as a whole in terms of maintenance and operation costs, rehabilitation needs and exposure of actors in the system to risks. Therefore, a complex system model of water distribution infrastructure needs to account for degradation and the effect that it has on service life, condition states, future maintenance and rehabilitation expenses. The physical degradation process of pipework is not clearly understood, with published literature citing several factors such as age, material and network pressure as driving mechanisms, meaning, different functions may be implemented to capture the process [
  <a rid="pone.0207674.ref041" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207674.ref041">41</a>]. However, several deterioration model studies have correlated age with condition thereby establishing that the process is age-dependent [
  <a rid="pone.0207674.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207674.ref042">42</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From a system perspective, age-based deterioration can be used as a criterion to sort various sections (lengths) of piping in the network into discrete age groups based on pre-defined age ranges. As a consequence, aging sections would move from one age group to the next during the process of deterioration. Thus, modeling degradation as a dynamic process would capture long-term transformation effects in the network which would lend greater accuracy to the assessment of the system’s resilience.</p>
</sec>
