<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The pathway from ecosystems, their biophysical structure, processes and functions to their benefit and value to human society, is illustrated by the ES cascade model, which portrays ES as emerging from the functional and structural properties of the ecosystem (
 <xref rid="B98" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Potschin and Haines-Young, 2011</xref>). In the Common International Classification of ES (CICES), services are classified into provisioning, regulating and maintenance, and cultural services (
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Haines-Young and Potschin, 2018</xref>). Several studies have discussed mapping of ES provision potential at different scales (
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Burkhard et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B134" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Vihervaara et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Maes et al., 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Albert et al., 2016a</xref>). The European Commission seeks to improve the basis for implementing the EU Biodiversity Strategy for 2020 (
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">European Commission, 2011</xref>) by encouraging national ES assessments of the member states of EU through its flagship project MAES (
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">European Commission, 2018</xref>). National accounting of natural capital needs information from national ES accounts and ongoing development of natural-capital accounts also supports national ES assessments (
 <xref rid="B113" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Schröter et al., 2016</xref>). 
 <xref rid="B111" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Saastamoinen et al. (2014)</xref> applied the CICES hierarchy on the boreal forest ES in Finland, reporting their results in a conceptual and historical context. 
 <xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Mononen et al. (2016)</xref> developed a framework of ES indicators for Finland that complies with both national circumstances and international typologies such as the cascade model (
 <xref rid="B98" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Potschin and Haines-Young, 2011</xref>) and the CICES framework (
 <xref rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Haines-Young and Potschin, 2018</xref>). ES are increasingly used to inform policies, and frameworks including ES analysis for decision support are becoming available (
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Albert et al., 2016b</xref>). Potentially highly promising avenues for underpinning resource allocation decisions are based on detailed place-based analyses of supply and demand of ES (e.g., 
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kopperoinen et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B133" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Vauhkonen and Ruotsalainen, 2017</xref>). On the other hand, broad, unspecified ES may be more easily adopted by policy actors, according to 
 <xref rid="B130" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Van Oudenhoven et al. (2018)</xref>.
</p>
