<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The question now arises as to why the growth of both sexes of 
 <italic class="italic">A. butcheri</italic> in each of four estuaries declined between periods but did not likewise occur with body condition in one of those estuaries, that is, Wellstead Estuary. As the point for the mass and age at 250 mm for both the females and males in Wellstead Estuary in 1993–96 lies well below the regression line relating mass and age of each sex at 250 mm across estuaries and periods, the body condition of 
 <italic class="italic">A. butcheri</italic> in that estuary was atypically low in 1993–96. It therefore appears pertinent that, due to its isolation from the sea and limited freshwater input, Wellstead Estuary became markedly hypersaline for an interval in that period and that 
 <italic class="italic">A. butcheri</italic> becomes osmotically stressed when salinities reach 60 (Hoeksema, Chuwen, &amp; Potter, 
 <xref rid="ece34236-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>; Partridge &amp; Jenkins, 
 <xref rid="ece34236-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2002</xref>; Young &amp; Potter, 
 <xref rid="ece34236-bib-0085" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2002</xref>). While relatively transient, but extreme, environmental changes may, therefore, have deleteriously affected body condition on a temporary basis, they would have had far less influence on overall growth, as growth curves are calculated using lengths at age, which, particularly in older fish, represent a cumulative effect over a protracted time scale. It is thus particularly pertinent that the 
 <italic class="italic">A. butcheri</italic> caught in the Wellstead Estuary in 1993–96 were overwhelmingly dominated by the 1991–1993 year classes and that these years corresponded to those when freshwater discharge was typically greatest. This would account for the growth of both sexes in the Wellstead Estuary declining between 1993–96 and 2013–15 as the environment deteriorated and thus parallel the trends in other estuaries as the extent of hypoxia likewise increased.
</p>
