<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">While rising temperatures per se improve life conditions for trees at high elevations, there are aspects of climate change that may amplify or dampen temperature effects on forest dynamics and create feedback effects. Changes in precipitation and cloud cover can alter water availability (Lloyd &amp; Fastie, 
 <xref rid="ece33290-bib-0065" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2002</xref>), pathogen infection rates (Barbeito, Brücker, Rixen, &amp; Bebi, 
 <xref rid="ece33290-bib-0005" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>), and incoming radiation (Grace, Berninger, &amp; Nagy, 
 <xref rid="ece33290-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2002</xref>). Due to the inverse relationship between tree lifespan and growth rate (Bigler &amp; Veblen, 
 <xref rid="ece33290-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>; Di Filippo, Biondi, Maugeri, Schirone, &amp; Piovesan, 
 <xref rid="ece33290-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>), improved growing conditions may enhance forest turnover (Bugmann &amp; Bigler, 
 <xref rid="ece33290-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>; Stephenson &amp; Van Mantgem, 
 <xref rid="ece33290-bib-0086" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2005</xref>). Finally, changing stand density modifies canopy cover, thereby affecting tree‐to‐tree competition and root zone temperatures, which feed back to tree growth rates (Barbeito, Dawes, Rixen, Senn, &amp; Bebi, 
 <xref rid="ece33290-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>; Malanson et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33290-bib-0069" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>; Wang et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33290-bib-0094" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). The interactions of these processes and the potential feedback effects make it challenging to predict tree population dynamics at the treeline ecotone in a changing climate, which in turn are expected to also have consequences for trees at lower elevations (e.g., Holtmeier &amp; Broll, 
 <xref rid="ece33290-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2005</xref>; Seidl, Schelhaas, Lindner, &amp; Lexer, 
 <xref rid="ece33290-bib-0084" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>). Yet, knowledge about the future development of tree population dynamics may be inferred from past dynamics at the treeline and their temporal variability with respect to changing climatic conditions.
</p>
