<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">A distinguished feature of many tree‐ring chronologies—not only in the Alps but worldwide—is accelerated growth, often starting around the year 1950 (Kipfmueller &amp; Salzer, 
 <xref rid="ece33290-bib-0056" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>). While early studies attributed this increase to CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> fertilization (e.g., La Marche, Graybill, Fritts, &amp; Rose, 
 <xref rid="ece33290-bib-0060" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1984</xref>; Nicolussi, Bortenschlager, &amp; Körner, 
 <xref rid="ece33290-bib-0075" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1995</xref>), more recent work has questioned this hypothesis (Handa, Körner, &amp; Hättenschwiler, 
 <xref rid="ece33290-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>). Lately, positive trends in growth rates are mostly ascribed to a direct climatic cause, especially rising temperatures and the extending growing season (Graumlich, 
 <xref rid="ece33290-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1991</xref>; Kipfmueller &amp; Salzer, 
 <xref rid="ece33290-bib-0056" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>; Motta &amp; Nola, 
 <xref rid="ece33290-bib-0073" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2001</xref>; Salzer et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33290-bib-0083" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>). Although tree‐ring data are often available as long time series, which renders them an ideal measure for multi‐decadal to centennial growth trend analyses, isolating the low‐frequency variability caused by abiotic influencing factors remains challenging. This variability is often confounded with the trees' age‐related trend, and the choice of detrending method for disentangling abiotic influences and age effects can greatly bias the results (Peters, Groenendijk, Vlam, &amp; Zuidema, 
 <xref rid="ece33290-bib-0078" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). Furthermore, the sampling design may induce biases to the data that can void results on growth trends (Bowman, Brienen, Gloor, Phillips, &amp; Prior, 
 <xref rid="ece33290-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Nehrbass‐Ahles et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33290-bib-0074" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). Thus, it is advisable to thoroughly design dendroecological sampling and carefully choose the detrending method when attempting to analyze the long‐term effects of increasing temperatures on growth rates of treeline trees and identify feedback effects.
</p>
