<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par7">Instead of considering a collection of rational agents engaging in one-shot Public Goods Games
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>
 </sup>, here we adopt an evolutionary description of the behavioral dynamics
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>
 </sup>, in which individuals tend to copy those appearing to be more successful. Success (or fitness) of individuals is here associated with their average payoff. All individuals are equally likely to interact with each other, causing all cooperators and defectors to be equivalent, on average, and only distinguishable by the strategy they adopt. Therefore, and considering that only two strategies are available, the number of cooperators is sufficient to describe any configuration of the population. The number of individuals adopting a given strategy (either 
 <bold>
  <italic>C</italic>
 </bold> or 
 <bold>
  <italic>D</italic>
 </bold>) evolves in time according to a stochastic birth–death process
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>
 </sup>, which describes the time evolution of the social learning dynamics (with exploration): At each time-step each individual (
 <italic>X</italic>, with fitness 
 <italic>f</italic>
 <sub>X</sub>) is given the opportunity to change strategy; with probability 
 <italic>μ</italic>, 
 <italic>X</italic> randomly explores the strategy space
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>
 </sup> (a process similar to mutations in a biological context that precludes the existence of absorbing states). With probability (1-
 <italic>μ</italic>), 
 <italic>X</italic> may adopt the strategy of a randomly selected individual (
 <italic>Y</italic>, with fitness 
 <italic>f</italic>
 <sub>Y</sub>), with a probability that increases with the fitness difference (
 <italic>f</italic>
 <sub>Y</sub>
 <italic>–f</italic>
 <sub>X</sub>)
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>
 </sup>. This renders the stationary distribution (see Methods) an extremely useful tool to rank the most visited states given the ensuing evolutionary dynamics of the population. Indeed, the stationary distribution provides the prevalence of each of the population’s possible configuration, in terms of the number of 
 <bold>
  <italic>C</italic>
 </bold>s (
 <italic>k</italic>) and 
 <bold>
  <italic>D</italic>
 </bold>s (
 <italic>Z-k)</italic>. Combined with the probability of success characterizing each configuration, the stationary distribution can be used to compute the overall success probability of a given population – the average group achievement, 
 <italic>η</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>G</italic>
 </sub>. This value represents the average fraction of groups that will overcome the 
 <bold>CRD</bold>, successfully preserving the public good.
</p>
