<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>This work estimated the responses of watershed hydrological and sedimental processes to future climate change in two typical watersheds in the Chinese Loess Plateau with different dominant land use covers of woodland and cultivated field, respectively. The following three main conclusions can be drawn from the study: 
 <list list-type="simple">
  <list-item>
   <label>(1)</label>
   <p>There was a hotter and wetter trend of climate change in the study area. The amount of streamflow in CGM would increase firstly and then decrease, with the peak level appearing in the 2050s under the scenario of RCP 4.5. The changes in streamflow in WW were generally negative due to intense evapotranspiration in hot weather conditions, which could offset the increased precipitation. The runoff in both CGM and WW would increase in the 2050s, which is conducive to sediment delivery.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <label>(2)</label>
   <p>There were increasing trends of erosion and sediment yields in both CGM and WW under all climate change scenarios. The woodland represented greater resistance stability than cultivated field, with a lesser increment in sediment in hotter and wetter weather conditions. The sediment yields in both CGM and WW would reach their peak in the 2050s in the near future, indicating urgent demands for sediment control.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <label>(3)</label>
   <p>There is great demand for effective management measures to address the impacts of future climate change on sediment yields. The strategy of increasing woodland areas is one of the most effective approaches, such as through policies of afforestation and returning farmland to forests. Without essential land use conversion, various soil conservation measures should be implemented in cultivated land to reduce erosion yields, including conservation tillage, cover crops, crop rotations, contour farming and terraces, etc. In addition, a series of installations that could block the delivery of sediment from erosion should be constructed, such as vegetable buffers, man-made drainage courses and wetlands.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <label>(4)</label>
   <p>The approach of integrated multi-model applications used in this study showed great ability to quantitatively estimate the responses of hydrological and sedimental processes to future climate change in the Yellow River Basin and may also be applicable in other areas with similar conditions.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
