<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par21" class="p">We showed that, as predictable, biometric (allometric) parameters, such as tree height, d.b.h. and crown width decrease with the altitude, with significant differences between trees in the dense treeline (at about 2,150 m a.s.l.) and those growing at higher elevation (up to 2,300 m a.s.l.). These differences, however, could be due not only to an upward shift of the new saplings but also to a differential growth trend related to altitudinal effects
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" class="xref">50</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" class="xref">51</xref>
 </sup>. In fact, trees living at the limits of the treeline may show a reduced growth when subject to harder climatic conditions then their physiological limits (i.e. lower temperatures, frozen soil, stronger wind, etc.)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" class="xref">52</xref>
 </sup>. To test if a variation in the tree growth trends and an upward shift of the treeline ecotone might be caused by increasing local and global temperatures, we further analyzed dendrochronological samples collected along some altitudinal transects. From an analysis of the complete dendrochronological time series from 1902 to 2017, we found a slight decrease in the general growth trend and relevant growth peaks for many years, all dated before 1968, when the mean annual temperature was always below the identified −4.3 °C threshold. In the last 50 years, trees did not show any sign of increased growth compared to the average trend for the century. This could be due to the fact that high-mountain trees are quite sensitive to low temperatures and grow more under a certain threshold (−4.3 °C in our study-site)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" class="xref">53</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" class="xref">55</xref>
 </sup>. In fact, comparing the available mean annual temperature observations from 1956 to 2009 with our dendrochronological time series, we detected that - in this time frame - the highest growth peaks (in 1952–1956, 1961–1962 and 1968) correspond (with a few years of lag) to the lowest temperature for the period. However, after 1968 (i.e. in the last 50 years except for 1983–1988, when the temperature dropped for a while and the tree growth temporarily increased), the temperatures were often above a −4.3 °C threshold, and the tree growth was constant (without any sudden growth peak) and slightly decreasing. The fact that the precipitation trend shows no change for the whole region in the last 50 years
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" class="xref">31</xref>
 </sup> gives more weight to temperature importance and to its low extremes.
</p>
