<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par25" class="p">In general, the rapid upward treeline shift that we detected combined with the reduced tree growth, may radically change the composition and landscape of the montane ecosystems. In areas on our study site where we did not recorded any trees, we found that a high percentage of the soil was covered by highly biodiverse meadows (with approx. 14 identified herb species, data not reported here) and by both economically and culinary valuable shrubs, including 
 <italic class="italic">Juniper spp</italic>., 
 <italic class="italic">Vaccinium spp</italic>. and 
 <italic class="italic">Ribes spp</italic>. A continuous upward shift tendency, as the one documented for the last century in this study, would presumably lead to an expansion of the forest at the expense of meadow and shrub species, which would have no other area to migrate to once the mountain summit is reached
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" class="xref">62</xref>
 </sup>. On the other hand, we also identified a partial tendency inversion for the most recent decade of tree expansion at high elevations, which could represent a “temporary relief” for the survival of high-altitude meadow and shrub species. Trees did not move upward after 2004 and this might reflect the recent temperature decrease observed both at the local meteorological stations
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" class="xref">31</xref>
 </sup> and from our estimates derived from the hyperbolic relationship between the mean annual growth and the 1956–2009 field-recorded temperatures. In fact, we found that as −4.3 °C represents a threshold between the negative growth tendency before the 1978 and the positive one after this year, estimated temperatures from 2010 to 2017 show a decreasing trend that, at least, could temporarily hinder the upward shift of the treeline. Further resources to reach and study these remote high-mountain areas would clarify whether this threshold of −4.3 °C applies to other treelines of the Altai Mountains.
</p>
