<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The results of the present study demonstrate the difficulty that may exist in shifting perceived efficacy on the issue of climate change. Climate change is increasingly polarized along political lines [
 <xref rid="pone.0157658.ref052" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>], which can lead to hardened opinions that are resistant to change [
 <xref rid="pone.0157658.ref008" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. Also, given that some scholars have characterized political efficacy as a relatively stable psychological trait [
 <xref rid="pone.0157658.ref032" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>], perceptions of efficacy may not be vulnerable to short-term change as the result of a single message exposure, as was utilized in this experiment. In particular, our manipulation may not have been strong enough to change perceptions of efficacy cultivated by long-term exposure to media coverage about climate change, which tends not to emphasize efficacy information [
 <xref rid="pone.0157658.ref011" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0157658.ref017" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. We note that the stimuli materials were entirely text based, and did not utilize images, which some previous work has suggested may shift efficacy perceptions [
 <xref rid="pone.0157658.ref053" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">53</xref>]. It is also possible that messages that use rich narratives to facilitate involvement with characters and narrative transportation [
 <xref rid="pone.0157658.ref054" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>] may be more effective in shifting efficacy perceptions as well. Finally, a manipulation incorporating repeated exposure, rather than a single exposure, to efficacy information may show different results. Future work may benefit by utilizing various text, imagery, and narrative combinations, in additional to different levels of exposure, to assess how these may affect efficacy perceptions and engagement.
</p>
