<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract abstract-type="summary" class="abstract">
 <title class="title">Author summary</title>
 <sec id="sec004" class="sec">
  <title class="title">Why was this study done?</title>
  <list list-type="bullet" class="list">
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">Heatwaves can cause a significant impact on population health worldwide, including a rise in mortality and morbidity.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">There will be an increase in the frequency and severity of heatwaves in the future worldwide because of climate change.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">Evidence about the impacts of climate change on heatwave-related mortality at a global scale is limited.</p>
   </list-item>
  </list>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec005" class="sec">
  <title class="title">What did the researchers do and find?</title>
  <list list-type="bullet" class="list">
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">We developed a model to estimate heatwave–mortality associations in 412 communities within 20 countries/regions from January 1, 1984 to December 31, 2015. The associations were used to project heatwave-related excess mortality, with projected daily mean temperature series from four scenarios of greenhouse gas emissions during 1971–2099.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">We used three scenarios of population changes (low, moderate, and high variant) and two adaptation scenarios (no adaptation and hypothetical adaptation).</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">If people cannot adapt to future climate change, heatwave-related excess mortality is expected to increase the most in tropical and subtropical countries/regions, while European countries and the United States will have smaller increases. The more serious the greenhouse gas emissions, the higher the heatwave-related excess mortality in the future.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">If people have ability to adapt to future climate change, the heatwave-related excess mortality is expected to still increase in future under the most serious greenhouse gas emissions and high-variant population scenarios. However, the increase is expected to be much smaller than the no adaptation scenario.</p>
   </list-item>
  </list>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec006" class="sec">
  <title class="title">What do these findings mean?</title>
  <list list-type="bullet" class="list">
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">Future changes in heatwave-related excess mortality are highly affected by greenhouse gas emissions and human adaptation to climate change.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">Stricter mitigation policy to reduce greenhouse gas emission is expected to produce greater health benefits related to heatwaves.</p>
   </list-item>
   <list-item class="list-item">
    <p class="p">Adaptation strategies should be planned to reduce the health impacts of heatwaves in all the countries/regions, particularly developing countries in tropic and subtropical regions.</p>
   </list-item>
  </list>
 </sec>
</abstract>
