<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div id="Fig1" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
 <div class="caption">
  <p>Change in soil organic C (tonnes C ha
   <span class="sup">−1</span>) between no-till and full tillage management across depths from 0 to 80 cm over 20 years. Positive values represent more soil organic C with no-till management. Graphs include the following climatic and edaphic conditions: (
   <span class="bold">A</span>) loamy, silty and clayey (LSC) soils in tropical dry climates, (
   <span class="bold">B</span>) sandy soils in tropical dry climates, (
   <span class="bold">C</span>) LSC soils in tropical moist/wet climates, (
   <span class="bold">D</span>) sandy soils in tropical moist/wet climates, (
   <span class="bold">E</span>) LSC soils in warm temperate dry climates, (
   <span class="bold">F</span>) sandy soils in warm temperate dry climates, (
   <span class="bold">G</span>) LSC soils in warm temperate moist climates, (
   <span class="bold">H</span>) sandy soils in warm temperate moist climates, (
   <span class="bold">I</span>) LSC soils in cool temperate dry climates, (
   <span class="bold">J</span>) sandy soils in cool temperate dry climates, (
   <span class="bold">K</span>) LSC soils in cool temperate moist climates, and (
   <span class="bold">L</span>) sandy soils in cool temperate moist climates. Sandy soils contain 50% or more sand. The red lines represent the observed changes in soil organic C at the depth range of each line, the blue shading is a 95% confidence interval for the estimated change in SOC stocks, and grey vertical line denotes a depth of 30 cm. These results are based on the measured differences at each depth without adjustment for equivalent mass (See Table 
   <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a> for adjusted results).
  </p>
 </div>
 <div xlink:href="41598_2019_47861_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e560" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</div>
