<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Last, we find that GPP and NEP are projected by ESMs to become more sensitive to low SM than to high VPD in the Northern Hemisphere throughout the 21st century. SM stress is a requisite driver of long-term carbon consequences of drought, as plant hydraulic failure is the primary physiological driver of drought-driven mortality across widespread plant species (
 <xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">31</italic>
 </xref>–
 <xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">34</italic>
 </xref>). Recent studies have also emphasized the importance of atmospheric moisture demand on plant carbon uptake and food production, as many plant species strongly limit stomatal conductance under high VPD to reduce water losses and the risk of hydraulic failure (
 <xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">3</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">6</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">21</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">35</italic>
 </xref>). According to flux tower observations, plant carbon uptake responds nonlinearly to SM decline, with higher sensitivity when SM is lower than a certain threshold. On the other hand, further increases in VPD beyond the threshold needed to induce stomatal closure may lead to diminishing effects on productivity. Projected increases in the intensity and frequency of compound drought and aridity events likely correspond to enhanced risk of vegetation mortality (
 <xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">36</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">37</italic>
 </xref>), but the plant hydraulic response to SM stress and atmospheric demand is highly simplified in ESMs, and this is a major driver of uncertainty in terrestrial carbon response to climate change (
 <xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">38</italic>
 </xref>).
</p>
