<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Six variables, including two constructed from multiple sub-variables, were combined to calculate the index of adaptive capacity: fisheries subsidies (
 <italic class="italic">AC</italic>
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">1</italic>
 </sub>); ratio of industrial to small-scale fisheries (
 <italic class="italic">AC</italic>
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">2</italic>
 </sub>); healthy life expectancy (
 <italic class="italic">AC</italic>
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">3</italic>
 </sub>); governance capacity (unweighted mean of six dimensions of governance) (
 <italic class="italic">AC</italic>
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">4</italic>
 </sub>); education levels (combination of literacy rates and school enrolment rates) (
 <italic class="italic">AC</italic>
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">5</italic>
 </sub>); per capita gross domestic product (GDP) (
 <italic class="italic">AC</italic>
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">6</italic>
 </sub>) (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0179632.g001" class="xref">Fig 1</xref>). Total fisheries subsidies as a percentage of landed monetary value were collected from the Sea Around Us project, averaged for available years, and normalized [
 <xref rid="pone.0179632.ref028" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>][
 <xref rid="pone.0179632.ref029" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>]. The ratio of industrial to small-scale (artisanal, subsistence and recreational) fisheries (in 2010) was likewise compiled from the latest Sea Around Us data [
 <xref rid="pone.0179632.ref027" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>]. Statistics from 2015 on healthy life expectancy (HALE) at birth were collected and normalized [
 <xref rid="pone.0179632.ref040" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>]. Due to the exceptionally high degree of correlation between literacy rates and primary school enrolment rates for countries reporting both types of data (Spearman’s 
 <italic class="italic">ρ</italic> = 0.97), these values were used interchangeably to fill in gaps in each respective dataset to remove the necessity of excluding countries from the analysis [
 <xref rid="pone.0179632.ref041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>][
 <xref rid="pone.0179632.ref042" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>]. The Worldwide Governance Indicators project calculates governance across six individual dimensions, namely voice and accountability, political stability and absence of violence, government effectiveness, regulatory quality, rule of law, and control of corruption; we calculated an unweighted average of these six individual values and normalized this average to generate a single governance variable [
 <xref rid="pone.0179632.ref043" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>]. Finally, the latest per capita GDP levels were extracted from the World Bank Development Indicators database [
 <xref rid="pone.0179632.ref044" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>]. While the calculation of the adaptive capacity index starts with the same method as the sensitivity index described in 2.2, a further step was taken, namely the weighting of the two fisheries-related variables. This departure from the methodology of Allison et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0179632.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>] is meant to ensure that all three elements of the vulnerability index (exposure, sensitivity and adaptive capacity) are explicitly linked to the marine context. The adaptive capacity variables used by Allison et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0179632.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>] are all broad socio-economic factors without a direct connection to the fisheries sector. The mean of these four normalized socio-economic variables makes up one half of the adaptive capacity index, while the mean of the two normalized fisheries-related variables makes up the second half of the adaptive capacity index (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0179632.g001" class="xref">Fig 1</xref>). This gives the fisheries-related variables a greater weight than the socio-economic variables, and results in an adaptive capacity index more specifically designed to match the fisheries sector. As with the sensitivity index, the resulting adaptive capacity index is then normalized on a scale from 0 to 1.
</p>
