<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">To evaluate the present‐day representation of rainfall intensity, we include observations from two products that have been used extensively in previous model evaluation, the Global Precipitation Climatology Project One‐Degree Daily (GPCP 1DD) (Huffman et al., 
 <xref rid="jame20562-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2001</xref>, 
 <xref rid="jame20562-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012a</xref>) and the Tropical Rainfall Measuring Mission 3B42 version 7 (TRMM 3B42; Huffman et al., 
 <xref rid="jame20562-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>, 
 <xref rid="jame20562-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012b</xref>). GPCP 1DD is a daily estimate of accumulated precipitation on a 1° global grid, based on infrared (IR) measurements calibrated to monthly Special Sensor Microwave Imager and GPCP version 2 satellite‐gauge precipitation data (Huffman et al., 
 <xref rid="jame20562-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2001</xref>). TRMM 3B42 is a 3 hourly estimate of instantaneous precipitation on a 0.25° grid from 50°S to 50°N, which combines visible, IR, and microwave radiometer measurements from the TRMM satellite calibrated to monthly Global Precipitation Climatology Center rain gauge data (Huffman et al., 
 <xref rid="jame20562-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>); 3 hourly estimates have been averaged to form a daily mean time series for this study. For many high‐order statistics, including the intensity of moderate rain rates evaluated here, these two data products differ significantly. Many studies evaluating rainfall intensity statistics have found the TRMM 3B42 daily rate estimates to be more reliable than GPCP 1DD (Behrangi et al., 
 <xref rid="jame20562-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>; Dinku et al., 
 <xref rid="jame20562-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>; Liu &amp; Allan, 
 <xref rid="jame20562-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>; Tan et al., 
 <xref rid="jame20562-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>), but we include both products here to provide a range of observational estimates and global coverage outside the TRMM region. These data products are used in the present‐day comparison in section 
 <xref rid="jame20562-sec-0010" ref-type="sec" class="xref">3.1</xref> and have been regridded to the horizontal resolution of the model (0.9° × 1.25°) using an area‐conserving interpolation scheme.
</p>
