<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par19">Second, to our knowledge, we have offered the first quantitative estimate of the global distribution of MMTs. MFT is easy to calculate, and we might, therefore, estimate the MMT in any geographical location and in any period. Based on the current association between MMT and MFT, in order to validate whether the association is still reliable in the future, we have searched all available studies which provided the values of MMTs at different times in the same location. We found there were six papers which provided the MMT values of 62 locations from eight counties (USA
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>
 </sup>, UK
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>
 </sup>, Finland
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>
 </sup>, France
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>
 </sup>, Spain
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>
 </sup>, Netherlands
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>
 </sup>, Japan
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>
 </sup>, and South Korean
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>
 </sup>) in different years. We calculated the MFTs of these locations during the same period. We found that: (1) In most locations, the temporal trends of MMT and MFT are consistent
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>
 </sup>; (2) The MMT and MFT have increased in most locations of the studied countries
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>
 </sup>; (3) Although in some locations MMT did not change or reduced, MFT had the similar trend in most of these locations
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>
 </sup>. For example, Donaldson found that from 1972 to 1997, MMTs rose 3.6 °C in North Carolina, 2.7 °C in Southeast England and 1.3 °C in South Finland
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>
 </sup>, and the MFTs in these three locations during the same period have increased 3 °C, 2 °C, and 1 °C, respectively (Supplementary Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">3</xref>). Similar results have also been reported in other countries such as Japan
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>
 </sup> and Spain
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>
 </sup>. Chung found that from 1972 to 2012, MMT rose about 4.8 °C in Japan, and the MFT in the same period has increased 5 °C. Achebak found that from 1980 to 2016, MMT rose from 19.5 °C to 20.3 °C in Japan, and the MFT in the same period rose from 19.5 °C to 20.5 °C. Based on this finding, we estimate the global distribution of MMTs in the future (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>).
</p>
