<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Under both irrigation schemes in the growth chamber and at the end of the third year all seedlings achieved similar heights without differences among populations and provenances. Similarly, Harter et al. (
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>) did not find any differences in seedling height between two beech provenances under water deficit for 60 days. Various studies report that non-frequent irrigation leads to lower shoot height in seedlings (Arend et al., 
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>; Thiel et al., 
 <xref rid="B117" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>). However, in the current study, seedling height was generally larger under long drought intervals (irrigation scheme A1) rather than more frequent irrigation (scheme A2). In our study, the distribution pattern of water was more critical for seedling growth than the absolute amount of water received. It is possible that fewer but significant rain events may yield higher biomass increase than more frequent but minor events as it is already reported for plant communities (e.g., Bates et al., 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2006</xref>; de Dios Miranda et al., 
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>). This highlights the necessity for considering the rainfall patterns in terms of frequency and quantity rather than rainfall means alone as factor affecting the adaptation of plants (de Dios Miranda et al., 
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>). Since this kind of irrigation pattern comparison has not yet been performed in any other common environment study for forest trees, the growth behavior of beech seedlings in this experiment needs to be further investigated using physiological and anatomical traits (Bolte et al., 
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>). In any case, these responses to irrigation frequency seem to be temporary and reversible after a short time, revealing the existence of possible trade-offs between different traits as part of a complex adaptive strategy aiming at the best possible use of the available water.
</p>
