<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">About 100 tonnes of mercury are delivered to the Arctic Ocean from the air each year, which is about the same inflowing amount from the Atlantic and Pacific Oceans, rivers and coastal erosion [
 <xref rid="B21-ijerph-12-03579" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B22-ijerph-12-03579" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-ijerph-12-03579" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-ijerph-12-03579" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-ijerph-12-03579" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-ijerph-12-03579" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>]. These inputs already comprise inorganic and small amounts of methylated and dissolved gaseous mercury resulting from transformations that occurred in these reservoirs even before the mercury reached the Arctic environment. During spring flood, boreal rivers transport large quantities of mercury from the continents (e.g., Siberia) to the Arctic Ocean. The Arctic Ocean seawater accumulates about 25 tonnes of mercury each year [
 <xref rid="B5-ijerph-12-03579" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>]. The budget calculations suggest that about 75 to 90 tonnes of mercury are exported from the Arctic Ocean in ocean outflow each year and that about 110 tonnes are deposited in Arctic Ocean shelf and in deep ocean sediments [
 <xref rid="B5-ijerph-12-03579" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-ijerph-12-03579" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. Trough measurements and flux estimates, an input of 80 tonnes per year of river total mercury to the portion of Arctic marine waters has been found between 70°–90° N [
 <xref rid="B27-ijerph-12-03579" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B28-ijerph-12-03579" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>]. Fisher 
 <italic class="italic">et al.</italic> [
 <xref rid="B27-ijerph-12-03579" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>] further report that atmospheric net deposition (45 tonnes) and coastal erosion (15 tonnes per year) follows river inputs as the most important sources of mercury. Evasion of mercury from the surface ocean (90 tonnes per year) and particle settling (43 tonnes per year) they claim to be the most important processes removing mercury from surface ocean waters. Evasion of mercury from the surface ocean has furthermore been proposed to explain the summertime peak in concentrations observed in the Arctic atmosphere [
 <xref rid="B27-ijerph-12-03579" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-ijerph-12-03579" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>].
</p>
