<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="section5-0013916513503832" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Adaptation and Mitigation in Agriculture</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate change adaptation and mitigation in agriculture are related concepts, but have important biophysical, economic, and conceptual differences that may affect farmer attitudes toward action. Adaptation is defined as “initiatives and measures to reduce the vulnerability of natural and human systems against actual or expected climate change effects” (
  <a rid="bibr33-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr33-0013916513503832">IPCC, 2007</a>, p. 809). Adaptation has always been central to farming, and over millennia farmers have generally been adept at adapting agriculture to a changing environment (
  <a rid="bibr59-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr59-0013916513503832">Organisation for Economic Co-operation and Development [OECD], 2012</a>). Although farmers manage at multiple scales, their adaptation decisions are primarily driven by private benefits reaped in the here and now (
  <a rid="bibr37-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr37-0013916513503832">Jackson et al., 2010</a>). Examples of adaptation of agriculture to the impacts of climate change might include adjustments in planting dates, crop varieties, drainage systems, and land management regimes to maintain yields and soil fertility. In the U.S. Midwest, commonly recommended adaptive actions include increased use of practices such as minimization of tillage and use of cover crops to protect soils from erosion and build soil organic matter (
  <a rid="bibr41-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr41-0013916513503832">Lal et al., 2011</a>). Such practices have relatively observable, immediate impacts, such as reduced vulnerability, that accrue largely to the individual farmer or landowner who adopts them (
  <a rid="bibr73-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr73-0013916513503832">Walthal et al., 2012</a>). Thus, adaptation strategies are familiar and have tangible individual-level benefits.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Whereas adaptation has long been integral to agriculture, climate change mitigation is a relatively new attitude object. Mitigation is defined as “technological change and substitution that reduce resource inputs and emissions per unit of output” (
  <a rid="bibr33-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr33-0013916513503832">IPCC, 2007</a>, p. 818). In agriculture, mitigation is focused primarily on reducing GHG emissions and/or increasing carbon sequestration and storage (
  <a rid="bibr33-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr33-0013916513503832">IPCC, 2007</a>). In contrast to adaptation action, the potential benefits of mitigation action are uncertain, entail substantial lag time, and accrue globally rather than locally (
  <a rid="bibr73-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr73-0013916513503832">Walthal et al., 2012</a>). Because the benefits of mitigative action are diffuse, much of the public discussion related to GHG production and mitigation to reduce emissions has focused on 
  <span class="italic">collective</span> responses by civil society, private sectors, and, especially, government bodies (
  <a rid="bibr77-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr77-0013916513503832">World Bank, 2012</a>). In agriculture, too, major proposed strategies to induce GHG reduction have focused on collective, government-led responses including legislative mandates to reduce emissions, emissions taxes, and cap and trade regimes (
  <a rid="bibr15-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr15-0013916513503832">Council for Agricultural Science and Technology [CAST], 2011</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hence, while adaptation and mitigation policy and action are responses to threats from climate change, they are fundamentally different. Whereas adaptation is generally initiated at the local level by individuals or communities in reaction to specific threats, mitigation action tends to be initiated at the international or national levels and managed by government bodies (
  <a rid="bibr40-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr40-0013916513503832">Klein et al., 2007</a>). Furthermore, the rationale for mitigation in agriculture is almost entirely predicated on the assumption that human production of GHGs is the primary driver of climate change. Thus, while adaptation in agriculture is relatively routine—farmers continuously adapt to changing conditions regardless of beliefs about climate change—attitudes toward and willingness to support mitigative action are likely influenced largely by beliefs about climate change and the role of human activities as a cause.
 </p>
</sec>
