<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" id="section20-0013916513503832" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The consensus view among scientists is that to maintain long-term societal food security, we urgently need to reduce agriculture’s vulnerability to predicted changes in climate and reduce GHG emissions (e.g., 
  <a rid="bibr31-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr31-0013916513503832">Hatfield et al., 2011</a>; 
  <a rid="bibr41-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr41-0013916513503832">Lal et al., 2011</a>). The results of this study show that Iowa farmers, in general, seem to be willing to adapt to changing climate conditions and view their responses as risk management strategies to maintain crop productivity. However, perceptions of mitigation activities by government are less straightforward. Farmers who believe that climate change is happening and primarily anthropogenic are more likely to favor government action on GHGs, yet they represent a small fraction of the farmers in our sample. Moreover, more than half did not believe that climate change is occurring, were uncertain about its existence, or believed that it is primarily due to natural causes.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our research suggests that farmers (and possibly the greater agricultural community) are more open to adaptation than mitigation. Farmers adapt for a living (
  <a rid="bibr59-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr59-0013916513503832">OECD, 2012</a>), and they pride themselves on their ability to solve problems (
  <a rid="bibr56-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr56-0013916513503832">Nowak, 2013</a>). 
  <a rid="bibr45-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr45-0013916513503832">Lobell, Baldos, and Thomas (2013</a>, p. 1) offer a solution to addressing agriculture’s contribution to GHG emissions in their findings that “broad-based efforts to adapt agriculture to climate change have mitigation co-benefits” and note that adaptation is often considerably less expensive than actions whose main purpose is mitigation. Many of the practices that reduce vulnerability of cropping systems most effectively—reductions in tillage, planting of a cover crop to hold soil during fallow periods, managing fertilizers more efficiently—can also have significant GHG-reducing properties (
  <a rid="bibr41-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr41-0013916513503832">Lal et al., 2011</a>). By using outreach strategies that focus on adaptive practices that reduce risks and GHG emissions, the dual goals of adaptation and mitigation could be pursued while engaging the majority of farmers who do not believe in anthropogenic climate change.
 </p>
</sec>
