<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="section12-0013916513503832" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Descriptive Statistics for the Variables in the Model</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Responses for the nine items that comprise the two 
  <span class="italic">trust</span> variables—trust in agricultural and environmentally oriented entities, respectively, as sources of information about climate change—varied substantially. Among the agricultural interests, the percentage of farmers who indicated at least some trust ranged from 40% for “farm groups” to 24% for “agribusiness companies” (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="table1-0013916513503832" href="#table1-0013916513503832">Table 1</a>). Among environmentally oriented groups, “scientists” were the most trusted (42%) and the mainstream news media were the least trusted (9%).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results for the 
  <span class="italic">climate change belief and attribution</span> variable revealed that most farmers (68%) believed that climate change is occurring (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="table2-0013916513503832" href="#table2-0013916513503832">Table 2</a>). Attribution of cause varies substantially, with just 10% believing climate change is mostly attributable to human activities. Slightly more than one third believed that it is caused by natural changes and human activities equally, and 23% believed it is mostly due to natural variation. Furthermore, a sizable proportion of farmers believed there is not enough evidence to determine if it is occurring (27%) or it is not happening at all (5%).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Summary statistics for the four items that measure 
  <span class="italic">perceived risks</span> associated with climate change are presented in 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="table3-0013916513503832" href="#table3-0013916513503832">Table 3</a>. The items that elicited the highest levels of agreement were concern about impact on the respondents’ own operations (46% agreement) and on Iowa agriculture in general (43%). Thirty-five percent of farmers indicated belief that extreme weather would become more common in the future. On the other hand, 33% agreed that climate change is not a big issue because human ingenuity will enable us to adapt to changes.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results showed substantial levels of support for both 
  <span class="italic">adaptation</span>-related items. About two thirds of respondents agreed that farmers should take steps to protect their land, and 45% agreed that investment in agricultural drainage systems should be stepped up (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="table3-0013916513503832" href="#table3-0013916513503832">Table 3</a>). Support for government actions to 
  <span class="italic">mitigate</span> climate change through GHG reduction was lower, with 33% of farmers in agreement with that statement.
 </p>
</sec>
