<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="section6-0013916513503832" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hypotheses</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The literature reviewed above indicates that beliefs about climate change and perceptions of associated risks can be important predictors of public support for climate change action. Furthermore, evidence suggests that the mediating influence of actors that attempt to shape the framing and debate over climate change and societal responses should be accounted for in analyses of public understanding of climate change. Based on this previous research, for this study of Iowa farmers, we propose two models that posit pathways of effect-prioritized relationships between trust in agricultural and environmental interest groups as sources of climate change information, beliefs about climate change and its causes, the perceived risks of climate change for agriculture, and support for (1) adaptive or (2) mitigative responses to climate change among Iowa farmers.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our specific hypotheses are as follows:</p>
 <div list-type="simple" id="list1-0013916513503832" class="list" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Hypothesis 1a (H1a):</span> Trust in agricultural interest groups will be negatively associated with belief in human-induced climate change;
   </p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Hypothesis 1b (H1b):</span> Trust in environmentally oriented interest groups will be positively associated with belief in human-induced climate change;
   </p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Hypothesis 2 (H2):</span> Belief that climate change is occurring will be positively associated with perceptions regarding risks to agriculture;
   </p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Hypothesis 3 (H3):</span> Higher levels of perceived risk will predict stronger support for adaptation responses to climate change;
   </p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Hypothesis 4 (H4):</span> Belief that climate change is occurring and caused by human activity will have a direct, positive effect on support for mitigation policy.
   </p>
  </div>
 </div>
</sec>
