<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Materials and Methods</div>
 <sec id="s4a" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study Area</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our study is part of the large-scale long-term research program ‘Biodiversity Exploratories’ (details and scope are summarized in 
   <a rid="pone.0053121-Fischer1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0053121-Fischer1">[2]</a>), which aims at investigating the impact of forest and grassland management on various organisms and ecosystem services. Three study sites in Germany, with 50 experimental plots each, in forests of different structure and management regimes have been selected for this research program. For the present study we selected 11 experimental plots in forests of the Schwäbische Alb Exploratory in south-western Germany (approximate centre coordinates: 48.411° North and 9.497°East, 500–800 m a. s. l.).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s4b" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Forest Types and Forest Structure</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our experimental plots cover two forest management regimes, with managed forests of spruce (
   <span class="italic">Picea abies</span>) and beech (
   <span class="italic">Fagus sylvatica</span>) of different ages 
   <a rid="pone.0053121-Fischer1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0053121-Fischer1">[2]</a>. These 11 experimental plots have been selected based on dominant tree species (large trees with canopy cover over 70% of the experimental plot area). The experimental plots within each habitat type have supposedly similar average diameter at breast height (DBH) and age structure. While five plots have been placed in spruce forests (AEW01, AEW02, AEW10, AEW12, AEW34), six have been located in beech forests (AEW08, AEW04, AEW07, AEW28, AEW46, AEW45). The maximum distance between the plots is 20 km; plots are located in discontinuous forest patches, separated by other forest types or open landscapes.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Light Detection And Ranging (LiDAR) methods have been shown to provide continuous environmental variables that largely outcompete traditional forest type classifications which many times are also relatively coarse 
   <a rid="pone.0053121-Nikolov1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0053121-Nikolov1">[36]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0053121-Lefsky1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0053121-Lefsky1">[44]</a>–
   <a rid="pone.0053121-Bradbury1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0053121-Bradbury1">[48]</a>. We used LiDAR to obtain continuous environmental variables of all experimental plots during leave-on (deciduous trees) season end of July 2010. A Riegl LMS-Q 560 scanner was mounted on a helicopter flying at an altitude of 600 m. The size of the footprint diameter ranged between 20 cm and 30 cm and the sampling accuracy was 50 cm horizontally and 15 cm vertically. Based on normalized raw data and the Canopy Height model we then mathematically derived forest structure parameters, which are Roughness (vertical heterogeneity), Understory (extent of shrubs and bushes close to the forest ground), Island (canopy islands), Stem Zone (extent of the stem zone which is shows no leave, basically to open area within a forest), Euphotic Zone (leave area which resembles basically the canopy), and Forest Height (the mean height of the outer canopy height; further details of LiDAR parameters are explained in 
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0053121.s004" href="#pone.0053121.s004">Table S1</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s4c" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cafeteria Trials</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Food types were selected to represent different amounts of energy per 100 g and had different fat to carbohydrate ratios (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="pone-0053121-t001" href="#pone-0053121-t001">Table 1</a>). Food types represented natural non-animal food of the bird species predicted for the study area and were classified as fat-rich, carbohydrate-rich, and fruit (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="pone-0053121-t001" href="#pone-0053121-t001">Table 1</a>). However, grain size of food types was similar and varied less than 1 mm in diameter (except for fruit, which were slightly larger, and control). Each food was offered in a plastic dish (hereafter ‘food dish’) in equal amounts (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="pone-0053121-t001" href="#pone-0053121-t001">Table 1</a>). Each food type was mixed with the same amount of pure lard to fix the grains to the food dish, so preventing wind or landing birds dispersing the grains. To test the effect of lard on feeding preferences, we added two control food dishes of lard to each feeding station.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">At each experimental plot we placed two feeding stations (each with four food dishes), which consisted of modified, free-hanging plastic flowerpots prepared to hold the food dishes (
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0053121.s002" href="#pone.0053121.s002">Figures S1</a>, 
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0053121.s003" href="#pone.0053121.s003">S2</a>). Each feeding station had a roof to prevent snow and rain from covering the food and also to exclude large predators. Each food dish placeholder was numbered randomly from 1 to 8, but specific numbers have been assigned to each food type (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="pone-0053121-t001" href="#pone-0053121-t001">Table 1</a>). To prevent mice and large mammals from stealing food, the feeding stations hung free (at least 1.5 m above the ground and from the next tree or branch), and the suspension ropes were blocked with free-rotating discs (
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0053121.s001" href="#pone.0053121.s001">Notes S1</a> on the procedures and methods are provided in Supporting Information). Food consumption was measured through counts of birds at feeding stations. All counts per species and time unit (60 minutes) is activity.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s4d" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Bird Observations</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Observers recorded birds (counts) at feeding stations for 60 minutes in the morning (earliest start at 08: 05, latest start at 13: 35) on each observation day. The observation period started on the 30
   <span class="sup">th</span> November 2010 and ended on the 8
   <span class="sup">th</span> April 2011. At any given time, six camera traps (AMG Viper 3 BM Ltl-5210 were used and supported by one (until February) or two (March/April) observers. Two camera traps per plot (as each camera recorded images of four food dishes per flower pot only), recorded all birds (i.e., six camera traps at 3 plots and Possler or Winkler/Baur at other plots). Both observers and camera traps finished recording after 60 minutes simultaneously, covering four plots a day (three plots by camera traps and one by observer). We set up cameras each day to start at the same time as the observers. Each image was analyzed and birds were counted for 60 minutes. We use activity = 
   <span class="italic">N</span>
   <span class="sup">−h</span> as our baseline unit for all comparison and analyzes, where 
   <span class="italic">N</span> are the counted observations normalized for 60 minutes (activity), and h is the number of hours. For a single day when we observed birds for only 55 minutes, we tested the influence of the missing time and adjusted the data for 60 minutes. In case we pooled together food sources (which have been similar regarding carbohydrate or fat contents), we adjusted count values if necessary to 60 minutes counts (i.e. normalizing of data: fat-rich food was offered in two food dishes at each feeding station, grain in three, control in two, and fruit in one; 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="pone-0053121-t001" href="#pone-0053121-t001">Table 1</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For each day and plot we recorded start and ending time, snow cover (present/absent/partial), local temperature, and other remarks of potential interest for our study. Camera trap failures have been adjusted by later repetitions of the same plot to have always the exactly same amount of observed hours per feeding station. We obtained air temperature data for each plot as measured during the observation hour (max, min, mean of each hour when observed, measured 10 cm above ground within 50 m of the feeding stations) as available (no temperature data available for AEW12 during our study).</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s4e" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Bird Activity Recorded with Cameras Traps</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Each ‘count’ represented a bird observed at any feeding station. Observer counted simultaneously as the camera traps recorded birds in 5-second-intervals. Therefore we analyzed data from images and direct observations. A count was analyzed, when (1) an individual bird was detected, leaving the food station with food in the beak (we noted time/date, plot, species, food type, remarks), (2) an individual bird was observed feeding without leaving the food station (counted as 1), and (3) an individual bird was photographed at the feeding station by a camera trap (regardless of whether consuming the food or not). We did not consider counts as part of the activity, when (i) an individual bird was detected feeding several times without flying up nor without changing food dish within 5 seconds, (ii) an individual bird was detected by the camera trap in a sequence of images and it was certainly the same individual in the same food dish, (iii) an individual bird was detected at the fringe or roof of the food station, but was not feeding at any given dish (except when the bird had food in the beak), (iv) it was impossible to identify the species ('something' flying away, for instance dark image/steep shadow, only shape visible, and uncertain identification of some 
   <span class="italic">Parus</span> species). When necessary, we corrected for different sample size (amount of plots) between habitat types in the analysis.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s4f" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical Analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From structural and climate variables we selected models based on the information theoretic approach for activity of species at feeding stations 
   <a rid="pone.0053121-Burnham1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0053121-Burnham1">[49]</a> to get the minimum adequate model. We tested whether food preferences (i.e. activity at any specified food source offered) of the birds are related to forest type, temperature (Air temperature at 10 cm, minimum and maximum values), or whether snow cover affected activity of birds at the feeding stations. We used the function lm() in R for testing activity with single or combined variables. In a first step we calculated for each of our research questions an ANOVA to show response of single parameters on activity of birds at feeding stations. For seasonality, we use the Observation Day during the study as independent variable.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Finally we analyzed all variables together to establish a best fitting model explaining (with the available datasets) response of birds to temperature, snow, and forest types. Our full model included all temperature, forest types, and snow cover variables and was:</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Activity ∼ Air temperature (min)+Air temperature (max)+Air temperature at 10 cm+snow+Roughness+Understory+Island+Stem Zone+Euphotic Zone+Forest Height+(1|food type)+(1|Plot ID)+(1|Observation Hour)+(1|Species Code), data = f, family = Poisson)</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">with activity as observed feeding event at feeding station (all variables explained in detail in 
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0053121.s004" href="#pone.0053121.s004">Table S1</a>). We excluded however all likely auto-correlated variables (temperature). We assumed Poisson distributions. We scaled or ln-transformed variables (however not snow, nor forest type) with the command scale() or log() in R. We used command lmer() in packages lme4() 
   <a rid="pone.0053121-Bates1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0053121-Bates1">[50]</a> on a R 2.12.0 x64 Environment 
   <a rid="pone.0053121-R1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0053121-R1">[51]</a> for all statistical analyses if not indicated differently, and lattice() 
   <a rid="pone.0053121-R1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0053121-R1">[51]</a> for plotting graphs.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
