<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s4f" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical Analysis</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From structural and climate variables we selected models based on the information theoretic approach for activity of species at feeding stations 
  <a rid="pone.0053121-Burnham1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0053121-Burnham1">[49]</a> to get the minimum adequate model. We tested whether food preferences (i.e. activity at any specified food source offered) of the birds are related to forest type, temperature (Air temperature at 10 cm, minimum and maximum values), or whether snow cover affected activity of birds at the feeding stations. We used the function lm() in R for testing activity with single or combined variables. In a first step we calculated for each of our research questions an ANOVA to show response of single parameters on activity of birds at feeding stations. For seasonality, we use the Observation Day during the study as independent variable.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Finally we analyzed all variables together to establish a best fitting model explaining (with the available datasets) response of birds to temperature, snow, and forest types. Our full model included all temperature, forest types, and snow cover variables and was:</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Activity ∼ Air temperature (min)+Air temperature (max)+Air temperature at 10 cm+snow+Roughness+Understory+Island+Stem Zone+Euphotic Zone+Forest Height+(1|food type)+(1|Plot ID)+(1|Observation Hour)+(1|Species Code), data = f, family = Poisson)</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">with activity as observed feeding event at feeding station (all variables explained in detail in 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0053121.s004" href="#pone.0053121.s004">Table S1</a>). We excluded however all likely auto-correlated variables (temperature). We assumed Poisson distributions. We scaled or ln-transformed variables (however not snow, nor forest type) with the command scale() or log() in R. We used command lmer() in packages lme4() 
  <a rid="pone.0053121-Bates1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0053121-Bates1">[50]</a> on a R 2.12.0 x64 Environment 
  <a rid="pone.0053121-R1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0053121-R1">[51]</a> for all statistical analyses if not indicated differently, and lattice() 
  <a rid="pone.0053121-R1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0053121-R1">[51]</a> for plotting graphs.
 </p>
</sec>
