<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3">In this context, island biodiversity requires specific attention for several reasons. Insular communities, because they are spatially segregated and have evolved in isolation, are characterized by extremely high rates of endemism
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>
 </sup>. Although they occur on less than 5% of the Earth’s terrestrial area, island plants and vertebrates have an endemic richness that may exceed that of mainland species by a factor of 9.5
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>
 </sup>. Island biota are also very prone to extinction: around 80% of past extinctions and a third of threatened terrestrial species are found on islands
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>
 </sup>. Past extinctions were probably triggered by invasive species, the naïveté of insular species, and the high range-restriction of some populations
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>
 </sup>. Although climate change might impact island biota in many different ways, it is likely that sea level rise and climate shifts will be of major importance due to their direct association with the availability of suitable habitats for terrestrial organisms. Sea level rise is expected to lead to the submergence of several islands
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>
 </sup>. Sea level rise may also increase coastal erosion and saline water intrusion, impacting natural habitats
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>
 </sup>. This means that elevation, area, and the complexity of shoreline inlets are of major importance regarding vulnerability to sea level rise
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>
 </sup>. As for climate shift, it includes changes in the frequency and intensity of extreme weather events (e.g. droughts, storm surges, hurricanes), as well as altered patterns of seasonal and mid-term weather systems. This leads to the displacement of suitable climatic conditions to different altitudinal or latitudinal ranges, which implies that for some island species, suitable climates may only be found far beyond their limits
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>
 </sup>. Island size and topographic heterogeneity will then play a central role in preserving habitats where species could survive. When suitable habitats disappear, species that are able to adapt or/and have advantageous traits, e.g. flowering times that can track temperature shifts
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>
 </sup>, will probably be naturally selected under the new environmental conditions, whereas others may go extinct. Shifts in climatic conditions may then promote a cascade of local extinctions.
</p>
