<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The SADC region needs to adopt water management practices and aim to produce more food and energy with less water resources. One such initiative would be the promotion and cultivation of indigenous underutilised crops that suit local harsh environmental conditions [
 <xref rid="B54-ijerph-15-02306" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>]. Cultivating indigenous crops would allow for agricultural expansion, and marginal areas currently deemed unsuitable for crop production without increasing water withdrawals for agriculture which currently stands at 70% of available water resources [
 <xref rid="B55-ijerph-15-02306" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>]. Their low input requirements give them an economic advantage over adapted crops like maize, rice, and wheat [
 <xref rid="B56-ijerph-15-02306" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">56</xref>]. Indigenous underutilised crops help to ensure food and nutrition security as part of a balanced diet, when adapted crops fail, or in between harvests [
 <xref rid="B57-ijerph-15-02306" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>]. In addition, this could contribute to utilising currently underutilised large tracts of land that have been deemed unsuitable for the production of major staple commercial crops. Thus, their cultivation would neither create new demands for water nor would they compete for current prime agricultural land. Further improvements to water and energy use efficiencies related to irrigated agriculture would also mitigate the risk of increasing water and associated energy demands from agriculture. In this regard, promotion of micro irrigation, use of solar powered pumps and other forms of farming, such as hydroponics, would go some way in mitigating trade-offs associated with increasing food production. Concurrently, research and development should focus on multi-purpose agro-systems which deliver on more than just food but also water and energy. For example, the development of multi-purpose dams that serve irrigation, power generation, aquaculture, and eco-tourism.
</p>
