<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">GHGs (water vapor, CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>, CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub>, N
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O) act to make the surface warmer by absorbing and emitting heat energy in all the directions. Addition of more GHGs to the atmosphere make more effective in preventing the heat from escaping into space. The GHG’s concentration increased significantly since the industrial revolution began. The atmospheric concentrations of CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>, CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub>, N
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O has increased by 40%, 150% and 20%, respectively. This increase in GHGs is due to emissions by human activities, which alter the Earth’s energy balance resulting in significant increase in ST thus global warming. The anthropogenic forcings plays a significant role in climate change hence global warming. Humans alter aerosols not only at the surface (e.g. industrial emissions) but also at the higher altitudes. Due to increase in populations, the natural vegetation decreases for thousands of years by deforestation. The largest changes occurred in 20
 <sup class="sup">th</sup> century. Hence changing land cover affects the climate by modifying the surface reflectivity and the hydrological cycle. In addition to the direct radiative effects, LU can affect the sources and sinks of GHG’s and the amount of dust lifted into the atmosphere by the wind. For example, atmospheric CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>, CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub>, and N
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O concentrations are increased by deforestation, cultivation of rice and by use of nitrogen fertilizers in agriculture activity. Natural variability of aerosols, particularly due to volcanoes eruptions (e.g. Mt. Pinatubo in 1991) are recognized as a significant climate change indication, which alters the Earth’s radiation balance and thus tends to cause the increase in temperature. These and other lines of evidence point conclusively to the fact that the elevated CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> concentration in our atmosphere is the result of human activities. It is well known that net global warming is very sensitive to the region of focus. Different local and regional topographical and meteorological factors play an important role in determining global warming and climate change. India will observe changes in precipitation, cyclone occurrence, human health, agriculture, extreme events
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">21</xref>
 </sup>. Although a sudden increase in ST was observed during the last century, the annual precipitation over India showed only moderate increase. However, the extreme precipitation frequency and magnitude increased rapidly
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">22</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">23</xref>
 </sup>. Nevertheless, newly introduced forcing agents such as historical emissions of carbonaceous aerosols should be included in future studies for a better understanding of global warming impacts. Uncertainties related to future warming in model analysis also need further investigation. CMIP5 coordinated climate models experiments had leads to better understanding of past, present, and future climate change and variability. However, the science gaps and outstanding questions have promoted to design new experiments known as CMIP6, which address the science aspects such as Earth system respond to forcings, sources and consequences of systematic biases and assessment of future climate changes given climate variability, predictability and uncertainties in scenarios. In recent years, the asymmetry of the forcing has been noticed and attracted more and more attention of scientists. For example, the asymmetric volcanic eruptions at different latitudes can affect the global climate differently
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">24</xref>
 </sup>. In CMIP6, the latitude-dependent GHG concentration will also considered, that should have different effect on the Indian surface temperature compared to CMIP5.
</p>
