<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece34146-sec-0010" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.4</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Active management approaches</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On degraded reefs, removal of human pressures may be insufficient to facilitate recovery to coral‐dominated ecosystems, suggesting that active reef restoration may be necessary to maintain healthy ecosystems more resilient to climate change (Abelson et al., 
  <a rid="ece34146-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0001">2016</a>; Adam et al., 
  <a rid="ece34146-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0002">2015</a>; Rogers et al., 
  <a rid="ece34146-bib-0148" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0148">2015</a>). Introducing artificial complexity to replace the lost habitat structures of low complexity reefs, for example due to acidification, has been successful at small scales such as in the Gulf of Aqaba, Red Sea (Al‐Horani &amp; Khalaf, 
  <a rid="ece34146-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0004">2013</a>; Rogers et al., 
  <a rid="ece34146-bib-0148" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0148">2015</a>). Coral “gardening”, where corals are farmed in mid‐water structures then transplanted to colonies, has been successful, leading to increased reproduction and larval dispersal (Rinkevich, 
  <a rid="ece34146-bib-0144" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0144">2014</a>), for example, a 35% increase in oocyte production in farmed coral in Eilat, Red Sea (Amar &amp; Rinkevich, 
  <a rid="ece34146-bib-0005" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0005">2007</a>). Furthermore, coral transplantation could be used to reduce tourism exposure to natural reefs (Rogers et al., 
  <a rid="ece34146-bib-0148" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0148">2015</a>). These techniques are unlikely to provide larger‐scale solutions, yet can be effective locally.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Human‐assisted evolution of coral reef organisms is another novel management tool, whereby genetically modified stress‐tolerant corals are transplanted onto reefs (Anthony, 
  <a rid="ece34146-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0006">2016</a>; van Oppen et al., 
  <a rid="ece34146-bib-0164" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0164">2015</a>). This could also increase organisms’ resilience to environmental change by increasing resistance to stressors such as warming and acidification, and recovery from disturbances (van Oppen et al., 
  <a rid="ece34146-bib-0164" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0164">2015</a>), and could maintain important ecosystem services provided by corals (Anthony, 
  <a rid="ece34146-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0006">2016</a>). However, it could lead to a monopoly of a few resistant species, reducing overall biodiversity (Anthony, 
  <a rid="ece34146-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0006">2016</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
