<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece34146-sec-0006" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">CORAL REEF MANAGEMENT IN A CHANGING ENVIRONMENT</div>
 <sec id="ece34146-sec-0007" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.1</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Towards ecosystem‐based management of coral reefs</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conservation goals for coral reefs have traditionally focused on reversing declines and returning the ecosystem to “pristine” conditions (Rogers et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0148" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0148">2015</a>). However, many people rely on reefs for food and livelihoods and multi‐use of reefs requires careful consideration of the identification and understanding of trade‐offs among conflicting management and conservation objectives. This also requires a detailed understanding of the multiple stakeholders involved in direct use of and those involved in distal activities that could be impacting reefs, for example, in the case of land‐based pollution (Fredston‐Hermann et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0071" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0071">2016</a>) and logging (Hamilton et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0088" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0088">2017</a>). The type of management and conservation measures in place needs to take into account a combination of the changing environmental and human impacts as well as their potentially changing benefits.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Marine protected areas or no‐take marine reserves are the most common form of reef management, focusing predominantly on reducing local anthropogenic pressures (Agardy, di Sciara, &amp; Christie, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0003">2011</a>; Mellin, Aaron MacNeil, Cheal, Emslie, &amp; Julian Caley, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0122" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0122">2016</a>). The recent trend in designations of very large, remote MPAs such as the 640,000 km
   <span class="sup">2</span> Chagos MPA (Jones &amp; De Santo, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0103" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0103">2016</a>) to meet the 10% coverage target of the Convention on Biological Diversity may represent political rather than science‐based interests. These MPAs cost little to designate but may not be effective or representative (Jones &amp; De Santo, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0103" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0103">2016</a>). They do not protect the most threatened reefs—those associated with high human population densities—nor address social issues such as maintaining ecosystem services for those reliant on reefs for food or income (Sale et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0150" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0150">2014</a>). Their designation should not divert attention from management of more damaged coral reefs in highly populated areas.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There is increasing recognition that coral reef management has been unable to halt degradation, and that returning to “pristine” conditions is an unrealistic goal (Abelson et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0001">2016</a>; Burke et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0027">2011</a>; Hughes et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0098" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0098">2017</a>; Rinkevich, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0145" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0145">2015</a>), particularly in the context of changing environmental conditions. Conservation is moving away from this more traditional approach, as research seeks to provide conservation practitioners with a more diverse toolbox, including a range of indicators (Nash &amp; Graham, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0129" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0129">2016</a>) and modelling frameworks (McClanahan et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0115" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0115">2012</a>). The focus of management has changed from individual species and selected reefs, to management of the whole seascape, as the complexity of reef ecosystem responses to climate change and local human stressors has been realised (McClanahan, Graham, Macneil, &amp; Cinner, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0118" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0118">2015</a>; Olsson, Folke, &amp; Hughes, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0135" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0135">2008</a>; Weijerman et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0169" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0169">2015</a>). Ecosystem‐based management (EBM) is a more holistic framework, incorporating interactions within ecosystems and socialecological links, impacts of multiple stressors on key functional groups and ecosystem processes, with the goal of maintaining ecosystem functioning and services (Levin &amp; Lubchenco, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0110" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0110">2008</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The concept of resilience has been advocated and can be used to support the design and implementation of EBM (Hughes et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0098" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0098">2017</a>; Levin &amp; Lubchenco, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0110" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0110">2008</a>). Ecological resilience can be defined as the ability of an ecosystem to maintain the same structure and functioning in a changing environment, including resistance to stress and recovery from disturbances (Levin &amp; Lubchenco, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0110" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0110">2008</a>; McClanahan et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0115" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0115">2012</a>). One of the benefits of embedding this framework into EBM for reefs is that resilience of coral reefs has been relatively well studied, for example, in the context of recovery following disturbance events such as bleaching (Anthony, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0006">2016</a>) and socio‐ecological resilience (Cinner, Pratchett, et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0039">2016</a>; Kittinger, Finkbeiner, Glazier, &amp; Crowder, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0106" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0106">2012</a>). Vulnerability frameworks that integrate across ecological, social and economic aspects of coral reefs are an important part of developing adaptive and more integrated ecosystem management strategies under climate change (Cinner, Huchery, et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0036">2013</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the context of climate change, changes in underlying reef resilience could also occur if key recovery processes (such as recruitment, growth or dispersal) are impacted by climate change (Anthony, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0006">2016</a>). Management strategies could therefore enhance resilience to ongoing stressors (e.g., warming, sedimentation) and act directly to reduce the impacts of disturbances, such as control of CoTS (Anthony et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0008">2015</a>). Reducing local drivers of coral reef decline may increase the chances of re‐establishment of coral‐dominated reefs from degraded reefs which are themselves resistant to change (Graham et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0077" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0077">2013</a>). Maintaining resilience also means retaining diversity and functional redundancy in the face of change, managing ecosystem connectivity, understanding and managing feedbacks, and promoting social principles including encouraging education, broadening participation and advocating integration of multiple stakeholders (Biggs et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0020">2012</a>; Hughes et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0098" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0098">2017</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To maintain the resilience of social‐ecological systems to climate change, we advocate for the need to (1) minimise local stressors, (2) design MPAs that address not only local pressures but also incorporate measures to address global environmental change, (3) utilise active management approaches such as human‐assisted evolution and reef restoration, and (4) develop coordinated management and governance at multiple scales from local customary tenure and community participation, to broader‐scale MSP, to regulations at the international scale. Each of these approaches is considered in depth below.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece34146-sec-0008" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.2</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Minimising local stressors</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Reducing local anthropogenic impacts may make coral reefs more resilient to climate change and OA by reducing the harmful interaction with climate change factors (see Table 
   <a rid="ece34146-tbl-0001" ref-type="table" href="#ece34146-tbl-0001">1</a>) (Hoegh‐guldberg &amp; Bruno, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0094" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0094">2010</a>; Hughes et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0097" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0097">2003</a>; IGBP, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0101" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0101">2013</a>; Knowlton &amp; Jackson, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0107" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0107">2008</a>; Pandolfi et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0137" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0137">2011</a>). Reducing local stressors also buys time for coral reef species to adapt or acclimate (Hoegh‐Guldberg, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0093" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0093">2014</a>), especially in more thermally resistant coral reefs with higher adaptive potential (e.g., Carilli et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0029">2012</a>), such as in the northern Red Sea and Arabian Gulf (Coles &amp; Riegl, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0040">2013</a>; Fine, Gildor, &amp; Genin, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0067" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0067">2013</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A long‐term (20 years), large‐scale (150,000 km
   <span class="sup">2</span>) study of coral reef communities on the Great Barrier Reef provided strong evidence that reducing local anthropogenic impacts might make coral reefs more resilient to a range of stressors, including coral bleaching (Mellin et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0122" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0122">2016</a>). This was seen through 21%–38% higher stability of reef community composition, lower susceptibility to initial impacts, and 20% increased recovery times (Mellin et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0122" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0122">2016</a>). A simulation model for Bolinao in the Phillipines found that management of water quality, and to a lesser extent fishing, can significantly improve reef state under future climate change scenarios, by enhancing recovery after bleaching events (Gurney, Melbourne‐Thomas, Geronimo, Alino, &amp; Johnson, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0086" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0086">2013</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Increasing water quality through minimising sedimentation and nutrient enrichment could improve ecosystem health within decades (Fabricius, De’ath, McCook, Turak, &amp; Williams, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0060" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0060">2005</a>). Better watershed management through improved agricultural practices near rivers, restoration of riparian reserves along rivers and of coastal floodplains and returning to more natural flow regimes could reduce run‐off and nutrient enrichment (Kroon, Schaffelke, &amp; Bartley, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0108" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0108">2014</a>). Regulation of waste water could reduce bleaching severity (Wagner, Kramer, &amp; Van Woesik, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0168" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0168">2010</a>), while minimising sedimentation should reduce coral diseases (Pollock et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0140" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0140">2014</a>) and decreasing nutrient loads could allow more time for the adaptation of the coral–zooxanthellae symbiosis to global change (Wooldridge, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0174" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0174">2009</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On eliminating fishing in protected areas, reef resilience may be increased through a number of mechanisms: herbivory, reduced coral predation, maintaining structural complexity and increased response diversity, and promoting recovery from bleaching events (Adam, Burkepile, Ruttenberg, &amp; Paddack, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0002">2015</a>; Graham &amp; Nash, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0081" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0081">2013</a>; Graham et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0079" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0079">2015</a>; Mumby et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0124" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0124">2007</a>; Nash, Graham, Jennings, Wilson, &amp; Bellwood, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0130" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0130">2015</a>). No‐take marine reserves control fishing effort and enable fish populations to recover (Burke et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0027">2011</a>), but enforcement is often limited and reserves do not fulfil their function (McClanahan, Marnane, Cinner, &amp; Kiene, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0119" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0119">2006</a>; McClanahan et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0118" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0118">2015</a>). Determining the carrying capacity of fish biomass in relation to environmental and anthropogenic variables could help managers to develop reference levels that would reduce trade‐offs between fisheries’ objectives and the protection of reef function (Valdivia, Cox, &amp; Bruno, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0162" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0162">2017</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Alternative fishing restrictions, such as controlling species caught, fishing gear and access, and seasonal closures of breeding sites, can be successful at sustaining fish biomass while maintaining key ecosystem functions such as herbivory (Burke et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0027">2011</a>; MacNeil et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0111" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0111">2015</a>; McClanahan et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0118" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0118">2015</a>; Nash, Abesamis, Graham, McClure, &amp; Moland, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0128" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0128">2016</a>). Setting fisheries targets is challenging due to the multiple species with diverse ecological functions, however total catch biomass alone can provide easy, effective targets where more information is not available (McClanahan et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0118" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0118">2015</a>). Climate change and certain fishing gears may simultaneously select for functionally important species. For example, spear guns target specific herbivorous species that are susceptible to climate change, and as a result, restrictions on spear‐guns could be a targeted strategy for supporting reefs under pressure from climate change (Cinner et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0038" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0038">2009</a>). A key challenge is the quantification of the full suite of ecological, social and economic trade‐offs associated with changes in any of the management levers that are used, but this could be addressed using management strategy evaluation (Fulton, Smith, Smith, &amp; Johnson, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0074" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0074">2014</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece34146-sec-0009" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.3</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Marine protected areas</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The efficacy of current MPAs is debatable. A meta‐analysis of 310 MPAs found coral cover remained stable within MPAs but declined in fished areas outside, while marine reserves can successfully maintain reef fish biomass, but only in high compliance with MPA regulations (Cinner, Huchery, et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0037">2016</a>). A recent study in the GBR suggests MPAs can increase coral reef resilience to natural disturbances exacerbated by climate change, such as coral bleaching, disease and storms (Mellin et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0122" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0122">2016</a>), while in the Seychelles recovery after a bleaching event was faster within MPAs provided macroalgal cover was low (Wilson et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0172" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0172">2012</a>). However, several studies have not shown measurable positive impacts (Bruno &amp; Valdivia, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0026">2016</a>; Graham et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0080" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0080">2008</a>, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0079" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0079">2015</a>; Selig, Casey, &amp; Bruno, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0153" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0153">2012</a>), and many MPAs are small, with low enforcement and compliance, and as such do not achieve management objectives (Norström et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0132" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0132">2016</a>; Sale et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0150" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0150">2014</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Given limited conservation resources (McCarthy et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0114" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0114">2012</a>) and the time needed to produce positive benefits within MPAs (McClanahan &amp; Graham, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0116" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0116">2015</a>), investing in MPAs without considering future threats may result in them becoming less effective over time (McLeod, Salm, Green, &amp; Almany, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0121" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0121">2009</a>). If MPAs are to support the resilience of coral reefs in the face of climate change, providing time for acclimation, adaptation or dispersal by reef species, forward looking design is critical (Ban et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0017">2011</a>; Lawler, Watson, &amp; Game, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0109" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0109">2015</a>; McLeod et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0121" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0121">2009</a>). Although research has highlighted general characteristics of effective MPAs today (no‐take, enforced, old, large and isolated) (Edgar et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0055">2014</a>), other factors need to be considered in a high‐CO
   <sub>2</sub> world. MPA design needs to address future scenarios in addition to present issues (Makino et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0113" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0113">2014</a>, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0112" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0112">2015</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">New MPAs should protect key areas under a range of future environmental scenarios. Key areas include locations where change is more gradual (“climate refugia”), ecologically important areas including fish spawning aggregations, and areas predicted to be more resilient in the long‐term, such as those with high herbivore populations and low sedimentation (Ban et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0017">2011</a>; Graham et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0080" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0080">2008</a>; Groves et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0085" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0085">2012</a>; McLeod et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0121" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0121">2009</a>). Recent research has also highlighted the importance of protecting degraded reefs in addition to healthy, resilient ones, due to their increasing percentage of global reef area (Abelson et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0001">2016</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Small, unconnected MPAs are unsustainable as the surrounding seascape also needs to be managed, often in MPA networks (McLeod et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0121" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0121">2009</a>). MPA networks in particular should replicate habitat types within them (“spreading risk”), maintain ecological connectivity to facilitate recruitment and dispersal, and sustain not just biodiversity but ecosystem functioning and services, and key functional groups such as herbivorous fish (Groves et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0085" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0085">2012</a>; Lawler et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0109" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0109">2015</a>; McLeod et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0121" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0121">2009</a>; Mumby &amp; Steneck, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0125" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0125">2008</a>). MPA placement should therefore reflect both current and future species distributions where ranges are expected to change, to facilitate dispersal (Makino et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0113" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0113">2014</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Implementing MPAs that have been effectively designed to meet climate change objectives is not always sufficient because implementation does not always equate to compliance (McClanahan et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0119" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0119">2006</a>). A total of 70% of coral reefs are found in developing nations with low enforcement capacity (Ban et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0017">2011</a>); thus, MPAs may suffer from poor compliance (McClanahan et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0119" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0119">2006</a>), which can have serious consequences for their effectiveness (McClanahan &amp; Graham, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0116" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0116">2015</a>). Including local stakeholders in MPA planning and design may drive improved levels of compliance and improve reef resilience outcomes (Cinner, Huchery, et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0037">2016</a>). Bottom‐up, participatory management and conservation approaches that account for the local context are central to successful management outcomes on many coral reefs, particularly in developing nations (Christie et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0033">2009</a>; Norström et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0132" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0132">2016</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">MPAs that are planned, designed and implemented using participatory approaches and with explicit climate change objectives represent an important strategy in marine management. The benefits of an MPA could spill over into surrounding areas supporting fisheries (Harrison et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0090" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0090">2012</a>; Hughes et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0099" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0099">2010</a>; McCook et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0120" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0120">2010</a>), although benefits are unlikely to be distributed evenly, introducing issues of inequity (Cinner et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0034">2014</a>; Daw et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0044" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0044">2015</a>). Furthermore, MPAs are unlikely to be a cure‐all for coral reef conservation because they do not provide direct protection from external impacts such as sedimentation from land run‐off (Fabricius et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0060" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0060">2005</a>; Gilby, Maxwell, Tibbetts, &amp; Stevens, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0076" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0076">2015</a>), and may only be effective at maintaining ecosystem services in reefs of high structural complexity (Rogers et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0148" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0148">2015</a>). Where structural complexity is lost, reefs are heavily degraded, climate change impacts are unpredictable and there is high reliance on reefs, MPAs will need to be combined with other management approaches (Abelson et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0001">2016</a>; Graham et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0077" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0077">2013</a>; Makino et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0112" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0112">2015</a>; Rogers et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0148" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0148">2015</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece34146-sec-0010" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.4</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Active management approaches</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On degraded reefs, removal of human pressures may be insufficient to facilitate recovery to coral‐dominated ecosystems, suggesting that active reef restoration may be necessary to maintain healthy ecosystems more resilient to climate change (Abelson et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0001">2016</a>; Adam et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0002">2015</a>; Rogers et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0148" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0148">2015</a>). Introducing artificial complexity to replace the lost habitat structures of low complexity reefs, for example due to acidification, has been successful at small scales such as in the Gulf of Aqaba, Red Sea (Al‐Horani &amp; Khalaf, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0004">2013</a>; Rogers et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0148" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0148">2015</a>). Coral “gardening”, where corals are farmed in mid‐water structures then transplanted to colonies, has been successful, leading to increased reproduction and larval dispersal (Rinkevich, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0144" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0144">2014</a>), for example, a 35% increase in oocyte production in farmed coral in Eilat, Red Sea (Amar &amp; Rinkevich, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0005" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0005">2007</a>). Furthermore, coral transplantation could be used to reduce tourism exposure to natural reefs (Rogers et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0148" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0148">2015</a>). These techniques are unlikely to provide larger‐scale solutions, yet can be effective locally.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Human‐assisted evolution of coral reef organisms is another novel management tool, whereby genetically modified stress‐tolerant corals are transplanted onto reefs (Anthony, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0006">2016</a>; van Oppen et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0164" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0164">2015</a>). This could also increase organisms’ resilience to environmental change by increasing resistance to stressors such as warming and acidification, and recovery from disturbances (van Oppen et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0164" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0164">2015</a>), and could maintain important ecosystem services provided by corals (Anthony, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0006">2016</a>). However, it could lead to a monopoly of a few resistant species, reducing overall biodiversity (Anthony, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0006">2016</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece34146-sec-0011" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.5</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Combining different tiers of conservation management with spatial planning</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conservation management cannot focus solely on biodiversity measures or maintaining pristine reefs in remote locations. Six million fishers from nearly 100 countries rely on coral reefs for their livelihoods (Teh, Teh, &amp; Sumaila, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0159" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0159">2013</a>); therefore, management needs to support the resilience of both coral reefs and the communities that depend on them (Anthony et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0008">2015</a>; Cinner, Pratchett, et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0039">2016</a>). Climate change impacts on reef social‐ecological systems are bi‐directional: how climate change impacts on communities determines how they then interact with the environment. For example, if climate change and local human pressures reduce local fish populations, will fishers look further afield for more fish, or turn to alternative incomes (Cinner, Pratchett, et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0039">2016</a>)? Such impacts are poorly understood, so the resilience of social‐ecological systems to climate change cannot be predicted.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Reducing dependency on fishing is imperative to protecting coral reefs, but highly challenging in societies with population growth, a lack of alternative income sources and poor governance (Burke et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0027">2011</a>; Newton, Côté, Pilling, Jennings, &amp; Dulvy, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0131" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0131">2007</a>). These factors cannot be managed by conservation practitioners; however, management strategies built upon access rights, particularly, customary tenure are gaining traction (Christie et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0033">2009</a>; Jupiter, Cohen, Weeks, Tawake, &amp; Govan, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0105" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0105">2014</a>). A key study of over 2,500 reefs globally showed that reefs doing better than predicted from their environmental and social context commonly had customary management schemes and marine tenure (Cinner, Huchery, et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0037">2016</a>). In contrast, reefs doing worse than predicted had technological commonalities such as intensive netting methods (Cinner, Huchery, et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0037">2016</a>). These findings suggest reef management may benefit from integrating customary and/or marine tenure arrangements, and gear restrictions rather than focusing solely on MPAs. These arrangements arise within indigenous communities or kinship groups and restrict certain behaviours, for example fishing at specific times or locations. Importantly, these restrictions may support key reef functions and processes, with positive implications for coral reef resilience (Aswani, Albert, Sabetian, &amp; Furusawa, 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0013">2007</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Further considerations often overlooked are large‐scale or “distal” human drivers of coral reef degradation, which influence local anthropogenic threats such as fishing and pollution (Hughes et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0098" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0098">2017</a>). These include international demand for certain species for food or the aquarium trade; increasing human migration (which may be exacerbated by climate change); foreign investments driving land use change; and changing fishing effort (Cinner, Graham, et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0035">2013</a>; Norström et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0132" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0132">2016</a>; Rhyne et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0143" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0143">2012</a>; Sale et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0150" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0150">2014</a>). Broader management strategies, especially marine spatial planning, need to be used to combat these external drivers. MSP incorporates MPAs and zoning, supports key ecosystem services, and separates conflicting uses of marine resources, for example by dividing coastal waters for different activities (e.g., conservation, food security and livelihoods) and integrating local and regional targets (Agardy et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0003">2011</a>; Sale et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0150" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0150">2014</a>). This approach compensates for many of the deficits of MPAs on their own, incorporating them into a broader system of management and preventing degradation of surrounding areas (Agardy et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0003">2011</a>). It should also reduce conflicts, maintain ecosystem services, and can facilitate rights‐based governance (Sale et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0150" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0150">2014</a>). For instance, models for a national spatial plan for Belize which quantified ecosystem services led to a 25% increase in coastal protection with increases in tourism and doubling of fishing revenue when contrasted with models only including stakeholder views (Arkema et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0012">2015</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Prioritisation of goals at national and regional scales, the inclusion of ecosystem services, and broad, coordinated conservation planning are essential to protecting coral reefs. Successful implementation of MSP will require adaptation to local need and governance, participation of communities and stakeholders, political motivation at national and international levels, and support from NGOs and international development partners. Internationally, regulation of markets and the aquarium trade could reduce demands on coral reefs by ensuring fish are caught through sustainable measures (Burke et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0027">2011</a>). For example, international screening for the effects of cyanide poisoning on live fish could promote sustainable fishing (Calado et al., 
   <a rid="ece34146-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0028">2014</a>). From local, rights‐based management, through to regional and national marine planning and international laws and regulations on trade, coral reef conservation is a multi‐scale objective requiring support from a wide variety of stakeholders and organisations.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
