<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece34146-sec-0001" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">INTRODUCTION: INCREASING THREATS TO CORAL REEF ECOSYSTEMS</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Coral reefs are extremely diverse and valuable ecosystems, providing habitat for a third of marine species in just 0.2% of the ocean (Pandolfi, Connolly, Marshall, &amp; Cohen, 
  <a rid="ece34146-bib-0137" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0137">2011</a>). They provide important ecosystem services to over 450 million people living within 100 km of them (Crabbe, 
  <a rid="ece34146-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0042">2008</a>; Pandolfi et al., 
  <a rid="ece34146-bib-0137" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0137">2011</a>), including fisheries, tourism, building materials, and protection from storm waves and coastal erosion. As such, they are valued at US$350,000 per year for an “average” hectare of coral reef (De Groot et al., 
  <a rid="ece34146-bib-0045" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0045">2012</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Yet, coral reefs are under severe threat. Because they exist in coastal waters, they are vulnerable to the effects of human activities, with very few pristine reefs left (Bellwood, Hughes, Folke, &amp; Nyström, 
  <a rid="ece34146-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0019">2004</a>; Graham, Cinner, Norstrom, &amp; Nystrom, 
  <a rid="ece34146-bib-0078" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0078">2014</a>). An estimated two‐thirds of coral reef fish have been lost compared to historical baselines (Edgar et al., 
  <a rid="ece34146-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0055">2014</a>), with fish biomass decreasing closer to major markets (Cinner, Graham, Huchery, &amp; Macneil, 
  <a rid="ece34146-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0035">2013</a>; Cinner, Huchery, et al., 
  <a rid="ece34146-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0037">2016</a>). Besides local pressures, coral reefs are facing additional threats from anthropogenic carbon emissions.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The amount of carbon dioxide (CO
  <sub>2</sub>) in the atmosphere has increased from 280 to ~405 ppm since the industrial revolution (Dlugokencky &amp; Tans, 
  <a rid="ece34146-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0049">2017</a>), despite a third of all emissions having been absorbed by the oceans (Feely, Doney, &amp; Cooley, 
  <a rid="ece34146-bib-0066" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0066">2009</a>). There are two overarching effects of CO
  <sub>2</sub> and other greenhouse gas emissions on marine systems. First, upper oceans have already been warmed by 0.11°C per decade between 1971 and 2010 (Rhein et al., 
  <a rid="ece34146-bib-0142" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0142">2013</a>), and by 2100 the average temperature is predicted to have increased by 12°C (Scott, 
  <a rid="ece34146-bib-0152" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0152">2016</a>). There are likely to be more frequent extreme high‐temperature events, such as those associated with El Niño‐southern oscillation (ENSO) (Frieler et al., 
  <a rid="ece34146-bib-0073" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0073">2012</a>). Second, increased emissions have caused lower ocean pH, decreased carbonate ion concentrations and reduced the saturation state of aragonite (Ωa)—together known as “ocean acidification” (OA) (Doney, Fabry, Feely, &amp; Kleypas, 
  <a rid="ece34146-bib-0051" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0051">2009</a>; Orr et al., 
  <a rid="ece34146-bib-0136" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0136">2005</a>). pH has already declined by 0.1 units (Doney et al., 
  <a rid="ece34146-bib-0051" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0051">2009</a>; Orr et al., 
  <a rid="ece34146-bib-0136" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0136">2005</a>; Yeakel et al., 
  <a rid="ece34146-bib-0177" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0177">2015</a>), with a further reduction of 0.3–0.4 units predicted by 2,100 (Feely et al., 
  <a rid="ece34146-bib-0066" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0066">2009</a>; Orr et al., 
  <a rid="ece34146-bib-0136" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0136">2005</a>). Furthermore, on a more localised scale, tropical storms are predicted to increase in frequency and intensity due to climate change. Such storms can cause devastating damage to coral reefs, for example accounting for 42% of the coral loss in the Great Barrier Reef (GBR) from 1985 to 2012 (De’ath, Fabricius, Sweatman, &amp; Puotinen, 
  <a rid="ece34146-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0047">2012</a>; Emanuel, 
  <a rid="ece34146-bib-0056" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0056">2013</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In 2016, record high temperatures caused the third global‐scale mass coral bleaching event—a key consequence of climate change‐affecting 93% of reefs in the GBR, one of the most recognised and well‐managed ecosystems on the planet (ARC Centre of Excellence for Coral Reef Studies, 
  <a rid="ece34146-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0010">2016</a>). Corals were hit again by bleaching in 2017, altogether severely affecting two‐thirds of the reef in consecutive years (ARC Centre of Excellence for Coral Reef Studies, 
  <a rid="ece34146-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34146-bib-0011">2017</a>) and making this the most extreme bleaching event ever recorded globally. While local managers cannot address the global impacts of ocean warming and acidification, research has sought to provide ways to mitigate against them.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We review recent advances in our understanding of the impacts of ocean warming, acidification and other anthropogenic pressures on coral reef ecosystems, including organism and community responses to their changing environments. We argue the need to integrate ecosystem‐based management and resilience thinking, and then review management and governance strategies for coral reefs under future environmental change. These include the need for climate‐ready marine protected areas (MPAs), alternative mechanisms for reducing local anthropogenic stressors, active management, participatory conservation strategies and marine spatial planning (MSP). We provide an overview of the huge conservation effort necessary to preserve coral reefs and their ecosystem services, and support the communities dependent upon them.</p>
</sec>
