<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Several approaches have been used to select environmental datasets for ecological niche modeling; the best environmental datasets would be ecological relevant to species in question [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006021.ref029" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>]. At regional and continental scales, climatic factors have excellent predictive power in determining risk associated with disease transmission (e.g. schistosomiasis [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006021.ref025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="pntd.0006021.ref026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>], West Nile virus [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006021.ref030" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>]). Hence, we used subsets of the 19 bioclimatic variables developed by Hijmans et al. [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006021.ref031" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>], chosen as follow. First, variables that combined temperature and precipitation (i.e. mean temperature of wettest quarter, mean temperature of driest quarter, precipitation of warmest quarter, precipitation of coldest quarter) were excluded because they display artificial discontinuities between adjacent grid cells in some areas [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006021.ref032" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>]. The importance of each of the remaining 15 variables was assessed by a jackknife analysis of variable importance in Maxent ([
 <xref rid="pntd.0006021.ref033" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>], see below for Maxent detail), and unimportant variables were discarded. Highly correlated variables were then removed in SDMtoolbox, a python-based GIS toolkit for spatial analysis [
 <xref rid="pntd.0006021.ref034" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>]. Eight variables (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pntd.0006021.s001" class="xref">S1 Table</xref>) that showed ecological relevance (regularized training gain &gt;0.14) and low correlation with other variables (Pearson correlation &lt;0.9) were chosen in the end. All variables were analyzed at a spatial resolution of 2.5 minute.
</p>
