<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Climate change is projected to have cascading effects on estuarine and freshwater ecosystems. In addition to rising water temperature and sea level (
 <xref rid="coy076C76" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">IPCC, 2013</xref>), predicted increases in extreme weather events with climate change are already occurring in some locations. In particular, increased frequency and duration of drought periods are occurring in California and may exacerbate the warming effects of climate change on the San Francisco Estuary (SFE), which includes San Francisco Bay and a tidal freshwater Delta complex formed by the confluence of Sacramento and San Joaquin Rivers (see map of the SFE in Fig. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="coy076F1" class="xref">1</xref>). Already, drought periods in the SFE have shown associated increases in water temperature (
 <xref rid="coy076C33" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Jeffries 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2016
 </xref>), and changes in salinity regimes may be correlated (
 <xref rid="coy076C12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Cloern 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2011
 </xref>). Although precipitation in California is not consistently predicted to decrease (
 <xref rid="coy076C15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Dettinger 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2015
 </xref>), and may even increase with warming (
 <xref rid="coy076C59" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Polade 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2017
 </xref>), the greater incidence of rainfall versus snowfall means that summertime conditions of the SFE are likely to have lower outflows, from decreased influence of snow melt, and increased salinity. Increased temperature and salinity regimes in the SFE ecosystem may lead to negative impacts on biological communities (
 <xref rid="coy076C37" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Knowles and Cayan, 2002</xref>; 
 <xref rid="coy076C12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Cloern 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2011
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="coy076C11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Cloern and Jassby, 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="coy076C46" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Mahardja 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2017
 </xref>). Already, entire SFE fish assemblages have declined in abundance (a trend called the Pelagic Organism Decline [POD]) including native Osmerids, with some to near extinction (
 <xref rid="coy076C9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Brown and Moyle, 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="coy076C22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Feyrer 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2007
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="coy076C66" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Sommer 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2007
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="coy076C71" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Thomson 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2010
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="coy076C28" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hobbs 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2017
 </xref>). While some of the declines have been attributed to impacts to food web dynamics caused by the invasive overbite clam (
 <xref rid="coy076C21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Feyrer 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2003
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="coy076C44" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Mac Nally 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2010
 </xref>), non-native predators (
 <xref rid="coy076C1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Baerwald 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2012
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="coy076C62" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Schreier 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2016
 </xref>), and physical changes including altered hydrologic regimes (
 <xref rid="coy076C6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Brown and Bauer, 2010</xref>) and increasing water clarity (
 <xref rid="coy076C44" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Mac Nally 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2010
 </xref>), it remains unclear how multiple stressors of climate change, such as elevated temperature and salinity interact to affect fish survival and in doing so, influence population abundance and distribution. SFE inflow is highly regulated seasonally for economic uses and maintaining fish habitat, creating substantial conflicts over resource use (
 <xref rid="coy076C63" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Service, 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="coy076C52" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Moyle 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2018
 </xref>). Therefore, a better understanding of fish vulnerability to elevated temperature and elevated salinity may provide insight into some of how best to balance conservation efforts for California’s native fishes while also managing the state’s water supply (
 <xref rid="coy076C7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Brown 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2013
 </xref>).
</p>
