<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We used a total of 10 abundant and representative species from three different phyla (cnidaria, porifera, and tunicata) and four different growth forms (including encrusting, massive, cup and/or tree‐like forms) that are commonly and ubiquitously found in Mediterranean coralligenous assemblages over the whole Mediterranean basin (Ballesteros, 
 <xref rid="ece35045-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>; Casas‐Güell, Teixidó, Garrabou, &amp; Cebrian, 
 <xref rid="ece35045-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). Specifically, we used three species of anthozoans (cnidarians): 
 <italic class="italic">Parazoanthus axinellae</italic>(Schmidt, 1862)
 <italic class="italic">, Leptopsammia pruvoti</italic>(de Lacaze‐Duthiers, 1897), and 
 <italic class="italic">Alcyonium acaule</italic> (Marion, 1878); six species of demosponges (poriferans): 
 <italic class="italic">Agelas oroides</italic>(Schmidt, 1864), 
 <italic class="italic">Axinella polypoides</italic> (Schmidt, 1862), 
 <italic class="italic">Axinella damicornis</italic> (Esper, 2784), 
 <italic class="italic">Crambe crambe</italic> (Schmidt, 1862), 
 <italic class="italic">Dysidea avara</italic> (Schmidt, 1862), and
 <italic class="italic"> Petrosia ficiformis</italic> (Poiret, 1789); and one species of ascidian (tunicate): 
 <italic class="italic">Cystodytes dellechiajei</italic>(Della Valle, 1877) (See Supporting information Methods 
 <xref rid="ece35045-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S1</xref>, Figure 
 <xref rid="ece35045-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S1</xref> and Table 
 <xref rid="ece35045-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S1</xref>). For 
 <italic class="italic">Parazoanthus axinellae</italic>, two different and easily distinguished morphotypes were used: the rather yellow and thin “slender” morphotype, which mostly lives in rocky substrates but can also usually be found as an epibiont on demosponges, and the bright orange “stocky” morphotype, which is mainly found in primary substrates (Cachet et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35045-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). We distinguished between these two morphotypes because of the ongoing scientific debate about whether they could, in fact, be two separated species (Cachet et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35045-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). Moreover, the presence of highly bioactive secondary metabolites, named “parazoanthines,” in only the “slender” morphotype could potentially lead to contrasting responses to warming between these two morphotypes, as secondary metabolites are usually associated in plants and many benthic organisms with protection against different abiotic and biotic stresses, including warming (Bennett &amp; Wallsgrove, 
 <xref rid="ece35045-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1994</xref>; Cachet et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35045-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Reverter, Perez, Ereskovsky, &amp; Banaigs, 
 <xref rid="ece35045-bib-0057" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>).
</p>
