<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The evidence suggests that future climate change, if not mitigated, will very likely impact the length of the transmission season and the geographical range of a significant proportion of infectious diseases.
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" class="xref">18</xref> On a broader scale, climate change will reshuffle the geographical distribution of animal species, and one of the most prominent illustrations of this is an image of a starving polar bear, released by the National Geographic Society in December 2017. The direct impact of climate change on habitat, and therefore ecosystem change, combined with increasing anthropogenic pressure on the natural environment, is severely affecting biodiversity, further impacting the emergence and transmission of infectious diseases.
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" class="xref">19</xref> An important point to emphasize is that of attribution and detection: how can recent spatiotemporal changes in infectious diseases be attributed, wholly or in part, to long‐term anthropogenic climate change? This is a complicated question to answer, hindered by the lack of good quality health and climate datasets over long time periods, by the various nonclimatic factors at play and by the influence of natural climate variability modes that are now occurring in a warmer background, such as the crucial El Niño Southern Oscillation. The latter issue led to controversy over the attribution of climate change effects on recent malaria changes observed in the East African highlands.
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" class="xref">20</xref>, 
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" class="xref">21</xref>, 
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" class="xref">22</xref>, 
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" class="xref">23</xref>, 
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" class="xref">24</xref>, 
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" class="xref">25</xref>, 
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" class="xref">26</xref> However, there is clear evidence that climate change has already affected the latitudinal and altitudinal ranges of avian malaria in wild birds.
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" class="xref">27</xref>, 
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" class="xref">28</xref> The health of wild animals, particularly birds, is assumed to be a better indicator of early climate change effects because very little or no control measures are undertaken to protect them.
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" class="xref">29</xref>, 
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0030" ref-type="ref" class="xref">30</xref> VBDs seriously affect the health of domestic animals and livestock (e.g., trypanosomiasis, Rift Valley Fever, and bluetongue), and consequently, climate change will also indirectly affect our health through its multifaceted impacts on food security, including livestock and plant crops.
</p>
