<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Once central authority and the urban framework collapsed, the irrigation and drainage systems—those that had made the environs of Tel Dan down to the Hula Valley a highly productive system—were no longer maintained, and the valley reverted to its marshy, disease-ridden former self (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4" class="xref">Fig. 4</xref>). To understand what ensued in and around Tel Dan during these periods, a parallel can be drawn with the settlement pattern of the Hula Valley from the medieval period up until the 19th century CE (
 <xref rid="R49" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">49</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R63" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">63</italic>
 </xref>–
 <xref rid="R66" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">66</italic>
 </xref>). Lacking a strong central authority to manage drainage and irrigation systems after the Mongol raids (~1240 CE) (
 <xref rid="R67" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">67</italic>
 </xref>), marshes expanded in the valley up to Tel Dan. Irrigation reservoirs, channels, and sluices were left to decay, creating a “muddy wilderness” (
 <xref rid="R63" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">63</italic>
 </xref>) infected by water-borne diseases, mainly malaria (
 <italic class="italic">Plasmodium</italic>), spread by the mosquito genus 
 <italic class="italic">Anopheles</italic> (
 <xref rid="R64" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">64</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R68" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">68</italic>
 </xref>). Since Hippocrates (5th century BCE) and, later, in the Roman Empire period, malaria has been related to marshes (
 <xref rid="R69" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">69</italic>
 </xref>), with the disease interpreted as a miasma arising from the marshes (
 <xref rid="R70" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">70</italic>
 </xref>). Nomad inhabitants moved out of the Hula Valley during summer time when the densities of mosquito larva and adults are higher (
 <xref rid="R71" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">71</italic>
 </xref>) and returned for the sowing of sorghum and rice planting; however, malaria was so widespread that the disease controlled the density of Bedouin populations (
 <xref rid="R67" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">67</italic>
 </xref>). In the 19th to 20th centuries CE, the Bedouins who lived in the Hula Valley (“Buhairat al Hula” in Arabic) only maintained their permanent settlements because of a constant but low-level influx of population. Marshes offered inhabitants only a marginal subsistence, and heat and malaria worsened the harsh and challenging conditions (
 <xref rid="R72" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">72</italic>
 </xref>). Their subsistence lifestyle was based on resources from the marshes (for example, papyrus harvest), from animals (water buffalo and cattle), and from agriculture (maize, rice, and wheat) in and around the wetlands (
 <xref rid="R64" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">64</italic>
 </xref>), similar to that of the Ma’Dan Marsh Arabs of the Tigris-Euphrates marshes in southern Iraq (
 <xref rid="R73" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">73</italic>
 </xref>). Mortality rates were extremely high due to chronic disease (
 <xref rid="R63" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">63</italic>
 </xref>) and to fecal-oral pathogens transmitted through the consumption of stagnant water (diarrheal disease or gastrointestinal illnesses).
</p>
