<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Malaria was so alarming for populations that, between 1951 and 1958 CE, the wetland was drained not only to expand agricultural production but also to eliminate water-borne disease (
 <xref rid="R64" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">64</italic>
 </xref>). According to our data from Tel Dan, conditions for malaria became optimal during periods when the city became a low-density village (~2500 to 1950 BCE, ~1050 to 840 BCE, and since ~550 BCE), with the abandonment of irrigation and drainage systems during periods of reduced inputs from Mount Hermon, collectively resulting in organically polluted basins, ponds, and puddles of stagnant water. Malaria, wrongly interpreted as being imported by the crusaders (
 <xref rid="R63" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">63</italic>
 </xref>), was a well-established scourge in the Levant. Its spread is thought to have started between 10,000 and 5000 years ago in Africa and the Middle East, favored by the emergence of agriculture and early urban development (
 <xref rid="R74" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">74</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R75" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">75</italic>
 </xref>). The earliest evidence for Bronze Age malaria in the Eastern Mediterranean comes from Egypt, where genetic fingerprinting of Tutankhamun’s body has revealed traces of the disease (first regnal year 1348 to 1339 BCE) (
 <xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">37</italic>
 </xref>), as well as in Tutankhamun’s immediate lineage (
 <xref rid="R76" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">76</italic>
 </xref>) and in mummy tissues in tomb complexes dating from the New Kingdom to the Late Period (
 <xref rid="R77" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">77</italic>
 </xref>). Malaria was endemic to the Nile Valley at least as early as the 2nd millennium BCE (
 <xref rid="R76" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">76</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R78" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">78</italic>
 </xref>) and probably as early as the 4th millennium BCE (
 <xref rid="R79" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">79</italic>
 </xref>). Many Egyptians would have been carriers of malaria. Egyptians were resident in the Jordan Valley at least as early as the Late Bronze Age, ~1500 BCE (
 <xref rid="R80" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">80</italic>
 </xref>–
 <xref rid="R82" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">82</italic>
 </xref>). They also arrived as settlers to the coastal plain of the southern Levant in the Early Bronze Age in the late 4th millennium BCE (
 <xref rid="R83" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">83</italic>
 </xref>). It is near certain that malaria was a key factor in shaping human lifestyles in the lowlands of ancient Canaan (
 <xref rid="R84" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">84</italic>
 </xref>). The Nile Valley and the Nile Delta were vast marshy areas and, consequently, perfect breeding grounds for 
 <italic class="italic">Anopheles</italic> (
 <xref rid="R76" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">76</italic>
 </xref>), similar to the Dan area down to the Hula Valley.
</p>
