<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The great disturbances promoted by factors associated with climate change in plant communities reflect their impact on essentially all levels of plant organization. In fact, over the last years, numerous studies have demonstrated the diversity of strategies and defense mechanisms of plants exposed to extreme weather events, as well as the factors related to tree mortality under those conditions (Allen et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>; Anderegg, Flint, et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>; Anderegg, Hicke, et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>; Bennett, McDowell, Allen, &amp; Anderson‐Teixeira, 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0032" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>; Choat et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0050" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>; Liang et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0130" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>; McDowell et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0157" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>; Mitchell et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0160" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>; Park Williams et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0178" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>; Rodríguez‐Calcerrada et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0191" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>; Tognetti &amp; Palombo, 
 <xref rid="ece35663-bib-0227" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>). However, although our understanding of the mechanisms behind forest dieback has grown considerably, the knowledge about this topic still remains very fragmented. Therefore, the present review aimed to provide a broad and integrated perspective of the main biochemical, physiological, and morpho‐anatomical disorders associated with exposure to the stress factors triggered by extreme climatic events (mainly drought, flooding, and global warming), which may compromise the performance and, ultimately, the survival of tree species and forest ecosystems in a global scale. In addition, we also discuss the controversial effects of high [CO
 <sub>2</sub>] in enhancing plant growth and reducing the deleterious effects of some extreme climatic events. We conclude with a discussion about the possible effects that the factors associated with the climate change might have on species distribution and forest composition.
</p>
