<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Empirical evidence of quantitative effects of vertebrate predation on leaf damage is scarce, especially for European temperate forest ecosystems. Whether and in what manner the effects of vertebrate predation on intensity of arthropod herbivory can be quantified and associated with predator diversity, forest composition and tree age are of central importance for a deeper understanding of ecosystem processes and the role of diversity on its function.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In accordance with our expectations, this study convincingly shows that the exclusion of birds and bats from tree crowns of the temperate tree species 
  <span class="italic">Quercus robur</span> results in significantly higher intensity of arthropod herbivory. This result provides strong evidence that the consumption of herbivorous arthropods by birds and bats represents an important ecosystem service of predators in temperate forest canopies.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although we could not include an analysis of the type and number of herbivorous arthropods in our work, the distinct increase in herbivory within the exclusions suggests that birds and bats limit arthropod feeding activity by reducing their numbers. We propose that the increase of leaf damage measured as the loss in leaf area and the increase in the mean number of holes per leaf in netted oak trees (young and mature trees) are based on an increase of arthropod abundance. Our estimates of leaf damage are in accordance with other studies on understorey plants (e.g. bilberry stands, coffee, vines, tree saplings) in northern Europe and in north and central America. There, insectivorous birds have been shown to reduce arthropod populations, mainly caterpillars, to about half of their population density and leaf damage to around 50% 
  <a rid="pone.0017857-Marquis1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0017857-Marquis1">[12]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0017857-Gradwohl1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0017857-Gradwohl1">[20]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0017857-Greenberg1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0017857-Greenberg1">[22]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0017857-Schwenk1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0017857-Schwenk1">[27]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0017857-Holmes1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0017857-Holmes1">[40]</a>. Thus, herbivory control through vertebrate insectivores is undoubtedly an important process affecting leaf damage in temperate forest canopies of both young and mature trees in Europe. The extent of the top-down control, however, differs in relation to the age of trees and the composition of forest stands, which strongly influence predator diversity; increasing forest age and tree species diversity are known to increase bird and bat diversity 
  <a rid="pone.0017857-GilTena1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0017857-GilTena1">[41]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0017857-Kalcounis1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0017857-Kalcounis1">[42]</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Leaf damage was greater in young relative to mature trees, suggesting that young trees harbour more herbivores than mature oaks, as seen in other tree species 
  <a rid="pone.0017857-Sanz1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0017857-Sanz1">[13]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0017857-VanBael2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0017857-VanBael2">[14]</a>. This pattern might be linked in part to the amount of secondary metabolites produced by the plants. Secondary metabolites such as tannins form part of the chemical defence of a plant against herbivorous arthropods and usually occur at lower concentrations in the leaves of young than in the leaves of mature trees, as they are costly to produce 
  <a rid="pone.0017857-Feeny2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0017857-Feeny2">[32]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0017857-Coley1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0017857-Coley1">[43]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0017857-Brossa1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0017857-Brossa1">[45]</a>. Another reason for the higher intensity of arthropod herbivory on young trees might be that the relatively dense tree crowns of young trees provide less favourable foraging grounds for foliage-gleaning birds and bats that are active in the canopy and that prefer more open spaces 
  <a rid="pone.0017857-Bhm1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0017857-Bhm1">[36]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0017857-Schnitzler1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0017857-Schnitzler1">[46]</a>. These assumptions are in agreement with our observations on the Schwäbische Alb where species richness of foliage-gleaning birds was lower in the vicinity of young oaks compared with mature trees.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We cannot rule out that differences in leaf damage between young and mature trees of the Schwäbische Alb might also be influenced by annual fluctuations in arthropod abundance as we sampled young and mature trees in two different years. We did not find any signs for obvious differences in arthropod abundance between the two years and climatic conditions, for instance, were similar in both years (German Weather Service, pers. com.), although further consideration of possible variation in annual interactions awaits further research.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In accordance with our expectations that species-rich predator assemblages would lead to a stronger reduction in arthropod damage because of higher predation rates, we have found that a higher species richness of birds and presumably also bats coincided with lower intensity of arthropod herbivory in the deciduous-mixed forest stands of the Hainich-Dün compared with the beech-dominated stands on the Schwäbische Alb. We can exclude to a large degree that regional differences in species richness and in abundance patterns of arthropods led to the documented regional differences in herbivory, because arthropod diversity was similar in the two study regions according to large-scale sampling in forest stands near the oak trees studied (Martin Gossner, unpublished data).</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is rather unlikely that other arthropod predators, parasites, and parasitoids, such as parasitic wasps, might have influenced our results, as the large mesh width of our nets allowed free access for them to both netted trees and controls. Hence, we assume that vertebrate predation is one of the major drivers leading to differences in intensity of arthropod herbivory between the two study sites.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Regional differences among the study sites might have contributed as well to the observed differences. Both study regions are about 300 km apart and differ in abiotic features such as topography and climate. The Schwäbische Alb is higher (500–900 m a.s.l.) than the Hainich-Dün (300–400 m a.s.l.) with lower annual mean temperatures (6–7°C vs. 6.5–7.5°C) and higher annual mean precipitation (700–1,000 mm vs. 750–800 mm). Hence, the more moderate climate of the Hainich-Dün might lead to higher herbivore abundance than the colder and wetter climate of the Schwäbische Alb. Contrary to this expectation we found higher intensity of herbivory on the Schwäbische Alb than in the Hainich-Dün. We assume that the observed differences are mainly due to differences in predator diversity as species richness and abundance of vertebrate predators were significantly higher in the Hainich-Dün than on the Schwäbische Alb and conclude that vertebrate predation (species richness and abundance of birds and bats) mainly influence herbivory.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As the canopy represents the major foraging habitat of foliage gleaning birds, a large number of insectivorous bird species feed on caterpillars, which constitute the most important herbivores in numbers and in species richness in temperate forest 
  <a rid="pone.0017857-Feeny1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0017857-Feeny1">[4]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0017857-Lill1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0017857-Lill1">[47]</a>. In addition to the often rather specialized foliage-gleaning birds such as warblers, dietary preferences of some tree trunk gleaners such as 
  <span class="italic">Dendrocopos major</span> (great spotted woodpecker) and 
  <span class="italic">Sitta europaea</span> (European nuthatch) might further enhance herbivory control, as they have also been found to glean caterpillars off leaves 
  <a rid="pone.0017857-Bhm1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0017857-Bhm1">[36]</a>. Our interpretation that greater species richness of birds leads to a reduction of leaf-eating arthropods is further corroborated by the experimental study of Sanz 
  <a rid="pone.0017857-Sanz1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0017857-Sanz1">[13]</a> where the installation of nest-boxes for tits and flycatchers in a Pyrenean oak forest stand led to an increase in the number of insectivorous birds accompanied by a distinct reduction in the number of caterpillars in parallel with a reduction in leaf damage.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition to birds, foliage-gleaning insectivorous bat species are also likely to contribute to reduce herbivory in the canopy as they feed on herbivorous arthropods as well, mainly on caterpillars, moths and beetles 
  <a rid="pone.0017857-Anderson1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0017857-Anderson1">[48]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0017857-Goerlitz1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0017857-Goerlitz1">[50]</a>. In accordance with our observation of higher species richness of birds in the Hainich-Dün compared with the Schwäbische Alb, bat species richness and activity followed a similar pattern (Kirsten Jung, unpublished data). A large-scale monitoring study in both regions in the vicinity of the study oaks showed higher numbers of foliage-gleaning bat species in the Hainich-Dün (seven species) compared with the Schwäbische Alb (four species). Furthermore, the overall activity of foliage-gleaning bat species (number of passes per minute) was higher in the Hainich-Dün than on the Schwäbische Alb (Kirsten Jung, unpublished data).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To date, the effects of foliage-gleaning bats on the abundance of herbivorous arthropods have only been investigated in the tropics where the diversity of bat species and other groups in the food web are considerably higher 
  <a rid="pone.0017857-Kalka1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0017857-Kalka1">[8]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0017857-WilliamsGuilln1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0017857-WilliamsGuilln1">[10]</a>. Kalka et al. 
  <a rid="pone.0017857-Kalka1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0017857-Kalka1">[8]</a> and Williams-Guillén et al. 
  <a rid="pone.0017857-WilliamsGuilln1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0017857-WilliamsGuilln1">[10]</a> have demonstrated a distinct impact of insectivorous birds and bats on the abundance of herbivorous arthropods and leaf damage. Moreover, the impact of foliage-gleaning bats on the reduction of leaf damage was even stronger than that of birds 
  <a rid="pone.0017857-Kalka1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0017857-Kalka1">[8]</a>. However, because of the lower numbers of foliage-gleaning bat species (≈ 7–10 species) in central Europe compared with that of insectivorous birds (≈ 70–80 species), we assume that birds contribute more to herbivore control than do bats, although this awaits further investigation. Because of logistic difficulties in conducting the study in the canopy, we could not differentiate between bird and bat predation in the canopy; it was impossible to remove and re-install the nets on a daily basis as carried out in the study of Kalka et al. 
  <a rid="pone.0017857-Kalka1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0017857-Kalka1">[8]</a> in the understorey and in the study of Williams-Guillén et al. 
  <a rid="pone.0017857-WilliamsGuilln1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0017857-WilliamsGuilln1">[10]</a> in agricultural areas.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In accordance with other studies, our results support the notion that higher species richness of vertebrate predators has a positive effect on herbivory control and ecosystem stability 
  <a rid="pone.0017857-VanBael1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0017857-VanBael1">[7]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0017857-Sanz1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0017857-Sanz1">[13]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0017857-Perfecto1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0017857-Perfecto1">[18]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0017857-Paine1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0017857-Paine1">[51]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0017857-McCann1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0017857-McCann1">[52]</a>. Studies in tropical ecosystems have demonstrated that the species richness of insectivores, mainly birds, is the main driver controlling arthropods, because species richness of predators correlates with functional richness. Hence, higher species richness of predators increases the probability that highly efficient species are present 
  <a rid="pone.0017857-Perfecto1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0017857-Perfecto1">[18]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0017857-Philpott1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0017857-Philpott1">[19]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0017857-Duffy1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0017857-Duffy1">[53]</a>. We suggest that in temperate systems, similar to the tropics, higher numbers of foliage-gleaning birds and bats are more efficient in herbivore reduction than species-poor predator assemblages (see also Philpott et al. 
  <a rid="pone.0017857-Philpott1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0017857-Philpott1">[19]</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The protection of trees by birds and bats against excessive damage by herbivores might also directly affect the survival of individual leaves. As suggested by preliminary observations after our exclusion experiments, heavily damaged leaves might be shed earlier in the vegetation period than intact leaves (personal observations). Although trees were almost fully foliated at our last sampling season, our herbivory measurements probably were thus somewhat biased by early shed leaves. We thus propose that herbivory is also likely to affect the overall lifespan of leaves. Both factors leaf area and lifespan determine the primary production of deciduous trees 
  <a rid="pone.0017857-Suwa1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0017857-Suwa1">[54]</a>. Although plants can compensate loss of leaf area by production of new leaves, leaf re-growth incurs costs and increased risk that newly emerged and less protected leaves are more likely consumed by herbivores. The high production of new leaves might even temporarily lead to a population increase of herbivores 
  <a rid="pone.0017857-Utsumi1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0017857-Utsumi1">[2]</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Plants can protect themselves against herbivores and leaf damage by investing in secondary metabolites that lower leaf palatability for arthropods and/or aid as an olfactory cue to guide predators, parasitoids or foliage-gleaning insectivorous birds to infested leaves 
  <a rid="pone.0017857-Mntyl1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0017857-Mntyl1">[55]</a>. As shown by Mäntylä et al. 
  <a rid="pone.0017857-Mntyl1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0017857-Mntyl1">[55]</a>, three volatile organic compounds ((E)-DMNT [(E)-4,8-dimethyl-1,3,7-nonatriene], β-ocimene, and linalool), that are involved in the attraction of parasitoids and predatory mites, were also positively correlated with increased predation rates of foliage-gleaning birds on 
  <span class="italic">Betula pubescens</span> (mountain birches 
  <a rid="pone.0017857-Mntyl1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0017857-Mntyl1">[55]</a>). Overall, lower intensity of arthropod herbivory is likely to facilitate plant growth and reproduction as more resources are available to the plant 
  <a rid="pone.0017857-Coley2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0017857-Coley2">[56]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0017857-Vehvilinen1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0017857-Vehvilinen1">[62]</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To conclude, standardized quantitative and qualitative studies on the impact of birds and bats in the top-down regulation of herbivores at a broad geographical scale and under various diversity scenarios are indispensable for a better understanding of ecosystem functioning and deliver base-line data for the prediction of effects of environmental changes on ecosystem services relevant for forest primary productivity 
  <a rid="pone.0017857-Marquis1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0017857-Marquis1">[12]</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our study shows that the top-down control of leaf damage strongly depends on predator diversity. Changes in species richness and abundance of birds and bats, e.g. through human induced changes in land use or climatic change, might have far-reaching consequences on ecosystem functioning and services, as a decrease in species richness of birds and bats are likely to lead to a steep increase in the number and abundance of arthropod herbivores. This is likely to profoundly influence intensity of leaf damage and, ultimately, fitness of trees and thus forest productivity 
  <a rid="pone.0017857-Sekercioglu1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0017857-Sekercioglu1">[63]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0017857-Whelan1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0017857-Whelan1">[64]</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Forest management practices with the aim of maintaining important ecosystem services should therefore consider conservation aspects, such as the preservation of structural heterogeneity, dead wood and ecologically valuable tree species, e.g. oaks, which provide cavities for the nesting and roosting of birds and bats. Moreover, additional conservation measures for birds and bats (e.g. maintenance of refugia habitats such as hedges and installation of nest-boxes) should be fostered in agricultural areas, where crops may also benefit from natural pest control, as has been demonstrated by Cleveland et al. 
  <a rid="pone.0017857-Cleveland1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0017857-Cleveland1">[65]</a> for 
  <span class="italic">Tadarida brasiliensis</span> (Brazilian free-tailed bat).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our study has revealed that bird and bat predation on arthropod herbivores significantly reduces leaf damage and biomass loss of the canopy in oak trees of the temperate zone. Profound changes in intensity and type of land use, including forest management, are accelerating reduction in animal and plant diversity in Europe. Therefore, in-depth studies on the functional roles of vertebrates are crucial if we are to predict reduction or loss of ecological function and services caused by decreasing diversity of bird and bat assemblages on the local and the regional level. A deeper understanding of the role of birds and bats in the top-down regulation of herbivory in the canopy of a temperate forest is a crucial step to providing baseline data for conservation decisions targeted at the maintenance of this important ecosystem service.</p>
</sec>
