<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Salmonellosis is a common foodborne bacterial disease in Australia, with 
 <inline-formula class="inline-formula">
  <math id="M7" class="math">
   <mrow class="mrow">
    <mo class="mo">&gt;</mo>
    <mn class="mn">80,000</mn>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> cases annually [after adjusting for under-reporting; 
 <xref rid="c22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hall et al. 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="c38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">NNDSS 2016</xref>). Salmonellosis presents as gastrointestinal symptoms that last approximately one week. Most patients recover without treatment; however, approximately 9% of patients develop reactive arthritis (ReA), and 10% develop post-infectious irritable bowel syndrome (PI-IBS; 
 <xref rid="c18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ford et al. 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="c37" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Neal et al. 1997</xref>; 
 <xref rid="c46" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Thabane et al. 2007</xref>). The Australian Department of Health and Ageing estimated that, circa 2004, foodborne diseases, including salmonellosis, cost 
 <inline-formula class="inline-formula">
  <math id="M8" class="math">
   <mrow class="mrow">
    <mo class="mo">&gt;</mo>
    <mtext class="mtext">AUD</mtext>
    <mn class="mn">1,250,000,000</mn>
    <mtext class="mtext"> </mtext>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> annually in health care, disease surveillance, and absenteeism (
 <xref rid="c1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Abelson et al. 2006</xref>). These costs were based on the most comprehensive assessment of foodborne disease incidence at the time (
 <xref rid="c9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Australian epartment of Health and Ageing 2005</xref>) and on data obtained primarily from government sources pertaining to the costs of lost productivity for businesses and individuals; health care; premature mortality; food safety recalls; and government foodborne disease surveillance, investigation, and safety systems (
 <xref rid="c1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Abelson et al. 2006</xref>). In addition, reported cases of salmonellosis have increased in Australia from approximately 29 cases per 100,000 people per year in the early 1990s to approximately 60 cases per 100,000 people per year during 2011–2015 (
 <xref rid="c38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">NNDSS 2016</xref>). The increasing incidence of salmonellosis in Australia warrants research to inform prevention strategies to reduce the associated costs.
</p>
