<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int J Environ Res Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Int J Environ Res Public Health</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ijerph</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>International Journal of Environmental Research and Public Health</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1661-7827</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1660-4601</issn><publisher><publisher-name>MDPI</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6695699</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/ijerph16152642</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ijerph-16-02642</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Changes in Olive Urban Forests Infected by <italic>Xylella fastidiosa</italic>: Impact on Microclimate and Social Health</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-9239-9060</contrib-id><name><surname>Semeraro</surname><given-names>Teodoro</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ijerph-16-02642">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1-ijerph-16-02642">&#x02020;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gatto</surname><given-names>Elisa</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ijerph-16-02642">1</xref><xref ref-type="author-notes" rid="fn1-ijerph-16-02642">&#x02020;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-0102-7235</contrib-id><name><surname>Buccolieri</surname><given-names>Riccardo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ijerph-16-02642">1</xref><xref rid="c1-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0003-3122-2389</contrib-id><name><surname>Vergine</surname><given-names>Marzia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ijerph-16-02642">1</xref><xref rid="c1-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1657-8734</contrib-id><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Zhi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2-ijerph-16-02642">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-6047-3526</contrib-id><name><surname>De Bellis</surname><given-names>Luigi</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ijerph-16-02642">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">https://orcid.org/0000-0002-2207-7493</contrib-id><name><surname>Luvisi</surname><given-names>Andrea</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1-ijerph-16-02642">1</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="af1-ijerph-16-02642"><label>1</label>Department of Biological and Environmental Sciences and Technologies, University of Salento, 73100 Lecce, Italy</aff><aff id="af2-ijerph-16-02642"><label>2</label>School of Architecture and Urban Planning, Nanjing University, Nanjing 210093, Jiangsu Province, China</aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1-ijerph-16-02642"><label>*</label>Correspondence: <email>riccardo.buccolieri@unisalento.it</email> (R.B.); <email>marzia.vergine@unisalento.it</email> (M.V.)</corresp><fn id="fn1-ijerph-16-02642"><label>&#x02020;</label><p>Equal contribution to this work.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>24</day><month>7</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>8</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>16</volume><issue>15</issue><elocation-id>2642</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>30</day><month>5</month><year>2019</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>21</day><month>7</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2019 by the authors.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access"><license-p>Licensee MDPI, Basel, Switzerland. This article is an open access article distributed under the terms and conditions of the Creative Commons Attribution (CC BY) license (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>).</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>This paper is devoted to the analysis of the impact of changes in olive urban forests affected by <italic>Xylella fastidiosa</italic> on ecosystem services. The focus is on microclimate and thermal comfort evaluated by two indices: the temperature of equivalent perception (TEP) and the predicted mean vote (PMV), which take into account both microclimate parameters and personal factors (heat resistance of clothing and human activity). The work has been carried out through (i) a qualitative analysis of the potential ecosystem services changes caused by temporary transition from olive groves to uncultivated soil, (ii) a study of the potential change of land use from monumental olive groves to other types of use, and (iii) a quantitative analysis on microclimate impact due to the loss of ecosystem services in two selected neighborhoods located in the Apulia region and chosen due to their proximity to the urban context. The analysis revealed that (i) direct effects on ecosystem services are principally linked with regulation functions and cultural services, (ii) a critical loss of cultural value of monumental olive groves occurred in the two neighborhoods, (iii) such a loss may lead to an increase of TEP and PMV, indicating a decrease of thermal comfort in the whole neighborhoods. Thus, it is necessary to plan the replanting policies of the use of the areas affected by <italic>X. fastidiosa</italic> not only in terms of agricultural planning but also in terms of landscape, urban planning, and human well-being.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>ecosystem services</kwd><kwd>urban forest</kwd><kwd>phytopathology</kwd><kwd>numerical modelling</kwd><kwd>microclimate</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-ijerph-16-02642"><title>1. Introduction</title><p>The global trend towards urbanization is determining the importance of the green component of the system that includes roads, car parks, footpaths, and other utility buildings. The social and environmental benefits of trees and woodlands are the result of an intricate array of processes that demonstrate the wide-ranging role that they play in the environment, economy, culture, and human well-being [<xref rid="B1-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>]. Several studies suggest that trees and green space positively affect people&#x02019;s self-perceived health, determined by direct and indirect social and biological benefits such as increase of attention [<xref rid="B2-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,<xref rid="B3-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>], reduction of stress [<xref rid="B4-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>], increase of life satisfaction [<xref rid="B5-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>] and positive emotions [<xref rid="B6-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>,<xref rid="B7-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>], lower mortality rates [<xref rid="B8-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,<xref rid="B9-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], and increase of physical activity [<xref rid="B10-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].</p><p>An important element of urban green space is the urban forest, defined as a network or a system that includes all the woods, groups of trees, and individual trees located in urban and peri-urban areas. It, therefore, includes forests, road trees, trees in parks, gardens, and trees in abandoned corners [<xref rid="B11-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. The urban forests produce ecosystem services, reducing air, water, noise pollution and the urban heat island, working as natural air conditioners, preventing solar radiation from heating the buildings and surfaces, cooling the air by evapotranspiration and reducing wind speed [<xref rid="B12-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,<xref rid="B13-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,<xref rid="B14-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>].</p><p>In this context, the beneficial impact, as well as biodiversity conservation, increases if large old trees are considered [<xref rid="B15-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Large old trees are among the biggest and most long-lived organisms on the earth. They greatly affect emotional perception and have many human cultural [<xref rid="B16-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] and aesthetic values [<xref rid="B17-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>], as well as a key ecological role [<xref rid="B18-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. Large old trees also play a key ecological role and some studies have examined the important interactions on distribution, abundance, and interrelationships of many other elements such as water, nutrients, and organisms including fungi, other plants, and numerous species of animals [<xref rid="B19-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Despite their fundamental impact on the life of the communities, these trees are declining globally [<xref rid="B20-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Once the large old trees are lost from the community, some vulnerable ecosystems will collapse, and it will be hard to replace their cultural and ecological functions [<xref rid="B21-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. The real problem is that the large old trees will evolve far more slowly than most of their pathogens, such as microbes, fungi, bacteria, herbivores or wood-boring insects and vertebrate folivores. The negative impacts of invasive species are likely to be an increasingly important factor given the explosive rate at which foreign species are being introduced into ecosystems [<xref rid="B22-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="B23-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. A classic example is the collapse of populations of the American chestnut (<italic>Castanea dentata</italic>) throughout the eastern USA as a result of the introduction of chestnut blight (<italic>Cryphonectria parasitica</italic>) from Asia, or the largest kauri trees (<italic>Agathis australis</italic>) in New Zealand, which are vulnerable to the effects of an introduced fungus-like pathogen (<italic>Phytophthora agathidicida</italic>) and for which there is presently no known effective treatment [<xref rid="B24-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>].</p><p><italic>Xylella fastidiosa</italic> represents an emerging threat in Europe, since its finding at the end of 2013 in the Salento peninsula (Apulia region, southern Italy), associated to a previously unknown disease on olive trees (<italic>Olea europaea</italic> L.) which causes a leaf scorch (the so-called &#x0201c;olive quick decline syndrome&#x0201d;, OQDS), a rapid decline and the death of trees [<xref rid="B25-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. These symptoms are particularly severe on specifically large old plants of the most sensible cultivar &#x0201c;Cellina di Nard&#x000f2;&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;Ogliarola&#x0201d; [<xref rid="B26-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>,<xref rid="B27-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,<xref rid="B28-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>], the most widespread in the whole area. The evidence and the following research studies indicated a connection with the bacterium <italic>Xylella fastidiosa</italic> subsp. <italic>pauca</italic> ST53 [<xref rid="B29-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">29</xref>] (<italic>X. fastidiosa</italic> hereinafter). <italic>X. fastidiosa</italic> can be found worldwide, though its diseases are most prominent in America [<xref rid="B30-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">30</xref>]. The further findings in France and Spain allow considering it as an expanding global pathogen [<xref rid="B31-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], which could reshape not only agriculture but the landscape and human relations with plants. Indeed, the pathogen represents both an environmental threat (it is capable of infecting several woody plants and shrubs besides olive tree) and an economic plague (about 11 million of olive tree are planted in the Apulian infected area, while in the whole Mediterranean areas olive tree is among predominant cultivated species) [<xref rid="B32-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. Unfortunately, no cure is yet available and its control relies on uprooting infected trees and vector control. Furthermore, olive trees have a long historical and cultural link with the infected areas, and their demise causes a strong emotional impact on inhabitants and visitors [<xref rid="B33-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>].</p><p>Thus, the arrival of <italic>X. fastidiosa</italic> in Apulia has marked a political rupture due to the imposition of mandatory actions. This bacterium has threatened agriculture but also social and anthropological balances [<xref rid="B33-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. The conspicuous loss of an environmental, social-cultural, and economic heritage determined by this phytosanitary emergency prompts us to consider the fundamental interdisciplinary approach to understand, prevent, and reduce the harmful effects of invasive alien plant pathogens and pests in urban and peri-urban forests. At the same time, it is also crucial to evaluate the economic, environmental, and social loss, to foresee future scenarios and to be ready to implement policy actions aimed at mitigating such loss.</p><p>The aim of this study was the assessment of the human health benefits lost directly related to the devastating impact of the plant pathogen (<italic>X. fastidiosa</italic>) on olive trees. The study was divided into three steps:</p><p>The first step involved a qualitative analysis of the potential ecosystem services changes caused by the loss of olive trees through bibliographic research.</p><p>The second step was devoted to the study of the potential change of land use from olive groves to other types of use. Historical and current maps were employed. The social-cultural aspect of the loss of olive trees was also discussed.</p><p>In the third step, a quantitative analysis was performed to evaluate the impact on microclimate due to the loss of ecosystem services provided by olive trees in two transition areas (i.e., between urban boundaries and agricultural areas). This was assessed by air temperature and thermal comfort indices obtained through modelling simulations performed with the computational fluid dynamics and microclimate model ENVI-met. Three scenarios were considered: pre-epidemy (plants in good phytosanitary status), epidemy (actual status, with severe symptoms on plants) and a future scenario which considers the transition from olive trees in good health to uncultivated soil.</p><p>This study may provide useful indications in the planning of agricultural areas affected by <italic>X. fastidiosa</italic> that for their spatial location, ecological and social functions should be thought of as green spaces.</p></sec><sec id="sec2-ijerph-16-02642"><title>2. Study Area</title><p>The Province of Lecce located in southern Apulia (southern Italy) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-02642-f001">Figure 1</xref>a) is characterized by the cultural landscape, which is the result of strong historical interactions between ecological, economic, and social components. The province extends for about 279,887 ha and about 41% of its extension is covered by olive groves. Unfortunately, many olives trees have been infected by <italic>X. fastidiosa</italic>, causing the desiccation and the death of infected plants, even if some resistant cultivars were identified [<xref rid="B34-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,<xref rid="B35-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. The data retrieved in the institutional database (<uri xlink:href="http://sit.puglia.it/portal/portale_gestione_agricoltura/Cartografie">http://sit.puglia.it/portal/portale_gestione_agricoltura/Cartografie</uri>) confirm the presence of the pathogen in all the Lecce area, and the presence is considered as not eradicable [<xref rid="B28-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>].</p><p>Urban and rural areas are often interconnected, and a net separation is not evident. In these cases, peri-urban areas are characterized by agroecosystems [<xref rid="B35-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,<xref rid="B36-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. Indeed, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-02642-f001">Figure 1</xref>b, many municipalities are characterized by a core urban area mainly surrounded by olive groves, the latter currently strongly affected by <italic>X. fastidiosa</italic>. The destructive effect caused by this pathogen on olive trees can potentially compromise the practical and ecological purposes of olive groves with direct and indirect effects on ecosystem services and effects on human health.</p><p>Two peri-urban neighborhoods characterized by olive groves in the municipality of Parabita (40&#x000b0;03&#x02032; N 18&#x000b0;08&#x02032; E, where almost 9047 people live in an area of 2109 ha) and Matino (40&#x000b0;02&#x02032; N 18&#x000b0;08&#x02032; E, where 11,444 people live in an area of 2800 ha) [<xref rid="B37-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>] were selected to assess the effect of their loss on the local population health, measured as loss or decrease in ecosystem services. These neighborhoods have been chosen due to their proximity to the urban context and representing the main spatial types of interaction between urban areas and olive groves. In the first case (municipality of Parabita), the olive groves surround the portion of the urban area, in the second case (municipality of Matino), the olive groves penetrate the urban area, to form an intrusion of the agroecosystem into the urban area (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-02642-f001">Figure 1</xref>c).</p></sec><sec id="sec3-ijerph-16-02642"><title>3. Materials and Methods</title><sec id="sec3dot1-ijerph-16-02642"><title>3.1. Ecosystem Services Changes</title><p>In order to evaluate the ecosystem service changes and, thus, the impact on human health caused by peri-urban areas land use transformation, a methodological analysis using the Environmental Impact Assessment (EIA) was followed, as indicated by the Directive 2001/42/EC of the European Parliament and of the Council of 27 June 2001, commonly applied to a wide range of public plans and programs (e.g., land use, transport, energy, waste, agriculture, etc.). The alterations which occurred in the main environmental matrices (air, soil, water, landscape, biodiversity) were selected from the literature (see <xref rid="ijerph-16-02642-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> caption later in the text) and applied to likely scenario (from olive groves to uncultivated soil) following the implementation of the regulation of the Apulia region of 5 February 2019 which requires the felling of trees infected with <italic>X. fastidiosa</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-02642-f002">Figure 2</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec3dot2-ijerph-16-02642"><title>3.2. Changes in Olive Grove and Disease Severity Assessment</title><p>First, the olive groves maps of years 1887 and 2016 have been digitized and analyzed using the Geographic Information System software QGIS (qgis.org). For 1887, the historical map of land use carried out by the milizia forestale was used. The map of the olive groves for years 2016 was downloaded in shapefile format from the official Territorial Information System (SIT) of the Apulia Region (<uri xlink:href="www.sit.puglia.it/">www.sit.puglia.it/</uri>). After that, a change detection analysis was carried out overlapping olive groves maps of 1887 and 2016 to identify potential old olive groves in the Apulia region. Such a long timespan of the land-use analysis has been chosen to define the potential spatial distribution of monumental olive groves in the Salento area.</p><p>The cultural value of monumental olive groves was then analyzed through objective measures concerning the diameter of the trunk and through a visual analysis of the shape of the trunk of the plants as established by the regional law 14/2007 (B.U.R. PUGLIA&#x02014;N. 83, 07/06/2007). Symptoms of <italic>X. fastidiosa</italic> related to leaf scorching and wilting of the canopy were assessed by visual inspection, estimating disease severity and using the following severity scale: 0 = symptomless, 1 = leaf scorching on few branches or few desiccated branches affecting the portion of the canopy, 2 = leaf scorching on several branches or desiccation affecting a large part of the portion of the canopy, and 3 = canopy with desiccated branches uniformly distributed [<xref rid="B32-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec3dot3-ijerph-16-02642"><title>3.3. Impact of Olive Tree Loss on Microclimate in the Selected Neighborhoods</title><p>As mentioned in <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec2-ijerph-16-02642">Section 2</xref>, the two neighborhoods analyzed are located in Matino and Parabita, two small-size cities of south Italy characterized by a Mediterranean climate and a classical Mediterranean architectural design, consisting of two-to-three-story buildings and narrow street canyons (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-02642-f003">Figure 3</xref>). The neighborhoods are characterized by buildings heights ranging from 7 to 11 m (heights estimated using the DISTO) and by the presence of about 155 olive trees in Matino and 170 in Parabita.</p><p>The leaf area index (LAI) of tree crowns was estimated from measurements of the photo-synthetically active radiation (PAR) acquired by an Accu-PAR LP80 ceptometer. All measurements were taken parallel to the ground. Five replicas were done just near the crown (where the sensor measured unobstructed PAR) and at its base (where it was supposed that the LAI is maximum). The leaf area density (LAD, m<sup>2</sup>m<sup>&#x02013;3</sup>) was thus estimated dividing LAI by the depth of the tree crown. The analysis allowed to characterize the infected olive groves having a height of 8 m and a crown depth of 3 m, crown height of 4 m, and a leaf area density (LAD) of 0.3 m<sup>2</sup>m<sup>&#x02013;3</sup>. Olive groves in good health have the same height, but a depth crown of 5 m and a LAD of 1.1 m<sup>2</sup>m<sup>&#x02013;3</sup>.</p><p>Three scenarios have been modeled: (i) the current scenario with olive groves affected by <italic>X. fastidiosa</italic> (epidemy scenario), (ii) a scenario with plants in good phytosanitary status (pre-epidemy scenario), and (iii) a scenario with no olive trees representing a transition to an uncultivated soil (future scenario).</p><sec id="sec3dot3dot1-ijerph-16-02642"><title>3.3.1. Numerical Simulations</title><p>ENVI-met is a prognostic non-hydrostatic model for the simulation of surface-plant-air interactions composed by a 3D main model and, in addition, a one dimensional (1D) atmospheric boundary layer (ABL) model which extends from the ground surface up to 2500 m. ENVI-met has a typical horizontal resolution from 0.5 to 5 m and a typical time frame of 24 to 48 h with a time step of 1 to 5 s, which meet the criteria for the accurate simulation of physical processes, suitable for microclimate studies at the neighborhood scale. The atmospheric system solves Reynolds-averaged Navier-Stokes equations using a 1.5 order turbulence closure <italic>k-&#x003b5;</italic> model. Equations related to surfaces thermal exchanges are calculated from an energy balance of the net radiative energy fluxes, turbulent fluxes of heat and vapor and soil heat flux. Evapotranspiration processes are simulated during the entire daily cycle on the basis of the biological and thermo-physical properties of plants and soils. Several studies have shown that ENVI-met is able to simulate both spatial and temporal temperature and wind speed for the evaluation of microclimate in both simple and complex urban areas. The recent review by [<xref rid="B38-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] provides evidence of its suitability for the cases studied in this paper. See also [<xref rid="B39-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>] for a review of validation studies.</p><p>The 3D simulation area (computational domain) of the Matino neighborhood has a dimension of 300 m (x-direction) &#x000d7; 300 m (y-direction) &#x000d7; 60 m (z-direction), while the area of the Parabita neighborhood is 300 m &#x000d7; 200 m &#x000d7; 60 m. The areas were meshed using a regular grid with a resolution of 2 m &#x000d7; 2 m &#x000d7; 2 m, except for the lowest (close to the ground) five cells whose vertical resolution was 0.4 m (i.e., the equidistant option was employed in ENVI-met). To improve model accuracy and stability, five nesting grids were also employed. The cyclic type method was selected for the lateral boundary conditions (LBC) because the study area is located in the city where the neighborhood space layout is similar to the study area. Hourly air temperature and relative humidity were forced at the model boundary to drive the simulation with meteorological input of 18 August 2018, selected as representative of a typical summer day, since the temperature profile was reasonably correlated with the average temperature profile, and the wind (speed = 1.56 m/s; direction = 329&#x000b0;) was rather stationary and consistent with the prevailing wind during the period July&#x02013;August 2018. Data have been obtained from a 10 m high ARPA-Puglia (the Regional Agency for Environmental Protection of the Apulia region) meteorological station (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-02642-f003">Figure 3</xref>), located at about 20 km from the neighborhoods (<uri xlink:href="http://www.arpa.puglia.it/web/guest/serviziometeo">http://www.arpa.puglia.it/web/guest/serviziometeo</uri>). The minimum and maximum temperatures were 22.1 &#x000b0;C and 32.9 &#x000b0;C, while the minimum and maximum relative humidity were 44% and 87%. Wind speed was set to 1.56 m/s (mean daily value) and wind direction to 329&#x000b0; (median of wind directions during the day). For each case, ENVI-met was run for a 16 h period, starting at 06:00.</p></sec><sec id="sec3dot3dot2-ijerph-16-02642"><title>3.3.2. Thermal Comfort Indices</title><p>Together with air temperature, the impact of olive groves and their loss on thermal comfort was evaluated by means of the predicted mean vote (PMV) and the temperature of equivalent perception (TEP). PMV (-) allows for the evaluation of the thermal sensation based on the heat balance of the human body. It takes into consideration the air temperature, the mean radiant temperature (MRT), the wind speed and the relative humidity, as well as the personal factors, e.g., heat resistance of clothing and human activity [<xref rid="B40-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. The outdoor PMV range and the corresponding human thermal sensation are: 4 (very hot), 3 (hot), 2 (warm), 1 (slightly warm), 0 (neutral), &#x02212;1 (slightly cool), &#x02212;2 (cool), &#x02212;3 (cold), &#x02212;4 (slightly cold). TEP (&#x000b0;C) is sensitive to changes in air temperature and MRT [<xref rid="B41-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>]. Personal factors such as clothing insulation and the level of activity are not considered (as in PMV). The thermal perception ranges are: &#x02265;42.5 &#x000b0;C (very hot), 34.9&#x02013;42.4 &#x000b0;C (hot), 27.3&#x02013;34.8 &#x000b0;C (warm), 19.6&#x02013;27.2 &#x000b0;C (neutral), 12.0&#x02013;19.5 &#x000b0;C (cool), 4.4&#x02013;11.9 &#x000b0;C (cold), &#x0003c;4.3 &#x000b0;C (very cold).</p><p>Temperature, PMV, and TEP were calculated based on parameters directly obtained from ENVI-met. The data were extracted at receptors indicated in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-02642-f003">Figure 3</xref> to evaluate the influence of olive trees within the olive grove and in nearby street canyons. The selected height for the calculations was 1.4 m (pedestrian height).</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec4-ijerph-16-02642"><title>4. Results</title><sec id="sec4dot1-ijerph-16-02642"><title>4.1. Analysis of Ecosystem Services Changes</title><p>The whole Province of Lecce has been classified as infected by the bacterium and the completely compromised agroecosystem is causing a temporary transition from olive groves to uncultivated soil. It should be also noted that a regional law (5 February 2019) indicated the removal of infected trees within the infected areas [<xref rid="B42-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>], and, thus, it is expected that the Province of Lecce will have a sudden change in the landscape pattern with direct effects on the ecosystem services linked principally with the regulation functions like CO<sub>2</sub> and climate regulation (<xref rid="ijerph-16-02642-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). In particular, the CO<sub>2</sub> sequestered per century-old tree is estimated to be about 2600 kg CO<sub>2</sub> which could be reintroduced in the atmosphere if all the wood produced by the explant of the trees were disposed of by burning. However, these changes can be considered reversible in the medium-to-long term, if the areas of monumental olive trees are be replaced by other arboreal plants that may constitute the future forests of the Salento. It is possible to consider that in 30&#x02013;40 years, the planting of arboreal plants could restore the ecological functions lost due to the loss of the historic olive groves.</p><p>Other important aspects linked to the loss of ecosystem services are related to agricultural heritage information and functions (<xref rid="ijerph-16-02642-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Although the importance of the monumental olive groves on the historical and cultural value of the Salento landscape is certified by the regional law (14/2007), this aspect is difficult to quantify. These changes can be considered irreversible over time because there are no longer social, economic, and environmental conditions that can lead to the development of a historic olive grove as it is known now. These effects could be felt more in urban areas where there is a large number of individuals who benefit every day from the relations existing between peri-urban forests consisting of historic olive groves and the well-being of the population.</p><table-wrap id="ijerph-16-02642-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="pii">ijerph-16-02642-t001_Table 1</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Functions, goods and services identified for natural and semi-natural ecosystems [<xref rid="B43-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="B44-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,<xref rid="B45-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,<xref rid="B46-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,<xref rid="B47-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>] integrated with the potential variation of such services connected with the change of land use from old olive groves to uncultivated land [<xref rid="B48-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,<xref rid="B49-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,<xref rid="B50-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,<xref rid="B51-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,<xref rid="B52-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,<xref rid="B53-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,<xref rid="B54-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>,<xref rid="B55-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>,<xref rid="B56-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>,<xref rid="B57-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>,<xref rid="B58-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>,<xref rid="B59-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>,<xref rid="B60-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>,<xref rid="B61-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. The emoticon &#x0263a; indicates positive alteration, &#x02639; indicates negative alteration, whereas the symbol = indicates no significant alteration. The number of emoticons gives an estimate of the intensity of the alteration: 1: low alteration; 2: medium alteration; 3: strong alteration.</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th colspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1">Functions</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ecosystem Processes and Components</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ecosystem Services</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variation from Old Olive Groves to Uncultivated Areas</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Environmental M atrix Directed and Undirected Affected</th><th align="center" valign="middle" style="border-top:solid thin;border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reversible</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="11" align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1"><bold>Regulation functions</bold><break/>(Maintenance of essential ecological processes and life support systems)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gas regulation</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Role of ecosystems in bio-geochemical cycles (e.g., CO<sub>2</sub>/O<sub>2</sub> balance, ozone layer, etc.)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UVB-protection by O<sub>3</sub> (preventing disease);<break/>Maintenance of (good) air quality;<break/>Influence on climate </td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02639;&#x02639;&#x02639;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Air<break/>Biodiversity<break/>population</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Climate regulation</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Influence of land cover and biol. Mediated processes (e.g., DMS-production) on climate</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maintenance of a favorable climate (temp., precipitation, etc.) for human habitation, health, cultivation.</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02639;&#x02639;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Air<break/>Soil<break/>Water<break/>Biodiversity<break/>population</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Disturbance prevention</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Influence of ecosystem structure on dampening env. disturbances</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Storm protection (e.g., by coral reefs);<break/>Flood prevention (e.g., by wetlands and forests)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">not evaluated</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Water regulation</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Role of land cover in regulating runoff and river discharge</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drainage and natural irrigation</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">=</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soil<break/>Water<break/>Biodiversity<break/>population</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Water supply</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Filtering, retention and storage of fresh water (e.g., in aquifers)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Provision of water for consumptive use (e.g., drinking, irrigation and industrial use)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">=</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soil<break/>Water<break/>Biodiversity<break/>population</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soil retention</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Role of vegetation root matrix and soil biota in soil retention</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maintenance of arable land;<break/>Prevention of damage from erosion/siltation.</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02639;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soil<break/>Biodiversity<break/>population</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soil formation</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Weathering of rock, accumulation of organic matter</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maintenance of productivity on arable land;<break/>Maintenance of natural productive soils; </td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02639;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soil<break/>Biodiversity<break/>population</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nutrient regulation</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Role of biota in storage and recycling of nutrients (e.g., N, P and S)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maintenance of healthy soils and productive ecosystems</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02639;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soil<break/>Water<break/>Biodiversity<break/>population</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Waste treatment</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Role of vegetation and biota in removal or breakdown of xenic nutrients and compounds</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pollution control/detoxification;<break/>Filtering of dust particles (air quality)<break/>Abatement of noise pollution</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">not evaluated</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soil<break/>Water<break/>Biodiversity<break/>population</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pollination</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Role of biota in movement of floral gametes</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pollination of wild plant species;<break/>Pollination of crops.</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">=</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Biodiversity<break/>population</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Biological control</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Population control through trophic-dynamic relations</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Control of pests and diseases;<break/>Reduction of herbivory (crop damage).</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">not evaluated</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soil<break/>Biodiversity<break/>population</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1"><bold>Habitat functions</bold><break/>(Providing habitat (suitable living space) for wild plant and animal species)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Refugium function</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Suitable living space for wild plants and animals</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maintenance of biological and genetic diversity (and, thus, the basis for most other functions)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02639;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Biodiversity<break/>Population<break/>cultural landscape</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Nursery function</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Suitable reproduction-habitat</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maintenance of commercially harvested species</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02639;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Biodiversity<break/>Population<break/>cultural landscape</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1"><bold>Production functions</bold><break/>(Provision of natural resources)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Food</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Conversion of solar energy into edible plants and<break/>animals</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Hunting, game, fruits, etc.<break/>Small-scale subsistence </td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02639;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Biodiversity<break/>Population<break/>cultural landscape</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Raw materials</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Conversion of solar energy into biomass for human construction and other uses</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Building and Manufacturing (e.g., lumber);<break/>Fuel and energy (e.g., fuel wood); </td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02639;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Population<break/>cultural landscape</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genetic resources</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genetic material and evolution in wild plants and animals</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Improve crop resistance to pathogens and pests;<break/>Other applications (e.g., health care)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">not evaluated</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Medicinal resources</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variety in (bio)chemical substances in, and other medicinal uses of, natural biota</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Drugs and pharmaceuticals;<break/>Chemical models and tools;<break/>Test and essay organisms</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">not evaluated</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="5" align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1"><bold>Information functions</bold><break/>(Providing opportunities for cognitive development)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Aesthetic information</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Attractive landscape features</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Enjoyment of scenery (scenic roads, housing, etc.)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02639;&#x02639;&#x02639;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Population<break/>cultural landscape</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Re-creation</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variety in landscapes with (potential) re-creational uses</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Travel to natural ecosystems for eco-tourism and (re-creational) nature study</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02639;&#x02639;&#x02639;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Population<break/>cultural landscape</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cultural and artistic information</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variety in natural features with cultural and artistic value</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Use of nature as motive in books, film, painting, folklore, national symbols, architect</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02639;&#x02639;&#x02639;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Population<break/>cultural landscape</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spiritual and historic information</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variety in natural features with spiritual and historic value</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Use of nature for religious or historic purposes (i.e., heritage value of natural ecosystems and features)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02639;&#x02639;&#x02639;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Population<break/>cultural landscape</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Science and education</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variety in nature with scientific and educational value</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Use of natural systems for school excursions, etc.<break/>Use of nature for scientific research</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02639;&#x02639;&#x02639;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Population<break/>cultural landscape</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1"><bold>Carrier functions</bold><break/>(Providing a suitable substrate or medium for human activities and infrastructure)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Habitation</td><td rowspan="2" align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" colspan="1">Depending on the specific land use type, different requirements are placed on<break/>environmental conditions (e.g., soil stability and fertility, air and water quality, topography, climate, geology, etc.</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Living space (ranging from small settlements to<break/>urban areas)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02639;&#x02639;&#x02639;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Population<break/>cultural landscape</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td></tr><tr><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tourism-facilities</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tourism-activities (outdoor sports,<break/>beach-tourism, etc.)</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02639;&#x02639;&#x02639;</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Population<break/>cultural landscape</td><td align="center" valign="middle" style="border-bottom:solid thin" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec4dot2-ijerph-16-02642"><title>4.2. Analysis of Changes in Olive Grove and Disease Severity Assessment</title><p>The maps (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-02642-f004">Figure 4</xref>) revealed that 150 years ago the olive grove covered about an extension of 124,138 ha, which was about 44% its extension. Around 66,475 ha of olive groves can potentially be classified as historical, because they are shown on the maps of 1887 and 2016. In this sense, the monumental olive grove represents 58% of the olive groves currently present and about 24% of the total extension of the Province of Lecce. Therefore, old olive groves represent a structural element in the pattern of the province, and many olive trees are secular plants with a high cultural value recognized and protected by the Apulia regional law 14/2007.</p><p>From a field survey, it emerged that over the 51% of olive groves located in the two study neighborhoods are characterized by monumental plants, therefore, they can be considered historic olive groves. The trees present a sculptural shape like defined in the regional law (14/2007) and trunk size is greater than 100 cm of diameter. This confirms what was found in the previous analysis of the olive grove change. These old olive groves are an important element of the cultural urban area of Matino and Parabita. However, as visible in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-02642-f005">Figure 5</xref>, most plants have the symptoms of desiccation caused by <italic>X. fastidiosa</italic>, with a disease severity esteemed between levels 2 to 3 out of 3. Therefore, they are subjected to decay or death.</p></sec><sec id="sec4dot3-ijerph-16-02642"><title>4.3. Analysis of the Impact of Olive Tree Loss on Microclimate in the Selected Neighborhoods</title><sec id="sec4dot3dot1-ijerph-16-02642"><title>4.3.1. Temporal Profiles of Air Temperature, TEP and PMV</title><p>As suggested from <xref rid="ijerph-16-02642-t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, the variation from old olive groves to uncultivated soil (uncultivated areas) is expected to affect their climate regulation and thus the maintenance of a favorable climate in terms of temperature, humidity, etc. for human health. In order to quantitatively evaluate such impact, temporal profiles of air temperature, TEP and PMV, at the receptors located inside the street canyon and within the olive groves for the two selected neighborhoods are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-02642-f006">Figure 6</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-02642-f007">Figure 7</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-02642-f008">Figure 8</xref>.</p><p><xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-02642-f006">Figure 6</xref> shows that in both neighborhoods the air temperature (Tair) in the future scenario (i.e., uncultivated soil without olive trees) is higher than that in the other two scenarios (epidemy and pre-epidemy) during all day, and especially during the central and hottest hours of the day (10:00&#x02013;17:00). As expected, the presence of trees leads to a decrease of air temperature, even though the effect is small [<xref rid="B32-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], and it is larger with olive trees in good phytosanitary status (pre-epidemy scenario) due to larger shading and evapotranspiration effects.</p><p>Further, it is possible to observe that, due to the different configuration of the olive groves and the geometry of the neighborhoods, the effect of the presence of trees (in terms of decrease of air temperature) is more evident in Matino, and the largest decreases for all cases occur at 15:00. In particular, the street canyon in Matino shows a decrease of 0.30 &#x000b0;C in the epidemy scenario and 0.80 &#x000b0;C in the pre-epidemy scenario, while within the olive grove a decrease of 0.75 &#x000b0;C and 1.15 &#x000b0;C, respectively, occur. On the other hand, Parabita shows only a decrease within the olive grove (of 0.40 &#x000b0;C and 0.70 &#x000b0;C, respectively), while no effect of the trees is observed in the street canyon, likely due to the distance of the canyon from the olive grove location.</p><p>To evaluate the effect on thermal comfort, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-02642-f007">Figure 7</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-02642-f008">Figure 8</xref> show that TEP and PMV decrease in the presence of trees, suggesting an improvement of thermal comfort. Different from the air temperature, where the profiles follow the same behavior, here TEP and PMV profiles show substantial differences between the two receptors (i.e., in the street canyon and within the olive grove) and during the day, since the thermal comfort (here in terms of TEP and PMV) depends not only on the air temperature but also on relative humidity, wind speed, and MRT.</p><p>Specifically, for TEP profiles inside the street canyon in Matino, a decrease during the central hours of the day (9:00&#x02013;16:00) is observed, with a maximum of 0.61 &#x000b0;C in the epidemy scenario and 2.35 &#x000b0;C in the pre-epidemy scenario at 14:00. Within the olive grove there is a very large decrease during the morning (3.95 &#x000b0;C at 8:00) and the afternoon (up to more than 10 &#x000b0;C at 17:00) between the pre-epidemy and future scenarios, but this is due to the shading effect of trees and, thus, to its effects on decreasing MRT in that particular receptor location. A similar trend is observed for PMV with the largest decrease at 15:00 in the street canyon (equal to 0.42 in the epidemy scenario and 0.11 in the pre-epidemy scenario) and at 17:00 within the olive grove (equal to 0.75 in the epidemy scenario and 1.57 in the pre-epidemy scenario).</p><p>In the case of Parabita, the main differences (for both TEP and PMV) are found within the olive grove during the first hours (7:00&#x02013;10:00), with the largest decrease of more than 12 &#x000b0;C for TEP and 1.41 points for PMV at 8:00. As mentioned before, this is caused by the shading effect of trees which lead to a low MRT at the receptor location.</p></sec><sec id="sec4dot3dot2-ijerph-16-02642"><title>4.3.2. Spatial Distribution of PMV</title><p>Finally, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-02642-f009">Figure 9</xref> shows 1.4 m high spatial contours of PMV in the afternoon (at 15:00). As expected, since the simulations were performed on 18 August 2018, a typical hot summer day, all the maps show an uncomfortable condition (from hot to very hot, see <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec3dot3dot2-ijerph-16-02642">Section 3.3.2</xref>). In both neighborhoods, the presence of olive groves in good health (pre-epidemy scenario) induces an overall improvement of the thermal comfort (i.e., a decrease of PMV), while the PMV distribution of the current (epidemy) and future (uncultivated soil) scenarios are similar. Specifically, in Matino, the presence of olive grove leads to an average PMV reduction of 0.22 in the epidemy scenario and 0.65 in the pre-epidemy scenario, while in Parabita, the average PMV reduction is equal to 0.20 and 0.33, respectively.</p><p>It is worth noting that, as already mentioned before and suggested by the profiles of Tair, TEP, and PMV, the overall effect is more evident in Matino and the pre-epidemy scenario with an extra impact not only close to the trees but also in nearby empty street canyons.</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec5-ijerph-16-02642"><title>5. Discussion</title><p>The present study represents one of the first analyses of the impact of urban olive groves on ecosystem services, and, in particular, on microclimate regulation. The study area comprises the municipalities of Matino and Parabita (Province of Lecce, Italy), which together represent a wide range of urban forms present in the social-ecological landscape of the Apulia region.</p><p>The old and monumental olive groves in the Province of Lecce are characterized by a tree structure with an average height of 5&#x02013;8 m and a crown diameter of 3&#x02013;5 m and characterized by a high LAI, so their widespread presence in the territory configures them as a forest. They are ecosystem service providers, due not only to the production of ecosystem goods (olives and oil), but also to their ecological role of sink biodiversity, which seems to simulate the role of forests in facing disturbances across spatial and temporal scales [<xref rid="B62-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>].</p><p>The severity of the problem of OQDS in Apulia is characterized by the fact that most of the olive trees in the region are monumental and thus cherished for their ecological and cultural value. The bacterium <italic>X. fastidiosa</italic> caused, up to now, an incurable disease, and the only available solution to reduce the spread of both the pathogen and its insect vectors are the elimination of diseased plants and control measures of the vector. Unfortunately, the phytosanitary policies have been largely criticized and strongly opposed by some local administrators and by organized social and environmental movements, causing a <italic>de facto</italic> spread of the bacterium at the local and regional scale, with economic and cultural impacts on the landscape. The spread of <italic>X. fastidiosa</italic> will produce a conversion of land use in the short-to-medium term leading to a reduction in ecosystem services and thus introduce critical issues. In particular, the case studies of Matino and Parabita have shown that the current scenarios of olive groves are close to uncultivated soil scenario characteristics in terms of microclimate regulation and, in particular, of thermal comfort. For example, the high concentration of dry biomass linked to the mortality of olive groves near urban areas is expected to increase potentially damaging fires [<xref rid="B61-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>,<xref rid="B63-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>], while the cutting of dry trees will produce a high emission of CO<sub>2</sub> in the atmosphere due to the destruction of the wood mass and less absorption of CO<sub>2</sub> with direct effects on population health.</p><p>Local management practices have resulted in distinctive cultural landscapes adapted to the specific climate and geographic areas, and old olive groves are the result of continuous interactions between nature and human activities [<xref rid="B60-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>,<xref rid="B61-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]. The current state of the olive groves in the Province of Lecce derives from a type of tree cultivation aimed at favoring the manual harvesting of olives. The sculptural form of the trunk, on the other hand, is the result of plant maintenance actions aimed at eliminating the rotten wood of the trunk. The planting of new olive groves will adapt to the mechanical harvesting of olives and, therefore, to types of trees with short stems. Moreover, there will be a greater turnover of single trees to always maintain high productivity. The destruction of the old olive groves could mean the loss of the historical-cultural and natural heritage that cannot be recovered. Therefore, the process leading from agroforestry to cultural landscape must be considered in the land use transformation in peri-urban areas, not only for agricultural production but also for major contributions in the heritage of the peri-urban area on the wellbeing of the population [<xref rid="B18-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>].</p><p>In particular, the conversion of the monumental olive groves into uncultivated areas in the context of urban areas could also cause a worsening of the soundscape linked to the presence of fauna linked to the old olive groves. Therefore, old olive groves in the peri-urban area may be considered of high nature and cultural value (HNCV) green urban spaces that integrates woody vegetation with crops activities, and which are valued for their biodiversity, ecosystem services support, and their cultural heritage [<xref rid="B64-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>].</p><p>Thus, it is necessary to undertake planning actions devoted to the construction of new peri-urban landscapes and keeping important ecosystem services to improve the quality of human life and well-being. New landscape policies able to improve the adaptability and the capacity of actors in a system to influence and manage resilience is thus required [<xref rid="B65-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. In the case of old olive groves in peri-urban area, the adaptability could be interpreted like the capacity of the actors to develop a new system because the ecological, economic, or social (including political) conditions make the existing system untenable [<xref rid="B65-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>,<xref rid="B66-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>], but keeping the main ecological functions able to produce ecosystem services supporting wellbeing of the people that live in peri-urban area. Therefore, the adaptability and transformability, in this way, are not in contrast but complementary. Naturally, in a social-ecological system, the policy must considerate the panarchy because of cross-scale interactions, the resilience of a system at a particular focal scale will depend on the influences from states and dynamics at scales above and below. For example, external oppressive politics, invasions, market shifts, or global climate change can trigger local unexpected changes [<xref rid="B65-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>].</p><p>An obstacle in trying to improve the adaptability and transformability in the peri-urban forest in Matino and Parabita is the strong fragmentation of property. This situation also impedes the management of olive groves affected by <italic>X. fastidiosa</italic>, because of multiple notifications for uprooting area being requested, and proprieties of olive groves are not always easily assertible. Owners that do not have an agricultural income may show little interest in investing money to recreate a new urban forest with the intent of producing the same ecosystem services as the old olive groves.</p><p>In the future, it will be necessary to develop territorial governance action or policies that will have to combine with the different needs of many stakeholders of the territory, or worse, with the limited interest of the stakeholders in investing economic resources and time in the landscape [<xref rid="B36-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. In particular, in areas adjacent to the urban context, such as those of Matino and Parabita investigated here, the problem of <italic>X. fastidiosa</italic> should also be managed through urban planning policies and not only considering agricultural policies. Our numerical results have shown that the trees have an effect on thermal comfort where they are located, but the effect can spread over the whole neighborhood and, thus, it is crucial to plan their planting within appropriate urban development Ppans. An urban planning tool useful for managing these areas could be the Equalization and Urban Compensation (Apulia regional law 27/07/2001) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-02642-f010">Figure 10</xref>).</p></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec6-ijerph-16-02642"><title>6. Conclusions</title><p>This study evaluates the impact of the loss of olive groves due to the plant pathogen <italic>X. fastidiosa</italic> in the Apulia region, with a focus on the Province of Lecce. <italic>X. fastidiosa</italic> is an expanding global pathogen which can be found worldwide, as confirmed by further findings in France and Spain. In this study, its effects have been evaluated in two neighborhoods of the province (located in the small towns of Matino and Parabita), selected due to their proximity to the urban context and representing the main spatial types of interaction between urban areas and olive groves in the province. The rationale behind this study is that olive trees play a key role in the urban environment of the Apulia region, not only from the agronomical and social-cultural point of views, but also because they improve the microclimate and mitigate the effects of climate change and Urban Heat Island. The present study has confirmed the impact of disease severity and has shown that the transition from olive trees in good health status to uncultivated soil has an effect on microclimate and, in particular, on thermal comfort. This impact is not just limited to places where trees are located (at the boundaries of the two neighborhoods) but in the whole region. Thus, it is crucial to study their effects and plan their planting within appropriate urban planning strategies to maximize their benefits. In this sense, the current agricultural legislation provides for the restoration of the olive grove made up of <italic>X. fastidiosa</italic>-resistant cultivars (two of them have been defined [<xref rid="B34-ijerph-16-02642" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>], while research continues to find others), at the same time it would be desirable to avoid a monovarietal approach and thus, to increase the ecological resilience to this and other pathologies.</p><p>The replanting policies of the olive groves or of the use of the areas affected by <italic>X. fastidiosa</italic> must, thus, be addressed not only in terms of agricultural planning but also in terms of landscape and urban planning, to avoid the abandonment of these areas due to the lack of owners&#x02019; interest in investing in a new olive grove. This requires a transdisciplinary approach that goes from plant physiology to urban planning and is able to identify and correlate the interactions between ecological and anthropic processes and between the different ecological scales and institutional levels, allowing the development of a holistic vision of the evolution of the landscape. Although providing public-health benefits are not the primary focus of many urban-forestry programs, in this specific case strategic planning is needed, which should not be limited to simply replacing sick plants with new plants, but that should be able to encourage the development of a new landscape able to provide similar ecosystem services provided by old olive groves.</p><p>The Apulia region has started a new challenge, not just focusing on what the territory is losing, but on what it can be gained from this situation. This implies a change of approach to try to be more proactive and not just conservative.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We are grateful to Stefano Azeni for providing the 1887 historical map of land used in this study.</p></ack><notes><title>Author Contributions</title><p>Conceptualization, A.L., T.S. and R.B.; methodology, T.S. and M.V.; software, E.G., R.B. and Z.G.; formal analysis, T.S. and E.G.; writing&#x02014;original draft preparation, T.S., E.G. and M.V.; writing&#x02014;review and editing, A.L., R.B. and Z.G.; supervision, A.L., L.D.B., and R.B.</p></notes><notes><title>Funding</title><p>This research received no external funding.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Conflicts of Interest</title><p>The authors declare no conflict of interest.</p></notes><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1-ijerph-16-02642"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Snowdon</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Binner</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Agarwala</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Day</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bateman</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Harwood</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Valuing the Social and Environmental Contribution of Woodlands and Trees in England, Scotland and Wales</source><comment>Research Note</comment><publisher-name>Forestry Commission</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Edinburgh, UK</publisher-loc><year>2017</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2-ijerph-16-02642"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berman</surname><given-names>M.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jonides</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The cognitive benefits of interacting with nature</article-title><source>Psychol. Sci.</source><year>2008</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1207</fpage><lpage>1212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1467-9280.2008.02225.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19121124?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19121124</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3-ijerph-16-02642"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Berman</surname><given-names>M.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kross</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Krpan</surname><given-names>K.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Askren</surname><given-names>M.K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Burson</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Deldin</surname><given-names>P.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaplan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sherdell</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gotlib</surname><given-names>I.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jonides</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interacting with nature improves cognition and affect for individuals with depression</article-title><source>J. Affect. Disord.</source><year>2012</year><volume>140</volume><fpage>300</fpage><lpage>305</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2012.03.012</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22464936?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22464936</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4-ijerph-16-02642"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Grahn</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Stigsdotter</surname><given-names>U.A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Landscape planning and stress</article-title><source>Urban For. Urban Green.</source><year>2003</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>18</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1078/1618-8667-00019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5-ijerph-16-02642"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>M.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alcock</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wheeler</surname><given-names>B.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Depledge</surname><given-names>M.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Would you be happier living in a greener urban area? A fixed-effects analysis of panel data</article-title><source>Psychol. Sci.</source><year>2013</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>920</fpage><lpage>928</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0956797612464659</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23613211?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23613211</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6-ijerph-16-02642"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bratman</surname><given-names>G.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamilton</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hahn</surname><given-names>K.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Daily</surname><given-names>G.C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>J.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Nature experience reduces rumination and subgenual prefrontal cortex activation</article-title><source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><year>2015</year><volume>112</volume><fpage>8567</fpage><lpage>8572</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1510459112</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26124129?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26124129</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7-ijerph-16-02642"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mayer</surname><given-names>F.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Frantz</surname><given-names>C.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bruehlman-Senecal</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dolliver</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Why is nature beneficial: The role of connectedness to nature</article-title><source>Environ. Behav.</source><year>2009</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>607</fpage><lpage>643</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0013916508319745</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8-ijerph-16-02642"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Donovan</surname><given-names>G.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Butry</surname><given-names>D.T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Michael</surname><given-names>Y.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Prestemon</surname><given-names>J.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Liebhold</surname><given-names>A.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gatziolis</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mao</surname><given-names>M.Y.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The relationship between trees and human health: Evidence from the spread of the emerald ash borer</article-title><source>Am. J. Prev. Med.</source><year>2013</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>145</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.amepre.2012.09.066</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23332329?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23332329</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9-ijerph-16-02642"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>James</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hart</surname><given-names>J.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Banay</surname><given-names>R.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Laden</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exposure to greenness and mortality in a nationwide prospective cohort study of women</article-title><source>EHP Toxicogenomics</source><year>2016</year><volume>124</volume><fpage>1344</fpage><lpage>1352</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1289/ehp.1510363</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27074702?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27074702</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10-ijerph-16-02642"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ellaway</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Macintyre</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonnefoy</surname><given-names>X.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Graffiti, greenery, and obesity in adults: Secondary analysis of European cross sectional survey</article-title><source>BMJ</source><year>2005</year><volume>331</volume><fpage>611</fpage><lpage>612</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bmj.38575.664549.F7</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16113034?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16113034</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11-ijerph-16-02642"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salbitano</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Borelli</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Conigliaro</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chen</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Guidelines on Urban and Peri-Urban Forestry</source><comment>FAO Forestry Paper No.178</comment><publisher-name>Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Rome, Italy</publisher-loc><year>2016</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12-ijerph-16-02642"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Livesley</surname><given-names>S.J.</given-names></name><name><surname>McPherson</surname><given-names>E.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Calfapietra</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The urban forest and ecosystem services: Impacts on urban water, heat, and pollution cycles at the tree, street, and city scale</article-title><source>J. Environ. Qual.</source><year>2016</year><volume>45</volume><fpage>119</fpage><lpage>124</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2134/jeq2015.11.0567</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26828167?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26828167</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13-ijerph-16-02642"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Salmond</surname><given-names>J.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tadaki</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vardoulakis</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Arbuthnott</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Coutts</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Demuzere</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dirks</surname><given-names>K.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Heaviside</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Macintyre</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Health and climate related ecosystem services provided by street trees in the urban environment</article-title><source>Environ. Health</source><year>2016</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>36</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12940-016-0103-6</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26961700?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26961700</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B14-ijerph-16-02642"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Santamouris</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ban-Weiss</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Osmond</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paolini</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Synnefa</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cartalis</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Muscio</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zinzi</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morakinyo</surname><given-names>T.E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ng</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Progress in urban greenery mitigation science&#x02013;assessment methodologies advanced technologies and impact on cities</article-title><source>J. Civ. Eng. Manag.</source><year>2018</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>638</fpage><lpage>671</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3846/jcem.2018.6604</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B15-ijerph-16-02642"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pechanec</surname><given-names>V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Machar</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pohanka</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Opr&#x00161;al</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Petrovi&#x0010d;</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x00160;vajda</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x00160;&#x000e1;lek</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chobot</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Filippovov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cudl&#x000ed;n</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Effectiveness of Natura 2000 system for habitat types protection: A case study from the Czech Republic</article-title><source>Nat. Conserv.</source><year>2018</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>21</fpage><lpage>41</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3897/natureconservation.24.21608</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B16-ijerph-16-02642"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lester</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Big tree, small news: Media access, symbolic power and strategic intervention</article-title><source>Journalism</source><year>2010</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>589</fpage><lpage>606</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/1464884910373537</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B17-ijerph-16-02642"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blicharska</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mikusinski</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Incorporating social and cultural significance of large old trees in conservation policy</article-title><source>Conserv. Biol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>1558</fpage><lpage>1567</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/cobi.12341</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25115905</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B18-ijerph-16-02642"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oprsal</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kladivo</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Machar</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of selected biophysical factors in long-term land-use change of cultural landscape</article-title><source>Appl. Ecol. Environ. Res.</source><year>2016</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>40</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.15666/aeer/1402_023040</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B19-ijerph-16-02642"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bello</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Galetti</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pizo</surname><given-names>M.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Magnaso</surname><given-names>L.F.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Rocha</surname><given-names>M.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lima</surname><given-names>R.A.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Peres</surname><given-names>C.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ovaskainen</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jordano</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Defaunation affects carbon storage in tropical forests</article-title><source>Sci. Adv.</source><year>2015</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>e1501105</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/sciadv.1501105</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26824067</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B20-ijerph-16-02642"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lindenmayer</surname><given-names>D.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Laurance</surname><given-names>W.F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Franklin</surname><given-names>J.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global decline in large old trees</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2012</year><volume>338</volume><fpage>1305</fpage><lpage>1306</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1231070</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23224548</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B21-ijerph-16-02642"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lindenmayer</surname><given-names>D.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Laurance</surname><given-names>W.F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The ecology, distribution, conservation and management of large old trees</article-title><source>Biol. Rev. Camb. Philos. Soc.</source><year>2017</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>1434</fpage><lpage>1458</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/brv.12290</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27383287</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B22-ijerph-16-02642"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Daszak</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cunningham</surname><given-names>A.A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hyatt</surname><given-names>A.D.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Emerging infectious diseases of wildlife&#x02014;Threats to biodiversity and human health</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2000</year><volume>287</volume><fpage>443</fpage><lpage>449</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.287.5452.443</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10642539</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B23-ijerph-16-02642"><label>23.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Kleunen</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Dawson</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Essl</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pergl</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Winter</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weber</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kreft</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Weigelt</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kartesz</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nishino</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Global exchange and accumulation of non-native plants</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2015</year><volume>525</volume><fpage>100</fpage><lpage>103</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature14910</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26287466?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26287466</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B24-ijerph-16-02642"><label>24.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Waipara</surname><given-names>N.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>L.M.W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hough</surname><given-names>E.G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Horner</surname><given-names>I.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Surveillance methods to determine tree health, distribution of Kauri Dieback disease and associated pathogens</article-title><source>N. Z. Plant Prot.</source><year>2013</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>235</fpage><lpage>241</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B25-ijerph-16-02642"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giampetruzzi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morelli</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saponari</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Loconsole</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiumenti</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boscia</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Savino</surname><given-names>V.N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martelli</surname><given-names>G.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saldarelli</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcriptome profiling of two olive cultivars in response to infection by the CoDiRO strain of <italic>Xylella fastidiosa</italic> subsp. <italic>pauca</italic></article-title><source>BMC Genomics</source><year>2016</year><volume>1</volume><elocation-id>475</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s12864-016-2833-9</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27350531?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27350531</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B26-ijerph-16-02642"><label>26.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saponari</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boscia</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nigro</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martelli</surname><given-names>G.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Identification of DNA sequences related to <italic>Xylella fastidiosa</italic> in oleander, almond and olive trees exhibiting leaf scorch symptoms in Apulia (Southern Italy)</article-title><source>J. Plant Pathol.</source><year>2013</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>668</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B27-ijerph-16-02642"><label>27.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luvisi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicol&#x000ec;</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Bellis</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sustainable management of plant quarantine pests: The case of olive quick decline syndrome</article-title><source>Sustainability</source><year>2017</year><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>659</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/su9040659</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B28-ijerph-16-02642"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sabella</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Luvisi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aprile</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Negro</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vergine</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicol&#x000ec;</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miceli</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Bellis</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Xylella fastidiosa</italic> induces differential expression of lignification related-genes and lignin accumulation in tolerant olive trees cv. Leccino</article-title><source>J. Plant Physiol.</source><year>2018</year><volume>220</volume><fpage>60</fpage><lpage>68</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jplph.2017.10.007</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29149645?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29149645</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B29-ijerph-16-02642"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Loconsole</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saponari</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boscia</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x02019;Attoma</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morelli</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Martelli</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Almeida</surname><given-names>R.P.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intercepted isolates of <italic>Xylella fastidiosa</italic> in Europe reveal novel genetic diversity</article-title><source>Eur. J. Plant Pathol.</source><year>2016</year><volume>146</volume><fpage>85</fpage><lpage>94</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10658-016-0894-x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B30-ijerph-16-02642"><label>30.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chatterjee</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Almeida</surname><given-names>R.P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindow</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Living in two worlds: The plant and insect lifestyles of <italic>Xylella fastidiosa</italic></article-title><source>Annu. Rev. Phytopathol.</source><year>2008</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>243</fpage><lpage>271</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.phyto.45.062806.094342</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18422428?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18422428</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B31-ijerph-16-02642"><label>31.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lindow</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Money Matters: Fueling Rapid Recent Insight Into <italic>Xylella fastidiosa</italic>&#x02014;An Important and Expanding Global Pathogen</article-title><source>Phytopathology</source><year>2019</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>210</fpage><lpage>212</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/PHYTO-09-18-0325-PER</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30644806</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B32-ijerph-16-02642"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Luvisi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aprile</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Sabella</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Vergine</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicol&#x000ec;</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nutricati</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Miceli</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Negro</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Bellis</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>Xylella fastidiosa</italic> subsp. <italic>pauca</italic> (CoDiRO strain) infection in four olive (<italic>Olea europaea</italic> L.) cultivars: Profile of phenolic compounds in leaves and progression of leaf scorch symptoms</article-title><source>Phytopathol. Mediterr.</source><year>2017</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>259</fpage><lpage>273</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.14601/phytopathol_mediterr-20578</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B33-ijerph-16-02642"><label>33.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Colella</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carradore</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Cerro</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Problem Setting and Problem Solving in the Case of Olive Quick Decline Syndrome in Apulia, Italy: A Sociological Approach</article-title><source>Phytopathology</source><year>2019</year><volume>109</volume><fpage>187</fpage><lpage>199</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/PHYTO-07-18-0247-FI</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 30589371?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">30589371</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B34-ijerph-16-02642"><label>34.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Saponari</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boscia</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Altamura</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Loconsole</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zicca</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>D&#x02019;Attoma</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morelli</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Palmisano</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Saponari</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tavano</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Isolation and pathogenicity of <italic>Xylella fastidiosa</italic> associated to the olive quick decline syndrome in southern Italy</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2017</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>17723</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-17957-z</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 29255232?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29255232</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B35-ijerph-16-02642"><label>35.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maggiore</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Semeraro</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aretano</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>De Bellis</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Luvisi</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>GIS Analysis of Land-Use Change in Threatened Landscapes by <italic>Xylella fastidiosa</italic></article-title><source>Sustainability</source><year>2019</year><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>253</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/su11010253</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B36-ijerph-16-02642"><label>36.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Semeraro</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pomes</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Del Giudice</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Negro</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aretano</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Planning ground based utility scale solar energy as green infrastructure to enhance ecosystem services</article-title><source>Energy Policy</source><year>2018</year><volume>117</volume><fpage>218</fpage><lpage>227</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.enpol.2018.01.050</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B37-ijerph-16-02642"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="web"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>ISTAT. Geodemo</collab></person-group><article-title>Maps, Population, Demography of ISTAT&#x02014;Italian Institute of Statistics</article-title><year>2018</year><comment>Available online: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://demo.istat.it/pop2018/index.html">http://demo.istat.it/pop2018/index.html</ext-link></comment><date-in-citation content-type="access-date" iso-8601-date="2019-05-20">(accessed on 20 May 2019)</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="B38-ijerph-16-02642"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tsoka</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsikaloudaki</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Theodosiou</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Analyzing the ENVI-met microclimate model&#x02019;s performance and assessing cool materials and urban vegetation applications&#x02014;A review</article-title><source>Sustain. Cities Soc.</source><year>2018</year><volume>43</volume><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>76</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.scs.2018.08.009</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B39-ijerph-16-02642"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="web"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>ENVI-Met</collab></person-group><article-title>Decoding Urban Nature&#x02014;Microclimate Simulations, 2018</article-title><comment>Available online: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.envi-met.info/doku.php?id=kb:review">http://www.envi-met.info/doku.php?id=kb:review</ext-link></comment><date-in-citation content-type="access-date" iso-8601-date="2019-05-20">(accessed on 20 May 2019)</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="B40-ijerph-16-02642"><label>40.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rui</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Buccolieri</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name><name><surname>Ding</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name><name><surname>Shen</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The Impact of Green Space Layouts on Microclimate and Air Quality in Residential Districts of Nanjing, China</article-title><source>Forests</source><year>2018</year><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>224</elocation-id><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3390/f9040224</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B41-ijerph-16-02642"><label>41.</label><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Monteiro</surname><given-names>L.M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Alucci</surname><given-names>M.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Proposal of an outdoor thermal comfort index: Empirical verification in the subtropical climate</article-title><source>Proceedings of the 27th International Conference on Passive and Low Energy Architecture (PLEA 2011)</source><conf-loc>Louvain-la-Neuve, Belgium</conf-loc><conf-date>13&#x02013;15 July 2011</conf-date><fpage>433</fpage><lpage>438</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B42-ijerph-16-02642"><label>42.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Almeida</surname><given-names>R.P.P.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Can Apulia&#x02019;s olive trees be saved?</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2016</year><volume>353</volume><fpage>346</fpage><lpage>348</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.aaf9710</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27463657</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B43-ijerph-16-02642"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Costanza</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>d&#x02019;Arge</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>de Groot</surname><given-names>R.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Farber</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Grasso</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hannon</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Limburg</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name><name><surname>Naeem</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>O&#x02019;Neill</surname><given-names>R.V.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paruelo</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The value of the world&#x02019;s ecosystem services and natural capital</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1997</year><volume>387</volume><fpage>253</fpage><lpage>260</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/387253a0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B44-ijerph-16-02642"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Groot</surname><given-names>R.S.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Functions of Nature: Evaluation of Nature in Environmental Planning, Management and Decision-Making</source><publisher-name>Wolters Noordhoff BV</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Groningen, The Netherlands</publisher-loc><year>1992</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="B45-ijerph-16-02642"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Groot</surname><given-names>R.S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Boumans</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A typology for the description, classification and valuation of Ecosystem Functions</article-title><source>Goods Serv. Econ.</source><year>2002</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>393</fpage><lpage>408</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0921-8009(02)00089-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B46-ijerph-16-02642"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Groot</surname><given-names>R.S.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>&#x0201c;Function-analysis and valuation as a tool to assess land use conflicts in planning for sustainable, multi-functional landscapes&#x0201d;, Landscape and Urban Planning</article-title><source>Ecosystems and Human Well-Being: Synthesis</source><comment>Millenium Ecosystem Assessment</comment><publisher-name>Island Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Washington, DC, USA</publisher-loc><year>2006</year><volume>Volume 75</volume><fpage>175</fpage><lpage>186</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B47-ijerph-16-02642"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>K.J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Classification of ecosystem services: Problems and solutions</article-title><source>Biol. Conserv.</source><year>2007</year><volume>139</volume><fpage>235</fpage><lpage>246</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biocon.2007.07.015</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B48-ijerph-16-02642"><label>48.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burkhard</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kroll</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Windhorst</surname><given-names>W.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Landscapes&#x02018; Capacities to Provide Ecosystem Services&#x02014;A Concept for Land-Cover Based Assessments</article-title><source>Landsc. Online</source><year>2009</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3097/LO.200915</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B49-ijerph-16-02642"><label>49.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burkhard</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kroll</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name><name><surname>Nedkov</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mapping ecosystem service supply, demand and budgets</article-title><source>Ecol. Indic.</source><year>2012</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>29</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecolind.2011.06.019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B50-ijerph-16-02642"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benayas</surname><given-names>J.M.R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Bullock</surname><given-names>J.M.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Restoration of Biodiversity and Ecosystem Services on Agricultural Land</article-title><source>Ecosystems</source><year>2012</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>883</fpage><lpage>899</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10021-012-9552-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B51-ijerph-16-02642"><label>51.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Scolozzi</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Moroni</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Santolini</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Delphi-based change assessment in ecosystem service values to support strategic spatial planning in Italian landscapes</article-title><source>Ecol. Indic.</source><year>2012</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>134</fpage><lpage>144</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecolind.2011.07.019</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B52-ijerph-16-02642"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burkhard</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kandziora</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hou</surname><given-names>Y.</given-names></name><name><surname>M&#x000fc;ller</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ecosystem Service Potentials, Flows and Demands&#x02013; Concepts for Spatial Localisation, Indication and Quantification</article-title><source>Landsc. Online</source><year>2014</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3097/LO.201434</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B53-ijerph-16-02642"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koschke</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>F&#x000fc;rst</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Makeschin</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A multi-criteria approach for an integrated land-cover-based assessment of ecosystem services provision to support landscape planning</article-title><source>Ecol. Indic.</source><year>2012</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>54</fpage><lpage>66</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecolind.2011.12.010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B54-ijerph-16-02642"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vihervaara</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kumpula</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Tanskanen</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Burkhard</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ecosystem services&#x02014;A tool for sustainable management of human&#x02013;environment systems. Case study Finnish Forest Lapland</article-title><source>Ecol. Complex.</source><year>2010</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>410</fpage><lpage>420</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecocom.2009.12.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B55-ijerph-16-02642"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clerici</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Paracchini</surname><given-names>M.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Maes</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Land-cover change dynamics and insights into ecosystem services in European stream riparian zones</article-title><source>Ecohydrol. Hydrobiol.</source><year>2014</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>107</fpage><lpage>120</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecohyd.2014.01.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B56-ijerph-16-02642"><label>56.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gissi</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name><name><surname>Burkhard</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Verburg</surname><given-names>P.H.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ecosystem services: Building informed policies to orient landscape dynamics</article-title><source>Int. J. Biodivers. Sci. Ecosyst. Serv. Manag.</source><year>2015</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>185</fpage><lpage>189</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/21513732.2015.1071939</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B57-ijerph-16-02642"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="web"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>European Commission</collab></person-group><article-title>Mapping and Assessment of Ecosystems and their Services. Joint Research Centre Institute for Environment and Sustainability</article-title><year>2015</year><comment>Available online: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://publications.jrc.ec.europa.eu/repository/bitstream/JRC94889/lbna27143enn.pdf">http://publications.jrc.ec.europa.eu/repository/bitstream/JRC94889/lbna27143enn.pdf</ext-link></comment><date-in-citation content-type="access-date" iso-8601-date="2019-05-20">(accessed on 20 May 2019)</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="B58-ijerph-16-02642"><label>58.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aretano</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Petrosillo</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaccarelli</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name><name><surname>Semeraro</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zurlini</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>People perception of landscape change effects on ecosystem services in small Mediterranean islands: A combination of subjective and objective assessments</article-title><source>Landsc. Urban Plan.</source><year>2013</year><volume>112</volume><fpage>63</fpage><lpage>73</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.landurbplan.2012.12.010</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B59-ijerph-16-02642"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aretano</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Parlagreco</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Semeraro</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zurlini</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Petrosillo</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coastal dynamics vs. beach users attitudes and perceptions to enhance environmental conservation and management effectiveness</article-title><source>Mar. Pollut. Bull.</source><year>2017</year><volume>123</volume><fpage>142</fpage><lpage>155</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.marpolbul.2017.09.003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 28923578?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28923578</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B60-ijerph-16-02642"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aviron</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Berg</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Crous-Duran</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Franca</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;ade Jal&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Hartel</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mirck</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name><name><surname>Pantera</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Palma</surname><given-names>J.H.N.</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Agroforestry systems of high nature and cultural value in Europe: Provision of commercial goods and other ecosystem services</article-title><source>Agroforest Syst.</source><year>2018</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>877</fpage><lpage>891</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10457-017-0126-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B61-ijerph-16-02642"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Semeraro</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name><name><surname>Mastroleo</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Aretano</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name><name><surname>Facchinetti</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zurlini</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Petrosillo</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>GIS Fuzzy Expert System for the assessment of ecosystems vulnerability to fire in managing Mediterranean natural protected areas</article-title><source>J. Environ. Manag.</source><year>2016</year><volume>168</volume><fpage>94</fpage><lpage>103</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jenvman.2015.11.053</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 26696610?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26696610</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B62-ijerph-16-02642"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="web"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>IUCN&#x02014;International Union for Conservation of Nature and Natural Resources</collab></person-group><article-title>The IUCN Red List of Threatened Species</article-title><year>2014</year><comment>Version 2014.3</comment><comment>Available online: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.iucnredlist.org">http://www.iucnredlist.org</ext-link></comment><date-in-citation content-type="access-date" iso-8601-date="2019-05-20">(accessed on 20 May 2019)</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="B63-ijerph-16-02642"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zurlini</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name><name><surname>Petrosillo</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>K.B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>B.L.</given-names></name><name><surname>Riitters</surname><given-names>K.H.</given-names></name><name><surname>Medagli</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name><name><surname>Marchiori</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Zaccarelli</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Towards the planning and design of disturbance patterns across scales to counter biological invasions</article-title><source>J. Environ. Manag.</source><year>2013</year><volume>128</volume><fpage>192</fpage><lpage>203</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jenvman.2013.05.006</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23747370?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23747370</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B64-ijerph-16-02642"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andrews</surname><given-names>P.L.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Behave Plus Fire Modeling System, Version 5.0: Variables</source><comment>General Technical Report RMRS-GTR-213WWW Revised</comment><publisher-name>Department of Agriculture, Forest Service, Rocky Mountain Research Station</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Fort Collins, CO, USA</publisher-loc><year>2009</year><comment>Available online: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fs.fed.us/rm/pubs/rmrs_gtr213.pdf">http://www.fs.fed.us/rm/pubs/rmrs_gtr213.pdf</ext-link></comment><date-in-citation content-type="access-date" iso-8601-date="2019-05-20">(accessed on 20 May 2019)</date-in-citation></element-citation></ref><ref id="B65-ijerph-16-02642"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name><name><surname>Holling</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name><name><surname>Carpenter</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kinzig</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Resilience, adaptability and transformability in social-ecological systems</article-title><source>Ecol. Soc.</source><year>2004</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>5</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5751/ES-00650-090205</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="B66-ijerph-16-02642"><label>66.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cerroni</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Simonella</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name></person-group><source>Sociologia della Scienza. Capire la Scienza per Capire la Societ&#x000e0; Contemporanea</source><publisher-name>Carocci</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Rome, Italy</publisher-loc><year>2014</year></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back><floats-group><fig id="ijerph-16-02642-f001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Study area: (<bold>a</bold>) The Province of Lecce in south Apulia; (<bold>b</bold>) the municipalities of Apulia region are characterized by a core urban mainly surrounded by olive groves, the latter currently strongly affected by <italic>X. fastidiosa</italic>, (<bold>c</bold>) the two selected peri-urban neighborhoods characterized by olive groves in the municipalities of Parabita and Matino. In the first case (municipality of Parabita) the olive groves surround the portion of the urban area, in the second case (municipality of Matino) the olive groves penetrate into the urban area.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijerph-16-02642-g001"/></fig><fig id="ijerph-16-02642-f002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Example of eradication activity carried out in the early 2019. The scenarios represent the short- and medium-term transformation considered for the qualitative analysis of the change in ecosystem services caused by <italic>X. fastidiosa</italic>. (<bold>a</bold>) Picture of olive trees affected by <italic>X. fastidiosa</italic> (December 2018), (<bold>b</bold>) same as (<bold>a</bold>), but after eradication (February 2019), (<bold>c</bold>) same as (<bold>a</bold>) but some months after eradication (April 2019).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijerph-16-02642-g002"/></fig><fig id="ijerph-16-02642-f003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Geographical position of the ARPA-Puglia meteorological station with indication of the study neighborhoods (Matino and Parabita) (from Google Earth) and their reconstructions in ENVI-met (red rhombus indicate the receptors where data have been extracted for microclimate analysis).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijerph-16-02642-g003"/></fig><fig id="ijerph-16-02642-f004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Maps showing the presence of urban areas, olive groves and other land uses in the years 1887 and 2016 and relative intersection.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijerph-16-02642-g004"/></fig><fig id="ijerph-16-02642-f005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Olive trees studied in municipalities of (<bold>a</bold>) Matino and (<bold>b</bold>) Parabita with symptoms of disease (&#x0201c;olive quick decline syndrome&#x0201d;, OQDS) severity between level 2 to 3.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijerph-16-02642-g005"/></fig><fig id="ijerph-16-02642-f006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Air temperature hourly profiles for Matino (left) and Parabita (right) inside the street canyon (top) and within the olive grove (bottom) (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-02642-f003">Figure 3</xref> for the position of receptors R1, R2, R3 and R4).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijerph-16-02642-g006"/></fig><fig id="ijerph-16-02642-f007" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Temperature of equivalent perception (TEP) hourly profiles for Matino (left) and Parabita (right) inside the street canyon (top) and within the olive grove (bottom) (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-02642-f003">Figure 3</xref> for the position of R1, R2, R3 and R4 receptors).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijerph-16-02642-g007"/></fig><fig id="ijerph-16-02642-f008" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 8</label><caption><p>Predicted mean vote (PMV) hourly profiles for Matino (left) and Parabita (right) inside the street canyon (top) and within the olive grove (bottom) (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-02642-f003">Figure 3</xref> for the position of R1, R2, R3 and R4 receptors).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijerph-16-02642-g008"/></fig><fig id="ijerph-16-02642-f009" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 9</label><caption><p>Spatial distribution of PMV at 15:00 for Matino (top) and Parabita (bottom) inside the street canyon (top) and within the olive grove (bottom) (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-02642-f003">Figure 3</xref> for the position of receptors R1, R2, R3 and R4).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijerph-16-02642-g009"/></fig><fig id="ijerph-16-02642-f010" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 10</label><caption><p>Conceptual model of management of areas affected by <italic>X. fastidiosa</italic>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="ijerph-16-02642-g010"/></fig></floats-group></article>