<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Under the highest RCP scenario in which CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> concentrations will continue to increase till the year 2200 (RCP 8.5), regions vulnerable to PWD are likely to become wide-spread across Europe and Asia, resulting in serious economic and ecological damage. In northern Europe, the forestry industry is primarily based on native tree species, including 
 <italic class="italic">Pinus</italic> species such as 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">nigra</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">pinaster</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">sylvestris</italic> [
 <xref rid="pone.0182837.ref064" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">64</xref>]. Our study suggests that the majority of distribution areas of 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">nigra</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">pinaster</italic> will become vulnerable to PWD in the future, despite the low risk under current climate conditions. PWD damage of these species would seriously affect the European forestry industry. Moreover, in northwestern Russia, rare old-growth natural forests have been preserved [
 <xref rid="pone.0182837.ref064" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">64</xref>], and 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">sylvestris</italic> is the primary species of such forests [
 <xref rid="pone.0182837.ref004" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0182837.ref064" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">64</xref>]. If such forests were infected by PWD, the ecosystem structure of these valuable old-growth forests would be seriously modified. Boreal forests are also primary carbon sinks [
 <xref rid="pone.0182837.ref065" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">65</xref>], particularly 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">sylvestris</italic> forests in Siberia and European Russia [
 <xref rid="pone.0182837.ref065" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">65</xref>]. The spread of PWD in these areas would therefore change these forests into carbon sources with the death of large numbers of 
 <italic class="italic">Pinus</italic> trees.
</p>
