<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">
 <italic class="italic">A. nodosum</italic> populations at the northern fringe of sub-arctic are growing at the slowest rates when compared with those of the species across its the biogeographical distribution range (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" class="xref">6</xref>), which further underlines the stimulating role of temperature. Seawater summer temperature at the northern 
 <italic class="italic">A. nodosum</italic> population ranges from 6 to 14 °C whereas 
 <italic class="italic">A. nodosum</italic> populations below 50
 <sup class="sup">o</sup>N, exhibiting maximum growth rates, are exposed to seawater summer temperature exceeding 21 °C (Keser and Larson 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" class="xref">1984</xref>; Peckol et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" class="xref">1988</xref>; Keser et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">2005</xref>). Independent studies support the positive effect of warming on 
 <italic class="italic">A. nodosum</italic> growth until an upper threshold is reached (Fortes and Lüning 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">1980</xref>; Keser et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">2005</xref>; Wilson et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" class="xref">2015</xref>). An assessment of changes in the abundance of large brown seaweeds across the British Isles over past four decades reports overall favourable effects of warmer summer and winter temperatures on 
 <italic class="italic">A. nodosum</italic> where mean summer temperatures reach a maximum of about 16 °C (Yesson et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" class="xref">2015</xref>). Long-term (1979–2002) in situ studies of 
 <italic class="italic">A. nodosum</italic> growth in Connecticut, USA, also reported enhanced seaweed growth with warming until temperatures reached 25 °C. Growth rates decreased rapidly and mortality increased as temperatures exceeded 27–28 °C (Keser et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">2005</xref>). These findings were confirmed experimentally, when warming above 23 °C resulted in reduced growth and simulations of heat waves (26, 29 °C) increased the mortality of 
 <italic class="italic">A. nodosum</italic> in Nova Scotia, Atlantic Canada (Wilson et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" class="xref">2015</xref>). Both studies are in line with the fact that we found no studies of in situ 
 <italic class="italic">A. nodosum</italic> growth at summer temperatures above 24 °C. Longphuirt et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" class="xref">2013</xref>) further reported that 
 <italic class="italic">A. nodosum</italic> exhibits higher CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> affinity at higher temperature, suggesting a seasonal strategy of photosynthetic up-regulation during the growth period. Competitive interactions amongst coexisting intertidal species may also change with warming and affect 
 <italic class="italic">A. nodosum</italic> distribution patterns. Indeed, the increased occurrence of 
 <italic class="italic">Fucus vesiculosus</italic> in 
 <italic class="italic">A. nodosum</italic> beds has been attributed to synergetic effect of sea surface warming combined with harvesting (Ugarte et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" class="xref">2010</xref>).
</p>
