<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par4" class="p">For large mammals, loss of habitat and anthropogenic linear features are key drivers of many conservation problems. Establishment of protected areas has been shown to be effective in many cases as it prevents further habitat losses or creates a place for habitat recovery
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">15</xref>
 </sup>. Similarly, studies have shown that linear features such as secondary roads are heavily used by predators
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">17</xref>
 </sup> and, at high density, may increase predator-prey encounter rates
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">18</xref>
 </sup> and consequently prey mortality
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" class="xref">19</xref>
 </sup>. Thus, land rehabilitation through road removal (hereafter “road restoration”) could further benefit endangered prey species, like caribou, by reducing predation rates, a known factor in our study population’s decline
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">20</xref>
 </sup>. Their impacts on populations are numerous
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">21</xref>
 </sup>, depending on the size of the road: difficulty of crossing due to fences and light
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">22</xref>
 </sup>, increased probability of predator presence
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">18</xref>
 </sup>, and risk of collisions. Secondary roads (e.g., forestry roads) have the potential to be restored, and on primary roads (e.g., highways) over or under-passes can be installed (e.g., Banff National Park
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">23</xref>
 </sup>). We do not know how effective these two major conservation measures are, or to what degree they are able to compensate for predicted loses due to climate change.
</p>
