<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par5" class="p">In this study, we propose a simple framework illustrated with a case study to assess the effectiveness of compensatory conservation measures. This involves explicit coupling of efforts at quantifying climate change impacts with efforts at identifying and quantifying conservation measures that might have a similar magnitude, but opposite, impacts. By doing this, we explicitly identify conservation measures that can compensate for undesired changes due to future climate. For our case study, we were motivated by the need for species to move to follow their habitat as it changes with climate and land management and to allow or enhance mixing between disjunct populations. We therefore examine different movement behaviors, among which the movement potential, of an endangered population within a landscape. “Movement potential” has been used in two contrasting ways in the recent literature: by Gustine 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">24</xref>
 </sup> to refer to an estimated area accessible from a location given observed movement rates; and by Hooten 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" class="xref">25</xref>
 </sup> as a potential field whose value at a point is the preferred direction of movement, determined by the gradient of environmental conditions. For the purposes of this study, we define “movement potential” as the aggregate of individuals’ capability and propensity to change their spatial location. Capability depends on individuals’ physical ability and the spatial configuration of their environment
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" class="xref">26</xref>
 </sup>. Propensity reflects individuals’ desire to leave or reach certain places
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" class="xref">26</xref>
 </sup>. Climate change and anthropogenic activities can affect movement potential
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" class="xref">27</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>
 </sup> by altering environmental conditions
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">20</xref>
 </sup> thus changing either individual’s capability
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>
 </sup> or propensity
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">30</xref>
 </sup> to move.
</p>
