<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="P41" class="p">Observational metrics calculated at individual sites can provide insight into the physical and chemical processes that determine ozone and its variations on different timescales (e.g., 
 <xref rid="R124" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Logan, 1985</xref>; 
 <xref rid="R150" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Oltmans and Levy II, 1994</xref>). Hence, comparison of these metrics calculated at surface sites with modeled ozone levels is one method used to evaluate the performance of global models in predicting tropospheric ozone. Besides uncertainties in observations, a major problem in the comparison of site-specific data with model output is the representativeness of the available measurements. Problems related to the comparison of spatially and temporally sparse observations with coarse resolution global scale models, discussed in more detail in 
 <italic class="italic">TOAR-Model Performance</italic>, can be mitigated by comparing model output against globally gridded observational data products that have been aggregated based on site characterization (e.g., 
 <italic class="italic">TOAR-Surface Ozone Database</italic>). 
 <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref> summarizes the TOAR metrics (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.igacproject.org/activities/TOAR" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.igacproject.org/activities/TOAR</ext-link>) used for model-measurement comparisons (based on hourly average levels), which are: 
 <list list-type="bullet" id="L3" class="list">
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="P42" class="p">The monthly mean of the 24-h average (MMEAN) (in units of ppb);</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="P43" class="p">The monthly standard deviation, median, 5
    <sup class="sup">th</sup>, 25
    <sup class="sup">th</sup>, 75
    <sup class="sup">th</sup>, and 95
    <sup class="sup">th</sup> percentiles of the maximum daily average 8-h (MDA8) ozone values (in units of ppb);
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="P44" class="p">The monthly mean diurnal cycle (monthly average of 1-h ozone averages at 0100 h, 0200 h, 0300 h, etc.) (in units of ppb); and</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="P45" class="p">Monthly mean of daily minimum and maximum hourly average ozone (in units of ppb).</p>
  </list-item>
 </list> The MMEAN ozone at individual sites is commonly used to study surface ozone variability for global model-measurement comparisons (see 
 <italic class="italic">TOAR-Model Performance</italic>). The magnitude of MMEAN depends upon the influence of precursor emissions, photochemistry, meteorology, and atmospheric transport on the shape of the annual cycle of ozone at individual sites. Comparison of simulated and observed MMEAN provides a first order estimate of the model’s ability to simulate the observed annual cycle as well as long-term trends and inter-annual variability. However, the MMEAN smooths the pronounced diurnal cycle observed at continental rural sites due to photochemical ozone production and/or enhanced nighttime surface ozone deposition or in-situ chemical loss under shallow nocturnal boundary layers. Global models at coarse resolution may have difficulty in reproducing these low nighttime values (e.g., 
 <xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Derwent et al., 2004</xref>) because of errors in representing the nocturnal boundary layer (
 <xref rid="R121" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lin et al., 2008</xref>) and because many chemical processes are nonlinear and therefore may not be accurately simulated when spatially averaging sharp gradients over larger grid-cells. Therefore, global model evaluation against observed MMEAN at individual sites with strong diurnal cycles should be supplemented with comparison against metrics which characterize the observed diurnal cycle (discussed below) to estimate their ability in reproducing observations (see 
 <italic class="italic">TOAR-Model Performance</italic>). The MMEAN exposure metric smooths the large day-to-day variability that occurs at many polluted sites.
</p>
