<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Presentations of future impacts require explicit communication of uncertainties, which includes realistic levels of precision [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002624.ref017" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>] and clear guidance on the relevance of the information (or not) for planning and decision-making. The process of delineating their limitations may, in itself, be enough to deter decision-makers from direct use. Climate model outputs cannot be used to infer local conditions, and they perform especially poorly at the level of an individual model grid. Nor can we use climate projections to infer anything about the future climate over periods shorter than 30 years. Because projections do not capture the timing of interannual and decadal variations, statistics should always be calculated over at least three decades. Extracting model output over shorter windows of time could result in a substantial over- or underestimation of the trend, particularly over the next 10 to 30 years. Alternatively, the output from several models can be averaged to cancel out the different phases of variability in each model. However, only the trend remains after this multi-model averaging is performed; interannual to decadal variability is an additional source of uncertainty in the projections that should be factored into future scenarios, for example, by taking past variability as an indicator of variability in the future [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002624.ref018" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="pmed.1002624.ref019" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>]. Finally, we cannot set too much store by probabilistic projections because the ensemble of models used in the projections is not an accurate representation of the full range of possible futures [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002624.ref009" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. The complexities of these considerations point to the importance of close collaboration between climate and health experts when conducting research on future impacts. Failure to capture the full range of uncertainty in decisions could lead to maladaptation [
 <xref rid="pmed.1002624.ref020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>].
</p>
