<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par5" class="p">The main goal of this study was to assess the potential for offspring size variation in both directionally warming and fluctuating environments by simulating changes to the mean and variance of sea surface temperatures (SST) predicted under climate change
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">1</xref>
 </sup> using the marine threespine stickleback fish (
 <italic class="italic">Gasterosteus aculeatus</italic>) as a model. The threespine stickleback (herein referred to simply as stickleback) is an ideal model for investigating evolutionary processes in general, and behavioural, morphological, and life history plasticity specifically. Stickleback occur in marine, brackish and freshwater environments throughout the northern hemisphere and can be easily bred and reared under laboratory conditions. Their extensive intraspecific variation coupled with a comprehensive genomic toolbox make them highly amenable for studies of the adaptive value of particular phenotypes
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" class="xref">39</xref>
 </sup>. Here, the role of maternal environment effects on reproductive traits and offspring size was investigated by acclimating stickleback mothers to either constant, predictably variable or stochastically varying temperatures to determine whether they can adjust how resources are allocated to offspring, and if within-clutch variation in offspring size changes in response to changes in mean temperature and temperature variability. Similarly, the roles of TGP and WGP (G × E interactions) were investigated by rearing sibling offspring in each experimental climate scenario to determine the shape of their (family) thermal reaction norms and to test the extent of genetic variation for plasticity of offspring size. The population studied here inhabits an area of the North Sea with a mean SST of 17 °C during summer months, but with abrupt changes in temperature direction occurring at irregular intervals
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>
 </sup>. Previous studies found that exposure to a constant elevated temperature of 21 °C (simulated in accordance with a 2100 climate scenario
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" class="xref">45</xref>
 </sup>) reflected a chronic stress for this population that had negative effects on growth, development and survival compared to ambient (17 °C) conditions
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" class="xref">46</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" class="xref">49</xref>
 </sup>. When reared at 21 °C, offspring had lower hatching success
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" class="xref">48</xref>
 </sup>, reached smaller sizes
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" class="xref">49</xref>
 </sup>, had higher shape variance
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" class="xref">46</xref>
 </sup> and higher mortality when exposed to pathogens than when reared at 17 °C
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" class="xref">47</xref>
 </sup>. Yet, when mothers were acclimated to constant 21 °C during reproductive conditioning (two months just prior to spawning), TGP in response to predictable environmental cues of future warming resulted in (relatively) larger offspring at 21 °C
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" class="xref">48</xref>
 </sup>. However, when stickleback were acclimated to unpredictable environments where the mean temperature switched weekly between 17 °C and 21 °C, mothers produced more variably sized offspring, suggesting that they may have used a diversifying bet-hedging strategy to cope with the variable environment
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>
 </sup>. But how mothers respond to stochastically varying environments may differ from their response in predictably varying conditions. For instance, SST can change by several degrees very quickly depending on erratic weather patterns and less frequent but more extreme events such as heat waves or cold snaps
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">4</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">6</xref>
 </sup>. Here again, mothers should hedge their bets, but whether they should employ diversifying or conservative bet hedging has not been investigated. Moreover, predictions for optimal offspring size in stochastic environments are equivocal (increase, decrease or no change), and few direct tests of the role of environmental predictability in driving offspring size variation have been conducted to date
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" class="xref">41</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
