<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">where 
 <italic class="italic">N</italic>
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">t</italic>
 </sub> and 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">t</italic>
 </sub> represent respectively the population densities of the budmoth and the parasitoids, 
 <italic class="italic">Q</italic>
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">t</italic>
 </sub> the PQI, 
 <italic class="italic">β</italic> a measure of the intra-specific competition within the budmoth population, for resources and space, 
 <italic class="italic">δ</italic> the half saturation constant for the plant quality index, 
 <italic class="italic">γ</italic> controls the maximum rate of the moth population uptake upon the plant, 
 <italic class="italic">a</italic> the searching rate for the parasitoids, 
 <italic class="italic">w</italic> the wasting time of the parasitoids; the handling time of the parasitoids has been taken to be zero in these equations
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8" class="xref">8</xref>. The parameter 
 <italic class="italic">b</italic> stands for the number of surviving parasitoids produced by each parasitized moth. Here, the parasitoid-budmoth interaction is described through the Nicholson-Bailey model
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23" class="xref">23</xref> except that it incorporates a different functional response (Holling type-2)
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24" class="xref">24</xref> for the parasitoid which mimics some of the observed data; in particular, prey consumption rises as a function of prey population density at very small prey population numbers, while plateauing to a constant value with increased prey availability. The interaction between the larch tree and the budmoth is modelled as a plant-herbivore interaction through a Ricker-like growth model
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25" class="xref">25</xref>, and a density dependent growth rate that is proportional to the available larch needle-lengths.
</p>
