<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2b" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2.</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data collection</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our study focuses on six breeding seasons with complete data (1999, 2000 and 2010–2013) and includes three additional years (2002–2004) where data were only collected between August and December for the analysis of the onset of breeding (details below). Colonies were visited every 1–4 days, and the contents of individual chambers were inspected to obtain laying dates and the number of chicks that fledged (further details on the field methods are described in Covas 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. [
  <a rid="RSOS170835C22" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170835C22">22</a>]). The nestling period lasts 21–24 days [
  <a rid="RSOS170835C38" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170835C38">38</a>], but in order to avoid prompting premature fledging, chambers were inspected for the last time 17 days after the first egg hatched, and we refer to the survival of chicks up to this point as fledging [
  <a rid="RSOS170835C22" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170835C22">22</a>]. Colony sizes were estimated during captures conducted before the start of each breeding season and here include adults aged 2 years or older, as yearlings rarely reproduce [
  <a rid="RSOS170835C34" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170835C34">34</a>]. All encounters with snakes (the primary nest predators, principally Cape cobras, 
  <span class="italic">Naja nivea</span>, and boomslangs, 
  <span class="italic">Dispholidus typus</span> [
  <a rid="RSOS170835C22" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170835C22">22</a>]) during visits to colonies were recorded to estimate colony-specific predation rates (for inclusion in the analyses of reproductive output, see details below). We excluded from our study all colonies in which food had been experimentally supplemented [
  <a rid="RSOS170835C33" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170835C33">33</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS170835C39" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170835C39">39</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Daily rainfall and temperature data were obtained from the South African Weather Service. We used data from the Kimberley Airport weather station (28°48′ S, 24°45′ E; 11 km northwest of the study site) rather than locally collected data, as the latter were not available for every day of the study period. Where daily rainfall data were available for both the study site and Kimberley Airport (
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 479 days), they showed similar values, with a mean absolute difference and standard deviation of 1.7 ± 5.2 mm.
 </p>
</sec>
