<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2c" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3.</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical methods</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The aim of our study was to determine the best climatic predictors of breeding decisions and output (namely, onset and length of the breeding season, probability of breeding, number of clutches laid and number of fledglings produced per season), among a suite of measures of rainfall and temperature (details below). Model selection was based on an information-theoretic approach, and for each analysis we constructed a candidate set of models (see the electronic supplementary material). We used Akaike's information criterion values [
  <a rid="RSOS170835C41" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170835C41">41</a>] corrected for small sample sizes (AIC
  <sub>c</sub>) [
  <a rid="RSOS170835C42" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170835C42">42</a>] and estimated AIC
  <sub>c</sub> differences (Δ
  <sub>AIC</sub>, the model's AIC
  <sub>c</sub> minus the minimum AIC
  <sub>c</sub> across all candidate models). Models with Δ
  <sub>AIC</sub> less than two were considered to be the ‘best’, opting for simpler models (those with fewer estimated parameters) when more than one model had Δ
  <sub>AIC</sub> &lt; 2 and similar fits to the data in terms of log-likelihood [
  <a rid="RSOS170835C42" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170835C42">42</a>]. We used this stringent ΔAIC cut-off as we were attempting to find parsimonious models within candidate sets that included nested models and models where correlated climatic variables had been fitted separately into otherwise identical models (details below). Variance explained by our best models was estimated following the methods described by O'Quigley 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. [
  <a rid="RSOS170835C43" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170835C43">43</a>] (proportion of randomness explained, 
  <span class="italic">ρ</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span>) and by Nakagawa &amp; Schielzeth [
  <a rid="RSOS170835C44" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170835C44">44</a>] (total variance explained, 
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <sub>(c)</sub>
  <span class="sup">2</span>), for Cox proportional-hazards models and (generalized) linear mixed models ((G)LMM), respectively (descriptions of models are presented below). All statistical analyses were conducted in R v.3.2.1 [
  <a rid="RSOS170835C45" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170835C45">45</a>], using packages coxme 2.2-5 [
  <a rid="RSOS170835C46" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170835C46">46</a>] for Cox models and lme4 1.1-7 [
  <a rid="RSOS170835C47" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170835C47">47</a>] for (G)LMMs.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Candidate models in each of the analyses detailed below were fitted with breeding season (year) and colony identity as random intercept terms to account for repeated measures. Pairwise correlations between potential predictors (fixed terms, detailed for each analysis below) were assessed using scatter plots and Pearson's correlation coefficients (
  <span class="italic">r</span>) [
  <a rid="RSOS170835C48" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170835C48">48</a>], and terms with an absolute 
  <span class="italic">r</span> greater than 0.5 were not included in the same model. Continuous variables fitted as fixed terms were standardized by subtracting the mean and dividing by 2 s.d., to allow the direct comparison of their corresponding estimated effect sizes, and to facilitate the interpretation of the effects of variables involved in interactions [
  <a rid="RSOS170835C49" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170835C49">49</a>]. For all our best models, we present estimated effect sizes and their associated 95% confidence intervals (95% CI; calculated by subtracting and adding, from and to the effect size, 1.96 times its standard error, s.e.).
 </p>
 <sec id="s2c1" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3.1.</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Onset of the breeding season</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used laying dates from a total of 27 colonies (7–14 per season), monitored over nine breeding seasons, to investigate the effects of rainfall and temperature on time to laying of first clutches. We used mixed-effects Cox proportional-hazards models, which allowed us to assess the effects of fixed (e.g. winter temperature) and time-dependent covariates (e.g. daily temperature) on the probability that a clutch would be laid at a given time interval (i.e. day), while accounting for differences in the baseline hazard of each level of the random intercept terms incorporated in our models (see [
   <a rid="RSOS170835C6" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170835C6">6</a>] for a similar analytical approach). Our analysis was restricted to the two-month period (28 August to 31 October) in which the earliest-recorded clutch and approximately 60% of first clutches were laid in each of our six complete breeding seasons (remaining first clutches were laid within the following seven months). As Cox models allow the inclusion of censored data, our analysis included all potential breeding pairs, regardless of whether they bred during the observation period. The number of potential breeding pairs within each colony was taken to be half the number of adults aged 2 years or older, assuming an equal sex ratio [
   <a rid="RSOS170835C50" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170835C50">50</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We first built two candidate sets of models for the onset of breeding to determine the best predictors among various measures of recent (a) rainfall (electronic supplementary material, table S1a) and (b) temperature (electronic supplementary material, table S1b). We then built a third candidate set of models (electronic supplementary material, table S1c) to test for additive effects of recent rainfall and temperature, using the best predictors obtained for each of the two climatic variables. In the rainfall candidate set (a), we included rainfall during 7, 15 and 30 days, with a lag of 6 days [
   <a rid="RSOS170835C51" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170835C51">51</a>], before the focal day (mean (range) = 3 mm (0–60), 6 mm (0–69), 12 mm (0–77), respectively). In the temperature candidate set (b), we included: mean minimum winter (June to July) and early spring (August) temperatures (1°C (−1 to 4) and 3.3°C (1.1 to 5.3), respectively), minimum temperature on the focal day (8.8°C (−5.6 to 22.4)) and an adjusted minimum temperature on the focal day (average over the previous 30 days, estimated using linear weighting which gives smoothed daily measures of temperature more heavily influenced by recent temperatures; 7.6°C (0.9–13.9)). As rainfall and temperature are highly seasonal, our daily measures were strongly correlated with the time component in the models (day of the year). We therefore adjusted these time-dependent variables for day of the year before incorporating them into the models, by subtracting the day-specific mean values of rainfall or minimum temperature (estimated using data collected between 1990 and 2013). To account for the increasing variance in rainfall from August to October, we then divided the above adjusted daily measures of rainfall by day-specific standard deviations (see [
   <a rid="RSOS170835C52" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170835C52">52</a>] for a similar method). We also controlled for colony size (31 adults (4–150)) in all our models, and input variables were allowed to interact with the time component when assumptions of proportional hazards were not met (e.g. for a categorical variable, the laying curves for each level should have similar shapes and proportional values over time [
   <a rid="RSOS170835C53" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170835C53">53</a>]).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2c2" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3.2.</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Length of the breeding season</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used laying dates from a total of 24 colonies (7–14 per season), monitored over six complete breeding seasons, to assess the effects of rainfall and temperature on the length of the breeding season. For each colony, we estimated the length of the breeding season as the interval between the 10th and 90th percentile for all laying dates within a given season, rather than taking the first and last breeding attempt, in order to minimize the effect of outliers (see [
   <a rid="RSOS170835C54" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170835C54">54</a>] for a similar method). The resulting number of days was fitted as the response variable in a candidate set of LMMs (electronic supplementary material, table S2).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Candidate models of the length of the breeding season and models in all subsequent analyses (detailed below) were fitted with one of the following climatic variables of interest: rainfall during the entire, typical breeding season (September to March; mean (range) = 374 mm (208–652)), rainfall in the ‘early breeding season’ (September to November; 58 mm (31–100)) or mean maximum temperature for the entire typical breeding season (30°C (29–31)). Mean minimum winter temperature (June to July; 1°C (−1 to 4)) was excluded as a predictor (here and from all subsequent analyses) as it had a near-perfect negative correlation with the above breeding season temperature (
   <span class="italic">r</span> = −0.89, 
   <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.001) and was deemed to be of lesser importance due to its temporal separation from breeding. Rainfall in the previous breeding season (406 mm (226–652)) was also included as a predictor given its expected effect on current food availability [
   <a rid="RSOS170835C55" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170835C55">55</a>]. We also controlled for colony size (35 adults (4–150)) and breeding start date (i.e. the 10th percentile for laying dates), and the interaction of colony size with the climatic variables fitted in the model.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2c3" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3.3.</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Probability of breeding</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We assessed the effects of rainfall and temperature (as detailed in §2.3.2) on the number of pairs that bred per colony per season (data from 24 colonies across six breeding seasons). We considered a set of candidate GLMMs with binomial errors (electronic supplementary material, table S3) and fitted the number of pairs per colony that initiated a clutch (i.e. successes) and those that did not (i.e. failures) as the two-vector response variable, to account for differences in the number of potential breeders per colony (i.e. weighted regression [
   <a rid="RSOS170835C48" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170835C48">48</a>]). Candidate models were also fitted with rainfall in the previous breeding season, the estimated length of a colony's breeding season and colony size (as detailed in §2.3.2), and the interaction of colony size with the climatic variable fitted in the model.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2c4" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3.4.</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Reproductive output</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We assessed the effects of rainfall and temperature (as detailed in §2.3.2) on the total number of clutches laid and the total number of fledglings produced (i.e. chicks reaching 17 days old) per colony per season (data from 24 colonies across six breeding seasons). We considered sets of candidate GLMMs with Poisson errors (electronic supplementary material, tables S4 and S5) fitted with the predictor variables listed in §2.3.3 and with colony-specific predation rates to control for the effects of predation on reproductive success. Predation rates were estimated for each colony using data from nest failures attributable to snakes [
   <a rid="RSOS170835C22" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170835C22">22</a>] and the method devised by Mayfield [
   <a rid="RSOS170835C56" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170835C56">56</a>] for calculating nest mortality. Briefly, for each colony, the total number of nest predation events (i.e. predation of all eggs or chicks of a clutch or brood) was divided by the sum of nest days within a season (days elapsed between laying and nest failure or fledging for each clutch) to obtain a daily predation rate (mean (range) = 0.02 nests (0–0.08)).
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
