<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2c2" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3.2.</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Length of the breeding season</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used laying dates from a total of 24 colonies (7–14 per season), monitored over six complete breeding seasons, to assess the effects of rainfall and temperature on the length of the breeding season. For each colony, we estimated the length of the breeding season as the interval between the 10th and 90th percentile for all laying dates within a given season, rather than taking the first and last breeding attempt, in order to minimize the effect of outliers (see [
  <a rid="RSOS170835C54" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170835C54">54</a>] for a similar method). The resulting number of days was fitted as the response variable in a candidate set of LMMs (electronic supplementary material, table S2).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Candidate models of the length of the breeding season and models in all subsequent analyses (detailed below) were fitted with one of the following climatic variables of interest: rainfall during the entire, typical breeding season (September to March; mean (range) = 374 mm (208–652)), rainfall in the ‘early breeding season’ (September to November; 58 mm (31–100)) or mean maximum temperature for the entire typical breeding season (30°C (29–31)). Mean minimum winter temperature (June to July; 1°C (−1 to 4)) was excluded as a predictor (here and from all subsequent analyses) as it had a near-perfect negative correlation with the above breeding season temperature (
  <span class="italic">r</span> = −0.89, 
  <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.001) and was deemed to be of lesser importance due to its temporal separation from breeding. Rainfall in the previous breeding season (406 mm (226–652)) was also included as a predictor given its expected effect on current food availability [
  <a rid="RSOS170835C55" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170835C55">55</a>]. We also controlled for colony size (35 adults (4–150)) and breeding start date (i.e. the 10th percentile for laying dates), and the interaction of colony size with the climatic variables fitted in the model.
 </p>
</sec>
