<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec008" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Asia</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate change’s impacts on crop yield and consumable calories in Asia are varied. In China, mean climate changes overall benefitted crop yields and increased consumable food calories in these ten crops by ~2% (or ~1% across all consumable food calories), though there are exceptions such as decreases in rice yields in Guangxi and Fujian or wheat yields in Sichuan and Guizhou (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217148.g001" href="#pone.0217148.g001">Fig 1</a>). Consistent with 
  <span class="italic">Tao et al</span>. 
  <span class="italic">2017</span> [
  <a rid="pone.0217148.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217148.ref028">28</a>] and 
  <span class="italic">Meng et al</span>. 
  <span class="italic">2014</span> [
  <a rid="pone.0217148.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217148.ref029">29</a>] we find that wheat yields in large extent of the Huang-Huai-Hai plains and maize yields in Heilongjiang province similarly benefitted from climate change. In India we found some states with a persistent pattern of yield losses across all major crops as in the core Green Revolution state of Haryana and western Uttar Pradesh, and for rice in southern India (Tamil Nadu and Kerala states) with overall production losses in India in wheat (-0.7% or ~-0.5 MT) and rice in India (-2.1% or ~-2.2 MT broadly agreeing with [
  <a rid="pone.0217148.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217148.ref030">30</a>]). Consumable food calories reduced in India ~1.2% in these ten crops and ~0.8% overall on average annually. Losses in rice production have also occurred in Vietnam (~-1.0 MT) and in the Laguna province of Philippines (~11kg /ha/year or -0.2% in yields; 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217148.g001" href="#pone.0217148.g001">Fig 1f</a>), broadly agreeing with reported station experiments [
  <a rid="pone.0217148.ref031" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217148.ref031">31</a>], although overall rice production increased in the Philippines (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0217148.s017" href="#pone.0217148.s017">S4 Table</a>). Wheat production also decreased in Turkey (~-0.8 MT). Climate change has reduced consumable food calories in numerous Asian countries both food secure (such as in Iran and Israel) and insecure (as in Bangladesh, Nepal and India).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The impact on crop yields on account of only temperature change (holding the precipitation variables at historical climatological values) is mapped in 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0217148.s010" href="#pone.0217148.s010">S9 Fig</a>, whereas the impact due to only precipitation change (holding the temperature variables at historical climatological values) is mapped in 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0217148.s011" href="#pone.0217148.s011">S10 Fig</a>. Temperature only effects are stronger in some areas such as Europe and East Asia whereas precipitation only effects are equally strong as in sub-Saharan Africa, South Asia and Australia; these are not additive results and provide only an indication of the relative importance of temperature versus precipitation changes (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0217148.s017" href="#pone.0217148.s017">S4 Table</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
