<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Previous assessments of climate change impact on crop yields commonly combine future climate scenarios and process-based crop models to project future yields for a limited number of crops for 2050 or later [
  <a rid="pone.0217148.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217148.ref001">1</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0217148.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217148.ref004">4</a>]. At higher levels of warming, strong yield losses are predicted in lower latitudes especially for maize and wheat crops [
  <a rid="pone.0217148.ref002" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217148.ref002">2</a>]. Although these results provide insights into long-term future changes, there are large uncertainties in both the modeled climate projections [
  <a rid="pone.0217148.ref005" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217148.ref005">5</a>] and in the crop model parameters [
  <a rid="pone.0217148.ref006" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217148.ref006">6</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0217148.ref008" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217148.ref008">8</a>]. Hence, the distant time horizon, small number of crops, and coarse resolution limit the results’ utility for stakeholders and policy makers to develop goals and strategies.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Assessing the impacts of recent climate change complements long-term forecasts and identifies which crops and places are already at greater risk. Since the 1970s, global surface temperature warmed at an average of 0.16°C to 0.18°C per decade [
  <a rid="pone.0217148.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217148.ref009">9</a>], a rate higher than any period since the industrial revolution. During that same period, we find that the growing season temperature, over all harvested areas for the top ten global crops–barley, cassava, maize, rice, oil palm, rapeseed, sorghum, sugarcane, soybean and wheat–increased 0.5°C to 1.2°C (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0217148.s014" href="#pone.0217148.s014">S1 Table</a>; 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0217148.s002" href="#pone.0217148.s002">S1</a>–
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0217148.s005" href="#pone.0217148.s005">S4</a> Figs). Growing season precipitation changes were more variable; from a decrease of 3.4 mm averaged over all sugarcane harvested croplands to an increase of ~19 mm averaged over all oil palm harvested croplands (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0217148.s014" href="#pone.0217148.s014">S1 Table</a>; 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0217148.s002" href="#pone.0217148.s002">S1</a>–
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0217148.s005" href="#pone.0217148.s005">S4</a> Figs).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Given the complexities in modeling crop growth response to regional variability in climate and management, previous process based crop modeling efforts have had difficulty reproducing historical crop yields for the few major crops generally studied such as maize, rice, and wheat [
  <a rid="pone.0217148.ref007" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217148.ref007">7</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0217148.ref010" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217148.ref010">10</a>]. Empirical (statistical) global estimates of recent climate change impacts, which some studies have shown to perform equally well as process-based modeling in assessing future impacts on crop yields [
  <a rid="pone.0217148.ref011" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217148.ref011">11</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0217148.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217148.ref012">12</a>], is available, but only at the coarse national scale [
  <a rid="pone.0217148.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217148.ref013">13</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0217148.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217148.ref014">14</a>] or at selected locations, and only for the top few crops [
  <a rid="pone.0217148.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217148.ref004">4</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0217148.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217148.ref015">15</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To enable subnational analysis, we first constructed a database of harvested area, yield, weather, and climate statistics building on methods developed previously and accessing publicly available data from individual countries [
  <a rid="pone.0217148.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217148.ref016">16</a>]. Crop statistics were compiled from 1974–2013 for ten crops across ~20,000 political units globally (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0217148.s001" href="#pone.0217148.s001">S1 Text</a>). These ten crops account for ~83% of global kilocalorie production from all croplands [
  <a rid="pone.0217148.ref017" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217148.ref017">17</a>] and represent several major crop group types. (Crops were not distinguished between varieties and managements—see section 1 of 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0217148.s001" href="#pone.0217148.s001">S1 Text</a> for more details). Weather and climate statistics (seasonal and annual, normal and extreme, precipitation and temperature) were calculated for each political unit using the CRU TS4.01 gridded global dataset ([
  <a rid="pone.0217148.ref018" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217148.ref018">18</a>], see 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0217148.s001" href="#pone.0217148.s001">S1 Text</a> for further information on how political unit level weather and climate information was constructed). 
  <span class="italic">Historical climate</span> is defined as the 30-year average weather prior to 1974. 
  <span class="italic">Current climate</span> is defined as the historical climate plus the addition of the linear trend of the weather for the 35 years ending in 2008, from the year 1974.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We constructed statistical models relating the observed yields to observed weather at each political unit from 1974 to 2008. (The period 2009 to 2013 was set aside for out-of-sample cross validation of model predicted crop yields against observations, at each political unit). We used a time-series analysis (Methods below) in which the influence of technology and management changes were accounted for in linear and quadratic time terms, whereas the normal and extreme temperature and precipitation variations and their interactions were represented with linear and quadratic terms consistent with previous studies [
  <a rid="pone.0217148.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217148.ref016">16</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0217148.ref019" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217148.ref019">19</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0217148.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0217148.ref021">21</a>]. The analysis included only those political units that had crop data for each year from 1974 to 2008.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We base quantitative conclusions on models that are statistically significant (ANOVA F-statistic at p &lt; 0.05 level) and are applied within the domain of observed variables used in model construction (Methods below; 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0217148.s006" href="#pone.0217148.s006">S5</a> and 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0217148.s007" href="#pone.0217148.s007">S6</a> Figs). We applied models in the political units in which they were constructed. We confirmed that yield predictions were made only with historical and current climate conditions that were within the range of the observed weather used for model construction (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0217148.s007" href="#pone.0217148.s007">S6 Fig</a>). Further, testing the model residuals showed Gaussian nature of residuals everywhere and their general white noise nature (absence of autocorrelation) (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0217148.s008" href="#pone.0217148.s008">S7 Fig</a>) indicating that these models were robust relative to data quality issues. Cross validation of the model predicted yields, against observations, showed low average (2009 to 2013) harvested-area-weighted errors globally (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0217148.s015" href="#pone.0217148.s015">S2 Table</a>), and generally also low errors at the political units for individual crops (Methods below and 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0217148.s006" href="#pone.0217148.s006">S5 Fig</a>). The model coefficients of determination (R
  <span class="sup">2</span>) at the global level ranged from 0.76 (sorghum) to 0.87 (rice) (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0217148.s016" href="#pone.0217148.s016">S3 Table</a>; 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0217148.s009" href="#pone.0217148.s009">S8 Fig</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The potential impact of climate change at each political unit is the difference in crop yield under current, and under historical climate conditions. This yield change information at the political unit was then converted to production changes using the average harvested area information over the 2003 to 2008 period at each political unit. Then all the political unit level climate-driven production changes in a country were summarized to give the country-level climate-driven production changes. Finally, we translated the country-level production changes to country-level consumable food calorie changes. In this process we accounted for harvested calories that returned as food calories after getting processed through animals as feed, through food processing, and calories directly consumed with little to no processing (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0217148.s001" href="#pone.0217148.s001">S1 Text</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
