<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par16" class="p">Previous studies showed a delay in the sowing date of winter wheat of 1.5 days per decade on average but an advance in the harvest date of 1.4 days per decade; therefore, the whole growing period was shortened
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">15</xref>
 </sup>. Wang 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" class="xref">27</xref>
 </sup> reported that the summer maize sowing date occurred relatively early at 13 (48.1%) of 27 stations examined on the North China Plain, while maturity dates were significantly delayed at 10 (37.0%) stations; thus, the length of the whole growing period increased at 18 (63.0%) stations. Comparisons between these two crops showed that winter wheat and summer maize exhibited opposite results, whereas the results for cotton were more complex. These differences may be due to an impact of soil temperature on the sowing date and a warming trend in recent decades that has caused delayed sowing of winter wheat and advanced sowing of summer maize; however, because plastic film mulching technology has been applied for cotton, climate warming has less effect on cotton sowing date. Furthermore, the maturity date of winter wheat may have occurred early because warming may have accelerated crop growth and shortened the growing period. The maturity date of summer maize has been delayed because farmers have adopted appropriate farming practices and cultivars in response to climate warming, such as double delay technology for winter wheat and summer maize
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" class="xref">27</xref>
 </sup>. The harvest date of cotton has generally been advanced in the southern part of the North China Plain and delayed in the northern part, which may due to the indeterminate growth habit of cotton and the fact that the southern portion exhibits greater accumulated temperatures. Nevertheless, Lu 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. reported that increased temperatures advanced cotton phenology but whole growth period lengths were prolonged or shortened in various stations of eastern Australia, which was generally consistent with this study
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>
 </sup>. However, Huang and Ji reported that climate warming prolonged the whole growth period length of cotton in Xinjiang Province of China
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">8</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
