<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece34788-sec-0012" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">DISCUSSION</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The house sparrow may represent a sentinel species of the urban environment and, thus, is a good model to study the functional constraints of living in cities for urban exploiters. To better understand the potential causes of the recent decline of urban house sparrow populations, we conducted a large‐scale study to evaluate the impact of urbanization on the stress physiology of juvenile house sparrows. By using an integrative measure of CORT from feathers sampled across a rural–urban gradient, we found that urban juveniles had higher feather CORT levels than rural ones. These feathers grew during the developmental phase (i.e., in the nest); thus, our study highlights the functional constraints imposed by a city lifestyle and suggests that these constraints are most likely to occur during the developmental period prior to fledging. Feather CORT levels were not correlated to any juvenile attribute (body size, mass, or condition) except for the CORT stress response (the increase in CORT levels in response to a standardized stress protocol), suggesting that urban environmental conditions may affect the ontogeny of the CORT stress response in house sparrow nestlings.</p>
 <sec id="ece34788-sec-0013" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.1</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Impact of urbanization on feather CORT level</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We showed that an increasing level of urbanization was associated with higher feather CORT levels in juvenile house sparrows. This result partly contrasts with those from Hudin et al. (
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0052">2018</a>). In their study, they found no difference in feather CORT levels between urban and rural juvenile sparrows. Contrary to our study, they captured birds in early fall, when the post‐juvenile molt has already occurred in house sparrows. This could explain the discrepancy because most urban‐related constraints seem to occur during the developmental period when sparrows are growing their feathers in the nest (Meillère et al., 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0086" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0086">2017</a>; Seress et al., 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0108" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0108">2012</a>). Elevated feather CORT levels usually result from elevated circulating plasma CORT levels at the time of feather growth (Bortolotti et al., 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0014">2008</a>), as experimentally demonstrated in pigeons (
   <span class="italic">Columbia livia domestica</span>) and European starlings (
   <span class="italic">Sturnus vulgaris</span>; Lattin, Reed, DesRochers, &amp; Romero, 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0067" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0067">2011</a>; Jenni‐Eiermann et al., 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0054">2015</a>). Consequently, elevated feather CORT levels have been associated with challenging environmental conditions in various species (e.g., geese and eiders in Legagneux et al., 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0068" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0068">2013</a>; tree and barn swallows (
   <span class="italic">Tachycineta bicolor</span>, 
   <span class="italic">Hirundo rustica</span>) in Fairhurst et al., 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0034">2015</a>, 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0035">2011</a>; rhinoceros auklet (
   <span class="italic">Cerorhinca monocerata</span>) in Will et al., 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0123" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0123">2015</a>; mallard duckling (
   <span class="italic">Anas platyrhynchos</span>) in Johns, Marchant, Fairhurst, Speakman, &amp; Clark, 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0055">2017</a>) and are associated with reduced survival in house sparrows, specifically (e.g., Koren et al., 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0064" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0064">2012</a>). Our results support the hypothesis that urban sparrows are constrained during their development and suggest that urban juvenile sparrows may have a lower survival probability than rural ones (Meillère et al., 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0086" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0086">2017</a>; Meillère, Brischoux, Parenteau, et al., 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0087" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0087">2015</a>; Seress et al., 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0108" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0108">2012</a>). This interpretation is supported by multiple ecological studies, which have reported a negative impact of urbanization on house sparrow populations (e.g., population decline: De Coster et al., 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0028">2015</a>; reduced breeding success: Seress et al., 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0108" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0108">2012</a>; reduced body size and feather quality: Meillère et al., 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0086" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0086">2017</a>). However, exposure to moderate CORT levels during development can also be beneficial under some circumstances (reviewed in Madliger &amp; Love, 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0078" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0078">2014</a>). For example, Grava et al. (
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0044" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0044">2013</a>) found that elevated juvenile feather CORT levels were associated with potential benefits later in life (i.e., post‐fledging habitat quality, syrinx mass). Future studies should examine the fitness consequences of slight inter‐individual variation in feather CORT levels in juvenile sparrows.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Interestingly, visual inspection of our data suggests that urbanization may only be a constraint when it reaches a specific threshold (see. Figure 
   <a rid="ece34788-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#ece34788-fig-0002">2</a>). However, we lack statistical power to run non‐linear models (e.g., broken‐stick models), and sampling additional populations would be required to properly test this hypothesis.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There are numerous potential sources of stress for birds developing in an urban environment, which could impact nestlings either directly or indirectly through the modification of environmental constraints (Bonier, 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0011">2012</a>; Chace &amp; Walsh, 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0019">2006</a>; Meillère, Brischoux, &amp; Angelier, 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0084" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0084">2015</a>; Seress &amp; Liker, 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0109" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0109">2015</a>). Elevated feather CORT levels could result from a change in diet and food quality in urban environments. Recently, Hudin et al. (
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0052">2018</a>) experimentally showed that an urban diet is associated with elevated feather CORT levels in juvenile house sparrows, supporting the idea that the urban diet may not be suitable for developing house sparrow nestlings (Meillère et al., 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0086" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0086">2017</a>). Indeed, nestling house sparrows need a protein‐rich diet to grow properly (Anderson, 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0002">2006</a>; White, 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0121" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0121">2008</a>), but the availability of invertebrates is lower in cities relative to rural areas (Chace &amp; Walsh, 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0019">2006</a>; Hudin et al., 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0051" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0051">2017</a>; Moudrá, Zasadil, Moudrý, &amp; Šálek, 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0091" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0091">2018</a>; Paker, Yom‐Tov, Alon‐Mozes, &amp; Barnea, 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0096" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0096">2014</a>; Summers‐Smith, 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0115" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0115">2003</a>), and urban house sparrow parents feed their chicks a lower quality diet than their rural counterparts (Seress &amp; Liker, 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0109" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0109">2015</a>). In addition, urban food may contain heavy metals, which may contaminate nestlings (Dauwe, Janssens, Bervoets, Blust, &amp; Eens, 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0026">2004</a>; Raupp, Shrewsbury, &amp; Herms, 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0102" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0102">2010</a>; Zvereva &amp; Kozlov, 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0129" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0129">2010</a>) and lead to potential effects on growth, behavior or the immune system (e.g., pied flycatchers in Eeva, Hasselquist, Tummeleht, Nikinmaa, &amp; Ilmonen, 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0032">2005</a>; great tits in Gorissen et al., 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0041">2005</a>; feral pigeons (
   <span class="italic">Columbia livia</span>) in Chatelain, Gasparini, &amp; Frantz, 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0020">2016</a>; reviewed in Montiglio &amp; Royauté, 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0090" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0090">2014</a>). A low‐quality and/or contaminated diet could be associated with nutritional stress and, therefore, with elevated feather CORT levels in urban chicks (e.g., food restriction in rhinoceros auklets: Will et al., 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0122" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0122">2014</a>, 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0123" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0123">2015</a>; heavy metal contamination in blackbirds (
   <span class="italic">Turdus merula)</span>: Meillère et al., 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0085" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0085">2016</a>), especially in house sparrows (Hudin et al., 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0052">2018</a>). Feather CORT levels can also be affected by weather conditions, as previously shown in several species (Legagneux et al., 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0068" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0068">2013</a>), including the house sparrow (Treen, Hobson, Marchant, &amp; Bortolotti, 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0117" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0117">2015</a>). Unfortunately, climate data were not available for most sites, so we could not test this hypothesis. However, our results are unlikely to be biased by inter‐site variation in climate because the rural and urban sites were not spatially segregated (see Figure 
   <a rid="ece34788-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#ece34788-fig-0001">1</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Higher feather CORT levels in urban nestlings could also be a result of environmental perturbations, such as noise and light pollution. Noise pollution could indirectly affect nestlings by disrupting aspects of parental care such as incubation commitment or brood provisioning (Injaian, Taff, &amp; Patricelli, 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0053">2018</a>; Meillère, Brischoux, &amp; Angelier, 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0084" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0084">2015</a>; Schroeder, Nakagawa, Cleasby, &amp; Burke, 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0106" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0106">2012</a>). Noise pollution could also directly disturb the nestlings, and as a result, increase nestling CORT secretion as previously shown in a few bird species (Kleist et al., 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0063" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0063">2017</a>; Davies, Beck, &amp; Sewall, 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0027">2018</a>; but see Angelier, Meillère, Grace, Trouvé, &amp; Brischoux, 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0003">2016</a>). Previous studies have demonstrated that urban noise is associated with changes in nestlings growth, metabolism, and stress response, and with a reduced probability of survival in several bird species (e.g., tree swallows in Leonard &amp; Horn, 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0071" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0071">2008</a>; Injaian et al., 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0053">2018</a>; white‐crowned sparrows (
   <span class="italic">Zonotrichia leucophrys orienta</span>) in Crino, Johnson, Blickley, Patricelli, &amp; Breuner, 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0024">2013</a>; house sparrows in Meillère, Brischoux, Ribout, &amp; Angelier, 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0088" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0088">2015</a>; Brischoux, Meillère, Dupoué, Lourdais, &amp; Angelier, 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0015">2017</a>; western bluebirds (
   <span class="italic">Sialia mexicana</span>) in Kleist et al., 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0063" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0063">2017</a>). Light pollution may also result in an increase in feather CORT because it artificially increases the amount of time nestlings are active. For instance, an experimental study on great tits showed that urban light was associated with increased brood provisioning (Titulaer, Spoelstra, Lange, &amp; Visser, 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0116" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0116">2012</a>) and, therefore, with increased begging activity in urban nestlings (Ouyang et al., 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0094" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0094">2015</a>; Titulaer et al., 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0116" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0116">2012</a>). Increased activity (especially begging activity) has been associated with increased CORT levels in wild birds (Kitaysky, Kitaiskaia, Piatt, &amp; Wingfield, 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0061">2003</a>; Loiseau, Sorci, Dano, &amp; Chastel, 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0073" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0073">2008</a>; reviewed in Landys et al., 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0066" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0066">2006</a>). Since high‐quality food may be limited in cities (Seress &amp; Liker, 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0109" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0109">2015</a>), urban nestlings may be expending more energy by begging than they are receiving, leading to nutritional stress and increased feather CORT levels (Will et al., 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0122" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0122">2014</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece34788-sec-0014" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.2</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Feather CORT levels and body size</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In previous studies, we found that body size decreases as the degree of urbanization increases in house sparrows (Meillère et al., 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0086" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0086">2017</a>; Meillère, Brischoux, Parenteau, et al., 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0087" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0087">2015</a>). Although we found a positive correlation between feather CORT levels and the degree of urbanization, we surprisingly did not find any significant relationship between feather CORT levels and body size in juvenile house sparrows. As feather and structural growth occur simultaneously in the nest, our results suggest that CORT exposure during the post‐hatching period is not directly correlated with nestling growth. Previous studies have shown that elevated plasma and feather CORT levels can be correlated with reduced body size and mass in pigeon and sparrow nestlings (Grace, Froud, Meillère, &amp; Angelier, 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0043">2017</a>; Jenni‐Eiermann et al., 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0054">2015</a>). Interestingly, this correlation between CORT levels, body size, and body mass seems to attenuate and even disappear as the nestlings develop, suggesting that nestlings can compensate for a slow initial growth despite stressful or challenging conditions (Grace et al., 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0043">2017</a>; Jenni‐Eiermann et al., 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0054">2015</a>). This may explain why feather CORT levels and juvenile body size were not correlated in our study, although this may also result from a lack of statistical power (tarsus length was only available from 4 sites). Furthermore, CORT is progressively and irreversibly incorporated into feathers during growth and, therefore, feather CORT levels represent a sum of CORT exposure during feather growth (Bortolotti et al., 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0014">2008</a>; Jenni‐Eiermann et al., 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0054">2015</a>; Romero &amp; Fairhurst, 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0104" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0104">2016</a>; Will et al., 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0122" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0122">2014</a>). Growth and juvenile body size may be affected by acute and temporary stressful events during growth, which are not identifiable in the integrated feather CORT measurement.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece34788-sec-0015" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.3</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Feather CORT level and juvenile body condition and CORT levels</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Juvenile body mass and condition were not influenced by feather CORT levels. Unlike body size, body mass and condition are labile, and thus are likely to be more dependent on individual characteristics and the local environmental conditions that are present closer to the time of capture (e.g., food, weather, predation; Krebs &amp; Singleton, 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0065" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0065">1993</a>; Gosler, 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0042">1996</a>; Schulte‐Hostedde, Millar, &amp; Hickling, 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0107" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0107">2001</a>; Peig &amp; Green, 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0098" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0098">2009</a>). In contrast, feather CORT is determined weeks prior to the time of capture. This may blur a potential relationship between feather CORT levels and condition in juvenile sparrows. An alternative explanation may be that there is a progressive selective disappearance of individuals with low body condition in the population. Post‐fledging mortality is high in small passerines including house sparrows (Leloutre et al., 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0069" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0069">2014</a>). In addition, higher feather CORT concentrations are associated with lower survival probability in adult house sparrows (Koren et al., 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0064" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0064">2012</a>). This selection may eliminate individuals with a lower body mass and condition (see Lendvai, Loiseau, Sorci, &amp; Chastel, 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0070" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0070">2009</a>) and may, therefore, mask a potential relationship between developmental conditions (e.g., feather CORT levels) and juvenile attributes (body size, body mass and condition, and baseline CORT levels).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We measured baseline CORT and stress‐induced CORT in order to test whether the HPA axis and juvenile sensitivity to stress may be affected by developmental conditions and CORT exposure during development (i.e., feather CORT). We did not find evidence for any correlation between feather CORT levels and baseline CORT levels. However, we found a non‐significant positive trend between stress‐induced CORT levels and feather CORT levels. We also found a significant positive relationship between feather CORT levels and the CORT stress response (i.e., the increase in CORT levels in response to a standardized stressor) in juvenile sparrows. Such result has previously been found with a positive relationship between stress‐induced CORT levels and feather CORT levels in partridges (
   <span class="italic">Alectoris rufa</span>; Bortolotti et al., 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0014">2008</a>). These results suggest that the CORT stress response at the juvenile stage may be associated with developmental CORT exposure. Several laboratory studies have previously reported an effect of developmental CORT exposure on the CORT stress response of individuals later in life (e.g., Spencer, Buchanan, Goldsmith, &amp; Catchpole, 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0112" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0112">2003</a>; Spencer, Evans, &amp; Monaghan, 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0113" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0113">2009</a>; Haussmann, Longenecker, Marchetto, Juliano, &amp; Bowden, 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0048" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0048">2011</a>; Marasco, Robinson, Herzyk, &amp; Spencer, 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0079" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0079">2012</a>; Crino, Driscoll, &amp; Breuner, 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0023">2014</a>). For instance, Spencer et al. (
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0113" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0113">2009</a>) showed that CORT‐fed zebra finch nestlings had a steeper increase in plasma CORT levels in response to an acute stress as juveniles. Stressful conditions during development (e.g., nutritional restrictions) without any manipulation of plasma CORT levels can also increase plasma CORT levels of juveniles in response to stress, as shown in red‐legged kittiwakes and western scrub‐jays (Kitaysky, Kitaiskaia, Wingfield, &amp; Piatt, 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0062">2001</a>; Pravosudov &amp; Kitaysky, 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0101" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0101">2006</a>). Thus, developmental stress or developmental CORT exposure may have long‐lasting effects on the CORT stress response of house sparrows. This suggests that urban developmental conditions may modify the functioning of the HPA axis in urban birds. It is possible that an intense CORT stress response may provide some benefits to urban individuals during the juvenile or the adult stage (e.g., improved survival, Angelier et al., 
   <a rid="ece34788-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0006">2010</a>). To test this hypothesis, future studies would need to experimentally investigate the impact of developmental CORT exposure on the ontogeny of the HPA axis and the ability of individuals to subsequently cope with their environment.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
