<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece34788-sec-0015" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.3</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Feather CORT level and juvenile body condition and CORT levels</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Juvenile body mass and condition were not influenced by feather CORT levels. Unlike body size, body mass and condition are labile, and thus are likely to be more dependent on individual characteristics and the local environmental conditions that are present closer to the time of capture (e.g., food, weather, predation; Krebs &amp; Singleton, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0065" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0065">1993</a>; Gosler, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0042">1996</a>; Schulte‐Hostedde, Millar, &amp; Hickling, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0107" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0107">2001</a>; Peig &amp; Green, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0098" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0098">2009</a>). In contrast, feather CORT is determined weeks prior to the time of capture. This may blur a potential relationship between feather CORT levels and condition in juvenile sparrows. An alternative explanation may be that there is a progressive selective disappearance of individuals with low body condition in the population. Post‐fledging mortality is high in small passerines including house sparrows (Leloutre et al., 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0069" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0069">2014</a>). In addition, higher feather CORT concentrations are associated with lower survival probability in adult house sparrows (Koren et al., 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0064" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0064">2012</a>). This selection may eliminate individuals with a lower body mass and condition (see Lendvai, Loiseau, Sorci, &amp; Chastel, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0070" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0070">2009</a>) and may, therefore, mask a potential relationship between developmental conditions (e.g., feather CORT levels) and juvenile attributes (body size, body mass and condition, and baseline CORT levels).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We measured baseline CORT and stress‐induced CORT in order to test whether the HPA axis and juvenile sensitivity to stress may be affected by developmental conditions and CORT exposure during development (i.e., feather CORT). We did not find evidence for any correlation between feather CORT levels and baseline CORT levels. However, we found a non‐significant positive trend between stress‐induced CORT levels and feather CORT levels. We also found a significant positive relationship between feather CORT levels and the CORT stress response (i.e., the increase in CORT levels in response to a standardized stressor) in juvenile sparrows. Such result has previously been found with a positive relationship between stress‐induced CORT levels and feather CORT levels in partridges (
  <span class="italic">Alectoris rufa</span>; Bortolotti et al., 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0014">2008</a>). These results suggest that the CORT stress response at the juvenile stage may be associated with developmental CORT exposure. Several laboratory studies have previously reported an effect of developmental CORT exposure on the CORT stress response of individuals later in life (e.g., Spencer, Buchanan, Goldsmith, &amp; Catchpole, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0112" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0112">2003</a>; Spencer, Evans, &amp; Monaghan, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0113" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0113">2009</a>; Haussmann, Longenecker, Marchetto, Juliano, &amp; Bowden, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0048" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0048">2011</a>; Marasco, Robinson, Herzyk, &amp; Spencer, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0079" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0079">2012</a>; Crino, Driscoll, &amp; Breuner, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0023">2014</a>). For instance, Spencer et al. (
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0113" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0113">2009</a>) showed that CORT‐fed zebra finch nestlings had a steeper increase in plasma CORT levels in response to an acute stress as juveniles. Stressful conditions during development (e.g., nutritional restrictions) without any manipulation of plasma CORT levels can also increase plasma CORT levels of juveniles in response to stress, as shown in red‐legged kittiwakes and western scrub‐jays (Kitaysky, Kitaiskaia, Wingfield, &amp; Piatt, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0062">2001</a>; Pravosudov &amp; Kitaysky, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0101" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0101">2006</a>). Thus, developmental stress or developmental CORT exposure may have long‐lasting effects on the CORT stress response of house sparrows. This suggests that urban developmental conditions may modify the functioning of the HPA axis in urban birds. It is possible that an intense CORT stress response may provide some benefits to urban individuals during the juvenile or the adult stage (e.g., improved survival, Angelier et al., 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0006">2010</a>). To test this hypothesis, future studies would need to experimentally investigate the impact of developmental CORT exposure on the ontogeny of the HPA axis and the ability of individuals to subsequently cope with their environment.
 </p>
</sec>
