<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece34788-sec-0005" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Feather collection (11 sites), morphological measurements, and blood sampling (4 sites)</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Feathers were collected from all study sites. The two innermost rectrices of each individual were collected and stored in dry paper envelopes until laboratory analyses. We weighed (high‐resolution balance: ±0.01 mg) and measured the length (digital caliper: ±0.01 mm; see Meillère et al., 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0086" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0086">2017</a>) of all feathers. In addition to feather collections, morphological measurements and blood samples were collected at 4 of the 11 sites (two urban and two rural; see Table 
  <a rid="ece34788-tbl-0001" ref-type="table" href="#ece34788-tbl-0001">1</a>). For all juveniles captured at these four sites, body mass (electronic balance: ±0.1 g), wing length (steel rule: ±1 mm), tarsus length, and bill length (caliper: ±0.1 mm) were measured. Additionally, fat and muscle scores were recorded as detailed in Kaiser (
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0057" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0057">1993</a>), Brown (
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0016">1996</a>) and Leloutre, Gouzerh, and Angelier (
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0069" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0069">2014</a>). For consistency and to avoid potential methodological bias, morphological measurements were all collected by the same person. In addition to morphological measurements, juveniles from these four sites were bled within 3 min of capture (mean ± 
  <span class="italic">SE</span>: 2 min 39 s ± 2 s; range: 1 min 13 s – 3 min 45 s) to quantify baseline CORT concentration (Romero &amp; Reed, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0105" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0105">2005</a>). Following this first blood sample, birds were kept in cloth bags and sampled a second time 30 min after capture to obtain stress‐induced CORT levels (Wingfield, Davey, Peter, &amp; Tobe, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0124" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0124">1994</a>). CORT levels are at a maximum after 30‐min of restraint in this species (Romero, Cyr, &amp; Romero, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0103" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0103">2006</a>), and therefore, this allowed us to assess the CORT stress response (Wingfield et al., 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0125" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0125">1998</a>). We defined the “increase in plasma CORT” as the difference between stress‐induced CORT and baseline CORT levels. All blood samples were collected from the alar vein using a 25‐gauge needle and heparinized microcapillary tubes (up to 150 µl for CORT assay). Blood samples were centrifuged (4,500 rpm, 7 min), and plasma and red blood cells were separated (plasma for CORT assay and red blood cells for molecular sexing). Then, they were kept at −20°C until laboratory analyses at the “Centre d'Etudes Biologiques de Chizé” (hereafter CEBC).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To assess juvenile body condition, we used the “scaled mass index” (SMI) as recommended by Peig &amp; Green (
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0098" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0098">2009</a>, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0099" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0099">2010</a>). The SMI adjusts the mass of all individuals to that which would be expected if they all had the same body size (Peig &amp; Green, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0098" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0098">2009</a>). We used tarsus length to calculate the SMI because it had the greatest correlation with body mass (tarsus length: 
  <span class="italic">r</span> = 0.588, 
  <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.001; wing length: 
  <span class="italic">r</span> = 0.313, 
  <span class="italic">p</span> = 0.041). The SMI was computed for each individual as follows:
  <div id="ece34788-disp-0001" class="disp-formula">
   <div id="nlm-math-1" class="math">
    <div class="mrow">
     <div class="msub">
      <span class="mtext">SMI</span>
      <span class="mi">i</span>
     </div>
     <span class="mo">=</span>
     <div class="msub">
      <span class="mi">M</span>
      <span class="mi">i</span>
     </div>
     <span class="mo">×</span>
     <div class="msup">
      <div class="mrow">
       <span stretchy="false" class="mo">(</span>
       <div class="msub">
        <span class="mi">L</span>
        <span class="mn">0</span>
       </div>
       <span stretchy="false" class="mo">/</span>
       <div class="msub">
        <span class="mi">L</span>
        <span class="mi">i</span>
       </div>
       <span stretchy="false" class="mo">)</span>
      </div>
      <span class="mi">b</span>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">where 
  <span class="italic">M</span>
  <sub>i</sub> and 
  <span class="italic">L</span>
  <sub>i</sub> are body mass and tarsus length of the individual i, respectively, 
  <span class="italic">L</span>
  <sub>0</sub> is the arithmetic mean value of tarsus length for the whole study population (
  <span class="italic">L</span>
  <sub>0</sub> = 18.18 mm, 
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 43), and 
  <span class="italic">b</span> is the slope estimate of a standardized major axis (SMA) regression of log‐transformed body mass on log‐transformed tarsus length (
  <span class="italic">b</span> = 1.86).
 </p>
</sec>
