<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece34788-sec-0013" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Impact of urbanization on feather CORT level</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We showed that an increasing level of urbanization was associated with higher feather CORT levels in juvenile house sparrows. This result partly contrasts with those from Hudin et al. (
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0052">2018</a>). In their study, they found no difference in feather CORT levels between urban and rural juvenile sparrows. Contrary to our study, they captured birds in early fall, when the post‐juvenile molt has already occurred in house sparrows. This could explain the discrepancy because most urban‐related constraints seem to occur during the developmental period when sparrows are growing their feathers in the nest (Meillère et al., 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0086" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0086">2017</a>; Seress et al., 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0108" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0108">2012</a>). Elevated feather CORT levels usually result from elevated circulating plasma CORT levels at the time of feather growth (Bortolotti et al., 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0014">2008</a>), as experimentally demonstrated in pigeons (
  <span class="italic">Columbia livia domestica</span>) and European starlings (
  <span class="italic">Sturnus vulgaris</span>; Lattin, Reed, DesRochers, &amp; Romero, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0067" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0067">2011</a>; Jenni‐Eiermann et al., 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0054">2015</a>). Consequently, elevated feather CORT levels have been associated with challenging environmental conditions in various species (e.g., geese and eiders in Legagneux et al., 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0068" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0068">2013</a>; tree and barn swallows (
  <span class="italic">Tachycineta bicolor</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Hirundo rustica</span>) in Fairhurst et al., 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0034">2015</a>, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0035">2011</a>; rhinoceros auklet (
  <span class="italic">Cerorhinca monocerata</span>) in Will et al., 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0123" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0123">2015</a>; mallard duckling (
  <span class="italic">Anas platyrhynchos</span>) in Johns, Marchant, Fairhurst, Speakman, &amp; Clark, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0055">2017</a>) and are associated with reduced survival in house sparrows, specifically (e.g., Koren et al., 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0064" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0064">2012</a>). Our results support the hypothesis that urban sparrows are constrained during their development and suggest that urban juvenile sparrows may have a lower survival probability than rural ones (Meillère et al., 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0086" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0086">2017</a>; Meillère, Brischoux, Parenteau, et al., 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0087" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0087">2015</a>; Seress et al., 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0108" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0108">2012</a>). This interpretation is supported by multiple ecological studies, which have reported a negative impact of urbanization on house sparrow populations (e.g., population decline: De Coster et al., 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0028">2015</a>; reduced breeding success: Seress et al., 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0108" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0108">2012</a>; reduced body size and feather quality: Meillère et al., 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0086" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0086">2017</a>). However, exposure to moderate CORT levels during development can also be beneficial under some circumstances (reviewed in Madliger &amp; Love, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0078" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0078">2014</a>). For example, Grava et al. (
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0044" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0044">2013</a>) found that elevated juvenile feather CORT levels were associated with potential benefits later in life (i.e., post‐fledging habitat quality, syrinx mass). Future studies should examine the fitness consequences of slight inter‐individual variation in feather CORT levels in juvenile sparrows.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Interestingly, visual inspection of our data suggests that urbanization may only be a constraint when it reaches a specific threshold (see. Figure 
  <a rid="ece34788-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#ece34788-fig-0002">2</a>). However, we lack statistical power to run non‐linear models (e.g., broken‐stick models), and sampling additional populations would be required to properly test this hypothesis.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There are numerous potential sources of stress for birds developing in an urban environment, which could impact nestlings either directly or indirectly through the modification of environmental constraints (Bonier, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0011">2012</a>; Chace &amp; Walsh, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0019">2006</a>; Meillère, Brischoux, &amp; Angelier, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0084" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0084">2015</a>; Seress &amp; Liker, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0109" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0109">2015</a>). Elevated feather CORT levels could result from a change in diet and food quality in urban environments. Recently, Hudin et al. (
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0052">2018</a>) experimentally showed that an urban diet is associated with elevated feather CORT levels in juvenile house sparrows, supporting the idea that the urban diet may not be suitable for developing house sparrow nestlings (Meillère et al., 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0086" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0086">2017</a>). Indeed, nestling house sparrows need a protein‐rich diet to grow properly (Anderson, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0002">2006</a>; White, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0121" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0121">2008</a>), but the availability of invertebrates is lower in cities relative to rural areas (Chace &amp; Walsh, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0019">2006</a>; Hudin et al., 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0051" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0051">2017</a>; Moudrá, Zasadil, Moudrý, &amp; Šálek, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0091" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0091">2018</a>; Paker, Yom‐Tov, Alon‐Mozes, &amp; Barnea, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0096" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0096">2014</a>; Summers‐Smith, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0115" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0115">2003</a>), and urban house sparrow parents feed their chicks a lower quality diet than their rural counterparts (Seress &amp; Liker, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0109" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0109">2015</a>). In addition, urban food may contain heavy metals, which may contaminate nestlings (Dauwe, Janssens, Bervoets, Blust, &amp; Eens, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0026">2004</a>; Raupp, Shrewsbury, &amp; Herms, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0102" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0102">2010</a>; Zvereva &amp; Kozlov, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0129" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0129">2010</a>) and lead to potential effects on growth, behavior or the immune system (e.g., pied flycatchers in Eeva, Hasselquist, Tummeleht, Nikinmaa, &amp; Ilmonen, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0032">2005</a>; great tits in Gorissen et al., 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0041">2005</a>; feral pigeons (
  <span class="italic">Columbia livia</span>) in Chatelain, Gasparini, &amp; Frantz, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0020">2016</a>; reviewed in Montiglio &amp; Royauté, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0090" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0090">2014</a>). A low‐quality and/or contaminated diet could be associated with nutritional stress and, therefore, with elevated feather CORT levels in urban chicks (e.g., food restriction in rhinoceros auklets: Will et al., 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0122" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0122">2014</a>, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0123" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0123">2015</a>; heavy metal contamination in blackbirds (
  <span class="italic">Turdus merula)</span>: Meillère et al., 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0085" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0085">2016</a>), especially in house sparrows (Hudin et al., 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0052">2018</a>). Feather CORT levels can also be affected by weather conditions, as previously shown in several species (Legagneux et al., 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0068" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0068">2013</a>), including the house sparrow (Treen, Hobson, Marchant, &amp; Bortolotti, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0117" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0117">2015</a>). Unfortunately, climate data were not available for most sites, so we could not test this hypothesis. However, our results are unlikely to be biased by inter‐site variation in climate because the rural and urban sites were not spatially segregated (see Figure 
  <a rid="ece34788-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#ece34788-fig-0001">1</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Higher feather CORT levels in urban nestlings could also be a result of environmental perturbations, such as noise and light pollution. Noise pollution could indirectly affect nestlings by disrupting aspects of parental care such as incubation commitment or brood provisioning (Injaian, Taff, &amp; Patricelli, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0053">2018</a>; Meillère, Brischoux, &amp; Angelier, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0084" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0084">2015</a>; Schroeder, Nakagawa, Cleasby, &amp; Burke, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0106" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0106">2012</a>). Noise pollution could also directly disturb the nestlings, and as a result, increase nestling CORT secretion as previously shown in a few bird species (Kleist et al., 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0063" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0063">2017</a>; Davies, Beck, &amp; Sewall, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0027">2018</a>; but see Angelier, Meillère, Grace, Trouvé, &amp; Brischoux, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0003">2016</a>). Previous studies have demonstrated that urban noise is associated with changes in nestlings growth, metabolism, and stress response, and with a reduced probability of survival in several bird species (e.g., tree swallows in Leonard &amp; Horn, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0071" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0071">2008</a>; Injaian et al., 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0053">2018</a>; white‐crowned sparrows (
  <span class="italic">Zonotrichia leucophrys orienta</span>) in Crino, Johnson, Blickley, Patricelli, &amp; Breuner, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0024">2013</a>; house sparrows in Meillère, Brischoux, Ribout, &amp; Angelier, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0088" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0088">2015</a>; Brischoux, Meillère, Dupoué, Lourdais, &amp; Angelier, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0015">2017</a>; western bluebirds (
  <span class="italic">Sialia mexicana</span>) in Kleist et al., 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0063" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0063">2017</a>). Light pollution may also result in an increase in feather CORT because it artificially increases the amount of time nestlings are active. For instance, an experimental study on great tits showed that urban light was associated with increased brood provisioning (Titulaer, Spoelstra, Lange, &amp; Visser, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0116" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0116">2012</a>) and, therefore, with increased begging activity in urban nestlings (Ouyang et al., 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0094" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0094">2015</a>; Titulaer et al., 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0116" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0116">2012</a>). Increased activity (especially begging activity) has been associated with increased CORT levels in wild birds (Kitaysky, Kitaiskaia, Piatt, &amp; Wingfield, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0061">2003</a>; Loiseau, Sorci, Dano, &amp; Chastel, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0073" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0073">2008</a>; reviewed in Landys et al., 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0066" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0066">2006</a>). Since high‐quality food may be limited in cities (Seress &amp; Liker, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0109" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0109">2015</a>), urban nestlings may be expending more energy by begging than they are receiving, leading to nutritional stress and increased feather CORT levels (Will et al., 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0122" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0122">2014</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
