<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece34788-sec-0006" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.4</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Molecular sexing and CORT analyses</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The sex of juveniles was determined by molecular sexing as detailed in Fridolfsson and Ellegren (
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0039">1999</a>). DNA was extracted from blood samples, and PCR reactions were performed in order to amplify genomic DNA. DNA sequences with only the CHDIZ fragment correspond to males, whereas DNA sequences with the CHDIZ and/or the CHDIW fragment correspond to females. Plasma concentrations of CORT were measured in duplicate by radio‐immunoassay, as previously described (Lormée, Jouventin, Trouve, &amp; Chastel, 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0074" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0074">2003</a>). Feather CORT assays were conducted at the CEBC by following previously validated methods (Bortolotti et al., 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0014">2008</a>) with minor improvements (see Meillère et al., 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0085" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0085">2016</a>). Specifically, 10 ml of methanol (HPLC grade) were added to each feather sample to extract CORT from the whole feather. Then, feathers were incubated at 50°C overnight in a shaking water bath, the methanol was separated from feather material, and the feather remnants were washed before being added to the original methanol extract. Then, feather extracts were analyzed by radio‐immunoassay at the CEBC as previously described (Lormée et al., 
  <a rid="ece34788-bib-0074" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34788-bib-0074">2003</a>). Feather CORT levels were expressed either as ng of CORT per mg of feather (ng/mg) or as ng of CORT per mm of feather (ng/mm). The minimum detectable CORT level was 0.83 ng/ml. All samples were run in three assays, and the intra‐ and inter‐assay coefficients of variation were 7.07% and 9.99%, respectively.
 </p>
</sec>
