<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In a comprehensive review of several crop species, 
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ainsworth and Long (2005)</xref> reported that the predicted rise in atmospheric CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> concentrations will benefit most C
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> plants. Elevated CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> is expected to stimulate photosynthesis and enhance light use efficiency into biomass and crop yield as well as improve water use efficiency (WUE) through closing stomata and preventing transpirational water loss (
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ainsworth and Rogers, 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Dahal et al., 2014b</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Dahal and Vanlerberghe, 2018a</xref>). Short-term exposure of C
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> plants from ambient to elevated CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> immediately stimulate the rates of photosynthesis (
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Cheng et al., 1998</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Long et al., 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ainsworth and Rogers, 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Dahal et al., 2012</xref>). This CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> stimulation of rates of carbon assimilation in C
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> plants is accounted for by two reasons. First, Ribulose-1,5-bisphosphate carboxylase/oxygenase (RuBisCO) is limited by CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> substrate at current ambient CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> concentrations of 380 ppm, the value close to the K
 <sub class="sub">m</sub> (CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>) for RuBisCO (
 <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Long et al., 2004</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B126" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Tcherkez et al., 2006</xref>). Therefore, an immediate increase in RuBisCO carboxylation velocity can be achieved through increased availability of CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> substrate for RuBisCO following exposure to elevated CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>. Second, high CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> competitively suppresses rates of photorespiratory carbon loss since CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> is a competitive inhibitor of the RuBisCO oxygenation reaction (
 <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Long et al., 2004</xref>). However, during long-term growth at elevated CO
 <sub class="sub">2,</sub> C
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> plants may exhibit feedback inhibition of initial photosynthetic stimulation achieved following short-term exposure. The feedback inhibition of photosynthesis is accounted for by accumulation of non-structural carbohydrates in the source leaves (
 <xref rid="B123" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Stitt and Quick, 1989</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Foyer, 1990</xref>). For details, the readers are suggested to read the theoretical model of the photosynthetic response of C
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> plants to CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> proposed by 
 <xref rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Farquhar et al. (1980)</xref>. Up on long-term growth at elevated CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>, and when measured at higher C
 <sub class="sub">i</sub>, photosynthetic rate is usually limited either by the capacity of photosynthetic electron transport chain to supply ATP and NADPH to regenerate Ribulose-1,5-bisphosphate (RuBP) or by the capacity of starch and sucrose synthesis to utilize triose phosphates and regenerate P
 <sub class="sub">i</sub> (
 <xref rid="B141" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Yang et al., 2016</xref>). The P
 <sub class="sub">i</sub> regeneration-limited photosynthesis is governed by the balance between the source leaves and sink strength to supply and consume the carbon (
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Arp, 1991</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Drake et al., 1997</xref>). The initial stimulation of carbon assimilation by elevated CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> results in the accumulation of carbohydrates due to limited sink capacity to utilize carbohydrates and concomitant decreased carbon export to the sinks (
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kramer, 1981</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Arp, 1991</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Drake et al., 1997</xref>). This results in a short-term depletion in stromal P
 <sub class="sub">i</sub> due to decreased utilization of phosphorylated intermediates. Consequently, ATP synthesis in the chloroplast is inhibited leading to a decrease in the rate of phosphoglyceric acid (PGA) conversion to triose phosphate and eventually feedback limitation of photosynthesis (
 <xref rid="B117" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Sharkey and Vanderveer, 1989</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B123" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Stitt and Quick, 1989</xref>). The feedback limitation of photosynthesis is also suggested to be associated with the downregulation of the key regulatory photosynthetic gene expression and corresponding enzyme activities (
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Harley and Sharkey, 1991</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Drake et al., 1997</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B91" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Moore et al., 1999</xref>).
</p>
