<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Although potato plant exhibits photosynthetic acclimation to elevated CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>, it will increase tuber yield most from increasing CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> concentrations relative to other chief food crops such as, corn, rice and wheat (
 <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Jaggard et al., 2010</xref>). So, enhancing potato yield would be crucial for food security and meet the nutrition requirements of the rising population. However, most of these high CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> experiments have been conducted under ambient temperature with no water limitations. Given that the predicted rise in atmospheric CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> is expected to be coupled with an increase in temperature, the yield gain achieved through high CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> may be offset by yield loss due to high temperature and agricultural drought. For instance, although the projected increase in atmospheric CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> is predicted to cause about 1.8% increase in global crop yields per decade over the next few decades the projected high temperature stress, water deficit and, insect and disease threats may decrease the crop yield by a 0–4% over the same period (
 <xref rid="B146" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ziska et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">DeLucia et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B82" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lobell and Gourdji, 2012</xref>). 
 <xref rid="B129" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Tonkaz et al. (2010)</xref> have reported a 30% decrease in winter wheat yield by a 6°C increase in growth temperature. Thus, future research on high CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> experiment needs to be performed in combination with heat stress, drought and soil salinity in order to understand the effects of high CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> on growth and tuber yield of potato under changing environment. In addition, it is still not understood clearly about the molecular, biochemical and physiological mechanisms of CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>-stimulation of yield and biomass for potato. For instance, does rising CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> affect source-sink ratio? carbon and energy balance? carbon export to tubers? These are the key areas of future high CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> research.
</p>
