<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We demonstrated that strong trade‐offs between the stability and level of ecosystem service provisioning exist in temperate forest ecosystems. Our results indicate that increasing the level of service provisioning might at the same time reduce its temporal stability. This generally supports the hypothesis of a negative relationship between the stability and level of ES provisioning. However, the strength of the trade‐off varied with ES and focal indicator. Relationships were generally stronger for stock indicators than for flows, in particular for processes such as C uptake and water runoff. The strong influence of high‐frequency climate variability was weakening a generally negative stability–provisioning relationship for flow indicators. In addition to “fast” (i.e., annual) climate variability, “slow” variability induced by stand development (i.e., at time scales of decades) influenced the temporal stability of ES provisioning. In particular, initial conditions, reflecting the legacies of past disturbances in the form of a skewed age‐class distribution, can have a long‐lasting effect on future ecosystem trajectories (see Appendix 
 <xref rid="eap1785-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S1</xref>: Fig. 
 <xref rid="eap1785-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S17</xref> and Temperli et al. 
 <xref rid="eap1785-bib-0071" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>) and influence the future stability of ecosystems (Schurman et al. 
 <xref rid="eap1785-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2018</xref>). As a consequence of such slow variability from stand development, we found a change in the trade‐off between stability and level of ecosystem service provisioning over time (Appendix 
 <xref rid="eap1785-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S1</xref>: Table 
 <xref rid="eap1785-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S5</xref>), underlining that the choice of study period (here 200 yr) can distinctly influence results regarding stability.
</p>
