<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">A field experiment was used to calibrate and validate the simulation capability of the DNDC model for CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> emissions in this study area. The experiment was conducted in 2017 at the National Rice Irrigation Experiment Center in Suihua City, Heilongjiang Province (127°40′ E, 46°57′ N). The annual average temperature is 2~3 °C, the annual average rainfall is 500~600 mm, and the frost-free period is 128 days. The soil is loam. The bulk density of 0–10-cm soil is 1.26 g/cm
 <sup class="sup">3</sup>, the clay content is 21%, the porosity is 0.45%, the organic matter content is 41.8 g/kg, and the pH is 6.4. The rice variety was “Longqing 3” (
 <italic class="italic">japonica</italic>), which is the main local cultivar, with a planting density of 30 cm × 10 cm. It was transplanted on 20 May 2017 and harvested on 20 September 2017. Except for mid-season drainage from 1 July to 7 July 2017, the water layer was maintained in paddy fields during the rice growth period. The chemical fertilizers that were used were urea (N 46%), superphosphate (P
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O
 <sub class="sub">5</sub> 12%), and potassium chloride (K
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O 60%), respectively. A total of 135 kg/hm
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> of N, 45 kg/hm
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> of P
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O
 <sub class="sub">5</sub>, and 80 kg/hm
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> of K
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O were used. For N fertilizer, the ratio of types of fertilizer was 4.5:2:1.5:2 in the sequence of basal fertilizer: tillering fertilizer: promoting flower fertilizer: preserving flower fertilizer. K
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O fertilizer was used twice as the basal fertilizer and 8.5 leaf age, respectively, with a ratio of 1:1. P
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O
 <sub class="sub">5</sub> fertilizer was applied once as the basal fertilizer. The maximum biomass values of grain, leaf, stem, and root were 4600 kg C/hm
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>, 1859 kg C/hm
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>, 1957 kg C/hm
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>, and 1370 kg C/hm
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>, respectively. The content of C and N in each part was determined by Element Analyzer (Flash 2000 HT, Thermo Fisher Science, USA), and the methods for measuring are described in reference [
 <xref rid="B43-ijerph-16-00692" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>] and [
 <xref rid="B44-ijerph-16-00692" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>]. The C/N ratios of grain, leaf, stem, and root adjusted by DNDC model parameters were 46, 58, 58, and 72, respectively. The nitrogen fixation index of local rice calculated by our research group was 1.26. The daily meteorological data in the year of the experiment were derived from the automatic weather station of the experiment station, including daily Tmax, Tmin, rainfall, average wind speed, average humidity, and radiation. For the observation and calculation methods of CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> fluxes, refer to reference [
 <xref rid="B30-ijerph-16-00692" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>].
</p>
