<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Radiative forcing</div>
 <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Values of radiative forcing (RF) for CH
  <sub>4</sub> and CO
  <sub>2</sub> were calculated with equations from Etminan 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span> (their Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>). Due to overlapping absorption, the RFs of CH
  <sub>4</sub> and CO
  <sub>2</sub> depend on their own concentrations but also on that of N
  <sub>2</sub>O. The RF equations require as input the reference (e.g. year 1750) and perturbed (e.g. year 2100) concentrations of CH
  <sub>4</sub>, CO
  <sub>2</sub> and N
  <sub>2</sub>O. Concentrations of CO
  <sub>2</sub> and N
  <sub>2</sub>O were taken from those RCP scenarios that are consistent with our GAINS anthropogenic emission scenarios, i.e. RCP 2.6 for MFR and RCP 6.0 for CLE
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>
  </span>. CH
  <sub>4</sub> concentrations are calculated using our one-box model of atmospheric CH
  <sub>4</sub>, which incorporates the whole range of maximum feasible reduction in methane emissions and also takes into account our estimates of natural emission changes.
 </p>
 <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is important to note that in this study we have only calculated the direct RF of CH
  <sub>4</sub> concentration change. We did not consider the indirect effects of ozone and stratospheric water vapor that would result from an increase in methane emissions. Myhre 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
  </span> accounted for the ozone and stratospheric water vapour contributions by multiplying the effect of CH
  <sub>4</sub> by 1.50 and 1.15, respectively, but these scaling factors strictly apply to the pre-industrial to present-day period only. Calculating indirect effects for our future scenarios would require more advanced modelling tools but their consideration would not change the conclusions of the study, as they would increase the anthropogenic and natural contributions to methane RF by similar percentage amounts.
 </p>
</sec>
