<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">According to many ancient myths, humans did not invent fire-making de novo but rather learned it from personalities like Prometheus and subsequently spread the practice amongst themselves. These stories reveal how ancient myth-makers already grasped the fundamental importance of social learning—the process whereby individuals learn new behaviours, values and opinions from others [
  <a rid="pcbi.1007000.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1007000.ref001">1</a>]. Social learning is no less relevant in the era of human-environment challenges [
  <a rid="pcbi.1007000.ref002" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1007000.ref002">2</a>–
  <a rid="pcbi.1007000.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1007000.ref004">4</a>]. The importance of social learning and social processes more generally in climate change mitigation and adaptation is well recognised [
  <a rid="pcbi.1007000.ref005" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1007000.ref005">5</a>–
  <a rid="pcbi.1007000.ref008" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1007000.ref008">8</a>]. Increasingly sophisticated geophysical climate models are helping us understand the impacts of anthropogenic greenhouse gas (GHG) emissions [
  <a rid="pcbi.1007000.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1007000.ref009">9</a>–
  <a rid="pcbi.1007000.ref011" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1007000.ref011">11</a>], and the importance of these models is hard to understate. However, climate projections depend strongly on the assumed trajectory of GHG emissions [
  <a rid="pcbi.1007000.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1007000.ref012">12</a>]. This trajectory is determined by human behaviour and yet climate models generally do not incorporate dynamic social processes relevant to GHG emissions. Rather, GHG emissions are assumed to follow some specified trajectory. These trajectories are constructed with socio-economic factors in mind, (see Representative Concentration Pathways [
  <a rid="pcbi.1007000.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1007000.ref012">12</a>] and Shared Socioeconomic Pathways [
  <a rid="pcbi.1007000.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1007000.ref013">13</a>] for instance), but are not coupled to climate dynamics and do not capture human responses to climate change in a mechanistic way.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Just as human behaviour influences climate trends, climate change in turn influences human behaviour concerning GHG emissions, including both climate change mitigation and adaptation [
  <a rid="pcbi.1007000.ref005" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1007000.ref005">5</a>, 
  <a rid="pcbi.1007000.ref006" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1007000.ref006">6</a>, 
  <a rid="pcbi.1007000.ref008" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1007000.ref008">8</a>, 
  <a rid="pcbi.1007000.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1007000.ref014">14</a>, 
  <a rid="pcbi.1007000.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1007000.ref015">15</a>]. Individuals in places with rising average temperatures are more likely to perceive climate change [
  <a rid="pcbi.1007000.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1007000.ref015">15</a>], and social effects are apparent when individuals take steps in response to such shifting perceptions [
  <a rid="pcbi.1007000.ref006" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1007000.ref006">6</a>, 
  <a rid="pcbi.1007000.ref008" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1007000.ref008">8</a>]. There is also an important distinction between social learning and social norms—socially accepted and widely practised modes of conduct [
  <a rid="pcbi.1007000.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1007000.ref016">16</a>]. Social norms are known to have a strong influence on human behaviour [
  <a rid="pcbi.1007000.ref017" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1007000.ref017">17</a>] including aspects relating to climate change [
  <a rid="pcbi.1007000.ref007" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1007000.ref007">7</a>, 
  <a rid="pcbi.1007000.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1007000.ref016">16</a>, 
  <a rid="pcbi.1007000.ref018" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1007000.ref018">18</a>] and therefore play an important role in determining emission trajectories [
  <a rid="pcbi.1007000.ref006" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1007000.ref006">6</a>]. Multiple studies show a tendency for individuals to conform to emerging norms in support of climate change mitigation [
  <a rid="pcbi.1007000.ref007" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1007000.ref007">7</a>, 
  <a rid="pcbi.1007000.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1007000.ref016">16</a>]. Moreover, it appears that individuals are often not consciously aware of the importance of social norms in their decision-making and instead falsely ascribe their decisions to other factors [
  <a rid="pcbi.1007000.ref018" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1007000.ref018">18</a>]. However, it is important to note that social norms do not automatically promote socially beneficial outcomes. They can equally well force conformity to a destructive norm such as political extremism [
  <a rid="pcbi.1007000.ref019" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1007000.ref019">19</a>]. This also happens in the context of climate change behaviour, where it has been found that individuals may also conform to a norm of non-mitigation, by adjusting their habits to match those of less environmentally friendly neighbours [
  <a rid="pcbi.1007000.ref018" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1007000.ref018">18</a>, 
  <a rid="pcbi.1007000.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1007000.ref020">20</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hence, Earth’s climate and human subsystems are part of a single coupled system where social dynamics play a vital role. Yet, models of Earth’s coupled climate-behaviour system remain essentially undeveloped. One such approach [
  <a rid="pcbi.1007000.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1007000.ref021">21</a>] couples a sophisticated climate model [
  <a rid="pcbi.1007000.ref011" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1007000.ref011">11</a>] to a model for individual behavioural change based on the theory of planned behaviour—a dominant paradigm in psychology [
  <a rid="pcbi.1007000.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pcbi.1007000.ref022">22</a>]. The authors find that the sensitivity of global temperature change to human factors such as response to extreme events, social norms and perceived ability to adopt mitigative strategies is of a similar magnitude to its sensitivity to geophysical factors. They deduce that quantifying behavioural uncertainty and physical uncertainty in climate projections deserve equal attention. The model focuses on how individual psychology and behaviour are influenced by extreme weather events. Social effects are modelled phenomenologically (i.e., exogenously imposed): individuals do not learn behaviour or opinions from one another, and social norms are treated as a fixed effect that does not depend on the population’s current composition of attitudes.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here, we treat social learning and social norms endogenously, by modelling their dynamics as they emerge from rules governing how individuals interact, learn and behave. Our first objective is to develop qualitative insights into how different aspects of the system—endogenous social processes, temperature trends, and mitigation costs—separately and together determine possible dynamics of the larger socio-climate system. Our second objective is to illustrate potential uses of coupled socio-climate models to chart social and economic policy pathways that mitigate climate change as quickly as possible. To meet these objectives, we sought to develop a model that (1) could capture a range of IPCC climate change scenarios, ranging from 4 degrees of warming by 2100 (RCP 8.5 scenario) to sub 2 degrees of warming (RCP 2.6 scenario), (2) was simple enough to analyse so that we could learn which mechanisms drive the predicted socio-climate dynamics, (3) was based on existing approaches for modelling social dynamics and climate dynamics, and (4) captured the salient features of social and climate systems. Given the model’s simplicity, it is primed for insights as to how social and climate processes interact, though limited in its predictive capacity due to the complexity of the socio-climate system. The development of more complex socio-climate models will be an important research avenue, once the mechanisms of socio-climate dynamics are better understood.</p>
</sec>
