<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">With this in mind, research has explored the role that health outcomes can play in providing a justification for enhanced domestic climate change action. Research undertaken around climate change communication has found that framing climate change from a health perspective can positively influence an individual’s acceptance of robust climate policies, irrespective of political preferences [
 <xref rid="B11-ijerph-13-00927" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-ijerph-13-00927" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. Further, the health co-benefits literature has established that there are significant, shorter-term, and localized health—and consequently economic—benefits that result from the implementation of emissions reduction (mitigation) policies [
 <xref rid="B13-ijerph-13-00927" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. For example, in justifying the implementation of the Clean Power Plan in 2015, the United States (US) Environmental Protection Agency estimated that, by 2030, health benefits for the US would include up to 3600 fewer premature deaths and up to 90,000 fewer pediatric asthma attacks, totaling an economic saving of up to USD$54 billion in 2030 alone [
 <xref rid="B14-ijerph-13-00927" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. These health co-benefits have been quantified to allow for comparison with economic costs often considered in the development of climate change mitigation policies. While environmental health impacts researchers acknowledge that health co-benefits have not gained the political traction they potentially warrant in the development of climate policy [
 <xref rid="B15-ijerph-13-00927" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-ijerph-13-00927" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-ijerph-13-00927" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>], there is minimal research examining the role of health co-benefits in the development of national climate change mitigation policies. To begin to address this knowledge gap, we have explored how health co-benefits have been considered and accounted for in the development of Australian climate change mitigation policies.
</p>
