<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.0 20040830//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Evol Appl</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Evol Appl</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">eva</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Evolutionary Applications</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1752-4571</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1752-4571</issn><publisher><publisher-name>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Chichester, UK</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4662346</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">26640522</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/eva.12329</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Impacts of local adaptation of forest trees on associations with herbivorous insects: implications for adaptive forest management</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sinclair</surname><given-names>Frazer H</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>Graham N</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Nicholls</surname><given-names>James A</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Cavers</surname><given-names>Stephen</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gibbs</surname><given-names>Melanie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Butterill</surname><given-names>Philip</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>Stefanie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au5">5</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ducousso</surname><given-names>Alexis</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au5">5</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Gerber</surname><given-names>Sophie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au5">5</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Petit</surname><given-names>R&#x000e9;my J</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au5">5</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kremer</surname><given-names>Antoine</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au5">5</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au6">6</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sch&#x000f6;nrogge</surname><given-names>Karsten</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="au2">2</xref></contrib><aff id="au1"><label>1</label><institution>Institute of Evolutionary Biology, University of Edinburgh</institution><addr-line>Edinburgh, UK</addr-line></aff><aff id="au2"><label>2</label><institution>Centre for Ecology and Hydrology</institution><addr-line>Wallingford, UK</addr-line></aff><aff id="au3"><label>3</label><institution>Centre for Ecology and Hydrology</institution><addr-line>Edinburgh, UK</addr-line></aff><aff id="au4"><label>4</label><institution>Faculty of Science, Biology Center, The Czech Academy of Sciences, University of South Bohemia</institution><addr-line>&#x0010c;esk&#x000e9; Bud&#x0011b;jovice, Czech Republic</addr-line></aff><aff id="au5"><label>5</label><institution>INRA, UMR 1202 BIOGECO</institution><addr-line>Cestas, France</addr-line></aff><aff id="au6"><label>6</label><institution>UMR 1202 BIOGECO, University of Bordeaux</institution><addr-line>Talence, France</addr-line></aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><bold>Correspondence</bold> Graham N. Stone, Institute of Evolutionary Biology, University of Edinburgh, Edinburgh EH9 3JT, UK., Tel.: +44&#x000a0;131&#x000a0;6507194;, fax: +44 131 6506556, e-mail: <email>graham.stone@ed.ac.uk</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>12</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>13</day><month>10</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>10</issue><fpage>972</fpage><lpage>987</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>17</day><month>8</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>20</day><month>9</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2015 The Authors. <italic>Evolutionary Applications</italic> published by John Wiley &#x00026; Sons Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Disruption of species interactions is a key issue in climate change biology. Interactions involving forest trees may be particularly vulnerable due to evolutionary rate limitations imposed by long generation times. One mitigation strategy for such impacts is Climate matching &#x02013; the augmentation of local native tree populations by input from nonlocal populations currently experiencing predicted future climates. This strategy is controversial because of potential cascading impacts on locally adapted animal communities. We explored these impacts using abundance data for local native gallwasp herbivores sampled from 20 provenances of sessile oak (<italic>Quercus petraea</italic>) planted in a common garden trial. We hypothesized that non-native provenances would show (i) declining growth performance with increasing distance between provenance origin and trial site, and (ii) phenological differences to local oaks that increased with latitudinal differences between origin and trial site. Under a local adaptation hypothesis, we predicted declining gallwasp abundance with increasing phenological mismatch between native and climate-matched trees. Both hypotheses for oaks were supported. Provenance explained significant variation in gallwasp abundance, but no gall type showed the relationship between abundance and phenological mismatch predicted by a local adaptation hypothesis. Our results show that climate matching would have complex and variable impacts on oak gall communities.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>adaptive forest management</kwd><kwd>climate matching</kwd><kwd>gallwasp</kwd><kwd>local adaptation</kwd><kwd>plant&#x02013;insect interactions</kwd><kwd>population nonindependence</kwd><kwd>provenance trials</kwd><kwd><italic>Quercus petraea</italic></kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>Ecosystems across the world are experiencing profound climate change (IPCC, <xref rid="b42" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>), driving population responses whose effects can influence community structure and function (Walther et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b85" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>; Parmesan and Yohe <xref rid="b58" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>). Forest ecosystems are expected to be particularly sensitive to pressures imposed by climate because the long generation times of trees result in low rates of adaptation (Lindner et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b49" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). Furthermore, because forest trees are foundation (and also often keystone) species for associated communities of plants, animals, fungi and microbes (Kennedy and Southwood <xref rid="b44" ref-type="bibr">1984</xref>; McEwan et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b51" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Lindenmayer et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b48" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>), effects on them are expected to cascade through associated trophic levels (Frelich et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b27" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). Consequently, there is considerable interest in developing adaptive forest management strategies to preserve ecosystem productivity and services in the face of climate change (Spittlehouse and Stewart <xref rid="b72" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>; Broadmeadow et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b14" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Aitken et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b1" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Bower and Aitken <xref rid="b13" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Bolte et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b12" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). Assisted migration, in the form of climate matching, has emerged as one potential strategy facilitating forest adaptation to predicted future climates (Hoegh-Guldberg et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b40" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Dawson et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b20" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>), particularly in commercial forestry where potential for <italic>in&#x000a0;situ</italic> adaptation may be limited (Broadmeadow et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b14" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; but see Cavers and Cottrell <xref rid="b16" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Climate matching is based on the premise that natural forest stands are locally adapted to current local climates (Savolainen et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b66" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>, <xref rid="b67" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Alberto et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b3" ref-type="bibr">2013a</xref>), and for a given species and planting location involves the following steps: (i) identify climate variables that predict performance for the target tree species across its range; (ii) use regional climate models to predict future climates at the proposed planting site; (iii) identify locations within the species range that currently experience the predicted conditions; (iv) plant seed from tree populations in the identified locations (termed provenances in forestry) in the expectation that resulting trees will be well matched to future climates, and contribute adaptive variation that accelerates subsequent local adaptation (Broadmeadow et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b14" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>).</p><p>As remediation strategies, climate matching and other forms of assisted migration remain subjects of vigorous debate (Dawson et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b20" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Lunt et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b50" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Cavers and Cottrell <xref rid="b16" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Forests are biologically diverse ecosystems, and the value of climate matching, or any other strategy that modifies the genetic, physical or spatial structure of tree populations, must be considered not only in terms of its effectiveness in promoting forest adaptation and resilience, but also its impacts on local associated biodiversity. Community genetic research has shown that the organisms associated with forest stands reflect the genotypes and genetic diversity of the host trees (Dungey et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b22" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>; Wimp et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b92" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Whitham et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b90" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>), and a range of studies have shown adaptation of plants to local herbivores and <italic>vice versa</italic> (Sork et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b70" ref-type="bibr">1993</xref>; Hanks and Denno <xref rid="b34" ref-type="bibr">1994</xref>; Egan and Ott <xref rid="b24" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Tack and Roslin <xref rid="b77" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Bernhardsson et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b10" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). As such, the introduction of new tree genotypes as part of a climate matching strategy may drive changes in the identity, abundance and genetics of associated species (Lefevre et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b47" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). However, it is difficult to forecast the direction and magnitude of such changes. While some studies predict increased abundance of herbivores on non-native tree provenances (Bernhardsson et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b10" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>), others suggest the opposite through local herbivore adaptation to plant phenology (Van Asch and Visser <xref rid="b81" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Visser <xref rid="b84" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Pearse and Karban <xref rid="b59" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). The key issues are the extent to which host plant provenances vary in phenotypic traits relevant to herbivore success, and the magnitude of herbivore population responses to such variation.</p><p>Here we explore the community effects of climate matching by quantifying the impact of provenance on (i) the phenotype (growth performance and phenology) of an important and widespread European oak, <italic>Quercus petraea</italic>, and (ii) the abundance of associated insect herbivores. Our approach exploits an established INRA forestry trial at La Petite Charnie in Northwest France, where 96 provenances of <italic>Q.&#x000a0;petraea</italic> grow surrounded by natural oak forest and are exposed to native herbivores. Our study focuses on oak cynipid gallwasps (Hymenoptera; Cynipidae), specialized herbivores whose larvae develop in galls on their oak hosts (Sch&#x000f6;nrogge et al. <xref rid="b68" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>; Stone and Sch&#x000f6;nrogge <xref rid="b74" ref-type="bibr">2003</xref>; Harper et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b35" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>). Gall induction requires access to host oak tissues at the correct developmental stage (Harper et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b35" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>), and oak cynipids are highly sensitive to host plant phenology (Askew <xref rid="b5" ref-type="bibr">1962</xref>; Crawley and Akhteruzzaman <xref rid="b18" ref-type="bibr">1988</xref>). These aspects of gallwasp biology, coupled with a partly parthenogenetic lifecycle, are associated with local adaptation to specific host plant populations (Mopper et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b53" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>; Mopper <xref rid="b52" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Egan and Ott <xref rid="b24" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Tack et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b78" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>) and individuals (Egan and Ott <xref rid="b24" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>) and make gallwasps an appropriate sentinel taxon for exploration of the potential effects of climate matching.</p><p>We expect the performance of oak provenances to correlate positively with the extent to which they are adapted to prevailing climatic conditions (Broadmeadow et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b14" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Lefevre et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b47" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). This hypothesis predicts that performance of locally native provenances will decline over time &#x02013; and recent rapid climate change may mean that populations of long-lived trees are already somewhat mismatched to the conditions in which they grow. The hypothesis also predicts that provenances selected to match conditions furthest in the future should be least well matched to current conditions and so perform least well in the present. We test this hypothesis using multiple performance measures for 20 provenances planted at the La Petite Charnie provenance trial, selected to maximize the available range in source latitude and longitude as well as the mismatch in climate between the provenance trial and the provenance origin. We then test two contrasting hypotheses linking herbivorous insect abundance to observed variation in performance among oak provenances. The plant stress hypothesis predicts that herbivores should show improved performance and abundance on physiologically stressed plants, due to higher levels of mobilized nitrogen in stressed plant tissues and an associated increase in resource quality for herbivores (White <xref rid="b87" ref-type="bibr">1969</xref>, <xref rid="b88" ref-type="bibr">1974</xref>, <xref rid="b89" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). In contrast, the plant vigour hypothesis (Price <xref rid="b62" ref-type="bibr">1991</xref>; Cornelissen et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b17" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>) predicts increased herbivore performance and abundance on more vigorous plants or plant organs (those with high growth rates or large ultimate size relative to the population mean) through elevated nutrient content and reduced concentrations of defensive compounds. Here we test both hypotheses using abundance data across provenances for 20 cynipid gall types.</p><p>Phenological matching of key biological events is crucial for many interactions between forest trees and associated organisms. For example, synchronization of breeding with high plant resource availability (budburst for leaf-eating herbivores) is central to reproductive success in herbivores and associated trophic levels. We thus expect associated organisms to show local adaptation to host plant phenology (Ducousso et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b21" ref-type="bibr">1996</xref>; Yukawa <xref rid="b93" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>; Van Asch and Visser <xref rid="b81" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Van Asch et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b82" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Alberto et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b4" ref-type="bibr">2013b</xref>). Many plants show latitudinal clines in phenological events, such as the timing of budburst, whose onset is often determined by photoperiodic cues (Savolainen et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b66" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Aitken et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b1" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>) or the interaction between photoperiod and temperature (Laube et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b46" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). This is relevant to climate matching because, in a warming world, it often involves introducing plants to higher latitudes from lower latitudes. As a result, phenological mismatches with local herbivores might occur by disrupting any adaptation to the local combination of thermal and photoperiod cues, with associated impacts on the fitness of herbivores and trophically linked taxa such as natural enemies (Visser <xref rid="b84" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Thomson et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b79" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Kerstes and De Jong <xref rid="b45" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>; Van Asch et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b82" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>). Here we quantify the phenotypic mismatch in budburst date between the same 20 provenances and assess the impact of phenological mismatch on cynipid gall abundance. Specifically, we test the local adaptation hypothesis, that is that herbivore abundance will decline with increasing phenological difference between introduced and locally native oak provenances. We distinguish phenological effects from other potential differences between provenances (e.g., variation in chemical defences) by incorporating provenance phenology into our analyses.</p><p>Our analytical approach recognizes that tree populations are linked by shared common ancestry and gene flow and hence are unlikely to represent statistically independent replicates (Stone et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b76" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). Here we investigate the impact of potential nonindependence by comparing the results of analyses that incorporate the expected variance&#x02013;covariance among populations in a generalized linear mixed model framework (Hadfield and Nakagawa <xref rid="b33" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>).</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Materials and methods</title><sec><title>Provenance trial design</title><p>Provenance effects were explored using a large experimental trial of <italic>Q.&#x000a0;petraea</italic> at La Petite Charnie in Northwest France (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">Fig. 1</xref>; 48.086&#x000b0; north, 0.168&#x000b0; west; details on the planting and layout of the trial are provided in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sd1">Data&#x000a0;S1</xref>). We selected 20 provenances whose origins span 15&#x000b0; of latitude and 34&#x000b0; of longitude, incorporating the greatest available geographic separation and source environmental variation (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">Fig. 1</xref>, Table&#x000a0;S1 in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sd1">Data&#x000a0;S1</xref>), and included the closest provenance to the trial site (For&#x000ea;t de Berc&#x000e9;, approximately 50&#x000a0;km from La Petite Charnie). Each sampled provenance is planted in multiple replicate plots of 24 trees distributed across five soil zones (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sd1">Data&#x000a0;S1</xref>). We selected two plots per soil zone per provenance, giving a total of 200 study plots containing 4800 trees. Previous INRA surveys provided data for each tree for the following phenotypic traits (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sd1">Data&#x000a0;S1</xref> for illustrations of character states):</p><fig id="fig01" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Location of the Petite Charnie provenance trials and the 20 selected study provenances. Sites are identified by number in Table<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">1</xref>. Countries contributing provenances are indicated by their two letter ISO codes.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="eva0008-0972-f1"/></fig><list list-type="order"><list-item><p>
<italic>Budburst</italic> &#x02013; spring budburst phenology was scored on a 0&#x02013;5 ordinal scale, where 0 is a dormant bud and 5 is a fully open bud, in spring 1995 (this closely parallels that used in other studies on oak (Crawley and Akhteruzzaman <xref rid="b18" ref-type="bibr">1988</xref>; Tack et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b78" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). A higher score on the survey date indicates earlier budburst. Although oak phenology is not known to show strong <italic>G</italic>&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;<italic>E</italic> interactions across years (Alberto et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b2" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>), we nevertheless repeated phenology scoring in 2009 for 582 trees in a subset of eight provenances. Phenology scores for the same tree in 1995 and 2009 were significantly and positively correlated (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sd4">Data&#x000a0;S4</xref>). We thus regard using the 1995 data for all 20 provenances as unlikely to produce misleading or contrary results.
</p></list-item><list-item><p>
<italic>Diameter at breast height</italic> (<italic>DBH</italic>) &#x02013; tree diameter at a height of 1.3&#x000a0;m, measured during winter 2001&#x02013;2002. A higher value is associated with more rapid growth and higher plant vigour.
</p></list-item><list-item><p>
<italic>Form</italic> &#x02013; a measure based on tree shape, recorded on an ordinal scale from 1 to 10 during winter 2001&#x02013;2002. Stressed trees with bushy, irregular growth and poor apical dominance receive a low score, while healthy trees with straight stems, even branching and strong apical dominance score highly. These phenotypic measures showed substantial variation among provenances (discussed in more detail below), providing the basis for examination of impacts of phenological matching (<italic>Budburst</italic>) and performance (<italic>DBH</italic>, <italic>Form</italic>) on herbivore abundance (Table<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">Fig. 2</xref>).
</p></list-item></list><table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Summary of the 20 studied provenances of <italic>Quercus petraea,</italic> ordered by longitude from west to east showing their three digit INRA provenance codes, provenance origin (site name and country), latitude and longitude in decimal degrees, altitude (Alt), the availability of genotypic data and the mean values across all trees of each provenance for the phenotypic traits <italic>Budburst, Diameter at breast height</italic> (<italic>DBH</italic>) and <italic>Form</italic></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site number in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01">Fig. 1</xref></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Code</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Provenance name</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Country</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Long (DD)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lat (DD)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alt (m)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genotypic data</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean <italic>Budburst</italic>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean <italic>DBH</italic>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean <italic>Form</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">185</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Blakeney</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">UK</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;2.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.78</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">76</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.08</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">120</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.24</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>2</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>217</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Berc&#x000e9;</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>France</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>0.39</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>47.81</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>155</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Yes</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>1.59</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>98</bold></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>4.2</bold></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">237</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">R&#x000e9;no Valdieu</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">France</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">230</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.65</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">116</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.14</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">210</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Saint Germain</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">France</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.08</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.71</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">113</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.13</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">194</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soudrain</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">France</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.38</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.95</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">178</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.24</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">110</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.33</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">211</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pr&#x000e9;mery</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">France</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">300</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.55</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">106</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.34</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">201</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">La Haie Renaut</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">France</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.95</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.67</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">180</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.77</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">109</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.24</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">245</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x000c9;tangs</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">France</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.96</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46.93</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">200</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">113</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.19</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">233</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vach&#x000e8;res</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">France</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.63</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.98</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">650</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.69</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.15</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">230</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Romersberg</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">France</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.73</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.82</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">220</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.06</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">101</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.17</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">250</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cochem</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Germany</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.08</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">400</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.86</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">112</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.43</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">225</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Still</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">France</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.25</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48.58</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">688</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.55</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">105</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.56</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">252</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Johanneskreuz</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Germany</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.83</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">460</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.03</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">116</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.42</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">257</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wolfgang</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Germany</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">50.15</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">160</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.61</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.92</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">181</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Horbylunde</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Denmark</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.41</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">56.13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">80</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.88</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">89</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.99</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">255</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spakensehl</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Germany</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">115</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.54</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">102</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.74</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">248</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kloster-marienberg</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Austria</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.57</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.41</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">310</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.23</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">103</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">179</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sycow</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Poland</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.93</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.18</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">210</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.42</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">104</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.76</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">249</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bolu</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Turkey</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.67</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.92</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1200</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yes</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.58</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.39</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">184</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Telavi</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Georgia</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.47</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.88</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">700</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.79</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.06</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn><p>Values for the provenance closest to the trial site, For&#x000ea;t de Berc&#x000e9;, are shown in bold.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="fig02" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Between-provenance variation in three phenotypic variables (A) <italic>Form</italic>, in which higher values indicate healthier trees; (B) and (D) <italic>Diameter at breast height</italic> (<italic>DBH</italic>), in which higher values indicate more vigorous growth; and (C) <italic>Budburst</italic> date, in which higher values indicate earlier budburst in the spring. In (A) and (B), the position of provenances on the <italic>x-axis</italic> relates to their genetic differentiation (estimated as <italic>Geo</italic><italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub>) from the provenance closest to the provenance trial site (For&#x000ea;t de Berc&#x000e9;). In (C) and (D), their position relates to the latitude of their site of origin with the identity of For&#x000ea;t de Berc&#x000e9; shown. Modelling was conducted in the MCMCglmm <sc>r</sc> package, and response variables were modelled with provenance fitted as a fixed effect and provenance, soil zone, plot and tree fitted as random effects. Models of (A) and (C) were fitted with a Poisson distribution, and (B) and (D) with a Gaussian distribution. Priors, burn-in, number of iterations and sampling frequency follow that described previously for the modelling of provenance effects on gall abundance. Vertical bars represent 95% confidence intervals for each mean. MCMC, Markov Chain Monte Carlo.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="eva0008-0972-f2"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Herbivore sampling</title><p>The cynipid species surveyed in this study all have broad geographic distributions; like <italic>Q.&#x000a0;petraea</italic> and closely related oaks, they span the Western Palaearctic from the Iberian Peninsula eastwards to Iran and the Caucasus. Cynipid gall abundance was sampled across the 20 selected provenances in 2008 and 2009. Gallwasps have a spring (sexual) and autumn (asexual) gall generation each year, and both were sampled, giving four surveys in total. For each of the 200 study plots, we sampled galls from 12 of the 24 available trees, a total of 2400 trees. To minimize edge effects, surveyed trees comprised the two internal rows of six trees within each plot. During each survey, using a pole pruner giving us approximately 4&#x000a0;m reach we selected 10 twigs on each tree, each consisting of the last 2&#x000a0;years&#x02019; growth identified using ring scars on the bark. For each twig, we surveyed the galls on all parts (buds, leaves, stem, catkins, acorns; there are no cynipid galls on female flowers in Europe) of its terminal shoot (a module of woody growth from the previous year carrying the new leaves). Galls were identified to species and generation in the field using a morphological key (Redfern and Shirley <xref rid="b64" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>) and our own extensive field experience with this group (Stone et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b75" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>; Cs&#x000f3;ka et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b19" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical analysis</title><sec><title>Controlling for statistical nonindependence of provenances</title><p>One way to address potential statistical nonindependence of&#x000a0;populations within species is to incorporate expected similarities among populations (due to shared common ancestry and/or gene flow) as one or more variance&#x02013;covariance matrices in the random effect structure of a generalized linear mixed model (Stone et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b76" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). Covariance matrices for nonindependence arising through each of migration and common ancestry can be generated for small numbers of populations using population genomic data (e.g., Hearn et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b37" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). However, for larger numbers of populations (as here), and where more limited genotypic data are available, an alternative is to use a measure of pairwise genetic differentiation between populations such as <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> (Weir and Cockerham <xref rid="b86" ref-type="bibr">1984</xref>) as an estimate of their expected covariance (Stone et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b76" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). Where genetic differentiation between populations correlates strongly with geographic distance, variance&#x02013;covariance can be estimated as a function of geographic separation between populations.</p><p>We used data from 10 putatively neutral microsatellite markers (listed in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sd1">Data&#x000a0;S2</xref>; Guichoux et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b31" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>) available for 17 of our 20 study provenances (Table<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl1">1</xref>) to estimate pairwise <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> as implemented in <sc>fstat</sc> version 2.8.3.2 (Weir and Cockerham <xref rid="b86" ref-type="bibr">1984</xref>; Goudet <xref rid="b30" ref-type="bibr">1995</xref>). For comments on the impact of using alternative measures of genetic differentiation related to <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub>, see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sd2">Data&#x000a0;S2</xref>. To allow us to analyse data for all 20 study provenances, we used the highly significant relationship between <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> and geographic distance for the 17 provenances (Mantel test in the <italic>adegenet</italic>
<sc>r</sc> package, <italic>P&#x000a0;</italic>=<italic>&#x000a0;</italic>0.01 with 999 iterations) to estimate a pseudo-<italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> for the full set of 20 provenances, referred to hereafter as <italic>GeoF</italic><sub>ST</sub> (full details are given in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sd2">Data&#x000a0;S2</xref>). Variance&#x02013;covariances between provenances were then estimated as either 1&#x02212;<italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> or 1&#x02212;<italic>GeoF</italic><sub>ST</sub>, such that expected covariance was greatest between provenances with lowest differentiation.</p><p>To explore the consequences of using alternative approaches to control for provenance nonindependence, all of the analyses described below were conducted using the following five dataset/covariance matrix combinations: (i) the subset of 17 provenances for which genotypic data were available, using an identity matrix as the provenance covariance matrix. This identity model assumes provenances to be statistically entirely independent (i.e., 0 covariance between all populations); (ii) the same 17 provenances, using a covariance matrix estimated as 1&#x02212;<italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub>; (iii) the same 17 provenances, using a covariance matrix estimated as 1&#x02212;<italic>GeoF</italic><sub>ST</sub>; (iv) the full set of 20 provenances using an identity model; and (v) the full set of 20 provenances where covariance is estimated as 1&#x02212;<italic>GeoF</italic><sub>ST</sub>. A detailed discussion of this approach to addressing population nonindependence, and values used in the covariance matrices, are provided in the <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sd2">Data&#x000a0;S2</xref>.</p></sec><sec><title>Statistical modelling of provenance effects on gall abundance</title><p>To investigate the influence of tree provenance on the abundance of each individual gall type, we combined the data for the two survey years and used generalized linear mixed models (GLMMs) to partition the variance of gall counts per shoot into the effects of year (as a fixed effect with two levels) and provenance, soil zone, plot and tree (all as random effects). When applying an identity model for the relationship between provenances, the effect of provenance was represented by a single random effect with a unique independent level for each provenance. In models that incorporated the relationship between provenances, provenance co-variance was represented by two random effects. One incorporated the specified variance&#x02013;covariance matrix (1&#x02212;<italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> or 1&#x02212;<italic>GeoF</italic><sub>ST</sub>) to account for provenance nonindependence, while the second incorporated an identity matrix to capture the &#x02018;nugget effect&#x02019; (Matheron <xref rid="b201" ref-type="bibr">1963</xref>), in which variation in the response variable exceeds that expected through correlation between levels of the effect. Models were fitted in a Bayesian Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) framework using the package MCMCglmm version 2.16 (Hadfield <xref rid="b32" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>) in <sc>r</sc> version 2.15.1. For fixed effects, prior settings assumed a normal distribution with a mean (<italic>&#x000b5;</italic>) of 0 and a variance (<italic>V</italic>) of 10<sup>8</sup>. For random effect variances, scaled <italic>F</italic>_{1,1} priors (with scale 1000) were used (Gelman <xref rid="b28" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>) except for the residual variance for which an inverse-gamma prior was used with shape and scale equal to 0.001. Models were run for 500&#x000a0;000 iterations with a burn-in of 50&#x000a0;000 and parameter sampling every 450 iterations. As the response variable was count data and usually contained many zeros, a Poisson error distribution was applied. Our incorporation of <italic>year</italic> as a fixed effect allowed for variation in abundance between years, while estimating the relationship between gall abundance and tree phenotypic traits across both years. The proportion of variance explained by the <italic>year</italic> fixed effect was estimated as the marginal <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> of the model (RsqM), following Nakagawa and Schielzeth (<xref rid="b55" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>) (<sc>r</sc> code for deriving RsqM from MCMCglmm objects is provided in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sd3">Data&#x000a0;S3</xref>). The variance component of each random effect was calculated by dividing its estimated variance parameter by the sum of all the random effect variance parameters, including the residual UNIT term &#x02013; a random effect with a distinct level for each data unit that is fitted automatically for Poisson distributed models in the MCMCglmm package to account for overdispersion &#x02013; and then multiplying each by the proportion of variance not explained by the fixed effect (i.e., 1&#x02212;RsqM). We addressed the effects of multiple tests on false discovery rates &#x02013; the expected proportion of false discoveries among the rejected hypotheses &#x02013; following Benjamini and Hochberg (<xref rid="b8" ref-type="bibr">1995</xref>) and Benjamini and Yekutieli (<xref rid="b9" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>). The false discovery rate is a less stringent condition than the family-wise error rate, so this approach is more powerful than alternatives such as Bonferroni (Nakagawa <xref rid="b54" ref-type="bibr">2004</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Effect of tree phenotype</title><p>To investigate whether tree phenotypic traits were good predictors of variation in gall abundance, GLMMs were used to model counts of individual gall types with <italic>DBH</italic> (growth), <italic>Form</italic> (tree health) or <italic>Budburst</italic> (spring phenology) as fixed effects. While the influences of tree growth and health on gall abundance are expected to be linear, the local adaptation hypothesis for herbivores predicts that the influence of phenology will be curvilinear, with lower gall abundance on provenances that show budburst either before or after local oaks. The fixed effect <italic>Budburst</italic> was therefore fitted as both untransformed and squared terms. To account for potential differences in abundance levels between the two study years, a factor <italic>year</italic> was fitted as a fixed effect.</p><p>For each gall type, counts per shoot were initially modelled with <italic>year</italic> and either <italic>Form</italic>, <italic>DBH</italic>, <italic>Budburst</italic> or both <italic>Budburst</italic> and <italic>Budburst</italic><sup>2</sup> as fixed effects. The severity of co-linearity between these variables was assessed by their variance inflation factors (VIFs) using the <sc>r</sc> package <italic>HH</italic> version 2.3-23 (Heiberger <xref rid="b38" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). To assess the importance of interactions between tree phenotypic traits, a model containing the fixed main effects <italic>Form</italic>, <italic>DBH</italic>, <italic>Budburst</italic>, and their three pairwise interactions was fitted for each gall type. All models were fitted in the MCMCglmm package with the random effect structures and prior specifications described above. The probability that the posterior distribution of the fixed effect coefficients did not include zero (pMCMC) was used to assess the predictive capacity of the fixed effects.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Phenotypic variation among provenances</title><p>If provenances are locally adapted, and divergence in selection history between provenance origins and the trial site increases with genetic distance, then we expect more genetically divergent provenances to show higher stress (measured using <italic>Form</italic>) and lower vigour (measured using <italic>DBH</italic>). <italic>Form</italic> shows no linear relationship, but increases in variance in more divergent provenances (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">Fig. 2A</xref>). Only the most genetically divergent provenance, from Telavi in Georgia, showed a markedly lower <italic>Form</italic> score than other provenances. Plant vigour, measured using <italic>DBH</italic>, does decrease with increasing genetic divergence (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">Fig. 2B</xref>), consistent with local adaptation. Budburst phenology shows a strong relationship with latitude (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">Fig. 2C</xref>), with more southerly provenances showing earlier budburst: by the time some southern provenance trees have open leaves (scores 4 and 5), northern provenances have yet to burst their buds (scores 0 and 1). We thus expect phenological mismatch with native oaks to correlate with differences in latitude between provenance origins and the trial site.</p></sec><sec><title>Herbivore abundance</title><p>We recorded approximately 725&#x000a0;000 galls of 20 gall types (seven sexual generation and 13 asexual generation) during the four survey seasons, representing 15 different gallwasp species (Table<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">2</xref>). No acorn galls were recorded. Total counts of individual gall types varied over five orders of magnitude, from just 4 (asexual generation <italic>Cynips longiventris</italic>) to over 330&#x000a0;000 (asexual generation <italic>Neuroterus anthracinus</italic>). Gall abundance differed significantly between years for all gall types except <italic>Andricus solitarius</italic>, with five types exhibiting &#x0003e;10-fold differences (Table<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl2">2</xref>) and without any consistent pattern between years or seasons. Six of the 20 gall types occurred on &#x0003c;1% of shoots in both survey years and were excluded from further analysis.</p><table-wrap id="tbl2" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Prevalence, incidence and between-year variation in the abundance of the 20 gall types recorded at La Petite Charnie. Columns show, for each survey year, the total number of each gall type, the mean number of galls per shoot and incidence &#x02013; the proportion of shoots bearing galls, and the ratio of mean galls per shoot between 2008 and 2009</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Gall type (species and generation)</th><th align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">2008</th><th align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">2009</th><th align="left" rowspan="2" colspan="1">Ratio of mean galls/shoot 2008:2009</th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total galls</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean galls/shoot</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Incidence</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total galls</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean galls/shoot</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Incidence</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" rowspan="1">Spring sexual generation surveys</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;<italic>Andricus inflator</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0022</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0018</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02013;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;<italic>Andricus testaceipes</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">973</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.041</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0025</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2291</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.095</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.067</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:2.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;<italic>Biorhiza pallid</italic>a</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00054</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00046</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00042</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00042</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.3:1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;<italic>Neuroterus albipes</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">822</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.034</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5828</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:8</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;<italic>Neuroterus anthracinus</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14&#x000a0;278</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7411</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.31</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.9:1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;<italic>Neuroterus numismalis</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1154</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.048</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.039</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17&#x000a0;486</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:15</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;<italic>Neuroterus quercusbaccarum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5808</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7834</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:1.4</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="8" rowspan="1">Autumn asexual generation surveys</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;<italic>Andricus callidoma</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00021</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00021</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0019</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0018</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:9</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;<italic>Andricus fecundatrix</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">334</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.017</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1103</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.046</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.029</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:2.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;<italic>Andricus glandulae</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0043</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0037</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">335</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.014</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.012</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:2.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;<italic>Andricus inflator</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">44</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0023</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.002</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00013</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00013</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19:1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;<italic>Andricus kollari</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0001</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0001</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0018</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0012</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:18</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;<italic>Andricus solitarius</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">528</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.028</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.026</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">726</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.028</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;<italic>Cynips divisa</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1901</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.099</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.057</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">184</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0077</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0057</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13:1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;<italic>Cynips longiventris</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000052</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.000052</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00013</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00013</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:2.5</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;<italic>Cynips quercusfolii</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">197</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.0085</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">456</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.019</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.013</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1:2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;<italic>N.&#x000a0;albipes</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45&#x000a0;771</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.38</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27&#x000a0;531</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.15</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.1:1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;<italic>N.&#x000a0;anthracinus</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">313&#x000a0;507</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.33</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23&#x000a0;820</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.99</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16:1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;<italic>N.&#x000a0;numismalis</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12&#x000a0;194</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.037</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12&#x000a0;124</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.028</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.2:1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02003;<italic>N.&#x000a0;quercusbaccarum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">123&#x000a0;708</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.44</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.56</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94&#x000a0;830</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.95</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.6:1</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Oak provenance effects on gall abundance</title><p>The percentage of variance in gall abundance per shoot explained by differences between provenances (expressed as the mean variance component, ranging between 0% and 100%) varied substantially between the statistical models used. In identity models of the 20 provenance dataset (which assume provenances to be fully independent statistically), the percentage of variance in gall abundance explained by provenance ranged from 3% (in sexual generation <italic>Neuroterus albipes</italic>) to 33% (in asexual generation <italic>Neuroterus quercusbaccarum</italic>) and was &#x0003e;10% for seven of the 14 gall types (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">Fig. 3</xref>). Because provenances are related, the identity model is unlikely to be appropriate. All models incorporating provenance covariance gave higher estimates of the variance component for provenance effects (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sd1">Data&#x000a0;S2</xref> for comparison of results across the alternative datasets and models). Incorporation of provenance covariance using the 1&#x02212;<italic>GeoF</italic><sub>ST</sub> covariance matrix for the same 20 provenance dataset attributes between 38% (sexual generation <italic>N.&#x000a0;albipes</italic> and 95% (asexual generation <italic>N.&#x000a0;quercusbaccarum</italic>) of variance in gall abundance to provenance effects (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig03">Fig. 3</xref>). The identity models should thus be viewed as providing artificially low estimates of the variation in gall abundance attributable to differences between provenances (Table&#x000a0;S2.2, Figure&#x000a0;S2.1 in Data&#x000a0;S2). On this basis, host tree provenance is an important predictor of the abundance of many gallers, explaining at least 10%, and as much as 95% of the variation in abundance of seven of the 14 gall types tested. Without more knowledge of the form of variance&#x02013;covariance relationship, it is not possible to give a correct estimate. Importantly for what follows, analysis of fixed effects was not influenced by our choice of variance&#x02013;covariance model.</p><fig id="fig03" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>The proportion of variation in gall abundance attributed to the effect of provenance for the 20-provenance dataset that either do not (black circles) account for population nonindependence (i.e., identity models) or incorporate a 1&#x02212;<italic>GeoF</italic><sub>ST</sub> variance&#x02013;covariance matrix (open circles). Vertical bars represent 95% confidence intervals for each mean.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="eva0008-0972-f3"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Tree phenotypic traits as predictors of variation in gall abundance</title><p>Significant relationships between gall abundance per shoot and at least one of the provenance phenotypic traits were identified for all but three of the 14 gall types tested (Table<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl3">3</xref>). The signs and strengths of relationships were stable across the various datasets and provenance co-variance structures (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sd2">Data&#x000a0;S2</xref> for full comparison of results), and here, we therefore focus on the results of the 1&#x02212;<italic>GeoF</italic><sub>ST</sub> co-variance matrix models for the 20-provenance dataset, identifying where they differ from the identity models for the same dataset (Table<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl3">3</xref>). The phenotypic variables <italic>Form, DBH</italic> and <italic>Budburst</italic> were not confounded, with low VIFs (1.05, 1.02 and 1.02, respectively). Because our analyses yielded only one significant interaction term (<italic>Budburst</italic>:<italic>Form</italic> for sexual generation galls of <italic>Neuroterus numismalis</italic>; mean coefficient&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.031, pMCMC&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.014), hereafter we consider each trait in isolation.</p><table-wrap id="tbl3" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Summary of GLMMs for tree phenotypic predictors, showing the significance and sign of those fixed effect coefficients that differed significantly from zero. Significance was assessed using pMCMC. Where the result of the identity models differed from the 1&#x02212;<italic>GeoF</italic><sub>ST</sub> models, the identity result follows the 1&#x02212;<italic>GeoF</italic><sub>ST</sub> result</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Gallwasp species (generation)</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Year</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Form</italic>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>DBH</italic>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Budburst</italic>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Budburst</italic>
<sup>2</sup>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Budburst: DBH</italic>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Budburst: Form</italic>
</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>Form: DBH</italic>
</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Andricus testaceipes</italic> (sex)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf3-5">***</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf3-4">**</xref>/+<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf3-3">*</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Neuroterus albipes</italic> (sex)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf3-5">***</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Neuroterus anthracinus</italic> (sex)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf3-5">***</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf3-3">*</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Neuroterus numismalis</italic> (sex)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf3-5">***</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf3-4">**</xref>/+<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf3-5">***</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf3-5">***</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf3-3">*</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf3-3">*</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Neuroterus quercusbaccarum</italic> (sex)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf3-5">***</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf3-5">***</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Andricus fecundatrix</italic> (asex)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf3-5">***</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf3-5">***</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf3-4">**</xref>/+<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf3-3">*</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Andricus glandulae</italic> (asex)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf3-5">***</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf3-3">*</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Andricus solitarius</italic> (asex)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cynips divisa</italic> (asex)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf3-5">***</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf3-3">*</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Cynips quercusfolii</italic> (asex)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf3-5">***</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf3-3">*</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>N.&#x000a0;albipes</italic> (asex)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf3-5">***</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf3-3">*</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>N.&#x000a0;anthracinus</italic> (asex)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf3-5">***</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>N.&#x000a0;numismalis</italic> (asex)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf3-5">***</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf3-3">*</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf3-5">***</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf3-3">*</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>N.&#x000a0;quercusbaccarum</italic> (asex)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf3-5">***</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf3-5">***</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf3-5">***</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="tf3-3">*</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NS</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="tf3-1"><p>DBH, diameter at breast height; MCMC, Markov Chain Monte Carlo.</p></fn><fn id="tf3-2"><p>Significance codes in the table are as follows:</p></fn><fn id="tf3-3"><label>*</label><p><italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05</p></fn><fn id="tf3-4"><label>**</label><p><italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.01</p></fn><fn id="tf3-5"><label>***</label><p><italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001, NS, <italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003e;&#x000a0;0.05, nonsignificant. Consideration of false-positive discovery rates for multiple testing following Benjamini and Hochberg (<xref rid="b8" ref-type="bibr">1995</xref>) and Benjamini and Yekutieli (<xref rid="b9" ref-type="bibr">2001</xref>) resulted in adjustment of <italic>P</italic>-values indicated as <sup>*</sup> to <italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003e;&#x000a0;0.05, while all other results indicated as <sup>**</sup> or <sup>***</sup> in the table below remain significant at <italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.05.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Tree health, as measured by <italic>Form</italic>, significantly predicted the abundance of only one gall type (asexual generation <italic>Cynips quercusfolii</italic>; Table<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig04">Fig. 4A</xref>) for which healthier trees supported more galls per shoot, as predicted by the plant vigour hypothesis. Tree vigour, as measured by <italic>DBH</italic>, was a better overall predictor of gall abundance per shoot, with significant relationships for five of the 14 gall types (two sexual and three asexual generations; Table<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig04">Fig. 4B</xref>). For the spring sexual generation galls (<italic>Andricus testaceipes</italic> and <italic>N.&#x000a0;numismalis</italic>), galls were more abundant on larger trees (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig04">Fig. 4B</xref>, as predicted by the plant vigour hypothesis). Relationships varied for the three autumn asexual generation gall types: <italic>N.&#x000a0;albipes</italic> were more abundant on larger trees (as predicted by the plant vigour hypothesis), while <italic>N.&#x000a0;numismalis</italic> and <italic>N.&#x000a0;quercusbaccarum</italic> showed the opposite pattern (as predicted by the plant stress hypothesis).</p><fig id="fig04" position="float"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Plots of significant relationships between gall abundance and (A) <italic>Form,</italic> (B) <italic>Diameter at breast height</italic> (<italic>DBH</italic>) and (C) <italic>Budburst</italic>. Higher <italic>Form</italic> scores indicate healthier trees, while higher <italic>Budburst</italic> scores indicate earlier budburst. Distributions of <italic>y</italic> at intervals across the range of a phenotypic predictor (<italic>x</italic>) were derived from the 1000 stored Markov Chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) samples as: <italic>y</italic><sub><italic>i</italic></sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;exp(intercept<sub><italic>i</italic></sub>&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;<italic>x</italic>(mean coefficient<sub><italic>i</italic></sub>)&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;0.5<italic>x</italic> &#x02211; random effect variances<sub><italic>i</italic></sub>). Plots show the means (bold lines) and 95% confidence intervals from these distributions for each of the two study years. Dotted vertical lines indicate the mean value of the phenotypic trait for the most local tree provenance (For&#x000ea;t de Berc&#x000e9;). Plots for models of the asexual generation galls of <italic>Neuroterus numismalis</italic> could not be produced in this way due to high random effect variances.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="eva0008-0972-f4"/></fig><p>Phenology, as measured by <italic>Budburst</italic>, was the best overall predictor of gall abundance/shoot, with significant correlations for eight gall types (Table<xref ref-type="table" rid="tbl3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig04">Fig. 4C</xref>). Four gall types showed significantly nonlinear relationships, incorporating a significant <italic>Budburst</italic> squared term. However, no gall type showed peak abundance at an intermediate phenological stage, as expected for the local adaptation hypothesis. Instead, spring sexual generation galls were generally most abundant on provenances showing the earliest budburst (high budburst score), while the summer/autumn asexual generation galls were most abundant on trees showing the latest budburst (low budburst score, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig04">Fig. 4C</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Predicting future change in ecosystem functioning requires an understanding of the community impacts of both global environmental change and any associated remediation strategies. Climate change impacts on foundation species are likely to influence the diversity, distribution and abundance of associated taxa &#x02013; whether these are beneficial ecosystem service providers or potential pests. The challenge for a given system is then to estimate likely consequences of both nonintervention and remediation; and where the impacts of remediation strategies take time to develop, to understand their trajectories through time. All of these aspects apply in particular to climate matching of long-lived foundation trees, which involves introduction of non-native genotypes that take decades to establish and live for centuries. Our analyses shed light on the likely consequences for native herbivores of introducing tree provenances that, although not initially climate-matched, become increasingly so as climate changes, while native provenances become increasingly mismatched and decline in performance. A key aspect of our study is its use of a provenance trial to quantify the consequences of host plant variation in performance and phenology on multiple species in the same guild, addressing a recognized need to quantify the impacts of environmental change at guild and community levels (e.g., Forkner et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b26" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Van Asch et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b82" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Ohlberger et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b57" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Petanidou et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b60" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>; Vatka et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b83" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>).</p><sec><title>Influences of oak provenance on the gallwasp guild, and incorporation of provenance covariance</title><p>Our results show that oak provenances vary significantly in phenotypic traits likely to influence associated herbivores and that this in turn is associated with significant variation in the population density (abundance per oak shoot) of multiple gallwasp species. We show that the form of these relationships is robust across models that assume very different patterns of variance&#x02013;covariance among oak provenances, from identity models assuming total independence to models that estimate covariance based on population genetic and provenance origin data. Our results indicate that models that treat provenances as statistically independent entities, which we know not to be true, consistently underestimate provenance effects on gall densities relative to models in which covariance is specified based on a measure of genetic differentiation (<italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> or <italic>GeoF</italic><sub>ST</sub>). If these models accurately describe provenance co-variance, then the influence of tree provenance on gall abundance is substantially greater (38&#x02013;95%) than would be inferred by assuming provenances to be statistically independent. While pairwise <italic>F</italic><sub>ST</sub> and related measures are consistently significantly larger than 0 (Tables&#x000a0;S2.1 and S2.3 in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sd2">Data&#x000a0;S2</xref>), their absolute values are small, providing little resolution of the relationship of genetic differentiation and geographic distance (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sd2">Data&#x000a0;S2</xref> for a comprehensive discussion). It is therefore difficult to estimate a &#x02018;true&#x02019; value for the impact of provenance and its explanatory power given the nonindependence of populations (Felsenstein <xref rid="b200" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>; Stone et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b76" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>).</p><p>The strong provenance effects we show are consistent with the growing body of community genetics work linking host plant genotypic variation to associated trophic levels (Wimp et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b92" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Bangert and Whitham <xref rid="b7" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>). A key challenge in this field is to understand the importance of host genetic effects for herbivore communities relative to other ecological factors (Hersch-Green et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b39" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). Working near the northern limit of pedunculate oak (<italic>Quercus robur</italic>) in Finland, Tack et&#x000a0;al. (<xref rid="b78" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>) found spatial effects to be more important than tree genotypic effects in structuring a community of herbivorous insects that included several gallwasps. In reciprocal transplant experiments at local and regional scales, Tack et&#x000a0;al. (<xref rid="b78" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>) found no effect of tree genotype for any of the three gall types in their study (asexual and sexual generations of <italic>N.&#x000a0;quercusbaccarum</italic> are shared with our study). The contrast between this and the strong host plant provenance effects present at the Petite Charnie trial is likely to reflect contrasting levels of adaptive genetic and phenotypic diversity of the oaks in each study. Although Finnish oak populations show substantial intraspecific genetic diversity (Vakkari et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b80" ref-type="bibr">2006</xref>), they show substantially less genetic diversity (and we expect also phenotypic diversity) than the much wider geographic array of provenances present at La Petite Charnie (Petit et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b61" ref-type="bibr">2002</xref>). Our provenance trial study involves a much greater array of genetic diversity than would be expected from a single natural population, a feature shared with the studies of genetically diverse hybrid populations (e.g., Dungey et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b22" ref-type="bibr">2000</xref>) that often show strong plant genotype effects on associated herbivores (Tack et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b78" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). Generally, the importance of host genetic effects relative to other factors is likely to correlate positively with the adaptive genetic diversity within a tree population present at a site, and we would expect this to be increased in&#x000a0;situations where climate matching or other forms of assisted migration are implemented.</p></sec><sec><title>Impacts of between-provenance variation in phenology</title><p>The strongest predictor of between-provenance variation in gallwasp density is variation in spring budburst phenology. Phenological changes have long been recognized as a major component of species responses to climate change that can cascade through associated trophic levels. This has been shown, for example, in work on the impact of changes in oak budburst phenology on abundance of associated leaf-feeding moths and breeding responses of insectivorous birds &#x02013; particularly <italic>Parus major</italic> (Van Asch and Visser <xref rid="b81" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Visser <xref rid="b84" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Van Asch et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b82" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Vatka et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b83" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). A key question in research on these systems has been the extent to which responses of herbivores, and their natural enemies are the result of phenotypic plasticity and local adaptation.</p><p>It is striking that although adaptation to individual trees has been demonstrated in oak&#x02013;gallwasp interactions (Egan and Ott <xref rid="b24" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>), none of our gall types showed declining abundance with increasing phenological mismatch between native oaks and planted provenances, rejecting our local adaptation hypothesis. We also found the responses of the spring and autumn generations in the gallwasp lifecycle can be very different. Spring galls were more abundant on early budbursting trees, while autumn generations of the same species (<italic>N.&#x000a0;numismalis</italic> and <italic>N.&#x000a0;quercusbaccarum</italic>) were more abundant on late budbursting trees. Similar relationships to those we observed were recorded for <italic>Neuroterus</italic> gallwasps in response to local phenological variation in native UK <italic>Q.&#x000a0;robur</italic> populations by Askew (<xref rid="b5" ref-type="bibr">1962</xref>, <xref rid="b6" ref-type="bibr">1984</xref>) and Crawley and Akhteruzzaman (<xref rid="b18" ref-type="bibr">1988</xref>); our results show that the same trends can be extended to the wider phenological variation present in a provenance trial. We hypothesize that this contrast between the spring and autumn generations may exist because later budbursting trees may have higher abundance of phenologically young tissues suitable for gall induction. Annual gallwasp phenology may thus be the result of contrasting selection on the two lifecycle generations, perhaps limiting local phenological adaptation in either generation (Singer and Parmesan <xref rid="b69" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). The dynamics of such complex lifecycles are poorly understood, and complex bottom-up impacts may apply to other groups with multivoltine or more complex lifecycles, particularly where these involve alternation between generations and/or plant hosts (including many aphids; Harrington et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b36" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>).</p></sec><sec><title>Impacts of between-provenance variation in tree vigour</title><p>Tree vigour also explained significant between-provenance variation in oak gall density. In contrast, tree shape &#x02013; commonly used as an indicator of physiological stress &#x02013; had little impact. As with phenology, the sign of correlations between gall density and tree vigour varied among gall generations and taxa. Significant correlations with tree vigour were positive for spring sexual generation gall types, while two of three were negative for asexual generation gall types. Support was thus evenly split between the plant vigour hypothesis (Price <xref rid="b62" ref-type="bibr">1991</xref>; Cornelissen et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b17" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>) and the plant stress hypothesis (White <xref rid="b87" ref-type="bibr">1969</xref>, <xref rid="b88" ref-type="bibr">1974</xref>, <xref rid="b89" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>). One possibility is that the apparent contrast in patterns for spring and autumn generation galls could be driven by the long-known seasonal shift in oak resource investment from growth in the spring to metabolic defence in the summer (Feeny <xref rid="b25" ref-type="bibr">1970</xref>). Highly vigorous trees could then be both best for spring generation galls and worst (=best defended) for autumn generation galls. Mechanisms of oak defence against gallwasps remain poorly understood.</p></sec><sec><title>Predicting the impact of climate-matched planting on associated herbivores</title><p>Climate matching necessarily requires introduction of phenotypically divergent tree populations. In Europe, climate models predict warmer summers and winters (Giorgi and Coppola <xref rid="b29" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>; Jenkins et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b43" ref-type="bibr">2009</xref>), and climate matching will thus always involve introducing more southerly provenances that show earlier budburst (Ducousso et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b21" ref-type="bibr">1996</xref>; Broadmeadow et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b14" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>). Under low and high emissions scenarios for 2050, Broadmeadow et&#x000a0;al. (<xref rid="b14" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>) identified climate-matched sites for five UK locations that were 0&#x02013;2&#x000b0; and 5&#x02013;12&#x000b0; further south, respectively (Broadmeadow et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b14" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>). Our results (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02">Fig. 2C</xref>) suggest that while the small latitudinal shifts required under a low emission scenario would probably have little impact on oak phenology, the shifts of &#x0003e;10&#x000b0; of latitude required under a high emission scenario could lead to major phenological differences between native and climate-matched trees, and significantly dissimilar gallwasp assemblages.</p><p>The widespread existence of latitude-dependent photoperiod cues in plant phenology (Aitken et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b1" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>) suggests that the phenological contrasts between climate-matched and native oak populations will be shared by other plant species. The extent to which any such differences influence associated herbivores is likely to vary according to specific plant&#x02013;herbivore interactions, reflecting available herbivore phenotypic plasticity and adaptive genetic diversity. We hypothesized that impacts of phenological mismatch will be greatest for interactions in which herbivore fitness is strongly correlated with successful exploitation of a narrow phenological &#x02018;window of opportunity&#x02019; (Durant et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b23" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Van Asch and Visser <xref rid="b81" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Forkner et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b26" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Netherer and Schopf <xref rid="b56" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). This includes many insects that feed on newly flushed leaves (Van Asch and Visser <xref rid="b81" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Forkner et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b26" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>). However, we found no evidence of such a window for gallwasps: while they prefer to oviposit (or survive better on) young tissues, they show no strong preference for host trees at a single phenological stage. As discussed above, impacts on herbivores with multivoltine or multihost lifecycles may be complex.</p><p>The relationships we found between host plant vigour and herbivore abundance are relevant to two stages in a climate matching strategy: the expected poor performance under current climates of introduced provenances matched to predicted future conditions, and the expected decline in the performance of native provenances as climates move away from any locally adapted range. The slope of the relationship between environmental variables and vigour for a specific provenance will dictate not only the impact on associated trophic levels, but also whether climate matching with that provenance is feasible at all. The challenge for forest managers is to identify a climate-matched provenance that is able to survive as a sapling and young tree before the conditions justifying its selection have been reached and become established before native provenances fail. Climate matching is a recently developed strategy and its success at maintaining forest productivity is untested (Broadmeadow et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b14" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>). Current guidelines in UK forestry advocate mixed planting of both matched and local provenances, which increases local resource heterogeneity for herbivores (Hubert and Cottrell <xref rid="b41" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>), and creates conditions that accelerate both environmental selection on host trees (Lefevre et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b47" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>) and host plant-mediated selection on associated organisms.</p><p>Assisted migration is increasingly seen as a viable strategy for commercial and conservation settings (Broadmeadow et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b14" ref-type="bibr">2005</xref>; Stone <xref rid="b73" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Dawson et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b20" ref-type="bibr">2011</xref>). Issues cited as slowing down the implementation of climate matching as an adaptive forestry strategy include lack of operating procedures, uncertainties over which climate models to use in matching algorithms and risks associated with moving plants outside their current ranges (Williams and Dumroese <xref rid="b91" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>). Theoretical studies nevertheless suggest that such adaptive-, rather than resilience-targeted strategies may be the best way to safeguard forest systems (Buma and Wessman <xref rid="b15" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>; Lefevre et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b47" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). We would add that the community impacts of assisted migration need to be carefully considered, particularly so for foundation species such as forest trees. This requires better understanding of the relative contributions of host plant genotype and other ecological factors to the tree phenotypes exposed to herbivores (Tack et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b78" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). Geographical patterns of local adaptation and tree phenotypic variation have only been mapped in a tiny minority of species (Savolainen et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b66" ref-type="bibr">2007</xref>; Robakowski et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b65" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Sork et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b71" ref-type="bibr">2013</xref>), and studies that target multiple provenance trial locations are required to separate genetic and environmental contributions to provenance phenotypes (Tack et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b78" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>). While our study was based on a single trial, the oak phenotypic traits we analysed have been shown to be highly heritable in the sampled provenances (Sinclair <xref rid="b900" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>), so we expect the provenance effects we found to contain a significant genetic component. Given strong environmental effects on plant traits including phenology, repetition of the work in an array of trials spanning different environments is clearly desirable. Understanding herbivore numerical and adaptive responses then in turn requires understanding the impacts of both plant phenotypes and other ecological processes, including the mortality inflicted on herbivores by their natural enemies (Bidart-Bouzat and Imeh-Nathaniel <xref rid="b11" ref-type="bibr">2008</xref>; Thomson et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b79" ref-type="bibr">2010</xref>; Van Asch et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b82" ref-type="bibr">2012</xref>; Rasmann et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="b63" ref-type="bibr">2014</xref>). Much more needs to be done before forest managers can take informed decisions concerning likely impacts of climate matching on forest-associated biodiversity.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>This research comprises work under the CLIMAFO NERC-funded research project &#x02018;Climate change and management of forest biodiversity: predicting the impacts of climate matching strategies on plant&#x02013;herbivore&#x02013;enemy interactions&#x02019; (NE/H000038/1). We thank Jarrod Hadfield for statistical advice, Ally Phillimore, Tom Oliver and Christine Tansey for feedback on drafts of the manuscript, and Kat Bradley, Julja Ernst, Matt Wainhouse, Stefan Curtis and Katherine Rushton for invaluable help in the field. We thank Axios Review for their role in the development of this manuscript.</p></ack><sec><title>Data archiving statement</title><p>Data for this study are available for download from the NERC Environmental Information Data Centre: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.org/10/647">http://doi.org/10/647</ext-link>.</p></sec><ref-list><title>Literature cited</title><ref id="b1"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aitken</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Yeaman</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Holliday</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Curtis-Mclane</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adaptation, migration or extirpation: climate change outcomes for tree populations</article-title><source>Evolutionary Applications</source><year>2008</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>111</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25567494</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b2"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alberto</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouffier</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Louvet</surname><given-names>J-M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamy</surname><given-names>J-B</given-names></name><name><surname>Delzon</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kremer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adaptive responses for seed and leaf phenology in natural populations of sessile oak along an altitudinal gradient</article-title><source>Journal of Evolutionary Biology</source><year>2011</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>1442</fpage><lpage>1454</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21507119</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b3"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alberto</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Aitken</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Alia</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez-Mart&#x000ed;nez</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#x000e4;nninen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kremer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lef&#x000e8;vre</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Potential for evolutionary responses to climate change evidence from tree populations</article-title><source>Global Change Biology</source><year>2013a</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1645</fpage><lpage>1661</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23505261</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b4"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Alberto</surname><given-names>FJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Derory</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Boury</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Frigerio</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Zimmermann</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kremer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Imprints of natural selection along environmental gradients in phenology-related genes of <italic>Quercus petraea</italic></article-title><source>Genetics</source><year>2013b</year><volume>195</volume><fpage>495</fpage><lpage>512</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23934884</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b5"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Askew</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The distribution of galls of <italic>Neuroterus</italic> (Hym: Cynipidae) on oak</article-title><source>The Journal of Animal Ecology</source><year>1962</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>439</fpage><lpage>455</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b6"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Askew</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Anathakrishnan</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The biology of gallwasps</article-title><source>The Biology of Galling Insects</source><year>1984</year><publisher-loc>New Delhi</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Oxford and IBH Publishing Co</publisher-name><fpage>223</fpage><lpage>271</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bangert</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whitham</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic assembly rules and community phenotypes</article-title><source>Evolutionary Ecology</source><year>2007</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>549</fpage><lpage>560</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b8"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benjamini</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hochberg</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Controlling the false discovery rate: a practical and powerful approach to multiple testing</article-title><source>Journal of the Royal Statistical Society Series B</source><year>1995</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>289</fpage><lpage>300</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b9"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Benjamini</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yekutieli</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The control of the false discovery rate in multiple testing under dependency</article-title><source>Annals of Statistics</source><year>2001</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>1165</fpage><lpage>1188</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b10"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bernhardsson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name><name><surname>Abreu</surname><given-names>IN</given-names></name><name><surname>Jansson</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Albrectsen</surname><given-names>BR</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ingvarsson</surname><given-names>PK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Geographic structure in metabolome and herbivore community co-occurs with genetic structure in plant defence genes</article-title><source>Ecology Letters</source><year>2013</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>791</fpage><lpage>798</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23601188</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b11"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bidart-Bouzat</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Imeh-Nathaniel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Global change effects on plant chemical defenses against insect herbivores</article-title><source>Journal of Integrative Plant Biology</source><year>2008</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>1339</fpage><lpage>1354</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19017122</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b12"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bolte</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ammer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x000f6;f</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Madsend</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Nabuurse</surname><given-names>G-J</given-names></name><name><surname>Schallb</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Spathelff</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Adaptive forest management in central Europe: climate change impacts, strategies and integrative concept</article-title><source>Scandinavian Journal of Forest Research</source><year>2009</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>473</fpage><lpage>482</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b13"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bower</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Aitken</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ecological genetics and seed transfer guidelines for <italic>Pinus albicaulis</italic> (Pinaceae)</article-title><source>American Journal of Botany</source><year>2008</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>66</fpage><lpage>76</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21632316</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b14"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Broadmeadow</surname><given-names>MSJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Samuel</surname><given-names>CJA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Climate change and the future for broadleaved tree species in Britain</article-title><source>Forestry</source><year>2005</year><volume>78</volume><fpage>145</fpage><lpage>161</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b15"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Buma</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wessman</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Forest resilience, climate change, and opportunities for adaptation: a specific case of a general problem</article-title><source>Forest Ecology and Management</source><year>2013</year><volume>306</volume><fpage>216</fpage><lpage>225</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b16"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cavers</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cottrell</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The basis of resilience in forest tree species and its use in adaptive forest management in Britain</article-title><source>Forestry</source><year>2014</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>26</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b17"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cornelissen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fernandes</surname><given-names>GW</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vasconcellos-Neto</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Size does matter: variation in herbivory between and within plants and the plant vigor hypothesis</article-title><source>Oikos</source><year>2008</year><volume>117</volume><fpage>1121</fpage><lpage>1130</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b18"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Crawley</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Akhteruzzaman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Individual variation in the phenology of oak trees and its consequences for herbivorous insects</article-title><source>Functional Ecology</source><year>1988</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>409</fpage><lpage>415</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b19"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cs&#x000f3;ka</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Withers</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Melika</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Raman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Schaefer</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biology, ecology and evolution of gall-inducing cynipidae</article-title><source>Biology, Ecology and Evolution of Gall-Inducing Arthropods</source><year>2005</year><publisher-loc>Enfield, NH</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Science Publishers</publisher-name><fpage>573</fpage><lpage>642</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b20"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dawson</surname><given-names>TP</given-names></name><name><surname>Jackson</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name><surname>House</surname><given-names>JI</given-names></name><name><surname>Prentice</surname><given-names>IC</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mace</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Beyond predictions: biodiversity conservation in a changing climate</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2011</year><volume>332</volume><fpage>53</fpage><lpage>58</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21454781</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b21"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ducousso</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Guyon</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kremer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Latitudinal and altitudinal variation of budburst in western populations of sessile oak (<italic>Quercus petraea</italic> (Matt) Liebl)</article-title><source>Annales Des Sciences Foresti&#x000e8;res</source><year>1996</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>775</fpage><lpage>782</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b22"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dungey</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Potts</surname><given-names>BM</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitham</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant genetics affects arthropod community richness and composition: evidence from a synthetic eucalypt hybrid population</article-title><source>Evolution</source><year>2000</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>1938</fpage><lpage>1946</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11209771</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b23"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Durant</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hjermann</surname><given-names>DO</given-names></name><name><surname>Ottersen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stenseth</surname><given-names>NC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Climate and the match or mismatch between predator requirements and resource availability</article-title><source>Climate Research</source><year>2007</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>271</fpage><lpage>283</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b24"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Egan</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ott</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Host plant quality and local adaptation determine the distribution of a gall-forming herbivore</article-title><source>Ecology</source><year>2007</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>2868</fpage><lpage>2879</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18051656</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b25"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Feeny</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Seasonal changes in oak leaf tannins and nutrients as a cause of spring feeding by winter moth caterpillars</article-title><source>Ecology</source><year>1970</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>565</fpage><lpage>581</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b200"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Felsenstein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Veuille</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Slatkin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Contrasts for a within-species comparative method</article-title><source>Modern Developments in Theoretical Population Genetics</source><year>2002</year><publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name><fpage>118</fpage><lpage>129</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b26"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Forkner</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Marquis</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lill</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Le Corff</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Timing is everything? Phenological synchrony and population variability in leaf-chewing herbivores of <italic>Quercus</italic></article-title><source>Ecological Entomology</source><year>2008</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>276</fpage><lpage>285</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b27"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frelich</surname><given-names>LE</given-names></name><name><surname>Peterson</surname><given-names>RO</given-names></name><name><surname>Dovciak</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Reich</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name><surname>Vucetich</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eisenhauer</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trophic cascades, invasive species and body-size hierarchies interactively modulate climate change responses of ecotonal temperate-boreal forest</article-title><source>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London. Series B, Biological sciences</source><year>2012</year><volume>367</volume><fpage>2955</fpage><lpage>2961</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23007083</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b28"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gelman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Prior distributions for variance parameters in hierarchical models (comment on an Article by Browne and Draper)</article-title><source>Bayesian Analysis</source><year>2006</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>515</fpage><lpage>533</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b29"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giorgi</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Coppola</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Projections of twenty-first century climate over Europe</article-title><source>Erca: From the Human Dimensions of Global Environmental Change to the Observation of the Earth from Space</source><year>2009</year><volume>1</volume><fpage>29</fpage><lpage>46</lpage><comment>Vol. 8,</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="b30"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goudet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>FSTAT (Version 1.2): a computer program to calculate F-statistics</article-title><source>Journal of Heredity</source><year>1995</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>485</fpage><lpage>486</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b31"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guichoux</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lagache</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Leger</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petit</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Two highly validated multiplexes (12-plex and 8-plex) for species delimitation and parentage analysis in oaks (<italic>Quercus</italic> spp.)</article-title><source>Molecular Ecology Resources</source><year>2011</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>578</fpage><lpage>585</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21481218</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b32"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hadfield</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>MCMC methods for multi-response generalized linear mixed models: the MCMCglmm R package</article-title><source>Journal of Statistical Software</source><year>2010</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>22</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20808728</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b33"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hadfield</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakagawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>General quantitative genetic methods for comparative biology: phylogenies, taxonomies and multi-trait models for continuous and categorical characters</article-title><source>Journal of Evolutionary Biology</source><year>2010</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>494</fpage><lpage>508</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20070460</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b34"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hanks</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Denno</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Local adaptation in the armored scale insect <italic>Pseudaulacaspis-pentagona</italic> (Homoptera, Diaspididae)</article-title><source>Ecology</source><year>1994</year><volume>75</volume><fpage>2301</fpage><lpage>2310</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b35"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harper</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sch&#x000f6;nrogge</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Lim</surname><given-names>KY</given-names></name><name><surname>Francis</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lichtenstein</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cynipid galls: insect-induced modifications of plant development create novel plant organs</article-title><source>Plant Cell and Environment</source><year>2004</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>327</fpage><lpage>335</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b36"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harrington</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Welham</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Verrier</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Denholm</surname><given-names>CH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hulle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Maurice</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Environmental change and the phenology of European aphids</article-title><source>Global Change Biology</source><year>2007</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>1550</fpage><lpage>1564</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b37"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hearn</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><name><surname>Bunnefeld</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicholls</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Barton</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lohse</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Likelihood-based inference of population history from low-coverage de novo genome assemblies</article-title><source>Molecular Ecology</source><year>2014</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>198</fpage><lpage>211</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24188568</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b38"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heiberger</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><source>HH: Statistical Analysis and Data Display: Heiberger and Holland</source><year>2013</year><publisher-name>R Foundation for Statistical Computing</publisher-name><comment>R package version 2.3-36.</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="b39"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hersch-Green</surname><given-names>EI</given-names></name><name><surname>Turley</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Community genetics: what have we accomplished and where should we be going?</article-title><source>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London. Series B, Biological sciences</source><year>2011</year><volume>366</volume><fpage>1453</fpage><lpage>1460</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21444318</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b40"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoegh-Guldberg</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Mcintyre</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindenmayer</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Parmesan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Possingham</surname><given-names>HP</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Assisted colonization and rapid climate change</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2008</year><volume>321</volume><fpage>345</fpage><lpage>346</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18635780</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b41"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hubert</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cottrell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><source>The Role of Forest Genetic Resources in Helping British Forests to Respond to Climate Change</source><year>2007</year><publisher-loc>Edinburgh</publisher-loc><publisher-name>The Forestry Commission</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="b42"><element-citation publication-type="book"><collab>IPCC</collab><source>Climate Change 2013. The Physical Science Basis. Working Group I Contribution to the Fifth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change</source><year>2013</year><publisher-loc>New York, NY</publisher-loc><publisher-name>IPCC</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="b43"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jenkins</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Murphy</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sexton</surname><given-names>DMH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lowe</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kilsby</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name></person-group><source>UK Climate Projections: Briefing Report</source><year>2009</year><publisher-loc>Exeter</publisher-loc><publisher-name>U.K. Met Office Hadley Centre</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="b44"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kennedy</surname><given-names>CEJ</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Southwood</surname><given-names>TRE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The number of species of insects associated with British trees &#x02013; a re-analysis</article-title><source>Journal of Animal Ecology</source><year>1984</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>455</fpage><lpage>478</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b45"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kerstes</surname><given-names>NAG</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>De Jong</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detection of refuge from enemies through phenological mismatching in multitrophic interactions requires season-wide estimation of host abundance</article-title><source>Evolutionary Ecology</source><year>2011</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>485</fpage><lpage>498</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b46"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laube</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sparks</surname><given-names>TH</given-names></name><name><surname>Estrella</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hofler</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ankerst</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Menzel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chilling outweighs photoperiod in preventing precocious spring development</article-title><source>Global Change Biology</source><year>2014</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>170</fpage><lpage>182</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24323535</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b47"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lefevre</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Boivin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Bontemps</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Courbet</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Davi</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Durand-Gillmann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Fady</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Considering evolutionary processes in adaptive forestry</article-title><source>Annals of Forest Science</source><year>2014</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>723</fpage><lpage>739</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b48"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lindenmayer</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name><name><surname>Banks</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Laurance</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name><name><surname>Franklin</surname><given-names>JF</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Likens</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Broad decline of populations of large old trees</article-title><source>Conservation Letters</source><year>2014</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>72</fpage><lpage>73</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b49"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lindner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Maroschek</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Netherer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kremer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Barbati</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Garcia-Gonzalo</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Seidl</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Climate change impacts, adaptive capacity, and vulnerability of European forest ecosystems</article-title><source>Forest Ecology and Management</source><year>2010</year><volume>259</volume><fpage>698</fpage><lpage>709</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b50"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lunt</surname><given-names>ID</given-names></name><name><surname>Byrne</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Hellmann</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Garnette</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name><surname>Hayward</surname><given-names>M&#x000a0;W</given-names></name><name><surname>Marting</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Using assisted colonisation to conserve biodiversity and restore ecosystem function under climate change</article-title><source>Biological Conservation</source><year>2013</year><volume>157</volume><fpage>172</fpage><lpage>177</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b201"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matheron</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Principles of geostatistics</article-title><source>Economic Geology</source><year>1963</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>1246</fpage><lpage>1266</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b51"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McEwan</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Dyer</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pederson</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiple interacting ecosystem drivers: toward an encompassing hypothesis of oak forest dynamics across eastern North America</article-title><source>Ecography</source><year>2011</year><volume>34</volume><fpage>244</fpage><lpage>256</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b52"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mopper</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phenology &#x02013; how time creates spatial structure in endophagous insect populations</article-title><source>Annales Zoologici Fennici</source><year>2005</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>327</fpage><lpage>333</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b53"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mopper</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Stiling</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Landau</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Simberloff</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Zandt</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spatiotemporal variation in leafminer population structure and adaptation to individual oak trees</article-title><source>Ecology</source><year>2000</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>1577</fpage><lpage>1587</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b54"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakagawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A farewell to Bonferroni: the problems of low statistical power and publication bias</article-title><source>Behavioral Ecology</source><year>2004</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>1044</fpage><lpage>1045</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b55"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nakagawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schielzeth</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A general and simple method for obtaining R<sup>2</sup> from generalized linear mixed-effects models</article-title><source>Methods in Ecology and Evolution</source><year>2013</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>142</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b56"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Netherer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schopf</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Potential effects of climate change on insect herbivores in European forests-general aspects and the pine processionary moth as specific example</article-title><source>Forest Ecology and Management</source><year>2010</year><volume>259</volume><fpage>831</fpage><lpage>838</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b57"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ohlberger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Thackeray</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Winfield</surname><given-names>IJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Maberly</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vollestad</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>When phenology matters: age-size truncation alters population response to trophic mismatch</article-title><source>Proceedings of the Royal Society B-Biological Sciences</source><year>2014</year><volume>281</volume><fpage>20140938</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b58"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parmesan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yohe</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A globally coherent fingerprint of climate change impacts across natural systems</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2003</year><volume>421</volume><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>42</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12511946</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b59"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pearse</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Karban</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Leaf drop affects herbivory in oaks</article-title><source>Oecologia</source><year>2013</year><volume>173</volume><fpage>925</fpage><lpage>932</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23774946</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b60"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petanidou</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kallimanis</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Sgardelis</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Mazaris</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Pantis</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Waser</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Variable flowering phenology and pollinator use in a community suggest future phenological mismatch</article-title><source>Acta Oecologica</source><year>2014</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>104</fpage><lpage>111</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b61"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Petit</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Csaikl</surname><given-names>UM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bordacs</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Burg</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Coart</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Cottrell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>van Dam</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Chloroplast DNA variation in European white oaks &#x02013; phylogeography and patterns of diversity based on data from over 2600 populations</article-title><source>Forest Ecology and Management</source><year>2002</year><volume>156</volume><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>26</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b62"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The plant vigor hypothesis and herbivore attack</article-title><source>Oikos</source><year>1991</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>244</fpage><lpage>251</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b63"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rasmann</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pellissier</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Defossez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Jactel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kunstler</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Climate-driven change in plant&#x02013;insect interactions along elevation gradients</article-title><source>Functional Ecology</source><year>2014</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>46</fpage><lpage>54</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b64"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Redfern</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shirley</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><source>British Plant Galls: Identification of Galls on Plants and Fungi</source><year>2002</year><publisher-loc>UK</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Field Studies Council, Preston Montford</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="b65"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Robakowski</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Reich</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Local ecotypic and species range-related adaptation influence photosynthetic temperature optima in deciduous broadleaved trees</article-title><source>Plant Ecology</source><year>2012</year><volume>213</volume><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>125</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b66"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Savolainen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Pyh&#x000e4;j&#x000e4;rvi</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kn&#x000fc;rr</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Gene flow and local adaptation in trees</article-title><source>Annual Review of Ecology Evolution and Systematics</source><year>2007</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>595</fpage><lpage>619</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b67"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Savolainen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Lascoux</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Merila</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ecological genomics of local adaptation</article-title><source>Nature Reviews Genetics</source><year>2013</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>807</fpage><lpage>820</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b68"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sch&#x000f6;nrogge</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Harper</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lichtenstein</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The protein content of tissues in cynipid galls (Hymenoptera: Cynipidae): similarities between cynipid galls and seeds</article-title><source>Plant Cell and Environment</source><year>2000</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>215</fpage><lpage>222</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b900"><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sinclair</surname><given-names>FH</given-names></name></person-group><source>Community Level Consequences of Adaptive Management Through Climate Matching: Oak Galls as a Model System</source><year>2012</year><publisher-name>University of Edinburgh</publisher-name><comment>Unpublished PhD thesis,</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="b69"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Singer</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parmesan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phenological asynchrony between herbivorous insects and their hosts: signal of climate change or pre-existing adaptive strategy?</article-title><source>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London B: Biological Sciences</source><year>2010</year><volume>365</volume><fpage>3161</fpage><lpage>3176</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20819810</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b70"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sork</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name><name><surname>Stowe</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hochwender</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evidence for local adaptation in closely adjacent subpopulations of Northern Red Oak (<italic>Quercus rubra</italic> L) expressed as resistance to leaf herbivores</article-title><source>The American Naturalist</source><year>1993</year><volume>142</volume><fpage>928</fpage><lpage>936</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b71"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sork</surname><given-names>VL</given-names></name><name><surname>Aitken</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Dyer</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Eckert</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Legendre</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neale</surname><given-names>DB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Putting the landscape into the genomics of trees: approaches for understanding local adaptation and population responses to changing climate</article-title><source>Tree Genetics and Genomes</source><year>2013</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>901</fpage><lpage>911</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b72"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spittlehouse</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adaptation to climate change&#x000a0;in forest management</article-title><source>Journal of Ecosystems and Management</source><year>2003</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>11</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b73"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Home, home outside the range?</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2010</year><volume>329</volume><fpage>1592</fpage><lpage>1594</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20929823</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b74"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sch&#x000f6;nrogge</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The adaptive significance of insect gall morphology</article-title><source>Trends in Ecology and Evolution</source><year>2003</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>512</fpage><lpage>522</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b75"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><name><surname>Sch&#x000f6;nrogge</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Atkinson</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bellido</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pujade-Villar</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The population biology of oak gallwasps (Hymenoptera: Cynipidae)</article-title><source>Annual Review of Entomology</source><year>2002</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>633</fpage><lpage>668</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b76"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name><name><surname>Nee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Felsenstein</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Controlling for non-independence in comparative analysis of patterns across populations within species</article-title><source>Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London B: Biological Sciences</source><year>2011</year><volume>366</volume><fpage>1410</fpage><lpage>1424</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21444315</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b77"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tack</surname><given-names>AJM</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roslin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Overrun by the neighbors: landscape context affects strength and sign of local adaptation</article-title><source>Ecology</source><year>2010</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>2253</fpage><lpage>2260</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20836447</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b78"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tack</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Ovaskainen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Pulkkinen</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Roslin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Spatial location dominates over host plant genotype in structuring an herbivore community</article-title><source>Ecology</source><year>2010</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>2660</fpage><lpage>2672</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20957960</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b79"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Macfadyen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Predicting the effects of climate change on natural enemies of agricultural pests</article-title><source>Biological Control</source><year>2010</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>296</fpage><lpage>306</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b80"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vakkari</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Blom</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rusanen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Raisio</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Toivonen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genetic variability of fragmented stands of pedunculate oak (<italic>Quercus robur</italic>) in Finland</article-title><source>Genetica</source><year>2006</year><volume>127</volume><fpage>231</fpage><lpage>241</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16850227</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b81"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Asch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Visser</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Phenology of forest caterpillars and their host trees: the importance of synchrony</article-title><source>Annual Review of Entomology</source><year>2007</year><volume>52</volume><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>55</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b82"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Asch</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Salis</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Holleman</surname><given-names>LJM</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Lith</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Visser</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evolutionary response of the egg hatching date of a herbivorous insect under climate change</article-title><source>Nature Climate Change</source><year>2012</year><volume>484</volume><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>61</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b83"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vatka</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Rytkonen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Orell</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Does the temporal mismatch hypothesis match in boreal populations?</article-title><source>Oecologia</source><year>2014</year><volume>176</volume><fpage>595</fpage><lpage>605</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25024104</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b84"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Visser</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Keeping up with a warming world; assessing the rate of adaptation to climate change</article-title><source>Proceedings of the Royal Society of London B: Biological Sciences</source><year>2008</year><volume>275</volume><fpage>649</fpage><lpage>659</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b85"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walther</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Post</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Convey</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Menzel</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Parmesan</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Beebee</surname><given-names>TJC</given-names></name><name><surname>Fromentin</surname><given-names>J-M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Ecological responses to recent climate change</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2002</year><volume>416</volume><fpage>389</fpage><lpage>395</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11919621</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b86"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weir</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cockerham</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Estimating F-statistics for the analysis of population-structure</article-title><source>Evolution</source><year>1984</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>1358</fpage><lpage>1370</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b87"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>TCR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>An index to measure weather-induced stress of trees associated with outbreaks of psyllids in Australia</article-title><source>Ecology</source><year>1969</year><volume>50</volume><fpage>905</fpage><lpage>909</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b88"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>TCR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Hypothesis to Explain outbreaks of looper caterpillars, with special reference to populations of <italic>Selidosema</italic><italic>suavis</italic> in a Plantation of <italic>Pinus-radiata</italic> in New-Zealand</article-title><source>Oecologia</source><year>1974</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>279</fpage><lpage>301</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b89"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>TCR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant vigour versus plant stress: a false dichotomy</article-title><source>Oikos</source><year>2009</year><volume>118</volume><fpage>807</fpage><lpage>808</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b90"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whitham</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name><name><surname>Gehring</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lamit</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Wojtowicz</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Keith</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Community specificity: life and afterlife effects of genes</article-title><source>Trends in Plant Science</source><year>2012</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>271</fpage><lpage>281</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22322002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b91"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dumroese</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Preparing for climate change: forestry and assisted migration</article-title><source>Journal of Forestry</source><year>2013</year><volume>111</volume><fpage>287</fpage><lpage>297</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="b92"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wimp</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinsen</surname><given-names>GD</given-names></name><name><surname>Floate</surname><given-names>KD</given-names></name><name><surname>Bangert</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whitham</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Plant genetic determinants of arthropod community structure and diversity</article-title><source>Evolution</source><year>2005</year><volume>59</volume><fpage>61</fpage><lpage>69</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15792227</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="b93"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yukawa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synchronization of gallers with host plant phenology</article-title><source>Population Ecology</source><year>2000</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>105</fpage><lpage>113</lpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supporting Information</title><p>Additional Supporting Information may be found in the online version of this article:</p><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sd1"><p><bold>Data S1.</bold> Petite Charnie provenance trials.</p><media mimetype="docx" mime-subtype="docx" xlink:href="eva0008-0972-sd1.docx" xlink:type="simple" id="d36e6036" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sd2"><p><bold>Data S2.</bold> Investigating the issue of non-independence of provenances.</p><media mimetype="doc" mime-subtype="doc" xlink:href="eva0008-0972-sd2.doc" xlink:type="simple" id="d36e6042" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sd3"><p><bold>Data S3.</bold> Calculating marginal <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> of a MCMCglmm model.</p><media mimetype="docx" mime-subtype="docx" xlink:href="eva0008-0972-sd3.docx" xlink:type="simple" id="d36e6053" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sd4"><p><bold>Data S4.</bold> Consistency of spring bud-burst phenology between years.</p><media mimetype="docx" mime-subtype="docx" xlink:href="eva0008-0972-sd4.docx" xlink:type="simple" id="d36e6059" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sd5"><p><bold>Data S5.</bold> An exemplar .csv data frame for use with Data S3.</p><media mimetype="csv" mime-subtype="csv" xlink:href="eva0008-0972-sd5.csv" xlink:type="simple" id="d36e6065" position="anchor"/></supplementary-material></sec></back></article>