<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Regarding gene expression, to date, only heat shock experiments had been conducted on these species [
 <xref rid="pone.0181325.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0181325.ref020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. In this study, we provide new clues as how these two species can acclimate to projected climate change by simulating the effects of increasing temperature and water acidity, both separately and combined. In general, the combination of both effects resulted in higher impacts on gene expression compared with the control condition. Although the resulting altered gene expression could be considered an additive effect of both conditions, for some genes, such as 
 <italic class="italic">stip1</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">gbp1</italic> in the liver tissue of both species, the changes in expression were synergistic, since they were not observed in the independent temperature or pH experiments. Pimentel 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. (2015) observed cumulative changes in enzymatic activity under similar conditions (warming and acidification) in the flatfish 
 <italic class="italic">Solea senegalensis</italic> [
 <xref rid="pone.0181325.ref063" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">63</xref>]. Despite this, to date, many studies have focused on single stressors (e.g. either temperature or pH) [
 <xref rid="pone.0181325.ref008" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0181325.ref010" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0181325.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0181325.ref020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. Thus, our results emphasize the necessity to consider the combined effects of these stressors when assessing the impacts of climate change scenarios on organisms, since changes are neither the simple sum of these stressors nor can they be easily predicted by considering the effects of the two factors separately.
</p>
