<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The sediment substance in water bodies is of great importance for the aquatic ecosystem [
 <xref rid="B1-ijerph-16-04054" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-ijerph-16-04054" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Soil erosion and subsequent sediment transport is the main source of suspended sediment in riverine systems [
 <xref rid="B3-ijerph-16-04054" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B4-ijerph-16-04054" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Among them, soil erosion mainly depends on the basic conditions such as the amount and intensity of precipitation as well as the land use cover of the watershed. The sediment transport is driven by watershed hydrological processes, which are determined by the watershed land use cover and weather conditions for both precipitation and temperature. Temperature and precipitation changes in future climate change are expected to greatly affect the available water in the basin [
 <xref rid="B5-ijerph-16-04054" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-ijerph-16-04054" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>], so as to alter original soil loss and sediment delivery characteristics [
 <xref rid="B7-ijerph-16-04054" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-ijerph-16-04054" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-ijerph-16-04054" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. In addition, differences in underlying surface conditions in different watersheds would lead to high uncertainties in the extent and magnitude of these variations [
 <xref rid="B10-ijerph-16-04054" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-ijerph-16-04054" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Many studies have evaluated the response of runoff and sediment loading to climate and land use/land cover change, based on historical data and/or various modeling tools [
 <xref rid="B12-ijerph-16-04054" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-ijerph-16-04054" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-ijerph-16-04054" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. However, different areas possibly have different aspects of response behavior, and it is necessary to carry out case studies in critical areas.
</p>
