<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="methods" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study area</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The study site was located along a western slope of the Sierra Madre Occidental mountain range at the El Palmito Concordia ejidal lands (23°34′16″ N; 105°50′15″ W) in Sinaloa, Mexico, between 1,800 and 2,200 masl (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1" href="#fig-1">Fig. 1B</a>). The climate is temperate sub-humid with an average annual precipitation of 1,247 mm (
   <a rid="ref-52" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-52">SMN, 2018</a>). The Sierra Madre Occidental is the longest and most continuous mountain range in Mexico and represents an important temperate forest corridor (
   <a rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-24">González-Elizondo et al., 2012</a>). A vegetation gradient of oak forest, pine-oak forest and cloud forest mixed with riparian areas and secondary forest is present at the study site (
   <a rid="ref-18" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-18">Díaz, 2005</a>).
  </p>
  <div id="fig-1" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.7717/peerj.5131/fig-1</span>
   <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <div class="title">Map of the study site at El Palmito in Sinaloa, Mexico.</div>
    <p>(A) Location of the study site in Northwestern Mexico. (B) Location of the study site at El Palmito, Sinaloa. (C) Location of plots at study site; different symbols represent distinct vegetation types.</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="peerj-06-5131-g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A total of 14 hummingbird species have been described for the region: five residents (
   <span class="italic">Hylocharis leucotis</span>, 
   <span class="italic">Lampornis clemenciae</span>, 
   <span class="italic">Eugenes fulgens</span>, 
   <span class="italic">Selasphorus platycercus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">Atthis heloisa</span>), four altitudinal migrants (
   <span class="italic">Amazilia violiceps</span>, 
   <span class="italic">A. beryllina</span>, 
   <span class="italic">Cynanthus latirostris</span> and 
   <span class="italic">Colibri thalassinus</span>) and five latitudinal migrants (
   <span class="italic">Selasphorus rufus</span>, 
   <span class="italic">S. sasin</span>, 
   <span class="italic">S. calliope</span>, 
   <span class="italic">Calypte costae</span> and 
   <span class="italic">Archilochus colubris</span>; 
   <a rid="ref-34" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-34">López-Segoviano, 2012</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hummingbird censuses</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To determine the migratory phenology of the studied hummingbirds, we counted individuals in 20 fixed-radius plots (25 m radius) separated by at least 188 m (minimum distance between two plots; mean distance = 332.42 m; SD = 116.33 m). At the center of each plot, all detected hummingbirds were counted for 10 min. The plots were located in a 300 ha area covered with different types of vegetation (six plots with pine-oak forest, three plots with cloud forest, four plots with forest edges, four plots with clear-cut secondary vegetation and three plots with riparian vegetation; 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1" href="#fig-1">Fig. 1C</a>). The plots were fixed and distributed to represent the heterogeneity of the study site (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1" href="#fig-1">Fig. 1C</a>). All plots were sampled every 10 days from November 12 to February 20 in 2010–2011, 2013–2014 and 2015–2016, resulting in a total of 11 samples of each plot per sampling period.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We followed all recommended ethical guidelines to avoid harming hummingbird species and other animals in the research area and to minimize any effects on the environment (
   <a rid="ref-20" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-20">Fair, Ellen &amp; Jones, 2010</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We obtained permits from the Sub-Secretariat for Environmental Protection Management, General Directorate for Wildlife (Subsecretaría de Gestión para la Protección Ambiental, Dirección General de Vida Silvestre; permit numbers SGPA/DGVS/01833/11 and SGPA/DGGFS/712/1289/16) of Mexico. The collection permit allowed voucher specimens of plants to be collected for identification by specialists.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Flower censuses</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To evaluate flower availability, all flowers inside the fixed-radius plots used for bird counts were counted along transects of 40 m in length and 5 m in width. These transects intersected the center of each plot and were oriented toward the direction where the majority of flowers within the plot were found. The abundance and identity of all flowers were recorded. Floral censuses were carried out at the same frequency as the bird counts: 11 times per period for each plot.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The migratory phenologies and the relationship between hummingbird and flower abundances were analyzed using a generalized additive mixed model (GAMM). We used the numbers of 
   <span class="italic">A. beryllina</span> and 
   <span class="italic">S. rufus</span> species in each plot as the response variable and time, vegetation type (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1" href="#fig-1">Fig. 1C</a>) and the numbers of 
   <span class="italic">S. iodantha</span> and 
   <span class="italic">C. thyrsoideum</span> flowers and total flowers (total flowers of 15 plant species) as the predictor variables. Time was measured from 0 to 100 days where day 0 was the initial sampling date on November 12 and day 100 was the final sampling date on February 20. We fitted a GAMM with a Poisson (
   <span class="italic">S. rufus</span>) and Quasipoisson (
   <span class="italic">A. beryllina</span>) distribution, and the plots were incorporated as a random effect (
   <a rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-16">Crawley, 2007</a>; 
   <a rid="ref-62" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-62">Zuur et al., 2009</a>). We analyzed the model using the package mgcv (
   <a rid="ref-59" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-59">Wood, 2009</a>) in R software version 3.3.3 (
   <a rid="ref-45" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-45">R Core Team, 2017</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
