<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">However, determining impacts conditioned on global mean temperature targets is not free of uncertainties. Using only 2‐m air temperature (
 <italic class="italic">tas</italic> in CMIP5) for computing 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>
 <sub class="sub">glob</sub> leads to an overestimation of the CMIP5 multimodel median of global mean temperature of 0.18 °C compared to observed temperatures for the time period 2000–2009 with respect to 1861–1880 (Richardson et al., 
 <xref rid="eft2570-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). This offset is partly related to a reduced coverage in the observations (Cowtan et al., 
 <xref rid="eft2570-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). For instance, Antarctica is not well covered by observations and warms faster than the global average (Cowtan &amp; Way, 
 <xref rid="eft2570-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). It is not clear how the coverage will change in future; hence, here we consider the whole globe instead of assuming future changes in coverage. In addition to the effects of data coverage, observation‐based estimates of global mean temperature use air temperature over land and sea ice but sea surface temperatures over oceans (Cowtan et al., 
 <xref rid="eft2570-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Medhaug et al., 
 <xref rid="eft2570-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>; Richardson et al., 
 <xref rid="eft2570-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). To account for this, we compute 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>
 <sub class="sub">glob</sub> as “blended temperatures” (Cowtan et al., 
 <xref rid="eft2570-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>), that is, using air temperature over land and (dynamic) sea ice regions and sea surface temperature over the oceans (see section 
 <xref rid="eft2570-sec-0010" ref-type="sec" class="xref">2.8</xref>). This leads to a present‐day warming of +1.22 °C compared to +1.29 °C when only 
 <italic class="italic">tas</italic> is considered (
 <xref rid="eft2570-supinf-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">supporting information</xref> Figure 
 <xref rid="eft2570-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S3</xref>). Further differences between models and observations can be related to internal climate variability, overestimated radiative forcing in models, and model response error (Flato et al., 
 <xref rid="eft2570-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). Observations themselves are also uncertain with differences in mean global warming in the early 2000s of up to +0.4 °C (Medhaug et al., 
 <xref rid="eft2570-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>). Finally, the global mean temperature change also depends on the preindustrial reference period, which can lead to a shift of a decade to reach a specific warming level (Hawkins &amp; Sutton, 
 <xref rid="eft2570-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). Overall, because of these systematic differences between CMIP5 models and observations, our estimates of future exceedance probabilities at specific global mean temperature targets are conservative estimates.
</p>
