<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Montane environments of the western United States are losing breeding season avifauna diversity at all elevational gradients (Tingley &amp; Beissinger, 
 <xref rid="ece34876-bib-0109" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>), and latitude and elevation range shifts have been idiosyncratic (Auer &amp; King, 
 <xref rid="ece34876-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). Among the studies reporting elevation climate space tracking (Tingley et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34876-bib-0110" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>; Zuckerberg et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34876-bib-0130" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>), woodpeckers responded heterogeneously (Supporting information Table 
 <xref rid="ece34876-sup-0005" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S3</xref>). In the Sierra Nevada of California, avifauna with low and high elevation range centroids tend to track favorable precipitation and temperature conditions (Tingley et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34876-bib-0110" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ece34876-bib-0111" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>) shifting species upslope and downslope, respectively (Tingley et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34876-bib-0110" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). Comparing 1911–1929 to 2003–2009, Tingley and Beissinger (
 <xref rid="ece34876-bib-0109" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>) found avian populations decreased across all elevational gradients, species richness was lower, and compositions changed. However, woodpecker responses differed slightly from the community response with more than half not declining. The adaptive capacity of these woodpeckers is considered high (Supporting information Table 
 <xref rid="ece34876-sup-0003" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S1</xref>; Foden et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34876-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>), so climate change alone may not drive responses and community dynamics may not scale to the species level. Thus, accounting for two‐dimensional climate space interactions (Tingley et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34876-bib-0110" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>) and subsequent niche constraints in models is important for montane populations.
</p>
