<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="Coordination of taxonomic meta-data standard assessment" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Coordination of taxonomic meta-data standard assessment</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In biology, taxon names provide anchors that allow information about organisms to be linked. A taxonomic name, typically a species name, is attached to every primary data object (field observation, specimen, genetic data, etc.). Therefore names, together with their organisation into taxonomic classifications, are understood as core (meta-)data for biological information systems. There are many challenges in integrating data sources that contain taxonomic names and classifications, particularly where the sources extend over different biological kingdoms or national boundaries. Names may be erroneously assigned or incomplete and so searches based on exact character matching against names in current use may fail. Names that are synonyms or old combinations no longer in current use may occur in museum and herbarium specimen catalogues or in legislative lists. Names with orthographical errors occur in legislative lists on national or international level and some of them are often in use by certain taxonomists. There may also be disagreement amongst experts on the identity of specimens and on the taxonomic constituents of genera and the arrangement of classifications. The partners involved in PESI have extensive experience with handling such problems and PESI has produced practical solutions for many of these issues. The availability of authoritative taxonomic metadata standards is of particular relevance where species are directly linked to societal issues such as conservation and environmental control. PESI promotes harmonisation and certification of taxonomic metadata standards of prioritised taxa that are listed in various EU regulations and legislative lists. To address these issues, PESI had the following objectives:</p>
 <div list-type="bullet" class="list" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>To prepare a roadmap (conceptual development and strategic plan) for the application of taxonomic standards within Europe, with the purpose of overcoming the instability and inconsistency of taxon names (and concepts) and attached data. This work addressed technical, linguistic, educational and legal barriers to progress in defining and implementing appropriate standards.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>To promote co-operation between PESI and other networks and organisations. This optimised the cross-linking of European biodiversity resources using approved taxonomic data standards, and improved data quality and consistency. This facilitated discovery and exchange of biodiversity data, both within Europe, and between Europe and globally.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>To work closely with relevant standards organisations to identify appropriate authoritative standards and schemes and to ensure their adoption within the European biodiversity community. Work included development of a management classification scheme, utilisation of globally unique identifiers for names (GUIDs) and support for nomenclators (such as 
    <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://zoobank.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">ZooBank</span>, 
    <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ipni.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">International Plants Names Index</span>, 
    <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.indexfungorum.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Index Fungorum</span> and 
    <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.algaebase.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">AlgaeBase</span>) to help implement a practical name resolution service and support the definition of a future architecture for common names, proceeding from existing surveys (e.g. Suppl. material 
    <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1607157" href="#S1607157">1</a>).
   </p>
  </div>
 </div>
</sec>
