<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="Coordination and integration of European expert networks" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Coordination and integration of European expert networks</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The strengthening and integration of European taxonomic communities has been progressing since the start of the taxonomic indexing EU framework programmes 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.faunaeur.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Fauna Europaea</span> (
  <a rid="B1549410" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1549410">Jong et al. 2014</a>), 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.marbef.org/data/erms.php" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">European Register of Marine Species</span> (ERMS) (
  <a rid="B1549543" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1549543">Costello 2000</a>, 
  <a rid="B1549563" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1549563">Costello 2004</a>, 
  <a rid="B1549534" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1549534">Costello et al. 2001</a>, 
  <a rid="B1549573" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1549573">Cuvelier et al. 2006</a>), and 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.emplantbase.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Euro+Med PlantBase</span> (
  <a rid="B1635989" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1635989">Greuter and Raab-Straube 2005</a>, 
  <a rid="B1635999" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1635999">Raab-Straube and Raus 2013</a>). These initiatives built up expert networks to fulfil the project objectives and played an important role in helping to identify and consolidate the European taxonomic expert community. Other sources of taxonomic expertise are also included, such as the community of the EDIT Network of Excellence (EU FP6). PESI has reviewed and developed long-term strategies and plans for the sustainability of the contributing communities systems in terms of ownership and support of individual experts and institutions.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">PESI makes a significant addition to the species registers through the expansion of the network of expertise towards Eastern Europe. In addition to providing more comprehensive data for the pan-European species registers, this expansion has overcome the separation of knowledge and taxonomic practice over decades. Another achievement is the closer collaboration of the taxonomic societies, especially with respect to improving taxonomic coverage and addressing long-term maintenance and upgrading of the taxonomy.</p>
</sec>
