<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="PESI infrastructure potentials on a larger scale" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">PESI infrastructure potentials on a larger scale</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In its original stage, the PESI infrastructure implemented two gateways to European biodiversity based on the taxon-level information provided by the participating checklists:</p>
 <div list-type="bullet" class="list" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>a feature-rich web-portal offering convenient human-readable access</p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>a webservice layer, which has a small and effective set of methods for retrieving XML-encoded information that can be further processed by machines on any platform using any programming language.</p>
  </div>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Both webportal and webservices are optimised for a usage scenario with requests on individual objects (e.g. a particular name or taxon, information related to a particular identifier, etc.). However, we believe that PESI services will play an increasingly important role in workflow-driven systems. In this context, PESI will, for example, be used to expand a taxon name query to include its synonyms when combining independent scientific services that use different taxonomies. For this purpose several measures should be taken, including: (i) the extension of existing service layers supporting the retrieval of massive amounts of data, (ii) the optimisation of services for performance and reliability to ensure their usefulness in a workflow environment, and (iii) the optimisation of the PESI data warehouse structure for efficient output-oriented queries.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">With these extensions, new workflow-oriented scientific applications can be realised and add further value to the PESI infrastructure. Both the EC-FP7 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biovel.eu/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">BioVeL</span> and 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://i-marine.eu/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">iMarine</span> projects, in which PESI was represented, followed this approach towards a virtual biodiversity e-Library enabling pipelining of data and analysis into efficient integrated workflows (see subsection 'VREs', bellow).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Further European Taxonomic Backbone advancements are scheduled as part of the EU BON and LifeWatch projects:</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.eubon.eu/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">EU BON</span> project, 
  <span class="italic">Building the European Biodiversity Observation Network</span>, the PESI Backbone will be advanced to satisfy the needs of the 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://geobon.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">GEO BON</span> / 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.earthobservations.org" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">GEOSS </span>system, also serving as a taxonomic backbone for the projected EU BON Biodiversity Portal. The European Biodiversity Portal will be developed to serve as a main information hub by providing integrated biodiversity data from different fields. The linked data will come both from in-situ as well as from earth observation data and the taxonomic backbone will be essential to link the data from different disciplines and locations. This process (so far) includes: (i) the completion of the Fauna Europaea and Euro+Med PlantBase migration and integration to the 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cybertaxonomy.eu/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">EDIT Platform for Cybertaxonomy</span> (a process kicked-off in PESI), (ii) the registration of the third PESI Backbone version, as a 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://cybertaxonomy.eu/eubon-utis/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">EU BON taxonomic backbone</span> prototype, to the respective 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://geossregistries.info/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">GEOSS CRS</span> and 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.biodiversitycatalogue.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">BiodiversityCatalogue </span>services, (iii) the enhancement of relevant associated EDIT Platform functions, like the validation tools, and (iv) the harmonisation with other checklists, like the 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.catalogueoflife.org" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Catalogue of Life</span> (CoL), 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://fada.biodiversity.be/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">FADA </span>and 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.marinespecies.org" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">WoRMS</span>, to allow for federated (multiple checklist) searches and a unified data-model mapping (Suppl. materials 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1629551" href="#S1629551">30</a>, 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1629552" href="#S1629552">31</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A complementary effort is foreseen in 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://lifewatch.eu/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">LifeWatch</span> where, as part of the 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.lifewatch.be/en/about-taxonomic-backbone" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Flemish contribution to LifeWatch</span>, the LifeWatch Taxonomic Backbone will be established, especially focussed on the marine environment. This LifeWatch Taxonomic Backbone will integrate various taxonomic checklists, including EU-nomen, and a range of associated biogeographical, ecological, genomic and literature data resources, supporting the LifeWatch infrastructure developments (
  <a rid="B1629589" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1629589">Dekeyzer et al. 2014</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
