<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="Toward a European Clearing House on taxonomic expertise" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Toward a European Clearing House on taxonomic expertise</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Part of the PESI future progress lies in its potential to further engage and organise the taxonomic community participation as a vital, virtual workforce including (i) the instalment of proper expert network governance, (ii) the application of proper ownership licences, (iii) the use of appropriate mechanisms for acknowledging expert contributions, (iv) the ability to function as an efficient 'knowledge hub', supporting biodiversity research and decision making more generally, (v) the successful involvement of more open and dynamically organised social networks and communities, like non-professional taxonomists and citizen scientists.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Network governance</span>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Considering the overall decline of taxonomy as a scientific discipline, the maintenance of a basic (taxonomic) expertise capacity will be essential to satisfy the knowledge needs for a wide range of biodiversity-related information services in the near future, including the pan-European checklists. In PESI we moved forward from the efforts of 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.e-taxonomy.eu/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">EDIT</span> on establishing a collaborative workforce, adding the integrated PESI expert networks into a single EDIT Expert Database and by defining more sophisticated social networking standards. To support the process of expert network integration, the SMEBD licensing model was applied. Further, the role of taxonomic institutes on the sustainable hosting of the taxonomic databases was studied (
  <a rid="B1607713" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1607713">Costello et al. 2014</a>) as well as the need for a federal facility, offering secretarial support on the expert network functioning.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A network of European leading taxonomic institutions forms the 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cetaf.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Consortium of European Taxonomic Facilities</span> (CETAF), holding the majority of the worlds' biodiversity collections and their data. CETAF's mission contains the enhancement of Europe's knowledgebase capacity on taxonomy for a wide range of scientific and popular users (
  <a rid="B1642923" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1642923">Price 2014</a>). CETAF incorporates a legacy of past EC projects as working commissions and interest groups. CETAF has recognised the importance of data curation (
  <a rid="B1642943" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1642943">CETAF 2004</a>, 
  <a rid="B1642952" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1642952">CETAF 2008</a>) and is interested to consider the set up of a special body to take care of the integrated management of the PESI taxonomic workforce, including the continuing hosting of the EDIT Expert Database, as a European Clearing House on taxonomic expertise.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Accreditation and data papers</span>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An important vehicle for authoring metadata provenance, providing a clear recognition of all contributors and enabling the receipt of credits as a formal scientific publication by means of citation, are 'data papers'. Data papers also play an important role in the publication of small bits and pieces of information, like new distributions, which would otherwise be difficult to publish (termed 'micro-publication'). Data papers allow a more flexible/dynamic way of expert involvement within the process of data collation and reviewing, because contributions are more easily acknowledgeable than is currently the case. Finally, by using novel e-publishing tools, the process of manuscript drafting is highly automated, being more convenient for the editors, but also enabling a direct cross-indexing with other relevant metadata resources, supporting feedback mechanisms in foreseen name annotation workflows (see also 'next generation name infrastructure' subsection, below).</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">PESI already supports the publishing of data papers accompanying the WoRMS, Fauna Europaea and Euro+Med updating process (see 'Results'). More emphasis will be put on this work within the 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.eubon.eu/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">EU BON</span> project, to trigger expert participation, to automate the dissemination and back-linking (tagging) of taxon names (within data papers) to external resources (
  <a rid="B1632879" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1632879">Penev et al. 2010</a>, 
  <a rid="B1632908" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1632908">Catapano 2010</a>), and to support the evaluation of gaps in taxonomic information and knowledge (see 'e-Publishing' subsection, below).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Networks of Knowledge</span>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As part of the 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ipbes.net" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Intergovernmental Platform on Biodiversity and Ecosystem Services</span> (IPBES) developments and the 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://biodiversity.europa.eu/ecosystem-assessments" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Mapping and Assessing Ecosystems and their Services</span> (MAES) process, the European Commission is exploring mechanisms to build so-called Networks of Knowledge (NoKs), to interact more broadly with the whole community of knowledge holders on biodiversity and ecosystem services, to inform decision making and strengthen the knowledge-policy interface. 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.biodiversityknowledge.eu/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">BiodiversityKnowledge</span> (KNEU) is proposed as a governance structure for this NoK. PESI is involved in the development and testing of the BiodiversityKnowledge prototype, improving the knowledge flow between biodiversity knowledge holders and users in Europe, a process recently concluded (Suppl. material 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1607333" href="#S1607333">28</a>) and waiting for further H2020 application. A challenging issue in a Network of Knowledge involvement would be the implementation of the applicable sociology, motivating the actual experts participation in cross-disciplinary inventories and assuring a proper scientific reward system.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Non-professional taxonomists and citizen scientists</span>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Currently around 50% of the experts contributing to the updating of the pan-European checklists includes professional taxonomists. However, the contributions of non-professional taxonomists will significantly increase in the near future. PESI should effectively anticipate this development by implementing relevant social networking mechanisms, including mentoring, educational and accreditation systems, in close collaboration with taxonomic institutes and societies.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An associated exercise is the adequate integration of efforts of voluntary biodiversity recorders, who provide a major contribution to the continuing monitoring of Europe's biodiversity. During PESI an ESF networking proposal was submitted entitled “Citizens Monitoring Biodiversity (CMD)” to optimise the involvement of the volunteer biodiversity observation community into the European biodiversity programs (
  <a rid="B1613428" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1613428">Boumans and Jong 2009</a>). This ESF proposal was awarded, but constrained by the formal country convergence criteria and needs a follow-up.
 </p>
</sec>
