<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="Towards a European taxonomic workforce (ETW)" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Towards a European taxonomic workforce (ETW)</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">A pan-European Taxonomic Workforce (ETW)</span>, consisting of all people who carry out taxonomic work in Europe, was identified as pivotal for the integration and coordination of the current and future expert networks within Europe (Fig. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1613488" href="#F1613488">2</a>). This task force integrates the already existing expert networks supporting the pan-European checklists, extended by the collaborative capacity of the 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.e-taxonomy.eu/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">EDIT</span> institutional staff previously assembled within the EDIT Expert Database (Fig. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1613486" href="#F1613486">3</a>). The additional inclusion of the Focal Point network was an important step forward carried out by PESI. A report on the tasks, activities and operational standards necessary for a functional ETW was drafted (Suppl. material 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1604774" href="#S1604774">2</a>), taking into account the concepts of an 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sci-mate.org/item.php?id=21" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Open Source Society</span> model (Fig. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1605073" href="#F1605073">4</a>) and discussing the need for an 
  <span class="italic">accreditation system</span> for taxonomists, clarifying expert competency through certification, a citation system for online data, and a method for recognising the contribution of non-career taxonomists and other citizen scientists groups. Also the proper acknowledgement of (online) taxonomic databases curation by museum staff was evaluated and approved by 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cetaf.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">CETAF</span>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Quality control and standards</span>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">PESI has set out a working Intellectual Property Rights (IPR) model, based on the 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.smebd.eu/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">SMEBD</span> model, under which PESI can proceed with its aim to integrate taxonomic databases in Europe, ensuring the free and wide dissemination of data, and promoting the further virtualisation efforts (e-Taxonomy; e-Science; e-Publishing) in this field. The SMEBD model encourages scientists to input their data without being burdened with its upkeep. This allows scientists to retain full ownership of their work, knowing that data stewards are managing their data accordingly. This IPR model proposes a 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Creative Commons Attribution</span> (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">cc-BY</span>) license that allows for the wide dissemination of data to other scientists and interested parties, giving recognition to the creator of the data (but see 
  <a rid="B1648605" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1648605">Hagedorn et al. 2011</a> for pitfalls of the -by clause-). In relation to citation of data, PESI recommends (Suppl. material 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1604775" href="#S1604775">3</a>) that contributing databases adopt a standard citation system to simplify the citation system in PESI and that the date accessed be automatically added, as already done in ERMS.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Gap analyses and Continuity</span>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To secure the continuity of electronic biodiversity data, PESI has reviewed gaps in taxonomic expertise, species registers and informatics resources throughout Europe and surveyed potential ways to complete these gaps (Suppl. material 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1604799" href="#S1604799">4</a>). From the data presented in the report it was found that Kingdom 
  <div content-type="taxon-name" class="named-content">
   <div content-type="kingdom" class="named-content">Animalia</div>
  </div> is the closest to completion, followed by the Kingdoms Chromista, 
  <div content-type="taxon-name" class="named-content">
   <div content-type="kingdom" class="named-content">Plantae</div>
  </div>, 
  <div content-type="taxon-name" class="named-content">
   <div content-type="kingdom" class="named-content">Fungi</div>
  </div> and 
  <div content-type="taxon-name" class="named-content">
   <div content-type="division" class="named-content">Bacteria</div>
  </div>. However, it is clear that the completion of each of the Kingdoms will not be without problems and will require further funding.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The functional and successful operation of ETW involves a series of informatics resources, which will be addressed within the gap analysis, particularly in relation to successful developments in this area, like Scratchpads, the Platform for Cybertaxonomy and tools for e-Publishing.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Recently the hosting of the EDIT Expert Database (including the ETW) at the 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://zoologi.snm.ku.dk/english/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Zoological Museum Copenhagen</span> has ended in favour of a less centralised model, hosting the relevant (zoological, botanical, marine, terrestrial, etc.) expert data in the respective pan-European checklists databases. A collaboration with 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cetaf.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">CETAF</span> on the governance of taxonomic knowledge networks is under consideration (see section 'Progressions').
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The continuity of relevant electronic taxonomic biodiversity data resources and expertise networks were examined (Suppl. material 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1604823" href="#S1604823">6</a>), also as an input to the PESI business plan (Suppl. material 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1604869" href="#S1604869">7</a>). This shows a close collaboration with other initiatives like GBIF, LifeWatch, EU BON and Global Names (see also the sections 'Progressions' and 'Outlooks') and the PESI Focal Points network (see below).
 </p>
</sec>
