<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Materials and Methods</div>
 <sec id="s4a" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ethics statement</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">No live animals were used for this research, however, the project was reviewed and approved by the Zoological Society of London's Ethics Committee</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s4b" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Identification of the disease epidemic</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Since 2000, opportunistic nationwide monitoring of the causes of garden bird mortality in Great Britain has been carried out by the Institute of Zoology (IoZ, London), the Wildlife Veterinary Investigation Laboratory (Cornwall) and the Scottish Agricultural Colleges (Ayrshire). In 2005, these organisations, together with the BTO, the RSPB, the Department of Veterinary Pathology, University of Liverpool and the Universities Federation for Animal Welfare, established a coordinated surveillance network as part of the Garden Bird Health initiative (GBHi). The GBHi was established before the emergence of trichomonosis in British finches was identified and has always included wide-ranging investigations to identify pathogens responsible for garden bird disease.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The GBHi surveillance of garden bird morbidity and mortality takes place via opportunistic reports obtained from the general public and weekly reports from identified volunteers who form a systematic reporting network. As opportunistic reports are vulnerable to temporal or spatial observer bias, for example following regional media reports, the systematic surveillance network was established in April 2005 in order to quantify disease prevalence rates. This network utilised the BTO's Garden BirdWatch (GBW) volunteer network of approximately 15,000 households throughout Britain 
   <a rid="pone.0012215-Cannon1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0012215-Cannon1">[22]</a>. A random sample of 1,614 volunteers (stratified by the number of participants in each recording region) were approached with a view to recording additional information relating to the incidence of diseased and dying birds in their gardens. Of those GBW volunteers approached, 752 submitted data to the GBHi project in 2006. A visual examination of the spatial distribution of sites suggested no spatial bias in those who submitted data relative to those initially approached and there was no difference in the distribution of latitudes (F1,2356 = 1.14, NS) or longitudes (F1,2356 = 1.31, NS) between the two samples.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s4c" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Identification of disease organism</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Post mortem examinations using a standardised protocol were performed on carcasses submitted from a subset of reported garden bird mortality incidents. Cases were selected for post-mortem investigation based on fresh carcass availability. Birds thought to have died as a result of trauma, predation or infectious disease were examined; our selection criteria did not specifically or solely target finch species or suspected cases of trichomonosis, but rather aimed to achieve a representative cross-section of species and aetiologies. In 2005 and 2006, a combined total of 995 garden birds of 42 species were examined, of which Fringillidae species accounted for 64% of submissions.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fresh carcasses were submitted by post or were hand-delivered and were refrigerated at 4°C and examined fresh within 48 hours of submission where possible, or were frozen at −20°C on submission and examined at a later date. Each submitted carcass was assigned a unique post mortem reference code and the species, age, sex and body weight were recorded for each bird examined. Systematic external and internal examinations of body systems were performed and any gross lesions described. Where indicated, and where the state of carcass decomposition permitted, samples were taken for microbiological, parasitological and histopathological investigations.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Liver and contents of the mid-small intestinal loop were sampled aseptically from the majority of cases, as were any lesions found, and were examined for the presence of pathogenic bacteria. Briefly, liver was plated directly onto the following media: Colombia blood agar supplemented with 5% horse or sheep blood (CBA)(QCM laboratories, UK or E and O laboratories, UK), incubated under aerobic conditions, and Chocolate blood agar (CCBA) (QCM laboratories), incubated under 5–10% CO
   <sub>2</sub> conditions. Small intestinal contents were plated directly onto the following media: (1) Xylose-Lysine Deoxycholate (XLD) agar (QCM laboratories), or MacConkey agar without salt (E&amp;O laboratories) and Brilliant green agar (E&amp;O laboratories), incubated under aerobic conditions; (2) CBA, incubated under aerobic conditions; (3) Campylobacter Blood Free Selective medium (modified CCDA-Preston) (QCM laboratories), incubated under microaerophilic conditions, and (4) immersed into selenite Salmonella-selective enrichment broth (QCM laboratories or E&amp;O laboratories) under aerobic conditions for 24 h followed by subculture onto XLD agar aerobically. At the Institute of Zoology, liver also was plated onto CBA and incubated anaerobically. The same bacteriology protocol was used for examination of necrotic ingluvitis lesions as for the intestinal contents with the exception of the modified CCDA-Preston media. Bacterial isolates were identified using colony and Gram's staining morphology, followed by biochemical properties which were determined using the API biochemical test strip method (API-BioMerieux, Marcy l'Etoile, France).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition, oesophageal lesions (circa 5 mm
   <span class="sup">3</span>) from cases with necrotic ingluvitis were incubated at 30°C in Trichomonas Media No. 2. (Oxoid, UK) and screened for motile trichomonads at 24, 48, 72 hrs and 5 days. Wet mount preparations of small intestinal contents were examined in a subset of cases for evidence of nematode, cestode and protozoan parasites.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Samples from a range of organs (including brain, gizzard, heart, kidney, liver, lung, pectoral muscle, small intestine, spleen, trachea and any diseased tissues), were fixed in neutral-buffered 10% formalin and processed for histopathological examination using routine methods. Duplicate samples of organs and diseased tissues were stored frozen at −20°C or −80°C for future analyses.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A combination of morphological and molecular techniques was used to identify the trichomonad species. Giemsa-stained preparations of trichomonad cultures were examined using light microscopy to assess parasite morphology. These were prepared by placing a drop of active trichomonas culture onto a standard glass microscope slide; this was then air dried, alcohol-fixed and stained using routine methods. Transmission and scanning electron microscopy was performed on trichomonad cultures fixed in 2.5% buffered gluteraldehyde and post-fixed in 1% osmium tetroxide (VWR, UK) at the University College Medical School, Royal Free Campus, using Philips 201 and 501 microscopes.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">DNA was extracted from frozen/thawed necrotic ingluvitis lesions collected from finches using the Biosprint 15 DNA Blood Kit (Qiagen, UK) for purification of DNA from tissue according to the manufacturer's instructions. DNA was extracted from trichomonad cultures using the same technique. PCR was used to amplify the ITS1/5.8S/ITS2 ribosomal region using published TFR1 and TFR2 primers 
   <a rid="pone.0012215-GaspardaSilva1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0012215-GaspardaSilva1">[30]</a> with an adapted protocol. Briefly, PCR reactions were run with 3 µL of 10X PCR buffer (Qiagen), 3 µL of 25 mM MgCl
   <sub>2</sub> (Qiagen), 0.5 µL of 5 U/µL HotStar Taq Plus DNA Polymerase (Qiagen), 2 µL template DNA, 0.4 µL of 100 mM dNTP mix (Bioline, UK), 3 µL of 10 µM forward and reverse primer and molecular grade water to complete the 50 µL per reaction. Oligonucleotide primers were supplied by Operon Biotechnologies, Germany. After an initial 15 min denaturation at 94°C, 35 cycles of 94°C for 1 min, 65°C for 30 sec and 72°C for 1 min were carried out, followed by a 5 min extension at 72°C using a thermal cycler (Tec-571, Techne, UK). Each PCR run contained a negative control of water and a positive control of purified trichomonad DNA obtained from parasites cultured from an affected greenfinch found dead as part of this study.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The PCR products, consisting of a clear single band, were visualised under UV light after ethidium bromide staining of a 1% agarose gel and the expected product size (circa 400 bps) was confirmed using Ready-Load 100 bp DNA ladder (Invitrogen, UK). PCR products were purified using the QIAquick PCR purification kit (Qiagen) and submitted for sequencing at the John Innes Genome Laboratory, UK, using the Applied Biosystems 3730xl with POP7 polymer and the TFR1 and TFR2 primers. Chromatograph profiles were inspected using Chromas 2 software (
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.synthesisgene.com" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.synthesisgene.com</span>). Sequences from the forward TFR1 primer and the reverse complement of the TFR2 primer PCR product were aligned in both directions for each sample using MEGA 4.1 software and ClustalW (
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.megasoftware.net" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.megasoftware.net</span>). Sequences were compared with available gene sequences within NCBI Genbank using the BLAST search function to determine species identification within the Trichomonadidae.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s4d" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Molecular detection of Trichomonas infection</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A nested PCR protocol was designed to increase the sensitivity of detection of trichomonad parasite DNA in template DNA extracted from lesions sampled post mortem and to provide a diagnostic tool for cases where autolysed carcass condition precluded 
   <span class="italic">Trichomonas</span> sp. culture. Trichomonad small subunit (SSU) rRNA primers (forward -
   <div content-type="gene" class="named-content">TACTTGGTTGATCCTGCC</div> and reverse - 
   <div content-type="gene" class="named-content">TCACCTACCGTTACCTTG</div>) from 
   <a rid="pone.0012215-Cepicka1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0012215-Cepicka1">[43]</a> were used for the first reaction. The PCR product nucleotide sequence was obtained from a pure trichomonad culture obtained from an affected greenfinch. Nested primers, TN3 forward (
   <div content-type="gene" class="named-content">ATAGGACTGCAAAGCCGAGA</div>) and TN4 reverse (
   <div content-type="gene" class="named-content">TGATTTCACCGAGTCATCCA</div>), were then designed using Prime3 online software 
   <a rid="pone.0012215-Rozen1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0012215-Rozen1">[44]</a>. Primers were supplied by Eurofins MWG Operon (UK).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The first stage used 2 µL of 10X PCR buffer (Qiagen), 0.1 µL of 5 U/µL HotStar Taq Plus DNA Polymerase (Qiagen), 2 µL template DNA, 0.4 µL of 10 mM each dNTP mix (Qiagen), 0.4 µL of 100 µM forward and reverse primer and molecular grade water to complete the 20 µL reaction. After an initial 5 min denaturation at 94°C, 40 cycles of 94°C for 1 min, 55°C for 1 min and 72°C for 2 mins were carried out, followed by a 5 min extension at 72°C using a thermal cycler (GeneAmp PCR System 9700, Applied Biosystems, UK).</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The reaction mixture for the second amplification was the same as for the first, except for the use of the nested primers. The amplification mix comprised 19 µl of mix and 1 µl of PCR product template from the first amplification round. After an initial 5 min denaturation at 94°C, 35 cycles of 94°C for 45 sec, 50°C for 45 sec and 72°C for 45 sec were carried out, followed by a 7 min extension at 72°C. Each amplification contained a negative control, consisting of water and a positive control of purified DNA obtained from cultured trichomonad parasites from a greenfinch. Amplified PCR products were visualised under UV light after ethidium bromide staining of a 3% agarose gel and the expected product size (circa 200 bps) was confirmed using Easy Ladder I (Bioline). PCR products were submitted for sequencing at Cogenics (UK) using the ABI 3730 xl platform with the TN3 forward and TN4 reverse primers. Chromatograph profiles were inspected using Chromas 2 software
   <span class="monospace">.</span> The sequence from the forward TN3 primer and the reverse complement of the TN4 primer PCR product were aligned in both directions for each sample using MEGA 4.1 software and ClustalW. Sequences were compared with available gene sequences within NCBI Genbank using the BLAST search function.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Reliable discrimination between necrotic ingluvitis due to salmonellosis or trichomonosis in finches is not possible based on gross examination alone. In order to evaluate whether our nested PCR cross-reacted non-specifically with 
   <span class="italic">Salmonella</span> Typhimurium Definitive Type (DT)40 and DT56 variant (v), lesions from 56 greenfinches and six chaffinches confirmed to have died due to salmonellosis by microbiological examination in 2005 and 2006 (Lawson, 
   <span class="italic">unpublished data</span>) were screened. The majority of cases were negative on nested PCR (54/62 cases) and all cases examined during the study period 1 April 2006 to 30 September 2006 were negative. This indicates that 8 cases examined outside the study period might have had concurrent infection with 
   <span class="italic">Trichomonas</span> sp. and 
   <span class="italic">Salmonella</span> sp.. Carcass condition precluded parasite culture in all but one of these cases, but this case yielded trichomonad parasites confirming the existence of dual infection. These findings suggest that the nested PCR does not cross react non-specifically with 
   <span class="italic">Salmonella</span> Typhimurium DT40 and DT56(v) and can be used within our case definition for the diagnosis of trichomonosis in finches.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s4e" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Case definition</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cases of trichomonosis were diagnosed on the basis of the presence of necrotic ingluvitis lesions in combination with positive culture of motile trichomonads and/or positive nested PCR amplification. Salmonellosis also causes necrotic ingluvitis and this was diagnosed by lesions being positive for 
   <span class="italic">Salmonella</span> sp. on culture. No cases of dual infection were identified during the study period.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s4f" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Geographical and temporal distribution of the epidemic</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Garden Bird Watch participants (c. 9000) record the presence of a range of bird and other wildlife species encountered each week throughout the year; a subset (c. 30%) submit actual counts of each species seen using an online recording form. Participants maintain a consistent level of observational effort from one week to the next; data from weeks that are under- or over-observed are discarded. Variation in observer effort and competence is inevitable, but this can be controlled for by introducing a site effect into the models used to examine the data 
   <a rid="pone.0012215-Robb1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0012215-Robb1">[40]</a>. Almost all the participants provide food of some kind (the range of food provided for garden birds is also recorded on a weekly basis) for wild birds and feeding stations are generally the focal point of the study areas. The subset of participants that took part in GBH
   <span class="italic">i</span> surveyed all or part of their garden systematically in a consistent manner each week to record the number, and putative cause, of dead or sick birds found. The clinical signs of ill health in birds affected by trichomonosis typically included non-specific malaise, although dysphagia was noted in a large proportion of reported incidents. This contrasts with the clearly recognisable external signs of conjunctivitis caused by 
   <span class="italic">Mycoplasma gallisepticum</span> in the house finch and which were used to monitor spatial spread of mycoplasmosis 
   <a rid="pone.0012215-Dhondt1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0012215-Dhondt1">[20]</a>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to evaluate the geographical distribution of the trichomonosis epidemic, data from the opportunistic and systematic reporting schemes were examined for the period between 1 April and 30 September 2006. This interval was selected to minimise the likelihood of confounding these data with mortality due to salmonellosis, outbreaks of which occur during the winter months and which also result in non-specific signs of malaise in finches. Previous studies of salmonellosis in Great Britain 
   <a rid="pone.0012215-Pennycott3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0012215-Pennycott3">[45]</a>, continental Europe 
   <a rid="pone.0012215-Refsum1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0012215-Refsum1">[46]</a> and North America 
   <a rid="pone.0012215-Hall1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0012215-Hall1">[47]</a> along with our own observations on salmonellosis in passerines over the period 1995–2008 (Lawson and Cunningham, 
   <span class="italic">unpublished data</span>), have shown the disease to be seasonal, occurring almost exclusively within the period 1
   <span class="sup">st</span> October to 31
   <span class="sup">st</span> March.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s4g" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Incident definition</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As resources and logistics did not allow all dead birds found to be submitted for post mortem examination, we established specific criteria for determining if a mortality incident should be classified as likely being due to trichomonosis. For the purposes of this analysis, a trichomonosis incident was defined if, within the six month period of the study (between 1 April and 30 September 2006), mortality included two or more dead finches (greenfinch or chaffinch), one or more sick finch(es) with typical signs of disease, or if trichomonosis was confirmed post mortem. To give a measure of incidence for the opportunistic reports, we expressed the total number of trichomonosis incidents reported in each county per thousand households according to the 2001 UK National Census 
   <a rid="pone.0012215-Census1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0012215-Census1">[48]</a>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s4h" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Changes in bird abundance</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Each week, GBW participants recorded the presence of each bird species in their garden and, optionally, the peak number of birds counted each week 
   <a rid="pone.0012215-Cannon1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0012215-Cannon1">[22]</a>. For this analysis we used the 828 gardens for which data were submitted in every week from January 2005 to June 2007 in England south of 53.5°N (see below). We modelled bird abundance as the proportion of gardens in which the species was present (‘reporting rate’). We modelled reporting rates using generalised additive or linear mixed models, fitted using the gamm function in package 
   <span class="italic">mgcv</span> for R 2.6.0 
   <a rid="pone.0012215-R1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0012215-R1">[49]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0012215-Wood1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0012215-Wood1">[50]</a>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To exclude the possibility that changes in other environmental factors, such as climate, between years might have caused changes in greenfinch numbers, we also modelled reporting rates of chaffinch, which has a similar body size and ecology to the greenfinch, and was the second most frequently affected species in which trichomonosis was recorded, and of dunnock, which also feeds around garden feeders 
   <a rid="pone.0012215-Snow1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0012215-Snow1">[51]</a> but in which trichomonosis was rarely recorded (only three cases diagnosed in 2005 and 2006 combined). Both species show similar patterns of spatial and temporal abundance in gardens to the greenfinch 
   <a rid="pone.0012215-Cannon1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0012215-Cannon1">[22]</a>. We predicted that, if trichomonosis was responsible for changes in numbers, chaffinch should show an identifiable, but less marked, response and dunnock should show little response; if other factors, such as climatic factors or a change in resource availability, were involved then the response among the three species should be similar.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Abundance of birds in gardens varies seasonally in a non-linear fashion, with peak numbers occurring in late winter or spring and lowest counts in late summer/autumn, when many birds are moulting 
   <a rid="pone.0012215-Cannon1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0012215-Cannon1">[22]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0012215-Chamberlain1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0012215-Chamberlain1">[35]</a>. To model this variation we fitted a generalised additive model to the reporting rate as a function of week number (1–7 Jan = 1 to 25–31 Dec = 52) in the form of a thin-plate regression spline using gamm with a binomial error structure and logit link function 
   <a rid="pone.0012215-Wood1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0012215-Wood1">[50]</a>. We used the default level of smoothing, as increasing the potential for smoothing (by changing the basis, k) did not alter the results materially. To account for variation among gardens in the probability of birds being present and observer ability we included garden identifier as a random-effect term. Preliminary models including garden identifier as a fixed effect showed the distribution of these effects, as for other large-scale schemes run by BTO, were indeed approximately normally distributed. The weekly records of bird presence are likely to exhibit serial auto-correlation, both temporally and spatially. We initially fitted models with no temporal or spatial auto-correlation and while temporal correlation among the residuals was strong, spatial correlations (analysed using the correlog function in library ncf 
   <a rid="pone.0012215-Bjornstad1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0012215-Bjornstad1">[52]</a>), though statistically significant, were typically weak (r≤0.05). This may reflect the fact that distance between gardens was generally much greater than the ambit of individual foraging flocks and it is unlikely the provisioning behaviour in any one sample garden influenced the behaviour in neighbouring sample gardens. We therefore included an AR1 auto-regressive correlation structure (with weeks numbered consecutively through the entire period) to account for the correlation between records in consecutive weeks; the degree of auto-correlation was assumed to be the same for each garden.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To quantify impacts on the breeding season following the epidemic of trichomonosis in autumn 2006, we constructed a model to compare reporting rate at the start of the 2007 breeding season (weeks 13–21, 26 March–28 May) with the average reporting rate for the same period in the previous two years (which, as far as could be determined, were typical). We restricted the analysis to the previous two years to avoid potential confounding effects of long-term trends in bird numbers and reporting rates. As we were considering a relatively short time-span within a year, it was not necessary to fit a smoothed term of week; rather we modelled reporting rate as a function of garden size, week (and its square to account for any non-linearity) and a two-level dummy variable, year, with weeks in 2005/06 having year = 0 and those in 2007 year = 1. The estimate of this latter term then gives the change in reporting rate in 2007 relative to that in the previous two years. As before, we included garden identifier as a random effect and fitted an auto-correlated binomial error structure.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mortality due to trichomonosis varied spatially throughout the country, so we defined three regions representing areas of High, Intermediate and Low incidence of trichomonosis, based on the results of opportunistic sampling. We restricted these analyses to England south of a line from the Mersey to the Humber (approx. 53° 30′N) as it is in this region that gardens participating in GBW are most representative of the landscape as a whole (for example upland areas, where there tend to be few GBW sites, are relatively limited in extent). Greenfinch, chaffinch and dunnock populations occur widely across this region, being observed in 70–80% of gardens in the GBW scheme. For convenience, we defined these three regions in terms of administrative county boundaries with areas of High (Cheshire, Derbyshire, Gloucestershire, Herefordshire, Leicestershire, Shropshire, Staffordshire, Warwickshire and the West Midlands), Intermediate (Bedfordshire, Buckinghamshire Cambridgeshire, Lincolnshire, Northamptonshire, Nottinghamshire, Oxfordshire, South Yorkshire and Wiltshire) and Low (Berkshire, Essex, Hampshire, Hertfordshire, Greater London, Kent, Norfolk, Suffolk, Surrey and Sussex) incidence of trichomonosis. To test for differences in the change in reporting rate in spring 2007 among areas, we included an interaction term between area and the dummy year variable described above.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Numbers of birds present across Britain during the breeding season are monitored using line-transect counts in a sample of c. 3,000 randomly selected 1×1 km squares by the Breeding Bird Survey (BBS) 
   <a rid="pone.0012215-Newson1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0012215-Newson1">[23]</a>. BBS transects are undertaken in all habitats, rather than being restricted to gardens as with the GBW scheme. An index of relative abundance based on a generalized linear Poisson model with categorical site and year fixed-effects is produced annually; we obtained indices for the three county groupings to measure the relative change in breeding population between 2006 and 2007 in each region.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
