<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2c" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Geographical and temporal distribution of the epidemic</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Rates of opportunistic reports of trichomonosis (identified according to our incident definition) varied greatly among counties, with rates in excess of 0.20 incidents per thousand households (ipth) found in Gloucestershire, Powys and Warwickshire. We used the opportunistic reports to define regions of High, Intermediate and Low disease incidence (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0012215-g004" href="#pone-0012215-g004">Fig. 4</a>). Overall, the average reporting rate was 0.037 ipth but this varied markedly among the regions (aggregate average for the High region: 0.109 ipth; Intermediate region: 0.056 ipth; Low region: 0.003 ipth, χ
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 650.5, d.f. = 2, 
  <span class="italic">p</span>&lt;0.001). As these rates may have been influenced by local publicity, we quantified incidence in a network of garden sites where diseased birds were searched for systematically according to a defined protocol throughout the study period. Trichomonosis (according to our incident definition) was identified at 39 sites (5.2%) but the incidence varied spatially in a manner similar to the opportunistic reports, with 10.4% (n = 115) of participants in the High region reporting an incident, 7.8% (n = 154) in the Intermediate region and 0.0% (n = 164) in the Low region (χ
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 16.4, d.f. = 2, 
  <span class="italic">p</span>&lt;0.005).
 </p>
 <div id="pone-0012215-g004" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0012215.g004</span>
  <span class="label">Figure 4</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Distribution of finch trichomonosis incidents in 2006.</div>
   <p>Gardens reporting at least one incident of finch trichomonosis (large red dots) and all other sites (small yellow dots) contributing to the systematic survey. The shading indicates relative incidence of trichomonosis recorded by the opportunistic survey (incidents per thousand households for each county interpolated from county centroids). The heavy lines delineate areas of High, Intermediate and Low incidence, based on the opportunistic survey data.</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0012215.g004" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
