<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s4f" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Geographical and temporal distribution of the epidemic</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Garden Bird Watch participants (c. 9000) record the presence of a range of bird and other wildlife species encountered each week throughout the year; a subset (c. 30%) submit actual counts of each species seen using an online recording form. Participants maintain a consistent level of observational effort from one week to the next; data from weeks that are under- or over-observed are discarded. Variation in observer effort and competence is inevitable, but this can be controlled for by introducing a site effect into the models used to examine the data 
  <a rid="pone.0012215-Robb1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0012215-Robb1">[40]</a>. Almost all the participants provide food of some kind (the range of food provided for garden birds is also recorded on a weekly basis) for wild birds and feeding stations are generally the focal point of the study areas. The subset of participants that took part in GBH
  <span class="italic">i</span> surveyed all or part of their garden systematically in a consistent manner each week to record the number, and putative cause, of dead or sick birds found. The clinical signs of ill health in birds affected by trichomonosis typically included non-specific malaise, although dysphagia was noted in a large proportion of reported incidents. This contrasts with the clearly recognisable external signs of conjunctivitis caused by 
  <span class="italic">Mycoplasma gallisepticum</span> in the house finch and which were used to monitor spatial spread of mycoplasmosis 
  <a rid="pone.0012215-Dhondt1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0012215-Dhondt1">[20]</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to evaluate the geographical distribution of the trichomonosis epidemic, data from the opportunistic and systematic reporting schemes were examined for the period between 1 April and 30 September 2006. This interval was selected to minimise the likelihood of confounding these data with mortality due to salmonellosis, outbreaks of which occur during the winter months and which also result in non-specific signs of malaise in finches. Previous studies of salmonellosis in Great Britain 
  <a rid="pone.0012215-Pennycott3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0012215-Pennycott3">[45]</a>, continental Europe 
  <a rid="pone.0012215-Refsum1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0012215-Refsum1">[46]</a> and North America 
  <a rid="pone.0012215-Hall1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0012215-Hall1">[47]</a> along with our own observations on salmonellosis in passerines over the period 1995–2008 (Lawson and Cunningham, 
  <span class="italic">unpublished data</span>), have shown the disease to be seasonal, occurring almost exclusively within the period 1
  <span class="sup">st</span> October to 31
  <span class="sup">st</span> March.
 </p>
</sec>
