<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2a" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Identification of the disease epidemic</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Opportunistic monitoring of garden bird mortality by the Royal Society for the Protection of Birds (RSPB) between 2001 and 2004 showed an annual seasonal peak in mid-winter (Dec/Jan), with 37–76% of reports per annum occurring in these two months (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0012215-g001" href="#pone-0012215-g001">Fig. 1</a>, K. Peck, 
  <span class="italic">Unpublished data</span>); post mortem examinations indicated that this seasonal peak was largely due to salmonellosis in Fringillidae and Passeridae species (
  <a rid="pone.0012215-Pennycott1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0012215-Pennycott1">[15]</a> Kirkwood, Cunningham and Simpson, 
  <span class="italic">Unpublished data</span>). Between January 1
  <span class="sup">st</span> 2000 and December 31
  <span class="sup">st</span> 2004, we examined 750 garden birds post mortem, of which 67% of greenfinch deaths (168/252 birds) were due to salmonellosis and no cases of finch trichomonosis were confirmed.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Following the index case of trichomonosis in a British finch in April 2005, small numbers of finch mortality incidents were reported throughout 2005, unusually peaking during September to November 
  <a rid="pone.0012215-Pennycott2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0012215-Pennycott2">[17]</a>. In summer 2006, the number of finch, particularly greenfinch, mortality reports increased dramatically with a total of 1054 trichomonosis incidents recorded (according to our incident definition – see below), involving c. 6300 dead greenfinches and chaffinches combined, between 1 April 2006 and 30 September 2006. This comprised 50% of all reported incidents of garden bird morbidity and mortality during this period and compares with 84 incidents of trichomonosis for the same time period in 2005 and sporadic cases (none of which involved finches) in previous years. These reports from the public were unsolicited, not in response to a direct appeal and occurred prior to media coverage of the EID. Sick and dead birds at affected sites were typically observed in close vicinity to garden bird feeding stations and exhibited non-specific signs of malaise, for example lethargy and fluffed-up plumage, frequently in combination with dysphagia.
 </p>
</sec>
