<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The continental subspecies of the great cormorant 
 <italic class="italic">Phalacrocorax carbo sinensis</italic> has underwent one of the most greatest bird population booms and dispersals (along with the double‐crested cormorant 
 <italic class="italic">Ph. auritus</italic> in the U.S., Wires &amp; Cuthbert, 
 <xref rid="ece34348-bib-0082" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>) in less than three decades and is therefore an interesting model for testing these changes (Marion &amp; Le Gentil, 
 <xref rid="ece34348-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>). In Europe, the marine subspecies 
 <italic class="italic">Ph. c. carbo</italic> did not globally change its breeding distribution on the marine coasts of Iceland, Norway, the British Isles and northwestern France (with a newly described marine subspecies from Norway to France, 
 <italic class="italic">Ph. C. norvegicus,</italic> Marion &amp; Le Gentil, 
 <xref rid="ece34348-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>). In contrast, protection and the increase in food resources due to eutrophication of waters caused the continental 
 <italic class="italic">P. c. sinensis</italic> population to sharply increase. Once located in the refuge of the core area of the Baltic sea and the Netherlands, it extended to a large part of Europe (from around 5,000 breeding pairs in 1970 in northwest Europe to 191,000 in 2012, Van Eerden &amp; Munsterman, 
 <xref rid="ece34348-bib-0078" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1995</xref>; Marion, 
 <xref rid="ece34348-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1997a</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ece34348-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014b</xref>, Bregnballe et al. 
 <xref rid="ece34348-bib-0803" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>), and its wintering population increased concurrently from probably less than 15,000 individuals in 1970 to 600,000 in 2013 in northwest Europe and north Africa. These wintering birds generated new breeding populations within the wintering area (De Juana &amp; Garcia, 
 <xref rid="ece34348-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Marion, 
 <xref rid="ece34348-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1997a</xref>), probably in relation to progressive saturation of the northern native breeding areas (Marion &amp; Le Gentil, 
 <xref rid="ece34348-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>).
</p>
