<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">However, similar to other studies, this study has several limitations. First, data on air quality are analyzed for 120 cities that covers one-third of major cities in China. Therefore, findings from the study remain limited to its generalizability to the whole cities in China. Second, the associations of API with temperature, weekly and seasonal changes, and total mortality rates were analyzed cross-sectionally. Further analysis using prospective cohort data is needed to test the cause–effect association between exposure and outcomes. However, there is no reason to suspect that risk of mortality precedes high API. Furthermore, in the analysis of the time-lag effect between exposure and health outcomes, our results showed a positive correlation between mean API measured in 2007–2010 and mortality in 2012 and 2013. Several other studies have also demonstrated a significant association between air pollution and human health (
 <xref rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>–
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">56</xref>). Findings from our analyses are consistent with previous findings and support that there is a positive and significant correlation between air quality and total mortality (
 <xref rid="B57" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>). Third, we are unable to examine the association between individual pollutants and total mortality because data for the individual air pollutants are not available from China national report system. Nevertheless, because API is a standardized sum weighted indicator of five major air pollutants (particular matters, SO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>, NO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>, CO, and O
 <sub class="sub">3</sub>), and residents are not exposed to just a single air pollutant in the real world, API can be an efficient and valid indicator for the total burden of air pollution. Fourth, the associations between city-level API and health outcomes were analyzed using ecological analysis approach, a potential ecological fallacy may occur. Fifth, data for cities that had both measures of API and climatic factors were only available from 49 cities, this relative small sample size reduced the statistical power when we tested the association between API and mortality with adjustment for climatic factors (data not shown). The statistical powers were further reduced when we adjusted more covariates (SES, population density, and percentage of residents aged 60 and older). Certainly further studies with a large sample size are needed. Sixth, detail data on air quality and health outcomes remain limited from China. For example, city-level disease-specific mortality data and mortality rates by months and seasons are not publicly available. Therefore, we applied total mortality rate as the health outcome in this study. It is clear that further collaborative studies are needed to extend and confirm the current findings.
</p>
