<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par13" class="p">All our observations are explained by our wCTU model which provided a good fit to the sex ratios produced under a wide range of treatments (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3c</xref>), from constant temperature and artificially simplistic oscillations (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1a–m</xref>) to the natural conditions and profiles modified by our mathematical affine transformation (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref>). Further, the wCTU model accounted for the effect of all viable temperatures (including those outside of the linear range of development). Importantly, the wCTU model performed better than the alternative models on which it is based, such as the CTE
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>
 </sup> or CTU
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">24</xref>
 </sup> models (which apply only to temperatures in the linear developmental phase), and even the non-linear CTE model (nlCTEs)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">14</xref>
 </sup>, all of which provided a poor fit for the full range of sex ratios when used separately (results not shown). The wCTU results revealed the potential mechanistic basis of the effects of thermal fluctuations on sex ratios and mortality in general, and of predicted climate change in particular. Namely, female (or male) determination occurs when a larger proportion of the development takes place at temperatures above (or below) the constant-pivotal temperature (the value that produces 1:1 sex ratios), which is ~28.5 °C for 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">picta</italic> used here (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3</xref>). And temperatures within the viable thermal range (VTR) have a stronger potency to induce femaleness or maleness the further they deviate from the pivotal value. Importantly, this potency is amplified (or dampened) by the effect that temperatures within the VTR have on developmental rate (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3a</xref>). For instance, because higher temperatures within the VTR accelerate development, 1 hr spent 2 °C above the pivotal temperature has a stronger feminizing effect than the masculinizing effect of 1 hr spent 2 °C below the pivotal temperature because more development accrues at the warmer than at the colder temperature
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>
 </sup> each hour. The wCTU model explains the feminization we observed under the NatMale-IA ±6 °C or NatMale-NE ±6 °C treatments. Namely, these profiles exposed embryos to temperatures in the lower range of, or below, the VTR which retard development (and contributed little or nil to accrued development). These treatments also exposed embryos to temperatures above the pivotal value with greater feminizing-potency, because they accelerate development (and thus contribute disproportionately to accrued development) (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2b</xref>). A similar phenomenon would describe why virtually only females developed under experiments with accentuated oscillations around the semiNatFem-IA female-producing thermal profile, where most embryonic development accrued during exposure to temperatures above the pivotal value. The wCTU model also explains the masculinization and higher (albeit partial) mortality reported when 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">picta</italic> eggs were incubated under cycles of 12 hrs at 36 °C followed by 12 hrs at 26 °C (average 31 °C)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">14</xref>
 </sup>, because 36 °C is predicted to induce little to no development (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3a</xref>) such that most embryogenesis ensued under the male-inducing 26 °C. Notably, embryos incubated under severe oscillations could experience extreme temperatures with little potency to induce sex determination and that could even be lethal because they deviate too far outside the VTR, or because exposure is too prolonged or too frequent. This appears to have caused the high mortality under the NatFem-ON ±6 °C treatment (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3d</xref>) which exposed embryos to temperatures that exceeded the highest (42 °C) and lowest (10 °C) temperatures of all other profiles (which may be lethal when sustained for too long or repeatedly), and to temperatures that depress or halt development even if they are not lethal for short periods (11–20 °C and 36–41 °C). Our wCTU model may be applicable to other TSD taxa, provided that it is modified by adjusting the parameters to species- or population-specific values.
</p>
