<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Kiefer et al., argued that, despite the existence of considerable research and planning with regard to the public health and environmental aspects of climate change, there is little effort focused on its effects on workers’ health and safety [
 <xref rid="B4-ijerph-16-03458" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>]. Workers, especially those working outdoors, are often the first to be exposed to the effects of climate change. They may be exposed for longer durations and at greater intensities which in the long run could result in the increase in prevalence and severity of known occupational hazards and exposures, and also the emergence of new ones. Previous research has shown that climate change can contribute to a decrease in the ozone layer and affect UV radiation levels at the surface of the earth. This can cause outdoor workers to experience more frequent, intense, and longer exposure to UV radiation, resulting in an increased risk of adverse eye effects, skin cancer, and possibly immune dysfunction [
 <xref rid="B4-ijerph-16-03458" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B5-ijerph-16-03458" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="B6-ijerph-16-03458" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>]. In addition, exposure to higher temperatures with more frequent periods of heat may result in greater heat stress, potentially leading to more cases of heat-related illnesses such as heat stroke, heat exhaustion, increased susceptibility to chemical exposure, and fatigue. Exposure to increased temperature can also result in reduced vigilance creating an increased risk of injury or lapses in safety. Furthermore, elevated temperatures can increase levels of air pollution, including ground-level ozone; outdoor workers have longer exposure to such air pollutants, which are linked to chronic health effects, such as respiratory diseases and allergic reaction [
 <xref rid="B7-ijerph-16-03458" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-ijerph-16-03458" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-ijerph-16-03458" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-ijerph-16-03458" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-ijerph-16-03458" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-ijerph-16-03458" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>].
</p>
