<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The report compiled by TUC [
 <xref rid="B13-ijerph-16-03458" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] has acknowledged that climate changes are expected to bring about both risks and opportunities to every sector of the country’s economy. In the energy sector, for instance, the direct impact of climate change could result in power plant flooding, leading to power cuts affecting other economic sectors and on the demand side, energy use for indoor cooling during the summer is expected to increase. Workers required to respond to problems that may arise could be placed at higher risk during these extreme weather events. Seven categories of climate-related hazards—increased ambient temperature, air pollution, ultraviolet exposure, extreme weather, vector-borne diseases and expanded habitats, industrial transitions and emerging industries and changes in the built environment at work—have been the subject of climate change assessments on the health of outdoor workers in several studies [
 <xref rid="B4-ijerph-16-03458" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B8-ijerph-16-03458" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B9-ijerph-16-03458" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="B10-ijerph-16-03458" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B11-ijerph-16-03458" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-ijerph-16-03458" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. There has been an increasing concern around the impact of extreme heat on both indoors and outdoors workers health and safety due to increased heat and climate change [
 <xref rid="B14-ijerph-16-03458" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-ijerph-16-03458" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-ijerph-16-03458" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-ijerph-16-03458" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. As pointed out by St. Louis and Hess [
 <xref rid="B18-ijerph-16-03458" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] the health impact of climate change will not be distributed uniformly, but rather it is expected that the distribution patterns of health burdens will be increased around the globe.
</p>
