<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analyses</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We constructed general linear mixed models (GLMMs) with normal error and identity link, using PROC MIXED in SAS 9.0 (SAS Institute, Cary, NC, USA) to confirm the lack of differences in basic breeding parameters (laying date, hatching date and clutch size) between species and years, including their interactions.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We proceeded with Wilcoxon matched pairs and Student’s paired t tests when appropriate to analyze between-year differences in noctuid and tortricid biomasses within the eight forests and overall. These statistical analyses were performed with Statistica v.10 (Statsoft, Tulsa, OK, USA). Data are expressed as mean ± standard error (SE).</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We constructed a GLMM (normal error and identity link) as implemented in the “lmer” procedure of the R package “lme4”
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b41" href="#b41">41</a> to investigate which variables contributed to explaining the biomass of noctuids in the nestling diet. We included as categorical explanatory variables: ‘year’ (because 2012 and 2013 differed in caterpillar availability, see Results) and ‘species’ (blue tit 
  <span class="italic">vs</span>. great tit). As continuous explanatory variables we used noctuid availability (the mean biomass of noctuids per survey in that forest on the date of filming), and filming hour. Forest identity was included as a random factor. Here and hereafter, we included the interaction terms between categorical variables, and between each categorical variable and each continuous explanatory variable. We used the best subset procedure and second-order AIC corrected for small sample sizes (AICc) to identify the set of models best explaining the biomass of noctuids in the nestling diet, as implemented in “dredge” and “model.avg” procedures of the R package “MuMIn”
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b42" href="#b42">42</a>. To evaluate the relative explanatory power of competing best models, we calculated Akaike weights (ωi). Here we present those model subsets whose weights sum ≥0.95. In order to estimate the relative importance of the variables included in the best models, we calculated the sum of Akaike weights of the models where these variables were included
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b43" href="#b43">43</a>. We repeated the same schema to evaluate the factors contributing to the biomass of tortricids in the nestling diet, but including tortricid availability as a continuous explanatory variable instead of noctuid availability.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To examine the role of different factors on HA we constructed a GLMM with the following categorical explanatory variables: year, species and ‘female age’ (yearling 
  <span class="italic">vs</span>. adult; because female age could influence HA
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b25" href="#b25">25</a>). As continuous explanatory variables we included ‘hatching date’, ‘female mass’ (because smaller females could not effectively cover the whole clutch
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b19" href="#b19">19</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b44" href="#b44">44</a>) and both noctuid and tortricid availabilities. Forest and female identities were included as random factors.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To examine the role of different factors in RWD, we constructed a GLMM with year and species as categorical explanatory variables. As continuous explanatory variables we included HA and both noctuid and tortricid biomasses in the diet. Forest identity was again included as a random factor.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We evaluated the factors contributing to ‘mean nestling weight’ with a GLMM with year and species as categorical variables and HA, RWD and both noctuid and tortricid biomasses in the diet as continuous predictors. Forest identity was included as a random factor.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To analyze the factors influencing the fledging rate we assessed a GLMM with a binomial distribution and logit-link function as implemented in the “glmer” procedure of the R package “lme4”
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b41" href="#b41">41</a>. We included year and species as categorical variables and HA and RWD as continuous variables. Forest identity was included as a random factor.
 </p>
</sec>
