<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Building on previous work
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9" class="xref">9</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11" class="xref">11</xref>, we strengthen detection and attribution conclusions on the influence of externally forced signals of anthropogenic influences, but more importantly also from natural external changes, simultaneously on observed upper-ocean temperatures. We present the first multi-model detection study employing isotherm diagnostics of subsurface ocean temperature changes for the past sixty years. As air-sea heat flux changes are the main mechanism by which the anthropogenically-induced and natural external factors influence upper-ocean temperature changes, using a fixed isotherm as an alternative to a fixed depth for analyses aids to better isolate the surface forcing from changes due to ocean dynamical changes. The combination of incomplete observations and changes in ocean advection can potentially confound our efforts in accurately estimating the rate of global ocean heat uptake. However, using an isothermal approach, we improve the signal-to-noise ratio, where noise refers to both small-scale phenomena, such as internal waves and eddies, but also presumably a proportion of large-scale coherent climate variability, such as that associated with major climate modes. The isotherm framework helps to remove some of the large-scale noise from the observations (i.e. the observed phase of climate modes that are generally of a different phase in climate model simulations). Overall, the reduction of both high and low frequency intrinsic variability in temperature above the 14 °C isotherm (T
 <sub class="sub">14°C</sub>) allows a more uniform trend to emerge
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9" class="xref">9</xref>. Here, using a much larger ensemble of forced and unforced simulations from the latest generation of climate models and a fixed isotherm, we obtain a significant identification of both ANT and NAT fingerprints in the observed upper-ocean temperatures changes. This confirms previous results using only a single-model ensemble
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11" class="xref">11</xref>. It is shown that the externally forced signals for the fixed isotherm analysis (T
 <sub class="sub">14°C</sub>) are not affected by the use of an ensemble of an earlier generation of models (i.e. CMIP3 compared to CMIP5), however the NAT signal is not detected in the fixed depth analysis of CMIP3 (i.e. T
 <sub class="sub">220m</sub>). The availability of individual forcing simulations may be one reason for the different detection results (i.e. linear additive calculations of ANT and NAT, see Methods for details) or the fact that the larger ensemble size for CMIP5 compared to CMIP3 enhances the positive identification of the NAT signal, as is the case when compared to a single-model analysis
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11" class="xref">11</xref>, and the CMIP5 models contain more sophisticated aerosol schemes. Spatial trend maps and results from the optimal fingerprint analysis highlight the fact that the CMIP5 models tend to overestimate the upper-ocean warming during the last sixty years. However in poorly sampled regions, such as the Southern Hemisphere, it has been revealed that the observed changes are significantly underestimated
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28" class="xref">28</xref>, leading to such differences with the CMIP5 MMEM.
</p>
