<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par14" class="p">Tidal restoration to avoid CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> emissions is a relatively new concept for Blue Carbon management, and warrants consideration within GHG markets and emission offset programs, national and local-level efforts to reduce emissions, and national GHG inventories based on IPCC guidance. Within international climate change treaty negotiations there has been increasing emphasis on co-benefits accruing from GHG mitigation actions that involve improved landscape management, including forests, soils and potentially coastal and marine ecosystems. In 2013, the International Panel on Climate Change released the 2013 Supplement to the 2006 IPCC Guidelines for National GHG Inventories: Wetlands
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">18</xref>
 </sup>, to guide accounting of emissions and management of wetland soils. The Supplement includes guidance on CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> emissions for drained wetlands, but does not consider GHG emissions from impoundments in general, nor freshened or impounded wetlands due to tidal restriction. The U.S. has recently completed the first national inventory worldwide to include coastal wetlands in a National GHG Inventory, and the UN Framework Convention on Climate Change has asked countries to provide feedback on experiences with application of the Supplement, to inform future expansion of the accounting guidance where science is available. The analysis presented here indicates that tidally restricted wetlands meet the primary criteria for inventoried ecosystems in that they are managed landscapes, with emissions and sinks of substantial magnitude and rate of change. If other countries ultimately follow suit, then inclusion of those emissions in the U.S. Inventory will promote widespread recognition and management of the issue, and justify development of CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> EF for tidal restrictions and impoundments in IPCC guidance for GHG inventories. Note that since ecological restoration through tidal reconnection has been a widespread practice in some parts of the world, restorations that were conducted since the baseline year, typically 1990, may represent considerable, but as yet unrecognized, emissions reductions.
</p>
