<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par18" class="p">There is ongoing debate regarding the value, in terms of addressing climate change, of reducing CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> emissions vs CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> emissions, and the debate is relevant to selection of a GWP value for CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub>, and crediting timeframe, in C markets and offsets. Though there is not a simple answer, it is clear that aggressive reduction in emissions of CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> and other short-lived climate pollutants (SLCP) can reduce the rate of increase in global temperature during the current century, and can reduce peak temperature if coupled with rapid elimination of CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> emissions
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">38</xref>
 </sup>. Further, it has been shown that, although CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> is a short-lived climate pollutant, during the time that it resides in the atmosphere, a portion of the heat that it traps within the biosphere will be retained in oceans and contribute to sea level rise for several centuries
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" class="xref">39</xref>
 </sup>. However, if actions to reduce emissions of SLCP result in delayed reductions in CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> emissions, then higher peak temperatures will result
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">38</xref>
 </sup>. Therefore, society is likely to benefit most from simultaneous, but separate, efforts to reduce both CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> and SLCP emissions, to manage both short-term and long-term climate change. Utilization of offsets and emissions trading programs therefore requires relative evaluation of pollutants with distinct interactions with climate. Solutions might be to limit maximum utilization of offsets in C markets, as is done in California’s Cap and Trade Program
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" class="xref">40</xref>
 </sup>, or to develop separate reduction and trading programs for CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> and SLCP. For instance, the state of Massachusetts has specific emissions reduction goals for natural gas transmission
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" class="xref">41</xref>
 </sup>, New Zealand has separate targets for methane reductions in their Intended Nationally Determined Contribution
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" class="xref">42</xref>
 </sup>, and many national and subnational governments have programs to reduce methane emissions from agricultural sources
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" class="xref">43</xref>
 </sup>. As described in the present study, degraded tidal wetlands can be significant sources of both CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> and CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub>, while intact wetlands are generally a strong CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> sink. Thus, wetland management can contribute to management of both short and long-lived climate pollutants.
</p>
