<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec17" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An example of the approach for the ice production-ocean entrainment feedback</div>
 <p id="Par51" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We illustrate the methodology with the ice production–entrainment feedback
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>
  </span>. For this negative feedback, (1) the perturbation is a given amount of ice production, (2) the reference variable is ice thickness, (3) the full system is the sea ice plus ocean column with the entrainment process, and (4) the reference system is the sea ice plus ocean column but without entrainment. The intensity of this feedback can then be evaluated using the ratio
  <div id="Equ3" class="disp-formula">
   <span class="label">2</span>
   <div class="alternatives">
    <span id="M7" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$\upgamma _\theta = {\textstyle{{{\mathrm{Total}}{\kern 2pt} {\mathrm{ice}}{\kern 2pt} {\mathrm{thickness}}{\kern 2pt} {\mathrm{changes}} - {\mathrm{Ice}}{\kern 2pt} {\mathrm{thickness}}{\kern 2pt} {\mathrm{changes}}{\kern 2pt} {\mathrm{without}}{\kern 2pt} {\mathrm{entrainment}}} \over {{\mathrm{Total}}{\kern 2pt} {\mathrm{ice}}{\kern 2pt} {\mathrm{thickness}}{\kern 2pt} {\mathrm{changes}}}}}$$\end{document}</span>
    <div id="M8" display="block" class="math">
     <div class="msub">
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mi">γ</span>
      </div>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mi">θ</span>
      </div>
     </div>
     <span class="mo">=</span>
     <div class="mfrac">
      <div class="mrow">
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">Total</span>
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">ice</span>
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">thickness</span>
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">changes</span>
       <span class="mo">-</span>
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">Ice</span>
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">thickness</span>
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">changes</span>
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">without</span>
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">entrainment</span>
      </div>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">Total</span>
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">ice</span>
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">thickness</span>
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">changes</span>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="41467_2018_4173_Article_Equ3.gif" position="anchor" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par52" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Despite a different form, this expression is strictly equivalent to the original formulation proposed in ref. 
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>
  </span> and used for Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a> (see Supplementary Note 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a> for the demonstration).
 </p>
 <p id="Par53" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As the mixed layer deepens, it entrains water with increasing temperature (since temperature increases with depth) and the heat input grows. Consequently, the absolute value of the feedback factor 
  <span class="italic">γ</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">θ</span>
  </sub> increases with ice formation (meaning that its value decreases, since it is a negative feedback) until the end of winter (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>). This non-linear behavior can be illustrated using a simple analytical model as shown in Supplementary Note 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">3 and Supplementary Fig. 3</a>.
  <div id="Fig5" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 5</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Evolution of the ice production-entrainment feedback factor as a function of ice production. For each value of ice production, the entrainment is computed from the January–February 1990–2005 mean temperature and salinity profiles
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR115" href="#CR115">115</a>
     </span> assuming a mixed layer deepening restoring the static stability of the water column after the brine release. It is shown here for a Weddell Sea location typically covered by ice in winter (near 30°W, 65°S). The strength of the pycnocline is thus evaluated in summer but it must be measured below the layer close to the surface that is warmed above freezing point temperature if sea ice completely melts, as the heat in this layer is removed quickly in fall when the temperature drops and is not involved in the ice production-ocean entrainment feedback
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2018_4173_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e2039" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par54" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In practice, it is usually not possible to completely quantify all the dependencies of a non-linear, spatially variable feedback factor. This is why it has been suggested to select a prescribed perturbation representative of the condition of interest, similarly to the classical analysis of radiative forcing in terms of doublings of atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub> concentrations (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>). For the ice production-ocean entrainment feedback, we propose to evaluate 
  <span class="italic">γ</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">θ</span>
  </sub> by considering the response to a standardized perturbation corresponding to an increase in sea ice thickness of 10 cm (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>). The number of observed profiles being much higher in summer, the feedback parameter is evaluated from data collected during this season. It is clear that the corresponding values of the feedback factors are not universally valid but they provide a standard benchmark for comparisons and analyses.
 </p>
</sec>
