<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Feedbacks in polar regions</div>
 <sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Radiative feedbacks</div>
  <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The temperature feedback represents the changes in infrared (longwave) radiative fluxes due to changes in surface and tropospheric temperatures (Table 
   <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>). It can be decomposed into a Planck feedback due to radiation changes caused by vertically uniform warming of the surface and troposphere and a lapse rate feedback due to vertically non-uniform warming
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
   </span>. The negative Planck feedback is the climate system’s basic response to forcing that drives the system to a new equilibrium temperature. Due to the dependence of blackbody radiation on temperature, the Planck feedback, or in other words the increase in outgoing longwave radiation per unit of local warming, is less negative in polar regions than at lower latitudes
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
   </span>. While the lapse rate feedback is negative in the tropics, it is often positive in polar regions because stable stratification, especially in non-summer months, suppresses vertical mixing and warming remains largely confined to a thin near-surface layer
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>, 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>
   </span>.
   <div id="Tab1" class="table-wrap">
    <span class="label">Table 1</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Key radiative and non-radiative feedbacks in polar regions that are related to the atmosphere, ocean, sea ice, ice sheets and land surfaces and can be measured using a feedback factor</p>
    </div>
    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
     <thead>
      <tr>
       <th/>
       <th>Name</th>
       <th>Description</th>
       <th>Measure</th>
       <th>Reference(s)</th>
      </tr>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <tr>
       <td rowspan="7">Radiative feedbacks</td>
       <td>Planck (−)</td>
       <td>Higher surface and atmospheric temperatures increase outgoing longwave radiation, avoiding runaway warming</td>
       <td>Change of TOA flux due to temperature change at constant lapse rate divided by surface temperature change</td>
       <td>
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>–
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>,
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
       </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Lapse rate (+ in Arctic, close to 0 in Antarctic)</td>
       <td>In a warmer world and at high latitudes, stable stratification conditions in the lower troposphere result in a larger warming of the lower than of the upper troposphere, leading to a smaller increase in outgoing longwave radiation compared to vertically uniform warming, and thus to further warming</td>
       <td>Change of TOA flux due to lapse rate changes divided by surface temperature change (normalized by Planck feedback)</td>
       <td>
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>,
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>
       </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Surface albedo (+)</td>
       <td>Melting ice and snow lowers surface albedo, leading to increased absorption of shortwave radiation and amplified warming</td>
       <td>Change of TOA flux due to surface albedo change divided by surface temperature change (normalized by Planck feedback)</td>
       <td>
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>,
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>,
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>,
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101" href="#CR101">101</a>
       </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Water vapor (+)</td>
       <td>In a warming climate, the amount of water vapor in the atmosphere increases, which amplifies the greenhouse effect and leads to further warming</td>
       <td>Change of TOA flux due to water vapor change divided by surface temperature change (normalized by Planck feedback)</td>
       <td>
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>–
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
       </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Cloud (+/−) Two examples are provided below</td>
       <td>Warming of the atmosphere leads to changes in the amount and characteristics of clouds, modifying the radiative balance. The cloud contribution can be decomposed in several ways, two examples being given below</td>
       <td>Change of TOA flux due to changes in cloud properties divided by surface temperature change (normalized by Planck feedback)</td>
       <td>
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>,
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>–
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
       </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Example 1: Cloud-sea ice (+ in non-summer months, close to 0 in summer)</td>
       <td>Decreased sea ice extent in non-summer months results in greater cloud cover and increased downwelling longwave radiation, leading to further sea ice loss</td>
       <td>Change of TOA flux due to changes in cloud amount and opacity resulting from varying sea ice concentration divided by surface temperature change</td>
       <td>
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>–
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
       </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Example 2: Cloud optical depth (−)</td>
       <td>As the climate warms, the fraction of liquid water in mixed-phase clouds increases, resulting in higher cloud albedo, more reflection of shortwave radiation and reduced warming</td>
       <td>Change of TOA flux due to changes in cloud optical depth divided by surface temperature change</td>
       <td>
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>,
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>,
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>
       </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td rowspan="6">Non-radiative feedbacks</td>
       <td>Ice production–entrainment (−) (mostly active in Southern Ocean)</td>
       <td>Brine rejection during sea ice formation induces an ocean mixed layer deepening that brings to the surface warmer water from deeper levels, melting a part of the ice initially formed and inhibiting further ice production.</td>
       <td>Ratio of the sea ice melt due to the entrainment of warmer water in the mixed layer to the initial ice formation</td>
       <td>
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>,
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>
       </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Ice production–ocean heat storage (+) (mostly active in Southern Ocean)</td>
       <td>Anomalous sea ice production induces vertical exchanges of salt, a higher stratification, storage of heat at depth and finally lower oceanic heat fluxes that favor further ice production.</td>
       <td>Ratio of the latent heat associated to ice production to the heat content change of the ocean subsurface layer</td>
       <td>
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>,
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>
       </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Ice growth–thickness (−)</td>
       <td>Thin sea ice grows more rapidly than thick sea ice due to its higher heat conduction, dampening the response to an initial decrease imposed by a perturbation.</td>
       <td>Normalized difference in the thickness response to an energetic perturbation with and without thickness dependence of the ice growth rate</td>
       <td>
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>,
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>
       </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Surface mass balance–elevation (+) (mostly active in Greenland Ice Sheet)</td>
       <td>Increased air temperature leads to ice melting, which lowers the surface elevation of the ice sheet, hence leading to ice exposure to warmer air temperatures and further ice melting.</td>
       <td>Ratio of the additional sea level contribution due to this feedback to the sea level contribution without feedback</td>
       <td>
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>,
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>
       </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Ice shelf melting sea ice (−) (mostly active in Southern Ocean)</td>
       <td>Ocean warming leads to ice shelf melting, which releases freshwater into the ocean and reduces vertical mixing. This results in sea ice expansion and reduced ocean warming.</td>
       <td>Ratio of the additional change in sea ice extent caused by this feedback to the total change in extent without feedback</td>
       <td>
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">63</a>,
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" href="#CR64">64</a>
       </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td>Marine ice sheet instability (+) (mostly active in West Antarctic Ice Sheet)</td>
       <td>An initial retreat in the grounding line position of a marine ice sheet on an upward-sloping bed towards the ocean leads to increased ice discharge, ice thinning and further retreat.</td>
       <td>Ratio of the additional sea level contribution due to this feedback to the sea level contribution without feedback</td>
       <td>
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>–
        <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">60</a>
       </td>
      </tr>
     </tbody>
    </table>
    <div class="table-wrap-foot">
     <p>The proposed selection is illustrative rather than exhaustive. The sign in the first column indicates whether the feedback is positive or negative in polar regions</p>
    </div>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As the surface warms, additional water vapor amplifies the greenhouse effect and induces further warming
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>, 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
   </span>. This water vapor feedback is largest in the tropics where the climatological temperature is higher and the increase in water vapor is at its maximum. In polar regions, the positive water vapor feedback is weaker than in the tropics but it still plays a relevant role in the polar response to the forcing
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>, 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>, 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
  <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The surface albedo feedback is a first-order visible (shortwave) positive radiative climate feedback mechanism in polar regions
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>–
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
   </span>. As the climate warms, snow and ice cover melt, exposing underlying surfaces that typically have much lower albedos. This leads to an increased absorption of shortwave radiation by the surface, and as a result amplifies the initial warming. When melting, the snow covering Arctic sea ice contributes to forming melt ponds. increasing the absorption of solar radiation and amplifying the surface albedo feedback
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
   </span>. Melt ponds do not form in the Southern Ocean as surface melting is very limited there, providing an illustration of different ways snow and ice interactions affect the surface albedo feedback
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>, 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
  <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Clouds influence the heat balance of the Earth by affecting the radiative fluxes in both visible and infrared bands and are involved in a variety of feedbacks
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>, 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>, 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
   </span>. The sign of any cloud feedback depends on the balance of shortwave cooling and longwave heating by the clouds. Cloud feedbacks are the most uncertain of all the radiative feedbacks as the cloud radiative effect depends on several factors that can be modified by the initial response to the perturbation
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>, 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>–
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
   </span>. Among all mechanisms involved, two polar-specific cloud feedback examples are listed in Table 
   <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>: the cloud sea-ice feedback
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>–
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
   </span> and the cloud optical depth feedback
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>, 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>, 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>
   </span>. When sea ice melts and new open water is exposed, surface turbulent heat fluxes can increase humidity in the lower atmosphere and increase low-level clouds. During polar night, increasing low cloud increases downwelling longwave radiation, leading to further sea ice loss and thus to a positive feedback. Observational evidence shows that this cloud-sea ice feedback operates in non-summer months in both the Arctic
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>, 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
   </span> and the Antarctic
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
   </span>. The cloud optical depth feedback operates both at mid- and high- latitudes. Cloud liquid particles are smaller than cloud ice particles, and are therefore more efficient at reflecting solar radiation back to space. As the climate warms, the total amount of cloud water in mixed phase clouds increases, which increases the amount of reflected solar radiation (i.e., increase the planetary albedo), acting as a negative feedback
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
   </span>. At the same time, the fraction of cloud water that is liquid also increases, enhancing the effect of this cloud optical depth feedback (Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>). Climate models robustly show this feedback
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
   </span> but in a manner that is stronger than implied by observations
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>, 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>
   </span> —in many cases due to excessive cloud ice in the present-day modeled climate
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>–
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Feedbacks related to sea ice and the ocean</div>
  <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As the magnitude of some radiative feedbacks is modulated by processes that may appear hidden in their overall evaluation, focused analyses have been proposed to reveal elements specifically related to sea ice and ocean. For instance, the surface albedo feedback is more efficient for thin than for thick sea ice as a similar change in thickness induced by a given perturbation will lead to a larger increase in the open water area and thus a larger change in albedo. This has led to the definition of the open water formation efficiency as the percent open water formation per cm of ice melt over the melt season
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
  <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Some other feedbacks are not directly related to radiative processes. For example, basal sea ice growth rate is largely driven by heat conduction, which varies as the inverse of sea ice thickness: thin ice grows much faster than thick ice
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>
   </span>. At the same time, sea ice melt rate is nearly independent of ice thickness. This leads to the negative ice growth-thickness feedback. When a positive radiative perturbation is applied to the sea ice surface energy balance leading to an initial ice thinning, ice formation in winter is enhanced so that the ice adjusts its thickness to match the new growth rates to the new melting rates
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>
   </span>, resulting in a new equilibrium for the sea ice thickness. As the thermal insulation power of snow is even more efficient than that of sea ice, its influence on the ice growth-thickness feedback is important, but not fully quantified due to the complex relationship between snow depth and sea-ice thickness
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
  <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Because of the large heat fluxes at the ocean–ice interface in the Southern Ocean, feedback analyses there have often focused on the interactions between ocean and sea ice. In the ice-covered parts of the Southern Ocean, the stability of the upper water column is controlled by salinity, with the ocean temperature and salinity increasing with depth below the surface mixed layer (the ocean layer that has a nearly homogeneous density). In winter, when brine is released by sea ice formation, surface mixed layer density increases, inducing a mixed layer deepening and the entrainment of relatively warm water into the surface oceanic layer. This warm water reduces ice formation and can even melt ice, which partly compensates for the initial ice formation, leading to a negative ice production–entrainment feedback
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>, 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>
   </span>
  </p>
  <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ice production–entrainment feedback is acting at the seasonal scale but the magnitude of the ice–ocean flux can also be modulated at inter-annual to decadal timescales, leading to the positive ice production heat-storage feedback
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>, 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>
   </span>. If ice production is very large during a particular year, the mixed layer will be deeper and the salt released by ice formation will be distributed over a larger depth range. In summer, the mixing is weaker and the freshwater input due to ice melting will be spread over a shallower layer, leading to a net downward vertical salt transport. This can restrain the vertical exchanges in the water column the subsequent winter, leading to less heat transfer to the surface and more heat storage at depth. Finally, the weaker heat flux at the ice–ocean interface would favor additional ice formation, leading to a positive feedback amplifying the initial perturbation. The heat storage at depth can also be reinforced by a net freshwater input at the surface (due for instance to a net transport of sea ice to the region) that further stabilizes the water column.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Feedbacks related to land surfaces and ice sheets</div>
  <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">At low and mid-latitudes, a drying of the soils in response to an initial temperature rise can amplify the warming as the evapotranspiration that normally cools the surface is reduced
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>
   </span>. This positive soil moisture–temperature feedback is less active at high latitudes but, despite the low temperatures, evapotranspiration strongly contributes to moderate the summer warming over land
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
  <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ice sheets, glaciers and snow cover over land provide key components to the surface albedo feedback
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>–
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
   </span>. They also give rise to a number of specific feedback mechanisms. Three important ones are discussed here. Compared to the feedbacks mainly involving the atmosphere and sea ice, ice sheets generally, but not exclusively, play a role on longer time scales. In the positive surface mass balance–elevation feedback, increased air temperature leads to ice melting, which lowers the surface elevation of the ice sheet, exposing the ice to warmer air temperatures and thus further melting
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>, 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>
   </span>. This positive feedback is mostly relevant for the Greenland ice sheet where surface melting is substantial, while currently the Antarctic ice sheet hardly experiences it due to very low surface temperature.
  </p>
  <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The marine ice sheet instability has the potential to destabilize large ice sheet regions
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>–
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">60</a>
   </span>. The stability of a marine ice sheet such as the West Antarctic Ice Sheet is determined by the position of the grounding line, i.e., the boundary between the grounded ice sheet and the floating ice shelf. If it is located on a bedrock sloping downward toward the interior of the ice sheet, an initial retreat of the grounding line, for instance due to basal ice melting, leads to an increase in ice discharge, which results in a further retreat of the grounding line inland until a new stable position is reached. Rapid changes in ice sheets may also be linked to the acceleration of the ice transport due to basal lubrication caused by meltwater penetration at the bed or to breakup of the ice shelves because of a weakening of the ice due to surface melting
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">61</a>, 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" href="#CR62">62</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
  <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another feedback mainly acting in the Southern Ocean is related to the interactions between floating ice shelves, sea ice and the surrounding ocean. A subsurface Southern Ocean warming leads to increased basal ice shelf melting, and the upper ocean layers get fresher due to the resulting cold freshwater input. This results in lower heat flux from the ocean interior to the surface, sea ice expansion and reduced ocean surface warming, providing a negative ice shelf melting sea ice feedback
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">63</a>, 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" href="#CR64">64</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Non-local feedbacks and feedbacks involving other components of the climate system</div>
  <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While this Perspective focuses on feedbacks that act through physical processes in polar regions (Table 
   <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>, Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>), we should mention that many other feedback processes exist, some of which involve biological processes and biogeochemical cycles
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" href="#CR65">65</a>–
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" href="#CR68">68</a>
   </span>. One example is the bio-optical feedback, which occurs when climate warming and sea ice retreat in the Arctic Ocean lead to intense phytoplankton blooms
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" href="#CR69">69</a>
   </span>. These blooms trap the penetrating solar heat flux at the ocean surface, which increases sea surface temperature. As a result, sea ice concentration decreases, which leads to enhanced absorption of solar energy into the ocean and further warming of the Arctic
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" href="#CR70">70</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
  <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The response to a perturbation also implies a redistribution of the energy between different latitudes. First, the warming of the tropics under greenhouse gas forcing leads to enhanced poleward energy transport by the atmospheric circulation to higher latitudes, contributing to warming there
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71" href="#CR71">71</a>–
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75" href="#CR75">75</a>
   </span>. This indicates a coupling between radiative feedbacks and atmospheric heat transport
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74" href="#CR74">74</a>, 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76" href="#CR76">76</a>, 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77" href="#CR77">77</a>
   </span>. Moreover, radiative feedbacks at low latitudes may influence polar warming through their effect on poleward energy transport, while changes in polar regions may affect dynamics in the lower latitudes
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78" href="#CR78">78</a>
   </span>. This is an area of ongoing research, and it is not yet clear if the response of the system has a direct impact on the original perturbation itself such that a closed feedback loop can be identified.
  </p>
  <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Second, the ocean heat transport has been found to strongly shape polar climate change, with increased poleward heat transport into the Arctic
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79" href="#CR79">79</a>–
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81" href="#CR81">81</a>
   </span> and decreased poleward heat transport into the Southern Ocean
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>, 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79" href="#CR79">79</a>
   </span> under global warming. Here too, it is unclear whether these changes can be represented in terms of a closed feedback loop (e.g., sea ice thinning enhancing ocean heat transport into the Arctic
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81" href="#CR81">81</a>
   </span>) or should be classified as important drivers of polar climate change that cannot be expressed within a feedback framework.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
