<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec12" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Implications of correctly quantifying feedbacks</div>
 <p id="Par38" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The analysis and quantification of feedbacks have many potential applications. This is illustrated in this section by explaining how this can be used to understand the higher temperature changes expected in the Arctic compared to other regions, to perform a process-oriented evaluation of model behavior, and to reduce the uncertainty in projections.</p>
 <sec id="Sec13" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Polar amplification</div>
  <p id="Par39" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Overall, climate feedbacks are less stabilizing (i.e., feedback parameters are less negative or more positive) in polar regions than in the tropics. This explains the larger temperature changes experienced in polar regions in response to a perturbation (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>), a phenomenon referred to as polar amplification
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>, 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>, 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>, 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97" href="#CR97">97</a>
   </span>. For the climate changes projected for the 21st century, polar amplification is much stronger in the Arctic than in the Antarctic. In the Arctic, the large amplification mostly results from (1) a relatively large and positive lapse rate feedback, due to a different vertical distribution of the temperature change compared to the tropics; (2) a relatively weak negative Planck response, due to smaller blackbody emissions per unit warming at lower temperatures (Stefan–Boltzmann law); and (3) a large positive surface albedo feedback, due to the loss of high albedo snow and ice-covered surfaces, as well as a contribution from atmospheric heat transport (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3a</a>). In the Antarctic, both the weak Planck response and the positive surface albedo feedback induce polar amplification. Warming is damped relative to the Arctic due to a less positive lapse rate feedback, more negative cloud feedback, and strong ocean heat uptake in the Southern Ocean under transient warming (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3b</a>).
   <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Contributions of each feedback and atmospheric forcing to polar amplification. 
      <span class="bold">a</span> Arctic (60–90N) relative to tropics (30S–30N), and 
      <span class="bold">b</span> Antarctic (60–90S) relative to Arctic (60–90N) at year 100 of abrupt CO
      <sub>2</sub> quadrupling in climate models involved in the fifth phase of the Coupled Model Intercomparison Project (CMIP5). The feedbacks shown are the lapse rate (LR), surface albedo (A), water vapor (WV), cloud (C), and latitudinal variation in the Planck response (P’, local difference from its global-mean value 
      <span class="italic">λ</span>
      <sub>0</sub>); the additional energetic contributions shown are the CO
      <sub>2</sub> forcing (CO
      <sub>2</sub>), atmospheric heat transport convergence (ΔAHT) and ocean heat uptake (ΔOHU) (see method section). The feedbacks are expressed as warming contributions to the total temperature change
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="41467_2018_4173_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e1722" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p id="Par40" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Note that if feedbacks are defined using global mean rather than local surface temperature change, the Planck feedback appears strongly negative in the Arctic because the local temperature change exceeds the local mean. Additionally, the polar amplification has a large seasonal cycle, displaying over the Arctic a minimum in summer and a maximum in fall/winter. In summer, the influence of the large positive surface albedo feedback is compensated by a strong oceanic heat uptake and negative cloud feedbacks while in fall/winter the heat released by the ocean, the contribution of lapse rate feedback and cloud feedbacks induce a large warming
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>, 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98" href="#CR98">98</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec14" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Origin of model biases</div>
  <p id="Par41" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In polar regions, many studies have identified model strengths and weaknesses in reproducing observations
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>, 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>, 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>, 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99" href="#CR99">99</a>, 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100" href="#CR100">100</a>
   </span>. Yet, perhaps the most important challenge is identifying the climate system processes that must be represented in order to consider a model realistic enough for mechanistic studies and projections. More generally, simple comparisons between model results and observations do not allow estimating the origin of model biases or their impact. Process-based model evaluation offers the possibility of exploring the causes of discrepancies more deeply, identifying the links between various variables and ultimately suggesting model improvements
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>, 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>, 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101" href="#CR101">101</a>–
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103" href="#CR103">103</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
  <p id="Par42" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To illustrate this point, we compare the ice production–entrainment feedback in three existing simulations for all the sectors of the Southern Ocean with estimates derived from observations and a reanalysis (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>). A clear link is found between the value of the feedback factor and the amplitude of the seasonal cycle of ice volume: since the ice production–entrainment feedback is negative, it tends to damp the seasonal cycle; i.e., a stronger feedback corresponds to a weaker seasonal cycle. The spread across simulations and Antarctic sea ice regions in Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a> stresses the large sensitivity of the feedback to the ocean properties. As many climate models suffer from large biases in their representation of the vertical structure of the Southern Ocean, they are unlikely to predict this feedback accurately. For instance, the overestimation of the amplitude of the seasonal cycle of sea ice volume in the model CCSM4 is likely related to a too weak negative feedback and improvements in the representation of ocean properties, in particular of temperature and salinity below the surface layer, would reduce this bias.
   <div id="Fig4" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Amplitude of the sea ice volume seasonal cycle versus the ice production-entrainment feedback factor. The ice production-entrainment feedback factor 
      <span class="italic">γ</span>
      <sub>
       <span class="italic">θ</span>
      </sub> is defined as the ratio of the melting due to warm water entrainment to the initial ice formation
      <span class="sup">
       <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>
      </span>. The values are estimated over 1990–2005 for a standardized perturbation corresponding to an increase of 10 cm of sea ice. For both observational and model datasets, the evaluation of 
      <span class="italic">γ</span>
      <sub>
       <span class="italic">θ</span>
      </sub> is performed on the basis of temperature and salinity profiles in the Southern Ocean, averaged over January–February for the period 1990–2005. Values are represented by five crosses corresponding to five sectors of the Southern Ocean
      <span class="sup">
       <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR111" href="#CR111">111</a>
      </span>. Results for NEMO-LIM
      <span class="sup">
       <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR112" href="#CR112">112</a>
      </span>, CCSM4
      <span class="sup">
       <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR113" href="#CR113">113</a>
      </span>, and IPSL
      <span class="sup">
       <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR114" href="#CR114">114</a>
      </span> models are in colors. Estimates are given in black based on oceanic observations
      <span class="sup">
       <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR115" href="#CR115">115</a>
      </span> and the sea ice volume derived from a reanalysis
      <span class="sup">
       <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR116" href="#CR116">116</a>
      </span>. For all datasets, the plain circles correspond to the average of 
      <span class="italic">γ</span>
      <sub>
       <span class="italic">θ</span>
      </sub> and of the amplitude of the ice volume seasonal cycle over all sectors, and 
      <span class="italic">ρ</span> is the correlation coefficient between these two quantities
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="41467_2018_4173_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e1833" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec15" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Uncertainties in model projections</div>
  <p id="Par43" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One justification of the development of the radiative feedback framework is to determine the processes that can explain the range of model projections for a specific scenario of future changes in radiative forcing. As expected, the models displaying the largest surface temperature changes are the ones for which the radiative feedbacks have the largest (most positive) values. The same approach can be applied to the non-radiative feedbacks investigated here as they are related to the magnitude of the response to any type of perturbation.</p>
  <p id="Par44" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although it is better if a model is able to reproduce the observations with a bias that is as small as possible, it is not clear for many variables, such as the global mean temperature, that the response to a perturbation is a function of this bias
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR104" href="#CR104">104</a>
   </span>. In other words, there is no a priori reason to believe that a model which reproduces the present global mean temperature well will provide more reasonable projections of future climate than a model that has larger biases. Indeed, a model may have a global mean temperature close to observations due to compensations between many factors that may not necessarily balance in a projected climate
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR105" href="#CR105">105</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
  <p id="Par45" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The situation is distinctive for polar regions, where the feedbacks are strongly non-linear and thus state dependent. This provides an instructive way to interpret the range of model responses as a function of the value of some variables for present-day conditions
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106" href="#CR106">106</a>, 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR107" href="#CR107">107</a>
   </span>. Furthermore, it has been argued that a model displaying a more realistic mean state in polar regions will also have a better representation of key processes and thus will provide a more likely estimate of future climate changes than a model with larger biases. This has then been used to justify the selection of models based on their mean state
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR108" href="#CR108">108</a>, 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR109" href="#CR109">109</a>
   </span>. This idea appears useful in principle but is hard to generalize and is subject to criticism. In particular, it is not always clear to determine how to evaluate models, which variable should be used to select models, and if the currently available model sample is adequate to apply a meaningful selection. This has led to strong debate in the community about the justification of this approach, which may artificially reduce the uncertainty range by discarding model results that are as likely as the others
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR110" href="#CR110">110</a>
   </span>. We propose to use feedback quantification more extensively to evaluate model behavior, and foresee that this can contribute to more robust estimates of the likelihood of projections.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
