<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Limitations of the linear approach</div>
 <p id="Par33" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The standard radiative feedback framework assumes that the response of the system can be expressed as a linear function of the surface temperature. It is a very useful approximation but some processes cannot be expressed in terms of functions of single variables and the radiative feedback framework has to be adjusted to capture changes in the system not directly related to surface temperature
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91" href="#CR91">91</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92" href="#CR92">92</a>
  </span>. Moreover, assuming linearity in feedbacks fails in many cases, as can be expected for a system as complex as the Earth’s climate. For example, the magnitude of the climate feedback parameter 
  <span class="italic">λ</span> generally decreases with time in climate models after a rise in atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub> concentration, corresponding to increasing climate sensitivity as equilibrium is approached
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76" href="#CR76">76</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92" href="#CR92">92</a>
  </span>. 
  <span class="italic">λ</span> may also depend on the magnitude of the perturbation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87" href="#CR87">87</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93" href="#CR93">93</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95" href="#CR95">95</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par34" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The non-linearity of the feedbacks can be described in different ways. A simple definition will be used here: the feedback is non-linear if the feedback factor 
  <span class="italic">γ</span> is not constant. Non-linearities can be caused by several processes. The strength of the feedback can be a function of the state of the system. This state dependence can often be expressed as a time dependence when the state changes with time. Furthermore, the different processes controlling the response to a perturbation may have different time scales. Their relative contribution to local and global scale feedbacks may thus evolve leading to spatially or temporally non-constant feedback factors
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76" href="#CR76">76</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92" href="#CR92">92</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96" href="#CR96">96</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par35" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In polar regions, the presence of different phases of water implies that many feedback parameters display a particularly strong dependence on the state of the system near the freezing point and are thus highly non-linear. For instance, phase changes play an important role in polar clouds leading to non-linearities in the cloud feedback
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>
  </span>. Furthermore, feedbacks related to the cryosphere generally depend on the surface area covered by snow or ice. As temperatures rise, this area decreases and the feedback strength is reduced. This is illustrated
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87" href="#CR87">87</a>
  </span> in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a> for the surface albedo feedback in response to three consecutive doublings of CO
  <sub>2</sub> in the Community Climate System Model version 3 (CCSM3). At many latitudes, the value of the feedback factor is smaller for the third doubling (8 × CO
  <sub>2</sub>–4 × CO
  <sub>2</sub>) than it is for the first (2 × CO
  <sub>2</sub>–CNTL). Between 50°S and 60°S the feedback approaches zero for the third doubling, since the Southern Ocean is already ice-free at these latitudes in the 4xCO
  <sub>2</sub> climate, and no further melting can occur. On the other hand, the value of the feedback factor increases at northern high latitudes (75°N–90°N), as the sea ice edge retreats within the central Arctic at high warming.
  <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Nonlinearity in the surface albedo feedback factor for three consecutive doublings of CO
     <sub>2</sub>. The feedback factor, defined as the ratio of the magnitude of the albedo feedback on the Planck feedback, is calculated using the radiative kernel technique
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85" href="#CR85">85</a>
     </span> and zonal averages are plotted for three consecutive doublings of CO
     <sub>2</sub> concentrations in CCSM3. The global average feedback factor decreases
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87" href="#CR87">87</a>
     </span> from 0.097 for 2xCO
     <sub>2</sub>–CNTL to 0.053 for 8xCO
     <sub>2</sub>–4xCO
     <sub>2</sub>
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2018_4173_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e1618" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
