<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0095" class="p">However, political economic and agroecological contexts in contemporary SSA poorly resemble those of 1960s and 1970s Asia. In contrast to consistent national markets and robust state-led subsidy programs that facilitated Green Revolutions in India, for example, decades of neoliberal reforms in SSA have meant weakened state involvement in agriculture and dependence on erratic global markets (
 <xref rid="b0045" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bezner Kerr, 2012</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0125" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Dorward and Kydd, 2004</xref>). There is growing evidence that input-based agricultural intensification has done little to meet pro-poor development goals in SSA. Although aggregate crop yields may have increased in some places, national-level food production figures say little about local-level food access (
 <xref rid="b0050" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bezner Kerr, 2013</xref>). Technology-driven intensification policies appear to have done little to address longstanding unevenness in land and resource access among smallholders, resulting in exacerbated malnutrition and inequality among some rural communities while large-holders, urban populations, and agribusiness benefit (
 <xref rid="b0045" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bezner Kerr, 2012</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0330" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Moseley et al., 2010</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0335" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Moseley et al., 2015</xref>). Moreover, increased yields in rural areas do not guarantee the emergence of nonfarm employment opportunities (
 <xref rid="b9020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Haggblade, Hazell, &amp; Reardon, 2010</xref>) and increased commercial activity is not universally beneficial across the socially diverse range of smallholder farmers (
 <xref rid="b9030" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Clay, 2018b</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b9035" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gengenbach et al., 2018</xref>). To speak to the viability of intensification policies for pro-poor rural development in SSA, local-level research is needed to scrutinize links between intensification, yield increases and poverty reduction (
 <xref rid="b0005" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Abro, Bamlaku, &amp; Hanjra, 2014</xref>).
</p>
