<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0100" class="p">With its Crop Intensification Program (CIP), Rwanda is an archetype of the New Green Revolution in SSA. In 2007, the country was the first to sign a compact with the Comprehensive Africa Agriculture Development Program (CAADP), a pan-African framework of agriculture-led growth. Since 2004, Rwanda’s Strategic Plans for the Transformation of Agriculture (PSTAs) have systematically transformed rural landscapes and livelihoods through land reform and technology adoption (
 <xref rid="b0090" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Clay, 2017</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0210" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">GOR, 2004</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b9040" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">MINAGRI, 2012</xref>). Striving to become a middle-income country by 2020, the GoR aims to convert largely subsistence-based smallholders to professional farmers. With its Land Policy (since 2006) and CIP (implemented since 2007 in pilot phases and countrywide since 2010), the Government of Rwanda (GoR) and development partners have formalized land tenure, drained marshlands, and constructed terraces throughout the country (
 <xref rid="b0250" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kathiresan, 2012</xref>). The CIP aims to increase the productivity of export-oriented crops by increasing access to hybrid seed and fertilizer, by augmenting agricultural extension services, and by compelling smallholders to consolidate landholdings with neighbors and cultivate crops selected by government authorities (
 <xref rid="b0320" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">MINAGRI, 2011</xref>). Crops under this ‘crop regionalization’ mandate (wheat, maize, rice, bean, cassava) were selected via a national-level exercise that considered agroecological zones and the crops’ export potential (
 <xref rid="b0230" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Huggins, 2014</xref>). Contracts (
 <italic class="italic">imihigo</italic>) with higher administrative levels outline hectare targets on which to consolidate land and plant selected crops, assuring that national-level targets are enacted at local levels (
 <xref rid="b0235" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ingelaere, 2014</xref>). Routine audits at various levels further solidify the top down nature of this program. To ensure that they meet government quotas for land in the CIP: local administrators threaten noncompliant farmers with fines, uprooting crops, or appropriating land (
 <xref rid="b0085" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Cioffo et al., 2016</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0090" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Clay, 2017</xref>).
</p>
