<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0105" class="p">As a CIP report states, the program “encourages crop specialization to realize economies of scale and to orient the agricultural sector more towards the commercial market” (
 <xref rid="b9040" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">MINAGRI, 2012, p30</xref>). While increases in agricultural production and commercialization are seen to have played a role in driving Rwanda’s impressive economic growth (8 percent yearly from 2000 to 2012) and poverty reduction (EICV, 2015; 
 <xref rid="b0520" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">World Bank, 2014</xref>), research also shows that these policies may exacerbate uneven land access (
 <xref rid="b0115" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Dawson, Martin, &amp; Sikor, 2016</xref>) and food insecurity (
 <xref rid="b9030" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Clay, 2018b</xref>). Studies on the initial phases of the CIP found that smallholder autonomy has been constrained, especially for socioeconomically disadvantaged households (Ansoms, Walker, &amp; Murison, 2014; 
 <xref rid="b0230" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Huggins, 2014</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0395" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Pritchard, 2013</xref>). Studies also demonstrate that smallholders’ ability to succeed with CIP-prescribed land use practices is highly uneven—varying according to agroecolgical conditions and pre-existing resource access inequalities (
 <xref rid="b0085" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Cioffo et al., 2016</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0090" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Clay, 2017</xref>). The present research builds on this work by investigating how Rwanda’s Green Revolution-inspired agricultural policies shape smallholders’ capacities to adaptively respond to perceived social-environmental changes. This research is timely as the GoR and development partners are currently scaling up these policies (
 <xref rid="b9040" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">MINAGRI, 2012</xref>, 
 <xref rid="b0520" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">World Bank, 2014</xref>) and given that similar policies are being widely implemented across sub-Saharan Africa (
 <xref rid="b9015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Schurman, 2018</xref>).
</p>
