<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">It is well established that multimodel ensembles exhibit a wide spread in the patterns of change for a particular scenario (Christensen et al., 
 <xref rid="grl56635-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; IPCC, 
 <xref rid="grl56635-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013a</xref>). This spread is often portrayed by collecting all available model information and evaluating appropriate statistics for a given climate variable (e.g., mean annual temperature) grid point by grid point using for example certain percentiles (e.g., 25th and 75th) to express likely lower or upper bounds around a median or mean value, that is, ignoring any physical interdependence between grid points. This approach was adopted in the Fifth Assessment Report (IPCC, 
 <xref rid="grl56635-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013a</xref>) from the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC), where regional information on projected changes was provided in an Atlas (IPCC, 
 <xref rid="grl56635-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013b</xref>), globally as well as for a number of larger regions around the world. It is specifically mentioned in the Atlas that the maps provided do not represent a robust estimate of the uncertainty associated with the projections but rather that “the range of model spread is provided as a simple, albeit imperfect, guide to the range of possible futures (including the effect of natural variability).” Here we identify some additional and potentially highly problematic inconsistencies within this approach and point out that similar inconsistencies may occur in regional applications where subsampling of CMIP models is performed; such approaches are frequently adopted within impacts and adaptation research (e.g., Lutz et al., 
 <xref rid="grl56635-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>; McSweeney et al., 
 <xref rid="grl56635-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>; Ruane &amp; McDermid, 
 <xref rid="grl56635-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>; Wilcke &amp; Bärring, 
 <xref rid="grl56635-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>).
</p>
