<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ack class="ack">
 <title class="title">Acknowledgments</title>
 <p class="p">We acknowledge the World Climate Research Programs Working Group on Coupled Modelling, which is responsible for CMIP, and we thank the climate modeling groups for producing and making available their model output. For CMIP, the U.S. Department of Energy’s Program for Climate Model Diagnosis and Intercomparison provides coordinating support and led development of software infrastructure in partnership with the Global Organization for Earth System Science Portals. We acknowledge the E-OBS dataset from the EU-FP6 project ENSEMBLES (
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ensembles-eu.metoffice.com" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://ensembles-eu.metoffice.com</ext-link>) and the data providers in the ECA&amp;D project (
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ecad.eu" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.ecad.eu</ext-link>). 
  <bold class="bold">Funding:</bold> E.B. received funding from the Volkswagen Foundations CE:LLO project (Az.: 88468) and M.V. from the “EUPHEME” ERA4CS project. 
  <bold class="bold">Author contributions:</bold> E.B. and D.M. had the idea of the study and designed the work. E.B. carried out the data analysis. E.B. wrote the paper with D.M. and with contributions from M.I.V. E.B. performed the astronomical tide simulations, M.I.V. and E.V. performed storm surge runs, and L.M. performed the wave runs. E.V., L.M., and M.I.V. collected the observed sea level data and derived the observed astronomical tides. M.V. gave conceptual inputs during the data analysis. All authors discussed the results and commented on the manuscript. 
  <bold class="bold">Competing interests:</bold> The authors declare that they have no competing interests. 
  <bold class="bold">Data and materials availability:</bold> All data needed to evaluate the conclusions in the paper are present in the paper and/or the Supplementary Materials. The statistical analyses were carried out using the R packages cited in Materials and Methods. Custom codes developed for the analyses are available from the corresponding author. Precipitation data from CMIP5 models are available from the Earth System Grid Federation (ESGF) Peer-to-Peer system (
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://esgf-node.llnl.gov/projects/cmip5" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://esgf-node.llnl.gov/projects/cmip5</ext-link>). Precipitation data from ERA-Interim are available from the ECMWF Public Datasets web interface (
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://apps.ecmwf.int/datasets" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://apps.ecmwf.int/datasets</ext-link>). The model FES2012 used for the astronomical tides simulations was produced by Noveltis, Legos, and CLS Space Oceanography Division and distributed by Aviso, with support from CNES (
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.aviso.altimetry.fr/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.aviso.altimetry.fr/</ext-link>). Sea level data are available at 
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://data.jrc.ec.europa.eu/collection/liscoast" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://data.jrc.ec.europa.eu/collection/liscoast</ext-link> (further inquiries should be addressed to M.I.V.).
 </p>
</ack>
