<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The impact of climate change will be felt by different parts of the world and by different people; poor countries like Bangladesh are going to be worst hit. For example, research by Furberg et al. [
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>] on Sami population shows that rapidly changing unstable weather patterns affect their living patterns. Furthermore, studies by Adebo and Sekumade [
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>], Adeniyi et al. [
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>], and Guha-Sapir et al. [
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>] suggest that women and children tend to be the worst affected. Additional studies by Devkota et al. [
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>], Kendrovski and Spasenovska [
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>], Davies et al. [
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>], and Bhuiyan and Khan [
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>] also show how these groups are suffering from health problems because of climate change. In disaster times, children and babies lack the capacity to escape from the hazard. In a study of 1991 Bangladesh cyclone, for example, children and older people died more disproportionately than others in the population [
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. About 71% of respondents mentioned that children suffer most due to the adverse effects of climate change and this was closely followed by elderly people and women at 63%, respectively [
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. This shows that women are the most vulnerable group who are the worst victim of the climate change followed by children and the elderly population. Other pieces of research show that the elderly populations suffer the most adverse health conditions due to changes in weather conditions Grundy [
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>], Hansen et al. [
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>], Mortreux and Barnett [
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>], and Filiberto et al. [
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>].
</p>
