<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par11" class="p">At a more general level, the pathway towards species declines is a function of alterations to the ecological and demographic stability of populations, which can occur due to different mechanisms. For example, as a consequence of loss of their suitable distributional area, which can erode the genetic diversity to respond to rapidly changing selection regimes
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" class="xref">42</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" class="xref">50</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" class="xref">52</xref>
 </sup>. However, other species may not be experiencing shrinking of their geographic ranges, and yet, may still face demographic alterations via other mechanisms such as novel forms of competition with species in newly encountered assemblages
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" class="xref">53</xref>
 </sup>, or exposure to climatically suitable, but not necessarily structurally suitable (e.g., topographically) environments. Therefore, range shifts in diverse directions rather than towards higher latitudes (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>) are expected to impact on the ecological and demographic stability of those species by exposing them to novel environments and networks of species where selection regimes will be different. In some cases, these impacts may lead to population declines and thus, to increased risk of extinction via factors not necessarily connected directly with changing temperatures. For instance, a recent study on 
 <italic class="italic">Liolaemus</italic> lizards showed that, in contrast with the traditionally established ‘cold-climate hypothesis’ that declines in environmental temperatures operate as drivers of natural selection for viviparity
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" class="xref">32</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" class="xref">54</xref>
 </sup>, reductions in atmospheric oxygen levels play a central role as agents of selection, promoting embryo retention and evolution of viviparity
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" class="xref">34</xref>
 </sup>. Whether oxygen levels influence the magnitude and direction of alterations in range shifts of viviparous species via their interactions with thermal gradients remains an open question. However, this ‘hypoxia’ hypothesis contributes to the more general view that species’ range stability can be broken down into interactions between a range of external factors (e.g., climate, topography) and population features (e.g., abundance, morphology, life-history, physiology). Future studies could develop predictions about the effects of environmental factors on parity modes taking into account this strong role of oxygen, in combination with classic ecophysiological factors. Such predictions could expand the findings of, for example, Medina 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. Medina, 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>
 </sup>, who observed that the preferred body temperature in the laboratory (T
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">pref</italic>
 </sub>) does not differ among 
 <italic class="italic">Liolaemus</italic> species with different parity models (while, however, field body temperature in the laboratory (T
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">pref</italic>
 </sub>) does not differ among 
 <italic class="italic">Liolaemus</italic> species with different parity models (while, however, field body temperature, T
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">b</italic>
 </sub>, does).
</p>
