<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par5" class="p">Nevertheless, there is still a lack of systematic, integrative approaches to, and analyses of the joint institutionalization of mitigation and adaptation in local governments. Institutionalization, in this context, is defined as a process that is designed to instill mitigation and adaptation as persistent and consistent aspects of organizational culture, for example, by establishing a vision, goals, roles, rule-based standard operating procedures, and organizational routines, in order to strengthen the legitimacy, foster the stability, enhance the predictability, and support the sustainable inclusion of mitigation and adaptation as an integral part of city administrations (Meyer and Rowan 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" class="xref">1977</xref>; Scott 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72" class="xref">2003</xref>; van Waarden 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87" class="xref">2003</xref>; Anguelovski and Carmin 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">2011</xref>). However, most research and many guidelines continue to focus either on the implementation of municipal climate mitigation or on adaptation structures, plans, and strategies (Kern et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" class="xref">2005</xref>; Deutsches Institut für Urbanistik 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">2011</xref>; Göpfert 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" class="xref">2014</xref>; UN-Habitat 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85" class="xref">2014</xref>; Reckien et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" class="xref">2014</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" class="xref">2015</xref>; Wamsler 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89" class="xref">2015b</xref>; Runhaar et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" class="xref">2017</xref>). Others simply focus on synergetic strategies and measures, and examine potentially complementary, conflicting or neutral interdependencies between mitigation and adaptation (Deutsches Institut für Urbanistik 2015a; Landauer et al. 2015). The holistic operationalization or joint institutionalization of these policy fields has received very little attention.
</p>
