<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">It is worth noting that the addition of pollutants resulted in an additional increase in DOC concentration (Figure 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" class="xref">1A</xref>), which was probably caused by two factors: the organic pollutants added contributing directly to the DOC pool (
 <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ripszam et al., 2015b</xref>) and the use of methanol as the solvent in which the pollutant cocktail was solubilized for addition to the mesocosms. The clear increase in DOC concentration in pollutant treatments compared to their controls at week 1 decreased over the duration of the experiment, and this is very much in keeping with the decreasing trends in pollutants as they became associated and partitioned within the mesocosms (
 <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ripszam et al., 2015b</xref>; Supplementary Figure 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM9" class="xref">S2</xref>). The concentration of methanol was not monitored during the experiment, and given that this compound is known to be used as carbon and energy source by a number of bacteria (
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lidstrom, 1992</xref>), its presence could act as a confounding factor when discriminating between bacterial responses attributed to methanol or other organic pollutants. However, we found some strong significant correlations between specific pollutants and OTUs, suggesting a direct cause–effect relationship. One clear example in the present study is OTU_81, which corresponds to a betaproteobacterium belonging to the genus 
 <italic class="italic">Methylophilus</italic>. It appears highly likely that the trends observed for this OTU were due to the utilization of methanol as a carbon and energy source, as described previously (
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Jenkins et al., 1987</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B52" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Neufeld et al., 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B87" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Vishnivetskaya et al., 2010</xref>). This OTU was found to be positively affected by pollutant addition in both the presence and absence of increased tDOM concentration. Furthermore, the genus 
 <italic class="italic">Methylophilus</italic> has been described to have an active role in the degradation of organic pollutants such as biphenyl (
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Jenkins et al., 1987</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Uhlik et al., 2009</xref>) and anthracene (
 <xref rid="B98" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Zhang et al., 2011</xref>), among others, which were present in the cocktail of pollutants used in this study. In fact, biphenyl was one of the organic pollutants found to significantly correlate with 
 <italic class="italic">Methylophilus</italic> abundance (Supplementary Table 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM6" class="xref">S6</xref>). All these correlations were negative, with an apparent delayed response of 
 <italic class="italic">Methylophilus</italic> to the addition of pollutants (Figure 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6" class="xref">6</xref>), possibly due to the steady development of the population of this bacterial genus. While this bacterial genus barely represented 0.06% of the community when pollutants were not present, it became relatively abundant after long exposure to pollutants (up to 3.27% of the community by week 5).
</p>
