<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The increasing probability that different areas of the globe simultaneously experience multiple climate stresses has important implications for a number of sectors. Given the historical sensitivity of agriculture to episodes of hot, dry conditions, the increase in joint probability of warm+dry years has direct implications for the ability of international trade to buffer the impacts of yield shocks within a region (
 <xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">3</italic>
 </xref>–
 <xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">5</italic>
 </xref>). Of particular concern is the yield volatility (
 <xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">3</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">5</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">6</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">22</italic>
 </xref>), which can increase the risk of commodity price volatility (
 <xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">3</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">22</italic>
 </xref>), poverty vulnerability (
 <xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">6</italic>
 </xref>), and supply chain disruption (
 <xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">7</italic>
 </xref>). By increasing the occurrence of low-yield years, increases in the frequency of hot years can increase yield volatility (
 <xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">5</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">22</italic>
 </xref>), independent of changes in temperature variability. Thus, although we do not explicitly quantify changes in year-to-year temperature variations and although changes in subannual extremes (such as heat waves) are likely to be even more extreme than the annual-scale climate anomalies studied here (
 <xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">22</italic>
 </xref>), annual-scale anomalies that exceed 4 SDs of the baseline temperature variability are sufficiently extreme to cause substantial negative yield shocks and associated increases in yield volatility (
 <xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">5</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">22</italic>
 </xref>).
</p>
