<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0045" class="p">We used MaxEnt to project species distribution under current and 2070 climate conditions (
 <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Phillips et al., 2006</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Elith et al., 2011</xref>). Occurrence data and environmental layers for the current time period and the 2070 projection were used as input data in the model. We used the default settings for MaxEnt parameters and set the iteration time as 10 for each species, then we used the average logistic output layer (based on the ten replicates of cross-validation runs for each species) for subsequent calculations. Values for area under the receiver operating characteristic curves (AUC) were used to evaluate the performance of the models, where the value 0.5 indicates a random prediction and 1.0 a perfect model prediction (
 <xref rid="bib2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bai et al., 2018</xref>). We reclassified the MaxEnt output file using the 10-percentile training presence logistic (10TPL) threshold value (
 <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref>) to define a species potential distribution region, above which species were considered “present” in the region, a method widely recognized for distinguishing suitable from unsuitable regions (
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Escalante et al., 2013</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kramer-Schadt et al., 2013</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Radosavljevic et al., 2014</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hughes, 2017</xref>). We then calculated the longitude, latitude, elevation and range size for each pixel of potential presence and estimated the mean values for the current time period and 2070 for each species. The average value of longitude, latitude and elevation between the current time period and 2070 were compared within and among species. The shifts in total range size from the current time period to 2070 were also estimated. We then overlaid the distribution maps for the two time periods to detect potential changes in the occupied area.
</p>
