<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Alternative Stabilized Earth Pathway</div>
 <p content-type="flushleft" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">If the world’s societies want to avoid crossing a potential threshold that locks the Earth System into the Hothouse Earth pathway, then it is critical that they make deliberate decisions to avoid this risk and maintain the Earth System in Holocene-like conditions. This human-created pathway is represented in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" href="#fig01">Figs. 1</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">2</a> by what we call Stabilized Earth (small loop at the bottom of 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" href="#fig01">Fig. 1</a>, 
  <span class="italic">Upper Right</span>), in which the Earth System is maintained in a state with a temperature rise no greater than 2 °C above preindustrial (a “super-Holocene” state) (
  <a rid="r11" ref-type="bibr" href="#r11">11</a>). Stabilized Earth would require deep cuts in greenhouse gas emissions, protection and enhancement of biosphere carbon sinks, efforts to remove CO
  <sub>2</sub> from the atmosphere, possibly solar radiation management, and adaptation to unavoidable impacts of the warming already occurring (
  <a rid="r48" ref-type="bibr" href="#r48">48</a>). The short broken red line beyond Stabilized Earth in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" href="#fig01">Fig. 1</a>, 
  <span class="italic">Upper Right</span> represents a potential return to interglacial-like conditions in the longer term.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In essence, the Stabilized Earth pathway could be conceptualized as a regime of the Earth System in which humanity plays an active planetary stewardship role in maintaining a state intermediate between the glacial–interglacial limit cycle of the Late Quaternary and a Hothouse Earth (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">Fig. 2</a>). We emphasize that Stabilized Earth is not an intrinsic state of the Earth System but rather, one in which humanity commits to a pathway of ongoing management of its relationship with the rest of the Earth System.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A critical issue is that, if a planetary threshold is crossed toward the Hothouse Earth pathway, accessing the Stabilized Earth pathway would become very difficult no matter what actions human societies might take. Beyond the threshold, positive (reinforcing) feedbacks within the Earth System—outside of human influence or control—could become the dominant driver of the system’s pathway, as individual tipping elements create linked cascades through time and with rising temperature (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3</a>). In other words, after the Earth System is committed to the Hothouse Earth pathway, the alternative Stabilized Earth pathway would very likely become inaccessible as illustrated in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">Fig. 2</a>.
 </p>
 <sec id="s6" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">What Is at Stake?</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hothouse Earth is likely to be uncontrollable and dangerous to many, particularly if we transition into it in only a century or two, and it poses severe risks for health, economies, political stability (
   <a rid="r12" ref-type="bibr" href="#r12">12</a>, 
   <a rid="r39" ref-type="bibr" href="#r39">39</a>, 
   <a rid="r49" ref-type="bibr" href="#r49">49</a>, 
   <a rid="r50" ref-type="bibr" href="#r50">50</a>) (especially for the most climate vulnerable), and ultimately, the habitability of the planet for humans.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Insights into the risks posed by the rapid climatic changes emerging in the Anthropocene can be obtained not only from contemporary observations (
   <a rid="r51" ref-type="bibr" href="#r51">51</a>
   <a href="#r52">*</a>
   <a href="#r53">*</a>
   <a href="#r54">*</a>–
   <a rid="r55" ref-type="bibr" href="#r55">55</a>) but also, from interactions in the past between human societies and regional and seasonal hydroclimate variability. This variability was often much more pronounced than global, longer-term Holocene variability (
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1810141115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>
   </span>). Agricultural production and water supplies are especially vulnerable to changes in the hydroclimate, leading to hot/dry or cool/wet extremes. Societal declines, collapses, migrations/resettlements, reorganizations, and cultural changes were often associated with severe regional droughts and with the global megadrought at 4.2–3.9 thousand years before present, all occurring within the relative stability of the narrow global Holocene temperature range of approximately ±1 °C (
   <a rid="r56" ref-type="bibr" href="#r56">56</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1810141115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Table S4
   </span> summarizes biomes and regional biosphere–physical climate subsystems critical for human wellbeing and the resultant risks if the Earth System follows a Hothouse Earth pathway. While most of these biomes or regional systems may be retained in a Stabilized Earth pathway, most or all of them would likely be substantially changed or degraded in a Hothouse Earth pathway, with serious challenges for the viability of human societies.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For example, agricultural systems are particularly vulnerable, because they are spatially organized around the relatively stable Holocene patterns of terrestrial primary productivity, which depend on a well-established and predictable spatial distribution of temperature and precipitation in relation to the location of fertile soils as well as on a particular atmospheric CO
   <sub>2</sub> concentration. Current understanding suggests that, while a Stabilized Earth pathway could result in an approximate balance between increases and decreases in regional production as human systems adapt, a Hothouse Earth trajectory will likely exceed the limits of adaptation and result in a substantial overall decrease in agricultural production, increased prices, and even more disparity between wealthy and poor countries (
   <a rid="r57" ref-type="bibr" href="#r57">57</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The world’s coastal zones, especially low-lying deltas and the adjacent coastal seas and ecosystems, are particularly important for human wellbeing. These areas are home to much of the world’s population, most of the emerging megacities, and a significant amount of infrastructure vital for both national economies and international trade. A Hothouse Earth trajectory would almost certainly flood deltaic environments, increase the risk of damage from coastal storms, and eliminate coral reefs (and all of the benefits that they provide for societies) by the end of this century or earlier (
   <a rid="r58" ref-type="bibr" href="#r58">58</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s7" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Human Feedbacks in the Earth System.</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the dominant climate change narrative, humans are an external force driving change to the Earth System in a largely linear, deterministic way; the higher the forcing in terms of anthropogenic greenhouse gas emissions, the higher the global average temperature. However, our analysis argues that human societies and our activities need to be recast as an integral, interacting component of a complex, adaptive Earth System. This framing puts the focus not only on human system dynamics that reduce greenhouse gas emissions but also, on those that create or enhance negative feedbacks that reduce the risk that the Earth System will cross a planetary threshold and lock into a Hothouse Earth pathway.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Humanity’s challenge then is to influence the dynamical properties of the Earth System in such a way that the emerging unstable conditions in the zone between the Holocene and a very hot state become a de facto stable intermediate state (Stabilized Earth) (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">Fig. 2</a>). This requires that humans take deliberate, integral, and adaptive steps to reduce dangerous impacts on the Earth System, effectively monitoring and changing behavior to form feedback loops that stabilize this intermediate state.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There is much uncertainty and debate about how this can be done—technically, ethically, equitably, and economically—and there is no doubt that the normative, policy, and institutional aspects are highly challenging. However, societies could take a wide range of actions that constitute negative feedbacks, summarized in 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1810141115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Table S5
   </span>, to steer the Earth System toward Stabilized Earth. Some of these actions are already altering emission trajectories. The negative feedback actions fall into three broad categories: (
   <span class="italic">i</span>) reducing greenhouse gas emissions, (
   <span class="italic">ii</span>) enhancing or creating carbon sinks (e.g., protecting and enhancing biosphere carbon sinks and creating new types of sinks) (
   <a rid="r59" ref-type="bibr" href="#r59">59</a>), and (
   <span class="italic">iii</span>) modifying Earth’s energy balance (for example, via solar radiation management, although that particular feedback entails very large risks of destabilization or degradation of several key processes in the Earth System) (
   <a rid="r60" ref-type="bibr" href="#r60">60</a>, 
   <a rid="r61" ref-type="bibr" href="#r61">61</a>). While reducing emissions is a priority, much more could be done to reduce direct human pressures on critical biomes that contribute to the regulation of the state of the Earth System through carbon sinks and moisture feedbacks, such as the Amazon and boreal forests (
   <a rid="t01" ref-type="table" href="#t01">Table 1</a>), and to build much more effective stewardship of the marine and terrestrial biospheres in general.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The present dominant socioeconomic system, however, is based on high-carbon economic growth and exploitative resource use (
   <a rid="r9" ref-type="bibr" href="#r9">9</a>). Attempts to modify this system have met with some success locally but little success globally in reducing greenhouse gas emissions or building more effective stewardship of the biosphere. Incremental linear changes to the present socioeconomic system are not enough to stabilize the Earth System. Widespread, rapid, and fundamental transformations will likely be required to reduce the risk of crossing the threshold and locking in the Hothouse Earth pathway; these include changes in behavior, technology and innovation, governance, and values (
   <a rid="r48" ref-type="bibr" href="#r48">48</a>, 
   <a rid="r62" ref-type="bibr" href="#r62">62</a>, 
   <a rid="r63" ref-type="bibr" href="#r63">63</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">International efforts to reduce human impacts on the Earth System while improving wellbeing include the United Nations Sustainable Development Goals and the commitment in the Paris agreement to keep warming below 2 °C. These international governance initiatives are matched by carbon reduction commitments by countries, cities, businesses, and individuals (
   <a rid="r64" ref-type="bibr" href="#r64">64</a>
   <a href="#r65">*</a>–
   <a rid="r66" ref-type="bibr" href="#r66">66</a>) , but as yet, these are not enough to meet the Paris target. Enhanced ambition will need new collectively shared values, principles, and frameworks as well as education to support such changes (
   <a rid="r67" ref-type="bibr" href="#r67">67</a>, 
   <a rid="r68" ref-type="bibr" href="#r68">68</a>). In essence, effective Earth System stewardship is an essential precondition for the prosperous development of human societies in a Stabilized Earth pathway (
   <a rid="r69" ref-type="bibr" href="#r69">69</a>, 
   <a rid="r70" ref-type="bibr" href="#r70">70</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition to institutional and social innovation at the global governance level, changes in demographics, consumption, behavior, attitudes, education, institutions, and socially embedded technologies are all important to maximize the chances of achieving a Stabilized Earth pathway (
   <a rid="r71" ref-type="bibr" href="#r71">71</a>). Many of the needed shifts may take decades to have a globally aggregated impact (
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1810141115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Table S5
   </span>), but there are indications that society may be reaching some important societal tipping points. For example, there has been relatively rapid progress toward slowing or reversing population growth through declining fertility resulting from the empowerment of women, access to birth control technologies, expansion of educational opportunities, and rising income levels (
   <a rid="r72" ref-type="bibr" href="#r72">72</a>, 
   <a rid="r73" ref-type="bibr" href="#r73">73</a>). These demographic changes must be complemented by sustainable per capita consumption patterns, especially among the higher per capita consumers. Some changes in consumer behavior have been observed (
   <a rid="r74" ref-type="bibr" href="#r74">74</a>, 
   <a rid="r75" ref-type="bibr" href="#r75">75</a>), and opportunities for consequent major transitions in social norms over broad scales may arise (
   <a rid="r76" ref-type="bibr" href="#r76">76</a>). Technological innovation is contributing to more rapid decarbonization and the possibility for removing CO
   <sub>2</sub> from the atmosphere (
   <a rid="r48" ref-type="bibr" href="#r48">48</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ultimately, the transformations necessary to achieve the Stabilized Earth pathway require a fundamental reorientation and restructuring of national and international institutions toward more effective governance at the Earth System level (
   <a rid="r77" ref-type="bibr" href="#r77">77</a>), with a much stronger emphasis on planetary concerns in economic governance, global trade, investments and finance, and technological development (
   <a rid="r78" ref-type="bibr" href="#r78">78</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s8" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Building Resilience in a Rapidly Changing Earth System.</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Even if a Stabilized Earth pathway is achieved, humanity will face a turbulent road of rapid and profound changes and uncertainties on route to it—politically, socially, and environmentally—that challenge the resilience of human societies (
   <a rid="r79" ref-type="bibr" href="#r79">79</a>
   <a href="#r80">*</a>
   <a href="#r81">*</a>–
   <a rid="r82" ref-type="bibr" href="#r82">82</a>). Stabilized Earth will likely be warmer than any other time over the last 800,000 years at least (
   <a rid="r83" ref-type="bibr" href="#r83">83</a>) (that is, warmer than at any other time in which fully modern humans have existed).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition, the Stabilized Earth trajectory will almost surely be characterized by the activation of some tipping elements (
   <a ref-type="sec" rid="s4" href="#s4">
    <span class="italic">Tipping Cascades</span>
   </a> and 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3</a>) and by nonlinear dynamics and abrupt shifts at the level of critical biomes that support humanity (
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1810141115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Table S4
   </span>). Current rates of change of important features of the Earth System already match or exceed those of abrupt geophysical events in the past (
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1810141115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
    <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>
   </span>). With these trends likely to continue for the next several decades at least, the contemporary way of guiding development founded on theories, tools, and beliefs of gradual or incremental change, with a focus on economy efficiency, will likely not be adequate to cope with this trajectory. Thus, in addition to adaptation, increasing resilience will become a key strategy for navigating the future.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Generic resilience-building strategies include developing insurance, buffers, redundancy, diversity, and other features of resilience that are critical for transforming human systems in the face of warming and possible surprise associated with tipping points (
   <a rid="r84" ref-type="bibr" href="#r84">84</a>). Features of such a strategy include (
   <span class="italic">i</span>) maintenance of diversity, modularity, and redundancy; (
   <span class="italic">ii</span>) management of connectivity, openness, slow variables, and feedbacks; (
   <span class="italic">iii</span>) understanding social–ecological systems as complex adaptive systems, especially at the level of the Earth System as a whole (
   <a rid="r85" ref-type="bibr" href="#r85">85</a>); (
   <span class="italic">iv</span>) encouraging learning and experimentation; and (
   <span class="italic">v</span>) broadening of participation and building of trust to promote polycentric governance systems (
   <a rid="r86" ref-type="bibr" href="#r86">86</a>, 
   <a rid="r87" ref-type="bibr" href="#r87">87</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
