<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">For autochthonous CHIKV transmission to occur in a previously nonendemic location, four conditions must be met: introduction of CHIKV via an infected traveler (condition C1), a susceptible human population (condition C2), climatic suitability for a competent vector (condition C3) and climatic suitability for CHIKV transmission potential by that vector (condition C4) (
 <xref rid="c68" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ogden et al. 2015</xref>). Canada is one of the leading destination countries for travelers returning from CHIKV-endemic countries over the summer months (
 <xref rid="c50" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Khan et al. 2014</xref>). In 2014, there were 320 confirmed and 159 probable CHIKV cases returning to Canada, up from 1–20 cases per year in previous years (
 <xref rid="c24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Drebot et al. 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="c70" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Pan American Health Organization 2016</xref>). Because CHIKV infections can cause high viremia and a significant proportion (20%) of infected returned Canadian travelers are viraemic at the time of seeking medical treatment (
 <xref rid="c24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Drebot et al. 2014</xref>), condition C1 is likely currently met although worth noting is that the majority of Canadians travel to CHIKV-affected countries during winter when virus transmission risk is lowest in Canada (
 <xref rid="c84" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Statistics Canada 2016</xref>). Although there is no population immunity to CHIKV in Canada, it may be that Canadian residents spend enough of their time during the summer months indoors in air-conditioned buildings and homes that the frequency of mosquito bites is too low to maintain person-to-person transmission. However, the endemic (and sometimes epidemic) transmission of West Nile virus resulting in human cases during the summer months in Canada lends support for the existence of condition C2. Although conditions C1 and C2 are important for autochthonous CHIKV transmission, this study focused on the ecological risk factors essential for endemic CHIKV transmission in Canada (conditions C3 and C4). The current climatic suitability for the presence of 
 <italic class="italic">Ae. albopictus</italic> in Canada (condition C3) was identified as unsuitable with the exception for southern coastal British Columbia and in south central and southeastern Canada, but northward expansion is possible with anticipated climate change (
 <xref rid="c69" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ogden et al. 2014</xref>). However, we do not know the current and future climatic suitability for CHIKV transmission in Canada (condition C4), specifically, the effect of temperature on virus survival and replication within mosquitoes, mosquito survival beyond the extrinsic incubation period (EIP) (the time required for the development of CHIKV to spread from the mosquito’s gut to the salivary glands where the virus can be transmitted), and virus transmissibility between humans and mosquitoes. In this study we explore the potential for autochthonous, but not necessarily sustained, transmission of CHIKV in Canada. We used a stochastic mathematical model parameterized for 
 <italic class="italic">Ae. albopictus</italic> under climatic conditions in the warmest months of the year in locations across Canada. We then combined the climatic suitability for CHIKV transmission potential in the warmest months of the year (condition C4) with climatic suitability indicators for the endemic presence of 
 <italic class="italic">Ae. albopictus</italic> (condition C3) to produce risk maps identifying areas in Canada most suitable for autochthonous CHIKV transmission under recent and projected climate.
</p>
