<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">A couple of scenarios can take place once these parasites are in a waterway. First, extreme rainfall events and flooding may render some wastewater treatment plants unable to accommodate the amount of influent sewage. Wastewater treatment plants are typically equipped with overflow systems that allow excess sewage to bypass treatment, other than a primary filter that removes large debris. This sewage then gets returned to the waterway untreated and with parasitic organisms still infective. This issue is augmented for island nations that flood easily during extreme weather events, such as hurricanes, and the groundwater may even be contaminated.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="bibr89-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">89</xref>
 </sup> In 1987, people living on the Chuuk Islands of the Federated States of Micronesia experienced a sudden increase in amebiasis due to flooding from Typhoon Nina.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="bibr90-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">90</xref>
 </sup> Second to overflows, parasites may not be killed by common disinfectants used at wastewater and drinking water treatment facilities and remain in the water. For example, chlorine is a common disinfectant that is not capable of killing 
 <italic class="italic">Cryptosporidium</italic> spp. in oocyst form.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="bibr87-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">87</xref>,
  <xref rid="bibr91-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">91</xref>
 </sup> Even a more revered disinfection method, the usage of UV light, is not always effective at killing these oocysts.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="bibr92-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">92</xref>
 </sup> Water temperature and UV exposure time play a role in parasite mortality, and for maximum effectiveness, these parameters must be carefully determined.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref rid="bibr92-1178633617732296" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">92</xref>
 </sup> In either case discussed, humans ultimately come into contact with these contaminated waters and drink or otherwise ingest parasites because of climatic events.
</p>
