<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="P10" class="p">Data on environmental risk factors for each city was acquired from independent datasets. We concentrate here on selected variables relating to meteorological parameters, air pollution and flood risk, as follows: 
 <list list-type="bullet" id="L1" class="list">
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="P11" class="p">Climate/temperature projections: Simulated data on current and possible future climates was provided by the Climatic Research Unit (CRU) at the University of East Anglia, using estimates for SHUE cities extracted for the nearest model grid square (typically several hundred kilometres in resolution) derived from an ensemble of 18 global climate models (GCMs) for the years 2015, 2050 and 2100 under a "business as usual" high greenhouse gas emissions scenario (RCP8.5) (
    <xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>–
    <xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>). The model simulations were from CMIP5 (Coupled Model Intercomparison Project Phase 5) (
    <xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>). Analyses were based on the monthly mean of daily mean temperatures for the hottest month of the year.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="P12" class="p">Air pollution: Annual average concentrations of fine particulate matter (PM
    <sub class="sub">2.5</sub>) for each city were obtained from the WHO’s ambient air pollution in cities database 2016 (
    <xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>), which contains estimates based on measurements from monitoring stations covering the period 2010-2015.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="P13" class="p">Flooding: Gridded estimates of exposures to flooding, ranging from 1 (low) to 5 (extreme), were obtained from the United Nations Environment Programme (UNEP) (
    <xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>). Each city’s risk was estimated based on the grid cell (0.1 x 0.1 degrees) containing the city centre.
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
