<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Additionally, although there has been some work indicating that interactions between storm surge and tide are not strictly linear (
 <xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>), flood heights are calculated here relative to MTL, and a full tidal cycle is not accounted for in our discussion of changing flood heights from the preindustrial era to the future. It is possible that tides may evolve in a changing climate (
 <xref rid="r55" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>). Although recent work suggests that changing bathymetric depth has little influence at the Battery, evidence does support a strong, approximately linear relationship between GT and the bathymetric depth of Long Island Sound (
 <xref rid="r56" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">56</xref>). Further, tides can be very important in determining overall flooding, influencing the highest water levels reached during a storm-surge event (
 <xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r56" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">56</xref>). The influence of tides upon overall flood heights varies greatly from storm to storm (
 <xref ref-type="sec" rid="si1" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">Supporting Information</italic>
 </xref>) but is likely to be most significant with large or slow-moving TCs, such as Hurricane Sandy. Tidal contributions to overall flood heights are well-documented for major historical TCs impacting NYC, including the 1938 New England Hurricane (40% tidal contribution to the overall 1.57-m storm tide), Hurricane Donna (1960; 29% tidal contribution to the overall 2.30-m storm tide), Hurricane Gloria (1985; 12% tidal decrease of the 1.9-m surge to a 1.7-m storm tide), and Hurricane Sandy (19% tidal contribution to the overall 3.47-m storm tide; ref. 
 <xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>). Thus, our decision to make our calculations using the MTL tidal datum constitutes an important caveat for this work.
</p>
