<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">When analyzing each crop separately, we found that guava, tomato, coffee and mandarin pollinators will potentially be the most affected by pollinator loss. Of these, guava and tomato are greatly dependent on pollinators and may be greatly affected. Specifically, considering the impact on the pollinators of tomato, our results are corroborated by a previous study that analyzed five pollinator species of tomato in Brazil, showing reductions of between 10 and 70% in their distributional range [
 <xref rid="pone.0182274.ref043" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>]. Although coffee is modestly dependent on pollinators, it is mostly produced in the southeastern region (the most affected region according to our scenario) with very high values of annual production and the second highest economic value of pollination in Brazil (almost US$ 2 billion/year) [
 <xref rid="pone.0182274.ref011" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>]. Mandarin has little dependence on pollinators but is also highly produced in the southern areas of Brazil. Therefore, pollinator loss for these crops may cause high economic and social impacts. Interestingly, new suitable areas for the production of the abovementioned crops may be found in the northern regions, and the feasibility of increasing their cultivation in these regions should be investigated. Particularly in western Amazonia (northern Brazil), there are continuous areas of natural habitats, and many crops are still collected in an extractive manner [
 <xref rid="pone.0182274.ref044" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0182274.ref045" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>] or produced on small farms. In contrast, in the southern region of Brazil, natural areas are fragmented and croplands are usually more extensive and homogeneous. Additionally, new habitat losses will likely continue to occur all over the country, and there is a debate in the literature regarding whether the necessity of expanding agricultural areas to compensate the decrease in crop yield due to climate change will increase [
 <xref rid="pone.0182274.ref046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>], which could bring new challenges to pollinator protection. All of the abovementioned aspects are intricately associated and can affect agricultural production.
</p>
