<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="evl3103-sec-0090" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Depending on the used relatedness estimator and whether estimates were scaled according to the pedigree the estimated accuracy of GEBVs for egg‐laying date varied between 0.197 and 0.210. This is lower than what is normally found in domesticated species. One study in dairy cattle on a variety of traits found accuracies that ranged from 0.63 to 0.83, with an average of 0.70 (VanRaden et al. 
  <a rid="evl3103-bib-0072" ref-type="ref" href="#evl3103-bib-0072">2009</a>). An early review study on dairy cattle based on considerably smaller training populations of only 332 to 637 individuals still found accuracies of 0.60 on average (Hayes et al. 
  <a rid="evl3103-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" href="#evl3103-bib-0037">2009b</a>). The average accuracy in a large number of studies on plants, mainly crop species, was ca. 0.60 (reviewed in Lin et al. 
  <a rid="evl3103-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" href="#evl3103-bib-0049">2014</a>). It hence seems that the accuracies estimated here are smaller than the ones typically found in domesticated animal and plant species. This is maybe not too surprising as genomic prediction relies on the markers being in linkage disequilibrium with the loci determining the trait. Effective population sizes of cattle breeds can be as low as ∼100 (e.g., de Roos et al. 
  <a rid="evl3103-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" href="#evl3103-bib-0019">2008</a>). Due to the larger effective population sizes of natural populations and the therefore higher number of independently segregating genome segments fewer causal loci will be “tagged” by the markers in natural populations resulting in lower expected accuracy of GEBVs (e.g., Goddard 
  <a rid="evl3103-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" href="#evl3103-bib-0032">2009</a>; Hayes et al. 
  <a rid="evl3103-bib-0038" ref-type="ref" href="#evl3103-bib-0038">2009c</a>; Daetwyler et al. 
  <a rid="evl3103-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" href="#evl3103-bib-0017">2010</a>). Another factor determining the accuracy is the number of individuals in the training population, i.e. the number of individuals of which both phenotype and genotype are known. For example, increasing the size of the training population from 1151 to 3576 individuals increased the accuracy of the predicted GEBVs from 0.35 to 0.53 in Holstein dairy cattle (VanRaden et al. 
  <a rid="evl3103-bib-0072" ref-type="ref" href="#evl3103-bib-0072">2009</a>). Our training population of about 2000 individuals was smaller than typical datasets from animal and plant breeding, especially recent studies that have been based on &gt;20,000 genotyped individuals (e.g., Lin et al. 
  <a rid="evl3103-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" href="#evl3103-bib-0049">2014</a>; Schöpke and Swalve 
  <a rid="evl3103-bib-0063" ref-type="ref" href="#evl3103-bib-0063">2016</a>). The accuracy of GEBVs also depends on the trait's heritability (e.g., Goddard et al. 
  <a rid="evl3103-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" href="#evl3103-bib-0033">2011</a>; Su et al. 
  <a rid="evl3103-bib-0067" ref-type="ref" href="#evl3103-bib-0067">2012</a>; Brito et al. 
  <a rid="evl3103-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" href="#evl3103-bib-0009">2017</a>), which was 0.24 when estimated from the pedigree and 0.17 when estimated using the markers and hence roughly comparable to the traits analyzed in, for example, VanRaden et al. (
  <a rid="evl3103-bib-0072" ref-type="ref" href="#evl3103-bib-0072">2009</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The predicted accuracy of the GEBVs for egg‐laying date was lower than the estimated accuracy and also very low in absolute terms, about 0.01, when estimating 
  <span class="italic">M
   <sub>e</sub>
  </span> from the effective population size in Laine et al. (
  <a rid="evl3103-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" href="#evl3103-bib-0047">2016</a>). The factor driving this low predicted accuracy was the very large effective population size in great tits, more than half a million (Laine et al. 
  <a rid="evl3103-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" href="#evl3103-bib-0047">2016</a>). While there is very little genetic differentiation between European great tit populations (Kvist et al. 
  <a rid="evl3103-bib-0046" ref-type="ref" href="#evl3103-bib-0046">2003</a>; Laine et al. 
  <a rid="evl3103-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" href="#evl3103-bib-0047">2016</a>), this very large effective population size may still be an overestimate. When we calculated 
  <span class="italic">M
   <sub>e</sub>
  </span> from the variation in genomic relatedness, the predicted and estimated accuracies corresponded much better (0.21 vs. 0.18). This illustrates that estimating 
  <span class="italic">M
   <sub>e</sub>
  </span> from 
  <span class="italic">N
   <sub>e</sub>
  </span> can be challenging (Brard and Ricard 
  <a rid="evl3103-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" href="#evl3103-bib-0008">2015</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Goddard et al. (
  <a rid="evl3103-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" href="#evl3103-bib-0033">2011</a>) showed that the number of markers also affects the accuracy of GEBVs because if the number of markers is too small the true relatedness at the causal loci will be estimated too imprecisely. The expected accuracy increased with the number of SNPs but started to plateau at around 3000 SNPs (Goddard et al. 
  <a rid="evl3103-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" href="#evl3103-bib-0033">2011</a>). This is in line with earlier findings that increasing the number of SNPs from ∼10,000 to ∼38,000 had very little effect on estimated accuracies in Holstein dairy cattle (VanRaden et al. 
  <a rid="evl3103-bib-0072" ref-type="ref" href="#evl3103-bib-0072">2009</a>). We used here more than ten times more markers, 502,951 SNPs, which seemed to have “compensated” for the larger effective population size and the hence increased number of independently segregating genome segments. We also could demonstrate the previously expected pattern that the accuracy plateaued with an increasing number of markers indicating that the number of markers used here was sufficient (Fig. 
  <a rid="evl3103-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#evl3103-fig-0003">3</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The accuracy of the estimated breeding values (EBVs) from a pedigree‐based animal model was very similar to the accuracies of GEBVs but the pedigree‐based heritability was higher (Table 
  <a rid="evl3103-tbl-0001" ref-type="table" href="#evl3103-tbl-0001">1</a>). The effect that using the pedigree rather than the GRM led to higher heritabilities could also be seen when more weight was given to the pedigree matrix relative to the GRM in a combined, weighted relatedness matrix (Table 
  <a rid="evl3103-tbl-0002" ref-type="table" href="#evl3103-tbl-0002">2</a>). One potential reason for the higher pedigree‐based estimate is environmentally caused similarity among relatives inflating estimates of 
  <span class="italic">V
   <sub>A</sub>
  </span> and 
  <span class="italic">h</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> (van der Jeugd and McCleery 
  <a rid="evl3103-bib-0069" ref-type="ref" href="#evl3103-bib-0069">2002</a>). Animal models have been thought to suitably account for this potential bias (e.g., Kruuk 
  <a rid="evl3103-bib-0044" ref-type="ref" href="#evl3103-bib-0044">2004</a>; Wilson et al. 
  <a rid="evl3103-bib-0077" ref-type="ref" href="#evl3103-bib-0077">2010</a>) but a simulation study showed that not all pedigrees, including the one of the Hoge Veluwe study population, may be informative enough to allow this (Gienapp et al. 
  <a rid="evl3103-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" href="#evl3103-bib-0031">2013b</a>). The low relatedness information in the pedigree‐based analysis means that it is difficult for the model to disentangle the genetic and permanent environmental effects with too much of the permanent environment variance being absorbed into the additive genetic variance and the EBVs. Using genomic instead of pedigree relatedness has been shown to improve the ability of the model to disentangle variances of possibly confounded effects (Lee et al. 
  <a rid="evl3103-bib-0048" ref-type="ref" href="#evl3103-bib-0048">2010</a>). Thus, the additional information contained in the GRM compared to the pedigree may have been able to remove more of the environmentally caused similarity among relatives, which would mean that the pedigree‐based heritability estimate would be inflated. However, to ultimately address this, cross‐fostering experiments (e.g., Kruuk and Hadfield 
  <a rid="evl3103-bib-0045" ref-type="ref" href="#evl3103-bib-0045">2007</a>) or models directly fitting the spatial correlation would be necessary (e.g., Stopher et al. 
  <a rid="evl3103-bib-0066" ref-type="ref" href="#evl3103-bib-0066">2012</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While GEBVs have an obvious use in animal and plant breeding, they also have the potential for useful applications in natural populations. Whether this will be possible and useful obviously depends on the accuracy of the estimated GEBVs, which will depend on species‐ and population‐specific parameters, which determine 
  <span class="italic">N
   <sub>e</sub>
  </span> and 
  <span class="italic">M
   <sub>e</sub>
  </span>, and the number of available markers. Whether these potential constraints prohibit the useful applications of GEBVs in certain species or populations, requires further investigation. GEBVs could, for example, be used to select individuals for assisted migration or release programs. Assisted migration aims to mitigate negative effects of climate change by transplanting suitable individuals to new locations that could only be slowly reached by natural dispersal, that is “assisting” their dispersal, which has already been used in forest tree management (Aitken and Whitlock 
  <a rid="evl3103-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" href="#evl3103-bib-0003">2013</a>). In breeding programs for endangered species GEBVs could also play a role by helping to identify individuals that are well adapted to the, potentially altered, release environments (Griffiths and Pavajeau 
  <a rid="evl3103-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" href="#evl3103-bib-0034">2008</a>). Currently, genotyping is more costly than measuring phenotypes but with dropping genotyping costs this may change, especially for phenotypes that are difficult to measure. Even though the variance in estimated (genomic) breeding values is downward biased in comparison to the additive genetic variance (e.g., Hadfield et al. 
  <a rid="evl3103-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" href="#evl3103-bib-0035">2010</a>) it may still serve as a useful proxy. Genotyping individuals in newly studied populations and predicting their GEBVs could allow us to (roughly) predict the evolutionary potential of these populations without the need for, potentially very laborious, quantitative genetic studies. Potential limitations of GEBVs for such applications can, however, arise from Genotype‐by‐Environment interactions (G × E) or different genetic trait architectures in different populations. G × E is common in many traits (e.g., Pigliucci 
  <a rid="evl3103-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" href="#evl3103-bib-0059">2001</a>; Wood and Brodie 
  <a rid="evl3103-bib-0078" ref-type="ref" href="#evl3103-bib-0078">2016</a>), which would mean that the “ranking” of individual breeding values in different environments can differ. As a consequence of this, the accuracy of predicting GEBVs across environments can be substantially reduced. Predicting GEBVs across populations, while ignoring this in the model, assumes that the genetic architecture of the trait is identical, that is that the same loci segregate in both populations. Cross‐breed prediction of GEBVs in domesticated populations has been attempted but accuracies are much lower than typical within‐breed accuracies (Moghaddar et al. 
  <a rid="evl3103-bib-0056" ref-type="ref" href="#evl3103-bib-0056">2014</a>; Hidalgo et al. 
  <a rid="evl3103-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" href="#evl3103-bib-0039">2016</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">High‐density marker panels have been available in animal and plant breeding and have been used in these fields for considerably longer than in evolutionary ecology to estimate relatedness from markers or even genomic selection (Gienapp et al. 
  <a rid="evl3103-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" href="#evl3103-bib-0024">2017a</a>). Early approaches aimed at estimating relatedness in natural populations from markers failed due to the limited number of markers available at that time (Coltman 
  <a rid="evl3103-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" href="#evl3103-bib-0014">2005</a>; Csilléry et al. 
  <a rid="evl3103-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" href="#evl3103-bib-0015">2006</a>), which is again stressed by our results that about 100,000 SNPs were necessary to obtain reliable accuracies of GEBVs. More recently, studies in natural populations of mammals, birds, and plants successfully estimated additive genetic variances in a number of traits and were even able to predict GEBVs (Robinson et al. 
  <a rid="evl3103-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" href="#evl3103-bib-0062">2013</a>; Stanton‐Geddes et al. 
  <a rid="evl3103-bib-0065" ref-type="ref" href="#evl3103-bib-0065">2013</a>; Beaulieu et al. 
  <a rid="evl3103-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" href="#evl3103-bib-0006">2014</a>; Bérénos et al. 
  <a rid="evl3103-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" href="#evl3103-bib-0007">2014</a>). Consequently, genomic prediction and also marker‐based quantitative genetics could become possible in a wide range of species, which has the potential to widen our understanding of evolutionary dynamics in natural populations (Gienapp et al. 
  <a rid="evl3103-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" href="#evl3103-bib-0024">2017a</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
