<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="discussion" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study presents two novel strategies to identify SNP loci that are correlated to environmental gradients, with the ultimate aim being the discovery of candidates for quantitative trait loci (QTLs) for environmental stress tolerance through subsequent correlative tests of phenotypic response. Both methods revealed likely signatures of selection in up to 55% of the loci tested. This is a considerable improvement compared to the previously reported 2-10% in non-targeted, genome-wide scans for outliers [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B69" href="#B69">69</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Of a small subset of SNPs screened across a large spatial scale on the Great Barrier Reef (GBR), four, two and three SNP(s) were found to be correlated to either temperature or water clarity in the reef-building coral species 
  <span class="italic">Acropora millepora, Pocillopora damicornis</span> (type α) and 
  <span class="italic">Pocillopora damicornis</span> (type β), respectively. These represent the first genetic markers in corals for environmental stress tolerance. After validation of these candidate loci, i.e., through laboratory or field assessment of relative stress tolerance of colonies harbouring different alleles at these loci, it is anticipated that a proportion of these loci can be used as 
  <span class="italic">de facto</span> QTLs.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The risk of confounding effects (e.g. population history, neutral “surfing” allele of an expanding population, endogenous genetic barrier) causing false positives as discussed in Bierne et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B19" href="#B19">19</a>] is reduced by actively selecting SNPs for either function or population divergence prior to being tested for correlations. Furthermore, test on independent allelic data at 11 putatively neutral microsatellite loci in 
  <span class="italic">A. millepora</span> provided an estimated the occurrence of false positives to be a maximum of ~10%.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All the SNPs that were selected in 
  <span class="italic">A. millepora</span> and at least one (
  <span class="italic">EF-1-α )</span> of the three significant SNPs in 
  <span class="italic">P. damicornis</span> were non-synonymous mutations (Tables 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="T1" href="#T1">1</a> and 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="T2" href="#T2">2</a>), hence are likely to be non-neutral makers upon which selection can act, either directly through a change in expression or function, or through linkage to other loci that are under selection. β- gamma-crystallin is mostly studied in relation to cataracts in humans and other model vertebrates [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B70" href="#B70">70</a>]. The protein has also been shown to bind calcium in bacteria [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B71" href="#B71">71</a>] and cephalochordates [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B72" href="#B72">72</a>]. The binding of Ca2+ influences the stability of the protein and thus alters its thermal denaturation points [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B71" href="#B71">71</a>], which may correlate to more successful calcification at higher temperatures. In corals, expression levels of 
  <span class="italic">β- gamma-crystallin</span> has been shown to have a high heritability (h
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.38), indicative of the existence of adaptive variation, and have been correlated to variations in larval responses to elevated temperatures and settlement cues [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B48" href="#B48">48</a>]. Another gene that is involved in the calcification process, which exhibits allele frequency distributions that correlate to thermal gradients in the present study, is galaxin
  <span class="italic">.</span> The protein this genes encodes was originally characterised from the coral 
  <span class="italic">Galaxea fascicularis</span> and is a soluble protein from the coral exoskeleton, where it is involved in calcification [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B73" href="#B73">73</a>]. Three genes that are related to galaxin, amgalaxin , amgalaxin like-1 and amgalaxin like-2 have been characterised in 
  <span class="italic">A. millepora</span>. The two amgalaxin like proteins are expressed exclusively during the early stages of calcification in the newly settled coral polyp, while amgalxin is continuously expressed also in the adult colony [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B74" href="#B74">74</a>]. Recent studies indicate that temperature plays a pivotal role in coral calcification rates [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B26" href="#B26">26</a>], supporting the correlation between temperature and proteins involved in the calcification process observed here. Ubiquitin is a protein that targets damaged proteins and marks them for destruction, a process referred to as ubiquitylation [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B75" href="#B75">75</a>]. Thus, measurements of relative levels of ubiquitin provide an index of the structural integrity of cellular proteins and have been used as a biomarker for cellular stress in corals [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B76" href="#B76">76</a>]. Differences in levels of ubiquitin conjugated proteins remain fixed during reciprocal transplantation of the coral 
  <span class="italic">Porites lobata</span>, with corals from environmentally variable back reef sites showing consistently higher levels, regardless of transplant location [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B77" href="#B77">77</a>], which adds to the current indication of a genetic difference contributing to variations to environmental stress response. SNP allele frequencies in the 
  <span class="italic">Ligand of numb X2</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Thioredoxin</span> genes correlated to water clarity. Ligand of numb X2 is a close homologue to the Ligand of numb X, which is an important ligase for ubiquitin [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B78" href="#B78">78</a>] while thioredoxin is involved in the sequestration of reactive oxygen species that are produced during oxidative stress [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B79" href="#B79">79</a>]. Further to its putative role during oxidative stress, thioredoxin has been shown to be significantly differentially expressed along pollution gradients in the Bermudas [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B40" href="#B40">40</a>], indicating that this protein is involved in the response to a range of stressors, including water quality.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In 
  <span class="italic">P. damicornis</span>, two genes of known function were found to have significant correlations with temperature and/or water clarity, namely 
  <span class="italic">EF 1-α</span> and 
  <span class="italic">β-hexosaminidase.</span> Apart from its role in the process of cellular binding of actin [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B80" href="#B80">80</a>], 
  <span class="italic">EF 1-α</span> has been shown to be significantly down-regulated during cancer cell senescence [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B81" href="#B81">81</a>] and during cell apoptosis associated with other cell malfunctions such as tetraploidy [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B82" href="#B82">82</a>]. Hence, a possible change in function of this protein may impact the onset of apoptosis in stressed corals. β-hexosaminidase is involved in a range of functions including the glycosalation of proteins, cleaving of N-acetylgalactosamine (GalNAc) residues that form part of the cell signaling pathway, and correct protein folding mechanisms. It has also been shown to play a role in mycobacterium defense [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B83" href="#B83">83</a>], which suggests it may play a role in the immune response. It is well documented that stressed corals show increased susceptibility to disease [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B84" href="#B84">84</a>-
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B86" href="#B86">86</a>], hence a correlation between an immune response and increasing temperature or declining water quality is expected.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although phenotypic responses are rarely determined by a single locus, but rather by the cumulative small effects of multiple loci [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B15" href="#B15">15</a>], it has been observed in some studies that SNPs may be responsible for a large part of the variance in a specific phenotypic trait [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B11" href="#B11">11</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B23" href="#B23">23</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B87" href="#B87">87</a>]. Hence, the direct utility of DNA-based QTLs is that the presence or absence of a certain allele is indicative of the relative stress tolerance of an individual or a population, as was shown to be the case of the relative proportion of one LDH-β allozyme and its correlation to increased thermal stress tolerance in populations of the killifish 
  <span class="italic">F. heteroclitus</span>[
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B22" href="#B22">22</a>]. The use of QTLs is widespread in crop science, where extensive QTL mapping is used to direct controlled breeding for desired traits such as drought and pest resistance [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B88" href="#B88">88</a>]. The link between genotype at the SNP loci presented here and the coral phenotype is currently being validated through aquarium experiments and 
  <span class="italic">in situ</span> observations.
 </p>
</sec>
