<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">SNPs</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From the eight SNPs that were selected from the transcriptome of 
  <span class="italic">P. damicornis</span> (type β) only one was a transversion (24_CA_2390). This SNP occurred at Night and Tydeman reefs with the rare allele (A) occurring at a frequency of 18.1% and 7.6% respectively. In the original transcriptome data, this allele occurred at Wilke Islet reef, which is located in the same geographic region as Night and Tydeman (Figure 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">1</a>). The remaining seven SNPs were all transitions (C/T or G/A). The resolution of the single step PCR to HRM method used in this study did not allow discrimination of A to T or C to G mutations. Hence, all the SNPs analysed by this method caused a change in the number of hydrogen bonds in the DNA chain, which produced a large enough change in the melting temperature to allow accurate scoring.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The final data set for 
  <span class="italic">P. damicornis</span> (type β) was based on the allele frequencies at eight SNP loci. In 
  <span class="italic">P. damicornis</span> (type α)
  <span class="italic">,</span> five loci were amplified using the primers developed for 
  <span class="italic">P. damicornis</span> (type B) (Table 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="T1" href="#T1">1</a>). The other three loci were excluded from trials in 
  <span class="italic">P. damicornis</span> (type α) due to ambiguous scoring patterns of the HRM curves in this species (see Additional file 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">1</a>: Figure S1 for examples of HRM curves). In 
  <span class="italic">P. damicornis,</span> the SNPs were found in genes of known and unknown function and included both synonymous and non-synonymous mutations. The genes of known function included 
  <span class="italic">Elongation factor 1-α, β-hexosamidase, Carbonic anhydrase</span> and the 
  <span class="italic">40S ribosomal protein S3</span> (Table 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="T1" href="#T1">1</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
