<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Potential vertebrate hosts and vectors</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">At this stage, we can only speculate about the potential vertebrate hosts of the two different filariae. In the case of 
  <span class="italic">Setaria tundra </span>it seems prudent to assume roe-deer as the vertebrate host, as in the past this has been reported from Germany [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B21" href="#B21">21</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B37" href="#B37">37</a>] and neighbouring countries [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B38" href="#B38">38</a>-
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B40" href="#B40">40</a>]. In southern Germany the prevalence of 
  <span class="italic">S. tundra </span>in roe-deers ranges between 1.6% in North Rhine-Westphalia [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B37" href="#B37">37</a>] and 12.3% in northern Bavaria [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B21" href="#B21">21</a>]. In Finland, roe-deer seem to be the main reservoir, but reindeer and moose can also be infected [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B41" href="#B41">41</a>]. The transmission of 
  <span class="italic">S. tundra </span>by various German mosquito species such as 
  <span class="italic">Oc. sticticus</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Ae. vexans </span>and 
  <span class="italic">An. claviger </span>is similar to findings from Finland, where 
  <span class="italic">Ae. communis, Ae. punctor, Ae. hexodontus and Ae. excrucians </span>were incriminated as natural vectors [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B28" href="#B28">28</a>]. The veterinary importance of 
  <span class="italic">S. tundra </span>is due to a reported outbreak of peritonitis with significant economic losses in Finnish semi-domesticated reindeer in 2003-5 [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B42" href="#B42">42</a>]. Similar outbreaks may occur in any other wild or semi-domesticated cervid population outside Finland, e.g. in zoos.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Regarding the filarial species derived from Culex mosquitoes, birds might serve as vertebrate hosts, because of the ornithophilic behavior of most Culex species in Europe [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B38" href="#B38">38</a>]. Potential bird parasite genera known from Europe are Cardiofilaria, Chandlerella, 
  <span class="italic">Eufilaria</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Eulimdana</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Pelecitus</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Pseudlemdana</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Sarconema </span>and 
  <span class="italic">Splendidofilaria </span>[
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B12" href="#B12">12</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B43" href="#B43">43</a>-
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B49" href="#B49">49</a>], some of which are found in common birds such as Blackbirds (
  <span class="italic">Turdus merula</span>), Magpies (
  <span class="italic">Pica pica</span>) or Great Tits (
  <span class="italic">Parus major</span>) ([
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B12" href="#B12">12</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B50" href="#B50">50</a>]), others in domesticated exotic birds [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B51" href="#B51">51</a>]. However, only certain Cardiofilaria and Pelecitus species are known to be vectored by culicines from Asia and North America [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B12" href="#B12">12</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B52" href="#B52">52</a>]. A single record from German birds of prey [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B47" href="#B47">47</a>] makes 
  <span class="italic">Cardiofilaria pavlovskyi </span>the favourite candidate for our unidentified specimens. It is also known from various birds in Spain, France, Poland and Latvia [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B12" href="#B12">12</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B45" href="#B45">45</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B49" href="#B49">49</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B50" href="#B50">50</a>]. Final conclusions are prevented by the paradox that on one hand, sequences are not available for 
  <span class="italic">Cardiofilaria </span>and for the majority of the about 90 known genera of onchocercid filariae [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B17" href="#B17">17</a>], of which only 20 genera are currently represented in GenBank. On the other hand our study protocol did not allow morphological examination prior to homogenization for DNA extraction, and the same applies to most if not all vector-borne specimens listed in GenBank. The only bird parasite that was confirmed by morphology and DNA sequencing during a bird die-off in late 2011 was 
  <span class="italic">Diplotriaena </span>sp. (Nematoda: Diplotriaenidae) in two dead blackcaps (
  <span class="italic">Sylvia atricapilla</span>), but the 12S DNA sequence turned out to be very different from the 
  <span class="italic">Culex </span>filariae (unpublished observations by the authors).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is generally assumed that avian filarioid parasites are rarely pathogenic, and clinical signs may occur only in some bird species or in some individuals within one species [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B53" href="#B53">53</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
