<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate Predictions and Simulations</div>
 <p id="Par39" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To predict changes of the four climate change factors used to drive the EwE and Ecotracer modelling approach, we used climate change data from the Earth System Model using Modular Ocean Model ESM2M developed by the NOAA- Geophysical Fluid Dynamics Laboratory (GFDL)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
  </span>, combined with representative concentration pathways (RCPs), including RCP 2.6, which was used as an optimistic climate scenario, and RCP 8.5 as the pessimistic scenario (Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S3</a>). Because there are no downscaled predictions for the study area, we used the results predicted for a larger region (Northeastern Pacific), engulfing the Hecate Strait, Queen Charlotte Sound, Strait of Georgia and Puget Sound, as well as outer coast of BC and offshore waters of Haida Gwaii and Vancouver Island’s west coasts (Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S1</a>). Thus, predictions for temperature, pH, oxygen and primary production (chlorophyll a) were obtained from ESM2M (over the period 1950–2100 for RCP 2.6 and RCP 8.5), as shown in Appendix 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">I</a>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par40" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on Guenette 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
  </span>, we assumed that all physical-chemical factors (temperature, pH and oxygen) affected the scope of growth of species and vulnerability of prey. This was modelled in Ecopath with Ecosim by introducing a forcing function (time series of relative change according to the climate predictions) that influences the ratio of consumption to biomass (Q/B) of each species by directly modifying the prey vulnerability for predators in the EwE model
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
  </span>. This assumes that the predicted changes in environment will make the species a more or less efficient predator, converting consumers into super predators or inferior predators, and resulting in increased/decreased growth and thus, increasing or decreasing their biological productivity
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
  </span>. Changes in primary production were modelled using a forcing function directly on primary production, modifying biological production
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par41" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The time period baseline for climate change forcing factor data used in the model represents the average state by 2005 (i.e. 20 years average from 1996 and 2015). Then, the time series data for each climate change factor in a given year were adjusted to this average to produce an index (rescaled to 1). Thus, the predicted effects of climatic factors on growth and prey vulnerability of the predator were at the last year of the fitted EwE model (2015). The simulations described here begin at the end of the fitted period (2015) and were run until 2099.</p>
 <p id="Par42" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The simulation scenarios (RCP 2.6 and RCP 8.5) were compared to a baseline reference scenario in the absence of climate change forcing, simulated in the EwE model with Ecotracer.</p>
</sec>
