<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" sec-type="discussion" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our simulations show the expected differences between MeHg and PCBs due to pollutant amplification under climate change. These differences are driven by different dietary uptake and total elimination rates and species biomass transfer through the food web. These differences are also expected to occur because the biotransformation and biomagnification of pollutants, and bioenergetics in ectothermic and endothermic species vary greatly, i.e. endothermic animals more likely to biomagnify chemicals than ectothermic species
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
  </span>. The specific bioaccumulation and thermodynamics of organic pollutants also diverge between gill-ventilating/water-respiring organisms and air-breathing organisms, responding differently to chemical bioaccumulation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
  </span> and temperature exposures
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>
  </span>. Ultimately, changes in food web structure and metabolic efficiency (i.e. ratio of consumption to production in the food web) leading to changes of biomass in functional groups of species of the food web are mechanisms influencing PCB and MeHg bioaccumulation and biomagnification under climate change forcing.
 </p>
 <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The discrepancies in amplification patterns of bioaccumulation between pollutants and species to climate change are likely to be explained in part by differences in the bioaccumulation rate of pollutants (i.e. pollutant-specific bioaccumulation) and the sensitivity to climate effects between functional groups (i.e. species-specific bioaccumulation) (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4A,B</a>). Changes in relative abundance of prey and predator functional groups affect the pathways of bioaccumulation. For example, squid, an important prey item for Chinook salmon, and other species (e.g., hake, 
  <span class="italic">Merluccius productus;</span> rockfish, 
  <span class="italic">Sebastes</span> spp.; pink salmon, 
  <span class="italic">O</span>. 
  <span class="italic">gorbuscha</span>) are higher in biomass projected under RCP 8.5 relative to those under RCP 2.6 (i.e. biomass ratio RCP 8.5 to RCP 2.6 &gt;1; Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S9</a>). In contrast, other functional species (i.e. forage fish, flatfish) are projected to have relatively lower biomass under RCP 8.5 than under RCP 2.6 (Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S9</a>). As a result, squid (trophic levels, TL = 3.4) becomes a more important source of biomass to support the production of predatory species such as salmon (TL = 3.9) and killer whales (Tl = 4.8) under RCP 8.5. As the bioaccumulation of PCB is more efficient through squid than other prey items of Pacific salmon (i.e. Chinook salmon), the concentration of PCB in these predatory species is higher under RCP 2.6 (i.e. the lower biomass of squid under RCP 2.6 increases its per unit PCB concentration).
 </p>
 <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While there is a food web-specific pollutant biomagnification process driving the long-term bioaccumulation pattern for either MeHg or PCBs in SRKWs, the high trophic level, long life span, and less pulse in the declining biomass of SRKWs in response to both climate change forcing and contaminant burden in major prey (Pacific salmon, i.e. Chinook salmon) are plausible reasons to explain in part the behavior of these contaminant trends in SRKWs over the simulation period.</p>
 <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The increase in projected MeHg concentrations observed in salmon and SRKW can be explained by the continuous accumulation of MeHg through diet combined with a slow elimination and also a long biological half-life in these animals
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>
  </span>. Mercury concentrations in large predatory fish and cetaceans are strongly influenced by the length of and changes in structure of the food web
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>
  </span>. Moreover, low trophic level organisms from coastal-marine food webs can play a crucial role in the trophic transfer of MeHg, as climate change can increase its exposure and enhance the MeHg bioaccumulation factor in zooplankton by a factor of 2 to 7, as reported by Jonsson 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
  </span>. Here, we demonstrated that bioaccumulation in zooplankton increases by 3% under RCP 2.6 and by 12% under RCP 8.5 relative to the reference baseline (control) scenario (i.e. no climate change) for the simulation period 2005–2099 (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a> and Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2B</a>). The increase in MeHg concentration in zooplankton is much higher (i.e. 9.5% for RCP 2.6 and 22% for RCP 8.5) at the end of the century (i.e. simulation period 2070–2099; see Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2A</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The projected decrease in simulated PCB concentrations in SRKW is similar to past trends observed in recent modelling work not including climate change forcing
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span>. PCB concentrations in the northeast Pacific declined rapidly in most marine fauna following the PCB-ban in the 1970s. The decrease in POPs under global control by the Stockholm Convention should be expected in marine biota
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span>. However, the metabolic recalcitrance of PCBs can delay responses to such declines in large, long-lived species, including the highly PCB-contaminated SRKW of the Northeastern Pacific
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span>. Particularly, PCB contamination in this killer whale ecotype, specialized in consuming salmon, can be further exacerbated during periods of nutritional stress and bioenergetic requirements when the abundance of highly PCB-contaminated Chinook salmon is the lowest during ocean warming conditions (i.e. climate change-induced contaminant sensitivity)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span>. This is consistent with our model outputs that show bioamplification of PCBs, increased by one order of magnitude, when lipid reserves are the lowest in both Chinook salmon and SRKWs, as shown in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6</a>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Decreasing biomass of key species groups in terms of energy flow and protracted reduction and density of apex predators under RCP 2.6 and RCP 8.5 at the end of the century (Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S9</a>) is a possible contributing factor influencing the lack of difference in TMFs when compared against the reference scenario (no climate change). We postulate that pollutant bioamplification could reach a climax level due to impending contaminant oversaturation across the food web under low or high CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions (i.e. RCP 2.6 or RCP 8.5), at which additional trophic magnification of contaminants cannot be detected (i.e., the food web and the ecosystem could be inhibited and unable to continue bioamplifying contaminants).
 </p>
 <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Simulations of the influence of dynamic temperature scenarios (e.g., high contaminant concentrations) compared to constant temperature scenarios on the body weight and contaminant concentration in fish and seabirds have demonstrated the bioamplification process
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>
  </span>. Pollutant bioamplification is a special case of bioaccumulation, driving increasing concentrations of organic contaminants when marine animals lose weight during periods of nutritional stress, fasting, reproduction and migrations
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>
  </span>. In the context of climate change, the shrinking of fish due to the alteration of the metabolic scope rate caused by ocean warming, reduced oxygen and other biochemical factors
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
  </span> can contribute to pollutant bioamplification
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Some assumptions were required for simplicity due to data limitations. For instance, the octanol-water (
  <span class="italic">K</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">OW</span>
  </sub>) and octanol-air (
  <span class="italic">K</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">O</span>A
  </sub>) partition/distribution coefficients for PCBs and MeHg under ambient/ectotherm and endotherm temperatures are not directly accounted for in the model; excretion of PCBs and MeHg was assumed to be negligible for most organisms because of high uptake and absorption of PCBs and MeHg (i.e. we assumed that 100% of PCBs and MeHg is absorbed for the purpose of this work) in marine biota in general (see Tables 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S4</a> and 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S5</a> for input data and references). MeHg biogeochemistry was not directly accounted in the model. Water column and sediment MeHg concentrations can be changed by SST, pH and dissolved oxygen (DO) concentration (e.g., photodegradation rate formation/reductions rates of MeHg)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
  </span>. Particularly formation and degradation rates of MeHg in seawater are largely DO, pH, UV availability, and dissolved organic carbon (DOC)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
  </span>. Future studies could incorporate direct effects of changing ocean biogeochemistry on contaminants bio-availability into the model.
 </p>
 <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The outcomes of the model bias analysis generally agrees with predicted PCB concentrations in SRKW from 1930 forward to the early 2000s reported by Hickie 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As empirical data for mercury concentrations (MeHg) are limited for the majority of marine organisms of the food web from the study region (e.g., absence of MeHg data for killer whales precluded the 
  <span class="italic">MB</span>-assessment for this species), we conducted a comparison (i.e. 
  <span class="italic">MB</span> ratio) of projected MeHg concentrations for wild Chinook, chum and coho salmon species against the observed MeHg data reported for these species in coastal BC in 2003
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
  </span>. Therefore, based on the limited empirical MeHg data reported for these salmon species (i.e. Chinook, chum and coho) for a single year
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
  </span>, the model simulations showed systematically overprediction when compared to observed MeHg concentrations (Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S10</a> and Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S7</a>). The lack of empirical MeHg data for most species/functional groups prevented a concerted assessment of the model bias and uncertainty. However, the accuracy of the simulations for the model was tested by comparing the model PCB projections in biota to empirical data and calculating 95% CI around the geometric mean of the 
  <span class="italic">MB</span>, as an indication of the uncertainty of model predictions (Figs 
  <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6</a> and 
  <a rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig7">7</a>; Tables 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S5</a> and 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S6</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Several empirical studies in the Arctic provide evidence of the influence of climate change in increasing concentrations of POPs in polar bears
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
  </span> and mercury in sea birds
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
  </span>. Conversely, some field contributions have shown that concentrations of many legacy POPs have decreased in food webs of seabirds or exhibited a lack of increase in polar bear populations
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
  </span>. While MeHg concentrations are increasing, the decrease in POPs has been attributed to shifts in diets and in trophic position, and the phase-out of some POPs (i.e., PCBs, DDTs) in the late 1970s
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span>. The model projections for MeHg are also consistent with the outcomes of a climate change-mercury bioaccumulation EwE-model, involving Atlantic cod (
  <span class="italic">Gadus morhua</span>) and pilot whales (
  <span class="italic">Globicephala melas</span>)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our findings reveal that climate change and contaminants can potentially combine to trigger pollutant bioamplification in the food web, improving our understanding of climate-pollution interactions. A more comprehensive awareness of the risks of multiple anthropogenic stressors can thus highlight key areas for concerted research and potential pollution mitigation policies including limiting mercury and greenhouse gas emissions from human activities.</p>
</sec>
