<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s7" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Continental US Soil Moisture Feedback Analysis.</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The analysis of Tuttle and Salvucci (ref. 
  <a rid="r6" ref-type="bibr" href="#r6">6</a>; results shown in their figure 1A and B) identified the causal influence of soil moisture on the occurrence of next-day precipitation. Precipitation is often autocorrelated, with precipitation events occurring in clusters over timescales of weeks, months, or years. This autocorrelation may be due to local (e.g., soil moisture feedbacks) or far-field influences (e.g., synoptic weather patterns, sea surface temperatures). No matter the cause of the autocorrelation in precipitation, this signal will be passed on to soil moisture, due to the direct coupling between the two (i.e., when it rains, soil moisture increases). Therefore, any lagged correlation between soil moisture and subsequent precipitation will be contaminated by autocorrelation in precipitation, regardless of the cause (
  <a rid="r47" ref-type="bibr" href="#r47">47</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To isolate the effect of soil moisture on the occurrence of next day precipitation, Tuttle and Salvucci (
  <a rid="r6" ref-type="bibr" href="#r6">6</a>) used generalized linear modeling (specifically, probit regression) within a Granger causality framework. Precipitation occurrence (a binary variable: rain vs. no rain) was modeled as a function of sinusoids that represented various modes of interannual variability and seasonality, and up to 4 d of past precipitation (see ref. 
  <a rid="r6" ref-type="bibr" href="#r6">6</a> for details). For each given location, models with all possible combinations of the independent variables were separately evaluated against observed precipitation (i.e., “all possible models” or “all possible regressions”), and the model with the combination of independent variables that yielded the lowest AIC was chosen as the best “restricted” model for that given location. Then, a similar probit regression model was evaluated, with 1-d lagged, seasonal soil moisture anomaly as the independent variable (along with 4 d of lagged atmospheric pressure) and the residual precipitation occurrence from the “restricted” model as the dependent variable. This second, “unrestricted” model tested whether or not soil moisture exerted a statistically significant influence on next-day precipitation occurrence, after accounting for seasonality, interannual variability, and precipitation persistence. The ratio of the predicted precipitation probability from the models with and without soil moisture as an independent variable provided a quantification of the impact of soil moisture on the occurrence of next-day precipitation (i.e., results shown in ref. 
  <a rid="r17" ref-type="bibr" href="#r17">17</a>, 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" href="#fig01">Fig. 1 
   <span class="italic">A</span> and 
   <span class="italic">B</span>
  </a>). The precipitation data used in Tuttle &amp; Salvucci (2016) are from the North American Land Data Assimilation System, Phase 2 (
  <a rid="r48" ref-type="bibr" href="#r48">48</a>). 2 soil moisture datasets derived from Advanced Microwave Scanning Radiometer for the Earth Observing System satellite observations ref. 
  <a rid="r49" ref-type="bibr" href="#r49">49</a> in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" href="#fig01">Fig. 1
   <span class="italic">A</span>
  </a>; ref. 
  <a rid="r50" ref-type="bibr" href="#r50">50</a> in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" href="#fig01">Fig. 1
   <span class="italic">B</span>
  </a>) were evaluated against the precipitation data. The analysis was restricted to the contiguous United States from June 2002 to June 2011 and to months without freezing air temperatures.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Because community-weighted trait maps are not currently available for our key traits at continental scales, we used a tree species richness map for the continental United States (
  <a rid="r51" ref-type="bibr" href="#r51">51</a>). In addition, we drew upon a biome map (
  <a rid="r52" ref-type="bibr" href="#r52">52</a>), gridded monthly soil moisture data from the Global Land Data Assimilation System (
  <a rid="r53" ref-type="bibr" href="#r53">53</a>), and gridded data of leaf area index from Moderate Resolution Imaging Spectroradiometer from July 2005 (
  <a rid="r54" ref-type="bibr" href="#r54">54</a>), which was chosen to represent the peak growing season in the continental United States, and central in time for our analysis in the soil moisture feedback datasets. We included these ancillary datasets either as masks or covariates in our analyses (see below).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For each of the 2 estimates of soil moisture–precipitation feedback, we restricted our analyses to only grid cells dominated with woody vegetation (cover types 1–9) and removed grid cells with values of 1 (no statistically significant feedback, which constituted 38% of woody vegetation grid cells). We then performed a multivariate ordinary least squares regression of the feedback as a function of species richness, average leaf area index, and their interaction term, which was the model that had the lowest AIC. We tested for spatial autocorrelation in our data with a Moran’s I test (
  <a rid="r55" ref-type="bibr" href="#r55">55</a>), which was not significant. Given the saturation of the feedback at higher values of richness, we further fit a generalized additive model with feedback as a function of richness.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To ensure that our results were not driven by a correlation of average soil moisture with the soil moisture feedback estimates, we also ran analyses where we first regressed the soil moisture feedback against average soil moisture from 1989 to 2008 and then used the residuals of this regression against tree species richness, which was still significant (
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.19, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.00001).
 </p>
</sec>
