<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Soil Moisture Feedback Methods.</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We restricted our data to the plant-active season using 2 different methods. In both, we removed all data where a quality flag indicated that a measurement of soil moisture, temperature, vapor pressure deficit, or sensible heat may have been flawed. We further verified this by plotting annual time courses of all variables for all sites to ensure that all data were within reasonable bounds. In the first method, we implemented a daily average temperature threshold of 15 °C for temperate and 10 °C for boreal sites and further removed 1 wk on either end of each plant-active season. In the second method, we implemented the cross-site method proposed by Gu et al. (40) and considered a growing season to be between the “stabilization day” and “downturn day” of annual GPP (via the nighttime partitioning method) time series. These methods yielded largely similar results (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" href="#fig01">Fig. 1</a> and 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1904747116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S2
  </span>), and thus we present the temperature threshold (first) method in the main text.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We followed a number of previous studies in estimating the strength of soil moisture feedbacks and drought intensification as the correlation between previous soil moisture and subsequent T, VPD, or SH (
  <a rid="r3" ref-type="bibr" href="#r3">3</a>, 
  <a rid="r8" ref-type="bibr" href="#r8">8</a>, 
  <a rid="r41" ref-type="bibr" href="#r41">41</a>, 
  <a rid="r42" ref-type="bibr" href="#r42">42</a>). Quantifying land surface feedbacks is inherently challenging because 1) observational data are typically at much smaller spatial scales (e.g., an eddy covariance footprint) than the relevant atmospheric processes, 2) effects may arise from autocorrelation of dependent variables (e.g., synoptic patterns in precipitation), and 3) lagged correlations among variables may not mean causation (
  <a rid="r2" ref-type="bibr" href="#r2">2</a>, 
  <a rid="r42" ref-type="bibr" href="#r42">42</a>). Challenge 1 is largely unavoidable for site-level analyses where plant trait data are available, but we believe our approach is still reasonable for several reasons. First, this limitation has not precluded the detection of likely soil moisture feedbacks in previous studies (
  <a rid="r3" ref-type="bibr" href="#r3">3</a>, 
  <a rid="r43" ref-type="bibr" href="#r43">43</a>). Second, inferring feedbacks from site-level data are reasonable if the sites are representative of broader regional vegetation types (thereby capturing the main mechanisms for regional-scale feedbacks), which is largely the case of our focal flux towers. Finally, we analyze broader continental-scale datasets as well, which show a consistent pattern with flux-tower data (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3</a>). In addition, soil depth or properties such as soil texture, rooting depth, and belowground plant or mycorrhizal traits could all influence land–atmosphere interactions, but were not considered here due to a lack of available data. Challenge 2 is a much larger problem for the detection of soil moisture–precipitation feedbacks, and analyses focusing on soil moisture–temperature are likely to be more robust than soil moisture–precipitation feedbacks (
  <a rid="r2" ref-type="bibr" href="#r2">2</a>, 
  <a rid="r42" ref-type="bibr" href="#r42">42</a>). This is because soil moisture–temperature feedbacks are directly influenced by surface radiation budgets (e.g., Bowen ratio), are less likely to be driven by an external variable (e.g., sea surface temperatures), and are less influenced by statistical challenges of precipitation persistence (
  <a rid="r2" ref-type="bibr" href="#r2">2</a>). We further aimed to minimize the problems of challenge 2 by using an array of time windows and removing seasonal patterns in variables (see below). Challenge 3 is an important caveat in all soil moisture feedback analyses, and causality can only be fully prescribed with mechanistic model simulations that vary soil moisture boundary conditions, something that cannot be done with observational datasets. However, some statistical techniques assess “predictive causality” (e.g., Granger causality), which is more rigorous than simple correlation, and is used for the satellite-based feedbacks assessed here (
  <a rid="r6" ref-type="bibr" href="#r6">6</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1904747116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S1
  </span> presents an illustration of how we quantified feedbacks by showing the calculation from a given day 
  <span class="italic">i</span> at a given site. Within each growing season at each eddy covariance site, we first calculated all nonoverlapping 1-, 7-, and 14-d averages for T, VPD, and SH. From each period, we then calculated the preceding 1-, 7-, and 14-d period averages for soil moisture. Where preceding soil moisture data were not within the plant-active season, those dates were dropped from the analysis (for example, day 2 of a growing season would have a value for the preceding 1-d period, but not the preceding 7- or 14-d period, and thus would not be included in those analyses). In the case of data gaps, a majority of days with data were required to be included. The 3 time periods of dependent variables (T, VPD, SH) and 3 time periods of the independent variable (preceding soil moisture) led to 9 combinations over which we calculated Pearson correlation coefficients, where negative correlations indicate “drought intensification” because declines in soil moisture are correlated with subsequent increases in T/VPD/SH. We used this suite of different time periods to 1) ensure that the patterns in drought intensification that we observed were robust to different methods, and 2) to capture effects at longer timescales where autocorrelation of T, VPD, and SH are much lower (
  <a rid="r44" ref-type="bibr" href="#r44">44</a>). In addition, we calculated these correlations after removing a seasonal pattern from all variables via fitting a quadratic regression for each year and performing the correlations on the residuals for a random subset of 10 flux sites. The feedback correlations on the deseasonalized data were quite similar to the correlations used in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" href="#fig01">Fig. 1</a> (
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.65, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.001), indicating that seasonal or synoptic patterns are not likely behind site differences. Because the correlations were quite consistent across different time period combinations (e.g., 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" href="#fig01">Fig. 1</a>), we averaged all 9 time period combinations to yield an average feedback strength for each site for the model selection analyses.
 </p>
</sec>
