<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Trait and Climate Data.</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on an extensive review of the literature and publications from individual eddy covariance sites, we compiled lists of the dominant tree species present in the footprint of each tower and, where possible, the relative abundance of these species. Abundance data were available for around 60% of sites. We then compiled the functional traits for species present in these sites, drawing on the Global Wood Density Database (
  <a rid="r34" ref-type="bibr" href="#r34">34</a>) for wood density data, the dataset presented in ref. 
  <a rid="r35" ref-type="bibr" href="#r35">35</a> for light-saturated maximum photosynthetic rate and SLA, and the Xylem Functional Traits dataset (
  <a rid="r36" ref-type="bibr" href="#r36">36</a>) for data on the water potential at 50% loss of stem hydraulic conductivity and the hydraulic safety margin. These traits influence a diversity of important plant functions, including maximum gas exchange rate and the vulnerability of water transport to drought conditions. Furthermore, these traits are actively being incorporated into next-generation land surface models (
  <a rid="r13" ref-type="bibr" href="#r13">13</a>, 
  <a rid="r31" ref-type="bibr" href="#r31">31</a>, 
  <a rid="r32" ref-type="bibr" href="#r32">32</a>, 
  <a rid="r37" ref-type="bibr" href="#r37">37</a>) and thus their importance for drought intensification is useful to test. At each site, we calculated the community-weighted (i.e., composition weighted) trait mean and SD for each trait with values for more than 80% of the plant community. The mean provides an estimate of the average plant strategy in the ecosystem and the SD provides insight into the diversity of strategies/traits present.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition, we compiled the reported age of the canopy trees and the mean annual temperature and mean annual precipitation reported as metadata in the FLUXNET2015 dataset for each site as important climate variables that might influence cross-site patterns. We used the site latitude and longitude to extract the growing season (defined here as June–August for northern hemisphere and December–February for southern hemisphere) temperature and precipitation from Climatic Research Unit data (
  <a rid="r38" ref-type="bibr" href="#r38">38</a>) for the 1980–2008 period. We further extracted annual and growing season potential evapotranspiration (PET) for each site (averaged over the 1980–2008 period) from the Sheffield dataset (
  <a rid="r39" ref-type="bibr" href="#r39">39</a>) and included site mean annual PET, mean growing season PET, mean annual precipitation minus mean annual PET, and mean growing season precipitation minus mean growing season PET as potential climate predictor variables. Growing season temperature was also predictive of feedbacks, but was less strongly correlated with feedbacks than MAT (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1904747116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S7
  </span>) and thus was not included in the final models. See 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1904747116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Table S2
  </span> for all predictor variables.
 </p>
</sec>
