<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par5" class="p">The Pearl River basin is a much studied system, with numerous previous studies focusing on diverse system characteristics such as the formation and evolution of the delta
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" class="xref">42</xref>
 </sup>, hydrological changes in response to human activities
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" class="xref">43</xref>
 </sup>, sediment trapping rates in dams
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">38</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" class="xref">39</xref>
 </sup>, delta shoreline changes
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" class="xref">41</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" class="xref">44</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" class="xref">46</xref>
 </sup>, estuarine engineering (e.g. sand excavation, reclamation, and dike building)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" class="xref">47</xref>
 </sup> and fluvial sediment loads
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" class="xref">32</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" class="xref">33</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">38</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" class="xref">39</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" class="xref">48</xref>
 </sup>. However, all previous studies on the latter, which is the focus of this study, have concentrated on changes observed over the second half of the 20
 <sup class="sup">th</sup> century and the first decade or so of the 21
 <sup class="sup">st</sup> century. Here, for the first time, we investigate fluvial sediment loads in the Pearl River over the extended period 1954–2100; a period that not only encompasses marked historical changes caused by human activities, but also the future effects of projected accelerated climate change
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">30</xref>
 </sup>. Specifically, here we analyse changes in fluvial sediment loads in the historical period 1954–2013, and derive future projections of fluvial sediment loads up to the end of the 21
 <sup class="sup">st</sup> century under a worst case climate change scenario. The analysis of results provides quantitative insights on the relative contributions of climate change and human activities to variations in fluvial sediment supply to the coast over this ~150 year period spanning the past and the future.
</p>
