<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Coherence between national policies are essential for working towards shared goals limiting conflicting or maladaptive strategies. National policy processes, such as the Joint NAPs of several countries in the Pacific, are important for identifying disaster and climate change vulnerabilities, and DRR and CCA options and priorities [
 <xref rid="B26-ijerph-15-00793" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>,
 <xref rid="B90-ijerph-15-00793" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">90</xref>]. Numerous examples for successful integration have been identified, including in the South-West Pacific, particularly the Solomon Islands and Vanuatu [
 <xref rid="B51-ijerph-15-00793" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">51</xref>]. These links between DRR and CCA have since been reflected at the regional level through the replacement of the Pacific DRR and Disaster Management Framework for Action 2005–2015 and Pacific Islands Framework for Action on Climate Change 2006–2015 [
 <xref rid="B51-ijerph-15-00793" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">51</xref>] with the Framework for Resilient Development in the Pacific An Integrated Approach to Address Climate Change and Disaster Risk Management 2017–2030, and the development of the Pacific Platform for Disaster Risk Management and Climate Change [
 <xref rid="B112-ijerph-15-00793" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">112</xref>]. These policies themselves represent technical synergies. They also have the potential to facilitate further technical and operational synergies in the implementation of DRR and CCA. National DRR and CCA in health policies are an important foundation for building technical and operational links. The H-NAP process or similar disaster policy and planning processes in health may also offer opportunities for building technical and operational synergies. It is important for climate policies in health to pay adequate attention to the health risks of extreme weather [
 <xref rid="B81-ijerph-15-00793" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">81</xref>]. However, there is no research on links between DRR and CCA through similar policy processes in health. An important step in the H-NAP process is the Vulnerability and Adaptation Assessment.
</p>
