<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Our model incorporates 
 <italic class="italic">q</italic>-deformation in the equations, as the tritrophic system’s population cycles bear memory of previous years’ growth of the larch. There is a strong and complex interplay between the parasitoids living off budmoth larvae, the plant quality index measuring the health of the larch, and the larch budmoth. This memory makes the system non-ergodic, since all possible states are no longer equiprobable and certain events may possibly be favoured over others. The probability distribution is now skewed, since the organisms’ behaviour, led by different kinds of signals received at different times
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15" class="xref">15</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16" class="xref">16</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17" class="xref">17</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18" class="xref">18</xref>, causes a suppression of some probabilities while enhancing others. Owing to the variety of factors contributing to the information content in a biological system at any instant of time, with memory of previous configurations being retained in the system, a Boltzmann-Gibbs distribution that attributes equal probabilities to all situations is no longer applicable and fails. Such systems as well as those with long range interactions and strong correlations are better explained with Tsallis probability distribution
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19" class="xref">19</xref> which introduces a parameter 
 <italic class="italic">q</italic> that allows, depending upon its value, some probabilities to be suppressed and some to be enhanced. Thus the 
 <italic class="italic">q</italic>-value would indicate how the system’s behaviour is manifested — whether through rare events or through common events. Tsallis’ non-extensive statistical mechanics expresses naturally through 
 <italic class="italic">q</italic>-deformed numbers, with 
 <italic class="italic">q</italic> ≠ 1, the standard Boltzmann-Gibbs distribution being recovered in the limit 
 <italic class="italic">q</italic> → 1.
</p>
