<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par33" class="p">However, precipitation is not constant but varies on multi-annual time scales. In the tropics, rainfall over land is often controlled by the magnitude and distribution of sea surface temperature (SST). Tropical SSTs show characteristic modes of variability like the El Nino Southern Oscillation (ENSO), Pacific decadal oscillation (PDO) and Atlantic multidecadal oscillation (AMO) which affect tropical rainfall. For example, high Atlantic SSTs can lead to severe droughts in the Amazon like those observed in recent years
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77" class="xref">77</xref>
 </sup>, and changes in ENSO activity strongly affect Amazon rainfall and vegetation
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78" class="xref">78</xref>
 </sup>. Proxy-based reconstructions suggest that ENSO amplitude was low during the mid-Holocene, and relatively high in recent decades
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79" class="xref">79</xref>
 </sup>. Moreover, tree rings indicate that ENSO amplitude and frequency have changed substantially on decadal to centennial time scales during the last 1,000 years
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80" class="xref">80</xref>
 </sup>. The time scales of such changes are on the same order of magnitude than the time scale of tree growth which suggests the possibility that terrestrial tipping points can be triggered by changes in ENSO variability
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81" class="xref">81</xref>
 </sup>. It is important in this context that a dieback caused by a large-scale drought can occur within a much shorter time than regrowth – in contrast to our example model above, the system is not symmetric. This time scale asymmetry suggests that forests are not safe from a drought-induced collapse even if the long-term mean rainfall is very large.
</p>
