<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec009" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our sampling strategy was to include junipers from all age classes within the forest and at stands along different altitudinal gradients, resulting in a new and substantial TRW network for eastern UZ and the whole of KG. At some sites and regions, old and slow-grown trees were found such as at KS (Naryn, KG) or ZNP-JUSE (UZ) with chronologies extending back to AD 1269 and 1482 (un-truncated; 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0153888.s001" href="#pone.0153888.s001">S1 Table</a>), respectively. However, further endeavors are necessary to develop well-replicated and robust millennial-long chronologies as shown by Seim 
  <span class="italic">et al</span> [
  <a rid="pone.0153888.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153888.ref035">35</a>]. On the other hand, junipers at some sites were comparatively young in age, for instance at AE and KM (Naryn, KG), pointing to large-scale clear cuts at the end/beginning of the 19
  <span class="sup">th</span>/20
  <span class="sup">th</span> century. At both sites, single juniper individuals with ages of ~470 years (AE) and ~350 years (KM) were found. However, strong differences in growth variations between old and young trees hampered successful crossdating, and TRW measurements of those old trees were excluded in this study, restricting our common period to 1935–2011.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is important to note that the CRU grid points (
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 12) located closest to the sampling sites (with an average linear distance of ~ 14 km from the sampling sites) (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0153888.g001" href="#pone.0153888.g001">Fig 1</a>), might not fully represent local climate conditions. By comparing observations from the closest available meteorological stations (average linear distance of ~ 29 km from the sampling sites) in KG and UZ [
  <a rid="pone.0153888.ref041" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153888.ref041">41</a>] for the baseline period 1961–1990, absolute annual temperatures derived from the CRU grid point data were on average lower (2.3°C) than those obtained from the stations. This is especially evident in winter where the temperature differences were up to 3.3°C, whereas summer temperatures differed only by 1.5°C. For precipitation, overall drier conditions were observed in the CRU data compared to the instrumental data, especially during summer, with an average of 40 mm less rainfall. However, it is also not expected that even meteorological station data might fully represent the climate condition at the sampling sites due to differences in elevation, as discussed by Seim 
  <span class="italic">et al</span> [
  <a rid="pone.0153888.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153888.ref035">35</a>]. Nevertheless, overall long-term trends in temperature and precipitation anomalies for the CRU and station data are in high agreement as shown by Harris 
  <span class="italic">et al</span> [
  <a rid="pone.0153888.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153888.ref042">42</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">By choosing two climatological periods at each end of this time window, we detected changes in climate and in the climate sensitivity of the juniper trees. However, less distinct results were obtained when using variations in juniper growth since the trees respond not only to sudden changes in climate but also to human impacts, stand dynamics (i.e. competition) and other abiotic and biotic disturbance factors [
  <a rid="pone.0153888.ref045" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153888.ref045">45</a>]. Therefore, adding information of tree growth for longer time scales would make the interpretation more robust.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It should be noted that spatial interpolation methods use the maximum range of given values and thus, might be biased by single sites, i.e. data points, while altitudinal differences at the same location are captured only insufficiently. The IDW applied here, however, is a valuable tool to present geographical point data spatially with high efficiency and easy interpretation skills [
  <a rid="pone.0153888.ref046" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153888.ref046">46</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The observed changes in climate during the past ~80 years are in accordance with previous findings for Central Asia (e.g. [
  <a rid="pone.0153888.ref003" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153888.ref003">3</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0153888.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153888.ref004">4</a>]). Our results confirm a spatially uniform temperature increase while trends in precipitation regimes are highly diverse across the study region. Shifts in climatic means are additionally enhanced by feedback mechanisms such as increased evaporation due to rising temperatures, changes in snow cover (depth and duration) and in glacier resources [
  <a rid="pone.0153888.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153888.ref004">4</a>]. Although increased greenhouse gas emissions caused a warming of the atmosphere over the past century [
  <a rid="pone.0153888.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153888.ref001">1</a>], the observed climatic trends and patterns across Central Asia are most likely attributed to 1) feedback mechanisms with the diverse topography and land use [
  <a rid="pone.0153888.ref006" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153888.ref006">6</a>] and 2) observed changes in atmospheric circulation patterns. In the latter case, our 1982–2011 period concurs with an exceptionally strong positive phase of the North Atlantic Oscillation since the 1980s, which contributed to higher than normal winter temperatures, not only in northern Europe, but also in Central Asia [
  <a rid="pone.0153888.ref047" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153888.ref047">47</a>]. In addition, an increase in spring to autumn hot extremes was observed in western and central Asia during the last 30 years, associated with an increase in persistent anticyclonic pressure systems [
  <a rid="pone.0153888.ref048" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153888.ref048">48</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although changes in climate during the past eight decades were remarkable and comparatively rapid, trends in juniper growth are less obvious and uniform. Combining the obtained results, we can summarize that juniper trees at the sites in Karakol, KG, with humid growing season climate (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0153888.g001" href="#pone.0153888.g001">Fig 1</a>) seem to have benefited from drier summers and consequently, showed increasing growth rates. Conversely, the drier and warmer sites in our study region (i.e. Zaamin, UZ, or Naryn, KG) showed no increases, or slight declines, in annual increments over the analyzed period. Our results, although not being very distinct, are in agreement with general trends observed for semi-arid environments in Asia and Europe. Liu 
  <span class="italic">et al</span> [
  <a rid="pone.0153888.ref049" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153888.ref049">49</a>] found significant reductions in tree growth for a compilation of various coniferous species in Inner Asia from 1994 onwards, particularly at semi-arid sites. Also, Galvan 
  <span class="italic">et al</span> [
  <a rid="pone.0153888.ref050" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153888.ref050">50</a>], reviewing 66 dendrochronological studies including different broadleaf and coniferous species from more than 640 sites, detected an overall tendency of positive (negative) growth trends at temperate (xeric) sites across the Mediterranean Basin since the 1970’s. Differences in juniper growth at different sites can be linked to different physiological responses regarding gas exchange and water use. Increasing atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub> concentrations have been related to increased intrinsic water-use efficiency, where increased drought stress can lead to reduced stomatal conductance to compensate water loss at the expense of secondary growth [
  <a rid="pone.0153888.ref051" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153888.ref051">51</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0153888.ref054" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153888.ref054">54</a>]. However, detailed studies are needed on 1) all three juniper subspecies as individual tree species seem to perform differently, e.g. [
  <a rid="pone.0153888.ref055" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153888.ref055">55</a>] and 2) trees from different climate regimes and sites across Central Asia. Moreover, changes in climate responses during winter and spring may additionally modify annual growth as has previously been reported for spruce at tree-line sites in Alaska, where warmer July temperatures lead to a decline in growth and warmer springs enhanced growth [
  <a rid="pone.0153888.ref056" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153888.ref056">56</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Over the full 1935–2011 period, the growth-climate relationships of the juniper sites generally showed benefiting effects on tree growth from warm temperatures at high altitudes and abundant moisture supply at low elevation sites (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0153888.g002" href="#pone.0153888.g002">Fig 2</a>), agreeing with the general assumption of limiting factors on tree growth [
  <a rid="pone.0153888.ref045" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153888.ref045">45</a>]. Although the temperature signal in the juniper TRW data was not as strong and statistically significant as, for example, in conifers from tree-line sites in the European Alps [
  <a rid="pone.0153888.ref057" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153888.ref057">57</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0153888.ref058" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153888.ref058">58</a>] or the Tibetan Plateau [
  <a rid="pone.0153888.ref059" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153888.ref059">59</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0153888.ref061" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153888.ref061">61</a>], our results are in accordance with findings from earlier studies in KG [
  <a rid="pone.0153888.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153888.ref028">28</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0153888.ref062" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153888.ref062">62</a>] and UZ [
  <a rid="pone.0153888.ref024" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153888.ref024">24</a>]. The most likely cause for the relatively low number of statistically significant correlations between juniper growth (i.e. TRW) from high elevations and temperature are temporal instabilities in the climate signal, as indicated by our results. We found distinct response shifts where junipers from high elevation sites were becoming increasingly drought stressed during the past 30 years (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0153888.g005" href="#pone.0153888.g005">Fig 5</a>), a result that not only deviates from the principle of uniformitarianism but also from the principle of limiting factors of tree growth in high mountain environments [
  <a rid="pone.0153888.ref045" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153888.ref045">45</a>]. Shifting growth-climate responses have also been detected at high elevation conifer sites in Europe (e.g., [
  <a rid="pone.0153888.ref063" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153888.ref063">63</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0153888.ref064" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153888.ref064">64</a>]), restricting the development of temperature reconstructions, or for bristlecone pines near the tree line in the White Mountains of California, USA [
  <a rid="pone.0153888.ref065" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153888.ref065">65</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conversely, junipers at lower altitudes showed distinct and persistent drought responses, which has previously been shown for 
  <span class="italic">J</span>. 
  <span class="italic">seravschanica</span> in the Zaamin National Park, UZ [
  <a rid="pone.0153888.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153888.ref035">35</a>]. Liu 
  <span class="italic">et al</span> [
  <a rid="pone.0153888.ref049" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153888.ref049">49</a>] or Liang 
  <span class="italic">et al</span> [
  <a rid="pone.0153888.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153888.ref016">16</a>] noted also an increase in sensitivity to drought and drought-related parameters in Inner Asia. However, increasing temperatures and more frequent droughts that are predicted for the future [
  <a rid="pone.0153888.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153888.ref001">1</a>], are likely to increase the risk of forest decline, starting at lower elevations [
  <a rid="pone.0153888.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153888.ref015">15</a>]. Moreover, upslope shifts of the juniper forests due to increased tree mortality can be expected, which can occur rapidly and over large areas, as observed for a semi-arid ecotone in northern New Mexico after a severe drought event [
  <a rid="pone.0153888.ref066" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0153888.ref066">66</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The identified growth-climate response shifts in our study, which occurred only within the past 40 to 50 years, most likely indicate impacts of the ongoing climate change on juniper growth in Central Asia. We therefore stress the importance of long-term conservation measures to counteract possible losses or reductions of the mountain juniper forest ecosystems in UZ and KG. Our findings also highlight the need of time-dependency analyses in paleo-climatological studies when using high elevation juniper trees, as well as the integration of growth-climate response shifts when assessing and predicting vegetation dynamics in Central Asia.</p>
</sec>
