<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec008" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Changes in climate, juniper growth, and climate responses</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From 1935–1964 to 1982–2011, winter temperatures increased by 0.6°C to 2.4°C from eastern UZ to eastern KG, whereas the highest increase in summer temperatures of 1.1°C was recorded in central and eastern KG (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0153888.g003" href="#pone.0153888.g003">Fig 3A and 3B</a>). Winter rainfall increased by 56 mm in eastern UZ but remained more or less constant in central and eastern KG (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0153888.g003" href="#pone.0153888.g003">Fig 3C</a>). The smallest changes in rainfall were observed during summer in the eastern parts of both countries, increasing by 12 mm in northeastern UZ (Chimgan) and southern KG (Karakuldja) (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0153888.g003" href="#pone.0153888.g003">Fig 3D</a>).
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0153888.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0153888.g003</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 3</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Changes in climate from the 1935–1964 to 1982–2011 period spatially interpolated from the climate data (CRU grid point, red dots) closest to the tree-ring sites (black dots) for a) winter (previous year December to current year February, pDJF) and b) summer (June–August; JJA) temperature and c) winter and d) summer precipitation.</div>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0153888.g003" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Changes in annual tree growth using detrended TRW indices indicated slight but significant (
  <span class="italic">p</span>&lt;0.01) increases in increments by ~0.2 index units, being most pronounced mainly at the highest altitudes (&gt; ~2500 m asl) in southwestern KG (Khaidarkan and Kyrgyz Ata) (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0153888.g004" href="#pone.0153888.g004">Fig 4A and 4B</a>). On the other hand, no changes or even slight decreases in annual growth were observed at the lower elevation sites in Zaamin (UZ) and at sites in Sari Chelek and Naryn (KG). However, considering the temporal variability among the individual TRW chronologies over the last decades (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0153888.s004" href="#pone.0153888.s004">S1 Fig</a>), those values might not be fully representative. Changes in growth patterns at interannual to decadal time scales, most likely related to anthropogenic impacts, were observed at B2H (Chimgan, UZ) and KAnw (Kyrgyz Ata, KG) (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0153888.s004" href="#pone.0153888.s004">S1 Fig</a>).
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0153888.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0153888.g004</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 4</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Changes in juniper growth from the 1935–1964 to 1982–2011 period a) spatially interpolated from the 33 sites (black dots) and b) shown as a function of altitude.</span> Red dots denote the sites closest CRU grid point.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0153888.g004" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Distinct changes in the climate response of juniper trees were observed across the study area and with respect to elevation (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0153888.g005" href="#pone.0153888.g005">Fig 5</a>). Focusing on the temperature response in JJA, sites located in Zaamin (UZ), Kyrgyz Ata and Karakuldja (southern KG) and Karakol (eastern KG), showed increased negative responses to high temperatures (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0153888.g005" href="#pone.0153888.g005">Fig 5A</a>). In contrast, junipers in Chimgan (UZ) seem to be less stressed by warm temperatures in recent decades, and significant changes in correlations were observed at B2H with 
  <span class="italic">r</span> = 0.47 (
  <span class="italic">p</span>&lt;0.01; from 
  <span class="italic">r</span> = -0.22 to 
  <span class="italic">r</span> = 0.25) and B2L with 
  <span class="italic">r</span> = 0.41 (
  <span class="italic">p</span>&lt;0.05; from 
  <span class="italic">r</span> = -0.35 to 
  <span class="italic">r</span> = 0.06) (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0153888.s003" href="#pone.0153888.s003">S3A Table</a>). Thus, during 1935–1964, there was an increasingly positive influence of temperatures with increasing altitude (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0153888.g005" href="#pone.0153888.g005">Fig 5B</a>). On the contrary, in the past 30 years at several high elevation sites, junipers have become negatively influenced by high temperatures (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0153888.g005" href="#pone.0153888.g005">Fig 5B</a>), where the most pronounced shifts are seen in the high-pass filtered data (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0153888.g005" href="#pone.0153888.g005">Fig 5B</a>, dashed trend lines).
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0153888.g005" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0153888.g005</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 5</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Changes in climate response for the June–August (JJA) season of all 33 sites (black dots) with its closest CRU grid point dataset (red dots) from the 1935–1964 to 1982–2011 period.</div>
   <p>Differences in 
    <span class="bold">a)</span> temperature and 
    <span class="bold">c)</span> precipitation response were spatially interpolated. TRW sites with significant correlations for one of the periods are shown as a function of elevation for 
    <span class="bold">b)</span> temperature (15 sites) and 
    <span class="bold">d)</span> precipitation (22 sites) with the unfiltered and filtered (see legend and numbers in brackets) data.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0153888.g005" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Regarding the spatial precipitation responses, all regions except Karakuldja (southern KG) showed increased positive correlations in 1982–2011 compared to 1935–1964 (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0153888.g005" href="#pone.0153888.g005">Fig 5C</a>), although this was manifested in different ways. Junipers in the east of our study area, e.g. in Chimgan (UZ), showed increases in the positive correlations with precipitation, i.e. at B1H from 
  <span class="italic">r</span> = 0.14 to 
  <span class="italic">r</span> = 0.56 (
  <span class="italic">p</span>&lt;0.01) or ML from 
  <span class="italic">r</span> = 0.17 to 
  <span class="italic">r</span> = 0.53 (
  <span class="italic">p</span>&lt;0.01). However, for junipers in Karakol (eastern KG), where growth was limited by high precipitation during 1935–1964, decreasing precipitation amounts led to improved growing conditions in recent decades. Significant changes in correlation values were found for all three sites but especially for AY (from 
  <span class="italic">r</span> = -0.36 to 
  <span class="italic">r</span> = 0.18) and ADJ (from 
  <span class="italic">r</span> = -0.43 to 
  <span class="italic">r</span> = -0.08) (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0153888.s003" href="#pone.0153888.s003">S3B Table</a>). Across all altitudes, a tendency towards increasingly positive correlations with precipitation was observed (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0153888.g005" href="#pone.0153888.g005">Fig 5D</a>), suggesting a higher water demand for tree growth also at high elevation sites.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">However, the observed changes were not only restricted to summer. Warmer winters had positive influences on juniper growth at seven sites, while increased spring temperatures negatively affected tree growth at four sites (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0153888.s003" href="#pone.0153888.s003">S3 Table</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
