<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec007" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Growth-climate response (1935–2011)</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The growth-climate responses obtained for the full 1935–2011 period highlight the diversity in climate sensitivity of junipers across different elevations and regions (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0153888.s001" href="#pone.0153888.s001">S1 Table</a>). Only junipers in southwest KG showed a distinct precipitation response at lower elevations (Khaidarkan and Krygyz Ata until ~2500 m asl; Karakuldja until ~2000 m asl) and a temperature response at higher altitudes towards the end of the growing season (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0153888.s001" href="#pone.0153888.s001">S1 Table</a>). Juniper at all other sites and regions responded either to a lack in water supply or to high temperatures in spring, summer or during the full growing season, i.e. April to October (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0153888.s001" href="#pone.0153888.s001">S1</a> and 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0153888.s002" href="#pone.0153888.s002">S2</a> Tables).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Moreover, only a few sites responded to one single climate parameter (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0153888.s002" href="#pone.0153888.s002">S2 Table</a>). TRW in KAnw (Kyrgyz Ata, KG), TOH (Karakuldja, KG) and ADJ (Karakol, KG) was positively correlated with temperature, while TRW in SK (Chimgan, UZ), TLL (Karakuldja, KG), SH1 and ARN (both Naryn, KG) showed distinct precipitation associations at monthly to seasonal scales (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0153888.s002" href="#pone.0153888.s002">S2 Table</a>). The remaining 26 sites exhibited either a mixed climate response or changing responses over the course of the year. Strong responses to drought, expressed as negative/positive correlations with temperature/precipitation at the same time, were observed for ZNP-JUSE (Zaamin, UZ) and most of the sites in Naryn, central KG, especially in summer but also during the entire vegetation period (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0153888.s002" href="#pone.0153888.s002">S2 Table</a>). Regarding changes in climate sensitivity, six (five) sites experienced changing temperature (precipitation) responses during all seasons (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0153888.s002" href="#pone.0153888.s002">S2 Table</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In summer, a total of seven sites located at higher elevations showed significant positive summer temperature responses, while drought was the dominant growth limiting factor at lower altitudes (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0153888.g002" href="#pone.0153888.g002">Fig 2</a>; 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0153888.s002" href="#pone.0153888.s002">S2 Table</a>). Thus, an overall linear increasing trend in temperature sensitivity and decreasing trend in precipitation sensitivity with increasing elevation, was observed for both original and high-pass filtered data (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0153888.g002" href="#pone.0153888.g002">Fig 2</a>).
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0153888.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0153888.g002</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 2</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Climate response for June–August a) temperature and b) precipitation of all 33 juniper sites as a function of elevation for the AD 1935–2011 period.</span> Correlation values are shown for the original and filtered (10-year high-pass (HP)) data.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0153888.g002" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
