<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Management aiming at favouring adaptation processes in forest ecosystems encompasses three different strategies, namely (i) breeding programs incorporating new and adapted genes; (ii) silvicultural methods directed to enhance local adaptation; and (iii) management strategies to prevent disease occurrence. Selecting one of them should directly depend on exposure and on the importance of the target population on the regional economies. When deciding among these, exposure assessment, together with productivity, play a fundamental role. Forest management of 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">pinaster</italic> would benefit from strategies directed at improving the species’ capacities to deal with drought stresses as well as at enhancing the species’ resistance to 
 <italic class="italic">Fusarium circinatum</italic>. In this direction, breeding programs are likely to be effective, as differences in responses to drought and to the pathogen have been reported to be genetically controlled [
 <xref rid="pone.0171549.ref074" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">74</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0171549.ref075" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">75</xref>]. In fact, in a provenance/progeny trial [
 <xref rid="pone.0171549.ref041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>], large differences in resistance to pitch canker disease were found among and within populations suggesting a host response to the disease through natural or artificial selection, with important genetic gain for 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">pinaster</italic> resistance. Nevertheless, because breeding programs are expensive and long lasting, they should be applied to specific, highly-exposed and valuable populations with impact on regional economies, such as those located at the northernmost edge of the distribution [
 <xref rid="pone.0171549.ref076" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">76</xref>], which coincide overall with areas under high biotic exposure (seed zones 1 to 6). In addition, areas under uncertain biotic exposure (particularly those from seed zones 1 and 2) should be closely monitored, given the potential consequences of a disease outbreak, and that a modification in the dynamic of the host-pathogen interaction could result in significant changes in the predicted impact of the disease. The remaining populations are mostly affected by abiotic exposure, so a monitoring program should be applied to detect changes either in the host or the pathogen, and silvicultural practices aimed to fasten adaptation. Among these practices, those directed at reducing competition for (water) resources, such as decreasing tree density [
 <xref rid="pone.0171549.ref043" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>] and favouring unevenness between sizes and ages of the trees in a stand [
 <xref rid="pone.0171549.ref073" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">73</xref>], are particularly adequate for 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">pinaster</italic>. In addition, thinning [
 <xref rid="pone.0171549.ref043" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>] and extending rotation times—as juveniles are more sensitive to droughts than adults [
 <xref rid="pone.0171549.ref073" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">73</xref>]–are other recommended management guidelines for threatened populations.
</p>
