<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Health risks are likely to be influenced by the interaction of future climate change with concomitant changes in sociodemographic, physical, and ecological systems (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1" class="xref">Figure 1</xref>). Global climate change not only affects ecosystems (e.g., changing the range and distribution of vectors), but events attributable to climate change such as heat waves, floods, droughts, and bushfires can influence socioeconomic development (e.g., damaging major roads, community services, and public health infrastructure). All these will have an impact and will increasingly affect human health and sustainable development. Therefore, there is an urgent need to understand these interactions, and facilitate public understanding and informed policy making. However, climatic and non-climatic effects are often complex and difficult to disentangle. The modeling of joint effects is a challenge as there is a wide range of unforeseeable and powerful changes that might occur in social and economic circumstances. It is necessary to develop better research methods (e.g., scenario-based forecasting models) and better data to tackle these complex issues. For example, it is important to project future impacts of climate change on malaria to support effective policy-making and intervention activity concerning malaria control and prevention. Accruing evidence converges on a singular point: The direct effect of climate change on future malaria transmission results in an increase of the simulated length of the malaria transmission season over the tropical highlands (
 <xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Caminade et al. 2014</xref>). This evidence was further corroborated by 
 <xref rid="r21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Siraj et al. (2014)</xref> who employed climatic and malaria incidence observations over the plateaus of Ethiopia and Colombia, and is also consistent with results published in the AR5-Working Group II report of the IPCC (
 <xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">IPCC 2014</xref>). Climate change will likely expand the distribution of disease vectors to non-endemic areas, increase the length of the disease-transmission season, and facilitate the host–vector-environment interactions in many regions (
 <xref rid="r22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Smith et al. 2014</xref>). The recent spread of the Zika virus may be an indication of what we can expect with continuous environmental changes, and it is suggested that, even though the geographic expansion of the Zika virus is primarily related to increased international travel, climate change may also have helped the spread of this virus (
 <xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Paz and Semenza 2016</xref>). Therefore, it is necessary to enhance the effort to develop vaccines for climate sensitive diseases. It is also important to note that vaccine development would greatly lessen the burden of suffering from those diseases regardless of the climate change impacts.
</p>
