<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Considering previous evidence for climate‐related differences in color morphs, it is surprising that only one of our predictions was supported. There are a few plausible reasons for this. First, 
 <italic class="italic">P. cinereus</italic> populations are relatively isolated (Cabe et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32573-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>), and it is possible that morph‐specific differences are not maintained in the population we studied. Differences would only be maintained if climate was a strong disruptive selective pressure (Barrett &amp; Schluter, 
 <xref rid="ece32573-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>), and Maryland's climate may be variable enough that selection is stabilizing. Behavioral adaptation is one of the fastest evolutionary responses, so stabilizing selection would result in a fixed breadth of behavioral responses for both morphs in a relatively short amount of time (Snell‐Rood, 
 <xref rid="ece32573-bib-0075" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). Second, the environmental conditions we observed may not have been extreme enough to influence demography, or if morph differences did exist, it may not lead to behavioral or demography differences for the factors we measured. Lastly, the 
 <italic class="italic">P. cinereus</italic> color morph may not be a useful indicator in understanding climate tolerances. Our findings lend credence to growing evidence that the polymorphism is not tied to climate (Moore &amp; Ouellet, 
 <xref rid="ece32573-bib-0050" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>), but may be maintained by assortative mating (Anthony et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32573-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>) or apostatic selection (Fitzpatrick, Shook, &amp; Izally, 
 <xref rid="ece32573-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>). Our study suggests that the color morph is an equivocal proxy at best for understanding climate tolerance variability.
</p>
