<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec022" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Changes in the species phenology and trophic consequences</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The majority (i.e., two third) of fish species and all zooplankton species exhibited modification in their yearly abundance pattern in the Gironde estuarine nursery ground for at least one indicator. Most of these species occurred earlier in the estuary during the last ‘intershift’ periods than during the first one. This may be explained through an adaptation of species spawning period in order to optimize the timing of migration towards the coast in optimal environmental conditions, such as reported for the anchovy in the Bay of Biscay [
  <a rid="pone.0173752.ref072" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0173752.ref072">72</a>]. Other studies reported precocity in downstream migration of fish (e.i 
  <span class="italic">Platichthys flesus</span>) driven by rising temperature [e.g. 71]. For copepods and mysids, our study is the first to demonstrate an early peak of production in the Gironde estuary, although similar phenological changes have previously been observed in other aquatic systems for those groups [
  <a rid="pone.0173752.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0173752.ref016">16</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0173752.ref066" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0173752.ref066">66</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0173752.ref073" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0173752.ref073">73</a>]. Changes in the timing of annual zooplankton production may be explained by the earlier appearance of “spring” warmer environmental conditions [
  <a rid="pone.0173752.ref017" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0173752.ref017">17</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0173752.ref074" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0173752.ref074">74</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0173752.ref075" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0173752.ref075">75</a>]. A similar situation may therefore pertain in the Gironde estuary. In the Gironde, upstream movement of copepods, associated with changes in their ecological niche [
  <a rid="pone.0173752.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0173752.ref044">44</a>], could contribute to explain observed changes in their production seasonality [
  <a rid="pone.0173752.ref076" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0173752.ref076">76</a>]. Other authors made similar observations for fish in other estuarine systems. For instance, the combination of warming and increase of river and estuary water discharge is a crucial trigger of upstream movements in estuaries for marine fish such as soles and flounders [
  <a rid="pone.0173752.ref068" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0173752.ref068">68</a>] and for diadromous species such as the Alosa sapidissima in northwestern United [
  <a rid="pone.0173752.ref077" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0173752.ref077">77</a>] State. Such impact of environmental shifts on species phenological cycle have been documented in many other aquatic and terrestrial ecosystems [
  <a rid="pone.0173752.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0173752.ref020">20</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0173752.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0173752.ref021">21</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0173752.ref071" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0173752.ref071">71</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0173752.ref078" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0173752.ref078">78</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0173752.ref079" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0173752.ref079">79</a>]. However, understanding if a phenological modification is a direct response to environmental modifications or an indirect response to prey availability remains a challenge. In the Gironde estuary, we observed a synchronous modification of the first three major environmental variables (salinity, river discharge and air temperature) in spring (between March and May). Spring temperatures and salinity increased during the last two periods, whereas river discharge decreased. This suggests an “earlier spring” as proposed by Le Treut [
  <a rid="pone.0173752.ref080" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0173752.ref080">80</a>] in the Gironde estuary? Further comprehensive studies about the causal link between earlier spring conditions and phenological observations highlighted in our study therefore appear essential.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For five fish species, no phenological change among the three periods examined were observed 
  <span class="italic">L</span>. 
  <span class="italic">ramada</span> and 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">anguilla</span> recruit in the estuary during the winter season, while 
  <span class="italic">O</span>. 
  <span class="italic">eperlanus</span>, 
  <span class="italic">P</span>. 
  <span class="italic">flesus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Solea sp</span>. enter the estuary in spring. Occurrences of these two groups of species in the estuary are therefore driven by different environmental triggers. 
  <span class="italic">O</span>. 
  <span class="italic">eperlanus</span> also disappeared from our samplings from 2006 onwards. The very small abundance of 
  <span class="italic">O</span>.
  <span class="italic">eperlanus</span> observed in the last decades [
  <a rid="pone.0173752.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0173752.ref039">39</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0173752.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0173752.ref043">43</a>] and the highly fluctuating abundances of flounders in recent years [
  <a rid="pone.0173752.ref010" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0173752.ref010">10</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0173752.ref081" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0173752.ref081">81</a>] together suggest a strong modification in environmental conditions triggering their migration in the estuary. However, we still cannot explain the case of 
  <span class="italic">Solea solea</span> which exhibited changes in estuarine recruitement timing in other temperate estuarine ecosystems [
  <a rid="pone.0173752.ref068" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0173752.ref068">68</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0173752.ref074" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0173752.ref074">74</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0173752.ref078" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0173752.ref078">78</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results also showed that almost 40% of studied fish species exhibited changes in their residence time in the estuary. Although the situations were contrasted among species, most of them appeared to spend less time in the estuary during recent periods. These results are contradictory with local observations on the anchovy which have recently increased in abundance and residence time in the estuary [
  <a rid="pone.0173752.ref010" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0173752.ref010">10</a>]. In our study, anchovy’s time of residence in the estuary also increased from the first to the last period, unlike most of the other species examined. Considering the whole set of indicators, we can assume that the Gironde estuary was a more suitable habitat for anchovies in the last two periods, explaining its recent dominance in fish assemblages.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All the fish species we studied use estuaries as nursery grounds or feeding areas during young stages (or entire life cycle for goby) and most of them exhibit a specialist feeding strategy [
  <a rid="pone.0173752.ref082" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0173752.ref082">82</a>]. Zooplankton species, especially copepods and mysid are their preferential prey or represent a significant part of their diet. Trophic interactions between fishes and the aforementioned preys require spatial overlap and temporal synchronicity [
  <a rid="pone.0173752.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0173752.ref015">15</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0173752.ref032" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0173752.ref032">32</a>]. Synchronicity was assessed in this study by estimating the time overlap between preys and predators yearly patterns. Modifications of this overlap (expressed as a % of overlap) induced by temporal shifts in species-specific yearly patterns can be assumed to affect the overall trophic structure of the estuarine community. Our results therefore highlight that monospecific phenological changes affects temporal synchronicity between fish juveniles and preferential preys. These synchronicities were significantly modified for many predator / prey couples and concerned 9 of the 14 fish species included in the present study. This means that for most of the main fish species, a temporal shift in interaction with at least one of their principal preys, occurred in the last three decades. Among all the tested interactions, one third changed over the last three decades, with half of that proportion due to a decrease in temporal overlap. For these species, we hypothesize that these mismatches could cause a drop in prey availability. This mainly concerns 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">fallax</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Pomatoschistus sp</span>., 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">regius</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Dicentrarchus sp</span>. 
  <span class="italic">and Syngnathus sp</span>. 
  <span class="italic">and</span>, 
  <span class="italic">to a lesser extent</span>, 
  <span class="italic">A</span>. 
  <span class="italic">alosa</span>, 
  <span class="italic">E</span>. 
  <span class="italic">encrasicolus and S</span>. 
  <span class="italic">sprattus</span>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As a summary, many fish species seem to spend less time in the estuary and that would lead to a temporal mismatch with their prey. This questions the quality of the Gironde estuarine nursery grounds for marine juveniles [
  <a rid="pone.0173752.ref083" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0173752.ref083">83</a>] especially as their growth and survival is a key factor for a successful subsequent recruitment in marine ecosystems [
  <a rid="pone.0173752.ref084" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0173752.ref084">84</a>]. Further data on marine fish growth within the estuary would therefore provide valuable complementary information to assess the issue of the Gironde nursery quality.Although this study highlighted an alarming situation with regards to the potentiality of the Gironde estuarine ursery grounds, further study should be conducted to explicitly explore the possible limitation of zooplankton resources, and its consequences on the productivity of fish species during their estuarine life through data on juvenile fish condition and growth patterns for example. Measure of fish size, weight, condition and growth, potentially using biomarkers techniques such as fatty acids stable isotopes or sclerochronology, should therefore be implemented to confirm our conclusions and hypothesis.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The aspects of potential degradation of the nursery function (mismatch situations and shorter time of residence) highlighted in our study questioned the more quantitative aspects shown by Pasquaud [
  <a rid="pone.0173752.ref045" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0173752.ref045">45</a>] who linked up the actual marinisation process of the estuary and the increase of juvenile marine fish in the median part with an increase of this nursery function. This raises the question of whether or not this function (in quality and in quantity) of the Gironde estuary is ecologically sustainable.
 </p>
</sec>
