<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion and Conclusions</div>
 <p content-type="flushleft" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Studies of the future evolution of the Antarctic Ice Sheet have estimated the uncertainty in future sea-level rise due to poorly constrained model parameters (
  <a rid="r5" ref-type="bibr" href="#r5">5</a>, 
  <a rid="r6" ref-type="bibr" href="#r6">6</a>, 
  <a rid="r31" ref-type="bibr" href="#r31">31</a>
  <a href="#r32">*</a>
  <a href="#r33">*</a>–
  <a rid="r34" ref-type="bibr" href="#r34">34</a>). Other studies (
  <a rid="r35" ref-type="bibr" href="#r35">35</a>) have investigated the role of internal climate variability in the Greenland Ice Sheet contribution to sea-level rise, but with simulations that were too short to capture much of the marine ice sheet instability that may occur in the future. No study has provided a theoretical framework explaining the role of ice sheet dynamics in setting the amount and structure of uncertainty in sea-level rise projections. We provide such a theoretical framework in this study and find that ice sheet instabilities are amplifiers of uncertainty, which is a common mathematical property of unstable nonlinear systems (
  <a rid="r22" ref-type="bibr" href="#r22">22</a>). Although there are processes not considered here that might stabilize (
  <a rid="r36" ref-type="bibr" href="#r36">36</a>) or further destabilize (
  <a rid="r6" ref-type="bibr" href="#r6">6</a>) an ice sheet, our analysis shows that we should expect more rapid instability (of any kind) to cause more rapid uncertainty growth. Indeed, the theoretical framework developed in this study applies to a sufficiently broad set of assumptions regarding ice sheet dynamics, such that we expect that any type of ice sheet instability, regardless of the processes involved, will experience rapid growth in the ice sheet projection uncertainty during periods of most rapid instability. Integrating the contribution of marine ice sheet instability over many glaciers also integrates the uncertainty of each glacier’s future evolution, potentially leading to considerable uncertainty in sea-level projections, as has been seen in ensemble studies of total ice sheet contribution to future sea-level rise (
  <a rid="r5" ref-type="bibr" href="#r5">5</a>, 
  <a rid="r6" ref-type="bibr" href="#r6">6</a>, 
  <a rid="r32" ref-type="bibr" href="#r32">32</a>, 
  <a rid="r34" ref-type="bibr" href="#r34">34</a>, 
  <a rid="r35" ref-type="bibr" href="#r35">35</a>). We have shown that model ensembles can be used to quantify a range of possible scenarios for future sea-level rise, including potentially catastrophic scenarios of rapid sea-level rise. However, large model ensembles can be prohibitively expensive when extended to the entire Antarctic Ice Sheet. To fully capture the complete range of possible Antarctic futures, we will need efficient methods for uncertainty quantification (
  <a rid="r32" ref-type="bibr" href="#r32">32</a>, 
  <a rid="r37" ref-type="bibr" href="#r37">37</a>) and model order reduction that captures the complexities of ice sheet dynamics (
  <a rid="r31" ref-type="bibr" href="#r31">31</a>, 
  <a rid="r34" ref-type="bibr" href="#r34">34</a>). Such sophisticated methods will ensure that we can make the most useful sea-level projections beyond 2100 for those stakeholders who depend on them.
 </p>
</sec>
