<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Large Ensembles of Thwaites Glacier Instability.</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To demonstrate that the intuition gained from the theoretical framework developed in the previous section applies to realistic glacier models, we simulate ensembles of the future retreat of Thwaites Glacier in West Antarctica using the Ice Sheet System Model (ISSM), a state-of-the-art finite-element model of ice sheet flow (
  <a rid="r23" ref-type="bibr" href="#r23">23</a>). Thwaites Glacier rests on a reverse-sloping bed and is currently retreating rapidly, which is argued to be the result of the marine ice sheet instability (
  <a rid="r24" ref-type="bibr" href="#r24">24</a>, 
  <a rid="r25" ref-type="bibr" href="#r25">25</a>). In ISSM, as in other models, ocean-induced ice sheet melting is parameterized with a depth-dependent melt rate, with maximum melt rate, 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="i48" class="math">
    <div class="msub">
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mi">M</span>
     </div>
     <div class="mrow">
      <div mathvariant="italic" class="mstyle">
       <span class="mi">m</span>
       <span class="mi">a</span>
       <span class="mi">x</span>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div>, prescribed at some depth (
  <a rid="r25" ref-type="bibr" href="#r25">25</a>). We treat 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="i49" class="math">
    <div class="msub">
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mi">M</span>
     </div>
     <div class="mrow">
      <div mathvariant="italic" class="mstyle">
       <span class="mi">m</span>
       <span class="mi">a</span>
       <span class="mi">x</span>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div> as a first-order autoregressive noise process that varies monthly with a prescribed decorrelation timescale (
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="i50" class="math">
    <div class="msub">
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mi">τ</span>
     </div>
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mi">F</span>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div>), a mean of 80 m/y, no long-term trend, and no variation in space. Many observations and models indicate that subice shelf melt rates at glaciers in the Amundsen Sea, and elsewhere in Antarctica, exhibit strong variability on decadal (and longer) timescales (
  <a rid="r17" ref-type="bibr" href="#r17">17</a>, 
  <a rid="r26" ref-type="bibr" href="#r26">26</a>, 
  <a rid="r27" ref-type="bibr" href="#r27">27</a>). A short run of a regional ocean model simulation for the Amundsen Sea region (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1904822116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>
  </span>) produces variability in 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="i51" class="math">
    <div class="msub">
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mi">M</span>
     </div>
     <div class="mrow">
      <div mathvariant="italic" class="mstyle">
       <span class="mi">m</span>
       <span class="mi">a</span>
       <span class="mi">x</span>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div> with interannual SD of 1.4 m/y. This estimate of variability is likely an underestimate since the ocean simulation was run for only 15 y (the time period over which reanalysis forcing is available) and did not include coupled ocean–atmosphere feedbacks. Thus, for our baseline ensemble of Thwaites Glacier, our conservative estimate for the statistics of ocean-induced melt variability is 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="i52" class="math">
    <div class="msub">
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mi">τ</span>
     </div>
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mi">F</span>
     </div>
    </div>
    <span class="mo">=</span>
    <span class="mn">10</span>
   </div>
  </div> y and 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="i53" class="math">
    <div class="msub">
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mi">σ</span>
     </div>
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mi">M</span>
     </div>
    </div>
    <span class="mo">=</span>
    <span class="mn">1.4</span>
   </div>
  </div> m/y. In reality, we also expect that 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="i54" class="math">
    <div class="msub">
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mi">M</span>
     </div>
     <div class="mrow">
      <div mathvariant="italic" class="mstyle">
       <span class="mi">m</span>
       <span class="mi">a</span>
       <span class="mi">x</span>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div> varies in space, due to (for example) the Coriolis effect on ocean circulation in the subshelf cavity, which would quantitatively (but not necessarily qualitatively) affect our results.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3
   <span class="italic">A</span>
  </a> shows the evolution of the probability distribution of a 500-member ensemble of ISSM-simulated ice volume at Thwaites Glacier in response to decadal variability in subice shelf melt rate. All ensemble members initialized with the modern state of Thwaites Glacier eventually reach complete deglaciation (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3
   <span class="italic">B</span>
  </a>), in agreement with previous studies (
  <a rid="r24" ref-type="bibr" href="#r24">24</a>, 
  <a rid="r25" ref-type="bibr" href="#r25">25</a>). The rate of grounding-line migration (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3
   <span class="italic">C</span>
  </a>) experiences significant variability over the course of the retreat due to the stochastic ocean forcing and the presence of forward-sloping “speed bumps” in the bed topography, both of which can slow the rate of retreat or even cause advance for short durations (
  <a rid="r28" ref-type="bibr" href="#r28">28</a>). Even with the relatively conservative assumption that there is no variability in surface mass balance and a small amplitude of subshelf melt variability (representing 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="i55" class="math">
    <span class="mo">&lt;</span>
    <span class="mn">2</span>
    <span class="mi">%</span>
   </div>
  </div> of the time-averaged subshelf melt), the spread in the ensemble spans 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="i56" class="math">
    <span class="mo">∼</span>
   </div>
  </div>20 cm of uncertainty in projected sea-level rise during periods of fast retreat (i.e., the green probability distribution functions [PDFs] in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3
   <span class="italic">A</span>
  </a>), with a probability distribution skewed in the direction of lower ice volume (greater contribution to sea level). This uncertainty is over 25% of the entire sea-level rise due to deglaciation of Thwaites Glacier and 50% of the median sea-level rise achieved during those periods of fast retreat. This spread between simulations amounts to instantaneous differences of hundreds of kilometers in the grounding-line position (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3
   <span class="italic">D</span>
  </a>). Following this growth of uncertainty during the centuries of most rapid retreat, the ensemble then contracts and skews in the opposite direction as individual ensemble members achieve complete deglaciation of Thwaites Glacier, due to the limited model domain used in our simulations. In simulations of the entire Antarctic Ice Sheet in which the marine ice sheet instability spreads to other glaciers (
  <a rid="r5" ref-type="bibr" href="#r5">5</a>, 
  <a rid="r6" ref-type="bibr" href="#r6">6</a>), we would expect even faster amplification of uncertainty as multiple glaciers become involved in deglaciation.
 </p>
 <div id="fig03" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 3.</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Evolution of a 500-member ensemble of ISSM simulations of Thwaites Glacier evolution over 500 y (where year 0 in model time is the modern glacier state) in response to decadal variability and constant average in maximum subice shelf melt rate. (
    <span class="italic">A</span>) Evolution of ensemble PDF over time, plotted every 25 y, with probability on the 
    <span class="italic">y</span> axis and Thwaites Glacier ice volume (in cm sea-level equivalent [SLE]) on the 
    <span class="italic">x</span> axis. (
    <span class="italic">B</span>) Black lines are simulated ice volume contained in Thwaites Glacier catchment in cm SLE for all ensemble members. (
    <span class="italic">C</span>) Black dots are evolving grounding-line migration rates for all ensemble members (based on the centroid of the 2D grounding line). (
    <span class="italic">D</span>) Snapshots (red, orange, and pink lines) of grounding-line positions at year 635 in model time, from 5th percentile, 50th percentile, and 95th percentile ice volume ensemble members.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div id="gra3" xlink:href="pnas.1904822116fig03" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig04" href="#fig04">Fig. 4</a>, we compare Thwaites Glacier ensemble statistics, given a comparable amplitude (
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="i57" class="math">
    <div class="msub">
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mi">σ</span>
     </div>
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mi">M</span>
     </div>
    </div>
    <span class="mo">=</span>
    <span class="mn">1.4</span>
   </div>
  </div> m/y) of variability in 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="i58" class="math">
    <div class="msub">
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mi">M</span>
     </div>
     <div class="mrow">
      <div mathvariant="italic" class="mstyle">
       <span class="mi">m</span>
       <span class="mi">a</span>
       <span class="mi">x</span>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div>, but differing degrees of temporal persistence. As predicted by theory, ensemble spread (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig04" href="#fig04">Fig. 4
   <span class="italic">A</span>
  </a>) increases with longer persistence in forcing variability (proportional to 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="i59" class="math">
    <div class="msqrt">
     <div class="mrow">
      <div class="msub">
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mi">τ</span>
       </div>
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mi">F</span>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div>; 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1904822116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>
  </span>). During the century of fastest retreat, multidecadal ocean variability (yellow line; 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="i60" class="math">
    <div class="msub">
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mi">τ</span>
     </div>
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mi">F</span>
     </div>
    </div>
    <span class="mo">=</span>
    <span class="mn">30</span>
   </div>
  </div> y) produces skewed uncertainty that is nearly 50% of the total ice loss from Thwaites glacier or 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="i61" class="math">
    <span class="mo">∼</span>
   </div>
  </div>40 cm of uncertainty in projected sea-level rise. Some studies have suggested that Antarctic glaciers may be subject to such multidecadal variability in forcing through low-frequency coupled modes of the ocean–atmosphere system (
  <a rid="r26" ref-type="bibr" href="#r26">26</a>) or sporadic detachment of very large tabular icebergs (
  <a rid="r29" ref-type="bibr" href="#r29">29</a>).
 </p>
 <div id="fig04" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 4.</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Evolution of uncertainty and skewness of uncertainty in four Thwaites Glacier ensembles (500 simulations each). Three of the ensembles have variability in ocean forcing specified using a first-order autoregressive model: Including variability at interannual (
    <div class="inline-formula">
     <div id="i62" class="math">
      <div class="msub">
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mi">τ</span>
       </div>
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mi">F</span>
       </div>
      </div>
      <span class="mo">=</span>
      <span class="mn">1.1</span>
     </div>
    </div> y, blue line), interdecadal (
    <div class="inline-formula">
     <div id="i63" class="math">
      <div class="msub">
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mi">τ</span>
       </div>
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mi">F</span>
       </div>
      </div>
      <span class="mo">=</span>
      <span class="mn">10</span>
     </div>
    </div> y, red line; 
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3</a>), and multidecadal (
    <div class="inline-formula">
     <div id="i64" class="math">
      <div class="msub">
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mi">τ</span>
       </div>
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mi">F</span>
       </div>
      </div>
      <span class="mo">=</span>
      <span class="mn">30</span>
     </div>
    </div> y, yellow line) timescales. One ensemble has no temporal variability, but the constant maximum subshelf melt rate is uncertain and so drawn from a Gaussian distribution (with 
    <div class="inline-formula">
     <div id="i65" class="math">
      <div class="msub">
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mi">σ</span>
       </div>
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mi">M</span>
       </div>
      </div>
      <span class="mo">=</span>
      <span class="mn">5</span>
     </div>
    </div> m/y and the same mean as other ensembles, purple line). (
    <span class="italic">A</span>) “Fractional projection uncertainty” given by the ratio of ensemble spread (measured by 
    <div class="inline-formula">
     <div id="i66" class="math">
      <span class="mo">±</span>
      <span class="mn">2</span>
      <span class="mi">σ</span>
     </div>
    </div> of ensemble) to total ice loss at the end of simulation: 
    <div class="inline-formula">
     <div id="i67" class="math">
      <span class="mn">4</span>
      <div class="msub">
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mi">σ</span>
       </div>
       <div class="mrow">
        <div mathvariant="italic" class="mstyle">
         <span class="mi">v</span>
         <span class="mi">o</span>
         <span class="mi">l</span>
        </div>
       </div>
      </div>
      <span class="mo">/</span>
      <div class="msub">
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mi">μ</span>
       </div>
       <div class="mrow">
        <div mathvariant="italic" class="mstyle">
         <span class="mi">v</span>
         <span class="mi">l</span>
         <span class="mi">o</span>
         <span class="mi">s</span>
         <span class="mi">s</span>
        </div>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>. (
    <span class="italic">B</span>) Ensemble skewness, with negative skewness representing a distribution skewed toward lower total ice volume (more ice loss and more sea-level rise).
   </p>
  </div>
  <div id="gra4" xlink:href="pnas.1904822116fig04" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Poorly constrained subice shelf properties [such as roughness (
  <a rid="r30" ref-type="bibr" href="#r30">30</a>)] and the small scale of the turbulent ice–ocean boundary layer make it difficult to accurately simulate even the time-averaged subice shelf melt rate given some change in global climate. Consequently, we also consider uncertainty in the time-averaged subshelf basal melt rate (which may also result from uncertainties in future anthropogenic emissions) by keeping 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="i68" class="math">
    <div class="msub">
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mi">M</span>
     </div>
     <div class="mrow">
      <div mathvariant="italic" class="mstyle">
       <span class="mi">m</span>
       <span class="mi">a</span>
       <span class="mi">x</span>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div> constant in time, but varying it between ensemble members (drawing from a Gaussian distribution with SD of 5 m/y). As in the minimal model, this ensemble (purple line in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig04" href="#fig04">Fig. 4</a>) has a very strong amplification of skewed uncertainty due to the accumulation of differences in subshelf basal melt rate among ensemble members over the course of the instability. For several centuries, the spread in this ensemble amounts to nearly the entire signal of ice loss from Thwaites Glacier (i.e., some ensemble members have retreated completely while others have lost almost no ice at all), skewed in the direction of more ice loss throughout most of the early period of the simulation.
 </p>
</sec>
