<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The ability of 
 <italic class="italic">G. pallida</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">G. rostochiensis</italic> to overcome potentially larger relative increases in warm extremes associated with increased temperature variability over land during the summer is also likely to differ (
 <xref rid="msy132-B100" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gregory and Mitchell 1995</xref>; 
 <xref rid="msy132-B101" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kharin and Zwiers 2005</xref>). J2 stage of 
 <italic class="italic">G. pallida</italic> are less thermotolerant than 
 <italic class="italic">G. rostochiensis</italic>, taking significantly longer to recover from an acute thermal stress. This is consistent with our previous findings that females of 
 <italic class="italic">G. pallida</italic> take significantly longer than those of 
 <italic class="italic">G. rostochiensis</italic> to recover from a diurnal thermal stress (
 <xref rid="msy132-B44" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Jones et al. 2017</xref>). Transcriptomic analysis revealed that, although members of hsp40, hsp70, and hsp90 gene families are induced similarly in the two species by heat stress, interestingly 
 <italic class="italic">hsp-110</italic> transcripts are heat inducible only in 
 <italic class="italic">G. rostochiensis.</italic> Further investigation confirmed that this gene is duplicated in 
 <italic class="italic">G. rostochiensis</italic> with the promoter of one gene copy harboring the HSEs that suggest regulation by the HSF-1 transcription factor (
 <xref rid="msy132-B29" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">GuhaThakurta et al. 2002</xref>). Only a single copy of 
 <italic class="italic">hsp-110</italic>, lacking HSEs, is present in 
 <italic class="italic">G. pallida</italic> and the related species 
 <italic class="italic">G. ellingtonae</italic>. Phylogenetic analysis suggests a relatively recent duplication of 
 <italic class="italic">hsp-110</italic> and its promoter in the 
 <italic class="italic">G. rostochiensis</italic> lineage during rapid expansion and diversification of 
 <italic class="italic">Globodera</italic> species. Gene duplication events have been shown to produce rapid adaptive changes at the population level (
 <xref rid="msy132-B68" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Perry et al. 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="msy132-B78" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Schrider and Hahn 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="msy132-B4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bass and Field 2011</xref>) but divergence in protein function or expression is required for both copies to be maintained in the genome (
 <xref rid="msy132-B60" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lynch and Conery 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="msy132-B31" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hahn 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="msy132-B4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bass and Field 2011</xref>). Since nonconservative substitutions were not found within either predicted substrate- or nucleotide-binding domains, acquisition of HSEs in the promoter region, conferring enhanced expression and recovery from a thermal stress most likely explains the maintenance of two differently regulated copies of 
 <italic class="italic">hsp-110</italic> in 
 <italic class="italic">G. rostochiensis</italic>. A recent analysis of the Hsp40, Hsp70, and Hsp90 gene families in eusocial Hymenoptera which radiated across a wide range of thermal environments also found differences in gene copy number and in cis-regulation (
 <xref rid="msy132-B65" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Nguyen et al. 2016</xref>).
</p>
