<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece35247-sec-0001" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">INTRODUCTION</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Earth's past climate changes have played a key role in shaping the evolution and distribution of macroorganisms (Svenning, Eiserhardt, Normand, Ordonez, &amp; Sandel, 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0076" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0076">2015</a>). During the late Quaternary (the last 2.6 Myr), global temperature oscillated dramatically between cold glacial and warm interglacial periods (Ruddiman, 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0071" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0071">2014</a>), with major consequences for the diversity and composition of macroorganism communities (Dobrovolski, Melo, Cassemiro, &amp; Diniz‐Filho, 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0024">2012</a>; Normand et al., 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0061">2011</a>; Svenning et al., 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0076" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0076">2015</a>; Svenning &amp; Skov, 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0078" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0078">2007</a>). Late Quaternary climate change has influenced current biodiversity patterns by driving changes in migration, extinction, and speciation rates (Dynesius &amp; Jansson, 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0027">2000</a>; Hoffmann, 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0042">2012</a>; Ma, Sandel, &amp; Svenning, 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0054">2016</a>; Svenning et al., 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0076" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0076">2015</a>). Late Quaternary climate change has led to reduced plant species diversity in Arctic islands (Hoffmann, 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0042">2012</a>) and some tree extinctions in Europe (Svenning, 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0075" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0075">2003</a>). Furthermore, late Quaternary climate change has played a major role in shaping plant community compositions (Cabral, Weigelt, Kissling, &amp; Kreft, 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0014">2014</a>; Feng et al., 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0032">2014</a>; Ma et al., 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0054">2016</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Most studies of historical climate changes have focused on macroorganisms (Ma et al., 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0054">2016</a>; Normand et al., 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0061">2011</a>; Svenning et al., 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0076" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0076">2015</a>), while the effect of historical climate changes on microorganisms has received little attention (Capo et al., 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0015">2016</a>; Delgado‐Baquerizo, Bissett, et al., 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0022">2017</a>). Previous studies found that a direct effect of paleoclimate on microbial communities might have occurred in the past (e.g., in response to a severe climatic event), but if the microbial communities response to past climatic change slowly which lead to the consequences of this compositional shift might still be detectable today (Capo et al., 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0015">2016</a>; Delgado‐Baquerizo, Bissett, et al., 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0022">2017</a>). For example, Delgado‐Baquerizo, Bissett, et al. (
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0022">2017</a>) found that paleoclimate explained a unique proportion of the variation in soil bacterial richness and community composition across a global scale.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fungi are a crucial component of soil microorganism communities and exhibit a wide range of lifestyles including mycorrhizal, endophytic, pathogenic, and saprotrophic (Peay, Kennedy, &amp; Bruns, 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0064" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0064">2008</a>). They play important roles in biodiversity maintenance, community assembly, and ecosystem functioning (Bardgett &amp; van der Putten, 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0008">2014</a>; van der Heijden, Bardgett, &amp; van Straalen, 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0085" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0085">2008</a>). Previous studies have shown that the diversity and composition of soil fungal communities are related to contemporary environmental factors, such as climate, soil, geography, and plant community composition (Gao et al., 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0033">2017</a>; Glassman, Wang, &amp; Bruns, 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0037">2017</a>; Prober et al., 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0069" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0069">2015</a>; Talbot et al., 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0079" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0079">2014</a>; Tedersoo et al., 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0081" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0081">2014</a>). For example, temperature and precipitation can influence soil fungal communities by affecting their metabolic and growth rates (Bååth, 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0003">2001</a>; Hawkes et al., 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0041">2011</a>; Malcolm, López‐Gutiérrez, Koide, &amp; Eissenstat, 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0055">2008</a>; Pietikäinen, Pettersson, &amp; Bååth, 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0067" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0067">2005</a>). Plants can influence fungal communities through specific host relationships (Bahram, Harend, &amp; Tedersoo, 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0004">2014</a>; Bennett &amp; Cahill, 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0012">2016</a>; Nguyen, Williams, et al., 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0060" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0060">2016</a>; Põlme et al., 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0068" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0068">2017</a>; Wardle, 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0087" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0087">2006</a>), and fungal communities can be influenced by soil through the physiological processes of soil biota and nutrient availability (Mexal &amp; Reid, 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0057" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0057">1973</a>; Peay, Kennedy, &amp; Talbot, 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0065" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0065">2016</a>; Waldrop, Zak, Blackwood, Curtis, &amp; Tilman, 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0086" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0086">2006</a>). However, there are few studies investigating the effect of historical climatic change on soil fungal communities (Capo et al., 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0015">2016</a>). If historical climate change can be used to explain the current distribution of soil fungal communities, then it may improve our capacity to predict how soil fungal communities will respond to forecasted climate changes in the future.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The late Quaternary climate oscillations in some areas were mild, promoting assemblages with certain community compositions, while others are unstable, tending to select for a different set of communities (Svenning et al., 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0076" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0076">2015</a>). In general, the temperate region encountered repeated glaciations and a generally cool climate during the Quaternary period, while tropic–subtropical regions were less influenced by glacial cooling, resulting in stronger late Quaternary climate oscillations in temperate regions than in tropic–subtropical areas (Feng, Mao, Sandel, Swenson, &amp; Svenning, 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0031">2016</a>; Feng et al., 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0032">2014</a>; Loarie et al., 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0052">2009</a>; Ruddiman, 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0071" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0071">2014</a>). Given the stronger effect of late Quaternary climate change on plant communities in temperate regions than in tropic–subtropical areas (Feng et al., 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0031">2016</a>, 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0032">2014</a>), the late Quaternary climate change may similarly have a stronger effect on the soil fungal community (either directly or indirectly via impacts on plant communities) in temperate than in tropic–subtropical regions. In addition, contemporary environmental variables including climate, plant community structure, and soil physicochemical properties vary from temperate to tropic regions, and these changes result in different fungal biogeographical patterns across ecosystems (Andrew et al., 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0001">2018</a>; Bahram et al., 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0006">2013</a>; Tedersoo et al., 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0082" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0082">2012</a>). For example, saprotrophic and ectomycorrhizal (EM) fungal communities have shown contrasting biogeographical patterns driven by different environmental variables from temperate to tropic forests (Andrew et al., 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0001">2018</a>; Bahram et al., 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0006">2013</a>; Tedersoo et al., 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0082" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0082">2012</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Forest ecosystems are widely distributed across temperate, subtropical, and tropic regions in China, and they differ widely in plant community composition and diversity. They also encompass a wide range of soil types and climate zones (López‐Pujol &amp; Ren, 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0053">2010</a>). Furthermore, with increasing latitude, the magnitude of late Quaternary climate oscillations increases (Feng et al., 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0031">2016</a>, 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0032">2014</a>). In this study, we investigated soil fungal communities in Chinese temperate, subtropical, and tropic forests from the north to the south (geographic distance up to ~5,500 km) using Illumina MiSeq sequencing to test the following questions (a) late Quaternary climate change affects fungal community composition and fungal richness, (b) late Quaternary climate change influences the fungal community composition of temperate forests more than that of tropic–subtropical forests, and (c) the main contemporary environmental factors affecting fungal community in the different forests are different.
 </p>
</sec>
