<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece35247-sec-0007" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.5</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Late Quaternary climate change data</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Among the late Quaternary climate change variables, the velocity of MAT and MAP is a measure of the local rate of displacement of climatic conditions over Earth's surface (Loarie et al., 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0052">2009</a>; Sandel et al., 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0072" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0072">2011</a>); the anomaly of MAT and MAP represents temporal difference in extreme events such as extreme high or low in temperature and precipitation (Garcia, Cabeza, Rahbek, &amp; Araújo, 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0035">2014</a>). The velocity and anomaly of MAP and MAT metrics have been widely applied to examine the effect of late Quaternary climate change on macroorganisms (Feng et al., 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0032">2014</a>; Garcia et al., 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0035">2014</a>; Sandel et al., 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0072" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0072">2011</a>). Therefore, we used the velocity and anomaly of MAT and MAP as representatives of the late Quaternary climate change variables. We computed the velocity and anomaly for MAT and MAP between the last glacial maximum (LGM; ~21,000 years ago) and the present (1950–2000), with a resolution of 2.5 arc minutes (Sandel et al., 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0072" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0072">2011</a>). Velocity and anomaly calculations require estimates of climate (at least two time points). To summarize LGM climate, we used estimates of past MAT and MAP from the Paleoclimate Modelling Intercomparison Project Phase II (Braconnot et al., 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0013">2007</a>), using the means of the CCSM3 (Collins et al., 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0018">2006</a>) and MIROC3.2 (K‐1 model developers, 
  <a rid="ece35247-bib-0045" ref-type="ref" href="#ece35247-bib-0045">2004</a>) simulations. The information of paleoclimate of each study site is summarized in Table 
  <a rid="ece35247-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#ece35247-sup-0001">S1</a>.
 </p>
</sec>
