<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece35247-sec-0003" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study site and sampling</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study was conducted in 12 sites, including temperate (5 sites), subtropical (5 sites), and tropic (2 sites) forests in China (Figure 
  <a rid="ece35247-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#ece35247-fig-0001">1</a>). Longitude, latitude, and altitude at the sites were provided by the Chinese Forest Biodiversity Monitoring Network (CForBio), and estimates of the mean annual temperature (MAT) and mean annual precipitation (MAP) were obtained from the WorldClim global climate data (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.worldclim.org" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.worldclim.org</span>) set with a resolution of 2.5 min. In each site, one permanent forest plot (varying from 15–25 ha) was constructed by the CForBio. In each plot, all trees with a diameter ≥1 cm at breast height have been mapped, identified, and measured. During June to October in 2014, 20 quadrats (20 × 20 m) in each plot were randomly selected, and ten soil cores (10 cm in depth, 5 cm in diameter) were randomly collected and mixed as one composite sample in each quadrat. A total of 240 soil samples were therefore used in this study. Soil samples were immediately packed in an ice box and transported to the laboratory. Fresh soil samples were sieved through a 2‐mm sieve to remove roots and debris. Subsamples for DNA extraction were stored at −80°C until analysis, and the remaining subsamples were air‐dried for soil analysis. The information of geographic and current climatic variables of each study site is summarized in Table 
  <a rid="ece35247-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#ece35247-sup-0001">S1</a>.
 </p>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece35247-fig-0001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Geographic distribution of sampling sites in China. Temperate forests include Genhe (GH), Liangshui (LS), Changbaishan (CBS), Donglingshan (DLS), and Baotianman (BTM); subtropical forests include Gutianshan (GTS), Badagongshan (BDGS), Tiantongshan (TTS), Heishiding (HSD), and Dinghushan (DHS); tropic forests include Nonggang (NG) and Xishuangbanna (XSBN)</p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-3" xlink:href="ECE3-9-6678-g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
