<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Lianas are common in forests across the world and influence forest ecosystem functioning (Schnitzer &amp; Bongers, 
 <xref rid="ece34388-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2002</xref>; Tymen et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34388-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>) and carbon storage capacity (van der Heijden, Powers, &amp; Schnitzer, 
 <xref rid="ece34388-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). They affect key ecological processes such as tree mortality, susceptibility to wind damage, compositional turnover, and species diversity (Allen, Sharitz, &amp; Goebel, 
 <xref rid="ece34388-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>; Körner, 
 <xref rid="ece34388-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2004</xref>; Ladwig &amp; Meiners, 
 <xref rid="ece34388-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>; Schnitzer &amp; Bongers, 
 <xref rid="ece34388-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2002</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ece34388-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>). Lianas may also be one group that could strongly benefit from climate change and they significantly increased in abundance and productivity in the last decades (Phillips et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34388-bib-0030" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2002</xref>; Schnitzer, 
 <xref rid="ece34388-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Schnitzer &amp; Bongers, 
 <xref rid="ece34388-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2002</xref>). The drivers behind this trend remain contentious. Liana increase was first reported in the neotropics (Phillips et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34388-bib-0030" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2002</xref>) but since then, contrasting results have been shown in temperate (Heinrichs &amp; Schmidt, 
 <xref rid="ece34388-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>) and African forests (reviewed in Schnitzer, 
 <xref rid="ece34388-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>), where there have been no long‐term changes in liana abundance. European lianas, on the other hand, have attracted limited attention, other than as invasive species in North American forests (Heinrichs &amp; Schmidt, 
 <xref rid="ece34388-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). This is likely due to the low abundance and economic impact of European liana species in forestry, to the point that they have even been dismissed as “mainly decorative” (Silvertown, 
 <xref rid="ece34388-bib-0038" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>). However, lianas are still an important part of European forest biodiversity and their loss from forests could have cascading effects on the biodiversity of other groups. Therefore, understanding the response of European lianas to climate change is important to predict future trends in forest biodiversity.
</p>
