<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Still, it can be assumed that results represent an underestimation due to lack of data or appropriateness of modelling. These include psychological benefits due to more physical activity, reduced noise, increased social interaction (e.g., when switching from car to public transport) or increased green spaces (when sealed areas are rebuilt as is included in the scenarios). Such further aspects have been evaluated e.g., by Mueller et al. [
 <xref rid="B1-ijerph-15-00880" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>], de Nazelle et al. [
 <xref rid="B72-ijerph-15-00880" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">72</xref>] and Boniface et al. [
 <xref rid="B73-ijerph-15-00880" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">73</xref>]. By using qualitative methods like systematic surveys, the assessment of these costs and benefits could be amended. A further underestimation occurs because climate and congestion costs have not been included in the study. Noise costs include health costs and costs of annoyance. Applying an average cost factor per passenger-km [
 <xref rid="B74-ijerph-15-00880" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">74</xref>] of 1.7 € per 1000 p-km would yield cost savings of 3 to 5.5 million € a year. The same procedure for external climate costs leads to cost savings that would range from 5 to 30 million € per year for the GM scenario and 10 to 55 million € per year for the GE and ZE scenario depending on the climate change scenario. Due to these uncertainties, broad ranges of cost factors not including specific spatial distribution, infrastructure conditions and exposure to the population these numbers were not included in the result tables. Further research could be done by using specific data from NEMO to calculate spatially specific changes of noise and merging these results with population data. The value of statistical life (VSL) or the value of a life year (VOLY) is mostly done by Willingness-to-Pay analysis, which is seen to be of considerably varying results (cf. Xia et al., [
 <xref rid="B12-ijerph-15-00880" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]). However we included the VOLY concept in our analysis to depict the intangible costs. As we based our calculations on the YLL and YLD values which were not available for all diseases, changes in intangible costs can be seen as the lower bound. While there are increasing voices that clearly think that the VOLY concept is more meaningful in the context of air quality [
 <xref rid="B57-ijerph-15-00880" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>,
 <xref rid="B58-ijerph-15-00880" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">58</xref>,
 <xref rid="B75-ijerph-15-00880" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">75</xref>] other studies still apply the VSL approach [
 <xref rid="B76-ijerph-15-00880" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">76</xref>,
 <xref rid="B77-ijerph-15-00880" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">77</xref>]. Bollen et al. [
 <xref rid="B77-ijerph-15-00880" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">77</xref>] argue that the VSL would follow the precautionary principle and would be statistically more reliable. We therefore applied two VOLY factors and contrasted them to the VSL results. Changes in morbidity and sick leaves are also considered in the Macroeconomic Model (5) depicting their implications on GDP, employment and welfare.
</p>
