<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="S0003" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Genomic divergence related to speciation has historically been associated with changes in allele frequencies in response to adaptation [
  <a rid="CIT0042" href="#CIT0042">42</a>,
  <a rid="CIT0043" href="#CIT0043">43</a>]. New knowledge in genomics, however, portraits a much more complex scenario of genomic dynamics that occur during speciation in which many other factors, including genetic drift and biased mutations, have an important role in shaping genetic diversity [
  <a rid="CIT0044" href="#CIT0044">44</a>]. Many fundamental questions remain unanswered in speciation genetics, such as 
  <span class="italic">which genetic elements are relevant? how many loci are involved? where are the genomic determinants located?</span> or 
  <span class="italic">what is the role of rearrangements, gene conversions and other molecular changes?</span> [
  <a rid="CIT0043" href="#CIT0043">43</a>] In the present paper, we studied genomic dynamics related to CpG sites by focusing on the recent process of chicken diversification and using a reduced genome approach unbiased for CpG density (GBS). Importantly, CpG sites are on the one hand susceptible to undergo methylation [
  <a rid="CIT0045" href="#CIT0045">45</a>], and on the other hand relate to biased mutations [
  <a rid="CIT0016" href="#CIT0016">16</a>–
  <a rid="CIT0019" href="#CIT0019">19</a>]
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our study identified SNPs and CNVs common to all breeds (thus, unrelated to their divergence), as well as breed-specific SNPs and CNVs that could be relevant for the diversification of the chicken breeds studied here. RJF was confirmed as the most ancestral of the breeds analysed, while BLR was found to be the most derived. Among the Swedish breeds, KIN was classified as the closest to RJF, while GOT was the most distant. The fact that the neighbour joining analysis correctly clustered each individual within the corresponding clade indicates the appropriateness of using GBS-generated sequencing data for inferring phylogenetic correlations. GBS has been used previously to infer domestication scenarios in Lima Bean (
  <span class="italic">Phaseolus lunatus L</span>.) in Mesoamerica [
  <a rid="CIT0046" href="#CIT0046">46</a>]. The vast majority of the SNPs identified between our chicken breeds and the Japanese quail are shown to have evolved under neutrality (97.5%), while only 0.6% evolved due to positive section. This is concordant with previous estimates in humans showing that virtually all of the genome has evolved under neutrality, while the occurrence of positive selection is rare [
  <a rid="CIT0047" href="#CIT0047">47</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We then inquired about the contribution of CpGs in relation to the SNPs and CNVs identified. We found that 9.51% of all SNPs are related to CpGs, which is above the expected value of 1/16 (i.e., 6.25%). This is the probability of occurrence of CG dinucleotides among all dinucleotides, which is what is expected in case all dinucleotides would contribute equally to SNP formation. Thus, CG dinucleotides disproportionally influence SNP formation. Moreover, the more distant the breed is from RJF, the more SNPs emerge from CpGs, reaching the value of 100.7% above expectancy for broilers. This suggests CpGs, in addition to being hotspots of mutations [
  <a rid="CIT0015" href="#CIT0015">15</a>–
  <a rid="CIT0019" href="#CIT0019">19</a>], are hotspots of SNPs that are relevant for genomic speciation. CpGs in CNVs, on the other hand, are highly under-represented, being present at less than 2% of their expected value, and their presence is independent of genetic relatedness to RJF.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Next, we investigated if SNPs mutation dynamics are different depending on whether mutations emerge from fixed or alternate bases. Overall, as genetic relatedness to RJF decreases, substitutions emerging from either C-SNPs or CpG-SNPs tend to produce a progressive disappearance of fixed Cs correlated and the appearance of degenerated C/T bases. This is consistent with the tendency of CpGs to mutate to TpGs [
  <a rid="CIT0016" href="#CIT0016">16</a>–
  <a rid="CIT0019" href="#CIT0019">19</a>] and indicates C to T substitutions are very prone to occur in a context of diversification, being influenced by other factors in addition to the hypermutability of CpG sites. The observed increased C to T mutability related to phylogenetic distance could have an important causative role in species diversification, a possibility that would need further investigation.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">However, our results show it is not only important in genomic dynamics whether Cs are within CpG sites or not but also their status as alternate or reference base. Mutations in alternate Cs generate a different outcome than mutations in reference Cs. Although both reference and alternate Cs tend to mutate to T, in positions where Cs are alternate Gs substantially disappear by mutating to C, which is reflected in the concomitant raise of degenerate G/C bases. Although it is expected that C and G mutations trend together due to being complementary bases, it is somehow surprising that Gs tend to generate Cs. This substitution represents a transversion, which are less common than transitions [
  <a rid="CIT0048" href="#CIT0048">48</a>]. Since transitions are known to be influenced by CpGs [
  <a rid="CIT0024" href="#CIT0024">24</a>], it is possible that other epigenetic mechanisms might induce transversions.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We also observed mutation differences between true CpGs and D/CpGs. Mutations from true CpGs expectedly produce degenerated C/T positions, while mutations from D/CpGs are mainly related to A/G degenerate bases that progressively increase at the expense of fixed As and Gs. This confirms previous observations showing that CpGs mutate significantly different than other positions, being important for the over-representation of transitions relative to transversions in mammalian genomes [
  <a rid="CIT0024" href="#CIT0024">24</a>]. Overall, our mutation analyses reveal a general trend of disappearance of fixed Cs and Gs as genetic diversification from RJF increases. It remains to be seen if this pattern occurs in the genetic diversification of other vertebrates. This trend is i) concomitant with the appearance of degenerate bases (i.e., C/T, G/C and A/G), ii) dependent on the alternate/reference status of the base, and iii) dependent on whether mutations relate to CpG sites. In the particular case of CpGs, mutations in true CpGs expectedly produce degenerated C/T positions, while mutations in D/CpGs are mainly related to A/G degenerate bases that progressively increase at the expense of fixed As and Gs. The observed overall increase in degenerate bases due to the higher mutability of Cs in relation to phylogenetic distance could have an important, and maybe causative, role in genome diversification associated with speciation. The possibility that this trend would also occur in the genomic evolution of other organisms needs to be investigated.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Functional annotation of the mutations observed revealed that SNPs and CNVs are mostly present in intergenic regions, followed by intronic regions. Intergenic regions include regulatory elements such as exons, splice junctions, and proper genes [
  <a rid="CIT0049" href="#CIT0049">49</a>]. Mutations in intergenic regions may affect so-called ‘Dark Matter’ transcripts, which are mostly located near genes and associate with regulatory elements such as alternative cleavage or polyadenylation sites, promoter- and terminator-associated transcripts, as well as alternative exons [
  <a rid="CIT0050" href="#CIT0050">50</a>]. Meanwhile, mutations in intronic regions may affect splicing with consequences for RNA processing [
  <a rid="CIT0051" href="#CIT0051">51</a>]. Mutations in splicing sites are associated with human diseases such as cancers [
  <a rid="CIT0052" href="#CIT0052">52</a>], and neurological [
  <a rid="CIT0053" href="#CIT0053">53</a>,
  <a rid="CIT0054" href="#CIT0054">54</a>] and metabolic [
  <a rid="CIT0055" href="#CIT0055">55</a>] disorders. The evolutionary relevance of mutations in intergenic and intronic regions of the genome deserves further investigation, since mutations in these regions might relate with the emergence of new genes or altered genomic regulation and function [
  <a rid="CIT0056" href="#CIT0056">56</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As for features of CpG-related mutations, specifically, CpG-SNPs are overrepresented in coding regions, while CpG-CNVs are overrepresented in coding regions and promoters. This suggests different functional consequences depending on whether CpGs are involved in the appearance of SNPs or CNVs. Although in both cases most probably intergenic regions will be affected, CpG-CNVs will have more chances of affecting promoters and coding regions than CNVs, CpG-SNPs or SNPs. CNVs in promoters can alter protein length and introduce frameshifts and are strongly associated with protein binding, followed by morphogenesis [
  <a rid="CIT0057" href="#CIT0057">57</a>]. A famous case of the effect of CNV in a coding region is the role of CAG repeats in the etiology of Huntington’s Disease [
  <a rid="CIT0058" href="#CIT0058">58</a>]. Interestingly, recent research has shown that CNVs can be directed by environmental factors, regulated by histone modifications [
  <a rid="CIT0059" href="#CIT0059">59</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Next, we inquired into associations between the mutations found and repetitive elements. In general, repetitive elements were found to be marginally more associated with CNVs than with SNPs. When looking at specific categories, however, noticeable particularities emerged. CpG-CNVs are much more associated with LINE/CR1 elements than CNVs in general, which occurs at the expense of simple repeats. LINE elements are well known to be suppressed by DNA methylation [
  <a rid="CIT0060" href="#CIT0060">60</a>] and involved in genomic rearrangements produced due to their ‘cut-and-paste’ and ‘copy-and-paste’ activities [
  <a rid="CIT0061" href="#CIT0061">61</a>]. Moreover, LINE elements are highly active during germ line development, which is crucial for the maintenance of the transgenerationally transmitted genomic integrity [
  <a rid="CIT0062" href="#CIT0062">62</a>]. CR1 stands for ‘Chicken repeat 1ʹ LINE elements, which were initially discovered in chickens but have been identified in many bird species [
  <a rid="CIT0063" href="#CIT0063">63</a>]. Considering this background, the association found between LINE/CR1 elements and CNVs suggests that changes in DNA methylation (particularly in the germ line) in LINE elements would have a role in allowing their retro-transposition for the consequent generation of CNVs that will be inherited. Interestingly, we have previously reported in rats that developmental exposure to an environmental toxicant (vinclozolin) generates DNA methylation changes and CNVs (particularly duplications [
  <a rid="CIT0037" href="#CIT0037">37</a>]) in the male germ line three generations after the exposure [
  <a rid="CIT0037" href="#CIT0037">37</a>,
  <a rid="CIT0064" href="#CIT0064">64</a>]. This combined information calls for further research on the role of germ line methylation and activity of LINE elements in generating CNVs.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In parallel, ‘simple’ and ‘low complexity’ repeats seem to be increased in breed-specific SNPs in comparison to all the SNPs, particularly in CpG-SNPs, at the expense of LINE elements. Interestingly, simple repeats in flanking regions of introns exhibit high mutation rates, making introns a rapidly evolving type of genomic element [
  <a rid="CIT0065" href="#CIT0065">65</a>]. Coincidentally, as mentioned above, many of the mutations found in the present study were indeed in intronic regions. Our results raise questions about the role of simple repeats in speciation and on their relation to SNPs. Important differences were also observed in the composition of LTR elements between the SNPs and CNVs identified; ERV1 and ERVK elements are overrepresented in CpG-SNPs, while ERVL is overrepresented in CpG-CNVs, in relation to reference values. Although not many studies exist on the role of LTR elements in evolution, in plants LTR elements are generally associated with genomic expansion, and have recently been found to be a major diversification force in the speciation of 
  <span class="italic">Capsicum spp</span>, where new proteins were created by their retroduplication [
  <a rid="CIT0066" href="#CIT0066">66</a>]. One of the most striking findings, however, was the much higher presence of breed-specific CpG-SNPs in satellite elements of the W chromosome, suggesting that this sex-chromosome could have more relevance in speciation than previously thought. Although the W chromosome has received much less attention than the Z in birds’ speciation, recent evidence suggests that the W chromosome is highly involved in speciation [
  <a rid="CIT0067" href="#CIT0067">67</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We then investigated the relation of CpG-related mutations to DNA methylation in RJF sperm, the closest living relative to the ancestor. Although we cannot assert that DNA methylation in RJF sperm have directly influenced CpG mutation rates in the domesticated breeds evaluated here, the associations found can provide clues about this connection. We studied two traits related to DNA methylation in RJF sperm (levels and variability across individuals) to build nine categories representing combinations of these variables. We hypothesized that a non-association of sperm CpG methylation and mutations would mean to observe the same distribution of these categories in all the CpGs in which DNA methylation was measured in the sperm, and in subgroups of those CpGs related to mutations (SNPs or CNVs). Although a similar pattern of methylation is observed between all sperm CpGs and CpGs-CNVs, striking differences are observed with CpGs-SNPs, suggesting that medium levels of CpG methylation in sperm combined with medium/high interindividual variability are important variables influencing SNP formation. Moreover, while the majority of CpG-SNPs associate with medium levels of methylation and medium/high variation in RJF sperm, the majority of CpG-CNVs associate with high levels of methylation and low/medium variability in RJF sperm. This combined information suggests different DNA methylation features in the germ line (e.g., levels and inter-individual variability) can lead to the emergence of different types of mutations. Current knowledge points towards an important role for CpG methylation in biasing mutations, however, we show that other aspects need to be taken into consideration such as DNA methylation variability in a population. Moreover, the high mutation rates of CpGs are usually considered in relation to SNPs but not to CNVs. A recent study observed CNV breakpoints in nearly half of the genes of great tits (
  <span class="italic">Parus major</span>) [
  <a rid="CIT0068" href="#CIT0068">68</a>]. These CNV breakpoints were prominent at repetitive (segmental duplications) and regulatory regions, overlapped with transcription start sites, and were CpG rich [
  <a rid="CIT0068" href="#CIT0068">68</a>]. These results combined with ours show the importance of addressing the specific mechanisms in which CpG methylation regulate retro-transposition to promote genomic instability related to evolution.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Through Bayesian analyses, we showed that the probability of mutating to SNPs or CNVs varied substantially among RJF sperm CpG methylation categories, with each category exhibiting well-defined and specific ranges of mutation probabilities. Interestingly, for some of these categories (MM-HV and MM-MV; 
  <a rid="F0007" href="#F0007">Figure 7</a>) the mutation rate increases as genetic relatedness to RJF decreases. This finding suggests CpGs with medium levels of methylation and high/medium inter-individual variability in the sperm are related to SNPs of relevance for speciation. Interestingly, this pattern was not observed in CNVs. Thus, our sperm DNA methylation analysis suggests CpG-CNVs are not related to speciation, while CpGs-SNPs would be relevant for the emergence of genomic features involved in speciation. However, the bulk of CpG-related mutations found in our study are related to CNVs (~20 times more CpG-CNVs than CpG-SNPs). Based on this combined information we suggest the majority of CpGs in the genome, those related to CNVs, provide a source of genomic ‘flexibility’ in evolution, i.e., the ability of the genome to expand its functional possibilities. Meanwhile, a small fraction of CpGs, those related to SNPs, will provide genomic ‘specificity’ in evolution, thus, representing mutations related to phenotypic traits relevant for speciation. The germ line has previously been proposed as a catalyst for genomic evolution [
  <a rid="CIT0056" href="#CIT0056">56</a>,
  <a rid="CIT0069" href="#CIT0069">69</a>], by propitiating the emergence of novel genes that subsequently adopt functions in somatic tissues. It will be important in the future to know the role of CpG methylation in regulating the activity of repeat elements in the germ line and its relation to genome integrity and variability in descendants.
 </p>
</sec>
