<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="S0004-S2007" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">DNA methylation</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">DNA methylation was measured in RJF sperm in the same fraction of the genome in which SNPs and CNVs were evaluated, i.e., the fraction of the genome digested with the 
  <span class="italic">PstI</span> restriction enzyme. This enzymatic digestion is not affected by the methylation status of CpG sites because 
  <span class="italic">PstI</span> cuts the AG dinucleotide in the recognition site 5ʹ CTGCAG 3ʹ [
  <a rid="CIT0038" href="#CIT0038">38</a>], as described by manufacturer information (New England Biolabs). Another important feature of genome restriction by 
  <span class="italic">PstI</span> is that the resulting digested genome is already enriched for CpG sites [
  <a rid="CIT0038" href="#CIT0038">38</a>], capturing CpG regions in CpG-rich micro-chromosomes [
  <a rid="CIT0070" href="#CIT0070">70</a>]. Genome restriction by 
  <span class="italic">PstI</span> allowed to compare the same fraction of reduced genome across all individuals tested. Once the RJF sperm genome was 
  <span class="italic">PstI</span> fragmented, the methylated DNA fraction of sperm cells was captured through methylated DNA immunoprecipitation (MeDIP) by an anti-methyl-cytosine antibody (2 µg/µl; catalogue number C15200006, Diagenode, Denville, NJ, USA), following a protocol previously optimized for chicken DNA in our lab [
  <a rid="CIT0071" href="#CIT0071">71</a>]. This DNA, which represents a reduced fraction genome that is enriched for methylation, was then barcoded in order to individualize the DNA fragments, and pooled for sequencing in Illumina platform (SciLife Lab, Uppsala, Sweden). We have recently used this approach for the determination of differential DNA methylation in a reduced fraction of the chicken genome [
  <a rid="CIT0041" href="#CIT0041">41</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
