<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="S0002-S2001" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">General sequencing parameters of genotyping</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To identify SNPs and CNVs emerging between the domesticated chicken breeds and RJF we used Genotype-by-Sequencing, which we have recently described in chickens [
  <a rid="CIT0038" href="#CIT0038">38</a>]. This is an approach that enzymatically reduces the genome (with 
  <span class="italic">PstI</span>) and is unbiased for CpG density. 
  <span class="italic">PstI</span> digestion reduced the genome to a sequenced fraction of ~2.2%. Approximately 112 million reads were retained per library (3 libraries) after quality trimming by SeqyClean [
  <a rid="CIT0039" href="#CIT0039">39</a>]. Approximately 106 million reads were retained after application of the Tassel filter (reads &gt;64 bp and properly identified with barcodes). The number of unique sequence tags that aligned against the chicken reference genome (Gallus gallus 4.0, NCBI) was ~1.1 million and 91.2% of them could be mapped (detailed coverage per breed is shown in 
  <a rid="T0001" href="#T0001">Table 1</a>). We identified SNPs and CNVs common to all breeds (thus, unrelated to divergence), as well as breed-specific SNPs and CNVs that could be relevant for the diversification of the chicken breeds studied here. A total of 150,348 SNPs was identified when comparing the 
  <span class="italic">PstI</span>-reduced genomes of individuals from the domesticated breeds to the same fraction in RJF (used as reference). Among these SNPs, 30.29% were breed specific. 
  <a rid="F0001" href="#F0001">Figure 1(a</a>) shows a Venn-diagram with the number of SNPs detected in each domesticated breed in relation to RJF. Additionally, CNVs were identified in the 
  <span class="italic">PstI-</span>reduced genomes of individuals from the domesticated breeds compared to the same fraction in RJF (used as reference). These are presented as base pairs covered by CNVs emerging between RJF and the domesticated breeds, which allowed us to compare CNV regions to CpG locations. A total of 161,686,613 bp was identified in regions of CNVs, with 32.9% of these base pairs being breed specific. 
  <a rid="F0001" href="#F0001">Figure 1(b</a>) shows a Venn-diagram with the number of base pairs covered by CNVs emerging in each domesticated breed in relation to RJF.
  <div id="T0001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="table-wrap">
   <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1080/15592294.2019.1609868-T0001</span>
   <span class="label">Table 1.</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Summary of sequencing coverage in the chicken breeds analysed, in relation to the reference genome.</p>
   </div>
   <!--OASIS TABLE HERE-->
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <colgroup>
     <col width="1*" align="left"/>
     <col width="1*" align="char" char="±"/>
     <col width="1*" align="char" char="±"/>
     <col width="1*" align="char" char="±"/>
     <col width="1*" align="char" char="±"/>
    </colgroup>
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th align="left">Breeds</th>
      <th align="center" char="±">Depth ± SD</th>
      <th align="center" char="±">Coverage (million) ± SD</th>
      <th align="center" char="±">nucleotide sequenced (million) ± SD</th>
      <th align="center" char="±">% of the GGA 4.0 ± SD</th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td align="left">HED</td>
      <td align="char" char="±">17,1 
       <span class="bold">±</span> 8,0
      </td>
      <td align="char" char="±">461 
       <span class="bold">±</span> 289,3
      </td>
      <td align="char" char="±">24,5 
       <span class="bold">±</span> 5,5
      </td>
      <td align="char" char="±">2,3 
       <span class="bold">±</span> 0,5
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left">KIN</td>
      <td align="char" char="±">16,9 
       <span class="bold">±</span> 7,9
      </td>
      <td align="char" char="±">449 
       <span class="bold">±</span> 283,9
      </td>
      <td align="char" char="±">24,3 
       <span class="bold">±</span> 5,5
      </td>
      <td align="char" char="±">2,3 
       <span class="bold">±</span> 0,5
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left">GOT</td>
      <td align="char" char="±">17,4 
       <span class="bold">±</span> 4,9
      </td>
      <td align="char" char="±">450 
       <span class="bold">±</span> 198,7
      </td>
      <td align="char" char="±">24,4 
       <span class="bold">±</span> 5,6
      </td>
      <td align="char" char="±">2,3 
       <span class="bold">±</span> 0,5
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left">BRL</td>
      <td align="char" char="±">17,2 
       <span class="bold">±</span> 4,9
      </td>
      <td align="char" char="±">444 
       <span class="bold">±</span> 203,2
      </td>
      <td align="char" char="±">24,3 
       <span class="bold">±</span> 5,8
      </td>
      <td align="char" char="±">2,3 
       <span class="bold">±</span> 0,5
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left">RJF</td>
      <td align="char" char="±">10,6 
       <span class="bold">±</span> 2,8
      </td>
      <td align="char" char="±">255 
       <span class="bold">±</span> 108,9
      </td>
      <td align="char" char="±">22,8 
       <span class="bold">±</span> 3,9
      </td>
      <td align="char" char="±">2,1 
       <span class="bold">±</span> 0,4
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left">
       <span class="bold">Average</span>
      </td>
      <td align="char" char="±">15,8 
       <span class="bold">±</span> 2,6
      </td>
      <td align="char" char="±">412 
       <span class="bold">±</span> 78,4
      </td>
      <td align="char" char="±">24,1 
       <span class="bold">±</span> 6,5
      </td>
      <td align="char" char="±">2,2 
       <span class="bold">±</span> 0,1
      </td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
  </div>
  <div id="F0001" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
   <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1080/15592294.2019.1609868-F0001</span>
   <span class="label">Figure 1.</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Categorization of SNPs and CNVs found among domesticated breeds of chickens and RJF. (a) Venn diagram showing SNPs emerging between the domesticated breeds analysed and RJF. (b) Venn diagram showing base pairs covered by CNVs emerging between the domesticated breeds analysed and RJF. (c) SNP based phylogenetic tree of the chicken breeds studied here, constructed with neighbour joining and using the Japanese quail as the outgroup. (d) Schematic representation of the F
     <sub>st</sub> analysis against heterozygosity performed among the breeds studied here; dots with different colours represent SNPs evolving under balancing selection (yellow), neutral evolution (light blue), or positive selection (red).
    </p>
   </div>
   <div specific-use="web-only" content-type="color" xlink:href="kepi-14-07-1609868-g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
