<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="S0001" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The emergence of novel genomic conformations is a fundamental process in evolution that has been the focus of recent high-profile studies [
  <a rid="CIT0001" href="#CIT0001">1</a>–
  <a rid="CIT0005" href="#CIT0005">5</a>]. One of the main challenges in evolution is to understand how genomes diversify. Domesticated organisms are ideal to study this process because domestication represents recent and trackable events of diversification that have radically changed phenotypes and genotypes over short time spans [
  <a rid="CIT0006" href="#CIT0006">6</a>]. Although domestication has been used as a proof-of-principle for evolution since Darwin, it has only recently started to be explored as a way to disentangle the genetic mechanisms underlying evolutionary processes. Particularly, chicken domestication has led to marked phenotypic differences between breeds and to the accumulation of mutations in each of them [
  <a rid="CIT0005" href="#CIT0005">5</a>]. Domesticated breeds of chickens are acknowledged to have originated from wild populations of Red Jungle Fowl (RJF) [
  <a rid="CIT0007" href="#CIT0007">7</a>,
  <a rid="CIT0008" href="#CIT0008">8</a>]. This domestication process is thought to have started recently, between 5,400 [
  <a rid="CIT0009" href="#CIT0009">9</a>] to 3,000 [
  <a rid="CIT0008" href="#CIT0008">8</a>] years ago in Southeast Asia. Currently, a wild form of RJF still inhabits Southeast Asia and regions of China and India [
  <a rid="CIT0008" href="#CIT0008">8</a>]. RJF is considered as the living variety of chickens that is the closest relative to the common ancestor of all known chicken breeds [
  <a rid="CIT0007" href="#CIT0007">7</a>,
  <a rid="CIT0008" href="#CIT0008">8</a>]. Considering the proximity of living RJF to the ancestor of all chickens and the ample variety of existing domesticated types [
  <a rid="CIT0008" href="#CIT0008">8</a>], the process of chicken diversification is a valuable model to study mechanistic aspects of genomic diversification in vertebrates.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Until recently it was common in evolutionary biology to assume genomic changes related to evolutionary novelties were mainly generated by random (stochastic) mutation events [
  <a rid="CIT0010" href="#CIT0010">10</a>,
  <a rid="CIT0011" href="#CIT0011">11</a>], which occurred independently from environmental influences [
  <a rid="CIT0012" href="#CIT0012">12</a>]. One line of thought to have challenged this assumption is the ability of epigenetic modifications to influence genomic variability [
  <a rid="CIT0013" href="#CIT0013">13</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The influence of epigenetic state on mutation rate has, for example, been demonstrated in cytosines of 5ʹ to 3ʹoriented CG dinucleotides. These so-called CpG sites are prone to DNA methylation, an enzymatic reaction in which methyl groups (-CH
  <sub>3</sub>) are added to the carbon 5 of their cytosine ring [
  <a rid="CIT0014" href="#CIT0014">14</a>]. Interestingly, a methylated cytosine is one reaction (hydrolytic deamination) away from a complete mutation to a thymidine, a conversion that can even occur spontaneously [
  <a rid="CIT0015" href="#CIT0015">15</a>]. CpG to TpG transitions occur with much higher frequency than any other point mutation and depend on the methylation status. Estimations show that DNA methylation in CpGs increase CpG to TpG mutation rates by ~12 fold [
  <a rid="CIT0016" href="#CIT0016">16</a>–
  <a rid="CIT0019" href="#CIT0019">19</a>]. The increase is even higher in the male germ line [
  <a rid="CIT0020" href="#CIT0020">20</a>]. In 
  <span class="italic">Escherichia coli,</span> experiments have shown CpGs are hotspots for mutations only when methylated [
  <a rid="CIT0015" href="#CIT0015">15</a>]. The hypermutability of CpGs is suggested to have influenced their deficiency in vertebrate genomes [
  <a rid="CIT0021" href="#CIT0021">21</a>,
  <a rid="CIT0022" href="#CIT0022">22</a>] and reported to be important in the evolution of transcription factor binding sites [
  <a rid="CIT0023" href="#CIT0023">23</a>]. In mammals, CpG-related mutations have influenced the well-known higher rate of transitions relative to transversions [
  <a rid="CIT0024" href="#CIT0024">24</a>] and contributed to the evolution of the 
  <span class="italic">BRCA1</span> gene [
  <a rid="CIT0016" href="#CIT0016">16</a>]. Additionally, CpGs are known to influence the mutation rates of neighbouring non-CpG DNA [
  <a rid="CIT0025" href="#CIT0025">25</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">CpG mutation rates in natural populations could be influenced by environmental exposures affecting their methylation status [
  <a rid="CIT0026" href="#CIT0026">26</a>]. Interestingly, since epigenetic alterations can be maintained for several generations (at least eight in plants) [
  <a rid="CIT0027" href="#CIT0027">27</a>,
  <a rid="CIT0028" href="#CIT0028">28</a>], there are many opportunities for CpGs with altered methylation patterns to mutate to TpGs. In addition to biasing point mutations, DNA methylation in CpGs is also involved in the generation of larger genomic rearrangements. DNA methylation regulates the activity of transposable elements [
  <a rid="CIT0029" href="#CIT0029">29</a>], which in turn impact the formation of new genomic arrangements such as insertions, deletions or duplications [
  <a rid="CIT0030" href="#CIT0030">30</a>]. Recent evidence shows that transposition of repetitive elements had a crucial role in the genome diversification resulting from the radiation of African cichlid fish [
  <a rid="CIT0001" href="#CIT0001">1</a>]. In spite of the known mechanistic connection between CpG methylation and genetic mutations, the precise role that CpG-related mutations play in evolution and genomic diversification is not known.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Studies in Darwin finches [
  <a rid="CIT0031" href="#CIT0031">31</a>] and darter fish [
  <a rid="CIT0032" href="#CIT0032">32</a>] show that differentiation between methylomes is greater than genetic divergence among closely related populations of animals. These studies, however, have the limitation of not addressing epigenetic changes solely in the germ line. Our previous study in Finches evaluated the methylome of red blood cells [
  <a rid="CIT0031" href="#CIT0031">31</a>], while Smith et al. [
  <a rid="CIT0032" href="#CIT0032">32</a>] investigated the methylome in ovaries, which contain both somatic and germ cells. DNA methylation differences in lungs of chickens from Fayoumi and Leghorn lines suggest the implication of DNA methylation in differential immune responses among these lines [
  <a rid="CIT0033" href="#CIT0033">33</a>]. Although it is interesting to find a correlation between somatic epigenetic marks and evolution, causation between epigenetic changes and genomic changes can only be established when the methylome is assessed in the germ line. Previous research comparing the sperm methylome obtained from one chicken to a publicly available human sperm methylome map suggests that sperm CpG hypermutability has strongly impacted the evolution of GC content of vertebrates [
  <a rid="CIT0034" href="#CIT0034">34</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Using the model of chicken diversification, the present study addresses the role of CpG sites in generating genetic diversity in the form of Single Nucleotide Polymorphisms (SNPs) and Copy Number Variations (CNVs). We address in a number of chickens of different breeds the extent the chicken genome has been affected by CpG-related mutations. For this, we have analysed the dynamics of CpG-related mutations between RJF (in its condition of closest related to the ancestor) and four domesticated breeds, including broiler (BRL) and three heritage breeds from different regions of Sweden: Kindahöna (KIN), Hedemorahöna (HED) and Gotlandshöna (GOT).</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Additionally, we investigated correlations between the germ line methylome of RJF and CpG-related mutations. Assuming the germ line methylome of current and past populations of RJF are highly similar, we evaluated whether the germ line methylome of current RJF specimens exhibits associations with the genomic variation observed between RJF and selected domesticated breeds. We focused on the germ line because germ line mutations can have transgenerational consequences, making them suitable to pinpoint the role of DNA methylation in generating genomic novelty. Both environmental exposures and DNA methylation changes have been associated with germ line mutations. For example, germ line mutations in rodents are shown to be influenced by environmental factors and subsequently carried over through generations, producing genomic variability representing evolutionary novelty [
  <a rid="CIT0035" href="#CIT0035">35</a>,
  <a rid="CIT0036" href="#CIT0036">36</a>]. Also in rodents, environmentally induced transgenerational changes in DNA methylation in the germ line associated with increased copy number variations (specifically, genomic gains) three generations after the exposure [
  <a rid="CIT0037" href="#CIT0037">37</a>]. In human sperm, Alu insertions exhibit CpG hypomethylation in their flanking regions [
  <a rid="CIT0029" href="#CIT0029">29</a>], suggesting CpGs are involved in regulating Alu transposition, which could induce CNVs.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From a biological and evolutionary perspective, it is fundamental to understand mutation dynamics in genomic regions that on one hand are susceptible to environmental influences, and on the other hand influence mutation rates, such as CpG sites. Taking advantage of the recent and well-studied diversification process that has originated domesticated chicken breeds, we evaluated how CpG-related mutations could have influenced genomic variability between RJF and four domesticated breeds. Additionally, we addressed correlations between germ line DNA methylation in RJF and the emergence of SNPs and CNVs in the domesticate breeds studied. The present study is the first to evaluate CpG mutation dynamics to this depth in the context of vertebrate genomic diversification.</p>
</sec>
