<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="S0002-S2003" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Relation of CpGs to mutations</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We then identified the SNPs and CNVs that occurred specifically in overlapping positions to CpGs observed in the sequenced 
  <span class="italic">PstI</span>-reduced RJF genome and created the subgroups CpG-SNPs and CpG-CNVs, respectively. A total of 14,298 CpG-SNPs was found, representing 1.71% of all the CpGs analysed (835,182 CpGs). 9.51% of all SNPs are related to CpGs, which is 52.16% above the expected value (P &lt; 0.001, Chi-Square; Suppl Table S1). We defined the expected value (1/16) as the probability that CpG dinucleotides would contribute the same as other dinucleotides to SNP formation (i.e., 1 out of all 16 possible dinucleotide combinations). Thus, our results show CG dinucleotides disproportionally influence SNP formation. Interestingly, the more genetically distant the breed is from RJF, the more CpG-SNPs are present above expectancy. In BRL, CpG-SNPs presence is as high as 100.7% above expectancy (P &lt; 0.001, Chi-Square; 
  <a rid="F0002" href="#F0002">Figure 2(a))</a>. This suggests CpGs, in addition to being hotspots of mutations [
  <a rid="CIT0015" href="#CIT0015">15</a>–
  <a rid="CIT0019" href="#CIT0019">19</a>], are hotspots of SNPs that are relevant for genomic speciation. While 31.3% of CpG-SNPs are breed-specific, the fractions of breed-specific CpG-SNPs in relation to all CpG-SNPs are 8.05% in KIN, 9.2% in HED, 9.4% in GOT and 12.54% in BRL (Suppl Table S1). A Venn-diagram showing the number of CpG-SNPs detected in each domesticated breed in relation to RJF is shown in 
  <a rid="F0002" href="#F0002">Figure 2(b)</a>.
  <div id="F0002" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
   <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1080/15592294.2019.1609868-F0002</span>
   <span class="label">Figure 2.</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Categorization of CpG-SNPs and CpG-CNVs found among domesticated breeds of chickens and RJF. (a) Plot depicting the incidence of CpG-SNPs in the domesticated breeds in relation to RJF (* depicts P &lt; 0.001; Chi-Square). (b) Venn diagram showing CpG-SNPs emerging between the domesticated breeds analysed and RJF. (c) Venn diagram showing base pairs covered by CpG-CNVs emerging between the domesticated breeds analysed and RJF.</p>
   </div>
   <div specific-use="web-only" content-type="color" xlink:href="kepi-14-07-1609868-g002" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">CpG-CNVs were defined as counts of CpGs present in base pairs covered by CNVs emerging between RJF and the domesticated breeds. A Venn-diagram with the CpG-CNVs detected in each domesticated breed in relation to RJF is shown in 
  <a rid="F0002" href="#F0002">Figure 2(c)</a>. A total of 285,097 CpG-CNVs was identified, with 23.6% of these being breed-specific (Suppl Table S2). This represents 34.1% of all the CpGs analysed (835,182 CpGs). Thus, we identified nearly 20 times more CpG-CNVs than CpG-SNPs. In contrast to the pattern observed for CpG-SNPs, CpGs are highly under-represented in CNVs in relation to expected values (approximately 98% decrease; Suppl Table S2), and the percentage of decrease in CpG-CNVs expectancy per breed is independent of genetic relatedness to RJF (Suppl Table S2).
 </p>
</sec>
