<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="S0002-S2007" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Relation of CpG-related mutations to DNA methylation in RJF sperm</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on the observations that mutation dynamics differ between Cs in or outside CpGs, we inquired into potential correlations between DNA methylation levels in the sperm of our RJF population (from ejaculates) and CpG-related mutations. For the DNA methylation analysis, we used a novel combination of methods (Genotyping-by-Sequencing and Methylated DNA immunoprecipitation) that we developed previously [
  <a rid="CIT0041" href="#CIT0041">41</a>]. RJF sperm DNA methylation was also measured in the 
  <span class="italic">PstI</span>-reduced genome, thus we compared them to mutations in the same genomic fraction. Although we cannot assert that DNA methylation in RJF sperm has directly influenced CpG mutation rates in the domesticated breeds evaluated here, we rationalized that the analysis of DNA methylation from sperm from our RJF population could give a good approximation of ancestral sperm DNA methylation patterns. We investigated whether two variables in RJF sperm DNA methylation, namely i) DNA methylation levels, and ii) associated inter-individual variability, correlated to the SNPs or CNVs observed between RJF and the domesticated breeds. The methylated fraction of the 
  <span class="italic">PstI</span>-reduced sperm RJF genome was captured by Methylated DNA immunoprecipitation (
  <span class="italic">PstI</span>-MeDIP), as previously described [
  <a rid="CIT0041" href="#CIT0041">41</a>]. Sequencing of this 
  <span class="italic">PstI</span>-MeDIP fraction resulted in an average of 1.4 million thousand reads per individual (N = 20) aligned against the chicken reference genome (
  <span class="italic">Gallus_gallus</span> 4.0, NCBI). This corresponds to 80.7% of the sequenced reads. In average, 227 million bps were sequenced, spanning 7 million unique genomic positions covered at 22.3 ± 11.3 X per individual. This corresponds to 0.6% of the total chicken genome per individual. To identify CpG sites to be analyzed, we merged the data from 20 RJF individuals. This merging resulted in 2.9 billion bps being analyzed, spanning 35 million unique genomic positions covered at 81.8X in average. This corresponds to 3.34% of the total chicken genome. The merging allowed to identify 835.182 CpGs, which corresponds to 7.8% of all CpGs within the chicken genome. Of these, 572,066 CpGs (68.5%) presented some degree of methylation in at least one individual and were therefore selected for further analyses.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The measured sperm DNA methylation was categorized according to i) the level of DNA methylation, and ii) the variation in DNA methylation across the individuals studied (inter-individual variation). 
  <a rid="F0006" href="#F0006">Figure 6(a</a>) shows the level of DNA methylation (represented by the normalized number of reads by which each CpG is covered) versus the inter-individual variation in DNA methylation in these CpGs.
  <div id="F0006" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
   <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1080/15592294.2019.1609868-F0006</span>
   <span class="label">Figure 6.</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Association of CpG-related mutations in domesticated breeds with DNA methylation in RJF sperm. (a) Inter-individual DNA methylation variation plotted against the level of DNA methylation, measured per window, and grid representation of the division of CpGs in nine DNA methylation categories. (b) Pie representation of the number of CpGs within each DNA methylation category in sperm RJF. (c) Representation of the subgroups of CpGs that relate to mutations (CpGs or CNVs) in each domesticated breed. (d) Pie representations of DNA methylation categories of the subgroups of CpGs measured for DNA methylation in sperm RJF that relate to SNPs (CpG-SNPs) or to CNVs (CpG-CNVs) in the domesticated breeds. (e) Bar plots summarizing how levels and inter-individual variation of DNA methylation in RJF sperm associate with mutations (SNPs or CNVs) in the domesticated breeds.</p>
   </div>
   <div specific-use="web-only" content-type="color" xlink:href="kepi-14-07-1609868-g006" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nine categories were defined for these CpGs based on their DNA methylation levels and inter-individual variation: Low Methylation-Low Variation (LM-LV); Low Methylation-Medium Variation (LM-MV); Low Methylation-High Variation (LM-HV); Medium Methylation-Low Variation (MM-LV); Medium Methylation-Medium Variation (MM-MV); Medium Methylation-High Variation (MM-HV); High Methylation-Low Variation (HM-LV); High Methylation-Medium Variation (HM-MV); High Methylation-High Variation (HM-HV). The criteria for the definition of the limits of these categories are described in detail in the Materials and Methods section. CpG proportions across DNA methylation categories in RJF sperm are shown in 
  <a rid="F0006" href="#F0006">Figure 6(b</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The majority of CpGs detected in the methylated fraction of the 
  <span class="italic">PstI</span>-reduced fraction of the sperm genome are LM-MV (50.12%), followed by MM-MV (16.03%), and LM-LV (14%). We then investigated if DNA methylation status in the male germ line of RJF would associate to the mutations (SNPs and CNVs) observed between RJF and the domesticated breeds. To determine this, we selected CpG sites that were in the same genomic locations where SNPs (i.e., CpG-SNPs) or CNVs (i.e., CpG-CNVs) emerged between RJF and the domesticated breed. The number of CpGs in which DNA methylation was evaluated in the sperm of RJF, and the number of CpG-SNPs and CpG-CNVs obtained in each breed are shown in 
  <a rid="F0006" href="#F0006">Figure 6(c</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We hypothesized that if no correlation between RJF sperm DNA methylation and SNPs or CNVs exists, then the distribution of CpGs across the nine DNA methylation categories in the RJF sperm (all sperm CpGs measured; reference pattern) is expected to be the same as in the CpG-SNPs or CpG-CNVs subgroups (in each domesticated breed). Interestingly, our results show major differences in the distribution of CpGs across the nine DNA methylation categories between the reference pattern (
  <a rid="F0006" href="#F0006">Figure 6(a</a>); all CpGs measured in RJF sperm) and the CpG-SNPs subgroups (
  <a rid="F0006" href="#F0006">Figure 6(d</a>), top panel). For instance, when considering all CpGs in RJF sperm, the largest category of CpG methylation is LM-LV, while in the subgroups of CpG-SNPs in the domesticated breeds the largest category is MM-HV. Furthermore, the distribution is altered in relation to the reference value in a consistent manner in all domesticated breeds, which represent independent replicates. In contrast, in the CpG-CNVs subgroups, the distribution of CpGs across methylation categories in the domesticated breeds is similar to the reference value (
  <a rid="F0006" href="#F0006">Figure 6(d</a>), lower panel). Thus, patterns of CpG methylation differ considerably between the CpG-SNPs and CpG-CNVs subgroups, with the latter being similar to the reference value.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We then tested which of the DNA methylation variables studied (i.e., DNA methylation levels or inter-individual variation) were altered the most between all RJF sperm CpGs (reference pattern) and the subgroups of CpGs related to mutations (SNPs or CNVS). For this, we compared the amount of CpGs in each DNA methylation category within the CpG-SNPs or CpG-CNVs subgroups against the reference value in RJF sperm (
  <a rid="F0006" href="#F0006">Figure 6(e))</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We found that CpGs in RJF sperm with medium levels of DNA methylation together with medium (P &lt; 0.001) to high levels (P &lt; 0.001) of inter-individual variation are substantially overrepresented in the CpG-SNPs subgroups, as well as CpGs with high levels of DNA methylation and medium variation (P &lt; 0.001) (
  <a rid="F0006" href="#F0006">Figure 6(e))</a>. Conversely, CpGs in RJF sperm with high levels of DNA methylation and low (P &lt; 0.05) to medium (P &lt; 0.05) variation are overrepresented in the CpG-CNVs subgroups, as well as CpGs with medium levels of DNA methylation and low variation (P &lt; 0.005) (
  <a rid="F0006" href="#F0006">Figure 6(e</a>)). Interestingly, the combination of high methylation with medium variation is overrepresented in both subgroups. For both CpG-SNPs and CpG-CNVs the significant increases in some categories are compensated by decreases in other categories. In summary, the majority of CpG-SNPs associate with medium levels of methylation and medium/high variation in RJF sperm, while the majority of CpG-CNVs associate with high levels of methylation and low/medium variability in RJF sperm.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on these associations between DNA methylation features in RJF sperm and mutations emerging in specific breeds, we inquired about the mutation probabilities of CpGs within each DNA methylation category. We implemented Bayesian inference and calculated posterior distributions of mutation probabilities (separately for SNPs and CNVs) for the RJF sperm CpGs methylation categories, and observed substantial differences among them, both in relation to SNPs (
  <a rid="F0007" href="#F0007">Figure 7(a</a>)) and CNVs (
  <a rid="F0007" href="#F0007">Figure 7(b))</a>. Additionally, the patterns of these mutation probabilities are different when related to SNPs or CNVs. A very interesting finding is that in two of the methylation categories, MM-HV and MM-MV, the CpG to SNP mutation rate increases as genetic relatedness to RJF decreases (
  <a rid="F0007" href="#F0007">Figure 7(a))</a>, while none of the categories exhibit this pattern in CpGs related to CNVs (
  <a rid="F0007" href="#F0007">Figure 7(b))</a>.
  <div id="F0007" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
   <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1080/15592294.2019.1609868-F0007</span>
   <span class="label">Figure 7.</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Posterior distributions (scaled to give equal rights to all density curves) of mutation probabilities of CpGs within the sperm RJF DNA methylation categories, in relation to (a) SNPs; (b) CNVs.</p>
   </div>
   <div specific-use="web-only" content-type="color" xlink:href="kepi-14-07-1609868-g007" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
