<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Understanding the scope of climate change impacts on marine environments requires integration of empirical observations, theory, and models across disciplines. Nevertheless, specific marine disciplines often apply distinct methodologies that operate at disparate scales, influencing interpretations of global responses to climate (Parmesan, 
 <xref rid="gcb12978-bib-0065" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>). Studies of climate‐driven change in marine environments may be impeded by spatially limited or generally short ocean time series, which are often inadequate to establish the necessary baselines upon which to assess change (Rosenzweig 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="gcb12978-bib-0083" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>; Brown 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="gcb12978-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>). The highest confidence in attribution of biological impacts to climate change occurs at the scale of ocean basins or larger (Parmesan 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="gcb12978-bib-0067" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>). Long‐term marine biological datasets are particularly lacking compared to key physical records (Brierley &amp; Kingsford, 
 <xref rid="gcb12978-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>; Edwards 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="gcb12978-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>; Koslow &amp; Couture, 
 <xref rid="gcb12978-bib-0046" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>), yet they are necessary to understand how physical and chemical environmental changes may drive biological change. Mismatches in spatial and temporal sampling of biological responses compared to physical processes complicate climate change studies that require separation of complex natural cycles from climate change impacts (Hobday &amp; Evans, 
 <xref rid="gcb12978-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Parmesan 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="gcb12978-bib-0068" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>).
</p>
