<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Free trade cannot entirely compensate monetary losses in agriculture caused by climate change. Moreover, this damage is unequally distributed between consumers and producers and among different sociogeographic regions. Even in the case of liberal trade, certain consumers and producers will be worse off. There is a clear tendency that consumers in all regions will end up paying more for agricultural products. On the other hand, given that many subsistence and smallholder farmers live in developing regions, policies will have to be advanced to help them to adapt their production under changing market conditions (
 <xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">42</italic>
 </xref>). In light of the recent Bali Package trade agreement (
 <xref rid="R43" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">43</italic>
 </xref>), which was part of the Doha Development Round trade negotiations within the World Trade Organization (
 <xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">44</italic>
 </xref>), appropriate policy reforms can be justified based on this study because trade liberalization is beneficial for abating climate change impacts on agricultural welfare. However, regions that are bound to see decreases in export shares as a consequence of climate change (for example, LAM in our analysis) have an incentive to implement policies to support domestic production, for example trade barriers or export subsidies to domestic producers, which could diminish economic gains in higher-latitude regions. Given the amplifying effect of climate change on the gradient between developed and developing countries, trade policies will also have to be accompanied by measures for poverty reduction in developing countries. Food security measures have to be actively supported, and the agents’ adaptive capacity to the dynamics of liberalization has to be taken into account.
</p>
