<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec003" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Between 1980 and 2010, selection on egg-laying date changed from initially stabilising to directional selection for early laying, but this directional selection relaxed again during the last decade. We found no evidence indicating that this pattern was explained by environmental variables measured within the breeding season nor by the temporal mismatch with the food peak [
  <a rid="pbio.1002120.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1002120.ref035">35</a>,
  <a rid="pbio.1002120.ref041" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1002120.ref041">41</a>]. Instead, the annual variation in selection was correlated with spring temperatures up to two years after breeding, with stronger selection for earlier laying when spring temperatures in the arrival year for the cohort were high. In our study, the increase in spring temperatures initially led to stronger selection for early egg-laying, as offspring from early nests were more likely to recruit than offspring from late nests under warm conditions upon arrival (
  <a rid="pbio.1002120.g001" ref-type="fig" href="#pbio.1002120.g001">Fig. 1C</a>). Between 2000 and 2010, however, arrival temperatures have decreased. This cooling has weakened the strength of directional selection on egg-laying date in this population. We thus show that changes in spring temperatures have a clear impact on selection on a key life history trait: timing of reproduction.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We found no strong evidence for an effect of a phenological mismatch with the caterpillar peak on selection in this migratory species, as previously has been suggested [
  <a rid="pbio.1002120.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1002120.ref035">35</a>,
  <a rid="pbio.1002120.ref041" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1002120.ref041">41</a>] based on other systems [
  <a rid="pbio.1002120.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1002120.ref009">9</a>–
  <a rid="pbio.1002120.ref011" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1002120.ref011">11</a>,
  <a rid="pbio.1002120.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1002120.ref042">42</a>]. This is unexpected, as synchrony between food peaks and avian timing of reproduction has often been suggested to be important [
  <a rid="pbio.1002120.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1002120.ref043">43</a>,
  <a rid="pbio.1002120.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1002120.ref044">44</a>], and differential phenological responses across trophic levels to climate change have been a major hypothesis explaining increased selection, reduced reproduction, and population declines [
  <a rid="pbio.1002120.ref045" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1002120.ref045">45</a>,
  <a rid="pbio.1002120.ref046" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1002120.ref046">46</a>]. Also in our study population, caterpillars are an important component in the nestling diet of pied flycatchers, and in warm years, strong seasonal declines in the proportion of caterpillars in the diet were observed [
  <a rid="pbio.1002120.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1002120.ref037">37</a>]. We did find that the height of the peak in caterpillar abundance, rather than the temporal synchrony with the caterpillar peak, affected the seasonal decline in number of fledglings (
  <a rid="pbio.1002120.t001" ref-type="table" href="#pbio.1002120.t001">Table 1</a>). In years with high caterpillar abundance, there was only a weak decline in the number of fledglings over the course of the season; whereas in low caterpillar peak years, this decline was much stronger. This suggests that caterpillars are indeed important as a food source affecting flycatcher fitness and that their availability per se influences selection on seasonal timing. The lack of an effect of synchrony could thus be partly obscured by variation in caterpillar peak height. Caterpillar availability strongly fluctuates between years, with a factor 20 or more between the lowest and highest caterpillar density years [
  <a rid="pbio.1002120.ref047" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1002120.ref047">47</a>] and a cycle period of around 9–10 y [
  <a rid="pbio.1002120.ref048" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1002120.ref048">48</a>]. Within our dataset, we had periods with peak abundances around 1996 and 2009, and in these years, even birds that breed out of synchrony with the caterpillar peak do not have a strongly reduced offspring production, although very late birds always do poorly because of reduced food availability later in the season [
  <a rid="pbio.1002120.ref049" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1002120.ref049">49</a>]. In line with this, the seasonal decline in clutch size is stronger in years when the birds breed late relative to the food peak [
  <a rid="pbio.1002120.ref050" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1002120.ref050">50</a>]. Predictions of potential effects of climate change should thus not just consider temporal matching but also potential changes in food abundance [
  <a rid="pbio.1002120.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1002120.ref042">42</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our fitness measure is the number of fledglings that locally recruit in our population, and therefore this fitness estimate does not include all offspring that survive and disperse out of the study population. Our best estimate is that about four times as many fledglings recruit elsewhere with dispersal distances up to 600 km [
  <a rid="pbio.1002120.ref051" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1002120.ref051">51</a>]. This means that measuring fitness as the number of local recruits is potentially biased if differential dispersal exists with respect to laying date of the mother. If offspring that originate from early- or late-laid clutches differ in the likelihood that they recruit outside the study areas, this will lead to apparent selection for egg-laying date. However, correlative and experimental data in pied flycatchers do not support this idea; experimentally delayed hatching date (during three consecutive breeding seasons) did not affect natal dispersal in a metapopulation setup where dispersing offspring could be tracked up to 25 km [
  <a rid="pbio.1002120.ref052" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1002120.ref052">52</a>]. Thus, we have no indication that differential dispersal with respect to timing exists in our study system.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The idea of differential dispersal in response to climate change is that late-arriving individuals in warm years benefit by continuing their migration further north and thereby matching habitat phenology with their own timing [
  <a rid="pbio.1002120.ref053" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1002120.ref053">53</a>]. Support for northwards dispersal has been found in black-winged stilts in dry springs [
  <a rid="pbio.1002120.ref054" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1002120.ref054">54</a>] and in American redstarts that depart later from their wintering grounds [
  <a rid="pbio.1002120.ref055" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1002120.ref055">55</a>], but these studies could not unequivocally demonstrate that differential dispersal for a phenotypic trait was related to environmental variation. In our case, we predict that such a pattern would result in especially late-arriving individuals showing high survival in cold years, and low survival in warm years, whereas little effect is expected for early-arriving individuals. Our results, however, do not support these predictions for differential dispersal: late-born offspring recruited equally well when returning in colder or warmer springs (
  <a rid="pbio.1002120.g001" ref-type="fig" href="#pbio.1002120.g001">Fig. 1C</a>: comparing data points for laying dates &gt;5). Variation in selection between warm and cold years was thus not caused by differential survival of late-born offspring but rather for early-born offspring that return more in warmer than in colder years (
  <a rid="pbio.1002120.g001" ref-type="fig" href="#pbio.1002120.g001">Fig. 1C</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In almost any natural population, permanent dispersal is difficult to separate from mortality, especially when dispersal can occur over large distances. A key consideration in this respect is to assess whether this dispersal likelihood is correlated with the trait of interest, i.e., egg-laying date. We cannot rule out the possibility that differential dispersal affects our fitness estimates, but available evidence suggests that differential dispersal is not a main factor explaining our results. Additionally, differential dispersal would only mediate the patterns observed in 
  <a rid="pbio.1002120.g001" ref-type="fig" href="#pbio.1002120.g001">Fig. 1A</a> if its relationship with laying date changed over time, which is unlikely. Consequently, in our opinion, the pattern depicted in 
  <a rid="pbio.1002120.g001" ref-type="fig" href="#pbio.1002120.g001">Fig. 1A</a> is most parsimoniously explained by temporal variation in the relationship between egg-laying date and fitness.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As in many studies of natural populations, the correlation between trait (here egg-laying date) and fitness could potentially be caused by covariance with some environmental variable [
  <a rid="pbio.1002120.ref056" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1002120.ref056">56</a>]. Further mechanistic experimental work could therefore be useful in determining whether variation in offspring phenology, and its consequences for offspring and parental fitness, is caused by parental egg-laying date and hence hatch date per se, or if it covaries with parental egg-laying date because of genetic or environmental correlations [
  <a rid="pbio.1002120.ref057" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1002120.ref057">57</a>]. We also need more insights into why offspring from early-hatched clutches do so much better when the temperatures are high when they arrive (
  <a rid="pbio.1002120.g001" ref-type="fig" href="#pbio.1002120.g001">Fig. 1C</a>). Does an early arrival give them a competitive advantage which is offset against a higher mortality in colder years? This could yield further insights into the evolutionary potential of these phenological traits through parameterisation of more formal models [
  <a rid="pbio.1002120.ref058" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1002120.ref058">58</a>,
  <a rid="pbio.1002120.ref059" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1002120.ref059">59</a>] of the relationships between parental and offspring phenotype and fitness.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Studies have rarely demonstrated a relationship between selection on life history traits and climate change-altered environmental variables (i.e., selective agents [
  <a rid="pbio.1002120.ref025" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1002120.ref025">25</a>]). Yet, all of these studies found immediate effects, i.e., within the same season in which the life history trait is expressed [
  <a rid="pbio.1002120.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1002120.ref009">9</a>,
  <a rid="pbio.1002120.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1002120.ref028">28</a>,
  <a rid="pbio.1002120.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1002120.ref029">29</a>]. Here, we have shown the apparent absence of such immediate effects but demonstrated an effect of conditions years after the life history trait is expressed. Such effects have been little studied in this context, but might be common. Studies of both delayed effects of environmental variables and the interaction between demographic and evolutionary processes on selection are urgently needed as selection is a key component for microevolution of life history traits, which is ultimately the only route for populations to adapt to novel environments [
  <a rid="pbio.1002120.ref060" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1002120.ref060">60</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
