<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Thermal safety margins (TSM), the difference between a fish’s upper temperature limits (CTMax values from 20°C-acclimated fish) and habitat temperatures differed by species and were dependent on location within the SFE. Non-native Silversides and Largemouth Bass had larger TSMs (5–14°C) compared to native Delta Smelt (3.6–8.6°C) at all SFE regions included in the analysis (Fig. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="coy076F1" class="xref">1</xref>), driven by the lower upper thermal tolerance limits of Delta Smelt (Table 
 <xref rid="coy076TB3" ref-type="table" class="xref">3</xref>). Currently, wild Delta Smelt caught around their mean habitat temperature of 20°C may have a wide TSM of 8.6°C; however, average water temperatures in the SFE have been continuously increasing above 20°C over the past 20 years (see Fig. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="coy076F1" class="xref">1</xref> in 
 <xref rid="coy076C33" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Jeffries 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2016
 </xref>), are projected to increase in the SFE over the next 100 years (
 <xref rid="coy076C7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Brown 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2013
 </xref>), and during drought periods and heat wave events temperatures routinely reach 25–28°C (
 <xref rid="coy076C74" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Wagner 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2011
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="coy076C32" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Interagency Ecological Program MAST, 2015</xref>). Increasing periods of high temperature in the SFE is concerning as numerous studies indicate that climate change extinctions of species will occur in species with the narrowest TSM and demonstrating a limited capacity to acclimate (
 <xref rid="coy076C68" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Stillman, 2003</xref>; 
 <xref rid="coy076C16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Deutsch 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2008
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="coy076C25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gunderson and Stillman, 2015</xref>). Climate change predictions of 2–4°C increased in water temperature (
 <xref rid="coy076C12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Cloern 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2011
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="coy076C74" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Wagner 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2011
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="coy076C7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Brown 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2013
 </xref>) indicate Delta Smelt TSMs of less than 1°C at South Delta regions may reflect what TSMs of Delta Smelt could be across all SFE regions in the future. As previously described, Largemouth Bass do have further capacity to increase their upper thermal limits by 3–4°C above what was recorded in this current study (
 <xref rid="coy076C64" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Smith and Scott, 1975</xref>; 
 <xref rid="coy076C14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Currie 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 1998
 </xref>), thereby further increasing their TSM across all SFE regions. Delta Smelt may not have much if any additional acclimation capacity to increase upper thermal limits, although this requires investigation. Although upper thermal tolerance does vary across ontogeny, creating stage-specific TSMs, 
 <xref rid="coy076C39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Komoroske 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic> (2014)
 </xref> estimated TSMs for Delta Smelt finding negative margins in some cases for juveniles and adults compared to earlier larval stages with higher upper temperature tolerances. In evaluating implications of warming and increased salinity regimes on CTMax, it is important to acknowledge that CTMax (used to calculate TSM) provides insight into the maximum temperatures a fish can acutely survive and not how physiological performance is affected by sub-lethal warming on more ecologically relevant time scales. For example, 
 <xref rid="coy076C38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Komoroske 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic> (2015)
 </xref> showed Delta Smelt experience sub-lethal critical thresholds at 4–6°C below their CTMax such that fish had reduced ability to restore homeostastic mechanisms. Narrow TSM, limited physiological acclimation capacity, sub-lethal sensitivity, and already low population abundance (
 <xref rid="coy076C28" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hobbs 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2017
 </xref>) suggest juvenile Delta Smelt will be particularly vulnerable to continued rises in Delta water temperatures and climate change.
</p>
