<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In conclusion, each SFE species had the capacity to tolerate a series of multiple stressors that might be experienced during drought conditions. For prey species including Delta Smelt and Mississippi Silversides, short-term thermal history, but not salinity history influenced upper thermal tolerance; however, both thermal and salinity history influenced Largemouth Bass upper temperature tolerance. As expected, non-native fish were more thermally tolerant than native Delta Smelt and differed in thermal plasticity. Species-specific differences in temperature sensitivity and tolerances likely underlie the habitat range constraints in Delta Smelt and may explain increasing abundance and niche expansion in the non-native species. Climate change and increased occurrence of drought will likely continue to have a significant role in the shifted species assemblages in the SFE, favoring non-native fishes (as described in 
 <xref rid="coy076C60" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Quiñones and Moyle, 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="coy076C46" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Mahardja 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2017
 </xref>). For example, native species including Longfin Smelt (
 <italic class="italic">Spirinchus thaleichthys</italic>), Chinook salmon (
 <italic class="italic">Oncorhynchus tshawytscha</italic>), and Steelhead (
 <italic class="italic">Oncorhynchus mykiss irideus)</italic> also exhibit lowered physiological tolerances and/or plasticity compared to non-natives (
 <xref rid="coy076C10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Cech and Myrick, 1999</xref>; 
 <xref rid="coy076C53" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Muñoz 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2015
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="coy076C33" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Jeffries 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2016
 </xref>); however, there are some native species that will not be as vulnerable demonstrated by higher tolerances (to warming or salinity). Restoration projects assisting the conservation of native species in California’s SFE, to be successful in the long-term, must find a solution to deter non-native species that have wider physiological tolerances of environmental conditions and threaten to occupy restored habitat. The larger issue for endangered Delta Smelt is how to create thermal refugia due to their low thermal tolerance and increasingly warmer temperatures across the SFE. One restoration option to consider is to provide increased downstream (seaward) habitat, thereby facilitating cooler temperatures for Delta Smelt, which may be less favorable to other non-native species.
</p>
