<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Climate change is expected to have large effects on global wheat production: for every 1°C increase in temperature, global wheat yields are predicted to decline by 4.1–6.4% [
 <xref rid="pone.0204932.ref010" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. Wheat grown in warmer regions is likely to experience greater yield losses than that grown in cooler regions, though there is also general agreement that high latitude spring wheat production will benefit from a warmer climate through an extension of the growing period [
 <xref rid="pone.0204932.ref011" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>]. Simulations of wheat cultivation in the Canadian Prairies estimate that warmer temperatures could lead to yield increases of 26–37% (when elevated CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> concentration was simulated), or up to 15% without considering increased CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> [
 <xref rid="pone.0204932.ref012" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. Wang et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0204932.ref013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>] assessed the impact of climate change on wheat production in 2050 in southern Saskatchewan, Canada. Compared to the baseline (1961–1990), precipitation is projected to increase in every month except July and August while annual mean air temperature is projected to increase by 2.7–3.6°C, depending on the model used. Biomass and grain yield are expected to increase, though heat shocks could cause severe yield reductions. Early seeding must be undertaken to avoid heat damage during the reproductive phase. Using 1961–1990 as a baseline, climate change scenarios projected significantly earlier seeding dates than those currently used [
 <xref rid="pone.0204932.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. There is no projected reduction in grain yield because precipitation increases during sensitive wheat growth stage. Swinnen et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0204932.ref015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>] estimates that from a biophysical perspective, under different scenarios of land use and climate change, Kazakhstan, Russia and Ukraine could produce an additional 40–110 million tons of wheat compared to current production. Balkovic et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0204932.ref016" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>] also predicts that rainfed wheat in Russia has significant potential for growth.
</p>
