<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Implications and discussion</div>
 <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study demonstrates the importance of climate, land use change, and organic nucleation for the evaluation of anthropogenic aerosol RF. Organic nucleation has a large and complex influence on the aerosol size distribution as well as on the activation of particles to form cloud droplets. Here we show that organic nucleation leads to a 12.5% reduction in the direct plus indirect RF between the PD and PI atmosphere. Moreover, the total RF is further reduced by 4.0% when we include the effects of climate and land use change. Thus, we find a 16% smaller forcing due to anthropogenic aerosols as a result of including organic nucleation, land use change and climate change.</p>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The calculation of SOA and the RF is uncertain in part because of poorly defined chemical formation mechanisms. We currently have limited knowledge of the explicit chemical reactions that lead to the production of extremely low volatility HOMs, although there should be many ways that these form
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
  </span>. Here, we included those HOMs that have been shown to contribute to nucleation in quantum chemical calculations, but it is possible that there are other HOMs that contribute to nucleation and will be identified in the future. The use of different HOMs that lead to nucleation is expected to contribute to a large uncertainty in the RF estimation associated organic nucleation. Most experiments indicated that HOMs are produced through H-shift and peroxy radical autoxidation of monoterpenes
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span>, although some experiments regarded HOMs as a first-generation product from precusor gases, while others include them after a series of oxidation steps
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
  </span>. Here, we have primarily focused on α-pinene as a precursor to HOM. Exocyclic monoterpenes like β-pinene mostly react with OH and do not form HOMs, so while excluding the production of HOMs from exocyclic monoterpenes adds some uncertainty, it is not likely to be large compared to other uncertainties. The suppression of new particle formation by isoprene has been detected in some field and chamber experiments
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
  </span>. However, it is not clear how isoprene and its oxidation products may change the oxidation chemistry of terpenes
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
  </span>. Including isoprene suppression could reduce the number of new organic particles in the PBL further. The temperature dependence of the nucleation rate used in our model is based on a quantum chemical calculation and could cause some uncertainty in the newSOA number concentration. As shown in Supplementary 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S3.1</a>, the total RF of anthropogenic aerosol is increased by 5.3% without the temperature dependence. The growth rate of newSOA is another important uncertainty that affects the RF estimate. When the low volatility products formed from isoprene epoxydiol (IEPOX), glyoxal and methylglyoxal contribute to the growth of newSOA, the total RF is increased by 12% (see Supplementary 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S3.2</a>). The emissions of aerosols in the PI atmosphere have large differences depending on different models. For example, Hamilton et al.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>
  </span> used several fire emissions data sets to suggest that the cloud albedo forcing might be reduced by 35% when larger fire emissions are used in the PI atmosphere. Larger emissions would also alter our results by adding additional condensation sinks. In addition, uncertainties in the change in land use and vegetation type will also alter the BVOC emissions, leading to an uncertainty in the baseline of SOA in the PI atmosphere
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
</sec>
