<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Influence of SOA on radiative forcing</div>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here we evaluate the radiative effects of SOA with and without organic nucleation and with and without climate and land use change in both the PD and PI atmosphere. Previous studies did not evaluate the influence of organic nucleation on the direct radiative forcing (DRF)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>. Our model indicates that the PD direct radiative effect (DRE) of SOA is 25% larger due to organic nucleation (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>). The burden of total SOA in PIall is 13% larger than that in PIemi, resulting in the 19% larger global average DRE of SOA in PIall compared to PIemi (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">10</a>). The size distribution of newSOA also influences the DRE of SOA. The burden of newSOA contributes 45 and 48% to the total SOA burden in PIemi and PIall, respectively. Although the burden of newSOA in PIall is 22% larger than that in PIemi, the total surface area of newSOA in PIall is only 3.4% larger than that in PIemi due to changes in the size distribution. Moreover, the difference in organic nucleation caused by climate and land use change can alter the concentration of sulfate indirectly. The sulfuric acid condensed on newSOA (SO4SOA) is decreased by 4% in PIall compared to PIemi (Supplementary Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2</a>). As a result, the additional sulfuric acid gas in PIall promotes new particle formation of sulfate and the growth of more new sulfate particles to a larger size. The column number concentration of new sulfate in the Aitken and accumulation modes in PIall is 15% and 4.5% larger than that in PIemi, respectively (Supplementary Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2</a>). As a result, the DRF of anthropogenic aerosol is estimated to be −0.384 W m
  <span class="sup">−2</span> using PIall but −0.410 W m
  <span class="sup">−2</span> using PIemi (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2a, b</a>). Thus, the anthropogenic aerosol DRF is decreased by 6.3% when changes in climate and land use are included. The difference in DRF of anthropogenic aerosols comes from the combined effects of changes in the total SOA burden and the size distributions of new sulfate particles and newSOA. The total surface area of new sulfate and newSOA in PIall is 7.8% larger than that in PIemi, causing a smaller forcing. Without organic nucleation, the DRF of anthropogenic aerosol using PIall is −0.469 W m
  <span class="sup">−2</span>, which is 22% larger than the DRF with organic nucleation (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">11</a>). This is because the total new aerosol surface area decreases by 17% in the PI atmosphere due to the decrease in the total aerosol number concentration.
  <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>The radiative forcing of anthropogenic aerosol with different preindustrial schemes. 
     <span class="bold">a</span>–
     <span class="bold">d</span> The direct radiative forcing (DRF; 
     <span class="bold">a</span>, 
     <span class="bold">b</span>) and indirect radiative forcing (IRF; 
     <span class="bold">c</span>, 
     <span class="bold">d</span>) of anthropogenic aerosol with the preindustrial values from PIemi (
     <span class="bold">a</span>, 
     <span class="bold">c</span>) and PIall (
     <span class="bold">b</span>, 
     <span class="bold">d</span>). The global average radiative forcing is shown on the top right of each panel
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2019_8407_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e1045" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The AIE of SOA is much more sensitive to the inclusion of organic nucleation since it strongly depends on the change in the aerosol number concentration as well as the size distribution. The AIE of SOA is small without organic nucleation (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>). Organic nucleation produces newSOA and some grow to CCN size and increase cloud droplet number concentrations (CDNC). In addition, the large number concentration of newSOA decreases water supersaturations drastically due to enhanced condensation. SOA enhances the global average accumulation mode particle number concentration in the PBL by 22 cm
  <span class="sup">−3</span> (Supplementary Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>) and the CDNC at the top of water liquid clouds by 1.32 × 10
  <span class="sup">6</span> m
  <span class="sup">−3</span> (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">12a</a>), resulting in an AIE of SOA of −0.148 W m
  <span class="sup">−2</span> in the PD (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">13a</a>). However, in regions of the NH where the number concentration of sulfate is large, the CDNC at the top of liquid water clouds decreases due to SOA because the maximum supersaturation is significantly reduced by the newSOA and this suppresses many of other particles from being activated to cloud droplets. SOA with organic nucleation results in a positive AIE of SOA in the regions of the NH in the PD (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">13a</a>). SOA also lowers the supersaturation in the PI atmosphere, but the CDNC always increases due to SOA because of the low number concentrations of other aerosols. Organic nucleation results in a column number of newSOA in the accumulation mode of 2.8 × 10
  <span class="sup">10</span> and 2.4 × 10
  <span class="sup">10</span> m
  <span class="sup">−2</span> for PIemi and PIall, respectively (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>). The SOA in PIemi causes an increase in the CNDC by 9.91 × 10
  <span class="sup">6</span> m
  <span class="sup">−3</span> at the top of liquid water clouds (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">12b</a>), while in PIall the CDNC increases by 9.69 × 10
  <span class="sup">6</span> m
  <span class="sup">−3</span> due to the smaller number concentration of newSOA (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">12c</a>). As a result, the AIE due to SOA in PIall is 8.3% smaller than that in PIemi (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">13b, c</a>). However, the column number concentration of new sulfate particles in the Aitken and accumulation modes in PIall increases by 15 and 4.5%, respectively, compared to PIemi due to smaller amounts of sulfuric acid condensed on newSOA in PIall. As a result, climate and land use change enhance the preindustrial value of the AIE of SOA. The indirect radiative forcing (IRF) of anthropogenic aerosol is −1.675 W m
  <span class="sup">−2</span> using PIall (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2c</a>), which is 3.5% smaller than the forcing (−1.735 W m
  <span class="sup">−2</span>) using PIemi (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2d</a>). Without organic nucleation, the IRF of anthropogenic aerosol is −1.878 W m
  <span class="sup">−2</span> using PIall (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">14</a>). Thus, the inclusion of organic nucleation leads to a 11% smaller IRF of anthropogenic aerosol, which is much smaller than the 27% reduction indicated in ref. 
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>. Some of this difference is due to our use of a temperature dependence for the nucleation rate. For example, Gordon et al.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span> found a 17% reduction of IRF when they used the same temperature dependence as we use (see also Supplementary 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S3.1</a>). However, some is due to the fact that the organic nucleation in our model primarily occurs in the upper troposphere so that only 4.3 and 6.0% of the total accumulation mode newSOA occurs in the PBL for the PD and PIall, respectively. In contrast, organic particles mostly form near the surface using the methods in ref. 
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>, which may overestimate the influence of organic nucleation in the PI atmosphere and thus its influence on the IRF.
 </p>
</sec>
