<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Aerosols play a key role in determining the Earth’s radiation budget, both directly by absorbing and scattering radiation and indirectly by altering the albedo of clouds
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span>. The effects of aerosols on climate constitute the largest uncertainty in the current understanding of climate change
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span>. Climate and land use change contribute to this uncertainty by causing changes in biogenic volatile organic carbon (BVOC) emissions that form secondary organic aerosol (SOA) particles. SOA often represents a major fraction of submicron-sized atmospheric organic aerosol and dominates ambient aerosol in tropical and remote regions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nucleation of atmospheric vapors is the largest source of atmospheric aerosol number concentration
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span>, and is thought to contribute to up to half of the global cloud condensation nuclei (CCN)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
  </span>. Most models only use a particle formation rate based on the concentration of sulfuric acid
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>
  </span>. However, these models fail to reproduce nucleation rates in ambient observations with a low concentration of sulfuric acid
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>
  </span>. Recently, highly oxygenated molecules (HOMs) with extremely low volatility were shown by experiments in the CLOUD (Cosmics Leaving Outdoor Droplets) project to be able to form new particles even in the absence of sulfuric acid
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
  </span> and to drive initial particle growth
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span>. Ion-induced nucleation of pure organic particles is expected to be a potentially widespread source of new aerosol particles in pristine regions as well as in the preindustrial (PI) atmosphere
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The aerosol number concentration and size distribution are important factors determining the CCN concentration and largely determine the aerosol indirect effect (AIE)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>
  </span>. A small AIE (&lt;−0.1 W m
  <span class="sup">−2</span> for the global average) of SOA was estimated without organic nucleation involving either pure organics or a heteromolecular process involving organics and sulfuric acid, since most SOA is internally mixed with particles in the accumulation mode that are already CCN
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span>. A much stronger AIE of SOA (−0.22 to −0.77 W m
  <span class="sup">−2</span>) associated with including new particle formation from BVOC and sulfuric acid was calculated due to the increase in the number of CCN-size particles
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span>. Gordon et al.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span> indicated that pure organic nucleation enhances the baseline of particle number concentrations in the PI environment, resulting in a 27% decrease in anthropogenic aerosol radiative forcing (RF)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>. However, previous model studies applied empirical or semi-empirical fixed and instantaneous HOM yields
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
  </span>. These studies assumed that autoxidation occurs rapidly and produces HOMs after the initial oxidation step based on the CLOUD project experiments. The latter took place under specific chamber conditions that may not exactly reflect what occurs in the atmosphere. This assumption affects the vertical and horizontal distribution of newly formed SOA as well as the time scales for SOA formation, and it places most new particles near the surface, where BVOC concentrations are highest. In addition, most studies that estimated RF omitted the influence of climate and land use change on the emissions of BVOC, so they are unable to properly represent the change of SOA between the present-day (PD) and PI atmosphere and thus are unable to estimate RF accurately.
 </p>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study uses a comprehensive nucleation scheme that includes the heteromolecular, pure neutral, and ion-induced organic nucleation of HOMs that are produced through an explicit chemical mechanism
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>
  </span> instead of the assumption of fast autoxidation in previous studies. Using this model, we are able to reproduce observations of the vertical distribution of condensation nuclei in the Amazon. The influence of organic nucleation as well as climate and land use change on aerosol RF is calculated. Overall, we find a 16% reduced radiative forcing associated with anthropogenic aerosols with the combined effect of organic nucleation, climate, and land use change.
 </p>
</sec>
