<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Simulation scheme</div>
 <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The PD scheme used PD emissions, climate, and land use. The PIemi scheme was run with emissions from 1750 but with the climate and land use from the PD. The PIall scheme was run with the same anthropogenic emissions as in PIemi but with climate and land use in the PI. The PD anthropogenic and biomass burning emissions are adopted from those used in Community Atmosphere Model (CAM) with Chemistry for 2000
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>
  </span> and those from Community Emission Data System (CEDS) for 1750
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>
  </span>. The emission of BVOC are predicted based on MEGAN 2.1 (Model of Emissions of Gases and Aerosols from Nature, version 2.1)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>
  </span> which is embedded in the CESM. The BVOC emission rates depend on the light, temperature, leaf area index (LAI), and fractional coverage of plant functional types (PFT). The monthly mean time-varying LAI and PFT take into account the anthropogenic land use/land cover change for PD (year 2000) and PI (year 1850)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">59</a>
  </span>. The sea surface temperature and sea ice distributions are prescribed using the HadOIBl dataset in CAM for PD (year 2000) and PI (year 1850)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">60</a>
  </span>. The concentration of CO
  <sub>2</sub> is set to 367.0 ppm for the PD and 284.7 ppm for the PI. The simulation of climate is determined by sea surface temperatures, the sea ice distribution, and CO
  <sub>2</sub> concentration. Each model simulation was performed for 5 years with a 1-year spin-up. We used 5 years of monthly average aerosol concentrations together with the first year of 4 hourly meteorological conditions to calculate the radiative effects
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">61</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" href="#CR62">62</a>
  </span>. The DRE and AIE of SOA are defined as the difference in radiation at the top of atmosphere (TOA) with and without SOA. The anthropogenic RF was defined as the difference between the radiation at TOA simulated with all aerosols in PD and PIemi or PIall scheme.
 </p>
</sec>
