<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par6" class="p">Herein, we develop CIs of aspects of aerosol populations relevant for aerosol-radiation interactions and climate at the regional scale, and using output from MERRA-2 apply the aerosol-CIs to each NCA region (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>) to provide an illustrative example of how they can be used to quantify, characterize, and diagnose causes of historical trends in climate-relevant aerosol properties. To the first order, three key properties of the aerosol population determine the magnitude of the forcing due to aerosol-radiation interactions and thus the climate impact: Total columnar burden, size of the aerosols, and their composition
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" class="xref">19</xref>
 </sup>. Thus the aerosol-CIs we propose are based on: (1) AOD (550 nm), which is a measure of the column-integrated extinction of radiation and is approximately proportional to the aerosol mass concentration. (2) Ångström exponent (AE; 470–870 nm) which is qualitatively inversely proportional to particle size with a secondary dependence on aerosol composition. (3) Single scattering albedo (SSA; 550 nm) which is the ratio of scattering to total extinction, and describes the relative efficiency of radiation scattering (leading to an increase in the global albedo and cooling) by aerosols to radiation absorption (leading to atmospheric warming)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" class="xref">2</xref>
 </sup>. As aerosols potentially impact regional scale climate in the U.S.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">4</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">20</xref>
 </sup>, the proposed aerosol-CIs are designed to characterize and track changes in regionally averaged mean conditions of these variables and their extreme values. Further aerosol forcing must occur on relatively large scale for an appreciable climate impact, and therefore the aerosol-CIs also characterize and track changes in the spatial scales of aerosol features (both spatial autocorrelation and scales of coherence) (see Methods).
</p>
