<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece31745-sec-0017" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The aim of this study was to explore the utility of freely available remotely sensed satellite data for predicting small‐scale phenological variation in breeding behavior of birds. This investigation revealed that vegetation green‐up date related to timing of laying and hatching at the individual level, and the predictive power of this measure varied over space, depending on habitat type. Vegetation phenology varied considerably within the study site, and these spatial patterns varied between years. The existence of this small‐scale variation suggests that selection should favor individuals that respond to cues within their immediate environment in order to match their phenology to that of their food source. Knowledge of the environmental cues organisms use to time their breeding, and the scales at which these cues are experienced, is likely to be central to understanding how selection acts on these phenological traits.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To our knowledge, this is the first study to demonstrate spatial variability in synchrony within a single population. That this variability is related to habitat composition suggests that some individuals may be responding to cues from their environment, other than those closely linked to pixel‐level vegetation phenology (as detected by remote sensing). In fact, we find that tit and vegetation phenology are most synchronized in woodland areas dominated by the tree species in which great tits and blue tits predominantly forage. Not only does this add credence to the suggestion that the satellite‐derived phenology data is biologically meaningful at this scale, it also provides insight into small‐scale trophic interactions. Such marked within‐population variation in the extent to which phenology of different trophic levels match suggests that more attention should be given to studying environmental variation at a scale relevant to individual animals when exploring the causes and consequences of phenological synchrony.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To conclude, this promising approach to studying within‐population variation in phenology not only reduces the expense and manpower needed to quantify vegetation phenology, but also provides a standardized measure that could be used across studies. This approach will prove more informative for study sites where vegetation is well characterized. More work is clearly needed to understand which vegetation signals are driving remotely sensed green‐up in different habitats. These data do have great potential as they can be obtained in retrospect and therefore can be coupled with long‐term datasets to assess trophic interactions over time. As a result, this approach could greatly broaden the scale and scope of studies exploring phenological synchrony between trophic levels. The use of satellite‐derived data is now commonplace in conservation and population‐level ecological studies and has clear potential for exploring more small‐scale processes.</p>
</sec>
