<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece31745-sec-0005" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Satellite data</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used freely available data from the MODIS sensors (NASA 
  <a rid="ece31745-bib-0030" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31745-bib-0030">2008</a>) to determine vegetation spring green‐up dates for Wytham. These sensors are on‐board Terra and Aqua satellites, which were launched in 1999 and 2002, respectively, and acquire multispectral images over the whole Earth surface every 1 to 2 days. All pixels covering Wytham (
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 117, see Supplementary Methods and Figure S2) were projected to 240 m resolution on WGS 1984 UTM 30N coordinate system. The enhanced vegetation index 2 (EVI2) (Jiang et al. 
  <a rid="ece31745-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31745-bib-0022">2008</a>) was then calculated for each pixel in each 8‐day period. For each 240 m pixel and 8‐day period, there were potentially 16 (8 
  <span class="sc">am</span> and 8 
  <span class="sc">pm</span>) available clear cloud‐free observations of the land surface. However, in practice, because of cloud, typically only approximately 4 clear observations of the land surface were available for each 240 m pixel in each 8‐day period. Observations are flagged as “cloudy” or “cloud‐free” by the MOD03 cloud‐detection algorithm. EVI2 on the middle day of each 8‐day period was then estimated as the mean of all available clear observations in the 8‐day period. Very rarely (&lt;0.5%), no clear observations were available for a particular 240 m pixel in an 8‐day period and it was not possible to estimate EVI2 for that time period.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There are many methods of calculating spring phenological transition dates from time series of multispectral images for deciduous woodlands (Jönsson and Eklundh 
  <a rid="ece31745-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31745-bib-0023">2004</a>), mostly corresponding to the date at which the rate of change in curvature in a vegetation index (VI) exhibits local minima or maxima (Zhang et al. 
  <a rid="ece31745-bib-0060" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31745-bib-0060">2003</a>). The inflexion point of the piece‐wise logistic curve fitted to VI data (i.e., the point of maximum rate of change) has been shown to be a good indicator of the onset of oak bud‐burst in deciduous woodlands (Soudani et al. 
  <a rid="ece31745-bib-0046" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31745-bib-0046">2008</a>). In this study, we used generalized additive models (GAMs; Hastie and Tibshirani 
  <a rid="ece31745-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31745-bib-0017">1990</a>) to calculate a very similar metric, which were selected because we did not want to impose any prior assumption on the shape of the green‐up curve. A GAM was fitted to the EVI2 data for each pixel individually (EVI2 vs. day of year). The day of vegetation green‐up for each pixel was calculated as the day on which the derivative of this function was maximized (i.e., the day of the greatest rate of change in green‐up per year, see Figure 
  <a rid="ece31745-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#ece31745-fig-0001">1</a>). GAMs were fitted using the R package “mgcv” version 1.8‐4 and differentiated using the function predict.gam of mgcv (Wood 
  <a rid="ece31745-bib-0058" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31745-bib-0058">2011</a>).
 </p>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece31745-fig-0001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Method for calculating pixel‐specific vegetation green‐up dates: (A) 117 MODIS pixels (240 m × 240 m) which intersect with Wytham (gray dots show nestboxes); enhanced vegetation index was calculated for each pixel for every 8‐day period, (B) an example generalized additive model (GAM) curve fitted to the EVI2 data for a single pixel, and (C) plot showing the change in EVI2 over time for the same data, the arrow indicates maximum rate of change, and the vegetation green‐up date. Dashed lines in (B) and (C) show 95% confidence intervals.</p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-3" xlink:href="ECE3-5-5057-g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nestbox‐specific green‐up dates were calculated in ArcGIS 10.2 using a weighting procedure to account for where in a pixel a nestbox was located, as well as what proportion of a pixel was made up of nonwoodland habitat (see Supplementary Methods and Figure S2 for further details).</p>
</sec>
