<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">DNA extraction, DNA sequencing and AFLP fingerprinting</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the phylogeographic DNA analyses, we sequenced three cpDNA-IGS regions (
  <span class="italic">psb</span>A–
  <span class="italic">trn</span>H, 
  <span class="italic">trn</span>L–
  <span class="italic">trn</span>F, 
  <span class="italic">trn</span>T–
  <span class="italic">trn</span>L) and the ITS region (i.e. ITS1 + 5.8S + ITS2). The primers and methodology for amplification of these four DNA regions were described in Shaw 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b57" href="#b57">57</a> and Gielly 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b58" href="#b58">58</a>. Sequences were generated on an ABI 377XL DNA sequencer and were edited, assembled, and aligned in 
  <span class="sc">geneious</span> v.4.8.5
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b59" href="#b59">59</a>. All sequences were deposited in GenBank (see 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">Table S2</a> for accession numbers).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The AFLP protocol followed the procedure described by Vos 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b60" href="#b60">60</a>, with minor modifications that included the use of fluorescent-dye-labeled primers (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, California, USA) for selective amplification in multiplex analysis. Selective primer pairs were initially screened on 50 individuals from 25 populations. Of the 64 primer pair combinations tested, nine pairs that gave the best results with respect to polymorphism and clarity of AFLP profiles (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">Table S3</a>) were chosen for the full survey (further details in 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">Supplementary Method S2</a>). We also performed four separate test runs with 15 individuals and each chosen primer combination. These test runs confirmed that AFLP fragments were reproducible, resulting in an average error rate of 0.21% (±0.07) per fragment (see also Knowles &amp; Richards
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b61" href="#b61">61</a>). The AFLP data matrix is available in 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">Supplementary Dataset</a>.
 </p>
</sec>
