<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Present, past and future distribution modelling</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Assuming 
  <span class="italic">E. henryi</span> has not changed (and will not change) its climatic preference over at least the last glacial/interglacial cycle and into the future
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b79" href="#b79">79</a>, we reconstructed ENMs to determine the potential distribution of 
  <span class="italic">E. henryi</span> across its range under present (1950
  <span class="italic">–</span>2000), past [the Last Glacial Maximum (LGM, 
  <span class="italic">c</span>. 21 kya)
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b80" href="#b80">80</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b81" href="#b81">81</a> and the Last Interglacial (LIG, 
  <span class="italic">c</span>. 130–114 kya)
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b82" href="#b82">82</a>] and future (2080) climatic conditions using the maximum entropy method implemented in 
  <span class="sc">maxent</span> v.3.2.1. In addition to the 38 distribution records included in this study, 76 herbarium-recorded presences were sourced from the Chinese Virtual Herbarium (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cvh.org.cn" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.cvh.org.cn</span>) and the National Specimen Information Infrastructure of China (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nsii.org.cn" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.nsii.org.cn</span>). Based on a total of 114 records, a current distribution model was developed using six bioclimatic data layers (annual mean temperature, annual precipitation, precipitation of wettest, driest, warmest and coldest quarter) available from the WorldClim database (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.worldclim.org" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.worldclim.org</span>)
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b83" href="#b83">83</a> at 2.5 arc-min resolution for the present (1950–2000), assumed to be important for temperate species in East Asia
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b39" href="#b39">39</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b49" href="#b49">49</a>. This restricted dataset was used to avoid including highly correlated variables (data not shown), and thus to prevent potential over-fitting
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b84" href="#b84">84</a>. The established model was then projected onto the set of climatic variables simulated by the Model for Interdisciplinary Research on Climate (MIROC)
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b85" href="#b85">85</a> to infer the extent of suitable habitat during the LGM and the LIG (see above). Future projections for 2080 were performed based on the Canadian Centre for Climate Modelling and Analysis model (CCCMA-CGCM31) under the A2 scenario that were provided by the CIAT downscaled GCM Data Portal (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gisweb.ciat.cgiar.org/GCMPage/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://gisweb.ciat.cgiar.org/GCMPage/</span>) with 30 arc-second resolution.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Model performance was evaluated using receiver operating characteristic (ROC) analyses in 
  <span class="sc">maxent</span>. Values of the area under the ROC curve (AUC) between 0.7 and 0.9 indicate good fit
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b86" href="#b86">86</a>. We modelled the modern distribution 10 times, using different subsets of 70% of the localities to train the model and 30% to test the model, and visually compared AUC scores and jackknife tests of variable importance to assess consistency between runs.
 </p>
</sec>
