<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Although climate change is the focus of this paper, it is important to stress that the introduction of exotic diseases and disease vectors in Europe is primarily facilitated by globalisation (Semenza 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016a</xref>). Trade and travel in particular can increase the importation risks. Global air travel and seaborne trade appear to facilitate the expansion of invasive mosquito species (Tatem, Hay and Rogers 
 <xref rid="bib69" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2006</xref>). Human migration, while leading occasionally to large-scale population movements, has not been shown to lead to an increased risk of disease spread with ‘host’ populations in Europe (Semenza 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="bib60" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016b</xref>). One consequence of globalisation is that in a highly interconnected world, seemingly unrelated factors from disparate locations may combine to contribute to the generation of novel infectious disease risks (Suk 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="bib65" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014a</xref>). A notable example of this in continental Europe was the detected outbreaks of Chikungunya, identified in Italy in 2007 and 2017 (Rezza 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="bib51" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2007</xref>; Venturi 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="bib74" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2017</xref>), which were, in part, due to global trade in tires that enabled the introduction of 
 <italic class="italic">Aedes albopictus</italic> mosquitos into Europe, a permissive climate for the expansion of these mosquitos in Europe, and global air traffic that subsequently led to the introduction of the virus in a region where the mosquito was present and active. Myriad additional ecological and socio-economic drivers are important contributors to the establishment and ultimate transmission of vector-borne diseases, including land use and farming practices, fauna, public health capacities and human exposure to vectors (Jones 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="bib30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2008</xref>; Suk and Semenza 
 <xref rid="bib64a" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>; McMichael 
 <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>; Semenza 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="bib59" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016a</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib61" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016c</xref>).
</p>
