<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Another important methodological decision to make when implementing panel regression models concerns the inclusion of other time-varying observables, 
 <italic>Z</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>it</italic>
 </sub>. Including 
 <italic>Z</italic>
 <sub>
  <italic>it</italic>
 </sub> may absorb residual variation, hence producing more precise estimates. However, adding more controls will not necessarily produce an estimate of 
 <italic>β</italic> that is closer to the true 
 <italic>β</italic>. If the 
 <italic>Z</italic>'s are themselves an outcome of 
 <italic>C</italic>, which may well be the case for controls such as GDP, institutional measures, and population, including them will induce an “overcontrolling problem” (in the language of the model, if 
 <italic>Z</italic> is in fact 
 <italic>Z</italic>(
 <italic>C</italic>), then Equation (
 <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="EEq1">1</xref>) would instead be written as 
 <italic>y</italic> = 
 <italic>f</italic>(
 <italic>C</italic>), 
 <italic>Z</italic>(
 <italic>C</italic>)) and estimating an equation that included both 
 <italic>Z</italic> and 
 <italic>C</italic> would not capture the true net effect of 
 <italic>C</italic> on 
 <italic>y</italic> (again, see Dell et al. [
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]). For example, suppose that poorer counties in the United States tend to be both hot and have low-quality institutions. If hot climates were to cause low-quality institutions, which in turn cause low income, then controlling for institutions in Equation (
 <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="EEq1">1</xref>) can have the effect of partially eliminating the explanatory power of climate, even if climate is the underlying fundamental cause. Therefore, if the incidence of LD is the outcome of interest, for example, then controlling for changes in health personnel or infrastructure would be problematic if the climatic variables influence those changes, directly or indirectly. Our preferred specification of Equation (
 <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="EEq1">1</xref>) does not include additional time-varying explanatory variables, but we also report separate estimates for counties above and below the U.S. median per capita income. This variable should reflect patterns of development across the nation.
</p>
