<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec6" sec-type="discussion" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An evaluation of the surface energy budget of current global and regional model configurations, which are used for weather forecasting and reanalysis products, highlights the importance of the simulation of snow on sea-ice. Three CSEs occurred during polar night are analysed using the N-ICE 2015 drift campaign data. The analysis shows that the models in their standard configurations are 5 to 15 °C too warm during these events. In the CSE-1 the low incoming longwave radiation in the model products is low, which indicates that the clear-sky conditions are reasonably well resolved. However, the outgoing longwave radiation is too high, as the consequence of a warm bias in the surface temperature. In turn, this bias can be attributed to the overestimation of the conductive heat flux from the ocean to the surface by 20 to 
  <div id="IEq51" class="inline-formula">
   <div class="alternatives">
    <span id="M101" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$40\ {\mathrm{W}}{{\mathrm{m}}}^{-2}$$\end{document}</span>
    <div id="M102" class="math">
     <span class="mn">40</span>
     <span width="0.33em" class="mspace"/>
     <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">W</span>
     <div class="msup">
      <div class="mrow">
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">m</span>
      </div>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mo">−</span>
       <span class="mn">2</span>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
    <span xlink:href="41467_2019_11975_Article_IEq51.gif" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </div>. This heat flux is regulated by the difference between the ocean and atmospheric temperatures and by the thickness of the sea-ice and snow layers. A snow layer, which has a thermal conductivity about seven times lower than that of sea-ice, is missing in most of the analysed models, and thus, is identified as the main reason for the deviations in the surface energy budget.
 </p>
 <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The warm bias in the ice surface temperatures is a characteristic feature of the analysed global reanalysis products on the pan-Arctic scale. By comparing to a multiyear product obtained from infrared satellite measurements we show that all tested systems have issues in simulating the extreme low temperatures over large parts of the Arctic. The most drastic deviations in the temperature are found over the areas with the thick snow cover according to the winter snow climatology (see the Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3b–f</a>). This strengthens the argument that the snow layer is strongly connected to the temperature bias found in the global atmospheric reanalyses. In two of the reanalyses, which have thicker sea-ice (JRA-55 and NCEP-2), the warm bias is reduced, but instead a cold bias is produced, specifically in areas where sea-ice is thinner than the prescribed 2 m and only a thin snow layer exists. In general, the characteristics of the surface temperature in the reanalysis products can be explained by the surface energy budget. We conclude that the snow component on the sea-ice improves the surface atmospheric energy budget in cold atmospheric conditions and thus is an important but often missing component in state-of-the-art reanalysis and forecasting systems. In addition, sea-ice thickness plays an important role, as well, but mainly in the areas where the snow layer is thin.
 </p>
 <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The surface energy budget is an integral part of many climate processes in the Arctic. For example, it determines the available energy for sea-ice melting and freezing, and also the thermal stratification in the lower troposphere. Thus, the accuracy of its representation can have a strong impact on the skill of climate prediction and our understanding of large-scale climate dynamics. The bias in the surface energy budget due to the misrepresentation of the snow and sea-ice layer is about 
  <div id="IEq52" class="inline-formula">
   <div class="alternatives">
    <span id="M103" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$20\ {\mathrm{W}}{{\mathrm{m}}}^{-2}$$\end{document}</span>
    <div id="M104" class="math">
     <span class="mn">20</span>
     <span width="0.33em" class="mspace"/>
     <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">W</span>
     <div class="msup">
      <div class="mrow">
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">m</span>
      </div>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mo">−</span>
       <span class="mn">2</span>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
    <span xlink:href="41467_2019_11975_Article_IEq52.gif" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </div>. Compared to the spread of 20 and 
  <div id="IEq53" class="inline-formula">
   <div class="alternatives">
    <span id="M105" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$60\ {\mathrm{W}}{{\mathrm{m}}}^{-2}$$\end{document}</span>
    <div id="M106" class="math">
     <span class="mn">60</span>
     <span width="0.33em" class="mspace"/>
     <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">W</span>
     <div class="msup">
      <div class="mrow">
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">m</span>
      </div>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mo">−</span>
       <span class="mn">2</span>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
    <span xlink:href="41467_2019_11975_Article_IEq53.gif" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </div> between the various climate models in the winter-time net longwave radiation budget
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span>, the temperature bias, which is induced by the missing snow layer and misrepresentation of sea-ice thickness, is of significant importance. This bias in the net radiation budget can induce wrong conclusions, e.g., assuming that the climate models have a “cold temperature” bias in winter
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span>, or generally refine process studies which rely on the atmospheric reanalyses 
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Due to the widespread use of the atmospheric reanalysis products for model validation, initialisation of prediction systems, forcing of ocean and sea-ice reanalyses
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
  </span>, etc., it is very important to take into account this temperature bias in the contemporary reanalyses. Future reanalyses could be enhanced primarily by considering a prognostic parameterisation scheme to represent snow cover over the sea-ice, and by improving the spatial characteristics of the sea-ice thickness.
 </p>
</sec>
