<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">One exceptionally understudied species is the eastern coral snake (
 <italic class="italic">Micrurus fulvius</italic>). Although coral snakes are well-known for their striking coloration (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1" class="xref">Fig. 1</xref>) and potent venom, relatively little is known about the natural history of this species (
 <xref rid="ref-77" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Steen et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-50" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Jackson &amp; Franz, 1981</xref>). 
 <italic class="italic">M. fulvius</italic> has historically ranged throughout the Southeastern United States from the southern tip of Florida to the Sandhills of North Carolina (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2" class="xref">Fig. 2</xref>). At a coarse scale, 
 <italic class="italic">Micrurus fulvius</italic> inhabits sandy flatwoods and maritime forests (
 <xref rid="ref-11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Beane et al., 2010</xref>), and one recent survey suggest a microhabitat preference for sandy soils and scrub/shrub habitat (
 <xref rid="ref-77" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Steen et al., 2015</xref>). Their diet primarily consists of other snakes and lizards (
 <xref rid="ref-11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Beane et al., 2010</xref>). Although the International Union for the Conservation of Nature (IUCN) listed 
 <italic class="italic">M. fulvius</italic> as “Least Concern” in 2007 based on its total global population size (
 <xref rid="ref-39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hammerson, 2007</xref>), it is of significant conservation concern at the local level throughout most of its range; it is listed as Endangered in North Carolina (
 <xref rid="ref-63" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">North Carolina Wildlife Resources Commission, 2014</xref>), Imperiled in South Carolina (
 <xref rid="ref-76" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">South Carolina Department of Natural Resources, 2014</xref>), and of Highest Conservation Concern in Alabama (
 <xref rid="ref-64" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Outdoor Alabama, 2017</xref>). The fate of these populations at the edges of its range depends on how its range shifts in response to climate change.
</p>
