<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec009" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">NAO WI and local spring warmth</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For our 23-year study period, local spring weather, measured as the warmth sum, showed a significant (R
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.426, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.001) negative relationship with a one year time-lagged NAO WI, i.e. warmth sum for year = i and NAO WI for year = i-1 (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0155241.g004" href="#pone.0155241.g004">Fig 4</a>). In contrast, there was a positive relationship between the warmth sum and the NAO WI for the immediately preceding winter, i.e. warmer springs were associated with positive values of the NAO WI, but the relationship was not significant (warmth sum = 678 + 12.5 NAO WI, R
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.141, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.077). There was also a positive relationship between the warmth sum and the annual change in the NAO WI (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0155241.g005" href="#pone.0155241.g005">Fig 5</a>), but this relationship was significant (R
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.568, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.001) with a greater R
  <span class="sup">2</span> value than the relationship with the time-lagged NAO WI. Thus greater fluctuation in the NAO WI, i.e. larger positive changes between years, were associated with warmer springs, which is consistent with current observations of both warmer and more extreme weather in the UK [
  <a rid="pone.0155241.ref032" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155241.ref032">32</a>].
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0155241.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0155241.g004</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 4</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Time-lagged relationship between local spring warmth (warmth sum) and the NAO winter index.</div>
   <p>Values of the NAO WI are for the winter of the year before, i.e. warmth sum for year i, NAO WI for year i-1. Least squares regression equation is: warmth sum
    <sub>i</sub> = 701–21.8 NAO WI
    <sub>i-1</sub>, R
    <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.426, 
    <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.001.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0155241.g004" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <div id="pone.0155241.g005" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0155241.g005</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 5</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Relationship between local spring warmth (warmth sum) and the annual change in the NAO winter index.</div>
   <p>The change in the NAO WI is calculated as the current year minus the previous year. Least squares regression equation is: warmth sum = 686 + 18.4 NAO WI change, R
    <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.568, 
    <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.001.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0155241.g005" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Using a 23-year sliding window to examine the relationships between the warmth sum and the NAO WI in the longer term showed that, in the past, significant relationships with the immediately preceding NAO WI (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0155241.g006" href="#pone.0155241.g006">Fig 6</a>) were more common than those with the time-lagged NAO WI (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0155241.g007" href="#pone.0155241.g007">Fig 7</a>), and especially so from the late 1930s to the early 1970s (Periods 49 to 84). This span of years includes the years (1948 to 1957) when Sanz [
  <a rid="pone.0155241.ref017" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155241.ref017">17</a>] found significant relationships between the immediately preceding NAO WI and timing of breeding in some great tit populations. However, more recently, from the mid 1970s (about Period 87) onwards, the time-lagged relationship has become the most significant which is suggestive of a change in climate patterns in recent years (although given the smoothing effect of this approach, these results must be interpreted carefully). There was no significant correlation between the NAO WI in successive years, either in the whole of the period 1878–2015, or in the 23-year periods in which there were highly significant relationships between the NAO WI and the warmth sum (Ljung-Box tests, Q ≤ 2.6, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> &gt; 0.10 in all cases).
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0155241.g006" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0155241.g006</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 6</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Parameters (slope and R
    <span class="sup">2</span>) of the linear regression relationships between the warmth sum and the current year, i, NAO WI (i.e. no time-lag) for 116 successive 23-year periods.
   </div>
   <p>Period 1 = 1878–1900; Period 116 = 1993–2015 (current study period). The relationships were significant (
    <span class="italic">P</span> ≤ 0.05) in Periods 1 and 2, Periods 19 to 37 and 39, and Periods 49 to 84, 89 to 97, 101 and 102. The slopes of the relationships were all positive.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0155241.g006" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <div id="pone.0155241.g007" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0155241.g007</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 7</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Parameters (slope and R
    <span class="sup">2</span>) of the linear regression relationships between the warmth sum and the previous year, i-1, NAO WI (i.e. with time-lag) for 116 successive 23-year periods.
   </div>
   <p>Period 1 = 1878–1900; Period 116 = 1993–2015 (current study period). The relationships were significant (
    <span class="italic">P</span> ≤ 0.05) in Periods 1 to 5, Periods 13, 14 and 16, Periods 91 to 97 and Periods 112 to 116. Slopes were both positive and negative, with negatives slopes becoming more frequent in the latter half of the dataset (since c. 1950).
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0155241.g007" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
