<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec003" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study sites</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our study area is located in Cambridgeshire in eastern England (52° 22’N, 0° 13’W) [
  <a rid="pone.0155241.ref018" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155241.ref018">18</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0155241.ref019" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155241.ref019">19</a>]. Breeding parameters were recorded for pairs of great tits and blue tits (
  <span class="italic">Cyanistes caeruleus</span>) using nest boxes in three study woods: Monks Wood (MW) National Nature Reserve 157 ha: 1993–2000, 22 boxes; 2001–2015, 35 boxes; Brampton Wood (BW), Wildlife Trust Nature Reserve, 132 ha: 1993–2015, 22 boxes; Wennington Wood (WW), privately owned, 72 ha: 1993–1999, 21 boxes; 2000–2015, 35 boxes). Most of the boxes are accessible (controlled by hole diameter: 32 mm both species, 25 mm blue tits only) to both species except in WW where 19 boxes are accessible to both and 16 (including all 14 erected after 2000) only to blue tits. Boxes are located in approximately one half of each of MW and BW and throughout WW giving densities of about 0.45, 0.33 and 0.49 boxes per ha respectively. This results in smaller numbers of study nests per wood than in some other long-term studies of tits [
  <a rid="pone.0155241.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155241.ref020">20</a>], but we adopted this policy to reduce the risk of unduly increasing tit population densities which can affect timing of breeding [
  <a rid="pone.0155241.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155241.ref021">21</a>] whilst also obtaining adequate sample sizes. However, from the mid 1990s BW has also contained c. 200 dormouse boxes which, until 2013 when they were redesigned, could be accessed by blue tits which probably increased the blue tit population in this wood. The main tree species are common ash (
  <span class="italic">Fraxinus excelsior</span>), English oak (
  <span class="italic">Quercus robur</span>) and field maple (
  <span class="italic">Acer campestre</span>) with an understory chiefly of hawthorn (
  <span class="italic">Crategus</span> spp.), hazel (
  <span class="italic">Corylus avellana</span>) and blackthorn (
  <span class="italic">Prunus spinosa</span>). BW also has some blocks of conifers but the boxes are located in deciduous areas.
 </p>
</sec>
