<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec004" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Timing of breeding</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Timing of breeding was recorded for 23 years from 1993 to 2015 and was defined as the laying date (expressed as April 1
  <span class="sup">st</span> = 1) of the first egg of the clutch. Tits typically lay one egg per day, early in the morning, and begin incubation on the day the last egg is laid to achieve synchronous hatching (although in poor weather delayed incubation after clutch completion is common, 22). The average clutch size in woodland is 9 for great tits and 11 for blue tits [
  <a rid="pone.0155241.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155241.ref023">23</a>]. We inspected boxes approximately weekly during the laying period and calculated first egg dates by counting back from the number of eggs observed [
  <a rid="pone.0155241.ref024" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155241.ref024">24</a>]. We included only nests which were active at the time of observation (i.e. at least one more egg was laid) and only those of first breeding attempts. For each wood, we calculated an annual mean first egg date (NERC-Environmental Information Data Centre 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.5285/2efa9bf4-e5c0-42f9-8fcb-90dca2bb9c66" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://doi.org/10.5285/2efa9bf4-e5c0-42f9-8fcb-90dca2bb9c66</span>) [
  <a rid="pone.0155241.ref025" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155241.ref025">25</a>]. For great tits, the mean (± SD) and range of the numbers of nests included in the calculation of the annual mean first egg date for each wood were: MW, 18 ± 5.0, range = 12–28; BW, 15 ± 2.8, range = 11–20; WW, 10 ± 2.1, range = 6–14. The numbers of blue tits using the boxes were smaller (MW, 8 ± 3.3, range = 3–13; BW, 3 ± 1.3, range = 2–6; WW, 9 ± 3.0, range = 5–15) because, as the larger of the two species at c. 19 g versus 10 g for blue tits, great tits are usually dominant. The results for blue tits were similar to those of great tits, but due to the small sample sizes per year we include here only those for great tits. All bird data were collected with the permission of the landowners (MW: Natural England; BW: The Wildlife Trust; WW: the Abbots Ripton Estate) by licenced (British Trust for Ornithology Ringing Scheme, permit nos. A4101 and C3288) persons experienced in the running and maintenance of nest boxes.
 </p>
</sec>
