<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The elasticity and decomposition methods built on the Budyko framework involve uncertainties, such as separating relative contributions of climate change and human impacts on changes to streamflow, abrupt change and temporal trends of streamflow. For example, assuming 1980 and 1990 to be the change-point year for non-RHBN and RHBN watersheds, respectively, and climatic regimes and human impacts remained relatively stable in both periods, etc., may be not true. Therefore, we further analyzed streamflow changes under five 10-year windows attributed to climate change and human impacts from 1961 to 2010, relative to the 1930–1960 base period, for 30 (mostly non-RHBN) watersheds.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From 1960s onward, human activities generally lead to decreasing streamflow until 2010 (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f4" href="#f4">Fig. 4a</a>), while climate change predominantly lead to increasing streamflow but the impact could be opposite for some watersheds until about 1980s, when the reverse happened (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f4" href="#f4">Fig. 4b</a>). The range of standard deviations (mean) in climate and human contributions to streamflow change over the five 10-year windows of data analyzed for the 30 watersheds was 8.5–75.3 mm (33.7 mm) and 8.8–54.8 mm (29.4 mm), respectively. It seems that the mean contributions of climate change and human activities to streamflow change of these 30 watersheds obtained from the five 10-year window analysis for 1961–2010 agree well with results obtained from using 1980 as the common change-point for the 30 watersheds (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f4" href="#f4">Fig. 4c</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Human impacts on streamflow change of the 96 watersheds divided into 10 groups were further explored using a correlation analysis between streamflow change and human activities such as LUCC, increased municipal water consumption due to population increase and increased evaporation due to water impounded behind dams. In each group all watersheds have comparable range of streamflow change and human activities categorized under population density, number of dams, percentage of cropland and rangeland.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Because of a lack of long-term data related to human activities, we assume that streamflow to landscape changes detected for each watershed to be directly dependent on certain indicators collected in a particular year only. The relationships between “human” indicators and streamflow change for these 10 groups of watersheds are shown in 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">Supplementary Fig. S9</a>. The proportion of impervious areas of urban watersheds with large population density tends to grow over the years, resulting in decreased infiltration but increased surface runoff. Conversely, water impoundment by dams results in increased evaporation loss and so decreased streamflow. The expansion of cropland means converting perennial vegetation to seasonal cropping systems that reduces annual evapotranspiration and increased streamflow during non-growing season. On the other hand, rangelands could have higher evapotranspiration than natural lands, resulting in less streamflow. However, streamflow could change in a manner opposite to above relationships, e.g., irrigated lands could have higher evapotranspiration than natural lands which resulted in less streamflow. Further, crop water consumption depends on crop types, and so streamflow could decrease with intensive cultivation of certain crop types. Therefore, human impacts on the streamflow change could depend on various combinations of physical and climatic factors.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition to the above human indicators, we have also considered trends of normalized difference vegetation index (NDVI), which is related to the percent of green cover, as a possible factor contributing to decreased streamflow in Canada. 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">Supplementary Fig. S9e</a> shows the negative correlation between NDVI trends for the first half of August over 1981–2011 and annual streamflow change of Canada. As most Canada landmass became greener (NDVI increase) in southern and Arctic regions (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">Supplementary Fig. S11a</a>) over 1981–2011, annual evapotranspiration could increase because of increased NDVI even though there is no consistently positive trend detected in the evapotranspiration of Canada
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b7" href="#b7">7</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b27" href="#b27">27</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b28" href="#b28">28</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b29" href="#b29">29</a>. Even though increased NDVI could be related to both the climate change and human contribution
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b30" href="#b30">30</a>, it is difficult to separate their relative contributions to the increased NDVI.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In high-latitude and mountainous regions of Canada, the widespread retreat of glaciers has contributed to increase in streamflow
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b31" href="#b31">31</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b32" href="#b32">32</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b33" href="#b33">33</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b34" href="#b34">34</a>. Since this study does not account for impacts of climate change on retreat of glaciers, it underestimated the actual human contribution to decreased streamflow. Some studies show that potential impacts of a warmer climate do not significantly affect the availability of water in snow-dominated regions such as Canada
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b17" href="#b17">17</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b35" href="#b35">35</a>. However, recent studies reported conflicting results on the sensitivity of streamflow to global warming impact, e.g., a general decrease in observed streamflow caused by a shift from snowfall to rainfall in USA
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b15" href="#b15">15</a>; and a projected increase (decrease) in streamflow of Canada (USA) under climatic change impact
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b36" href="#b36">36</a> which may be partly because hydrologic impacts of human activities are not considered in hydroclimatic models. More detailed analysis will be necessary to better estimate anthropogenic impacts such as landuse changes and streamflow regulations to watersheds studied.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A limitation of Budyko-based methods for separating the relative contribution of human impacts and effects of climate change to the streamflow change in snow-dominated watersheds is that the change in snow ratio (SR, amount of snowfall to total precipitation) which is more related to the effect of climate change than direct human impact. Watersheds with a higher SR tend to have a lower 
  <span class="italic">E</span>/
  <span class="italic">P</span> (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">Supplementary Fig. S10</a>). This means that under similar climatic conditions and landscape properties, streamflow will tend to be higher. This empirical relationship has been found in watersheds of USA
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b15" href="#b15">15</a> and China
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b37" href="#b37">37</a>, but its mechanism is still unknown. The stationary assumption of SR in Budyko-based methods is violated in some watersheds given North American Regional Reanalysis (NARR) data show that SR has increased in southern Canada because of the increase in winter precipitation, but SR has decreased in northern Canada over 1979–2014 (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">Supplementary Fig. S11b</a>), as also been observed in station climate data
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b26" href="#b26">26</a>. Given that streamflow in southern Canada has decreased even though it should have increased because of increased SR, the contribution of human impact to decreased streamflow could have been higher.
 </p>
</sec>
