<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">where cost
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">i</italic>
 </sub> is the cost assigned to pixel 
 <italic class="italic">i</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic> is a dissimilarity penalty (
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>=2 dimensionless units per 
 <sup class="sup">o</sup>C in this study such that cost
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">i</italic>
 </sub> increases by 1 for each 0.5 °C in climate dissimilarity), 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic> is the 0.1 °C temperature increment of interest, and 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">i</italic>
 </sub> is the temperature of pixel 
 <italic class="italic">i;</italic> a value of one is added because least-cost approaches do not allow costs of zero and it ensures that cost
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">i</italic>
 </sub>=distance when trajectories pass through pixels with an analogous climate. We then computed, among all intermediate cost surfaces, the minimum cost for each pixel (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6" class="xref">Fig. 6b–d</xref>); this minimum cost is used to generate the final cost surfaces (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6" class="xref">Fig. 6d</xref>). Cost surfaces were developed for each 0.1 °C temperature increment (
 <italic class="italic">n</italic>=567 cost surfaces). For each increment, climate analogues were defined based on bins that were 0.5 °C wide so that matching pixels (±0.25 °C) were assigned a cost of one and cost values increased with the level of dissimilarity as integers (for example, 5.3 °C±0.25–0.75 °C was assigned a cost of two; see 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f6" class="xref">Fig. 6</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="t1" class="xref">Table 1</xref>). We evaluated every 0.1 °C increment, yet used a bin width of 0.5 °C to define climate analogues. This was intended to reduce boundary effects; that is, we wanted to ensure that pixels with temperatures of 4.9 and 5.1 °C were considered climate analogues as opposed to being treated as separate bins (
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="t1" class="xref">Table 1</xref>). In the final cost surfaces, lakes and ocean were arbitrarily assigned a cost value of 5,000 to heavily penalize open water, thereby forcing trajectories to avoid water when possible (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Supplementary Fig. 3</xref>). Excluding water, cost values generally ranged from 1 to ∼100, reflecting the ∼50 °C difference in mean annual temperature across North America.
</p>
