<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par5" class="p">The global land C models differ in model structure, parameter values, and initial conditions, each of which may contribute substantially to the overall uncertainty across models. Past studies have shown that different model structures can generate different soil C projections
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">12</xref>
 </sup>; initial conditions positively correlate with projected soil C content
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">5</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">13</xref>
 </sup>; and classical parameterization causes large uncertainty in projected changes in soil C
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">14</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">15</xref>
 </sup>. Model structure may determine the range of model projection and meantime the choice of parameter values for a given model structure defines the quantitative accuracy relative to observations. Therefore, parameterization is likely to interact with model structure and even initial conditions to impact the model projections. These considerations imply that diverse soil C decomposition models are needed to increase projection confidence
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>
 </sup>. Alternative structures to the conventional Century-type models include microbial models that simulate decomposition processes with explicit microbial traits as well as models that simulate interactions between soil layers at different depths
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" class="xref">19</xref>
 </sup>. Exploring uncertainty generated by these model structures and parameterization is critical for global land C modeling, but little effort has been dedicated to addressing it, especially at a global scale due mostly to computational cost.
</p>
