<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par30" class="p">A recently proposed Universal Thermal Climate Index (UTCI) (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93" class="xref">2009</xref>), based on an advanced human thermoregulation model, directly uses meteorological data to predict the impact of outdoor climate on thermal physiological and perceptual responses (Jendritzky et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" class="xref">2012</xref>; Bröde et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">2012a</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">b</xref>; Fiala et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" class="xref">2012</xref>; Havenith et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" class="xref">2012</xref>; Kampmann et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" class="xref">2012</xref>; Parsons 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75" class="xref">2013</xref>; Havenith and Fiala 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" class="xref">2016</xref>). The UTCI equivalent temperature (°C) provides a one-dimensional characteristic of complex thermal environments as determined by air temperature, heat radiation, humidity and wind speed. The UTCI equivalent temperature for a given combination of wind, radiation, humidity and air temperature is defined as the air temperature of a reference environment, which produces the same heat strain. The reference environment is defined as an environment with 50% relative humidity (but water vapour pressure not exceeding 2 kPa; this will be reached at 29 °C), still air (v
 <sub class="sub">a</sub> = 0.5 m/s at 10 m height, about 0.3 m/s at 1.1 m height) and mean radiant temperature equal to air temperature (Bröde et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">2012a</xref>; Havenith and Fiala 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" class="xref">2016</xref>). Mean radiant temperature is usually not directly measured at weather stations so it cannot be directly used as an input parameter for the calculation of UTCI, however, it can be estimated based on synoptic observations (e.g. cloud cover, global radiation) and various models based meteorological variables (Matzarakis et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73" class="xref">2007</xref>; Lindberg et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" class="xref">2008</xref>; Schreier et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83" class="xref">2013</xref>; Błażejczyk et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">2014</xref>; Kruger et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" class="xref">2014</xref>). However, the application of UTCI to the assessment of outdoor environmental and occupational heat stress and resulting body heat strain, is limited by the assumed moderate activity level (135 W/m
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>) and the chosen exposure time of two hours (Bröde et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">2016</xref>).
</p>
