<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">However, there is recognition that co-benefits have not gained commensurate political traction in a majority of Parties to the UNFCCC [
 <xref rid="B12-ijerph-15-00674" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-ijerph-15-00674" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-ijerph-15-00674" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="B48-ijerph-15-00674" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>,
 <xref rid="B49-ijerph-15-00674" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>]. Limited and varying explanations have been proposed. Some of these explanations align with political economy thinking. For example, Nemet and colleagues (2010) argued that a political “focus on cost minimization—rather than comparison of benefits and costs—diminishes the role of benefits in general” [
 <xref rid="B12-ijerph-15-00674" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>] (p. 1). In their literature review of co-benefits, Mayrhofer and Gupta (2016) concluded that, given the dominant influence of economists, the application of “co-benefits ends up being a ‘business-as-usual’ incremental approach which does not adequately call for the structural change needed to address climate change…” [
 <xref rid="B18-ijerph-15-00674" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>] (p. 28). Our findings on the role of health co-benefits in the development of Australian climate change mitigation policies support the notion that a number of barriers constrain the consideration of health co-benefits in mitigation policy development, including the disproportionate influence of economic modelling and vested interests [
 <xref rid="B49-ijerph-15-00674" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>]. Other conclusions posit alternative explanations. For example, Remais and colleagues (2014) advanced the need to enhance the policy relevance of health co-benefits studies by prompting health co-benefits researchers to “iteratively engage policy makers actively in their work” [
 <xref rid="B13-ijerph-15-00674" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>] (p. 453). Others suggest that the science–policy interface presents a number of challenges, and a viable solution requires an integrated approach [
 <xref rid="B50-ijerph-15-00674" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>,
 <xref rid="B51-ijerph-15-00674" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">51</xref>]. While the explanations offered to date provide a solid foundation for exploring solutions to enhancing the role of health in the climate change agenda, additional insights may be gleaned from consideration of the political and economic structures and processes that underpin policy development. 
</p>
