<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The configuration of future habitat is important when modeling shifts in climate envelopes in part because of the importance of micro- and macrorefugia in allowing the persistence of populations. VIWTP may show resilience to climate change-induced habitat loss through the use of microrefugia. Microrefugia differ from macrorefugia in that they are small areas with unusual microclimates that allow species to persist in areas that might be deemed unsuitable according to average background climates [
 <xref rid="pone.0142110.ref060" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">60</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0142110.ref061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">61</xref>]. Coarse scale species distribution models tend to overestimate extinction risk because they use climate grids that are too coarse to predict locations of fine-scale topographic relief that may provide microrefugia [
 <xref rid="pone.0142110.ref062" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">62</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0142110.ref063" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">63</xref>]. Although we used a smaller climate grid (100 m) than many species distribution modeling studies, we acknowledge that we can still only identify climate macrorefugia. Randin 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="pone.0142110.ref064" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">64</xref>] found that local-scale models (25 m grid cells) predicted some persistence of suitable habitats at high elevations for European plant species that were predicted to lose all of their suitable habitat according to large-scale models (10′ grid cells). Similarly, ptarmigan may be able to utilize microclimates created by fine-scale landscape features (e.g., boulders, ravines, and water bodies), vegetation type, or small variations in slope or aspect not accounted for in our models to persist in habitat that is predicted to be lost (see [
 <xref rid="pone.0142110.ref065" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">65</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0142110.ref066" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">66</xref>]). In contrast, Trivedi 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="pone.0142110.ref067" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">67</xref>] found that coarse scale models overestimated species thermal tolerances and underestimated the potential impact of climate change on high elevation species compared to local-scale models, suggesting that microclimatic refugia may not allow for persistence as speculated.
</p>
