<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece34902-sec-0004" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chickadee PIT‐tagging and RFID‐equipped feeders</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We captured chickadees from late October to early January in two consecutive winters (2015–2016, 2016–2017) from 08:00 to 17:00 PST on fair days (i.e., clear sky to light drizzle, wind speed &lt;10 km/hr) using a combination of mist‐nets and traps that were affixed to feeders. We PIT‐tagged a total of 174 chickadees that were available for this study; 86 birds were captured during pilot work undertaken during October 2015–January 2016, and 88 birds were captured from October 2016–January 2017. We fitted each captured individual with a unique combination of legs bands that consisted of a USGS aluminum leg band, a colored plastic leg band, and a colored band that contained a uniquely numbered PIT tag (IB Technology, Aylesbury, UK). At initial capture, we also measured body mass and right tarsus length to assess variation in size among individuals.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Each of our supplemental feeders consisted of a customized seed tube that had one feeding port at its base so that only a single chickadee could visit the feeder at a single time (Figure 
  <a rid="ece34902-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#ece34902-fig-0001">1</a>). We hung each feeder approximately 2.5 m off the ground from a metal pole that was fitted with a metal baffle to deter use of feeders by the western gray squirrel (
  <span class="italic">Sciurus griseus</span>) and the Douglas squirrel (
  <span class="italic">Tamiasciurus douglasii</span>). We also fitted feeders with a 10 × 15 cm wire mesh trap attached around the feeding portal to capture individual chickadees for tagging. Each feeder was capable of holding approximately 3 kg of unhulled black oil sunflower (
  <span class="italic">Helianthus annuus</span>) seeds, and we provided food ad libitum in all feeders throughout the course of the study. On the base of each feeder, we attached a small waterproof box that housed a 12‐volt battery for power and an RFID data logger (Bonter &amp; Bridge, 
  <a rid="ece34902-bib-0005" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34902-bib-0005">2011</a>), and we programmed the data logger to record all visits that occurred between 1 hr before sunrise and 1 hr after sunset. We affixed an antenna with a ~5‐cm detection range to the perch of the feeding port on each feeder that recorded feeder use by PIT‐tagged birds. Specifically, for each visit by a PIT‐tagged chickadee the unique bird identification number, unique feeder identification number, date, and time of day (to the nearest second) were recorded by the data logger, allowing us to get fine‐scale temporal data on feeder visits by all tagged individuals across the period of our study (i.e., October 23, 2016–March 31, 2017). Chickadees typically make short‐duration visits to bird feeders to obtain a sunflower seed before flying away to consume or cache the seed; therefore, we programmed RFID data loggers to scan for PIT tags once every 0.5 s which was followed by a 0.5‐s pause; this prevented us from missing especially short visits of tagged chickadees. Previous work has found that chickadees typically take &gt;10 s to handle sunflower seeds obtained from feeders (Lima, 
  <a rid="ece34902-bib-0046" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34902-bib-0046">1985</a>), which we confirmed in our study (Lajoie, 
  <a rid="ece34902-bib-0044" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34902-bib-0044">2018</a>). Therefore, we considered a unique feeder visit to be one that was separated from other visits by at least 10 s to minimize the likelihood that individuals were double‐counted during a single feeder visit.
 </p>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece34902-fig-0001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Example of a supplemental feeder used in this study to quantify feeder use by Black‐capped Chickadees in a Mediterranean climate in Corvallis, Oregon, USA. The light blue PIT tag is evident on the chickadee's left leg, but the aluminum leg band and colored plastic leg band on the bird's right leg is out of sight in this image. Note that the wire mesh trap attached to the feeder for capturing birds has been removed in this photograph for clarity</p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-3" xlink:href="ECE3-9-2535-g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
