<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece34902-sec-0013" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">5</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">CONCLUSION</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our study in a Mediterranean climate found large variation among individuals in the extent of their use of supplemental bird feeders during winter, with limited influence of weather‐related variables that have been linked to feeder use patterns in continental regions experiencing colder winters. In particular, our study suggests that temperature may play a lesser role in driving the use of feeders by birds in warmer regions such as the Mediterranean climate in which we worked, perhaps because weather conditions were insufficient to impose strong energetic challenges to individuals. Nevertheless, this finding has implications for feeder use patterns in mild climates, as well as in continental climates where climate change is expected to result in winter warming (Zuckerberg et al., 
  <a rid="ece34902-bib-0080" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34902-bib-0080">2011</a>). One important question that arises from our study is whether the variation in supplemental feeder visits was tied to the physiological health of individuals (Wilcoxen et al., 
  <a rid="ece34902-bib-0075" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34902-bib-0075">2015</a>), which is a critical question for understanding why individuals varied in their use of feeders. For example, individuals that made a surplus of feeder visits may have been in relatively good body condition, and visited feeders at high rates to cache seeds for future use. Alternatively, chickadees with high use of feeders may have been in worse health relative to other individuals and therefore may have been more dependent on supplemental feeders to provide them with an easily accessible, constant, and predictable food source during challenging environmental conditions. Distinguishing between these alternatives cannot be accomplished via descriptive studies, so investigations that experimentally manipulate body condition and concurrently monitor feeder use are needed to evaluate the extent of feeder dependency across a range of environmental conditions.
 </p>
</sec>
