<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece34902-sec-0002" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">MATERIALS AND METHODS</div>
 <sec id="ece34902-sec-0003" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study area and focal species</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We established 21 bird feeders in September 2016 on lands owned by Oregon State University near the Corvallis, Oregon, USA campus (44.6°N, 123.3°W, 90 masl). We placed feeders at 200‐m intervals along the Oak Creek riparian area such that the two most distant feeders were 3.2 km away from each other; this distance is within the range of what an individual chickadee could theoretically cover in the course of our study period based on previous work with homing experiments conducted during winter (Odum, 
   <a rid="ece34902-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34902-bib-0052">1941</a>) and studies of winter flock space use (Desrochers &amp; Hannon, 
   <a rid="ece34902-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34902-bib-0023">1989</a>; see Discussion). In two instances, we were forced to place feeders approximately 400 m apart because of site access restrictions. We installed each feeder within 60 m of a continuously flowing creek in habitat that was dominated by Oregon white oak (
   <span class="italic">Quercus garryanna</span>), Himalayan blackberry (
   <span class="italic">Rubus discolor</span>), bigleaf maple (
   <span class="italic">Acer macrophyllum</span>), poplar (
   <span class="italic">Populus </span>spp.), and willow (
   <span class="italic">Salix </span>spp.) and contained a mixture of native shrubs, grasses, and forbs. We selected feeder locations that were a minimum of 50 m from buildings, and although it is possible that our tagged birds could have accessed feeders other than those established for our study, we found that there was no evidence that use of individual feeders varied relative to their distance to the nearest building (
   <span class="italic">F</span>
   <sub>1,19</sub> = 0.05, 
   <span class="italic">p</span> = 0.82, 
   <span class="italic">R</span> = 0.05; Supporting Information Figure 
   <a rid="ece34902-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#ece34902-sup-0001">S1</a>). Therefore, we did not consider distance to buildings further in any of our analyses.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We selected the chickadee for this study because this species (a) is a small‐bodied songbird (10–14 g) with high energetic needs during the nonbreeding season (Foote et al., 
   <a rid="ece34902-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34902-bib-0029">2010</a>; Smith, 
   <a rid="ece34902-bib-0070" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34902-bib-0070">1991</a>), (b) is a year‐round resident that occurs in temporally stable flocks throughout the winter, at least in continental climates (Desrochers &amp; Hannon, 
   <a rid="ece34902-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34902-bib-0023">1989</a>; Smith, 
   <a rid="ece34902-bib-0070" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34902-bib-0070">1991</a>), and (c) is one of the most common visitors of recreational bird feeders (Brittingham &amp; Temple, 
   <a rid="ece34902-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34902-bib-0009">1989</a>; Horn et al., 
   <a rid="ece34902-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34902-bib-0035">2014</a>; Smith, 
   <a rid="ece34902-bib-0070" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34902-bib-0070">1991</a>). In addition, chickadees typically remove a single sunflower seed from feeders during each visit before moving away from the feeder to consume or cache the seed (Ficken, Weise, &amp; Popp, 
   <a rid="ece34902-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34902-bib-0027">1990</a>; Foote et al., 
   <a rid="ece34902-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34902-bib-0029">2010</a>), making the number of feeding visits a close proxy of the number of seeds obtained when estimating the amount of food obtained by individuals from feeders (Latimer, Cooper, Karasov, &amp; Zuckerberg, 
   <a rid="ece34902-bib-0045" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34902-bib-0045">2018</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece34902-sec-0004" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chickadee PIT‐tagging and RFID‐equipped feeders</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We captured chickadees from late October to early January in two consecutive winters (2015–2016, 2016–2017) from 08:00 to 17:00 PST on fair days (i.e., clear sky to light drizzle, wind speed &lt;10 km/hr) using a combination of mist‐nets and traps that were affixed to feeders. We PIT‐tagged a total of 174 chickadees that were available for this study; 86 birds were captured during pilot work undertaken during October 2015–January 2016, and 88 birds were captured from October 2016–January 2017. We fitted each captured individual with a unique combination of legs bands that consisted of a USGS aluminum leg band, a colored plastic leg band, and a colored band that contained a uniquely numbered PIT tag (IB Technology, Aylesbury, UK). At initial capture, we also measured body mass and right tarsus length to assess variation in size among individuals.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Each of our supplemental feeders consisted of a customized seed tube that had one feeding port at its base so that only a single chickadee could visit the feeder at a single time (Figure 
   <a rid="ece34902-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#ece34902-fig-0001">1</a>). We hung each feeder approximately 2.5 m off the ground from a metal pole that was fitted with a metal baffle to deter use of feeders by the western gray squirrel (
   <span class="italic">Sciurus griseus</span>) and the Douglas squirrel (
   <span class="italic">Tamiasciurus douglasii</span>). We also fitted feeders with a 10 × 15 cm wire mesh trap attached around the feeding portal to capture individual chickadees for tagging. Each feeder was capable of holding approximately 3 kg of unhulled black oil sunflower (
   <span class="italic">Helianthus annuus</span>) seeds, and we provided food ad libitum in all feeders throughout the course of the study. On the base of each feeder, we attached a small waterproof box that housed a 12‐volt battery for power and an RFID data logger (Bonter &amp; Bridge, 
   <a rid="ece34902-bib-0005" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34902-bib-0005">2011</a>), and we programmed the data logger to record all visits that occurred between 1 hr before sunrise and 1 hr after sunset. We affixed an antenna with a ~5‐cm detection range to the perch of the feeding port on each feeder that recorded feeder use by PIT‐tagged birds. Specifically, for each visit by a PIT‐tagged chickadee the unique bird identification number, unique feeder identification number, date, and time of day (to the nearest second) were recorded by the data logger, allowing us to get fine‐scale temporal data on feeder visits by all tagged individuals across the period of our study (i.e., October 23, 2016–March 31, 2017). Chickadees typically make short‐duration visits to bird feeders to obtain a sunflower seed before flying away to consume or cache the seed; therefore, we programmed RFID data loggers to scan for PIT tags once every 0.5 s which was followed by a 0.5‐s pause; this prevented us from missing especially short visits of tagged chickadees. Previous work has found that chickadees typically take &gt;10 s to handle sunflower seeds obtained from feeders (Lima, 
   <a rid="ece34902-bib-0046" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34902-bib-0046">1985</a>), which we confirmed in our study (Lajoie, 
   <a rid="ece34902-bib-0044" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34902-bib-0044">2018</a>). Therefore, we considered a unique feeder visit to be one that was separated from other visits by at least 10 s to minimize the likelihood that individuals were double‐counted during a single feeder visit.
  </p>
  <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece34902-fig-0001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Example of a supplemental feeder used in this study to quantify feeder use by Black‐capped Chickadees in a Mediterranean climate in Corvallis, Oregon, USA. The light blue PIT tag is evident on the chickadee's left leg, but the aluminum leg band and colored plastic leg band on the bird's right leg is out of sight in this image. Note that the wire mesh trap attached to the feeder for capturing birds has been removed in this photograph for clarity</p>
   </div>
   <div id="nlm-graphic-3" xlink:href="ECE3-9-2535-g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece34902-sec-0005" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Vegetation cover surrounding feeders</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Feeder use by birds may be influenced by nearby vegetation used to hide from predators (Cowie &amp; Simons, 
   <a rid="ece34902-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34902-bib-0018">1991</a>; Lima, 
   <a rid="ece34902-bib-0046" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34902-bib-0046">1985</a>; Ya‐Fu, Yen‐Min, &amp; Bollinger, 
   <a rid="ece34902-bib-0079" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34902-bib-0079">2005</a>), so we quantified vegetative cover surrounding feeders as a measure of escape cover. To do this, we established a 20‐m radius circle that was centered at each feeder, and within each circle, we visually estimated the proportion that was covered by vegetation in the tree layer (&gt;3 m above the ground), shrub layer (0.5–3.0 m), and herbaceous layer (&lt;0.5 m). When multiple vegetation layers occurred, we measured vegetation closest to the ground first and then calculated the percentage for the next higher layer by subtracting the lower layer's measurement from the percent of ground surface covered by this next vertical layer. We used these data to identify differential use of feeders due to the presence of escape cover; however, we found no relationship between the extent of feeder use and vegetation cover (
   <span class="italic">F</span>
   <sub>1,19</sub> = 2.64, 
   <span class="italic">p = </span>0.12, 
   <span class="italic">R</span> = 0.35). Thus, we concluded that feeder use was not linked to escape cover immediately surrounding feeders and therefore did not consider vegetative cover in any subsequent analyses.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece34902-sec-0006" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.4</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Weather data</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We obtained weather data recorded at the Corvallis Municipal Airport in Corvallis, OR (44°33′N, 123°15′W) by the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NCEI, 
   <a rid="ece34902-bib-0051" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34902-bib-0051">2017</a>) for each day during which we quantified chickadee feeder use. The weather station was located within 9 km of all feeders, and we assumed it to be representative of local conditions experienced at those feeder locations. We selected variables known to influence feeder use from prior studies which included: minimum daily ambient temperature (°C, hereafter 
   <span class="italic">T</span>
   <sub>min</sub>), average daily wind speed (km/hr, hereafter wind speed), and total daily precipitation (mm, hereafter precipitation). In addition, we obtained sunrise and sunset times for the location of the weather station from the Astronomical Applications Department of the U.S. Naval Observatory (Department of Defense, 
   <a rid="ece34902-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34902-bib-0022">2011</a>) and calculated photoperiod length by subtracting sunrise time from sunset time for each day during which we quantified chickadee feeder use (hereafter photoperiod). For analysis, we binned photoperiod into 1‐hr blocks across the daylight period. When a feeder visit occurred in the hour before sunrise, we assigned it to 0 with respect to the hour from sunrise; when a feeder visit occurred ≥1 hr from sunrise, we considered the hour since sunrise to be 1, with the same approach taken for successive hour increments.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece34902-sec-0007" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.5</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Energetics of black oil sunflower seeds</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To determine the amount of potential energy that chickadees acquired from feeders, we had extraction analysis performed by the Linus Pauling Institute at Oregon State University on a haphazardly selected sample (
   <span class="italic">n</span> = 20) of hulled black oil sunflower seeds taken from the pool of seeds used in feeders in our study. Initially, the sample was separated into two equal groups (i.e., 10 seeds) and analysis took place on a 0.2 g sample of dried and ground sunflower seeds from each group. Next, samples were combined with 4 ml 50% MeOH:H
   <sub>2</sub>O with 1% HCl, and 450 µl 17:1 of FFA IS2, an internal standard added to all samples to aid with quantitation. After 10 min of vortexing and sonication, 4 ml of chloroform was added, followed by a second 10‐min vortex and sonicate session, and then centrifuged 10 min at 1,000 G. After saving the lower layer, the upper layer was re‐extracted in the same manner as above. The lower layer was then combined with the re‐extracted upper layer, and a 3 ml 0.88% KCl solution was added, followed by 5 min of vortexing and sonication, then centrifuged 10 min at 2,000 G to achieve phase separation. The upper layer was removed and discarded, chloroform:MeOH 2:1 was added, the sample was dried under N
   <sub>2</sub>, and then the extracted lipids were weighed. The lipid extraction yielded an average of 0.26 kcal of fat per seed.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To quantify how many black oil sunflower seeds a chickadee would require to fulfill its daily energy requirements, we assumed that chickadees required 65.5 kJ of energy/day (Karasov, Brittingham, &amp; Temple, 
   <a rid="ece34902-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34902-bib-0039">1992</a>), that the rate of metabolizable energy from a sunflower seed was 0.865 (Wu, 
   <a rid="ece34902-bib-0078" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34902-bib-0078">2018</a>), that lipids were the primary energy source individuals obtained from sunflower seeds, and that individuals only consumed sunflower seeds to obtain energy. Using our empirical estimates of fat content, we determined that an individual chickadee required approximately 70 sunflower seeds/day to cover its entire daily energy expenditure (DEE). Given that chickadees do not subsist on seeds alone in the winter (Smith, 
   <a rid="ece34902-bib-0070" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34902-bib-0070">1991</a>) and that previous estimates of energy use were taken from locations with lower ambient temperatures than those of our study site (Karasov et al., 
   <a rid="ece34902-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34902-bib-0039">1992</a>), our estimate of 70 seeds/day is likely to be an upper limit of what an individual bird in our study population would need to consume in a single day during the course of our study.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece34902-sec-0008" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.6</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To address the relationship between feeder use and our focal variables, we computed two response variables for each PIT‐tagged bird. For the first response variable, we calculated the number of visits made to all feeders on each day that an individual visited at least one feeder during the study period (October 23, 2016–March 31, 2017), hereafter termed “total daily visits.” We used this metric to assess how feeder use varied between individual chickadees and quantify the extent to which it was linked to weather variables. To quantify individual‐level variation in feeder use, we summarized the distribution of total daily visits for each bird and the number of feeders visited across the season for each bird, using variance estimates of random effects to quantify the ratio of among‐bird variation to within‐bird variation from our statistical model.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To assess how weather variables were linked to feeder use, we undertook a modeling approach to assess how mean total daily visits were associated with 
   <span class="italic">T</span>
   <sub>min</sub>, wind speed, precipitation, and photoperiod. Exploratory analysis of data prior to modeling found that the general pattern of response was similar among individual birds; however, the magnitude of the response exhibited large variation, so we included a random effect for each bird in all models. Because total daily visits were measured on multiple days for each bird, we graphically assessed the temporal autocorrelation function of residuals in each of our single‐variable models and found that a first‐order autoregressive model had the best fit for the temporal autocorrelation among total daily visits. We found that mean total daily visits were best modeled with a negative binomial distribution allowing for overdispersion. In addition, our initial graphical assessment of total daily visits relative to weather variables found that mean total daily visits varied differently before and after the winter solstice. Thus, we investigated whether effects of environmental variables differed between the pre‐solstice period when photoperiod was decreasing, and the postsolstice period when photoperiod was increasing. We fit generalized linear mixed models (GLMMs) using the glmmTMB package (Magnusson et al., 
   <a rid="ece34902-bib-0048" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34902-bib-0048">2017</a>) in R version 3.4.0 (R Core Team, 
   <a rid="ece34902-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34902-bib-0061">2017</a>), and we used Akaike's Information Criterion (AIC) statistics to rank the degree of support for each regression model. We calculated AIC weights and evidence ratios for our models of mean total daily visits (Burnham, Anderson, &amp; Huyvaert, 
   <a rid="ece34902-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34902-bib-0012">2011</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We regressed total daily visits on 
   <span class="italic">T</span>
   <sub>min</sub>, wind speed, precipitation, photoperiod, and an indicator variable for the postsolstice period. In an effort to evaluate a small but meaningful set of potential models (Burnham et al., 
   <a rid="ece34902-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34902-bib-0012">2011</a>), we fit three models for each weather variable. We fit a model that contained only the weather variable, a second model that contained the weather variable and the interaction of the weather variable and the postsolstice indicator, and a third model that contained the weather variable, the interaction of the weather variable and our postsolstice indicator, and all remaining weather variables. We also fit a null model that contained no weather variables.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used a two‐step process to evaluate the influence of weather variables. First, we compared the first and second model to the null model to evaluate the association between the weather variable and the response variable, and whether the slope of the association differed before and after the solstice. We concluded that the relationship differed before and after the solstice if the AIC for the 2nd model was two or more units less than the AIC for the first model and the null model. If the AIC for the first model was two or more units less than the AIC for the second model and for the null model, we concluded that the relationship was similar before and after the solstice. We concluded that there was no support for the weather variable if the AIC for the null model was two or more units less than the AIC for the first and second models, or if the AIC for the null model was within 2 AIC units of the model with the lowest AIC. In step two, we compared the third model to the model with the smallest AIC in the first step to evaluate whether the weather variables, in combination with each other, were associated with the response variable. We concluded that weather variables were needed in combination if the AIC from model three was 2 or more AIC units less than the AIC from the best‐supported model in step 1.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For our second response variable, we summed the number of visits made to all feeders during each hour since sunrise for each day from November 9, 2016 through January 31, 2017, hereafter termed “total hourly visits.” We restricted this analysis to this period because day length during this period varied minimally (8.8–9.8 hr) and resulted in the shortest foraging days for chickadees during our study. As above, we used a Poisson GLMM with the glmmTMB package (Magnusson et al., 
   <a rid="ece34902-bib-0048" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34902-bib-0048">2017</a>) in R version 3.4.0 (R Core Team, 
   <a rid="ece34902-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34902-bib-0061">2017</a>) to quantify the relationship between the mean total hourly visits and hour since sunrise. We included the number of days each bird visited any feeder within each hour since sunrise as an offset in the model to adjust for the varying number of days an individual bird visited during each hour of the day. We graphically assessed the autocorrelation function of residuals and used AIC statistics to identify the best‐supported autocorrelation structure. We found the relationship between total hourly visits and time since sunrise was concave but asymmetrical, suggesting that a linear or quadratic relationship between mean total hourly visits and time since sunrise would have been a poor fit, and a cubic relationship with multiple changes of slope did not occur. Therefore, we treated hour since sunrise as a categorical variable in the regression model and used AIC as a measure of the support for this variable.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For analyses pertaining to individual variation, we report averages and their associated standard deviations (SDs); for analyses pertaining to variation due to time (time since sunrise, photoperiod) or weather (
   <span class="italic">T</span>
   <sub>min</sub>, wind speed, precipitation), we report the rate at which the mean total daily visits changed with changes in time or weather (slope) and the associated 95% confidence interval. The sample size for all analyses is 
   <span class="italic">n</span> = 70 individuals unless otherwise noted.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
