<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece34902-sec-0003" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study area and focal species</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We established 21 bird feeders in September 2016 on lands owned by Oregon State University near the Corvallis, Oregon, USA campus (44.6°N, 123.3°W, 90 masl). We placed feeders at 200‐m intervals along the Oak Creek riparian area such that the two most distant feeders were 3.2 km away from each other; this distance is within the range of what an individual chickadee could theoretically cover in the course of our study period based on previous work with homing experiments conducted during winter (Odum, 
  <a rid="ece34902-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34902-bib-0052">1941</a>) and studies of winter flock space use (Desrochers &amp; Hannon, 
  <a rid="ece34902-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34902-bib-0023">1989</a>; see Discussion). In two instances, we were forced to place feeders approximately 400 m apart because of site access restrictions. We installed each feeder within 60 m of a continuously flowing creek in habitat that was dominated by Oregon white oak (
  <span class="italic">Quercus garryanna</span>), Himalayan blackberry (
  <span class="italic">Rubus discolor</span>), bigleaf maple (
  <span class="italic">Acer macrophyllum</span>), poplar (
  <span class="italic">Populus </span>spp.), and willow (
  <span class="italic">Salix </span>spp.) and contained a mixture of native shrubs, grasses, and forbs. We selected feeder locations that were a minimum of 50 m from buildings, and although it is possible that our tagged birds could have accessed feeders other than those established for our study, we found that there was no evidence that use of individual feeders varied relative to their distance to the nearest building (
  <span class="italic">F</span>
  <sub>1,19</sub> = 0.05, 
  <span class="italic">p</span> = 0.82, 
  <span class="italic">R</span> = 0.05; Supporting Information Figure 
  <a rid="ece34902-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#ece34902-sup-0001">S1</a>). Therefore, we did not consider distance to buildings further in any of our analyses.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We selected the chickadee for this study because this species (a) is a small‐bodied songbird (10–14 g) with high energetic needs during the nonbreeding season (Foote et al., 
  <a rid="ece34902-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34902-bib-0029">2010</a>; Smith, 
  <a rid="ece34902-bib-0070" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34902-bib-0070">1991</a>), (b) is a year‐round resident that occurs in temporally stable flocks throughout the winter, at least in continental climates (Desrochers &amp; Hannon, 
  <a rid="ece34902-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34902-bib-0023">1989</a>; Smith, 
  <a rid="ece34902-bib-0070" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34902-bib-0070">1991</a>), and (c) is one of the most common visitors of recreational bird feeders (Brittingham &amp; Temple, 
  <a rid="ece34902-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34902-bib-0009">1989</a>; Horn et al., 
  <a rid="ece34902-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34902-bib-0035">2014</a>; Smith, 
  <a rid="ece34902-bib-0070" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34902-bib-0070">1991</a>). In addition, chickadees typically remove a single sunflower seed from feeders during each visit before moving away from the feeder to consume or cache the seed (Ficken, Weise, &amp; Popp, 
  <a rid="ece34902-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34902-bib-0027">1990</a>; Foote et al., 
  <a rid="ece34902-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34902-bib-0029">2010</a>), making the number of feeding visits a close proxy of the number of seeds obtained when estimating the amount of food obtained by individuals from feeders (Latimer, Cooper, Karasov, &amp; Zuckerberg, 
  <a rid="ece34902-bib-0045" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34902-bib-0045">2018</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
