<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap id="tbl1" position="float" class="table-wrap">
 <label class="label">Table 1</label>
 <caption class="caption">
  <p class="p">Arabana core values and aligned adaptation options within the Arabana adaptation strategy.</p>
 </caption>
 <alt-text id="alttext0020" class="alt-text">Table 1</alt-text>
 <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" class="table">
  <thead class="thead">
   <tr class="tr">
    <th class="th">Value</th>
    <th class="th">Arabana words (indicative quotes)</th>
    <th class="th">Adaptation options suggested</th>
   </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody class="tbody">
   <tr class="tr">
    <td align="left" class="td">History</td>
    <td align="left" class="td">“I think we need to get something like tourism back on country there now we have native title. There has to be something back there whether in Marree or Finniss Springs something so that people can visit it a cultural centre there, something big for the tourists to see, if you got tourists visiting it gets all over the world. All our history – those travelling the Oodnadatta track – grey nomads to Darwin – last weekend it's just not funny the amount of people going through, but not stopping – if there was something there for them to see get that historical knowledge, take a tour think that would be good” (Alice Springs respondent 4, 2012).</td>
    <td align="left" class="td">Cultural keeping Centres
     <break class="break"/>Getting youth involved in tourism
     <break class="break"/>Teaching youth their family history
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr class="tr">
    <td align="left" class="td">Place</td>
    <td align="left" class="td">“Need to be on country to actually monitor changes and other things” (Darwin respondent 1 2012).
     <break class="break"/>“Need to strengthen people to withstand climate change and get them to look after that country respect that land. Lots of people would jump on the opportunity to go back to country” (Darwin respondent 7 2012).
     <break class="break"/>“There used to be lots of stumpies there, and cadnis – frilled neck, used to be lots but don't see them anymore- this would be good program to restock those” (Darwin respondent 7 2012).
    </td>
    <td align="left" class="td">Going back to country
     <break class="break"/>Restocking native vegetation and wildlife
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr class="tr">
    <td align="left" class="td">Livelihoods</td>
    <td align="left" class="td">“In terms of overarching priorities – we must be able to organise means of generate income on country and water – keep water in places where we want to generate an income…if food and water goes back to land, so will Arabana especially if you can find way to stimulate an income” (Adelaide respondent 2, 2012).</td>
    <td align="left" class="td">Pastoralism on Finniss
     <break class="break"/>Cultural Tourism Rangers
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr class="tr">
    <td align="left" class="td">Culture</td>
    <td align="left" class="td">“We could set up cultural centres. Where the people can go and meet. People only got their own houses where they can meet but if you got an Arabana centre, all your history there, your family names things you could go there and see – a video about climate change like that – your kids and grandchildren can see, get continuity - keep that information coming through to the families. Have that country look/meet every two years. Centres will help people where they live and not make them stress out about having to go to country as they can still learn about country – have it for the future – might get our kids and grandchildren know where they come from” (Alice Springs respondent 4 201).</td>
    <td align="left" class="td">Cultural revitalization Centres
     <break class="break"/>Enhanced use of ICT
    </td>
   </tr>
   <tr class="tr">
    <td align="left" class="td">Country</td>
    <td align="left" class="td">“Have some rangers. Look after it as a cultural place properly” (Darwin respondent 7 2012).
     <break class="break"/>“We need to set up one and management, in Marree, maybe Finniss…” (Marree respondent 2, 2012).
    </td>
    <td align="left" class="td">Setting up ranger stations
     <break class="break"/>Revegetation programs
    </td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
</table-wrap>
