<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Despite ongoing global warming, number of continuously freezing days has increased and minimum temperatures have decreased over northern mid-latitude continents since the 1990s, while the frequency of unusually cold winter months in Eurasia markedly decreased from the 1980s to 1990s
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span>. This trend reversal in cold extremes is associated with the development of Siberian high
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span> that leads to cold advection and frequent occurrence of cold events over Eurasia. Arctic sea-ice reduction is suggested as the driver of the recent trend, but mechanisms underlying this Arctic–Eurasian climate linkages proposed by many previous studies is yet inconclusive
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
  </span>. The impact of Arctic sea ice variations on mid-latitude climate is a topic of much debate.
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Meanwhile, the Arctic climate variation is not necessarily closed within the Arctic and high-latitude regions. Several studies have implicated fluctuating sea surface temperatures (SST) outside the polar cap as an important driver of the recent Arctic warming
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span>. In particular, tropical Pacific SST variability, which is regarded as a key pacemaker of surface global warming
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>
  </span>, is suggested as a cause of recent surface warming in Greenland through atmospheric teleconnection
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span>. Here we show that a combination of atmospheric teleconnection originating in the tropical oceans and Arctic sea-ice variability is a driver of the Arctic–Eurasian climate linkage. This study focuses on early winter (OND: October–December) during the freezing season, when recent Arctic warming is most pronounced and the impact of Arctic sea-ice loss on the atmosphere is likely to maximise
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span>. Seasons refer to those in the Northern Hemisphere.
 </p>
</sec>
