<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Macroecological approaches represent a popular analytical tool to assess and predict the impacts of climate change (e.g. [
 <xref rid="pone.0154869.ref054" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0154869.ref056" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">56</xref>]) as well as to assess spatial patterns of biological invasions in order to prioritize regions for the early detection of invasion outbreaks (e.g. [
 <xref rid="pone.0154869.ref042" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0154869.ref057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0154869.ref058" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">58</xref>]). The utility of Species Distribution Models (SDMs) to predict future spread of non-indigenous species has been demonstrated repeatedly (e.g. [
 <xref rid="pone.0154869.ref057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0154869.ref059" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">59</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0154869.ref060" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">60</xref>]). For general assumptions and methods see Elith and Lethwick [
 <xref rid="pone.0154869.ref061" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">61</xref>]. Previous research targeting 
 <italic class="italic">X</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">laevis</italic> showed large areas in Asia, southern Australia, south-western Europe, North and South America to be particularly vulnerable to colonization [
 <xref rid="pone.0154869.ref052" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>]. Owing to its ability to settle on various continents and its expected impact on local wetland communities [
 <xref rid="pone.0154869.ref046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0154869.ref049" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0154869.ref062" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">62</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0154869.ref065" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">65</xref>], 
 <italic class="italic">X</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">laevis</italic> is recognized as a major invasive amphibian species worldwide [
 <xref rid="pone.0154869.ref050" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>]. For such species it is crucial to develop accurate models of potential colonization and range shifts accounting for short-term climate changes. Such models may help to identify zones that could be colonized, refine risk assessments, and target prevention measures. Aiming to contribute to the future management of 
 <italic class="italic">X</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">laevis</italic>, this study investigates the present and forecasts the future potential invasion range of the species on a global scale, based on an updated and extended occurrence data set and a similar set of bioclimatic variables as those used by Measey 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="pone.0154869.ref050" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>].
</p>
