<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Metrics</div>
 <p id="Par32" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The strength of the Pacific trade winds is estimated by taking the area average of zonal wind stress over the western and central tropical Pacific (160°E–150°W, 5°S–5°N) where the trade wind anomaly pattern shows the most pronounced interannual to multi-decadal variability
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>
  </span>. To examine the link between the IPO and the trade winds, we use the TPI as a proxy for the IPO
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
  </span>. This index is defined as the difference between the SST anomaly over the central tropical Pacific (10°S–10°N, 170°E–90°W) and the average of the SST anomalies over the Northwest (25°N–45°N, 140°E–145°W) and Southwest Pacific (50°S–15°S, 150°E–160°W). These regions are shown with rectangular boxes in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1d</a>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par33" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To reduce the impacts of the long-term spurious climate drift on our results, linear trend simulations was subtracted from control runs
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">59</a>
  </span>. To estimate the range of uncertainty in the GMT projections on different timescales, which result from internal variability alone, we utilized moving trends (with a window size ranging from 5 to 35 years) on annually averaged GMT control run time series. For each window size, the 1 and 99 percentile range in ensemble trends is used to quantify the uncertainty owing to internal variability.
 </p>
 <p id="Par34" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Historical uncertainty in the 20-year climate simulations is estimated by analyzing the periods corresponding to 1992–2011 in the CESM-Hind-Proj ensemble set. The uncertainty is defined as the spread in the 20-year trends across the model ensemble members. In regard to future climate projections, the uncertainty is estimated from the 20-year period corresponding to 2016–2035 in the CESM-Hind-Proj and the first 20-year period of simulation in the other ensembles.</p>
</sec>
