<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s4" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The LIG has occasionally been considered as an analogue for the impacts of global warming on species' distribution [
  <a rid="RSOS182111C13" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C13">13</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS182111C60" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C60">60</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS182111C61" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C61">61</a>]. At face value, the LIG fossil record of reef corals depicts a global biogeographic pattern that is considerably dissimilar to that observed in the present day (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS182111F1" href="#RSOS182111F1">figure 1</a>). Whereas today, both species abundance and diversity are highest within the tropics, with an equatorial dip, the LIG record shows a poleward shift in occurrence records and species diversity, with both increasing at higher latitudes in the Northern Hemisphere, and a prominent equatorial decline [
  <a rid="RSOS182111C24" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C24">24</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS182111C25" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C25">25</a>]. Support for this observed pattern is also provided when subsampling methods are applied to ameliorate biases pertaining to uneven latitudinal sampling [
  <a rid="RSOS182111C13" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C13">13</a>]. However, using ENM, our findings provide little support for an equatorial decline in habitability for reef corals during the LIG. Instead, LIG reef corals occupied similar, though not equivalent, niches to those of modern reef corals. Our results suggest that during the LIG, global habitability was generally greater than the modern, particularly at equatorial latitudes. In addition, modelled habitability is more pronounced at high latitudes in both hemispheres, particularly, within the Northern Hemisphere. These results support a poleward range expansion of reef corals during the LIG, as suggested by previous studies [
  <a rid="RSOS182111C13" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C13">13</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS182111C24" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C24">24</a>], but not an equatorial decline [
  <a rid="RSOS182111C13" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C13">13</a>]. This suggests that the observed equatorial decline in the fossil record might be a result of sampling bias within equatorial regions.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Under climate scenarios RCP4.5 and RCP8.5, our results indicate that high latitude habitability should increase (i.e. range expansion), while equatorial latitudes will see a large decrease in favourable habitats (i.e. range retraction) compared to the modern. Most notably, this includes the centre of the Coral Triangle, in the Indo-Pacific Ocean, the ‘heart’ of modern-day coral biodiversity, with 605 reef coral species, representing over three-quarters of global reef coral diversity [
  <a rid="RSOS182111C62" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C62">62</a>]. In addition to the direct risk to biodiversity (including the multitude of species that live in reef coral environments), the economic, social and cultural benefits that coral reefs provide are of crucial importance to island communities within this region [
  <a rid="RSOS182111C63" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C63">63</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS182111C64" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C64">64</a>]. However, our results do also suggest that under RCP4.5 and RCP8.5, we can expect to see an increase in marginal habitats within the Coral Triangle, which might have important implications for future recovery. Nevertheless, it should also be borne in mind that reef corals, and coral reef ecosystems, are far less likely to survive other stressors, such as overfishing and pollution, when residing in marginal habitats. Furthermore, as our projections do not include aragonite saturation state, they may be relatively optimistic in the face of anthropogenic climate change as they do not account for the impacts of ocean acidification.
 </p>
 <sec id="s4a" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.1.</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Implications for the evolution of the latitudinal biodiversity gradient</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Attempts to reconstruct latitudinal biodiversity gradients in geological time have historically been achieved using direct reading of occurrence records [
   <a rid="RSOS182111C65" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C65">65</a>], potentially leading to circumscribed results [
   <a rid="RSOS182111C66" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C66">66</a>]. Although subsampling approaches have been applied in more recent studies, and provide more useful insights than uncorrected ‘raw’ diversity data [
   <a rid="RSOS182111C13" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C13">13</a>], they ultimately cannot predict which data we might be missing, i.e. fossils and/or palaeoenvironments that we have not sampled, or that never entered the fossil record [
   <a rid="RSOS182111C67" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C67">67</a>,
   <a rid="RSOS182111C68" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C68">68</a>]. Our model results suggest that the LIG reef coral record is geographically biased through the amount of predicted habitable area within latitudinal bins, herein referred to as the latitudinal habitability gradient. Thus, we predict that, given suitable preservational conditions, we should expect to find additional LIG reef coral occurrence data from equatorial latitudes.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">‘Modern-type’ latitudinal biodiversity gradients, with tropical peaks in diversity, have been suggested to form under cold icehouse climate regimes, whereas flattened gradients or temperate peaks are restricted to warmer greenhouse regimes [
   <a rid="RSOS182111C66" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C66">66</a>]. Additionally, it has been proposed that non-modern-type latitudinal biodiversity gradients might also form during interglacials [
   <a rid="RSOS182111C66" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C66">66</a>,
   <a rid="RSOS182111C69" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C69">69</a>]. However, based on modelled habitability, our findings imply a contrarian result for the LIG, and suggest that interglacials might not be warm enough to produce latitudinal biodiversity gradients similar to those we observe in greenhouse climate regimes.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s4b" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.2.</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Utility of the fossil record in forecasting</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Variable contribution analyses computed within biomod2 [
   <a rid="RSOS182111C55" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C55">55</a>] clearly demonstrate that bathymetry and SST are the principal parameters controlling the distribution of both modern and LIG reef corals (electronic supplementary material, SM2: table SM3). It is to be expected that bathymetry has the largest explanative power as the very nature of reef (zooxanthellate) corals restricts them to shallow marine settings. While LIG bathymetry is generally similar to that of the modern at a global scale, several areas have experienced localized tectonic uplift (e.g. Huon Peninsula, Barbados, Sumba and Vanuatu [
   <a rid="RSOS182111C70" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C70">70</a>]). However, this is not likely to impact our results, based on our sea-level sensitivity test (see electronic supplementary material, SM2). As both models used the same DEM, SST might be considered the dominant factor in determining any difference between ENM and projected distributions. In fact, our results are in line with those suggested by palaeoclimatic proxy and modelling data, which propose that annual mean SST and seasonality at low latitudes for the LIG were similar to those of the modern [
   <a rid="RSOS182111C27" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C27">27</a>,
   <a rid="RSOS182111C28" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C28">28</a>,
   <a rid="RSOS182111C70" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C70">70</a>]. Data from uplifted LIG coral reefs from the Huon Peninsula of New Guinea and western Australia also indicate mean annual temperatures and seasonal ranges comparable to present-day SST [
   <a rid="RSOS182111C70" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C70">70</a>,
   <a rid="RSOS182111C71" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C71">71</a>]. However, it has also been suggested that seasonality was greater at higher latitudes, with increased SST and insolation modelled in the Northern Hemisphere [
   <a rid="RSOS182111C27" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C27">27</a>,
   <a rid="RSOS182111C72" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C72">72</a>,
   <a rid="RSOS182111C73" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C73">73</a>]. This might have permitted reef corals to reside at greater depths at higher latitudes, as well as at more poleward localities due to higher insolation and SST in the LIG, as supported by our habitability modelling results.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To avoid environmentally driven extinction, taxa need to be able to adapt to changing environments, either through distributional shifts (i.e. habitat tracking) or by altering their abiotic preferences [
   <a rid="RSOS182111C24" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C24">24</a>,
   <a rid="RSOS182111C30" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C30">30</a>,
   <a rid="RSOS182111C74" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C74">74</a>]. The thermal limits of organisms are widely acknowledged as shaping diversity gradients on geological time scales (e.g. [
   <a rid="RSOS182111C69" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C69">69</a>,
   <a rid="RSOS182111C75" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C75">75</a>,
   <a rid="RSOS182111C76" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C76">76</a>]). Although the latitudinal habitability gradient remained fairly stable between the LIG and modern climatic regimes, we might expect to see a greater reshaping of the latitudinal habitability and biodiversity gradients under future scenarios. While reef corals might be able to adapt over geological time intervals, it is unlikely that they will be able to keep pace with the rapid rate of climatic change predicted under RCP4.5 or RCP8.5 scenarios. Studies based solely on modern occurrences [
   <a rid="RSOS182111C16" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C16">16</a>,
   <a rid="RSOS182111C77" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C77">77</a>] propose a much more drastic decline in coral reefs under RCP4.5 and RCP8.5 scenarios than our results indicate for reef corals. This is likely the consequence of differences in methodological approach, selection of environmental variables, GCMs and differences in training datasets for modelling. Perhaps of particular note is the lack of aragonite saturation state and cumulative thermal stress variables applied in this study, whereas bathymetry was not directly considered in others (see [
   <a rid="RSOS182111C16" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C16">16</a>]). We acknowledge that the inclusion of environmental variables such as aragonite saturation state would likely improve our model predictions; however, such data are not available for the geological record. With this in mind, our model outputs are likely optimistic in the face of anthropogenic climate change, particularly for reef corals in high latitude regions, as the aragonite saturation state is generally lower than at tropical latitudes [
   <a rid="RSOS182111C78" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C78">78</a>]. In relation to other environmental variables, best practice requires the construction of generalized models when projecting to other time slices. An ENM focused on one spatial or temporal extent may perform very well with a large number of explanatory variables. However, an ENM might also find causal relationships that are non-existent, resulting in over-fitting, hindering the applicability and any projections of the model under different spatial/temporal extents. Sensitivity analyses comparing modern projections from modern-trained ENMs with and without aragonite saturation state suggest little difference between predictions at global scale. However, some noticeable variations are observable at local scale (electronic supplementary material, SM2: figure SM2). Our variable contribution analyses indicate aragonite saturation state is of secondary importance in the construction of global ENMs (electronic supplementary material, SM2: table SM1). However, under continued acidification of the world's oceans, aragonite saturation state may become more of a limiting factor for reef corals than what is observed in the modern. Therefore, RCP4.5 and RCP8.5 projections should be considered as relatively optimistic in the face of continued CO
   <sub>2</sub> emissions. However, this is conditional on reef corals being able to acclimatize to heightened temperatures or shift distributions to suitable temperature localities in the first place. Integrating palaeontological data into ENM promotes two clear advantages to aid model projections: (i) the opportunity to test models with empirical evidence across temporal windows and climate regimes and (ii) the ability to combine palaeontological and neontological data to consider the full ecological limits of a particular taxon, rather than just the occupied niche in its current biogeographic pattern.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although the LIG fossil record is biased, the inclusion of fossil reef coral data provides additional insight into the niche hypervolume and potential distribution of reef corals under future climate change. As with previous studies [
   <a rid="RSOS182111C20" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C20">20</a>], predictions including fossil data suggest significantly more habitability at wider geographical ranges than those based solely on modern occurrences. ENM predictions which only include modern occurrences run the risk of modelling the occupied niche, whereas fossil occurrences can provide additional understanding into the fundamental niche of a species [
   <a rid="RSOS182111C79" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C79">79</a>,
   <a rid="RSOS182111C80" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C80">80</a>]. Indeed, this particular study still might provide limited insights into the fundamental niche due to the incompleteness of the LIG reef coral record. However, the inclusion of fossil occurrences enables us to test which models perform best across temporal boundaries, as well as the importance of establishing the fundamental niche using true positive fraction. It is clear from our results that a multi-temporal approach improves predictive performance, particularly when considering higher binary thresholds, providing support for projected habitat suitability under future climate scenarios.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
