<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s3b2" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2.2.</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Geographical predictions</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results from binary habitability maps (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS182111F2" href="#RSOS182111F2">figure 2</a>; raw, binary and clamping mask maps available in electronic supplementary material, SM2: figures SM15–22) for models trained on the modern occurrence dataset predict a larger habitable region at low latitudes (0–30°) than the LIG-trained ENM for all climate scenarios, converging only at higher latitudes. Models trained on the LIG occurrence dataset consistently calculate a smaller sum of habitable cells within the tropics than the modern-trained ENM. Combining model outputs (electronic supplementary material, SM2: figures SM23 and SM24) for both modern-trained and LIG-trained ENMs shows no distinctive increase in habitable cells at varying latitudes for all climate scenarios under the binary thresholds 5LPT and 10LPT. However, under the binary conversion threshold 20LPT (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS182111F3" href="#RSOS182111F3">figure 3</a>), the combined data increase the predicted habitability substantially at higher latitudes in the Northern Hemisphere, yet provide no such significant results for lower latitudes or in the Southern Hemisphere. 
  <div id="RSOS182111F2" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 2.</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Latitudinal plots for predicted habitability from ecological niche modelling, using three binary thresholds: the 5th-, 10th- and 20th-percentiles of the lowest tail of habitat suitability values (5LPT, 10LPT and 20LPT). Plots indicate habitability for the LIG, modern, representative concentration pathway 4.5 (RCP4.5) and 8.5 (RCP8.5). In this instance, habitability is the sum of cells designated as habitable, within 5° latitudinal bins, by the mean prediction, trained on the (
     <span class="italic">a</span>) modern occurrence dataset, and (
     <span class="italic">b</span>) LIG occurrence dataset. Grey shaded area represents the extent of the tropics in the present day. Dashed lines indicate the Equator, the Northern Tropic and the Southern Tropic.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="rsos182111-g2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <div id="RSOS182111F3" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 3.</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Combined binary maps (using threshold 20LPT) showing the potential distribution of reef corals under LIG, modern, RCP4.5 and RCP8.5 climate regimes. (
     <span class="italic">a</span>) Global maps of habitability under the four climate scenarios. Grey cells represent the potential distribution predicted through using only the modern reef coral training dataset. Yellow cells characterize cells gained when coupling LIG and modern-trained predictions. Blue cells indicate unsuitable locations, while black indicates no data cells (landmass). (
     <span class="italic">b</span>) Habitability maps clipped to Indo-Pacific for all climate scenarios to highlight change in habitability within the Coral Triangle. Yellow cells highlight suitable habitats, while blue cells indicate unsuitable locations, and black indicates no data cells (landmass).
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="rsos182111-g3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Threshold selection for binary conversion has important consequences on predicted habitability for future climate scenarios. When comparing predictions from modern-trained ENMs and different binary thresholds, LIG and modern habitability predictions reduce uniformly between thresholds, whereas RCP4.5 and RCP8.5 do not (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS182111F2" href="#RSOS182111F2">figure 2</a>). When applying binary threshold 5LPT, global habitability seems to increase under RCP4.5 and RCP8.5. However, under 20LPT, there is a substantial reduction in habitability relative to the modern and LIG. These results suggest that under RCP4.5 and RCP8.5, there will be an increase in marginal habitats for reef corals, and a prominent decrease in those more favourable.
 </p>
</sec>
