<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s1" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1.</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Anthropogenic climate change, with projected global warming of 2–4.8°C, is the principal challenge of the twenty-first century [
  <a rid="RSOS182111C1" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C1">1</a>]. Rising sea-surface temperatures (SSTs), associated with global warming, have already generated ecological disturbances and substantial range shifts of marine organisms [
  <a rid="RSOS182111C2" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C2">2</a>–
  <a rid="RSOS182111C4" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C4">4</a>]. Today, reef corals house some of the most biologically diverse and economically valuable ecosystems in the marine realm. Thermal stress, as a direct result of global warming, has generated unprecedented mass bleaching of reef corals, with three pan-tropical events recorded in the last two decades, leading to a decline in abundance, diversity and habitat structure [
  <a rid="RSOS182111C5" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C5">5</a>–
  <a rid="RSOS182111C7" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C7">7</a>]. Global warming has also led to clear poleward range expansion of some corals [
  <a rid="RSOS182111C8" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C8">8</a>–
  <a rid="RSOS182111C12" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C12">12</a>], although the evidence for equatorial range retractions is debatable [
  <a rid="RSOS182111C9" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C9">9</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS182111C13" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C13">13</a>]. However, because studies on extant species are based on short-term observations, during which time a taxon might never have occupied its full geographical or environmental space, it is difficult to predict whether this expansion/retraction trend is a function of global warming, or simply reflects the ongoing response of a species to a pre-existing forcing already applied to the system. Greater understanding of the range dynamics of reef corals is, therefore, critical to their conservation.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Several studies have used ecological niche modelling (ENM) to evaluate the environmental controls on coral reefs and predict global distribution under future climate change scenarios [
  <a rid="RSOS182111C14" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C14">14</a>–
  <a rid="RSOS182111C17" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C17">17</a>]. However, the fossil record provides the only empirical evidence for the long-term responses of organisms to environmental perturbations (e.g. [
  <a rid="RSOS182111C18" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C18">18</a>]), offering a ground truth for model projections under varying climate scenarios, and potentially enabling additional insights into niche hypervolume (the full multi-dimensional abiotic space which a taxon might occupy indefinitely), commonly referred to as the fundamental niche [
  <a rid="RSOS182111C19" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C19">19</a>]. Furthermore, it has been demonstrated that the integration of both palaeontological and neontological data improves biodiversity risk assessments [
  <a rid="RSOS182111C20" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C20">20</a>–
  <a rid="RSOS182111C23" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C23">23</a>]. Future projections trained solely on modern occurrences might therefore underestimate habitability due to a restricted present-day range in climatic variation. Through incorporation of the fossil record, more of this variation is captured. Thus, palaeontological data from warmer intervals should improve projections to future climate scenarios that are closer analogues than the present day.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Apparent range shifts have been observed in the Quaternary (2.58–0 Ma) fossil record of reef corals [
  <a rid="RSOS182111C12" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C12">12</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS182111C13" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C13">13</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS182111C24" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C24">24</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS182111C25" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C25">25</a>], with one study [
  <a rid="RSOS182111C13" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C13">13</a>] demonstrating poleward range shifts and an equatorial decline in reef corals during the Last Interglacial (LIG), 
  <span class="italic">ca</span> 125 000 years ago. Several authors have provided approximations on global SSTs for the LIG, with estimates ranging from no significant difference to as much as 2°C warmer than today [
  <a rid="RSOS182111C26" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C26">26</a>–
  <a rid="RSOS182111C28" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C28">28</a>]. Kiessling 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span> [
  <a rid="RSOS182111C13" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C13">13</a>] proposed that this temperature rise was the driver of the dramatic range shifts observed in LIG reef corals. Consequently, these authors suggested that anthropogenic global warming today means that an equatorial decline of reef corals is likely to follow their current poleward expansion, which has important implications for conservation, such as which geographical regions should be prioritized. However, the fossil record is inherently biased both spatially and temporally, impacted by incomplete sampling, variable fossil preservation, erosion and burial. Although existing subsampling methods, such as those applied by Kiessling 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span> [
  <a rid="RSOS182111C13" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C13">13</a>], can ameliorate problems associated with uneven ‘raw’ occurrence data (e.g. [
  <a rid="RSOS182111C29" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C29">29</a>]), they cannot account for the absence of data. ENM offers the prospect of mitigating for biases caused by the uneven distribution of known occurrences (i.e. raw data) by measuring habitat availability, providing insights into the potential geographical distribution of organisms through consideration of their observed realized niche.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here, we use ENM to: (i) evaluate the extent to which the LIG equatorial decline of reef corals is the result of fossil bias or a genuine loss in habitability; (ii) quantify the variation in geographical range of reef corals during the LIG and under future climate scenarios, with implications for understanding the evolution of the reef coral latitudinal biodiversity gradient; and (iii) demonstrate the value of using fossil reef coral data to improve biodiversity risk assessment through consideration of the realized niche under varied climate states.</p>
</sec>
