<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s3b3" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2.3.</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Range dynamics</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The LIG binary maps (hindcasted and trained) indicate habitat suitability at equatorial latitudes (figures 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS182111F2" href="#RSOS182111F2">2</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS182111F3" href="#RSOS182111F3">3</a>) for all binary thresholds. For latitudinal bin 0–5°, the LIG-trained ENM predicts 52, 51 and 45 presence cells for 5LPT, 10LPT and 20LPT, respectively, whereas the modern-trained ENM predicts 116, 86 and 63 cells (electronic supplementary material, SM3). Based on the results from the combined, modern-trained and LIG-trained projections, for all binary thresholds, habitability was generally greater within the tropics (−25° to 25°) during the LIG than in the modern (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS182111F2" href="#RSOS182111F2">figure 2</a>; electronic supplementary material, figures SM23 and SM25 and SM3). More specifically, results from the combined projections indicate that LIG equatorial regions (−5° to 5°) were more habitable than during the modern, with 34 (5LPT), 19 (10LPT) and 40 (20LPT) additional habitable cells predicted. In addition, habitability is generally greater at higher latitudes in both hemispheres for the LIG than in the modern, for all binary thresholds, suggesting that reef coral range size was likely larger during this time. To provide an example, for 5LPT, only three cells were predicted for latitudinal bin 40–45° in the modern Northern Hemisphere, yet 14 cells were predicted for the LIG (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS182111F2" href="#RSOS182111F2">figure 2</a>; electronic supplementary material, SM3).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Under RCP4.5 and RCP8.5, the models predict a considerable decrease in habitability (for all binary thresholds) within the tropics with a 5% (5LPT), 20% (10LPT) and 59% (20LPT) loss in habitable cells for RCP8.5 relative to the modern (SM3), notably in the centre of the hyper-diverse Coral Triangle (Indo-Pacific Ocean) (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS182111F3" href="#RSOS182111F3">figure 3</a>). By contrast, habitability increases significantly at higher latitudes (25–45°) in the Northern Hemisphere (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS182111F3" href="#RSOS182111F3">figure 3</a>), with a 36% (5LPT), 40% (10LPT) and 43% (20LPT) increase in habitable cells from the modern (SM3). South of the Equator, there is a similar gain at higher latitudes (25° to 45°), with a 30% (5LPT), 40% (10LPT) and 46% (20LPT) increase in habitable cells (SM3). However, the clamping masks, particularly for RCP8.5, highlight some uncertainty for equatorial tropical latitudes due to one environmental variable being outside the range used for model calibration (electronic supplementary material, SM2: figures SM21 and SM22). This finding highlights the need to incorporate fossil data from various climatic regimes to reduce uncertainty when projecting to future climate scenarios, which represent climate conditions outside modern experience [
  <a rid="RSOS182111C59" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS182111C59">59</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
