<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The ability to modulate evaporative water loss through the use of selective brain cooling may have contributed to the evolutionary success of artiodactyls (
 <xref rid="cow078C86" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Mitchell and Lust, 2008</xref>). It can be assumed that the carotid rete, and therefore selective brain cooling, evolved concomitantly with the emergence of the modern artiodactyl orders, at least 45 million years ago (
 <xref rid="cow078C51" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Janis, 2009</xref>). When the diversity trends of Artiodactyla (presumably all rete bearing) and their sister clade Perissodactyla (presumably not rete bearing) are compared across the Cenozoic, discrepancies in generic richness are established in three pulses, each of which corresponds to a trend of aridification, whether warming or cooling (Fig. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="cow078F6" class="xref">6</xref>). In the earlier half of the Cenozoic, global climate is best described as a ‘tropical hothouse’ (
 <xref rid="cow078C13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Buchardt, 1978</xref>; 
 <xref rid="cow078C118" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Wolfe, 1978</xref>; 
 <xref rid="cow078C116" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Wing, 1987</xref>; 
 <xref rid="cow078C48" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Huber and Sloan, 2001</xref>; 
 <xref rid="cow078C11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bowen and Zachos, 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="cow078C35" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Galeotti 
  <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 2010
 </xref>). During this period of abundant moisture, artiodactyls and perissodactyls enjoyed similar generic richness (Fig. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="cow078F6" class="xref">6</xref>). However, a pronounced period of cooling and drying across the Eocene to Oligocene transition began to shift this relationship (
 <xref rid="cow078C22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Diester-Haass and Zahn, 1996</xref>; 
 <xref rid="cow078C71" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lear 
  <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 2008
 </xref>). Although many large-bodied mammals faced extinction throughout this period (
 <xref rid="cow078C96" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Prothero, 1985</xref>; 
 <xref rid="cow078C47" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hooker, 1992</xref>; 
 <xref rid="cow078C72" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Legendre and Hartenberger, 1992</xref>), artiodactyls enjoyed a comparatively higher degree of survivorship both during and after this event. Throughout the drier, temperate Oligocene (
 <xref rid="cow078C63" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kennett, 1985</xref>; 
 <xref rid="cow078C25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ehrmann and Mackensen, 1992</xref>), artiodactyl generic richness remained elevated relative to perissodactyls (Fig. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="cow078F6" class="xref">6</xref>). Across the Late Oligocene to Early Miocene transition, another period of aridification swept the globe, this time accompanied by warming (
 <xref rid="cow078C63" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kennett, 1985</xref>; 
 <xref rid="cow078C101" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Retallack, 2013</xref>). This period of warming and aridification saw a pulse in generic richness of artiodactyls capable of selective brain cooling, immediately before the Mid-Miocene expansive radiation of C
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> grasslands. It is often the expansion of grasslands and the artiodactyl rumen that have been associated and promoted as the driver of artiodactyl success (
 <xref rid="cow078C99" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Retallack, 1991</xref>, 
 <xref rid="cow078C100" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2001</xref>, 
 <xref rid="cow078C97" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2007a</xref>, 
 <xref rid="cow078C98" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">b</xref>, 
 <xref rid="cow078C101" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="cow078C49" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Jacobs 
  <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 1999
 </xref>). Although the late Cenozoic (Mid-Miocene to present) diversification patterns are largely attributable to the ruminant digestive physiology of bovids (
 <xref rid="cow078C54" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Janis 
  <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 1998
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="cow078C20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Clauss 
  <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 2003
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="cow078C53" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Janis, 2007</xref>, 
 <xref rid="cow078C51" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="cow078C19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Clauss and Rössner, 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="cow078C93" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">O'Brien, 2016</xref>), this highly specialized mode of digestion is variably present and cannot solely be responsible for earlier Cenozoic survivorship and diversification patterns. Indeed, it is likely that the influence of selective brain cooling insulated artiodactyls from extensive periods of aridification, whether warming or cooling, that saw declines among non-selective-brain-cooling ungulates (
 <xref rid="cow078C93" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">O'Brien, 2016</xref>). 
</p>
