<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">This study pointed out that the changes of atmospheric CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> concentration and temperature were the main climatic factors affecting CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> fluxes from paddy fields in cold regions. Tokida et al. [
 <xref rid="B53-ijerph-16-00692" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">53</xref>] conducted a two-year experiment in Iwate Prefecture, Japan (39°38′ N). The effects of increasing atmospheric CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> concentration (background concentration +200 ppm) and soil temperature (background temperature +2 °C) on CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> emissions from paddy fields were studied. This was similar to the atmospheric CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> concentration at RCP 4.5 and the amplitude of elevated temperature at the end of the simulation in this study. The atmospheric CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> concentration, Tmin, and Tmax in the 2070s stage increased by 1.90 °C, 2.17 °C, and 172 ppm, respectively (
 <xref rid="ijerph-16-00692-t003" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 3</xref>). His results showed that increasing atmospheric CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> concentrations, soil temperatures, and their combination increased CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> fluxes by 26%, 44%, and 88%, respectively, which were larger values than the increase of 13.74%, 16.31%, and 32.78% in scenarios two, three, and four in this study under RCP 4.5, respectively. The climate conditions in his experimental area were similar to those in this study, but the latitude was lower than that in this study area. Higher temperatures are more conducive to CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> fluxes. In his study, soil and surface water were heated directly to increase temperature, which is different from the temperature increase effect of 60 years that was used in this study. Under actual global warming conditions, soil temperature increases gradually, and SOC decreases gradually without the artificial addition of carbon sources. However, the initial soil condition of each treatment in his study was the same; therefore, the CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> fluxes might be overestimated. In addition, although the temperature of the soil increased the biomass of the aboveground part, it accelerated the senescence of the root system, and reduced the biomass of the root system by 8%. This may provide more substrates for the production of CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub>. Due to the heating method, the mid-season drainage was also not set in his experiment, which further overestimated CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> fluxes. Tokida’s results and previous studies also pointed out that increasing CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> concentration increased the plant biomass, while CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> fluxes were positively correlated with both, and increased CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> fluxes. Van et al. [
 <xref rid="B3-ijerph-16-00692" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>] pointed out through a meta-analysis that the increase of CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> concentration (range 463 to 780 ppm) resulted in an increase of 43.4% in CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> fluxes from paddy fields. The results of this study are similar to those of previous studies. Kazumori et al. [
 <xref rid="B27-ijerph-16-00692" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>] used an improved DNDC-Rice model to analyze the effects of RCP 4.5 on SOC content in a 30-cm soil layer, the biomass of the aboveground part, and the CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> fluxes in double-cropping paddy fields in Suphan Buri, Thailand, from 2000 to 2060. The results showed that increasing atmospheric CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> concentration alone could increase soil SOC content, biomass, and CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> fluxes, which were the same as the results of this study. However, in his study, the increase of temperature did not improve the soil SOC content and the biomass of the aboveground parts, which was different from the results of this study. It may be that the tropical climate of Thailand is more conducive to the decomposition of soil SOC. Meanwhile, the soil in this study is frozen or thawed for most of the time except for the crop-growing season, which is conducive to the accumulation of soil SOC. Furthermore, a high temperature will produce temperature stress on rice plants, which is not conducive to crop growth, leading to a decline in the biomass above ground. Neither this study nor Kazumori’s studies considered the effects of crop varieties on CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> fluxes. The study results showed that the rice cropping system in Heilongjiang Province has shown its adaptability to climate change, and the planting boundary tends to expand northward [
 <xref rid="B26-ijerph-16-00692" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>]. Later-maturing varieties gradually replace early-maturing varieties, which will inevitably increase the biomass of the aboveground parts and roots of rice, and increase the plant litter, stubble incorporated and the root exudates of rice plants. As DNDC sets the biomass and yield response with the increase of atmospheric CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> concentration but not with the increase of temperature, the simulation results of CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> fluxes in this study may be larger for historical periods, but smaller for future periods, resulting in the overall low climatic tendency for CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> fluxes. Due to the climate, soil, and crop differences, the CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> flux response on atmospheric CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> concentration and temperature across different regions is not consistent.
</p>
