<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2b" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study Species and Individual Identification</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The study species were those belonging to the tree-gleaning guild of the mountainous forests of central Spain that have omnivorous diets 
  <a rid="pone.0068448-Perrins1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0068448-Perrins1">[22]</a>: 
  <span class="italic">Cyanistes caeruleus</span> (Blue Tit, 10–12 g, own data), 
  <span class="italic">Lophophanes cristatus</span> (Crested Tit, 10–12 g), 
  <span class="italic">Sitta europaea</span> (Nuthatch, 23–25 g), 
  <span class="italic">Parus major</span> (Great Tit, 18–20 g) and 
  <span class="italic">Periparus ater</span> (Coal Tit, 9–10 g). These small-sized species mainly forage in the foliage, twigs and branches of trees, although they can also use the forest floor or trunks as foraging substrates (especially the Nuthatch, the Great Tit and the Crested Tit; 
  <a rid="pone.0068448-Carrascal3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0068448-Carrascal3">[23]</a>). In addition, they are regular exploiters of artificial feeders in the study region (e.g., 
  <a rid="pone.0068448-Carrascal1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0068448-Carrascal1">[6]</a>). Potential predators of small birds in the study area are the Sparrowhawk (
  <span class="italic">Accipiter nisus</span>) and the Tawny Owl (
  <span class="italic">Strix aluco</span>), although we did not see any of them during the marking or the sampling period. However, predation risk may be higher around feeders than elsewhere if predators are attracted there because of a higher abundance of prey. Birds typically react to predator presence by fleeing to the nearest vegetation cover (see 
  <a rid="pone.0068448-Carrascal1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0068448-Carrascal1">[6]</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0068448-Mozetich1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0068448-Mozetich1">[24]</a> for more details on previous study in the same field station).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to trap birds for individual identification, five rectangular funnel traps (40×40×60 cm) were placed all around the study area, 50–100 m apart and hanging from branches 1.5 m above the ground, from 1 December 2010 to 20 January 2011. This kind of trap is especially efficient at capturing tit species and can be used under adverse weather conditions 
  <a rid="pone.0068448-Senar1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0068448-Senar1">[25]</a>. Funnel traps were permanently baited with two cylindrical feeders, hanging from the trap roof, which contained husked peanuts. A translucent plastic sheet covered the roof of the traps to prevent birds from getting wet on rainy or snowy days. The escape doors of the traps remained opened on non-capture days, so birds could use the peanuts as a supplementary food source, but they were closed during the capture days from dawn to dusk. Trapping was conducted on 13 days from 8:30 to 17:30 hours GMT. On capture days, traps were inspected every 30–45 min. Captured birds were given unique color rings and released as quickly as possible after manipulation (handling time: 2–10 min). The Spanish agency in charge of environmental policy and animal welfare of Madrid (Consejería de Medio Ambiente, Comunidad de Madrid) approved the capture and study of birds (permit number 10/479348.9/10).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We marked a total of 60 individuals: 10 nuthatches, 17 great tits, 12 blue tits, 12 crested tits and 11 coal tits. Birds were recaptured an average of 6.45 times. Recaptures become steadily more frequent along the capture period, until reaching almost 100% of total captures in the five studied species.</p>
</sec>
