<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Wheat yields increased significantly when PD was set to earlier than the baseline scenario at Swift Current under RCP8.5 scenarios. At this location, Bootsma and De Jong [
 <xref rid="pone.0207370.ref062" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">62</xref>] estimated the ideal seeding date of spring wheat using selected environmental criteria including (a) snow cover&lt;10 mm for the day; (b) Daily precipitation&lt;2.5 mm; (c) 0.75Tmax+0.25Tmin&gt;7°C; (d) The SW1 (soil water at the top 5% of the soil profile) &lt; 90% Available Water Holding Capacity (AWHC); (e) SW2 (soil water at the next 7.5% of the profile) &lt; 0.95 AWHC. The study concluded that the wheat seeding date can be 10 to 15 days earlier than the current planting date at Swift Current. Gan et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0207370.ref063" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">63</xref>] used a 4-year seeding date trial to determine that seeding 10 to 12 days earlier than baseline could increase grain yields of spring wheat near Swift Current. At Woodslee, late planting of maize in the baseline scenario had a negative effect on maize yield because maize cannot reach maturity with a reduced number of growing degree days and insufficient heat units. However, for future climate conditions, higher temperature can ensure that maize will get enough heat to mature. In addition, early planting under future climate scenarios could result in water stress for maize since the precipitation would on average, decrease significantly and the temperature would increase by 4°C in July compared to the baseline scenario. In contrast, delayed planting would be beneficial to maize growth in the critical growth stage because of the increased precipitation in August. In addition, soil nitrate leaching significantly increased when the PD was delayed for the baseline scenario due to low crop N removal, but it did not have a significant impact on nitrate leaching under future climate conditions. Our results were in agreement with Wang et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0207370.ref020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>], who reported that maize yields would increase from delayed planting dates under future climate scenarios in Iowa (similar climate to southwestern Ontario). In contrast, Babel and Turyatunga [
 <xref rid="pone.0207370.ref064" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">64</xref>] illustrated that the maximum maize yields could be obtained by early planting under SRES scenarios, which could be attributed to the differences in local climate patterns (e.g. distributions of precipitation), crop management practices (e.g. tillage, fertilizer, cultivars), and IPCC scenarios (e.g. SRES, RCPs).
</p>
