<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In terms of current effectiveness of PAs based on SDM, our results are in accordance with those from recently analysed Brazilian protected areas [
 <xref rid="pone.0215229.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0215229.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. Here, we also provide an evaluation of future effectiveness of the currently established PAs for avian assemblages in SE Amazonia. Our SDMs project a significant loss of species considering future warming climate scenarios in the focal area, and this is even worse considering each PA apart, in which species loss can reach 100% (e.g., Frugivores in IL Guajajara, RCP 6.0 and 8.5). In fact, considering future effectiveness based only on the differentiation between current and future mean temperatures, it was estimated that approximately 19–67% of all current protected areas in Brazil will potentially not have similar temperature regimes in the future [
 <xref rid="pone.0215229.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. In addition, the frugivores are the trophic guild class that shows the strongest loss (ranging between 5–100% species loss, in Carajás Mosaic, RCP 2.6, 2050, and IL Guajajara, RCP 6.0, 2050, respectively), and other studies have already suggested this guild is more extinction-prone [
 <xref rid="pone.0215229.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. Frugivores play a key role in providing seed dispersal services [
 <xref rid="pone.0215229.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>], mainly in tropical rainforests (70–94% of woody plants [
 <xref rid="pone.0215229.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>]). Additionally, studies have demonstrated that species may not vanish from the ecosystem, but large population declines are sufficient to diminish the amount and quality of seed dispersal to such an extent that plant recruitment is no longer feasible, triggering negative feedback impacts on plant populations, community dynamics and hence ecosystem functions [
 <xref rid="pone.0215229.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0215229.ref064" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>]. Proportionally, our analysis shows that insectivores constitute the second most sensitive guild, despite including more species loss than any other group in absolute terms (between 4–74% species loss, in Terra do Meio Mosaic, RCP 2.6, 2050, and ESEC Rio Ronuro, RCP 8.5, 2050, respectively). Regardless of the low number of studies that have been conducted, the importance of insectivorous birds in reducing plant damage from herbivory has been demonstrated in Neotropical forest canopies [
 <xref rid="pone.0215229.ref065" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>]. Although less sensitive than other guilds, nectarivores could potentially lose up to 60% of their current projected diversity (e.g., IL Kayabi and Rikbaktsá, RCP 8.5, 2050). A recent estimation found that &gt;90% of angiosperm species in tropical communities are animal pollinated [
 <xref rid="pone.0215229.ref066" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>] and over 111 avian species pollinate plants in Brazil (effectively or potentially), but their importance in pollination is not well documented [
 <xref rid="pone.0215229.ref067" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>]. The possible impact of climate change on reducing bird-pollination services is unknown and could include decrease in gene flow among plants, as well in fruit and seed set [
 <xref rid="pone.0215229.ref068" ref-type="bibr">68</xref>]. Using knowledge of biological interactions coupled with current and expected future climate conditions is a key strategy to improve the efficiency of conservation plans in terms of restoration and strengthening landscape connectivity [
 <xref rid="pone.0215229.ref069" ref-type="bibr">69</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0215229.ref070" ref-type="bibr">70</xref>]. Notwithstanding, as noted previously, such information need to be more deep- and locally accessed to better evaluate the consequences for other communities of species that interact with avian species. Moreover, the species losses mentioned above did not consider species turnover (i.e., the amount of arriving species), and when it was considered, the SR in each PA did not change substantially. At first glance, this could be considered resilience if it is interpreted as a community response to perturbation, but a large part of this turnover was due to generalists. Several questions remain unanswered about "functional homogenization" in terms of if generalists represent a new degraded state, a transition that will return to the initial equilibrium, or a transition to a novel ecosystem; regardless, generalists invariably affect functioning and productivity, reducing resistance and resilience (see [
 <xref rid="pone.0215229.ref071" ref-type="bibr">71</xref>] for a review).
</p>
