<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Strong relationships have been found between above ground tissue and δ
 <sup>13</sup>C
 <sub>atm</sub> values (
 <italic>p</italic> &lt; 0.001; 
 <xref rid="ref-47" ref-type="bibr">Jahren, Arens &amp; Harbenson, 2008</xref>; 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-5">Fig. 5</xref>), and this study provides a higher resolution look at the relationship between δ
 <sup>13</sup>C
 <sub>leaf</sub> and δ
 <sup>13</sup>C
 <sub>atm</sub> in a long-lived species within a natural system. In this initial natural experiment, the δ
 <sup>13</sup>C
 <sub>leaf</sub> of 
 <italic>T. occidentalis</italic> tracked changes in δ
 <sup>13</sup>C
 <sub>atm</sub> (
 <italic>R</italic>
 <sup>2</sup> = 0.74, 
 <italic>p</italic>-value &lt; 0.0001), mostly unencumbered by other climate factors. The slope for the linear relationship between δ
 <sup>13</sup>C
 <sub>leaf</sub> and δ
 <sup>13</sup>C
 <sub>atm</sub> is close to, but not exactly, 1, likely because the rate of change for δ
 <sup>13</sup>C
 <sub>atm</sub> has not been linear, and acceleration in the change of δ
 <sup>13</sup>C
 <sub>atm</sub> may not have been recorded immediately. Additionally, while there is no statistically significant relationship between any of the climate variables we tested and Δ
 <sub>leaf</sub>, it is unlikely that climate variables, especially in aggregate, play no role in carbon isotope discrimination within this species. Because δ
 <sup>13</sup>C
 <sub>leaf</sub> showed a strong coefficient of determination with δ
 <sup>13</sup>C
 <sub>atm</sub>, and no climate variables showed significant relationships with Δ
 <sub>leaf</sub> values, we can assume that δ
 <sup>13</sup>C
 <sub>leaf</sub> values of modern 
 <italic>T. occidentalis</italic> are strongly affected by δ
 <sup>13</sup>C
 <sub>atm</sub> values. Additional work must be done to evaluate error in paleo uses of δ
 <sup>13</sup>C
 <sub>leaf</sub> values of 
 <italic>T. occidentalis</italic>, and future experiments should recreate more geologically reasonable conditions and climate changes (independent of anthropogenic factors). The relationship between δ
 <sup>13</sup>C
 <sub>leaf</sub> and δ
 <sup>13</sup>C
 <sub>atm</sub> values has implications for paleoclimate reconstructions of δ
 <sup>13</sup>C
 <sub>atm</sub> as well as reconstructions of [CO
 <sub>2</sub>] (
 <xref rid="ref-18" ref-type="bibr">Cerling et al., 1991</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-35" ref-type="bibr">Franks et al., 2014</xref>). We emphasize how important it is to identify the value of δ
 <sup>13</sup>C
 <sub>atm</sub>, such as in 
 <xref rid="ref-94" ref-type="bibr">Tipple, Meyers &amp; Pagani (2010)</xref> study, rather than just using the Pre-Industrial value of −6.5‰ (
 <xref rid="ref-18" ref-type="bibr">Cerling et al., 1991</xref>) because the δ
 <sup>13</sup>C
 <sub>atm</sub> value has such a dramatic effect on the terrestrial part of the carbon cycle.
</p>
