<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par13" class="p">In addition, we acknowledge that there are limitations in the analyzing approach. First, the period 1971–2000 was chosen as the present-day period. Hence, our results could be dependent on the reference period chosen for analyses. Second, it is commonly accepted that drought is a multi-scalar phenomenon
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" class="xref">58</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" class="xref">59</xref>
 </sup>. The time scale over which water deficits accumulate is also important
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">11</xref>
 </sup>. Therefore, droughts identified by the three indices would depend on the fitting function and time scales selected in this study. The longer time scale SPI, SSI and SRI would be very similar due to the high correlation among precipitation, soil moisture and runoff. Whereas climate-based indices such as SPI describe the precipitation anomalies, we emphasize the importance to use hydrologic indices to describe the effects of climate anomalies on hydrologic conditions which are governed by land surface physical processes. However, only one impact model (i.e., VIC) is used in deriving agricultural and hydrological conditions. 
 <italic class="italic">Van Huijgevoort et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" class="xref">32</xref>
 </sup> found that the spread of simulated hydrological drought among ten hydrological models is largest in regions with low runoff and smallest in regions with high runoff. Fourth, we focus on the changes of drought at the decade scale, ignoring the seasonality of drought which would change disproportionately, especially in snow dominated regions. Indeed, warmer temperatures tend to reduce snow cover through melting of the existing pack and increasing of the rainfall fraction to snowfall. Fifth, drought index has to rely on an assumption that samples follow a given probability density function. However, there is no single probability density function which is suitable for the whole world. In US, there are about 12% of sub-basins where the selected drought index can’t be fitted by the selected lognormal probability density function (Supplementary Figure 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S4</xref>). Therefore, caution should be exercised when interpreting the drought changes in these regions. Indeed, to fit one type of probability density across US characterized with distinct hydro-climatic regimes is difficult. This is one of the major challenges facing drought assessments as pointed out in our previous efforts on non-parametric drought index development
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" class="xref">59</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" class="xref">60</xref>
 </sup>. To focus on drought index is not within the scope of this study. Rather, we aim to provide an up-to-date comprehensive investigation of droughts of various types for the US domain. In addition, a drought event is defined when the drought index value is below -1 (corresponding to 6.7% of probability). Therefore, we have to acknowledge that the results may vary if a different drought threshold is used. Overall, although the revealed frequency-duration-intensity relations are dependent on the case study, impact model, drought index and drought threshold, and the model spread as quantified by the standard deviation is fairly large, it helps understand how regional drought of various types and its probabilistic distribution respond to various level of global warming amount.
</p>
