<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par12" class="p">Third, in the absence of restoration, enhanced CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> emissions in an impounded and freshened wetland can be expected to continue indefinitely, due to a continuous supply of new organic matter substrate for methanogenesis from ongoing primary production
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" class="xref">35</xref>
 </sup>. Thus, although CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> is considered to be a short-lived climate pollutant, with an atmospheric perturbation lifetime of only 12.4 years, restoration can avoid a long-term, sustained emission, and the cumulative mass of avoided CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> and magnitude of climatic cooling will continue to increase indefinitely through time (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" class="xref">4d</xref>). In contrast, although avoidance of CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> emissions by tidal restoration in drained salt marshes can have an RF in the first few decades that is as great as avoided CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> in freshened marshes, the duration and ultimate cumulative magnitude of enhanced CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> emissions in a drained wetland is limited by the mass of the C stock contained in soil above the level of drainage. Therefore, where wetlands have been drained for decades to centuries, the benefit of restoration may be relatively minor (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" class="xref">4b</xref> emission factor 1). Where pre-restoration CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> respiration is rapid, re-wetting will be of substantial benefit (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" class="xref">4b</xref> emission factor 2), but the anticipated duration of that benefit will be uncertain (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" class="xref">4e</xref>). Based on IPCC Tier 1 marsh soil C stocks and respiration rates in drained marshes, the stock in the top meter of soil would be consumed within approximately 3 decades following drainage
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">18</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
