<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par13" class="p">A fourth critical feature of wetland tidal restoration as a climate change intervention is that the CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> emissions thus avoided will have what can be referred to as “inherent permanence”: following tidal restoration and onset of reduced methane emissions, the emissions thus avoided cannot be cancelled, even if emissions were to resume in the future due to a change in ecosystem status. For instance, if a tidal restriction were re-established 30 years after restoration, emissions would resume, but the biosphere and atmosphere would maintain for extended time a deficit of heat and of GHG equivalent to 30 years of reduced emissions. Further, since GHG emissions from tidally-restricted wetlands are caused by human activity, they are anthropogenic emissions, and reducing anthropogenic wetland emissions will have an effect on climate that is equivalent to reduced emission of an equal quantity of fossil fuel GHG. Therefore, avoiding CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> emissions as a landuse-based climate change intervention is a distinct concept from biological C sequestration projects to enhance C storage in forest or wetland biomass or soil. Biological C sequestration accumulates climate benefit at a relatively slow rate, and the C sink must persist for a century or more to have significant impact on climate (see Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" class="xref">4f</xref>, new salt marsh example). During that time, there is a risk that the stored C will be rapidly returned to the atmosphere, through processes such as fire or ecosystem degradation and organic matter decomposition. As a result, the monetary and climate change mitigation value of biological C sequestration projects must be discounted in C markets and in trading programs to account for the “non-permanence risk” that stored C will be returned to the atmosphere
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" class="xref">36</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" class="xref">37</xref>
 </sup>. To be clear, this discussion is not intended to suggest that temporary reductions in CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> emissions will achieve effective management of climate change, but rather to highlight a distinction between avoided emissions and C sequestration.
</p>
