<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The protected area management plans evaluated in our study differed enormously in their quality and contents (and assumingly in their function in actual management). Nolte et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0185972.ref037" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>] found management planning to be one of the weak elements with regard to protected area management effectiveness. The present study does not account for unofficial or non-published internal management documents which might in fact play an important role with regard to climate change adaptation efforts [
 <xref rid="pone.0185972.ref029" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0185972.ref074" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">74</xref>]. For instance, the management framework 
 <italic class="italic">(Rahmenkonzept)</italic> of Schaalsee Biosphere Reserve was published in 2003 [
 <xref rid="pone.0185972.ref083" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">83</xref>] and remains the official guiding document. Climate change is only scarcely considered in this document. Since 2007 the BR has engaged very actively in climate change mitigation and adaptation with several projects, cooperative partnerships and studies (e.g., [
 <xref rid="pone.0185972.ref084" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">84</xref>]) which are mainly presented on the website of the BR [
 <xref rid="pone.0185972.ref085" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">85</xref>]. At the same time, it is questionable in how far the contents of even well-composed management plans find actual implementation. Judging from our experience, we would argue that an evaluation of actual management performance and effectiveness might produce even lower climate change-robustness scores. In many cases, in Germany, Natura 2000 sites have assigned neither staff exclusively in charge nor regular resources for implementation. Often the areas are very small and do not have appropriate buffer zones. Due to the lack of demarcation they are often not even recognizable for visitors or land users. There is a clear risk that management plans might not actually be used as the basic and guiding instruments for management. The low values of climate change-robustness might represent the tip of an iceberg of management deficiencies. If management plans constitute a key element of adaptation to climate change, their quality, functional role, preparation and implementation need to be improved.
</p>
