<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Prior to assessing isolation by landscape resistance (IBR), we evaluated fine‐scale spatial genetic structure by quantifying spatial autocorrelation in genetic relatedness. To do so, we used local polynomial fitting (LOESS) of pairwise relatedness to pairwise geographic distance (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/rojaff/Lplot" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://github.com/rojaff/Lplot</ext-link>; Bruno, Macchiavelli, &amp; Balzarini, 
 <xref rid="eva12794-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>). Yang's relatedness between pairs of individuals (Yang et al., 
 <xref rid="eva12794-bib-0086" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>) was used, since similar measures of relatedness have been found to be highly accurate as individual‐based genetic distance metrics for landscape genetic studies (Shirk, Landguth, &amp; Cushman, 
 <xref rid="eva12794-bib-0073" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>). We then evaluated the contribution of habitat amount, elevation, terrain roughness, temperature, and precipitation in explaining patterns of gene flow (Balkenhol et al., 
 <xref rid="eva12794-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). We created a first resistance surface using the reclassified land cover/land use map for 2013 described above, attributing low resistance (0.1) to habitat pixels and high resistance (0.9) to nonhabitat pixels. This allowed us to test whether gene flow is enhanced by natural habitats or hindered by habitat‐deployed environments (Jaffé, Castilla, et al., 
 <xref rid="eva12794-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). A second resistance surface was then created using an inverted forest cover map from the University of Maryland (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://earthenginepartners.appspot.com/science-2013-global-forest/download.html" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://earthenginepartners.appspot.com/science-2013-global-forest/download.html</ext-link>), to test for higher gene flow across forested areas. To test for a reduced gene flow across highlands and corrugated terrains, we created elevation and terrain roughness surfaces, using raw elevation and terrain roughness maps. While elevation was retrieved from WorldClim (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.worldclim.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.worldclim.org/</ext-link>), terrain roughness was created from this elevation layer using the Terrain Analysis plug‐in in QGIS V2.14. To evaluate resistance due to environmental conditions, we created three additional resistance surfaces containing the raw values from those WorldClim bioclimatic variables explaining most variation across our study region (mean temperature of coldest quarter, temperature annual range, and precipitation of driest quarter; see details below). We thereby tested for reduced gene flow across areas with higher temperatures, higher temperature range, and higher precipitation. To assess isolation by geographic distance (IBD), we created a last resistance surface replacing all pixel values in our elevation map with 0.5. Using the program Circuitscape V4.0 (McRae, 
 <xref rid="eva12794-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>), we then calculated pairwise resistance distances between all samples, employing all the resistance surfaces described above. Due to Circuitscape's computing limitations, all rasters were cropped to the extent of sample locations plus a buffer area of one decimal degree to minimize border effects (Jaffé, Castilla, et al., 
 <xref rid="eva12794-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>), and all pixels containing zero values were replaced with 0.001.
</p>
