<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We also present a sample application of the state‐dependent management framework, using a single set of inputs to eqns 
 <xref rid="jpe12864-disp-0001" ref-type="disp-formula" class="xref">1</xref> and 
 <xref rid="jpe12864-disp-0002" ref-type="disp-formula" class="xref">2</xref>, to evaluate its performance under a wide range of conditions including declining 
 <italic class="italic">K</italic>. The key outcome for this application was Δ
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>
 <sub class="sub">extirpation</sub>, the incremental change in the probability of extirpation (i.e. 1−
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>
 <sub class="sub">persist</sub>) for identical projections with and without harvest. Projections were performed for all combinations of the following inputs: 
 <list list-type="order" id="jpe12864-list-0003" class="list">
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">Four hundred sets of vital rates representing a plausible parameter space that encompasses estimates of vital rates from case studies for polar bears (Table 
    <xref rid="jpe12864-sup-0003" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S1</xref>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">Three rates of change in the proxy for 
    <italic class="italic">K</italic>: (i) no temporal trend (i.e. stable carrying capacity), (ii) −7% per decade, approximately the mean trend in the proxy for 
    <italic class="italic">K</italic> as estimated from sea‐ice data for the CS and SB regions; and (iii) −14% per decade.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">Two approaches to harvest: (i) no harvest; and (ii) harvest using 
    <italic class="italic">F</italic>
    <sub class="sub">O</sub> = 0·75, 
    <italic class="italic">SR</italic> = 2, and 
    <math id="nlm-math-11" class="math">
     <mover accent="true" class="mover">
      <mi class="mi">N</mi>
      <mo stretchy="false" class="mo">~</mo>
     </mover>
    </math> selected as the 15th percentile of the sampling distribution for 
    <italic class="italic">N</italic>, with a data precision level of 3. These inputs to the state‐dependent management framework correspond broadly to the historic standard 4·5% harvest rate for polar bears (Taylor 
    <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. 1987) when applied to the mean vital rates from case studies.
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
