<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion and conclusion</div>
 <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Using corpus linguistic methods, textual data show that, except for the indirect link between climate change and maritime security via migration/displacement, the IMO narrative does not encapsulate the interlinkages between climate change and maritime security. Despite having interests and responsibility in offering solutions to tackle both climate change and maritime security, the IMO does not seem to narratively represent the two issues (and the impacts of the two issues) as something linked or something that could potentially be linked, except indirectly in the case of climate change-induced migration. It is worth noting that findings might be limited by the following methodological constraint: the span of ± 5 (chosen in order to stay within typical linguistic structures and to reduce noise) does not take into account a potential narrative between climate change and maritime security that might be developed across entire paragraphs.</p>
 <p id="Par28" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This reveals the need to start serious discussions with the help of both natural scientists and social/political scientists in a bid to initiate a reflexion on the existence of links and dependencies between the two issues. The existing literature has shown that the impacts of climate change on natural systems, such as a loss, or change in, marine biodiversity, can then reverberate on human, social and political systems, via economic slow-down, food insecurity, natural disasters, extreme weather events, forced displacements, vulnerability of coastal populations as well as the synergistic impacts of these processes. This can in turn increase the incentive to engage in maritime criminal activities (e.g. illegal fishing, piracy, human smuggling) as well as increase the risk of illegal immigration (e.g. Allison et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2009</a>; Cinner et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">2012</a>; Cordner 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">2010</a>; Jasparro 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">2009</a>; Jasparro and Taylor 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">2008</a>; Kaye 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">2012</a>; Mazaris and Germond 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">2018</a>; Perch-Nielsen et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">2008</a>; Pomeroy et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">2016</a>; Rahman 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">2012</a>; Rahman and Tsamenyi 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">2010</a>; Suárez de Vivero and Mateos 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">2017</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">So long as actors tasked to tackle climate change concentrate on mitigation and adaptation (something that the IMO narrative seems to put forward), and so long as they do not include a reflexion on the impacts of damaged or threatened natural systems not only on food security, income and living conditions but also on the occurrence of (maritime) criminality, an important element of the puzzle will be missed. Our analysis has shown that this lack of interlinkages in narrative may be due to the very conceptualisation of climate change on the one hand and of maritime security on the other hand. In both cases, textual data shows that the vocabulary employed to conceptualise the two issues is very technical, ranging from institutional processes and frameworks, to policy requirements and settings, to generic calls for action and coordination. The specific framing of climate change within institutional processes and policy settings rather than a cause/consequence process involving issues at the societal level, whereas maritime security is conceptualised as a series of illegal practices that must be tackled, certainly explains the current lack of narrative linking the two issues. The origin of this technicality can be traced back to the IMO’s traditional role which is to improve the safety of the maritime shipping industry. In this organisational context, climate change and maritime security issues are likely to be associated to threats to maritime shipping, hence the problem-solving/technical approach of the IMO consisting in setting up rules, regulations, guidelines and agenda as well as promoting multilateral responses to transnational threats. This also seems to fit with the “technocratic and industry-oriented” nature of the IMO secretariat discussed by Campe (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">2009</a>: 144).
 </p>
 <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our findings have practical implications for both academics and practitioners. This article reveals the need for academics to find ways to conceptualise these dependencies between climate change and maritime security and to quantify the synergistic links between the two issues. It is crucial to work on better integrating indicators reflecting ecological risk (e.g. extreme weather events, loss of biodiversity, velocity of climate change), social vulnerability (e.g. capacity to adapt), exposure to impacts (e.g. localization on the global grid), economic consequences of climate change as well as maritime criminality indexes. Practitioners will benefit from such scientific advances, but they are also invited to move beyond an institutional processes/policy setting narrative so as to further account for the interlinkages between climate change and maritime security. Linking maritime security and climate change parallels the move from a problem-solving approach to one that deals with the underlying causes of maritime criminality, of which climate change is but one. This would help pushing forward the climate change-maritime security nexus agenda forward, which would eventually improve current ocean governance practices.</p>
</sec>
