<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We built the plant phylogeny encompassing 244 species using phylomatic, which combines taxonomic information with a backbone tree to obtain the phylogeny of a given set of plant species (figs. S1 and S2) (
 <xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>45</italic>
 </xref>). We used their conservative tree with relations up to the family level and pseudobranch lengths in million years and resolved relationships within Asteraceae encompassing 56 species following (
 <xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>46</italic>
 </xref>). Species in multiple networks were included as soft polytomies in analyses because they exhibit multiple estimates of extinction and coextinction probabilities (276 tip data). We then estimated the phylogenetic signal of categorical functional traits with a function designed ad hoc by one of us (E.L. Rezende, 
 <italic>phylo.signal.disc</italic>). This function randomizes the tip data and compares the minimum number of character state changes inferred with parsimony with a null model (
 <xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>47</italic>
 </xref>). An equivalent phylogeny comprising 1122 tip data was built for the pollinators combining phylogenetic and taxonomic information. Briefly, a backbone phylogeny of insect orders was built on the basis of the relationships described in two large-scale analyses (
 <xref rid="R48" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>48</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R49" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>49</italic>
 </xref>). Then, relationships between families within each order were resolved on the basis of different sources: Coleoptera (
 <xref rid="R50" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>50</italic>
 </xref>), Lepidotpera (
 <xref rid="R51" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>51</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R52" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>52</italic>
 </xref>), Hemiptera (
 <xref rid="R53" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>53</italic>
 </xref>), Hymenoptera (
 <xref rid="R54" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>54</italic>
 </xref>), and Diptera (
 <xref rid="R55" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>55</italic>
 </xref>).
</p>
