<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec019" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fishermen respond to the reproductive timing of the fished species</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It may be common knowledge that fishermen respond to the demographic timing of the fished species, in particular reproductive timing. However, we have quantified how a simple reproductive metric (GSI) can be used to predict industry metrics, which can in turn be useful for management strategy evaluation and planning.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fishermen respond to red sea urchin reproductive variability due to differences in roe quality and price. During, the beginning of the spawning season (November through December) prices are still relatively high but then they drop rapidly as spawning continues (January through April). Our results indicate that red sea urchins are more valuable in the western channel, especially during peak GSI in the fall. Consistent with this pattern, fishermen harvest more in western locations than eastern locations, especially during this period (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0196864.g004" href="#pone.0196864.g004">Fig 4</a>; 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="pone.0196864.t003" href="#pone.0196864.t003">Table 3</a>; [
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref035">35</a>]). By contrast, during the trough of the reproductive season, GSI showed the opposite spatial pattern–lower in the west than in the east (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0196864.g002" href="#pone.0196864.g002">Fig 2</a> and Figure A in 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0196864.s002" href="#pone.0196864.s002">S2 Appendix</a>). During the trough of the reproductive season, fishermen still fished more in the west subregion, but the regional differences in fishing effort and landings were not nearly as pronounced during this time of year (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="pone.0196864.t003" href="#pone.0196864.t003">Table 3</a>). There were no significant differences in effort and landings between the central and east subregions (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="pone.0196864.t003" href="#pone.0196864.t003">Table 3</a>). Fishermen likely do not more aggressively switch to harvesting more sea urchins in the east during the period of low GSI because of the higher abundance of larger and potentially more valuable urchins in the western regions [
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref036">36</a>]. In addition, an interesting pattern surfaced opposing our prediction that effort would steadily increase tracking the gonad growth after the annual low point (in April); by June effort in the western region increased higher than expected and this happens to be the month when effort restrictions are in place. We suspect this pattern is partially due to the more favorable summer weather after spring winds have subsided allowing for a greater number of days fished—especially in this more exposed western region. Also, during this time the gonad quality is high, so fishermen likely are “racing” to collect as many urchins as possible before their fellow fishermen do, especially since in recent years this period coincides with heavy domestic demand (D. Rudie, pers. obs.).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When we examined the most heavily fished subregion, the west, we found that high temporal variation in the quality of a fished resource drove predictable seasonal patterns of fishing. We found that quality, total effort, total landings, mean price, and total value in sea urchins harvested from the Channel Islands are highly predictable based on the reproductive cycle, measured here as GSI. These fishery metrics and GSI during our sampling period (2009–2011) were significantly and strongly related (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0196864.g005" href="#pone.0196864.g005">Fig 5</a>). In addition, we used these GSI data to predict historical metrics of the fishery (1978–2008). These relationships were similar and stronger indicating that the red sea urchin’s reproductive cycle has been a strong driver of the sea urchin industry patterns over those 30 years of the fishery. Our results from southern California corresponded with historical data from northern California showing gonad yield and price to be positively correlated (Figs 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0196864.g003" href="#pone.0196864.g003">3</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0196864.g005" href="#pone.0196864.g005">5</a>; [
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref027" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref027">27</a>]). However, historically the catch in northern California was inversely related to price (data 1985–1994; [
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref027" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref027">27</a>]), which was contrary to our findings. Fishermen may have been somewhat limited by unsafe boating conditions in the winter, when prices tended to be higher in northern California [
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref027" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref027">27</a>], and because of these constraints they fished more during the season of low prices.
 </p>
</sec>
