<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Quality plays an important role in the price of all fish products, especially when the product is served raw. High-grade fresh fish can be worth 4 to 20 times the price of lower-grade fish [
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref001">1</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref002" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref002">2</a>]. The manner in which a fish is caught, handled, and stored affects quality and thus price [
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref003" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref003">3</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref005" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref005">5</a>]. In addition, quality is also often related to a species’ reproductive cycle. For example, in several fisheries (sea urchin, scallop, herring, sturgeon, squid, and salmon) quality peaks before the spawning season [
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref003" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref003">3</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref006" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref006">6</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref010" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref010">10</a>]. Reproductive condition can vary across seasons, years, and regions due to many environmental and ecological factors, such as resource availability and quality, spawning or nursery habitat availability and quality, temperature, climate, and upwelling regime [
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref003" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref003">3</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref011" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref011">11</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref021">21</a>]. Understanding how reproduction in a marine resource varies can not only inform population models but also can provide insight into the value of a fished product.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When a fishery is roe-based and the product is served raw, such as sea urchins, there can be a high variability in quality due to the reproductive state of the organism and thus a high variability in product price [
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref022">22</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref023">23</a>]. In recent decades, hundreds of millions of pounds of red sea urchins have been hand-collected by commercial fishermen diving in California’s coastal waters (California Department of Fish and Wildlife [CDFW] data 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wildlife.ca.gov/Conservation/Marine/Invertebrates/Sea-Urchin" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.wildlife.ca.gov/Conservation/Marine/Invertebrates/Sea-Urchin</span>). This multi-million-dollar industry relies on a consistent, fresh product and is marketed as the sushi product 
  <span class="italic">uni</span> (see 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0196864.s001" href="#pone.0196864.s001">S1 Appendix</a> for more details). The principal sea urchin species exploited in California is the red sea urchin, 
  <span class="italic">Mesocentrotus franciscanus</span> (previously 
  <span class="italic">Strongylocentrotus</span> A. Agassiz, 1863; see [
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref024" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref024">24</a>]). Once sea urchin divers bring their catch to shore, the gonads are typically processed, packaged into boxes, and shipped overnight to buyers.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Knowledge about spatial and temporal variability in sea urchin reproduction has been used to inform management, resulting in seasonal closures that serve to limit harvest during a particular reproductive season. For instance in Japan, Chile, and Baja California, Mexico the sea urchin fisheries are closed during the spawning seasons [
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref025" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref025">25</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref026" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref026">26</a>]. Within Japan and Chile these spawning seasons and thus closure periods vary in timing and duration among regions; in Japan there are up to 14 different management zones for two sea urchin species [
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref026" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref026">26</a>]. Rather than setting fishing limits based on spawning period, the seasonal management scheme in California was modeled after the state of Washington’s fishery, where harvest was closed during the season with low gonad quality. The rationale was that it would be economically advantageous to limit effort during the period of lowest gonad yield and depressed value (P. Kalvass, pers. comm.). The California Department of Fish and Wildlife (CDFW) partially based California’s state-wide seasonal regulations on data from a two-year period of red sea urchin processor gonad and price data from northern California (P. Kalvass, pers. comm.). Statewide in California the limited fishing season, originally set in 1990, was during May through September, and the northern California fishery was also closed in July, the month of lowest gonadosomatic index (GSI; i.e., the ratio of wet gonad weight to wet whole weight) [
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref027" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref027">27</a>]. When these regulations went into place initially, members of the sea urchin fishing industry in southern California agreed with this reduction in fishing days in the summer due to a diminished Japanese demand and to prevent oversupply during this favorable-weather season (D. Rudie, pers. obs.). Managers in California advocated a complete summer closure, when gonad quality, size, and thus prices were considered low. However, managers compromised with members of the industry, who wanted to avoid a long industry closure to keep an active market and skilled labor employed in the processing companies, and instead established seasonal fishing-day limitations (P. Kalvass, pers. comm. and D. Rudie, pers. obs.). Currently across the entire state of California the sea urchin fishery is limited to four days per week from June through October and is open the rest of the year (California Code of Regulations § 120.7, Title 14, 2008 Amendment). It is important to note that limiting effort during the period of depressed value may be ineffective, if effort is already low during this season. Effort limitations could be placed during the time of year when effort is likely to be highest, and in California this is the reproductive season of highest gonad yield and prices.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A key question is whether a single seasonal regulation makes sense for a state with such diverse ecological regions, spanning two marine provinces [
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref028">28</a>]. The majority of the state’s red sea urchin landings originate from the northern Channel Islands area in Southern California, however regulations were based on the reproductive dynamics of sea urchins in Northern California (nearly 800 kilometers away) and may be inappropriate for Southern California. The Port of Fort Bragg in Northern California ranks third for cumulative commercial sea urchin landings since the start of the fishery, accounting for approximately 13% of the state’s landings, however landings originating from the northern Channel Islands region (into the Ports of Santa Barbara and Oxnard, ranking first and second, respectively) account for approximately 47% of the state’s cumulative landings since the start of the fishery (CDFW data). We therefore focused on the fishery within the northern Channel Islands in this study to evaluate seasonal reproductive dynamics and seasonal fishing patterns. Our research investigated three objectives: (1) to evaluate the spatial and seasonal dynamics of the red sea urchin reproductive cycle and its relationship with industry-quality estimates and price; (2) to assess fishing patterns across the regulatory time periods, regions, and seasons; and (3) to quantify how fishermen respond to urchin reproductive dynamics, relating fishing effort, landings, price, and value to spatial and temporal variation in red sea urchin reproductive condition.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the ecological literature, reproductive condition (i.e., a proxy of potential reproductive output) is often measured as gonadosomatic index (GSI) [
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref029">29</a>]. This metric is simple and objective; it can be easily measured in a laboratory, boat, or dock. Furthermore, it is quantitative, as opposed to the qualitative processor grading scale that is typically employed by buyers in the industry. Gonadosomatic index is predictable across the various stages in the reproductive cycle [
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref021">21</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref029">29</a>], so it is a simple way to compare demographics among seasons and locations.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although California sea urchin are fished year round, the price differential paid for sea urchin roe across varying reproductive stages can be substantial [
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref022">22</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref027" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref027">27</a>], which creates a strong incentive for selectively harvesting in the best locations and at the best times during the year. Urchins increase in gonad size due to the growth of nutritive phagocytes (NPs) [
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref022">22</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref030">30</a>], for red sea urchins this occurs during the summer as they consume abundant drift kelp. Then these NPs support the growth and development of the germ cells (GCs) just before and during the spawning season [
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref022">22</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref030">30</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref031" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref031">31</a>]. Typically, urchins spawn just after they reach their peak in gonad size. The reproductive “ripeness,” or fully mature gonads at the end of gametogenesis, occurs during the spawning season when most of the nutritive phagocytes have shrunken [
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref022">22</a>]. This is the season when sushi quality declines as GSI declines. Spawning generally indicates lower quality to processors, since most consumers do not like the grainy, watery texture of spawning gonads [
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref022">22</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref032" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref032">32</a>]. The gonad reaches its maximum size (highest GSI) just before spawning begins and subsequently shrinks as more gametes are released [
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref017" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref017">17</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref022">22</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref033">33</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref034">34</a>]. Once a sea urchin has fully spawned, the gonad is not as sweet and is smaller (with the lowest GSI) but has a firmer texture, which is preferred by the industry due to the more lasting quality of the product, or “shelf life” (D. Rudie, pers. obs.). In this study, we investigate whether GSI can also be an effective indicator of gonad quality, and thus the quality component of price. Although price may reflect the seasonal supply and demand, the grade of a sea urchin has a large influence on its price. When grading the quality of sea urchin for sushi, processors consider size and several qualitative measures, such as taste, shape, color, texture, and firmness (see 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0196864.s001" href="#pone.0196864.s001">S1 Appendix</a> for more details on sushi grades; [
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref022">22</a>]). If GSI is a good proxy for the industry’s quality metric, it can be used as a quantitative measure to predict the potential seasonal value of sea urchins.
 </p>
</sec>
