<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec018" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Potential drivers of red sea urchin reproduction and quality</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As in many species, these seasonal patterns of reproduction may be driven by seasonal patterns in resource abundance or quality for adults or larval stages [
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref032" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref032">32</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref034">34</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref044">44</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref046" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref046">46</a>]. Previous studies have shown that food availability and quality for adult sea urchins influences gonad quality [
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref047" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref047">47</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref049" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref049">49</a>]. In the spring months, kelp begins to recover from winter storm disturbance [
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref050" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref050">50</a>], which is synchronous with the increase in red sea urchin allocation to reproductive growth. There is high inter-annual variability in kelp canopy biomass, but it generally peaks at SMI, SRI and SCI around June through August [
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref050" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref050">50</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref051" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref051">51</a>] during the period of peak GSI increase. In addition, drift kelp, an important resource for sea urchins, tends to be higher in the summer and fall, when kelp biomass is higher and water movement is lower [
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref041" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref041">41</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref043">43</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref052" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref052">52</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref053" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref053">53</a>]. Following the timing of high abundance of drift kelp, purple sea urchins have shown subsequent peaks in both the stomach (percent weight of stomach, intestines, and gut contents of the total body weight) and gonad indices [
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref054" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref054">54</a>]. Within our study region, kelp canopy biomass is generally lowest in the winter months due to age-dependent mortality [
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref055" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref055">55</a>] and disturbance in response to increased wave heights from winter storms [
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref050" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref050">50</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref056" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref056">56</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref057" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref057">57</a>]. The spawning period of red sea urchins coincides with the period of minimum kelp biomass. Thus, spawning occurs in the months when resources for adults are more limited, so there is less opportunity to garner new resources to support gonadal growth.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As with other urchin species, if food is limiting to larval success, we would also expect spawning to coincide with phytoplankton blooms (the primary resource for the larval stages of sea urchin), rather than temperature [
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref046" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref046">46</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref058" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref058">58</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref060" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref060">60</a>]. Sea urchin larvae begin to feed within the first week of life and remain in the water column for about 40 days (ranging from 27 to 131 days depending on food and temperature; [
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref061" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref061">61</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref062" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref062">62</a>]). Recent data (1997–2015) suggest that the Santa Barbara Channel experiences extreme inter-annual variability in the timing of chlorophyll peaks, but in general blooms begin between March and June, with some years starting in February and some peaking in September [
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref063" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref063">63</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref064" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref064">64</a>]. However, red sea urchin spawning begins and peaks in December and January and appears to continue through June (Table A in 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0196864.s003" href="#pone.0196864.s003">S3 Appendix</a>). While the timing of peaks in phytoplankton and red sea urchin spawning do not appear to be perfectly aligned, the month of lowest levels of chlorophyll and highest sea surface temperatures in September coincides with the lowest spawning levels observed in this study (Table A in 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0196864.s003" href="#pone.0196864.s003">S3 Appendix</a>; [
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref063" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref063">63</a>]). The reproductive timing of red sea urchins is likely tightly linked with both adult resources (kelp) and larval resources (phytoplankton) [
  <a rid="pone.0196864.ref065" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0196864.ref065">65</a>]. However, further studies are needed to disentangle the relative influence of temperature and food availability (specific to various life-cycle stages) on the reproductive timing of sea urchins, and there are a number of other factors to consider (e.g., currents, topography, settlement timing, habitat quality).
 </p>
</sec>
