<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We selected eight AIWs that are widely distributed in China: 
 <italic class="italic">Amaranthus retroflexus</italic>,
 <italic class="italic"> Amaranthus spinosus</italic>,
 <italic class="italic"> Amaranthus viridis</italic>,
 <italic class="italic"> Bidens pilosa</italic>,
 <italic class="italic"> Conyza bonariensis</italic>,
 <italic class="italic"> Conyza canadensis</italic>,
 <italic class="italic"> Galinsoga parviflora</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Physalis angulata</italic> (Li, 
 <xref rid="ece32684-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1998</xref>; Xu &amp; Qiang, 
 <xref rid="ece32684-bib-0066" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>). We obtained occurrence records for both the invasive and native ranges from the Global Biodiversity Information Facility (GBIF; 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gbif.org" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.gbif.org</ext-link>). For China, we also added some occurrences from the Chinese Virtual Herbarium (CVH; 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cvh.org.cn" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.cvh.org.cn</ext-link>). The occurrence records from the native range (i.e., the American continent including North America, South America, and the Caribbean region), which we also used as ENM inputs, were obtained from GBIF. Species were selected for this study based on three criteria: (1) they have at least 40 occurrence records after duplicates were removed and the locality and taxonomy checked for each record for both native and invasive ranges to improve the ENM accuracy (Coudun &amp; Gégout, 
 <xref rid="ece32684-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>; Dellinger et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32684-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>), (2) they have a wide distribution and long introduction history in China to avoid the assessment uncertainty of climatic niche shifts as a result of dispersal lags (Gallien, Douzet, Pratte, Zimmermann, &amp; Thuiller, 
 <xref rid="ece32684-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>), and (3) they are known to have a negative impact on a variety of endangered plant species and ecosystems (Table S1).
</p>
