<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data-model comparison</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Recent comparisions of Holocene temperature simulations for the extratropical Northern Hemisphere performed by four different models (
  <a rid="R6" ref-type="bibr" href="#R6">
   <span class="italic">6</span>
  </a>) have shown that the trend behavior for summer and the MAATs for Greenland, northern Canada, and northeastern and northwestern Europe is consistent between models under investigation. As discussed above, the MC-FIT, the multiproxy (
  <a rid="R2" ref-type="bibr" href="#R2">
   <span class="italic">2</span>
  </a>), and other—namely, physical—proxy reconstructions are in contradiction with all MAAT simulations for the early to middle Holocene but do agree with the summer model output. When looking at regional simulation for northwestern Europe (
  <a rid="R6" ref-type="bibr" href="#R6">
   <span class="italic">6</span>
  </a>), the winter simulations exhibit variabilities from strong warming [~+4°C from 9 to 6 ka BP, Community Climate System Model version 3 (CCSM3) simulation] to cooling trends [~−1 to −2°C, FAst Met Office/UK Universities Simulator (FAMOUS) simulation], the latter being similar to our MC-FIT reconstruction.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As stated earlier, the MC-FIT record may only be biased toward the cold season due to a lack of precipitation infiltrated in the epikarst in summer, while the biological proxies used in the multiproxy global temperature reconstruction (
  <a rid="R2" ref-type="bibr" href="#R2">
   <span class="italic">2</span>
  </a>) are thought to be biased toward the summer season (
  <a rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" href="#R3">
   <span class="italic">3</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R4" ref-type="bibr" href="#R4">
   <span class="italic">4</span>
  </a>). Confirmation of this statement would mean that both winter-biased and summer-biased proxies express the same pattern, suggesting in turn that seasonal bias in the biological records (which include North Atlantic SST records) is not the source of the Holocene temperature conundrum. Moreover, a summer-season bias for the multiproxy reconstruction (
  <a rid="R2" ref-type="bibr" href="#R2">
   <span class="italic">2</span>
  </a>) would also mean that, given the similarities between the different reconstructions (including regional pollen data, as shown in fig. S7A), the other supraregional to global proxies (global ocean temperature composite, ocean temperatures at intermediate depths, mean ocean temperatures, and Greenland temperatures) were also summer biased, which seems unlikely, especially for the physically constrained proxy. The contradiction between this array of global cooling evidence with warming in the high-latitude Eurasian, European, and American pollen and speleothem records (
  <a rid="R4" ref-type="bibr" href="#R4">
   <span class="italic">4</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R5" ref-type="bibr" href="#R5">
   <span class="italic">5</span>
  </a>) sheds light on the influence of the LIS and FIS that would act on high-latitude continental proxies, as modeled for summer temperatures (
  <a rid="R1" ref-type="bibr" href="#R1">
   <span class="italic">1</span>
  </a>), while mid to low latitudes are less affected. This observation associated to the similarity between MC-FIT and pollen trend for the study site (fig. S7A) suggests a strong difference in temperature between northern and central-western Europe, which may hamper a global mean reconstruction valid for every grid cell of the Northern Hemisphere, which may also be an issue for models and composites of hemispheric reconstructions.
 </p>
</sec>
