<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec6" sec-type="materials|methods" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="bold">T</span>he fully coupled atmosphere-ocean general circulation model (AOGCM), Community Climate System Model version 3 (CCSM3)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
  </span> is employed here. Both the atmospheric module (CAM3) and the land module (CLM3) were run at a horizontal resolution of T31 (3.75° × 3.75°), and both the ocean (POP1.4) and sea ice (CSIM5) modules at “gx3v5” (with 100 and 116 grid points in the zonal and meridional directions, respectively). In the vertical, the atmosphere and ocean were divided into 26 and 25 levels, respectively. In this version of CCSM3, dust loading in the atmosphere is prescribed. The model calculates only the shortwave radiative effect of the dust, omitting the longwave effect and the indirect effect
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>
  </span>. Most estimates show that the global-mean longwave effect is much smaller than the shortwave effect both at the surface
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span> and at the top of atmosphere
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
  </span>. The indirect effect of dust through its interaction with cloud (mainly on ice cloud
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
  </span>) may be large for the present day climate locally, but there is few estimate of its global influence.
 </p>
 <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The MH control climate was obtained by running the model with MH orbital parameters (at 6 ka), set according to the PMIP2 MH benchmark experiment
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>
  </span>, while everything else, including Greenhouse gas concentrations and ozone, were prescribed the same as for PI. The only change for the EH control climate simulation relative to the MH climate simulation is the orbital parameters (from 6 ka to 9 ka). The climate effect of dust removal during the EH is assumed to be the same whether the remnant ice sheet is considered or not. This may not be a bad assumption because the orbital effect is larger than the effect of remnant ice sheet in CCSM3
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span>. The present-day dust distribution is prescribed, which was produced using an aerosol assimilation system
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>
  </span> and released with CCSM3. The dust loading is mostly over northern Africa, Arabia, Iranian plateau and western India (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2a</a>), and has the largest amplitude during boreal spring and summer (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2</a>). To test the effect of dust reduction on global surface temperature, the atmospheric dust loading is reduced uniformly by a factor of, 25%, 50%, 75% and 100% for the MH, and 50% and 100% for the EH. This uniform dust reduction is somewhat crude but is based on the following considerations: (1) there are both observational
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>
  </span> and modeling
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>
  </span> evidence that climate was wetter not only in northern Africa during MH, but also over Arabia and western India; (2) the dust deposition rate in the tropical and northern Atlantic, the Arabia Sea and east Asia all showed some depression over the mid Holocene relative to the late Holocene
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
  </span>; (3) the coupled dust and climate modeling could not provide consistent dust loading for the Holocene
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
  </span>; (4) the dust loading is much smaller over regions like Gobi desert, Australia and South America at least in the present day (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2a</a>), decrease of which may not be climatically consequential.
 </p>
 <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The control and dust-reduction experiments for EH and MH are all initialized from the PI equilibrium climate state, and are run for 1000 years. Running the control and dust-reduction experiments in parallel allows early diagnosis of the dust effect and saves waiting time. It is found that the dust effect diagnosed around model year 400 and year 1000 has negligible difference. Sensitivity experiments show almost the same the results if the control experiment was run to equilibrium first and then initialize the dust-reduction experiment from this equilibrium state. Therefore, it is not necessary to run the experiments to equilibrium to diagnose the effect of dust, and experiments for non-100% reduction are run for 500 years. At that time, the surface temperature are drifting at rate of ~0.4 °C/1000 years for both the control and dust-reduction experiments. The last 50 years of data are used for analyses. The MH control experiment shows a global cooling of 0.5 °C from the PI of the same dust, within the range of the state of the art models in PMIP experiments (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>).
 </p>
 <sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data availability</div>
  <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The datasets generated during and/or analysed during the current study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
