<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par2" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A recent reconstruction of global annual mean surface temperature in the Holocene shows a cooling trend from the peak warming of ~0.5 °C in the Holocene Thermal Maximum (HTM) (~10–6 thousand years ago; ~10–6 ka) towards the pre-industrial (PI)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span>. This cooling trend is opposite to current transient climate simulations, which show a robust warming trend forced mainly by the retreat of the residual ice sheet and the increase of greenhouse gases (GHG)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span>. Moreover, snapshot experiments of the 6 ka climate by 31 atmosphere-ocean general circulation models (AOGCMs) participated in the Paleoclimate Modeling Intercomparison Project phase II (PMIP2) and phase III (PMIP3) mostly produced a cooler or negligibly warmer climate than the PI (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>). The cause of this apparent model-data inconsistency, termed the Holocene temperature conundrum
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span>, has remained elusive. Here, we propose that the neglect of mineral dust response in climate models could contribute significantly to this discrepancy. Using a climate model, we show that the reduced atmospheric dust loading, which can be generated mainly by an enhanced monsoon and in turn vegetation cover in the North Africa during the mid-Holocene, could generate a global annual mean warming up to 0.3 °C. This model bias, when combined with the potential seasonal bias of the proxy record, can reduce the model-data discrepancy significantly.
 </p>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It has been suggested that one potential cause of the model-data discrepancy is the summer bias in some temperature proxies
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span>. This bias can contribute to a warming in HTM period due to the increased summer insolation in the Northern Hemisphere
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span>. Taking into account of the summer bias in proxy records, transient climate modeling can indeed generate a global cooling trend as in the reconstruction, especially in the Northern Hemisphere (red lines in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a,b</a>). However, summer bias in the proxy data cannot account for all the discrepancies. First, even with this summer bias, models still underestimate the warming during the HTM period, both in the transient simulations (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>) and in the snapshot simulations of PMIP models (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1b</a>). Second, summer bias cannot explain the observed warming in the Southern Hemisphere (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1d</a>). Indeed, an austral summer bias would lead to a cooling in the HTM period in the SH because of the reduced summer insolation there, leading to an even greater model-data discrepancy. It should also be noted that, since most of the data here
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span> are reconstructions of the sea surface temeprtures, the model-data discrepancy over the proxy sites can’t be reconciled as in the land-based proxy reconstruction from North America and Europe
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span>. Therefore, additional mechanisms are needed to reconcile the model-data discrepancy. One potential mechanism is the model bias associated with the changing mineral dust, which has been neglected in previous transient model simulations that were used in the study of the Holocene conundrum
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span>.
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Modified from Fig. 
     <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a> of Liu 
     <span class="italic">et al</span>.
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
     </span>. The standard 5° × 5° weighted temperature stack for the last 11 kilo-years from the proxy dataset (blue curves)
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
     </span> and similarly stacked global and regional mean temperatures from transient simulations (black and red curves). The simulation results shown here are the ensemble mean of three models: CCSM3, LOVECLIM and FAMOUS, with both the site-stacked annual mean (black) and site-stacked seasonally biased (red). (
     <span class="bold">a</span>–
     <span class="bold">d</span>) are the global mean, Northern Hemisphere (30–90° N) mean, tropical (30° S–30° N) mean, and Southern Hemisphere (90–30° S) mean, respectively. The reference climate is the average between 1.5 ka and 0.5 ka. The change of surface temperature due to dust removal at 6 ka and 9 ka are indicated by pentacles.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2018_22841_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e356" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the HTM period, the stronger boreal summer insolation leads to a significant enhancement of monsoon and, in turn, vegetation cover in the Northern Hemisphere
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
  </span>. Especially over North Africa, during the African Humid Period (AHP; 14.8–5.5 ka)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
  </span>, shrub and grassland expanded greatly over the Saharan desert
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>, which should lead to a great reduction of dust emission and, in turn, dust loading in the atmosphere.
 </p>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Marine sediment records along the northwest African coast in the Atlantic all show substantial decrease of dust output from Africa during AHP
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span>. A few modeling studies have attempted to simulate the dust cycles during the mid-Holocene using general circulation models
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>
  </span>. There is still large uncertainty in modeling the dust cycle
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>
  </span>. For example, the global dust loading at 6 ka simulated by Albani 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
  </span> using the Community Earth System Model (CESM) was only ~25% weaker than that during the preindustrial, although it has been recognized that this dust emission from the North Africa seems to be overestimated compared to sedimentary records
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
  </span>. The dust deposition flux simulated by Egerer 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span> seemed to fit the sedimentary cores well, their study suggested that the dust emission flux from North Africa during mid-Holocene was 27% of the preindustrial and the global dust loading was ~38% of the preindustrial.
 </p>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate modeling indicates that the Atlantic ocean temperature is sensitive to local change of dust aerosol, and dust reduction may be able to explain 69% of the upward trend observed between 1982–2007
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
  </span>. By reducing the dust loading over tropical North Atlantic region by 50% (while keeping the loading elsewhere), Williams 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span> showed that the same region would warm by a fraction of a degree under present-day climate condition. There have also been studies on the dust effect in the Holocene, mostly on the regional response in African monsoon and nearby region monsoon
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
  </span> or ENSO
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
  </span>. There has, however, been no systematic study on the effect of dust reduction on global surface temperature in the Holocene.
 </p>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here we use a fully coupled atmosphere-ocean general circulation model, CCSM3, to test the influence of dust reduction on the early Holocene (9 ka; EH) and mid-Holocene (6 ka; MH) climate. The atmospheric dust loading is reduced by different amounts in a series of simulations. The model version and resolution are chosen to be the same as that used by Liu 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span> in simulating the transient climate evolution from LGM to PI. Therefore, the response of global surface temperature to dust reduction obtained here may serve as a correction to that obtained in Liu 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span>, to see whether it helps to resolve the Holocene temperature conundrum.
 </p>
</sec>
