<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<table-wrap id="T0001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="table-wrap">
 <label class="label">TABLE 1</label>
 <caption class="caption">
  <p class="p">Narrative description of factor arrays 1 and 4.</p>
 </caption>
 <table frame="hsides" rules="groups" class="table">
  <thead class="thead">
   <tr class="tr">
    <th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="th">Factor (Worldview)</th>
    <th valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="th">Description and/or factor narrative</th>
   </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody valign="top" class="tbody">
   <tr class="tr">
    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="td">Factor 1: Collectivist and/or liberal</td>
    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="td">‘The climate change we experience today is not a punishment for people’s sins and neither is it a sign that the world is ending, but rather a natural occurrence where nature wants to reshape itself. Since the climate affects people’s emotions, it can also cause people to change their beliefs. If we unite we have better chance at solving climate problems and influencing the next generation’s attitudes towards nature. This is important since the climate influences the growth of crops and production of food, and we have to act now to prevent further changes to the climate’.</td>
   </tr>
   <tr class="tr">
    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="td">Factor 4: Technology and/or human</td>
    <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1" class="td">‘The climate plays an important part in our lives and we need to respect the environment. We have the right to know about climate issues that affect us directly and indirectly. Even though the climate is changing, it’s not caused by population growth and is not a sign that the world is ending. Sometimes I think that traditional healers can cause the climate to change, but I also believe that the changes in the climate are related to the burning of fossil fuels and people damaging the environment when they are trying to make money. This means that we should rather try to use sustainable technologies, since this would benefit the environment. It may not be possible for humans to control the climate through technology, but if we work together, we can make a difference’.</td>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
 <table-wrap-foot class="table-wrap-foot">
  <fn class="fn">
   <p class="p">Note: For further contextualisation of 
    <xref rid="T0001" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref>, refer to 
    <xref ref-type="app" rid="app002" class="xref">Appendix 2</xref>.
   </p>
  </fn>
 </table-wrap-foot>
</table-wrap>
