<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We select two ensembles containing four GCM runs from the CMIP5 database [
 <xref rid="pone.0165630.ref083" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">83</xref>]: one ensemble for the medium stabilization scenario RCP4.5 and one ensemble for the very high radiative forcing scenario RCP8.5. We did not include the mitigation scenario leading to a very low radiative forcing level (RCP2.6). It is unlikely that this RCP can be met, since it requires an immediate drastic decline of emissions followed by ongoing carbon sequestration in the second half of the 21
 <sup class="sup">st</sup> century, whereas the future emissions expected to come from existing capital are large [
 <xref rid="pone.0165630.ref084" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">84</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0165630.ref085" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">85</xref>]. As we aim to present robust, realistic projections in our study we choose not to include RCP2.6 in the climate model ensemble. By selecting RCP4.5 and RCP8.5 we cover the entire range of radiative forcing resulting from RCP4.5, RCP6 and RCP8.5. To include a wide range of possible futures and because for our study area there is no particular GCM performing best, and no GCM is able to simulate all aspects of the precipitation dynamics in the region satisfactory [
 <xref rid="pone.0165630.ref042" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0165630.ref086" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">86</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0165630.ref087" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">87</xref>], we choose to use the entire range of projections available. For both ensembles we therefore select four GCM runs covering the entire spectrum of projected changes in temperature and precipitation, as projected by all the CMIP5 GCM runs with output available for that RCP (
 <xref rid="pone.0165630.t003" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 3</xref>). We select the models closest to the 10
 <sup class="sup">th</sup> and 90
 <sup class="sup">th</sup> percentile values of the projections, to avoid the inclusion of outliers, similar as in other studies [
 <xref rid="pone.0165630.ref003" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0165630.ref037" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0165630.ref088" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">88</xref>].
</p>
