<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The temporal context in which warming is considered (e.g. long-term mean climatic warming versus short-term extreme events) also affects how temperature variability influences the sensitivity of locally adapted populations. If the thermal niche of a locally adapted population reflects the local thermal range of its habitat, then populations living in areas with a broad thermal range may be able to absorb larger increases in mean temperature than those adapted to low-variability environments (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSTB20180550F2">figure 2</xref>). For example, a 1°C increase in the mean will fall within the historic thermal range of a variable environment but may fall outside the historic thermal range of a stable environment (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSTB20180550F2">figure 2</xref>). However, in the context of extreme events, if local temperature variability remains constant under warming, then a 1°C anomaly above summer maximum may fall beyond historical temperature regimes in both stable and variable environments (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="RSTB20180550F2">figure 2</xref>). In this case, populations adapted to variable environments would need larger TSMs than those adapted to stable environments, in order to be more resistant to warming. Short-term extreme temperature anomalies (i.e. marine heatwaves) are increasing in magnitude and frequency [
 <xref rid="RSTB20180550C64" ref-type="bibr">64</xref>] and can have devastating impacts on locally adapted or acclimatized organisms, such as corals [
 <xref rid="RSTB20180550C65" ref-type="bibr">65</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSTB20180550C66" ref-type="bibr">66</xref>], seagrasses [
 <xref rid="RSTB20180550C67" ref-type="bibr">67</xref>] and seaweeds [
 <xref rid="RSTB20180550C13" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>]. These events act as a force selecting the most resistant genotypes within a population and are, therefore, expected to play a major role in the evolution of the TSM of local populations. Future research examining changes in TSMs of locally adapted populations in response to local temperature variability is required to better understand their sensitivity to extreme events. 
</p>
