<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec004" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study areas</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Using the same methods, we recorded wintering birds in 26 towns and cities (hereafter called urban areas), each paired with a nearby rural area, across Poland (
  <a rid="pone.0130299.g001" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0130299.g001">Fig 1</a>; for more details see 
  <a rid="pone.0130299.s006" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#pone.0130299.s006">S1 Table</a>). The study areas were chosen to cover all of Poland and span the entire Polish winter climate. Within each urban and rural area there were three square plots (25 ha) where birds were surveyed. Thus, the total number of squares was 156. The distance between paired rural and urban squares was 1–12 km. The benefit of this approach is that paired rural and urban study squares were characterised, as far as is practical, by similar climatic conditions. Squares were classified as urban or rural based on two criteria which both had to be met: (1) local authority designated as urban or rural (land management and policy in cities differs from that in rural districts); (2) squares in both environments had to include built up areas. For example, squares consisting only of arable land in urban local authorities were not considered. On average, each observer surveyed 1.81 ± 0.17 SE paired areas (range: 1–3), and all paired squares (urban-rural) were always visited by the same observer.
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0130299.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0130299.g001</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Location of the study areas.</div>
   <p>Location of the 26 paired areas used to study winter differences in birds between rural and urban environments in Poland.</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0130299.g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <sec id="sec005" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Field methods</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Birds were counted twice in the winter of 2012/2013: firstly in December 2012 and repeated in January 2013. At this time of year, only truly wintering birds occur in Poland. As stated above, counts were carried out within three 0.25 km2 squares (500 × 500 m) in each of the urban areas, and in three 0.25 km2 squares within the neighbouring rural area, with surveys paired in time as closely as possible. The order of recording rural and urban squares was chosen randomly by observers. Birds were surveyed during favourable weather conditions (no snowfall or rain, wind below 4 m s-1) between 8:00 and 13:00. Single observers, with at least 10 years’ experience in counting wintering birds, walked in a 
   <span class="italic">zig-zag</span> pattern in order to cover the entire square visually and to note bird vocalizations [
   <a rid="pone.0130299.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref013">13</a>]. The duration of the survey was 
   <span class="italic">ca</span> 2 hours for each square. Only birds exhibiting resting or foraging behaviour were included in the analysis. Hence, for example, high flying gulls, geese and corvids were ignored. The survey time ensured that birds were mainly foraging, and flights were rare. In some species, flights occurred between foraging and roosting places, however these occur mainly in the early morning and late afternoon and are thus outside the period devoted to fieldwork.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We measured the following environmental variables potentially affecting bird species richness (number of species) and abundance (number of individuals recorded in study squares): 
   <div list-type="order" class="list">
    <div class="list-item">
     <p>type of environment: urban or rural;</p>
    </div>
    <div class="list-item">
     <p>cover (%) within the square of: trees, amenity grass, arable, fallow, meadows, buildings and roads, water;</p>
    </div>
    <div class="list-item">
     <p>number of bird feeders;</p>
    </div>
    <div class="list-item">
     <p>human population size in the urban area;</p>
    </div>
    <div class="list-item">
     <p>geographical latitude and longitude.</p>
    </div>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
