<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec006" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data handling and analysis</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cover variables were calculated with ImageJ software from detailed maps and aerial photos of the studied squares or directly in the field using a GPS. We used high resolution images, freely available from the National Data Base Geoportal (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://maps.geoportal.gov.pl/webclient/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://maps.geoportal.gov.pl/webclient/</span>). Basic characteristics of the investigated urban areas are summarised in 
  <a rid="pone.0130299.s006" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#pone.0130299.s006">S1 Table</a>, and their location within Poland is presented in 
  <a rid="pone.0130299.g001" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0130299.g001">Fig 1</a>. For each square the total number (richness) of species, total number of birds (abundance) and Gini-Simpson Index of Diversity [
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref022">22</a>]) were calculated. The Gini-Simpson index gives the probability that two randomly chosen birds (individuals) from a community are not the same species. Thus, the higher values of this index the more diverse the community is. The index was moderately correlated with species richness (Spearman rs = 0.455, P&lt;0.001, n = 312) but not with number of birds (Spearman rs = -0.072, P = 0.206, n = 312) which justified its use in the analyses.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although detectability of species and of individuals in winter is relatively high [
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref023">23</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref024" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref024">24</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref025" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref025">25</a>], we also calculated the number of species and number of birds corrected for imperfect detection. The problem of detectability of species in our analyses was solved by using probabilistic methods for correcting species richness known as the Chao1 bias-corrected estimator of species richness [
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref026" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref026">26</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref027" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref027">27</a>]. Chao’s estimator is commonly used in ecological science and it was derived from the observation that rare species are undetectable because they are represented mostly by single individuals (singletons) or two individuals (doubletons). The formal equation for this index is: E(
  <span class="italic">S</span>) = 
  <span class="italic">S</span>obs+ 
  <span class="italic">n</span>1(
  <span class="italic">n</span>1-1)/ 2(
  <span class="italic">n</span>2+1), where: E(
  <span class="italic">S</span>) is the estimated number of species, 
  <span class="italic">S</span>obs is the observed number of species, 
  <span class="italic">n</span>1 is the number of singleton species, and 
  <span class="italic">n</span>2 is the number of doubleton species [
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref026" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref026">26</a>]. A simulation study showed the superior performance (lower bias, higher precision and accuracy) of this index over many parametric methods (e.g. rarefaction curves) [
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref028">28</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The corrected number of species in a square was calculated for each survey month separately in Spade software [
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref029">29</a>]. Then, to estimate the detectability of species we subtracted the recorded number of species from the estimated number of species for each square. This estimate indicates how many species remained undetected in a square and thus may be used to compare differences in species detectability between environments, months, and observers. The difference between observed and estimated numbers of species was analysed with generalized linear mixed models (see below).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used two methods, proposed by Royle [
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref030">30</a>] and by Kendall et al. [
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref031" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref031">31</a>] and implemented in the Presence 6.1. software [
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref032" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref032">32</a>], to correct for imperfect detection of individuals. The Royle estimator [
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref030">30</a>] (contrary to many other methods based on presence-absence data and devoted to calculation of detectability) directly takes the number of individuals into account. However, the method assumes the population is closed, which might not be entirely true in winter. Violation of this assumption causes the estimated detection probability to be always lower than in reality and leads to excessive estimation of abundance, although this should still correctly represent differences between environments. In order to validate the Royle estimator, the unbiased estimator of detectability proposed by Kendall [
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref031" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref031">31</a>] was used. This method relaxes the closure assumption within a season by permitting staggered entry and exit times for the species of interest at each site (square). However, this method requires at least three surveys to estimate confidence intervals but we were only able to perform two surveys (December and January). Thus, we calculated the correlation coefficient between Royle and Kendall estimators which was statistically significant (
  <a rid="pone.0130299.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#pone.0130299.s001">S1 Fig</a>). Moreover, we validated the Royle estimator by plotting species-estimates of detectability against their body sizes (= body length). Detectability is usually positively related to body size [
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref033">33</a>] and we found that this was also the case in our study (
  <a rid="pone.0130299.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#pone.0130299.s002">S2 Fig</a>). Thus, we used the Royle estimator to correct abundances for imperfect detection in our data.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The detection probabilities of species and individuals were calculated for each environment and survey (December and January) separately. We conducted and present two sets of analyses—with and without corrections for detectability. Although corrected and uncorrected data were significantly correlated (
  <a rid="pone.0130299.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#pone.0130299.s003">S3</a> and 
  <a rid="pone.0130299.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#pone.0130299.s004">S4</a> Figs) the results of statistical analyses were different. Therefore, we present only results based on corrected data.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Before formal testing of the effects of environmental variables on species richness, abundance and diversity index we had to perform data reduction. Since there were seven habitat composition variables which were correlated with each other (
  <a rid="pone.0130299.s007" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#pone.0130299.s007">S2 Table</a>), we used Principal Components Analysis (PCA) to calculate a reduced number of independent variables. We included longitude and latitude as supplementary variables in PCA to obtain ordination scores of environmental variables which were not correlated with geographical coordinates. The first two principal components explained 54% of the variability in habitat cover variables (
  <a rid="pone.0130299.t001" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0130299.t001">Table 1</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0130299.s005" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#pone.0130299.s005">S5 Fig</a>). The first principal component (PCA1, eigenvalue = 1.952) was associated with a gradient from built up areas to open agricultural habitats. The second principal component (PCA2, eigenvalue = 1.190) described a gradient from semi-natural grasslands to intensively managed amenity grasses (
  <a rid="pone.0130299.t001" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0130299.t001">Table 1</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0130299.s005" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#pone.0130299.s005">S5 Fig</a>).
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0130299.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0130299.t001</span>
  <span class="label">Table 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Results of the Principal Components Analysis (PCA) performed on the correlation matrix of the environmental variables describing cover of different habitat types.</div>
  </div>
  <div class="alternatives">
   <div id="pone.0130299.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0130299.t001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <colgroup span="1">
     <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
     <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
     <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
     <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
    </colgroup>
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</th>
      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Comm. (%)</th>
      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCA1</th>
      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PCA2</th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Buildings and roads</td>
      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">70.3</td>
      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
       <span class="bold">-0.831</span>
      </td>
      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.113</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fallow</td>
      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.8</td>
      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
       <span class="bold">0.704</span>
      </td>
      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.046</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arable</td>
      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.5</td>
      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
       <span class="bold">0.615</span>
      </td>
      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
       <span class="bold">0.507</span>
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Water</td>
      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">20.5</td>
      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.362</td>
      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.272</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Amenity grass</td>
      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">59.8</td>
      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.059</td>
      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
       <span class="bold">-0.771</span>
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Meadow</td>
      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">41.9</td>
      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.043</td>
      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
       <span class="bold">0.646</span>
      </td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Trees</td>
      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.4</td>
      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.088</td>
      <td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">-0.277</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
  </div>
  <div class="table-wrap-foot">
   <fn id="t001fn001" class="fn" xmlns="">
    <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">After varimax raw rotation, highly significant loading factors of the variables on the PCA axes are emboldened. Comm. (%) is the percentage of the total communality of each variable extracted by the first two PCA axes.</p>
   </fn>
  </div>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A generalized linear mixed model (GLMM) with Gaussian error and identity link function was carried out on the summary variables (bird species richness, total number of birds, Gini-Simpson Index of Diversity) from all 156 surveyed squares and both months. Two variables: environment type (urban/rural) and month (December/January) and their interaction were fixed categorical factors. Number of bird feeders, human population size, longitude, latitude, PCA1 and PCA2 scores (described above) were covariates. Interaction terms between environment type and covariates were also included in GLMMs to test for a different response of dependent variables to covariates in the two environments.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Observer identity, urban area pairing and square identity were random blocking factors in the GLMMs. Square identity was nested in urban-rural area pair. We used Akaike Information Criterion (AICc) to select the best reduced model and we present results for models which had values of ΔAICc (the difference between the models with lowest AICc and the given model) below 2 [
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref034">34</a>]. We used model averaging to get estimates of the function slopes (using a 99% confidence set).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Similar GLMMs were built for 10 of the most abundant species to test if environment type, geographical location, PCA1 and PCA2 scores, number of bird feeders and human population size affected their abundance. Interaction terms between the environment type and covariates were also included. Random factors were the same as described above. When analysing these species we encountered right-skewed distributions which are typical for count data with zeros. Thus, for species with excess zero counts we fitted a GLMM with a negative binomial error and logarithmic link function. The choice of Gaussian or negative binomial error variance was determined by examining AICc scores and the model with the lowest AICc was chosen [
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref034">34</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Moreover, we also built GLMMs for all individual species with reasonable sample size, testing differences in abundance between the two environments and between the two months. The effect of covariates was omitted from this analysis. Bird species with low counts (&lt; 10 individuals) were not individually analysed. The choice of Gaussian or negative binomial error variance was determined by examining AICc scores as described above.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Unless otherwise stated all GLMMs and correlation analyses were carried out using the SPSS 21 package [
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref035">35</a>]. An ordination of the mean counts for the 26 urban and 26 rural areas (i.e. averaged across three squares and two months) was undertaken in the CANOCO package [
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref036">36</a>]. We used a Detrended Correspondence Analysis (DCA), a multivariate statistical technique widely used by ecologists, to elucidate the relationships between biological assemblages of species and their environment [
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref036">36</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref037">37</a>]. We used DCA because most ordination methods suffer from two major problems: the arch effect (caused by unimodal species response curves) and compression of the ends of the environmental gradient. Because of the first problem, the second ordination axis is an artefact and cannot be interpreted. The second problem is that the spacing of species (or samples) along the first axis is not necessarily related to the amount of change along the primary gradient. DCA overcomes these problems by dividing the first axis into segments, and rescales each segment to have mean value of zero on the second axis—this effectively compresses the curve to become flat. It also rescales the axis so that the ends are no longer compressed relative to the middle [
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref037">37</a>]. Species data were 
  <span class="italic">log</span> x+1 transformed and downweighted for rare species in DCA. Downweighting was applied because ordination analyses are sensitive to rare species which influence analytical results to a much greater extent than would be predicted by their abundance [
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref036">36</a>]. The downweighting procedure replaces the abundance values of rare species in the data set, 
  <span class="italic">a</span>ij, with new values, 
  <span class="italic">a</span>ij’. A species is defined as being rare if its frequency in the data set, 
  <span class="italic">f</span>1, is lower than 
  <span class="italic">f</span>i,max/5, where 
  <span class="italic">f</span>i,max is the maximum frequency of any species. For the rare species, the formula [
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref038">38</a>] for downweighted abundance is: 
  <span class="italic">a</span>ij’ = 
  <span class="italic">a</span>ij × [
  <span class="italic">f</span>i/(
  <span class="italic">f</span>i,max/5)]. DCA was carried out with the above mentioned twelve environmental variables (seven cover variables, environment type, bird feeders, human population size, latitude and longitude) used as supplementary variables, i.e. not influencing the original ordination [
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref036">36</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In our analyses we performed multiple tests. However, we did not apply corrections for multiple testing. There are two basic reasons for this decision. First, we tested hypotheses on different species and obviously each species has a unique life-history and different biology. Therefore, there is no reason to assume that species responses would behave as random statistical processes. Secondly, the number of species tested was high, thus if the correction for multiple tests had been applied then one would not have been able to effectively test any hypothesis (for example with 50 species tested the Bonferroni corrected critical p value is 0.001 which means that tests are unfeasible and interpretation impossible). This problem has been discussed in many papers and the pitfalls of using such corrections are discussed in a paper by Garcia [
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref039">39</a>]. However, we provide information in the text and tables about corrected critical p-values for each set of tested hypotheses after using the Benjamini-Hochberg method for false discovery rates in multiple statistical tests [
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref040" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref040">40</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Means are given with standard errors (SE).</p>
</sec>
