<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Urban development is increasing across the globe, with major impacts on animal life-histories [
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref001">1</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref002" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref002">2</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref003" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref003">3</a>]. Ecological effects of urbanization have long been recognized, e.g. disturbance regimes, changes in light conditions, habitat distribution, predation pressure, and species composition [
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref004">4</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref005" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref005">5</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref006" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref006">6</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref007" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref007">7</a>]. In addition, urban environments support more anthropogenic food resources, and the climate of urban areas differs from that of nearby rural environments [
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref006" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref006">6</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref008" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref008">8</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref009">9</a>] due to the so-called urban heat island phenomenon [
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref009">9</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Urban environments provide more stable and predictable food supplies, higher temperatures and reduced temperature variability [
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref002" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref002">2</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref010" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref010">10</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref011" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref011">11</a>]. Food may be more readily available in the proximity of humans during winter, thereby facilitating urbanization of wildlife, at least in sedentary and partially migratory species [
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref012">12</a>]. In consequence, survival in cities may be easier than in other habitats [
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref013">13</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref014">14</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref015">15</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref016">16</a>]. On the other hand, non-natural habitats, non-natural food resources, traffic related mortality and disease risk, may negatively impact birds living in urban environments [
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref009">9</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref011" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref011">11</a>]. The structure of habitats may be complex in some urban areas, which can be especially important in winter when birds may need to forage in different locations to meet energetic demands and find roosting sites [
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref004">4</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref006" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref006">6</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref013">13</a>]. However, to date, the majority of studies on the effect of urbanization, and comparisons of rural and urban avifauna, have only been carried out in the breeding season, and have focussed on local scales [
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref003" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref003">3</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref004">4</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref017" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref017">17</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref018" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref018">18</a>]. Therefore, knowledge about the large scale distribution and diversity of birds in winter appears crucial for understanding the effects of faster urbanization rates in recent decades [
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref003" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref003">3</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref004">4</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The objectives of this study were to identify differences in bird communities between rural and urban areas in winter. Differences in species richness and population density between urban and nearby rural environments provide an estimate of the extent to which different species have adapted to the urban environment [
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref017" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref017">17</a>]. Obviously, some factors other than urbanization level (e.g. human disturbance, microclimate, difference in dispersal, predation pressure) may influence bird density, and may affect different ecological groups and particular species in different ways [
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref019" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref019">19</a>]. To reduce potential local effects we decided to carry out our study at a national scale, with study sites located throughout Poland. We paid special attention to the location and characteristics of study squares (e.g. the cover of different microhabitats) which might influence bird species richness and density during winter. Our focus on a large geographical area covers a wide range of winter environments, because in Poland there is a marked increase in winter severity from the north to the south (from the Baltic Sea to the Carpathian Mountains), and even more so from the west to the east (from Atlantic influence to a more continental climate; [
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref020">20</a>]). The severity of winter has been suggested as the main factor affecting winter bird communities in temperate zones [
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref013">13</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref016">16</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0130299.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0130299.ref021">21</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Therefore, mainly due to the availability of additional food and thus improved survival, we predict higher species richness and population densities of birds in urban areas during winter than in the surrounding rural areas. Although this idea is simple it is surprising that, to the best of our knowledge, this has not been investigated in winter at so large a geographical scale.</p>
</sec>
