<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Extinctions could be the ultimate consequence of negative impacts of climatic variables [
 <xref rid="RSOS160158C85" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">85</xref>]. However, even though amphibians are experiencing unprecedented declines and a large number of species and population extinctions have been documented during the last decades, climate change has rarely been identified as the main cause for any of the reported extinctions: Pounds 
 <italic class="italic">et al.</italic> [
 <xref rid="RSOS160158C8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>] attributed extinctions of Middle and South American amphibians to changing climatic conditions that favoured the chytrid fungus (
 <italic class="italic">Batrachochytrium dendrobatidis</italic>); and Sinervo 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="RSOS160158C20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>] related several extinctions of lizard populations to rising temperatures that surpassed the thermal tolerance of reptilian species. However, other studies found no evidence for chytridiomycosis being influenced by changing climates [
 <xref rid="RSOS160158C52" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>] or thermal tolerance being directly linked to extinctions in reptiles [
 <xref rid="RSOS160158C86" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">86</xref>] or amphibians [
 <xref rid="RSOS160158C87" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">87</xref>]. Most studies based on observations rather than on extrapolations from models cannot directly relate climate change to extinctions. In fact, all recently extinct reptiles, except the south African 
 <italic class="italic">Tetradactylus eastwoodae</italic>, went extinct on islands, usually because of introduced predators or direct prosecution [
 <xref rid="RSOS160158C88" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">88</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSOS160158C89" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">89</xref>]. However, several models predict future species extinctions in both amphibians [
 <xref rid="RSOS160158C55" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSOS160158C90" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">90</xref>] and reptiles [
 <xref rid="RSOS160158C20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSOS160158C64" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">64</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSOS160158C91" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">91</xref>] due to climate change.
</p>
