<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The results presented here are at least somewhat inconsistent with those of previous research on mutualistic networks. For example, one study [
 <xref rid="pone.0157929.ref032" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>] reported an association between nestedness/modularity and human impacts in seed-dispersal networks, whereas no relationship was observed here. The results of another study [
 <xref rid="pone.0157929.ref031" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>] indicated that nestedness and modularity are associated with temperature-change velocity in pollination networks, but again, no such relationships were observed in this study (Tables 
 <xref rid="pone.0157929.t001" ref-type="table" class="xref">1</xref> and 
 <xref rid="pone.0157929.t002" ref-type="table" class="xref">2</xref>). These discrepancies may be due to the different datasets used in this study and those used in previous studies; for instance, the dataset on pollination used in our study (
 <italic class="italic">n</italic> = 62) is larger than that used in a previous study [
 <xref rid="pone.0157929.ref031" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>] (
 <italic class="italic">n</italic> = 54); moreover, the similarity of the datasets was low [Jaccard index (JI) of approximately 0.4 (35/81)]. Although the number of seed-dispersal networks is almost similar between this study (
 <italic class="italic">n</italic> = 30) and the previous study [
 <xref rid="pone.0157929.ref032" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>] (
 <italic class="italic">n</italic> = 34), the similarity of the datasets was low [JI ≈ 0.5 (21/43)] because the previous study included unpublished data. In addition, the discrepancy may also be partially attributed to methodological differences. For example, the previous study [
 <xref rid="pone.0157929.ref031" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>] did not consider climate seasonality and human impacts, and was based on a unipartite version of modularity despite pollination networks traditionally represented as bipartite networks. Moreover, they did not consider the standardization of nestedness (NODF), although the 
 <italic class="italic">Z</italic>-score (i.e., standardization) allows comparisons of networks with different levels of connectivity (i.e., connectivity or matrix fill strongly affects NODF) [
 <xref rid="pone.0157929.ref037" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>].
</p>
