<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Definitions for nestedness and modularity also vary, although here we focused on NODF and 
 <italic class="italic">M</italic> for ease of comparison to previous studies. For nestedness, one previous study [
 <xref rid="pone.0157929.ref038" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>] used a spectral graph approach, and proposed the largest eigenvalue of a community matrix (mutualistic networks) for measuring nestedness, instead of using NODF-like nestedness indices. Moreover, the heterogeneity of degree distributions was shown to dominantly determine nestedness [
 <xref rid="pone.0157929.ref039" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>], network measures that may be useful as alternative indices for nestedness. The definition of modularity used in this study and in many previous studies is well known to have resolution-limitation problems [
 <xref rid="pone.0157929.ref040" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0157929.ref041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>]. We avoided this issue as much as possible by using a simulated-annealing algorithm, according to [
 <xref rid="pone.0157929.ref041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>]; however, the conclusions reached in this study regarding network modularity are unavoidably limited. Although network modularity is useful for revealing functional architecture in ecological networks [
 <xref rid="pone.0157929.ref042" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>], the modules detected based on network topology may be inconsistent with biologically functional modules because the link weight and overlap of functional modules that are observed in real-world networks were not included in this study. To minimize these restrictions, module detection methods for weighted networks [
 <xref rid="pone.0157929.ref028" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>] and overlapping communities (e.g., [
 <xref rid="pone.0157929.ref043" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0157929.ref044" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>]) may be useful because they more accurately predict functional modules.
</p>
