<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Southern Rock Lobster (
 <italic>Jasus edwardsii</italic>) (Hutton 1875) are a key target of regional fisheries of Australia’s southern continental shelf between Geraldton in Western Australia (29° S, 114° E) and Coffs Harbour in northern New South Wales (30° S, 172° E) [
 <xref rid="pone.0225144.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>], and have an annual commercial catch of ~3000 t valued at ~AUD $250 million in 2016/17 [
 <xref rid="pone.0225144.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>][
 <xref rid="pone.0225144.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. In South Australia, Southern Rock Lobster are the state’s most valuable fisheries resource, with an annual landed value of AUD $120 million in 2016/17 [
 <xref rid="pone.0225144.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>]. Fishing by the South Australian Rock Lobster Fishery is undertaken using baited traps within two management areas, the Northern Zone and Southern Zone (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0225144.g001">Fig 1</xref>). The division into two zones reflects ecological and biological characteristics that differ in both regions in relation to habitat [
 <xref rid="pone.0225144.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], growth [
 <xref rid="pone.0225144.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] and recruitment [
 <xref rid="pone.0225144.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>]. Fishing in both zones is managed using a suite of controls including limited entry, vessel-size and power restrictions, protection of ovigerous females, and seasonal and spatial closures. In addition, a Total Allowable Commercial Catch (TACC) has been in place in the Southern Zone since 1993 and in the Northern Zone since 2003 [
 <xref rid="pone.0225144.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>][
 <xref rid="pone.0225144.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0225144.g001">Fig 1</xref>). Individual minimum legal size limits that reflect spatial differences in growth [
 <xref rid="pone.0225144.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>] and size at maturity [
 <xref rid="pone.0225144.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>][
 <xref rid="pone.0225144.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>] have been set in each zone to protect brood stock and maintain egg production. In the Southern Zone, the minimum legal size limit of 98.5 mm carapace length (CL) has been in place since 1970 [
 <xref rid="pone.0225144.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. In the Northern Zone, minimum legal size limits have changed over time, increasing from 98.5 to 102 mm CL in 1995, and further to 105 mm CL in 2000 [
 <xref rid="pone.0225144.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>].
</p>
