<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The strong phylogeographic structure among the population of 
 <italic class="italic">G. przewalskii </italic>observed here was largely due to the few haplotypes shared among regions. The phylogenetic tree of cpDNA and STRUCTURE analysis of SSRs together support that the genotypes of Tarim Basin of 
 <italic class="italic">G. przewalskii</italic> are a separate group (Figures 
 <xref rid="ece35113-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ece35113-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" class="xref">4</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ece35113-fig-0005" ref-type="fig" class="xref">5</xref>). According to grouping strategy of SAMOVA of ITS, the GITS1 and GITS2 represent the Tarim group. The analysis of mantel tests and AMOVA indicated that there were huge genetic differences between Tarim and other regions. The phylogenetic and median‐joining tree of ITS support the separation of haplotypes of GITS4 (Alxa Desert + Wulate Prairie) from GITS3 (Hami Basin + Hexi Corridor). And almost no haplotypes were shared among the Tarim Basin, Hami Basin + Hexi Corridor, and Alxa Desert + Wulate Prairie (Figures 
 <xref rid="ece35113-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ece35113-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ece35113-fig-0005" ref-type="fig" class="xref">5</xref>, Table 
 <xref rid="ece35113-tbl-0002" ref-type="table" class="xref">2</xref>). Therefore, based on the available data, the genotypes of this species were roughly divided into three groups. The lack of shared cpDNA or ITS haplotypes among these three discrete groups indicated that there has been little gene flow among the groups since their formation, leading to the accumulation of haplotypes differences. Moreover, each of the three groups has its own distribution and habitat (Figure 
 <xref rid="ece35113-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref>), which could also be responsible for the high genetic differentiation among groups. The Tarim Basin is surrounded by mountains on three sides, the Pamir Plateau on the west, the Tianshan Mountains on the north, and the Kunlun and Altun Mountains on the south, forming a relatively closed environment and preventing gene flow with other regions. Badain Jaran Desert and Tengger Desert are effective geographical barriers for population of Hami Basin + Hexi Corridor and Alxa Desert + Wulate Prairie. In addition, the weak dispersability of 
 <italic class="italic">G. przewalskii </italic>seeds also have contributed to the large genetic distances and limited gene flow among groups (Ma &amp; Zhang, 
 <xref rid="ece35113-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>; Ma et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35113-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>).
</p>
