<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par14" class="p">With respect to the significant climate shifts projected by 2100
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" class="xref">49</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" class="xref">50</xref>
 </sup>, the Mediterranean Basin will become an important hotspot for biodiversity conservation
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" class="xref">51</xref>
 </sup>. Our results are thus consistent with recent updates on projected species habitat losses due to global warming in the Mediterranean and Middle East
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" class="xref">52</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" class="xref">53</xref>
 </sup>. Nevertheless, the effects of climate change on species range shifts in the eastern Mediterranean has not properly been investigated in the literature, and the few existing studies have only focused on very local patterns
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" class="xref">54</xref>
 </sup>. A key finding of this study is that there is a strong difference in the climate change impacts among the three species clades inhabiting three different eastern Mediterranean sub-regions. Accordingly, our results highlight a significant sub-regional variation in the impacts of climate change on biodiversity, specifically in wide-ranged species such as mountain vipers. Previous studies on climate change projection over the period 1979–2100 have revealed that among the Middle East - North Africa domain the alpine ecosystems of Turkey and Iran are likely to face the largest increase in temperatures, particularly during March-May
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" class="xref">49</xref>
 </sup>. This time of the year coincides with the post-hibernation mating activities for 
 <italic class="italic">Montivipera</italic> species. Accordingly, apart from projected reductions in the mountain vipers’ suitable habitats and increasing habitat fragmentation, climate changes might also interfere with the species reproductive cycles, and thus their demographic rates.
</p>
