<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par18" class="p">In this study, we performed ENM analyses at a clade level above the species rank rather than at the species level due to the sparse availability of data on species distributions. This procedure assumes that niche conservatism holds for recently diversified species in mountain vipers, which is likely the case in most species that have evolved mostly from allopatric speciation. This speciation mode tends to retain ancestral ecological traits (e.g. ecological niche)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" class="xref">70</xref>
 </sup>. In fact, niche conservatism in climatic tolerance might have limited the geographic range expansion of mountain vipers and may have resulted in very similar species-specific ecological niches in this genus. However, we admit that our approach of phylogenetically lumping occurrence points may have introduced some bias. First, our approach expands geographic range size of the species by assigning them to clades. Given the positive correlation between species’ range size and niche breadth
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71" class="xref">71</xref>
 </sup>, and given that aggregations may smooth over smaller lower-ranked taxonomic units
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72" class="xref">72</xref>
 </sup> this method may inflate niche breadth and overestimate the range of suitable habitats for species-specific local populations. The resulting habitat suitability maps may thus be rather optimistic. In reality, there will likely be fewer suitable patches available to any species than what is modelled at the clade level, particularly in the absence of unlimited dispersal. Another key assumption of ENMs is that a species is in equilibrium with the climate
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" class="xref">67</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73" class="xref">73</xref>
 </sup>, meaning that the observed distribution represents the total of suitable habitats of the species. Regarding the evolutionary history of 
 <italic class="italic">Montivipera</italic>, high degrees of new-endemism, isolated distribution to mountain and limited dispersal abilities
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" class="xref">45</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74" class="xref">74</xref>
 </sup> might have eradicated the species from some areas that once were suitable. This could mean that 
 <italic class="italic">Montivipera</italic> species might be isolated from otherwise suitable habitats, thus violating to some degree the equilibrium assumption. If true, this would underestimate the true width of suitable habitats, and thus, counteract the overestimation imposed by aggregating species to clades. We believe that both effects are considerably small given the very clear and specific niche identified by our models.
</p>
