<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Datasets</div>
 <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We sourced monthly time series from 1950 to 2014 from the Center Research Unit (CRU V3.23; 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://crudata.uea.ac.uk/cru/data/hrg/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://crudata.uea.ac.uk/cru/data/hrg/</span>) at a 0.5° resolution for air temperature (AT) and from the Met Office Hadley Center (HadISST; 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.metoffice.gov.uk/hadobs/hadisst/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.metoffice.gov.uk/hadobs/hadisst/</span>) at a 1° resolution for sea surface temperature (SST). These raster maps are composed of 67325 and 32619 monthly observations time series for AT and SST, respectively. The number reported for the latter excludes pixels that were mostly composed of ice as those pixels are not temperature time series and can’t be analyzed with EWIs.
 </p>
 <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To determine whether some ecoregions were more likely to approach a critical transition than others, as already shown for other facets of change
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span>, we extracted terrestrial biomes from the Köppen-Geiger climatic classification (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://koeppen-geiger.vu-wien.ac.at" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://koeppen-geiger.vu-wien.ac.at</span>) whereas for sea surface temperature we compiled biomes from the World Wildlife Fund (WWF) Marine Ecoregions Of the World (MEOW; 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.worldwildlife.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.worldwildlife.org/</span>). The year band used for the Köppen-Geiger classification was 1986–2010. Note that we haven’t used the WWF classification for the terrestrial system because ecoregions were not comparable to the marine ecoregions. We nonetheless report result for this classification in the supplementary material (Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S2</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
