<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2c1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1. Sampling methods</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The study was conducted between August and October in 2008 near Turku (60°26′ N, 22°11′ E) in southwest of Finland, where we had three sampling sites. Each species were attempted to collect as quickly as possible to avoid the seasonal and temperature variation. The collection periods for the species were: great tit (12.8.-26.8.), blue tit (6.8.-20.8), chaffinch (12.8.-25.9.), greenfinch (20.8.-17.9.), house sparrow (12.8.-1.9.), willow warbler (6.8.-16.9.), sedge warbler (6.8.-25.8.), reed warbler (6.8.-18.9.), reed bunting (15.9.-15.10) and barn swallows (21.8.-19.9.2007). Most of the species were caught within a month, thus minimizing the temporal variation. In reed warblers all but one was collected till the 10
  <span class="sup">th</span> of September. Those species that were caught over a time period more than one month, however, did not show remarkable variation between catching time and EROD activity.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The habitats included a common alder (
  <span class="italic">Alnus glutinosa</span>) dominated grove, a reed bed (
  <span class="italic">Phragmites</span>) and garden habitats. There were no major pollution sources near our study areas, although aerial contamination (e.g. via wind or roads) cannot be fully excluded. However, owing to the tendency of young birds to move and mix a lot in autumn (meaning that their origin varies a lot even within a species) we consider it most unlikely that exposure to pollutants would produce a systematic species-related bias in our data. Barn swallows were collected in 2007 near Turku as well. The birds were caught with mist nets (Ecotone). The nets were checked every 30 minutes. All the birds collected in this study were young females (born during summer 2008), 12–22 individuals per species, except in the case of reed warblers and sedge warblers, for which sex determination in field was impossible. The number of these two species was increased to 30 individuals and they were sexed later in the laboratory. By collecting young birds we were able to exclude the possible influence of migration and the diet consumed in their overwintering grounds, as well as reduce variation in their life-time pollution exposure and age-related pollutant accumulation. We also wanted to concentrate on one sex to avoid sex specific variation in their detoxification capacity. The birds were measured for their wing length and body mass. As a condition index we used wing length (mm) relative to body mass (g). Also moulting phase, an index of visible subcutaneous fat and muscle index were recorded and used to define the condition of the birds at time of capture. Birds were sacrificed by decapitation and subsequently dissected for the liver tissue, which was separated and placed in plastic Eppendorf tubes. Liver was chosen as a sampling site, because it is the major site for detoxification process (Whyte et al. 2000). Liver tissue were stored immediately in liquid nitrogen and later kept at −80°C until laboratory analyses. The carcasses of the birds were stored for sex identification and future analyses. The data were collected under the license of the Environmental Centre of southwest of Finland.
 </p>
</sec>
