<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2c3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.3. Statistical analyses</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The inter-specific variation in EROD activity was analysed with general linear models (GLMs with Type III SS) in IBM SPSS Statistics software 19.0 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-IBM1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-IBM1">[35]</a>. The species was used as an independent variable in the model. Pairwise comparison between the species was done using Tukey's test. The variation in EROD activity between diets and migration status were also analysed with GLMs using diet and migration status as independent variables. EROD activity was log
  <sub>10</sub> transformed before the analyses to normalize distributions. Within-species correlations between the variables (EROD, condition index and fat index) were analysed using Spearman's correlations, because variables were not normally distributed.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We combined the data from basal metabolic rates collected from the literature 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-McKechnie1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-McKechnie1">[36]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-McNab1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-McNab1">[24]</a> and the data of liver masses of the studied species (unpublished data of A.P. Møller) to our data to see how EROD activity is related to relative BMR (W/body mass [g]) and relative liver mass (liver mass [g]×100/body mass [g]) (average values for the species) (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="pone-0033926-t001" href="#pone-0033926-t001">Table 1</a>). The average liver masses for the species were derived from samples collected between June and September to minimize the seasonal variation in liver masses. The variation between the months was tested with general linear models and since there was no major monthly variation in liver mass, the mean values based on those four months were included in the final analyses (Felsenstein's correlations). The amount of species varied in the analyses, because liver mass was not available for sedge warbler and BMR for reed warbler respectively. The phylogenetically corrected (OLS) regression (with 95% confidence (CI) and predicted intervals (PI) mapped onto the original data space) and correlations between the variables were analysed with Felsenstein's contrasts in Mesquite phylogenetic software (Version 2.74) 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-Maddison1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-Maddison1">[37]</a> by using PDTREE module of PDAP after ensuring the normality of the distributions. Felsenstein's correlations (r
  <sub>F</sub>) are based on phylogenetically independent contrasts (PIC), enabling correlations among the sets of characters for a number of species that are not statistically independent, due to the common ancestor in their phylogenetic history.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Phylogenetic relationships of the studied species were taken from Treplin et al. 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-Treplin1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-Treplin1">[38]</a> and branch lengths of the topology were estimated using DNA sequence data from six gene regions. The DNA sequences were downloaded from GenBank (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0033926.s001" href="#pone.0033926.s001">Table S1</a>) and analyzed in a maximum likelihood framework using PAUP* 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-Swofford1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-Swofford1">[39]</a>. In some cases a closely related species had to be used as there were no sequences available for species used in this study (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0033926.s001" href="#pone.0033926.s001">Table S1</a>). The topology was fixed and a standard general time reversible model with a gamma correction to allow for rate heterogeneity was applied to the concatenated six gene dataset. To allow the estimation of the length of the basal branches, two outgroups were included (
  <span class="italic">Corvus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Oriolus</span>). This produced a phylogenetic tree with branch lengths in substitutions per site per time unit, which was input into Mesquite for the independent contrasts analysis after the outgroups were pruned from the tree. Phylogeny was not included in the analyses of diet and migration status, because these variables only had two categories, and especially diet was so strongly dependent on phylogeny (insectivores vs. granivores) that there would be no power in the analysis to detect phylogenically independent variation with this number of species.
 </p>
</sec>
