<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The interspecific variation in basal EROD activity between small passerine species suggests that species differ from each other in their need/capacity of detoxification. Our study indicates that the difference is related to different feeding habits and migratory status, EROD activities being generally higher in insectivorous than in granivorous species. Migratory insectivores showed the highest EROD activity, whereas migratory granivores had lower or similar EROD activity than in non-migratory/partially migratory granivores.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results are parallel to the study of Fossi et al. 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-Fossi3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-Fossi3">[4]</a>, who showed that omnivores, which use variable diet, have more efficient detoxification capacity than specialist birds, which concentrate on only one or a few food items. In our study parids, which use mixed diet (mainly insects in summer and seeds in winter) and could also be considered omnivores rather than pure insectivores, had lower EROD activity than pure insectivores, but still higher than granivores, most probably due to their diet (e.g. moths) containing relatively low amount of defence chemicals. Sometimes also granivores can feed their offspring and themselves with insects, especially during their breeding season making the division between granivores and insectivores less clear. However, the amount and diversity of animal food in granivores is still low compared to pure insectivores and thus the low EROD activity could reflect the relatively low amount of animal food taken in as also the results in parids suggest. Brower 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-Brower1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-Brower1">[40]</a> and Müller et al. 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-Mller1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-Mller1">[41]</a> for example have shown insectivorous birds to be able to distinguish prey with low defence chemicals. Also granivores can distinguish the seeds containing high amounts of harmful secondary compounds (e.g. the seeds of the plant families Malvaceae, Convolvulaceae, Rubiaceae and most Leguminosae) and avoid them to get better quality and more digestible food 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-Schluter1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-Schluter1">[42]</a>. Fossi et al. 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-Fossi3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-Fossi3">[4]</a> had also included one passerine species in their studies, the Italian sparrow (
  <span class="italic">Passer italiae</span>), which is mainly a granivore, but feeds also on insects during the breeding season. In agreement with our results, the Italian sparrow had relatively low activities of EROD and aldrin epoxidase, which is another good indicator of detoxification ability. A close relative of Italian sparrow, the house sparrow, also showed relatively low EROD activity in our study, but still higher than in other granivores, which might be due to its more variable diet compared to the other granivores in our study set. However, a direct comparison with the levels in the study of Fossi et al. 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-Fossi3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-Fossi3">[4]</a> cannot be done, as they have used liver microsomes, whereas in our study liver homogenate with a different measurement technique was used. Liukkonen-Anttila et al. 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-LiukkonenAnttila1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-LiukkonenAnttila1">[43]</a> compared the EROD activities in galliform birds and pigeons and found also species specific variation. Pheasants (
  <span class="italic">Phasianus colchicus</span>), which use a variety of different seeds and plant material as food items, showed the highest EROD activity, whereas capercaillies (
  <span class="italic">Tetrao urogallus</span>) with their narrow diet showed low EROD activities 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-LiukkonenAnttila1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-LiukkonenAnttila1">[43]</a>. Galliformes seem to have relatively low EROD activities compared to Passeriformes examined in our study. However also in the case of Liukkonen-Anttila et al. 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-LiukkonenAnttila1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-LiukkonenAnttila1">[43]</a>, the measurements have been done using hepatic microsomes and thus the results are not directly comparable. Kennedy et al. 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-Kennedy1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-Kennedy1">[44]</a> have studied the rank order of sensitivity to EROD induction in birds, showing that the chicken (
  <span class="italic">Gallus domesticus</span>) was the most sensitive to halogenated aromatic hydrocarbons (HAH), with some other galliform species following the same trend, suggesting that Galliformes in general have relatively low detoxification capacity. In our study, the reed bunting showed very low EROD activity compared to any other species we studied. The reason to this is not known, but it is possible that their main food, such as the seeds of annual weeds (e.g. 
  <span class="italic">Chenopodium</span>) 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-Orowski1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-Orowski1">[45]</a>, contains relatively little defence chemicals and therefore their detoxification system may be less efficient. This may be the reason also for the lower level of EROD activity in migratory granivores compared to non-migratory/partial migratory granivores in this study. The chaffinch, with a similar life history to the reed bunting, instead had similar EROD levels with non-migratory/partial migratory granivores.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There are several alternative hypotheses to explain why migratory insectivores showed the most efficient detoxification capacity, as indicated by the highest EROD activities measured. High detoxification capacity in migratory insectivores might be due to their more variable diet containing a wider range of natural toxins that may affect the evolution of their MFO system and further to their ability to tolerate harmful compounds. The lower EROD activity in migratory granivores instead may be related to their narrower and less natural toxins containing diet. Plant species in tropics tend to have more defence chemicals than plants in temperate forests 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-Coley1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-Coley1">[46]</a>. Tropical forests also have higher variety of plant species, meaning that herbivores and their predators in tropics also encounter greater amount of defence chemicals 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-Janzen1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-Janzen1">[47]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-Janzen2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-Janzen2">[48]</a>. Some insect herbivores are able to use those defensive compounds for their own purposes to defend themselves from insectivorous predators 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-Pasteels1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-Pasteels1">[49]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-Pasteels2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-Pasteels2">[50]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-Discher1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-Discher1">[51]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-Opitz1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-Opitz1">[52]</a>. Thus, the large variety of ‘unpalatable’ insects in tropics may have caused birds to develop different detoxification mechanisms to cope with the toxic compounds in their diet 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-Brown1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-Brown1">[53]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-Schoonhoven1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-Schoonhoven1">[54]</a>. Insectivorous birds for example are the main predators of herbivorous insects during the breeding time of the birds, when also the insect larvae are abundant 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-Holmes1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-Holmes1">[55]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-Robinson1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-Robinson1">[56]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-Holmes2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-Holmes2">[57]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-Marshall1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-Marshall1">[58]</a>. Of our study species willow warblers, which showed the highest liver EROD activity, partly overwinter in rainforests 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-Morel1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-Morel1">[59]</a>, but other migratory species inhabit other habitats (e.g. reed beds), having different prey items with different defence chemicals. The pied flycatchers (
  <span class="italic">Ficedula hypoleuca</span>), which also overwinter partly in rainforests 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-Morel1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-Morel1">[59]</a> show high EROD activities as well 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-Tanhuanp1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-Tanhuanp1">[10]</a>. Migratory birds also encounter variable diet in their stopover sites during the long distance flights. Since all granivores in our study overwinter in Europe, whereas insectivores in Africa, it would be important to find out whether the overwintering habitat (Europe vs. Africa) explains the different EROD activities between granivorous and insectivorous migrants. The EROD activities between local insectivores and granivores in Africa would also be worth measuring to see whether there are diet related differences in EROD activity, when migration is excluded.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another hypothesis to explain the variation in detoxification capacity among species is that the energetically expensive long distance migration itself may have produced physiological adaptations between migrants and non-migrants, which can possibly be reflected in their detoxification capacity as well. For example, the relationship between metabolic rate and detoxification capacity is poorly known in birds. It has been shown that BMR is significantly higher in migratory birds than in non-migratory birds 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-Jetz1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-Jetz1">[60]</a>. Long distance migrants also often have large intra-annual changes in their BMR, which means that physiological adjustments are associated with different stages of their migratory cycle 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-McKechnie2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-McKechnie2">[61]</a>. In our study set, long-distance migrants had relatively high relative BMR coupled with high detoxification capacity, suggesting that higher metabolic rate could be related to more effective metabolic products. Nonetheless, after correcting for phylogeny the correlation between EROD activity and relative BMR was not so strong.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is also noted that tropical birds in general have lower BMR than birds living in temperate-zone 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-Weather1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-Weather1">[62]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-Hails1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-Hails1">[63]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-Pettit1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-Pettit1">[64]</a>, but see 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-Scholander1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-Scholander1">[65]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-Vleck1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-Vleck1">[66]</a>. This is supported also by the study of Wiersma et al. 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-Wiersma1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-Wiersma1">[67]</a>, where they found significantly lower BMR in 69 tropical species compared to 59 species living in temperate habitat, even when phylogeny is taken into account. The result did not change either when body-mass-adjusted BMR was used 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-Wiersma1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-Wiersma1">[67]</a>. This is suggested to be due to slower pace of life in tropics, meaning that life-history traits covary with the rate of energy expenditure, tropical birds being at the slow end of the life-history axis and temperate birds at the opposite end 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-Wiersma1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-Wiersma1">[67]</a>. Tropical migrants instead lied there in the middle having higher BMR than birds in tropics but lower than in temperate birds 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-Wiersma1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-Wiersma1">[67]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-Williams1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-Williams1">[68]</a>. In our study the relative BMR was highest in small migratory insectivores, whereas the larger migratory granivores had slightly lower relative BMR, followed by non-migrants, suggesting that relative BMR is not only associated with the migration status, but also to the size of the birds. Our result is opposite to the studies of Wiersma et al. 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-Wiersma1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-Wiersma1">[67]</a>, though it is possible that the higher relative liver mass in small migratory insectivores affects relative BMR as the positive correlation between them suggests. The elevated mass-specific BMR has been also detected with the larger size of other organs in the study of Daan et al. 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-Daan1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-Daan1">[26]</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The organ masses relative to body mass (e.g. liver, kidney, heart) of the tropical birds have been found to be smaller than those of temperate birds 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-Rensch1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-Rensch1">[69]</a>. However, we did not find this kind of trend in our data set, since the trans-Saharan migrants, especially the willow warbler, but also the reed bunting and the reed warbler, had relatively large liver mass in relation to their body mass. The high EROD activity and relatively large liver mass in the willow warbler and the reed warbler might reflect their higher capacity to detoxify secondary compounds as well as pollutants. Despite the large relative liver mass, the reed bunting had very low EROD activity and also other enzyme activities related to glutathione metabolism (Rainio et al. unpublished data), which may be due to its narrow diet. The reed warbler and the sedge warbler, which are close relatives, had very similar level of EROD activities. Also the willow warbler seemed to follow the same trend being also related to other warblers used in this study. The chaffinch and the greenfinch, again close relatives, showed also similar EROD activity levels with each other, although they eat different kind of food. They may still however share the same kind of MFO system. Parid species instead, which are also close relatives differ from each other in their EROD activity, great tits having higher EROD activity than blue tits in relation to their relative liver mass, which may be due to differences in their metabolic machinery since they both use relatively similar food. However, knowledge of the relationship between EROD activity, basal metabolic rate and organ mass relative to body mass in small passerine species is still poor and needs more studies on a larger number of species both at the ecotoxicological and physiological levels to confirm the relationship between those factors.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The diet has been shown to be related to BMR in birds and therefore it may affect species detoxification capacity as well. To our best knowledge this study is the first in small passerine birds, where EROD activity measurements have been combined with BMR and diet. To date, the uric acid levels (indicating protein metabolism) in blood plasma of migratory birds have been shown to be lower in frugivorous species than species feeding mainly on arthropods 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-Newton1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-Newton1">[70]</a>. Frugivorous birds instead showed high levels of triglycerides, which indicate great dependence on fat metabolism. This suggests that different species use fat and protein at different ratios during migration and species using different diets most probably also accumulate fat and protein as fuel in different ratios 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-Newton1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-Newton1">[70]</a>. The studies on food habits hypothesis (FHH) have shown contradictory results of the relation of BMR and dietary habits among the species 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-McNab3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-McNab3">[71]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-McNab1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-McNab1">[24]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-Sabat1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-Sabat1">[72]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-Sabat2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-Sabat2">[73]</a>. The hypothesis predicts that species/populations using food with low energy content and/or low digestibility as well as unpredictable food availability will have low mass-independent BMR 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-McNab3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-McNab3">[71]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-CruzNeto1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-CruzNeto1">[74]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-McNab4" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-McNab4">[75]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-Bozinovic1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-Bozinovic1">[76]</a>. McNab 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-McNab1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-McNab1">[24]</a> has concluded that omnivore species have higher BMR than species feeding only insects, seeds or aquatic invertebrates. Sabat et al. 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-Sabat2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-Sabat2">[73]</a> instead found no correlation between the BMR and diet among passerine bird species, probably due to different evolutionary response to natural diets 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-Foley1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-Foley1">[77]</a>. In contrast, the intraspecific studies of Sabat et al. 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-Sabat1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-Sabat1">[72]</a> with a generalist species, the rufous-collared sparrow (
  <span class="italic">Zonotrichia capensis</span>), showed that sparrows that consumed food at a lower trophic level had higher BMR compared to birds that used more animal food. In that case, the higher BMR might be due to detoxification pathway activated by secondary compounds in plants 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-Cork1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-Cork1">[78]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0033926-Silva1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0033926-Silva1">[79]</a>. Our results showed slightly lower relative BMR in granivores compared to insectivores, which might be due to the size of the birds, because granivores were slightly bigger than insectivores in this study. However, also the detoxification capacity was lower in granivores, which means that the secondary compounds of the plants most probably do not increase the BMR in this case. Since the number of species was relatively small in our study further investigation is still needed to confirm the relation between metabolic rate, diet and detoxification capacity.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To conclude, the study species differ from each other in their hepatic EROD activity and the difference is related to their feeding habits and migratory status. Migratory species likely use more variable food with higher amounts of secondary compounds both in their breeding and overwintering habitats and have therefore developed higher detoxification capacity, which makes them better adapted to natural and man-made toxic compounds than non-migratory species. The lower EROD activity in migratory granivores compared to insectivores may be related to their narrower and less natural toxins containing diet, which means that their MFO system may not have evolved as effectively as in insectivores. Higher metabolic activity and oxygen consumption can increase ROS production and probably affect their detoxification ability as well. Nonetheless the metabolic rate did not seem to be the main reason for the variation in species detoxification capacity in this study, because there was no correlation between relative BMR and EROD activity even when the phylogeny was taken into account. EROD activity instead correlated positively with relative liver mass, suggesting that the detoxification capacity is related to organ size. However, the number of species as well as the sample size within the species was relative small, so a critical view is needed when drawing conclusions from the results. Our study shows that there is a lot of species-specific variation in basal EROD activity, which means that direct inter-specific comparison of pollution induced EROD activities cannot be done without first knowing the basal level of EROD activity in each species. Also, the EROD activity measurements at different times of the year would be valuable to see whether EROD activity shows seasonal variation in birds. Moreover, in further studies it would be important to measure both granivorous and insectivorous migrants from overwintering areas to see whether the diet in overwintering habitat affects to the variation in EROD activity. The knowledge of basal levels of EROD activities among the species is important to improve its use as biomarker in ecotoxicological studies. The increasing knowledge of tolerance and detoxification ability will also help in identifying the species most sensitive to environmental pollution and in understanding the mechanisms that may decrease bird populations in contaminated areas. Our results suggest that granivores are likely more vulnerable to environmental contaminants than insectivores and migratory birds are likely less susceptible to contamination load than resident birds. Diet and migration status however are strongly related to each other, with diet varying a lot between breeding and overwintering habitats.</p>
</sec>
