<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">A second group of assumptions relates to parameterization of pollution and degradation processes:
 <list id="l2" list-type="bullet" class="list">
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">
    <underline class="underline">BOD degradation rates</underline>: as mentioned earlier, a constant rate coefficient k of 0.35 day
    <sup class="sup">−1</sup> is used. This value is similar to laboratory measured values and to a value of 0.23 day
    <sup class="sup">−1</sup> used in another large-scale modelling study
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11" class="xref">11</xref>. Previous work
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34" class="xref">34</xref>
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b35" class="xref">35</xref> has considered these values representative of rivers with discharge larger than 22.7 m
    <sup class="sup">3</sup>/s
    <sup class="sup">32</sup> (i.e. most of the rivers in our study). While k values may change spatially with river hydraulic conditions, these effects are currently not included in the model. A possible model extension is to include these effects via settling and bed effects equations in shallow streams
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34" class="xref">34</xref>. We note that the direct effect of river flow velocity on degradation 
    <italic class="italic">is</italic> included (
    <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq4" class="xref">Eq. 4</xref>). In addition, neither secondary effects of organic pollution such as eutrophication nor light degradation in in-stream reservoirs are included in our calculation
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4" class="xref">4</xref>, as it depends on daily or seasonal variation and oxidizable nitrogen compounds in polluted waters
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b44" class="xref">44</xref>
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b45" class="xref">45</xref>.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">
    <underline class="underline">wastewater treatment fractions and efficiencies</underline>: assumed spatial distributions of treatment fractions reflect available data (by city or country for domestic sources, and by region for livestock farming; see 
    <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">section S1.2</xref> and 
    <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Table S1</xref> in the Supplement). Similarly, domestic treatment efficiencies are only available by country. In the absence of systematic data on treatment efficiency in intensive livestock farming, we assumed a uniform efficiency of 85% (secondary level) based on the following considerations:(i) other studies
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b46" class="xref">46</xref>
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b47" class="xref">47</xref> considered intensive livestock farming a manufacturing activity subject to secondary or tertiary treatment, at least in European countries
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31" class="xref">31</xref>, (ii) in Asia, effluents from large livestock farms are either diluted and reused for irrigation, or processed through (an) aerobic treatment plants such as lagoons, resulting in organic removal rates that approach secondary treatment levels
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b48" class="xref">48</xref>
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b49" class="xref">49</xref>, and (iii) a sensitivity analysis reveals that computed BOD concentrations are relatively insensitive to the assumed efficiency in Africa and South America because of the low fractions of livestock farming wastewater treatment in these regions (from 6% to 20%, 
    <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Fig. S6</xref>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
