<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We used a linear mixed effects model with an exponential spatial correlation structure that included each data point's latitude, longitude, and elevation to correct for spatial autocorrelation. We modeled, separately, the responses of SVL (log‐transformed) and Julian day, with the year of collection as a random intercept and fit five models to include all possible combinations of FFD, precipitation, and their interaction as well as an intercept‐only model (Table 
 <xref rid="ece33636-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S4</xref>). Both FFD and precipitation were centered and scaled prior to analyses. We fit all models using maximum likelihood and determined the best model for SVL and Julian day based on lowest AICc (Burnham &amp; Anderson, 
 <xref rid="ece33636-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2002</xref>). We confirmed that all our models met the assumptions of homogeneity of variances, normally distributed residuals, and linearity by inspecting plots of standardized residuals versus fitted values, quantile–quantile plots, and plots of our three response variables against our fixed effects, respectively. For the model with the lowest AICc, we determined significance of the fixed effect using a likelihood ratio test. When multiple models received substantial support (i.e., ΔAICc ≤ 2), we averaged competing models and determined significance based on whether the 95% confidence intervals overlapped with zero. We report the marginal and conditional 
 <italic class="italic">R</italic>
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> values of all models tested (Table 
 <xref rid="ece33636-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S4</xref>), where marginal 
 <italic class="italic">R</italic>
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> (
 <italic class="italic">R</italic>
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>
 <italic class="italic">m</italic>) is a measure of the proportion of the variance explained by the fixed effects, and the conditional 
 <italic class="italic">R</italic>
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> (
 <italic class="italic">R</italic>
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>
 <italic class="italic">c</italic>) measures the proportion of the variance explained by both the random and fixed effects (Nakagawa &amp; Schielzeth, 
 <xref rid="ece33636-bib-0045" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). We tested each parameter (temperature, FFD, FFD+precipitation, etc.) independently to determine whether it was significantly related to body size or Julian day of collection (breeding).
</p>
