<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s0004" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Analytical framework</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Stakeholder attributes such as agency play essential role in the proactive and reactive approaches to disaster risk management (Mojtahedi &amp; Oo 
  <a rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0050">2017</a>). This includes factors such as perception of risk, habit, social status and age which operate at individual and consequently collective action decision-making levels (Adger et al. 
  <a rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0003">2009</a>). Cognition or knowledge about risks is thus critical in risk reduction planning. Accordingly, approaches in climate change action need to integrate indigenous knowledge with latest scientific insights, address multiple stressors and trade-offs, build adaptive management capacity as well as focus on information management, sustainability, monitoring and evaluation of risks (DEA 
  <a rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0018">2013</a>; UN 
  <a rid="CIT0078" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0078">2015</a>; UNISDR 
  <a rid="CIT0081" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0081">2015</a>). However, individual adaptation hinges on whether an impact, anticipated or experienced, is perceived as a risk and whether it should (and could) be acted upon through adaptation policies, or is constrained by inertia and cultures of risk denial (Adger et al. 
  <a rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0003">2009</a>). As existing models are inadequate for effective public participation (FAO 
  <a rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0029">2014</a>), there is need for a hybrid climate change communication model that integrates bottom-up and top-down processes, embraces information and communication technologies (ICTs), empowers local communities and nurtures collective action (Evans et al. 
  <a rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0025">2018</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Proactive engagement of stakeholders in early phases of disaster risk management is a requisite for resilient societies and built environment against disasters (Mojtahedi &amp; Oo 
  <a rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0050">2017</a>). As adaptation is a continuous stream of activities, actions, decisions and attitudes that inform all aspects of life that reflect existing social norms (Nelson et al. 
  <a rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0053">2007</a>), it is important to frame it from social system lenses, the structure of which is provided by various individuals and groups of which it is composed (Rogers 
  <a rid="CIT0065" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0065">2004</a>). This is critical because social relations influence expectations, commitment and understanding of risks by individuals and communities (Kasperson et al. 
  <a rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0041">1988</a>). As the functional element within a social system is the potential or actual behaviour of the individual and the collectives in a social system in terms of knowledge, attitudes and behaviour, there has been a shift from diffusion and transfer of technologies to a broader understanding of how to involve multi-stakeholders through communication activities (FAO 
  <a rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0028">2010b</a>; Servaes &amp; Lie 
  <a rid="CIT0072" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0072">2013</a>). This could be extended to holistic approaches that apply feedback loops between the climate system, the human system and ecosystems in assessment of adaptation planning (David &amp; Elise 
  <a rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0017">2007</a>). Effective communication of the risks is thus posited to play an important role in smallholder farmers’ adaptation to climate change.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The characteristics that impact risk perception and behaviour and the degree of dread associated with the risk vary with the public’s familiarity with the risk (Slovic 
  <a rid="CIT0074" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0074">2000</a>). As hazards interact with psychological, social and cultural processes in ways that can heighten or attenuate individual and social perception of risk and shape risk behaviour (Renn et al. 
  <a rid="CIT0062" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0062">1992</a>), debates concerning societal values and world views require good understanding of the social context on which risk management decisions are made (OECD 
  <a rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0054">2002</a>). More critical is the observation that collective action influences individual action in climate change risk management (David &amp; Elise 
  <a rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0017">2007</a>). As individual and social characteristics, in particular risk perception, interact with underlying values to form subjective and mutable limits to adaptation that currently hinder society’s ability to act, it could preclude adaptation at societal scales (Adger et al. 
  <a rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0003">2009</a>). This creates the need for integration of social learning and communication concepts in adaptation planning (Servaes &amp; Lie 
  <a rid="CIT0072" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0072">2013</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Under risk perception normalisation theory (Becker, Ronan &amp; McClure 
  <a rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0008">2017</a>), people tend to think that they are not at risk from an existing risk. Perceptions of being safe may, however, change to perceptions of being at risk immediately after a disaster by providing a window of opportunity to motivate preparedness and mitigation. The impact of seeing what other people have performed to prepare and mitigate a disaster is a stronger motivation for taking action than receiving information about the need to take action (Mileti &amp; Darlington 
  <a rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0048">1997</a>). Diffusion of technology models (Rogers 
  <a rid="CIT0065" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0065">2004</a>) could be used in partly explaining such observation. Diffusion innovation theory holds that observability is critical to adoption processes. In this way, people can bring direct, indirect and vicarious experiences to bear on their risk assessments and preparedness decision-making (Becker et al. 
  <a rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0008">2017</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Risk-based decision-making results into balanced judgement that reflects factual evidence about the matter at hand in relation to interests and values, including messages on emerging risks that are currently not of public concern (Renn 
  <a rid="CIT0064" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0064">2006</a>). In principle, mobilising and influencing risk dispositions and behaviour of individuals through education and disclosures may transfer the agency of environmental and health risks control and enforcement from the state to individual (Rose 
  <a rid="CIT0067" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0067">2003</a>). In this way, risk communication offers a better alternative to regulatory enforcement. This may be utilised in the prediction, prevention and remediation of environmental and health risks (Wardman 
  <a rid="CIT0084" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0084">2008</a>). Implicitly, risk communication is a cost-effective alternative to regulatory systems in the abatement of environmental and health risks, and integral to effective decision-making in climate change action and sustainable development discourses.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While the inherent post-disaster emergency relief planning approach that is implicit in the risk normalisation bias theory (Becker et al. 
  <a rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0008">2017</a>) is relevant in reinforcing positive risk behaviour, it stands at crossroad with proactive approaches advocated by the disaster risk reduction paradigm. It is also at variance with precautionary principles in the management of environmental risks. According to the isolation paradox (Baumol 
  <a rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0007">2004</a>), individuals are willing to make a sacrifice on their present consumption (through abatement of ecological degradation risks) to benefit future generations if others do so. However, under the free rider analogy (Hardin 
  <a rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0032">1968</a>), individuals expect benefits from other people’s abatement initiatives, yet they are unwilling to do the same. As the agency of safeguarding and enforcing public interest through abatement falls on the government enforcement and compliance systems and institutions (Rose 
  <a rid="CIT0067" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0067">2003</a>), the relevance of the risk communication, particularly the governability model, is critical.
 </p>
</sec>
