<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s0005" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Contextualising the critical issues</div>
 <sec id="s20006" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Adaptation as disaster risk reduction pathway among farmers under changing climate</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate change is the change in the state of climate whether because of natural variability or as a result of human activity that can be identified by changes in the mean and/or the variability of its properties, and that persists for extended period, typically decades or longer (IPCC 
   <a rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0036">2007</a>). Evidence of climate change includes changes in patterns of temperature and precipitation, irregular and un-predictable rainfall, intense downpours, rising temperature and generally increase in frequency of extreme and harsh weather such as droughts (IPCC 
   <a rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0037">2014</a>). In realisation of the negative impacts of climate change, urgent action to combat climate change through adaptation has been proposed (UN 
   <a rid="CIT0078" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0078">2015</a>). Accordingly, adaptation is a key factor that influences the future severity of climate change impacts (Easterling et al. 
   <a rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0022">2007</a>). Adaptation to climate change takes place through adjustments to reduce vulnerability or enhance resilience in response to observed or expected changes in climate and associated extreme weather events. It involves changes in social and environmental processes, perceptions of climate risk, practices and functions to reduce potential damages or to realise new opportunities. Adaptation includes anticipatory and reactive actions (Adger et al. 
   <a rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0001">2007</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Maladaptation is underlying risk in climate change action (Adger et al. 
   <a rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0002">2005</a>; Barnett &amp; O’Neill 
   <a rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0006">2010</a>; FAO 
   <a rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0027">2010a</a>). Hence, there is a need to investigate policies, plans and programmes in terms of risks and opportunities critical in sustainable development agenda. Underlying risks refer generally to the socio-economic and environmental factors that are the primary causes of a disaster. Individual and societal stocks of knowledge, attitudes, skills and the consequent risk behaviour are among the key factors that influence vulnerability (Satya 
   <a rid="CIT0070" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0070">2010</a>). Nuanced against the urgency for adaptation action in an environment of cognitive failure, the critical question is on who has the power to act or the ‘agency’ in safeguarding public good (interests). To answer the question requires an understanding of how hazards (trigger events), vulnerability and capacity interact. Models for such analysis are provided by Mimura et al. (
   <a rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0049">2014</a>) and Turner et al. (
   <a rid="CIT0077" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0077">2003</a>). In the current article, we contextualise the risks of salinisation from irrigation among small-scale farmers.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Salinisation is a major impediment in many arid and semi-arid regions of the world (Qadir, Qureshi &amp; Cheraghi 
   <a rid="CIT0060" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0060">2007</a>). The global extent of primary salt-affected soils is about 955 million hectares (ha), while secondary salinisation affects some 77m ha, with 58% of these in irrigated areas. Salinisation is attributed to irrigation of unsuitable soils or use of poor-quality irrigation water.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For example, of the 34m ha of land under cultivation in Iran, 4.1 million ha is affected by salinisation. This represents $1 billion in annual economic losses (Qadir et al. 
   <a rid="CIT0060" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0060">2007</a>). The need for increase in area under irrigation in adaptation to and mitigation of adverse climate change impacts on food and forage production and thus presents a serious challenge to sustainability of irrigated production systems. This calls for risk reduction initiatives.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s20007" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Irrigation ecological sustainability linkages</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Though definitions of sustainability vary across sectors, their common theme is to change the way resources are exploited, and how hazards are managed so that adverse impacts downstream or for subsequent generations are reduced (Kates et al. 
   <a rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0040">2005</a>). Sustainable development principles call for integration of economic and development policies so that in case of conflict between the two, ecological interests are given preference (UNEP 
   <a rid="CIT0079" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0079">2012</a>). The ratio of total factor productivity to changes in the critical soil property, such as salinity (magnitude of soluble salts in the soil) or the total natural resource productivity (TNRP), is used in the current article to contextualise the impact of irrigation on sustainability. As a coefficient or index of sustainability, TNRP accounts for indirect costs from degradation of a natural resource (Lal 
   <a rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0043">1997</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Water quality and its suitability for use in irrigation are judged on potential severity of problems that can be expected to develop during its long-term use (FAO 
   <a rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0026">1985</a>; Ravikumar &amp; Somashekar 
   <a rid="CIT0061" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0061">2012</a>). The most important determinants of quality and suitability of water for irrigation are total concentration of soluble salts (salinity hazard) in terms of electro-conductivity (EC), relative proportion of sodium to other principal cations (sodium hazard) expressed as sodium adsorption ratio (SAR), bicarbonate concentration relative to the concentration of calcium plus magnesium and boron hazards or concentration of boron or other toxic elements (Ravikumar &amp; Somashekar 
   <a rid="CIT0061" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0061">2012</a>). Salinity hazards or EC exceeding certain threshold levels reduce water availability to crop in the root zone. Salinity hazards above such thresholds could cause 8%– 86% loss in crop yields (FAO 
   <a rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0026">1985</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s20008" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The role of communication in the transformation of socio-ecological system</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The most attractive adaptation measures are those that offer benefits in the near future as well as reduce vulnerabilities in the long-term (Mimura et al. 
   <a rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0049">2014</a>). Hence, adaptation to climate change requires supportive policy environment and support systems for resilience building. A supportive environment includes policies that improve access to quality services, leadership that promotes social and behavioural change among members of society, allocation of resources for social and behavioural change, community contribution to the implementation of solutions in general and support of individuals’ own behavioural change (FAO 
   <a rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0028">2010b</a>). This considers the interaction of individuals’ knowledge and behaviour on social change.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Participation, a central tenet in development planning discourses, refers to the inclusion of those who are affected or who can affect a decision (Hobley 
   <a rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0034">1996</a>). Rowe and Frewer (
   <a rid="CIT0068" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0068">2000</a>) conceptualise participation from a two-way flow of communication in terms of information dissemination to passive participants and gathering information from participants. The rationale for participation in natural resources management, however, is largely informed by local resistance to state control of natural resources and need to address tragedy of the commons arguments (Bixler et al. 
   <a rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0010">2015</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Several authors (EEA 
   <a rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0023">2014</a>; Arnstein 
   <a rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0004">1969</a>) have reviewed broad spectrum of forms of public participation. According to some of the findings (Chambers 
   <a rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0013">1994</a>; Scoones 
   <a rid="CIT0071" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0071">1998</a>), participation improves the quality of decision-making process and improves use of available information and creativity in the society. Moreover, participation improves public understanding of the management issues at stake, enhances transparency in decision-making and might stimulate better coordination, monitoring and evaluation among government agencies. Participation increases better understanding, dialogue, out of thinking discipline, nuanced focus on relevant problems that confront the real drivers of change and formulation of strategy and policy (Mostert et al. 
   <a rid="CIT0052" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0052">2007</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Empowerment refers to the capacity of people to make effective choices, envision alternatives, participate in decision-making, negotiate with influence, control and hold accountable institutions that affect their lives and livelihoods (World Bank 
   <a rid="CIT0086" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0086">2007</a>). Accordingly, empowerment is central to community-based disaster risk reduction and resilience planning initiatives (UNISDR 
   <a rid="CIT0081" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0081">2015</a>) with communication being at the core of empowerment, participation and nurturing collective responsibility in climate change decision-making processes (Evans et al. 
   <a rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0025">2018</a>; Servaes &amp; Lie 
   <a rid="CIT0072" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0072">2013</a>). The underlying philosophy in communication for development is built around the principle of empowerment in the identification of problems, development of solutions and implementation strategies, monitoring and evaluation (FAO 
   <a rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0028">2010b</a>). This includes use of communication in extension education and research as a tool for improving productivity, incomes, welfare and sustainable natural resources management outcomes among farmers. For example, a democratic participatory approach that incorporates the interests, capacities and cultural identity of local communities at all levels has the potential to unpack the limitations of traditional media in empowering the community (Servaes &amp; Lie 
   <a rid="CIT0072" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0072">2013</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Communication for development is defined as planned use of strategies and processes of communication in achieving development and behaviour change (Srampickal 
   <a rid="CIT0075" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0075">2006</a>). The three basic components of communication for development are advocacy, social mobilisation and behavioural change (or behavioural development) communication. The other components include participatory communication and communication for structural and sustainable social change (Servaes &amp; Lie 
   <a rid="CIT0072" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0072">2013</a>). Effective communication relies on the synergistic use of the three strategic components (UNICEF 
   <a rid="CIT0080" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0080">2008</a>). Advocacy informs and motivates leadership to create a supportive environment to achieve programme objectives and the related development goals. In essence, the advocacy component is aimed at changing policies, allocating resources, public dialogue and conversation on critical issues. Climate change action and sustainable development agenda are some of the cross-scalar issues.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Advocacy, sustained publicity and education can converge value systems to reduce gaps in knowledge, attitudes and beliefs (FAO 
   <a rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0028">2010b</a>) as well as translate existing adaptive capacities into adaptation actions that reduce vulnerability (Mimura et al. 
   <a rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0049">2014</a>). The backbone of advocacy whether national or at the local level comes from a combination of data analysis and community input (UNICEF 
   <a rid="CIT0080" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0080">2008</a>). Possible results of an advocacy intervention can be targeted at leaders taking actions, such as legal reform, or enactment of new law(s), or rules, policy decisions, formulation of and/or reform, administrative directives resource mobilisation and financial allocation. In addition, the advocacy component can build the capacity of leaders to become advocates themselves and speak out on issues pertinent on funding priorities, policy change and addressing social barriers.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Social mobilisation engages and supports participation of institutions, community networks, social/civic and religious groups to raise demand for or sustain progress towards a development objective by strengthening participation in activities at the grassroots level (UNICEF 
   <a rid="CIT0080" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0080">2008</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The backbone of developing the social mobilisation component of a communication strategy comes from a combination of data, participant and behavioural analyses (FAO 
   <a rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0028">2010b</a>; UNICEF 
   <a rid="CIT0080" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0080">2008</a>), as well as community input. Behaviour change communication involves face-to-face dialogue with individuals or groups to inform, motivate, problem-solve or plan with the objective of promoting and sustaining change (UNICEF 
   <a rid="CIT0080" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0080">2008</a>). In agricultural extension and adoption of technologies, sustaining the change implies attaining a critical mass of adopters of a given desirable action (Rogers 
   <a rid="CIT0065" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0065">2004</a>), in this case ecological sustainability or package of technology that mediates ecological sustainability. According to public engagement conceptual framework (Devine-Wright 
   <a rid="CIT0021" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0021">2011</a>), effective communication encompasses the understanding of community’s attitudes and believes. The integration of beliefs and attitudes, and the processes used in the assessment of economic, social and environmental dimensions or substantive sustainability, and procedural sustainability is thus relevant (Del Rio &amp; Burguillo 
   <a rid="CIT0019" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0019">2009</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">South Africa and Kenya are classical examples of countries whose agricultural sector is highly vulnerable to changing rainfall patterns. For instance, the area under irrigation as a result of increase in temperature and evaporation in South Africa is projected to increase by 4% – 6% in the interior hydrological zone and 15% – 30% under the hotter and drier hydrological scenarios (DEA 
   <a rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0018">2013</a>). In Kenya, irrigation is recognised as a critical pillar in food security. Of critical importance is that most of the land mass in South Africa and Kenya is located in arid and semi-arid regions. The two countries represent good case studies of potential salinisation risks in climate change action. The possibility of salinisation risks in adaptation to increasing frequency of extreme weather events such as drought in a number of countries, such as Kenya and South Africa, provides an example envisaged by Asghar et al. (
   <a rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0005">2005</a>) where environmental impacts have the potential to increase the severity of disasters and the need for integrative use of analytical lenses that encompass the precautionary principle, disaster risk reduction and risk communication. The above analyses demonstrate the centrality of development for communication strategies in disaster risk reduction.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s20009" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Linkages between development for communication, risk communication and sustainable development</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The main motivation for future action in disaster preparedness and mitigation is dependent on 
   <span class="italic">a priori</span> information received. The information disseminated to households, observed information, information density and information content are thus key factors that directly or indirectly increase household action-taking in disaster preparedness and mitigation (Dennis et al. 
   <a rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0020">2011</a>). This increases discussion, perceived effectiveness or efficacy of recommended mitigation or preparedness actions. Though no single generic view of risk communication suffices (Wardman 
   <a rid="CIT0084" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0084">2008</a>), risk communication is generally defined as the process of disseminating information among interested parties about the nature, magnitude, significance and control of the risk (Covello 
   <a rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0016">1992</a>), dialogue between communication and stakeholders (Palenchar &amp; Heath 
   <a rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0057">2007</a>) and ongoing risk monitoring (Coombs 
   <a rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0015">2012</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Risk communication action raises people’s awareness about given risks, enabling them to be party to individual and collective risk decision-making (Rogers 
   <a rid="CIT0065" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0065">2004</a>; Stirling 
   <a rid="CIT0076" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0076">2005</a>). Risk communication plays an integral role in shaping individual risk perceptions as well as risk aversion or reduction behaviours. Risk communication is also a crucial element in risk management processes, as it enables actors to recognise and understand risks, identify their roles and jointly engage in monitoring, reduction, mitigation and recovery efforts (Sato 
   <a rid="CIT0069" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0069">2015</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As risk communication focuses on the characteristics that impact risk perception and behaviour, it can be appraised through elicitation of the degree of dread associated with a particular risk and the public’s familiarity with the risk (Slovic 
   <a rid="CIT0074" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0074">2000</a>). Hence, engaging the public in risk appraisal facilitates the correction and adjustment of people’s dispositions and risk behaviour (Stirling 
   <a rid="CIT0076" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0076">2005</a>). Familiarity and the corresponding dread is used in categorisation of risks into routine, uncertain and controversial risks, respectively (Covello 
   <a rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0016">1992</a>). In this categorisation, the less understood risks are referred to as uncertain risks. Risks that require discussion on values, lifestyles and world views are referred to as controversial risks. Ecological degradation risks could be classified as uncertain risks. In this article, the risk categories are conceptualised on routine-controversial-uncertainty risk continuum.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The risk message model, the risk dialogue model, governability risk model and risk field communication model have been explored in detail by Wardman (
   <a rid="CIT0084" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0084">2008</a>). The risk message model is about one-way provision of information about the nature of risks (Jaeger &amp; Renn 
   <a rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0038">2001</a>). In the risk message model, it is assumed that people communicate to convey information which may be used by others to enhance their understanding about a given risk. The model focuses on providing or disseminating information about risks which does not necessarily lead to greater understanding (Wardman 
   <a rid="CIT0084" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0084">2008</a>). Further, it does not consider the effect of complex social networks on expectations, commitment and understanding and co-construction of risk messages and meanings (Jaeger et al. 
   <a rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0038">2001</a>; Horlick-Jones 
   <a rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0035">2008</a>). The mechanistic nature of risk message model (sender–receiver model without engagement or interaction) limits participation thus excluding knowledge from risk message recipients. Such asymmetry reduces the likelihood of the recipient accepting or adopting a particular risk proposition or viewpoints advanced by the experts (O’Neill 
   <a rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0054">2002</a>). In addressing such drawbacks, risk dialogue, risk governability and risk field model have been suggested.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Risk dialogue model seeks to promote participation and inter-subjectivity with an objective of overcoming linearity weaknesses associated with risk message model (Jovchelovitch 
   <a rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0039">2007</a>). Hence, it utilises a two-way communication model to incorporate interests of all actors involved in a particular risk issue. Under the model, the actors are regarded equally and treated like partners. The approach nurtures responsibility and allows for debates as well as collaborative interaction in risk management (Fischhoff 
   <a rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0030">2005</a>). The inter-subjective understanding of risk allows for consensus building between citizens (Jovchelovitch 
   <a rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0039">2007</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The risk field model considers agency in terms of the strategic conduct and interests of competing social actors (Wardman 
   <a rid="CIT0084" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0084">2008</a>). This is in an attempt to secure legitimacy and enhance trust in risk management and regulatory governance (Pidgeon &amp; Rogers-Hayden 
   <a rid="CIT0059" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0059">2007</a>). Risk governance model includes interventions that empower individual capacities for self-control, shaping actors and their own sense of self- and self-interest in managing particular risks (Rose 
   <a rid="CIT0067" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0067">2003</a>). It interrogates how rules that govern the field of possible activity are structured and bear upon the dispositions and behaviour of those concerned. In principle, it focuses on how education and policy discourses can be utilised to mobilise and influence risk dispositions and behaviour of individuals and the transfer of the agency of environmental and health risks control and enforcement from the state to an individual (Rose 
   <a rid="CIT0067" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0067">2003</a>). As communication for development focuses on use of communication processes, methods and tools to empower people to advance towards full awareness of their situations and their options for change (FAO 
   <a rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0028">2010b</a>), its role is significant in the mitigation of environmental externalities associated with adaptation to climate change in the agricultural sector.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Though risk communication can be used in creating awareness about risks, it has some drawbacks, such as linearity that renders them ineffective (Evans et al. 
   <a rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0025">2018</a>; Servaes &amp; Lie 
   <a rid="CIT0072" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0072">2013</a>). As the communication for development is concerned with re-engineering diffusion research into a process of innovation, identifying the problem, stakeholder mapping, stakeholder engagement, critical evaluations and reviews as well as addressing the social costs in a participatory manner are some of the prerequisites in re-engineering the process (Leeuwis 
   <a rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0046">2004</a>). We argue that communication for development lenses can be utilised in enhancing the robustness and utility of risk communication in adaptation planning.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The four main elements in the innovation-diffusion model (Rogers 
   <a rid="CIT0065" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0065">2004</a>) are new ideas or the innovation (in this article adaptation measures and correlated environmental risks), communication channels, time and the social system. Diffusion is facilitated through a communication process by which participants’ access and share information with one another to reach a mutual understanding, form attitudes and implement the idea. Forming attitudes towards an innovation is a mental process in the decision-making and implementation process (Rogers et al. 
   <a rid="CIT0066" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0066">2007</a>). Disposition about ecological risks, risk behaviour outcomes and agency are thus akin to innovation-diffusion process. Risk communication can thus enhance adoption of positive risk behaviour and technology in the abatement of environmental and health risks (Rogers 
   <a rid="CIT0065" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0065">2004</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s20010" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The proposed conceptual framework</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A common feature of contemporary natural resource management issues is the underlying uncertainty in accounting for the problems (such as externalities) and predicting the effect of a particular management strategy. These uncertainties are, in part, a product of the growing emphasis on long-term, multi-scalar and integrative aspects of resource management among researchers, community of practice and policy makers (Biggs et al. 
   <a rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0009">2015</a>). We argue that while multi-scalar and existing integrated models are noble, cognitive failure and biases, lack of approaches for effective participation in environmental risk abatement 
   <span class="italic">vis-à-vis</span> the agency and the accountability dilemma could exacerbate the externalities and the attendant social costs.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Risk communication is strategic to a meaningful collective action in the governance and management of environmental externalities and securing public interest. However, in adaptation to climate change, policy makers and climate change adaptation actors are more concerned with immediate livelihoods needs (Easterling et al. 
   <a rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0022">2007</a>). As cognitive dissonance about a risk, such as salinisation, may result in such probabilities being downplayed or being ignored (Renn 
   <a rid="CIT0063" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0063">1998</a>), the use of communication for development and social change approaches that encompass dialogue, agency and mobilisation has been suggested as potential tools in social transformation and resilience building (Evans et al. 
   <a rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0025">2018</a>). In human- environment interactions, a risk-reduction-based planning model that incorporates knowledge, attitudes and behaviour at community level has high potential to cure cognitive failures and contribute to social transformation (Volenzo &amp; Odiyo 
   <a rid="CIT0082" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0082">2018</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Adaptation-Mitigation-Sustainable Development (AMSD) frameworks are an integral part of wider development goals in transition to sustainability and critical in policy formulation, decision-making, governance and behavioural development (Bizikova, Robinson &amp; Cohen 
   <a rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0011">2007</a>). AMSD includes the creation of local implementation pathways that increase opportunities for social learning processes and capacities for effective adaptation and mitigation (FAO 
   <a rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0028">2010b</a>). As the status of soil salinity as well as its temporal variation can be used as an indicator in the monitoring of degradation risks and as a sustainability indicator (Metternicht &amp; Zinck 
   <a rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0047">2003</a>), salinity levels can serve as an indicator of maladaptation in AMSD frameworks.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Risk communication focuses on information presentation, persuasion and strategic messages (Heath &amp; O’Hair 
   <a rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0033">2010</a>). Hence, it is critical in closing gaps between what is known by different actors about a particular risk and what needs to be known (Wardman 
   <a rid="CIT0084" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0084">2008</a>). As knowledge offers insights as to how a system might be managed, farmer’s awareness, perception of environmental risks as well as risk behaviour can be used in modelling environmental impacts in adaptation to climate change. This has the potential in resolving the social-ecological-policy dilemmas. Risk communication can thus be viewed as an integral to risk assessment, risk control, risk monitoring and review planning frameworks for sustainable climate change action. 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F0001" href="#F0001">Figure 1</a> presents the proposed conceptual framework on linkages between risk communication, communication for development and sustainability in climate change action.
  </p>
  <div id="F0001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">FIGURE 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Authors’ conceptual framework on integration between risk communication and sustainable climate change action.</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="JAMBA-11-703-g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </sec>
</sec>
