<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s20007" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Irrigation ecological sustainability linkages</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Though definitions of sustainability vary across sectors, their common theme is to change the way resources are exploited, and how hazards are managed so that adverse impacts downstream or for subsequent generations are reduced (Kates et al. 
  <a rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0040">2005</a>). Sustainable development principles call for integration of economic and development policies so that in case of conflict between the two, ecological interests are given preference (UNEP 
  <a rid="CIT0079" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0079">2012</a>). The ratio of total factor productivity to changes in the critical soil property, such as salinity (magnitude of soluble salts in the soil) or the total natural resource productivity (TNRP), is used in the current article to contextualise the impact of irrigation on sustainability. As a coefficient or index of sustainability, TNRP accounts for indirect costs from degradation of a natural resource (Lal 
  <a rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0043">1997</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Water quality and its suitability for use in irrigation are judged on potential severity of problems that can be expected to develop during its long-term use (FAO 
  <a rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0026">1985</a>; Ravikumar &amp; Somashekar 
  <a rid="CIT0061" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0061">2012</a>). The most important determinants of quality and suitability of water for irrigation are total concentration of soluble salts (salinity hazard) in terms of electro-conductivity (EC), relative proportion of sodium to other principal cations (sodium hazard) expressed as sodium adsorption ratio (SAR), bicarbonate concentration relative to the concentration of calcium plus magnesium and boron hazards or concentration of boron or other toxic elements (Ravikumar &amp; Somashekar 
  <a rid="CIT0061" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0061">2012</a>). Salinity hazards or EC exceeding certain threshold levels reduce water availability to crop in the root zone. Salinity hazards above such thresholds could cause 8%– 86% loss in crop yields (FAO 
  <a rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0026">1985</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
