<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s20002" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The review context</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Adaptation to climate change is reflected in social, ecological and economic changes that mitigate the adverse impacts and take advantage of arising opportunities (Easterling et al. 
  <a rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0022">2007</a>). Adaptation to climate risks involves technical measures and modifications to farm practices with respect to climatic and non-climatic stimuli and conditions (Wall, Smit &amp; Wandel 
  <a rid="CIT0083" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0083">2004</a>). Irrigation or the artificial application of water to supplement or compliment the available moisture for plant growth in response to prolonged dry spells, erratic rains or poorly distributed rains is one of the most common adaptation measures in agriculture. However, adaptation may or may not succeed in moderating harm or exploiting beneficial opportunities because system transformations are more challenging than planning or implementing immediate measures to cope with a climate-driven disaster (Moser &amp; Ekstrom 
  <a rid="CIT0051" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0051">2010</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Consideration for behavioural dynamics in the transformative processes is integral to social learning and sustainability agenda (Pelling 
  <a rid="CIT0058" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0058">2011</a>). Transformational agenda seeks to address the root cause of vulnerability by introducing fundamental changes to attributes of a system (Eriksen, Nightingale &amp; Eakin 
  <a rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0024">2015</a>). Rethinking and reframing of policy and practice, engaging multiple knowledges as well as questioning subjectivities inherent in discourses and problem understanding are critical in pursuit of transformational agenda (Eriksen et al. 
  <a rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0024">2015</a>). Such analytical frameworks are inclusive of individual, community, state and non-state actors’ interests, aspirations and interactions. Building upon the foregoing argument, the rising need for resilience building to climate-related hazards (UN 
  <a rid="CIT0078" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0078">2015</a>), the importance of identifying underlying risk factors in risk reduction initiatives (UNISDR 
  <a rid="CIT0081" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0081">2015</a>) and the centrality of strategic planning, monitoring and evaluation advocated under comprehensive conceptual model for disaster management (Asghar, Alahakoon &amp; Churilov 
  <a rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0005">2005</a>), we explore some concepts in disaster risk reduction in the next section.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Disaster risk management involves strategic planning (Asghar et al. 
  <a rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0005">2005</a>), administrative decisions and operational activities in the prevention, response, recovery, mitigation and early-warning for disasters (Satya 
  <a rid="CIT0070" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0070">2010</a>). Though the administrative activities are cross-cutting and a shared responsibility among various actors, the administrative decisions in agriculture are largely policy related while operational activities are largely farmer dependent. Risk reduction and resilience building at community level require analytical and conceptual lenses that unbundle cognitive biases and failures as well as integrate and transform individual and collective agency (Volenzo &amp; Odiyo 
  <a rid="CIT0082" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0082">2018</a>). In farmers’ use of irrigation as an adaptative measure to climate change, the critical question is on how to transform communities and individuals to collectively internalise the salinisation risks.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The crunch-release model (Blaikie et al. 
  <a rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0012">1994</a>) is a broad analytical framework on the causes of a disaster and disaster mitigation. The model espouses factors influencing vulnerability to a disaster by considering trigger events, elements at risk of damage or loss and vulnerable conditions both socio-ecological and physical, against actions that address underlying causes to achieve safe conditions or resilience. Developmental advocacy, policy and legislative actions, risk assessments, multi-hazards early-warning systems, public awareness and education and training (Satya 
  <a rid="CIT0070" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0070">2010</a>) are among the disaster prevention and mitigation actions suggested in the model.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Disaster risk reduction is underscored as an overarching pillar for attainment of SDGs (UN 
  <a rid="CIT0078" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0078">2015</a>). Accordingly, there is need for improved understanding of disaster risks in all its dimensions of exposure, vulnerability, hazard characteristics, strengthening of disaster risk governance for prevention, mitigation, preparedness, recovery and rehabilitation. Though precautionary principle is a tool of choice for disaster risk reduction concerning health and environmental threats in an environment of scientific uncertainty, there is paucity of appropriate frameworks for integrating implementation and decision-making support processes in the application of the principle (Fisher, Jones &amp; von Schomberg 
  <a rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0031">2006</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Most of the natural resource management technologies, such as irrigation, have both larger spatial scales and longer time horizon impacts or externalities (Knox, Meinzen-dick &amp; Hazell 
  <a rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0042">1998</a>). Failure to recognise and/or discount such threats constitutes cognitive failure and imposes long-term social costs on society (Coase 
  <a rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0014">1960</a>). The socio-ecological dilemma is rooted in isolation paradox (Baumol 
  <a rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0007">2004</a>) and free rider (Hardin 
  <a rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0032">1968</a>) analogies. This is particularly critical in planning adaptation to climate change because existence of strong environmental and conservation polices and legislation in many countries does not necessarily imply effective implementation and enforcement (Shivakoti, Ullah &amp; Pradhan 
  <a rid="CIT0073" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0073">2016</a>). Designing cost-effective collective action strategies required for abatement of environmental externalities inherent in climate change action is thus a development planning challenge.
 </p>
</sec>
