<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s20010" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The proposed conceptual framework</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A common feature of contemporary natural resource management issues is the underlying uncertainty in accounting for the problems (such as externalities) and predicting the effect of a particular management strategy. These uncertainties are, in part, a product of the growing emphasis on long-term, multi-scalar and integrative aspects of resource management among researchers, community of practice and policy makers (Biggs et al. 
  <a rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0009">2015</a>). We argue that while multi-scalar and existing integrated models are noble, cognitive failure and biases, lack of approaches for effective participation in environmental risk abatement 
  <span class="italic">vis-à-vis</span> the agency and the accountability dilemma could exacerbate the externalities and the attendant social costs.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Risk communication is strategic to a meaningful collective action in the governance and management of environmental externalities and securing public interest. However, in adaptation to climate change, policy makers and climate change adaptation actors are more concerned with immediate livelihoods needs (Easterling et al. 
  <a rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0022">2007</a>). As cognitive dissonance about a risk, such as salinisation, may result in such probabilities being downplayed or being ignored (Renn 
  <a rid="CIT0063" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0063">1998</a>), the use of communication for development and social change approaches that encompass dialogue, agency and mobilisation has been suggested as potential tools in social transformation and resilience building (Evans et al. 
  <a rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0025">2018</a>). In human- environment interactions, a risk-reduction-based planning model that incorporates knowledge, attitudes and behaviour at community level has high potential to cure cognitive failures and contribute to social transformation (Volenzo &amp; Odiyo 
  <a rid="CIT0082" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0082">2018</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Adaptation-Mitigation-Sustainable Development (AMSD) frameworks are an integral part of wider development goals in transition to sustainability and critical in policy formulation, decision-making, governance and behavioural development (Bizikova, Robinson &amp; Cohen 
  <a rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0011">2007</a>). AMSD includes the creation of local implementation pathways that increase opportunities for social learning processes and capacities for effective adaptation and mitigation (FAO 
  <a rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0028">2010b</a>). As the status of soil salinity as well as its temporal variation can be used as an indicator in the monitoring of degradation risks and as a sustainability indicator (Metternicht &amp; Zinck 
  <a rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0047">2003</a>), salinity levels can serve as an indicator of maladaptation in AMSD frameworks.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Risk communication focuses on information presentation, persuasion and strategic messages (Heath &amp; O’Hair 
  <a rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0033">2010</a>). Hence, it is critical in closing gaps between what is known by different actors about a particular risk and what needs to be known (Wardman 
  <a rid="CIT0084" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0084">2008</a>). As knowledge offers insights as to how a system might be managed, farmer’s awareness, perception of environmental risks as well as risk behaviour can be used in modelling environmental impacts in adaptation to climate change. This has the potential in resolving the social-ecological-policy dilemmas. Risk communication can thus be viewed as an integral to risk assessment, risk control, risk monitoring and review planning frameworks for sustainable climate change action. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F0001" href="#F0001">Figure 1</a> presents the proposed conceptual framework on linkages between risk communication, communication for development and sustainability in climate change action.
 </p>
 <div id="F0001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">FIGURE 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Authors’ conceptual framework on integration between risk communication and sustainable climate change action.</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="JAMBA-11-703-g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
