<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The probabilistic framework of random forests is very suitable for animal vocalisations classification tasks. Assuming that there are 
  <span class="italic">N
   <sub>tr</sub>
  </span> annotated recordings available for training then a feature matrix 
  <span class="bold">S</span> = 
  <span class="italic">N
   <sub>tr</sub>
  </span>x
  <span class="italic">N
   <sub>ft</sub>
  </span> can be constructed where 
  <span class="italic">N
   <sub>ft</sub>
  </span> represents different kinds of features stacked by column corresponding to different perspectives on how to engineer features out of spectrograms. Random forests do not need feature normalization among these heterogeneous features and can deal with dimensionality of features that can reach many thousands of dimensions. Their embedded feature selection ability during their growing effectively removes features that are not useful enough for the classification task.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As regards the computational cost deriving all features from raw recordings but the cross-correlation of ROIs (that is 
  <span class="bold">S
   <sub>1</sub>
  </span> and 
  <span class="bold">S
   <sub>2</sub>
  </span>) takes 13 minute on an I7 3.4 GHz PC. The training on 687 recordings and recognition of 1000 recordings takes another 10 minutes. The calculation of 
  <span class="bold">S
   <sub>3</sub>
  </span> takes almost 1 day and the training and testing of the whole set about 20 minutes on the same machine. One should note that the employment of Graphical Processing Units (GPUs) is possible to reduce this computational effort to a couple of hours and we are currently working to this direction.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another feature that in 
  <a rid="pone.0096936-Briggs2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0096936-Briggs2">[23]</a> was demonstrated to be highly beneficial and can potentially be integrated naturally in the statistical framework of random forests is the location of the recording device and the time-stamp of the recording. This kind of information can bias the classifier towards certain species. Location information can be inserted into ARUs during installation or through a Global Positioning System and this information can be passed automatically to the header of the sound files or to their filenames. The location of the ARUs can offer some information as regards the micro-biodiversity of the local habitat. Certain species are always found near lakes (e.g. the common kingfisher 
  <span class="italic">Alcedo Atthis</span> or around the sea-coast etc.), while others only in rocky areas far away from lakes/coast. Species information provided by the expert can be combined with location information to provide the 
  <span class="italic">a-priori</span> probability of a species being at this location. This probability is calculated as the frequency of a species appearing there to the total number of species tagged by the human expert during training. This probability matrix of all species serves as a feature that can be appended to the 
  <span class="bold">S</span> matrix. The same matrix type can be calculated for the test recordings and the classifier is responsible to resolve the situation. Time information can be drawn from the internal clock of the ARU and also passed to the header of the recording or to the filename. Time information is also important as some birds show strong preference towards the time they call or sing (e.g. night-birds). The NIPS database did not include such information but; it is information often ignored while it can be obtained easily directly from the hardware of the ARUs. We deem that this information will be vital when the number of classes will reach many hundreds of species which however neither appear altogether in a certain location not they sing/call all day long.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One would then naturally ask: what are the main difficulties in recognizing taxon-rich communities in the wild using only the acoustic modality? If one could concentrate erroneous cases they would cluster due to the following reasons:</p>
 <div list-type="alpha-lower" class="list" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>Noise in low frequencies appears quite often and quite strong because wind is low-pass and many abiotic sounds (e.g. motors, planes etc.) are also of low-pass character and can seriously mask night-birds and other species that vocalise in very low frequencies.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>Cicadas have a noise-like spectrum that resembles the spectrum of wind when they are at large distance from the recorder and their acoustic emissions are affected by reverberation. If one applies enhancement algorithms to reduce the noise and the ROIs that will be associated with noise then one can also wipe out insect species, especially when the gain of their signal is small. If one does not apply any kind of enhancement then one will face the problem of having a large number of ROIs due to noise. Cicadas can sing for the whole duration of recordings and therefore no restriction can be applied on the size of the ROIs as in other species.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>Call repertoire of one species can be very similar at least partially to that of another to the point that even a trained ear may be in doubt (e.g., different taxa of 
    <span class="italic">Parus-</span>tits or the notable case of the common kingfisher and the Dunnock - 
    <span class="italic">Prunella modularis</span>). In such cases the human observer seeks other queues of information to resolve the situation (e.g. repetition patterns) that are currently not taken into account in this work.
   </p>
  </div>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This work assessed the potential of bioacoustic monitoring of a taxon-rich community. We have developed an approach that can monitor 78 bird species, 8 insects and 1 amphibian (a total number of 87 species under quite challenging environmental conditions). The classification accuracy was assessed by independent observers and found 91.252%.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We propose that our method is a contribution towards monitoring biodiversity at large scales through the recording of vocal fauna such as birds, insects, amphibians and mammals. We claim that the approach presented will be very robust when the training and operational data are matched and we plan to apply them at diverse environments such us underwater acoustics mainly for the recognition of cetaceans and also on bats. The classification of the immense number of recordings stemming from the deployment of a large number of ARUs will allow the following:</p>
 <div list-type="alpha-lower" class="list" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>Collection of relevant data to support decisions concerning the presence, absence and distribution of species.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>Data analysis in fully automated fashion that can function in degraded audio environments.</p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>Humans and their activities can be tracked in protected areas provided they leave an audio imprint.</p>
  </div>
 </div>
</sec>
