<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There are many questions that scientists are called to address regarding the state of knowledge of global biodiversity. For all taxonomic groups only a percentage of 10–20% is known and logged. Even as regards known groups, their population, distribution and dynamic changes are mostly unknown to us. The urgent problem of grave importance is to be able to assess when an ecosystem reaches a degraded state to the point of irreversibility and answer such questions as ‘What is the state of the habitat in order to design policies and take conservation action to achieve sustainable use of the environment?’ or ‘How is climate change related to rates of species loss and migration?’.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Biodiversity monitoring provides the essential information on which conservation action is based. The monitoring process is typically carried out by qualified humans who observe and write down notes while taking logs of instruments that concentrate on the particular observation site. While the ability of a qualified scientist can be unparalleled to any kind of machine, there are also some limitations in human monitoring. The ability and the qualifications of the observers vary and this introduces a bias 
  <a rid="pone.0096936-Fitzpatrick1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0096936-Fitzpatrick1">[1]</a> in the total assessment. In addition, human expeditions are costly and can cover a limited number of sites and only work for a limited time. Moreover, the monitoring process can become more limited or even dangerous in remote, inaccessible areas. Besides, it can also be obtrusive on the species of observation.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Automatic acoustic monitoring of biodiversity is a means to provide information on species diversity with a view to the ones that are endemic, in a threatened or endangered status, or have special importance serving as indicator species. Moreover, each species is unique of its kind but can also have an additional importance due to its social, scientific, cultural or economic role.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Acoustic monitoring is limited to the part of the fauna that emits sound (birds, certain insects, certain amphibians, bats etc), which is only a subsample of the total biodiversity. However, inferring the correct taxa of this fauna and their densities can also give us an indirect cue for non-emitting sound species through their inter-dependence in the life-cycle, since animal populations are correlated.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Acoustic monitoring of biodiversity becomes, with time, a more attractive approach, as autonomous recording units (ARUs) become more affordable, can be power sufficient and can transmit their data through GSM or satellite connections from remote areas straight to the laboratory that can be located as far as in another continent. Therefore ARUs will eventually allow gathering of observations at larger spatial and time scales.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The challenge that comes along with such approach is the processing and logging of the deluge of data coming from the network of these sensors. Considering that ARUs can be operated in 24/7 modus and that several recorders can be used simultaneously, huge amounts of audio data can be gathered in relatively short periods of time. It is hardly feasible for human experts to listen to or visually inspect the complete sample of recordings. Thus semi-automatic processing of the sound files is a prerequisite for analysing the information within reasonable time limits.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The possible applications of acoustic monitoring in terrestrial environments using microphone arrays are thoroughly presented in 
  <a rid="pone.0096936-Blumstein1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0096936-Blumstein1">[2]</a>. Acoustic entropy indices 
  <a rid="pone.0096936-Sueur1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0096936-Sueur1">[3]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0096936-Riede1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0096936-Riede1">[4]</a> are also proposed as a means to assess the type of the habitat and the extent of human intervention.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There is a rich literature on automatic species identification of specific target taxon like birds 
  <a rid="pone.0096936-Briggs1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0096936-Briggs1">[5]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0096936-Potamitis1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0096936-Potamitis1">[7]</a>, amphibians 
  <a rid="pone.0096936-Slimani1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0096936-Slimani1">[8]</a>, cetaceans 
  <a rid="pone.0096936-Halkias1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0096936-Halkias1">[9]</a>, insects 
  <a rid="pone.0096936-Riede2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0096936-Riede2">[10]</a>, fish 
  <a rid="pone.0096936-Kottege1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0096936-Kottege1">[11]</a>, bats 
  <a rid="pone.0096936-Skowronski1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0096936-Skowronski1">[12]</a> and mice 
  <a rid="pone.0096936-Grimsley1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0096936-Grimsley1">[13]</a>. All these approaches are valuable as they pave the way for automatic analysis of animal vocalisations. However, they have not yet proven generic enough to scale to taxa and habitats other than the ones described in their original publication. Moreover, the misses and false alarms of these methods will cause a very large number of cases to be further investigated manually for a system that works on a 24/7 basis. Clearly the classification scores must face the high level of false positive and false negative results in order to make acoustic monitoring practical.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The present work is an attempt to shed some light on the possibility of monitoring taxon-rich communities recorded in the wild. It is our belief, shared by others, that in order to have solid progress in this research field, researchers should depart from using private data and focus on unprocessed data as typically recorded in nature. This paper introduces our approach that took part in a taxon-rich classification challenge organized by NIPS 2013 conference for bioacoustics 
  <a rid="pone.0096936-Glotin1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0096936-Glotin1">[14]</a> that involves 87 species (78 birds, 8 insects and 1 amphibian) in unprocessed wild life recordings. Competition challenges are very useful as a means to put theories into practice and assess what is the state of the art, as all competing approaches are bound by a common corpus; moreover, the assessment is guaranteed not to be biased towards a private approach, as the organizers of the challenge have the responsibility of assessing the approaches and base their final ranking on data that are unknown to the contestants 
  <a rid="pone.0096936-Glotin2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0096936-Glotin2">[15]</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We have examined all reported approaches to bioacoustic challenges 
  <a rid="pone.0096936-Glotin2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0096936-Glotin2">[15]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0096936-Bas1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0096936-Bas1">[18]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0096936-Briggs2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0096936-Briggs2">[23]</a> to find structural parallels among the best performing approaches, gather candidate functional sub-components, integrate our novel features, and finally shape our personal strategy towards the task of classifying large taxa of animal vocalisation in unprocessed field recordings. Our research concluded into three key observations that we will thoroughly analyse in the following sections:
 </p>
 <div list-type="alpha-lower" class="list" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>The treatment of sound as picture through the spectrogram as well as the application of image-based transformations to identify local properties of the target spectral blobs can have certain advantages over frame-based audio classification approaches to the task of species identification in noisy, real environments. This work belongs to the research trend the treats audio as a picture through its spectrogram 
    <a rid="pone.0096936-Briggs1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0096936-Briggs1">[5]</a>, 
    <a rid="pone.0096936-Halkias1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0096936-Halkias1">[9]</a>, 
    <a rid="pone.0096936-Brandes1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0096936-Brandes1">[16]</a>, 
    <a rid="pone.0096936-Lundy1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0096936-Lundy1">[17]</a>.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>Multi-instance, multi-label approaches have an indisputable advantage over single- label approaches in species classification tasks 
    <a rid="pone.0096936-Briggs1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0096936-Briggs1">[5]</a>.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>The synthesis of heterogeneous features is beneficial as it can provide complementary information that can be naturally integrated into the framework of decision trees in random forest ensembles.</p>
  </div>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This paper is organized as follows: In Section entitled ‘Methods’ we present: a) the database and its main difficulties as regards species recognition, b) the feature extraction and classifier from the perspective of image analysis of spectrograms, c) the single and multi-label approaches as well as the benefits of the latter. In Section entitled ‘Results’ we analyse the fine-tuning of the pattern recognition methods, perform experiments with real-field data and analyse the results of the current work. A discussion of the results concludes this work by presenting possible extensions and summarizing the implications of the results.</p>
</sec>
