<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">European beech (
 <italic class="italic">Fagus sylvatica</italic> L.) dominates the natural forest vegetation in moist to moderately dry areas of the sub-mountainous altitude range in Central Europe [
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref001" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>]. About one third of the potential beech forest area in Central Europe is located on calcareous soil that is highly susceptible to water deprivation. For future forestry in Central Europe, it has even been suggested to replace spruce by beech [
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref002" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref003" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>]. However, beech responds to lower water availability with reduced growth and competitive power, and this apparent drought sensitivity of beech is a matter of current concern and debate [
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref004" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref010" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>] due to observations of increased heat waves and drought periods in wide regions of Central Europe [
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref011" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>]. This trend is expected to continue and intensify in the coming decades [
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref012" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. Two different mechanisms have been proposed to explain the sensitivity of beech to increased temperature and drought [
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref004" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref006" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>]: (1) tree physiological limitations; and (2) nutritional limitations due to decelerated microbial N turnover in soil, specifically due to impaired liberation and provision of bioavailable N by soil microbes. The latter mechanism may be of particular importance in calcareous soils and apply especially for beech seedlings with their restricted root system, because Rendzic Leptosols are poor in bioavailable N [
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>]. Furthermore, these soils are characterized by a shallow profile, high gravel content, clayey texture, and low water and nutrient retention capacity. Hence, bioavailable N released by microorganisms is frequently limiting growth of this forest type [
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref005" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref017" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. However, due to the lack of experimental evidence, and a range of severe methodological problems in the quantification of gross N turnover in the plant-soil-microbe system, this mechanism remained a hypothesis.
</p>
