<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Nitrogen mineralization and nitrification as well as the subsequent competitive partitioning of bioavailable organic N monomers and inorganic N compounds between the soil microbes and vegetation regulate tree N uptake in N-limited forests. There is now ample evidence that trees—including European Beech—successfully compete for organic N as well as for mineral N with free living microorganisms in a wide range of forest ecosystems with or without the help of mycorrhizal fungal symbionts [
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref005" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref016" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref018" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>]. Hence, trees can actively influence soil microbial N turnover processes by competing for the same substrates at several stages of the N cycle: (1) Trees may take up monomeric organic compounds such as amino acids thus limiting this substrate for microbial uptake of dissolved organic nitrogen (DON) and microbial ammonification. (2) Trees may take up ammonium (NH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub>
 <sup class="sup">+</sup>) thus reducing substrate availability for autotrophic nitrification and microbial immobilisation. (3) Trees may take up nitrate (NO
 <sub class="sub">3</sub>
 <sup class="sup">-</sup>) thus limiting microbial NO
 <sub class="sub">3</sub>
 <sup class="sup">-</sup> utilization [
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref005" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref018" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref019" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>]. Furthermore, trees influence microbial N turnover in soil by the determination of organic matter composition via plant residues, thus influencing substrate quality for N mineralization [
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>] and by direct carbon (C) allocation to microorganisms via root exudation [
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref005" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref016" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>].
</p>
