<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Surprisingly, the recognition of the importance of plant-microbe interactions for gross N turnover has only rarely been reflected in experimental designs for quantification of soil or plant N turnover. In contrast, soil scientists usually determine gross N turnover rates in plant-free disturbed soil, and plant physiologists frequently deploy N uptake measurements with washed roots in absence of soil and soil microorganisms [
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref023" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>]. Such experimental approaches neglect plant-soil-microbe C/N interactions such as plant-microbe competition for N, microbial resupply of plant nutrients and plant rhizodeposition effects on microbial soil N turnover [
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref005" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>]. Hence it may be questioned if N flux rates determined based on isolated views of the plant or soil compartments are realistic. Studies interlinking both sides are less common and have been performed aiming at elucidating plant-microbial competition for N in different ecosystems like tundra [
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>], alpine meadow [
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>], grassland [
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref030" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>] and temperate forests [
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref031" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref036" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>]. However, these studies almost exclusively performed simple tracing experiments aiming at the determination of 
 <sup class="sup">15</sup>N recovery rates in plant and microbial N pools rather than providing actual N turnover rates. Studies characterizing the competition for N between plants and microorganisms in a process-oriented way, i.e., by determining simultaneously occurring rates of microbial N turnover in soil and N uptake by plants are still very rare [
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref005" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0158823.ref037" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>].
</p>
