<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Soil and Water Assessment Tool (SWAT) is a comprehensive, hydrological model that incorporates hydrological, chemical, and ecological processes and management practices in watershed simulation and analysis (Arnold et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">1998</xref>; Neitsch et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" class="xref">2011</xref>). It simulates the plant growth by simplifying the generic crop growth module from the erosion productivity impact calculator (EPIC) model (Neitsch et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" class="xref">2011</xref>). This model has been successfully applied for studying impact of climate change on water resources (e.g., Gosain et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">2011</xref>; Singh and Gosain 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" class="xref">2011</xref>; Narsimlu et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">2013</xref>) as well as in crop production (e.g., Lakshmanan et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" class="xref">2011</xref>; Bhuvaneswari et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">2013</xref>) in different river basins of India. Lakshmanan et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" class="xref">2011</xref>) modelled the hydrology and rice yield of the Bhavani basin in Tamil Nadu, India and showed that the SWAT can be employed under different climate change as well as management scenarios for developing adaptation strategies to sustain rice production under changing climate scenarios. SWAT has also been used to assess the impact of El Niño/Southern Oscillation on hydrology and rice productivity in the Cauvery basin in India (Bhuvaneswari et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">2013</xref>). The main objective of this paper is to assess the climate change impact on rice and wheat yield in the Gomti River basin using the SWAT hydrological model and climate change projections from Model of Interdisciplinary Research on Climate (MIROC–HiRes) GCM.
</p>
