<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Limited sampling of most species across time and space (e.g., vouchers in natural history collections), coupled with limited geographic ranges of species, makes assessing body size and phenology shifts due to climate change challenging for all but relatively few taxa. In North America, the wood frog (
 <italic class="italic">Lithobates sylvaticus</italic>) provides one such rare opportunity. The species is well represented in natural history collections; has the largest range of any amphibian on the continent (~10 million km
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>); spans 35°–65°N latitude; and has a latitudinal gradient in body size that follows the converse of James’ rule (i.e., larger in the south, smaller in the north, Angilletta &amp; Dunham, 
 <xref rid="ece33636-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2003</xref>; Davenport &amp; Hossack, 
 <xref rid="ece33636-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>; Martof &amp; Humphries, 
 <xref rid="ece33636-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1959</xref>), hypothesized to reflect the greater number of available feeding days in the south, leading to larger body sizes there compared to more northern latitudes (Martof &amp; Humphries, 
 <xref rid="ece33636-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1959</xref>). Interestingly, studies by Berven (
 <xref rid="ece33636-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1982</xref>) of the same species across elevational rather than latitudinal gradients demonstrated that animals from higher (colder) elevations were larger than those at lower (warmer) elevations. Together, these studies indicate that mechanisms operating at small (e.g., within a mountain range across elevations) and large (e.g., continental) scales may differ or that our conclusions as to the mechanisms depend on scale. In this study, we quantify the relationship between climate and both body size and phenology of wood frogs across their entire range (Figure 
 <xref rid="ece33636-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>) from prior to rapid climate warming (1901–1960) using a spatially explicit approach. We then test whether those relationships are maintained during rapid climate warming (1961–2000), in order to determine whether climate is likely to be acting directly or indirectly on size and breeding phenology.
</p>
