<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Global Alliance against chronic Respiratory Disease (GARD)</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In view of these reviewed evidences, it is important that the scientific community engages in advocacy activities. An important tool for pulmonologists and allegologists is GARD, a partnership among WHO, governments, scientific societies and patients organization, launched in Beijing in 2006.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hundreds of millions of people of all ages suffer from chronic respiratory diseases which include asthma and respiratory allergies, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, occupational lung diseases and pulmonary hypertension. More than 500 million patients live in developing countries or in deprived populations. Chronic respiratory diseases are increasing in prevalence. Although the cost of inaction is clear and unacceptable, chronic respiratory diseases and their risk factors receive insufficient attention from the healthcare community, government officials, media, patients and families. The Fifty-Third World Health Assembly recognised the enormous human suffering caused by chronic diseases and requested the World Health Organization (WHO) Director General to give priority to the prevention and control of chronic diseases, with special emphasis on developing countries. This led to the formation of the WHO Global Alliance against Chronic Respiratory Diseases (GARD). GARD is a voluntary alliance of organisations, institutions and agencies working towards a common vision to improve global lung health according to local needs. GARD is developed in a stepwise approach using the following three planning steps: estimate population need and advocate action; formulate and adopt policy; and identify policy implementation steps [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The 2008-2013 WHO action plan on noncommunicable diseases (NCDs) includes chronic respiratory diseases as one of its four priorities. Major chronic respiratory diseases (CRDs) include asthma and rhinitis, chronic obstructive pulmonary disease, occupational lung diseases, sleep-disordered breathing, pulmonary hypertension, bronchiectiasis and pulmonary interstitial diseases. A billion people suffer from chronic respiratory diseases, the majority being in developing countries. CRDs have major adverse effects on the life and disability of patients. Effective intervention plans can prevent and control CRDs, thus reducing morbidity and mortality. A prioritised research agenda should encapsulate all of these considerations in the frame of the global fight against NCDs. This requires both CRD-targeted interventions and transverse NCD programmes which include CRDs, with emphasis on health promotion and disease prevention [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The prevention of CRDs and reducing their social and individual impacts means modifying environmental and social factors and improving diagnosis and treatment. Prevention of risk factors (tobacco smoke, allergens, occupational agents, indoor/outdoor air pollution) will significantly impact on morbidity and mortality. The Italian Ministry of Health (MoH) has made respiratory disease prevention a top priority and is implementing a comprehensive strategy with policies against tobacco smoking, indoor/outdoor pollution, obesity, and communicable diseases. Presently these actions are not well coordinated. The Global Alliance against Chronic Respiratory Diseases (GARD), set up by the World Health Organization, envisages national bodies; the GARD initiative in Italy, launched 11/6/2009, represents a great opportunity for the MoH. Its main objective is to promote the development of a coordinated CRD program in Italy. Effective prevention implies setting up a health policy with the support of healthcare professionals and citizen associations at national, regional, and district levels. What is required is a true inter-institutional synergy: respiratory diseases prevention cannot and should not be the responsibility of doctors alone, but must involve politicians/policymakers, as well as the media, local institutions, and schools, etc. GARD could be a significant experience and a great opportunity for Italy to share the GARD vision of a world where all people can breathe freely [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">GARD Italy has been engaged in the following projects:
  <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>A) Period 2010-2012:</p>
   </div>
  </div>
  <div list-type="order" class="list">
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Prevention program for schools of indoor risks for respiratory and allergic diseases</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Smoking and environment in the household</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Development of predictive medicine within respiratory diseases</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Early diagnosis implementation through pathways for health staff</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p>Care continuity
     <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
      <div class="list-item">
       <span class="label"/>
       <p>B) Period 2012-2014:</p>
      </div>
     </div>
     <div list-type="order" class="list">
      <div class="list-item">
       <p>Environment and respiratory diseases</p>
      </div>
      <div class="list-item">
       <p>Surveillance of respiratory diseases</p>
      </div>
      <div class="list-item">
       <p>Education: asthma and allergies in childhood</p>
      </div>
      <div class="list-item">
       <p>Smoking and environment in the household</p>
      </div>
      <div class="list-item">
       <p>Care continuity: respiratory impairment
        <div list-type="bullet" class="list">
         <div class="list-item">
          <span class="label"/>
          <p>Within the Program “Environment and respiratory diseases”, a national Workshop, convened by Annamaria De Martino, Italian MoH officer, at the Ministry of Health building in Rome has been held on December 16-17, 2013, to contribute to the European “Year of the Air”. The topics have been: Climate, Air Quality and Respiratory Health. Italian and European projects (EPIAIR, REVIHAP, ESCAPE, OFFICAIR, for outdoor pollution; SEARCH, HESE, HESEINT, SINPHONIE, for indoor pollution) have been reviewed. The opinions of patients have been described by the representatives of asthma and COPD patients associations. A round table on “Environment and Health: The role of the Institutions” has been performed by representatives of the MoH, Ministry of Environment, Ministry of Education, University and Research, Regions, National Health Institute, National Environmental Protection Institute</p>
         </div>
         <div class="list-item">
          <span class="label"/>
          <p>During the Italian Presidency of the Council of European Union (July 1- December 31, 2014), a Meeting of Chief Medical, Chief Nursing and Chief Dental Officers at the Ministry of Health building in Rome has been held on October 6-7, 2014. Giovanni Viegi (Italian representative in the international GARD) has delivered a speech on “Prevention and Organizational Models for Respiratory Chronic Diseases (including Allergies) and has collaborated with Giselda Scalera and Giovanna Laurendi, Italian MoH medical officers, to draft a working document on “CRD: an important public health problem”, with the following sections: Definition; Epidemiology; EU and international scenario; Proposal for discussion (CRD surveillance; CRD care) aimed at EU strategy for prioritizing CRD prevention, diagnosis and care.</p>
         </div>
         <div class="list-item">
          <span class="label"/>
          <p>At last, convened by Annamaria De Martino, Italian MoH medical officer, a Workshop on “Indoor Air Pollution and Health in Italian Schools” at the Ministry of Health building in Rome has been held on February 23, 2015. In such occasion, results of the Italian CCM funded project on “Exposure to indoor pollutants: guidelines for the assessment of risk factors in school environment and definition of the measures for respiratory health protection of schoolchildren and adolescents”, coordinated by ISS and CNR, have been reported.</p>
         </div>
        </div>
       </p>
      </div>
     </div>
    </p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
