<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">With the implementation of Grain for Green Project in the Loess Plateau, apple production is becoming one of the dominating industries for the local economy. However, due to severe water scarcity, the sustainability of apple tree growth is threatened. To evaluate the sustainability of apple tree development in the Loess Plateau, this paper established a water suitability model for apple plantations and analyzed the apple tree water suitability in each of the sub-regions. The main findings are as follows: 
 <list list-type="simple" class="list">
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <label class="label">(1)</label>
   <p class="p">In the past period (1990–2013), the order of the average water demand of apple trees in each sub-region was Shaanxi Province &gt; Yuncheng Region &gt; Gansu Province &gt; Sanmenxia Region, and the water demand ranged from 500 to 950 mm. The temporal variability of water suitability from 1990 to 2013 was large, and the higher values of water suitability were concentrated in the late growth stage of the apple trees and the lower values were concentrated in the early growth stage of the apple trees. </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <label class="label">(2)</label>
   <p class="p">In the future (2019–2050), the temporal evolution of apple tree water suitability is projected to be relatively stable, and the spatial distribution is projected to be relatively even. Generally, the water suitability in the northern and western areas is expected to be lower than that in the southern and eastern areas. </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <label class="label">(3)</label>
   <p class="p">We found that the water suitability is mainly affected by effective precipitation and meteorological factors including wind speed (U
    <sub class="sub">2</sub>), solar radiation (R
    <sub class="sub">n</sub>), average temperature (T
    <sub class="sub">mean</sub>), and actual vapor pressure (e
    <sub class="sub">a</sub>). The contribution rates of the four factors to ET
    <sub class="sub">0</sub> change are respectively 18%, 36%, 38%, and 8%. 
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <label class="label">(4)</label>
   <p class="p">The findings in this paper indicate that the water suitability of apple plantations showed a decreasing trend in the past period (1990–2013) but that the slope of downward trend of water suitability is expected to be greatly reduced in the future period. Therefore, we speculate that the water available for apple tree growth will be more sufficient under future climate change than that observed in the past period. However, with that said, it is important not to be over-optimistic. With this in mind, we also proposed several key measures to improve the sustainability of apple plantations in the Loess Plateau in the future.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
