<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Of the literature used in this analysis, six studies failed to consider the direct effect of high [CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>] on soybeans. All studies projected yield losses for soybean, which might be mitigated by agricultural management adaptations such as changing the planting date (
 <xref rid="pcx141-B34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">do Rio et al. 2016</xref>), change of cultivars (
 <xref rid="pcx141-B10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Battisti et al. 2017</xref>) or introducing double-cropping systems (
 <xref rid="pcx141-B69" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Lant et al. 2016</xref>). The global study of 
 <xref rid="pcx141-B122" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Tatsumi et al. (2011)</xref> projected yield decrease for all the major soybean producing areas. However, this study applied several significant simplifications such as use of monthly step climatic data, ignoring CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> fertilization effects and the water-holding capacity of soils. Twenty-seven studies that took into account CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> fertilization effects projected significant yield gains. Of these, only one global assessment that took into account the added carbon gain arising from future high atmospheric [CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>], projected moderate (5–15%) yield losses and this was only for regions in US and Latin-America (
 <xref rid="pcx141-B31" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Deryng et al. 2014</xref>). The same study did not investigate the potential of management adaptation options. In relation to adaptation, in fact, we find that some 16 out of the 37 studies investigated adaptation options. These studies suggest that management adaptation options can have a significant effect in counterbalancing the negative effects of climate change (
 <xref rid="pcx141-B127" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Tubiello et al. 2000</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pcx141-B23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Challinor et al. 2014b</xref>). According to some simulations, some crop management options (e.g. winter rye cover) have no effect on future yields but they have the potential to reduce soil erosion and nitrous oxide emissions significantly (
 <xref rid="pcx141-B8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Basche et al. 2016</xref>).
</p>
