<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec009" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Population growth rate</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Population growth rates declined over time for most species in both DBR and BCI (
  <a rid="pone.0126228.g002" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0126228.g002">Fig 2</a>). In DBR, except for 
  <span class="italic">C</span>. 
  <span class="italic">chinensis</span> and 
  <span class="italic">C</span>. 
  <span class="italic">concinna</span> in community II (the 
  <span class="italic">Pinus-Castanopsis-Schima</span> community), the population growth rates of the other species in the two communities decreased over time (
  <a rid="pone.0126228.g002" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0126228.g002">Fig 2A and 2B</a>). We analysed the distribution of the change rates for population growth rate in BCI, and the results showed that the population growth rates for most species (84.4%; 65 of 77 species) decreased (Figs 
  <a rid="pone.0126228.g002" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0126228.g002">2C</a> and 
  <a rid="pone.0126228.g003" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0126228.g003">3A</a>), with 27.7% of those species showing a significant decrease. Based on the 77 species in BCI, we carried out a correlation analysis between the population growth rate (lnλ) and time (the median of each five-year interval) to explore the relationship between the correlation coefficients and the abundances of species. The results indicated that many species with higher abundance showed decreasing trends of population growth rate (
  <a rid="pone.0126228.g003" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0126228.g003">Fig 3B</a>).
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0126228.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0126228.g002</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 2</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Changes in population growth rate, lnλ, over time in DBR and BCI.</div>
   <p>Vertical lines indicate census years, and points indicate the population growth rate, lnλ, per interval. Community I: 
    <span class="italic">Cryptocarya</span> community; Community II: 
    <span class="italic">Pinus-Castanopsis-Schima</span> community.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0126228.g002" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <div id="pone.0126228.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0126228.g003</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 3</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Distribution of the rate of change in population growth rate for 77 dominant species in BCI.</div>
   <p>(a) Distribution of the liner regression coefficient β of lnλ over time. (b) Relationship between abundance and the correlation coefficient for lnλ and time.</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0126228.g003" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Species in the two communities on DBR responded differently to the time factor (
  <span class="italic">t</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">1</span>
  </sub>
  <span class="italic">+t</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">2</span>
  </sub>). Population growth rate of the 3 species showed a negative response to time in community I, while showing a positive response in community II (
  <a rid="pone.0126228.g004" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0126228.g004">Fig 4</a>). The annual precipitation had a positive effect on community I but had a negative effect on community II. The annual average temperature had a positive effect on 
  <span class="italic">C</span>. 
  <span class="italic">concinna</span> in community I and on the 3 species in community II. For the 77 species in BCI, the population growth rate, lnλ, showed a negative response to the time factor (
  <span class="italic">t</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">1</span>
  </sub>
  <span class="italic">+t</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">2</span>
  </sub>) (87%, significant), a negative association with the annual average precipitation (62.3%, significant) and a positive association with the annual average temperature (85.7%, significant).
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0126228.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0126228.g004</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 4</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">A multivariate linear regression revealed the effects of climate and time factors on population growth rate in DBR and BCI.</div>
   <p>The climate factors are annual mean precipitation (mm) and annual mean temperature (°C) for each time interval. The time factor is 
    <span class="italic">t</span>
    <sub>
     <span class="italic">1</span>
    </sub>
    <span class="italic">+t</span>
    <sub>
     <span class="italic">2</span>
    </sub> (year), which is the sum of two observation years. All 3 models in community I, the model of 
    <span class="italic">C</span>. 
    <span class="italic">chinensis</span> in community II of DBR, and the 77 models in BCI are significant (P&lt;0.05). Estimates and 95% confidence intervals of coefficients for three variables are indicated.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0126228.g004" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
