<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Resilience is popularly understood as the degree of elasticity in a system, its ability to rebound or bounce back after experiencing some stress or shock. The concept of resilience is unusually “plastic” [
 <xref rid="B44-ijerph-13-01211" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>], “highly ambiguous” [
 <xref rid="B45-ijerph-13-01211" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>], vague and malleable [
 <xref rid="B37-ijerph-13-01211" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>], and often used as a promiscuous approach, like global commodity chains [
 <xref rid="B46-ijerph-13-01211" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>,
 <xref rid="B47-ijerph-13-01211" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>] incorporating different meanings in different contexts. This is because of a blending of descriptive (what the case is) and normative aspects (what the case should be) within its conceptualization [
 <xref rid="B37-ijerph-13-01211" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>]. Although there are scholarly arguments on the positives and negatives of the ambiguity and plasticity of the concept of resilience [
 <xref rid="B34-ijerph-13-01211" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B37-ijerph-13-01211" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="B44-ijerph-13-01211" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>,
 <xref rid="B45-ijerph-13-01211" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="B48-ijerph-13-01211" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>], the positives and the negatives of the malleability of the concept can be offset through a ‘division of labor’ of the resilience scientists. Resilience as a descriptive concept, with precise definition and meaning and operationalized quantitatively, can be applied to hard systems in physical, ecological, and climate hard sciences. Resilience, in this usage, can be dubbed as ecosystem resilience, ecological resilience, engineering resilience, or simply, resilience. Resilience as a normative concept, on the other hand, with inherent vagueness and malleability, and with an opportunity to be operationalized qualitatively, can be applied to trans-disciplinary analyses of soft systems like social, political, and cultural systems. In this usage, resilience can be termed as ‘social resilience’, ‘cultural resilience’, ‘economic resilience’, or ‘community resilience’.
</p>
