<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Resilience of a system (or community) incorporates both static and dynamic properties. On the one hand, resilience is conceptualized as an inherent or antecedent condition or state or ‘outcome’ [
 <xref rid="B10-ijerph-13-01211" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-ijerph-13-01211" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="B45-ijerph-13-01211" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="B51-ijerph-13-01211" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">51</xref>]. Inherent resilience reflects an ontological definition of resilience which focuses on the system’s ‘being’ [
 <xref rid="B52-ijerph-13-01211" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>,
 <xref rid="B53-ijerph-13-01211" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">53</xref>], i.e., its ability to function well under normal circumstances in non-crisis periods and its ability to reinstate the pre-crisis stability (i.e., bounce back) if any catastrophe strikes it. In other words, inherent resilience can be thought of “as a snapshot in time or as a static state” [
 <xref rid="B42-ijerph-13-01211" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>], a system’s latent attributes [
 <xref rid="B49-ijerph-13-01211" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>,
 <xref rid="B50-ijerph-13-01211" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>]. On the other hand, a system’s resilience is also its adaptive quality during and after a crisis—it is a ‘process’. This dimension is related with the phenomenological view which focuses on ’becoming’ [
 <xref rid="B52-ijerph-13-01211" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>] or ’doing’ [
 <xref rid="B53-ijerph-13-01211" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">53</xref>]. In this view, resilience is not a fixed property of the system; rather, it incorporates the idea that a resilient system has flexibility in responding to hazards in that the system’s initial structure or function might undergo some necessary changes—resilience is viewed as “a quality, characteristic or result that is generated or developed by the processes that foster or promote it” [
 <xref rid="B34-ijerph-13-01211" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>]. Dovers and Handmer view outcome vs. process dimensions of resilience as reactive and proactive resilience. At the center of reactive resilience is the “quest for constancy or stability” [
 <xref rid="B54-ijerph-13-01211" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>], while proactive resilience “accepts the inevitability of change and tries to create a system that is capable of adapting to new conditions and imperatives” [
 <xref rid="B55-ijerph-13-01211" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>]. Static and dynamic resilience can lead to diverse community resilience programs. For example, outcome-oriented resilience schemes tend to espouse ‘command and control styles’ which aim to retain the social status quo. Process-oriented disaster resilience schemes, on the other hand, focus on the series of actions that enhance a community’s coping capacity over time.
</p>
