<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The overall high yield potentials of DT and DS ideotypes and their differences under future climatic conditions could be considered as the interactive effects between drought tolerance/sensitivity during reproductive development and eight cultivar parameters optimized for high yield potential under the target climatic condition. Our results demonstrate the importance of the drought tolerance trait during reproductive development in achieving higher yield potentials for the DT ideotype, along with an extra beneficial effect of improved cultivar parameters, linked with high yield and drought tolerance directly and indirectly, whereas results for the DS ideotype, where selected cultivar parameters were not able to be optimized to the same extent as for DT, show that drought sensitivity during reproductive development limits optimization of those parameters. However, optimized cultivar parameters in the DS ideotype compensated for the potential yield loss due to drought sensitivity during reproductive development at least to some extent. Thus, the present study reveals that improved cultivar parameters, such as decreased leaf senescence, reduced response of photosynthesis to water stress and increased root water uptake, may increase yield potentials also for drought-sensitive cultivars. Different studies reported similar importance of drought tolerance during reproductive development and different improved plant traits for high yield potentials of different crops including wheat (
 <xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Manschadi 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2006
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Cattivelli 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2008
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ji 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2010
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Farooq 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2014
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="CIT0066" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Semenov 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2014
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="CIT0083" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Yadav and Sharma, 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="CIT0069" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Shavrukov 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2017
 </xref>).
</p>
