<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The SDM was estimated using Maxent from the R package “dismo” (
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hijmans et al., 2017</xref>) with bioclimatic variables obtained from the WorldClim database (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hijmans et al., 2005</xref>). This model was used to predict habitat suitability under a climate change scenario with severe greenhouse gas emissions. Future climate data downscaled to 10 arc minutes (according to the Delta Method of IPCC AR4) was downloaded from the CCAFS-Climate data portal using the R package “ccafs” (
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Chamberlain, 2017</xref>). The decanal availability of downscaled data constrained the choice of climate change scenario – I used the Global Circulation Model “mpi_echam5” (developed at the Max Planck Institute for Meteorology) with the emissions scenario “A2” (which predicts temperature increases of 2.0–5.4°C by 2100) for the period 2020–2090. Besides bioclimatic variables, only cells where water was present were defined as suitable. The presence of water was obtained from the Global Lakes and Wetlands Database (WWF, the Center for Environmental Systems Research, University of Kassel, Germany). To avoid collinearity and model overfit in the SDM, bioclimatic variables were selected by using a backward selection procedure in which variables that were less important to explain species presence and had correlation coefficients &gt;0.70 were first excluded until all pairwise correlations were below 0.70. Model performance was assessed using cross-validation and the ROC curve area between training and test data. The most important variable for all species was the temperature annual range, except for 
 <italic class="italic">B. maritimus</italic>, which was temperature seasonality. Other important variables common to all species included precipitation seasonality and mean temperature of wettest quarter. Common variables to at least two species included the mean temperature of driest quarter and minimum temperature of coldest month (
 <bold class="bold">Table 
  <xref ref-type="table" rid="T1" class="xref">1</xref>
 </bold>). Model performance ranged from 0.91 to 0.96, as estimated by the ROC curve area corresponding to the Somers’ Dxy rank correlation between training and test data.
</p>
