<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The Iberian Peninsula is at the frontier between two contrasting climate types: the Atlantic in the northern region that is characterized by mild temperatures, and the Mediterranean in the southern region (one of 25 biodiversity hotspots [
 <xref rid="pone.0181325.ref012" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]), typified by high temperatures and droughts [
 <xref rid="pone.0181325.ref013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0181325.ref016" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. Freshwater fish of the 
 <italic class="italic">Squalius</italic> genus (Cyprinidae family) are endemic to river basins and regions in these two different climates, providing an opportunity to study closely-related species under these two climate types [
 <xref rid="pone.0181325.ref017" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. 
 <italic class="italic">S</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">carolitertii</italic> [
 <xref rid="pone.0181325.ref018" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>] inhabits the Atlantic-type northern region, whereas 
 <italic class="italic">S</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">torgalensis</italic> [
 <xref rid="pone.0181325.ref019" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>], a critically endangered species, has a more restricted distribution within the Mira river basin in the Mediterranean-type southwestern region [
 <xref rid="pone.0181325.ref019" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>]. Hence, these two species reside under different environmental conditions, with distinct seasonal and even daily water temperature fluctuations, and demonstrate different traits that are possibly the result of adaptation to these contrasting environmental conditions [
 <xref rid="pone.0181325.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0181325.ref015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>]. Compared to 
 <italic class="italic">S</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">carolitertii</italic>, S. 
 <italic class="italic">torgalensis</italic> has a shorter life span, earlier spawning age, and a smaller body size, all of which are characteristics of species inhabiting more unstable environments [
 <xref rid="pone.0181325.ref015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>]. Also, 
 <italic class="italic">S</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">torgalensis</italic> may be better adapted to cope with higher temperatures, since it is able to induce 
 <italic class="italic">hsps</italic> genes in response to high temperatures and acute thermal stress [
 <xref rid="pone.0181325.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0181325.ref020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. Conversely, 
 <italic class="italic">S</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">carolitertii</italic> was shown to be unable to cope with temperatures as high as 35°C and either lacked or presented a weak response in terms of 
 <italic class="italic">hsps</italic> gene expression under stress [
 <xref rid="pone.0181325.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0181325.ref020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. Furthermore, in a transcriptomic study, these two species presented differences in gene expression patterns between control (18°C) and heat shock treatment (30°C) [
 <xref rid="pone.0181325.ref020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. Moreover, a vast set of potential target genes involved in protein folding, energy metabolism, circadian rhythms and immune responses for use in thermal studies of these species has become available.
</p>
