<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2a" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Material</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We analyzed stable isotope profiles (expressed as 
  <span class="italic">δ</span>
  <span class="sup">13</span>C and 
  <span class="italic">δ</span>
  <span class="sup">15</span>N values) of muscle tissues of 110 grey wolves from Russia, Belarus, Latvia, Ukraine, and Poland. They represented a subsample of 317 individuals from 15 geographical regions that were analyzed for mitochondrial DNA (mtDNA) control region and 14 microsatellite loci by Pilot 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span>
  <a rid="pone.0039341-Pilot1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0039341-Pilot1">[7]</a>. That earlier study had found support for two cryptic subpopulations as defined by the microsatellite DNA data (here referred to as NUC1 and NUC2), and further subdivision based on mtDNA data (MIT1 – MIT4) 
  <a rid="pone.0039341-Pilot1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0039341-Pilot1">[7]</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Between 4 and 15 samples were analyzed from each geographical region, except for the southernmost region, CHAR, where only one sample was analyzed. Geographic distribution of the samples is presented in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0039341-g001" href="#pone-0039341-g001">Figure 1</a>. The number of samples analyzed per region was limited by the availability of the suitable material (i.e. muscle tissue samples preserved frozen). Other types of tissue could not be used in the comparative analysis due to differences in the isotopic turnover rate, and ethanol-preserved samples were not suitable for the analysis. As shown in the study on North American grey wolves, the sample sizes of n ≥4 should correctly reflect the stable isotope profiles of the local populations 
  <a rid="pone.0039341-FoxDobbs1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0039341-FoxDobbs1">[17]</a>. These results are consistent with another study performed for the black-tailed deer 
  <a rid="pone.0039341-Clementz1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0039341-Clementz1">[18]</a>. All samples were collected in the winter season (November-March) over a period of 9 years between 1995 and 2004. All individuals were adults or subadults, i.e. all were weaned. Individuals of both sexes were analyzed: 68 (62%) males and 42 (38%) females.
 </p>
 <div id="pone-0039341-g001" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0039341.g001</span>
  <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Geographic distribution of the grey wolf samples used in the stable isotope analysis.</div>
   <p>One point represents an individual or a group of individuals sampled in the same location, and large circles represent geographical regions the samples were grouped into. The samples were assigned to subpopulations delimited based on allele frequencies at 14 microsatellite loci (NUC 1 and NUC2), and frequencies of mtDNA haplotypes (MIT1-MIT4) based on the analysis of a larger dataset in Pilot 
    <span class="italic">et al.</span>
    <a rid="pone.0039341-Pilot1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0039341-Pilot1">[7]</a>. Dashed line represents the approximate border between two habitats: temperate mixed forest and forest-steppe.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0039341.g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We analyzed muscle tissue samples which have a relatively fast turnover rate (a few months), because this allowed us to assess the diet obtained from an individual within a single locality, and to thereby avoid confounding signals from diet during earlier life stages (as would be reflected in bone collagen). Most wolves disperse from their natal packs, and they are able to move over distances up to 1000 km 
  <a rid="pone.0039341-Wabakken1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0039341-Wabakken1">[19]</a>. Therefore, using muscle tissue instead of bone collagen allowed us to control for geographic location when comparing isotopic variation against genetic diversity. The short time span represented in the muscle tissues is compensated by the fact that the samples from all but three regions were obtained in multiple years, and from a range of dates through the winter months. Therefore they represent averaged diet signals from several winter seasons and provide a good representation of the full winter season. Our data are thus season-specific yet time-averaged.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Additionally, in order to check whether stable isotope profiles accurately reflect wolf diet, we analyzed muscle tissue samples from the most common wolf prey species in Eastern Europe: moose 
  <span class="italic">Alces alces</span> (5 individuals), red deer 
  <span class="italic">Cervus elaphus</span> (5), roe deer 
  <span class="italic">Capreolus capreolus</span> (5), wild boar 
  <span class="italic">Sus scrofa</span> (4), beaver 
  <span class="italic">Castor fiber</span> (5), and brown hare 
  <span class="italic">Lepus europaeus</span> (9). These species accounted for a majority of biomass consumed by wolves in Eastern European ecosystems, as inferred from feces or stomach content composition 
  <a rid="pone.0039341-Filonov1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0039341-Filonov1">[20]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0039341-Zunna1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0039341-Zunna1">[25]</a>. The prey tissues were also sampled in Central-Eastern Europe, but did not cover all the geographic range of the wolf samples. Small sample size and geographic coverage of prey species (due to the limited availability of contemporary samples for this study) limits our resolution for determining diet composition, but this is not a primary objective for this study where our focus is instead on comparing a proxy to diet (wolf 
  <span class="italic">δ</span>
  <span class="sup">15</span>N and 
  <span class="italic">δ</span>
  <span class="sup">13</span>C stable isotope values) to population genetic structure.
 </p>
</sec>
