<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Recent studies on highly mobile carnivoran mammals have revealed cryptic population genetic structures that correlate to transitions in habitat types and prey species composition 
  <a rid="pone.0039341-Rueness1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0039341-Rueness1">[1]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0039341-MuozFuentes1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0039341-MuozFuentes1">[10]</a>. For example, in the Canadian lynx 
  <span class="italic">Lynx canadensis</span>, three genetically distinct units were revealed throughout the species range, which corresponded to three demographically distinct populations, each with synchronized population cycles, inhabiting three climatic regions 
  <a rid="pone.0039341-Rueness1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0039341-Rueness1">[1]</a>. Further study suggested that differential snow conditions between these regions leads to different predator-prey dynamics of the lynx and its main prey, the snowshoe hare 
  <span class="italic">Lepus americanus</span>, which de-synchronizes population cycles between regions and leads to the genetic structure 
  <a rid="pone.0039341-Stenseth1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0039341-Stenseth1">[2]</a>. Other examples show genetic differentiation that appears to be directly correlated to prey specialization. Dalén 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. 
  <a rid="pone.0039341-Daln1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0039341-Daln1">[4]</a> demonstrated that the genetic structure of the Arctic fox 
  <span class="italic">Alopex lagopus</span> throughout its range corresponds to two ecotypes, one specialized on lemmings and another feeding on coastal food. Habitat and dietary differentiation has also been shown to correlate with genetic structure in the grey wolf 
  <span class="italic">Canis lupus</span>
  <a rid="pone.0039341-Pilot1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0039341-Pilot1">[7]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0039341-MuozFuentes1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0039341-MuozFuentes1">[10]</a>. More similar examples can be found in some social Odontocete (toothed whale) species that also show cryptic population subdivisions correlating with habitat structure or prey specializations (see review in 
  <a rid="pone.0039341-Hoelzel1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0039341-Hoelzel1">[11]</a>). For the killer whale 
  <span class="italic">Orcinus orca</span>, it has been proposed that social learning about how and where to exploit reliable prey resources promotes philopatry, and leads to the genetic differentiation between sympatric and parapatric populations that specialize on different prey resources 
  <a rid="pone.0039341-Hoelzel2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0039341-Hoelzel2">[12]</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It could be argued that differentiation with respect to diet may be expected among populations that have been isolated enough to differentiate genetically, and that there may be no causative relationship. However, it is not always the case that resource specialization is correlated to population genetic structure. For example, sympatric habitat specialist oystercatchers (
  <span class="italic">Haematopus ostralegus</span>) showed no sign of genetic differentiation (in contrast to sympatric killer whale specialists, see above) 
  <a rid="pone.0039341-vanTreuren1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0039341-vanTreuren1">[13]</a>, and the pattern of speciation among sibling species of triplefin fish (Tripterygiidae) did not always follow expectations based on resource specializations 
  <a rid="pone.0039341-Wellenreuther1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0039341-Wellenreuther1">[14]</a>. There is a need to define the specific mechanisms, in order to better understand why reproductive isolation is promoted in some cases and not others.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A candidate mechanism leading to genetic differentiation based on resource specialization is biased dispersal towards familiar resource or habitat. Non-random dispersal, possibly directed by suitable habitat or resource acquisition, may lead to genetic structuring and evolutionary differentiation by genetic drift. For example, a study of a local population of great tits 
  <span class="italic">Parus major</span> showed that non-random dispersal driven by differences in habitat quality may reinforce rapid evolutionary differentiation over spatial scales that are surprisingly small relative to the dispersal range of the species 
  <a rid="pone.0039341-Garant1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0039341-Garant1">[15]</a>. Behavioral studies on a broad range of animal taxa indicate that dispersing animals exhibit preferences toward habitats containing cues comparable to those in their natal habitat 
  <a rid="pone.0039341-Davis1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0039341-Davis1">[16]</a>. However, most evidence gathered so far that habitat and/or dietary differentiation may promote genetic differentiation at neutral markers has been indirect, based on correlative studies of populations living in different ecological conditions. More direct evidence is rare, however a study that combined direct tracking of individual coyotes (
  <span class="italic">Canis latrans</span>) with the analysis of genetic differentiation demonstrated that conservative habitat selection among individual dispersers served as a proximate mechanism for genetic structuring 
  <a rid="pone.0039341-Sacks1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0039341-Sacks1">[5]</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this study, we analyzed the diet (as reflected in stable isotope profiles) of individual European grey wolves with known genotypes in an area where cryptic population genetic structure has been earlier revealed. Pilot 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span>
  <a rid="pone.0039341-Pilot1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0039341-Pilot1">[7]</a> studied 643 wolves from 59 locations representing most of this species distribution in eastern Europe and found population genetic structure that correlated with climate, habitat type and diet composition. In that study, the correlation between prey choice and population structure was studied using the mean share of four ungulate prey species in wolf diet (based on published data about the frequency of a given species among the ungulates killed by wolves in a given area). However, the data on wolf diet were only available for 17 out of 59 regions studied, and in most cases they were not collected in exactly the same locality as the samples for the genetic analyses. For regions where prey composition could not be included, another environmental variable tested, the vegetation type, was the most important variable in terms of the strength of the correlation and the percentage of genetic variation explained 
  <a rid="pone.0039341-Pilot1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0039341-Pilot1">[7]</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Where diet composition could be tested, the strength of the correlation depended on the genetic markers used (mitochondrial vs nuclear). However, because the species composition of ungulates (being the staple prey of wolves) strongly depends on habitat type and climate, genetically differentiated wolves may be expected to differ in diet composition, either due to differential prey choice, or another habitat cue correlating with prey composition. We therefore use stable isotope analysis to obtain discrete information on the individual diet of wolves for which microsatellite and mtDNA genotypes have been obtained in the earlier study 
  <a rid="pone.0039341-Pilot1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0039341-Pilot1">[7]</a>. We test the hypothesis that dietary data explain the greatest proportion of neutral genetic variance for local populations of the grey wolf in comparison with data on geographic distance – a result expected if wolf population differentiation is shaped by ecological factors rather than geographical constraints.
 </p>
</sec>
