<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2b" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sample Preparation and Stable Isotope Analysis</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The samples were dried at 60°C for 48 h and homogenized with a mortar and pestle. To extract lipids, dried powdered samples were placed in glass tubes and immersed in 1.5 ml of 2∶ 1 mixture of chloroform : methanol. Samples were left in a shaker for 24 hours, then left undisturbed for 30 min, centrifuged for 10 min at 8 000 rpm and the supernatant was then discarded. This process was repeated at least three times or more until the supernatant was completely clear and colorless following centrifugation. Then samples were dried at 60°C for 24 h.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One mg of each sample was loaded into tin capsules. The samples were analyzed for their 
  <span class="sup">15</span>N and 
  <span class="sup">13</span>C isotopic composition using an automated nitrogen-carbon analyser (ANCA) coupled to a 20/20 isotope ratio mass spectrometer (IRMS) (SerCon Ltd, Crewe, UK). Two different analytical quality control samples (AQCs) were also analyzed with each batch for quality control purposes. These two AQCs were glutamic acid (
  <span class="italic">δ</span>
  <span class="sup">15</span>N
  <sub>Air</sub>: −5.04‰ and 
  <span class="italic">δ</span>
  <span class="sup">13</span>C
  <sub>VPDB</sub>: −28.50‰) and leucine (
  <span class="italic">δ</span>
  <span class="sup">15</span>N
  <sub>Air</sub>: 10.77‰ and 
  <span class="italic">δ</span>
  <span class="sup">13</span>C
  <sub>VPDB</sub>: −31.18‰). The international reference materials used for scale calibration were IAEA-CH6 (
  <span class="italic">δ</span>
  <span class="sup">13</span>C
  <sub>VPDB</sub> = −10.45‰, IAEA, Vienna, Austria), IAEA-600 (
  <span class="italic">δ</span>
  <span class="sup">13</span>C
  <sub>VPDB</sub> = −27.77‰, 
  <span class="italic">δ</span>
  <span class="sup">15</span>N
  <sub>Air</sub> = 1.00‰, IAEA, Vienna, Austria) and USGS40 (
  <span class="italic">δ</span>
  <span class="sup">13</span>C
  <sub>VPDB</sub> = −26.39‰, 
  <span class="italic">δ</span>
  <span class="sup">15</span>N
  <sub>Air</sub> = −4.52‰, IAEA, Vienna, Austria. International reference and standard materials for stable isotope analysis are administered, controlled, and issued by the Internal Atomic Energy Agency (IAEA, Vienna, Austria). Results of the isotopic analysis were expressed as 
  <span class="italic">δ</span>-values relative to the international standards VPDB (Vienna-Pee Dee Belemnite) and Air (atmospheric N) for 
  <span class="sup">13</span>C and 
  <span class="sup">15</span>N, respectively. The analysis was replicated for 11 (10%) randomly selected samples. Each replicate was processed independently starting from the stage of sample powdering. The standard deviation for the replicates was &lt;0.2‰ for 
  <span class="italic">δ</span>
  <span class="sup">13</span>C and &lt;0.4‰ for 
  <span class="italic">δ</span>
  <span class="sup">15</span>N.
 </p>
</sec>
