<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec008" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Meso level limits</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Respondents argued that meso-level factors underpinning a lack of collective action between reef and non-reef sectors within the Great Barrier Reef region were also experienced as limits to adaptation. Effective adaptation by reef industries depends on maintenance of important public goods (e.g., water quality and community safety), which are impacted by land-based sectors beyond the sphere of influence of reef industries. Negative externalities that emerge from the predominance of terrestrial private property rights, and the powerful interests and deeply embedded identities linked to Australian agricultural industries (e.g., cattle grazing and sugar cane production), mining, and coastal lifestyles (e.g., beach-front properties) represent a limit to business planning and stewardship by reef industries (Tables 
  <a rid="pone.0150575.t003" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0150575.t003">3</a> and 
  <a rid="pone.0150575.t004" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0150575.t004">4</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the Great Barrier Reef region, institutions and incentives that protect and reinforce private rights on land represent a particularly intractable set of limits to adaptation for the reef and its industries [
  <a rid="pone.0150575.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0150575.ref033">33</a>]. The declining water quality in the Great Barrier Reef resulting from siltation and pollution run-off from current land-use practices in the catchment is already a high management priority [
  <a rid="pone.0150575.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0150575.ref034">34</a>]. Respondents argued that as graziers and farmers become more climate-stressed and undertake their own adaptations on private land, the externalities impacting marine ecosystems and industries are likely to increase. Beyond a certain threshold these externalities will undermine any efforts by reef operators and managers to improve outcomes through adaptation.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Respondents suggested that individual property rights on land exercised in coastal development decisions would also produce externalities that could limit adaptation of reef industries in two ways. First, coastal property owners have the right to fortify their properties against sea-level rise. If many individuals do so, the implications for marine ecosystems and dependent sectors are considerable: fortification presents a limit to ecological adaptation preventing distributional shifts of important coastal habitats, including mangroves, and impacts on ecosystem health and fisheries productivity [
  <a rid="pone.0150575.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0150575.ref035">35</a>]. Again, respondents suggested that beyond a certain point these activities would render their efforts to adapt through stewardship activities ineffective. Second, the current building and safety standards that coastal residents are encouraged to adhere to are deemed inadequate by respondents in the face of more intense extreme events, and there are no incentives for coastal residents to exceed these standards. Respondents argued that the high costs of resultant emergency response are then passed on to coastal fisheries and tourism businesses as financial externalities (insurance premiums and recovery levies). Limits to adaptation by individual businesses that build or retrofit infrastructure to high standards are experienced when other individuals do not act collectively in a way that improves community safety, reduces the cost of emergency response and subsequently prevents the transfer of significant financial externalities (see also [
  <a rid="pone.0150575.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0150575.ref036">36</a>]). In aggregate, the individual actions of land-users produce externalities such as competition for space, siltation and pollution [
  <a rid="pone.0150575.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0150575.ref034">34</a>], and emergency response costs that, beyond a certain point, render ineffective (rather than inefficient) key adaptation strategies by reef industries.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Participants noted the strong identities tied up with coastal lifestyles, mining and agricultural industries, which drive political interests and are used to justify the actions and rights of land-based industries in the Great Barrier Reef region thereby reinforcing structural limits to adaptation in reef-based industries. Federal and state governments are perceived to be unwilling to act against the economic interests of their more powerful constituents, thereby prioritising the interests of influential (but not necessarily majority) groups over the long-term sustainability of the reef (see also [
  <a rid="pone.0150575.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0150575.ref037">37</a>]), and marginalising groups like commercial fishers who reported feeling ‘unwanted’ and undervalued (
  <a rid="pone.0150575.t004" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0150575.t004">Table 4</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
