<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2-1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ambient temperature and effect on mental health</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Increased exposure to heat is likely to become more common with the rise in the global temperatures. It has been suggested that there is a relation between temperature rise and aggressive behavior.[
  <a rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref10">10</a>] Increase in rates of criminality and aggression have been observed during the hot summer months, suggesting a link between aggressive behaviors and temperatures.[
  <a rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref11">11</a>
  <a rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref12">12</a>] With global warming, it is possible that the rates of aggression may increase over time. Association has been also been seen with the rates of suicides and the temperatures. It has been seen that suicides, especially violent ones are more common with the recent increase in temperatures.[
  <a rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref13">13</a>
  <a rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref14">14</a>
  <a rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref15">15</a>]
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Heat waves have been associated with mental and behavioral disorders. A study from Australia suggests that heat waves are associated with increased rates of admissions for mental disorders also, in conjunction with other disorders such as cardiovascular and renal illness.[
  <a rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref16">16</a>] Such heat waves have been associated with mood disorders, anxiety disorders, dementia and anxiety related disorders among others.[
  <a rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref17">17</a>] Extreme heat exposure can lead to physical as well as psychological exhaustion.[
  <a rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref18">18</a>] A study from Thailand suggests that occupational heat stress is associated with greater psychological distress among the workers.[
  <a rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref19">19</a>] Similar other studies have found an association between increased temperatures in the work place and greater psychological distress.[
  <a rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref20">20</a>]
 </p>
</sec>
