<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec15" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conditioning</div>
 <p id="Par52" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Contrary to habituation, which occurs through simple repetition, behavioural conditioning occurs when a certain coping behavioural is consistently met with positive or negative reinforcement, through which the animal learns to perform one response and/or avoid another. For example, hatchery-reared rainbow trout (
  <span class="italic">Oncorhynchus mykiss</span>) that were conditioned to recognise chemical predator cues as dangerous, significantly increased anti-predator behaviours (decreased foraging, increased hiding), unlike trout from a control group. This response was still exhibited up to 21 days after conditioning (Brown and Smith 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">1998</a>). Conditioning can work fast, when it concerns stimuli that are sufficiently harmful, but often works slowly if the negative reinforcement is not very consistent or if the payoff from taking the risk is higher than the cost of negative reinforcement (Adret 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">1993</a>; Lovibond and Shanks 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR194" href="#CR194">2002</a>). As such, predictability of the response, both in quality and in timing, is essential in learning whether to avoid or approach a challenging situation (Krebs et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR179" href="#CR179">2017</a>). For example, when mice were exposed to conditioned and unconditioned stimuli in unpredictable patterns, they began to express freezing behaviours even at the conditioned response (Seidenbecher et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR280" href="#CR280">2016</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par53" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Like other processes that allow for coping behaviours to be tuned to environmental conditions, conditioning appears to be especially effective early in life. In young male zebra finches (
  <span class="italic">T. guttata</span>), conditioning with a song as reward influenced the effectiveness of song learning during development but not song preferences in adulthood (Adret 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">1993</a>). The effects of conditioning depend not only on age, but within that have also been shown to depend on state: within a small time window around nursing, rabbit pups (
  <span class="italic">O. cuniculus</span>) could be habituated to human handling, but not outside this window (Pongrácz and Altbäcker 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR251" href="#CR251">1999</a>). Similar to habituation, there are differences between species and individuals in the way conditions affect behaviour. For example, two closely related species of tadpoles (
  <span class="italic">Rana lessonae</span> and 
  <span class="italic">R. esculenta</span>) were conditioned for 30 days to a variety of predators, after which species differences were found in the ways general activity levels and use of refuge changed, as well as differences in the type of predator they responded to (Semlitsch and Reyer 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR282" href="#CR282">1992</a>). Finally, again similar to habituation, behavioural conditioning depends strongly on the predictability of challenging situations and, as such, is relevant to changing environments, as animals often exhibit modulating behavioural changes (freeze, approach, etc.) preceding a predictable event they are conditioned to (Krebs et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR179" href="#CR179">2017</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
