<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Coping behaviours: definitions and precursors</div>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to survive and meet their basic needs, all animals constantly interact with their environment. They search to acquire food and other resources, watch out for predators and other dangers, and secure a safe place to rest. They interact with animals of their own species, attempt to find a suitable mate and take care of their offspring. Although coping, animal personality, temperament and behavioural syndromes differ importantly in underlying theory and context (Stamps and Groothuis 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR297" href="#CR297">2010</a>), all are commonly used to study how animals react to challenges in their surroundings. Coping is commonly considered as the behavioural and physiological efforts to master a challenging situation (Koolhaas et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR174" href="#CR174">1999</a>), while behavioural syndrome is often defined as individual differences in behaviour patterns that are either correlated across time or contexts (Sih and Bell 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR290" href="#CR290">2008</a>; Dochtermann and Dingemanse 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94" href="#CR94">2013</a>), and animal personality, similar to coping styles (Réale et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR257" href="#CR257">2007</a>), is commonly defined as underlying behavioural tendencies that differ across individuals, that are consistent within individuals over time and that affect the behaviour that is expressed in different contexts (Caspi et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71" href="#CR71">2005</a>; Réale et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR257" href="#CR257">2007</a>; synthesised in Stamps and Groothuis 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR297" href="#CR297">2010</a>). While coping and personality have been linked many times (McCrae and Costa 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR209" href="#CR209">1986</a>; Jang et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR156" href="#CR156">2007</a>; Carver and Connor-Smith 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" href="#CR70">2010</a>; Kaiseler et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR161" href="#CR161">2012</a>) and are sometimes used interchangeably (Melotti et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR215" href="#CR215">2011</a>), they cannot be considered identical, as personality makes assumptions on cross-context and cross-time repeatability (Dingemanse et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89" href="#CR89">2012</a>), whereas coping does not.
 </p>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Due to the recent popularity of studies of coping and animal personality, terminology used for the behaviours animals use to respond to their environment can be confusing, overlapping or inconsistent (Carter et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" href="#CR69">2013</a>). As a result, the same behaviour is often studied from many different perspectives, sometimes with slightly different connotation, and it is often unclear what the exact distinction is between a behaviour and a behavioural syndrome, coping style or personality, especially in species or populations where behaviours are tightly correlated into behavioural suites. Exploration is an excellent example: some studies consider exploration to be one aspect of animal personality (Wolf et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR348" href="#CR348">2007</a>; Minderman et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR220" href="#CR220">2009</a>; Schuett et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR279" href="#CR279">2013</a>), or part of a behavioural syndrome (Bell and Sih 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">2007</a>; Dingemanse et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91" href="#CR91">2007</a>; Wisenden et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR345" href="#CR345">2011</a>); others group it in with the active-passive axis of coping (Janczak et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR154" href="#CR154">2003</a>), yet others study it as a single behaviour (Dingemanse et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88" href="#CR88">2002</a>; Mettke-Hofmann et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR218" href="#CR218">2002</a>). Depending on the aim of the study, all of these approaches can be correct. However, distinguishing whether a behaviour is part of a behavioural suite or a coping axis or a personality suite or only partially or not at all falls far outside the scope of this review, especially since the answers to such questions differ widely between species and even populations within species (Carter et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" href="#CR69">2013</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the purpose of this review, we use the more generic, inclusive term “coping behaviours”, defined here as “the behaviours that individuals exhibit aimed at responding to environmental challenges”, including but not limited to exploration, avoidance, approach, boldness, shyness, aggression and response to novelty. Where they are clearly relevant to coping behaviours, we also discuss animal personality traits such as anxiety, stress responsiveness or impulsivity. We furthermore include expressions of sociality, as social behaviour is an important component to coping with challenges for group-living animals (Fischer et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR116" href="#CR116">2015</a>). For the sake of a comprehensive and balanced review, studies were evaluated on a case-by-case basis and only included if the behaviour could reasonably be considered a behavioural response to an environmental challenge. As such, we often (but not always) included studies on exploration as well as those on personality and excluded studies on genetics, neurochemistry and theoretical models. This allows us to consider all relevant empirical work dealing with behaviours currently thought to be involved in coping with environmental challenges, regardless of the terminology or framework used in the study, while still excluding generic behaviour that is not in any obvious way related to immediate response to environmental challenge.
 </p>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It should be noted that in order to create the broad scale experimental design necessary to study animal personality, coping styles or behavioural syndromes, testing is often done under laboratory conditions with stock animals that, while creating genetic and environmental homogeneity between studies, may be unable to exhibit behavioural responses that are ecologically or evolutionary relevant (Koolhaas et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR173" href="#CR173">2011</a>; Carter et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" href="#CR69">2013</a>; Junco 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR160" href="#CR160">2017</a>). Laboratory conditions, whether experienced by the parents, in early-life, or during the experiment, warp the behaviours with which animals respond. However, only very little developmental work has been done under natural conditions (Rödel et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR265" href="#CR265">2017</a>), and as long as the aforementioned caveat is kept in mind, non-natural experimental conditions still provide important insights into the underlying developmental mechanisms of coping.
 </p>
 <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When coping behaviours are considered as the decision an animal makes with regards to the behaviour it will use to mediate a challenge presented by its environment, as follows from our definition, it becomes relevant to consider precursors to that decision. For all animals, it can be hypothesised that successful adaptation to environmental conditions depends on (at least) four pillars: 
  <span class="italic">perceiving</span> a need for a response (1), 
  <span class="italic">evaluating</span> an effective response (2), 
  <span class="italic">ability</span> to give that response (3) and 
  <span class="italic">paying the cost</span> for that response (4). As a thought experiment: in order to successfully cope with a larger animal encroaching into its habitat, a potential prey has to have a sensory awareness of the larger animal, followed by the perception (1) that this animal is either harmless or dangerous. If the latter is the case, the prey has to evaluate (2) whether hiding or running away is the most effective way to respond in this situation and to this type of predator, and (3) whether it is physically capable of running fast enough to get away. If it does hide or run, it can lose foraging time and valuable resources or encounter other dangers. These state- and condition-dependent costs need to be factored into the decision in favour of a particular coping behaviour.
 </p>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There is strong selection on traits making up each of these four pillars, as each directly factors into an individual’s coping behaviour, and there are immediate and possibly life-threatening consequences to responding with ineffective behaviours (Stirling et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR300" href="#CR300">2002</a>; Adriaenssens and Johnsson 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">2013</a>). As such, these precursors to coping behaviour, like coping behaviours themselves, are strongly influenced by early-life environment developmental process. Below, we briefly detail these four precursors and their evolutionary relationship to the early-life developmental period, in order to more fully understand the relationship between coping behaviours and the early-life environment.
 </p>
 <sec id="Sec2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Perception</div>
  <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Perceiving a threat is a first and necessary step to coping (Edenbrow and Croft 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100" href="#CR100">2013</a>), whether that perception happens on a conscious or unconscious level (Lovibond and Shanks 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR194" href="#CR194">2002</a>). Animals cannot respond to dangerous situations that their sensory systems cannot perceive (Shettleworth 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR286" href="#CR286">2001</a>; Guesdon et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR135" href="#CR135">2011</a>). Herein also lays a vulnerability, one that has been widely explored within the domain of psychology (Brewer et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">2007</a>; Volk et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR333" href="#CR333">2010</a>; Arran et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">2014</a>) but surprisingly much less considered in animal biology. The perception of a threat can be inaccurate, thereby preventing successful coping from the start. Individuals may fail in sensory perception of a threat or fail to perceive a situation accurately enough to consider it a threat. For example, iguanas who were confronted with an approaching human, moved earlier, ran earlier and ran farther when the human’s face was exposed versus covered by hair, as a covered face gave the conflicting stimulus of both approaching and retreating (Burger and Gochfeld 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">1993</a>). Alternatively, individuals may perceive a threat where there is none, for example in animals that are over-easily startled in response to novel but non-threatening sounds or visuals such as digital ringtones or billboards (King et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR168" href="#CR168">2003</a>; Potvin 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR252" href="#CR252">2017</a>), or to human outdoor recreation (Tablado and Jenni 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR305" href="#CR305">2017</a>), which can lead to (social) stress and the many negative health consequences that come from long-term stress (Moberg 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR224" href="#CR224">1985</a>; Tapp and Natelson 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR312" href="#CR312">1988</a>; Blanchard et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">2001</a>; Cockrem 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79" href="#CR79">2007</a>).
  </p>
  <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to perceive threats more accurately, animals use several strategies, such as becoming more sensitive to predator behaviour and specific morphological traits to distinguish one type of predator from another (Stankowich and Blumstein 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR298" href="#CR298">2005</a>). Another effective strategy is to increase vigilance. Perceiving the environment with accuracy for an extended period of time in order to detect potential dangers is costly, as it takes away from other activities such as foraging, which some species of animals can minimise by increasing group size and sharing vigilance (Eilam et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101" href="#CR101">2011</a>). As a result, many group-living animal species have evolved within-group sharing of acquired and evaluated information (Liddell et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR187" href="#CR187">2004</a>; Magrath et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR197" href="#CR197">2015</a>; Wingfield 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR344" href="#CR344">2015</a>) and a sensitivity to alarm displays from conspecifics (Liddell et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR187" href="#CR187">2004</a>; Brown et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">2006</a>; Rieucau et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR262" href="#CR262">2014</a>) as well as cues directly from predators (Rieucau et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR262" href="#CR262">2014</a>). Detection of such cues does not need to be conscious (Liddell et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR187" href="#CR187">2004</a>).
  </p>
  <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For young animals, there is little room for trial-and-error in distinguishing between friend and foe, as they are often vulnerable to predation from predator species as well as their own kind. For this reason, there is strong selection for young animals to acquire effective risk appraisal (or risk assessment) early in life. As a result, the situations they perceive as a threat or a danger later in life is closely linked to early-life conditions. An adult responding aggressively in certain situations may be doing so because their early-life environment has induced a heightened threat perception, or may respond impulsively because their experiences did not prepare them for the possibility of a predator (Bell et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">2011</a>; El Balaa and Blouin-Demers 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103" href="#CR103">2011</a>). Although it is widely recognised in animal biology that threat perception is an important aspect of animal functioning (Burger and Gochfeld 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">1993</a>; Kirschvink 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR170" href="#CR170">2000</a>; Chamaillé-Jammes et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73" href="#CR73">2014</a>; Rieucau et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR262" href="#CR262">2014</a>), threat perception and differences therein based on early-life environment are rarely linked to the development of coping behaviours (Brown et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">2013</a>; Zidar et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR352" href="#CR352">2017</a>). In part, this is because risk perception (degree of “fear”) is difficult to study in animals (Stankowich and Blumstein 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR298" href="#CR298">2005</a>) and especially difficult to separate from the subsequent response.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Evaluation</div>
  <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Evaluating an effective response to a situation can be defined simply as carrying out any response that successfully mediates the challenging situation to where there is no longer a threat or opportunity. When an individual does not correctly estimate which response should be given, it creates a mismatch between behaviour and environment that can be fatal to the animal. This was observed, for example, when captive-bred angelfish (
   <span class="italic">Pterophyllum scalare</span>), who had never experienced a predator before, were challenged to respond to predator cues, to which they responded less appropriately than wild-bred fish with past experience of a predator (El Balaa and Blouin-Demers 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103" href="#CR103">2011</a>). Such a mismatch also occurs when individuals respond too readily to possible threats. Responding only to individuals of a predator species that display sufficiently threatening behaviour allows prey species to minimise energy expenditure and other costs of predator avoidance, which is especially relevant if the predator is common but attacks are infrequent (Papworth et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR245" href="#CR245">2013</a>).
  </p>
  <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It must be noted that the coping responses that animals display are often non-conscious and part of a stimulus-response bond (Liddell et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR187" href="#CR187">2004</a>), a pathway that has become engrained through a myriad of developmental processes (see “
   <a rid="Sec11" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec11">How the early-life environment affects the development of coping/developmental processes affecting coping behaviours</a>” section). Yet there is indication that animals choose from multiple available strategies, as outlined below, when environmental conditions incite them to respond to a threat (Benus et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">1991</a>; Belsky 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">2007</a>; Mathot et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR204" href="#CR204">2012</a>). Which strategy is estimated as the most effective is dependent upon current environmental conditions as well as past experience and the animal’s personal success rate with the available coping strategies. The threat-sensitive predator avoidance model (Bishop and Brown 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">1992</a>; Brown et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">2006</a>; Chamaillé-Jammes et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73" href="#CR73">2014</a>; Rieucau et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR262" href="#CR262">2014</a>) predicts that animals should take into account perceived predation risk to balance the intensity of their antipredator response. Research on cichlids showed that when threatened, isolated individuals exhibited reduced time moving and foraging than individuals in shoals, and small shoals exhibited a higher response threshold than large shoals (Brown et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">2006</a>). Similarly, wild-caught herrings provided the strongest avoidance reactions when exposed to versatile predator sensory cues (Rieucau et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR262" href="#CR262">2014</a>). These findings and others (Bishop and Brown 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">1992</a>) indicate that response patterns are flexible and situation dependent, and subject to natural selection processes.
  </p>
  <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As much as threat perception, threat evaluation is dependent at least to a degree on experiences during early life (Olff et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR242" href="#CR242">2005</a>). Familiarity with the situation and habituation, both of which play a role in estimating effective coping behaviours, are built through either personal experience with similar situations earlier in life (Snell-Rood et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR294" href="#CR294">2013</a>), or learning from others who previously experienced the situation (Brown et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">2006</a>; Rieucau et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR262" href="#CR262">2014</a>). Domestically raised animals, for example, no longer perceive humans as threats, whereas many wild animals do. While they perceive similar cues, they evaluate the presence of a human differently and so display different coping behaviours. The ability to evaluate which response to take under different circumstances is especially relevant in coping with novelty, when little previous experience is available (Tang et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR311" href="#CR311">2011</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ability</div>
  <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Even when a challenge has been perceived and an appropriate response has been evaluated, successful coping is not guaranteed. Animals may not be able to give the response that is most effective, due to physical or developmental constraints or negative experiences earlier in life (Long 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR192" href="#CR192">1990</a>; Leichty et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR186" href="#CR186">2012</a>). Stressors or deprivation of nutrients, care, personal experience or parental example early in life may have made it impossible to give an adaptive response. For example, the nest environment in young rats was shown to affect ontogeny of personality types, with heavier individuals being more bold and more explorative than lighter individuals, and individuals from both small and large litters being more anxious than individuals from medium-sized litters (Rödel and Meyer 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR266" href="#CR266">2011</a>). Thus, the appropriate coping behaviour for a rural rat facing food shortage might be to go into an urban area to forage, but because the rat in question had a low birth weight and came from a large litter, its coping behaviours were developed towards the shy and anxious range, leaving it behaviourally unable to cope with the noise and novelty of an urban environment. A rat with even slightly different early-life circumstances, by contrast, might make the transition to the new environment and survive the food shortage. In addition to stressors or deprivation, which focuses specifically on negative early-life events, development of behavioural processes may of necessity have canalised (Hermanussen et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR145" href="#CR145">2001</a>; Dochtermann and Dingemanse 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94" href="#CR94">2013</a>) in a particular direction that excludes the desired behaviour.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cost</div>
  <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Finally, if an animal responds with a particular coping behaviour, it must be able to incur the costs of that behaviour; otherwise, the coping response will lead to a loss of fitness rather than a gain, either immediately or over a longer time span. Such costs can come in many forms. An animal that responds to the appearance of a competitor at the feeding ground with flight, freezing or hiding loses the opportunity to forage and obtain resources (McArthur et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR207" href="#CR207">2014</a>). An animal that responds with aggression, on the other hand, may incur cost to its physical health sustained in fighting displays (Marler and Moore 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR199" href="#CR199">1988</a>; Johnstone 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR158" href="#CR158">2001</a>; Lane and Briffa 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR182" href="#CR182">2017</a>). If the aggression is part of a behavioural construct, where the same coping behaviour is habitually displayed across contexts (Bell and Stamps 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">2004</a>), the individual may incur costs when the same aggression effectively displayed towards a rival male becomes lethal when displayed towards a predator, or alternatively, when effective aggressive behaviour towards predators may incur costs on other coping behaviours such as vigilance (Hess et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR146" href="#CR146">2016</a>).
  </p>
  <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Life-history aspects such as offspring weight (Ferrari et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR114" href="#CR114">2015</a>), parental care (Budaev et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">1999</a>; Reddon 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR258" href="#CR258">2012</a>; van Oers et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR328" href="#CR328">2015</a>), rank within the social structure (Verbeek et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR330" href="#CR330">1999</a>) and predation pressure are important in determining physical strength as well as resultant behavioural flexibility across an individual lifetime, and so affect whether or not an animal can afford the cost of a particular coping behaviour or behavioural syndrome (Fish et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR118" href="#CR118">2004</a>; Rödel and Monclús 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR267" href="#CR267">2011</a>). For example, physically strong individuals, as well as animals reared in nutritionally challenging environments, may have higher chances of survival if they develop coping behaviours involving boldness, exploration and high levels of activity (Krause et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR178" href="#CR178">2009</a>; Noguera et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR237" href="#CR237">2015</a>). However, for physically weak animals, or those living under high predation pressures, active and bold coping behaviours may be extremely costly, illustrated by the inducement of a boldness-aggression behavioural correlation in sticklebacks under predation pressure (Bell and Sih 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">2007</a>), which suggests that in this high-risk environment, it is adaptive for animals to be bold only if they are also (able to be) aggressive. In addition, the cost of a coping behaviour relates to the experience an animal has performing this behaviour, as it is considered risky to attempt novel coping behaviours when faced with a threat (King et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR168" href="#CR168">2003</a>; Martin and Réale 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR202" href="#CR202">2008</a>; Rothwell et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR271" href="#CR271">2011</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
