<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec19" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Habitat</div>
 <p id="Par61" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Within eligible studies in this review (see Supplementary materials), effects of early-life habitat conditions were studied by means of natural habitat (Kelley et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR166" href="#CR166">2005</a>; Moretz et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR228" href="#CR228">2007a</a>; Aubret and Shine 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">2008</a>; Sweeney et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR304" href="#CR304">2013</a>), housing environment (Bolhuis et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">2004</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">2005</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">2006</a>), restricted bedding (Fuentes et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR123" href="#CR123">2014</a>) and environmental enrichment (Roberts et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR264" href="#CR264">2011</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par62" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Most current work on the effects of early-life habitat on coping behaviours studies the question how laboratory and housing conditions affect animal’s coping style. Early-life housing conditions were extensively studied in pigs (
  <span class="italic">Sus domesticus</span>), where they were shown to affect coping behaviours: barren housed pigs were less active, less explorative and less playful and showed more social aggression than pigs raised in enriched housing (Bolhuis et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">2005</a>). Similarly, pigs from enriched housing were shown to have more difficulty responding to changes in a spatial discrimination maze than pigs from barren housing (Bolhuis et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">2004</a>), behaviour which relates to their ability to cope with changes in foraging conditions. Housing conditions did not affect all individuals equally: low-resisting pigs were more affected by adverse housing than high-resisting pigs across various behaviours, including chewing, manipulative and play behaviours (Bolhuis et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">2006</a>). In rats, behavioural effects due to restricted bedding during the first days after birth (in addition to another early life stressor) were shown to affect males and females differently across different coping behaviours (Fuentes et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR123" href="#CR123">2014</a>). However, the effects of laboratory environment are by no means restricted to mammals. Laboratory-reared skiffia fish (
  <span class="italic">Skiffia multipunctata</span>) displayed increased courtship, aggression and curiosity towards a novel predator compared to pond-reared fish and commenced foraging on novel food more rapidly (Kelley et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR166" href="#CR166">2005</a>). In juvenile Atlantic salmon (
  <span class="italic">Salmo salar</span>), exposure to enriched conditions improved learning and ability to navigate a maze without errors (Salvanes et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR274" href="#CR274">2013</a>). Similarly, enrichment of rearing environment was found to affect several aspects of mahseer fish (
  <span class="italic">Tor putitora</span>) behaviour: exploratory behaviour, predation and anti-predation response were higher in fish reared in enriched or semi-natural environments than in barren environments (Ullah et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR321" href="#CR321">2017</a>). Laboratory-reared spiders (penultimate 
  <span class="italic">Agelenopsis pennsylvanica</span>) never exhibited a behavioural syndrome between boldness and foraging aggressiveness, while field-reared penultimates (but not juveniles) did (Sweeney et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR304" href="#CR304">2013</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par63" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In a more ecological setting, snakes (
  <span class="italic">Notechis scutatus</span>) were found to base habitat choice, an important life-history decision that affects coping success in many aspects of life, on the habitat type in which they had been reared—an adaptive effect as they were also found to be more effective in locomotion in these habitats than in others (Aubret and Shine 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">2008</a>). There is some indication of effects of variation in temperature, humidity and wind speed, possibly modulated by resource availability, although this has not been studied specifically with regards to early-life environment (Love et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR193" href="#CR193">2013</a>). While there is increasing interests in the effects of urbanisation, habitat fragmentation and quality on behavioural development, few studies have specifically considered how experiencing such habitats during early-life affects coping behaviours later in life.
 </p>
 <p id="Par64" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It seems clear from the examples above that the early-life habitat has important effects on the development of coping behaviours, partially through the amount and quality of stimuli received, which impacts neurological development, and partially through a lack of experience with relevant environmental cues. Consequences of a suboptimal habitat include inability to survive in a natural setting, anxiety and aggressive behaviours, and difficulty in responding to novelty and change. Such effects of habitat and housing conditions experienced early in life are especially relevant with regards to experimental design of animal behaviour studies (Bolhuis et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">2006</a>; Trocino and Xiccato 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR319" href="#CR319">2006</a>) and the extent to which we can interpret coping behaviours from animals with non-ecologically valid early-life housing (Salvanes et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR274" href="#CR274">2013</a>), but are also interesting in relation to an animal’s ability to adapt to shifts in habitat quality or size and to better understand the impact of urban conditions on previously rural species (Lapiedra et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR184" href="#CR184">2017</a>; Miranda 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR221" href="#CR221">2017</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
