<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Inheriting parental behaviours</div>
 <p id="Par39" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Coping strategies may be transferred from one generation to the next without a genetic basis (Rosenzweig and Bennett 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR270" href="#CR270">1996</a>; Grether 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR131" href="#CR131">2005</a>; Leichty et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR186" href="#CR186">2012</a>). Evolutionary theory suggests several advantages to non-genetic transmission of behaviour (Marshall and Uller 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR200" href="#CR200">2007</a>). Importantly, it allows learned behaviours to be passed on from one generation to the next. In reasonably stable and predictable environments, offspring gain a distinct advantage if their parents can pass on their own experience with current ecological conditions (Shea et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR283" href="#CR283">2011</a>), and prime them for the situations they are likely to face in life. It allows juveniles to quickly obtain complicated responses and display behavioural strategies that proved successful to their parents, without having to take risks and gain experience with the environment themselves (see “
  <a rid="Sec20" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec20">Parents</a>” section).
 </p>
 <p id="Par40" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another benefit of non-genomic transmission of behaviour concerns parent-child resemblance and parental investment: this theory is based on the understanding that males, unlike females, cannot be certain about paternity, and should provide less paternal investment to young who are unlikely to be their offspring (Bressan 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">2002</a>; Apicella and Marlowe 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">2004</a>; Anderson 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">2006</a>; Heijkoop et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR141" href="#CR141">2009</a>). It is expected for males to have developed ways to estimate relatedness through cues of physical and behavioural resemblance, and for offspring to have developed methods to increase resemblance to fathers also in cases where the father is not genetically related. For example, it was recently discovered through cross-fostering experiments in zebra finches that exploratory behaviour of foster parents, but not that of the genetic parents, was predictive of the exploratory behaviour of offspring (Schuett et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR279" href="#CR279">2013</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
