<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec12" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Parental effects</div>
 <p id="Par42" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Maternal effects, defined as the direct effect of a mother’s phenotype on that of her offspring (Bernardo 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">1996</a>; Reddon 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR258" href="#CR258">2012</a>), have been researched in detail both in animals and humans over the past decades. Developmentally, maternal effects relate to the need for developing systems to receive the appropriate (amount of) input. Depending on the quality and quantity of input received, the young develop or fail to develop a variety of phenotypic characteristics, including many coping behaviours. Maternal effects have been found across many species during the gestation period and after (Bernardo 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">1996</a>; Mousseau and Fox 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR231" href="#CR231">1998</a>) and have been studied with respect to hormones (Adkins-Regan et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">2013</a>), nutrition (Langley-Evans et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR183" href="#CR183">2005</a>), behaviour (Weaver et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR339" href="#CR339">2004</a>), predator experience (Bell et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">2016</a>; Freinschlag and Schausberger 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR121" href="#CR121">2016</a>), birth weight (Taborsky 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR306" href="#CR306">2006a</a>) and maternal care (Champagne et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76" href="#CR76">2003</a>; Champagne and Meaney 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77" href="#CR77">2006</a>), or a combination of all of the above. More recently, paternal effects have received more interest as well, although compared to maternal effects, still much less is known regarding the role of paternal factors (Rodgers et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR268" href="#CR268">2013</a>). The most significant difference between maternal and paternal effects is the gestation period, during which the maternal phenotype is in intimate physical contact with that of the offspring, which allows for nourishment and hormones to pass from mother to child. Instead of separating between maternal and paternal effects, some studies consider the more generic parental effects (Uller 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR322" href="#CR322">2008</a>; Badyaev and Uller 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">2009</a>; Burgess and Marshall 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" href="#CR62">2014</a>). The topic knows a rich literature of its own (reviewed in Badyaev and Uller 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">2009</a>; Reddon 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR258" href="#CR258">2012</a>) that falls outside our scope to review in its entirety.
 </p>
 <p id="Par43" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Early-life influences that affect offspring coping behaviours through parental effects can be as straightforward as parental behaviour, although this is underrepresented in empirical studies. Parents can change key parameters of offspring’s regulatory system through their behaviour prior to and after the offspring’s experience of a stressor and, in this way, change the offspring’s experience of the stressor and the way its developmental processes are impacted (Tang et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR310" href="#CR310">2014</a>). Furthermore, cross-fostering experiments in zebra finches (
  <span class="italic">T. guttata</span>) showed that offspring exploratory type was predicted by exploratory type of the foster, but not the genetic parents (Schuett et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR279" href="#CR279">2013</a>). In addition, the amount and quality of parental care seems to strongly affect the development of effective coping behaviours (Budaev et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">1999</a>; Moons et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR225" href="#CR225">2005</a>). In convict cichlid (
  <span class="italic">Cichlasoma archocentrus</span>), parental activity during parental care was negatively correlated with the freezing versus activity factor in female offspring (Budaev et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">1999</a>). However, parental effects seem to be more complicated than a simple case of more care is better (Tang et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR310" href="#CR310">2014</a>). The predictability of parental sensory signals has been shown to affect cognitive development, with unpredictable maternal signals leading to poor cognitive performance in behavioural tests (Davis et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84" href="#CR84">2017</a>). Beyond providing care and behavioural example, parental affects can prepare for fluctuating environments (Proulx and Teotónio 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR253" href="#CR253">2017</a>), mediate the impact of environmental input or stressors, as well as change the offspring’s experience of an environmental situation (Tang et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR310" href="#CR310">2014</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par44" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Especially maternal stress (Thornberry et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR314" href="#CR314">2009</a>) and maternal care (see “
  <a rid="Sec20" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec20">Parents</a>” section) have been shown to affect offspring coping behaviours (Champagne et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76" href="#CR76">2003</a>; Fish et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR118" href="#CR118">2004</a>). It is becoming increasingly evident that maternal exposure to adversity during pregnancy can lead to life-long effects in offspring (Matthews and Phillips 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR205" href="#CR205">2010</a>). For example, male offspring of stressed rat mothers were more active in maze tests and entered the open arms of the maze more often than male offspring of control mothers (Götz and Stefanski 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR129" href="#CR129">2007</a>). The effects of maternal stress during pregnancy on behavioural outcomes in the first-generation offspring are thought to be highly dependent on species, sex and age (Sullivan et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR303" href="#CR303">2011</a>), as well as on the time in pregnancy when stress is experienced (Matthews and Phillips 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR205" href="#CR205">2010</a>), although this is predominantly studied in rodents at the moment.
 </p>
 <p id="Par45" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There has been some discussion whether the effects that parents have on their offspring’s phenotype are necessarily adaptive (Uller et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR323" href="#CR323">2013</a>). Some maternal effects seem to have a clear adaptive advantage either for the mother, the offspring or both (Wells 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR340" href="#CR340">2007a</a>). For example, female western bluebirds (
  <span class="italic">Sialia mexicana</span>) increase androgen concentrations in their eggs as competition from their sister species increases, resulting in more aggressive male offspring that are more likely to disperse and create new colonies (Duckworth et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97" href="#CR97">2015</a>).While a body of experimental work implies adaptive advantages to parental effects (Mousseau and Fox 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR231" href="#CR231">1998</a>; Marshall and Uller 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR200" href="#CR200">2007</a>; Nätt et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR233" href="#CR233">2009</a>; Jensen et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR157" href="#CR157">2014</a>) and the term maternal programming is being used increasingly to indicate mother’s active preparation of offspring for future circumstances (Fish et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR118" href="#CR118">2004</a>; Weaver et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR339" href="#CR339">2004</a>; Langley-Evans et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR183" href="#CR183">2005</a>), there are also indications that adaptive advantage cannot be assumed for all parental effects (Marshall and Uller 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR200" href="#CR200">2007</a>; Tang et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR310" href="#CR310">2014</a>; Freinschlag and Schausberger 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR121" href="#CR121">2016</a>). For example, maternal exposure to predation risk actually decreases offspring anti-predator behaviour in three-spined sticklebacks (McGhee et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR212" href="#CR212">2012</a>). It has been argued that the information a foetus receives is not in fact about the environment it is likely to face in its lifetime, but rather about the condition of its mother (Wells 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR341" href="#CR341">2007b</a>). Overall, the adaptive value of maternal effects is strongly ecologically dependent and can backfire under variable conditions. In such situations, parents may benefit by producing offspring that vary in sensitivity to particular experiences (Frankenhuis and Panchanathan 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR120" href="#CR120">2011</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
