<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec28" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Passing on the past</div>
 <p id="Par90" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There is increasing evidence that environmental effects experienced even before conception can be transmissible to subsequent generations (Burton and Metcalfe 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">2014</a>). There are several cases, notably in rodents, in which unfavourable conditions in previous generations negatively impacted coping behaviours of current and future generations. For example, dams that were exposed to chronic social stress displayed impaired maternal care to their first generation (F1) offspring, who in turn displayed impaired maternal care to their (F2) offspring. Both male and female offspring displayed decreased social behaviour (Babb et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">2014</a>). Hypo-responsiveness to stress across several behavioural categories was shown in rhesus macaques (
  <span class="italic">Macaca mulatta</span>) whose mothers had been exposed to early-life stress, even when those mothers no longer displayed hypo-responsiveness themselves (Kinnally et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR169" href="#CR169">2013</a>). Similar patterns were found in Japanese quail (
  <span class="italic">C. japonica</span>), where prenatal stress experienced by mothers resulted in the same stress-coping traits in the offspring across all phenotypic levels studied, including behavioural traits (Zimmer et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR353" href="#CR353">2017</a>). Abusive behaviour as well can be transmitted across generations: more than half of the female rhesus monkeys who were abused by their mothers during their first month of life displayed abusive parenting with their firstborn offspring, regardless of whether they were reared by their biological mother or a foster mother (Maestripieri 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR196" href="#CR196">2005</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par91" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A recent term for negative effects from multiple generations ago is ancestral stress or ancestral trauma (McCreary et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR210" href="#CR210">2016</a>; Ambeskovic et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">2017</a>; Faraji et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR110" href="#CR110">2017</a>), to differentiate from single-generation parental effects. There is some indication that ancestral trauma can be advantageous to a certain extent, but causes greater vulnerability to additional stressors later in life. In rats, a family history of recurrent ancestral prenatal stress was related to improved movement and skilled reaching, relevant in foraging behaviours, compared to rats without ancestral stress. The advantage of ancestral stress disappeared when rats experienced another stressor in adulthood, suggesting multiple stressors may limit behavioural flexibility rather than improve it (Faraji et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR110" href="#CR110">2017</a>), even in a system where ancestral stress leads to adaptive developmental adjustments. In similar studies, social isolation during later-life stress caused cognitive retardation and reduced stress coping in rats from ancestral stress lines, but not in rats from unstressed lines (Faraji et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR111" href="#CR111">2017</a>). In mice, postnatal trauma of unpredictable maternal separation and maternal stress altered coping behaviours in adverse conditions both in males when adult, and in their adult male offspring. These behavioural symptoms were not transmitted to the next generation when fathers experienced an enriched environment (Gapp et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR126" href="#CR126">2016</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par92" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is not only negative experience that is passed on through intergenerational effects, however. Mouse dams rearing pups in communal nests displayed increased maternal care, to which their F1 offspring displayed reduced anxiety-like behaviour when placed in a novel environment, and increased quality of parenting behaviours towards their own offspring. F2 offspring also displayed reduced anxiety-like behaviour and better parenting compared to mice raised outside a communal nest (Curley et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82" href="#CR82">2009</a>). An elegant early study in vervet monkeys (
  <span class="italic">Cercopithecus aethiops sabaeus</span>) showed that the amount of contact mothers had with their offspring was related to the amount of contact they themselves had with their mothers. In this, a female’s experience in infancy was a better predictor of adult mothering than variables such as social learning as a juvenile, shared circumstances and average similarity between mothers and daughters (Fairbanks 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR109" href="#CR109">1989</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par93" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The effects of (negative) environmental cues across multiple generations have been studied almost exclusively in rodents and are often targeted to understanding depression, anxiety and effects of stress in humans. This one-sided approach makes it more difficult to place empirical findings in an ecologically relevant context, although it does provide advantages in testing the limits of the developmental system in ways ecological studies in the wild would not. It might be argued, given the positive effects on coping behaviours consistently shown by cage enrichment and communal housing, that laboratory conditions in themselves represent multigenerational environmental stress on the level of habitat, parents, social group and possibly other influences.</p>
</sec>
