<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Perception</div>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Perceiving a threat is a first and necessary step to coping (Edenbrow and Croft 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100" href="#CR100">2013</a>), whether that perception happens on a conscious or unconscious level (Lovibond and Shanks 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR194" href="#CR194">2002</a>). Animals cannot respond to dangerous situations that their sensory systems cannot perceive (Shettleworth 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR286" href="#CR286">2001</a>; Guesdon et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR135" href="#CR135">2011</a>). Herein also lays a vulnerability, one that has been widely explored within the domain of psychology (Brewer et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">2007</a>; Volk et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR333" href="#CR333">2010</a>; Arran et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">2014</a>) but surprisingly much less considered in animal biology. The perception of a threat can be inaccurate, thereby preventing successful coping from the start. Individuals may fail in sensory perception of a threat or fail to perceive a situation accurately enough to consider it a threat. For example, iguanas who were confronted with an approaching human, moved earlier, ran earlier and ran farther when the human’s face was exposed versus covered by hair, as a covered face gave the conflicting stimulus of both approaching and retreating (Burger and Gochfeld 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">1993</a>). Alternatively, individuals may perceive a threat where there is none, for example in animals that are over-easily startled in response to novel but non-threatening sounds or visuals such as digital ringtones or billboards (King et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR168" href="#CR168">2003</a>; Potvin 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR252" href="#CR252">2017</a>), or to human outdoor recreation (Tablado and Jenni 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR305" href="#CR305">2017</a>), which can lead to (social) stress and the many negative health consequences that come from long-term stress (Moberg 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR224" href="#CR224">1985</a>; Tapp and Natelson 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR312" href="#CR312">1988</a>; Blanchard et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">2001</a>; Cockrem 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79" href="#CR79">2007</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to perceive threats more accurately, animals use several strategies, such as becoming more sensitive to predator behaviour and specific morphological traits to distinguish one type of predator from another (Stankowich and Blumstein 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR298" href="#CR298">2005</a>). Another effective strategy is to increase vigilance. Perceiving the environment with accuracy for an extended period of time in order to detect potential dangers is costly, as it takes away from other activities such as foraging, which some species of animals can minimise by increasing group size and sharing vigilance (Eilam et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101" href="#CR101">2011</a>). As a result, many group-living animal species have evolved within-group sharing of acquired and evaluated information (Liddell et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR187" href="#CR187">2004</a>; Magrath et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR197" href="#CR197">2015</a>; Wingfield 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR344" href="#CR344">2015</a>) and a sensitivity to alarm displays from conspecifics (Liddell et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR187" href="#CR187">2004</a>; Brown et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">2006</a>; Rieucau et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR262" href="#CR262">2014</a>) as well as cues directly from predators (Rieucau et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR262" href="#CR262">2014</a>). Detection of such cues does not need to be conscious (Liddell et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR187" href="#CR187">2004</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For young animals, there is little room for trial-and-error in distinguishing between friend and foe, as they are often vulnerable to predation from predator species as well as their own kind. For this reason, there is strong selection for young animals to acquire effective risk appraisal (or risk assessment) early in life. As a result, the situations they perceive as a threat or a danger later in life is closely linked to early-life conditions. An adult responding aggressively in certain situations may be doing so because their early-life environment has induced a heightened threat perception, or may respond impulsively because their experiences did not prepare them for the possibility of a predator (Bell et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">2011</a>; El Balaa and Blouin-Demers 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103" href="#CR103">2011</a>). Although it is widely recognised in animal biology that threat perception is an important aspect of animal functioning (Burger and Gochfeld 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">1993</a>; Kirschvink 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR170" href="#CR170">2000</a>; Chamaillé-Jammes et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73" href="#CR73">2014</a>; Rieucau et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR262" href="#CR262">2014</a>), threat perception and differences therein based on early-life environment are rarely linked to the development of coping behaviours (Brown et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">2013</a>; Zidar et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR352" href="#CR352">2017</a>). In part, this is because risk perception (degree of “fear”) is difficult to study in animals (Stankowich and Blumstein 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR298" href="#CR298">2005</a>) and especially difficult to separate from the subsequent response.
 </p>
</sec>
