<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec16" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Perceptual learning</div>
 <p id="Par54" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Perceptual learning is considered as any relatively permanent change of perception as a result of experience (Fahle 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR108" href="#CR108">2004</a>). This process allows individuals to distinguish between similar cues in their environment, for example to differentiate between a dangerous predator and a harmless animal (Brown et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">2011</a>) or to signal and perceive the identity of intra-group conspecifics (Rendall et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR260" href="#CR260">1996</a>). Perceptual learning can occur not only under training conditions but also in situations of passive sensory stimulation, without awareness and without any task relevance (Watanabe et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR338" href="#CR338">2001</a>; Seitz and Dinse 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR281" href="#CR281">2007</a>), which means that frequently occurring stimuli may sensitise perceptual systems, just as habituation desensitised them. It relates to threat and opportunity recognition (“
  <a rid="Sec2" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec2">Perception</a>” section) and the ability to evaluate the correct response to environmental stimuli (“
  <a rid="Sec3" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec3">Evaluation</a>” section), and subsequently can often affect adult behaviour (Beach and Jaynes 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">1954</a>). Studies in humans have shown that perceptual learning can account for more than 76% of the rapid early improvement in performance (Hawkey et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR140" href="#CR140">2004</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par55" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Retention of perceptual learning is shaped by a suite of factors such as the strength of initial conditioning as well as individual personality. In a more recent empirical study, shy versus bold rainbow trout showed no difference in conditioned response, but there was a significant effect of personality on retention of learned predator recognition, where shy fish continued to display a conditioned response after 8 days but bold fish did not (Brown et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">2013</a>). In accord with this study, a low-responsive strain in the same species displayed longer retention of a conditioned response (Øverli et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR243" href="#CR243">2007</a>). Recently, it has been argued that rather than having multiple perceptual systems, the animal-environment interaction cannot be correct unless individual forms of ambient energy such as light and sound exist in emergent, higher order patterns, i.e. a single overarching perceptual system that includes all kinds of perception (Stoffregen et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR301" href="#CR301">2017</a>). This is relevant to the study of early perceptual learning, as empirical work is often (but not always) biased towards visual cues.
 </p>
</sec>
