<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec29" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Resilience and reversibility</div>
 <p id="Par94" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Important concepts when discussing the adaptive advantages and disadvantages that come with sensitivity of developmental processes to early-life conditions are resilience and reversibility. Resilience, the capacity to recover from difficulties, is important in estimating the strength with which negative experiences continue to influence animal health and fitness (Walker et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR336" href="#CR336">2006</a>; Cicchetti 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78" href="#CR78">2010</a>). Reversibility relates to the ability to reverse or undo the effects of (harmful) environmental conditions (Francis et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR119" href="#CR119">2002</a>; Ruedi-Bettschen et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR273" href="#CR273">2004</a>), and is especially important once coping behaviours have been established yet found unfavourable, or when the conditions on which their development was based have changed. While adaptation to early-life conditions can clearly be an adaptive mechanism, the ability to reverse the effects of early-life environments seems equally adaptive especially in the case of improved conditions or changed environments from infancy to adulthood.
 </p>
 <p id="Par95" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although some negative influences of the early-life environment have been shown to be reversible, this reversibility does not appear to apply to all affected coping behaviours. While there is evidence that beneficial later-life circumstances can partially remedy or even completely negate developmental limitations (Salzen and Meyer 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR275" href="#CR275">1968</a>; Francis et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR119" href="#CR119">2002</a>; Gabriel 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR124" href="#CR124">2005</a>), there is also evidence that negative experiences during development continue to negatively affect behavioural functioning for the entire lifespan of an individual (Champagne 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74" href="#CR74">2010</a>). For example, the effects of prenatal stress have been shown to be reversible by enrichment of the physical environment. Cage enrichment during pre-adolescence increased social behaviour and reduced response to stress in prenatally stressed rats, while the same enrichment showed no effects on non-stressed rats (Morley-Fletcher et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR230" href="#CR230">2003</a>). In part, this may be linked to the timing of the negative influence (Keiley et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR165" href="#CR165">2001</a>; Knudsen 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR172" href="#CR172">2004</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par96" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Reversibility of early-life damage such as stress experienced by either mother or child has been shown in mice (Curley et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82" href="#CR82">2009</a>), rats (Champagne et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76" href="#CR76">2003</a>; Cui et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81" href="#CR81">2006</a>) and humans (Keay and Bandler 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR164" href="#CR164">2001</a>; Francis et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR119" href="#CR119">2002</a>). Reversibility of imprinting on early-life stimuli, however, seems to be much harder as imprinted behaviours appear quite stable throughout later in life even with extensive training upon other stimuli (Salzen and Meyer 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR275" href="#CR275">1968</a>). As the processes of early perceptual learning, habituation and conditioning as such have not received much attention, little is known as to the differences between these processes in resilience and reversibility. However, the reversibility of the effects that social learning has on coping behaviours has been studied to a greater extent, and the effects of maternal separation and social deprivation have been shown to be reversible in some species and some situations. For example, for young chimpanzees who grew up without their mother or without conspecifics at all, recovery of healthy behaviours may occur with access to an enriched social environment (Martin 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR201" href="#CR201">2002</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par97" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In some cases, especially when environmental conditions impact developmental processes that occur early in ontogeny or canalisation, negative behavioural consequences of environmental influences may not be reversible. In such a case, the individual finds itself stuck with the coping strategies developed during early life and may suffer fitness consequences. For example, cross-over studies in animals suggest that exposure to adversity in early life does not necessarily increase fitness in tough adult environments. Rather, those malnourished in early life do worse in adult environments, but particularly so in tough adult conditions (Taborsky 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR307" href="#CR307">2006b</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par98" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In other cases, however, the effects of early-life conditions, even when they have been carried over across many generations, may still be reversed. For example, the Balb/c mouse strain is often considered “socially-incompetent” and anxious, yet when the young of this strain were reared in a communal nest instead of under regular laboratory conditions, anxiety-like behaviours and parental care were improved in both first- and second-generation offspring (Curley et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82" href="#CR82">2009</a>). Results such as these imply that the harmful coping behaviours in this strain may be a result of intergenerational effects of standard housing conditions, which can be attenuated both within and across generations in cases where the appropriate environmental cues allow the harmful coping behaviours to become reversible. This example from animal models is encouraging and may be applied in other species, including humans.
 </p>
</sec>
