<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec22" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Social group</div>
 <p id="Par73" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The relationship between individuals and a group of conspecifics is often referred to as their social environment or social group, which especially in recent years has been an increasingly studied topic in animal behaviour. The social group is important in processes of social learning (see “
  <a rid="Sec17" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec17">Social learning</a>” section) but also relates to safety from predators for animals living in groups, competition for resources and dominance interactions (Love et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR193" href="#CR193">2013</a>). Within selected studies, the effects of early-life social environment were studied quantitatively in the context of early-life social isolation (Van Den Berg et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR326" href="#CR326">1999</a>; Tuchscherer et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR320" href="#CR320">2006</a>; Kemme et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR167" href="#CR167">2008</a>; Tanaka et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR309" href="#CR309">2010</a>; Hesse et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR147" href="#CR147">2016</a>; Riley et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR263" href="#CR263">2017</a>) and group size (Edenbrow and Croft 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99" href="#CR99">2011</a>; Naguib et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR232" href="#CR232">2011</a>; Rödel and Meyer 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR266" href="#CR266">2011</a>; Niemelä et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR236" href="#CR236">2012</a>; Riley et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR263" href="#CR263">2017</a>), and qualitatively in the context of relationships with siblings and other conspecifics (Carere et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" href="#CR67">2005</a>; Moretz et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR228" href="#CR228">2007a</a>; Hudson et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR151" href="#CR151">2011</a>; Wismer et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR346" href="#CR346">2014</a>). The effects of social group are predominantly studied in rodents, specifically rats. Frequency, duration and latency of various social behavioural elements such as social exploration, approach/following and anogenital sniffing were affected when juvenile rats were isolated from their social group. However, once social contact was initiated, a relatively normal behavioural pattern was displayed (Van Den Berg et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR326" href="#CR326">1999</a>). Other studies found that socially isolated juvenile rats had difficulty with social recognition (Tanaka et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR309" href="#CR309">2010</a>). In rodent species like rats and mice, social environment can be studied through the communal nest, an experimental setting similar to a natural nest, in which juveniles can interact with peers as well as with their mother and siblings (Branchi 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">2009</a>). Communally reared rats were found to display reduced anxiety-like behaviour when exposed to novel environments, and females were more subordinate and less aggressive when exposed to an intruder male (Curley et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82" href="#CR82">2009</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par74" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The influence of the presence and absence of a social group has also been studied in other species. Group housing in zebra finches (
  <span class="italic">T. guttata</span>), for example, was related to a higher number of social interactions in males (Bölting and von Engelhardt 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">2017</a>). In cichlids (
  <span class="italic">N. pulcher</span>), fry raised with adults showed more aggressive and submissive behaviour to each other than fish raised with siblings only (Arnold and Taborsky 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">2010</a>). When early-life social rearing was combined with simulated predation threat in cichlids, individuals developed specialised behavioural competences leading to different developmental trajectories with respects to, among others, dispersal (Fischer et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR117" href="#CR117">2017</a>). In addition, a study on water striders (Gerridae sp
  <span class="italic">.</span>) showed that being raised in a social environment affected the degree of behavioural plasticity males exhibited later in life, i.e. the flexibility they had to choose a coping behaviour depending on the situation at hand, something that can significantly affect a male’s fitness (Han and Brooks 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR137" href="#CR137">2014</a>). Spiders (
  <span class="italic">Marpissa muscosa</span>) reared in groups are better at exploration of a maze and at sociality than those reared in isolation, which is especially relevant since isolated rearing adds no known additional stress in this species (Liedtke and Schneider 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR188" href="#CR188">2017</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par75" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Not only the presence or absence of the group was found to be relevant to behavioural development, but also size of the group. Litter size affected anxiety in rats in a non-linear way: young rats born to small- or large-sized litters had higher scores of anxiety-like behaviours than those from medium-sized litters (Rödel and Meyer 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR266" href="#CR266">2011</a>). A review on rabbits, rats and mice showed that early sibling relations, such as position in the huddle, contributed to the development of individual differences in behavioural style (Hudson et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR151" href="#CR151">2011</a>). Group size also affected aggression, fear and display behaviours in black-headed gulls (
  <span class="italic">Larus ridibundus</span>), which was not reversed after birds were re-housed in larger groups (Groothuis and Mulekom 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR132" href="#CR132">1991</a>). Rearing-group size and the time juveniles spent in these groups interactively influenced the development of social skills in cichlids (Fischer et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR116" href="#CR116">2015</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par76" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Social group appears to not affect the development of all coping behaviours, even in species that are sensitive to social cues during development, nor does it necessarily affect sociality itself. An interesting study into the effects of housing different strains of zebrafish (
  <span class="italic">Danio rerio</span>) together as juveniles showed that the type of social experience during early life affected social behaviours: all mixed-group fish were more inclined to biting, while mixed-group fish of one strain were also more exploratory. No effects were found on activity, predator response or stress recovery (Moretz et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR229" href="#CR229">2007b</a>). In field crickets (
  <span class="italic">G. integer</span>), young males reared in the presence of conspecific acoustic sexual signals were less aggressive and less likely to become dominant relative to those reared in the absence of acoustic signals (DiRienzo et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93" href="#CR93">2012</a>). Studies such as these show that there is a need to look beyond simple presence/absence of social group when studying sociality as an early-life factor impacting coping behaviours.
 </p>
</sec>
