<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec17" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Social learning</div>
 <p id="Par56" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Social learning includes a wide range of mechanisms through which individuals receive and integrate information from other members of their social group. In animals, juveniles learn in very similar ways as humans, namely through mimicking the role model provided by conspecifics (most commonly parents), through active parenting by means of example and correction, and through conditional parenting based on offspring performance. What all such mechanisms have in common is that they involve learning from observation of a conspecific or from interaction with them (Heyes 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR148" href="#CR148">1994</a>; Hoppitt and Laland 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR150" href="#CR150">2008</a>). A special subset of social learning in humans and perhaps some kinds of primates is teaching, where older or more experienced members of the same social group intentionally pass on information, techniques or behaviours to juveniles. Through social learning, animals can acquire more information, skills and behaviours that allow them to deal with their environment than they might reasonably acquire based on personal experience, as shown for example in a study of wild meerkats (
  <span class="italic">Suricata suricatta</span>) where adults were shown to teach pups prey-handling skills (Thornton and McAuliffe 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR315" href="#CR315">2006</a>). Social learning also helps juveniles to learn the dominance hierarchy within a group, which facilitates group living and, as such, the protection and cooperation provided by a larger group size. A potential disadvantage is that individuals rely on others for the signal they get about environmental conditions rather than relying on their own sensory systems. Social learning is especially common in species where offspring are dependent on their parents for survival for a long time (van Schaik 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR329" href="#CR329">2010</a>), or where they live in strongly social groups. Mice, for example, are highly social animals, and young mice reared in a communal nest develop relevant social behaviours that mice reared with single mothers do not (Branchi 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">2009</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par57" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Models of social learning predict that animals living in stable environments should be more attentive to socially acquired information than animals living in variable environments (Zentall and Galef 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR351" href="#CR351">1988</a>), as social learning can be maladaptive when the information modelled by the parents has become outdated with regard to the current environment or when the environment is highly variable (Galef and Whiskin 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR125" href="#CR125">2004</a>; Laland 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR181" href="#CR181">2004</a>), causing juveniles to acquire coping behaviours that are mismatched to their environment (Lof et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR191" href="#CR191">2012</a>). It can also be adaptive, as shown when fairy wren (
  <span class="italic">Malurus cyaneus</span>) learned to recognise unfamiliar sounds as alarm calls through social “eavesdropping” (Magrath et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR197" href="#CR197">2015</a>). Models also predict that animals should be influenced more by the coping behaviour of older than younger group members (Benskin et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">2002</a>), as they are more experienced. Empirical work on rats supported the first, but not the second of these models (Galef and Whiskin 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR125" href="#CR125">2004</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par58" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Through the development of behavioural patterns within social groups, rearing conditions can have lasting effects on the expression of adult coping behaviours (Rice 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR261" href="#CR261">2008</a>; Roulin et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR272" href="#CR272">2010</a>). Of concern to conservation and coping with challenges of a changing world is recent evidence that wildlife can learn harmful behaviours from each other: whether or not bottlenose dolphins (
  <span class="italic">Tursiops aduncus</span>) become conditioned to being illegally fed by recreational fishers depended on both the degree to which the dolphins would frequent areas with a lot of tourism, and the degree to which they associated with previously conditioned dolphins (Donaldson et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95" href="#CR95">2012</a>). Not only is social learning in this way related to conditioning, it is also, like many of the other processes that link coping behaviours to the early-life environment, modulated by maternal care (Lindeyer et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR189" href="#CR189">2013</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
