<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Boons, et al. [
 <xref rid="B27-ijerph-14-01472" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>] and Owens [
 <xref rid="B95-ijerph-14-01472" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">95</xref>] posited that distributing appropriate information helps improve popular perceived risks and increase environmental concern over GCC among uninformed people. When people aware of the environmental risks of GCC, the relevant scientific principles and technologies that are easy to understand [
 <xref rid="B36-ijerph-14-01472" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="B96-ijerph-14-01472" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">96</xref>,
 <xref rid="B97-ijerph-14-01472" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">97</xref>], which can be used to develop concepts for reducing environmental risks. Preventive measures should also be taken to protect the future and meaningful operational strategies should be established. The more individuals with high- and low-scoring personality traits understand the environmental risks of GCC, the stronger their pro-environmental attitudes should become. For both groups of individuals, changes in their pro-environmental attitudes and their understanding of perceived risks of GCC tend to be consistent. An important step in the theoretical development of this approach is to examine the relationships among currently available instruments and variables and how they combine to predict environmental behavior. The present study’s premise was that individuals engage in pro-environment behavioral intentions of GCC adaptation to the degree that is allowed by their pro-environmental attitudes. The results show that the theoretical and methodological background of green educators can be enriched by using antecedent variables for pro-environment behavioral intentions within survey procedures. This is a powerful predictive model of self-reported pro-environment behavioral intention as well as provides a better understanding of the structure of individual personality traits.
</p>
