<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">To create a more robust final predictive map of each species for each time slice (current, 2050, and 2070), we generated ensemble forecasts to reconcile the inherent uncertainties generated from the use of different algorithms, AOGCMs, and RCPs (Araújo &amp; New, 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>). Regarding the baseline projections, the climatic suitability map of each species considered the mean value per grid cell of the four algorithms, whereas the 2050 and 2070 projections considered the mean value per grid cell of the four algorithms X 3AOGCMs X 2RCPs (Araújo et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>). Further, we generated a binary map for each species based on the mean threshold value among the different algorithm predictions of the sensitivity‐specificity equality approach (Liu, Berry, Dawson, &amp; Pearson, 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2005</xref>). The dispersal ability of species under climate change, which means assuming species presence in those climatically suitable sites that are not suitable in the baseline predictions, was only considered for those continuous predictions. That is, any continuous climatically suitable area that partially overlaps the baseline prediction has the potential to be colonized by a given species. On the other hand, this assumption is more critical to isolated climatically suitable areas due to the necessity of a given species to disperse throughout a climatically unsuitable area. Then, we kept the main predicted continuous areas of species irrespective if there are new climatically suitable areas compared to the baseline predictions; yet we individually checked each binary prediction to delete unrealistic isolated predictions (i.e., environmentally suitable areas of a given species instead of predicted distributions) more than 400 km away from the main predicted area or any known occurrence record of a species (Vasconcelos et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). Finally, these binary maps were used to create a presence–absence matrix to determine the alpha and beta diversity metrics for each time slice. All pre‐processing (preparation of species and climate data), processing (model running), and post‐processing (model evaluation and ensemble maps) procedures were performed using the 
 <italic class="italic">sdm</italic> package in the R environment (Naimi &amp; Araújo, 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>).
</p>
