<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Tipping Cascades.</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3</a> shows a global map of some potential tipping cascades. The tipping elements fall into three clusters based on their estimated threshold temperature (
  <a rid="r12" ref-type="bibr" href="#r12">12</a>, 
  <a rid="r17" ref-type="bibr" href="#r17">17</a>, 
  <a rid="r39" ref-type="bibr" href="#r39">39</a>). Cascades could be formed when a rise in global temperature reaches the level of the lower-temperature cluster, activating tipping elements, such as loss of the Greenland Ice Sheet or Arctic sea ice. These tipping elements, along with some of the nontipping element feedbacks (e.g., gradual weakening of land and ocean physiological carbon sinks), could push the global average temperature even higher, inducing tipping in mid- and higher-temperature clusters. For example, tipping (loss) of the Greenland Ice Sheet could trigger a critical transition in the Atlantic Meridional Ocean Circulation (AMOC), which could together, by causing sea-level rise and Southern Ocean heat accumulation, accelerate ice loss from the East Antarctic Ice Sheet (
  <a rid="r32" ref-type="bibr" href="#r32">32</a>, 
  <a rid="r40" ref-type="bibr" href="#r40">40</a>) on timescales of centuries (
  <a rid="r41" ref-type="bibr" href="#r41">41</a>).
 </p>
 <div id="fig03" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 3.</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Global map of potential tipping cascades. The individual tipping elements are color- coded according to estimated thresholds in global average surface temperature (tipping points) (
    <a rid="r12" ref-type="bibr" href="#r12">12</a>, 
    <a rid="r34" ref-type="bibr" href="#r34">34</a>). Arrows show the potential interactions among the tipping elements based on expert elicitation that could generate cascades. Note that, although the risk for tipping (loss of) the East Antarctic Ice Sheet is proposed at &gt;5 °C, some marine-based sectors in East Antarctica may be vulnerable at lower temperatures (
    <a rid="r35" ref-type="bibr" href="#r35">35</a>
    <a href="#r36">*</a>
    <a href="#r37">*</a>–
    <a rid="r38" ref-type="bibr" href="#r38">38</a>).
   </p>
  </div>
  <div id="gra3" xlink:href="pnas.1810141115fig03" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Observations of past behavior support an important contribution of changes in ocean circulation to such feedback cascades. During previous glaciations, the climate system flickered between two states that seem to reflect changes in convective activity in the Nordic seas and changes in the activity of the AMOC. These variations caused typical temperature response patterns called the “bipolar seesaw” (
  <a rid="r42" ref-type="bibr" href="#r42">42</a>
  <a href="#r43">*</a>–
  <a rid="r44" ref-type="bibr" href="#r44">44</a>). During extremely cold conditions in the north, heat accumulated in the Southern Ocean, and Antarctica warmed. Eventually, the heat made its way north and generated subsurface warming that may have been instrumental in destabilizing the edges of the Northern Hemisphere ice sheets (
  <a rid="r45" ref-type="bibr" href="#r45">45</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">If Greenland and the West Antarctic Ice Sheet melt in the future, the freshening and cooling of nearby surface waters will have significant effects on the ocean circulation. While the probability of significant circulation changes is difficult to quantify, climate model simulations suggest that freshwater inputs compatible with current rates of Greenland melting are sufficient to have measurable effects on ocean temperature and circulation (
  <a rid="r46" ref-type="bibr" href="#r46">46</a>, 
  <a rid="r47" ref-type="bibr" href="#r47">47</a>). Sustained warming of the northern high latitudes as a result of this process could accelerate feedbacks or activate tipping elements in that region, such as permafrost degradation, loss of Arctic sea ice, and boreal forest dieback.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While this may seem to be an extreme scenario, it illustrates that a warming into the range of even the lower-temperature cluster (i.e., the Paris targets) could lead to tipping in the mid- and higher-temperature clusters via cascade effects. Based on this analysis of tipping cascades and taking a risk-averse approach, we suggest that a potential planetary threshold could occur at a temperature rise as low as ∼2.0 °C above preindustrial (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" href="#fig01">Fig. 1</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
