<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Albedo values among plots met the assumption of normality, but failed the ANOVA assumption of homoscedasticity among treatment groups. Thus, we used simple linear regressions to related albedo to individual surface properties and multiple linear regression to related albedo to combined ground surface properties (cyanobacterial, moss, and lichen cover; soil moisture at 2 and 5 cm, and surface roughness) in the absence of treatment groupings; and used a non-parametric Kruskal-Wallis test to compare albedo among treatment groups with Steel-Dwass post-hoc pairwise comparisons (a non-parametric test that corrects for sequential comparisons similar to Tukey’s HSD) for individual treatment contrasts. The best fit multiple regression model (i.e., the model that explained the most variation in albedo using the fewest independent factors) was determined as the model with the smallest Bayesian information criterion (
 <italic class="italic">BIC</italic>) value via a stepwise, forward fitting procedure. Albedo was also modeled with cyanobacteria, soil roughness, and soil moisture via a structural equation model. Albedo measured on one watering treatment plot was considered to be a high-end outlier, due to an error while collecting the HCRF measurements in the field and was subsequently removed before analyses to avoid biasing our estimates of climate-manipulation treatments on albedo. However, this outlier is retained in a companion set of analyses using identical testing procedures for readers’ consideration within 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Supplementary Information Figs S2–S4</xref>. All statistical procedures were completed in JMP Pro 12.0.1
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b57" class="xref">57</xref>, with the exception of the SEM, which was constructed with the GLS estimator and vetted via minimum function test statistic and 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>-values using the 
 <italic class="italic">lavaan</italic> package in R version 3.1.2
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b58" class="xref">58</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b59" class="xref">59</xref>.
</p>
