<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Radiative effects at TOA</div>
 <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Clouds primarily scatter (and reflect) shortwave radiation and primarily absorb longwave (terrestrial) radiation. Clouds re-emit the absorbed radiation at the effective cloud temperature, which (except for temperature inversions) is usually lower than the surface temperature. The cloud is negatively related to the SIC at part of the Arctic area. When sea ice retreats, more clouds are expected to form and have radiative effects: (i) increase the solar energy reflected to space and thereby cool the atmosphere (surface), and (ii) reduce the outgoing longwave radiation which warms the surface. The net radiative effect of clouds may change from warming to cooling due to frequent temperature inversions and low solar elevations in the polar regions.</p>
 <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The cloud forcing anomalies of the TOA reflected shortwave irradiance are shown in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4b</a>: 2007 and Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4d</a>: 2008. For 2007, the cloud fraction has a positive anomaly of 6–8% (in absolute unit) in the Kara Sea and Laptev Sea areas. This 6–8% cloud fraction anomaly results in up to a 40 W/m
  <span class="sup">2</span> anomaly in shortwave TOA irradiance in the Kara Sea and Laptev Sea areas. The Beaufort Sea area, which has a 8–10% smaller cloud fraction than the longterm average, shows a negative anomaly of 4–10 W/m
  <span class="sup">2</span> in shortwave TOA irradiance.
  <div id="Fig4" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Cloud forcing anomaly of shortwave and longwave upward irradiance at the TOA during the investigated period. (
     <span class="bold">a</span>) The anomaly of longwave radiative forcing for 2007; (
     <span class="bold">b</span>) the anomaly of shortwave radiative forcing for 2007; (
     <span class="bold">c</span>) same as (
     <span class="bold">a</span>) but for 2008; (
     <span class="bold">d</span>) same as (
     <span class="bold">b</span>) but for 2008.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_44155_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e647" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For 2008, based on the observed cloud fraction and radiative flux, the cloud fraction shows a positive anomaly of 2–6% in the Beaufort Sea area, which implies an extra short wave radiative energy of 20–40 W/m
  <span class="sup">2</span> reflected to space compared to the longterm average (see Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). A negative cloud fraction is found in the Laptev Sea and East Siberian Sea (about – 4–6% in absolute units), where the cloud forcing anomaly of the TOA shortwave irradiance exceeds 30 W/m
  <span class="sup">2</span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition to the reflection of sunlight, clouds also act as effective longwave absorbers/emitters that redistribute the longwave radiation. More cloud cover means less longwave radiation emitted to space and vice versa. Figure 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a> shows the cloud forcing anomaly of the TOA longwave radiation. For 2007, the cloud fraction has a strong negative anomaly (over 10%) in the Beaufort Sea area and a moderately negative anomaly (4–6%) in the Chukchi Sea. Corresponding to these reductions in cloud amounts, these areas have strong/moderate (1–5 W/m
  <span class="sup">2</span>) positive anomalies of the longwave radiative forcing. The cloud forcing anomalies of the TOA longwave radiation are negative (over −5%) in the Laptev Sea area which has a positive cloud fraction anomaly (2–5%).
 </p>
 <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For 2008, the cloud fraction has a negative anomaly (−4–6%) in the Laptev Sea which shows a strong positive cloud forcing anomaly (2–4%) of the TOA longwave irradiance. A positive cloud fraction anomaly (2–5%) occurs in the Beaufort Sea which has up to −5 W/m
  <span class="sup">2</span> negative cloud forcing anomaly of TOA longwave radiation. A positive cloud fraction anomaly occurs in the Laptev Sea and East Siberian Sea in 2007 and in the Beaufort Sea in 2008 where a total (shortwave and longwave) extra irradiance of up to 35 W/m
  <span class="sup">2</span> escapes to space. A negative cloud fraction anomaly occurs in the Beaufort Sea in 2007 and in the Laptev Sea in 2008 where a total irradiance of 10–25 W/m
  <span class="sup">2</span> escapes to space. The strength of ice albedo feedback in the climate system can be represented by a feedback parameter defined as
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span>:
  <div id="Equ1" class="disp-formula">
   <span class="label">1</span>
   <div class="alternatives">
    <span id="M3" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$\lambda =\frac{\delta R}{\delta \sigma }\frac{\delta \sigma }{\delta {T}_{s}}$$\end{document}</span>
    <div id="M4" display="block" class="math">
     <span class="mi">λ</span>
     <span class="mo">=</span>
     <div class="mfrac">
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mi">δ</span>
       <span class="mi">R</span>
      </div>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mi">δ</span>
       <span class="mi">σ</span>
      </div>
     </div>
     <div class="mfrac">
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mi">δ</span>
       <span class="mi">σ</span>
      </div>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mi">δ</span>
       <div class="msub">
        <div class="mrow">
         <span class="mi">T</span>
        </div>
        <div class="mrow">
         <span class="mi">s</span>
        </div>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="41598_2019_44155_Article_Equ1.gif" position="anchor" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </div>where 
  <span class="italic">δR</span> is the change of TOA cloud radiative forcing, 
  <span class="italic">δσ</span> is the change of the sea ice loss given a perturbation in the surface temperature 
  <span class="italic">δT</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">s</span>
  </sub>. The first part of the right hand side in Eq. (
  <a rid="Equ1" ref-type="" href="#Equ1">1</a>) is defined as the radiative kernel. We use the anomaly of sea ice concentration to represent the change of surface. Thus the radiative kernel of ice albedo feedback is estimated through the observation with average of −0.46 ± 0.90 Wm
  <span class="sup">−2</span> percent
  <span class="sup">−1</span> for the shortwave radiation and +0.14 ± 0.087 Wm
  <span class="sup">−2</span> percent
  <span class="sup">−1</span> for the longwave radiation. These results mean that a one percent decline in SIC will result in an additional shortwave forcing of −0.46 Wm
  <span class="sup">−2</span> and longwave forcing of +0.14 Wm
  <span class="sup">−2</span> due to changes in cloud cover.
 </p>
 <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The neutral cases which have anomalies less than 8% are discarded to avoid the small number problem which means divided by a small number to produce unstable cases. The cases in the distribution range greater than 3 times of deviation are also discarded. These values represent the situation that sea ice anomaly not exceed 20%. Limited by the length of the CERES, CALIPSO, CloudSat, and MODIS (CCCM) merged dataset used in this study (see the “Method” section of details), the radiative kernels are based on observations from 2007 to 2010.</p>
</sec>
