<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec015" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Effects of space</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The correlations of species richness and proportion of frugivorous and insectivorous species with geographic distances indicate that the distribution of suitable habitats is largely spatially autocorrelated and that neighbouring localities are more likely to have a similar species richness and feeding guilds. The fact that spatial effects for different feeding guilds were detected but not for species composition, may indicate that different species from the same guilds may replace each other in neighbouring localities and the exact species composition is determined more by local habitat conditions. We should, however, be cautious about accepting this conclusion as the number of birds recorded at each sampling point was relatively low and the high turnover in species composition may be also at least partly caused by low sampling effort. Significant effect of longitude and latitude, which were included as covariates in the subsequent tests supported the importance of space for these variables. These variables can in fact act as surrogates of climatic variables at larger spatial scales [
  <a rid="pone.0150498.ref081" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0150498.ref081">81</a>]. In contrast to our results, the geographic variables (longitude and latitude) are regarded as important determinants not only of species richness [
  <a rid="pone.0150498.ref082" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0150498.ref082">82</a>] but also of the occurrence of specific birds and thus of species composition in several previous studies (e.g. [
  <a rid="pone.0150498.ref083" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0150498.ref083">83</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0150498.ref084" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0150498.ref084">84</a>]), which indicates that spatially autocorrelated edaphic and floristic differences are the main factors driving this pattern. These studies were, however, done in areas with a less variable topography and where large scale differences are likely to dominate over local habitat differentiation.
 </p>
</sec>
