<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Astronomically tuned chronology</div>
 <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The chronology is based on minimal tuning
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" href="#CR67">67</a>
  </span> of the benthic oxygen isotope record to a computed orbital solution
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>
  </span> (Supplementary Note 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>). We used an ET composite with equal weight of eccentricity and obliquity as tuning target and tuned δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O minima to ET maxima (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">4</a>). This strategy is based on the notion that relatively warm summers at high obliquity promote ice sheet melting at high latitudes and that a low summer insolation gradient between low and high latitudes at high obliquity leads to a decrease in poleward moisture transport, inhibiting ice sheet buildup
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" href="#CR68">68</a>
  </span>. We did not adjust our tuning for possible phase lags between δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O and insolation forcing, since the response time of smaller Miocene ice sheets is unknown. We did not include high-latitude summer insolation and/or precession (P) parameters in our tuning target to remain independent of possible changes between dominant northern (ET−P) or southern (ET+P) hemisphere precessional insolation forcing. We note that the obliquity cycle (41 kyr) and the eccentricity cycles (100 and 400 kyr) are also prominently imprinted in the benthic δ
  <span class="sup">13</span>C record (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">6A</a>). The detection of these astronomical frequencies in the δ
  <span class="sup">13</span>C record supports the age model, based on independent tuning of the δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O series. Age correlation points are given in Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">4D</a> and Supplementary Table 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>.
 </p>
</sec>
