<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec7" sec-type="materials|methods" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Revision of shipboard sediment splice</div>
  <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cores were sampled in ~5 cm intervals (~2 kyr time resolution) from a composite sequence (shipboard splice) of Holes 1146A and 1146C (Cores 1146C-30X to 1146C-39X). After comparison of the shipboard natural gamma ray, color reflectance, magnetic susceptibility data, and overlapping benthic isotope records over the splice tie points, we made the following modification to the original shipboard splice: we defined a new tie point between Cores 1146C-38X and 1146A-39X (1146C-38X-4, 122 cm at 359.52 m below sea floor (mbsf) tie to 1146A-39X-2, 107 cm at 359.87 mbsf), based on the match of isotope data from Holes 1146A and C. This adjustment resulted in the addition of an 80 cm splice segment from Hole 1146A to the meter composite depth (mcd) scale.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Benthic and planktic foraminiferal stable isotopes</div>
  <p id="Par28" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All samples were oven dried at 40 °C and weighed before washing over a 63 µm sieve. Residues were oven dried at 40 °C on a sheet of filter paper, then weighed and sieved into different size fractions. We measured δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O and δ
   <span class="sup">13</span>C in the epifaunal benthic foraminifers 
   <span class="italic">C. wuellerstorfi</span> and/or 
   <span class="italic">C. mundulus</span> and on the mixed layer foraminifer 
   <span class="italic">G. sacculifer</span>. Well-preserved tests were broken into large fragments, cleaned in alcohol in an ultrasonic bath, then dried at 40 °C. Stable isotopes were measured with a Finnigan MAT 253 mass spectrometer at the Leibniz Laboratory, University of Kiel. The instrument is coupled on-line to a Carbo-Kiel Device (Type IV) for automated CO
   <sub>2</sub> preparation from carbonate samples for isotopic analysis. Samples were reacted by individual acid addition (99% H
   <sub>3</sub>PO
   <sub>4</sub> at 75 °C). On the basis of the performance of international and lab-internal standard carbonates, the precision is better than ±0.09‰. Paired measurements in middle Miocene samples from ODP Sites 1146 and 1237 previously indicated no significant offset in δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O and δ
   <span class="sup">13</span>C between 
   <span class="italic">C. wuellerstorfi</span> and 
   <span class="italic">C. mundulus</span>
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
   </span>. Results were calibrated using the National Institute of Standard and Technology (Gaithersburg, MD) carbonate isotope standard and NBS (National Bureau of Standard) 19 and NBS 20, and are reported on the Vienna PeeDee Belemnite scale.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Astronomically tuned chronology</div>
  <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The chronology is based on minimal tuning
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" href="#CR67">67</a>
   </span> of the benthic oxygen isotope record to a computed orbital solution
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>
   </span> (Supplementary Note 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>). We used an ET composite with equal weight of eccentricity and obliquity as tuning target and tuned δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O minima to ET maxima (Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">4</a>). This strategy is based on the notion that relatively warm summers at high obliquity promote ice sheet melting at high latitudes and that a low summer insolation gradient between low and high latitudes at high obliquity leads to a decrease in poleward moisture transport, inhibiting ice sheet buildup
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" href="#CR68">68</a>
   </span>. We did not adjust our tuning for possible phase lags between δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O and insolation forcing, since the response time of smaller Miocene ice sheets is unknown. We did not include high-latitude summer insolation and/or precession (P) parameters in our tuning target to remain independent of possible changes between dominant northern (ET−P) or southern (ET+P) hemisphere precessional insolation forcing. We note that the obliquity cycle (41 kyr) and the eccentricity cycles (100 and 400 kyr) are also prominently imprinted in the benthic δ
   <span class="sup">13</span>C record (Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">6A</a>). The detection of these astronomical frequencies in the δ
   <span class="sup">13</span>C record supports the age model, based on independent tuning of the δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O series. Age correlation points are given in Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">4D</a> and Supplementary Table 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec11" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mixed layer temperature reconstructions</div>
  <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ma/Ca measurements were performed on ~30 well-preserved specimens of 
   <span class="italic">G. sacculifer</span> from the 250–315 μm fraction (average weights of ~400 μg). Sample spacing is 20 cm from Sample 1146C-30X-1, 33 cm (298.43 revised mcd) to Sample 1146A-39X-4, 88 cm (387.28 revised mcd), corresponding to a mean temporal resolution of ~7 kyr between 8.11 and 5.07 Ma. Sample spacing was decreased to 5 cm, corresponding to a temporal resolution of ~2 kyr, over the prominent benthic δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O maxima TG4, TG12, TG14, and TG22 between 6.0 and 5 Ma. Tests of 
   <span class="italic">G. sacculifer</span> were crushed between glass plates and cleaned with methanol and reductive (hydrazine) and oxidative (hydrogen peroxide) steps, as detailed in refs. 
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" href="#CR69">69</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" href="#CR70">70</a>
   </span>. Samples were then leached and diluted with nitric acid and analyzed with a SPECTRO Ciros
   <span class="sup">CCD</span> SOP ICP-OES at the ICP-MS Laboratory of the Institute of Geosciences, University of Kiel. We monitored Fe/Ca, Al/Ca, and Mn/Ca ratios to assess the efficacy of the cleaning procedure. These trace-element/Ca ratios do not show significant correlation with Mg/Ca. Mixed layer temperatures were estimated from Mg/Ca ratios using the exponential equation for 
   <span class="italic">G. sacculifer</span> with an assumed A constant of 0.09
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71" href="#CR71">71</a>
   </span>. Fifty-four duplicate measurements show a mean Mg/Ca standard deviation of 0.13 mmol mol
   <span class="sup">−1</span>. The error associated with mixed layer temperature estimates was defined by propagating the errors introduced by the Mg/Ca measurements and the Mg/Ca temperature calibration assuming no covariance among these errors, following ref. 
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72" href="#CR72">72</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec12" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Time frequency analysis</div>
  <p id="Par31" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Orbital tuning, bandpass-filtering, calculation of sedimentation rates, and Blackman–Tukey cross-spectral analyses are performed with AnalySeries 2.0.4.2
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73" href="#CR73">73</a>
   </span>. Cross-wavelet analysis is performed following ref. 
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74" href="#CR74">74</a>
   </span>. We utilize wavelet coherence to quantify coherence and phase relationships between the benthic δ
   <span class="sup">13</span>C and δ
   <span class="sup">18</span>O time series in frequency space. We employed the Morlet wavelet and a Monte Carlo count of 300 to establish the statistical significance level (5%). Prior to analysis, both time series were interpolated to 2 kyr time steps and standardized (zero mean and unit standard deviation). Software is available at 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pol.ac.uk/home/research/waveletcoherence/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.pol.ac.uk/home/research/waveletcoherence/</span>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec25" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data availability</div>
  <p id="Par32" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data are archived at the Data Publisher for Earth and Environmental Science (
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://doi.pangaea.de/10.1594/PANGAEA.887393" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://doi.pangaea.de/10.1594/PANGAEA.887393</span>).
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
