<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec11" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mixed layer temperature reconstructions</div>
 <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ma/Ca measurements were performed on ~30 well-preserved specimens of 
  <span class="italic">G. sacculifer</span> from the 250–315 μm fraction (average weights of ~400 μg). Sample spacing is 20 cm from Sample 1146C-30X-1, 33 cm (298.43 revised mcd) to Sample 1146A-39X-4, 88 cm (387.28 revised mcd), corresponding to a mean temporal resolution of ~7 kyr between 8.11 and 5.07 Ma. Sample spacing was decreased to 5 cm, corresponding to a temporal resolution of ~2 kyr, over the prominent benthic δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O maxima TG4, TG12, TG14, and TG22 between 6.0 and 5 Ma. Tests of 
  <span class="italic">G. sacculifer</span> were crushed between glass plates and cleaned with methanol and reductive (hydrazine) and oxidative (hydrogen peroxide) steps, as detailed in refs. 
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" href="#CR69">69</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" href="#CR70">70</a>
  </span>. Samples were then leached and diluted with nitric acid and analyzed with a SPECTRO Ciros
  <span class="sup">CCD</span> SOP ICP-OES at the ICP-MS Laboratory of the Institute of Geosciences, University of Kiel. We monitored Fe/Ca, Al/Ca, and Mn/Ca ratios to assess the efficacy of the cleaning procedure. These trace-element/Ca ratios do not show significant correlation with Mg/Ca. Mixed layer temperatures were estimated from Mg/Ca ratios using the exponential equation for 
  <span class="italic">G. sacculifer</span> with an assumed A constant of 0.09
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71" href="#CR71">71</a>
  </span>. Fifty-four duplicate measurements show a mean Mg/Ca standard deviation of 0.13 mmol mol
  <span class="sup">−1</span>. The error associated with mixed layer temperature estimates was defined by propagating the errors introduced by the Mg/Ca measurements and the Mg/Ca temperature calibration assuming no covariance among these errors, following ref. 
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72" href="#CR72">72</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
</sec>
