<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The selection of appropriate indicators and methods of calculation are key components in the empirical analysis. The “method types” include such selections and comparisons between different methods. Many researchers have used the detrended yield to assess the crop vulnerability to climate change. For example, the modeling crop yield
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b37" class="xref">37</xref>, or simulated yield at large scales can used to monitor or forecast regional variability in crop production
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b38" class="xref">38</xref>. To eliminate non-climatic effects on yields, the detrended yield was obtained by subtracting the trend yield from the actual yield
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b39" class="xref">39</xref>. The 21-year linear sliding average method was applied to remove trends in yields, while winter wheat yield was divided into trending yield and meteorological yield, which was further processed as the relative meteorological yield
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b40" class="xref">40</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b41" class="xref">41</xref>. Following previous research
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31" class="xref">31</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b42" class="xref">42</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b43" class="xref">43</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b44" class="xref">44</xref>, I use the detrended yield and averages of actual yield to measure crop sensitivity to drought. I detrended the annual crop yield via an auto-regression function with 3-year lags. Next,I calculated two Crop Failure Index (CFI) using the detrended yield (
 <inline-formula id="d33e286" class="inline-formula">
  <inline-graphic id="d33e287" xlink:href="srep33744-m1.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </inline-formula>) and the average yield (
 <inline-formula id="d33e289" class="inline-formula">
  <inline-graphic id="d33e290" xlink:href="srep33744-m2.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </inline-formula>), respectively,as in 
 <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq7" class="xref">equation (1)</xref>. A CFI of more than one indicates crop failure and the greater the CFI, the more severe is the crop failure.
</p>
