<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We used three different time-series analysis methods to test for a causal relationship between SCOR and DOT: (i) convergent cross mapping (CCM) [
 <xref rid="RSPB20170722C37" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSPB20170722C38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>], based on the concept of state space reconstruction from time-delay embedding [
 <xref rid="RSPB20170722C39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>]; (ii) information transfer (IT) analysis [
 <xref rid="RSPB20170722C40" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSPB20170722C41" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>], based on the concept of directional information flow [
 <xref rid="RSPB20170722C42" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>]; and (iii) Bayesian inference of causal connections based on linear stochastic differential equations (SDEs) [
 <xref rid="RSPB20170722C43" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSPB20170722C44" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>]. To distinguish unidirectional forcing from bidirectional causality, we calculated CCM for different time lags of the original time series. If there is a discernible delay between cause and effect, then CCM is expected to peak for negative time lags in the direction(s) of true causality (past predicts future). If true causality is unidirectional but with synchrony (inducing two-way predictability), then any CCM skill in the non-causal direction is expected to peak for positive lags (future predicts past). IT analysis has previously been applied to geological records [
 <xref rid="RSPB20170722C13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSPB20170722C41" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSPB20170722C45" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>]. Here, we expand on earlier applications by using time lags analogously to the lagged CCM. If there is a causal delay, then IT is expected to peak for negative time lags in the direction(s) of true causality (past → future), and any IT in the non-causal direction is expected to peak for positive lags. In the analysis of SCOR and DOT, lagged CCM and IT are both reported as median values and 95% ranges at each lag calculated by iterative sampling across an ensemble of SCOR curves, with significance evaluated against a distribution of surrogate time series. SDE analysis is a model-based approach. Here, we first determined the most probable stochastic models for SCOR and DOT separately, including possible hidden (unobserved) process layers, then we determined the most probable connections between these two models, distinguishing correlations from causal connections and inferring the relative strength, direction and response time of causal connections [
 <xref rid="RSPB20170722C43" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>]. A more detailed description of each time-series analysis method is provided in the electronic supplementary material.
</p>
