<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="section2-0013916513503832" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Beliefs About Climate Change and Support for Action</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Individuals’ beliefs about the world and their place in it are central to most major behavioral models. The expectancy-value (EV) model (
  <a rid="bibr24-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr24-0013916513503832">Fishbein, 1963</a>), the theory of planned behavior (
  <a rid="bibr2-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr2-0013916513503832">Ajzen, 1985</a>), and the VBN theory (
  <a rid="bibr65-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr65-0013916513503832">Stern, 2000</a>), all posit that beliefs provide the foundation from which attitudes toward objects and actions are formed, and those attitudes can be highly predictive of behaviors. It is critical to recognize, however, that beliefs may not be scientifically based and may vary substantially between individuals and groups. Indeed, “they may be irrational, based on invalid or selective information, be self-serving, or otherwise fail to correspond to reality,” but nevertheless “form the cognitive foundation for many of our responses to aspects of that world” (
  <a rid="bibr4-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr4-0013916513503832">Ajzen &amp; Gilbert Cote, 2008</a>, p. 290). This observation is particularly salient in relation to beliefs about climate change given the variance in U.S. public understanding of the phenomenon (
  <a rid="bibr46-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr46-0013916513503832">Maibach et al., 2009</a>; 
  <a rid="bibr75-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr75-0013916513503832">Weber &amp; Stern, 2011</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Studies examining the relationships between beliefs about climate change and behavior or policy support have used varied and generally indirect measures of belief. 
  <a rid="bibr17-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr17-0013916513503832">Dietz et al. (2007)</a> used two measures of “climate change information” consisting of (1) number of times respondents had obtained information specifically about climate change from various sources including newspapers, magazines, television, and the like and (2) a scale measure of how “well informed” about climate change respondents considered themselves to be. 
  <a rid="bibr57-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr57-0013916513503832">O’Connor, Bord, and Fisher (1999)</a> and 
  <a rid="bibr58-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr58-0013916513503832">O’Connor, Bord, Yarnal, and Wiefek (2002)</a> measured belief in climate change through a single-scale item rating the likelihood that average global temperatures would rise over the following 50 years, and measured understanding of causes through an index of several 3-point scales assessing the perceived role of several potential causes of climate change (e.g., heating and cooling homes). 
  <a rid="bibr78-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr78-0013916513503832">Zahran, Brody, Grover, and Vedlitz (2006</a>, p. 779) used two climate change “knowledge” variables. The first was measured through true/false responses to two statements: “Nitrous oxide is a greenhouse gas” and, “The major cause of increased atmospheric concentration of greenhouse gases is burning of fossil fuels.” 
  <a rid="bibr12-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr12-0013916513503832">Brody et al. (2012)</a> used an index measure constructed from five true/false statements about climate change and its causes, including items regarding scientific certainty about sea-level rise and increases in global precipitation, whether fossil fuels increase atmospheric concentration of GHGs, and whether N
  <sub>2</sub>O is a GHG.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Findings on the relationships between these varied dimensions of belief and support for action have been mixed. 
  <a rid="bibr17-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr17-0013916513503832">Dietz et al. (2007)</a> found no relationship between exposure to sources of information or self-rated knowledge about climate change and support for climate change policy. 
  <a rid="bibr57-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr57-0013916513503832">O’Connor et al. (1999)</a> found belief that global average temperature would rise over the next 50 years and knowledge of the causes of “global warming” to be positive predictors of policy support. On the other hand, 
  <a rid="bibr58-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr58-0013916513503832">O’Connor et al. (2002)</a> found no associations between belief in temperature rise and policy support or expressed likelihood of engaging in voluntary GHG-reducing behaviors, but did find positive relationships between understanding of causes and both of those variables. 
  <a rid="bibr78-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr78-0013916513503832">Zahran et al. (2006)</a> found a correlation between climate change policy support and knowledge about GHGs. 
  <a rid="bibr12-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr12-0013916513503832">Brody et al. (2012)</a>, on the other hand, detected no relationship between their larger set of climate knowledge/causes scale and willingness to adopt climate change mitigation behavior. Such studies have provided valuable insight into the role that different dimensions of climate change beliefs may play in shaping responses to climate change. However, variability in the measures used has made synthetic interpretation of results difficult.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Given that erroneous public understanding of climate change has been proposed as an important roadblock to public action (
  <a rid="bibr75-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr75-0013916513503832">Weber &amp; Stern, 2011</a>), it may be that inconsistencies in the measurement of public understanding of climate change is a barrier to better understanding of the relationships between beliefs and behavior/policy support. While use of straightforward measures of beliefs about climate change and its causes are common in public polling on the issue (e.g., 
  <a rid="bibr44-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr44-0013916513503832">Leiserowitz, Maibach, &amp; Roser-Renouf, 2011</a>) or used as dependent variables (e.g., 
  <a rid="bibr50-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr50-0013916513503832">McCright &amp; Dunlap, 2011a</a>), they are rarely used as predictors of policy support or behavior. Thus, most attempts to improve our understanding of the links between beliefs about climate change and behavioral and policy responses have used indirect rather than direct measures of belief and attribution. In other words, measures such as knowledge that N
  <sub>2</sub>O is a GHG may not be robust proxies for overall beliefs about whether climate change is occurring and what its causes are. As noted above, direct measures of belief and attribution have been used in surveys: It is known that some people strongly believe that climate change is occurring and attribute it to human activity, others do not believe that it is happening, and still others are uncertain (e.g., 
  <a rid="bibr46-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr46-0013916513503832">Maibach et al., 2009</a>). Such direct measures of climate change belief are not, however, commonly employed as predictors in multivariate modeling of behavior, support for policy, or other social action.
 </p>
</sec>
