<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="section19-0013916513503832" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mitigation Approaches</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The findings on mitigation, however, point to a much different dynamic and signal that support for mitigation and adaptation are activated in distinct ways. Whereas support for adaptation seems to be related to the interplay between beliefs and perceived risks to agriculture, support for mitigation appears to be conditionally independent of perceived risks, and is associated primarily with belief that climate change is occurring (and due to human activity). Moreover, only one third of the farmers endorsed the item measuring support for government action on GHGs, and they were almost exclusively those who indicated that climate change is occurring and due to human activity. Consistent with our expectations and norm activation theory (
  <a rid="bibr62-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr62-0013916513503832">Roser-Renouf &amp; Nisbet, 2008</a>; 
  <a rid="bibr66-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr66-0013916513503832">Stern, Dietz, Abel, Guagnano, &amp; Kalof, 1999</a>; 
  <a rid="bibr75-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr75-0013916513503832">Weber &amp; Stern, 2011</a>), it appears that only those farmers who assign blame to humans see value in societal efforts to reduce GHGs.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another important finding was the lack of a statistically significant relationship between perceived risks to agriculture (e.g., “potential impacts on my farm operation”) and support for mitigation. Given that the mitigation variable measured support for government action in a general sense (not specific to agriculture), and that the perceived risk items were specific to agriculture, this result is perhaps not surprising. Whereas adaptive action such as investment in protective conservation practices can have immediate positive impacts at the individual farm level, perhaps neutralizing climate risk, the climate-related impacts of government action on GHGs are diffuse and long-term. Future research might use measures of perceptions of more global, collective risks in addition to local, individual risks to further test variations in scale associated with mitigation.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our findings suggest that for a majority of farmers, outreach that focuses on mitigation will not likely resonate. Most Iowa farmers do not believe that human actions are responsible for climate change. Furthermore, farmer concerns about potential (local) risks to agriculture were not associated with endorsement of government action on GHGs.</p>
</sec>
