<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="section8-0013916513503832" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study Context and Data Collection</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The study focuses on farmers in the state of Iowa, the top U.S. producer of corn and soybean (
  <a rid="bibr71-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr71-0013916513503832">U.S. Department of Agriculture National Agricultural Statistics Service [USDA NASS], 2012</a>). Climate change-related shifts in long-term weather patterns predicted for the state include warmer winters, longer growing seasons, higher dew point temperatures, higher annual stream flow, and more frequent extreme weather events (
  <a rid="bibr34-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr34-0013916513503832">Iowa Climate Change Impacts Committee [ICCIC], 2011</a>). While changes such as a longer growing season may be favorable to Iowa agriculture, others could lead to negative impacts such as increased soil erosion, delays in planting or crop damage, higher incidence of pests and disease, and heat-induced pollination problems (
  <a rid="bibr31-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr31-0013916513503832">Hatfield et al., 2011</a>; 
  <a rid="bibr61-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr61-0013916513503832">Rogovska &amp; Cruse, 2011</a>). Iowa has experienced many of these in recent years (
  <a rid="bibr34-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr34-0013916513503832">ICCIC, 2011</a>), and thus represents a suitable context for research on farmer attitudes toward adaptation to such impacts.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Agriculture also emits a disproportionately high percentage of Iowa’s overall GHGs relative to other states. Whereas agriculture directly generates about 7% of US GHGs through activities such as enteric fermentation in ruminant livestock, manure management, and use of nitrogen fertilizers (
  <a rid="bibr72-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr72-0013916513503832">USEPA, 2013</a>, p. 6-1), in 2011, direct emissions of GHGs from agriculture comprised 26% of Iowa’s overall GHG emissions (
  <a rid="bibr36-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr36-0013916513503832">Iowa Department of Natural Resources [IDNR], 2012</a>, p. 3). Fifty-nine percent of agricultural GHGs stemmed from soil management for grain production and the balance from livestock production and waste (
  <a rid="bibr36-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr36-0013916513503832">IDNR, 2012</a>, p. 5). These activities primarily generate the potent GHGs CH
  <sub>4</sub> and N
  <sub>2</sub>O, which have “global warming potentials” 21 and 310 times that of CO
  <sub>2</sub>, respectively (
  <a rid="bibr25-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr25-0013916513503832">Forster et al., 2007</a>, p. 212). Thus, Iowa also provides an appropriate context for examining farmer attitudes toward mitigation action.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The data for this research were collected through the 2011 Iowa Farm and Rural Life Poll (IFRLP), an annual statewide survey of Iowa farmers conducted by Iowa State University Sociology Extension. Iowa Agricultural Statistics administers the survey following a survey–postcard–survey mailing protocol. The 2011 survey was mailed to 2,030 farmers in February 2011. Useable surveys were received from 1,276 farmers, for a response rate of 63%.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A note regarding the sample is warranted. The original survey panel was a random sample drawn from the Census of Agriculture master list, and the survey panel is periodically refreshed with random samples from this list to address attrition due to retirement and other factors. Because the IFRLP focuses so heavily on agricultural activities, many smaller-scale “farmers” who are sampled because they could potentially produce US$1,000 in sales (the USDA definition of farm), but do not actually farm, choose not to participate because the surveys do not apply to them. A comparison of 2011 IFRLP and 2007 Census of Agriculture statistics shows that this process has led to an IFRLP sample bias toward larger scale farmers. IFRLP farmers operated an average of 402 ac in 2011, compared with 331 ac among the 2007 census population. A comparison of farm sales finds that 15.2% of IFRLP farmers had 2011 gross farm sales of less than $10,000, compared with 38.6% of the 2007 Census population. At the other end of the sales spectrum, 48.2% of IFRLP farmers had 2011 sales greater than $100,000, compared with 35.6% for the 2007 census population (
  <a rid="bibr70-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr70-0013916513503832">USDA NASS, 2009</a>). While this bias toward larger scale farmers might be seen as a liability for some research efforts, for this study it is considered an asset because larger scale farms operate a disproportionate amount of acreage. For example, whereas only 39% of Iowa farms generate $100,000 or more in gross sales, they operate 83% of farmland acreage (
  <a rid="bibr70-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr70-0013916513503832">USDA NASS, 2009</a>). Thus, our findings regarding attitudes toward adaptation and mitigation activities are biased toward farmers who generate a larger proportion of Iowa’s agricultural production and farm operations that are reflective of mainstream, conventional agricultural systems in the Upper Midwest.
 </p>
</sec>
