<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="section4-0013916513503832" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Trust in Institutional Actors</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In an increasingly globalizing and specializing society, we are ever more dependent on what 
  <a rid="bibr28-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr28-0013916513503832">Giddens (1990)</a> termed 
  <span class="italic">abstract</span> or 
  <span class="italic">expert</span> systems. This is especially true for potentially globalized phenomena such as nuclear war or ecological catastrophe that people cannot “opt out of” (
  <a rid="bibr28-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr28-0013916513503832">Giddens, 1990</a>, p. 84). Such large-scale phenomena necessarily place the responsibility for management of associated risks on large, complex institutional contexts (
  <a rid="bibr26-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr26-0013916513503832">Freudenburg, 1993</a>). As society has become progressively more reliant on expert systems to manage risk, trust in the capacity of those systems and their component agencies and organizations to fulfill their mandate has come to have a significant influence on perceptions of large-scale risk (
  <a rid="bibr26-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr26-0013916513503832">Freudenburg, 1993</a>; 
  <a rid="bibr38-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr38-0013916513503832">Kahan et al., 2011</a>). While “the central tendency is to see most such technological systems as having worked properly, the vast majority of the time” (
  <a rid="bibr5-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr5-0013916513503832">Alario &amp; Freudenburg, 2003</a>, p. 199), periodic failures that cause harm can also lead to questioning of the ability “of institutional actors to carry out their responsibilities with the degree of vigor necessary to merit the societal trust they enjoy” (
  <a rid="bibr5-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr5-0013916513503832">Alario &amp; Freudenburg, 2003</a>, p. 200). Thus, perceptions of the seriousness of risks depend in large part on the degree to which we trust actors in expert systems to manage them appropriately (
  <a rid="bibr26-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr26-0013916513503832">Freudenburg, 1993</a>; 
  <a rid="bibr38-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr38-0013916513503832">Kahan et al., 2011</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As 
  <a rid="bibr17-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr17-0013916513503832">Dietz et al. (2007)</a> noted, people who make decisions under conditions of uncertainty and imperfect knowledge tend to look to trusted institutions for guidance, and level of trust correlates with public acceptance of policy response. However, social actors who profit from the 
  <span class="italic">status quo</span> can seek to influence discourse and the shaping of knowledge (
  <a rid="bibr19-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr19-0013916513503832">Dietz, Frey, &amp; Rosa, 2002</a>). The issue of climate change, in particular, has been highly contested, especially in the United States, with varied actors seeking to frame the issue and potential responses in ways that favor their interests (
  <a rid="bibr75-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr75-0013916513503832">Weber &amp; Stern, 2011</a>). While institutions such as the U.S. Environmental Protection Agency (USEPA), the IPCC, and the U.S. National Climate Assessment (NCA) have worked to inform society about the risks of and potential responses to climate change, some interest groups have mounted substantial counter-efforts to “manufacture uncertainty” regarding the phenomenon and shape discourse about how society should or should not respond (
  <a rid="bibr22-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr22-0013916513503832">Dunlap &amp; McCright, 2010</a>). Predominant strategies include “denial of global warming, the denial of its anthropogenic sources and the denial of its seriousness” (
  <a rid="bibr22-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr22-0013916513503832">Dunlap &amp; McCright, 2010</a>, p. 240). Such mediation of information by interest groups has muddled public understanding of climate change and retarded public action (
  <a rid="bibr75-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr75-0013916513503832">Weber &amp; Stern, 2011</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The recognition that public understanding of climate change is mediated by intermediary sources has led to the use of variables measuring trust in such entities as predictors of policy support. 
  <a rid="bibr78-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr78-0013916513503832">Zahran et al. (2006)</a> found that confidence in the competence of the EPA, the National Oceanographic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA), and the IPCC to “solve the problem of climate change” predicted support for climate change policy. 
  <a rid="bibr17-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr17-0013916513503832">Dietz et al. (2007)</a> found that generalized trust in government agencies and scientists working for the government was a positive predictor of climate policy support, while trust in industry (oil companies, coal companies, and scientists working for industry) was negatively associated. 
  <a rid="bibr57-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" href="#bibr57-0013916513503832">O’Connor et al. (1999)</a> found the degree to which survey respondents believed that government is a “helpful” institution predicted higher levels of willingness to endorse climate change mitigation policy. Thus, research suggests that trust in entities that are working to address climate change is associated with support for climate change policy, while trust in actors that have historically opposed action on climate change (i.e., industry) is associated with negative attitudes toward such action.
 </p>
</sec>
