<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec002" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec id="sec003" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study sites</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our study area is located in Cambridgeshire in eastern England (52° 22’N, 0° 13’W) [
   <a rid="pone.0155241.ref018" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155241.ref018">18</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0155241.ref019" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155241.ref019">19</a>]. Breeding parameters were recorded for pairs of great tits and blue tits (
   <span class="italic">Cyanistes caeruleus</span>) using nest boxes in three study woods: Monks Wood (MW) National Nature Reserve 157 ha: 1993–2000, 22 boxes; 2001–2015, 35 boxes; Brampton Wood (BW), Wildlife Trust Nature Reserve, 132 ha: 1993–2015, 22 boxes; Wennington Wood (WW), privately owned, 72 ha: 1993–1999, 21 boxes; 2000–2015, 35 boxes). Most of the boxes are accessible (controlled by hole diameter: 32 mm both species, 25 mm blue tits only) to both species except in WW where 19 boxes are accessible to both and 16 (including all 14 erected after 2000) only to blue tits. Boxes are located in approximately one half of each of MW and BW and throughout WW giving densities of about 0.45, 0.33 and 0.49 boxes per ha respectively. This results in smaller numbers of study nests per wood than in some other long-term studies of tits [
   <a rid="pone.0155241.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155241.ref020">20</a>], but we adopted this policy to reduce the risk of unduly increasing tit population densities which can affect timing of breeding [
   <a rid="pone.0155241.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155241.ref021">21</a>] whilst also obtaining adequate sample sizes. However, from the mid 1990s BW has also contained c. 200 dormouse boxes which, until 2013 when they were redesigned, could be accessed by blue tits which probably increased the blue tit population in this wood. The main tree species are common ash (
   <span class="italic">Fraxinus excelsior</span>), English oak (
   <span class="italic">Quercus robur</span>) and field maple (
   <span class="italic">Acer campestre</span>) with an understory chiefly of hawthorn (
   <span class="italic">Crategus</span> spp.), hazel (
   <span class="italic">Corylus avellana</span>) and blackthorn (
   <span class="italic">Prunus spinosa</span>). BW also has some blocks of conifers but the boxes are located in deciduous areas.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec004" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Timing of breeding</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Timing of breeding was recorded for 23 years from 1993 to 2015 and was defined as the laying date (expressed as April 1
   <span class="sup">st</span> = 1) of the first egg of the clutch. Tits typically lay one egg per day, early in the morning, and begin incubation on the day the last egg is laid to achieve synchronous hatching (although in poor weather delayed incubation after clutch completion is common, 22). The average clutch size in woodland is 9 for great tits and 11 for blue tits [
   <a rid="pone.0155241.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155241.ref023">23</a>]. We inspected boxes approximately weekly during the laying period and calculated first egg dates by counting back from the number of eggs observed [
   <a rid="pone.0155241.ref024" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155241.ref024">24</a>]. We included only nests which were active at the time of observation (i.e. at least one more egg was laid) and only those of first breeding attempts. For each wood, we calculated an annual mean first egg date (NERC-Environmental Information Data Centre 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://doi.org/10.5285/2efa9bf4-e5c0-42f9-8fcb-90dca2bb9c66" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://doi.org/10.5285/2efa9bf4-e5c0-42f9-8fcb-90dca2bb9c66</span>) [
   <a rid="pone.0155241.ref025" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155241.ref025">25</a>]. For great tits, the mean (± SD) and range of the numbers of nests included in the calculation of the annual mean first egg date for each wood were: MW, 18 ± 5.0, range = 12–28; BW, 15 ± 2.8, range = 11–20; WW, 10 ± 2.1, range = 6–14. The numbers of blue tits using the boxes were smaller (MW, 8 ± 3.3, range = 3–13; BW, 3 ± 1.3, range = 2–6; WW, 9 ± 3.0, range = 5–15) because, as the larger of the two species at c. 19 g versus 10 g for blue tits, great tits are usually dominant. The results for blue tits were similar to those of great tits, but due to the small sample sizes per year we include here only those for great tits. All bird data were collected with the permission of the landowners (MW: Natural England; BW: The Wildlife Trust; WW: the Abbots Ripton Estate) by licenced (British Trust for Ornithology Ringing Scheme, permit nos. A4101 and C3288) persons experienced in the running and maintenance of nest boxes.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec005" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate data and statistical analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Values for the NAO WI for the 23-year study period from 1993 to 2015 were obtained from the Climate Analysis Section, National Centre for Atmospheric Research (NCAR), Boulder, USA, [
   <a rid="pone.0155241.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155241.ref009">9</a>] 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://climatedataguide.ucar.edu/climate-data/hurrell-north-atlantic-oscillation-nao-index-station-based" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://climatedataguide.ucar.edu/climate-data/hurrell-north-atlantic-oscillation-nao-index-station-based</span>. Relationships between the annual mean timing of breeding of great tits in each wood and the NAO WI were then examined for the study period using least squares linear regression (Minitab Release 15). We used the NAO WI for the immediately preceding winter and also for one and two year time-lags, i.e. year i, year i-1 and year i-2. To test the predictive power of the one year time-lagged relationship for each wood, we used a jackknife approach to derive a mean % error (± SE) for the prediction of mean first egg date, i.e. we omitted each year sequentially and used the remaining 22 years to predict the timing of the missing year.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Timing of breeding in tits is known to be earlier in warmer springs [
   <a rid="pone.0155241.ref026" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155241.ref026">26</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0155241.ref027" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155241.ref027">27</a>], thus we also examined the relationships between the birds’ timing and local spring warmth in our study area, and between local spring warmth and the NAO WI (for year i and year i-1) using least squares regression. For our measure of local spring warmth, we used the ‘warmth sum’ calculated as the sum of maximum daily temperature for 1
   <span class="sup">st</span> March to 25
   <span class="sup">th</span> April [
   <a rid="pone.0155241.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155241.ref028">28</a>]. This index was found to be the most useful of several indices tested by Perrins and McCleery [
   <a rid="pone.0155241.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155241.ref029">29</a>] in relation to great tit breeding parameters. Although the time period of 1
   <span class="sup">st</span> March to 25
   <span class="sup">th</span> April is fixed whilst the average onset of breeding can vary by as much as 3–4 weeks between years depending on weather conditions, using a fixed index provides an unbiased measure of local spring warmth in relation to the NAO WI. We also examined how the warmth sum and/or the timing of breeding were related to the annual change, calculated as current year index minus previous year index, in the NAO WI. We used this annual change as an attempt to link events back to the previous year because, although it was clear how the immediately preceding NAO WI might have an influence, it was not clear how such an influence might act across time in the event of a one-year time-lag (but see 
   <a ref-type="sec" rid="sec010" href="#sec010">discussion</a>). We also investigated if winter or early spring rainfall might influence timing of breeding. We used a general linear modelling approach with site as a random factor, and warmth sum, NAO WI, rainfall and year as covariates. Rainfall was entered separately as the total monthly rainfall for the months of December, January, February and March, and was also modelled as combined winter rainfall, i.e. the total for December to March combined. We could not use year as a factor because, to avoid pseudoreplication, our first egg dates are average values for each wood for each year. However, year can be used as a covariate and this is also appropriate in the context of global warming promoting earlier breeding [
   <a rid="pone.0155241.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155241.ref015">15</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0155241.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155241.ref016">16</a>]. Maximum daily temperatures, and total monthly rainfall, for the 23-year study period were obtained from a UK Met Office weather station located approximately 50 m from the south side of Monks Wood (and approximately 4 km from WW and 9 km from BW).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To investigate the link between the warmth sum and the NAO WI in the longer term, we used a 23-year sliding window, with annual stepping, and data going back to 1878 [
   <a rid="pone.0155241.ref008" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155241.ref008">8</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0155241.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155241.ref030">30</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0155241.ref031" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155241.ref031">31</a>] to generate 116 linear regressions of warmth sum on NAO WI (for year i and year i-1). Values for the NAO WI and maximum daily temperatures from 1878 were obtained respectively from the Climate Analysis Section, National Centre for Atmospheric Research (NCAR), Boulder, USA, [
   <a rid="pone.0155241.ref007" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155241.ref007">7</a>] and the Met Office Hadley Centre Central England Temperature (HadCET) dataset, where daily maxima are available from 1878 [
   <a rid="pone.0155241.ref031" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0155241.ref031">31</a>]. The warmth sum calculated from the Monks Wood meteorological station data is a little warmer than that calculated using the HadCET data (for the period 1993 to 2015, mean, ± SD: Monks Wood, 686.6 ± 79.3; HadCET, 644.2 ± 78.9; mean difference, 42.2 ± 15.4; paired t-test, t = 13.34, 
   <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.001), but the two data sets are highly correlated: r = 0.981, 
   <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.001. In addition to the regression analyses, all other statistical comparisons were also carried out in Minitab Release 15.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
