<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece33082-sec-0008" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2.4</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Environmental and social variables</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used the winter North Atlantic Oscillation (NAO; Hurrell &amp; Van Loon, 
  <a rid="ece33082-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33082-bib-0034">1997</a>) index as a proxy for winter severity. As described in Manning, Medill, and McLoughlin (
  <a rid="ece33082-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33082-bib-0039">2015</a>), this was calculated as the geometric mean of daily NAO values from 1 January to 31 March, and developed into a continuous index using a 
  <span class="italic">Z</span>‐score (standard normal random variable). The data were extracted from the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration's National Weather Service (available at: 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.cpc.ncep.noaa.gov/products</span>). On Sable Island, negative NAO index values generally reflect mild winter conditions characterized by high daily minimum and maximum temperatures, low number of days with frost, and low precipitation; while positive NAO index values reflect harsh winter conditions (see Appendix 
  <a rid="ece33082-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#ece33082-sup-0001">S3</a> for details). Because location on Sable Island is correlated with horse habitat quality (Contasti et al., 
  <a rid="ece33082-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33082-bib-0013">2012</a>; Rozen‐Rechels et al., 
  <a rid="ece33082-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33082-bib-0059">2015</a>), we also considered each individual's median longitude during summer census surveys as a measure of local environmental quality.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We considered band size and band sex ratio, as well as local (area) sex ratio and density as extrinsic social variables. Local density was calculated as the number of individuals (excluding foals) within 8,000 m of an individual's summer centroid location divided by the vegetated surface area (km
  <span class="sup">2</span>) within that buffer which is the area used by horses for foraging (number of horses per km
  <span class="sup">2</span> of vegetated area; see Marjamäki, Contasti, Coulson, &amp; McLoughlin, 
  <a rid="ece33082-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33082-bib-0040">2013</a> for more details). Local density was then calculated as a function of vegetated area (km
  <span class="sup">2</span>) preventing any bias induced by the presence of unequal surface of available area 
  <span class="italic">versus</span> sea water inside the individual buffers. Local density was higher in the west compared to the east, and was highly correlated with habitat quality, with the best quality habitat supporting the highest densities (van Beest et al., 
  <a rid="ece33082-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33082-bib-0003">2014</a>). We estimated band size as the mean number of individuals (excluding foals) present in an individual's band during the summer. We calculated local and band sex ratios as the number of males aged 3 years or more divided by the total number of individuals aged 3 or more within 8,000 m of an individual's summer centroid location (local sex ratio) or in the individual's band (band sex ratio), respectively (Manning et al., 
  <a rid="ece33082-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33082-bib-0039">2015</a>). Sex ratio therefore ranges from one when only males are present to zero when only females are present.
 </p>
</sec>
