<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec13" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusions</div>
 <p id="Par39" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The most pronounced atmospheric circulation changes over the twentieth and twenty-first century to date have occurred in the Southern Hemisphere. The southern stratospheric polar vortex has strengthened and the SAM has shifted towards its positive phase (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>), most strongly in austral summer, associated with a poleward migration of the westerly jet. These trends are largely attributable to human influence, specifically, emission of GHG and ozone-depleting substances. The surface expression of the effects of Antarctic ozone depletion and increased GHG has reinforced one another, mainly in austral summer, driving the SAM trend over recent decades. Stratospheric ozone depletion may also have played a role in the observed deepening of the ASL; however, separating human influence from that of natural variability is harder than for the SAM. In the Northern Hemisphere, changes in the stratospheric polar vortex and NAM are within the bounds of natural variability and cannot be attributed to human-induced climate change, despite speculation that these changes are caused by Arctic sea-ice loss.
 </p>
 <p id="Par40" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Future projections of the NAM and SAM reflect the balance of multiple and opposing climate drivers. CO
  <sub>2</sub> concentrations are projected to continue to rise, at least until 2050 under the most-ambitious mitigation scenarios [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>]. As noted earlier, there are signs that Antarctic ozone concentrations are beginning to rise; however, increasing emissions of short-lived anthropogenic chlorocarbons could slow this recovery [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR138" href="#CR138">138</a>]. Thus, over coming decades, ozone recovery and GHG increases will likely have opposing effects on the SAM in austral summer. For the NAM, the effects of GHG and Arctic sea ice loss appear to oppose each other, particularly in boreal winter. Thus, in both hemispheres, what happens to the annular modes will reflect the balance of competing influences. Whilst the influence of GHG on the SAM and NAM is relatively consistent across seasons, the influence of Arctic sea ice loss on the NAM is greatest in boreal winter and the influence of ozone recovery on the SAM is greatest in austral summer. Thus, NAM and SAM projections are more uncertain in boreal winter and austral summer, respectively (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). Outside of these seasons, the effect of GHG is dominant, leading to more robust projections of increasingly positive NAM and SAM.
 </p>
 <p id="Par41" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Past changes in Arctic cyclones vary considerably by season and by region and are sensitive to the data set, time period and methods used. Overall, there is some evidence for a change in the frequency or behaviour of Arctic storms. Furthermore, storms are occurring in a changing larger-scale environment. Moist intrusions associated with the passage of cyclones into the Arctic appear to be becoming more common, owing to increased humidity of the source air masses. Despite model uncertainty, future projections tend to support a reduction in the number of Arctic cyclones in boreal winter and more frequent storms in boreal summer, reflecting opposite trends in baroclinicity in these seasons. In the sub-Antarctic, an observed increase in cyclones south of 60°S is closely related to the positive SAM shift.</p>
 <p id="Par42" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We have highlighted some of the progress being made in understanding how climate change is manifested in polar atmospheric circulation. This will remain a key area of scientific enquiry, due to substantial remaining uncertainties and because of the critical role that atmospheric circulation plays in setting both the magnitude of global climate change—e.g. SAM affects Southern Ocean CO
  <sub>2</sub> sequestration [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR139" href="#CR139">139</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR140" href="#CR140">140</a>]—and the character of regional climate change [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
