<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Arctic</div>
 <sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Northern Annular Mode</div>
  <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Northern Annular Mode (NAM), also known as the Arctic Oscillation, is the dominant mode of inter-annual variability in the extratropical Northern Hemisphere [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>]. The positive phase of the NAM is associated with anomalously low pressure over the Arctic and high pressure over mid-latitudes, a pattern that strengthens the zonally averaged westerly winds. Also, the westerly winds are typically located further poleward during positive NAM. Since changes in the westerly winds, storm tracks and the eddy-driven jet stream are intimately connected, both to each other and to the NAM, we will consider these collectively here.
  </p>
  <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the past few years, there has been considerable progress in understanding the role of Arctic sea ice as a driver of variability in the NAM. Interest in links between sea ice and the NAM has been sparked by the repeated coincidence of anomalously negative NAM and reduced sea ice conditions and the dramatic decline in Arctic sea ice. Several studies have noted a strong negative correlation between sea ice and the NAM over recent decades [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>]. Given that attributing causality is an intractable problem with observations alone, many studies have reported on model experiments with perturbed sea ice to isolate the atmospheric circulation response to sea ice. These modelling studies support a causal link between projected sea ice loss and the negative NAM [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>••, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>•, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>••]. A recent comparison of the atmospheric circulation response to projected Arctic sea ice loss in six coupled climate model experiments found a weakening and equatorward shift of the midlatitude westerly wind belt in each case [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>], implying a common negative NAM response. However, the NAM response to observed sea ice loss over the past 30–40 years is less clear, being model dependent and often obscured by internal variability [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>]. More detailed reviews on the possible links between Arctic sea ice loss and the Northern Hemisphere atmospheric circulation can be found elsewhere [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>].
  </p>
  <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sea ice loss can force a change in the NAM via a tropospheric pathway or through interaction with the stratosphere [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>]. The tropospheric pathway is associated with the adjustment of transient eddies to the change in meridional temperature gradient and baroclinic instability. The stratospheric pathway involves enhanced upward planetary-scale wave propagation and the weakening of the stratospheric polar vortex [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>], which then modifies the NAM. Idealised atmospheric general circulation model experiments, using configurations with and without an interactive stratosphere, suggest that when the stratosphere is inactive, the tropospheric jet still shifts equatorward in response to Arctic warming, but by approximately half the magnitude compared to that of an active stratosphere [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>]. The stratospheric pathway appears sensitive to the location of sea ice loss whereas the tropospheric pathway appears less so [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>].
  </p>
  <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Arctic sea ice loss is only one component of greenhouse gas (GHG)-induced climate change. A paradigm that has gained traction in recent years is that the climate response to sea ice loss may partly counteract other aspects of the response to increased GHG. Since the dominant characteristic of projected GHG-induced climate change, in the absence of sea ice loss, is pronounced warming of the tropical upper troposphere, this has been conceptualised as a “tug-of-war” between the Arctic and tropics. Whilst Arctic sea ice loss is thought to promote the negative NAM, projected tropical upper tropospheric warming has the opposite effect, favouring the positive NAM [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>]. The winter atmospheric responses to Arctic sea ice loss and to GHG increases appear to be distinct, separable and, to good approximation, linearly additive [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>•]. The weak projected climate change response of the NAM (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>) may reflect the partial compensation between the distinct—and opposing—responses to Arctic sea ice loss and GHG increases [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>••, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>•, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>•]. This tug-of-war paradigm has been used to explain across-model spread in winter NAM projections [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>]. More specifically, models that simulate larger Arctic warming are also those that simulate larger equatorward shifts of the storm tracks [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>] and jet stream [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>].
   <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Indices of the Northern Annular Mode (left) and Southern Annular Mode (right) from observations and models. The black line shows, for each season (top to bottom), the CMIP5 multi-model mean of historical and RCP4.5 simulations. The grey band shows the 5–95% confidence range based on the individual model simulations. The coloured lines show observational indices derived from HadSLP2 (red), NOAA-CIRES Twentieth Century Reanalysis (orange) and Japanese 55-year Reanalysis (blue). Simulated anomalies are shown relative to the 1861–1900 baseline, and observations are centred on the multi-model mean over the period for which they are shown. The symbols to the right of each line graph show changes between 1980–2029 and 2050–2099, for each individual model (black circles) and the multi-model mean (red line). Adapted from Gillett and Fyfe (2013), where further details on these data and methods can be found [
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>]
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="40641_2018_111_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Northern Stratospheric Polar Vortex</div>
  <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The dominant circulation feature of the Arctic stratosphere in winter is a strong circumpolar westerly jet, referred to as the stratospheric polar vortex [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>]. Whilst the vortex is omnipresent in winter and centred around the pole, it exhibits large variability in strength and location on intra-seasonal to multi-decadal timescales. It is well known that this stratospheric variability has a significant influence on tropospheric circulation, and weather and climate at the Earth’s surface [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>]. Sudden stratospheric warming (SSW) events in particular, when the stratospheric polar vortex is abruptly weakened and disrupted, are often a precursor to the negative phase of the NAM and cold-air outbreaks. Several recent studies have reported a weakening of the polar vortex over the last three or four decades [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>]. Kretschmer et al. (2018) identified occurrences of weak and strong polar vortices using a hierarchical clustering approach [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>]. They found a significant increase in the frequency of the weak vortex events, from an average frequency of 3 days per winter in the period 1979–1996 to 7 days per winter in the period 1998–2015. In contrast, the occurrence of strong vortex events halved from 12 to 6 days over the same years. SSW events have also been notably more frequent in the more recent period [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>]. This weakening of the polar vortex has been cited as a cause of increased cold extremes and sustained boreal winter cooling over midlatitude Eurasia [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>]. An apparent shift of the polar vortex towards the Eurasian continent and away from North America may have also contributed to cooling over Eurasia [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>].
  </p>
  <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The causes of observed polar vortex weakening are not fully understood. One hypothesised cause is the loss of Arctic sea ice [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>]. Kim et al. (2014) conducted atmospheric model simulations with reduced sea ice in the Barents and Kara Seas and found an increase in vertical wave activity propagation into the stratosphere [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>]. Enhanced wave breaking in the stratosphere caused a deceleration of the stratospheric westerly winds and hence, weakened the polar vortex. Although a general weakening of the polar vortex has been noted in many model experiments with perturbed Arctic sea ice [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>], the attribution of the observed change to sea ice loss is complicated by at least three factors. The first is divergence between different models [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>]. Second, there is an apparent sensitivity to the geographical location of ice loss. In model experiments, sea ice loss in the Atlantic sector appears to cause a weaker vortex, whereas a stronger vortex is found in response to sea ice loss in the Pacific sector [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>].
  </p>
  <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The third complicating factor is internal variability. Two recent studies argue that the observed polar vortex weakening is a manifestation of internal variability and not a forced response to Arctic sea ice loss, or to climate change more broadly. Seviour (2017) examined large ensembles of coupled climate model simulations and concluded that the forced response of the vortex was small relative to internal variability, and that vortex trends of similar magnitude to those observed can be generated purely by internal climate variability [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>]. The latter conclusion was also reached by Garfinkel et al. (2017), who found no consistent change in the strength of the polar vortex in model simulations forced with observed GHG concentrations, sea surface temperatures and sea ice [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>]. However, unforced internal variability was sufficiently strong that some individual ensemble members reproduced the observed polar vortex weakening.
  </p>
  <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Future projections of the stratospheric polar vortex are highly uncertain. For example, under global warming scenarios, some modelling studies find an increased frequency of SSW events but others do not [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>]. A recent reassessment of projected changes in SSW events, based on 12 models participating in the Chemistry Climate Model Initiative, found no evidence of future changes in the frequency or duration of SSW events [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Moist Intrusions</div>
  <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An aspect of Arctic meteorology that has garnered considerable scientific interest in recent years is intrusions of warm and moist air. Intrusions occur predominantly over the ocean basins and typically when a large-scale blocking pattern to the east of each basin deflects midlatitude cyclones and their associated moisture into the Arctic [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>]. Inter-annual variability of intrusions is strongly related with Arctic surface temperature, through their effect on the downward longwave radiation [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>]. In extreme cases, the passage of strong cyclones into the Arctic and their associated moist intrusions can lead to above-freezing temperatures in the central Arctic in the midst of winter [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>]. In recent years, a run of such Arctic midwinter warming events has focussed attention of whether intrusions are becoming more common [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>]. Woods and Caballero (2016) found an increase in the frequency of moist intrusions, which can explain roughly 45% of the surface warming trend and 30% of the sea ice loss in the Barents Sea during the past two decades [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>]. Park et al. (2015) concluded that nearly half the sea ice decline in the Atlantic sector could be explained by increased downward longwave radiation, related to increased poleward transport of heat and moisture [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>].
  </p>
  <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Moisture transport into the Arctic is projected to increase in a warming climate, as humidity increases more rapidly at lower latitudes per Kelvin temperature rise, leading to a larger poleward moisture gradient. Skific and Francis (2013) diagnosed that 75–80% of the total projected annual change in moisture transport across 70°N, between the late 20th and 21st centuries, is thermodynamically driven, being due to change in the meridional gradient of specific humidity [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>]. Although smaller, the dynamic term was also positive and related to an increase in low-pressure systems over the central Arctic that transport substantial moisture into the Arctic.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Arctic Cyclones</div>
  <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A ubiquitous aspect of the polar and sub-polar regions of both hemispheres is the presence of many synoptic systems. These play a central role in transporting heat and moisture from the midlatitudes into the polar regions. In recent times, the analysis of cyclonic activity has attracted increased attention. Part of the reason for this is that reduced sea ice is allowing increased human activity in the Arctic, for example shipping, and for which storminess is an important consideration. An issue that arises in this context is that there is no clear objective definition of what comprises a cyclone or its intensity. The fact that there are numerous state-of-the-art automated cyclone identification algorithms available reflects the existence of this ambiguity. Detection algorithms based on different physical assumptions and approaches have been shown to produce broadly consistent findings but with some deviations [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>]. A related matter is that a cyclone investigation can be undertaken with a choice of reanalysis data set. The basic fields (e.g. mean sea level pressure) are, in the main, quite coherent across the sets, but they can show sizeable deviations in the vicinity of cyclones and fronts. Hence, when discussing diagnosed cyclone behaviour, it is important to appreciate what identification scheme was applied, and what reanalysis data set was used. These issues may be of particular relevance when undertaking cyclone analysis in the Arctic region. Simmonds and Rudeva (2014) found that 10 state-of-the-art cyclone identification schemes, applied to intense systems in the ERA-Interim reanalysis, were in substantial agreement as to the location of the centre of these storms, while showing considerable differences between the central pressures diagnosed by the algorithms of typically 5–10 hPa [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>].
  </p>
  <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Rudeva and Simmonds (2015) analysed cyclone behaviour in 34 years of data and found significant increases in winter cyclone frequency to the north of the Canadian Arctic Archipelago and to the north of Greenland [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>]. In summer, they revealed a quite different pattern of change, with negative trends north of the Beaufort Sea and positive trends centred over the Laptev Sea. Similar trend results were achieved by Zahn et al. (2018) who used a somewhat shorter period and four reanalyses [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">59</a>]. They identified increasing winter cyclone frequency over most of the central Arctic Ocean and towards the Pacific, and decreasing winter cyclone frequency in the Barents Sea and north of the Russian coast. These cyclone frequency changes are consistent with observed winter changes in the frequency and longevity of high-latitude blocking [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">60</a>]. The contrasting regional trends were broadly consistent across the four reanalyses. They showed, however, that the magnitudes of trends differed in strength between reanalyses. When summed over the entire Arctic basin, the number of Arctic cyclones exhibits no significant linear trend in any season [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">61</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" href="#CR62">62</a>]. Given the opposing regional trends mentioned above, this finding is perhaps not surprising.
  </p>
  <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Arctic cyclone characteristics are correlated with key large-scale atmospheric indices, such as El Niño Southern Oscillation (ENSO) and NAM; however, these associations vary with season and none alone sufficiently explains cyclone variability or trends [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">61</a>]. The role that decreasing Arctic ice may be playing in these cyclone trends is a matter of considerable debate. Interaction between variability in Arctic sea ice and cyclones are complex, and apparent ice-cyclone associations appear dependent on data set resolution, and the identification method used [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">63</a>•]. Open water areas in the Arctic have led to increased transfer of heat and moisture from the ocean to the atmosphere, warming and moistening the Arctic atmosphere and increasing the 
   <span class="italic">potential</span> for cyclogenesis [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" href="#CR64">64</a>]. However, the effect of atmospheric moisture increases on cyclone behaviour is unclear and appears sensitive to the spatial resolution of the reanalysis dataset and/or how well current models represent moist processes [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" href="#CR64">64</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" href="#CR69">69</a>]. What is becoming clearer is that investigations undertaken with higher resolution data sets reveal more cyclonic structures [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" href="#CR70">70</a>•, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71" href="#CR71">71</a>]. For example, Tilinina et al. (2014) conducted a cyclone investigation using the high-resolution Arctic System Reanalysis and identified a considerably higher number of cyclones over the Arctic [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" href="#CR70">70</a>•]. They found the set allowed for more accurate description of the life cycle of the most intense Arctic cyclones, compared to the global reanalyses. At higher resolution, cyclones had lower central pressures, faster deepening and stronger winds on average. Trends in such intense Arctic cyclones are attracting much interest, and there are suggestions that these features are becoming more frequent [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72" href="#CR72">72</a>]. The so-called Great Arctic Cyclone of August 2012 [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73" href="#CR73">73</a>] broke the then-record of the lowest central pressure of all Arctic August storms since 1979 and this record still stands.
  </p>
  <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Turning now to future projections of Arctic cyclones, Day et al. (2018) conducted experiments with the CESM1-CAM5 climate model under a high GHG emission scenario [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74" href="#CR74">74</a>••]. They compared Arctic cyclone properties during 2071–2080 with those revealed over 1990–2005 in their historical simulation and found the response to vary with season. In winter, they found a significant reduction in both the number and intensity of storms, and a strong decrease in the frequency with which strong cyclones occur. The cyclone decrease was particularly marked in a band from Greenland to the Norwegian Sea, consistent with observed increases in high-latitude blocking near Greenland [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75" href="#CR75">75</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76" href="#CR76">76</a>]. By contrast they identified an increase in cyclone activity in the summer season and a rise in the frequency of strong storms. Their analysis allowed them to posit that this strong seasonality was associated with changes in the high-latitude meridional temperature gradient. In winter, this gradient is weakened as a result of amplified Arctic warming, while it is strengthened in summer because of the enhanced warming of high latitude continents compared to the Arctic Ocean.
  </p>
  <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A similar analysis, but using a different cyclone identification scheme, was conducted by Crawford and Serreze (2017) but they focussed on the summer season and on changes in the Arctic frontal zone [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77" href="#CR77">77</a>]. This zone is a tight band of strong horizontal temperature gradients and hence, baroclinicity, which develops along the Arctic Ocean coastline. They found that the strengthening of the frontal zone in June is accompanied by increases in cyclone activity along some parts of this zone, but little change in cyclone numbers over the Arctic basin.
  </p>
  <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The complex role of baroclinicity has been further explored by Tamarin-Brodsky and Kaspi (2017) in connection with the poleward shift, from 1980–1999 to 2080–2099, of storm tracks in climate models forced by increased GHG emissions from the Coupled Model Intercomparison Project phase 5 (CMIP5) [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78" href="#CR78">78</a>••]. They demonstrated that cyclones are not only formed more poleward in a warmer climate, but they also propagate more poleward until they reach their peak intensity. However, within the Arctic basin, they show that the CMIP5 models exhibit a winter decrease in cyclone numbers.
  </p>
  <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Regional climate models have also been used to investigate possible future change in Arctic cyclone characteristics. Cyclone changes from 1980–1999 to 2080–2099 were modelled by Akperov et al. (2015) using the HIRHAM model under a midrange GHG emission scenario [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79" href="#CR79">79</a>]. They found greater Arctic cyclone numbers in the warm season and fewer in the cool season, though neither of these changes was statistically significant. However, they detected clear changes in intensity and size of cyclones for both seasons.
  </p>
  <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In summary, observed and projected changes in the Arctic atmospheric circulation are of fairly modest magnitude compared to naturally occurring climate variability. We now turn our attention to the Southern Hemisphere, where the combined effects of GHG increases and stratospheric ozone depletion have led to clearer circulation changes over recent decades.</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
