<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Antarctic</div>
 <sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Southern Annular Mode</div>
  <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In recent decades, significant and robust large-scale changes have been observed in atmospheric circulation over Antarctica and the Southern Ocean [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80" href="#CR80">80</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85" href="#CR85">85</a>]. These changes are of major importance in terms of impacts on the broader coupled atmosphere-ocean-ice system across Antarctica and the Southern Ocean [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83" href="#CR83">83</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86" href="#CR86">86</a>]. The dominant pattern of lower- and mid-tropospheric circulation variability at high southern latitudes is the Southern Annular Mode (SAM) or Antarctic Oscillation. A more positive phase of SAM is associated with anomalously low atmospheric pressure over Antarctica and higher pressure at lower latitudes [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81" href="#CR81">81</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87" href="#CR87">87</a>]. In recent years, more direct diagnostics of the circumpolar mid-latitude southern near-surface westerlies (hereinafter the westerly jet) have become an important part of quantifying and understanding SAM-related changes in hemispheric-scale circulation [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88" href="#CR88">88</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90" href="#CR90">90</a>]. Strengthening and/or poleward shifting of the westerly jet are associated with a more positive SAM index and vice versa.
  </p>
  <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The depletion of stratospheric ozone and resulting strengthening of the polar vortex in the late twentieth century caused a major shift in Southern Hemisphere tropospheric climate, inducing a more positive SAM index mainly in the summer season (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>) [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80" href="#CR80">80</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81" href="#CR81">81</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84" href="#CR84">84</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85" href="#CR85">85</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91" href="#CR91">91</a>]. The causal chain for this starts with the fact that ozone absorbs solar radiation, and therefore in sunlit seasons, the depletion of stratospheric ozone induces local radiative cooling of the polar stratospheres [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92" href="#CR92">92</a>]. In response to cooling, the stratospheric polar vortex strengthens as changes in the vertical shear of zonal wind adjust to maintain thermal wind balance. Antarctic stratospheric ozone depletion is most pronounced in late winter/early spring since the chemical reactions responsible are linked to polar stratospheric clouds that form in the very cold conditions of the polar night [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93" href="#CR93">93</a>]. Consequently, there is a strong seasonality in polar ozone-related stratospheric cooling trends, which are most pronounced in early spring. In observations, the resulting stratospheric circulation anomalies propagate downwards gradually during spring to exhibit the strongest impact in summer [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80" href="#CR80">80</a>]. Identifying the precise mechanisms for this downward propagation is still a topic of debate [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83" href="#CR83">83</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94" href="#CR94">94</a>]. Despite uncertainty over the mechanisms, there is strong consensus that stratospheric ozone depletion has had an impact on tropospheric circulation based on evidence from both observations and modelling, and both in terms of the detection of the shift and its attribution to ozone depletion [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95" href="#CR95">95</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96" href="#CR96">96</a>]. This consensus has been increased in recent years due to the more widespread use of atmospheric models that extend high enough to include most of the stratosphere (so-called high top models), which more consistently reproduce the stratospheric impacts and downward propagation of circulation anomalies associated with stratospheric ozone depletion [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97" href="#CR97">97</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98" href="#CR98">98</a>]. However, the precise mechanisms for the transfer of signals from the stratosphere to the surface are still a subject of debate [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94" href="#CR94">94</a>]. Accurate modelling and improved understanding of mechanisms are important for accurately simulating the relative contribution from other factors that can influence the SAM. In particular, increasing GHG have likely re-enforced the recent ozone-induced SAM increases [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99" href="#CR99">99</a>]. The proportion of this contribution is, however, difficult to establish since multi-decadal climate variability has also been implicated as an important contributor to decadal time-scale SAM index trends [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100" href="#CR100">100</a>]. For example, a key role for decadal cooling of the western tropical Pacific has been identified as contributing to observed positive austral summer and autumn SAM index trends that have occurred since the end of rapid ozone depletion in the late 1990s [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101" href="#CR101">101</a>].
  </p>
  <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Observed changes in the SAM cannot be mapped simply onto changes in westerly jet strength, since changes in jet latitude and width also contribute to recent SAM trends [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90" href="#CR90">90</a>]. This is consistent with recent idealised model studies showing that shifting and strengthening of the westerly jet respond differently to different drivers and across different seasons [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR102" href="#CR102">102</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103" href="#CR103">103</a>••]. For example, a key aspect of behaviour that emerges from such atmospheric model experiments is that tropospheric heating on either side of the westerly jet acts to induce a change in jet strength, but heating collocated with the jet itself acts to shift the meridional temperature gradient maximum and the associated jet [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103" href="#CR103">103</a>••]. Ocean coupling does not appear necessary for simulating the jet shift. However, the patterns of warming and cooling under climate change are complex and include coupled ocean-atmosphere-ice feedbacks, the details of which are the subject of on-going research.
  </p>
  <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Looking to the future, further change is likely across a range of emission scenarios, but the character and even sign of these changes depends on a delicate balance between the relative contributions from a range of drivers. The CMIP5 models include either prescribed or simulated stratospheric ozone recovery over the twenty-first century to near pre-ozone-hole levels by 2100. Therefore, climate models exhibit a cancellation between SAM index decreases associated with stratospheric ozone recovery and SAM index increases associated with increased GHG and global warming. The most up-to-date studies indicate an approximate cancellation of effects for medium emission scenarios, mainly in summer (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>), but for high emission scenarios, a dominance of GHG driving overall SAM increases across all seasons by the year 2100 [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89" href="#CR89">89</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99" href="#CR99">99</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR104" href="#CR104">104</a>]. However, for a given scenario, the CMIP5 models still produce a wide range in projected changes [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88" href="#CR88">88</a>]. Diversity across different climate models in simulations of future changes in the SAM has been linked to a range of different processes including: uncertainties in the representation of shortwave radiative forcing (associated with clouds) [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR105" href="#CR105">105</a>]; the representation of eddy feedbacks [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR106" href="#CR106">106</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR107" href="#CR107">107</a>]; and uncertainties associated with the response of the coupled ocean-atmosphere-ice system across different timescales [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR108" href="#CR108">108</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR111" href="#CR111">111</a>]. In terms of the coupled system, recent research has shown that the jet strength component of projected westerly change is highly correlated with biases in Antarctic sea ice across the CMIP5 models [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR112" href="#CR112">112</a>]. Models with excessive sea ice in their baseline climate simulate more retreat in the future and more polar amplification. This stronger polar amplification weakens the lower-tropospheric temperature gradient across the storm track and acts to cancel out some of the strengthening of the westerlies that occurs due to other processes (in particular, increasing upper-tropospheric temperature gradients). This indicates a potential avenue for constraining future projections of the westerlies based on observed baseline climate, although improved understanding of the mechanisms involved is required.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Southern Stratospheric Polar Vortex</div>
  <p id="Par28" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although the southern polar vortex is situated at high altitudes in the stratosphere, the dramatic changes that have occurred in it over recent decades have been important for many of the surface climate changes observed over Antarctica and the Southern Ocean [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83" href="#CR83">83</a>]. There is a very pronounced annual cycle in the polar vortex, which is strongest in winter. The very low temperatures associated with the strong winter vortex provide conditions conducive to stratospheric ozone depletion by ozone depleting substances, as solar radiation returns to polar latitudes in early spring. Since ozone absorbs solar radiation, anomalously strong ozone depletion in spring leads to anomalously cold conditions in the mid-to-lower polar stratosphere. The formation of the ozone hole during rapid depletion between the 1970s and late 1990s is estimated to have produced a spring cooling of approximately 6 K and an associated strengthening of the polar vortex of 5–6 m s
   <span class="sup">−1</span> [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80" href="#CR80">80</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88" href="#CR88">88</a>].
  </p>
  <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Since approximately the year 2000, Antarctic stratospheric ozone depletion appears to have ended, with signs of possible recovery [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR113" href="#CR113">113</a>•]. Projections to the end of the twenty-first century generally indicate recovery approaching pre ozone-hole levels, but that lower-stratospheric cooling associated with greenhouse-gas induced global warming prevents full recovery due to lower temperatures in winter acting to increase the occurrence of polar stratospheric clouds, which enhances depletion of stratospheric ozone during the return of sunlight in spring [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR114" href="#CR114">114</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR115" href="#CR115">115</a>]. In isolation, the near-recovery of stratospheric ozone concentrations would result in a near reversal of the recent changes in the polar vortex in spring. The precise rate and eventual extent of ozone recovery and related reversal in polar vortex changes differ across different climate models with implications for projections of twenty-first century surface climate change. In particular, there is significant model uncertainty over the extent to which stratospheric ozone recovery may act to cancel out projected future greenhouse gas-induced poleward jet shifts [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR116" href="#CR116">116</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Amundsen Sea Low</div>
  <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Amundsen Sea Low (ASL) is a climatological low-pressure centre, which migrates seasonally west towards the Ross Sea in winter and east towards the Bellingshausen Sea in summer [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR117" href="#CR117">117</a>]. It is a key influence on variability of Antarctic-wide zonal wave numbers 1 and 3 since it forms one of the troughs of climatological wave-3 and also occurs in the vicinity of the ridge of wave-1 [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR118" href="#CR118">118</a>]. Regionally, changes in the depth and location of the ASL have a major impact on the climate of West Antarctica [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR119" href="#CR119">119</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR120" href="#CR120">120</a>] and it is therefore important in the broader context of understanding observed trends in regional sea ice and West Antarctic ice sheet mass balance [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR121" href="#CR121">121</a>].
  </p>
  <p id="Par31" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Analyses of past variability indicate that the ASL has deepened in recent decades in association with the increasingly positive polarity of the SAM. However, the drivers of change in the ASL are particularly complex to understand since it is situated in the region of largest atmospheric pressure variability in the Southern Hemisphere [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR122" href="#CR122">122</a>]. Consistent with this, observations and model results show that a significant part of changes in the post-1979 modern satellite era can be linked to tropical variability. Most notably, El Niño and La Niña are associated with weakening and intensification of the ASL, respectively, in association with a Rossby wave train from the central Pacific that is most prominent in winter. This Rossby wave train is a key explanation for the occurrence of the Pacific South American Pattern (PSA), which is a winter-dominated pattern of troughs and ridges that connects ENSO variability in the tropical Pacific with West Antarctica and the Antarctic Peninsula [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR123" href="#CR123">123</a>] and in particular, the depth of the ASL [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR117" href="#CR117">117</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR119" href="#CR119">119</a>]. However, more recently, the importance of the Pacific Decadal Oscillation (PDO) in spring has been highlighted in association with a wave train propagating from further west in the tropical Pacific that is consistent with a deepening of the ASL linked to the recent trend towards a negative polarity of the PDO [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR124" href="#CR124">124</a>]. The importance of tropical variability relative to external drivers such as GHG in explaining recent trends was highlighted by Schneider and Deser (2017), who found that historically forced climate model simulations only reproduced observed ASL deepening when tropical sea surface temperature variability was constrained to observed variability [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR125" href="#CR125">125</a>••]. Some climate models do, however, exhibit significant deepening of the ASL in response to stratospheric ozone depletion alone [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR126" href="#CR126">126</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR127" href="#CR127">127</a>], so it is possible that both tropical drivers and stratospheric ozone have contributed significantly.
  </p>
  <p id="Par32" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Looking at future climate change projections, Hosking et al. (2016) found that out of a subset of 11 CMIP5 models, selected based on skill at representing the ASL, the majority simulate a poleward migration of the ASL over the twenty-first century austral summer and autumn [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR128" href="#CR128">128</a>•]. Although less consistent, around half of the selected models also exhibit eastward shifts in autumn and winter. These changes are less consistent than the hemispheric-scale strengthening and poleward shift of the westerly jet that are simulated across the CMIP5 ensemble under the same future scenario, thus illustrating the greater uncertainty in projections of smaller-scale regional circulation change around Antarctica.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec11" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sub-Antarctic Cyclones</div>
  <p id="Par33" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The geography of the southern polar region differs significantly from its northern counterpart. This means that, distinct from those in the Northern Hemisphere, in the Southern Hemisphere the storm tracks and regions of heightened baroclinicity lie over, or very close to, the sea ice pack [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR129" href="#CR129">129</a>]. In addition, the circulation is much more zonally symmetric in the high southern latitudes. These and other factors mean that sea ice and large-scale atmospheric drivers might influence the behaviour of storms in different ways from those in the Northern Hemisphere. Cyclone activity is well correlated with the SAM, with more cyclones south of 60°S and fewer north of this latitude during the positive SAM phase [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR130" href="#CR130">130</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR131" href="#CR131">131</a>].
  </p>
  <p id="Par34" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Grieger et al. (2018) undertook a comprehensive analysis of sub-Antarctic cyclones making use of 14 state-of-the-art tracking methods applied to the ERA-Interim reanalysis [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR132" href="#CR132">132</a>]. Robust positive trends in cyclone numbers were identified by almost all methods for austral summer over the hemispheric region south of 60°S, mainly due to the strong relation to SAM, and in the Amundsen-Bellingshausen Seas sector. Fewer methods indicated significant positive trends over the East Antarctica and Weddell sectors. Trends in austral winter were positive for most regions and methods, but only statistically significant using some tracking methods.
  </p>
  <p id="Par35" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Antarctic region presents an environment somewhat different to that of the Arctic for cyclone properties simulated by models for the twenty-first century. Consistent with the Northern Hemisphere, Tamarin-Brodsky and Kaspi (2017) highlighted a summer poleward shift by 4.9° latitude of maximum zonally averaged cyclone track density and a notable increase in track density in the sub-Antarctic between 55 and 65°S [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78" href="#CR78">78</a>••]. Very marked in their results is a strong poleward expansion of the cyclogenesis region, with genesis increasing markedly in the 60–70°S band in response to the simulated shift in baroclinicity. With significant changes predicted in baroclinicity and total column water vapour [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR133" href="#CR133">133</a>] in the southern polar region, one would expect changes in the frequency of extreme cyclones. Indeed, the CMIP5 models depict significant increases in extreme cyclones (defined in numerous ways) around most of the periphery of the Antarctic continent [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR134" href="#CR134">134</a>].
  </p>
  <p id="Par36" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An indirect measure of the changes in sub-Antarctic cyclone behaviour can be obtained by examining phenomena that are directly influenced by these synoptic systems. Most of the Antarctic precipitation falls on the peripheral areas of the ice sheet, and this component of the precipitation is mainly influenced by sub-Antarctic cyclones and fronts. Palerme et al. (2017) investigated the changes, between 1986–2005 and 2080–2099, in annual Antarctic precipitation simulated by the CMIP5 models [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR135" href="#CR135">135</a>]. They found model-average increases ranging from 5.5 to 24.5% for low to high emission scenarios, implying greater cyclonic activity and/or more precipitation per cyclone due to increased moisture availability.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec12" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Comparing the Arctic and Antarctic</div>
  <p id="Par37" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is informative to briefly compare and contrast the two polar regions. Despite differing geography, the atmospheric circulations of the northern and southern hemispheres share a number of common features, including stratospheric polar vortices, tropospheric westerly jets and associated storm-tracks. There is broad hemispheric symmetry in how the polar circulation responds to well-mixed GHG. In both regions, increased GHG acts to shift poleward the westerly jets and storm-tracks, leading to more positive NAM and SAM indices.</p>
  <p id="Par38" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A major source of hemispheric asymmetry is the role of stratospheric ozone depletion, which is much larger in the Antarctic. In recent decades, the reinforcing effects of increasing GHG and ozone depletion have led to a robust Southern Hemisphere circulation changes, especially in austral summer. Anticipated ozone recovery may also exert a strong influence, but in the opposite sense, partly or fully offsetting changes to the increasing GHG. Another key difference over recent decades has been the contrasting changes in sea ice. Whilst Arctic sea ice has declined rapidly, there has been a small overall increase in Antarctic sea ice [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR136" href="#CR136">136</a>]. Related to this, the Arctic has warmed at a much faster rate than the global average—a phenomenon known as Arctic amplification. Arctic amplification is understood to be important influence on winter circulation change in the Northern Hemisphere [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>]. In contrast, the Southern Ocean has warmed slower than the global average. Although models suggest that Antarctic amplification will occur over the coming centuries, due to slow adjustment of the ocean circulation, its emergence is delayed relative to the Northern Hemisphere [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR137" href="#CR137">137</a>]. Accordingly, sea ice loss and polar amplification appear to be more important in modulating near-term circulation change in the Arctic than in the Antarctic.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
