<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Moist Intrusions</div>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An aspect of Arctic meteorology that has garnered considerable scientific interest in recent years is intrusions of warm and moist air. Intrusions occur predominantly over the ocean basins and typically when a large-scale blocking pattern to the east of each basin deflects midlatitude cyclones and their associated moisture into the Arctic [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>]. Inter-annual variability of intrusions is strongly related with Arctic surface temperature, through their effect on the downward longwave radiation [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>]. In extreme cases, the passage of strong cyclones into the Arctic and their associated moist intrusions can lead to above-freezing temperatures in the central Arctic in the midst of winter [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>]. In recent years, a run of such Arctic midwinter warming events has focussed attention of whether intrusions are becoming more common [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>]. Woods and Caballero (2016) found an increase in the frequency of moist intrusions, which can explain roughly 45% of the surface warming trend and 30% of the sea ice loss in the Barents Sea during the past two decades [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>]. Park et al. (2015) concluded that nearly half the sea ice decline in the Atlantic sector could be explained by increased downward longwave radiation, related to increased poleward transport of heat and moisture [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Moisture transport into the Arctic is projected to increase in a warming climate, as humidity increases more rapidly at lower latitudes per Kelvin temperature rise, leading to a larger poleward moisture gradient. Skific and Francis (2013) diagnosed that 75–80% of the total projected annual change in moisture transport across 70°N, between the late 20th and 21st centuries, is thermodynamically driven, being due to change in the meridional gradient of specific humidity [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>]. Although smaller, the dynamic term was also positive and related to an increase in low-pressure systems over the central Arctic that transport substantial moisture into the Arctic.
 </p>
</sec>
