<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Northern Annular Mode</div>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Northern Annular Mode (NAM), also known as the Arctic Oscillation, is the dominant mode of inter-annual variability in the extratropical Northern Hemisphere [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>]. The positive phase of the NAM is associated with anomalously low pressure over the Arctic and high pressure over mid-latitudes, a pattern that strengthens the zonally averaged westerly winds. Also, the westerly winds are typically located further poleward during positive NAM. Since changes in the westerly winds, storm tracks and the eddy-driven jet stream are intimately connected, both to each other and to the NAM, we will consider these collectively here.
 </p>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the past few years, there has been considerable progress in understanding the role of Arctic sea ice as a driver of variability in the NAM. Interest in links between sea ice and the NAM has been sparked by the repeated coincidence of anomalously negative NAM and reduced sea ice conditions and the dramatic decline in Arctic sea ice. Several studies have noted a strong negative correlation between sea ice and the NAM over recent decades [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>]. Given that attributing causality is an intractable problem with observations alone, many studies have reported on model experiments with perturbed sea ice to isolate the atmospheric circulation response to sea ice. These modelling studies support a causal link between projected sea ice loss and the negative NAM [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>••, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>•, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>••]. A recent comparison of the atmospheric circulation response to projected Arctic sea ice loss in six coupled climate model experiments found a weakening and equatorward shift of the midlatitude westerly wind belt in each case [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>], implying a common negative NAM response. However, the NAM response to observed sea ice loss over the past 30–40 years is less clear, being model dependent and often obscured by internal variability [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>]. More detailed reviews on the possible links between Arctic sea ice loss and the Northern Hemisphere atmospheric circulation can be found elsewhere [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sea ice loss can force a change in the NAM via a tropospheric pathway or through interaction with the stratosphere [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>]. The tropospheric pathway is associated with the adjustment of transient eddies to the change in meridional temperature gradient and baroclinic instability. The stratospheric pathway involves enhanced upward planetary-scale wave propagation and the weakening of the stratospheric polar vortex [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>], which then modifies the NAM. Idealised atmospheric general circulation model experiments, using configurations with and without an interactive stratosphere, suggest that when the stratosphere is inactive, the tropospheric jet still shifts equatorward in response to Arctic warming, but by approximately half the magnitude compared to that of an active stratosphere [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>]. The stratospheric pathway appears sensitive to the location of sea ice loss whereas the tropospheric pathway appears less so [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Arctic sea ice loss is only one component of greenhouse gas (GHG)-induced climate change. A paradigm that has gained traction in recent years is that the climate response to sea ice loss may partly counteract other aspects of the response to increased GHG. Since the dominant characteristic of projected GHG-induced climate change, in the absence of sea ice loss, is pronounced warming of the tropical upper troposphere, this has been conceptualised as a “tug-of-war” between the Arctic and tropics. Whilst Arctic sea ice loss is thought to promote the negative NAM, projected tropical upper tropospheric warming has the opposite effect, favouring the positive NAM [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>]. The winter atmospheric responses to Arctic sea ice loss and to GHG increases appear to be distinct, separable and, to good approximation, linearly additive [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>•]. The weak projected climate change response of the NAM (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>) may reflect the partial compensation between the distinct—and opposing—responses to Arctic sea ice loss and GHG increases [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>••, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>•, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>•]. This tug-of-war paradigm has been used to explain across-model spread in winter NAM projections [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>]. More specifically, models that simulate larger Arctic warming are also those that simulate larger equatorward shifts of the storm tracks [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>] and jet stream [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>].
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Indices of the Northern Annular Mode (left) and Southern Annular Mode (right) from observations and models. The black line shows, for each season (top to bottom), the CMIP5 multi-model mean of historical and RCP4.5 simulations. The grey band shows the 5–95% confidence range based on the individual model simulations. The coloured lines show observational indices derived from HadSLP2 (red), NOAA-CIRES Twentieth Century Reanalysis (orange) and Japanese 55-year Reanalysis (blue). Simulated anomalies are shown relative to the 1861–1900 baseline, and observations are centred on the multi-model mean over the period for which they are shown. The symbols to the right of each line graph show changes between 1980–2029 and 2050–2099, for each individual model (black circles) and the multi-model mean (red line). Adapted from Gillett and Fyfe (2013), where further details on these data and methods can be found [
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>]
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="40641_2018_111_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
