<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Northern Stratospheric Polar Vortex</div>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The dominant circulation feature of the Arctic stratosphere in winter is a strong circumpolar westerly jet, referred to as the stratospheric polar vortex [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>]. Whilst the vortex is omnipresent in winter and centred around the pole, it exhibits large variability in strength and location on intra-seasonal to multi-decadal timescales. It is well known that this stratospheric variability has a significant influence on tropospheric circulation, and weather and climate at the Earth’s surface [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>]. Sudden stratospheric warming (SSW) events in particular, when the stratospheric polar vortex is abruptly weakened and disrupted, are often a precursor to the negative phase of the NAM and cold-air outbreaks. Several recent studies have reported a weakening of the polar vortex over the last three or four decades [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>]. Kretschmer et al. (2018) identified occurrences of weak and strong polar vortices using a hierarchical clustering approach [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>]. They found a significant increase in the frequency of the weak vortex events, from an average frequency of 3 days per winter in the period 1979–1996 to 7 days per winter in the period 1998–2015. In contrast, the occurrence of strong vortex events halved from 12 to 6 days over the same years. SSW events have also been notably more frequent in the more recent period [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>]. This weakening of the polar vortex has been cited as a cause of increased cold extremes and sustained boreal winter cooling over midlatitude Eurasia [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>]. An apparent shift of the polar vortex towards the Eurasian continent and away from North America may have also contributed to cooling over Eurasia [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The causes of observed polar vortex weakening are not fully understood. One hypothesised cause is the loss of Arctic sea ice [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>]. Kim et al. (2014) conducted atmospheric model simulations with reduced sea ice in the Barents and Kara Seas and found an increase in vertical wave activity propagation into the stratosphere [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>]. Enhanced wave breaking in the stratosphere caused a deceleration of the stratospheric westerly winds and hence, weakened the polar vortex. Although a general weakening of the polar vortex has been noted in many model experiments with perturbed Arctic sea ice [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>], the attribution of the observed change to sea ice loss is complicated by at least three factors. The first is divergence between different models [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>]. Second, there is an apparent sensitivity to the geographical location of ice loss. In model experiments, sea ice loss in the Atlantic sector appears to cause a weaker vortex, whereas a stronger vortex is found in response to sea ice loss in the Pacific sector [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The third complicating factor is internal variability. Two recent studies argue that the observed polar vortex weakening is a manifestation of internal variability and not a forced response to Arctic sea ice loss, or to climate change more broadly. Seviour (2017) examined large ensembles of coupled climate model simulations and concluded that the forced response of the vortex was small relative to internal variability, and that vortex trends of similar magnitude to those observed can be generated purely by internal climate variability [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>]. The latter conclusion was also reached by Garfinkel et al. (2017), who found no consistent change in the strength of the polar vortex in model simulations forced with observed GHG concentrations, sea surface temperatures and sea ice [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>]. However, unforced internal variability was sufficiently strong that some individual ensemble members reproduced the observed polar vortex weakening.
 </p>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Future projections of the stratospheric polar vortex are highly uncertain. For example, under global warming scenarios, some modelling studies find an increased frequency of SSW events but others do not [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>]. A recent reassessment of projected changes in SSW events, based on 12 models participating in the Chemistry Climate Model Initiative, found no evidence of future changes in the frequency or duration of SSW events [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
