<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Southern Stratospheric Polar Vortex</div>
 <p id="Par28" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although the southern polar vortex is situated at high altitudes in the stratosphere, the dramatic changes that have occurred in it over recent decades have been important for many of the surface climate changes observed over Antarctica and the Southern Ocean [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83" href="#CR83">83</a>]. There is a very pronounced annual cycle in the polar vortex, which is strongest in winter. The very low temperatures associated with the strong winter vortex provide conditions conducive to stratospheric ozone depletion by ozone depleting substances, as solar radiation returns to polar latitudes in early spring. Since ozone absorbs solar radiation, anomalously strong ozone depletion in spring leads to anomalously cold conditions in the mid-to-lower polar stratosphere. The formation of the ozone hole during rapid depletion between the 1970s and late 1990s is estimated to have produced a spring cooling of approximately 6 K and an associated strengthening of the polar vortex of 5–6 m s
  <span class="sup">−1</span> [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80" href="#CR80">80</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88" href="#CR88">88</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Since approximately the year 2000, Antarctic stratospheric ozone depletion appears to have ended, with signs of possible recovery [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR113" href="#CR113">113</a>•]. Projections to the end of the twenty-first century generally indicate recovery approaching pre ozone-hole levels, but that lower-stratospheric cooling associated with greenhouse-gas induced global warming prevents full recovery due to lower temperatures in winter acting to increase the occurrence of polar stratospheric clouds, which enhances depletion of stratospheric ozone during the return of sunlight in spring [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR114" href="#CR114">114</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR115" href="#CR115">115</a>]. In isolation, the near-recovery of stratospheric ozone concentrations would result in a near reversal of the recent changes in the polar vortex in spring. The precise rate and eventual extent of ozone recovery and related reversal in polar vortex changes differ across different climate models with implications for projections of twenty-first century surface climate change. In particular, there is significant model uncertainty over the extent to which stratospheric ozone recovery may act to cancel out projected future greenhouse gas-induced poleward jet shifts [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR116" href="#CR116">116</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
