<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec11" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sub-Antarctic Cyclones</div>
 <p id="Par33" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The geography of the southern polar region differs significantly from its northern counterpart. This means that, distinct from those in the Northern Hemisphere, in the Southern Hemisphere the storm tracks and regions of heightened baroclinicity lie over, or very close to, the sea ice pack [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR129" href="#CR129">129</a>]. In addition, the circulation is much more zonally symmetric in the high southern latitudes. These and other factors mean that sea ice and large-scale atmospheric drivers might influence the behaviour of storms in different ways from those in the Northern Hemisphere. Cyclone activity is well correlated with the SAM, with more cyclones south of 60°S and fewer north of this latitude during the positive SAM phase [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR130" href="#CR130">130</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR131" href="#CR131">131</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par34" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Grieger et al. (2018) undertook a comprehensive analysis of sub-Antarctic cyclones making use of 14 state-of-the-art tracking methods applied to the ERA-Interim reanalysis [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR132" href="#CR132">132</a>]. Robust positive trends in cyclone numbers were identified by almost all methods for austral summer over the hemispheric region south of 60°S, mainly due to the strong relation to SAM, and in the Amundsen-Bellingshausen Seas sector. Fewer methods indicated significant positive trends over the East Antarctica and Weddell sectors. Trends in austral winter were positive for most regions and methods, but only statistically significant using some tracking methods.
 </p>
 <p id="Par35" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Antarctic region presents an environment somewhat different to that of the Arctic for cyclone properties simulated by models for the twenty-first century. Consistent with the Northern Hemisphere, Tamarin-Brodsky and Kaspi (2017) highlighted a summer poleward shift by 4.9° latitude of maximum zonally averaged cyclone track density and a notable increase in track density in the sub-Antarctic between 55 and 65°S [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78" href="#CR78">78</a>••]. Very marked in their results is a strong poleward expansion of the cyclogenesis region, with genesis increasing markedly in the 60–70°S band in response to the simulated shift in baroclinicity. With significant changes predicted in baroclinicity and total column water vapour [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR133" href="#CR133">133</a>] in the southern polar region, one would expect changes in the frequency of extreme cyclones. Indeed, the CMIP5 models depict significant increases in extreme cyclones (defined in numerous ways) around most of the periphery of the Antarctic continent [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR134" href="#CR134">134</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par36" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An indirect measure of the changes in sub-Antarctic cyclone behaviour can be obtained by examining phenomena that are directly influenced by these synoptic systems. Most of the Antarctic precipitation falls on the peripheral areas of the ice sheet, and this component of the precipitation is mainly influenced by sub-Antarctic cyclones and fronts. Palerme et al. (2017) investigated the changes, between 1986–2005 and 2080–2099, in annual Antarctic precipitation simulated by the CMIP5 models [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR135" href="#CR135">135</a>]. They found model-average increases ranging from 5.5 to 24.5% for low to high emission scenarios, implying greater cyclonic activity and/or more precipitation per cyclone due to increased moisture availability.
 </p>
</sec>
