<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Datasets that are not collected via systematic sampling are often subject to biases based on accessibility (
 <xref rid="ref-52" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kadmon, Farber &amp; Danin, 2004</xref>), dispersal ability, and level of scientific and community interest (
 <xref rid="ref-30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Fourcade et al., 2014</xref>). While we used some of the most robust available data for an elusive snake species (
 <xref rid="ref-31" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Franklin et al., 2009</xref>), bias can be reduced through the background selection process previously discussed. In addition to background selection, 
 <xref rid="ref-30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Fourcade et al. (2014)</xref> note that spatial filtering will further reduce bias associated with non-systematic sampling. Therefore, the 
 <italic class="italic">Spatially Rarefy Occurrence Data for SDMs</italic> tool set within the SDMtoolbox (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://sdmtoolbox.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://sdmtoolbox.org/</ext-link>) was used to classify and spatially filter the climate variables into different homogenous areas and reduce the number of points clustered around these homogenous zones (
 <xref rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Brown, Bennett &amp; French, 2017</xref>). SDMtoolbox is an ArcGIS extension that includes several tools to assist in running species distribution models. This further reduced the number of points to 142. Ten of these points were found to be outside of the range of one or more environmental variable layers used because they were located on islands that did not have bioclimate data available. Therefore, Maxent did not use these points in the model, reducing the number of used occurrence points to 132. This number is well above the locality sample size at which Maxent has been shown to be effective (
 <xref rid="ref-43" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hernandez et al., 2006</xref>). In addition, the benefits of additional occurrence points appear to plateau after 50 (
 <xref rid="ref-43" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hernandez et al., 2006</xref>); however, some studies disagree with 50 as either too conservative (
 <xref rid="ref-51" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Jiménez-Valverde &amp; Lobo, 2007</xref>) or too generous (
 <xref rid="ref-73" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Proosdij et al., 2016</xref>). In either case, the number of points we used was well above this threshold.
</p>
