<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece34963-sec-0010" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.8</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Temporal and spatial trends of changes in sea temperature</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Temperature has been implicated in both recruitment failure of sea urchins and the expansion of cancer crabs (Figure 
  <a rid="ece34963-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#ece34963-fig-0002">2</a>; Temperature → crab, Temperature → sea urchin). To evaluate whether the documented range expansion of the crab 
  <span class="italic">C. pagurus </span>(cf. Woll et al., 
  <a rid="ece34963-bib-0081" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34963-bib-0081">2006</a>, Brattegard, 
  <a rid="ece34963-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34963-bib-0006">2011</a>) and the collapse of 
  <span class="italic">S. droebachiensis</span> populations are likely to be driven by temperature change (cf. Stephens, 
  <a rid="ece34963-bib-0071" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34963-bib-0071">1972</a>), we explored time trends in the ocean climate along the south–north gradient within the study area over the last 38 years. We obtained temperature data from the three meteorological stations: Bud (63°N), Skrova (68°N), and Ingøy (71°N) (see Figure 
  <a rid="ece34963-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#ece34963-fig-0003">3</a> for the positions of the hydrographical stations and Figure 
  <a rid="ece34963-fig-0010" ref-type="fig" href="#ece34963-fig-0010">10</a> for mean and maximum temperature). Monthly sea temperatures measured at 1 m depth from 1972 to 2010 were available from Albretsen, Aure, Sætre, and Danielssen (
  <a rid="ece34963-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34963-bib-0001">2011</a>) for these three stations. Potential time trends in the climatic data were tested by the Mann‐Kendall trend tests for the Bud, Skrova, and Ingøy time series using the R library 
  <span class="italic">Kendall</span> (McLeod, 
  <a rid="ece34963-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34963-bib-0042">2011</a>).
 </p>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece34963-fig-0010" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 10</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Detrended seasonal averages (a) and yearly maximum (b) sea surface temperatures (SST, measured at 1 m depth) from climatic stations at Bud (63°N), Skrova (68°N), and Ingøy (71°N; see map in Figure 
    <a rid="ece34963-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#ece34963-fig-0003">3</a>)
   </p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-21" xlink:href="ECE3-9-2847-g010" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sea surface temperatures are generally lower at higher latitudes. There has been a significant increase in the temperature from 1972 to 2010 at all three climate stations (tau &gt; 0.154, 
  <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.0017, Figure 
  <a rid="ece34963-fig-0010" ref-type="fig" href="#ece34963-fig-0010">10</a>). From 2000s, the Lofoten area (i.e., Skrova) has experienced temperatures like those observed in mid‐Norway (i.e., Bud) 20–30 years earlier (Figure 
  <a rid="ece34963-fig-0010" ref-type="fig" href="#ece34963-fig-0010">10</a>a). During this time, the maximum sea surface temperature exceeded 15°C at the two stations in southern and middle part of the study coastline but remained below 11°C in the northernmost region (Figure 
  <a rid="ece34963-fig-0010" ref-type="fig" href="#ece34963-fig-0010">10</a>b).
 </p>
</sec>
