<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The anticipated effects of climate change on aquatic ecosystems globally will be complex [
  <a rid="pone.0202737.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202737.ref001">1</a>]-[
  <a rid="pone.0202737.ref002" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202737.ref002">2</a>] and are likely to result in increased temperature, decreased dissolved oxygen, increased toxicity of pollutants, and changes in hydrologic regimes [
  <a rid="pone.0202737.ref003" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202737.ref003">3</a>]. Stream fishes may be particularly susceptible to the effects of climate change. For example, climate change could affect stream fishes through changes in stream discharge patterns such as increased flooding chances [
  <a rid="pone.0202737.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202737.ref004">4</a>]. Spring floods can lead to failed year classes of fishes in streams (e.g., smallmouth bass 
  <span class="italic">Micropterus dolomieu</span>, [
  <a rid="pone.0202737.ref005" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202737.ref005">5</a>]; Salmonids, [
  <a rid="pone.0202737.ref006" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202737.ref006">6</a>]; shoal bass 
  <span class="italic">Micropterus cataractae</span>, [
  <a rid="pone.0202737.ref007" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202737.ref007">7</a>]). Flooding can affect smallmouth bass year class strength through nest destruction and fry displacement [
  <a rid="pone.0202737.ref008" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202737.ref008">8</a>]-[
  <a rid="pone.0202737.ref010" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202737.ref010">10</a>]. Flooding can also lead to mortality through rapid changes in water temperature [
  <a rid="pone.0202737.ref011" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202737.ref011">11</a>]. Timing of flooding can be important as the size of the fry can determine the response to the flood event [
  <a rid="pone.0202737.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202737.ref009">9</a>]-[
  <a rid="pone.0202737.ref010" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202737.ref010">10</a>]. Though chances of flooding could increase due to climate change, in some regions, climate change is also expected to result in an overall reduction in precipitation which could lead to lower mean discharge levels [
  <a rid="pone.0202737.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202737.ref012">12</a>]. Recruitment of fish in many stream systems can be positively affected by low discharge levels during the spawning and rearing period which often enhances year class strength [
  <a rid="pone.0202737.ref005" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202737.ref005">5</a>], [
  <a rid="pone.0202737.ref011" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202737.ref011">11</a>], [
  <a rid="pone.0202737.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202737.ref013">13</a>]-[
  <a rid="pone.0202737.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202737.ref014">14</a>]. Water temperature will also be affected by climate change and can influence growth and survival of stream fishes [
  <a rid="pone.0202737.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202737.ref015">15</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0202737.ref017" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202737.ref017">17</a>]. Changes in stream temperature could also lead to range restrictions or expansions [
  <a rid="pone.0202737.ref018" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202737.ref018">18</a>]. Because of the many potential effects of climate change on stream systems, it can be difficult to anticipate how stream fishes will be affected.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Harvest is also an important factor structuring stream fish populations. For example, harvest of stream black bass is an important contributor to mortality in streams open to exploitation (e.g., Suwannee bass and largemouth bass, [
  <a rid="pone.0202737.ref019" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202737.ref019">19</a>]; smallmouth bass, [
  <a rid="pone.0202737.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202737.ref020">20</a>]-[
  <a rid="pone.0202737.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202737.ref021">21</a>]). Climate change will likely make managing harvested fisheries more complex and harvest regulations will need to be adapted as fish populations change [
  <a rid="pone.0202737.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202737.ref022">22</a>]-[
  <a rid="pone.0202737.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202737.ref023">23</a>]. High harvest levels, when combined with climate and anthropogenic related stressors, could lead to population declines [
  <a rid="pone.0202737.ref024" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202737.ref024">24</a>]. As the world population grows, it is likely that fishing pressure will increase, potentially resulting in increased harvest levels that will need to be managed in conjunction with changing climate stressors.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Smallmouth bass are a warm-water riverine species broadly distributed throughout North America. The Ozark-Ouachita Interior Highlands of Arkansas lie at the southern extent of smallmouth bass native range. The southern region of the United States is projected to warm 3–4°C by the year 2050 [
  <a rid="pone.0202737.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202737.ref012">12</a>]. Along with the temperature change is an expected change in precipitation, including more extreme events leading to higher stochasticity and potentially an increase in flooding frequency and severity [
  <a rid="pone.0202737.ref025" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202737.ref025">25</a>] even though average annual precipitation is projected to decrease slightly in parts of the southern region [
  <a rid="pone.0202737.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202737.ref012">12</a>]. Precipitation patterns are likely to change seasonally and a decrease in precipitation is anticipated in the summer months [
  <a rid="pone.0202737.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202737.ref001">1</a>], potentially leading to more severe and longer drought conditions [
  <a rid="pone.0202737.ref026" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202737.ref026">26</a>]. At this southern range extent, smallmouth bass populations may be vulnerable to population declines due to climate change as summer temperatures will likely reach levels that will affect growth and survivorship [
  <a rid="pone.0202737.ref027" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202737.ref027">27</a>]-[
  <a rid="pone.0202737.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202737.ref028">28</a>], especially during summer drought conditions which are common in Arkansas streams and rivers [
  <a rid="pone.0202737.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202737.ref029">29</a>]-[
  <a rid="pone.0202737.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202737.ref030">30</a>]. Smallmouth bass are at risk of being outcompeted in some lotic habitats by largemouth bass and spotted bass, which both have a competitive advantage over smallmouth bass at higher temperatures [
  <a rid="pone.0202737.ref031" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202737.ref031">31</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To investigate the relative effects of angler harvest and climate change on the smallmouth bass population in the Buffalo National River, Arkansas (hereafter, Buffalo River) we created an age-structured population model to simulate various climate and harvest scenarios. The structure for the model was based on previous work comparing land use and climate change effects on lotic smallmouth bass in an Illinois river [
  <a rid="pone.0202737.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202737.ref013">13</a>]. We used empirical data collected in the Buffalo River to create a Ricker recruit-spawner model modified with environmental parameters which was subsequently used to predict annual recruitment of age-0 smallmouth bass within a stage structured simulation model. Our objective was to compare the effects of climate change stressors (i.e., flooding and drought) and harvest mortality on smallmouth bass. We hypothesized that changing climate conditions would negatively affect smallmouth bass populations. In addition, we hypothesized that if current levels of harvest were maintained or increased in future climate scenarios, then smallmouth bass populations would further decline and extinction probability would increase.
 </p>
</sec>
