<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec008" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Simulations</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The simulation model runs on an annual time step from October to October and each simulation was conducted over 100 years and replicated 1,000 times. We began each simulation with a very high abundance for each age group of fish (
  <a rid="pone.0202737.t002" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0202737.t002">Table 2</a>). A break-in period followed before the model settled into a relatively stable abundance of each age group of fish around year ten. Preliminary runs of our simulation model indicated an under prediction of adult abundance in present climate simulations compared to empirical data. Therefore, we modified the number of age-0 smallmouth bass predicted by the Ricker recruit-spawner model by multiplying by four in all simulations. This resulted in very similar predicted abundances in the present climate simulation to the mean CPUE of adult smallmouth bass collected in empirical data.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We conducted ten different simulations where we examined different climate and harvest related scenarios. The first simulation was based on present climate conditions where June discharge and May temperature were taken from historical values for the Buffalo River area. Using the NOAA climate station and USGS river gage described above, we calculated a mean value and standard deviations based on May temperature from the years 1948–2013, and a median value and standard deviation based on June discharge from the years 1940–2013. The remaining nine simulations were set at future climate conditions for June discharge and May temperature. We determined future mean monthly May temperature and mean monthly June discharge values based on climate simulation results from an ensemble average of 30 downscaled climate models for an RCP 8.5 emissions scenario at mid-century (2050–2074; USGS National Climate Change Viewer; [
  <a rid="pone.0202737.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202737.ref012">12</a>]). Mean minimum and maximum temperatures output by the climate models were averaged and used to determine a future mean monthly May temperature with standard deviation. Because the Buffalo River is runoff dominated [
  <a rid="pone.0202737.ref041" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202737.ref041">41</a>], we determined future discharge by modifying historical median discharge proportionally to the change in future projected precipitation (the mean is about 8% lower in June and 19% more variable).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We modeled two different types of drought simulations based on current and future projected drought frequency in the region. Summer drought conditions are presently common in runoff dominated rivers like the Buffalo River in this region [
  <a rid="pone.0202737.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202737.ref029">29</a>]-[
  <a rid="pone.0202737.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202737.ref030">30</a>], [
  <a rid="pone.0202737.ref041" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202737.ref041">41</a>] and climate change could lead to prolonged and more severe drought conditions in the region [
  <a rid="pone.0202737.ref026" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202737.ref026">26</a>]. We modeled drought probabilistically where each simulated year had a chance of being a drought year (
  <a rid="pone.0202737.t002" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0202737.t002">Table 2</a>). We based present drought chances on long term discharge data from the Buffalo River during summer months (June-September) where we defined a moderate drought year as being lower than 50% of mean discharge during the period of record (1940–2013) and a strong drought year as being less than 25% of mean discharge. Natural mortality during moderate drought years was increased 50% above normal levels for all age groups and natural mortality during strong drought years was increased 75% above normal levels for all age groups. In future higher frequency drought simulations, we modeled expected future increases in drought in this region (moderate drought 5% more frequent and extreme drought 9% more frequent; [
  <a rid="pone.0202737.ref026" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202737.ref026">26</a>]).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We modeled two different types of flood simulations based on current and future projected flood frequency in the region. We simulated flooding during the spawning and rearing period and the associated mortality of age-0 fish. Though floods likely affect older age groups as well, it is more difficult to quantify those effects. Similar to drought, we simulated flooding probabilistically where every year had a chance to be a flood year. We based present flood probability on discharge data from the Buffalo River (1940–2013) during June where we defined a flood event as an increase in mean June discharge of 100% above median discharge (about 10% of years from 1940–2013). If a flood year occurred, mortality of age-0 fish was set at 90%. We modeled some scenarios as having a higher flood chance to simulate an increase in extreme precipitation events due to climate change. Though increases in extreme precipitation events are expected in this region, there are no models projecting the associated effects on numbers of flood events with high confidence in this region [
  <a rid="pone.0202737.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202737.ref042">42</a>]. We chose to increase flood probability in a given year to 20% as an exploratory examination of future flooding potential.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We modeled two different harvest morality simulations. Though recent estimates of harvest of smallmouth bass in the Buffalo River are not available, we used harvest mortality estimates from similar Missouri Ozark rivers in our simulations (approximately 20% annual harvest mortality; [
  <a rid="pone.0202737.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202737.ref021">21</a>]). Use of the Buffalo River has increased in recent years (a 240% increase in visitors from 2000 to 2016; [
  <a rid="pone.0202737.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0202737.ref043">43</a>]) and is likely to increase in the future, potentially leading to higher harvest of smallmouth bass. Assuming no change in regulations and an increase in river use, we modeled a future harvest scenario as 75% higher than present harvest mortality (35% annual harvest mortality). Finally, we modeled a scenario where harvest of smallmouth bass is closed to facilitate a comparison of the importance of harvest and other mortality factors in affecting population levels.
 </p>
</sec>
