<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2dot2dot4-ijerph-12-13162" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2.4. Perceived Benefit or Cost (BOC)</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ajzen and Driver [
  <a rid="B38-ijerph-12-13162" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38-ijerph-12-13162">38</a>] distinguished behavioral beliefs into two independent types: beliefs about the costs or benefits of engaging in a behavior (instrumental beliefs) and beliefs about positive or negative feelings derived from the behavior (affective beliefs). This study refined the construct of behavioral beliefs by defining instrumental beliefs as the perceived benefit or cost (BOC). Perceived benefits are defined as beliefs about improved conditions or gains produced by a given action, whereas perceived costs involve beliefs about losses engendered by that action.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As with other behaviors, an individual’s BOC influences whether they engage in environmental behaviors; less benefit or more cost reduces the likelihood that individuals will engage in environmental behaviors [
  <a rid="B39-ijerph-12-13162" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39-ijerph-12-13162">39</a>]. For example, consumers who were willing to pay a higher price for emulsion lacquer paints with an environmental label expected a personal advantage from using the labeled products [
  <a rid="B40-ijerph-12-13162" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40-ijerph-12-13162">40</a>]. Similarly, mothers may have strong concerns about environmental and food safety and may thus be willing to pay more for eco-labeled apples [
  <a rid="B41-ijerph-12-13162" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41-ijerph-12-13162">41</a>]. In one study, approximately 49% of Australian tourist respondents were willing to pay extra for hotel accommodations powered by a micro-generation renewable energy supply [
  <a rid="B42-ijerph-12-13162" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42-ijerph-12-13162">42</a>]. In another study, aviation passengers were willing to pay 60 Euro Cent per 100 km when they flew to offset their GHG emissions, on average [
  <a rid="B43-ijerph-12-13162" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43-ijerph-12-13162">43</a>]. Altruistic and environmental attitudes, along with a greater ability to pay, have been shown to reliably predict willingness to pay a premium price for using green electricity [
  <a rid="B44-ijerph-12-13162" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44-ijerph-12-13162">44</a>]. Gaspar 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span> [
  <a rid="B45-ijerph-12-13162" ref-type="bibr" href="#B45-ijerph-12-13162">45</a>] argued that their results indicated a preference for first considering cost, followed by quality and energy consumption.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study distinguishes between PBC and BOC and uses different variables to assess them. PBC is concerned with the perceived ability to perform a behavior (or a sequence of behaviors), and it is quite similar to Bandura’s work on self-efficacy [
  <a rid="B35-ijerph-12-13162" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35-ijerph-12-13162">35</a>], whereas BOC indicates that more benefit or less cost would encourage individuals to engage in behaviors based on their behavioral intentions.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For example, although an incandescent light bulb and an LED light bulb emit the same luminous flux, an incandescent light bulb costs about US$1.57 in Taiwan, whereas an LED light bulb costs about US$4.72. The consumer has the perceived ability to buy both types of light bulbs. If the consumers do not have any more information, the cheap product is always purchased. However, including the BOC analysis in the same cases reveals that the annual electricity bill is approximately US$3.14 for an incandescent light bulb and US$1.50 for an LED light bulb. Thus, it is a good deal for the consumer to choose the LED light bulb over the incandescent light bulb if it will be used for more than 2 years.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ECC model followed the studies of Loureiro 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span> [
  <a rid="B41-ijerph-12-13162" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41-ijerph-12-13162">41</a>], Dalton 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span> [
  <a rid="B42-ijerph-12-13162" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42-ijerph-12-13162">42</a>], and Ward 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span> [
  <a rid="B46-ijerph-12-13162" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46-ijerph-12-13162">46</a>] and identified BOC as follows: energy-efficient appliances were typically more expensive than traditional appliances, but the reductions in energy bills that were achieved by using energy-efficient appliances totaled more than the premium price.
 </p>
</sec>
