<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec5-ijerph-12-13162" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">5. Conclusions and Recommendations</div>
 <sec id="sec5dot1-ijerph-12-13162" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">5.1. Conclusions</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To determine the key factors that might influence individuals’ intention to purchase energy-efficient appliances, this study extended the TPB by introducing BOC as an independent variable to develop the ECC model. All the independent variables of the ECC model (EA, SN, PBC, and BOC) significantly influenced the dependent variable (intention to purchase energy-efficient appliances). According to the invariance test, the ECC model showed stability and measurability across gender groups.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Regarding the comparison between the ECC model and TPB, the model fit indices of both the ECC model and TPB were acceptable, although the ECC model included more variables than the TPB. The parsimony index of the ECC model was also acceptable, and ultimately, the ECC model was superior to the TPB in explaining variation in the intention to purchase energy-efficient appliances.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although EA was able to predict the intention to purchase energy-efficient appliances, the standardized regression coefficient was only 0.105, and Chin [
   <a rid="B63-ijerph-12-13162" ref-type="bibr" href="#B63-ijerph-12-13162">63</a>] has argued that standardized regression coefficients should be greater than 0.2. This study suggests that energy-efficient appliances should not be promoted merely by making appeals to mitigating global warming or climate change because the effect of EA on the intention of purchasing energy-efficient appliances is insufficient. However, this finding does not indicate that appealing to mitigate global warming or climate change is useless. Rather, promotional strategies should focus on not only global warming but also on concepts such as SN, PBC, and BOC.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results of this study showed that SN can predict the intention to purchase energy-efficient appliances (
   <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.001), as the standardized regression coefficient (0.236) was significant in the ECC model. Thus, the opinions of a person of concern to an individual may influence that individual’s intention to purchase energy-efficient appliances.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Taiwanese government has encouraged citizens to purchase appliances with “energy-saving” labels. The results demonstrated that PBC can predict the intention to purchase energy-efficient appliances (
   <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.001), and standardized regression coefficient (0.333) showed significantly in the ECC model. Thus, popularizing energy-efficient appliances in the electrical market might increase individuals’ intention to purchase energy-efficient appliances.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results also showed that BOC can predict the intention to purchase energy-efficient appliances (
   <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.001) and those energy-efficient appliances are typically more expensive than traditional appliances. However, if an individual perceives the reduction in energy costs from energy-efficient appliances to exceed their premium price, then they may have a higher intention to purchase energy-efficient appliances.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The TPB and modified models had been used to examine various pro-environmental intentions and behaviors. This study revealed that promoting households’ intention to purchase energy-efficient appliances should focus not only on global warming but also on the concepts of subjective norm, perceived behavioral control and perceived benefit or cost. The findings of this study add to the existing literature on pro-environmental behavior by showing the importance of providing appropriate economic incentives in order to encourage households to choose energy-efficient appliances, which would engender energy savings.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec5dot2-ijerph-12-13162" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">5.2. Recommendations</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Extending previous studies based on the TPB, this study shows that BOC is a good complementary variable for the TPB and that the ECC model is superior to the TPB in explaining the variation in intention to purchase energy-efficient appliances. Thus, to increase households’ intention to purchase energy-efficient appliances and encourage citizens to purchase higher-priced, energy-efficient appliances, the government should help households understand that the energy cost savings of energy-efficient appliances exceed the price premiums of such appliances.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The amount of energy consumed is determined when appliances are brought to a house. One of the critical places within which the household sector can reduce GHG emissions is in the appliance market. This study recommends that the industrial sector provide the energy consumption information of all the appliances and make a comparison list for salespeople and retailers who introduce these appliances to consumers. Households can then compare the energy consumption and cost of the appliances immediately. For example, households could determine how many years it would take for the savings from reduced energy costs to exceed the price premium of an energy-efficient appliance. Such a strategy might increase households’ intention to purchase the most energy-efficient appliances.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec5dot3-ijerph-12-13162" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">5.3. Limitations and Further Research</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ECC model is subject to a number of limitations that can serve as starting points for further research. This study focused on the ECC model in the household sector, and future research may extend this model to other fields, such as offices and housing communities. Four types of electrical appliances were used as items in this study, and further research may extend the model to other appliances or equipment.</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
