<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The power of rapid-cycle breeding to drive climate change adaptation is illustrated in 
 <xref rid="f0005" ref-type="fig" class="xref">Fig. 1</xref>, which presents maize yields from the US state of Iowa (the heart of the US Corn Belt) for 50 years through 2013. From 1980 through 2013, growing season average temperature has increased by 0.15 C per decade, with decreased precipitation in the late growing season (
 <xref rid="bib17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Dai et al., 2015</xref>). Both trends are unfavorable for maize yield, but yields increased at an annual rate of 1.51% (142 kg ha
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>) during this period. 2012 was the worst drought year in Iowa since 1988 (
 <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Boyer et al., 2013</xref>). Yet the mean maize yield for the state in that year was 8.80 t ha
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>, a yield not reached in a favorable year until 1986, and not routinely achieved until the late 1990s. This is the result of rapid and effective maize breeding and seed delivery, driving yield improvement in the face of climate change. Commercial maize breeding in the US is a case study in how to design a plant breeding and seed system that delivers genetic gains and climate change adaptation. The key features of such a system can be identified by analyzing the three main components of the plant breeding and dissemination process (
 <xref rid="f0010" ref-type="fig" class="xref">Fig. 2</xref>):
 <list list-type="simple" class="list">
  <list-item id="u0050" class="list-item">
   <label class="label">1)</label>
   <p class="p">
    <italic class="italic">Population improvement,</italic> wherein segregating populations are formed, recombinants with high phenotypic and, presumably, genotypic value selected, and the selected recombinants intermated to form a new cycle of the breeding population, incrementally improved over the previous cycle as a result of changed allele frequencies. It is this component of the breeding system that drives climate change adaptation.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="u0055" class="list-item">
   <label class="label">2)</label>
   <p class="p">
    <italic class="italic">Commercial cultivar selection,</italic> wherein selected lines, families, or clones (usually the same as those selected for recombination) are subjected to further evaluation and selection to determine their potential for release to farmers as cultivars.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="u0060" class="list-item">
   <label class="label">3)</label>
   <p class="p">
    <italic class="italic">Release and dissemination of new cultivars, and replacement of obsolete ones,</italic> wherein candidate cultivars superior to currently-used varieties are scaled up and disseminated to farmers, with obsolete cultivars withdrawn from production.
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
