<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Rapid breeding cycles (step 1 above) drive climate change adaptation by changing allele frequencies in breeding populations; the commercial cultivar selection and release and dissemination steps are critical in determining how effectively this adaptation is delivered to farmers, but they do not drive allele frequency change in source populations until new lines are used as parents of the next breeding cycle. Rapid breeding cycles are particularly important in developing country cropping systems that are often rapidly intensifying and subject to progressive soil fertility decline (
 <xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Vanlaue et al. 2015</xref>). A rapid-cycle cultivar development, testing, and deployment system can provide cropping systems with adaptation to climate change by constantly generating incrementally changed allelic combinations and subjecting these combinations to intense selection pressure in the target population of environments (TPE). But the vast majority of breeding programs serving farmers in the developing world are cycling their breeding populations too slowly. Whereas the best private-sector programs have cycle times of three to four years from the generation of a new breeding population until the best lines selected from it are themselves used as parents of new populations, public sector breeding programs in developing countries usually have very long breeding cycles. They often take over 10 years to develop and evaluate a new variety to the point where they feel confident in “recycling” it as a parent, and even longer to deploy it. If the accuracy and intensity of selection is constant, then halving cycle time will double the rate of genetic gain. Cutting cycle time has the added benefit of increasing the frequency with which haplotypes are recombined and exposed for selection in the constantly changing environment, increasing the probability of creating and selecting allelic combinations that are closer to optimal for current conditions. Rapid breeding cycles are also critical for adaptation to evolving pest and pathogen populations.
</p>
