<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s0010" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Experimental design, materials and methods</div>
 <p id="p0040" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The new vector high-resolution river centerline shapefile dataset was digitized following the information extracted from base datasets as described above. Vector polylines of rivers were digitized manually by overlaying all three base map datasets (i.e., waterbody, basemap and Digital Elevation Model-DEM) and then drawing the polyline following the river flow direction assessed from the combination of all three datasets. First, we visually identified the start of rivers in the mountains and the end of rivers where the delta merges with the ocean. Polylines were then drawn (digitized) from headwaters of the river following river centerlines and contours down to its delta or river mouth. Locations where the topographic maps 
  <a rid="bib4" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib4">[4]</a> or water body dataset 
  <a rid="bib1" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib1">[1]</a> does not show any visible river body, DEM sinks were consulted to identify the centroid of river width and polylines were drawn following the linked pixels in DEM. Once the end of the river was reached in the digitization process, attributes of the rivers were transferred from the NE data to the new polyline. Every river polyline was assigned with its corresponding name, system, alternative names, scale, and length in kilometer (
  <a rid="t0010" ref-type="table" href="#t0010">Table 2</a>). The shapefile can be downloaded from 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/item/5a145fdde4b09fc93dcfd36c" id="ir0015" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.sciencebase.gov/catalog/item/5a145fdde4b09fc93dcfd36c</span>. Although there are shapefiles of river polylines at global scale exists, the major advancement of this layer is the improved resolution scale of 1:20,000 which will enable fisheries and aquatic scientist and managers to compare environmental data at ecologically relevant scales 
  <a rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib5">[5]</a>.
 </p>
</sec>
