<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec1dot1dot1-ijerph-15-00389" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1.1.1. Emergence of West Nile Virus in Europe</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">West Nile virus causes a febrile illness in both humans and horses that generally resolves without complications [
  <a rid="B44-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44-ijerph-15-00389">44</a>,
  <a rid="B45-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B45-ijerph-15-00389">45</a>]. In a small proportion of cases (usually &lt;1%), infected individuals develop more serious clinical symptoms and signs including encephalitis, meningitis and paralysis, followed by death in severe cases. The first isolation of WNV from the West Nile district of Uganda by Smithburn and co-workers is well documented [
  <a rid="B46-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46-ijerph-15-00389">46</a>]. Serum prepared from a blood sample taken from a febrile individual was inoculated into mice from which virus was isolated. Following its discovery, research in the 1950s in Africa identified an enzootic transmission cycle involving multiple bird species as natural reservoirs for the virus and mosquitoes as the primary vector group [
  <a rid="B47-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B47-ijerph-15-00389">47</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The majority of countries in sub-Saharan Africa have reported evidence of WNV presence, either through isolation of the virus or through seroprevalence studies [
  <a rid="B48-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B48-ijerph-15-00389">48</a>]. North African countries including Egypt [
  <a rid="B49-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49-ijerph-15-00389">49</a>], Morocco [
  <a rid="B50-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B50-ijerph-15-00389">50</a>] and Algeria [
  <a rid="B51-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51-ijerph-15-00389">51</a>] have also reported evidence of WNV. Due to its association with birds, avian migratory behaviour has been considered the most likely means for the translocation of WNV from Africa to northern latitudes [
  <a rid="B52-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B52-ijerph-15-00389">52</a>]. Repeated emergence of WNV in Israel, Italy, France and Spain correspond to bottlenecks of major flyways of migratory birds travelling north as they avoid the Mediterranean Sea, or cross at its narrowest points [
  <a rid="B53-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53-ijerph-15-00389">53</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">West Nile virus has caused sporadic outbreaks of disease in southern Europe in both humans and horses [
  <a rid="B54-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B54-ijerph-15-00389">54</a>]. Phylogenetic analysis has demonstrated at least eight distinct lineages of WNV, of which two, lineages 1 and 2, circulate in Europe [
  <a rid="B55-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B55-ijerph-15-00389">55</a>]. The most significant epidemic occurred in south eastern Romania with a focus in the capital, Bucharest. Almost 400 cases of encephalitis and 17 deaths were reported in 1996, with further cases reported in subsequent years [
  <a rid="B56-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B56-ijerph-15-00389">56</a>]. The Danube delta was considered the potential site of introduction but with transmission in an urban setting. Interest in WNV was also stimulated by its emergence in North America in 1999, initiating a major epidemic outbreak and highlighting its epidemic potential in other countries [
  <a rid="B57-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B57-ijerph-15-00389">57</a>]. The virus caused numerous cases of disease in birds, particularly North American crows (
  <span class="italic">Corvus brachyrhynchos</span>), domestic horses and humans. A wide range of indigenous mosquito species were found to be infected with WNV [
  <a rid="B58-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B58-ijerph-15-00389">58</a>], however, the 
  <span class="italic">Cx. pipiens</span> complex was considered to be the principal vector [
  <a rid="B59-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B59-ijerph-15-00389">59</a>,
  <a rid="B60-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B60-ijerph-15-00389">60</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">During the first decade of the 21st century, there was an increase in the number of detections of WNV outbreaks in Europe. It remains unclear if this phenomenon was due to more frequent annual re-introduction of WNV or a greater focus on surveillance in the Mediterranean Basin. The successful overwintering of virus in mosquito populations in Italy between 2008 and 2011 was a notable epidemiological shift [
  <a rid="B61-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B61-ijerph-15-00389">61</a>]. The virus causing the outbreaks in Italy and in other countries was identified as belonging to WNV lineage 1 [
  <a rid="B62-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B62-ijerph-15-00389">62</a>]. West Nile virus lineage 2 was first detected in Hungary during 2004 and then spread west and south, reaching Greece prior to 2010. The outbreak in Greece was notable for involving a high number of human cases, including 33 deaths attributed to the infection [
  <a rid="B14-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14-ijerph-15-00389">14</a>]. Mosquito species from the genus 
  <span class="italic">Culex</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Aedes</span> and other mosquito genera have been shown to transmit WNV under experimental conditions but the epidemiological significance for natural virus transmission is unclear [
  <a rid="B63-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B63-ijerph-15-00389">63</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
