<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec1dot4-ijerph-15-00389" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1.4. Distribution and Hybridisation</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Culex pipiens</span> is widely distributed across Eurasia and further afield [
  <a rid="B22-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-ijerph-15-00389">22</a>,
  <a rid="B90-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B90-ijerph-15-00389">90</a>]. Our understanding of the local and regional distribution of its ecoforms has, however, developed only relatively recently, aided by the increasing use of molecular species delineation methods. There remains, however, a poor understanding of the relationship between the genetics of the ecoforms and their phenotype [
  <a rid="B103-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B103-ijerph-15-00389">103</a>]. Initial evidence indicated a fairly consistent separation between the habitats of each ecoform: the ubiquitous pipiens ecoform was associated with natural and artificial aboveground habitats across rural and urban areas and the molestus form was found in urban underground habitats [
  <a rid="B22-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-ijerph-15-00389">22</a>]. Particularly in northern Europe, this habitat distinction was believed to serve as a barrier to hybridisation between the forms and this was supported by limited success in breeding between forms under laboratory conditions [
  <a rid="B90-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B90-ijerph-15-00389">90</a>,
  <a rid="B92-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B92-ijerph-15-00389">92</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Present evidence, however, suggests that this habitat separation is far less rigid, with cross-breeding experiments and analysis of genetic markers from field and colony specimens indicating that inter-breeding populations of pipiens and molestus can be found sympatrically in both above- and belowground urban habitats, as well as in rural and semi-rural areas [
  <a rid="B100-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B100-ijerph-15-00389">100</a>,
  <a rid="B103-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B103-ijerph-15-00389">103</a>,
  <a rid="B110-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B110-ijerph-15-00389">110</a>,
  <a rid="B114-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B114-ijerph-15-00389">114</a>,
  <a rid="B115-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B115-ijerph-15-00389">115</a>,
  <a rid="B116-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B116-ijerph-15-00389">116</a>,
  <a rid="B117-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B117-ijerph-15-00389">117</a>,
  <a rid="B118-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B118-ijerph-15-00389">118</a>,
  <a rid="B119-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B119-ijerph-15-00389">119</a>]. Indeed, natural hybrid pipiens/molestus forms have now been reported from at least 12 European countries (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-15-00389-f002" href="#ijerph-15-00389-f002">Figure 2</a>a) with reported rates of hybridisation of up to 25.7% [
  <a rid="B116-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B116-ijerph-15-00389">116</a>]. The relative abundance of each of the forms and hybridisation rates have been found to vary across latitudes, with the proportion of molestus populations relative to pipiens increasing from northern to southern latitudes [
  <a rid="B120-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B120-ijerph-15-00389">120</a>]. To add further complexity, hybridisation of 
  <span class="italic">Cx. pipiens</span> with 
  <span class="italic">Cx. quinquefasciatus</span> has been reported from the Mediterranean Basin (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-15-00389-f002" href="#ijerph-15-00389-f002">Figure 2</a>b) [
  <a rid="B102-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B102-ijerph-15-00389">102</a>,
  <a rid="B121-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B121-ijerph-15-00389">121</a>,
  <a rid="B122-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B122-ijerph-15-00389">122</a>], despite sympatric populations of these species existing without hybridisation in East Africa [
  <a rid="B123-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B123-ijerph-15-00389">123</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The occurrence of natural hybrid populations has important consequences for the risks of pathogen transmission [
  <a rid="B124-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B124-ijerph-15-00389">124</a>]. Changes to mosquito host preference, vector competence, the occurrence of autogeny and the ability to forgo diapause and continue reproduction through the winter months may all alter virus transmission dynamics. This may have contributed to the persistence of WNV in Romania during the 1990s where the presence of mosquitoes indoors and in flooded basements were considered risk factors for human infection [
  <a rid="B125-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B125-ijerph-15-00389">125</a>]. Additionally, the strains of the endosymbiont 
  <span class="italic">Wolbachia pipientis</span> associated with 
  <span class="italic">Cx. quinquefasciatus</span> and the different ecoforms of 
  <span class="italic">Cx. pipiens</span> differ [
  <a rid="B102-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B102-ijerph-15-00389">102</a>], and the impact of such differences on vector competence is not fully understood. Studies of 
  <span class="italic">Cx. pipiens</span> populations in Portugal demonstrated that gene flow occurred predominantly from the molestus to the pipiens form [
  <a rid="B119-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B119-ijerph-15-00389">119</a>]. Asymmetric gene flow in this fashion could alter feeding preferences of 
  <span class="italic">Cx. pipiens</span> from an ornithophilic to mammalophilic feeding preference, as demonstrated in the USA [
  <a rid="B126-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B126-ijerph-15-00389">126</a>]. The vector competence of molestus populations to WNV in The Netherlands was lower (6–10%) than that of pipiens (0–32%) and hybrid (0–14%) forms [
  <a rid="B127-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B127-ijerph-15-00389">127</a>]. In this context, gene flow from pipiens to molestus could result in increased vector competence and thus may be equally important in influencing local pathogen transmission dynamics.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Culex torrentium</span> has also been reported from many countries across Europe (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-15-00389-f003" href="#ijerph-15-00389-f003">Figure 3</a>) where its larvae are often found in sympatry with 
  <span class="italic">Cx. pipiens</span> [
  <a rid="B89-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B89-ijerph-15-00389">89</a>,
  <a rid="B114-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B114-ijerph-15-00389">114</a>,
  <a rid="B128-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B128-ijerph-15-00389">128</a>,
  <a rid="B129-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B129-ijerph-15-00389">129</a>]. In many studies little morphological separation is performed [
  <a rid="B79-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B79-ijerph-15-00389">79</a>], thus masking the true distribution of the two species. Initially believed to be a rare European species [
  <a rid="B130-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B130-ijerph-15-00389">130</a>], 
  <span class="italic">Cx. torrentium</span> is now recognised to be widespread in northern and central regions of Europe [
  <a rid="B79-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B79-ijerph-15-00389">79</a>,
  <a rid="B89-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B89-ijerph-15-00389">89</a>]. When compared with 
  <span class="italic">Cx. pipiens</span>, these species form an apparent contrasting gradient of abundance: in northern regions 
  <span class="italic">Cx. torrentium</span> dominates, in central Europe both species exist in similar proportions, and in southern Europe 
  <span class="italic">Cx. pipiens</span> is the dominant species and 
  <span class="italic">Cx. torrentium</span> is rarely reported [
  <a rid="B89-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B89-ijerph-15-00389">89</a>]. The current distribution of 
  <span class="italic">Cx. torrentium</span> may reflect a range expansion, perhaps in response to favourable anthroponotic environmental changes [
  <a rid="B110-ijerph-15-00389" ref-type="bibr" href="#B110-ijerph-15-00389">110</a>], but the misidentification of females as 
  <span class="italic">Cx. pipiens</span> prior to the widespread use of molecular analyses may have hindered information on its distribution.
 </p>
</sec>
