<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The widespread use of antifungal drugs has been suggested as a contributory cause in the emergence of 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. auris</named-content> (
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). Whereas selection by environmental azole use can certainly have contributed to drug resistance in this fungal species, it does not easily explain why this organism suddenly became a human pathogen on three continents. For example, the emergence of azole-resistant 
 <italic>Candida</italic> spp. began long before the appearance of 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. auris</named-content>, and there does not appear to be a correlation between the emergence of azole-resistant 
 <italic>Aspergillus</italic> spp. associated with azole agricultural use and the hot spots for 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. auris</named-content> emergence. The acquisition of drug resistance alone is very unlikely to confer upon a microbe the capacity for pathogenicity, since reduced susceptibility to drugs and virulence are very different properties, as evidenced by frequent fitness costs associated with mutations conferring resistance to antifungals to 
 <italic>Candida</italic> (
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>). Instead, as exemplified by the experience with 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">Aspergillus fumigatus</named-content>, aspergillosis was a well-known clinical entity before its putative acquisition of drug resistance from the agricultural use of azoles (
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>). Hence, one might have expected 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. auris</named-content> to have been known as a human and animal pathogen first and then to have acquired drug resistance, rather than emerging as drug resistant from agricultural drug use at the same time that it became a human pathogen. Another suggested explanation for the emergence of 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. auris</named-content> is that it recently acquired virulence traits that confer the capacity for virulence (
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">7</xref>). Although this explanation cannot be ruled out, the capacity for virulence is a complex property that emerges from many attributes, and it is improbable that it would have occurred concurrently on three continents, unless driven by another factor that selected for it.
</p>
