<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The hypothesis that 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. auris</named-content> broke the mammalian thermal barrier through adaptation to climate change suggests several experimental lines of investigation to obtain evidence for and against it. If 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. auris</named-content> thermal tolerance is indeed a new property, a careful analysis of the temperature range that permits replication might reveal that it is still less tolerant than 
 <italic>Candida</italic> spp. that have a long association with mammals. In this regard, isolates from earlier outbreaks may show differences in thermal tolerance from those of outbreaks that are more recent. Of course, analysis of thermal susceptibility requires a more detailed experimental approach to identify small differences than are normally measured by routine microbiologic characterization. A search for environmental reservoirs may produce closely related 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. auris</named-content> strains that have not yet adapted to higher temperatures, which may be expected if the process is stochastic and only some clades have made the transition. Increased sampling in these environments and hosts could test the involvement of wetlands and birds, respectively. Should evidence be found for 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. auris</named-content> or close relatives in these environments, then one might consider that the host jump from birds to humans follows mechanisms similar to those that operate for influenza virus. The possibility that 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. auris</named-content> was always a health care pathogen that has recently been discovered appears to have little support, given that no isolate was found prior to 1996 in fungal collections (
 <xref rid="B3" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>). Evaluating the contributory roles of high human population densities, migrations, increased city temperatures (
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>), poor hygiene, pollution, and regional and international travel (
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>) in the emergence of 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. auris</named-content> is difficult, given the available information, but these potential associations are fertile areas for research. The emergence of 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. auris</named-content> also poses interesting basic science questions on the thermal stability of its enzymatic processes and, in a broader sense, the mechanisms of virulence and adaptation for human-pathogenic fungi. For example, the evolutionarily conserved Hog1 stress-activated protein kinase (SAPK), the role for which in 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. neoformans</named-content> virulence is established (
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>), promotes stress resistance and virulence in 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. auris</named-content> (
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>), suggesting tantalizing connections between mechanisms for adaptation and virulence that are ripe for further study. A scheme for the possible factors operating on the emergence of 
 <named-content content-type="genus-species">C. auris</named-content> is shown in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig2">Fig. 2</xref>.
</p>
