<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Strengthening health systems is the first area of focus for most national health adaptation plans to reduce the current burden of climate-sensitive health outcomes. Components of strengthening health systems include the essential public health services. Of particular importance are the following elements
 <xref rid="bib14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bib15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>:
 <list list-type="simple" class="list">
  <list-item id="u0100" class="list-item">
   <label class="label">•</label>
   <p class="p">Building awareness of the health risks of climate change and the adaptation and mitigation actions needed to protect health today and in the future.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="u0105" class="list-item">
   <label class="label">•</label>
   <p class="p">Building the capacity of public health and health care professionals to monitor, diagnose, and treat cases of climate-sensitive health outcomes, even when they change their incidence, seasonality, and geographic range.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="u0110" class="list-item">
   <label class="label">•</label>
   <p class="p">Developing new methods and tools for preparing for, coping with, and recovering from outbreaks of climate-sensitive diseases, such as early warning systems based on environmental information.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="u0115" class="list-item">
   <label class="label">•</label>
   <p class="p">Strengthening monitoring and surveillance programs to track climate-sensitive health outcomes and improving health services delivery to ensure prompt and effective treatment.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="u0120" class="list-item">
   <label class="label">•</label>
   <p class="p">Strengthening evaluation (and learning) programs designed to identify lessons learned and best practices in health adaptation and how these can be scaled up and out within and across countries.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="u0125" class="list-item">
   <label class="label">•</label>
   <p class="p">Improving governance and policies for managing the health risks of climate variability and change.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="u0130" class="list-item">
   <label class="label">•</label>
   <p class="p">Conducting research to develop new insights and innovative solutions to, for example, emerging and re-emerging infectious diseases.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="u0135" class="list-item">
   <label class="label">•</label>
   <p class="p">Raising the necessary human and financial resources to undertake these actions.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
