<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">How do the community‐level responses to simulated climate change documented previously at BCCIL contrast with impacts below the species‐level documented in this study, and are these outcomes correlated? Species abundance and community composition at BCCIL have been shown to be mediated through the effects of both climate treatment and soil depth; these factors had comparable effect sizes on plant community structure (Fridley 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="gcb12966-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>). In contrast, multilocus (genomewide) genetic responses to simulated climate change were dominated by treatment‐level effects; the effects of soil depth were at least fivefold smaller in magnitude than those attributable to treatment (Table 
 <xref rid="gcb12966-tbl-0001" ref-type="table-wrap" class="xref">1</xref>). Furthermore, there was no clear relationship between the extent of community‐level compositional shifts in different climate treatments and the strength of genetic differentiation within individual species. For example, the highest multilocus genetic differentiation (
 <italic class="italic">F</italic>
 <sub class="sub">ST</sub>) was observed for the watered treatment, yet this was the treatment with the lowest community‐level compositional change relative to control plots (Fridley 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="gcb12966-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>). Finally, we found no evidence to support relationships between species diversity and multilocus genetic diversity or between ecological distance (community dissimilarity) and multilocus genetic distance within species. Thus, genomewide genetic responses to simulated climate change within individual species were likely to have been decoupled from, or occurring independently of community‐level compositional responses. We predict, however, that the abundance of individual species at BCCIL will be, in part, a function of genetic structure at a subset of genomic loci (including outlier loci) that mediate adaptation to particular climatic environments.
</p>
