<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="caption" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <div class="title">Amplitudes and lags calculated with the feedback model.</div>
 <p>(
  <span class="bold">a</span>) Shows the amplitude for the gST and (
  <span class="bold">b</span>) the amplitude for the global-mean precipitation as a function of period as calculated by the feedback model (
  <a ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq1" href="#eq1">equation (1)</a>). The dashed patterns denote solutions for different values of the applied forcing and the solutions for different values of 
  <span class="italic">α</span> are coloured. Note that 
  <span class="italic">α</span>
  <sub>M</sub> denotes the value obtained by solving the system of two equations that result from applying our GCM results of the simulations with a planetary semimajor axis of 1.165 a.u. in the Kepler-35 system for each 
  <span class="italic">O</span>
  <sub>B</sub> and 
  <span class="italic">O</span>
  <sub>P</sub> separately to 
  <a ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq1" href="#eq1">equation (1)</a>. The subscript ‘B' denotes the binary orbital period and the subscript ‘P' the planetary orbital period. The parameter 
  <span class="italic">β</span> in 
  <a ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq1" href="#eq1">equation (1)</a> is calculated separately for each value of 
  <span class="italic">α</span> such that the amplitude of the forced quantity for each value of 
  <span class="italic">α</span> is the same for a period of 
  <span class="italic">O</span>
  <sub>B</sub>. As a consequence all lines with equal dash patterns intersect at 
  <span class="italic">O</span>
  <sub>B</sub> and 
  <span class="italic">β</span> is inversely proportional to the amplitude of the forcing. The grey vertical lines denote the binary period 
  <span class="italic">O</span>
  <sub>B</sub> and planetary period 
  <span class="italic">O</span>
  <sub>P</sub>. The black marks denote the amplitude of the forced quantities obtained with the GCM for each of the periods. Note that because we calculate 
  <span class="italic">α</span>
  <sub>M</sub> from model results, the marks for 
  <span class="italic">O</span>
  <sub>P</sub> must lie on the red dashed line obtained for 
  <span class="italic">α</span>
  <sub>M</sub> and 
  <span class="italic">F</span>
  <sub>P</sub>. (
  <span class="bold">c</span>) Shows the lag of the gST and (
  <span class="bold">d</span>) the lag of the global-mean precipitation with respect to the solar forcing as calculated by the feedback model (
  <a ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq4" href="#eq4">equation (4)</a>). The different colours denote again the different values of 
  <span class="italic">α</span>. The lag calculated with 
  <a ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq4" href="#eq4">equation (4)</a> is independent of the forcing. Note that because 
  <span class="italic">α</span> was calculated using 
  <a ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq1" href="#eq1">equation (1)</a> the marks denoting the results from the GCM do not necessarily lie on the red line. The orange line is not visible on panels 
  <span class="bold">c</span> and 
  <span class="bold">d</span> as the lag for such a large value of 
  <span class="italic">α</span> is very close to zero.
 </p>
</div>
