<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Annual cycle of climate indicators</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">How do the variations in TSI affect the climate over one orbital period of the circumbinary planet in the Kepler-35 system? The variations in TSI affect different quantities such as the gST and the global-mean precipitation in surprisingly different ways. We choose to focus on these two quantities, as each of them shows a different behaviour. Moreover, the global-mean outgoing longwave radiation (OLR) is interesting, because it is an observable quantity. A spectral analysis of the daily-mean gST of the habitable planet with a semimajor axis of 1.165 a.u. reveals the peaks at periods of 
  <span class="italic">O</span>
  <sub>B</sub> and 
  <span class="italic">O</span>
  <sub>P</sub> (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f2" href="#f2">Fig. 2b</a>). However, unlike for the TSI, for the gST the amplitude of the peak at 
  <span class="italic">O</span>
  <sub>P</sub> is larger with 0.08 K than the one at 
  <span class="italic">O</span>
  <sub>B</sub> with 0.03 K. This supports the notion that the changes in the orbit do affect the climate of circumbinary planets. A spectral analysis of the daily mean of the global-mean precipitation shows two peaks as well (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f2" href="#f2">Fig. 2d</a>). The amplitude of the peak at 
  <span class="italic">O</span>
  <sub>P</sub> is smaller with 0.024 mm per day than the one of the peak at 
  <span class="italic">O</span>
  <sub>B</sub> with 0.050 mm per day. Compared to the mean precipitation, these amplitudes are small at all latitudes and thus do not substantially affect the mean climate. The global-mean OLR responds in a similar way as the global-mean precipitation to the variations in TSI, in that the peak for 
  <span class="italic">O</span>
  <sub>B</sub> is larger than for 
  <span class="italic">O</span>
  <sub>P</sub> (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f2" href="#f2">Fig. 2c</a>). The amplitude of the global-mean OLR is around one order of magnitude smaller than that of the TSI for both periods, implying that the OLR only slightly buffers the variations in the energy-balance of the planet.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Not only does the global-mean response to the double_periodic forcing differ for the aforementioned quantities, but also the meridional contribution of the quantities to the global-mean varies (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f4" href="#f4">Fig. 4</a>). The largest amplitudes of the surface temperature are found at high latitudes, whereas in the case of the precipitation the amplitudes are largest close to the equator. The meridional distribution of surface-temperature amplitude is also different for the periods 
  <span class="italic">O</span>
  <sub>B</sub> and 
  <span class="italic">O</span>
  <sub>P</sub>. The contribution from low-latitudes to the global-mean amplitude of surface temperature is substantially larger for 
  <span class="italic">O</span>
  <sub>P</sub> than for 
  <span class="italic">O</span>
  <sub>B</sub>.
 </p>
</sec>
