<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mean climate states</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">How will variations in insolation affect the mean climate and habitability? The simulations suggest that a habitable climate for an Earth-like planet in the Kepler-35 system with fixed CO
  <sub>2</sub> concentrations (at 354 ppm volume mixing ratio) is maintained in a region close to planetary semimajor axes of between around 1.165 and 1.195 a.u. (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="t1" href="#t1">Table 1</a>). The global-mean surface temperature (gST) of a planet with a semimajor axis of 1.165 a.u. is 291.0 K and that of a semimajor axis of 1.195 a.u. is 271.5 K. For a semimajor axis of 1.140 a.u., the planet goes into a Moist Greenhouse state, whereas a semimajor axis of 1.225 a.u. leads to a Snowball state. In terms of mean TSI we find a habitable climate between 0.954 and 1.004 
  <span class="italic">S</span>
  <sub>0</sub> with TSI values between 0.907 and 0.954 
  <span class="italic">S</span>
  <sub>0</sub> leading to a transition to a Snowball and a TSI between 1.004 and 1.052 
  <span class="italic">S</span>
  <sub>0</sub> leading to a Moist Greenhouse state.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">By performing simulations of the same planet on a circular orbit around our sun, we find that habitable climates can be maintained at a distance of 1.000 a.u. (1.000 
  <span class="italic">S</span>
  <sub>0</sub>) to 1.025 a.u. (0.952 
  <span class="italic">S</span>
  <sub>0</sub>) with planetary semimajor axes of 1.050 a.u. (0.907 
  <span class="italic">S</span>
  <sub>0</sub>) and 0.975 a.u. (1.052 
  <span class="italic">S</span>
  <sub>0</sub>) leading to uninhabitable states (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="t1" href="#t1">Table 1</a>). Thus, the extent of the region for which our planet can sustain a habitable climate in Kepler-35 in terms of TSI is comparable to that in our solar system (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="t1" href="#t1">Table 1</a>). However, due to the increased overall TSI, the habitability spans a somewhat larger range of planetary semimajor axes. This suggests that circumbinary systems similar to the one studied here would be good candidates to look for habitable planets. The gST is higher in the two colder states of the aquaplanet in our solar system than at similar TSI in the Kepler-35 system. The Bond albedo of the aquaplanet in our solar system is somewhat higher than that of the same aquaplanet in a similar climate state in the Kepler-35 system (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="t1" href="#t1">Table 1</a>), because of the slight red-shift of the combined spectrum of Kepler-35 AB.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We find three regimes of stable steady-states of our aquaplanet: The Snowball regime, the Earth-like regime and the Moist Greenhouse regime (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f3" href="#f3">Fig. 3</a>) that all have a similar temporal-mean structure of surface temperatures and of the large-scale circulation on the aquaplanet in the Kepler-35 and the aquaplanet in our solar system (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f3" href="#f3">Fig. 3</a>). However, when the annual cycle is considered, the imprint of the fluctuations of the TSI is clearly visible for planets around Kepler-35, especially at low surface temperatures (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f1" href="#f1">Fig. 1</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We find the transition to a hot uninhabitable state in the Kepler-35 slightly further away from the centre of mass of the system than a recent estimate of around 1.103 a.u. (ref. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b17" href="#b17">17</a>). The maximum TSI to cause global-glaciation in our solar system with fixed CO
  <sub>2</sub> concentrations is in good agreement with a study performed recently with another GCM in a similar setup
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b18" href="#b18">18</a>, but is much closer to the sun than in 1D models that use variable CO
  <sub>2</sub> concentrations
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b17" href="#b17">17</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b19" href="#b19">19</a>. A study conducted with an LEBM found the transition to a hot uninhabitable state in the Kepler-35 system to lie at around 0.65 a.u. (ref. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b6" href="#b6">6</a>) and thus considerably closer to the stars than in our simulations. The LEBM lacks the vertical dimension that is necessary to represent the climate instabilities at higher temperatures. Hence, the model is neither able to produce a Runaway Greenhouse
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b20" href="#b20">20</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b21" href="#b21">21</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b22" href="#b22">22</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b23" href="#b23">23</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b24" href="#b24">24</a> nor cloud-induced instabilities found in this and two previous studies that lead to a transition from a habitable state to a Moist Greenhouse state
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b13" href="#b13">13</a>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b25" href="#b25">25</a>. This explains why the transition to a hot uninhabitable state occurs so close to stars in ref. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b6" href="#b6">6</a>. In contrast, the minimum planetary semimajor axis to trigger a global glaciation with the same LEBM is in close agreement with ours
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b6" href="#b6">6</a>, because the LEBM captures the large ice-cap instability that causes the transition to the Snowball in both energy-balance models
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b26" href="#b26">26</a> and GCMs
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b27" href="#b27">27</a>.
 </p>
</sec>
