<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Periodic variations in total solar irradiance</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Owing to changes in the distance of the planet relative to the two stars of the Kepler-35 system, the total solar irradiance (TSI) varies with time. The changes in the TSI of a planet orbiting the Kepler-35 binary show a double periodic behaviour (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f1" href="#f1">Fig. 1a,b,d,e</a>). For a (habitable) planet with a semimajor axis of 1.165 a.u., these periods are of around 22 and 360 Earth-days. The oscillation with a period of approximately 22 Earth-days is caused by the rotation of the stars around the common centre of mass and will henceforth be denoted by 
  <span class="italic">O</span>
  <sub>B</sub>. The maximum of TSI with respect to 
  <span class="italic">O</span>
  <sub>B</sub> is attained when the more luminous star is closest to the planet (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f1" href="#f1">Fig. 1</a>, 
  <span class="italic">t</span>
  <sub>1</sub>) and the minimum when the less luminous star is closest (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f1" href="#f1">Fig. 1</a>, 
  <span class="italic">t</span>
  <sub>3</sub>). The oscillation with a period of around 360 Earth-days is caused by the eccentricity of the planetary orbit and will henceforth be denoted by 
  <span class="italic">O</span>
  <sub>P</sub>. The maximum of that oscillation is reached when the planet is closest to the centre of mass (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f1" href="#f1">Fig. 1</a>, 
  <span class="italic">t</span>
  <sub>2</sub>) and the minimum when the planet is at apastron (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f1" href="#f1">Fig. 1</a>, 
  <span class="italic">t</span>
  <sub>4</sub>). Note that an orbit cannot remain circular around a double star, due to angular momentum exchange between the stellar and planetary orbits. In nearly coplanar systems such as Kepler-35, solar eclipses occur in intervals of around 11 Earth-days and result in a brief but substantial reduction in TSI. An interesting peculiarity of this system is that due to the stellar parallax more than one hemisphere of the planet is illuminated at all times except during eclipses. A spectral analysis reveals that the amplitude of the oscillation of the global-mean TSI (which is equal to TSI/4) with a period of 
  <span class="italic">O</span>
  <sub>B</sub> is 18.8 W m
  <span class="sup">−2</span> and the one of 
  <span class="italic">O</span>
  <sub>P</sub> is 5.5 W m
  <span class="sup">−2</span> (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f2" href="#f2">Fig. 2a</a>). Including the solar eclipses, the daily-mean of the global-mean TSI varies roughly from 300 to 370 W m
  <span class="sup">−2</span> over one orbital period (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f1" href="#f1">Fig. 1d</a>) during the time-span we have considered. Owing to oscillations of planet's orbital eccentricity, the variations in TSI from 
  <span class="italic">O</span>
  <sub>P</sub> change. The climates presented here were evaluated over a 10,800-Earth-day period where the planet's orbital eccentricity was close to the forced eccentricity.
 </p>
</sec>
