<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">One way that negative intergroup relations could be transformed is through forging a more inclusive superordinate identity that encompasses conflicting subgroups (
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gaertner et al., 1993</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gaertner and Dovidio, 2000</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Opotow and Brook, 2003</xref>). Focusing sub-group members on a higher order, superordinate group identity helps to shift the context from one of ‘them’ and ‘us’ to ‘we’. Past research has shown that this strategy can reduce prejudice and discrimination (
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Gaertner and Dovidio, 2000</xref>) because outgroup members are now part of the ingroup and are therefore accorded the benefits of ingroup membership. 
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Batalha and Reynolds (2012)</xref> highlight the importance of superordinate identity as a way to develop more effective global negotiations around climate change mitigation. Drawing on the Actualizing Social and Personal Identity Resources model (ASPIRe model; 
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Haslam et al., 2003</xref>), they argue that negotiations may be more effective if subgroups are formed that reflect the mutual concerns and interests of like-minded nations and that these subgroups then work together to forge a superordinate framework. The ASPIRe model provides a process for forming superordinate identity beginning with identifying the current social identities that people use to define themselves, followed by the formation of subgroups and the articulation of subgroup goals. The final steps involve the overarching organizational group—incorporating all subgroups—formulating superordinate group goals that inform subsequent action. More broadly, the social identity literature suggests that conditions for making a group such as a superordinate identity ‘real’ are accessibility of the identity, fit (as discussed in section “The Fluidity of Social Identity”), and entitativity (i.e., a combination of interdependence, common fate, physical proximity, similarity; 
 <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Oakes et al., 1991</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B80" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Sherman et al., 1999</xref>).
</p>
