<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pgen.1008119.s007" class="supplementary-material">
 <label class="label">S6 Fig</label>
 <caption class="caption">
  <title class="title">Demographic models fit with ABC.</title>
  <p class="p">The general demographic models that were fit with ABC included histories with demes bottlenecking into the present 
   <bold class="bold">(A, B, G)</bold>, historic population expansion 
   <bold class="bold">(C, D, J)</bold>, historic population expansion followed by a bottleneck 
   <bold class="bold">(H)</bold>, and constant deme size 
   <bold class="bold">(E, F, N)</bold>. The shaded circles within the history outlines represent different demes. The actual number of simulated demes equaled the number of sampling localities, which were 10 for YNP 
   <italic class="italic">T</italic>. 
   <italic class="italic">alpinus</italic>, 3 for SS 
   <italic class="italic">T</italic>. 
   <italic class="italic">alpinus</italic>, and 8 for YNP 
   <italic class="italic">T</italic>. 
   <italic class="italic">speciosus</italic>. Demes were simulated under an island model (symmetric migration and identical deme sizes). Per generation migration rates (m) among all deme pairs were equal for the YNP 
   <italic class="italic">T</italic>. 
   <italic class="italic">alpinus</italic> and 
   <italic class="italic">T</italic>. 
   <italic class="italic">speciosus</italic> contrasts, while for SS 
   <italic class="italic">T</italic>. 
   <italic class="italic">alpinus</italic> the migration rates between different pairs of demes were allowed to differ. Solid versus dotted arrows between demes represent potentially different migration rates, while no arrows represent no migration between demes. The parameter m
   <sub class="sub">hist</sub> is the historic migration rate between two demes, m
   <sub class="sub">mod</sub> is the modern migration rate between a pair of demes, t
   <sub class="sub">mig_change</sub> is the number of generations in the past at which the migration rate changes, r
   <sub class="sub">grow</sub> is the intrinsic growth rate for population expansion, t
   <sub class="sub">grow_stop</sub> is the number of generations in the past that expansion stops, r
   <sub class="sub">shrink</sub> is the intrinsic growth rate of population decline, t
   <sub class="sub">shrink</sub> is the number of generations in the past that a bottleneck starts, and 'mod N
   <sub class="sub">e</sub>' is the effective size of each deme at the present. The presence of ‘90’ in the models involving migration rate change and/or a population bottleneck indicates that these demographic changes were set to occur 90 generations prior to the modern sample.
  </p>
  <p class="p">(PDF)</p>
 </caption>
 <media xlink:href="pgen.1008119.s007.pdf" class="media" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <caption class="caption">
   <p class="p">Click here for additional data file.</p>
  </caption>
 </media>
</supplementary-material>
