<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s4" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our findings are consistent with those of previous studies on behavioural divergence across the cane toad's Australian invasion range [
  <a rid="RSOS170789C55" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170789C55">55</a>]: range-edge toads were more exploratory and willing to take risks than were conspecifics from range-core populations. Importantly, the divergence in risk-taking behaviour was seen in captive-raised toads as well as wild-caught animals (and was statistically significant in analyses restricted only to data from captive-raised animals). The divergence in risk-taking behaviour in toads from different ancestral populations, even after the animals were raised in identical conditions, indicates a heritable component to this behaviour. Hence, behavioural divergence across the invasion range in this species cannot be due entirely to plastic responses to different environments.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The distinctive behavioural traits seen at expanding range edges may result from both adaptive and non-adaptive processes. First, traits that enhance dispersal and adaptation to novel environments may confer fitness advantages at the range edge, and hence evolve via natural selection [
  <a rid="RSOS170789C16" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170789C16">16</a>]. For example, ‘risk-taking’ individuals may be more likely to disperse into novel environments where competition for resources (such as food and shelter) and the numbers of pathogens and parasites are reduced by low densities of conspecifics [
  <a rid="RSOS170789C16" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170789C16">16</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS170789C17" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170789C17">17</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS170789C41" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170789C41">41</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS170789C65" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170789C65">65</a>]. High levels of exploration, risk-taking and neophilia also may enable individuals to exploit novel niches and resources [
  <a rid="RSOS170789C21" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170789C21">21</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS170789C66" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170789C66">66</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS170789C67" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170789C67">67</a>]. Even in the absence of such adaptive advantages, however, distinctive behavioural phenotypes may accumulate at the invasion front because of spatial sorting [
  <a rid="RSOS170789C43" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170789C43">43</a>]. That is, the increasingly fast-moving invasion front inevitably is dominated by fast-dispersing individuals, whose interbreeding produces even faster-dispersing offspring [
  <a rid="RSOS170789C5" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170789C5">5</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS170789C43" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170789C43">43</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS170789C68" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170789C68">68</a>]. The evolution of behavioural traits across an invasion range may also be indirectly affected by the rapid evolution of morphological, physiological or life-history traits if there are genetic links between behaviour and these traits (e.g. the ‘Pace of Life Syndrome’ hypothesis [
  <a rid="RSOS170789C69" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170789C69">69</a>]). Other processes such as genetic drift, surfing of deleterious mutations [
  <a rid="RSOS170789C70" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170789C70">70</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS170789C71" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170789C71">71</a>] and density-dependent selection [
  <a rid="RSOS170789C57" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170789C57">57</a>] may also influence the frequency of inherited traits at the invasion front.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Previous research using captive-raised (common-garden) cane toads has documented significant heritability for traits such as dispersal rate [
  <a rid="RSOS170789C57" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170789C57">57</a>], limb morphology [
  <a rid="RSOS170789C58" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170789C58">58</a>] and locomotor performance [
  <a rid="RSOS170789C72" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170789C72">72</a>]. Similarly, heritability of dispersal-related behavioural traits has been documented in the great tit (
  <span class="italic">Parus major</span>) [
  <a rid="RSOS170789C34" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170789C34">34</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS170789C65" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170789C65">65</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS170789C73" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170789C73">73</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS170789C74" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170789C74">74</a>], the red-cockaded woodpecker (
  <span class="italic">Picoides borealis</span>) [
  <a rid="RSOS170789C75" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170789C75">75</a>], the collared flycatcher (
  <span class="italic">Ficedula albicollis</span>) [
  <a rid="RSOS170789C76" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170789C76">76</a>] and the Glanville fritillary butterfly (
  <span class="italic">Melitaea cinxia</span>) [
  <a rid="RSOS170789C77" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170789C77">77</a>]. Our results on cane toads suggest a heritable component to behavioural traits that enhance dispersal, but we cannot quantify heritability without breeding experiments to allow cross-generational comparisons of behavioural traits between parents and offspring.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Heritability and plasticity are not mutually exclusive mechanisms [
  <a rid="RSOS170789C78" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170789C78">78</a>]. Indeed, behavioural plasticity is driven both by environmental conditions and by the constraints of evolved (genetically based) norms of reaction [
  <a rid="RSOS170789C66" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170789C66">66</a>]. However, these two responses are closely related, with reaction norms evolving such as to generate the most appropriate response to any given set of environmental conditions [
  <a rid="RSOS170789C79" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170789C79">79</a>]. Behavioural plasticity often may be beneficial in a novel environment, if it induces an individual to alter its behaviour appropriately and at a rate that fits the prevailing environmental conditions [
  <a rid="RSOS170789C27" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170789C27">27</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS170789C29" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170789C29">29</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS170789C80" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170789C80">80</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Adaptive activational plasticity occurs when an animal has the ability to express a trait (such as neophilia) but only does so in response to the appropriate stimulus [
  <a rid="RSOS170789C66" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170789C66">66</a>]. Activational plasticity may explain why neophilia varied so little among toads in this study (in wild-caught as well as captive-bred populations, and from the range edge as well as the range core). The potential advantage of neophilia at the range edge is clear, as it promotes movement through novel areas and exploitation of novel resources [
  <a rid="RSOS170789C11" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170789C11">11</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS170789C28" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170789C28">28</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS170789C67" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170789C67">67</a>]. Although cane toads from the range core are in a familiar environment, they nonetheless must often encounter novelty (especially, in urban habitats) and neophilic traits may also enhance fitness in this situation. If so, range-core individuals may possess neophilic traits but not express them unless they are exposed to novelty (e.g. during the neophilia trial) [
  <a rid="RSOS170789C1" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170789C1">1</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this study, we investigated whether the behavioural divergence documented in cane toads across their Australian invasion range [
  <a rid="RSOS170789C55" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170789C55">55</a>] is solely due to plastic responses to the profoundly different climatic, physical and demographic environments experienced by range-front versus range-core individuals, or if other mechanisms have a role to play. In keeping with the earlier report, we found that range-edge toads were more exploratory and willing to take risks than were toads from long-colonized areas—and importantly, that divergence was evident even if the toads had been raised in captivity. We thus infer that at least part of the behavioural divergence between range-core and range-edge cane toads in Australia is a result of rapid evolutionary change (i.e. heritable factors, that differ among populations), as has been documented also for a wide range of morphological and physiological traits [
  <a rid="RSOS170789C5" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170789C5">5</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS170789C41" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170789C41">41</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS170789C48" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170789C48">48</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS170789C50" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170789C50">50</a>–
  <a rid="RSOS170789C52" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170789C52">52</a>]. Further work is required to measure heritability in behavioural traits and to determine whether the shifts in these traits during the course of the toads' Australian invasion have been driven by adaptive or non-adaptive processes.
 </p>
</sec>
