<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Extratropical precipitation extremes at a given latitude occur when the atmosphere is warmer than average and are more closely tied to mean temperatures somewhat further equatorward [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">21</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" class="xref">61</xref>•, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" class="xref">62</xref>]. However, they are still expected to respond primarily to changes in mean temperatures in the extratropics rather than the tropics, and recent warming has been greater in the northern extratropics than the tropics. The sensitivities shown in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1a</xref> are based on global-mean surface temperature and do not account for the variation in warming with latitude. Figure 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1b</xref> shows an alternative analysis in which the annual-maximum daily precipitation rates at each grid box are regressed against the area-weighted mean temperature anomaly for the 15° latitude band that contains the grid box. The latitude-band temperature time series are filtered using a 9-year running mean prior to performing the regression. This filtering reduces the influence of short-term variability in regional temperatures which has previously been found to give a different sensitivity of precipitation extremes than long-term climate change [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" class="xref">58</xref>]. The results in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1b</xref> show a higher sensitivity of precipitation extremes in the tropics compared to the extratropics, although the uncertainty in the tropics is large reflecting the sparse data there. The sensitivity for the tropics (30S to 30N) is 9 % K
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup> (90 % confidence interval 6–14 % K
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>), while for the extratropics, it is 4 % K
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup> (90 % confidence interval 2–5 % K
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>). The choice of filter for the temperature time series affects the overall magnitudes of the sensitivities but not whether sensitivities are higher in the tropics than the extratropics. Interestingly, higher sensitivities in the tropics are also found when projections from global climate models are constrained by satellite observations [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" class="xref">58</xref>] as discussed in the “
 <xref rid="Sec6" ref-type="sec" class="xref">Tropical Precipitation Extremes</xref>” section.
</p>
