<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">For the vegetative CWMs, we observed fewer consistent changes in comparison with those previously reported to respond to an altered hydrology (Bernard‐Verdier et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33973-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>; Jung et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33973-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>; Mommer, De Kroon, Pierik, Bögemann, &amp; Visser, 
 <xref rid="ece33973-bib-0046" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2005</xref>; Violle et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33973-bib-0070" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>; Voesenek, Colmer, Pierik, Millenaar, &amp; Peeters, 
 <xref rid="ece33973-bib-0072" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>). There may be several, nonmutually exclusive, explanations to the less consistent response of trait CWMs to the contrasting hydrological settings in our study. First, different adaptive strategies for different species may co‐occur in a community, which may partly explain the relatively weak response observed when comparing the mean trait value of single traits (Bernard‐Verdier et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33973-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>; Douma et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33973-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). For example, some species may have small and thin leaves that facilitate oxygen uptake during submergence (Banach et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33973-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>; Nielsen &amp; Sand‐Jensen, 
 <xref rid="ece33973-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1989</xref>), enabling them to survive under flooded conditions, whereas other species may avoid flooded conditions by elongating their shoots, thereby accessing atmospheric oxygen (Voesenek, Rijnders, Peeters, Van de Steeg, &amp; De Kroon, 
 <xref rid="ece33973-bib-0073" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2004</xref>) as also observed in our study. Second, intraspecific variability was not considered for any of the traits in this study, which may have weakened community responses (Albert, Grassein, Schurr, Vieilledent, &amp; Violle, 
 <xref rid="ece33973-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>; Jung et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33973-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>). For example, many species can elongate shoots and petioles that enable them to survive shallow, prolonged flooding (e.g., Chen et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33973-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>), but such abilities will not be captured when applying mean trait values. Third, we only followed the communities for 3 years after the change in hydrological settings. Altered hydrological conditions will likely mediate fast exclusion of species intolerant of these changes, whereas the establishment of new species relies on their dispersal and establishment within the areas. Therefore, a delay in the response of mean trait values of the community to changed habitat conditions may occur (Oddershede, Svenning, &amp; Damgaard, 
 <xref rid="ece33973-bib-0050" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Sandel et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33973-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>), reflecting progressive filling of available niches within the community, eventually leading to stronger trait convergence (Helsen, Hermy, &amp; Honnay, 
 <xref rid="ece33973-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>; Roscher, Schumacher, Gerighausen, &amp; Schmid, 
 <xref rid="ece33973-bib-0058" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). This delay may be stronger in existing vegetation than in bare plots where colonization and environmental filtering may occur rapidly (Fraaije, Braak, Verduyn, Verhoeven, et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33973-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Fraaije, Braak, Verduyn, Breeman, et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33973-bib-0030" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>) as also seen in the bare plots in our study, which differed significantly in species composition from the existing vegetation. Finally, we did not have traits for all species found in the areas, and the results regarding the response of community‐weighted trait means should therefore be treated with caution.
</p>
