<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="Abs1" class="abstract">
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Purpose of Review</title>
  <p id="Par1" class="p">We present a review of the likely consequences of climate change for foodborne pathogens and associated human illness in higher-income countries.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Recent Findings</title>
  <p id="Par2" class="p">The relationships between climate and food are complex and hence the impacts of climate change uncertain. This makes it difficult to know which foodborne pathogens will be most affected, what the specific effects will be, and on what timescales changes might occur. Hence, a focus upon current capacity and adaptation potential against foodborne pathogens is essential. We highlight a number of developments that may enhance preparedness for climate change. These include the following:
   <list list-type="bullet" class="list">
    <list-item class="list-item">
     <p id="Par3" class="p">Adoption of novel surveillance methods, such as syndromic methods, to speed up detection and increase the fidelity of intervention in foodborne outbreaks</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item class="list-item">
     <p id="Par4" class="p">Genotype-based approaches to surveillance of food pathogens to enhance spatiotemporal resolution in tracing and tracking of illness</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item class="list-item">
     <p id="Par5" class="p">Ever increasing integration of plant, animal and human surveillance systems, One Health, to maximise potential for identifying threats</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item class="list-item">
     <p id="Par6" class="p">Increased commitment to cross-border (global) information initiatives (including big data)</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item class="list-item">
     <p id="Par7" class="p">Improved clarity regarding the governance of complex societal issues such as the conflict between food safety and food waste</p>
    </list-item>
    <list-item class="list-item">
     <p id="Par8" class="p">Strong user-centric (social) communications strategies to engage diverse stakeholder groups</p>
    </list-item>
   </list>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Summary</title>
  <p id="Par9" class="p">The impact of climate change upon foodborne pathogens and associated illness is uncertain. This emphasises the need to enhance current capacity and adaptation potential against foodborne illness. A range of developments are explored in this paper to enhance preparedness.</p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
