<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Climate variables are crucial in simulating the distribution of species. This article mainly analyzed the impact of climate change on the distribution of 
 <italic class="italic">N. jatamansi</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">N. chinensi</italic>s. Refer to other literature, 19 bioclimatic variables with 2.5-min resolution of the current conditions and future conditions (2050s and 2070s) were downloaded from the WorldClim-Global Climate Data (
 <uri xlink:href="http://worldclim.org/" class="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://worldclim.org/</uri>) (
 <xref rid="ref-28" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Suwannatrai et al., 2017</xref>). The 2.5-min resolution could meet the simulation requirements based on the published article (
 <xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bai, Wei &amp; Li, 2018</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Qu, Wang &amp; Zhang, 2018</xref>). These variables are derived from monthly temperature (maximum and minimum) and rainfall data, which express seasonality, annual trends and extreme conditions (
 <xref rid="ref-19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Mendoza-Gonzalez et al., 2013</xref>). The 19 bioclimatic variables with strong biological significance explained the adaptation of species with extreme environmental factors. Here, two greenhouse gas concentration scenarios, RCP 2.6 (the minimum greenhouse gas emission scenario) and RCP 8.5 (the maximum greenhouse gas emission scenario) were selected under the CCSM4 (The Community Climate System Model version 4.0) model in this work. Referring to the research of 
 <xref rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ma &amp; Sun (2018)</xref>, RCP2.6 and RCP8.5 are the most common emissions scenarios. The CCSM4 climate model, which was developed by the National Center for Atmospheric Research of the United States, has been thoroughly evaluated in China. It has recently been verified that the CCSM4 model can better simulate the climate characteristics of East Asia (
 <xref rid="ref-29" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Tian &amp; Jiang, 2013</xref>).
</p>
