<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec015" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Model limitations</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ecosystem modeling approaches are becoming more common as a support tool for EBM by providing quantitative evaluations and synthesis of complex dynamics in ecosystems. However, the complexity makes straight forward model skill assessments [
  <a rid="pone.0152577.ref052" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0152577.ref052">52</a>] very hard and in our case the lack of time series made it impossible. Another limitation of the model is that we did not incorporate possible scope for coral adaptation or acclimatization to changing environmental conditions [
  <a rid="pone.0152577.ref053" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0152577.ref053">53</a>], or the effects of cyclones or changes in nutrient supply from deeper waters as a result of predicted increased stratification [
  <a rid="pone.0152577.ref054" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0152577.ref054">54</a>]. Additionally, the physical state of the ecosystem contributed to the uncertainty of model outcomes as the oceanographic module, used to force water flows and the advection of nutrients and plankton, was based on a ROMS model developed for the Coral Triangle (CT-ROMS; Southwest of Guam) rather than targeted on Guam [
  <a rid="pone.0152577.ref032" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0152577.ref032">32</a>]. This meant that Guam was on the ‘edge’ of the CT-ROMS model domain, hence, not adequately incorporating all of the regional oceanographic initial conditions. Lastly, the positive bias in the model towards functional species groups with a high biomass (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0152577.s007" href="#pone.0152577.s007">S1 Text</a>) likely influenced the relative low response of herbivores compared to invertivores (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0152577.g002" href="#pone.0152577.g002">Fig 2</a>) as scrapers, in particular, had a biomass that was 3 times higher than the observed biomass in 2011 [
  <a rid="pone.0152577.ref026" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0152577.ref026">26</a>]. It is likely that the fishing mortality was therefore set too low resulting in a continued increase in the standing stock biomass of scrapers.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Because of the limitations of the model, the results presented here should only be considered relative to each other rather than in absolute terms. The analysis of management options can be considered as a first step and subject to uncertainty that could be resolved (to some degree) in the future by checking the relative performance of the management options across multiple parameterizations of the model.</p>
</sec>
