<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec005" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Performance evaluation</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Criteria to assess the performance of the scenarios were based on a model simulation with no stressors for ecosystem state conditions and for the fishery the current landings, hence, ecosystem metrics reaching these values were considered ‘best’ (
  <a rid="pone.0152577.t001" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0152577.t001">Table 1</a>). Performance of each scenario was measured at the end of the simulation against criteria for six ecosystem metrics based on the four management goals (
  <a rid="pone.0152577.t001" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0152577.t001">Table 1</a> and 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0152577.s008" href="#pone.0152577.s008">S2 Text</a>):
 </p>
 <div list-type="order" class="list" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>
    <span class="underline">Improved water quality (no additional LBSP)</span>. The metric used to assess the performance of this goal was the ratio of benthic calcifiers to non-calcifiers with calcifiers defined as corals and crustose-coralline algae (CCA) and non-calcifiers as turf and macroalgae.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>
    <span class="underline">Increased reef resilience</span>. Performance metrics for this goal were biomass of different ecologically important herbivorous fishes, as these groups are critical for maintaining coral-reef habitat and reversing macroalgal strands to cropped states [
    <a rid="pone.0152577.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0152577.ref036">36</a>].
   </p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>
    <span class="underline">Enhanced fish biomass.</span> Modeled outcome of total fish biomass was used as the metric for the performance of this goal.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div class="list-item">
   <p>
    <span class="underline">Maintenance of, or improved fishery landings</span>. Performance for this goal was measured by two fishery-related metrics: (a) the number of functional fish groups that are not overexploited, and (b) landings of reef fish.
   </p>
  </div>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To account for interannual variability, we took the mean of the last five simulated years. For ease of interpretation and visualization, the 5-year mean values were normalized over all strategies so that the best result of an ecosystem metric is assigned the value of 1 and all other values scaled accordingly.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Different weightings can be given to the ecosystem metrics in quantifying the overall performance of each management approach. Since managers identified four ecosystem goals and the identified ecosystem metrics are based on those goals, we weighted 1–4 equally and took the average of 2a and 2b for goal 2 and the average of 4a and 4b for goal 4. As the management goals can also be grouped into a conservation component, (goals 1–3) representing the functionality of the ecosystem, and a socio-economic component (goal 4), we also evaluated the cost and benefit tradeoffs between the metrics #1–3 (all weighted equally) and metric #4 by taking the overall average of these two components.</p>
</sec>
