<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Capture fisheries</div>
 <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Volumes of catches and targeted species from Arctic fisheries are presented in Table 
  <a rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" href="#Tab2">2</a>. Catches in Area 18 are small and limited to Russian fisheries in the White and Kara seas (Christensen et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">2014</a>). The major fishing countries in Area 21 are the USA, Canada and Greenland, while Norway, Iceland and Russia are the main fishing nations in Area 27. The USA, Canada and Russia totally dominate catches in Area 67 (FAO 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">2016</a>).
  <div id="Tab2" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Main economic actors, targeted species and volumes landed from Northeast Atlantic (FAO area 27) fisheries in 2014. Volumes in tonnes. Source: FAO (
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">2016</a>)
    </p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th align="left">Country</th>
      <th align="left">Volume</th>
      <th align="left">Share (%)</th>
      <th align="left">Species</th>
      <th align="left">Volume</th>
      <th align="left">Share (%)</th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td align="left">Norway</td>
      <td char="." align="char">2 133 576</td>
      <td char="." align="char">25.4</td>
      <td align="left">Herrings, Cod, Herring</td>
      <td char="." align="char">1 966 681</td>
      <td char="." align="char">23.4</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left">Iceland</td>
      <td char="." align="char">1 075 639</td>
      <td char="." align="char">12.8</td>
      <td align="left">Various pelagics</td>
      <td char="." align="char">1 880 763</td>
      <td char="." align="char">22.4</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left">Russia</td>
      <td char="." align="char">993 083</td>
      <td char="." align="char">11.8</td>
      <td align="left">Cod</td>
      <td char="." align="char">1 322 265</td>
      <td char="." align="char">15.7</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left">Denmark</td>
      <td char="." align="char">693 096</td>
      <td char="." align="char">8.2</td>
      <td align="left">Blue whiting</td>
      <td char="." align="char">1 158 005</td>
      <td char="." align="char">13.8</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left">The United Kingdom</td>
      <td char="." align="char">675 026</td>
      <td char="." align="char">8.0</td>
      <td align="left">Saithe</td>
      <td char="." align="char">280 925</td>
      <td char="." align="char">3.3</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left">Faroe islands</td>
      <td char="." align="char">533 380</td>
      <td char="." align="char">6.3</td>
      <td align="left">Haddock</td>
      <td char="." align="char">267 052</td>
      <td char="." align="char">3.2</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left">Spain</td>
      <td char="." align="char">346 272</td>
      <td char="." align="char">4.1</td>
      <td align="left">Flounders</td>
      <td char="." align="char">262 025</td>
      <td char="." align="char">3.1</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left">France</td>
      <td char="." align="char">310 045</td>
      <td char="." align="char">3.7</td>
      <td align="left">Crustaceans</td>
      <td char="." align="char">226 638</td>
      <td char="." align="char">2.7</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left">Others
       <span class="sup">a</span>
      </td>
      <td char="." align="char">1 644 156</td>
      <td char="." align="char">19.6</td>
      <td align="left">Others</td>
      <td char="." align="char">1 039 919</td>
      <td char="." align="char">12.4</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left">Total</td>
      <td char="." align="char">8 404 272</td>
      <td char="." align="char">100.0</td>
      <td align="left">Total</td>
      <td char="." align="char">8 404 272</td>
      <td char="." align="char">100.0</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
   <div class="table-wrap-foot">
    <p>
     <span class="sup">a</span>Other nations and catch which are not registered on the listed nations
    </p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The main targeted species in the northwest Atlantic (Area 21) are capelin (
  <span class="italic">Mallotus villosus</span>), Atlantic herring (
  <span class="italic">Clupea harengus</span>), Atlantic cod (
  <span class="italic">Gadus morhua</span>), blue whiting (
  <span class="italic">Micromesistius poutassou</span>), Greenland halibut (
  <span class="italic">Reinhardtius hippoglossoides</span>), queen crab (
  <span class="italic">Chionoecetes opilio</span>), deepwater redfish (
  <span class="italic">Sebastes mentella</span>) and northern prawn (
  <span class="italic">Pandalus borealis</span>) (Lam et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">2014</a>; FAO 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">2016</a>). These fishery resources are under stress from past and current exploitation (about 35% of stocks were estimated to be depleted in 2008) (FAO 2010). Some of these stocks have recently shown signs of recovery (Eide et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">2012</a>) but the collapsed cod stock has not yet recovered (Lam et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">2014</a>; Nogueira et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">2016</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Annual landings of all species exclusively from the Arctic region (Area 18) are very low, with only 4 tonnes reported in 2014 (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>). However, catches around 500 tonnes were reported in 2008 and 2010, by far the largest since 1970 (FAO 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">2016</a>) although still very low compared to adjacent regions. The polar cod (
  <span class="italic">Boreogadus saida</span>) spawning stock was particularly large in 2008 (FAO 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">2016</a>), which could explain the large catches. Polar cod stocks experience large variations in this region (Eide et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">2012</a>). Other Arctic species (stocks that appear only in ice-laden waters and spawn at below-zero temperatures) targeted in Arctic Sea Russian fisheries are navaga (
  <span class="italic">Eleginus nawaga</span>) and Arctic flounder (
  <span class="italic">Liopsetta glacialis</span>) according to Christensen et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">2014</a>). The main fishing activity taking place in these areas is inland “
  <span class="italic">small</span>-
  <span class="italic">scale subsistence fisheries among indigenous people (…) mostly</span> [for] 
  <span class="italic">freshwater and diadromous fishes</span>” (Christensen et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">2014</a>, p. 354).
 </p>
 <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Norway is the dominant fishing nation in the Northeast Atlantic but many countries have active fisheries in this area (Table 
  <a rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" href="#Tab2">2</a>). The main species landed in 2014 were herring, cod and haddock (
  <span class="italic">Melanogrammus aeglefinus</span>), together contributing to almost 60% of total catch. The capelin stock was not exploited in 2014 while it represented the largest catch 2 years before (FAO 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">2016</a>). This large variation illustrates the combined effects of a fluctuating ecosystem and the management system in place. When the capelin stock is below a critical level, the management system prioritises leaving the capelin in the sea as prey for cod instead of catching it (Eide et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">2012</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The International Council for Exploration of the Seas (ICES) advises on total allowable catch (TAC), which are then set by governments. The TAC advice for Norwegian spring spawning herring (in areas I, II, V, IVa and XIVa) in 2015 was 283 000 tonnes compared to 1 687 000 tonnes in 2009 (ICES 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">2016</a>). The Northeast Atlantic mackerel (
  <span class="italic">Scomber scombrus</span>) has a larger (and increasing) distribution area, and coastal states have not reached a final agreement on the allocation of quotas since 2007. For that stock, the advice went from 349 000–456 000 tonnes in 2008 to 927 000–1 011 000 tonnes in 2014. ICES estimated that 1 396 000 tonnes were landed in 2014 (ICES 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">2016</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While the fleets from the different nations all target the same common resource, they typically have different structures, with different boat sizes and gear types—often resulting from national institutional constraints. The industry is rather dynamic; for example, in 2013 a new fishery developed along the Eastern Greenland coast targeting mackerel that had recently reached further north in this region and all the way to the Spitsbergen fjords (Jansen et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">2016</a>). Also, quotas for Northeast Atlantic cod peaked in 2013 (and subsequent years) to the highest catch levels in 40 years (estimated to 966 000 tonnes in 2013). Atlantic herring biomass is decreasing in this area, while mackerel landings have been increasing since 2005. However, inter-year climate variations are large. For example, the joint Norwegian Russian Ecosystem survey in the Barents Sea could not survey the Spitsbergen region from August to October 2014 due to increased ice coverage compared to 2013 (Eriksen 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">2014</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Barents Sea is one of the most productive oceans in the world; the economically most important species are the Northeast Arctic cod, haddock and capelin, the latter being the main prey species of cod. Russia and Norway share these fish stocks. Occasionally large numbers of juveniles of the spring spawning herring (essentially a Norwegian Sea stock) flow into the Barents Sea basin, significantly affecting cod–capelin interaction (Huse et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">2002</a>). Figure 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a> shows catches of the main targeted species during the period in the Barents Sea. The figure reveals some correlation between these stocks. After the spring spawning herring collapsed at the end of the 1960s, a large capelin fishery took off in the Barents Sea. When the herring stock recovered, large quantities of young herring entered the Barents Sea in the mid-1980s. They preyed upon pelagic capelin larvae, thus causing a collapse in the capelin stock with a following starvation in the cod stock (Hamre 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">1994</a>; Tjelmeland and Bogstad 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74" href="#CR74">1998</a>; Gjøsæter et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">2016</a>). In the mid-1990s, another inflow of young herring caused a similar decline in the capelin stock but this time new management strategies quickly closed the capelin fishery preventing additional fishing pressure on the capelin stock (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>) (Gjøsæter et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">2016</a>).
  <div id="Fig4" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Barents Sea catches of the main targeted species during the period 1972–2014 (Source: Anon. 
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">2015</a>)
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="13280_2017_954_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
