<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec21" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Diseases and parasites</div>
 <p id="Par57" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate predictions indicate longer and more frequent periods of extreme temperatures (IPCC 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">2013</a>). Higher sea temperatures influence fish growth and disease. Diseases occur in most living organisms and increasingly so in farmed animals because the high biomass concentration in farms provides attractive breeding grounds for pathogens. Temperature extremes close to the fishes’ tolerance levels, combined with oxygen depletion, result in physiological stress and increased vulnerability to diseases. Changes in temperature can also change disease occurrence and spreading patterns in rather unpredictable ways (Gubbins 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96" href="#CR96">2006</a>). Pathogens have often shorter generation times at higher temperatures (Duguid et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97" href="#CR97">1978</a>). Common diseases in salmon and cod aquaculture include fransicellosis, vibriosis and furunculosis, all associated with high water temperatures (Lillehaug et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98" href="#CR98">2003</a>; Samuelsen et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99" href="#CR99">2006</a>). These are expected to become more abundant with increased temperature and occur more frequently throughout the year. However, diseases such as winter ulcers and cold-water vibriosis are associated with low temperatures and should become less frequent with higher temperature. In addition, some parts of the immune system may function more effectively at higher temperatures and better resist infections (Le Morvan et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100" href="#CR100">1996</a>; Eggset et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101" href="#CR101">1997</a>). Most disease outbreaks occur at extreme temperature events. The increased incidence of periods with high temperature will increase the risk of disease (Bergh et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR102" href="#CR102">2007</a>). Climate change may also shift the distribution of particular pathogens adapted to specific temperature ranges. Some exotic diseases may appear and others disappear.
 </p>
 <p id="Par58" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The occurrence and growth of parasites common in aquaculture also depend on temperature. Higher temperatures lead to a shorter generation time, higher production of parasites, and subsequent production losses and increasing mitigation costs. However, many parasites have complex life cycles, hence making it difficult to predict the actual effect from increased temperature. Different species also have different temperature ranges that they thrive within. Increasing temperature could hence result in redistributions of parasite populations. Sea lice (
  <span class="italic">Lepeophtheirus salmonis</span>), the most common salmon parasite (Boxaspen 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103" href="#CR103">1997</a>), is currently more problematic in the southern, warmer areas than in the Arctic. Sea lice spread depends on current patterns and larval stage. These are influenced by increased temperature and expected increase in freshwater runoff. The combined effects of sea lice are difficult to predict. However, infections will probably increase, resulting in higher costs for treatment, reduced productivity of farmed fish and higher infection rates among wild salmon (Bergh et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR102" href="#CR102">2007</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
