<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Iceland</div>
 <p id="Par39" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Only a limited part of Iceland’s coastline is protected against waves and suitable for aquaculture, and hence production is relatively small. Icelandic aquaculture has gone through several phases, with rapid growth in the 1980s followed by a period of stable production in the 1990s and a rapid decline in the mid-2000s when salmon production declined from about 7000 to about 500 tonnes. Arctic charr have had a relatively steady growth during the whole period and cod aquaculture started to develop first in early 2000. Arctic charr constitute about 50% of total value (Table 
  <a rid="Tab4" ref-type="table" href="#Tab4">4</a>). Atlantic cod and Atlantic salmon and some minor production of Atlantic halibut (
  <span class="italic">Hippoglossus hippoglossus</span>), turbot (
  <span class="italic">Scophthalmus maximus</span>), trout and blue mussels constitute the rest of the production. A large share of the overall production originates from land-based systems.
  <div id="Tab4" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Values of Icelandic aquaculture production in 2014 (1000 EUR, Source: FAO FishStat)</p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th align="left"/>
      <th align="left">Land-based</th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td align="left">Arctic char</td>
      <td char="." align="char">27 288</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left">Atlantic cod</td>
      <td char="." align="char">992</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left">Atlantic salmon</td>
      <td char="." align="char">19 032</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left">Rainbow trout</td>
      <td char="." align="char">3196</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left">Blue mussel</td>
      <td char="." align="char">144</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left">Total</td>
      <td char="." align="char">50 652</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
  </div>
  <div id="Tab5" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Box 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Food production and food security in the Arctic</p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" colspan="2">Food production and food security in the Arctic is complex and does not only encompass production and local people’s access to nutrition (The Alaskan Inuit Food Security Conceptual Framework, Inuit Circumpolar Council-Alaska (ICC-AK) 
       <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR109" href="#CR109">2015</a>). Ongoing and emerging climate change also poses a threat to existing food systems and food security by affecting indigenous peoples’ access to wildlife (Gunn et al. 
       <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR110" href="#CR110">2006</a>; Tesar 
       <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR111" href="#CR111">2007</a>; Heleniak 
       <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">2014</a>). For example, climate change alters migratory patterns of Arctic animals and i.e. Inuit hunters are struggling to adapt. Thus, the implications for traditional hunting, fishing, and gathering activities will have crucial local economic and dietary importance, and impact on social and cultural identities (Nuttall et al. 
       <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR112" href="#CR112">2005</a>). Imported foods have increasingly replaced local foods (Kuhnlein 
       <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR113" href="#CR113">1992</a>; Wein and Freeman 
       <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR114" href="#CR114">1992</a>) resulting in higher frequency of obesity, diabetes and heart diseases from increased intake of carbohydrates and saturated fats (Blanchet et al. 
       <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR115" href="#CR115">2000</a>; Kuhnlein et al. 
       <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR116" href="#CR116">2000</a>; Van Oost dam et al. 2005). In addition, marine mammals such as beluga and seals contain higher levels of contaminants, which impacts severely on indigenous peoples’ health. The relation with climate change is uncertain (NCP 2013). Warming may also increase opportunities for local food production in some regions as growing periods becomes more favourable. This means that conditions for crops and livestock farming will improve. A longer open-water season will make transportation more viable throughout the year, something that may reduce costs for local agriculture production inputs like e.g. seeds, fertilizers, fuel, etc. (IPCC 2001). Poor soil, unpredictable climate, and supply costs will still remain a challenge for the growth of the Arctic agricultural sector. In addition, although climate change resulted in warmer summers, they are also drier with potential negative implications for growth. Emergence of new shipping routes resulting from changed ice conditions may also influence Arctic people in multiple ways, however, resulting impacts on e.g. the fishing sector is difficult to foresee.
       <span class="break"/>
       <span xlink:href="13280_2017_954_Figa_HTML.gif" id="d29e1604" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
       <span class="break"/>Photo: Hunting and gathering have historically been the primary methods of supplying food for many local coastal communities in the Arctic. Climate change has influenced migratory patterns of Arctic animals forcing Inuit hunters to adapt. This adaptation has costs in the form of time, money and increased risks. (Photo: Wanny Woldstad, Photographer Unknown–Tromsø University Museum
      </td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par40" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Arctic charr constitute over 50% of total production (Table 
  <a rid="Tab4" ref-type="table" href="#Tab4">4</a>), with Atlantic salmon constituting a large fraction of the remaining half. Rainbow trout, Atlantic cod and some minor production of mussels constitute the rest. A large share of the overall production originates from land-based systems.
 </p>
</sec>
