<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Future climate development predictions indicate that we can expect large-scale changes in the Arctic marine food web the next 40–100 years (Hoegh-Guldberg et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">2014</a>). Possible future trajectories under climate change for capture fisheries (Eide 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">2016</a>) and for Arctic aquaculture (Hermansen and Troell 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">2012</a>) anticipate the movement of aquatic species into new waters, changes in dynamics of existing species, changes in management regimes and new regulations for novel commercial fisheries and aquaculture. Negative consequences are expected for traditional hunting of marine mammals, but for fish populations like Atlantic cod (
  <span class="italic">Gadus morhua</span>) in the Barents Sea environmental carrying capacity may instead increase (Perry et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" href="#CR65">2005</a>; Eide 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">2017</a>). Arctic aquaculture is an economically important business and makes up more than 50% of European Union volumes. The vast majority of this is Atlantic salmon (
  <span class="italic">Salmo salar</span>) farmed in Norway. The sector may face many challenges in a warmer future and some of these, being directly related to temperature increase, are already a reality for the industry. Other more indirect impacts will have more uncertain influence on the economic conditions of Arctic aquaculture production (Hermansen and Troell 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">2012</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate change affects food production and food security in the Arctic in complex ways. It encompasses many different dimensions, including health, pollution and globalisation through integrated markets. To date, there exists no pan-Arctic assessment that provides an overall picture (Arctic Council 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">2013</a>). Box 
  <a rid="Tab5" ref-type="table" href="#Tab5">1</a> presents a snapshot of the broader picture, but this paper limits its aims to reviewing and discussing possible impacts from climate change on Arctic industrial capture fisheries and aquaculture production. These are some of the most important industries in the Arctic and together they constitute relatively large shares of the gross domestic product (GDP) in some countries (e.g. 15% in Greenland and 10% in Iceland).
 </p>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the absence of standard definition (CAFF 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">2013</a>), we define Arctic capture fisheries to include all catches in marine areas in all Arctic and sub-Arctic waters that lie north of the Arctic Circle (i.e. north of 66°33′N, blue circle in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). However, due to reporting structure we also combine FAO statistics (FAO 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">2014</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">2016</a>) with this definition, and relevant FAO fishing areas in the Arctic include the Arctic Sea (Area 18), the Northeast Atlantic (Area 27) and the Northwest Atlantic (Area 21). Not all fishing within these areas is included as it stretches outside the defined Arctic boundary. The Arctic Sea (Area 18) includes Beaufort and Chukchi seas, Hudson Bay, Kara Sea, East Siberian and Laptev seas. The Northeast Atlantic area above the Arctic Circle (subareas I, II, V and XIV of Area 27, Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>) includes the Barents Sea, the Norwegian Sea, Svalbard, the Bear Island, Northeast Greenland, Iceland and the Faroese Grounds, while the Northwest Atlantic area above the Arctic Circle (subareas 0A, 1A and 1B of FAO area 21, Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>) includes part of Baffin Bay and Davis Strait. The Bering Strait being south of the Arctic Circle, we exclude fisheries in Northeast and Northwest Pacific (FAO area 67). In this respect, our definition of the Arctic fisheries area deviates from, for instance, Christensen et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">2014</a>) in that we exclude the Bering Sea and the Hudson Bay Complex.
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Different areal definitions of the Arctic and FAO major Fishing areas (Source: Young and Einarsson 
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82" href="#CR82">2004</a>; IPPC 
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">2013</a>)
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="13280_2017_954_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>FAO fishing regions: Northeast Atlantic, area 27 (red), and Northwest Atlantic, area 21 (yellow)</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="13280_2017_954_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This paper only to some extent discusses areas situated just outside of the defined Arctic boundary. To predict possible expansions or relocation of current activity or species migration into the Arctic under climatic change, a more careful consideration of such dynamic would be needed. Aquaculture is strictly limited in the Arctic and focus is here only on marine industrial farming and dominating production nations.</p>
</sec>
