<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec15" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Management challenges</div>
 <p id="Par47" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The large cod stock in the Barents Sea being distributed over a vast area could be the result of the combined effect of successful management and increased productivity resulting from favourable climate factors (Kjesbu et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">2014</a>). Studies of the Icelandic cod fishery (Mazzi 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">2005</a>) indicate that fisheries management indeed affects the prediction value of climate processes in explaining changes in recruitment and growth. Harvest control rules and precautionary approaches to management could represent more useful stock management strategies compared to using complex ecosystem models including climate variables. Indeed, the complexity of the climate system and lack of knowledge regarding model specification and parameterization effectively hinder improving management decisions (Punt et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">2014</a>; Kvamsdal et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">2016</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par48" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Management of many shared sub-Arctic fish stock builds on agreed shares of the TAC. Redistribution of common stocks due to climate change or other reasons potentially threaten existing agreements and also include new stakeholders and nations that previously were not exploiting these stocks. For example, in the North-eastern mackerel fishery, the emergence of an Icelandic mackerel fishery undermined previous agreements (Jansen et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">2016</a>). The risk of management collapse was not enough to bring the partners together. However, despite the lack of formal agreements, the expected serious overfishing did not occur. Instead, quasi-cooperation contributed to hinder overfishing (Hannesson 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">2014</a>). Although falling somewhat short compared with full management cooperation, the partners shared the basic principles of fisheries management and eventually acted according to their ideas about responsible fisheries.
 </p>
</sec>
