<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec16" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Markets (factor markets and consumer markets)</div>
 <p id="Par49" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate change may also indirectly influence demand for fish products, factor markets for production of fishing effort and the processing industry. Increased public awareness about climate change could put a price premium on products with less negative climate impact, i.e. products in which the production process generates less greenhouse gas emissions compared to others. Hence, demand for seafood could skew towards products that are harvested, processed and distributed in a more climate-friendly manner unless more responsible fisheries preventing bycatch also happen to be more energy intensive creating conflicting environmental objectives. Consumer power is organised to some degree through organisations that certify seafood based on sustainability and/or lesser climate impact (like ecolabelling and seafood sustainability standards such as Marine Stewardship Council, Aquaculture Stewardship Council, Friends of the Sea, WWF, Seafood Watch, KRAV and others). Price premiums have been observed on labelled seafood (Roheim et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" href="#CR67">2011</a>) but it is also criticised for being a necessary market signal in business-to-business marketing, not necessarily towards the customers (Roheim and Sutinen 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" href="#CR68">2006</a>; Washington and Ababouch 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80" href="#CR80">2011</a>; Nøstvold et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">2013</a>). Other studies have observed price premiums for long-line caught seafood in the UK market (Sogn-Grundvåg et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" href="#CR70">2013</a>), but the price premium can just as well come from the extra quality delivered by this fishing gear rather than the environmental concern.
 </p>
 <p id="Par50" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fishing industries worldwide, including all major fishing fleets in the Northeast Atlantic, benefit from heavily subsidised fuel prices (Tyedmers et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77" href="#CR77">2005</a>; Martini, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">2012</a>; Isaksen et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">2015</a>; Waldo et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79" href="#CR79">2016</a>). The fleets’ shares of national emissions are relatively modest (except for Greenland); however, abolishing fuel subsidy schemes could reduce emissions and potentially alter operations and fleet composition. However, since high-water fisheries in these areas often take place in international waters, international cooperation is necessary to avoid leakage (i.e. fuel bunkering abroad or in international waters, with the potential landings going the same way). It is, however, important to compare environmental performance (e.g. GHG emission) of fishing with production of animal proteins from land systems. Captured fish (and farmed fish) can offer more sustainable alternatives (Troell et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76" href="#CR76">2014</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
