<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">A total of three crop management scenarios were designed to analyze biophysical impacts of +2°C on calorie yields (Table 
 <xref rid="eft2292-tbl-0002" ref-type="table-wrap" class="xref">2</xref>). 
 <list list-type="order" id="eft2292-list-0002" class="list">
  <list-item id="eft2292-li-0004" class="list-item">
   <p class="p">The business‐as‐usual (BAU) scenario represents fertilization and irrigation practices around the year 2000, and serves as a baseline for future projection in this study. Fertilization intensity was estimated by computing fertilizer balances for subnational statistical regions (NUTS2). Crop‐specific annual nitrogen (N) and phosphorus (P) fertilizer application rates were estimated from NUTS2 livestock numbers and excretion coefficients as well as commercial fertilizer consumption from EUROSTAT (
    <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ec.europa.eu/eurostat" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://ec.europa.eu/eurostat</ext-link>). Fertilizer demands at NUTS2 level were calculated using crop and forage yields and acreages from EUROSTAT as well as nutrient uptake coefficients (Balkovič et al., 
    <xref rid="eft2292-bib-0005" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). Annual P and N fertilizer amounts comprise both mineral and organic fertilizers expressed in kilograms of mineral N and P equivalent per hectare and crop. Phosphorus was applied as a rigid amount together with tillage operation before sowing, while N amount was used as an upper application limit for automatic fertilization splitting in EPIC. Single N applications were triggered automatically based on crop requirements. As a rule, 80% of the amount applied in the previous season was applied at the beginning of the following season, while next applications were triggered using the same 80% rule always when crop requirements exceeded soil supply, until the annual limit was reached. As a result, N fertilizer is commonly split in two or three applications. Irrigation extent as well as area share of irrigated crops were taken from the European Irrigation Map (Wriedt et al., 
    <xref rid="eft2292-bib-0080" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>). Since spatial data for crop‐specific water application volumes are lacking, we assume that irrigated crops are supplied with ample water quantities to eliminate water stress (Folberth et al., 
    <xref rid="eft2292-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>; Rosenzweig et al., 
    <xref rid="eft2292-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). Irrigation water was supplied to refill soil water content to its field capacity each time when crop stress occurred, while the upper annual limit was set to 1000 mm crop
    <sup class="sup">−1</sup> (Balkovič et al., 
    <xref rid="eft2292-bib-0005" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>, 
    <xref rid="eft2292-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). Rice was simulated only under full irrigation, but without excessive water applications typical for paddy cultivation. The BAU calorie yield was calculated as an average of rainfed and irrigated yields weighted by crop‐specific share of irrigated and rainfed cropland (Section 2.4).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="eft2292-li-0005" class="list-item">
   <p class="p">The scenario P1 is designed to estimate the potential calorie yields assuming unconstrained intensification of the existing rainfed and irrigated production systems. Existing irrigation facilities identified by the EIM (Table 
    <xref rid="eft2292-tbl-0001" ref-type="table-wrap" class="xref">1</xref>) were allocated to all crops to fully compensate for water deficit as described above. Phosphorus fertilizer was supplied automatically in sufficient quantity to entirely avoid P stress (Gerik et al., 
    <xref rid="eft2292-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). The maximum annual application rate of 250 kg N ha
    <sup class="sup">−1</sup> crop
    <sup class="sup">−1</sup> was used to eliminate nitrogen stress on all cropland. To estimate N fertilization needed to achieve the P1 potential yield, the N application rate was distributed automatically by smaller quantities when crop nitrogen stress occurred, resulting in N applications lower or equal 250 kg ha
    <sup class="sup">−1</sup> crop
    <sup class="sup">−1</sup>. The final calorie yield was calculated while the fraction of area equipped for irrigation was used as a weight treating crops equally. Neither pest nor disease effects were considered.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item id="eft2292-li-0006" class="list-item">
   <p class="p">The P2 scenario assumes sufficient fertilization and irrigation in every SimU of European cropland, irrespective of existing irrigation infrastructure. This scenario provides calorie yield estimates close to the biophysical potential. Similar to the above scenarios, all crops except for rice were simulated on all the available cropland to account for possible shifts in future harvested areas. Pests and diseases were not considered.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
