<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="1" sec-type="methods" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate forcers related to Nr</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nr can exert a series of effects on GHG fluxes and on climate systems during its cascade flow. We needed to distinguish these “direct” biogeochemical consequences (i.e., radiative forcing) of atmospheric Nr emission from the “indirect” bio-geophysical climate feedbacks of terrestrial N dynamics through terrestrial GHG fluxes
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b47" href="#b47">47</a>. We considered six climate-driving forcers of Nr (designated as E1–E6 below) and show detailed interpretations in the 
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1" href="#s1">Supplementary Information</a> (
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1" href="#s1">Fig. S1</a>). The common metric GTP is used to reconcile the climate change impacts of diverse climate forcers into the common unit of equivalent CO
   <sub>2</sub> (CO
   <sub>2</sub>e) (
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1" href="#s1">Table S1</a>) for the inter-comparison of the relative contributions over 20-y and 100-y timescales, respectively.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The climate forcers E1–E3 refer to climate change impacts through the effects of the atmospheric Nr species (including N
   <sub>2</sub>O, NO
   <sub>x,</sub> and NH
   <sub>3</sub>) on trapping heat or scattering solar energy. So far, there has been no official national inventory of gaseous Nr species for China. The results from many published studies show a certain inconsistency due to the different approaches used. Rather than calculating the Nr emissions inventory, we compiled Nr emissions from the existing regional and global emissions inventories associated with China, including IIASA GAINS, EDGAR v4, RCPs, and MACCity. The data covered total volumes and sectoral structures of Nr emissions within the period 2000–2005 (
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1" href="#s1">Table S2</a>).We defined the uncertainty (i.e., standard deviation) using the variation ranges of all these inventories. The estimated results are proved to be comparable with the published local studies (
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1" href="#s1">Table S3</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The climate forcers E4–E6 refer to climate-change impacts through the feedback of the atmospheric NO
   <sub>x</sub> and terrestrial Nr enrichment (N deposition and N fertilization) on GHG's biogenic fluxes. We collected the monitoring data of N deposition rates from different sites around China mainly covering the period 2000–2005 from the extant studies (
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1" href="#s1">Table S4</a>). Through the application of ARCGIS 10, an explicit spatial map of N deposition rate around China was developed using the spatial interpolation technique (kriging). The deposition to each land cover type is obtained by overlapping with the nationwide land-use distribution map. In addition, the fertilization of cropland was adopted from the results of Cui 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>.
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b8" href="#b8">8</a>. Because of the greater heterogeneity of global terrestrial ecosystems, we reviewed and aggregated the data for N-induced GHG emission/uptake of China (
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1" href="#s1">Table S5</a>). N-induced GHG emission/uptake factors were estimated for different ecosystem types (
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1" href="#s1">Table S6</a>). In this section, we only accounted for the change in CO
   <sub>2</sub> and CH
   <sub>4</sub> fluxes, except for N
   <sub>2</sub>O, which has been included in the previous atmospheric Nr emission inventory.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Uncertainty analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The quantification of the significances of climate forcers E1–E6 were calculated normally through multiplying the effective Nr volumes by the corresponding metric GTP, so as to reconcile and inter-compare the diverse climate forcers. We used the Monte Carlo Sampling (MCS) and Latin Hypercube Sampling (LHS) methods to simulate and propagate the uncertainties through the calculations, respectively (
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1" href="#s1">Table S7</a>). These methods are based on the principle that the empirical process of actually drawing many random samples and observing the outcomes can assess the behavior of a statistic in random samples. The uncertainties of parameters, activity data, and formulas are propagated through the sequence of calculations. In the MCS approach, we assumed each value in the uncertainty range had equal likelihood and no correlation between the variables. A population of 10,000 estimates was built and ranked in order. The median and 90% confidence intervals were reported. The LHS approach was further used to calculate the uncertainties in our research. All variables were divided into 300 equal intervals. An ensemble of 300 sets of all parameters was selected randomly and ranked in order. The mean and standard deviation were reported. The results of the uncertainty analysis using MCS and LHS were similar. Hence, we only discuss the results of the LHS method here.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Scenario analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on the possible or expected changes of different driving forcers, we set up a new set of three scenarios to depict the future trend of climate change (
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="s1" href="#s1">Table S8</a>). Short-term projections (to 2020) were developed using a “baseline” path of development, which considered abatement options consistent with China's situation and policy. For long-term projections (to 2050), we applied a “storyline” approach similar to that used in the IPCC Special Report on Emission Scenarios (SRES) scenarios
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b21" href="#b21">21</a>. The situation in 2005 was used as the reference and those in 2020 and 2050 as the target years. (i) SRES I–Business as Usual (BAU) scenario is based on the assumption that Nr emissions will maintain the annual increase rate of 2000–2005 with no change. (ii) SRES II–Improvement scenario, builds on the BAU scenario and assumes that the N use efficiency of cropland will increase with an aspirational target of 20% until 2020
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b57" href="#b57">57</a> and a further 20% until 2050, which approaches the level of developed countries
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b27" href="#b27">27</a>. (iii) SRES III-Abatement scenario, is designed to cut 10% of NO
   <sub>x </sub>emissions in accordance with the reduction target of the “Twelfth Five-Year Plan” in 2020, and assumed that the nationwide NO
   <sub>x</sub> removal rate reaches 80% in 2050. Because of the limited C storage of terrestrial ecosystems, the N-induced C sequestration potential is projected to decline 50% and be negligible with the increased N use in 2020 and 2050. The values in 2010, 2030 and 2040 are calculated on the basis of the logistic growth model. In addition, we compared our SRES scenarios with the published Representative Concentration Pathway (RCP), with four scenarios based on different concentration levels (RCP2.6, RCP4.5, RCP6.0 and RCP8.5, with the numbers referring to different radiative forcing levels) rather than emissions
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b20" href="#b20">20</a>.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
