<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">A logistic regression model (
 <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq1" class="xref">Equation 1</xref>)
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b59" class="xref">59</xref> was calibrated for each of the 22 regions to produce a probability map that expresses for each generic land use class the likeliness of occurrence of a certain land use as a function of a wide set of (i) topographical, (ii) climate, (iii) soil-physical and (iv) socio-economic variables considering the 1990 land use status. More precisely.
 <list id="l1" list-type="order" class="list">
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">Height above sea level (m), slope steepness (%), deviation of the orientation of the slope towards the North (°) (i.e. N = 0°; NW &amp; NE = 45°; W &amp; E = 90°; SE &amp; SW = 135°; S = 180°) maps at a resolution of 90 metres were derived from “SRTM Digital Elevation Data”, distributed by “The CGIAR Consortium for Spatial Information (CGIAR-CSI)” and produced by NASA originally
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b60" class="xref">60</xref>.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">Yearly averaged temperature (°C) and total precipitation (mm yr
    <sup class="sup">−1</sup>) map were obtained from a 0.125° × 0.125° climatic grid covering entire metropolitan France distributed by Meteo-France
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24" class="xref">24</xref>.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">Soil’s top 30 cm clay, silt and stone content (%) as well as geometric mean particle size (Dg, mm) and bulk density (g cm
    <sup class="sup">−3</sup>) maps, after combining the 1/1,000,000-scale Soil Geographical Database of France (i.e. based on the European Soil Map) and the French national soil inventory database (i.e. DoneSol 2.0, N = 17,484)
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24" class="xref">24</xref>.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">ARCGIS software was used to map distance to the nearest main route (i.e. classified as “Motorway” or “National route” following the French road network system) as well as population and employment potential, using statistics provided by the National Institute for Statistics and Economic Studies
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b61" class="xref">61</xref> and spatially interpolated using an inverse distance weighted interpolator module.
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
