<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We selected climate surfaces commonly used in climate change and ecological analyses to identify and determine where novel, disappeared, and shared climates are distributed across the state of Alaska from the LGM to modern era. Previous studies have identified multivariate no‐analog climates; however, we compute univariate no‐analog climates as species have been found to be limited by a single environmental factor (Liebig's Law; De Baar, 
 <xref rid="ece35511-bib-0014" ref-type="ref">1994</xref>; Berryman, 
 <xref rid="ece35511-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">2003</xref>; Crimmins, Dobrowski, Greenberg, Abatzoglou, &amp; Mynsberge, 
 <xref rid="ece35511-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>), and we could identify which specific aspects of multivariate climate cause no‐analog climates. Polar regions are currently experiencing the highest rates of warming (Larsen et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35511-bib-0039" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>), making the state of Alaska, USA, an ideal location to study the impacts of spatial scale in climate change. To help clarify the effect of climate grid resolution on estimations of novel and disappeared climates, we analyzed how the amount of fractional area of novel, disappeared, and shared climates vary with climate grid spatial resolution by statistically downscaling coarse‐scale GCM (General Circulation Model) climate (~100 km) at scales ranging from 60 m to 12 km. We compared modeled distributions and fractional area of novel, disappeared, and shared climates across nine Alaskan ecoregions to ask the following specific questions: 
 <list list-type="order" id="ece35511-list-0001">
  <list-item>
   <p>Where are novel, disappeared, and shared climates located in Alaska from the LGM to modern era?</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p>How does the fractional area of novel, disappeared, and shared climates differ depending on the resolution of modeled climate grid data used for analysis?</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
