<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par40" class="p">Although passive fire suppression as a result of land use is included in this simulation following Pfeiffer et al.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>
 </sup>, and burning on used land is largely eliminated in many parts of the world, the PD simulation of LMfire still overestimates mean annual burned area in parts of the world, notably in the western United States, southern Europe, and the Middle East. Because these are PD regions known to be subject to large-scale industrial fire suppression efforts, we accounted for this fire suppression by further correcting the LMfire output in a model postprocessing step. To identify regions affected by potential model bias, we compared modelled burned area with GFED4s at the level of GFED regions, with Europe further subdivided into North and South at 45° N (Supplementary Figure 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">9</xref>). Within those regions where the discrepancy between modelled and observed burned area was ≥90%, i.e., the USA, southern Europe, and Middle East, we assumed that the primary reason for the discrepancy was active fire suppression. To correct this model PD bias in these regions, we scaled the modelled BC emissions by the ratio of GFED4s observed to LMfire modelled burned area calculated at the GFED regional level. This resulted in a slightly &lt;10% decrease to the global BC annual emission flux. In all other regions, we used modelled BC emissions without bias correction because the discrepancy was smaller and we could not justify industrial fire suppression as being the potential primary cause of model-data mismatch. The primary region where simulated burned area remains overestimated by LMfire is in the tropical seasonal forests of South America. This is both a region of rapid land use change over recent decades where anthropogenic influences on burning may not be well captured in the PD LMfire simulation, and where it has already been identified
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>
 </sup> as a place where the process representation of fire could be improved in the LMfire model.
</p>
