<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3" class="p">Here we investigate pre-Columbian demographic dynamics to investigate the resilience of early South American foraging adaptations to periods of abrupt climate change. We focus specifically on the initial transition to the Middle Holocene (8.2–4.2 k cal BP
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">13</xref>
 </sup>), during which South America was characterised by overall more arid conditions
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">14</xref>
 </sup>. Large-scale analyses using of South American radiocarbon data as a population proxy have previously noted exceptionally low relative population around ~8.2 k cal BP
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">5</xref>
 </sup>. We posit a connection between sudden, high-amplitude alterations to hydroclimate and widespread archaeological evidence of upheaval among human populations associated to the mid-Holocene transition. Globally, demographic overturn together with climate change has been suggested as a major driver of prehistoric culture change over this interval, with radiocarbon data proving especially instrumental in this regard
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">15</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">18</xref>
 </sup>. In South America, the broad range of research intensities, historical trends in scholarship, preservation conditions, and site formation processes, against the backdrop of its cultural and ecological diversity
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">3</xref>
 </sup>, requires any analysis to be undertaken in explicitly quantitative terms. We attend to this by assessing relative change in prehistoric South American demography using summed probability distributions of calibrated radiocarbon dates (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>, hereafter SPDs) combined with Monte Carlo simulation as an indirect proxy for demographic patterns over time
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" class="xref">19</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">21</xref>
 </sup>. To contextualise these findings, we also identify the frequency of hydroclimatic anomalies during the mid-Holocene across multiple palaeoclimatic time series (Methods), with the assumption that ecological shifts of direct consequence to human adaptations will track hydroclimatic regimes.
</p>
