<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec033" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results of this assessment indicate that a number of fish and invertebrate species in the Northeast U.S. Shelf are highly or very highly vulnerable to climate change and decadal scale variability (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0146756.g003" href="#pone.0146756.g003">Fig 3</a>). Climate vulnerability here is defined as the extent to which abundance or productivity of a species could be impacted by climate change. This vulnerability results from the relatively large magnitude of climate change projected for the region over the next 35 years (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0146756.s011" href="#pone.0146756.s011">S9 Supporting Information</a>), as well as attributes of individual species. Changes in population productivity have already been observed in the system [
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref004">4</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref008" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref008">8</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref044">44</a>] and the results presented here suggest that these changes are likely to continue in the future, possibly becoming widespread among species in the ecosystem. The results of this assessment also suggest a large number of species in the ecosystem have a high potential for a change in distribution (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0146756.g004" href="#pone.0146756.g004">Fig 4</a>). Distribution changes have already been observed in the system [
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref041" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref041">41</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref042">42</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref075" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref075">75</a>] and have been linked to climate variables and fishing [
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref076" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref076">76</a>]. Finally, this assessment suggests that approximately half of the species included will be affected negatively by climate impacts in the region (e.g., decreased productivity, distribution shifts out of the system). However, positive effects of climate change are expected for some fish and invertebrate species in the ecosystem.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ocean temperatures, shallow-water temperatures, and ocean acidification were the climate exposure factors with the largest magnitude of change expected by 2055, thereby contributing most to the high and very high climate exposure. There is more known about the impacts of temperature than the impacts of ocean acidification on the species in the NE LME and continued research on the effects of these factors should be a priority. The effects of temperature on species biology and ecology are well documented and there are numerous examples of incorporating temperature into models of population abundance and distribution [
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref011" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref011">11</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref014">14</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref077" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref077">77</a>]. These climate induced changes can result in changing reference points for management [
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref011" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref011">11</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref014">14</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref078" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref078">78</a>] and changes in stock distribution, which can also influence management [
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref079" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref079">79</a>]. Given the temperature changes experienced in recent decades and projected for the future in the region [
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref039">39</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref080" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref080">80</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref081" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref081">81</a>], temperature should be included in regional scientific advice and management. Further, research must continue to understand the mechanisms by which temperature affects species and to parameterize these affects for inclusion in population and ecosystem models [
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref082" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref082">82</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref084" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref084">84</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The effects of ocean acidification on species biology and ecology are not as well understood [
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref085" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref085">85</a>]. In recent years, a number of studies have started to fill this gap for species in the Northeast U.S. Shelf [
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref057" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref057">57</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref086" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref086">86</a>]. However, it is often difficult to place the impacts identified in experimental studies into the context of the magnitude of projected change. In the Northeast U.S. Shelf, pH is projected to decrease by 0.08 to 0.12 units by 2055 (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0146756.s011" href="#pone.0146756.s011">S9 Supporting Information</a>). Many of the studies however use treatments equivalent to ocean acidification conditions expected by 2100 or 2200. In addition, many studies use constant ocean acidification levels, but there is a large magnitude of daily, seasonal, interannual, and regional variability [
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref087" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref087">87</a>]. Research is needed that tests the impacts of ocean acidification at the levels expected over the next 20–40 years to support shorter term projections that can be used in management. One example is a recent study with Atlantic Sea Scallop where fishery yields are projected to decrease in the coming decades owing to the effects of ocean acidification [
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref016">16</a>]. Because a meta-analysis shows consistent negative impacts of ocean acidification on mollusc larvae [
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref085" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref085">85</a>] this methodology scored molluscs as very sensitive to ocean acidification (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0146756.s003" href="#pone.0146756.s003">S1 Supporting Information</a>). As these species also exhibit low adult mobility, molluscs were ranked with a high or very high vulnerability to climate change. This should be interpreted cautiously, and highlights the need for more research on species specific impacts of ocean acidification. It is imperative to experimentally examine the effect of ocean acidification on exploited species, incorporate this information into future climate vulnerability assessments, and include these effects in assessment models that evaluate the impact of acidification in the coming decades.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In contrast to the high influence of a limited number of exposure factors, the importance of biological sensitivity attributes was more variable; indicating the diversities in life history strategies among fish and invertebrates species in the Northeast U.S. Shelf. In general, Stock Status, Population Growth Rate, and Adult Mobility were the most influential attributes. Improved understanding of these attributes is identified as priority research areas. There are a number of other species specific needs that are identified in the species narratives (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0146756.s009" href="#pone.0146756.s009">S7 Supporting Information</a>). There is also a need to understand the relative role of climate change in concert with multiple other stressors in affecting population abundance. Here we focused on changing climate but included fishery status and other stressors as sensitivity attributes; stress from climate change will act in concert with other stressors. Including multiple stressors as exposure factors is possible in the vulnerability assessment framework [
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref021">21</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref023">23</a>]; for management to result in long-term sustainability, the important stressors need to be identified and included in management considerations [
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref088" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref088">88</a>]. Fishing is still a dominant factor, but as fishing mortality decreases, the relative importance of other stressors (e.g., climate change, habitat alterations) will increase [
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref008" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref008">8</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref076" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref076">76</a>]. New contaminant and disease concerns are being identified and require more study to understand their effect on fish and shellfish populations [
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref089" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref089">89</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref090" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref090">90</a>]. In addition, although barriers to diadromous fish passage are decreasing, a number of barriers remain [
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref091" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref091">91</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For this study, adaptive capacity was incorporated into the sensitivity attributes. Adaptive capacity includes a species ability to move when conditions change (adult dispersal), ability to acclimate to changes (plasticity in response, generalist versus specialist), and the ability to evolve as a population or species [
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref033">33</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref092" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref092">92</a>]. This methodology incorporated aspects of the first two, but not the third; the genetic ability to adapt to climate change remains under-known [
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref033">33</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref092" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref092">92</a>]. Understanding genotypic and phenotypic adaptive capacity in marine fish and invertebrates should be a priority for future research.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results from this assessment can be compared with detailed studies examining past changes in fish and invertebrate species and projecting future changes. In some cases, these more detailed studies seemingly contradict the results presented here. Population productivity of both the Southern New England Yellowtail Flounder and Winter Flounder stocks has decreased and these decreases have been attributed to changes in the environment [
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref008" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref008">8</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref044">44</a>]. In this climate vulnerability assessment, Yellowtail Flounder was ranked as having a low vulnerability to change in population productivity and Winter Flounder was ranked as having a very high vulnerability to changes in productivity. Similarly, Alewife and American Shad have exhibited some of the greatest shifts in distribution in the ecosystem [
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref041" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref041">41</a>], but the potential for a change in species distribution was low. The results of an expert-based assessment are never going to completely agree with the results of more detailed, empirical and process-oriented studies or assessments. However, expert opinion summarizes current knowledge in a defined framework and can guide future monitoring, research, and modeling studies. Further, the studies described above are not directly comparable with the results of this assessment. The changes in productivity were demonstrated for specific stocks of Yellowtail Flounder and Winter Flounder, those at the southern extent of the range, while this assessment was conducted at the species level encompassing two or three stocks. The directional effect measure estimates negative effects on both Yellowtail Flounder and Winter Flounder. Similarly, the distribution changes in Alewife and American Shad have been observed during the marine phase only. Natal homing is an important part of the life history of these species [
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref093" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref093">93</a>], so changes in spawning distribution are less likely to occur as predicted by this methodology. The important accomplishment of this assessment is to frame climate vulnerability for a majority of managed fish and invertebrate species in the ecosystem and for a number of unmanaged, but ecologically or commercially important species in the ecosystem.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The assessment was done at the species level. There are pros and cons associated with running a vulnerability assessment at finer (i.e. stock) and coarser (i.e. functional group) levels. A previous assessment in the region was performed at the functional group level [
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref030">30</a>] and management in many cases is at the stock level (sub-species) [
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref094" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref094">94</a>]. The analysis by functional group (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0146756.g008" href="#pone.0146756.g008">Fig 8</a>, 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0146756.s012" href="#pone.0146756.s012">S10 Supporting Information</a>) suggests that while “indicator” species or general functional groups can be used, similar species can have different biological attributes and different overall climate vulnerabilities. A stock specific assessment would be more appropriate to fisheries management, but only in cases where regional species vulnerability is different from stock-specific vulnerability. The choice of number of species (or stocks or functional groups) is dependent on the resources available and the objectives of the assessment.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our objective here was to provide a broad examination of climate vulnerability for fish and invertebrates on the Northeast U.S. shelf. There are other approaches to estimating species’ vulnerability to climate change. For example, thermal habitat modeling was completed to estimate available future thermal habitat on the Scotian Shelf [
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref015">15</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref095" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref095">95</a>]. While objectives were similar, the methodologies are different enough that the results provide answers to different questions (projected available habitat vs trait based vulnerabilities). Mechanistic climate-population models are another way of investigating climate vulnerability. Models have been developed for a few species (&lt;10 species) but to complete such detailed analyses for the 82 species included here will take several years at least [
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref011" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref011">11</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref014">14</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref077" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref077">77</a>]. Finally, Bioclimatic Envelop Modeling has been conducted at the global [
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref019" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref019">19</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref020">20</a>] and regional scale [
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref096" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref096">96</a>]. All of these approaches have value and can contribute to informing managers of the challenges and opportunities that result from climate change. Together, these studies indicate that climate change is going to impact fish and invertebrate species for the foreseeable future.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition to addressing scientific questions and identifying important research needs, the results of this assessment can be used by managers in at least four ways. First, the information resulting from the assessment can be used to inform management and regulatory documents, including fishery management plans developed under the Magnuson-Stevens Fishery Conservation and Management Act, Biological Opinions, and Listing Decisions under the Endangered Species Act, and Environmental Impact Statements under the National Environmental Policy Act [
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref097" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref097">97</a>]. Second, the results can be used to guide management actions. The climate vulnerability of 8 species decreases if Stock Status is removed from the analysis: Atlantic Halibut, Winter Flounder, Witch Flounder, Barndoor Skate, Dusky Shark, Porbeagle, Rossette Skate, Sand Tiger, and Thorny Skate. Efforts to decrease fishing mortality on these species might result in an increase in stock size and thus lower overall climate vulnerability. Third, the assessment can contribute to the development of regional Ecosystem-Based Fisheries Management [
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref098" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref098">98</a>], inform spatial management (e.g., management areas for future refuges of vulnerable species), and guide the inclusion of climate variables in single-, multi-species and ecosystem models [
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref099" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref099">99</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref100" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref100">100</a>]. Fourth, the vulnerability narratives are useful for identification of species specific research and management needs as they provide in-depth species specific scores as well as a discussion of earlier climate related studies on that species.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We advocate that the Fisheries Climate Vulnerability Assessment should be conducted iteratively. Most fishery stock assessments are conducted iteratively [
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref101" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref101">101</a>] and we recommend conducting the climate vulnerability assessments following the same interval as the IPCC Assessment Reports. Similarly, Integrated Ecosystem Assessments are planned to be iterative [
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref102" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref102">102</a>]. The implementation of the Climate Vulnerability Assessment Methodology was successful (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0146756.s013" href="#pone.0146756.s013">S11 Supporting Information</a>). However, there are improvements that should be considered for the next iteration. First, bottom temperature and improved ocean acidification projections should be included; both of these would require some form of regional downscaling [
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref077" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref077">77</a>] or higher resolution climate models [
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref103" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref103">103</a>]. Second, the ensemble uncertainty in climate change could also be included formally in the assessment (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0146756.s014" href="#pone.0146756.s014">S12 Supporting Information</a>), along with different emission scenarios and potentially time periods. Third, the next iteration should include an update of the species profiles and rescoring of both the climate exposure and sensitivity attributes. If information on species specific plasticity or evolutionary adaptability exist by the next iteration, this information should be included to improve the evaluation of adaptive capacity [
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref033">33</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref104" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref104">104</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref105" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref105">105</a>]. Fourth, the next assessment should include experts from a broader background than used here. This assessment included only NMFS employees with some outside observers. One of the main objectives of this effort was to provide the first implementation of NMFS Methodology [
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref034">34</a>]. This will not be an objective of the next iteration and efforts should be made to include a broad array of fisheries, protected species, and ecosystem stakeholders. Fifth, there are potential links that could be made between Overfishing Vulnerability Assessments [
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref024" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref024">24</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref025" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref025">25</a>], Habitat Vulnerability Assessments [
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref106" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref106">106</a>] and Social Vulnerability Assessments [
  <a rid="pone.0146756.ref107" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146756.ref107">107</a>]. The vulnerability assessment framework provides a powerful tool that can complement other assessment techniques and support the broader implementation of Ecosystem-Based Management and climate change adaptation strategies.
 </p>
</sec>
