<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec032" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Functional Group Results</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The effects of climate change exhibited some consistency across functional groups. In terms of overall climate vulnerability, Diadromous Fish and Benthic Invertebrate species had the highest vulnerabilities (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0146756.g008" href="#pone.0146756.g008">Fig 8</a>). Some Coastal Fish species also scored very highly vulnerable to climate change. Elasmobranchs and Groundfish groups had no species that scored very highly vulnerable, and Pelagic Fish and Cephalopod species had no species that scored very highly or highly vulnerable. Potential for distribution change also varied by functional groups (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0146756.g008" href="#pone.0146756.g008">Fig 8</a>). Only Pelagic Fish and Cephalopods and Elasmobranchs had very high potential for a distribution change. Diadromous Fish, Benthic Invertebrates, and Groundfish had species with a low potential for distribution change. Similarly, the directional effect of climate change varied across functional groups. All groups had species where negative effects of climate change are estimated and Benthic Invertebrates and Groundfish had greatest proportion of species with estimated negative effects. Only Coastal Fish and Pelagic Fish and Cephalopods had species where positive effects of climate change are estimated within the Northeast U.S. Shelf ecosystem. MDS ordination of sensitivity attributes exhibited some consistency within functional groups but also demonstrated that certain species have attribute that are more similar to species in other functional groups (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0146756.s012" href="#pone.0146756.s012">S10 Supporting Information</a>).
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0146756.g008" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0146756.g008</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 8</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Functional groups and climate vulnerability.</div>
   <p>Number of species from each functional group by overall climate vulnerability (A), potential for distribution change (B), and directional effect of climate change (C).</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0146756.g008" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
