<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec030" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Directional Effect of Climate Change</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on expert opinion of the directional effect of climate change, approximately half of the species were assessed to be negatively affected by climate change in the Northeast U.S. Shelf (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0146756.g005" href="#pone.0146756.g005">Fig 5</a>). Negative impacts are estimated for many of the iconic species in the ecosystem including Atlantic Sea Scallop, Atlantic Cod, and Atlantic Mackerel. In general, negative effects are anticipated for a number of Benthic Invertebrate and Groundfish species. However, positive effects are anticipated for 17% of species including Inshore Longfin Squid, Butterfish, and Atlantic Croaker. The certainty in directional effect score varied, but was &gt;95% for almost half of the species assessed. However, there were species with low certainty (&lt;66%) in all three directional effect categories. By comparing across the climate vulnerability, potential for distribution change, and directional effect scores, species can be identified that are likely to increase in productivity (e.g., Black Sea Bass) or shift into the region (e.g., Atlantic Croaker) or that are likely to decrease in productivity (e.g., Winter Flounder) or shift out of the region (e.g., Atlantic Mackerel).
 </p>
 <div id="pone.0146756.g005" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0146756.g005</span>
  <span class="label">Fig 5</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Directional effect of climate change.</div>
   <p>Colors represent expected negative (red), neutral (tan), and positive (green) effects. Certainty in score is denoted by text font and text color: very high certainty (&gt;95%, black, bold font), high certainty (90–95%, black, italic font), moderate certainty (66–90%, white or gray, bold font), low certainty (&lt;66%, white or gray, italic font).</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0146756.g005" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
