<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Species distribution models and their projections of newly suitable habitat can be useful for land management planning [
 <xref rid="pone.0205677.ref036" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0205677.ref037" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>]. Our results identify a number of locations that ragweed is not currently present but may expand into in the future and thus become a new or increased health concern. For example, metropolitan areas in the Northeast, such as Albany, New York, Montpelier, Vermont, Concord, New Hampshire, and Augusta, Maine are all at increased risk of ragweed expansion in the next 30 years. An expansion of ragweed at its northern margins of its current distribution is generally consistent with European studies [
 <xref rid="pone.0205677.ref018" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0205677.ref019" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0205677.ref021" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0205677.ref038" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>]. Therefore, Northeast metropolitan areas may be well advised to start monitoring for ragweed presence and potentially increase eradication efforts by local weed control boards. By contrast, some areas in southern Vermont and New Hampshire and parts of Massachusetts may become less suitable for ragweed by the end of the century. These areas may provide opportunities to displace ragweed with later-successional species [
 <xref rid="pone.0205677.ref039" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>]. It is important to recognize that ragweed is adapted to a diversity of habitats and tends to grow competitively on disturbed soils [
 <xref rid="pone.0205677.ref010" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. Therefore, urban development and planning efforts may consider minimizing the exposure of disturbed sites by requiring adequate soil coverage with other vegetation, or timing soil disturbance to occur in winter and spring, while ragweed is not dispersing.
</p>
