<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The spring time temperatures during bud break in 2014 and 2015 were very different (Figure 
 <xref rid="ece33352-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" class="xref">4</xref>). In 2014, several fluctuating warm periods provoked bud opening to the first stage even before recording started. However, bud break was over 8 days earlier in 2015. An effect of enhanced temperature on bud break, as similarly detected by Strømme et al. (
 <xref rid="ece33352-bib-0065" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>), was recorded in 2014 and to a small degree in 2015. Earlier studies show that spring events, such as leaf unfolding or needle flush, are particularly sensitive to temperature (Lechowicz, 
 <xref rid="ece33352-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1995</xref>; Sarvas, 
 <xref rid="ece33352-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1972</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ece33352-bib-0063" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1974</xref>). In accordance with our results on the after effect of the treatments in 2015, Fu et al. (
 <xref rid="ece33352-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>) found that 
 <italic class="italic">Betula pendula, Fagus sylvatica,</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Quercus robur</italic> were affected by the temperatures from the previous year. It can be speculated that in addition to the carry‐over effect of the temperature treatment, the enhanced bud break in intact individuals in 2015 could have also resulted from the previous year high autumn temperature which might have influenced the subsequent bud burst. Elevated temperature can alter the sugar levels in buds (Pagter, Andersen, &amp; Andersen, 
 <xref rid="ece33352-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>), and bud break is associated with low levels of soluble sugars (Lipavská, Svobodová, &amp; Albrechtová, 
 <xref rid="ece33352-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2001</xref>). In this case, the enhanced temperature would have reduced the sugar concentrations, as was also seen in 
 <italic class="italic">B. pendula</italic> seedlings (Riikonen et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33352-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>), which could be the mechanism behind the temperature‐forced bud break in 2014 and 2015.
</p>
