<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">According to our hypothesis, the bud phenology of male and female aspens differed in their responses to environmental changes. The males of some species of 
 <italic class="italic">Populus</italic> are more growth‐oriented than females (Lloyd &amp; Webb, 
 <xref rid="ece33352-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1977</xref>). In a greenhouse experiment, the males of 
 <italic class="italic">P. tremula</italic> were taller had higher shoot biomass and greater leaf area when compared to females (Randriamanana et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33352-bib-0057" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). This may mean that male bud development and entry into the vegetative phase may be faster than in females. In 
 <italic class="italic">P. tomentosa</italic>, An et al. (
 <xref rid="ece33352-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>) found that during the time of floral budding, the male buds normally progress and senesce earlier than female floral buds. This is due to the female requirement for more resources to prepare for reproduction than that of males (Hultine, Bush, West, &amp; Ehleringer, 
 <xref rid="ece33352-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>; McDowell, McDowell, Marshall, &amp; Hultine, 
 <xref rid="ece33352-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2000</xref>; Pickering &amp; Arthur, 
 <xref rid="ece33352-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2003</xref>). In a study conducted with one, four‐ and ten‐year‐old 
 <italic class="italic">Populus</italic> × 
 <italic class="italic">canadensis</italic> aimed at checking the expression of miRNA's during vegetative phase change
 <italic class="italic">,</italic> it was found that the change is evident in minor changes in leaf shape and internode length (Wang et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33352-bib-0068" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>). Our experimental plants changed leaf shape from triangular form to round form over the study years, demonstrating their transition from juvenile to vegetative phase. It may be that during the phase change, females show more responsive growth patterns compared to males, in order to compensate for their reproductive requirements.
</p>
