<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec001" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1.1 Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The marine fishing industry is currently failing to realize economic benefits estimated to be between USD 51 and 83 billion annually [
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref001">1</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref003" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref003">3</a>]. These unrealized benefits are largely due to stocks whose biomass has been reduced below levels that generate maximum sustainable yields (MSY), which leads to their continued exploitation generating higher costs. While some regions are experiencing a growth in fish catches due to rebuilding fish stocks [
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref004">4</a>], global catches are declining at a rate of 1.2 million tonnes annually [
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref005" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref005">5</a>]. These current trends illustrate the global picture of the state of the oceans, and point to the lost economic potential of capture fisheries. However, it also presents a major opportunity and incentives to rebuilding stocks globally. Through strong rebuilding, the benefits of increased catches and lower costs of fishing could outweigh short-term costs of temporarily reduced catches within a decade or so [
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref002" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref002">2</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A major challenge to addressing these potentially unrealized profits at the global scale is the opacity of seafood supply chains. Seafood is among the most highly traded food commodities [
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref006" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref006">6</a>], but its supply chains often include illegal and unreported fish or fish that is mis-labelled [
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref007" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref007">7</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref008" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref008">8</a>]. Thus, the stock-origin of much of the globally traded seafood supply is not readily ascertainable. Unreported and especially illegal fisheries production can be implicated in unsustainable fisheries practices, and creates challenges for the proper management of resources. Therefore, one major obstacle to separating sustainably and unsustainably caught seafood is the lack of transparency and traceability in industry supply chains.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In response to concerns about overfishing and the lack of transparency, as well as the general state of marine fisheries, many certification, ecolabeling and traceability schemes have been proposed, each with their own criteria of what makes a fishery or aquaculture system ‘sustainable’. For fisheries, the largest ecocertification initiative is the Marine Stewardship Council, which now covers 14% of reported global landings, and is aiming for 33% by 2030 [
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref009">9</a>]. However, this will require voluntary buy-in from the fishing companies involved, thus limiting the scope of these certification schemes’ effectiveness on the industry outside their program. In addition, the adequacy and enforcement of ecocertification criteria have come under scrutiny [
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref010" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref010">10</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref011" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref011">11</a>]. For example, the 
  <span class="italic">Star Shrimper XXV</span> is certified as a sustainable prawn fishing vessel under the ‘Friend of the Sea’ criteria because it uses nets that reduce turtle bycatch; however, the vessel was detained for fishing in the Exclusive Economic Zone (EEZ) of Liberia without an access agreement and while not using their selective fishing gear [
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref012">12</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One alternative to ecocertification and labeling schemes is an external review that links fishing practices of specific fish stocks to individual fishing companies, to better inform owners and potential investors. To gain a better coverage of the fishery practices of the seafood industry, we take this latter approach with regards to large seafood companies some of which are already involved in other seafood sustainability initiatives outside ecocertification programs [
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref013">13</a>]. Previous external reviews of fishing companies have demonstrated company links to illegal fishing, in addition to human trafficking and other illicit practices [
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref014">14</a>]. Clearly there are reputational and legal risks to these companies engaged in these activities, but here we focus on the biological sustainability of the fisheries they are engaged in and its implications for their economic returns.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our objective is to link specifically identified fisheries stocks with declining catches to the companies that are the key actors in those particular fisheries. Thereby, we aim to demonstrate the potential economic losses, or unrealized revenues and profits, at the specific company level from fisheries targeting overfished stocks, or not realizing the full potential benefits of currently lightly fished stocks.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We have developed an approach that attempts to help clarify the opaque environment that characterizes many seafood supply chains. Through a diversity of methods, we characterize current fishing practices of companies and relate a company’s products to the fishing grounds and the fish stocks targeted. We then evaluate the changing revenue streams from these fisheries due to changing fish populations and evaluate the fishery stock-status using established catch-based indicators of stock health applicable to every fishery in the world. It is worth noting that in current application, we explore linkages at the origins of the seafood supply chains (i.e., fish in the ocean with the companies that catch them). However, this method could be easily extended to processors and sellers downstream; hence encompasing complete seafood supply chains. We acknowledge the uncertainties linked to the latter approach, although similar uncertainties exist in other stock assessment approaches. However, the data we use reflect a collection of industry, national, reconstructed, and peer-reviewed data that together create a reasonably complete picture of these fisheries.</p>
</sec>
