<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec004" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2.2 Menhaden case study</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another major, although much smaller, reduction fishery is for Atlantic (
  <span class="italic">Brevoortia tyrannus</span>) and Gulf menhaden (
  <span class="italic">B</span>. 
  <span class="italic">patronus</span>) in the Southeastern USA. There, menhaden play an important role in ecosystems as a forage fish species, i.e., a major source of food for higher-trophic level organisms [
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref047" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref047">47</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref048" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref048">48</a>]. The fisheries for these two species are managed at a regional level by the Atlantic and Gulf States Marine Fisheries Commissions (ASMFC and GSMFC, respectively).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Omega Protein (owned by Cooke Aquaculture) takes over 75% of all Atlantic menhaden landings [
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref049" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref049">49</a>] and jointly, Omega Protein Corporation and Daybrook Fisheries (owned by the Oceana Group) are the major fishing companies for Gulf menhaden. These companies operate in federal- and state-controlled waters of the USA and are thus subject to the regulations of the ASFMC and GSMFC. These two species are fished exclusively with purse seines when caught by reduction fisheries [
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref050" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref050">50</a>], and have very low rates of by-catch and discards [
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref051" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref051">51</a>]. If considered together, the menhaden fisheries are the second largest fishery in US waters by tonnage [
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref050" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref050">50</a>], even though they are much smaller than in the past [
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref052" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref052">52</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We determined company vessel ownership through company reports [
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref053" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref053">53</a>] and third-party sources [
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref054" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref054">54</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref055" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref055">55</a>]. Landings data were obtained from the National Marine Fisheries Service using taxon identifier ‘Menhaden’ separated by Atlantic and Gulf regions [
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref050" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref050">50</a>]. Minor landings of other menhaden species (i.e., 
  <span class="italic">B</span>. 
  <span class="italic">gunteri</span> and 
  <span class="italic">B</span>. 
  <span class="italic">smithi</span>) may be included in the data from the National Marine Fisheries Service, but are unlikely to influence the general pattern observed. Catch per unit effort data were used as an indicator of relative abundance. CPUE data were obtained from each stock’s most recent stock assessment [
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref047" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref047">47</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref048" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref048">48</a>]. The intrinsic rate of growth parameter (
  <span class="italic">r</span>) was obtained from FishBase [
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref040" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref040">40</a>] using two standard deviations from the mean as the lower and upper bound estimates for Atlantic and Gulf menhaden (0.43–1.16 and 0.32–1.38 year
  <span class="sup">-1</span>, respectively). The landings, CPUE, and biological priors were used in the BSM and CMSY method [
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref018" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref018">18</a>]. The most recent ex-vessel prices were used from the National Marine Fisheries Service [
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref050" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref050">50</a>]. The cost of fishing was based on Atlantic menhaden, taking total costs of their operations minus processing plant labor costs (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0207768.s001" href="#pone.0207768.s001">S1 Table</a>) [
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref056" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref056">56</a>]. While this may slightly overestimate the cost per tonne of catch, it kept our estimates of potential profits conservative and thus this estimation was used for both Atlantic and Gulf menhaden.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As there are only two companies that fish Gulf menhaden, their actual individual landings are obscured by privacy laws [
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref057" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref057">57</a>]. However, separating their catch by known catch proportions reported by each company was possible based on landings by area and company reports [
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref049" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref049">49</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref053" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref053">53</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref058" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref058">58</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
