<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec009" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.1 Overall</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here, we were able to apply this method to two large case studies and the nine major companies involved in their exploitation. The total potentially unrealized annual profits for the two case studies presented here are USD 8 million for the Peruvian anchoveta and nearly USD 16 million for the US menhaden fisheries. These unrealized profits are based on the assumption that these fisheries can be managed to maintain biomass levels equal to or larger than required to produce MSY (B
  <sub>MSY</sub>) on an ongoing basis, and fisheries yield can be at MSY or F
  <sub>MSY</sub> when biomass is below B
  <sub>MSY</sub>. For clarity and simplicity, we demonstrated these potential unrealized benefits for two low-value fisheries, with high landings, and heavily concentrated fishing company actors. The biomass of the anchoveta stocks are below levels that optimize or maximize potential catches (i.e., B
  <sub>MSY</sub> levels), and thus would benefit from stock rebuilding. In contrast, the menhaden stocks are at healthy biomass levels with regards to estimated MSY, and there is thus flexibility for carefully increased catch, revenue and profits. These unrealized revenues and profits can motivate stakeholders at different levels in the fisheries sector, including investors in these companies, due to the unrealized potential benefits originating from suboptimal levels of fisheries stocks. In addition, fisheries with healthy biomass levels are more likely to qualify for eco-certification programs [
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref059" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref059">59</a>] that may receive a price premium [
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref060" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref060">60</a>] giving an extra incentive for these companies.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While the present study has focused our approach on fisheries examples where the stock biomass is lower (anchoveta) or higher than B
  <sub>MSY</sub> (menhadens), there is also the extreme case of overfishing leading to collapsed stocks. While not fitting the strict economic definition of ‘stranded assets’, where assets must be subject to regulatory or legislative changes rather than biological changes [
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref061" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref061">61</a>], fish stocks that collapse are indeed a form of ‘lost’ or unusable assets. For companies invested in such heavily overfished or even collapsed stocks that are then likely subject to more stringent limitations of fishing pressure, these fish stocks represent a form of stranded assets whose values to the companies are reduced [
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref061" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref061">61</a>]. When quotas for stocks cannot be realized due to low biomass of the fish stock, the owner’s resource rents are reduced to zero. However, even without fishing and resource rents being reduced to zero, continued fishing of stocks in a suboptimal state reduces long-term revenues. Thus, the concept of stranded assets can be extended to where overexploitation reduces the value of fisheries assets marginally or completely.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The scenario analysis of the anchoveta fisheries conducted here, comparing the Optimized-F scenario and the PGY scenario to the baseline scenario of actual fisheries and stock conditions illustrated differences in landings and revenues under different management scenarios. While we were able to demonstrate potentially more optimal fishing mortality rates to maximize these differences in the Optimize-F scenario, it is somewhat unrealistic for fisheries managers as they operate in an environment of imperfect information. However, the PGY scenario often had similar results with clear rules that can be operated on given knowledge about the status of the stock. The catch and revenue difference can be substantial over the time period analyzed, but on an annual basis are quite comparable for the Northern stock. Thus, it demonstrates the current high performance of the managers to maximize anchoveta yields and revenues of this fishery even though they could be higher if B &gt; B
  <sub>MSY</sub> as in the case of the menhaden fisheries.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We compared current and past landings to landings under modeled scenarios that rebuild the stocks with either optimal fishing mortality rates or a precautionary harvest control rule (0.91·MSY). It is important to recognize that multiple fisheries on a variety of species in the same area cannot achieve MSY simultaneously for all species due to ecosystem interactions [
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref020">20</a>]. It is thus important to retain a precautionary approach and not maximize landings (in terms of MSY) and ignore the ecological function that species fill in their ecosystem [
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref062" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref062">62</a>]. The PGY scenario models this more closely to reality as there is a precautionary limit placed on MSY with reductions for when the stock is below B
  <sub>MSY</sub>. Our example for anchoveta would eventually lead to increased landings and revenues, but only after having increased biomass and decreased annual variability in biomass. Our case study for Gulf menhaden was informed by the GSFMC that incorporates menhaden’s role as a forage fish into their fishing limits [
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref048" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref048">48</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Both case studies demonstrated the benefits of rebuilding fisheries stocks at the scale of individual companies acting in these fisheries. In the case of the anchoveta, currently unrealized benefits could only be attained after rebuilding the stock biomass to levels above B
  <sub>MSY</sub>, while the menhaden fishery with healthy biomass levels illustrated the ready availability for increased landings and profit potential, should appropriate economic drivers emerge such as increased prices for fishmeal or lower costs of fishing. It may be helpful to quantify potentially unrealized benefits at different scales and to express them in units relevant to the different stakeholders in the fisheries sector and beyond. Not only could it be important to those actors directly involved, such as company owners, shareholders and investors, but also to other important stakeholders such as governments that face foregone tax revenue or licensing fees due to overfished stocks or by not optimizing potential benefits of their natural resources. Unfortunately, governments far too often support fisheries well past the point of being economically profitable within ecologically sustainable limits through extensive harmful subsidies [
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref063" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref063">63</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref064" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref064">64</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
