<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec010" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.2 Anchoveta</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The anchoveta stocks are still in a depleted state. This is partially due to overfishing, particularly in the Southern stock, but also due to fluctuations driven by El Niño and La Niña events, and increasing variability due to climate change [
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref034">34</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref065" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref065">65</a>]. Our findings generally concur with the latest numbers of the national stock assessments conducted by PRODUCE and Chile’s Instituto de Fomento Pesquero [
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref036">36</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref039">39</a>]. The large differences in the modeled scenarios’ landings for the Southern stock are due to the current low biomass of leading to lower catches over the earlier years, whereas, the North-Central stock is fished close to the level in the Optimized-F and PGY scenarios proposed here. The North-Central stock’s biomass declined recently in the observed and modeled scenarios due to strong recruitment anomalies caused by recent El Niño and La Niña events [
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref039">39</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref066" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref066">66</a>]. Both anchoveta stocks could have delivered higher landings in the past if biomass levels would have been maintained at higher levels by pro-active management action. Increasing the anchoveta biomass by reducing fishing mortality rates to levels at or below F
  <sub>MSY</sub> or instituting a precautionary limit on MSY (see 
  <a ref-type="sec" rid="sec002" href="#sec002">Methods</a> for further details) could benefit these fishing companies in the future.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">However, it is important to highlight that rebuilding the stocks has a cost. The proposed theoretical MSY strategy generated losses in the earlier years of its implementation, particularly in the Southern stock (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0207768.g002" href="#pone.0207768.g002">Fig 2</a>). This shows that rebuilding the shared stock has an initial cost for Peruvian companies, but they benefit from the increased (and likely more stable) landings that result from a stock with higher average biomass in the later period (i.e., in the medium-term: after 10 years). Reported landings in Peru were higher than the scenarios’ landings for those initial years because the model restricted the higher levels of fishing to prevent overfishing the stock (F &gt; F
  <sub>MSY</sub>). Thus, the current low landings reported by Peru in the Southern stock are likely due to continued overfishing by both countries pressuring the stock into a depleted state (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0207768.g002" href="#pone.0207768.g002">Fig 2</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Recent landings of anchoveta have been volatile (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0207768.s002" href="#pone.0207768.s002">S2</a> and 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0207768.s003" href="#pone.0207768.s003">S3</a> Tables), although they were much more variable historically, particularly in the 1970s and 1980s. The current management regime based on individual transferrable quotas (ITQ) has the potential to improve the state of the anchoveta resource and fisheries over time [
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref067" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref067">67</a>], as long as the high data and assessment requirements for ITQ systems are maintained and management action is swift and proactive with regards to setting and adjusting annual allowable catch limits [
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref068" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref068">68</a>]. However, environmental fluctuations and the large effect of El Niño and La Niña events may continue to have negative repercussions for this industry [
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref034">34</a>]. Based on current fishing exploitation [
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref036">36</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref069" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref069">69</a>], there could be greater benefits realized in terms of higher landings and higher economic returns if biomass levels were to be increased and maintained at higher levels based on our estimates of B
  <sub>MSY</sub>. A constant MSY does not optimize yields of this fishery due to the high variation in stock sizes [
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref070" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref070">70</a>], but policies that optimize and adjust fishing mortality rates annually based on overall higher biomass levels have the potential to achieve higher landings and thus revenues.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is particularly important to highlight that the unrealized potential benefits of the industrial anchoveta fishery could be much higher if alternative uses for the landings were considered, namely direct human consumption rather than reduction [
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref030">30</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref035">35</a>]. Based on local value-chain multipliers [
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref030">30</a>] and the reported landings of anchoveta in 2013, a transition from the current use scheme (reduction) to a scenario were all landings were used by the canning industry for direct human consumption would result in up to 20% increases in net profits, a near doubling of employment, and an additional 700,000 tonnes a year of seafood for the human consumption market, while decreasing fishmeal production by half [
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref035">35</a>]. However, this reduction of fishmeal production from one of the largest supplies would obviously have negative effects for fishmeal intensive forms of aquaculture.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Southern stock of anchoveta is expected to shift its distribution further south due to climate change where the catches will no longer be available in Peru’s EEZ [
  <a rid="pone.0207768.ref071" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0207768.ref071">71</a>]. This means the share of this stock available to Peruvian companies will likely decline in the long-term, but our results show that these companies can benefit in the short to medium term (5–15+ years) from reducing fishing pressure and rebuilding the stock. The current overfished state of the stock is having negative repercussions for fishing companies in Peru and Chile, and the stocks being rebuilt could deliver higher landings and revenues in the future. While Chile is expected to have larger fisheries landings and revenues under the modeled scenario and into the future, this does not preclude Peru from cooperating in an agreement to rebuild the Southern stock. The short-term costs borne by Peru combined with the majority of benefits being derived by Chile could explain why Peruvian companies have been reluctant to support joint management of the shared stock. Finally, although not considered here, the bulk (~90%) of Chile’s landings of the shared stock is caught by a single company that could benefit considerably from the rebuilding strategies modeled here.
 </p>
</sec>
