<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Migration is a widespread phenomenon across the animal kingdom as a response to seasonality in environmental conditions, with a wide variety in migratory strategies across and within species (Dingle &amp; Drake, 
 <xref rid="ece33357-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>). In quite some species of birds, the young do not migrate in groups or families, clearly demonstrating that migratory behavior in space and time is endogenous (Liedvogel, Åkesson, &amp; Bensch, 
 <xref rid="ece33357-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>). Many of these migratory species actually show a geographical cline in migratoriness, meaning that the species’ area of distribution ranges from populations with migratory individuals to populations with residential individuals, following an environmental gradient (Newton, 
 <xref rid="ece33357-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>; Sahashi &amp; Morita, 
 <xref rid="ece33357-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). Partially migratory populations, in which both phenotypes co‐exist (Chapman, Brönmark, Nilsson, &amp; Hansson, 
 <xref rid="ece33357-bib-0005" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011b</xref>), can in such species occur between these two kinds of populations. The stability of partially migratory populations has long been debated (Chapman, Brönmark, Nilsson, &amp; Hansson, 
 <xref rid="ece33357-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011a</xref>). Clearly, under such conditions, all individuals carry the genetic migration program, yet it is differentially expressed between the migratory and residential phenotypes (Franchini et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33357-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>). As reasons for the differential expression of the genes related to migratory behavior, most empirical studies point toward fluctuating differences in survival or fecundity between phenotypes (Rolandsen et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33357-bib-0030" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>) and an important role for density dependence in the maintenance of the two phenotypes at the same location (Holt &amp; Fryxell, 
 <xref rid="ece33357-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>; Kaitala, Kaitala, &amp; Lundberg, 
 <xref rid="ece33357-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1993</xref>; Kokko, 
 <xref rid="ece33357-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>; Lundberg, 
 <xref rid="ece33357-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Shaw &amp; Levin, 
 <xref rid="ece33357-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>).
</p>
