<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Maximum entropy (MaxEnt) method is a general purpose machine learning method applied for producing species distribution maps using presence-only data [
 <xref rid="pone.0195752.ref029" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0195752.ref031" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0195752.ref032" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>]. MaxEnt, a bioclimatic model is widely used by conservation practitioners and researchers as a tool for prediction and distribution of species [
 <xref rid="pone.0195752.ref033" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>]. Wilson et al., [
 <xref rid="pone.0195752.ref034" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>] used the combination of MaxEnt and Generalized Linear Mixed Models (GLMMs) to identify areas of high conservation value for the endangered species 
 <italic class="italic">Margaritifera margaritifera</italic> (L.). Chitale et al., [
 <xref rid="pone.0195752.ref020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>] used MaxEnt to predict the distribution of 637 endemic plants in four global biodiversity hotspots including the Himalaya, by combining climatic and non-climatic variables. Whereas Adhikari et al., [
 <xref rid="pone.0195752.ref035" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>] modelled hotspots of invasive plant species through Ecological Niche Modeling (ENM) using MaxEnt for guiding the formulation of an effective policy for controlling the IAPS. For instance, West et al., [
 <xref rid="pone.0195752.ref036" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>] used a MaxEnt model with an invasive species 
 <italic class="italic">Bromus tectorum</italic> (cheatgrass) presence data and evaluated its usefulness in a management context. On the other hand, Qin et al., [
 <xref rid="pone.0195752.ref037" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>] investigated the spatial patterns of 
 <italic class="italic">Lantana camara</italic> habitat changes from its current distribution to future potential occupied areas using the MaxEnt ecological niche modeling technique. In this study also, MaxEnt modelling was used as it can achieve high predictive accuracy [
 <xref rid="pone.0195752.ref031" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>]. As the sample size shrinkages the model accuracy decreased however, MaxEnt modelling is less sensitive than other approaches to the number of presence locations [
 <xref rid="pone.0195752.ref031" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0195752.ref038" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>]. MaxEnt tuned their regularization in relation to sample size to avoid over fitting [
 <xref rid="pone.0195752.ref038" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0195752.ref039" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>]. Presence only data are good enough for species distribution modelling and the AUC scores obtained for predictions from it can be sufficiently accurate [
 <xref rid="pone.0195752.ref039" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0195752.ref040" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>]. SDMs have some limitations such as overestimation of presence of species. Assumption of random sampling of presence of species on the grid cells made by SDMs predicts large probability of presence in each cell, which could be in fact overestimation [
 <xref rid="pone.0195752.ref029" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>]. MaxEnt uses presence only data and it may give high predicted values for environmental conditions outside the range [
 <xref rid="pone.0195752.ref032" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>]. In order to avoid the over estimation, we applied a threshold value 0.5 was applied in this study and used only those pixels that have values equal to or higher than 0.5.
</p>
