<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In this paper, we use data of distribution of 11 invasive plants (namely 
 <italic class="italic">Ageratina adenophora</italic> L., 
 <italic class="italic">Ageratum conyzoides</italic> L., 
 <italic class="italic">Ageratum houstonianum</italic> Mill., 
 <italic class="italic">Amaranthus spinosus</italic> L., 
 <italic class="italic">Bidens pilosa</italic>
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carl_Linnaeus" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">L.</ext-link>, 
 <italic class="italic">Erigeron karvinskianus</italic> DC., 
 <italic class="italic">Lantana camara</italic> L., 
 <italic class="italic">Parthenium hysterophorus</italic> L., 
 <italic class="italic">Senna occidentalis</italic> (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carl_Linnaeus" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">L.</ext-link>) Link., 
 <italic class="italic">Senna tora</italic>
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carl_Linnaeus" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">L.</ext-link> Roxb. and 
 <italic class="italic">Xanthium strumarium</italic> L.) distributed in four districts of the Kailash Sacred Transboundary Landscape viz., Darchula, Baitadi, and Bajhang in Nepal and Pithoragarh district in India. The species considered in this study have been reported as ‘invasive’ in national level assessments and mapping [
 <xref rid="pone.0195752.ref041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0195752.ref042" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>]. In Nepal and Himalayas, most of the invasive species have been spreading from southern lowland to mid hills and mountains in the north. Some species (e.g. 
 <italic class="italic">Ageratina adenophora</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Lantana camara</italic>) are already widespread in the study region while other species (e.g. 
 <italic class="italic">Parthenium hysterophorus</italic>) are less abundant but they have already established small satellite population at a number of locations indicating their high potential to spread in the landscape. In absence of previous studies on invasive species in the region, it is not possible to estimate the duration for which the species is there. This could be an interesting topic of research for the future. The habitats known to be invaded by these species can be described as below:
</p>
