<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Both ideotypes, viz. DS and DT, were optimized to achieve high yield potentials in target environments. An evolutionary search algorithm with self-adaptation (EASA) was used in Sirius to optimize cultivar parameters in a high-dimensional parameter space with a complex fitness function for the best performance of crop ideotypes (
 <xref rid="CIT0059" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Schwefel and Rudolph, 1995</xref>; 
 <xref rid="CIT0074" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Stratonovitch and Semenov, 2010</xref>). The EASA is considered as a universal search optimization method. The main advantage of EASA compared with genetic algorithms is that it does not require tuning control parameters during the search, where predefined heuristic rules are unavailable or difficult to formulate (
 <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Beyer, 1995</xref>; 
 <xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bäck, 1998</xref>; 
 <xref rid="CIT0067" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Semenov and Terkel, 2003</xref>). The EASA optimized cultivar parameters by randomly perturbing (mutating) their values and testing their performance in the target environment. At each step of optimization, 16 new candidate ideotypes were generated from a ‘parent’ by perturbing its cultivar parameters randomly within the predefined parameters’ limits (
 <xref rid="T2" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 2</xref>). The parameter ranges were based on calibration of Sirius for modern cultivars allowing for variations reported in the literature for existing wheat germplasms (
 <xref rid="CIT0060" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Semenov and Halford, 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">He 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2012
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="CIT0064" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Semenov and Stratonovitch, 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="CIT0066" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Semenov 
  <italic class="italic">et al.</italic>, 2014
 </xref>). Yield was calculated for each of 16 candidates for 100 years under future climatic conditions. Ideotypes with the coefficient of variation (CV) of yield exceeding 10% were excluded from the selection process and the candidate with the highest mean yield over 100 years was selected as a ‘parent’ for the next step of optimization. The stopping rules of optimization process were: (i) no further improvement in yield potential is possible, and (ii) parameter convergence and parameter optimal state are achieved.
</p>
