<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par2" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Future concentrations of greenhouse gases (GHGs) in the atmosphere will determine the degree of warming the Earth will experience. Atmospheric methane, a powerful GHG, is controlled primarily by its anthropogenic and natural emissions and its destruction in the atmosphere. Methane is released into the atmosphere through a number of natural sources including wetlands, rivers and lakes, permafrost, wild animals, wildfires, termites, geological sources, and marine sources
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span>. While significant uncertainty exists in the estimates of emissions from each of these sources, the relative order of magnitude of total global natural emissions has remained robust. This is despite discrepancies between top-down (atmospheric) and bottom-up measurement-based estimates – derived by adding estimates of individual natural methane-generating processes
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span>. The rapid warming of the Arctic makes it plausible that natural emissions will increase in this area
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span> but the question remains whether these increases will be so large that they cannot be offset by reductions in anthropogenic emissions. To estimate the impact of future potential increases in natural methane emissions in the context of maximum technically feasible reductions in anthropogenic emissions, a modeling exercise was undertaken for this study, using an estimate of 202 Tg (±28 Tg) CH
  <sub>4</sub>/year
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span> for current global natural methane emissions. While on the lower side, this estimate lies within the range of estimates of total natural emissions (194–296 Tg CH
  <sub>4</sub>/yr) constrained by top-down approaches
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span> that take into account changes in atmospheric methane burden and methane’s lifetime in the atmosphere.
 </p>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As for the Arctic itself, different assessments have recently summarized the current understanding concerning the processes that generate, consume, store and release methane in high latitude terrestrial and marine systems
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span>, based on flux measurements, process studies, model simulations, and estimates of carbon stores. These show that both the terrestrial and marine Arctic regions are sources of methane
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span>, although their current estimated magnitudes and future projections vary strongly.
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For Arctic terrestrial systems, it is clear that the tundra region, inclusive of wetland areas, represents the major natural source of methane. Current estimates of natural methane emissions from Arctic tundra fall in the range of 11–39 Tg CH
  <sub>4</sub> per year
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span>. Our ability to constrain this estimate is limited by key uncertainties, primarily the limited measurements in time (few long-term records, and very limited measurements during the winter season) and in spatial coverage (very few measurement sites and most are located at “practical” rather than representative locations). Other limitations relate to gaps in understanding the biological and physical processes that control a release of methane from these ecosystems to the atmosphere. In addition to the terrestrial wetland emissions, the freshwaters of the Arctic are estimated to contribute as much as 13–16 Tg CH
  <sub>4</sub>/year
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
  </span>, yielding total terrestrial emissions in the range of 24–55 Tg CH
  <sub>4</sub> per year i.e. about 10–25% of global natural emissions. Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a> provides a summary of estimates for current Arctic natural methane emission sources.
  <div id="Tab1" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Natural arctic and global total current best emission estimates (CBEE)
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>,
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
     </span>.
    </p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th>Tg CH
       <sub>4</sub>/yr
      </th>
      <th/>
      <th>Range</th>
      <th>Best estimate</th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td rowspan="2">Arctic Terrestrial</td>
      <td>Tundra</td>
      <td>11 to 39</td>
      <td>25</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Lakes</td>
      <td>13 to 16</td>
      <td>15</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td rowspan="2">Arctic Marine</td>
      <td>Sub-sea permafrost</td>
      <td>1 to 17</td>
      <td>5</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Sea ice leads</td>
      <td>Not quantified</td>
      <td/>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Total Arctic</td>
      <td/>
      <td>25 to 72</td>
      <td>Ca 45</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Total global natural emissions</td>
      <td/>
      <td/>
      <td>202</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Future methane releases from Arctic tundra depend on how changes in Arctic temperatures and precipitation affect these controlling processes (leading to a change in methane production or consumption), physical changes (permafrost thaw, thermokarst) as well as the extent/magnitude of available carbon pools in Arctic soils. It is estimated that 1400–1850 Pg of carbon is frozen in Arctic soils
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>
  </span>. Since there is significant uncertainty in these estimates
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
  </span>, the potential release of this permafrost carbon to the atmosphere is also uncertain. The quantification of this uncertainty is further exacerbated due to the limited (or non-existent) representation of carbon and other biogeochemical cycle processes unique to the Arctic region and methane in Earth system models
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span>. Nevertheless, it is well recognized that significant stocks of frozen carbon exist in permafrost with the potential to thaw and decay, thus releasing methane and/or carbon dioxide as the Arctic continues to warm
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For Arctic marine systems, gas hydrates represent the largest potential source of marine methane release to the atmosphere due to the large amounts of methane contained within these deposits
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span>. Even so, many other source types (e.g. geological) contribute to a potential release of methane from the ocean. Current emissions from the Arctic Ocean into the atmosphere are estimated to range from 1 to as high as 17 Tg CH
  <sub>4</sub>/year
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span>. These emissions emanate primarily from shallow waters of the Arctic Ocean, since methane released from the deeper seabed is subject to significant oxidation during its ascent through the water column
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span>. Future methane release from the ocean depends on the methane stocks in marine reservoirs but also on the impact of changing temperatures and sea ice coverage on the controlling biological and physical processes
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A recent estimate put the quantity of carbon frozen in gas hydrates at 116 Pg
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span>. This is the basis for estimating a potential increase by 1.9 Tg per year in the release of methane into the Arctic Ocean over the next 100 years
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span>, which translates into an even smaller release to the atmosphere due to oxidative loss while methane rises through the water column. Overall, this is a relatively small additional contribution. However, this conclusion is tempered by significant uncertainty in the magnitude of marine hydrate carbon that is potentially vulnerable, and how much methane may pass the water column to the atmosphere, while observations that can act as a benchmark are severely lacking.
 </p>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Regardless of the limitations and uncertainties in characterizing Arctic natural (terrestrial and marine) methane emissions, their impact on global and Arctic climate has the potential to be significant and needs to be quantified. The future emission values presented in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a> represent four scenarios judged to characterize the range of possible future outcomes for changes in Arctic natural methane emissions (and their different combinations). The four scenarios used to estimate the climate response to changes in natural methane emissions are described as no change (+0 Tg CH
  <sub>4</sub>/year), a low (+50 Tg CH
  <sub>4</sub>/year), a high (+100 Tg CH
  <sub>4</sub>/year), and an extreme (+150 Tg CH
  <sub>4</sub>/year) increase by 2100 above the 202 Tg CH
  <sub>4</sub>/year global natural emissions baseline
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span>. We use a one box model of atmospheric methane and radiative forcing calculations to calculate impacts of future changes in methane emissions, both from anthropogenic and from natural sources, on concentrations of atmospheric methane and global climate forcing (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>, Table 
  <a rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" href="#Tab2">2</a>). This one box model describes the change in burden of atmospheric methane as a balance of natural and anthropogenic emissions, and the atmospheric and surface sinks (see Methods). It also models methane’s lifetime in the atmosphere as a function of its atmospheric concentration.
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Arctic methane generator. Generic scenarios of change in natural arctic methane emissions. Scenarios I–IV are used in the box-model calculations of atmospheric concentration change pathways.</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2018_37719_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e540" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <div id="Tab2" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Global radiative forcing (with respect to pre-industrial) and atmospheric concentrations of greenhouse gases with the baseline and scenarios for methane change described in this paper.</p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th/>
      <th/>
      <th/>
      <th/>
      <th colspan="4">CLE</th>
      <th colspan="4">MFR</th>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <th>Year</th>
      <th/>
      <th>1750</th>
      <th>2011</th>
      <th colspan="8">2100</th>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <th>Scenario</th>
      <th/>
      <th/>
      <th/>
      <th>I</th>
      <th>II</th>
      <th>III</th>
      <th>IV</th>
      <th>I</th>
      <th>II</th>
      <th>III</th>
      <th>IV</th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td rowspan="2">CH
       <sub>4</sub>
      </td>
      <td>RF W/m
       <span class="sup">2</span>
      </td>
      <td>—</td>
      <td>0.61</td>
      <td>1.00</td>
      <td>1.07</td>
      <td>1.15</td>
      <td>1.21</td>
      <td>0.42</td>
      <td>0.52</td>
      <td>0.61</td>
      <td>0.70</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>ppb</td>
      <td>722</td>
      <td>1803</td>
      <td>2842</td>
      <td>3060</td>
      <td>3284</td>
      <td>3511</td>
      <td>1423</td>
      <td>1616</td>
      <td>1816</td>
      <td>2021</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td rowspan="2">CO
       <sub>2</sub>
      </td>
      <td>RF W/m
       <span class="sup">2</span>
      </td>
      <td>—</td>
      <td>1.83</td>
      <td>4.87</td>
      <td>4.87</td>
      <td>4.87</td>
      <td>4.87</td>
      <td>2.24</td>
      <td>2.24</td>
      <td>2.24</td>
      <td>2.24</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>ppm</td>
      <td>278</td>
      <td>391</td>
      <td>670</td>
      <td>670</td>
      <td>670</td>
      <td>670</td>
      <td>421</td>
      <td>421</td>
      <td>421</td>
      <td>421</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Changed CH
       <sub>4</sub> forcing with respect to CLE/scenario I
      </td>
      <td>%</td>
      <td/>
      <td/>
      <td/>
      <td>7</td>
      <td>14</td>
      <td>21</td>
      <td>−58</td>
      <td>−48</td>
      <td>−39</td>
      <td>−30</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
   <div class="table-wrap-foot">
    <p>All RF values (also the ones for 2011) were calculated with the equations of Etminan 
     <span class="italic">et al</span>.
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
     </span>.
    </p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The anthropogenic methane emissions used here are updated versions of global GAINS model scenarios
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
  </span> describing a current legislation (CLE) and a maximum technically feasible reduction (MFR) scenario
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span>. The CLE scenario assumes no further abatement of emissions than prescribed in already adopted legislation, while the MFR scenario assumes maximum feasible implementation of existing abatement technology without considering effects of future technological development. Both scenarios fall within the ranges of the Representative Concentration Pathways
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>
  </span> (RCPs) of IPCC’s fifth assessment report
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>
  </span>. For the period from 2005 to 2050 for which the GAINS model is defined, the updated CLE and MFR scenarios use macroeconomic and energy system drivers consistent with the IEA World Energy Outlook New Policy Scenario 2017
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
  </span>. For the period from 2050 to 2100, growth in activity levels for the CLE and MFR scenarios, respectively, are consistent with the Shared Socioeconomic Pathways scenarios SSP3 6.0 and SSP3 2.6
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
  </span>. For further details, see the Methods section. Figure 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a> shows global anthropogenic methane emissions (excluding emissions from forest and grassland fires) over the 1990–2100 period in the CLE and MFR scenarios and in comparison with emissions for the RCP scenarios.
  <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Global anthropogenic methane emissions 1990–2100 in GAINS and in the Representative Concentration Pathways (RCPs)
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>,
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
     </span>.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2018_37719_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e866" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Within the Arctic Monitoring and Assessment Programme (AMAP, amap.no), which is one of the permanent scientific Working Groups under the Arctic Council, a multi-model study was conducted to isolate the effects of maximum feasible technical reductions in anthropogenic methane emissions on Arctic climate
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
  </span>. Three state-of-the-art Earth System Models were used, namely the Canadian Earth System Model CanESM2
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>
  </span>, the Norwegian Earth System Model
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>
  </span> (NorESM), and the Community Earth System Model CESM1-CAM5 developed at NCAR, USA
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>
  </span>, based on CLE and MFR emission scenarios from the GAINS model extending to 2050. The model results indicated that global implementation of maximum technically feasible reductions in anthropogenic methane is able to reduce the future average global climate warming by around 0.1–0.2 °C for the 2036–2050 period (including corresponding contributions from ozone and stratospheric water vapor), relative to a case with continuously increasing emissions according to the CLE scenario
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span>. These results from Gauss 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
  </span> also showed that a reduction in anthropogenic methane emissions can provide a significant contribution to achieve the target of the Paris agreement, which aims to keep global warming toward the end of this century well below 2.0 °C, preferably 1.5 °C, compared to the pre-industrial level. For the Arctic region, these Earth system model results showed even larger magnitudes of reduced warming related to maximum feasible reduction in anthropogenic methane emissions (due to Arctic amplification), but also larger variability
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span>. The results reported in that earlier study were based on atmospheric methane concentration changes obtained from the same one-box model of atmospheric methane that is used here. However, the Earth system model calculations in Gauss 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
  </span> did not consider changes in natural methane emissions and the results were analyzed only up to year 2050. Here, we use the one box model of atmospheric methane, extended to 2100, and based on the updated anthropogenic emissions for the MFR and CLE scenarios.
 </p>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Arctic warming driven by all climate forcers, primarily carbon dioxide, can potentially increase natural emissions from terrestrial and marine ecosystems. In contrast, the maximum technically feasible (MFR) emission reduction from the eight Arctic Council member states alone reduces anthropogenic emissions by 142 Tg CH
  <sub>4</sub>/year by 2100 in the MFR scenario (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>), which is considerably higher than the magnitude of the potential increase by 50 Tg CH
  <sub>4</sub>/year in natural emissions due to climate warming in the low scenario but comparable in size to the increase by 150 Tg CH
  <sub>4</sub>/yr in our extreme natural emission change scenario IV.
 </p>
 <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figure 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a> shows the resulting changes in atmospheric methane concentration obtained from the one box model for the MFR and CLE scenarios together with the corresponding four scenarios for changes in natural methane emissions. As Earth system models progressively include methane-related biogeochemical processes it will be possible to gain a better understanding of the effect of climate warming on methane-related feedbacks and quantify the effect of mitigation of anthropogenic methane emissions in a consistent framework. Here we use the changes in atmospheric methane concentration from Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a> to calculate global-mean radiative forcing (RF) for the year 2100 for the eight different combinations of changes in anthropogenic and natural emissions, using formulae from Etminan 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span>. The results for RF, along with the concentrations used, are listed in Table 
  <a rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" href="#Tab2">2</a>. All CH
  <sub>4</sub> RFs in the MFR case (0.42 to 0.70 W/m
  <span class="sup">2</span>) are smaller than the lowest CH
  <sub>4</sub> RF in the CLE case (1.00 W/m
  <span class="sup">2</span>), since the maximum feasible reduction in global anthropogenic emissions overwhelms the natural emissions increase even in the extreme Scenario IV. The maximum increase in naturally-induced CH
  <sub>4</sub> RF in the CLE case is 0.21 W/m
  <span class="sup">2</span> (“CLE + natural emissions scenario IV” minus “CLE + natural emissions scenario I”), while in the MFR case it is 0.28 W/m
  <span class="sup">2</span>. The slightly higher value in the MFR case is due to lower CH
  <sub>4</sub> concentrations (less saturation in the CH
  <sub>4</sub> absorption bands) and lower N
  <sub>2</sub>O concentrations in the MFR case.
  <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Box model results. Current legislation emission (CLE) and maximum feasible reduction (MFR) scenarios for anthropogenic impact on atmospheric methane concentrations towards 2100. The natural emission scenarios are from Fig. 
     <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1(I–IV)</a>. Each additional 50 Tg CH
     <sub>4</sub>/yr increase in natural emissions over the 2006–2100 period increase CH
     <sub>4</sub> concentration in 2100 by about 200 ppb. But CH
     <sub>4</sub> concentration in 2100 is reduced by about 1400–1500 ppb in response to going from CLE to MFR.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2018_37719_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e993" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">None of the naturally-induced CH
  <sub>4</sub> RF increases are as large in magnitude as the decrease in CH
  <sub>4</sub> RF range that is due to a reduction in anthropogenic emissions, represented by the differences between the CLE and MFR cases. The smallest decrease in CH
  <sub>4</sub> RF attributable to a reduction in anthropogenic emissions is 0.51 W/m
  <span class="sup">2</span> (‘CLE/Scenario IV’ minus ‘MFR/Scenario IV’) while the largest decrease is 0.58 W/m
  <span class="sup">2</span> (‘CLE/Scenario I’ minus ‘MFR/Scenario I’). Also, it has to be said that in the MFR case (featuring reductions in GHG global mean concentrations), methane-caused warming in the Arctic will be lower compared to the CLE, which would make the extreme scenario IV relatively less likely than in the CLE case.
 </p>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In conclusion, although sizeable for the impact on methane forcing alone, and approaching the scale of for example the cooling effect of sulphate aerosols in the atmosphere
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
  </span>, the feedback from natural methane emission changes in the Arctic remains minor compared to the effect of (global) anthropogenic emission cuts that could occur in a MFR-type scenario.
 </p>
 <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The scenarios used in this study cover a wide range of future emissions, up to an extreme scenario where the Arctic would emit an additional 150 Tg CH
  <sub>4</sub>/yr by 2100. Considering that this number is roughly equal to ~75% of current global natural emissions, such an increase appears unlikely. One of the few possible causes for such a large increase would be the widespread destabilization of gas hydrates, but recent model studies and observations indicate that this source is lower and more stable than previously thought
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
  </span>, and the geological record shows little evidence of large releases of methane from gas hydrates in the past
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span>. However, terrestrial sources may increase strongly with continued warming, and Arctic climate feedbacks are not limited to methane alone. The combined release of methane and CO
  <sub>2</sub> from the northern permafrost region represents a sustained source that can accelerate climate change
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
  </span>, while sea ice decline, snow cover loss and shrub expansion further amplify warming through a lowering of surface albedo
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>
  </span>. The cumulative effect of climate change on the terrestrial and marine Arctic, and the potential for positive feedbacks that affect the rest of the world, remains a topic of high concern. Methane, however, is too often portrayed as solely being able to cause runaway climate change. Despite large uncertainties associated with future projections of Arctic natural methane emissions, our current best estimates of potential increases in natural emissions remain lower than anthropogenic emissions. In other words, claims of an apocalypse associated solely with Arctic natural methane emission feedbacks are misleading, since they guide attention away from the fact that the direction of atmospheric methane concentrations, and their effect on climate, largely remain the responsibility of anthropogenic GHG emissions.
 </p>
 <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A rise in natural methane emissions may make it more challenging to reach the goals set by the Paris agreement, but they should not be a cause for indifference. On the contrary, the possibility for natural climate feedbacks emphasizes the need for a committed and strong reduction in anthropogenic GHG emissions starting sooner rather than later to avoid dangerous climate change.</p>
</sec>
