<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Similar changes have been observed even on shorter timescales, as in 6‐year surveys from Italy (Carbognani et al. 
 <xref rid="ece32354-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>) and Australia (Pickering et al. 
 <xref rid="ece32354-bib-0057" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). All these studies agree that the arrival and expansion of grassland species in the snowbed communities is likely a consequence of longer growing seasons induced by earlier snowmelt dates. The melt‐out date, which is an important driver of arctic and alpine plant growth (Jonas et al. 
 <xref rid="ece32354-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>), shifted earlier by 1–4 days per decade between 1998 and 2015 at 2110–2630 m.a.s.l. next to our three study sites (Appendix S6a). This shift, although not significant and covering a short time period, is corroborated by satellite observations in the high‐latitude and high‐elevation areas of the Northern Hemisphere (Dye 
 <xref rid="ece32354-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2002</xref>). This is probably the consequence of two associated factors: firstly, the increase in mean annual temperature, which has been calculated as 1.82 K between 1961 and 2008 in Switzerland (Serquet et al. 
 <xref rid="ece32354-bib-0070" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>), which is equivalent to the double of the mean change for the Northern Hemisphere (Rebetez and Reinhard 
 <xref rid="ece32354-bib-0060" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>), and secondly, the decrease in the snowfall/precipitation ratio estimated to be around 0.25% per year at the beginning and the end of the snow season from 1961 to 2008 (Serquet et al. 
 <xref rid="ece32354-bib-0070" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). The spring decreasing trend of snowfall/precipitation day ratio has been observed even at 2500 m a.s.l. by Marty and Meister (
 <xref rid="ece32354-bib-0050" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>) but is generally more pronounced at lower elevations (Scherrer et al. 
 <xref rid="ece32354-bib-0068" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2004</xref>; Serquet et al. 
 <xref rid="ece32354-bib-0070" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). In the three present study sites, despite a high interannual variability, the annual sum of fresh snow thickness decreased by 0.49–0.96% per year between 1964 and 2011 (Fig. 
 <xref rid="ece32354-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref>). The autumn and spring months seem to be crucial for snow duration, because at that period of the year, air temperatures are closer to the melting point than during the winter (Serquet et al. 
 <xref rid="ece32354-bib-0069" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>), and a slight increase is sufficient to reduce the snowfall part of precipitations. The lower snow amount and earlier melting dates observed in the study sites were accompanied by lagged snow falls in autumn (Appendix S6b). The resulting longer growing season (+5 to 14 days per decade between 1998 and 2015, not significant, Appendix S6c) allows the invasion of generally more competitive species, such as graminoids (Dullinger et al. 
 <xref rid="ece32354-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>). These species now have enough time to accomplish their life cycle in a snowbed. The establishment of species from adjacent communities could have been enhanced by (1) the proximity of grasslands to snowbeds (mostly &lt;20 m from the study sites), (2) the snowbed potential of trapping seeds (Larsson and Molau 
 <xref rid="ece32354-bib-0048" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2001</xref>), and (3) the high dispersal capacity of certain grassland species. Indeed, the increase in frequency of 
 <italic class="italic">Leontodon helveticus</italic> could be associated to its pappus appendage, which was shown to give an advantage to plant species in colonizing new Alpine summits (Matteodo et al. 
 <xref rid="ece32354-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>).
</p>
