<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We used fine scale climate models and species distribution modeling to evaluate the future success of a suite plant species commonly associated with U.S. Midwestern grasslands. We used native perennial grasses such as [
 <italic class="italic">Andropogon gerardii</italic> (Big bluestem), 
 <italic class="italic">Schizachyrium scoparium</italic> (Little bluestem), and 
 <italic class="italic">Sorghastrum nutans</italic> (Indian grass)] as these three species are particularly characteristic of the tallgrass prairie of the Midwestern U.S. region. Species distribution modeling has been used for both conservation planning and theoretical research on ecological and evolutionary processes, and these analyses are primarily conducted at coarse geographic scales (Ferrier et al., 
 <xref rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2002</xref>; Funk and Richardson, 
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2002</xref>; Loiselle et al., 
 <xref rid="B49" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2003</xref>; Rushton et al., 
 <xref rid="B65" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2004</xref>; Elith et al., 
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2006</xref>; Peterson, 
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2006</xref>; Kozak et al., 
 <xref rid="B46" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2008</xref>). In contrast, fine scale species distribution models have primarily been used for modeling distributions of a smaller number of either weedy or rare and endangered plant species (Collingham et al., 
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2000</xref>; Engler et al., 
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2004</xref>; Williams et al., 
 <xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>). These models establish relationships between occurrences of species and environmental conditions in the study area. A variety of species distribution modeling methods is available to predict potential habitat for a species (Guisan and Zimmermann, 
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2000</xref>; Kumar et al., 
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2006</xref>; Wisz et al., 
 <xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2008</xref>). Each method is unique with regard to data requirements, statistical methods and overall ease of use (Guisan and Zimmermann, 
 <xref rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2000</xref>). The prediction and mapping of potential habitat for threatened and endangered species can guide the monitoring and restoration of these declining native populations (Gaston, 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1996</xref>).
</p>
