<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The structure of the Paris Agreement, which requires each Party to the UNFCCC to make regular emissions reduction pledges of increasing ambition, will create economic conflicts of interest between stakeholders and sectors domestically [
 <xref rid="B103-ijerph-15-00674" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">103</xref>]. The implementation of mitigation policies, often regulatory in nature, naturally creates winners and losers [
 <xref rid="B96-ijerph-15-00674" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">96</xref>]. Longer-term, winners of ambitious climate change mitigation policies comprise nearly all sectors, including the renewable energy sector, as well as current and future populations, with benefits diffuse across space and time, and difficult to measure. Losers are likely to be big corporations as well as extractive industries, often able to exert undue power and influence over the policy-making process [
 <xref rid="B103-ijerph-15-00674" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">103</xref>]. In Australia, for example, there is acknowledgement that business and industry stakeholders are highly influential in the climate change policy-making process as a result of corporate contributions to economic growth and stability [
 <xref rid="B49-ijerph-15-00674" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>]. Conversely, those who suffer most from a delay in effective climate change policies are the most vulnerable populations with minimal to no power in the policy-making process: children, economically disadvantaged populations and future generations. Vested interests are not limited to corporate interests eager to maintain the status quo. Outside of the more obvious economic motivations that exist for the extractive industry, strong ideological motivations have been linked to the climate change denial movement that has particularly strong roots in the US. Specifically, “a staunch commitment to free markets and disdain of governmental regulations” remains a defining feature of climate change denialists, who appear determined to uphold the “modern Western social order” that is often characterized by political and economic conservatism [
 <xref rid="B104-ijerph-15-00674" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">104</xref>] (p. 144). This perspective is supported by analysis performed by Jacques and colleagues (2008), which confirmed a strong link between environmentally sceptic publications and conservative think tanks [
 <xref rid="B105-ijerph-15-00674" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">105</xref>].
</p>
