<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">A number of steps were taken to establish model credibility. In the discussion we reflect on credibility of simulated yields under climate change. In this section we reflect on credibility of simulated yields for the current situation. A recent study has shown that a very similar model as used in the current study (APSIM soil, ORYZA2000 crop) performed well in a wide range of contrasting environments in Asia (Gaydon et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb13967-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>). This provides some confidence that the same model, with the improvements presented here, will also predict accurately in a wide range of environments in Africa. A validation of the ORYZA2000v2n14s1model for Senegal, with the new heat, cold and phenology model was presented in (Van Oort, De Vries et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb13967-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>) and showed a high model efficiency for this particular environment. We simulated potential production (irrigated environments) and water‐limited production (rainfed environments) which assumes no soil fertility limitations and no biotic and abiotic production constraints such as weeds, pests and diseases, salinity and iron toxicity. In reality, many of these conditions are present virtually everywhere in rice in Africa (e.g. Niang et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb13967-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>; Tanaka et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb13967-bib-0056" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>). Even the farmers with 10% highest yields (Tanaka et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb13967-bib-0056" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>) have yield gaps. Consistent with this, simulated potential yields were equal to or higher than these top10% yields (result not shown). This is logical but unfortunately still tells us little about whether these potential yield estimates are accurate. There are few quantified data available that can be used to validate potential yields. Therefore, two qualitative methods were applied to assess model credibility. Firstly, we checked if the model correctly simulated spatial patterns across climatic zones and production systems. This was indeed the case. Both model and data reported in Niang et al. (
 <xref rid="gcb13967-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>) and Tanaka et al. (
 <xref rid="gcb13967-bib-0056" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>) show highest yields in irrigated systems in the semiarid zone, where radiation levels are high and where, if irrigation and fertilizer are available, high yields can be obtained. Simulated and actual yields were also high in the main season in the highlands of East Africa (e.g. central Madagascar), because low temperatures lead to a long growing season, allowing for high biomass accumulation. Simulated and actual yields are lower in the rainfed systems, due to drought and interannual variation in simulated rainfed rice yields was larger than that of irrigated rice yields. The second qualitative model credibility check was expert consultation. In the global yield gap atlas (GYGA) project, credibility of 81 simulated yields for was assessed for eight African countries also included in the current study. Model credibility was assessed by agronomists of each country involved, based on their “expert knowledge” and in collaboration with a senior rice agronomist at the Africa Rice Center (K. Saito; see Van Oort, Saito et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb13967-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). Country agronomists checked sowing dates, crop duration, yield levels and spatial patterns within their countries. This lead to various model improvements and this iterative process was continued until credible results were obtained for all sites, but unfortunately it did not result in reliable data for quantitative validation. Model accuracy also depends on quality of the input data. Quality controls as defined in (Grassini et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb13967-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>) were applied.
</p>
