<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="en"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue article.dtd?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType system?><?SourceDTD.DTDName article.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName bmc2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Parasit Vectors</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Parasit Vectors</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Parasites &#x00026; Vectors</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1756-3305</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3726513</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1756-3305-6-190</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23800283</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1756-3305-6-190</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Spatial disaggregation of tick occurrence and ecology at a local scale as a preliminary step for spatial surveillance of tick-borne diseases: general framework and health implications in Belgium</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" id="A1"><name><surname>Obsomer</surname><given-names>Valerie</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>valerie.obsomer@uclouvain.be</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A2"><name><surname>Wirtgen</surname><given-names>Marc</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>a.linden@ulg.ac.be</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A3"><name><surname>Linden</surname><given-names>Annick</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I3">3</xref><email>a.linden@ulg.ac.be</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A4"><name><surname>Claerebout</surname><given-names>Edwin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I4">4</xref><email>Edwin.Claerebout@UGent.be</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A5"><name><surname>Heyman</surname><given-names>Paul</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I5">5</xref><email>Paul.Heyman@mil.be</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A6"><name><surname>Heylen</surname><given-names>Dieter</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I6">6</xref><email>dieter.heylen@ua.ac.be</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A7"><name><surname>Madder</surname><given-names>Maxime</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I7">7</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I8">8</xref><email>mmadder@itg.be</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A8"><name><surname>Maris</surname><given-names>Jo</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I9">9</xref><email>Jo.Maris@dgz.be</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A9"><name><surname>Lebrun</surname><given-names>Maude</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I10">10</xref><email>gps@arsia.be</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A10"><name><surname>Tack</surname><given-names>Wesley</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I11">11</xref><email>Wesley.Tack@UGent.be</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A11"><name><surname>Lempereur</surname><given-names>Laetitia</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I12">12</xref><email>Laetitia.Lempereur@glasgow.ac.uk</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A12"><name><surname>Hance</surname><given-names>Thierry</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>thierry.hance@uclouvain.be</email></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" id="A13"><name><surname>Van Impe</surname><given-names>Georges</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">2</xref><email>georges.vanimpe@skynet.be</email></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1"><label>1</label>Universit&#x000e9; Catholique de Louvain, Earth and Life Institute, Georges Lemaitre climate and earth research centre, place Louis Pasteur 3, 1348, Louvain la Neuve, Belgium</aff><aff id="I2"><label>2</label>Biodiversity department ELIB, Universit&#x000e9; Catholique de Louvain, Earth and Life Institute, 4 place Croix du sud, 1348, Louvain-la-Neuve, Belgium</aff><aff id="I3"><label>3</label>Department of infectious and parasitic diseases, health and pathology of the wildlife, University of Li&#x000e8;ge, boulevard de Colonster 20, 4000, Li&#x000e8;ge 1, Belgium</aff><aff id="I4"><label>4</label>Laboratory of Parasitology, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, Ghent University, Salisburylaan 133 9820, Merelbeke, Belgium</aff><aff id="I5"><label>5</label>Reference Laboratory for Vector-Borne Diseases, Queen Astrid Military Hospital, Bruynstraat 1, 1120, Brussels, Belgium</aff><aff id="I6"><label>6</label>Evolutionary ecology group, Department of Biology, University of Antwerp, Groenenborgerlaan, 171-2020, Antwerpen, Belgium</aff><aff id="I7"><label>7</label>Institute for Tropical Medicine, 155 nationalestraat, B2000, Antwerpen, Belgium</aff><aff id="I8"><label>8</label>Department of Veterinary Tropical Diseases, University of Pretoria, Pretoria, South Africa</aff><aff id="I9"><label>9</label>ARSIA, All&#x000e9;e des Artisans, 2 - 5590, Ciney, Belgium</aff><aff id="I10"><label>10</label>Dierenarts Gezondheidszorg Herkauwers Veepeiler, DGZ Vlaanderen, l Hagenbroeksesteenweg 167&#x000a0;l, 2500, Lier, Belgium</aff><aff id="I11"><label>11</label>Laboratory of Forestry, Department of Forest and Water Management, Ghent University, Geraardsbergsesteenweg 267, 9090, Melle-Gontrode, Ghent, Belgium</aff><aff id="I12"><label>12</label>Laboratory of Parasitology and Pathology of Parasitic Diseases, Department of Infectious and Parasitic Diseases, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, University of Li&#x000e8;ge, Bd de Colonster 20 B43, 4000, Li&#x000e8;ge, Belgium</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>22</day><month>6</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><fpage>190</fpage><lpage>190</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>25</day><month>5</month><year>2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>6</month><year>2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2013 Obsomer et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Obsomer et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="http://www.parasitesandvectors.com/content/6/1/190"/><abstract><sec><title>Background</title><p>The incidence of tick-borne diseases is increasing in Europe. Sub national information on tick distribution, ecology and vector status is often lacking. However, precise location of infection risk can lead to better targeted prevention measures, surveillance and control.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p>In this context, the current paper compiled geolocated tick occurrences in Belgium, a country where tick-borne disease has received little attention, in order to highlight the potential value of spatial approaches and draw some recommendations for future research priorities.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p>Mapping of 89,289 ticks over 654 sites revealed that ticks such as <italic>Ixodes ricinus</italic> and <italic>Ixodes hexagonus</italic> are largely present while <italic>Dermacentor reticulatus</italic> has a patchy distribution. Suspected hot spots of tick diversity might favor pathogen exchanges and suspected hot spots of <italic>I. ricinus</italic> abundance might increase human-vector contact locally. This underlines the necessity to map pathogens and ticks in detail. While <italic>I. ricinus</italic> is the main vector, <italic>I. hexagonus</italic> is a vector and reservoir of <italic>Borrelia burgdorferi s.l.,</italic> which is active the whole year and is also found in urban settings. This and other nidiculous species bite humans less frequently, but seem to harbour pathogens. Their role in maintaining a pathogenic cycle within the wildlife merits investigation as they might facilitate transmission to humans if co-occurring with <italic>I. ricinus</italic>. Many micro-organisms are found abroad in tick species present in Belgium. Most have not been recorded locally but have not been searched for. Some are transmitted directly at the time of the bite, suggesting promotion of tick avoidance additionally to tick removal.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusion</title><p>This countrywide approach to tick-borne diseases has helped delineate recommendations for future research priorities necessary to design public health policies aimed at spatially integrating the major components of the ecological cycle of tick-borne diseases. A systematic survey of tick species and associated pathogens is called for in Europe, as well as better characterisation of species interaction in the ecology of tick-borne diseases, those being all tick species, pathogens, hosts and other species which might play a role in tick-borne diseases complex ecosystems.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>Tick</kwd><kwd>Vector</kwd><kwd>Spatial distribution</kwd><kwd>Ecology</kwd><kwd>Vector-borne diseases</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Background</title><p>The incidence of tick-borne diseases is increasing in Europe [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref>] and follows an increase in the number of tick bites [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>] attributed to two factors: abundance of questing ticks and human exposure to ticks [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. Measures targeting human exposure by promoting timely removal of ticks failed to stop the rise in Lyme borreliosis incidence in the Netherlands. On the other hand, this rise was related to an increase in <italic>Ixodes ricinus</italic> abundance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. Knowing the local variations in the distribution of the species interacting in tick-borne diseases systems, including ticks, pathogens and species influencing the presence and abundance of ticks and pathogens, could provide new opportunities to estimate potential infection risks locally, identify local hot spots and develop targeted prevention, surveillance and control.</p><p>Necessary information is lacking at national and sub national levels in many countries. The first missing information concerns the presence and distribution of tick species. Efforts to characterise tick distribution on a European scale [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>] are limited by the information available at sub national level and only target major vectors such as <italic>I. ricinus</italic>. Other tick species less willingly biting humans sometimes harbour high pathogen prevalence&#x02019;s and might contribute locally to the pathogens&#x02019; cycles [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. The role of all tick species present should be investigated jointly per pathogen and their distribution clarified. The second missing information concerns the spatial distribution of hosts, predators and species influencing tick populations and pathogens&#x02019; prevalence in ticks. The presence and abundance of tick species varies locally according to many factors, including host availability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>]. Pathogen prevalence in ticks also varies locally according to availability of reservoirs, dead-end hosts and vectors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref>]. The third set of missing information concerns pathogens associated to ticks, their presence, reservoirs, vectors and distribution. Pathogens found using classical PCR methods are those searched for, while others might be present but undetected. Because micro-organisms are increasingly found in ticks, a more systematic approach is needed. The list of micro-organisms found locally or abroad in local tick species could be narrowed by clarifying pathogenicity, vector capacity and presence of reservoirs to provide a list of potential pathogens to investigate locally. This would clarify the spectrum of pathogens potentially transmitted locally through a tick bite.</p><p>In this paper, occurrence records and information on tick species relevant for public health have been compiled for a country where tick-borne diseases received little attention. In Belgium, the limited quality of current information is obvious because of proximity to the Netherlands, a country that stands out for efficient investigations of tick-borne diseases. In the Netherlands, tick bites are subject to spatial monitoring [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. Lyme borreliosis is monitored by physician surveys targeting <italic>Erythema migrans</italic>, the most common symptom [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. In Belgium, only Lyme borreliosis is regularly diagnosed. In 2009, official numbers of cases varied from 500 to 1500 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref>] or 9000 cases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref>] according to the source. In the Netherlands, 22000 cases were recorded for that same year [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">2</xref>]. <italic>I. ricinus</italic> is believed to occur in Southeast Belgium but records occur elsewhere. Detailed distribution can approximate local exposure to ticks. This is of direct public health interest because according to European guidelines for Lyme borreliosis, an individual presenting an <italic>Erythema migrans</italic> is considered a confirmed case if potentially exposed to areas favourable for vector ticks [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref>]. Laboratory confirmation and remembering a tick bite are not necessary to confirm this diagnosis.</p><p>This study aims to show how an integrated spatial approach on tick species in a given country can provide the preliminary information needed for adapted national public health policies by providing: 1) a list of tick species present and their detailed distribution, 2) the micro-organisms they could harbour, 3) ecological traits influencing vector status, 4) implications for public health and suggestions for future research priorities.</p></sec><sec sec-type="methods"><title>Methods</title><p>Three sources of tick locations were considered: new tick collections, literature collections and &#x0201c;grey datasets&#x0201d;. Quality levels are proposed for each record to document for example accuracy of tick location according to type of host/vegetation (lower if captured on moving animals such as dog or deer). Information on localisation, collection, vegetation or host, pathogen load, and original data source were compiled in an excel database (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>). A systematic literature search was made based on ISI web of knowledge using the keywords &#x0201c;tick AND ecology&#x0201d; from 1989 to 2001 and &#x0201c;tick&#x0201d; from 2002 to 2011. Additional articles resulted from a specific search on presence and pathogenicity of microorganisms found in ticks. The database and additional literature articles form the basis for this paper and are examined for the following items: geographical distribution, species behaviour, ecology, presence of micro-organisms. Consequences for public health and prevention are highlighted. For some sites additional details were provided by authors, however, the methodology is already described in published articles and summarised in the Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>. This includes (1) Collection BAYER, 579 sites [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>], (2) Collection RLVBD, 51 sites [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>], (3) Collection UGENT FOREST, 33 sites [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref>], (4) Collection ARSIA, 17 sites [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref>], (5) Collection UCLIREC, 5 sites [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref>], and (6) Collection UA1, 16 sites [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">22</xref>]. Collection GREY DATA includes tick field observations from the website of NATAGORA and NATUURPUNT (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.observations.be">http://www.observations.be</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.waarnemingen.be">http://www.waarnemingen.be</ext-link>) by registered users involved with nature related activities from 1980 until February 2012. Methodologies for original tick collections are described in detail below:</p><sec><title>Collection VANIMPE</title><p>In the framework of the convention 5284a funded by IRSIA (Institut pour l&#x02032;encouragement de la recherche dans l&#x02032;industrie et l&#x02032;agriculture), the center of acarology (UCL) led two collection campaigns in the Campine, the plateau braban&#x000e7;on and the Condroz. The regions were selected based on local Lyme borreliosis cases and favourable tick habitat. The first campaign in 1989 targeted 30 sites and the second campaign prospected 234 sites from May to October 1990 including 79&#x000a0;days of prospection. Ticks were collected from the environment by flagging. Each collection lasted 2&#x000a0;hours and UTM coordinates were checked on maps (100&#x000a0;m).</p></sec><sec><title>Collection WILDSCREEN</title><p>From 2007 to 2009, ticks from wild cervids (<italic>Cervus elaphus</italic> and <italic>Capreolus capreolus</italic>) found dead, hunted or killed for sanitary reasons were collected by the Wild Screen Network disease monitoring activities in Southern Belgium [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>]. Ticks were preserved in 70% ethanol at room temperature, and morphologically identified up to stage and species level (by L. Lempereur and A. Nahayo). Sex and repletion were recorded. <italic>Dermacentor reticulatus</italic> was also collected on wild cervids from 2010 to 2012. As <italic>D. reticulatus</italic> and <italic>D. marginatus</italic> may show overlapping phenotypes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">24</xref>], a PCR was used for confirmation, targeting the <italic>Dermacentor</italic> second Internal Transcribed Spacer 2 (ITS2) with the following primers: ITS_forward (5&#x02032;-GTG-CGT-CCG-TCG-ACT-CGT-TTT-GA-3&#x02032;) and ITS_reverse (5&#x02032;-ACG-GCG-GAC-TAC-GAC-GGA-ATG-C-3&#x02032;) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">25</xref>]. The DNA purification was carried out using the NucleoSpin tissue kit for tissue protocol (Macherey-Nagel GmbH, Germany). Samples were frozen in liquid nitrogen and homogenized on a Tissue Lyser<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> (Qiagen, GmbH, Germany). PCR conditions were as follow: each reaction was carried out in 50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;L volume containing 4&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l of the DNA preparation, 5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l of each 2&#x000a0;mM dNTP, 2&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l of each 10&#x000a0;&#x003bc;M oligonucleotide primer, 2 U of TaqDNA polymerase (New England Bio labs) with 5&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l of the 10x PCR supplied buffer and completed to 50&#x000a0;&#x003bc;l with sterile water. PCR was achieved with an initial denaturation cycle at 95&#x000b0;C for 5&#x000a0;min, followed by 35&#x000a0;cycles (94&#x000b0;C, 45&#x000a0;s), annealing (53&#x000b0;C, 45&#x000a0;s), extension (72&#x000b0;C, 70&#x000a0;s) and a final extension step at 72&#x000b0;C for 10&#x000a0;min. All ITS2 PCR products were sequenced using a modified Sanger method with the Big Dye terminator kit version 3.1 and resolved with a 3730 ABI capillary sequencer (Applied Bio systems). Sequencing reaction was performed with the same primers as for the PCR and sequences aligned by BLAST search.</p></sec><sec><title>Collection ITG</title><p>Ticks were collected by flagging for several years (site 1, 60, 172).</p></sec><sec><title>Collection IRSNB</title><p>Additional tick locations registered in museum collections were provided by the IRSNB (Institut Royal des Sciences Naturelles de Belgique).</p></sec><sec><title>Collection DGZ</title><p>While investigating anaplasmosis in 11 farms in Flanders, in 2011, the Dierengezonheidzorg (DGZ &#x02013; Animal Health Care Flanders, Belgium) recorded <italic>I. ricinus</italic> ticks on several animals from those 11 farms.</p></sec><sec><title>Collection GLAXOSMITHKLINE</title><p>Ticks were captured by flagging in 1999 in 3 sites in Belgium (sites 228, 242, 353).</p></sec><sec><title>Collection MARTIN</title><p><italic>D. reticulatus</italic> was found on a human around Namur and a trypanosome discovered in the intestine of <italic>I. ricinus</italic> in the context of other research [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">26</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Collection UGENT VETE</title><p>The clinic of poultry diseases of Ghent University performs diagnosis required by individuals. In this framework they recorded a tick infestation on a pigeon from <italic>Argas</italic> species, probably <italic>Argas reflexus</italic> in July 2012 near Berlaar (site 303) in the province of Antwerp.</p></sec></sec><sec><title>Results and discussion</title><p>The database includes 1624 records for a total of 89,289 ticks and is summarized per collection in Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T1">1</xref>. Records within 3&#x000a0;km range were grouped for the display in 654 sites. Original details are available for each record (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>) and can be visualised using Google Earth (Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2">2</xref>). Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref> shows sites of occurrence for all tick species.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Tick species found in Belgium per collection</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left">&#x000a0;</th><th align="left"><bold>Species</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Number of species</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Number of ticks</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Number of records</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ixodes ricinus </italic>(1801/395)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ixodes hexagonus </italic>(634/164)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Dermacentor reticulatus </italic>(18/5)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Collection BAYER<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Rhipicephalus sanguineus </italic>(6/5)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">4<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">2264<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">577<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ixodes ricinus </italic>(868/271)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Dermacentor reticulatus </italic>(297/10)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Collection GREY DATA<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ixodes lividus </italic>(5/1)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">3<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">1170<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">282<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ixodes ricinus </italic>(43150/175)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ixodes lividus </italic>(7/2)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ixodes hexagonus </italic>(792/33)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Rhipicephalus sanguineus </italic>(97/13)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Argas reflexus </italic>(17/7)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Argas vespertilionis </italic>(9/3)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Hyalomma aegyptium </italic>(26/4)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ixodes acuminatus </italic>(1/1)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ixodes arboricola </italic>(190/3)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">I<italic>xodes canisuga </italic>(2/1)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ixodes frontalis </italic>(7/4)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ixodes trianguliceps </italic>(9/8)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Collection LITERATURE<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ixodes vespertilionis </italic>(29/11)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">13<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">44,655<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">273<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ixodes ricinus </italic>(5819/192)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ixodes hexagonus </italic>(1/1)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Collection VANIMPE<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Rhipicephalus sanguineus </italic>(1/1)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">3<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">5821<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">194<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ixodes ricinus </italic>(2232/87)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Collection WILDSCREEN<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Dermacentor reticulatus </italic>(159/11)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">2<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">2391<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">98<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ixodes ricinus </italic>(4000/8)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Dermacentor reticulatus </italic>(66/66)<hr/></td><td>&#x000a0;</td><td>&#x000a0;</td><td>&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Collection ITG<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ixodes frontalis </italic>(2/2)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">3<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">4068<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">76<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Collection RLVBD<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ixodes ricinus </italic>(22435/45)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">22,435<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">45<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ixodes ricinus </italic>(2670/5)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ixodes hexagonus </italic>(1/1)<hr/></td><td>&#x000a0;</td><td>&#x000a0;</td><td>&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ixodes arboricola </italic>(2790/12)<hr/></td><td>&#x000a0;</td><td>&#x000a0;</td><td>&#x000a0;</td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Collection UA<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ixodes lividus </italic>(18/2)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">4<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">5571<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">29<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Collection ARSIA<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ixodes ricinus</italic> (600/17)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">600<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">17<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ixodes ricinus </italic>(6/4)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ixodes hexagonus </italic>(4/2)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Dermacentor reticulatus </italic>(2/1)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Argas vespertilionis </italic>(5/1)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Dermacentor reticulatus </italic>(2/1)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ixodes canisuga </italic>(1/1)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ixodes frontalis </italic>(1/1)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ixodes trianguliceps </italic>(1/1)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Collection IRSNB<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ixodes vespertilionis </italic>(18/4)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">9<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">38<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">15<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Collection DGZ<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ixodes ricinus </italic>(11/11)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">11<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">11<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Collection GLAXOSMITHKLINE<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ixodes ricinus </italic>(167/3)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">167<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">3<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ixodes ricinus </italic>(1/1)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Collection MARTIN<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Dermacentor reticulatus </italic>(1/1)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">2<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">2<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">2<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Collection UGENT<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Argas reflexus </italic>(1/1)<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td><td align="center" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">TOTAL</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="center">14</td><td align="center">89289</td><td align="center">1624</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Species collected (number of ticks per species / number of location records per species), number of species, number of ticks and number of location recorded per collection. When the number of collected ticks is unknown the value is set to 1. (Details in Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>).</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="F1" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p><bold>Map of tick species recorded in Belgium before 2011. </bold>Map of existing tick species records in Belgium. One color corresponds to one species. When two or more species occur at the same site special symbols compile the colors of the two or more species. <italic>I. ricinus</italic> is in black color. Numbers labelling each site correspond to site number in Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1756-3305-6-190-1"/></fig><sec><title>Tick species in Belgium</title><p>Fourteen species were recorded in Belgium and 10 additional species are suspected to be present because they were recorded in surrounding areas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>] (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T2">2</xref>). <italic>I. ricinus</italic> (Linnaeus, 1758) and <italic>I. hexagonus</italic> (Leach 1815) are widely distributed (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>). <italic>I. ricinus</italic> is found in all the provinces. <italic>I. hexagonus</italic> is also present in all provinces and is known to be more abundant than <italic>I. ricinus</italic> in specific settings such as urban gardens [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>]. These species are also the easiest to catch through flagging (<italic>I. ricinus</italic>) or because they are present on pets investigated by veterinarian surveys. Other species records are sporadic and difficult to interpret. Those records might reflect patchy distribution for ticks associated with bat habitats for example, or just lack of systematic surveys for the recently investigated <italic>D. reticulatus</italic> (Fabricius, 1794) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>]. The distribution of species with 20 or fewer occurrences is difficult to analyse. Areas without records are due to absence or absence of surveys, thus leading to difficulties in the interpretation of the data.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Tick species of Belgium</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left"><bold>Tick name</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Records in BE (Ticks)</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Year for last record</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>NL</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>NW EU</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>N FR</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>GE</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>Established in the wild</bold><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ixodes ricinus</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1223 (88758)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2011<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ixodes hexagonus</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">201(1333)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1987<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Dermacentor reticulatus</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">102 (861)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2012<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ixodes frontalis</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">16 (102)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2011<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ixodes arboricola</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">15(2980)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2011<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ixodes lividus</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">5 (30)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1989<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ixodes canisuga</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2 (3)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1945<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ixodes trianguliceps</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">9 (10)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1987<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ixodes acuminatus</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1 (1)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1987<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Argas reflexus</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">8 (18)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2012<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Argas vespertilionis</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">4 (14)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1942<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ixodes vespertilionis</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">15 (47)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1969<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>Established in houses and recurrently imported on host</bold><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Rhipicephalus sanguineus</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">19 (104)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1982<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>Not established but recurrently imported on host</bold><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Hyalomma aegyptium</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">4 (26)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">(1965)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold>Potentially present but never found in Belgium</bold><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ixodes unicavatus</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Potential<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Never<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Maybe<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">No<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ixodes uriae</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Potential<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Never<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ixodes ventalloi</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Potential<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Never<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ixodes apronophorus</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Potential<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Never<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes (UK)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ixodes rugicollis</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Potential<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Never<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ixodes simplex</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Potential<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Never<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Dermacentor marginatus</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Potential<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">(1973)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Haemaphysalis punctata</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Potential<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Never<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes (UK)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Haemaphysalis concinna</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Potential<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Never<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Yes<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Haemaphysalis inermis</italic></td><td align="left">Potential</td><td align="left">Never</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">Yes</td><td align="left">Yes</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>List of tick species in Belgium (BE), the Netherlands (NL), North Western Europe (NW EU) including the United Kingdom (UK), North France (N FR) and Germany (GE). Number of records in BE (Total numbers collected include available records for larvae, nymphs and adult stages). Some collectors, however, do not collect the larvae even if they are present. The year of the last records is in brackets if only found on hosts from import. Other species are present in surrounding countries but were not considered because they are very rare (<italic>Rhipicephalus bursa</italic>, <italic>Amblyoma variegatum</italic>) or specific to host species rare in Belgium (<italic>Ixodes unicavatus</italic>, <italic>Ixodes rotchildi</italic>, <italic>Ixodes caledonicus</italic>, <italic>Ornithodoros maritimus</italic>).</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Most tick species are nidiculous and thus found mainly on hosts, nests or burrows. Off host habitats are important for <italic>I. ricinus</italic> and <italic>D. reticulatus</italic> which quest on the vegetation. <italic>I. ricinus</italic> is found in deciduous forests, pastures bordered by trees, hedges and bushes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>], or with tall grass and high humidity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>], vegetated sand dunes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>], pine forests [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref>] and city parks [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">36</xref>]. Contradictory definitions of <italic>D. reticulatus</italic> habitats exist in the literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>] with <italic>D. reticulatus</italic> found in drier areas than <italic>I. ricinus</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>] or in moist areas along rivers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">38</xref>] or on the fringe of meadows in dry vegetation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>] and variation in abundance in similar sites [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">40</xref>]. Many vertebrates are parasitized by <italic>I. ricinus</italic> (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>). <italic>I. hexagonus</italic> is present on many mammals but never birds [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">39</xref>]. Other species seem restricted to specific hosts such as birds (<italic>I. frontalis</italic> (Panzer, 1798), <italic>I. arboricola</italic> Schulze &#x00026; Schlottke, 1930, <italic>Argas reflexus</italic> (Fabricius, 1794), <italic>I. lividus</italic> Koch, 1844), rodents (<italic>I. trianguliceps</italic> Birula, 1895, <italic>I. acuminatus</italic> Neumann, 1901), mammals (<italic>I. canisuga</italic> Johnston, 1849<italic>, D. reticulatus</italic>) or bats (<italic>Argas vespertilionis</italic> (Latreille, 1796), <italic>I. vespertilionis</italic> Koch, 1844). <italic>Rhipicephalus sanguineus</italic> (Latreille, 1806) is imported on dogs and found occasionally in houses. <italic>Hyalomma aegyptium</italic> (Linnaeus, 1758) is imported on tortoises. Names are such as revised by Barker and Murrell [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">41</xref>] or used by Petney <italic>el al</italic>. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>]. While seasonality might be linked to host life cycle for bat ticks, most nidiculous ticks seem active year round (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T4">4</xref>). <italic>I. ricinus</italic> is more frequently recorded in spring and autumn but the decrease in summer seems to be an artefact due to vegetation stages influencing flagging efficiency [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">42</xref>]. Slight activity occurs in winter. <italic>D. reticulatus</italic> seems mainly absent on the vegetation in summer.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p><bold>Tick hosts and ecology in Belgium (details in Additional file</bold><xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2"><bold>2</bold></xref><bold>)</bold></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left">&#x000a0;</th><th align="left"><bold>host</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>off hostOOff</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>I. ricinus</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Canis lupus familiaris, Felis silvestris catus, Erinaceus europaeus, Bos taurus, Homo sapiens, Capreolus capreolus, Carduelis chloris, Cervus elaphus, Parus major, Cyanistes caeruleus, Anthus pratensis, Anthus trivialis, Apodemus sylvaticus, Clethrionomys glareolus, Erithacus rubecula, Hippolais icterina, Sturnus vulgaris, Talpea europaea, Turdus ericetorum, Phylloscopus erolius, Turdus pilaris, Turdus merula, Phylloscopus inornatus, Turdus iliacus, Sitta europea, Ficedula hypoleuca, Fringilla coelebs, Lacerta vivipara, Bubo bubo</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Plant species<italic>: Fagus sylvatica, Carpinus betulus(hornbeam), Betula pendula (birch), Quercus robur (oak), Quercus petraea (oak), Castanea sativa, Anemone nemorosa, Convallaria majalis, Prunus padus, Pteridium aquilinum, Athyrium filix-femina, Calamagrostis epigejos, Calluna vulgaris, Cytisus scoparius, Dryopteris filix-mas, Sorbus aucuparia, Cytisus scoparius, Holcus lanatus, Holcus mollis, Juncus effusus, Molinia caerulea, Persicaria hydropiper, Urtica dioica, Acer pseudoplatanus, Convallaria majalis, Maianthemum bifolium, Carpinus</italic> sp<italic>.., Corylus avellana, Cerasus sp, Sambucus nigra,Crataegus monogyna, Vaccinium myrtillus / Pinus, Hedera helix, Rubus fructicosus, Quercus robur &#x00026; Carpinus</italic> sp<italic>., Molinia caerulea</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Soils: loam or silt with limestone, clay and limestone or schists, leaf litter, schist in Famenne, limestone from Givet, sandstone, poor acid sandy soils, siliceous rock, nettles, impermeable clay soils<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Habitat: grazed pasture, forest ecotone, mixed acidophilous to acidophilous oak stands, birch stand with eagle fern, grassy path, garden, urban parcs, forest, dense thicket of beech, forest secondary pine poor acid sandy soils<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>D. reticulatus</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Capreolus capreolus, Cervus elaphus, Homo sapiens, Canis lupus familiaris</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Plant species: g<italic>rasses, hawthorn, blackthorn (Prunus spinosa), brambles blackberry (Rubus fruticosus), birch (Betula pendula), mixture of grasses, hornbeam (Carpinus betulus), woodland (mainly Picea abies), ferns (Pteridium aquilinum), jennets (Genista scorpius), oak (Quercus robur)</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Habitat: Fallow land, marshland, pasture used for grazing, woodland open<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>I. hexagonus</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Felis silvestris catus, Canis lupus familiaris, Ericaneus europeus, Cervus elaphus, mustela putorius</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Rabbit burrow, in herbis, in grassy nest, in house, burrow of <italic>Meles meles</italic>, endolithe nest of <italic>Coloeus monedula</italic>, pasture with edges or forest, impermeable clay soils, cave, burrow of fox<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>I. canisuga</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Polecat: Mustela putorius</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Riparian nest<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>I. trianguliceps</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Rodents, Rattus rattus, Rattus norvegicus, Apodemus sylvaticus, Clethrionomys glareolus</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Burrow of rodents<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>I. acuminatus</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Rodents: Apodemus sylvaticus</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>I. frontalis</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Birds: Parus major, Turdus merula, Sylvia atricapilla, Cyanistes caeruleus, Sturnus vulgaris, Parus montanus, Turdus viscivoru</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">It is sometimes found in understorey vegetation, experimental nest box<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>I. arboricola</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Birds: Parus major, Cyanistes caeruleus, Sitta europea, Corvus monedula</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Occurs in particular in bird nests inside cavities (like tree-holes for example), nest, Delichon urbica nest, experimental nest box<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>I. lividus</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Birds: Riparia riparia</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Riparia riparia (nest)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>R. sanguineus</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Canis lupus familiaris</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">house<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>A. reflexus</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Columba livia</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">flat, house, dovecot<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>A.. vespertilionis</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Bats: Pipistrellus pipistrellus, Eptesicus serotinus, rhinocephalus hipposideros</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>I. vespertilionis</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Bats: Rhinolophus hipposideros, Rhinolophus ferrumequinum, Barbastelle, Myotis myotis</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">Cave wall and on stalagmites<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>H.aegyptium</italic></td><td align="left"><italic>Tortoise: Testudo graeca, Testudo mauritanica</italic></td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap position="float" id="T4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>Seasonality of tick observations (number of ticks) in Belgium</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left">&#x000a0;</th><th align="left"><bold>Jan</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Feb</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Mar</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Apr</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>May</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Jun</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Jul</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Aug</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Sep</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Oct</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Nov</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Dec</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>I. ricinus</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">22<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1008<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">851<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2333<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1288<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1979<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1559<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">978<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">948<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">158<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">60<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>D. reticulatus</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">150<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">12<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">38<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">117<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>I. hexagonus</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">4<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">13<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">9<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">32<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">13<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">13<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">3<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>I. canisuga</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>I. trianguliceps</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>I. acuminatus</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>I. frontalis</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">10<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">5<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>I. arboricola</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">196<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>I. lividus</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">3<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">13<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">14<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>R. sanguineus</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">6<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">49<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>A. reflexus</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">5<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">100<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>A. vespertilionis</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">4<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">3<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>I. vespertilionis</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">5<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">4<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">11<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">1<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">8<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">2<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>H. aegyptium</italic></td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">22</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p>Co-occurrence of tick species in some sites raises the question of potential interactions with species recorded together on the same hosts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>], or their eggs found in the same shelter [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>]. Sites with high diversity of tick species might be hot spots of potential micro-organism exchanges. Indeed, although ticks specific, for example, to birds rarely bite humans, they might maintain a cycle of pathogens in their host populations. Those might be picked up by the generalist species <italic>I. ricinus</italic>, and passed onto humans [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>]. The possibility that co-occurring exotic and local species might facilitate establishment of exotic micro-organisms should be investigated.</p></sec><sec><title>Microorganisms associated to tick species</title><p>In addition to potential paralysis caused by the saliva of some female ticks, which seems very rare in Europe [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">46</xref>], the main impact of ticks on human health is through transmission of pathogens. Ticks acquire microorganisms through an infected meal or transovarial transmission. Micro-organisms recorded in ticks might come from a recent blood meal and presence in a tick does not mean that this tick species is a competent vector. For Ixodidae ticks feeding once per stage, the microorganisms need to survive molting and be transmitted to the next host while argasidae nymphs and adults bite repeatedly. Then, to be a pathogenic for humans, they must cause symptoms in humans. A list of 300 recorded micro-organism/tick associations is presented in Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3">3</xref>. Some sources have a low reliability but this exhaustive list is a basis for systematic investigations and reliability of vector status and pathogenicity are compiled to propose priorities for investigations. Associations are recorded mostly outside Belgium as this was little investigated in the country. Notably, while mycoplasmas are increasingly related to ticks in the USA [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">47</xref>], and their prevalence is increasing throughout Europe [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">48</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B49">49</xref>], there are no investigations of <italic>Mycoplasma</italic> in Belgian tick species in the literature.</p><p>For ticks present in Belgium, more than 100 associations with tick-borne (suspected) pathogens have been documented (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">5</xref>) with some recorded in Belgium (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). Pathogenic <italic>Borrelia</italic> (<italic>Borrelia burgdorferi</italic> s.s<italic>., B. valaisana, B. garinii, B. afzelii, B. spielmanii</italic>), <italic>Anaplasma phagocythophilum</italic> and suspected pathogens such as <italic>Borrelia lusitaniae</italic> and <italic>Rickettsia</italic> (<italic>R. helvetica</italic>, <italic>Rickettsia</italic> sp., <italic>R. massilae)</italic> seem to be present throughout the country. Transovarial transmission of some <italic>Babesia</italic> species including <italic>Babesia divergens</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B50">50</xref>], <italic>B venatorum</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B51">51</xref>], (but not <italic>B. microti</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B52">52</xref>] occurs in <italic>I. ricinus</italic>. A <italic>Babesia</italic> belt goes from Couvin (site 212) to Verviers (site 667) and has been documented for many years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B53">53</xref>]. Other sites are based on ticks found on dogs and the place of infection is unsure, but a local focus of <italic>Babesia canis</italic> exists near Mons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B54">54</xref>]. Some sites show a high diversity with more than 5 (suspected) pathogens. In site 575 (Genk), 481 (Ham) and 271 (Boortmeerbeek), high diversity might be linked to the presence of many ticks from many hosts. This means that (1) those localities have a higher diversity of (suspected) pathogens or (2) diversity is high everywhere but picked up there because of abundant tick material, or (3) diversity is high when ticks are abundant. Site 575 presents five pathogens (<italic>Borreliae burgdorferi</italic> s.s<italic>., B. valaisiana, B. afzelii, B. garinii</italic> and <italic>A. phagocytophilum</italic>) and three suspected pathogens (<italic>B. lusitaniae</italic>, <italic>Rickettsia helvetica and Rickettsia</italic> sp<italic>.</italic>) found in ticks collected from 38 cats (quite sedentary), thus suggesting a potential local transmission. Most interestingly, 4 pathogens (<italic>A. phagocytophilum</italic>, <italic>B. burgdorferi</italic> s.s<italic>., B. afzelii, B. garinii</italic>) and two suspected pathogens (<italic>Babesia</italic> sp<italic>.</italic>, <italic>Anaplasma</italic> sp.) were recorded from unfed <italic>I. ricinus</italic> nymphs (135 ticks) during flagging at site 297 (Vierves-sur-Viroin), highlighting vector status and local presence of the pathogens. This area seems to be a hot spot of <italic>I. ricinus</italic> abundance and the only place with up to 6 potential pathogens recorded in unfed questing ticks. Site 64 (Chercq) stands out with 5 cats harbouring 60 <italic>I. ricinus</italic> but no pathogens.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Tick/micro-organism associations for which pathogenic status and vector status for human should be investigated as a priority: pathogens and suspected pathogens/tick species associations found abroad or in Belgium referenced in the literature for tick species found in Belgium</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left"><bold>Tick species</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>V/U</bold></th><th align="left"><bold><italic>Borrelia</italic></bold></th><th align="left"><bold><italic>Babesia</italic></bold></th><th align="left"><bold><italic>Rickettsia</italic></bold></th><th align="left"><bold><italic>Coxiella, Franciscella Anaplasma</italic></bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Virus</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Other</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>I. ricinus</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">V<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold><italic>burgdorferi sensu stricto</italic></bold><italic>*</italic><bold><italic>, afzelii</italic></bold><italic>*</italic><bold><italic>, garinii</italic></bold><italic>*, </italic><bold><italic>lusitaniae valaisiana</italic></bold><italic>*</italic><bold><italic>, spielmanii</italic></bold><italic>*, </italic>sp <bold><italic>bavariensis</italic></bold><italic>*, miyamotoi*,</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold><italic>venatorum</italic></bold><italic>*</italic><bold><italic>, divergens</italic></bold><italic>*</italic><bold><italic>, microti</italic></bold><italic>*</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold><italic>helvetica</italic></bold><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>F. tularensis* </italic><bold><italic>A. phagocytophilum</italic></bold><italic>*</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>CCHF*, TBEV*, Louping Ill*</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">U<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>ruskii</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>bovis, bigemina, rodhaini</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>prowazekii*, </italic><bold><italic>conorii</italic></bold><italic>*</italic><bold><italic>,</italic></bold><italic>slovaca*, monacensis*, felis*, massiliae*, typhi*, sp.</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold><italic>C. burnetii</italic></bold><italic>*</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>WNV*, Eyack*, Erve* Tettnang*, Tribec*, KEMV*</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Bartonella henselae*, Serratia marcescens*, Staphylococcus aureus*, Candidatus Neoehrlichia mikurensis*, Toxoplasma gondii*, Pasteurella pneumotropica*, Chromobacterium violaceum*, Pseudomonas aeruginosa*, Diplorickettsia massilinsis</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>I. frontalis</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">U<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold><italic>afzelii</italic></bold><italic>*</italic><bold><italic>, garinii</italic></bold><italic>*</italic><bold><italic>, turdi-like burgdorferi sensu lato,</italic></bold><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>C. burnetii*</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>KEMV*, TBEV*</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Candidatus Neoehrlichia mikurensis*</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>I. acuminatus</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">U<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>burgdorferi sensu lato</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>C. burnetii* F. tularensis*</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Bhanja</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>I. hexagonus</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">V<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold><italic>burgdorferi sensu lato</italic></bold><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>TBEV*</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">U<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold><italic>burgdorferi sensu stricto</italic></bold><italic>*, </italic><bold><italic>valaisiana</italic></bold><italic>*, </italic><bold><italic>spielmanii</italic></bold><italic>*, </italic><bold><italic>garinii</italic></bold><italic>*, </italic><bold><italic>afzelii</italic></bold><italic>*, </italic><bold><italic>lusitaniae</italic></bold><italic>, bavariensis*</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>microti*, bovis</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>conorii*, </italic><bold><italic>helvetica</italic></bold><italic>, </italic><bold>sp.</bold><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold><italic>A. phagocytophilum</italic></bold><italic>*</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Erve*</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>I. arboricola</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">U<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><bold><italic>garinii</italic></bold><italic>*</italic><bold><italic>, valaisiana</italic></bold><italic>* </italic><bold><italic>afzelii</italic></bold><italic>*</italic><bold><italic>, burgdorferi sensu lato, spielmanii</italic></bold><italic>*</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>helvetica, </italic>sp.<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>TBEV*</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>I. lividus</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">U<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>burgdorferi sensu stricto*, garinii*</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>(heilongjiangensis), </italic>sp.<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>C. burnetii*</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>TBEV* Kama</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>I. canisuga</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">U<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>burgdorferi sensu lato</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>TBEV*</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Yersinia pestis </italic>(<italic>Plague</italic>) <italic>*</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>I. trianguliceps</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">V<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>microti*</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">U<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>burgdorferi sensu lato, afzelii*, garinii*</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>C. burnetii*, F. tularensis* A. phagocytophilum*</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Louping-ill*, TBEV*, CCHF*</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>I. vespertilionis</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">U<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Kul, TBEV*</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>D. reticulatus</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">V<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>microti*</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>sibirica*</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>C. burnetii*</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>OHF*</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">U<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>burgdorferi sensu lato</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>divergens* bigemina</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>slovaka*, canada*, conorii*, sp, helvetica*, raoultii*</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>F. tularensis* Francisella-like </italic><bold><italic>A. phagocytophilum</italic></bold><italic>*</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>TBEV*</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Bartonella henselae*</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>R. sanguineus</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">V<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>conorii*</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>CCHF*</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">U<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>burgdorferi sensu lato</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>microti-like*, gibsoni</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Candidatus rickettsia kulagini, </italic><bold><italic>massiliae</italic></bold><italic>*, canis, felis*, rickettsi*, rhipicephali,</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>C. burnetii*, A. phagocytophilum*</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Thogoto*</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Ehrlichia canis, Ehrlichia ewingii Hepatozoon canis, Salmonella bacteria, Batonella vinsonii, Rangelia vitalii, Dipetalonema dracunculoides, Mycoplasma haemocanis, Leishmania infantum</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>A. reflexus</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">U<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>C. burnetii*</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>WNV*, TBEV*, NYMV, QRFV</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>A. vespertilionis</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">U<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>burgdorferi sensu lato, borrelia sp</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>C. burnetii*</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>rabies*, IK (KTR),SOK</italic><hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom"><italic>Wolbachia persica, Treponoma vespertilionis</italic><hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>H. aegyptium</italic></td><td align="left">U</td><td align="left"><italic>turcica, sp</italic></td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left"><italic>C. burnetii*</italic></td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>V </italic>confirmed vector, <italic>U </italic>unknown vector status, <italic>*</italic> recognised pathogen, <italic>WNV </italic>West Nile Virus, <italic>CCHF </italic>Crimean-Congo Hemorrhagic fever, <italic>TBEV </italic>Tick borne Encephalitis virus, <italic>QRFV</italic> Quaranfi Virus, <italic>NYMV </italic>Nyamanini virus, <italic>KTR </italic>Ketera virus, <italic>OHF</italic> Omsk Hemorrhagic fever, <italic>SOK </italic>Sokolok, <italic>IK </italic>Issyk Kul, <italic>KEMV</italic> Kemerovo. In bold pathogen recorded in Belgium. Details in Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3">3</xref>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="F2" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p><bold>Map of the micro-organisms, suspected pathogens and pathogens found in ticks of Belgium. </bold>Map of existing information on micro-organisms found in ticks in Belgium. Information is presented at the genus level but if available, details of species are provided in additional file 2. Numbers labelling each site correspond to site number in Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1756-3305-6-190-2"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Ecological traits influencing the potential vector role of tick species</title><sec><title>The major vector <italic>I. ricinus</italic> &#x02013; a generalist species</title><p><italic>I. ricinus</italic> is a confirmed vector for many human pathogens (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">5</xref>). Several factors contribute to the efficiency of <italic>I. ricinus</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">55</xref>]: (1) it is the most abundant tick species in Europe with all stages readily biting humans [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B56">56</xref>]. (2) This species takes one meal on 3 different hosts in one life cycle and parasitizes a wide range of hosts from mammals (<italic>e.g.</italic> squirrels, badgers, wild boars, cervids, foxes, dogs, cats, cows, rodents, bats) to birds (common blackbird, European robin, pheasant, nest of the Eagle owl), reptiles, lizards and amphibians [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B57">57</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B59">59</xref>]. Larvae and nymphs are found on any hosts and frequently on rodents or birds [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B60">60</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B61">61</xref>]. Adults feed on larger mammals. A large range of hosts means that there are opportunities to encounter many pathogens and disperse in many habitats, with for example <italic>I. ricinus</italic> representing 20% of ticks found on <italic>Parus major</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. (3) Phenologic plasticity is wide with all stages surviving 2&#x000a0;weeks under water, several ticks surviving at -10&#x000b0;C, and non engorged nymphs kept alive several months in a fridge (5&#x000b0;C) waking up in minutes if heated by hand contact. The species is vulnerable to desiccation and will not be encountered in arid or non-vegetated environments. Temperatures over 35&#x000b0;C for two weeks will kill all stages [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>]. Tolerance to desiccation can be higher in ticks infected by pathogens [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B62">62</xref>]. This species walks on average 40&#x000a0;cm around its questing post and finds shelter in litter or soil cracks [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">35</xref>]. While ticks interrupt questing to move down the vegetation, in order to rehydrate (quiescence), Perret <italic>et al.</italic> discovered that after dark, quiescence was often interrupted by walking events not necessarily leading to questing, with ticks walking repeatedly 9&#x000a0;m. They suggested that some of these movements represent horizontal walks if the ticks were not confined to their experimental vertical channels and that some of these movements represent activities that enable ticks to find a favourable questing site in nature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B63">63</xref>]. Similar experiments but in horizontal arenas did not record such movements [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B64">64</xref>]. <italic>I. ricinus</italic> is widely distributed in Belgium with sites of apparently higher occurrence (around sites 219, 286, 288, 374, 499) (Figure&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). Lack of standardisation impedes calculation of tick densities and tick abundance and is presented here as the total number of specimens collected in a site. While abundance is expected to decrease from East to West with decreasing forest cover, this is not what comes out of the general map. Few occurrences are recorded in the Southeast despite high forest cover, but few surveys are carried out in that region, while many surveys took place in Campine to clarify tick presence. The large abundance around the Meuse area is picked up as well as decreased abundance between the Meuse and Brussels, which corresponds to a highly cultivated area (Hesbaye). Abundance is also lower along the coast, which is intensely cultivated. High abundances are recorded along the Dutch border and might reflect an increase in tick populations such as recorded in the Netherlands. These trends need, however, to be confirmed because of the lack of standardisation in sampling.</p><fig id="F3" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p><bold>Map of </bold><bold><italic>I. ricinus </italic></bold><bold>with abundance and hot spots. </bold>Map of existing <italic>I. ricinus</italic> records in Belgium. Abundance is based on number of ticks collected and is not standardized between sites. Collection lasted days in some sites and only a few hours in other sites, however, details on collection methods are often lacking and raw numbers of collected ticks are thus presented. Numbers labelling each site correspond to site number in Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="1756-3305-6-190-3"/></fig></sec><sec><title>Secondary vectors <italic>I. hexagonus</italic> and <italic>D. reticulatus</italic></title><p><italic>I. hexagonus</italic> is a confirmed vector of <italic>B. burgdorferi s.l.</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B65">65</xref>] with 28% prevalence recorded [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B66">66</xref>]. It is a nidiculous species found in burrows and occasionally in caves [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>]. This reduces human vector contact but several characteristics must be highlighted: 1) human infestations were frequent during the war when people sheltered in underground sites during air raids [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">45</xref>] and <italic>I. hexagonus</italic> is considered a common parasite of man in Germany and the United Kingdom [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>], 2) the species has a wide range of hosts such as hedgehogs, mustelids, foxes, polecat, badger, roe deer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>], as well as dogs and cats which can increase the spread of ticks and import ticks in gardens close to humans, 3) <italic>I. hexagonus</italic> is found in urban gardens [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>], 4) most hedgehogs are infested [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B67">67</xref>] and the presence of ticks in their surface nests is a potential threat when gardening [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">33</xref>], 5) This species brings pathogens to people normally not at risk for tick bites (just gardening) and can remain undetected for a longer time, 6) it is active throughout the year [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B68">68</xref>], 7) because of <italic>B. burgdorferi s.l.</italic> transovarial transmission [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B65">65</xref>], this species could maintain a silent high rate of infection creating long term foci of high infection in the wildlife in areas where it acts as reservoir, 8) finally, Lyme borreliosis could be picked up by <italic>I. ricinus</italic> sharing the same host. In Belgium, <italic>I. hexagonus</italic> is widespread on cats and dogs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>] and has been observed on many mammals (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>), on humans [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>], in nests, burrows, caves (sites 594, 617), house (site 200) and on grass (sites 492, 670). Populations might fluctuate between years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. The species in Belgium carries all the pathogenic species of <italic>Borrelia burgdorferi s.l</italic>., <italic>A. phagocytophilum</italic> as well as the suspected pathogen <italic>R. helvetica</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>].</p><p><italic>D. reticulatus</italic> might be restricted to limited areas and not actively questing in the warm months when people are entering risky areas. <italic>D. reticulatus</italic> is reported on wild boar, cervids, dogs, horses and cats in the French Ardennes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">37</xref>], wolves or rarely birds [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>]. It can bite humans [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B69">69</xref>]. Adults are captured by flagging but immatures are nidiculous. This species seems to be expanding its distribution in Europe. In Belgium, the tick has probably been present for some time with one specimen recorded on vegetation in 1950 (site 553), on a dog (site 567) and a human in the eighties (site 376). Established populations have only recently been monitored. Between 2007 and 2009, 16 out of 2297 ticks taken from 161 wild cervids [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">23</xref>] (WILDSCREEN collection) were <italic>D. reticulatus.</italic> From 2010 until March 2012, 150 additional <italic>D. reticulatus</italic> were discovered on 3 cervids in 6 sites including one confirmed by flagging (site 797). Confirmation of the species at a molecular level was carried out when sequences of the 646&#x000a0;bp of a part of the ITS2 gene were successfully obtained for 16 <italic>D. reticulatus</italic>. These 6 sites are in the Southeast but this tick is found on vegetation in the North (60, 130, 172, 535) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">34</xref>] and on hosts in other locations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Ticks parasite of birds</title><p>Birds probably carry ticks to most geographical locations but this does not mean that ticks will survive in these locations. The presence of all pathogenic species of <italic>B. burgdorferi s.l.</italic> in <italic>I. frontalis</italic> and <italic>I. arboricola</italic> in Belgium suggests a potential role in the <italic>Borrelia</italic> life cycle [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. Up to 50% of <italic>I. frontalis</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B69">69</xref>] and also <italic>I. lividus</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B70">70</xref>] were infected with <italic>B. burgdorferi s.l</italic>. in other countries. While seldom reported as biting humans, they might maintain the pathogen cycle in wildlife<italic>. I. frontalis</italic> (previously <italic>I. pari</italic>) is associated with a broad range of songbirds, including thrushes (Turdidae), the Great tit and the collared dove [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>], with up to 30 specimens per bird [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B71">71</xref>]. <italic>I. frontalis</italic> is occasionally collected by flagging [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B72">72</xref>] and evidence suggests that it might be more often present in under-storey vegetation than in nests [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">7</xref>]. In Belgium it has been found on birds in 11 sites. <italic>I. arboricola</italic> is found mainly in Europe but was recorded in Egypt on birds coming back to Europe [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. It is a nidicolous tick infesting birds and bats [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B73">73</xref>]. The Great tit might be the dominant host but heavy infestations occur on the Common starling and Peregrine falcon [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">32</xref>]. In Belgium it was recorded in 10 places including 3 sites with 70 specimens (sites 233, 252, 337) where the species was actively surveyed. Specimens were found on birds (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T3">3</xref>) and in nests of the House martin. <italic>I. lividus</italic> is found on the Sand martin and in their nests [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. Experimental records showed that these ticks were collected on the Great tit [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B74">74</xref>] and it was found repeatedly in nests of the House martin in Japan [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B75">75</xref>].</p></sec><sec><title>Ticks parasite of rodents and small mammals</title><p>Small mammals and particularly rodents are reservoirs of many diseases, but few studies have targeted ticks on rodents in Belgium. Next to <italic>I. ricinus</italic> and <italic>I. hexagonus</italic>, ticks present on rodents and small mammals include <italic>I. canisuga, I. trianguliceps</italic> and <italic>I. acuminatus.</italic> These species are carriers of some pathogens (Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T5">5</xref>) including <italic>B. burgdorferi s.l.</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B76">76</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B78">78</xref>] with 30% prevalence for <italic>I. canisuga</italic> in Spain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B66">66</xref>]. <italic>I. canisuga</italic> is part of a group of species difficult to discriminate morphologically (including <italic>I. hexagonus</italic>, <italic>I. arboricola</italic> and <italic>I. lividus</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. <italic>I. canisuga</italic> is widely distributed and found on half of the foxes in Northern France [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">30</xref>] but also on polecats, weasels, badgers, Eurasian owls, dogs and cats [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B79">79</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B80">80</xref>] with up to 200 specimens reported on one dog [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B81">81</xref>]. In Great Britain, 11% of the ticks found on dogs were <italic>I. canisuga</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B80">80</xref>] but none were reported in a Belgian survey [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>]. This nidiculous species is found in nests, burrows or rarely in caves [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>] with fed females climbing upwards in crevices above ground [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]. In Belgium, only two specimens were found, on a polecat (site 132) and a nest (site 207). <italic>I. trianguliceps</italic> is found almost exclusively on micromammals including shrews and rodents, exceptionally on moles, birds or goats and very rarely on humans [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">55</xref>]. The tick is nidiculous but may wait for hosts on the soil surface [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B82">82</xref>]. It is commonly found in wet biotopes including moorlands, meadows, or pine, deciduous and birch forests [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B83">83</xref>]. In France, immature are found with immature of <italic>D. reticulatus</italic>, <italic>I. acuminatus</italic>, and <italic>I. ricinus</italic> on the same rodents [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B84">84</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B85">85</xref>]. In Belgium, <italic>I. trianguliceps</italic> is probably frequent and found on rodents in 8 sites. <italic>I. acuminatus</italic> parasitizes small mammals, birds and sometimes humans and is mostly found in nests and burrows [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>]. Only one specimen was found in Belgium on a wood mouse (site 630).</p></sec><sec><title>Other tick species sharing habitats with humans</title><p>Three tick species are not frequent but bite humans and can establish populations inside houses, making them a potential threat. <italic>Rhipicephalus sanguineus</italic> is a tropical tick imported on dogs or rarely with hares, cattles, horses, or plants [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">55</xref>]. The tick cannot survive outside but multiplies inside houses and dog kennels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>]. Ticks hunt for hosts by moving actively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B86">86</xref>], can drink free water and survive for years inside. This was shown to cause house infestations in 12 cities in the Netherlands, in Switzerland [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B87">87</xref>] and 334 foci in Berlin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B88">88</xref>]. Tick populations can build up in some years from one engorged female to thousands of ticks and eggs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B87">87</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B89">89</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B90">90</xref>]. Eggs are hidden in cracks and crevices and ticks crawl around. Mean temperature probably limits its northward distribution [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B91">91</xref>]. This species is rarely found on humans [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>], but seems to more willingly bite humans occasionally, representing at times up to 7% of ticks biting men [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B92">92</xref>]. Up to 22 ticks on one man were reported in France [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B93">93</xref>]. Some studies suggest that this highlights a change of behaviour related to temperature increase [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B94">94</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B95">95</xref>] but this needs to be further investigated. <italic>R. sanguineus</italic> is a vector of highly pathogenic <italic>Rickettsiae conorii</italic> with confirmed transovarial passage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B96">96</xref>]. Prevalence in nymphs infesting houses can reach up to 40% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B87">87</xref>], against usually 1% [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B94">94</xref>] outside. In Belgium, <italic>R. sanguineus</italic> was found in houses in Antwerp [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>] (site 210), Hoboken (site 199) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B90">90</xref>] and Maldegem (site 71), but also on dogs with a travel history (e.g. sites 338, 426, 536, 684) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>] and on humans (site 210) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>].</p><p><italic>Argas reflexus</italic> is frequent mainly on pigeons but readily bites humans, chickens or horses in buildings in the absence of pigeons [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">55</xref>]. With <italic>Argas vespertilionis</italic> (see below) this species belongs to the Argasidae family, which differs from Ixodidae in their feeding habits. Ticks take many short meals. Nymphs and adults engorge in less than an hour. Ticks feed on eight to twelve hosts per life cycle and spend most of their life in the hosts&#x02019; habitat [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B97">97</xref>]. Building infestations are undetected for years because of nocturnal host-seeking behaviour, high host specificity and short meals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B98">98</xref>]. However, when pigeons are eradicated, <italic>A. reflexus</italic> appear seeking for alternative hosts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B97">97</xref>]. Even if the build-up of a large number of ticks takes years, thousands of ticks were found repeatedly when investigating 188 infested buildings in Germany [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B98">98</xref>]. Searching for ticks before renovating is now a current recommendation in Germany. Particularities include a long lifetime of up to 9&#x000a0;years without food, low water loss rate, absorption of water vapour at 75% relative humidity and high tolerance of temperature extremes. Movements are restricted to periods of host-seeking, the remaining time being spent resting aggregated in cracks of walls [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B97">97</xref>-<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B99">99</xref>]. In Belgium ticks were recorded in 7 sites from pigeons, pigeon houses, houses and flats. The bites may cause allergy, anaphylactic shock or loss of consciousness [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B100">100</xref>]. It is an unconfirmed vector of human pathogens.</p><p><italic>Argas vespertilionis</italic> parasitizes bats [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>]. They stay the whole year in or near caves or other shelters (roofs of houses), the hosts being present or not. Eggs were found together with eggs of <italic>I. hexagonus</italic> and <italic>I. vespertilionis</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">43</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">44</xref>]. Ticks bite alternative hosts in the absence of their usual host and readily bite man. People reported being bitten in caves or in their bed when bats are in the attics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B55">55</xref>]. Larvae attach for 19&#x000a0;days. Nymphs and adults feed in less than one hour [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B97">97</xref>]. They take many small meals on many hosts potentially accumulating pathogens. <italic>A. vespertilionis</italic> causes irritating bites on humans and viable strains of <italic>C. burnetii</italic> were isolated from ticks which had been dead for a year [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B97">97</xref>]. While 84% of museum specimens tested positive for <italic>B. burgdorferi s.l.</italic> in the UK [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B78">78</xref>], this might reflect sample contamination. <italic>Borrelia</italic> sp. organisms related to <italic>Borrelia recurrentis</italic>, <italic>B. duttonii</italic> and <italic>B. crocidurae</italic> were present in numbers in a dying bat in the UK [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B101">101</xref>] parasitized by <italic>A. vespertilionis</italic>. In Belgium, 11 ticks were found on hosts in four locations.</p></sec><sec><title>Species of little interest for human health</title><p><italic>Ixodes vespertilionis</italic> was never recorded biting man. It parasites the Lesser horseshoe and the Great bats. It actively searches for hosts by walking slowly on very long legs in caves. It is restricted to the darkest part of the caves, offering 100% humidity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">28</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B102">102</xref>]. Decrease of humidity to 61% increases tick activity until they die after a few hours. All stages are mainly found in caves, moving away with the host but coming back for molting and egg laying [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B102">102</xref>]. Specimens are not on the ground but on walls and roof crevices. In West France low densities are present in most caves. Ticks were found in caves or on bats in 10 sites in East Belgium [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">27</xref>].</p></sec></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions"><title>Conclusion</title><p>By providing a countrywide disaggregated approach on tick-borne diseases, this study provides essential preliminary information to build up a national public health policy based on spatial surveillance of tick-borne diseases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B103">103</xref>] and help to delineate priorities for future investigations. These are summarised in Table&#x000a0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="T6">6</xref>. (1) Regarding tick presence, this study highlights the lack of information about current species, and the need to search for species present in bordering regions. (2) In terms of tick distribution, occurrence data offers a useful picture, and this, particularly if the lack of detailed distribution of major determinants (hosts, predators) impeded building of adequate distribution models. However, modelling tick distribution could provide information in places not surveyed, clarify ecology and attach local probabilities to tick presence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B104">104</xref>]. For modelling exophilic tick distribution (<italic>I. ricinus</italic> and <italic>D. reticulatus</italic>)<italic>,</italic> examples in the field of malaria vectors show that occurrences can prove useful to delineate species distribution [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B105">105</xref>]. However, models perform better when explanatory variables englobe most ecologically relevant parameters [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B106">106</xref>]. Because of their influence on ticks and on the pathogens presence and abundance, distribution of relevant host species or valuable proxies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">3</xref>] should be integrated in the models with major habitat characteristics. Distribution of nidiculous species could be approached by mapping their specific hosts. (3) Because of the above, the potential roles (hosts, pathogen reservoir versus accidental host [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B107">107</xref>], influencing tick abundance, influencing pathogen prevalence, and predators) of the birds, mammals, reptiles, amphibian or other local species should be assessed and their distribution investigated. (4) With regards to pathogens, their presence needs to be clarified. The list of micro-organisms/tick associations provided here needs to be narrowed by investigating pathogenicity, identifying reservoirs (ticks and other species), selecting pathogens for which reservoirs are present, and identifying vector capacity for associated ticks. (5) With regards to pathogen distribution, pathogens should be monitored in ticks, reservoirs or any hosts to provide a spatial distribution per pathogen. (6) Human vector contact could be approached using public knowledge from groups at risk, such as nature lovers, hunters, foresters, veterinarians, health practitioners or even the general public. Such facilities for recording tick bites were developed successfully in the Netherlands [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref>]. (7) Finally a risk map should provide the following locally: integration of the above distribution maps to determine the probability of being bitten by a tick, to obtain an infected tick bite per pathogen, and a list of potential pathogens locally. In this context, potential hotspots could be identified as well as places needing further investigation. This would provide a spatial disaggregation of risk and prepare analysis of seasonal or yearly variations.</p><table-wrap position="float" id="T6"><label>Table 6</label><caption><p>Main findings and suggestions for further research priorities</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups" border="1"><colgroup><col align="left"/><col align="left"/><col align="left"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th align="left">&#x000a0;</th><th align="left"><bold>Current knowledge</bold></th><th align="left"><bold>Suggestions for future research priorities</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Tick presence<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02022;&#x02009;The current national list of occurring tick species (not previously available)<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02022;&#x02009;Search for tick species recorded in neighbouring countries country (targeting prefered host species or habitat)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="top">Tick distribution<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02022;&#x02009;A first distribution map for <italic>Ixodes ricinus </italic>based on occurrences which highlights presence of the species in all the provinces<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02022;&#x02009;Build up a distribution model for exophilic species such as <italic>Ixodes ricinus </italic>and <italic>Dermacentor reticulatus </italic>based on habitat preferences and distribution of other influencing species<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02022;&#x02009;Current very partial knowledge of distribution for the other tick species<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02022;&#x02009;Build up a distribution model for nidiculous species based on distribution of major host species<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02022;&#x02009;Perform a systematic tick survey across the country<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">Tick hosts/ reservoirs<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02022;&#x02009;Provide for each tick a list of hosts on which they have been recorded in the country<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02022;&#x02009;For each local vertebrate species check potential host status for each tick species or potential influence on tick population<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02022;&#x02009;Map the distribution of relevant species<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="4" align="left" valign="top">Presence of pathogens<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02022;&#x02009;Potential presence of pathogens such as <italic>Borrelia burgdoferi s.l. </italic>in many tick species<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02022;&#x02009;Check the pathogenicity of each micro-organisms species<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02022;&#x02009;List of microorganisms potentially present locally or aborad in local ticks species<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02022;&#x02009;For pathogenic microorganisms check vector status of associated ticks Identify presence of potential reservoirs for pathogens (tick/ hosts)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02022;&#x02009;List of tick/ micro-organisms associations<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02022;&#x02009;Investigate pathogen distribution across species to better comprehend<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02022;&#x02009;risk before modelling risk map<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="2" align="left" valign="top">Pathogen distribution<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02022;&#x02009;First map of (suspected) pathogens found in ticks<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02022;&#x02009;Search for additional pathogens in ticks of the country<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02022;&#x02009;Make a pathogen distribution map (found in ticks, hosts, reservoirs)<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">Human-vector contact<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02022;&#x02009;Use public knowledge from nature defense group, scouts, veterinary, general practitioner to localise and quantify tick bites<hr/></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3" align="left" valign="top">Tick-borne diseases risk map</td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02022;&#x02009;Some hot spot with highest <italic>I. ricinus </italic>abundance are highlighted but because of unreliable sampling those should be further investigated<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02022;&#x02009;Investigate presence and prevalence of pathogenic species<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x000a0;<hr/></td><td align="left" valign="bottom">&#x02022;&#x02009;Make a countrywide standardised survey to allow comparing abundance between sites.<hr/></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#x000a0;</td><td align="left">&#x02022;&#x02009;In a given area, what is the probability 1) to get a tick bite, 2) that this tick was infected with pathogens 3) infected by which pathogen(s)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><p><italic>I. ricinus</italic> is the main vector of diseases in Belgium because it is present in most vegetated areas, carries many pathogens and is responsible for most tick bites in humans. Its distribution highlights the possibility of becoming infected by the pathogenic agent of Lyme borreliosis in any province. Other species might play a role by maintaining pathogens present in wildlife, or by bringing pathogens closer to people in their houses and gardens. While the number of bites on humans caused by other species is less than by <italic>I. ricinus</italic>, occurrence of such an event in unexpected areas such as houses or gardens or during the winter season extends the risk to people not considered to be at risk and increases the probability of a tick bite being ignored. Some places seem to pose a greater risk with more abundant tick populations, higher diversity of pathogens or both, but this should be confirmed. Current prevention measures target <italic>B. burgdorferi s.l.</italic> mainly through deticking. Other pathogens are increasingly investigated and found in domestic animals, wildlife or humans and transmission of some of those can occur at the time of the tick bite without delay (e.g. TBEV). Avoidance behaviour should be promoted such as avoiding areas with ferns [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B108">108</xref>], wearing boots and long trousers or repellent, using deticking as the second line measure. Another reason to avoid ticks is that in Belgium only 30% of Lyme patients remember a bite and 35% never develop <italic>Erythema migrans</italic>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B109">109</xref>]. Lyme disease can be difficult to diagnose in the absence of <italic>Erythema migrans</italic> and particularly if additional symptoms are caused by co-occurring pathogens.</p><p>The analysis of the presence of pathogens in ticks might be easier than in human blood as organisms are more easily detected by PCR in ticks than in blood. Systematic surveys using ticks as sentinels could assess the prevalence of the pathogens in wildlife. Geolocation of tick and pathogen records allows integration into a more general databases such as those developed in the framework of The Vbornet [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>] or the TICK MAP initiative [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B110">110</xref>] and could help fulfil the empty maps for tick and tick-borne disease occurrence in Belgium [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref>]. This study based on imperfect sampling data calls for an increased surveillance of ticks and tick-borne species at a detailed spatial scale as well as clarification of local vector status for tick species and pathogens which occur in these species. A systematic survey of ticks and associated pathogens is called for in Europe, as well as better characterisation of species interaction in the ecology of tick-borne diseases.</p></sec><sec><title>Abbreviations</title><p>ARSIA: Association R&#x000e9;gionale de Sant&#x000e9; et d&#x02019;Identification Animale; BLAST: Basic Local Alignment Search Tool; CCHFV: Crimean Congo Hemorrhagic Fever virus; DGZ: Dierengezonheidzorg Animal Health Care Flanders Belgium; DNA: deoxyribonucleic acid; dNTP: deoxy ribonucleotide triphosphate; IK: Issuk Kul virus; IRSIA: Institut pour l&#x02032;encouragement de la recherche dans l&#x02032;industrie et l&#x02032;agriculture; IRSNB: Institut Royal des Sciences Naturelles de Belgique; ITS2: second Internal Transcribed Spacer 2; LIV: Looping Ill virus; OHFV: Omsk Hemorragic fever virus; PCR: Polymerase Chain Reaction; RLVBD: Reference Laboratory for Vector Borne Disease; SOK: Sokuluk virus; TBEV: Tick-borne Encephalitis virus; UA: University of Antwerp collection; UGENT FOREST: Ghent University, Forestry department collection; UGENT VETE: Ghent University, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine; UCLIREC: Universit&#x000e9; Catholique de Louvain Clinical and experimental research institute; WILDSCREEN: Network for disease surveillance in wildlife; WNV: West Nyle virus.</p></sec><sec><title>Competing interests</title><p>The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>VO: Design of the study, compilation of the record, writing up of the manuscript. MW: Organisation of data collection, tick and pathogens identification, writing up the manuscript. AL: Organisation of data collection, revising the manuscript. EC: Details on data collection, revising the manuscript. PH: Organisation of data collection, tick and pathogens identification, revising the manuscript. DH: Organisation of data collection, tick and pathogens identification, writing up the manuscript. MM: Organisation of data collection, tick and pathogens identification, revising the manuscript. JM: Organisation of data collection, revising the manuscript. ML: Details on data collection, revising the manuscript. WT: Details on data collection, revising the manuscript. LL: Details on data collection, tick and pathogens identification, revising the manuscript. TH: tick and pathogens identification, revising the manuscript. GvI: Collected many data, tick identification, advice on manuscript design, provided expert knowledge, and revised the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final version of the manuscript.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S1"><caption><title>Additional file 1</title><p><bold>Detailed information available per sites of occurrence for ticks recorded in Belgium.</bold> Description: table per site with geographical coordinates in latitude-longitude and in Belgian Lambert, list of records included in the site, list of species included in the sites, literature/collection references for the sites and general quality level. Additionally to the main tab a Memo tab describes each field. </p></caption><media xlink:href="1756-3305-6-190-S1.xls"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S2"><caption><title>Additional file 2</title><p><bold>Records of tick occurrence in Belgium. </bold>Description: a kmz file to open in Google Earth with 5 folders to navigate into the database. (1) Records per tick species: one point per record classified in folders by tick species, (2) Records per pathogens: one point per record classified in folders by pathogen genus then species, (3) Records per authors: one point per record classified in folders by authors, (4) Sites: one point per site with information on tick species and pathogens, (5) Records: One point per record with information available in the Additional file <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1">1</xref> included.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1756-3305-6-190-S2.kmz"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="S3"><caption><title>Additional file 3</title><p><bold>Micro-organisms found locally or abroad in tick species present or potentially present in Belgium. </bold>Description: tick species, reference of the article and details on the records, discussion on pathogenicity to humans and potential transmission by tick species, and pathogenicity status as well as reference to specific articles and overall assessment of vector status.</p></caption><media xlink:href="1756-3305-6-190-S3.xls"><caption><p>Click here for file</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><sec><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>Many thanks to Adrien Nahayo and other collaborators of the WILDSCREEN network for monitoring of diseases in wildlife and for their time and effort in collecting ticks. The authors would also like to thank Philippe Martin from the Saint-Luc hospital in Bouge Belgium, Thomas Kesteman from the UCL IREC Institute, the staff of the Royal Institute for Natural Sciences of Belgium (IRSNB) including Georges Wauthy and L&#x000e9;on Baert, the staff of GlaxoSmithKline including Yves Lobet and Pierre Voet for providing fresh records or additional details on their published records. The authors are grateful to the nature organisation NATAGORA and NATUURPUNT and particularly Wouter Vanreusel, Marc Herremans, Karin Gielen, Jean-Yves Paquet and Antoine Derouaux for providing details and numerous records of tick location. Thanks to Sophie Vanwambeke, Eva De Clercq, Sen li and Nienke Harteminck for support and raw literature. Thanks to BAYER for accepting to share their records for our research. Many thanks to the Belgian Sciences Policy Office for funding this work through the STEREO II project for Earth Observation (MULTITICK project).</p></sec><ref-list><ref id="B1"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Heyman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Cochez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hofhuis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Van der Giessen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Sprong</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Porter</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name><name><surname>Losson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Saegerman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Donoso-Mantke</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Niedrig</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Papa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>A clear and present danger: tick-borne diseases in Europe</article-title><source>Expert Rev of Anti-Infe</source><year>2010</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>33</fpage><lpage>50</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1586/eri.09.118</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hofhuis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Harms</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Van der Giessen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Sprong</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Notermans</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Pelt</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><article-title>Ziekte van Lyme in Nederland 1994&#x02013;2009: Aantal huisartsconsulten blijft toenemen. Is voorlichting en curatief beleid genoeg?</article-title><source>Infectieziekten Bull</source><year>2010</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>84</fpage><lpage>87</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sprong</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hofhuis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gassner</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Takken</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobs</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>van Vliet</surname><given-names>AJH</given-names></name><name><surname>van Ballegooijen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Giessen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Takumi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><article-title>Circumstantial evidence for an increase in the total number and activity of Borrelia-infected <italic>Ixodes ricinus</italic> in the Netherlands</article-title><source>Parasit Vectors</source><year>2012</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>294</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1756-3305-5-294</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23244453?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23244453</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Estrada-Pe&#x000f1;a</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Farkas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaenson</surname><given-names>TGT</given-names></name><name><surname>Koenen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Madder</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pascucci</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Salman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Tarr&#x000e9;s-Call</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Jongejan</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><article-title>Association of environmental traits with the geographic ranges of ticks (Acari: Ixodidae) of medical and veterinary importance in the western Palearctic. A digital data set</article-title><source>Experiment Appl Acarol</source><year>2013</year><volume>59</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>351</fpage><lpage>366</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10493-012-9600-7</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><mixed-citation publication-type="other"><source>VBORNET European network for arthropod vector surveillance for human public health</source><comment>[<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.vbornet.eu/">http://www.vbornet.eu/</ext-link>]</comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>EFSA Panel on Animal Health and Welfare (AHAW)</collab><article-title>Scientific opinion on geographic distribution of tick-borne infections and their vectors in Europe and the other regions of the Mediterranean basin</article-title><source>EFSA J</source><year>2010</year><volume>8</volume><issue>9</issue><fpage>1723</fpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Heylen</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Tijsse</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Fonville</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Matthysen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Sprong</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><article-title>Transmission dynamics of <italic>Borrelia burgdorferi s.l.</italic> in a bird tick community</article-title><source>Environ Microbiol</source><year>2013</year><volume>15</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>663</fpage><lpage>673</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/1462-2920.12059</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23279105?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23279105</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wielinga</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Gaasenbeek</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Fonville</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>de Boer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>de Vries</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Dimmers</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Akkerhuis Op Jager</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Schouls</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Borgsteede</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Giessen</surname><given-names>JWB</given-names></name><article-title>Longitudinal analysis of tick densities and <italic>borrelia</italic>, <italic>anaplasma</italic>, and <italic>ehrlichia</italic> infections of <italic>ixodes ricinus</italic> ticks in different habitat areas in the Netherlands</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2006</year><volume>72</volume><issue>12</issue><fpage>7594</fpage><lpage>7601</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.01851-06</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17028227?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17028227</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><source>Tekenradar.nl</source><year>2013</year><publisher-name>The Netherlands: Publisher Wageningen University, RIVM en De Natuurkalender</publisher-name><comment>[<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.tekenradar.nl/">http://www.tekenradar.nl/</ext-link>]</comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Ducoffre</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><source>Surveillance des maladies infectieuses par un r&#x000e9;seau de laboratoires de microbiologie 2009. Tendances epid&#x000e9;miologiques 1983&#x02013;2008</source><year>2009</year><publisher-name>Belgian Institute for Public Health (ISP-WIV): Belgium</publisher-name><comment>[http://www.iph.fgov.be/epidemio/epifr/plabfr/plabanfr/index09.htm. <italic>Rapport</italic> 2009]</comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vanthomme</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Bossuyt</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Boffin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Casteren</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><article-title>Incidence and management of presumption of Lyme borreliosis in Belgium: recent data from the sentinel network of general practitioners</article-title><source>Eur J Clin Microbiol Infect Dis</source><year>2012</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>2385</fpage><lpage>2390</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10096-012-1580-3</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22391757?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22391757</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Stanek</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Fingerle</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunfeld</surname><given-names>K-P</given-names></name><name><surname>Jaulhac</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaiser</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Krause</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kristoferitsch</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Connell</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ornstein</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Strle</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>Lyme borreliosis: clinical case definitions for diagnosis and management in Europe</article-title><source>Clin Microbiol Infect</source><year>2011</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>79</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-0691.2010.03175.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20132258?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20132258</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Claerebout</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Losson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Cochez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Casaert</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Dalemans</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>De Cat</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Madder</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Saegerman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Heyman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Lempereur</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><article-title>Ticks and associated pathogens collected from dogs and cats in Belgium</article-title><source>Parasit Vectors</source><year>2013</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>183</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1756-3305-6-183</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23777784?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23777784</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Heyman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Cochez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Simons</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanwambeke</surname><given-names>SO</given-names></name><article-title>A multi-level analysis of the relationship between environmental factors and questing <italic>Ixodes ricinus</italic> dynamics in Belgium</article-title><source>Parasit Vectors</source><year>2012</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>149</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1756-3305-5-149</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22830528?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22830528</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tack</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Madder</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Baeten</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanhellemont</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gruwez</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Verheyen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><article-title>Local habitat and landscape affect <italic>Ixodes ricinus</italic> tick abundances in forests on poor, sandy soils</article-title><source>Forest Ecol Manag</source><year>2012</year><volume>265</volume><fpage>30</fpage><lpage>36</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Tack</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Madder</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>De Frenne</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanhellemont</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gruwez</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Verheyen</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><article-title>The effects of sampling method and vegetation type on the estimated abundance of <italic>Ixodes ricinus</italic> ticks in forests</article-title><source>Exp Appl Acarol</source><year>2011</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>285</fpage><lpage>292</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10493-011-9444-6</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21431925?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21431925</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Lempereur</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lebrun</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Cuvelier</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>S&#x000e9;pult</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Caron</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Saegerman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Shiels</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Losson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><article-title>Longitudinal field study on bovine <italic>Babesia spp.</italic> and <italic>Anaplasma phagocytophilum</italic> infections during a grazing season in Belgium</article-title><source>Parasitol Res</source><year>2012</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>1525</fpage><lpage>1530</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00436-011-2657-0</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21947341?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21947341</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kesteman</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Rossi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bastien</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Brouillard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Avesani</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Olive</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Delm&#x000e9;e</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Prevalence and genetic heterogeneity of <italic>Borrelia burgdorferi sensu lato</italic> in <italic>Ixodes</italic> ticks in Belgium</article-title><source>Acta Clin Belg</source><year>2010</year><volume>65</volume><fpage>319</fpage><lpage>322</lpage><?supplied-pmid 21128558?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21128558</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Heylen</surname><given-names>DJA</given-names></name><name><surname>Madder</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Matthysen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><article-title>Lack of resistance against the tick <italic>Ixodes ricinus</italic> in two related passerine bird species</article-title><source>Int J Parasitol</source><year>2010</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>183</fpage><lpage>191</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijpara.2009.07.011</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19747483?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19747483</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Heylen</surname><given-names>DJA</given-names></name><name><surname>Matthysen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><article-title>Contrasting detachment strategies in two congeneric ticks (<italic>Ixodidae</italic>) parasitizing the same songbird</article-title><source>Parasitology</source><year>2010</year><volume>137</volume><fpage>661</fpage><lpage>667</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0031182009991582</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20025822?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20025822</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Heylen</surname><given-names>DJA</given-names></name><name><surname>Matthysen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><article-title>Differential virulence in two congeneric ticks infesting songbird nestlings</article-title><source>Parasitology</source><year>2011</year><volume>138</volume><fpage>1011</fpage><lpage>1021</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0031182011000618</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21733259?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21733259</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Heylen</surname><given-names>DJA</given-names></name><name><surname>Matthysen</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><article-title>Experimental evidence for host preference in a tick parasitizing songbird nestlings</article-title><source>Oikos</source><year>2011</year><volume>120</volume><fpage>1209</fpage><lpage>1216</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-0706.2010.19358.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B23"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Linden</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wirtgen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Volpe</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Nahayo</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Pirson</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Paternostre</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gr&#x000e9;goire</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><article-title>Surveillance of wildlife diseases in Belgium</article-title><source>Rev &#x000c9;pid San Anim</source><year>2011</year><volume>59&#x02013;60</volume><fpage>213</fpage><lpage>215</lpage><?supplied-pmid 23888493?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23888493</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zahler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gothe</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Rinder</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><article-title>Genetic evidence against a morphologically suggestive conspecificity of <italic>Dermacentor reticulatus</italic> and <italic>D. Marginatus</italic> (acari: ixodidae)</article-title><source>Int J Parasitol</source><year>1995</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>1413</fpage><lpage>1419</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0020-7519(95)00081-X</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 8719952?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8719952</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B25"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dobec</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Golubic</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Punda-Polic</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaeppeli</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Sievers</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title><italic>Rickettsia Helvetica</italic> in <italic>dermacentor reticulatus</italic> ticks</article-title><source>Emerg Infect Dis</source><year>2009</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>98</fpage><lpage>100</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3201/eid1501.080815</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19116063?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19116063</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bigaignon</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomasi</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lozes</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Gillion</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Fain</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>La maladie de Lyme en belgique:pr&#x000e9;sence du spiroch&#x000e8;te <italic>borrelia burgdorferi</italic> dans les tiques <italic>ixodes ricinus</italic> r&#x000e9;colt&#x000e9;es dans la r&#x000e9;gion mosane</article-title><source>Rev Med Liege</source><year>1989</year><volume>44</volume><issue>15&#x02013;16</issue><fpage>489</fpage><lpage>493</lpage><?supplied-pmid 2799146?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2799146</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B27"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Fain</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><source>Les tiques de belgique: acari, ixodoidea</source><year>1990</year><publisher-name>Belgium: Royal Belgian Institute of Natural Sciences Press</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B28"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Hillyard</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><source>Ticks of north-west Europe: keys and notes for identification of the species</source><year>1996</year><publisher-name>London: Linnean Society of London and the Estuarine and Coastal Sciences Association, Field Studies Council</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rageau</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>R&#x000e9;partition g&#x000e9;ographique et r&#x000f4;le pathog&#x000e8;ne des tiques (acariens: <italic>Argasidae</italic> et <italic>Ixodidae</italic>) en France</article-title><source>Wladomosci Parazytologiczne</source><year>1972</year><volume>43</volume><issue>4-6</issue><fpage>707</fpage><lpage>719</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B30"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Aubert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Contribution &#x000e0; l&#x02032;&#x000e9;tude du parasitisme du renard (<italic>Vulpes vulpes L</italic>.) par les <italic>Ixodidae</italic> (Acarina) dans le nord-est de la France</article-title><source>Acarologia</source><year>1975</year><volume>17</volume><issue>3</issue><fpage>452</fpage><lpage>479</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1266553</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B31"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Bronswijk</surname><given-names>JEMH</given-names></name><name><surname>Garben</surname><given-names>AFM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rijntjes</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><source>De teken ixodida van de benelux-landen</source><year>1979</year><publisher-name>The Netherlands: Wetenschappelijke mededelingen van de Koninklijke Nederlandse Natuurhistorische Vereniging</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B32"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Petney</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Pfaffle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Skuballa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>An annoted checklist of the ticks (Acari:<italic>Ixodida</italic>) of Germany</article-title><source>Syst Appl Acarol</source><year>2012</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>170</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gern</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Rouvinez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Toutoungi</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name><name><surname>Godfroid</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><article-title>Transmission cycles of <italic>Borrelia burgdorferi sensu lato</italic> involving <italic>Ixodes ricinus</italic> and/or <italic>I. hexagonus</italic> ticks and the European hedgehog, <italic>Erinaceus europaeus</italic>, in suburban and urban areas in Switzerland</article-title><source>Folia Parasitol</source><year>1997</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>309</fpage><lpage>314</lpage><?supplied-pmid 9437846?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9437846</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B34"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Cochez</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lempereur</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Madder</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Claerebout</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Simons</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>DE Wilde</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Linden</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Saegerman</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Heyman</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Losson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><article-title>Foci report on indigenous <italic>Dermacentor reticulatus</italic> populations in Belgium and a preliminary study of associated babesiosis pathogens</article-title><source>Med Vet Entomol</source><year>2012</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>355</fpage><lpage>358</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2915.2011.00998.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22211927?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22211927</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B35"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Aeschlimann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><source>Ixodes ricinus, Linn&#x000e9;e, 1758 Ixodoidea; Ixodidae: Essai pr&#x000e9;liminaire de synth&#x000e8;se sur la biologie de cette esp&#x000e8;ce en Suisse</source><year>1972</year><publisher-name>Switzerland: Verlag f&#x000fc;r Recht und Gesellschaft</publisher-name><?supplied-pmid 19194498?></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B36"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sch&#x000f6;ffel</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Schein</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Wittstadt</surname><given-names>U</given-names></name><name><surname>Hentsche</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>[Parasite fauna of red foxes in Berlin (West)]</article-title><source>Berl Munch Tierarztl Wochenschr</source><year>1991</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>153</fpage><lpage>157</lpage><?supplied-pmid 1872791?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1872791</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B37"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Panas</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>L&#x000e9;ger</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Kretz</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Dumesnil</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><article-title>[Ixodidae of the champagne-Ardennes region. Preliminary study]</article-title><source>Acarologia</source><year>1976</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>51</fpage><lpage>55</lpage><?supplied-pmid 948974?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">948974</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B38"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Liebisch</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahman</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><article-title>[Prevalence of the ticks <italic>dermacentor marginatus</italic> (sulzer, 1776) and <italic>dermacentor reticulatus</italic> (Fabricius, 1794) and their importance as vectors of diseases in Germany (author&#x02019;s transl)]</article-title><source>Tropenmed Parasitol</source><year>1976</year><volume>27</volume><fpage>393</fpage><lpage>404</lpage><?supplied-pmid 1006797?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1006797</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B39"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hornok</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Farkas</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><article-title>Influence of biotope on the distribution and peak activity of questing ixodid ticks in Hungary</article-title><source>Med Vet Entomol</source><year>2009</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>41</fpage><lpage>46</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2915.2008.00768.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19239612?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19239612</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B40"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Acunman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><source>Zecken and flussnahen biotopen in Baden-Wurttemberg</source><year>2010</year><publisher-name>Karlsruhe Institue of Technology: Bsc Thesis</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B41"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Barker</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Murrell</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><person-group person-group-type="editor">Bowman A, Nuttall P</person-group><article-title>Systematics and evolution of ticks with a list of valid genus and species names</article-title><source>Ticks biology, diseases and control</source><year>2008</year><publisher-name>Cambridge: Cambridge University Press</publisher-name><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>39</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B42"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dobson</surname><given-names>ADM</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Randolph</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><article-title>Tick (<italic>Ixodes ricinus</italic>) abundance and seasonality at recreational sites in the UK: hazards in relation to fine-scale habitat types revealed by complementary sampling methods</article-title><source>Ticks Tick Born Dis</source><year>2011</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>67</fpage><lpage>74</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ttbdis.2011.03.002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B43"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Arthur</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><source>British ticks</source><year>1963</year><publisher-name>London: Butterworth</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B44"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Beaucournu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Matile</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><article-title>Contribution &#x000e0; l&#x02032;inventaire faunistique des cavit&#x000e9;s souterraines de l&#x02032;Ouest de la France.3. Liste des esp&#x000e8;ces, bibliographie</article-title><source>Ann Speleol</source><year>1963</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>519</fpage><lpage>531</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B45"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bown</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lambin</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><name><surname>Telford</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogden</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><name><surname>Telfer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Woldehiwet</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><name><surname>Birtles</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><article-title>Relative importance of <italic>Ixodes ricinus</italic> and <italic>Ixodes trianguliceps</italic> as vectors for <italic>Anaplasma phagocytophilum</italic> and <italic>Babesia microti</italic> in field vole (<italic>Microtus agrestis</italic>) populations</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>2008</year><volume>74</volume><fpage>7118</fpage><lpage>7125</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/AEM.00625-08</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18820068?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18820068</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B46"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Mans</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Gothe</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Neitz</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><person-group person-group-type="editor">Bowman A, Nuttall P</person-group><article-title>Tick toxins: perspectives on paralysis and other forms of toxicoses caused by ticks</article-title><source>Ticks: biology, diseases and control</source><year>2008</year><publisher-name>Cambridge: Cambridge University Press</publisher-name><fpage>108</fpage><lpage>126</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B47"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Eskow</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Adelson</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Rao</surname><given-names>RVS</given-names></name><name><surname>Mordechai</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><article-title>Evidence for disseminated <italic>Mycoplasma fermentans</italic> in New jersey residents with antecedent tick attachment and subsequent musculoskeletal symptoms</article-title><source>J Clin Rheumatol</source><year>2003</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>87</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/01.RHU.0000062510.04724.07</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17041434?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17041434</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B48"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Polkowska</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Harjunpaa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Toikkanen</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lappalainen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Vuento</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Vuorinen</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Kauppinen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Flinck</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyytikainen</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><article-title>Increased incidence of <italic>Mycoplasma pneumoniae</italic> infection in Finland, 2010&#x02013;2011</article-title><source>Euro Surveill</source><year>2012</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>4</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B49"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Eibach</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Casalegno</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Escuret</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Billaud</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Mekki</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Frobert</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouscambert-Duchamp</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lina</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Morfin</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><article-title>Increased detection of Mycoplasma pneumoniae infection in children, Lyon, France, 2010 to 2011</article-title><source>Euro Surveill</source><year>2012</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>3</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B50"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bonnet</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Jouglin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Malandrin</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Agoulon</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>L'hostis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chauvin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Transstadial and transovarial persistence of Babesia divergens DNA in <italic>Ixodes ricinus</italic> ticks fed on infected blood in a new skin-feeding technique</article-title><source>Parasitology</source><year>2007</year><volume>134</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>197</fpage><lpage>207</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0031182006001545</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 17076925?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17076925</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B51"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bonnet</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Brisseau</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Hermouet</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jouglin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chauvin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Experimental in vitro transmission of Babesia sp. (EU1) by <italic>Ixodes ricinus</italic></article-title><source>Vet Res</source><year>2009</year><volume>40</volume><fpage>21</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1051/vetres/2009004</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19210953?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19210953</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B52"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>von Stedingk</surname><given-names>LV</given-names></name><name><surname>G&#x000fc;rtelschmid</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Granstr&#x000f6;m</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Transmission studies of babesia microti in <italic>ixodes ricinus</italic> ticks and gerbils</article-title><source>J Clin Microbiol</source><year>2002</year><volume>40</volume><issue>4</issue><fpage>1259</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1128/JCM.40.4.1259-1263.2002</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11923342?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11923342</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B53"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Famer&#x000e9;e</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Cotteleer</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Antoine</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><article-title>La bab&#x000e9;siose bovine en Belgique, une anthropozoonose envahissante et m&#x000e9;connue. Incidence des bab&#x000e9;sioses animales sur la sant&#x000e9; humaine</article-title><source>Rev Med Liege</source><year>1977</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>383</fpage><lpage>390</lpage><?supplied-pmid 897438?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">897438</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B54"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Losson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Mollet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Avez</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Malaise</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Mignon</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><article-title>Description de trois cas autochtones de babesiose canine (<italic>Babesia canis</italic>) en Belgique</article-title><source>Ann Med Vet</source><year>1999</year><volume>143</volume><fpage>119</fpage><lpage>124</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B55"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jaenson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Talleklint</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Lundqvist</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Olsen</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Chirico</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mejlon</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><article-title>Geographical distribution, host associations, and vector roles of ticks (Acari: <italic>Ixodidae</italic>, <italic>Argasidae</italic>) in Sweden</article-title><source>J Med Entomol</source><year>1994</year><volume>31</volume><fpage>240</fpage><lpage>256</lpage><?supplied-pmid 8189415?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8189415</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B56"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Estrada-Pe&#x000f1;a</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Sanchez Acedo</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Quilez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Del Cacho</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><article-title>Phenology of the tick, <italic>Ixodes ricinus</italic>, in its southern distribution range (central Spain)</article-title><source>Med Vet Entomol</source><year>2004</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>387</fpage><lpage>397</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.0269-283X.2004.00523.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15642006?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15642006</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B57"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mehl</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><article-title>The distribution and host relations of Norwegian ticks (Acari, Ixodides). Fauna Norvegica Serie B</article-title><source>Norw Journal Entomol</source><year>1983</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>46</fpage><lpage>51</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B58"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sevcik</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kristofik</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Uhrin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Benda</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><article-title>New records of ticks (Acari: Ixodidae) parasiting on bats in Slovakia</article-title><source>Vespertilio</source><year>2010</year><volume>13&#x02013;14</volume><fpage>139</fpage><lpage>147</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B59"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Fain</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Vangeluwe</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Degreef</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wauthy</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><article-title>Observations on mites inhabiting nests of Bubo bubo (L.) (Strigigformes, Strigidae) in Belgium</article-title><source>Bel J Zool</source><year>1993</year><volume>123</volume><issue>1</issue><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>26</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B60"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Kurtenbach</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Peacey</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Rijpkema</surname><given-names>SGT</given-names></name><name><surname>Hoodless</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name><name><surname>Nuttall</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Randolph</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><article-title>Differential transmission of the genospecies of <italic>Borrelia burgdorferi sensu lato</italic> by game birds and small rodents in England</article-title><source>Appl Environ Microbiol</source><year>1998</year><volume>64</volume><fpage>1169</fpage><lpage>1174</lpage><?supplied-pmid 9546150?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9546150</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B61"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Marsot</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Henry</surname><given-names>P-Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Vourc&#x02019;h</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Gasqui</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Ferquel</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Laignel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Grysan</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chapuis</surname><given-names>J-L</given-names></name><article-title>Which forest bird species are the main hosts of the tick, <italic>Ixodes ricinus</italic>, the vector of <italic>Borrelia burgdorferi sensu lato</italic>, during the breeding season?</article-title><source>Int J Parasitol</source><year>2012</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>781</fpage><lpage>788</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijpara.2012.05.010</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 22732161?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22732161</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B62"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Herrmann</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Voordouw</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Gern</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><article-title><italic>Ixodes ricinus</italic> infected with the causative agent of Lyme disease, Borrelia burgdorferi sensu lato, have higher energy reserves</article-title><source>Int J Parasitol</source><year>2013</year><volume>43</volume><issue>6</issue><fpage>477</fpage><lpage>483</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijpara.2012.12.010</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23416154?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23416154</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B63"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Perret</surname><given-names>J-L</given-names></name><name><surname>Guerin</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Diehl</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Vlimant</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gern</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><article-title>Darkness induces mobility, and saturation deficit limits questing duration, in the tick <italic>Ixodes ricinus</italic></article-title><source>J Exp Biol</source><year>2003</year><volume>206</volume><fpage>1809</fpage><lpage>1815</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/jeb.00345</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12728002?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12728002</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B64"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Crooks</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Randolph</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><article-title>Walking by <italic>Ixodes ricinus</italic> ticks: Intrinsic and extrinsic factors determine the attraction of moisture or host odour</article-title><source>J Experiment Biol</source><year>2006</year><volume>209</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>2138</fpage><lpage>2142</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1242/jeb.02238</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B65"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gern</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Toutoungi</surname><given-names>LN</given-names></name><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Aeschlimann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title><italic>Ixodes (Pholeoixodes) hexagonus</italic>, an efficient vector of <italic>Borrelia burgdorferi</italic> in the laboratory</article-title><source>Med Vet Entomol</source><year>1991</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>431</fpage><lpage>435</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2915.1991.tb00571.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 1773121?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1773121</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B66"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Estrada-Pe&#x000f1;a</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Oteo</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Estrada-Pe&#x000f1;a</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Gort&#x000e1;zar</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Os&#x000e1;car</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Moreno</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Castell&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title><italic>Borrelia burgdorferi sensu lato</italic> in ticks (Acari: Ixodidae) from two different foci in Spain</article-title><source>Exp Appl Acarol</source><year>1995</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>173</fpage><lpage>180</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00046289</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 7634972?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7634972</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B67"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Matuschka</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name><surname>Richter</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischer</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Spielman</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Nocturnal detachment of the tick <italic>Ixodes hexagonus</italic> from nocturnally active hosts</article-title><source>Med Vet Entomol</source><year>1990</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>415</fpage><lpage>420</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2915.1990.tb00459.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 2133008?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2133008</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B68"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pf&#x000e4;ffle</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Petney</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Skuballa</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Taraschewski</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><article-title>Comparative population dynamics of a generalist (<italic>Ixodes ricinus</italic>) and specialist tick (<italic>I. hexagonus</italic>) species from European hedgehogs</article-title><source>Exp Appl Acarol</source><year>2011</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>151</fpage><lpage>164</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10493-011-9432-x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21350974?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21350974</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B69"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Estrada-Pe&#x000f1;a</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jongejan</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><article-title>Ticks feeding on humans: a review of records on human-biting Ixodoidea with special reference to pathogen transmission</article-title><source>Exp Appl Acarol</source><year>1999</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>685</fpage><lpage>715</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1006241108739</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 10581710?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10581710</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B70"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Movila</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Gatewood</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Toderas</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Duca</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Papero</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Uspenskaia</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Conovalov</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Fish</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><article-title>Prevalence of <italic>Borrelia burgdorferi sensu lato</italic> in <italic>Ixodes ricinus</italic> and <italic>I. lividus</italic> ticks collected from wild birds in the Republic of Moldova</article-title><source>Int J Med Microbiol</source><year>2008</year><volume>298</volume><issue>Suppl 1</issue><fpage>149</fpage><lpage>153</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B71"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Monks</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Fisher</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Forbes</surname><given-names>NA</given-names></name><article-title><italic>Ixodes frontalis</italic> and avian tick-related syndrome in the United Kingdom</article-title><source>J Small Anim Pract</source><year>2006</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>451</fpage><lpage>455</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1748-5827.2006.00031.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16911113?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16911113</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B72"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gilot</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Beaucournu</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Chastel</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><article-title>Collecte &#x000ab;au drapeau&#x000bb; et fixation sur l&#x02032;homme d&#x02019;<italic>Ixodes (Trichotoixodes) frontalis</italic> (Panzer, 1795)</article-title><source>Parasite</source><year>1997</year><volume>4</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>197</fpage><lpage>199</lpage><?supplied-pmid 9296062?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9296062</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B73"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>&#x00160;pitalska</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Literak</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Kocianova</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Taragelova</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><article-title>The importance of <italic>ixodes arboricola</italic> in transmission of <italic>rickettsia spp.</italic>, <italic>anaplasma phagocytophilum</italic>, and <italic>borrelia burgdorferi sensu lato</italic> in the Czech republic, central Europe</article-title><source>Vector Borne Zoonotic Dis</source><year>2011</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>1235</fpage><lpage>1241</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1089/vbz.2010.0210</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21612531?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21612531</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B74"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ulmanen</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Saikku</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Vikberg</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sorjonen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title><italic>Ixodes lividus</italic> (acari) in sand martin colonies in fennoscandia</article-title><source>Oikos</source><year>1977</year><volume>28</volume><fpage>20</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/3543318</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B75"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Uchikawa</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>The occurrence of <italic>Argas japonicus</italic> and <italic>ixodes lividus</italic> in Nagano prefecture, Japan (ixodoidea: <italic>argasidae</italic>; <italic>ixodidae</italic>)</article-title><source>J Med Entomol</source><year>1969</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>95</fpage><lpage>97</lpage><?supplied-pmid 5775480?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5775480</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B76"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Doby</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bigaignon</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Launay</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Costil</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Lorvellec</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><article-title>Presence of <italic>borrelia burgdorferi</italic>, agent of tick spirochaetosis, in <italic>ixodes (exopalpiger) trianguliceps</italic> Birula, 1895 and <italic>ixodes (ixodes) acuminatus</italic> Neumann, 1901 (acari: <italic>ixodidae</italic>) and in <italic>ctenophthalmus baeticus arvernus</italic> Jordan, 1931 and <italic>megabothris turbidus</italic> (Rothschild, 1909) (insecta: siphonaptera), ectoparasites of small mammals in forests in western France</article-title><source>Bull Soc Fr Parasitol</source><year>1990</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>311</fpage><lpage>322</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B77"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Doby</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bigaignon</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Aubert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Imbert</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><article-title>Ectoparasites du renard et borreliose de Lyme. Recherche de <italic>borrelia burgdorferi</italic> chez les tiques <italic>ixodidae</italic> et insectes <italic>siphonaptera</italic></article-title><source>Bull Soc Fr Parasitol</source><year>1991</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>279</fpage><lpage>288</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B78"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hubbard</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Cann</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><article-title>Distribution of <italic>borrelia burgdorferi s.l.</italic> Spirochaete DNA in British ticks (<italic>argasidae</italic> and <italic>ixodidae</italic>) since the 19th century, assessed by PCR</article-title><source>Med Vet Entomol</source><year>1998</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>89</fpage><lpage>97</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2915.1998.00088.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 9513944?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9513944</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B79"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gilot</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Aubert</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Les Ixodidae (acarines, <italic>ixodoidea</italic>) parasites de carnivores sauvages dans les alpes fran&#x000e7;aises et leur avant-pays</article-title><source>Acarologia</source><year>1985</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>215</fpage><lpage>233</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B80"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Ogden</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><name><surname>Cripps</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Davison</surname><given-names>CC</given-names></name><name><surname>Owen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Parry</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name><name><surname>Timms</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Forbes</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><article-title>The ixodid tick species attaching to domestic dogs and cats in Great Britain and Ireland</article-title><source>Med Vet Entomol</source><year>2000</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>332</fpage><lpage>338</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2915.2000.00244.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11016442?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11016442</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B81"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>The life history of <italic>Ixodes canisuga</italic> (Johnston 1849) under laboratory conditions</article-title><source>Ann Trop Med Parasitol</source><year>1972</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>281</fpage><lpage>286</lpage><?supplied-pmid 5064532?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5064532</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B82"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Graf</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Mermod</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Aeschlimann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><article-title>Nouvelles donn&#x000e9;es concernant la distribution, l&#x02032;&#x000e9;cologie et la biologie d&#x02019;<italic>Ixodes (Exopalpiger) trianguliceps</italic> (Birula, 1895) en Suisse (Ixodoidea, <italic>Ixodidae</italic>)</article-title><source>Bull Soc Neuchat Sci Nat</source><year>1979</year><volume>102</volume><fpage>55</fpage><lpage>68</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B83"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Aeschlimann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>B&#x000fc;ttiker</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Diehl</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Eichenberger</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Immler</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Weiss</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><article-title>[Presence of <italic>Ixodes trianguliceps</italic> (Birula, 1895) and <italic>Ixodes apronophorus</italic> (Schulze, 1924) in Switzerland (Ixodoidea; Ixodidae)]</article-title><source>Rev Suisse Zool</source><year>1970</year><volume>77</volume><fpage>527</fpage><lpage>536</lpage><?supplied-pmid 5475284?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5475284</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B84"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Boyard</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Vourc&#x02019;h</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Barnouin</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>The relationships between <italic>Ixodes ricinus</italic> and small mammal species at the woodland-pasture interface</article-title><source>Exp Appl Acarol</source><year>2008</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>61</fpage><lpage>76</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10493-008-9132-3</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18247140?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18247140</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B85"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Pisanu</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Marsot</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Marmet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Chapuis</surname><given-names>J-L</given-names></name><name><surname>R&#x000e9;ale</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Vourc&#x02019;h</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><article-title>Introduced Siberian chipmunks are more heavily infested by ixodid ticks</article-title><source>Int J Parasitol</source><year>2010</year><volume>40</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>1277</fpage><lpage>1283</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ijpara.2010.03.012</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20406644?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20406644</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B86"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dantas-Torres</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><article-title>Biology and ecology of the brown dog tick, rhipicephalus sanguineus</article-title><source>Parasit Vectors</source><year>2010</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>26</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1756-3305-3-26</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 20377860?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20377860</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B87"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Aeschlimann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Buttiker</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><article-title>Importation de tiques en Suisse (Acarina: Ixodoidea)</article-title><source>Bull Soc Entomol Suisse</source><year>1975</year><volume>48</volume><issue>1-2</issue><fpage>69</fpage><lpage>75</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B88"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hoffmann</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><article-title>Die Braune hundezecke (<italic>rhipicephalus sanguineus</italic> L.) in Berlin (west). epizootologische untersuchungen unter einschaltung von massenmedien</article-title><source>Bundesgesundheitsblatt</source><year>1981</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>153</fpage><lpage>163</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B89"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>P&#x000e9;ter</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Burgdorfer</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Aeschlimann</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chatelanat</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><article-title><italic>Rickettsia conorii</italic> isolated from <italic>Rhipicephalus sanguineus</italic> introduced into Switzerland on a pet dog</article-title><source>Z Parasitenkd</source><year>1984</year><volume>70</volume><fpage>265</fpage><lpage>270</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00942229</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 6202074?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6202074</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B90"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sibomana</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Geerts</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>De Vries</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><article-title>[Establishment of <italic>Rhipicephalus sanguineus</italic> (Latreille, 1806) inside houses in Belgium]</article-title><source>Ann Soc Belg Med Trop</source><year>1986</year><volume>66</volume><fpage>79</fpage><lpage>81</lpage><?supplied-pmid 3718024?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3718024</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B91"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gray</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>Dautel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Estrada-Pe&#x000f1;a</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Kahl</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindgren</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><article-title>Effects of climate change on ticks and tick-borne diseases in Europe</article-title><source>Interdiscip Perspect Infect Dis</source><year>2009</year><volume>2009</volume><fpage>593232</fpage><?supplied-pmid 19277106?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19277106</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B92"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Campbell</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bowles</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name><article-title>Human tick bite records in a United States air force population, 1989&#x02013;1992: implications for tick-borne disease risk</article-title><source>J Wilderness Med</source><year>1994</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>405</fpage><lpage>412</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1580/0953-9859-5.4.405</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B93"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hemmersbach-Miller</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Parola</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Brouqui</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Raoult</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><article-title>A 51-year-old homeless man who died in Marseille, southern France</article-title><source>Clin Infect Dis</source><year>2004</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>1412</fpage><lpage>1493</lpage><?supplied-pmid 15164735?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15164735</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B94"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Parola</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Socolovschi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Jeanjean</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Bitam</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Fournier</surname><given-names>P-E</given-names></name><name><surname>Sotto</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Labauge</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Raoult</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><article-title>Warmer weather linked to tick attack and emergence of severe rickettsioses</article-title><source>PLoS Negl Trop Dis</source><year>2008</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>e338</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pntd.0000338</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19015724?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19015724</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B95"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Estrada-Pe&#x000f1;a</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouattour</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Camicas</surname><given-names>J-L</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><source>Ticks of domestic animals in the Mediterranean region: a guide to identification of species</source><year>2004</year><publisher-name>Zaragoza: University of Zaragoza</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B96"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Blanc</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Camino Pietros</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>Epidemiological and experimental studies on Boutonneuse fever done at the Pasteur institute in Athens</article-title><source>Arch Inst Pasteur Tunis</source><year>1932</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>343</fpage><lpage>394</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B97"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hoogstraal</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><article-title>Argasid and Nuttalliellid ticks as parasites and vectors</article-title><source>Adv Parasitol</source><year>1985</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>135</fpage><lpage>238</lpage><?supplied-pmid 3904345?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3904345</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B98"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dautel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheurer</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kahl</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><article-title>The pigeon tick (<italic>Argas reflexus</italic>): its biology, ecology, and epidemiological aspects</article-title><source>Zbl Bakt</source><year>1999</year><volume>289</volume><issue>5-7</issue><fpage>745</fpage><lpage>753</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B99"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dautel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Kahl</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Kn&#x000fc;lle</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><article-title>The soft tick <italic>Argas reflexus</italic> (F.) (Acari, <italic>Argasidae</italic>) in urban environments and its medical significance in Berlin (West)</article-title><source>J Appl Entomol</source><year>1991</year><volume>111</volume><fpage>380</fpage><lpage>390</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1439-0418.1991.tb00338.x</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B100"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hilger</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Bessot</surname><given-names>J-C</given-names></name><name><surname>Hutt</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Grigioni</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>De Blay</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Pauli</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Hentges</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><article-title>IgE-mediated anaphylaxis caused by bites of the pigeon tick Argas reflexus: cloning and expression of the major allergen Arg r 1</article-title><source>J Allergy Clin Immunol</source><year>2005</year><volume>115</volume><fpage>617</fpage><lpage>622</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jaci.2004.11.052</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15753913?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15753913</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B101"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Evans</surname><given-names>NJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bown</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Timofte</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>VR</given-names></name><name><surname>Birtles</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><article-title>Fatal <italic>Borreliosis</italic> in bat caused by relapsing fever spirochete, United Kingdom</article-title><source>Emerging Infect Dis</source><year>2009</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>1331</fpage><lpage>1333</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3201/eid1508.090475</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19751613?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19751613</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B102"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Beaucournu</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><article-title>Contribution &#x000e0; la connaissance de la biologie d&#x02019; <italic>Ixodes (Eschatocephalus) Vespertilionis</italic> Koch 1844 et d&#x02019;<italic>Ixodes (Pomerantzevella) simplex</italic> Neumann 1906 (Acarina, Ixodoidea), parasites des chiropt&#x000e8;res</article-title><source>Ann speleol</source><year>1967</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>543</fpage><lpage>580</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B103"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><name><surname>Obsomer</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Titeux</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Duveiller</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Vancutsem</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pekel</surname><given-names>J-F</given-names></name><name><surname>Ceccato</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Connor</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Coosemans</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><person-group person-group-type="editor">Manguin S</person-group><article-title>From <italic>Anopheles</italic> to spatial surveillance: a roadmap through a multidisciplinary challenge</article-title><source>Anopheles mosquitoes &#x02013; New insights into malaria vectors</source><year>2013</year><publisher-name>Rijeka, Croatia: InTech Publisher</publisher-name><comment>in press</comment><?supplied-pmid 23886925?></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B104"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Daniel</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kola Zeman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><article-title>GIS tools for tick and tick-borne disease occurrence</article-title><source>Parasitology</source><year>2004</year><volume>129</volume><fpage>329</fpage><lpage>352</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0031182004006080</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B105"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Sinka</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Bangs</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Manguin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chareonviriyaphap</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Patil</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Temperley</surname><given-names>WH</given-names></name><name><surname>Gething</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name><name><surname>Elyazar</surname><given-names>IRF</given-names></name><name><surname>Kabaria</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Harbach</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hay</surname><given-names>SI</given-names></name><article-title>The dominant anopheles vectors of human malaria in the Asia-pacific region: occurrence data, distribution maps and bionomic pr&#x000e9;cis</article-title><source>Parasit Vectors</source><year>2011</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>89</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1756-3305-4-89</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 21612587?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21612587</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B106"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Obsomer</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Defourny</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Coosemans</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><article-title>Predicted Distribution of major malaria vectors belonging to the anopheles dirus complex in Asia: ecological niche and environmental influences</article-title><source>PLoS One</source><year>2012</year><volume>7</volume><issue>11</issue><fpage>e50475</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0050475</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23226292?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23226292</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B107"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Charrel</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Attoui</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Butenko</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Clegg</surname><given-names>AMJC</given-names></name><name><surname>Deubel</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Frolova</surname><given-names>TV</given-names></name><name><surname>Gould</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gritsun</surname><given-names>TS</given-names></name><name><surname>Heinz</surname><given-names>FX</given-names></name><name><surname>Labuda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Lashkevich</surname><given-names>VA</given-names></name><name><surname>Loktev</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Lundkvist</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lvov</surname><given-names>DV</given-names></name><name><surname>Mandl</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name><name><surname>Niedrig</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Papa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Petrov</surname><given-names>VS</given-names></name><name><surname>Plyusnin</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Randolph</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Suss</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zlobin</surname><given-names>VI</given-names></name><name><surname>de Lamballerie</surname><given-names>X</given-names></name><article-title>Tick-borne virus diseases of human interest in Europe</article-title><source>Clin Microbiol Infect</source><year>2004</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>1040</fpage><lpage>1055</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-0691.2004.01022.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 15606630?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15606630</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B108"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Trotter</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name><article-title>Is bracken a health hazard?</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>1990</year><volume>336</volume><fpage>1563</fpage><lpage>1565</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0140-6736(90)93325-J</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 1979379?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1979379</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B109"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bigaignon</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Tomasi</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Goubau</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Martin</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Pierard</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Sindic</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Dupuis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Marcelis</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Degreef</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Willocx</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><article-title>A clinical and sero-epidemiological study of 190 Belgian patients suffering from Lyme borreliosis</article-title><source>Acta Clin Belg</source><year>1989</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>174</fpage><lpage>181</lpage><?supplied-pmid 2683538?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2683538</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="B110"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><source>Walter Reed biosystematics unit TICKMAP</source><publisher-name>USA: The Walter Reed Biosystematics Unit; accessed in April 2013</publisher-name><comment><ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.tickmap.org/index.htm">http://www.tickmap.org/index.htm</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>