<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Long-term demographic reconstruction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The existence of a common, homogeneous gene pool for the entire species also implies that all present-day colonies share a common demographic history. To test this, we reconstructed past Emperor penguin population size changes in BEAST2 (ref. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b30" href="#b30">30</a>) under an extended Bayesian skyline plot model. In accordance with our expectation, reconstructions based either on a single colony or on haplotypes sampled randomly from the whole continent converge to the same estimate of effective population size and to the same demographic history (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f2" href="#f2">Fig. 2a</a>). All reconstructions show a moderate increase in population size over the past 100,000 years (with some uncertainty as to the precise dating of the beginning of the expansion, because of the difficulty of precisely calibrating mutation rates in a multilocus approach), regardless of the very different present-day colony sizes (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f2" href="#f2">Fig. 2b</a>). This trend is in accordance with the findings of Li 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b31" href="#b31">31</a> based on a single-genome pairwise sequentially Markovian coalescent approach. Emperor penguin population size does not appear to have been affected by the last glacial period. This is in stark contrast with the sudden post-glacial population expansion of the Emperor's sister species, the King penguin 
  <span class="italic">A. patagonicus</span> from the sub-Antarctic region
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b32" href="#b32">32</a>, a difference probably explained by the contrasting breeding habitats and strategies of the two species, the King penguin being dependent on year-round ice-free breeding sites. The inferred long-term demographic stability also excludes past genetic fragmentation, which is known to reduce effective population size
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b33" href="#b33">33</a>. Thus, overall, the agreement of coalescent histories at both local and global sampling scales supports the idea that all extant colonies share the same genetic pool, and that the effects of neutral genetic drift between distant areas are durably counterbalanced by the intensity of gene flow.
 </p>
</sec>
