<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2.1. Effects on Environmental Fate and Behaviour</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Previous research studies have indicated that climate change now and in the future will influence the environmental fate of mercury [
  <a rid="B1-ijerph-12-03579" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-ijerph-12-03579">1</a>,
  <a rid="B4-ijerph-12-03579" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-ijerph-12-03579">4</a>]. Climate change typically affects several physical factors such as those related to long- range transport from wind direction, precipitation rates, ocean currents, melting of polar ice caps and mountain glaciers, higher frequency of extreme events, and biotic transport. Moreover, enhanced levels of mercury reaching the Arctic may lead to severe human health damage as the Arctic human population reliance on traditional diets cause them to consume fish and other seafood with high concentrations of toxic forms of mercury (mainly methylated mercury) [
  <a rid="B5-ijerph-12-03579" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-ijerph-12-03579">5</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The mercury cycle in the Arctic is vulnerable to climate variability and change through its biochemistry and changes to the cryosphere. Increased Arctic air temperature lead to the acceleration in the loss of sea-ice cover, which leads to a warmer upper ocean and consequently to the change in the atmospheric connections between the Arctic and lower latitudes. Atmospheric mercury chemistry, including AMDEs (atmospheric mercury depletion events) may also be affected by changing temperatures and precipitation [
  <a rid="B5-ijerph-12-03579" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-ijerph-12-03579">5</a>]. Temperature effects on the dependence on gaseous elemental mercury and bromine (Br) reactions or generation of bromine are also expected to affect AMDEs. Even though no studies are performed on low temperature dependence, theoretical calculations predict that the net oxidation of gaseous elemental mercury to HgBr2 will be much faster at cold temperatures, such as those observed in the Arctic [
  <a rid="B74-ijerph-12-03579" ref-type="bibr" href="#B74-ijerph-12-03579">74</a>]. It is thus expected that increased temperatures in the Arctic would slow down the mercury deposition if the concentrations of bromine are assumed to be the same.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Using the Danish Eulerian Hemispheric Model (DEHM) system, Christensen 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span>, [
  <a rid="B75-ijerph-12-03579" ref-type="bibr" href="#B75-ijerph-12-03579">75</a>] modelled in a long temporal perspective the atmospheric deposition in the Arctic due to climate change by using climate meteorological data from the ECHAM5/MPI-OM (SRES A1b scenario) for year 1900–1999, 2090–2099 and 2190–2199 (with an assumption of constant 2000 emissions). They modelled 20% to 40% higher mercury deposition over continental areas in the Arctic and near Arctic under climate change scenarios, compared to present-day climate. 20% to 40% lower deposition rates were modelled directly to the Arctic Ocean by 2090–2099 compared to the 1990–1999. The changes in mercury deposition were expected to be driven by changes in the atmospheric chemistry of mercury that result from reduced sea-ice cover and increased concentrations of ozone in the troposphere that are forecasted under the climate change scenario [
  <a rid="B75-ijerph-12-03579" ref-type="bibr" href="#B75-ijerph-12-03579">75</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For terrestrial systems increased temperature trends have led to a shorter period of ice and snow cover, reduced glaciers and permafrost, changed vegetation, river discharges, incidents of forest fire, and changes in migration pathways. A shorter period of ice and snow cover means that inorganic mercury through greater productivity are transformed to methylmercury in wetlands, marine and freshwaters [
  <a rid="B5-ijerph-12-03579" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-ijerph-12-03579">5</a>]. Mercury methylation may increase with higher temperatures and thus higher bacterial activity in sediments. On the contrary can microbial processes lead to demethylation from higher temperatures, but in general, it is expected that the net methylation rate increase with higher temperatures. Since global warming is likely to extend the ice-free season, the season for mercury methylation is also increased.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Stern 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span>, [
  <a rid="B4-ijerph-12-03579" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-ijerph-12-03579">4</a>] concluded that the most important impacts of climate warming in the Arctic have occurred in precipitation rates, and type of precipitation (
  <span class="italic">i.e.</span>, rain or snow), river discharge and seasonality, lake ice and sea ice seasonality, thickness and extent, declining length and depth of snow cover, increasing active layer depth in permafrost soils, altered vegetation and drainage basins, and changing atmospheric connectivity between the Arctic and southern latitudes.
 </p>
</sec>
