<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3. What will be the Future Impacts of Energy and Climate Changes on the Contamination of the Arctic Ecosystems?</div>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1. Energy and Technology Use Changes</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Energy and technology use changes and their relevance for mercury emissions depend on many factors, including those connected to national and international initiatives to reduce greenhouse gases (GHGs). Improvement of efficiency of energy production in power stations, replacement of fossil fuels by renewable sources, and improvement of efficiency of emission control devices are likely to have a positive impact on the reduction of releases of mercury [
   <a rid="B2-ijerph-12-03579" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-ijerph-12-03579">2</a>,
   <a rid="B9-ijerph-12-03579" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9-ijerph-12-03579">9</a>,
   <a rid="B72-ijerph-12-03579" ref-type="bibr" href="#B72-ijerph-12-03579">72</a>]. The International Energy Agency (IEA) has in the World Energy Outlook (WEO) and Energy Technology Perspectives (ETP) respectively, presented changes in energy production and consumption until the year 2035. In the projections, the WEO places focus on certain key aspects, such as energy prices, concerns for greenhouse gas emissions and its impacts on energy investments, the increasing use of renewable energy, changes in regulations and directives as well as recent developments in technologies for energy production. IEA further projects that the population for all the scenarios will increase from 6.7 billion (in 2008) to 8.5 billion (in 2035), population in non- OECD countries growing the most rapidly. In this period, the GDP on average is estimated to increase worldwide by 3.2% per year. India, China and Middle East are assumed to grow most rapidly in terms of GDP (Gross domestic Product) as well as increase in energy demand.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">New mercury emission estimates (for year 2035) involving both activity and technology variables projected for the Current Policy (CP) scenario, New Policy (NP) scenario, and the Maximum Feasible Reduction (MFR) scenario were recently presented in the EU GMOS project [
   <a rid="B19-ijerph-12-03579" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-ijerph-12-03579">19</a>]. The scenarios were based on assumptions from the IEA reports as well as previous results from the UNEP/AMAP, 2013 work. The CP Scenario assumed that governmental policies and measures existing in 2010 were adopted, including those that have not been fully implemented. The New Policies Scenario assumed that policy commitments and plans announced by countries worldwide to reduce greenhouse gas emissions, as well as phasing out fossil-energy subsidies, were going to be fully implemented. National climate commitments are related to the period of 2020, but additional measures were assumed to be implemented in the 2010 to 2020 pace for the period 2020 to 2035. The Maximum Feasible Reduction Scenario did set out a target of all counties reaching the highest feasible/available reduction efficiency in each emission sector. The assumptions for the energy sector were consistent with a 50% chance of limiting the average global temperature to 2 degree C (compared to pre- industrial levels). This requires the concentrations of greenhouse gases in the atmosphere of about 450 ppm of carbon dioxide equivalents. The scenario was not judged to be a very realistic one, but it illustrated the maximum possible mercury emission reductions that could be achieved if no other constraints are taken into account, such as economy and increased industry demand. The comparison of the EU GMOS future emission estimates indicated that if mercury continues to be emitted under the control measures and practices that are decided on today against a background of changing population- and economic growth, the 2010 emissions will remain the same in 2035 as in 2010. A full implementation of policy commitments and plans (the basic assumption of the NP scenario), implies a benefit of reducing global mercury emissions by almost 50% in 2035 under the assumptions employed in this scenario. A maximum feasible reduction of mercury emissions resulted in 85% less emissions than those envisaged under the CP scenario.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Irrespective of the above mentioned projections, Rafaj 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, [
   <a rid="B73-ijerph-12-03579" ref-type="bibr" href="#B73-ijerph-12-03579">73</a>], provided projections for the year 2050 on the implications of renewable energy policies on atmospheric emissions of mercury in Europe using the GAINS model. They further found that current emissions of mercury in Europe are likely to remain at the same level under baseline conditions, but applying current standard air pollution control devices would mean a 35% reduction of mercury emissions. Low carbon policies and renewable electricity deployment would also in this study bring considerable co-benefit removal of mercury.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Changes in energy sector are expected to affect the mercury contamination in the Arctic. A relatively modest reduction of deposition is expected for the Arctic from emission control equipment as these installations effectively control emissions of particulate and reactive forms that tend to deposit close to the emission source. The Arctic reduction is expected to occur from long- range transport of gaseous elemental mercury. The major effect of the emission reductions under the scenarios is likely to occur in South- East Asia. Previous atmospheric modelling results have indicated that the annual flux of mercury to the Arctic will decrease by around 10% under assumptions comparable to the NP scenario mentioned above [
   <a rid="B5-ijerph-12-03579" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-ijerph-12-03579">5</a>]. Descriptions of the 2020 scenarios are available in Pacyna 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span> [
   <a rid="B72-ijerph-12-03579" ref-type="bibr" href="#B72-ijerph-12-03579">72</a>]. No further extrapolation of the results of atmospheric deposition decreases until 2020 was made for concentrations of mercury in various environmental media.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Even though the future climate change mitigation options are expected to reduce emissions and thus the long-range transport of gaseous elemental mercury, it is not clear how important these emission reductions are to the changes in mercury in the Arctic, compared to factors impacted by climate change.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2. Climate Change</div>
  <sec class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2.1. Effects on Environmental Fate and Behaviour</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Previous research studies have indicated that climate change now and in the future will influence the environmental fate of mercury [
    <a rid="B1-ijerph-12-03579" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-ijerph-12-03579">1</a>,
    <a rid="B4-ijerph-12-03579" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-ijerph-12-03579">4</a>]. Climate change typically affects several physical factors such as those related to long- range transport from wind direction, precipitation rates, ocean currents, melting of polar ice caps and mountain glaciers, higher frequency of extreme events, and biotic transport. Moreover, enhanced levels of mercury reaching the Arctic may lead to severe human health damage as the Arctic human population reliance on traditional diets cause them to consume fish and other seafood with high concentrations of toxic forms of mercury (mainly methylated mercury) [
    <a rid="B5-ijerph-12-03579" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-ijerph-12-03579">5</a>].
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The mercury cycle in the Arctic is vulnerable to climate variability and change through its biochemistry and changes to the cryosphere. Increased Arctic air temperature lead to the acceleration in the loss of sea-ice cover, which leads to a warmer upper ocean and consequently to the change in the atmospheric connections between the Arctic and lower latitudes. Atmospheric mercury chemistry, including AMDEs (atmospheric mercury depletion events) may also be affected by changing temperatures and precipitation [
    <a rid="B5-ijerph-12-03579" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-ijerph-12-03579">5</a>]. Temperature effects on the dependence on gaseous elemental mercury and bromine (Br) reactions or generation of bromine are also expected to affect AMDEs. Even though no studies are performed on low temperature dependence, theoretical calculations predict that the net oxidation of gaseous elemental mercury to HgBr2 will be much faster at cold temperatures, such as those observed in the Arctic [
    <a rid="B74-ijerph-12-03579" ref-type="bibr" href="#B74-ijerph-12-03579">74</a>]. It is thus expected that increased temperatures in the Arctic would slow down the mercury deposition if the concentrations of bromine are assumed to be the same.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Using the Danish Eulerian Hemispheric Model (DEHM) system, Christensen 
    <span class="italic">et al.</span>, [
    <a rid="B75-ijerph-12-03579" ref-type="bibr" href="#B75-ijerph-12-03579">75</a>] modelled in a long temporal perspective the atmospheric deposition in the Arctic due to climate change by using climate meteorological data from the ECHAM5/MPI-OM (SRES A1b scenario) for year 1900–1999, 2090–2099 and 2190–2199 (with an assumption of constant 2000 emissions). They modelled 20% to 40% higher mercury deposition over continental areas in the Arctic and near Arctic under climate change scenarios, compared to present-day climate. 20% to 40% lower deposition rates were modelled directly to the Arctic Ocean by 2090–2099 compared to the 1990–1999. The changes in mercury deposition were expected to be driven by changes in the atmospheric chemistry of mercury that result from reduced sea-ice cover and increased concentrations of ozone in the troposphere that are forecasted under the climate change scenario [
    <a rid="B75-ijerph-12-03579" ref-type="bibr" href="#B75-ijerph-12-03579">75</a>].
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For terrestrial systems increased temperature trends have led to a shorter period of ice and snow cover, reduced glaciers and permafrost, changed vegetation, river discharges, incidents of forest fire, and changes in migration pathways. A shorter period of ice and snow cover means that inorganic mercury through greater productivity are transformed to methylmercury in wetlands, marine and freshwaters [
    <a rid="B5-ijerph-12-03579" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-ijerph-12-03579">5</a>]. Mercury methylation may increase with higher temperatures and thus higher bacterial activity in sediments. On the contrary can microbial processes lead to demethylation from higher temperatures, but in general, it is expected that the net methylation rate increase with higher temperatures. Since global warming is likely to extend the ice-free season, the season for mercury methylation is also increased.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Stern 
    <span class="italic">et al.</span>, [
    <a rid="B4-ijerph-12-03579" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-ijerph-12-03579">4</a>] concluded that the most important impacts of climate warming in the Arctic have occurred in precipitation rates, and type of precipitation (
    <span class="italic">i.e.</span>, rain or snow), river discharge and seasonality, lake ice and sea ice seasonality, thickness and extent, declining length and depth of snow cover, increasing active layer depth in permafrost soils, altered vegetation and drainage basins, and changing atmospheric connectivity between the Arctic and southern latitudes.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2.2. Effects on Bioaccumulation</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Through bioaccumulation mercury reaches higher concentrations in biota than are present in the environmental media in the first place. Under climate change, the structure and dynamics of marine food webs are in change. Arctic marine ecosystems are further affected by the reduction of sea- ice coverage and thickness [
    <a rid="B3-ijerph-12-03579" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3-ijerph-12-03579">3</a>]. The ability to adapt to ecosystem shifts depends on the individual species, so the effect on mercury bioaccumulation depends on the food-webs structures and their responses to climate change. Trophic structures vary geographically and occur in two ways; either from the “bottom-up”, or from the “top-down”. “Bottom-up” changes links to primary or secondary productivity, such as plankton and other organisms, stratification, nutrient supply, light intensity or ice cover [
    <a rid="B5-ijerph-12-03579" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-ijerph-12-03579">5</a>]. These can have major effects on the production of organisms on a higher trophic level, but the complexity of such systems does not bring any confidence in future predictions under climate change. Changes in the top of the food- web, relate e.g., to the loss of sea ice cover and subsequent a shift in diet, habitats and/or migration pathways.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2.3. Nutritional Transition and Change of Food Supply</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Changed biotope conditions and thus changed availability of current marine fish and mammals used for human consumption, as well as increased exploitation of natural resources, may have an influence on human exposure to mercury. Climate change may affect fish supply and the associations between habitual diet and blood concentrations for many contaminants. Furthermore, it is a serious concern that climate change will cause changes that affect the supply of traditional foods such as marine mammals and reindeer for people living in the Arctic. It has been concluded that the traditional foods and local products are more nutritionally adequate than the imported foods replacing them. Severely limiting the consumption of fish and seafood may do more harm than good by reducing the consumption of foods with health benefits and by increasing the consumption of alternative foods that have potential health risks such as increasing the possibility of obesity and diabetes.</p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
</sec>
