<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par2" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Range variations due to climate change have been described in several species and tend to result in the shift of climate envelopes towards the poles and higher elevations
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span>. For instance, a three degree Celsius increase matches with a 350 km shift in latitude, or a 500 m shift in altitude
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span>. Patterns of range shifts resulting from climate change have been well documented in migratory species despite large yearly variations
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span>, and a wide range of taxa displays such a range displacement (reviewed by Hughes, 2000
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span>). Several studies demonstrated a range shift for 22 species of non-migratory European butterflies
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
  </span>, Edith’s checkerspot butterfly
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
  </span>, mosquito species in equatorial areas
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>
  </span>, birds, anoline lizards
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>
  </span>, 59 British bird species
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
  </span>, 14 North American bird species
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span>, 19 North American mammals
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>, the bacterium 
  <span class="italic">Pseudomonas syringae</span> in China
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>
  </span> and benthic species in the Mediterranean sea
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span>. This is also the case for amphibians, with species such as red-eyed stream frogs (
  <span class="italic">Hyla uranochroa</span>) predicted to shift distribution as a result of climate change
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Species distribution models (SDMs) are spatial representations of species presence probability or abundance. They are created using responses to environmental predictor variables, spatial relationships such as convex hulls or interpolation, or a combination of the two. SDMs are easily projected across landscapes, and can therefore be helpful in circumstances where acquiring occurrence data on the distribution of species is not achievable, or when the ecological variables related to the distribution of the species have changed (reviewed by Guisan and Thuiller 2005
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span>). The change may result from long-term shifts in environmental variables, as illustrated by the range shift between the paleo and current distributions of the Japanese Treefrog, 
  <span class="italic">Dryophytes japonicus</span>, in North East Asia
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span>. SDMs can also be used to predict variations in the distribution of species due to future anomalies resulting from climate change
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
  </span>. Ecological models thus allow determining the range of species in conditions where it would not be otherwise doable or when the range boundaries are not known
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
  </span>. For instance, eight new localities of 
  <span class="italic">Vipera ursinii graeca</span> were found through landscape and climate modelling, doubling the known range of the species
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
  </span>. Spatial modelling for some clades without clear geographic boundaries, such as fish or birds
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
  </span> is inherently more complex. However, species like amphibians are perfect model species as they do not disperse over long distances
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>
  </span>, nor do they migrate over numerous climatic zones, and thus have generally continuous distribution patterns
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Amphibians are comparatively more endangered and less studied than their counterparts, be them flying or apex predator
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>
  </span>, and the range of most species is not accurately defined, with many species classified as Data Deficient under the IUCN criteria
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span>. This is especially true for geographic areas where ecological research is less widespread. For instance, the Suweon Treefrog (
  <span class="italic">Dryophytes suweonensis</span>) in the Republic of Korea saw its known range doubled between 2012
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span> and 2017
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here we focus on the only plethodontid salamander in Asia, the Korean Crevice Salamander, 
  <span class="italic">Karsenia koreana</span>. It is considered one of the most elusive Korean amphibian species, and although it was first collected in 1971
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span>, it was only described in 2005
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
  </span>. Accordingly, very little is known about its morphology
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
  </span> and genetics
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
  </span>. In additions, 
  <span class="italic">K. koreana</span> is not stringently bound to the aquatic environment as a result of the reacquisition of its larval stage
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>
  </span> and unusual breeding behaviour
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>
  </span>. Little or no information is available about the potential range shift for 
  <span class="italic">K. koreana</span> due to climate change
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>
  </span>, but the latter is expected to have a negative impact on habitat suitability for plethodontids in general
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>
  </span>. Climate change has likely caused body size reductions in other plethodontid salamander species
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>
  </span>, which affects fecundity (reviewed by Wells, 2007
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>
  </span>) and rates of water loss
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>
  </span>. In turn this may impact surface activity time
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>
  </span>, and consequently affect foraging, dispersal, reproduction, and might change future species’ distributions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>
  </span>. As the climate on the Korean peninsula is getting warmer
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>
  </span> and dryer
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>
  </span>, 
  <span class="italic">K. koreana</span> is also going to be affected by climatic variations and related ecological changes. The aims of this study were (1) to define the potential current distribution of 
  <span class="italic">K. koreana</span> through the development of a habitat suitability model and a set of bioclimatic and vegetation variables; (2) to investigate the potential impact of climate change on the distribution of 
  <span class="italic">K. koreana</span> in the Korean peninsula using four Representative Concentration Pathways (RCPs), which are climate change scenarios based on greenhouse gas concentration trajectories.
 </p>
</sec>
