<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec016" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <sec id="sec017" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The traits and trait syndromes that pattern with climate± and those that don’t</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A basic premise in much of trait-based ecology is that taxa may be grouped using physiological and morphological traits into functional types, with taxa in the same functional group displaying similar responses to the environment [
   <a rid="pone.0219908.ref119" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref119">119</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0219908.ref120" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref120">120</a>]. Consistent with this, major PCA analyses of the world flora have routinely identified two key dimensions of functional specialization, the ‘worldwide leaf economics spectrum’ and size [
   <a rid="pone.0219908.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref012">12</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0219908.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref013">13</a>]. Here, for populations within a single species, oleaster, we confirm these generalities. Axes 1 and 2 in our PCA analysis are analogous with the same two axes recognized in global studies (Tables 
   <a rid="pone.0219908.t003" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0219908.t003">3</a>–
   <a rid="pone.0219908.t010" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0219908.t010">10</a>). However, these axes did not consistently pattern with climatic variables. Instead, a further ‘climatic’ PCA axis 3, was identified defined primarily in terms of ecophysiological/’mechanistic’ leaf traits (
   <a rid="pone.0219908.t010" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0219908.t010">Table 10A</a>). Equally, a majority of the statistically significant correlations between individual traits and climate included ecophysiological/’mechanistic’ leaf traits rather than the more commonly used structural/‘functional’ ones (
   <a rid="pone.0219908.t010" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0219908.t010">Table 10A</a>). However, a precise interpretation in terms of ecological processes is not yet feasible. Both the origin and the generality of variability in trait expression are in need of further study. Oleaster is slow-growing and long-lived [
   <a rid="pone.0219908.ref056" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref056">56</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0219908.ref059" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref059">59</a>] and will experience variations in climate during its lifetime. Moreover, it exhibits high levels of genetic heterozygosity [
   <a rid="pone.0219908.ref054" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref054">54</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0219908.ref121" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref121">121</a>–
   <a rid="pone.0219908.ref127" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref127">127</a>]. Variability in trait expression will have been affected by genotype, phenotypic plasticity [
   <a rid="pone.0219908.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref016">16</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0219908.ref128" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref128">128</a>] and potentially differences in phenology and in the land-use and climatic history of the study sites. Furthermore, a different choice of species may have led to a very different set of results and conclusions: ‘functional’ traits are predicted to pattern more strongly with climate for fast-growing and short-lived species (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0219908.g001" href="#pone.0219908.g001">Fig 1</a>). Nevertheless, these equivocations do not alter the basic message of this study. ‘Mechanistic’ traits must be routinely included in climate-related studies.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec018" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A preliminary assessment of the ‘climatic’ PCA 3 axis in oleaster</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Oleaster is a thermophilic species with limited resistance to both cold and extreme aridity [
   <a rid="pone.0219908.ref055" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref055">55</a>]. Moreover, aridity is generally regarded as the key climatic factor determining species composition in Mediterranean vegetation. The ‘climatic’ PCA axis 3 was correlated positively with MAT, MAP, MTCM and AI and negatively with altitude (
   <a rid="pone.0219908.t010" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0219908.t010">Table 10A</a>). Thus, high values of PCA axis 3 equated to high mean annual temperature, high minimum temperature of the coldest month, high mean annual precipitation, high aridity and low altitude. In terms of the traits that define PCA axis 3 (
   <a rid="pone.0219908.t009" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0219908.t009">Table 9</a>), these climatic extremes were associated with low stomatal density (DS
   <span class="sup">–</span>) low leaf water content (SLWC
   <span class="sup">–</span>), small leaves (LL
   <span class="sup">–</span>) and high leaf construction costs (SLA
   <span class="sup">+</span>). The trends for DS were similar to those recorded elsewhere in relation to climate [
   <a rid="pone.0219908.ref129" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref129">129</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0219908.ref130" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref130">130</a>]. Similarly, elongate leaves with a potentially thinner boundary layer [
   <a rid="pone.0219908.ref099" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref099">99</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0219908.ref131" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref131">131</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0219908.ref132" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref132">132</a>] tended to be associated with harsher climates. PCA axis 3 may identify a water-use/succulence dimension. Moreover, site 13, excluded for its extremely high values for LT, LWC and SLWC (
   <a rid="pone.0219908.t003" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0219908.t003">Table 3</a>), may perhaps represent an extremely ‘succulent’ outlying population.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Succulence is an ecologically important functional mechanism defined as the ‘storage of utilizable water in living tissues in one or several plant parts in such a way as to allow the plant to be temporarily independent from external water supply but to retain at least some physiological activity’ [
   <a rid="pone.0219908.ref133" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref133">133</a>]. However, structural and physiological relationships involving succulence are complex [
   <a rid="pone.0219908.ref133" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref133">133</a>–
   <a rid="pone.0219908.ref136" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref136">136</a>]. As a result, whether PCA axis 3 identifies ‘succulence’, and provides a temporary drought avoidance mechanism, still requires experimental verification. Nevertheless, whatever the exact functional origins of climate-related PCA axis 3, its recognition was, importantly, only made possible through the inclusion of several traits not customarily included in trait-based ecological studies.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec019" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The way forward–an olive branch in the ‘functional’ versus ‘mechanistic’ debate</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results, and most of the relationships included in our literature review, point to ‘mechanistic’ traits being diagnostically superior to ‘functional’ ones in climate studies. Nevertheless, we believe it counterproductive to focus entirely on this ‘mechanistic’ superiority. To re-iterate arguments from the Introduction, ‘mechanistic’ studies are time-consuming with small datasets produced and species chosen primarily for ecological relevance. Without a level of co-ordination not currently in place between related ‘mechanistic’ investigations, precision of measurement will be offset by few shared species and no integration of findings (i.e. little generality). Trait based ecology, and ‘functional’ traits, can potentially provide this missing generality by producing large ecologically-balanced datasets. However, as in this study, results may require mechanistic clarification. Importantly, as currently implemented, trait-based ecology is methodologically flawed. Specialization routinely occurs at the cellular/biochemical level but may additionally be identified at a higher organizational scale by measuring organs or whole plants. So far, few suitable methodologies are available for the large-scale measurement of traits that can only be identified at the lowest, most fundamental cellular/biochemical level. As a result, the size of plants and their parts, plus SLA and LDMC, which can be measured using whole leaves, stand imprecisely at the centre of meta-analyses in trait-based ecology [
   <a rid="pone.0219908.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref012">12</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0219908.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref013">13</a>]. In contrast, some important ecological specializations expressed primarily at the cellular/biochemical level (e.g. aluminium tolerance in acidic soils and restriction by climate [
   <a rid="pone.0219908.ref047" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref047">47</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0219908.ref137" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref137">137</a>]) remain outside the scope of these meta-analyses. Moreover, this study only partly redresses this ‘climatic imbalance’. Many addition simply-measured ‘mechanistic’ traits will be required to routinely add a comprehensive climatic dimension to trait-based studies.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Volaire [
   <a rid="pone.0219908.ref048" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref048">48</a>] identified ‘functional’ traits as dealing with ecological strategies relating to multi-environmental factors and studied implicitly over long timescales. This is true but, equally, it is the product of methodological constraints rather than an ideological choice. Both the ‘mechanistic’ and ‘functional’ trait approaches have strengths, and weaknesses, but similar goals. In our search to understand and quantify impacts of changing climate on global vegetation composition and ecosystem function, the challenge will be to combine the strengths of both approaches–and to use both types of traits. ‘Mechanistic’ and ‘functional’ traits both contribute to our proposed plant-climate model (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0219908.g001" href="#pone.0219908.g001">Fig 1</a>) and each may be expected to add more generally to our understanding of climate-related processes.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
