<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec003" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Studying climate–a methodological dilemma</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Despite its long-appreciated importance [
  <a rid="pone.0219908.ref032" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref032">32</a>], our capacity to predict the potential impacts of climate change upon the world’s flora remains constrained by problems of ecological complexity [
  <a rid="pone.0219908.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref033">33</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0219908.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref035">35</a>]. Moreover, within the context of climate studies the 'functional trait’ approach described above has so far failed to identify and quantify mechanisms of climatic restriction. The most highly-cited paper [
  <a rid="pone.0219908.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref036">36</a>] simply asks the important but preliminary question ‘Which is the better predictor of plant traits, temperature or precipitation?’ More recently, global correlations between traits and climatic variables have also been used to predict possible impacts of climate change on biomass yield [
  <a rid="pone.0219908.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref037">37</a>]. In contrast, an alternative overtly ecophysiological approach has greatly increased our understanding of the impacts of climate on plant performance and survival. Through experimentation, syndromes of ‘mechanistic’ traits conferring tolerance of defined climatic factors have been identified with their function directly interpreted in terms of physics and chemistry. For example, thermal response time of the leaf to changes in surface energy fluxes has been recognized as a major component of physiological tolerance to drought [
  <a rid="pone.0219908.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref038">38</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0219908.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref039">39</a>]. Thermal response time is critical to leaf carbon economics and is defined by leaf traits such as dry matter mass, water mass, specific heat capacity, surface area, width, shape and stomatal density [
  <a rid="pone.0219908.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref039">39</a>]. Similarly, the characteristics of the plant’s hydraulic system additionally regulate response to climate [
  <a rid="pone.0219908.ref040" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref040">40</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0219908.ref041" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref041">41</a>]. Here, key traits include leaf water potential at turgor-loss point, plant hydraulic conductance or xylem vulnerability [
  <a rid="pone.0219908.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref042">42</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0219908.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref044">44</a>] and, more generally, root architecture [
  <a rid="pone.0219908.ref045" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref045">45</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0219908.ref046" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref046">46</a>]. Furthermore, encouragingly, Brodribb [
  <a rid="pone.0219908.ref047" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref047">47</a>] outlines how simple ‘mechanistic’ traits identified in ecophysiological studies define hydraulic physiology and may be used to explain and predict climatic restriction due to drought.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The contrast between the relatively climatically ineffectual ‘functional’ traits and the more ecophysiologically insightful ‘mechanistic’ traits has catalysed a debate as to how best to advance our understanding of plant-climate interactions [
  <a rid="pone.0219908.ref047" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref047">47</a>]. Provocatively, Brodribb writes: ‘By ‘mechanistic’ traits, I mean traits whose function can be clearly physiologically defined, as opposed to the more abstract ‘functional’ traits, such as leaf mass per area (LMA, also known as specific leaf area (SLA)), that have been used to great effect in explaining plant economics over the last 15 years [
  <a rid="pone.0219908.ref005" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref005">5</a>]’. Brodribb’s subdivision has been re-enforced by Volaire [
  <a rid="pone.0219908.ref048" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref048">48</a>]. Volaire separates ‘mechanistic’ traits as physiological strategies relating to one dominant environmental factor and studied explicitly over short timescales from ‘functional’ traits with ecological strategies relating to multi- environmental factors and studied implicitly over long timescales. However, this debate ignores a key point. ‘Mechanistic’ studies are time-consuming and most include few species. They provide precision in measurement but the general significance of each mechanism at a global scale is more difficult to study because inevitably datasets are small. In contrast, as outlined above, the ‘functional trait’ approach can quickly generate large datasets for whole floras with each species defined in many contrasted ecological dimensions. As in other comparative approaches the ‘functional trait’ approach has a strong potential for generality. ‘The collection and comparison of standardized information …… follows closely the philosophies prevailing in the physical sciences. Perhaps the most obvious of these is the role played by the Periodic Table of the Elements in classifying, analysing, and even predicting, the structure and properties of chemical elements and compounds’ [
  <a rid="pone.0219908.ref049" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref049">49</a>]. Why has the ‘functional trait’ approach had so little impact on understanding the role of climate on plant distribution? The failure appears to stem from the consistent use of a restricted and ‘climatically inappropriate’ set of traits. Traits linked to ‘mechanistic’ climate-related studies are conspicuously absent from ‘functional’ analyses both in studies describing general global patterns of specialization [
  <a rid="pone.0219908.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref012">12</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0219908.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref013">13</a>] and in those with a more climatic focus [
  <a rid="pone.0219908.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref036">36</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0219908.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref037">37</a>]. A plethora of potentially important climate-related traits still require further investigation. With interdisciplinary collaboration, the ‘functional trait’ approach has the potential to add important elements of generality and utility to the current pioneering ‘mechanistic’ studies …. provided, of course, that suitable, easily- and rapidly-measurable traits can be borrowed from the existing raft of ‘mechanistic’ studies.
 </p>
</sec>
