<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec017" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The traits and trait syndromes that pattern with climate± and those that don’t</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A basic premise in much of trait-based ecology is that taxa may be grouped using physiological and morphological traits into functional types, with taxa in the same functional group displaying similar responses to the environment [
  <a rid="pone.0219908.ref119" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref119">119</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0219908.ref120" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref120">120</a>]. Consistent with this, major PCA analyses of the world flora have routinely identified two key dimensions of functional specialization, the ‘worldwide leaf economics spectrum’ and size [
  <a rid="pone.0219908.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref012">12</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0219908.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref013">13</a>]. Here, for populations within a single species, oleaster, we confirm these generalities. Axes 1 and 2 in our PCA analysis are analogous with the same two axes recognized in global studies (Tables 
  <a rid="pone.0219908.t003" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0219908.t003">3</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0219908.t010" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0219908.t010">10</a>). However, these axes did not consistently pattern with climatic variables. Instead, a further ‘climatic’ PCA axis 3, was identified defined primarily in terms of ecophysiological/’mechanistic’ leaf traits (
  <a rid="pone.0219908.t010" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0219908.t010">Table 10A</a>). Equally, a majority of the statistically significant correlations between individual traits and climate included ecophysiological/’mechanistic’ leaf traits rather than the more commonly used structural/‘functional’ ones (
  <a rid="pone.0219908.t010" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0219908.t010">Table 10A</a>). However, a precise interpretation in terms of ecological processes is not yet feasible. Both the origin and the generality of variability in trait expression are in need of further study. Oleaster is slow-growing and long-lived [
  <a rid="pone.0219908.ref056" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref056">56</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0219908.ref059" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref059">59</a>] and will experience variations in climate during its lifetime. Moreover, it exhibits high levels of genetic heterozygosity [
  <a rid="pone.0219908.ref054" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref054">54</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0219908.ref121" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref121">121</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0219908.ref127" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref127">127</a>]. Variability in trait expression will have been affected by genotype, phenotypic plasticity [
  <a rid="pone.0219908.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref016">16</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0219908.ref128" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0219908.ref128">128</a>] and potentially differences in phenology and in the land-use and climatic history of the study sites. Furthermore, a different choice of species may have led to a very different set of results and conclusions: ‘functional’ traits are predicted to pattern more strongly with climate for fast-growing and short-lived species (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0219908.g001" href="#pone.0219908.g001">Fig 1</a>). Nevertheless, these equivocations do not alter the basic message of this study. ‘Mechanistic’ traits must be routinely included in climate-related studies.
 </p>
</sec>
