<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="eva12363-sec-0008" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Inferring functional/adaptive value</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As a tentative first inference into the potential adaptive value of variation in the candidate genes, we explored their functional relationships with a subset of genes previously identified as putatively under selection in a natural thermal gradient. In a companion paper, Smith et al. (unpublished) explored genomewide SNP variation along the latitudinal range of 
  <span class="italic">M. duboulayi</span> and observed 1141 loci putatively under climate‐mediated selection, as identified via outlier analysis using Bayescan (Foll and Gaggiotti 
  <a rid="eva12363-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12363-bib-0022">2008</a>). We first conducted a distant homology BLAST scan (gap opening and extension penalties 5 and 2; match/mismatch scores of 2 and −3; minimum percentage sequence identity 75) of the 93‐bp sequences of these outliers against the zebrafish genome (GRCz10; accessed July 28, 2015), reducing the data set to 411 annotated genes. We then used the BioMart package to retrieve identifiers (e.g. ENTREZ/NCBI accessions, official gene symbols) for use in subsequent analyses (Durinck et al. 
  <a rid="eva12363-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12363-bib-0018">2005</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We queried the KEGG database to identify all known molecular pathways in zebrafish comprising a co‐occurrence of at least one of the 12 candidate genes assayed for transcription and one of the annotated outlier genes (Kanehisa and Goto 
  <a rid="eva12363-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12363-bib-0040">2000</a>; Kanehisa et al. 
  <a rid="eva12363-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12363-bib-0041">2014</a>). Additionally, we performed a functional enrichment analysis and clustering of the two gene lists based on biological process and molecular function ontologies using DAVID (Huang et al. 
  <a rid="eva12363-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12363-bib-0036">2007</a>; Sherman et al. 
  <a rid="eva12363-bib-0072" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12363-bib-0072">2007</a>). Finally, we identified potential protein–protein interactions between members of each gene set by querying the STRING database (v10; accessed August 3, 2015; Snel et al. 
  <a rid="eva12363-bib-0075" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12363-bib-0075">2000</a>; Szklarczyk et al. 
  <a rid="eva12363-bib-0077" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12363-bib-0077">2015</a>). For each of the 12 candidate genes, we identified all known and predicted protein–protein interactions with the ‘highest’ confidence score (0.900). From this list, we identified 23 from the 411 genes putatively under selection and plotted their interaction network with the 12 candidate genes.
 </p>
</sec>
