<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="eva12363-sec-0006" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">RNA extractions &amp; qRT‐PCR</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Total RNA was extracted from liver tissue using the Ambion Magmax
  <span class="sup">™</span>‐96 total RNA isolation kit (Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA), following Smith et al. (
  <a rid="eva12363-bib-0074" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12363-bib-0074">2013</a>). RNA quality and concentration were measured using a Nanodrop 1000 spectrophotometer, then diluted to a standardized concentration (10 ng/μL). Each dilution was checked for DNA contamination by PCR amplification of a housekeeping gene using the SensiFAST SYBR Hi‐ROX kit (Bioline, London, UK), followed by electrophoresis on agarose gel. Samples exhibiting amplified DNA were treated with DNase MAX Kit (MO BIO) for a second time. Finally, we used random primers and the High Capacity cDNA Reverse Transcription Kit (Applied Biosystems) for cDNA synthesis, following manufacturer's protocols.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Primers were designed to amplify twelve candidate genes that are putatively differentially expressed in response to thermal stress (Smith et al. 
  <a rid="eva12363-bib-0074" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12363-bib-0074">2013</a>) – primer sequences and related information can be found in Table S1. Most importantly, candidate genes are believed to play a role in biological processes associated with a response to thermal challenge (e.g. oxidation reduction, metabolism, regulation of transcription; see Table S2). Candidates included homologues for the following zebrafish (
  <span class="italic">Danio rerio</span>) genes: alanine: glyoxylate aminotransferase a (
  <span class="italic">agxta</span>); cytochrome P450, family 1, subfamily A (
  <span class="italic">cyp1a</span>); glutathione S‐transferase rho (
  <span class="italic">gstr</span>, a.k.a. 
  <span class="italic">zgc:162356</span>); 3‐hydroxy‐3‐methylglutaryl‐coenzyme A synthase 1 (
  <span class="italic">hmgcs1</span>); heat‐shock protein 90, alpha (cytosolic), class A member 1, tandem duplicate 2 (
  <span class="italic">hsp90aa1.2</span>); nuclear receptor subfamily 1, group D, member 4b (
  <span class="italic">nr1d4b</span>); NAD(P)‐dependent steroid, dehydrogenase‐like (
  <span class="italic">nsdhl</span>); peroxisome proliferator‐activated receptor alpha b (
  <span class="italic">pparab</span>); thyrotrophic embryonic factor a (
  <span class="italic">tefa</span>); thioredoxin‐related transmembrane protein 2b (
  <span class="italic">tmx2b</span>); UDP glucuronosyltransferase 2 family, polypeptide A4 (
  <span class="italic">ugt2a4</span>); and ubiquinol‐cytochrome c reductase core protein IIb (
  <span class="italic">uqcrc2b</span>). Reference genes, to control for differences in template quantity due to variation among extractions and/or dilutions, were identified from a previous study as nondifferentially expressed between treatments (Smith et al. 
  <a rid="eva12363-bib-0074" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12363-bib-0074">2013</a>) and included ba1 globin (
  <span class="italic">ba1</span>, a.k.a. 
  <span class="italic">hbb</span>) and phosphoglycerate mutase 1a (
  <span class="italic">pgam1a</span>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Quantitative PCR was performed in 96‐well plates on a StepOnePlus Real‐Time PCR System (Applied Biosystems), using a SYBR Green reporter. Reactions contained 1 μL of diluted cDNA (10 ng/μL), 5 μL of 2× SensiFAST SYBR Hi‐ROX (Bioline), 0.05 μ
  <span class="sc">m</span> of each forward and reverse primer and 3.8 μL of RNase‐free water. Thermal cycles consisted of an initial denaturation step (95°C; 2 min), and 40 cycles of denaturation (95°C; 3 s), annealing (60°C; 10 s) and extension (72°C; 10 s). This was followed by a melt curve cycle of 95°C for 15 s, 60°C for 1 min and 95°C for 15 s. A single gene was amplified for a given 96‐well plate that also comprised: three negative controls; a fourfold serial dilution of a positive control, also in triplicate; three technical replicates for 30 experimental animals.
 </p>
</sec>
