<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="grl58044-sec-0009" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">5</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusions</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Pan‐Caribbean drought of 2013–2016 was appreciably more severe as a result of anthropogenic warming, a finding that is robust across a range of models and observationally based data sets. This result supports the idea that anthropogenic climate change is already impacting the Caribbean through temperature effects on PET and that the recent drought is likely to be a prelude to future drought events under anthropogenic climate change. That is, we expect future droughts in the region to be increasingly severe because of higher temperatures alone, regardless of changes in precipitation.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As is the case for many of the Small Island Developing States around the world (Holding et al., 
  <a rid="grl58044-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58044-bib-0020">2016</a>; Karnauskas et al., 
  <a rid="grl58044-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58044-bib-0024">2016</a>, 
  <a rid="grl58044-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58044-bib-0025">2018</a>), freshwater resources in the Caribbean are already facing a growing number of pressures ranging from saltwater intrusion from sea level rise to demands from the municipal, energy, agricultural, and tourism sectors. Importantly, in the Caribbean Islands, freshwater cannot be moved around at large scales as it can in continental locations like the U.S. southwest. Although, new technologies such as desalination have recently provided relief in some Caribbean Islands, particularly in the Lesser Antilles and the Bahamas (UNESCO, 
  <a rid="grl58044-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58044-bib-0042">2006</a>), the operational cost of desalination plants often outweighs their benefits. Moreover, the economic limitations of many Caribbean nations preclude the implementation of such an option (UNESCO, 
  <a rid="grl58044-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" href="#grl58044-bib-0042">2006</a>). Finally, though the 2013–2016 Pan‐Caribbean drought was unprecedented in an historical context, our work suggests that it might be a good analog for future droughts because of the important role temperature played in exacerbating its severity and extent. Further study of the 2013–2016 drought can help inform strategic policy and water management decisions across the region.
 </p>
</sec>
