<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Genotyping</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We extracted genomic DNA from 166 Galapagos sea lion skin samples and amplified 23 polymorphic microsatellite loci previously developed for the Galapagos sea lion and other pinniped species [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" href="#CR67">67</a>]. All genetic analyses were carried out at the University of Bielefeld, Germany, as described in [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" href="#CR67">67</a>]. Sequencing was performed on an Applied Biosystems 3130 Sequencer (Life Technologies) and genotyping was performed in GENEMARKER (Soft Genetics, USA). We tested for deviations from Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium (HWE) using Monte Carlo simulations in the 
   <span class="italic">adegenet</span> package [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" href="#CR68">68</a>] in R 2.14.1 [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" href="#CR69">69</a>], and for identity disequilibrium using the 
   <span class="italic">g</span>
   <sub>2</sub> measure [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Main statistical analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Samples were collected in two Galapagos sea lion colonies: one on an uninhabited island (control colony, Santa Fe), and one located in a town (human-impacted colony, San Cristobal) [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>]; and from sea lions in two ecologically distinct age-classes: pups (0–3 months old), which are restricted to land and are dependent on their mothers for nutrition; and juveniles (6–24 months old), which swim out to sea and are capable of foraging independently [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" href="#CR70">70</a>]. We sampled pups shortly after birth and at 3 months of age, between which two ages they undergo a growth spurt [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>]; and juveniles at 6, 12, 18 and 24 months of age. We captured sea lions using hoop nets and briefly restrained them in a prone position without the use of chemical immobilization, and without causing harm, by following the capture protocol in [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" href="#CR70">70</a>]. All work was approved by the Zoological Society of London Ethics Committee, and carried out under Galapagos National Park permits PC-18-09, N046-2009-PNG, N101-2010-PNG and N032-2010-PNG, which covered all fieldwork, capture and sample protocols. We used two measures of immune variation: immunoglobulin G (IgG) concentration and total leukocyte concentration, as they were highlighted in previous analyses as most likely to vary meaningfully with other aspects of Galapagos sea lion life history [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Galapagos sea lion pups undergo rapid growth and physiological development during the sampled period of their early development [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>]. In order to take these changes into account, and given that pups were only sampled at two time points during this period, we calculated absolute changes in body mass (kg), body length (cm), IgG concentration (mg/ml) and total leukocyte concentration (10
   <span class="sup">9</span>/l) between shortly after birth and 3 months of age. The possibility of phenotypic correlation [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>] means that growth and changes in immune measures may covary, and we have shown that the direction of these associations varies between colonies in the Galapagos sea lion [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>]. Therefore, in fast-growing pups, we partitioned variation in changes in each immune measure into subsets that were correlated with changes in body length and body mass in different ways using principal components analyses, carried out separately for each colony. For each colony and immune measure we fit generalised linear models with principal components that explained ≥ 5 % of the variation as response variables to homozygosity weighted by locus (HL) [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>], sex and their interaction as explanatory terms, removing interactions if they were non-significant [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71" href="#CR71">71</a>]. This amounted to eight statistical models fitted to pup data: two principal components, from two immune measures, in two colonies. This approach addresses the problem of the potentially confounding influence of phenotypic correlation on associations between HL and changes in immune measures in fast-growing pups, as it partitions the variation in changes in immune measures into components that are correlated with different kinds of growth, and allows for comparison between their association with homozygosity.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We chose HL as the most appropriate measure of heterozygosity for the main statistical analyses, so that they could be compared with other published results (e.g. [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>]), and because the distribution of the variation in HL was amenable to modelling in a generalised linear model (GLM) framework. However, we undertook a detailed exploration of the biases inherent in different estimates of heterozygosity and inbreeding using simulation analysis to provide context for these results, and other analyses that use measures of heterozygosity more generally (Additional file 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>: Supplementary Text 1.1–2, Table S2–3, Figure S1).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In comparison with pups, relatively little growth occurs in juvenile Galapagos sea lions between the ages of 6 and 24 months [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>], fewer physiological changes take place, and body mass and length are more closely correlated than in younger animals [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>]. In addition, we sampled juveniles at four rather than two time points. The nature of the juvenile data, therefore, allowed us to take a simpler approach to correcting for phenotypic correlation, which we did by including body mass as an explanatory variable. Separately for each colony, we fitted generalised linear mixed models (GLMMs) with each immune measure as a response variable and HL, body mass, sex and the interaction between HL and sex as explanatory terms. We included individual identity as a random effect to account for the pseudoreplication implicit in the repeated sampling of individuals. This amounted to four statistical models fitted to juvenile data, which covered two colonies and two immune measures. We compared models with and without the interaction between sex and HL using likelihood ratios tests [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72" href="#CR72">72</a>]. The analysis of juvenile data was therefore analogous to that of pup data, but did not require partitioning by principal components analysis. We checked all models for signs of heteroscedasticity, heterogeneity of variance, non-normality of error and the disproportionate influence of outliers.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
