<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec10" sec-type="conclusion" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusions</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although the links between heterozygosity and inbreeding are unresolved [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>], the context-dependent expression of patterns of covariance between heterozygosity and other traits can yield useful and interesting information. We offer these results as examples of covariation between aspects of genotype and phenotype in a natural population, which demonstrate the context-dependency of immune variation expression predicted by ecoimmunology, and which may provide new perspective on heterozygosity-fitness correlations, by allowing for the formation of increasingly detailed hypotheses on the mechanisms that drive them. Irrespective of their causes and mechanisms, and in light of recent findings in the Antarctic fur seal (
  <span class="italic">Arctocephalus gazelle</span>) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>], our results may also have implications for the management of declining populations, as they allow for the possibility that genetic effects interact with the two major threats to the Galapagos sea lion: climate-driven changes in food availability [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">66</a>] through effects on growth and condition; and disease threat [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>], through effects on immunity; both of which could act to compound the risk of decline and extinction.
 </p>
 <sec id="Sec11" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Availability of supporting data</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The genetic data used in the analyses are available in Additional file 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
