<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Immunoglobulin G (IgG) and heterozygosity</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Physiological measures of immune variation may be condition-dependent [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>], and variation in IgG concentration is correlated with growth in Galapagos sea lion pups [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>]. We partitioned variation in growth and IgG production into principal components to take this co-linearity into account. The majority of Galapagos sea lion pups grow [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>] and produce IgG [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>] during their first three months of life. Given the lack of evidence for infection or disease in the sampled Galapagos sea lion pups (Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>: Supplementary text 1.3–1.4), and a field experiment that showed IgG is not passed from mother to pup during the sampled stage of development in the Galapagos sea lion [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>], the observed IgG production is likely to be driven by post-natal antigen exposure, which stimulates the build-up of protective baseline populations of lymphocytes and antibodies [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Homozygosity weighted by locus (HL) was not associated with the first principal component derived from changes in IgG concentration, body mass and body length. This suggests that heterozygosity may not be straightforwardly related to fitness, as it was not correlated with the axis of variation that most likely describes phenotypic correlation between traits (Tables 
  <a rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" href="#Tab2">2</a> and 
  <a rid="Tab3" ref-type="table" href="#Tab3">3</a>) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>]. The second principal component was negatively correlated with HL, which, given the loadings (Tables 
  <a rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" href="#Tab2">2</a> and 
  <a rid="Tab3" ref-type="table" href="#Tab3">3</a>), suggests that relatively heterozygous individuals grew less but produced more IgG, which is congruent with findings from other systems [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>]. Such a pattern could arise through variation in resource allocation or acquisition between sea lion pups with different levels of heterozygosity [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>]. However, this does not explain why relatively homozygous pups appeared to grow more. The answer to this may lie in the relative magnitude of the length and mass loadings on the two components: there is a small difference between these in the first component (0.33 and 0.15 for length and mass respectively; Tables 
  <a rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" href="#Tab2">2</a> and 
  <a rid="Tab3" ref-type="table" href="#Tab3">3</a>), as we would expect under phenotypic correlation; but length loads more heavily on the second component than mass (−0.91 and −0.17 for length and mass respectively; Tables 
  <a rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" href="#Tab2">2</a> and 
  <a rid="Tab3" ref-type="table" href="#Tab3">3</a>). This suggests that the first component better represents overall growth that is more likely to be positively correlated with fitness, while the second represents elongation, which corresponds to a decrease in body condition [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Pups from the human-impacted colony varied less in terms of heterozygosity than pups from the control colony (Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>: Figure S1a-b), so the power to detect an effect may have been lower in the former, which could explain why the above pattern was only observed in the control colony. An alternative explanation is that pups (or mothers) in the human-impacted colony did not vary resource allocation according to heterozygosity in the same way that those in the control colony did. Pups in the human-impacted colony produced more IgG than pups from the control colony during the sampled period of development, which may be due to higher post-natal antigen exposure in the human-impacted colony [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>]. If this is the case, environmental stimulation of IgG production in the human-impacted colony may have over-ridden genetic influence on IgG production, which could obscure the statistical signal of genetic influence on IgG production in the human-impacted colony.
 </p>
</sec>
