<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<list list-type="order" class="list">
 <list-item class="list-item">
  <p class="p">Majority of the statistics-based approaches used for modeling the residential sector’s demand, leverage linear models to characterize the energy demand–climate nexus. However, recent research findings have shown that linear models are inadequate in capturing the complex and non-linear relationship between energy demand and climate variability and change [
   <xref rid="pone.0188033.ref003" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>,
   <xref rid="pone.0188033.ref011" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>,
   <xref rid="pone.0188033.ref016" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. On the other hand, the non-linear methods used for modeling an individual home’s demand trends (e.g., [
   <xref rid="pone.0188033.ref031" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>]) cannot be easily rolled up to represent the entire residential energy sector).
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item class="list-item">
  <p class="p">Most of the existing studies have focused on characterizing the end-use demand sensitivity to climate variability, using 
   <italic class="italic">cross-sectional</italic> data. While analyses based on cross-sectional data can help to extract useful information for a given point in time, they are not well-suited for medium- and long-term projections. This is because, cross-sectional data lack information on temporal variability. It should be noted that other studies have leveraged time-series data to capture medium- and long-term sensitivity of energy demand to climate [
   <xref rid="pone.0188033.ref003" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>,
   <xref rid="pone.0188033.ref011" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>–
   <xref rid="pone.0188033.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>,
   <xref rid="pone.0188033.ref016" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>, 
   <xref rid="pone.0188033.ref032" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>]. However, such studies used aggregate energy consumption data, with no breakdown of the climate sensitive portion of the end-use demand such as space heating, space cooling and water heating. Therefore, the results of such models (e.g., [
   <xref rid="pone.0188033.ref003" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>,
   <xref rid="pone.0188033.ref011" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>–
   <xref rid="pone.0188033.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>,
   <xref rid="pone.0188033.ref016" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]) cannot be integrated into energy-economy models (e.g., MARKAL and NEMS).
  </p>
 </list-item>
</list>
