<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1-ijerph-16-02662" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1. Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Solastalgia, preliminarily and broadly defined as the distress caused by the transformation and degradation of one’s home environment [
  <a rid="B1-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-ijerph-16-02662">1</a>,
  <a rid="B2-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-ijerph-16-02662">2</a>,
  <a rid="B3-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3-ijerph-16-02662">3</a>], is a relatively new concept with particular relevance to the environment–health–place nexus. Given the current speed and scale of climatic and environmental change, and the increasingly urgent calls to better understand the links between changing environments and human health, solastalgia merits further investigation and theoretical development [
  <a rid="B4-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-ijerph-16-02662">4</a>,
  <a rid="B5-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B5-ijerph-16-02662">5</a>,
  <a rid="B6-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6-ijerph-16-02662">6</a>]. As Louv [
  <a rid="B7-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-ijerph-16-02662">7</a>] argues, “if climate change occurs at the rate that some scientists believe it will, and if human beings continue to crowd into de-natured cities, then solastalgia will contribute to a quickening spiral of mental illness” [
  <a rid="B7-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B7-ijerph-16-02662">7</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Now is a critical time for an in-depth consideration of solastalgia. Individuals and communities worldwide are increasingly witnessing the dramatic and chronic degradation of environments and experiencing a range of associated responses and impacts. Although the physical health implications of climatic and environmental change are increasingly well documented [
  <a rid="B8-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8-ijerph-16-02662">8</a>,
  <a rid="B9-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9-ijerph-16-02662">9</a>,
  <a rid="B10-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10-ijerph-16-02662">10</a>], the emotional, mental, and spiritual health implications remain understudied [
  <a rid="B4-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-ijerph-16-02662">4</a>,
  <a rid="B10-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10-ijerph-16-02662">10</a>,
  <a rid="B11-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B11-ijerph-16-02662">11</a>,
  <a rid="B12-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12-ijerph-16-02662">12</a>,
  <a rid="B13-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13-ijerph-16-02662">13</a>]. Climate change is no longer a future threat, and we are witnessing a convergence of attention, an international wake-up call, to the perils of climatic and environmental change [
  <a rid="B14-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14-ijerph-16-02662">14</a>]. For example, consider the recent nexus of field reports of climate change, international climate reporting, and global protests. In October 2018, the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change issued a special report on the impacts of global warming of 1.5 °C [
  <a rid="B14-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14-ijerph-16-02662">14</a>]. Soon after, the Fourth National Climate Assessment was issued by 13 U.S. federal agencies and presented a stark warning for climate change consequences [
  <a rid="B15-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-ijerph-16-02662">15</a>]. In December 2018, the 24th Conference of the Parties to the United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change (COP24) outcomes highlighted the importance of staying within the 1.5 °C temperature rise target, as well as planning for how to achieve this goal [
  <a rid="B16-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16-ijerph-16-02662">16</a>]. At the core of this mounting evidence, the growing media attention, and the increasingly common lived experiences of climatic and environmental change, comes growing distress and a range of mental, emotional, and spiritual health consequences. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The overarching goal of this study is to characterize and synthesize the scholarly literature on solastalgia using a scoping review process. Scoping reviews are a form of knowledge synthesis used to map existing literature on a specific topic and are particularly useful when a topic is complex and heterogeneous [
  <a rid="B17-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17-ijerph-16-02662">17</a>,
  <a rid="B18-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-ijerph-16-02662">18</a>]. Scoping reviews aim to examine a body of literature on a given topic by contextualizing knowledge, mapping the key concepts underpinning a research area, and identifying the primary sources and types of evidence available [
  <a rid="B19-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-ijerph-16-02662">19</a>]. In doing so, scoping reviews advance conceptual clarity and identify gaps in the literature, offering valuable insight for future research directions [
  <a rid="B20-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-ijerph-16-02662">20</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this scoping review, we focus on the scholarly literature that uses solastalgia as a lens for examining emotional, mental, and spiritual health dimensions of climatic and environmental change. Although there is a range of related concepts used to understand environmentally-induced distress and the associated health impacts, ecological grief and eco-anxiety as key examples, we have not reviewed any such related concepts here. A key theoretical aspect of solastalgia that sets it apart from related concepts is an explicit focus on place: solastalgia is a place-based lived experience. In the paper that follows, we describe the scoping review process and findings and subsequently discuss the implications of these findings. We also make recommendations for advancing future solastalgia-related research. </p>
</sec>
