<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2dot4-ijerph-16-02662" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.4. Consultation Process </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Consultation with other scholars, practitioners, and potential knowledge-users (both settler and indigenous) was an important part of this study. The development of our specific research questions was informed in large part by knowledge gaps and priorities identified at a workshop entitled “Solastalgia: Investigating the nexus of climate change, place, and human well-being” which took place in October 2018 in Minnesota, USA. This workshop was inspired by place-based climate change research in the Western Lake Superior region [
  <a rid="B22-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-ijerph-16-02662">22</a>,
  <a rid="B23-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-ijerph-16-02662">23</a>,
  <a rid="B24-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-ijerph-16-02662">24</a>] including the North Shore Climate readiness project and the Twin Ports Climate Conversations [
  <a rid="B25-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25-ijerph-16-02662">25</a>] and was supported by funding from the University of Minnesota’s “On the Horizon” program. Participants included a diverse group of researchers and practitioners working on issues at the environment–health–place nexus in the Western Lake Superior region, and interested in exploring the concept of solastalgia, as well as research and practice concerning solastalgia more specifically. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">From the first workshop in October 2018, a more formal group formed, now calling itself the International Solastalgia Collaborative. “International” to acknowledge participation by First Nations people, Canadians, and Americans (and institutions from those nations). The International Solastalgia Collaborative met for a second workshop in January 2019 in Superior, Wisconsin. During the workshop, the authors of this paper presented preliminary findings of the scoping review and received criticism and feedback in a large group discussion. Feedback collected during the consultation process was documented and incorporated into the discussion and recommendations for further research presented in this paper. Final consultation took place in June 2019. The group was also invited to review and make comments on the manuscript at several stages throughout its development.</p>
</sec>
