<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3dot1-ijerph-16-02662" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1. General Characteristics of Papers</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Key findings from exploration of the general characteristics of the solastalgia literature show the literature to be recent, multidisciplinary, and empirical in nature, and further, the Australian origins of the work is clear. All papers were published between 2004 and 2018; our results indicate that the number of published scholarly papers has increased over these 15 years (See 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-02662-f002" href="#ijerph-16-02662-f002">Figure 2</a>). The concept of solastalgia was first introduced by Dr. Glenn Albrecht in 2003 at an Ecohealth Forum in Montreal, Canada, so it is not surprising that 2004 is the year when we begin to see publications. The year 2018 had the largest number of papers published (17%) suggesting a growing interest in solastalgia since the early 2000s. It should be noted that our review only covered articles published between January and October 2018, and therefore did not capture the full year. The use of the concept is not confined to a specific discipline; the solastalgia literature spans a wide range of academic disciplines, including public health, human geography, anthropology, and philosophy. Concerning geographic distribution among the papers in our final sample, there is a focus on Australia, which comprised half of all articles while another 19% of articles focused on the United States. The large proportion of solastalgia-related papers focused on Australia may be explained by the fact that more than half of the lead authors are situated in Australia and because Albrecht, who coined the term and still leads much of the work and discourse around solastalgia, resides in Australia. Countries in the Global South were underrepresented.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We coded papers in our review as ‘empirical,’ ‘theoretical/conceptual,’ ‘review papers,’ or ‘practice/policy focused papers.’ The majority were empirical papers (59%), 24% were theoretical or conceptual papers, and 17% were review papers. None were coded as practice/policy focused papers.</p>
</sec>
