<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3dot2-ijerph-16-02662" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2. How is Solastalgia Conceptualized and Applied in the Literature?</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Through the scoping review process, we sought to advance our understanding of how solastalgia is conceptualized and applied in the published literature. The data charting form included eight specific items to assist in answering the question (see 
  <a rid="ijerph-16-02662-t0A1" ref-type="table" href="#ijerph-16-02662-t0A1">Table A1</a>). We examined how authors define solastalgia in their work using textual analysis of verbatim definitions employed. Common elements of definition of solastalgia included: (i) a description of the transformation of the environment (i.e., unwelcome environmental change associated with resource extraction); (ii) a description of the place/environment being transformed (i.e., one’s valued home environment); and (iii) mention of specific impact(s) associated with the transformation (i.e., mental health impacts, depression). Textual analysis of the verbatim definitions illustrates that the words ‘environment’, ‘home,’ ‘distress,’ and ‘loss’ are the most commonly employed words when defining and describing solastalgia. Albrecht and his influential paper titled “‘Solastalgia’: A New Concept in Health and Identity” [
  <a rid="B1-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-ijerph-16-02662">1</a>] is commonly referenced by the papers in our review when defining solastalgia. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We also sought to gain a more in-depth understanding of the sources of environmental change resulting in solastalgic experiences as well as the terms employed to describe these sources. We found that there is a diversity of factors triggering solastalgia including extreme weather events, (e.g., Warsini [
  <a rid="B26-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26-ijerph-16-02662">26</a>]), resource extraction (e.g., Canu [
  <a rid="B27-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27-ijerph-16-02662">27</a>]), climate change (e.g., Tschekart et al. [
  <a rid="B28-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-ijerph-16-02662">28</a>]), and political violence (e.g., Sousa [
  <a rid="B29-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29-ijerph-16-02662">29</a>]) (See 
  <a rid="ijerph-16-02662-t002" ref-type="table" href="#ijerph-16-02662-t002">Table 2</a>). Extreme weather events such as flooding, drought, or earthquakes are the most commonly considered sources of environmental change described in the literature. Some of the factors causing the negative transformation of places ‘acute’ in nature, leading to dramatic and sudden transformation with ongoing impacts, while others are ‘chronic’ and result in more gradual and subtle degradation of places. Climate change is also a commonly examined cause of environmental degradation and transformation; interestingly, climate change leads to both acute impacts (e.g., floods and wildfires) and chronic degradation of places (e.g., sea level rise). Examples of terms commonly used to describe the environmental change include: ‘cumulative’, ‘compounding’, ‘imposed’, ‘unwelcome’, ‘unwanted’, ‘dramatic’, ‘negative’, and ‘profound/intense’ [
  <a rid="B1-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-ijerph-16-02662">1</a>,
  <a rid="B30-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30-ijerph-16-02662">30</a>,
  <a rid="B31-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31-ijerph-16-02662">31</a>,
  <a rid="B32-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32-ijerph-16-02662">32</a>,
  <a rid="B33-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33-ijerph-16-02662">33</a>,
  <a rid="B34-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34-ijerph-16-02662">34</a>,
  <a rid="B35-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35-ijerph-16-02662">35</a>,
  <a rid="B36-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36-ijerph-16-02662">36</a>,
  <a rid="B37-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37-ijerph-16-02662">37</a>,
  <a rid="B38-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38-ijerph-16-02662">38</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In terms of understanding how solastalgia is conceptualized and applied, we also examined whether the papers in our review describe related concepts—i.e., alternative concepts used to understand distress and associated emotional, spiritual, or mental health implications of changing environments—and if so, which concepts specifically. Solastalgia is part of an emerging set of concepts aimed at describing and accounting for the implications of climatic and environmental change on mental health and wellness. This emerging set of related emotional concepts has been described as “psychoterratic” or earth-related states [
  <a rid="B30-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30-ijerph-16-02662">30</a>,
  <a rid="B39-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39-ijerph-16-02662">39</a>]. Related concepts most commonly described in the solastalgia literature include ecological grief i.e., “the grief felt in relation to experienced or anticipated ecological losses including the loss of species, ecosystems, and meaningful landscapes due to acute or chronic environmental change” [
  <a rid="B33-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33-ijerph-16-02662">33</a>], and eco-anxiety, i.e., “anxiety related to a changing and uncertain environment...people become overwhelmed by the sheer scale, complexity and ‘wickedness’ of the problems we are facing" [
  <a rid="B31-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31-ijerph-16-02662">31</a>]. Other concepts discussed, but less commonly, include topophilia [
  <a rid="B40-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40-ijerph-16-02662">40</a>], nature-deficit disorder [
  <a rid="B41-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41-ijerph-16-02662">41</a>], and eco-paralysis. Most (75%) of the papers we reviewed make mention of at least one additional related concept. However, few papers provide clear definitions of these related concepts or outline explicitly the similarities and differences between solastalgia and these associated concepts leading to a lack of conceptual clarity in the literature overall. 
 </p>
</sec>
