<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec4dot1-ijerph-16-02662" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.1. Reflections on Place and People–Place Relationships in the Solastalgia Literature</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Place is a defining element of solastalgia, and people–place relationships are central to the ongoing study of the links between environmental change and human health and wellness. However, the ways in place and people–place relationships are understood are often unclear in the solastalgia literature. It is noteworthy that conceptual inconsistencies in terms of place-related concepts is common in other areas of inquiry as well [
  <a rid="B57-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B57-ijerph-16-02662">57</a>]. Cunsolo and Ellis [
  <a rid="B33-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33-ijerph-16-02662">33</a>] have called for caution and clarity when applying place-related concepts in their review of ecological grief. We echo these calls and argue that ongoing study of solastalgia will benefit from greater clarity regarding how place and people–place concepts (i.e., place attachment, sense of place, connectedness to nature, etc.) are understood and applied.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The landscape construct was used by some papers in this review (e.g., [
  <a rid="B30-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30-ijerph-16-02662">30</a>,
  <a rid="B38-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38-ijerph-16-02662">38</a>,
  <a rid="B58-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B58-ijerph-16-02662">58</a>]) and is increasingly used in the broader literature exploring the environment–health–place nexus as well [
  <a rid="B59-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B59-ijerph-16-02662">59</a>]. According to Wylie, [
  <a rid="B46-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46-ijerph-16-02662">46</a>] landscape describes a process of place; “what we witness when we examine landscape is a process of continual interaction in which nature and culture both shape and are shaped by each other”. Landscapes include people, nature, and other beings, a perspective which aligns with the way in which many Indigenous scholars describe the reciprocal relationships between land, health, language, etc. [
  <a rid="B60-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B60-ijerph-16-02662">60</a>,
  <a rid="B61-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B61-ijerph-16-02662">61</a>]. Landscapes are not neutral backdrops where human activities unfold [
  <a rid="B46-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46-ijerph-16-02662">46</a>], rather they are relational, dynamic, and nested social-ecological systems. Grounding solastalgia research in landscapes allows for an emphasis on the richly intertwined aspect of nature and culture defining the places that people cherish while acknowledging the interplay across local, regional, and global scales, which we see as particularly relevant when aiming to understand the mental, emotional, and spiritual impacts of climate change—a global phenomenon that is witnessed and experienced in regional and local landscapes [
  <a rid="B22-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-ijerph-16-02662">22</a>]. Thinking about places as landscapes may also help us to consider how individual and collective identity is wrapped up in place. Stobbelaar and Pedroli [
  <a rid="B62-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B62-ijerph-16-02662">62</a>], define landscape identity as “the unique psycho-sociological perception of a place defined in a spatial–cultural space”, reminding us of both collective and individual aspects of landscape. Thus, landscape identity is the ability to see oneself in the on-going creation of landscapes and to acknowledge how one has been shaped by landscapes. A recent application of the idea of landscape identity in relation to environmental change is a study by Butler et al. [
  <a rid="B63-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B63-ijerph-16-02662">63</a>] that considered landscape identity within an area altered by a catastrophic forest fire.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Drawing on the construct of landscape as described above, we define solastalgia as the distress caused by the unwelcome transformation of cherished landscapes resulting in cumulative mental, emotional, and spiritual health impacts. While initial solastalgia scales used a place descriptor of a specific location, in much of the solastalgia literature, place is described using the idea of ‘home’; we use ‘cherished landscapes’ instead. ‘Cherished’, to emphasize the deep emotional attachment to places that is common among those experiencing solastalgia. ‘Landscape’ to underline that places are dynamic, that humans are part of the biophysical world [
  <a rid="B64-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B64-ijerph-16-02662">64</a>], and that place can be understood across nested scales and in multiple ways (e.g., place as home, place as specific location, place as local, place as regional, place as territory, place as global). Moreover, this shift from home to landscape in our understanding of solastalgia accounts for the possibility that individuals can experience solastalgia due to the undesired transformation of valued places other than their home environment. It is important to note that the specific way of defining and describing solastalgia presented here is grounded in, and particularly relevant to, the landscapes in which members of the International Solastalgia Collaborative live, learn, work, play, and study: the Lake Superior watershed. While we expect that this shift in the definition of solastalgia may be relevant to others engaging in solastalgia work across different landscapes, we acknowledge that it may not be relevant to all. 
 </p>
</sec>
