<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec4dot2dot4-ijerph-16-02662" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.2.4. Mediating Factors </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This scoping review has revealed that our collective understanding of the factors mediating the relationship between the lived experience of environmental change and solastalgia—such as place attachment, connectedness to nature, and sense of powerlessness—is limited. Although place attachment is very commonly hypothesized as a mediating factor; specifically that “greater feelings of place attachment results in more intense impact” [
  <a rid="B3-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3-ijerph-16-02662">3</a>], there is limited empirical evidence in support of this notion. The potential role of uncertainty as a mediating factor, more specifically that uncertainty about the future due to climatic and environmental change, is also under-examined in the literature and is particularly relevant concerning the impacts of climate change. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A subset of articles from this review considered the relationship between environmental change, powerlessness, and solastalgia [
  <a rid="B2-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-ijerph-16-02662">2</a>,
  <a rid="B3-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3-ijerph-16-02662">3</a>,
  <a rid="B32-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32-ijerph-16-02662">32</a>,
  <a rid="B44-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44-ijerph-16-02662">44</a>]. Arguably, a perceived or actual inability to prevent the transformation of cherished landscapes, and therefore a sense of powerlessness, may exacerbate solastalgia. Askland and Bunn [
  <a rid="B48-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B48-ijerph-16-02662">48</a>], whose paper aims to “critically engage with the topic of solastalgia including a consideration of power and dispossession” argue that “whilst solastalgia may help explore the relationship between environmental and human distress, the sense of displacement and loss that emerge are entangled with questions of power and dispossession beyond the biophysical realm". Along a similar vein, Albrecht et al. [
  <a rid="B2-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-ijerph-16-02662">2</a>] write about the lived experiences of persistent drought as well as experiences of large-scale open-cut coal mining in Australia: “In both cases, people exposed to environmental change experienced negative affect that is exacerbated by a sense of powerlessness or lack of control over the unfolding process.” Also noteworthy, we found that the terms “unwanted”, “imposed”, and “unwelcome” are commonly employed when describing a source of environmental change causing solastalgia. These descriptive terms highlight the role that powerlessness (or perceived powerlessness) can play in one’s experience of environmental change and degradation of cherished landscapes. Nevertheless, the idea of power/powerlessness as a mediating factor of solastalgic experiences is under-investigated. How, for instance, does one’s positionality within society, access to resources, and decision-making power determine the likelihood or intensity of solastalgia? 
 </p>
</sec>
