<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec4dot2dot2-ijerph-16-02662" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.2.2. Attention to Diversity and Gender Dimensions </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another opportunity for advancing solastalgia study is to conduct research in a greater diversity of places and with a greater diversity of people and communities. This review highlighted that some regions of the world (e.g., global south) and specific population groups (e.g., youth, Indigenous peoples) are under-represented in the literature. Moreover, greater attention to the gendered dimensions of solastalgic experiences is warranted as the impacts of climatic and environmental change are “not gender neutral” [
  <a rid="B66-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B66-ijerph-16-02662">66</a>]. Although a number of the papers included gender as a demographic variable, only three focused on the gendered dimensions of solastalgia in a substantive way. A related unpublished study sampled a random population of 1000 Lower Hunter New South Wales older residents (average age 66, range 55–86, equal men and women); researchers found an almost identical mean solastalgia score for men and women. Age in this truncated cohort study was not associated with solastalgia, but those with university degrees had statistically higher solastalgia scores compared with both those with technical college education and those with primary/secondary level educations [
  <a rid="B67-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B67-ijerph-16-02662">67</a>]. It is clear from this review that gender is an understudied aspect of solastalgia research and an opportunity for advancement. 
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Intersectionality [
  <a rid="B68-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B68-ijerph-16-02662">68</a>,
  <a rid="B69-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B69-ijerph-16-02662">69</a>] and recent work applying the lens of intersectionality to climate change research and action (e.g., Kaijser [
  <a rid="B70-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B70-ijerph-16-02662">70</a>], Vinyeta et al. [
  <a rid="B71-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B71-ijerph-16-02662">71</a>], Djouti et al. [
  <a rid="B72-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B72-ijerph-16-02662">72</a>]) offers guidance for making progress towards paying attention to, and understanding, the ways in which gender, race, class and other identities intersect with experiences of solastalgia. Intersectionality “recognizes complex, horizontal (inter-community) and vertical (national, regional, local) interactions” while acknowledging context-specific mechanisms of exclusion and marginalization [
  <a rid="B72-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B72-ijerph-16-02662">72</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
