<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec4-ijerph-16-02662" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4. Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As noted previously, this review aimed to characterize and synthesize the scholarly literature on solastalgia. The data and key findings presented highlight important gaps in the literature and identify opportunities for theoretical, methodological, and practical advances concerning solastalgia. The following section discusses reflections on place that have emerged from the review process that merit further discussion. Subsequently, we present priority areas for future inquiry concerning solastalgia.</p>
 <sec id="sec4dot1-ijerph-16-02662" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.1. Reflections on Place and People–Place Relationships in the Solastalgia Literature</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Place is a defining element of solastalgia, and people–place relationships are central to the ongoing study of the links between environmental change and human health and wellness. However, the ways in place and people–place relationships are understood are often unclear in the solastalgia literature. It is noteworthy that conceptual inconsistencies in terms of place-related concepts is common in other areas of inquiry as well [
   <a rid="B57-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B57-ijerph-16-02662">57</a>]. Cunsolo and Ellis [
   <a rid="B33-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33-ijerph-16-02662">33</a>] have called for caution and clarity when applying place-related concepts in their review of ecological grief. We echo these calls and argue that ongoing study of solastalgia will benefit from greater clarity regarding how place and people–place concepts (i.e., place attachment, sense of place, connectedness to nature, etc.) are understood and applied.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The landscape construct was used by some papers in this review (e.g., [
   <a rid="B30-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30-ijerph-16-02662">30</a>,
   <a rid="B38-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38-ijerph-16-02662">38</a>,
   <a rid="B58-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B58-ijerph-16-02662">58</a>]) and is increasingly used in the broader literature exploring the environment–health–place nexus as well [
   <a rid="B59-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B59-ijerph-16-02662">59</a>]. According to Wylie, [
   <a rid="B46-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46-ijerph-16-02662">46</a>] landscape describes a process of place; “what we witness when we examine landscape is a process of continual interaction in which nature and culture both shape and are shaped by each other”. Landscapes include people, nature, and other beings, a perspective which aligns with the way in which many Indigenous scholars describe the reciprocal relationships between land, health, language, etc. [
   <a rid="B60-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B60-ijerph-16-02662">60</a>,
   <a rid="B61-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B61-ijerph-16-02662">61</a>]. Landscapes are not neutral backdrops where human activities unfold [
   <a rid="B46-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46-ijerph-16-02662">46</a>], rather they are relational, dynamic, and nested social-ecological systems. Grounding solastalgia research in landscapes allows for an emphasis on the richly intertwined aspect of nature and culture defining the places that people cherish while acknowledging the interplay across local, regional, and global scales, which we see as particularly relevant when aiming to understand the mental, emotional, and spiritual impacts of climate change—a global phenomenon that is witnessed and experienced in regional and local landscapes [
   <a rid="B22-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-ijerph-16-02662">22</a>]. Thinking about places as landscapes may also help us to consider how individual and collective identity is wrapped up in place. Stobbelaar and Pedroli [
   <a rid="B62-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B62-ijerph-16-02662">62</a>], define landscape identity as “the unique psycho-sociological perception of a place defined in a spatial–cultural space”, reminding us of both collective and individual aspects of landscape. Thus, landscape identity is the ability to see oneself in the on-going creation of landscapes and to acknowledge how one has been shaped by landscapes. A recent application of the idea of landscape identity in relation to environmental change is a study by Butler et al. [
   <a rid="B63-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B63-ijerph-16-02662">63</a>] that considered landscape identity within an area altered by a catastrophic forest fire.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Drawing on the construct of landscape as described above, we define solastalgia as the distress caused by the unwelcome transformation of cherished landscapes resulting in cumulative mental, emotional, and spiritual health impacts. While initial solastalgia scales used a place descriptor of a specific location, in much of the solastalgia literature, place is described using the idea of ‘home’; we use ‘cherished landscapes’ instead. ‘Cherished’, to emphasize the deep emotional attachment to places that is common among those experiencing solastalgia. ‘Landscape’ to underline that places are dynamic, that humans are part of the biophysical world [
   <a rid="B64-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B64-ijerph-16-02662">64</a>], and that place can be understood across nested scales and in multiple ways (e.g., place as home, place as specific location, place as local, place as regional, place as territory, place as global). Moreover, this shift from home to landscape in our understanding of solastalgia accounts for the possibility that individuals can experience solastalgia due to the undesired transformation of valued places other than their home environment. It is important to note that the specific way of defining and describing solastalgia presented here is grounded in, and particularly relevant to, the landscapes in which members of the International Solastalgia Collaborative live, learn, work, play, and study: the Lake Superior watershed. While we expect that this shift in the definition of solastalgia may be relevant to others engaging in solastalgia work across different landscapes, we acknowledge that it may not be relevant to all. 
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec4dot2-ijerph-16-02662" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.2. Priority Areas for Future Inquiry</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The research priorities presented below are not exhaustive, nor are they prescriptive. Instead, we offer research directions that have emerged from the scoping review process, highlighting what we see as most relevant to advancing solastalgia research overall as well as the application of solastalgia research specifically.</p>
  <sec id="sec4dot2dot1-ijerph-16-02662" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.2.1. Further Conceptual Clarity and Theoretical Development </div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Solastalgia was developed “to give greater meaning and clarity to environmentally induced distress” [
    <a rid="B2-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-ijerph-16-02662">2</a>]. The past 15 years of research have certainly contributed to growing conceptual clarity and theoretical advancement, as well as a more nuanced understanding of the emotional, mental, and spiritual health toll posed by our rapidly changing world. Nonetheless, additional research is needed to advance conceptual clarity and the theoretical foundations of solastalgia further. Efforts directed at clarifying the distinguishing features of solastalgia and unpacking the points of convergence and divergence between solastalgia and related concepts such as ecological grief, eco-anxiety, nature-deficit disorder, and mental health impacts of climate change, are particularly important. In their review of ecological grief, Cunsolo and Ellis [
    <a rid="B33-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33-ijerph-16-02662">33</a>] have similarly called for additional work to understand how ecological grief relates to solastalgia more fully. Albrecht [
    <a rid="B31-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31-ijerph-16-02662">31</a>,
    <a rid="B39-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39-ijerph-16-02662">39</a>,
    <a rid="B65-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B65-ijerph-16-02662">65</a>] has done recent work towards developing nuances of solastalgia, grief, morning, and related emotional states including a “psychoterratic typology” and describing what he calls negative and positive Earth emotions [
    <a rid="B39-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39-ijerph-16-02662">39</a>]; this is a strong foundation to build on to advance conceptual clarity and theoretical development.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec4dot2dot2-ijerph-16-02662" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.2.2. Attention to Diversity and Gender Dimensions </div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another opportunity for advancing solastalgia study is to conduct research in a greater diversity of places and with a greater diversity of people and communities. This review highlighted that some regions of the world (e.g., global south) and specific population groups (e.g., youth, Indigenous peoples) are under-represented in the literature. Moreover, greater attention to the gendered dimensions of solastalgic experiences is warranted as the impacts of climatic and environmental change are “not gender neutral” [
    <a rid="B66-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B66-ijerph-16-02662">66</a>]. Although a number of the papers included gender as a demographic variable, only three focused on the gendered dimensions of solastalgia in a substantive way. A related unpublished study sampled a random population of 1000 Lower Hunter New South Wales older residents (average age 66, range 55–86, equal men and women); researchers found an almost identical mean solastalgia score for men and women. Age in this truncated cohort study was not associated with solastalgia, but those with university degrees had statistically higher solastalgia scores compared with both those with technical college education and those with primary/secondary level educations [
    <a rid="B67-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B67-ijerph-16-02662">67</a>]. It is clear from this review that gender is an understudied aspect of solastalgia research and an opportunity for advancement. 
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Intersectionality [
    <a rid="B68-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B68-ijerph-16-02662">68</a>,
    <a rid="B69-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B69-ijerph-16-02662">69</a>] and recent work applying the lens of intersectionality to climate change research and action (e.g., Kaijser [
    <a rid="B70-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B70-ijerph-16-02662">70</a>], Vinyeta et al. [
    <a rid="B71-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B71-ijerph-16-02662">71</a>], Djouti et al. [
    <a rid="B72-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B72-ijerph-16-02662">72</a>]) offers guidance for making progress towards paying attention to, and understanding, the ways in which gender, race, class and other identities intersect with experiences of solastalgia. Intersectionality “recognizes complex, horizontal (inter-community) and vertical (national, regional, local) interactions” while acknowledging context-specific mechanisms of exclusion and marginalization [
    <a rid="B72-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B72-ijerph-16-02662">72</a>].
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec4dot2dot3-ijerph-16-02662" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.2.3. Youth Voices </div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A growing segment of the youth population is experiencing the impacts of climatic and environmental change in their everyday lives. Research has shown that young people may experience emotional, mental, and spiritual health impacts due to climate change [
    <a rid="B73-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B73-ijerph-16-02662">73</a>,
    <a rid="B74-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B74-ijerph-16-02662">74</a>,
    <a rid="B75-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B75-ijerph-16-02662">75</a>]. Youth voices are an emerging source of power and inspiration in the face of climate change; the 2019 strikes for climate action initiated by high school students all across the planet is one concrete example of this [
    <a rid="B76-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B76-ijerph-16-02662">76</a>]. Yet, despite youth concerns and responses, only one article in our review [
    <a rid="B77-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B77-ijerph-16-02662">77</a>] examined youth-specific solastalgic experiences. Research using solastalgia as a theoretical framework with an explicit focus on youth is an opportunity to enhance our understanding of solastalgia as well as the overall study of place, environmental change, and human health. Participatory action research, which could promote youth empowerment and could set the stage for coping with solastalgia, is perhaps the most appropriate methodology for study examining youth experiences of solastalgia. The method of photovoice may be particularly useful. 
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec4dot2dot4-ijerph-16-02662" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.2.4. Mediating Factors </div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This scoping review has revealed that our collective understanding of the factors mediating the relationship between the lived experience of environmental change and solastalgia—such as place attachment, connectedness to nature, and sense of powerlessness—is limited. Although place attachment is very commonly hypothesized as a mediating factor; specifically that “greater feelings of place attachment results in more intense impact” [
    <a rid="B3-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3-ijerph-16-02662">3</a>], there is limited empirical evidence in support of this notion. The potential role of uncertainty as a mediating factor, more specifically that uncertainty about the future due to climatic and environmental change, is also under-examined in the literature and is particularly relevant concerning the impacts of climate change. 
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A subset of articles from this review considered the relationship between environmental change, powerlessness, and solastalgia [
    <a rid="B2-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-ijerph-16-02662">2</a>,
    <a rid="B3-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3-ijerph-16-02662">3</a>,
    <a rid="B32-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32-ijerph-16-02662">32</a>,
    <a rid="B44-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44-ijerph-16-02662">44</a>]. Arguably, a perceived or actual inability to prevent the transformation of cherished landscapes, and therefore a sense of powerlessness, may exacerbate solastalgia. Askland and Bunn [
    <a rid="B48-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B48-ijerph-16-02662">48</a>], whose paper aims to “critically engage with the topic of solastalgia including a consideration of power and dispossession” argue that “whilst solastalgia may help explore the relationship between environmental and human distress, the sense of displacement and loss that emerge are entangled with questions of power and dispossession beyond the biophysical realm". Along a similar vein, Albrecht et al. [
    <a rid="B2-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-ijerph-16-02662">2</a>] write about the lived experiences of persistent drought as well as experiences of large-scale open-cut coal mining in Australia: “In both cases, people exposed to environmental change experienced negative affect that is exacerbated by a sense of powerlessness or lack of control over the unfolding process.” Also noteworthy, we found that the terms “unwanted”, “imposed”, and “unwelcome” are commonly employed when describing a source of environmental change causing solastalgia. These descriptive terms highlight the role that powerlessness (or perceived powerlessness) can play in one’s experience of environmental change and degradation of cherished landscapes. Nevertheless, the idea of power/powerlessness as a mediating factor of solastalgic experiences is under-investigated. How, for instance, does one’s positionality within society, access to resources, and decision-making power determine the likelihood or intensity of solastalgia? 
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec4dot2dot5-ijerph-16-02662" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.2.5. Accounting for the Cumulative Nature of Health Impacts</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ellis and Albrecht [
    <a rid="B35-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35-ijerph-16-02662">35</a>] argue that solastalgic experiences often come “on top of other economic and social stressors”, thereby exacerbating health disadvantages and inequities [
    <a rid="B35-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35-ijerph-16-02662">35</a>]. We certainly agree with this notion and see evidence of this in our review. The research aimed at understanding how multiple factors interact with the transformation of cherished landscapes, across both time and space, resulting in cumulative impacts on emotional, mental, and spiritual health is a priority moving forward. Integrating the work on historical trauma [
    <a rid="B78-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B78-ijerph-16-02662">78</a>,
    <a rid="B79-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B79-ijerph-16-02662">79</a>] into future solastalgia research could be a useful avenue for advancing our understanding of the cumulative nature of impacts. Historical trauma, understood as the cumulative and intergenerational experiences of multiple chronic traumas experienced by Indigenous peoples (and others) including, but certainly not limited to, land dispossession and degradation [
    <a rid="B78-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B78-ijerph-16-02662">78</a>,
    <a rid="B79-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B79-ijerph-16-02662">79</a>]. Solastalgic distress and other mental, emotional, and spiritual health impacts caused by environmental change “can be understood in light of historical trauma losses and disruptions tied to place or land” [
    <a rid="B80-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B80-ijerph-16-02662">80</a>]. The emerging literature on the cumulative environmental, community, and health impacts of resource development (e.g., Parkes [
    <a rid="B81-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B81-ijerph-16-02662">81</a>], Gillingham [
    <a rid="B6-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B6-ijerph-16-02662">6</a>]) could also be useful for scholars aiming to examine the cumulative nature of health impacts that emerge as a consequence of the transformation of cherished landscapes. 
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec4dot2dot6-ijerph-16-02662" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.2.6. Additional Mixed-Methods and Quantitative Research </div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Most of the empirical papers reviewed here used qualitative methods, specifically interviews, to collect data on the lived experiences of solastalgia. Qualitative methods are undoubtedly appropriate and useful, however, the solastalgia literature overall would benefit from additional quantitative and mixed-method research. A specific area for advancement is further development, validation, and application of scales to quantitatively measure solastalgia. The EDS developed by Higginbotham [
    <a rid="B3-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3-ijerph-16-02662">3</a>] and adapted by Warsini [
    <a rid="B42-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42-ijerph-16-02662">42</a>,
    <a rid="B43-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43-ijerph-16-02662">43</a>] and Eisenman [
    <a rid="B34-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34-ijerph-16-02662">34</a>] is a strong foundation to build on. Additional testing, across diverse landscapes and populations, and in response to a greater variety of sources of hazards (both acute and chronic), is warranted. Note, a number of masters and PhD studies have made use of EDS/solastalgia framework, and many of these have not shown up in the 29 studies (outside the scoping criteria); these additional sources may be able to provide support and/or critique to the use of the EDS [
    <a rid="B67-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B67-ijerph-16-02662">67</a>]. Further, population-based studies using quantitative data collection and analysis methods could help enhance our limited understanding of mediating factors as described above, risk factors, and vulnerable sub-groups, while also helping to address an important and yet unanswered question: what is the burden of solastalgia at the population level?
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec4dot2dot7-ijerph-16-02662" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.2.7. Research Led by or Conducted in Partnership with Indigenous Communities/Peoples </div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In early and foundational discussions of solastalgia, scholars took care to describe the nature of Indigenous peoples’ and non-Indigenous peoples’ relationships to the land [
    <a rid="B1-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-ijerph-16-02662">1</a>,
    <a rid="B2-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-ijerph-16-02662">2</a>,
    <a rid="B30-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30-ijerph-16-02662">30</a>,
    <a rid="B32-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32-ijerph-16-02662">32</a>]. In his early work, Albrecht [
    <a rid="B1-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B1-ijerph-16-02662">1</a>] described Indigenous experiences of distress related to environmental change as amplified given that “they (Indigenous peoples) live through the destruction of their cultural traditions and their lands”. In many cases, Indigenous people’s sense of personal and cultural identity derives from their relationships with the land (including water and non-human beings). Indigenous peoples suffer from distress when their ties to those places (or the places themselves) change, inferring that such distress may be experienced differently than the place-related distress of non-Indigenous people. However, there are other factors—in addition to strong relationships with the land—that are common among Indigenous populations, and that may impact Indigenous peoples’ experiences of solastalgia. Indigenous people’s collective and layered experiences of historical trauma like land dispossession, colonization and forced assimilation, boarding/residential schools, and broken nation-to-nation treaties may also shape experiences and responses to climatic and environmental change, or the intensity of experiences of solastalgia [
    <a rid="B49-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49-ijerph-16-02662">49</a>,
    <a rid="B82-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B82-ijerph-16-02662">82</a>,
    <a rid="B83-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B83-ijerph-16-02662">83</a>]. 
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Importantly, solastalgia may be an inadequate or even inappropriate way of describing Indigenous peoples’ experiences of distress related to changes to their cherished landscapes. In our consultation process, an Indigenous scholar asserted that “solastalgia is a colonized word, and using the term solastalgia (to describe Indigenous experiences) feels like trying to knock a square peg into a round hole. There are Indigenous concepts that can be used to describe solastalgia-like experiences better” [
    <a rid="B84-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B84-ijerph-16-02662">84</a>]. In some applications, solastalgia has been used to describe individual, rather than collective, experiences of distress, emphasizing an “individualism and colonial isolation that settler colonialism fosters” [
    <a rid="B85-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B85-ijerph-16-02662">85</a>]. It is also important to acknowledge that there is an intimate and reciprocal relationship between Indigenous languages and the landscapes and places in which they develop: “Indigenous Knowledge comes from the land through the relationships Indigenous People develop and foster with the essential forces of nature. These relationships are encoded in the structure of Indigenous languages and in Indigenous political and spiritual systems. They are practiced in traditional forms of governance, and they are lived in the hearts and minds of Indigenous People” [
    <a rid="B49-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49-ijerph-16-02662">49</a>]. Therefore, the concept of solastalgia may be best articulated in the specific language(s) of the peoples who are experiencing it. Albrecht [
    <a rid="B30-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30-ijerph-16-02662">30</a>] provides some examples of this, including the Baffin Island Inuit term 
    <span class="italic">uggianaqtuq</span>, which has connotations of “a friend acting ‘strangely’ or in an unpredictable way”. There are other bodies of literature that use different conceptual frameworks and theories to understand and describe Indigenous peoples’ experiences of distress related to environmental change and loss, including historical trauma, ecological grief, and the mental health impacts of climate change (sources). The work of Cunsolo et al. [
    <a rid="B13-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13-ijerph-16-02662">13</a>,
    <a rid="B86-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B86-ijerph-16-02662">86</a>] in Canada’s far North is an excellent example of community-led research examining the mental health implications of climatic change, in partnership with Inuit peoples. Another example is the research conducted by Rigby et al. [
    <a rid="B87-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B87-ijerph-16-02662">87</a>], which explored the impact of prolonged drought on the emotional well-being of Aboriginal communities in rural Australia, in collaboration with Aboriginal partners. 
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Some of these critical considerations could be addressed through research led-by, or conducted in partnership with, Indigenous scholars and Indigenous communities. Non-Indigenous scholars and practitioners seeking to understand Indigenous peoples’ experiences of solastalgia may benefit from using “two-eyed seeing” [
    <a rid="B88-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B88-ijerph-16-02662">88</a>] and decolonizing methodologies to inform and guide their collaborative solastalgia research. “Two-eyed seeing” is a framework that embraces both Indigenous and western ways of knowing in balance with one another and has the power to “reshape the nature of the questions we ask in the realm of Indigenous health research” [
    <a rid="B88-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B88-ijerph-16-02662">88</a>]. Decolonizing methodologies encourage scholars to care for the land and stewards of the land while also encouraging critical questions throughout research processes to “enhance, rather than simply describe or define, the lives of Indigenous peoples” [
    <a rid="B89-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B89-ijerph-16-02662">89</a>,
    <a rid="B90-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B90-ijerph-16-02662">90</a>]. Ultimately, it is for Indigenous researchers and their communities to decide if the idea of solastalgia is useful to express experiences of negative environmental change or if existing concepts from Indigenous scholarship are more appropriate. 
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="sec4dot2dot8-ijerph-16-02662" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.2.8. Practical Implications and Applications</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our scoping review process has underscored that the practical implications and the potential applications of solastalgia research are generally overlooked at present. Potential practical applications of solastalgia include its use in health and environmental impact assessment processes [
    <a rid="B51-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51-ijerph-16-02662">51</a>], clinical settings (i.e., social work, psychology), and climate change and health vulnerability assessments. How to integrate solastalgia into these practical arenas remains unclear and doing so will require further theoretical development in addition to the development of validated scales to empirically measure and monitor solastalgic experiences. 
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There is a rich scholarly history documenting that connectedness to nature is critical to health and wellness [
    <a rid="B91-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B91-ijerph-16-02662">91</a>,
    <a rid="B92-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B92-ijerph-16-02662">92</a>,
    <a rid="B93-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B93-ijerph-16-02662">93</a>,
    <a rid="B94-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B94-ijerph-16-02662">94</a>]. Therefore, an important practical implication of a better understanding of solastalgia is greater recognition of the importance of safeguarding access to nature. Efforts to expand equitable access to nature must be taken as part of a response to the distress experienced by negative transformations of cherished landscapes. Our interconnectedness with nature may not only be at the core of our distress, but also key to coping with unwelcome transformations we experience. Given the centrality of place in the lived experiences of solastalgia, interventions aimed at responding to, and coping with, solastalgic distress will have to be informed by an in-depth understanding of people–place relationships across unique landscapes. 
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Key questions also remain in terms of how to address solastalgia. For instance, how can individuals and groups cope with solastalgic distress? Can the restoration of degraded landscapes help people cope with distress and enable healing? Can interventions focused on collective healing enable coping with solastalgia in ways that promote human and ecosystem health? These questions will be a central focus of the International Solastalgia Collaborative in the Lake Superior basin moving forward. We believe that responses to solastalgia have the potential to simultaneously heal human and ecosystem health while inspiring collective action against the structural forces underpinning climatic and environmental change; how exactly we can and should go about this in practice remains untested and under-investigated. We also believe that benefits can be derived from exploring the emotional dimensions of climatic and environmental change more fully. Emotions are defined broadly as “that which moves us” [
    <a rid="B39-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39-ijerph-16-02662">39</a>]; it is often affect, rather than knowledge or information alone, that moves people to take action in the face of climatic and environmental change [
    <a rid="B95-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B95-ijerph-16-02662">95</a>,
    <a rid="B96-ijerph-16-02662" ref-type="bibr" href="#B96-ijerph-16-02662">96</a>]. 
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
</sec>
