<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The North China Plain (NCP), which is facing significant warming and water scarcity, has received worldwide attention
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5" class="xref">5</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17" class="xref">17</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18" class="xref">18</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19" class="xref">19</xref>. The NCP provides more than one-fourth of the national food supply in China
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20" class="xref">20</xref>. The dominant agricultural system in this region involves double cropping. Winter wheat (
 <italic class="italic">Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) is rotated with summer maize (
 <italic class="italic">Zea mays</italic> L.), resulting in two harvests annually
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21" class="xref">21</xref>. To adapt for the changing climate, researchers have adjusted planting and harvesting dates, and identified cultivars that require more days to maturity, to improve grain yield
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18" class="xref">18</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21" class="xref">21</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22" class="xref">22</xref>. However, because of the large gap between precipitation and water demand in the winter wheat–summer maize system, such adaption requires more than 250 mm groundwater for irrigation each year, even when water usage is optimized
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23" class="xref">23</xref>. As a consequence, the groundwater table in the northern part of the NCP has declined by about 1 m yr
 <sup class="sup">−1 </sup>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24" class="xref">24</xref>. This decline has caused a series of environmental problems and has restricted sustainable development in the region
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17" class="xref">17</xref>. It is now clear that incremental adaptation of planting dates and crop cultivars is inadequate in this region. Rather than small adjustments to the current cropping system, more systematic changes are now required to meet the challenges of global warming, water scarcity, and a growing demand for food.
</p>
