<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The results of the current study suggest a rather bleak outlook for 
 <italic class="italic">N</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">tentaculata</italic>, and a similar future could await several other montane 
 <italic class="italic">Nepenthes</italic> species from the higher mountains of Borneo, such as 
 <italic class="italic">Nepenthes lowii</italic> Hook.f., 
 <italic class="italic">Nepenthes rajah</italic> Hook.f., 
 <italic class="italic">Nepenthes villosa</italic> Hook. f. and 
 <italic class="italic">N</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">macrophylla</italic>. Although the current study uses Bornean examples, it is important to note that the findings are applicable to 
 <italic class="italic">Nepenthes</italic> species endemic to mountainous areas throughout the extensive geographical area occupied by the Nepenthaceae. It is worth reiterating the fact that the Nepenthaceae is largely a montane family, and particularly rich in cloud forest endemic species; in fact, only about one-third of 
 <italic class="italic">Nepenthes</italic> species are restricted to lowland habitats [
 <xref rid="pone.0183132.ref003" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>]. Therefore, many montane endemic 
 <italic class="italic">Nepenthes</italic> species outside of Borneo are potentially at risk from anthropogenic climate change. For instance, a number of species from Palawan are confined to the uppermost parts of the island's highest mountains. An example is 
 <italic class="italic">N</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">attenboroughii</italic>, which is confined to the uppermost 100 m around the summit of a single mountain. Even a slight change to local temperature and rainfall patterns could be sufficient to threaten this species with extinction. By contrast, we believe that the genus as a whole is unlikely to succumb completely to the predicted effects of anthropogenically-driven climate change. 
 <italic class="italic">Nepenthes</italic> are thought to have been in existence for tens of millions of years [
 <xref rid="pone.0183132.ref002" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0183132.ref060" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">60</xref>]. If this timescale is correct, the genus has likely endured equivalent or perhaps even greater climatic upheavals than those currently predicted.
</p>
