<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s3c" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conservation implications</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The extreme urbanization within the Simi Hills area has had a significant effect on lizard and bird population genetics. Unlike some other studies of landscape level genetic changes where a species' habitat is naturally patchy, this study examined genetic responses to species living in habitat that was likely once relatively continuous 
  <a rid="pone.0012767-Riley1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0012767-Riley1">[42]</a>. While these species are still widely distributed and relatively abundant throughout the study area, genetic effects of fragmentation have been manifested in a relatively short period of 40 years or less. This may be the most profound and potentially disturbing result of our study: the vulnerability even of species that are perceived to be common and thereby likely less affected by habitat fragmentation. This may be particularly true for low-vagility organisms, and for those with more specific habitat requirements. As a chaparral and coastal sage scrub requiring species, wrentits are likely rare in developed areas and have been shown to go extinct in habitat patches as urbanization progresses 
  <a rid="pone.0012767-Soule1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0012767-Soule1">[2]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0012767-Bolger1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0012767-Bolger1">[53]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0012767-Crooks2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0012767-Crooks2">[54]</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For rarer species in the region, such as horned lizards (
  <span class="italic">Phrynosoma coronatum</span>) and whiptail lizards (
  <span class="italic">Aspidoscelis tigris</span>), whose distributions have already been reduced by urban development 
  <a rid="pone.0012767-Fisher1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0012767-Fisher1">[55]</a>, the genetic effects of fragmentation may be even more profound. Many endangered species in southern California are declining because of habitat loss, and many of these species also have low dispersal abilities along with more specific habitat requirements (e.g. light-footed clapper rail, 
  <span class="italic">Rallus longirostris obsoletus</span>; Belding's savannah sparrow, 
  <span class="italic">Passerculus sandwichensis beldingi</span>; red-legged frog, 
  <span class="italic">Rana draytonii</span>; least bell's vireo, 
  <span class="italic">Vireo bellii pusillus</span>). It is also unknown how stressors, such as increasing local or global temperature and urbanization, might affect species in southern California. A recent study of 
  <span class="italic">Sceloporus</span> lizards in Mexico found that 12% of local populations have gone extinct since 1975 
  <a rid="pone.0012767-Sinervo2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0012767-Sinervo2">[56]</a>. Sites where these common lizards were extirpated were too hot for too many hours of the day, presumably due to increasing global temperatures, which caused lizards to seek refuge from the heat instead of spending time foraging. In addition, our results have implications for endangered species such as the California gnatcatcher, where lack of differentiation at certain loci (e.g. mtDNA; 
  <a rid="pone.0012767-Zink1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0012767-Zink1">[57]</a>) may not reflect important genetic differentiation detectable with other markers such as microsatellites.
 </p>
</sec>
