<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We searched the Web of Science on the portal available through the Potsdam Institute for Climate Impact Research (PIK) for articles that investigated current or future effects of various climatic factors on amphibians and reptiles. The initial criteria for article selection can be seen from the search terms listed in the electronic supplementary material, table S1. This initial search gave us a list of 1818 articles. We also included studies (
 <italic class="italic">n</italic> = 123) that we found in the process of contacting authors and reading other articles. After initial screening, we still had to assess 539 articles in more detail. Only 104 of those articles fit our selection criteria and were included in the analysis. The selection criteria were 
 <list list-type="simple" class="list">
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">(1) Articles had to be published between 2005 and April 2015, because we wanted to focus on the most recently published studies. Studies that were conducted before 2005 have already been included in previous reviews [
    <xref rid="RSOS160158C23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>,
    <xref rid="RSOS160158C25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>,
    <xref rid="RSOS160158C26" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>].
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">(2) The study included climatic factors, i.e. any factor that is directly affected by climate change. This includes, for example, temperature, precipitation, number of dry days, water temperature and storms (for a full list of climatic variables, see electronic supplementary material, table S2).</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">(3) The study was based on data collected in the field and conditions were not experimentally altered.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">(4) Data were collected over a period of at least 5 years [
    <xref rid="RSOS160158C27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>,
    <xref rid="RSOS160158C28" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>], including studies whose data (i.e. distributional information) came from museum specimens. We also included studies whose data were collected in disjunctive time intervals that were at least 5 years apart, and studies that modelled future distributions based on current distribution data from atlas data or long-term studies.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">(5) The study analysed observed patterns to determine current or future effects of climate change, including 
    <list list-type="simple" class="list">
     <list-item class="list-item">
      <p class="p">(a) a potential change of a trait (e.g. breeding date, distribution or body size) over time;</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item class="list-item">
      <p class="p">(b) a potential correlation between the temporal change of a species’ trait with changes in some facet of climate (e.g. temperature and rainfall volume);</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item class="list-item">
      <p class="p">(c) a potential change of some facet of climate over the period of the study; and</p>
     </list-item>
     <list-item class="list-item">
      <p class="p">(d) a before–after comparison that documents the impacts of severe weather events.</p>
     </list-item>
    </list>
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">(6) The original studies had to report the statistics needed to run a systematic review (i.e. 
    <italic class="italic">p</italic>-values that are needed to assess whether associations with climate were unlikely to have been observed by chance). See below for explanation for using 
    <italic class="italic">p</italic>-values and not more detailed information such as effect sizes.
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
