<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Here, we examine support for these two hypotheses, and the role of the Rift Valley as a long-term dispersal barrier, by reconstructing patterns of genetic variation in 
 <italic class="italic">Canarina eminii</italic> Asch. &amp; Schweinf, a strictly Afromontane species with a geographic distribution extending from the Ethiopian massifs to the SMSI in the northern end of Lake Malawi
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28" class="xref">28</xref>, along the Rift Valley. This species grows mostly as a twig epiphyte on trees, mainly of genera 
 <italic class="italic">Hagenia</italic> J.F.Gmel., 
 <italic class="italic">Conopharyngia</italic> G. Don, and 
 <italic class="italic">Afrocarpus</italic> (J. Buchholz &amp; E.G. Gray) C.N. Page
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28" class="xref">28</xref>, all characteristic elements of the Afromontane forest belt
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28" class="xref">28</xref>. Little is known about the reproductive biology of 
 <italic class="italic">C. eminii</italic>, except that the species is pollinated by sunbirds (unpublished field observations) and exhibits floral traits that have been associated with this type of ornitophilous pollination
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29" class="xref">29</xref> (e.g., large orange-red coloured flowers producing abundant diluted nectar). Fruits are fleshy, with the seeds enclosed in a sticky sweet jelly, suggesting endozoochorous dispersal (e.g., by monkeys
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30" class="xref">30</xref>). Mairal 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31" class="xref">31</xref> recently reconstructed the biogeographic history of 
 <italic class="italic">Canarina</italic> L., a small genus of three species within tribe Platycodoneae (family Campanulaceae). This genus exhibits a wide disjunct distribution across North Africa and probably originated from a Central Asian ancestor, which arrived to Eastern Africa in the Mid Miocene (13.7 Ma) through the Arabian Plate
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31" class="xref">31</xref>. The lineage leading to the Eastern African species 
 <italic class="italic">C. abyssinica</italic> diverged first, followed by the split between 
 <italic class="italic">C. eminii</italic> and the endemic Canarian species 
 <italic class="italic">C. canariensis</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31" class="xref">31</xref> in the Late Miocene (c. 7 Ma). Divergence within 
 <italic class="italic">C. eminii</italic> was traced back to 1.76 Ma
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31" class="xref">31</xref> (southern range of the Great Rift Valley and followed by subsequent colonisation of the northern range). However, the intraspecific sampling in the study by Mairal 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31" class="xref">31</xref> was limited, which prevented analysis of patterns of genetic variation or examination of the processes population divergence in 
 <italic class="italic">C. eminii</italic>.
</p>
