<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In order to test our hypotheses, we required georeferenced data (natural occurrence) of the plant species endemic to the Caatinga. Since biological collection networks such as SpeciesLink and GBIF provide georeferenced data without the possibility of filtering which points refer to individuals sampled in natural populations or cultivated in non-natural urban and rural areas, and we needed information exclusively from natural areas, we did not use georeferenced data from these databases. Alternatively, to assess precise information on the natural occurrence of plant species endemic to the Caatinga, we, therefore, used the catalogue of vascular plants by Moro 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="pone.0217028.ref054" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>], which compiled this information for more than 2000 species from 98 studies. In addition, we obtained positional data for species from 16 other studies that had not been included in Moro 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="pone.0217028.ref054" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>], because they are either more recent or non-floristic studies, but still contained checklists of Caatinga endemic plant species (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0217028.s001" class="xref">S1 Table</xref>; 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217028.g001" class="xref">Fig 1</xref>). The endemic species listed in these 114 studies had their synonymia and spelling checked based on the Flora do Brasil website [
 <xref rid="pone.0217028.ref057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>]. In total, we obtained georeferenced data (132 points) for 76 out of the 298 plants species endemic to the Caatinga listed on the 
 <italic class="italic">Flora do Brasil</italic> website [
 <xref rid="pone.0217028.ref057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>]. We thus considered these 76 species in this study. The 132 geographic coordinates are distributed across the phytogeographic formations of Caatinga forest. The analyses were based on the occurrence of life history traits. 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0217028.s002" class="xref">S2 Table</xref> summarizes the number of species per georeferenced points and per life history strategy.
</p>
