<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>For the future projections, the same 19 bioclimatic variables were averaged from the outputs of three general circulation models (GCM) commonly used in ecology [
 <xref rid="pone.0217592.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0217592.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. Two Community Earth System Models (CESMs) were chosen as they investigate a diverse set of earth-system interactions: the CESM1 BGC (a coupled carbon–climate model accounting for carbon feedback from the land) and the CESM1 CAM5 (a community atmosphere model) [
 <xref rid="pone.0217592.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Additionally, the Earth System component of the Met Office Hadley Centre HadGEM2 model family was used as the third and final model [
 <xref rid="pone.0217592.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>]. To generate the data, we chose Representative Common Pathway 4.5 (RCP 4.5) scenario from the Coupled Model Intercomparison Project Phase 5 (CMIP5) as the input. It is a stabilization scenario, meaning that it accounts for a stabilization of radiative forcing before 2100, anticipating the development of new technologies and strategies for reducing greenhouse gas emissions [
 <xref rid="pone.0217592.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. By using this optimistic climate change scenario, we represent conservative changes in climate conditions that are likely to occur even if substantial climate change mitigation occurs. For each output, a delta downscaling method developed by the CGIAR Research Program on Climate Change, Agriculture and Food Security (CCAFS) was applied to reach a resolution of 30 arc-seconds [
 <xref rid="pone.0217592.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>], using current conditions Worldclim 1.4 as a reference. Downscaling approach were necessary to assess climate conditions at the cities’ scale even if it induces a risk of pixel mismatch and consequently, a lower level of confidence for local scale analyses [
 <xref rid="pone.0217592.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0217592.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>].
</p>
