<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="discussion" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Migratory phenology</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our study showed variation in the relationship between the abundance of 
   <span class="italic">S. rufus</span> and the sampling date during the second period, while a constant relationship was found for 
   <span class="italic">A. beryllina</span> over all three sampled periods. This result contrasts with those of 
   <a rid="ref-54" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-54">Supp et al. (2015)</a> where long-migration hummingbird species like 
   <span class="italic">S. rufus</span> were found to have migratory periods with lower interannual variation in comparison to hummingbird species with shorter migratory routes. However, variation in climatic conditions can affect the migration times of some bird species (
   <a rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-14">Cotton, 2003</a>; 
   <a rid="ref-25" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-25">Gordo et al., 2005</a>; 
   <a rid="ref-37" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-37">Marra et al., 2005</a>; 
   <a rid="ref-49" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-49">Saino et al., 2007</a>). 
   <a rid="ref-37" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-37">Marra et al. (2005)</a> suggested that variation in spring temperatures influences the migration of long-distance migratory birds; in this study, birds were found to migrate earlier in warm years and later in colder years. The environmental conditions (i.e., precipitation) varied in the second period of our study, yet the change in the migration pattern of 
   <span class="italic">S. rufus</span> may also be the result of variation in local environmental conditions at its breeding sites.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Meanwhile, altitudinal migrant hummingbirds may perform movements of only a few kilometers but can search for resources along an altitudinal gradient. Generally, altitudinal migration is optional in the short term; sedentary species might migrate, for example, to avoid periods of adverse weather (reviewed by 
   <a rid="ref-19" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-19">Faaborg et al., 2010</a>). The altitudinal migrant 
   <span class="italic">A. beryllina</span> examined in our study may migrate depending on local climate conditions and resource quality. Several additional studies establish that seasonal variation of food resources is the main factor that influences the altitudinal migration of birds (
   <a rid="ref-33" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-33">Levey &amp; Stiles, 1992</a>; 
   <a rid="ref-42" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-42">Newton, 2007</a>; 
   <a rid="ref-19" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-19">Faaborg et al., 2010</a>; 
   <a rid="ref-6" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-6">Boyle, 2017</a>). For altitudinal migrant hummingbirds, the availability of food resources as well as competition with other hummingbirds for shared resources is an important factor (
   <a rid="ref-58" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-58">Wolf, Stiles &amp; Hainsworth, 1976</a>; 
   <a rid="ref-17" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-17">Des Ganges, 1979</a>). 
   <a rid="ref-58" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-58">Wolf, Stiles &amp; Hainsworth (1976)</a> stated that dominance interactions and floral availability influence the migration of altitudinal migrant hummingbirds. Meanwhile, 
   <a rid="ref-44" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-44">Rappole &amp; Schuchmann (2003)</a> proposed that hummingbird migrations respond to seasonal scarcity of resources as well as seasonal flushes of resources at other sites. However, more studies are needed to determine the importance of competition for resources and climatic conditions for 
   <span class="italic">A. beryllina</span>’s altitudinal migration.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Furthermore, annual variation in the climatic conditions of winter sites could decouple birds from their usual migratory phenology (
   <a rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-14">Cotton, 2003</a>; 
   <a rid="ref-49" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-49">Saino et al., 2007</a>). If migratory hummingbirds are unable to adjust their migration to specific flowering dates or shortened flowering duration of their preferred plants along their migratory routes, these hummingbirds will be less successful, and their populations will likely be reduced (
   <a rid="ref-19" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-19">Faaborg et al., 2010</a>). Thus, the decoupling of migrants and food resource availability along migratory routes can have direct consequences for the state of migratory populations (
   <a rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-4">Both et al., 2006</a>, 
   <a rid="ref-5" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-5">2009</a>; 
   <a rid="ref-30" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-30">Jones &amp; Cresswell, 2010</a>). For example, 
   <a rid="ref-46" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-46">Reed, Jenouvrier &amp; Visser (2013)</a> found such a mismatch can have strong effects on the relative fitness and egg-laying dates of the migratory bird 
   <span class="italic">Parus major</span> (Great Tits) for several years, although a weak effect was found for mean demographic rates. However, population decline as a result of phenological mismatching cannot be considered as a common process affecting all migratory bird species, as this may depend on multiple factors such as migration distance, continent and habitat seasonality (
   <a rid="ref-5" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-5">Both et al., 2009</a>; 
   <a rid="ref-30" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-30">Jones &amp; Cresswell, 2010</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Flowering synchrony</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our study found a relationship between the number of 
   <span class="italic">S. rufus</span> migratory birds and the number of 
   <span class="italic">S. iodantha</span> flowers. As the migration of 
   <span class="italic">S. rufus</span> is the longest of all migrating hummingbirds in North America (
   <a rid="ref-54" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-54">Supp et al., 2015</a>), the coupling of its migratory route with a diverse assemblage of blooming plant species is expected (
   <a rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-7">Calder, 1987</a>; 
   <a rid="ref-31" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-31">Kodric-Brown &amp; Brown, 1978</a>; 
   <a rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-48">Russell et al., 1994</a>). In this study, the presence of 
   <span class="italic">S. rufus</span> was coupled with the flowering of 
   <span class="italic">S. iodantha</span> in northwestern Mexico; this was also found in another area of western Mexico (Manantlán, Jalisco) where 
   <span class="italic">S. rufus</span> was the most abundant migratory hummingbird in winter and visited 
   <span class="italic">S. iodantha</span> flowers (vs. other flowers) more frequently (
   <a rid="ref-1" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-1">Arizmendi, 2001</a>). This confirms the importance of the flowering phenology of 
   <span class="italic">S. iodantha</span> for the fall migration of 
   <span class="italic">S. rufus</span> along its migratory route in western Mexico. This can be considered equivalent to the role of 
   <span class="italic">Impatiens biflora</span> flowers for the fall migration of the Ruby-Throated Hummingbird (
   <span class="italic">Archilochus colubris</span>); the peak in flowering times of 
   <span class="italic">I. biflora</span> is closely related to the peak migration time of the Ruby-Throated Hummingbird throughout the eastern United States (
   <a rid="ref-3" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-3">Bertin, 1982</a>). However, recent studies found that the correlation in phenology between Ruby-Throated Hummingbirds and 
   <span class="italic">I. biflora</span> is not supported in southern breeding individuals in United States (
   <a rid="ref-60" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-60">Zenzal et al., 2018</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this respect, migratory species’ selection of refueling sites directly influences their survival. In an unknown environment, migratory species have limited time and energy to sample the habitat and experience greater susceptibility to predation and increased competition (
   <a rid="ref-38" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-38">McGrath, van Riper &amp; Fontaine, 2009</a>). In response, 
   <span class="italic">S. rufus</span> has been shown to establish territories that exclude other hummingbird species along its migratory route in the United States to gain priority access to food resources (
   <a rid="ref-23" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-23">Gass, 1979</a>; 
   <a rid="ref-31" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-31">Kodric-Brown &amp; Brown, 1978</a>; 
   <a rid="ref-32" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-32">Kuban &amp; Neill, 1980</a>). However, in Mexico, local hummingbird species have larger body sizes (including 
   <span class="italic">A. beryllina</span>) and dominate smaller latitudinal migratory species, displacing them to floral patches with less rewarding resources (
   <a rid="ref-17" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-17">Des Ganges, 1979</a>; 
   <a rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-9">Calder &amp; Contreras-Martínez, 1995</a>; 
   <a rid="ref-47" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-47">Rodríguez-Flores &amp; Arizmendi, 2016</a>; 
   <a rid="ref-36" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-36">López-Segoviano, Bribiesca &amp; Arizmendi, 2018</a>). For this reason, 
   <span class="italic">S. rufus</span> individuals prefer to feed on floral patches of 
   <span class="italic">S. iodantha</span>; these flowers do not provide maximum energy quality but are available to 
   <span class="italic">S. rufus</span> because more dominant hummingbird species prefer other resources (
   <a rid="ref-36" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-36">López-Segoviano, Bribiesca &amp; Arizmendi, 2018</a>). This synchrony between the latitudinal migration of 
   <span class="italic">S. rufus</span> and flowering phenology may also be present at other sites along the migration route of 
   <span class="italic">S. rufus</span> in Mexico (
   <a rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-9">Calder &amp; Contreras-Martínez, 1995</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Regarding abundances, we found that 
   <span class="italic">A. beryllina</span> abundance was related to the availability of floral resources in general (
   <span class="italic">S. iodantha</span>, 
   <span class="italic">C. thyrsoideum</span> and total number of flowers) in the study area. This confirms that altitudinal migratory hummingbirds primarily respond to variability in the supply of local floral resources (
   <a rid="ref-53" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-53">Stiles, 1985</a>). During periods with less abundant floral resources, hummingbird species respond by performing altitudinal or partial migrations to areas with better supplies of floral resources (
   <a rid="ref-53" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-53">Stiles, 1985</a>). Thus, hummingbird communities change depending on the availability of local floral resources (
   <a rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-21">Feinsinger, 1976</a>; 
   <a rid="ref-2" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-2">Arizmendi &amp; Ornelas, 1990</a>; 
   <a rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-15">Cotton, 2007</a>). This is especially evident in species with short altitudinal migrations, such as 
   <span class="italic">A. beryllina</span>, which can navigate through regions with different vegetation types and climate. However, it is necessary to perform further studies on the additional factors that influence the migration of 
   <span class="italic">A. beryllina</span> such as biotic interactions (e.g., competition among species) and abiotic factors (e.g., climatic conditions).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Finally, we did not find a relationship between the number of 
   <span class="italic">S. rufus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">A. beryllina</span> hummingbirds and different vegetation types. Many temperate forests in Mexico have been clear-cut; some of these areas are now regenerating, resulting in secondary vegetation with abundant plants for hummingbirds to feed on. In some cases, secondary vegetation may even have more available flowers than pristine vegetation (
   <a rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-9">Calder &amp; Contreras-Martínez, 1995</a>; 
   <a rid="ref-47" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-47">Rodríguez-Flores &amp; Arizmendi, 2016</a>). 
   <a rid="ref-47" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-47">Rodríguez-Flores &amp; Arizmendi (2016)</a>, for example, found more 
   <span class="italic">A. beryllina</span> and 
   <span class="italic">S. rufus</span> individuals in secondary vegetation than in pine forest. Likewise, we found 
   <span class="italic">S. iodantha</span> and 
   <span class="italic">C. thyrsoideum</span> flowers in all vegetation types but to a greater extent in clearings with secondary vegetation. Even so, we did not find that vegetation type was important for the abundance of the studied hummingbird species. In another study, 
   <a rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-12">Cohen, Moore &amp; Fischer (2012)</a> translocated and released migrant songbirds in different forested habitat types during their spring migration; these authors found that migrants explore the habitat the morning after release and move further in habitat types characterized by reduced food resources. They also suggested that migrant songbirds may search for areas with sufficient food as opposed to areas with the most abundant food supply (
   <a rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-12">Cohen, Moore &amp; Fischer, 2012</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
