<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">To assess the potential impact of climate change on the transmission of schistosomiasis in the world we developed a biological model using available data from the literature. Compared to 
 <italic class="italic">S. japonicum</italic>, both 
 <italic class="italic">S. mansoni</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">S. haematobium</italic> required less total heat energy to complete one generation [
 <xref rid="B17-tropicalmed-03-00117" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-tropicalmed-03-00117" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-tropicalmed-03-00117" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>]. Therefore, the transmission intensity of the two latter species is generally somewhat stronger than that of 
 <italic class="italic">S. japonicum</italic>. However, the three different intermediate snail hosts had different temperature thresholds for survival that came into play in certain geographical areas. For example, the distribution of the 
 <italic class="italic">Oncomelania</italic> snail, utilized by 
 <italic class="italic">S. japonicum</italic>, was constrained by the temperature in January (when below 0 °C), which effectively limited its progress northwards, while 
 <italic class="italic">Biomphalaria</italic> (
 <italic class="italic">S. mansoni</italic>) and 
 <italic class="italic">Bulinus</italic> (
 <italic class="italic">S. haematobium</italic>) had thermal requirements that included an annual 
 <inline-formula class="inline-formula">
  <math id="mm21" class="math">
   <mrow class="mrow">
    <mrow class="mrow">
     <msub class="msub">
      <mi class="mi">T</mi>
      <mrow class="mrow">
       <mi class="mi">max</mi>
      </mrow>
     </msub>
    </mrow>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> of 15.5–31 °C and 20–33 °C respectively [
 <xref rid="B27-tropicalmed-03-00117" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>], which is one of the factors (so far) keeping these snails from entering Europe and other northern territories. Interestingly, 
 <italic class="italic">S. haematobium</italic> appears to have a better chance of a foothold in Europe than 
 <italic class="italic">S. mansoni</italic>, at least in the middle part of the century (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="tropicalmed-03-00117-f003" class="xref">Figure 3</xref>).
</p>
