<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Distribution of Ocean Heat Storage and Transport</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When averaged over the World Ocean, changes in ocean processes have no effect on global OHC (via conservation of heat). Here, we find that changes in ocean transport since 1871 have a negligible effect on the basin integrated Atlantic OHC as well. However, this is not the case when considering latitudinal patterns of heat storage. Any differences in the spatial pattern of heat storage between the GF reconstruction and observational products indicate a change in ocean processes leading to heat convergence or divergence (i.e., that the GF assumption of constant transport processes is not accurate). For example, we expect that changes in temperature will alter buoyancy gradients and therefore, the large-scale ocean circulation.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To probe the role of ocean circulation changes in shaping patterns of heat storage in the Atlantic, we examine the linear trends in all observational datasets and in the GF estimates from 1955 as a function of latitude for different depth ranges (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3</a>). The passive OHCs from GF estimates (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3 
   <span class="italic">A</span> and 
   <span class="italic">B</span>
  </a>, orange curve) and direct observations (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3 
   <span class="italic">A</span> and 
   <span class="italic">B</span>
  </a>, black) have similar latitudinal profiles in the Southern Ocean between 80° S and 20° S, with a peak of 0.18 ZJ per degree latitude per decade around 40° S in the upper 2,000 m. North of 20° S, the signature of a changing ocean circulation is more prominent.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Between 20° S and 50° N, the trends in passive OHC are consistently weaker than in direct estimates over the upper 2,000 m, with difference ranging from 0.05 ZJ per degree latitude per decade at 20° S to 0.1 ZJ per degree latitude per decade at 30° N (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3
   <span class="italic">B</span>
  </a>). Changes are also apparent north of 50° N, but these are not statistically significant due to the large uncertainty in the observational products and the presence of strong variability, especially in the upper 700 m (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1808838115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S3
  </span>). However, the peak OHC change in the upper 2,000 m of the North Atlantic based on GF estimates occurs in midlatitudes, with a maxima of 0.1 ZJ per degree latitude per decade around 45° N to 60° N (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3
   <span class="italic">B</span>
  </a>, orange curve) compared with 0.3 ZJ per degree latitude per decade around 30° N to 40° N in observations (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3
   <span class="italic">B</span>
  </a>, black). Most of the signature of ocean circulation changes is found at intermediate depths between 700 and 2,000 m (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3
   <span class="italic">C</span>
  </a>), which have higher signal to noise ratios than surface properties. The observed trends are of opposite signs to those of the GF-based estimates poleward of 20° N. Below 2,000 m, in the North Atlantic, passive heat storage is negative and decreases at a rate of 0.08 ZJ per degree latitude per decade north of 20° N. This result is consistent with ref. 
  <a rid="r38" ref-type="bibr" href="#r38">38</a> over the 1988–2007 period but not with observed warming during 1957–1987. South of 40° S, there is a trend in deep heat storage of 0.09 ZJ per degree latitude per decade since 1955 (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3</a>). Our analysis suggests that changes in ocean processes may have accelerated the warming rate in the top 2,000 m in low latitudes and midlatitudes of the Atlantic basin by shifting meridionally the pattern of ocean warming.
 </p>
</sec>
