<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Implications and Discussion</div>
 <p content-type="flushleft" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on the comparison between the GF and direct estimates, we can assess how changes in ocean transport have influenced patterns of ocean heat storage. Our results suggest that, if the heat storage was entirely determined by the climatological transports, its magnitude over the last 40 y would be less pronounced in low latitudes and more pronounced north of the Gulf Stream than observed, despite the large uncertainty in all estimates in these regions. We attribute 1.3 ZJ per degree latitude per decade of the heat storage between 20° N and 50° N in the North Atlantic to redistribution by changes in ocean transport. We infer that, during 1955–2017, one-third to one-half of the warming in the Atlantic basin between 20° S and 50° N was due to heat convergence from ocean circulation changes.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The changes in ocean transport inferred here also affect regional thermosteric sea-level change. During 1971–2017, changes in transport contributed to one-half of the observed 1.8-cm sea-level rise at 30° N to 40° N in the Atlantic (due to 0.3 ZJ per degree latitude per decade of heat convergence from ocean circulation changes) but led to a reduction poleward of 50° N (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">Fig. 3
   <span class="italic">F</span>
  </a>). Changes in ocean transport are responsible for up to 1 cm of thermosteric sea-level change in the North Atlantic (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">Fig. 3 
   <span class="italic">E</span> and 
   <span class="italic">F</span>
  </a>). This result is consistent with the magnitude of changes inferred from other observational studies (
  <a rid="r39" ref-type="bibr" href="#r39">39</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Several hypotheses, which are not mutually exclusive, could account for such OHC patterns arising from circulation changes. Changes in midlatitudes wind forcing (
  <a rid="r40" ref-type="bibr" href="#r40">40</a>, 
  <a rid="r41" ref-type="bibr" href="#r41">41</a>) can excite an upper ocean adjustment with a signature in both gyres, modifying the horizontal exchange of heat between the subtropical and subpolar regions. This signature can potentially be amplified by deep climatological mixed layers at high latitudes. The inferred latitudinal changes in heat storage could also be induced by changes in the upper branch of the meridional overturning circulation (MOC)—including both horizontal and vertical transport—driven by wind and buoyancy forcing and mixing (
  <a rid="r9" ref-type="bibr" href="#r9">9</a>). This hypothesis is consistent with a reduction in North Atlantic deep water formation and slowing of the MOC, leading to an increase in OHC at low latitudes (
  <a rid="r42" ref-type="bibr" href="#r42">42</a>
  <a href="#r43">*</a>–
  <a rid="r44" ref-type="bibr" href="#r44">44</a>). Lastly, different forcings at the surface or inflows of water from other basins below 2,000 m at low and high latitudes can act together to change heat storage in these regions independently from one another.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results highlight that the substantial amounts of heat accumulated in the ocean and associated sea-level rise can be influenced by ocean circulation changes and low- to midlatitude air–sea interactions. Changes in wind and air–sea fluxes, including those due to cloud feedbacks, may play an increasing role under anthropogenic climate change as suggested by the shape of passive OHC trends in the Atlantic during 1871–1955 versus 1955–2017 (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3</a> and 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1808838115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S4
  </span>). Future changes in ocean transport could have severe consequences for regional sea-level rise and the risk of coastal flooding. Monitoring and understanding OHC change and the role of circulation in shaping the patterns of warming remain key to predicting global and regional climate change and sea-level rise.
 </p>
</sec>
