<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s6" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Observation-Based Datasets.</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We use the ECCO-GODAE (ECCO version 2) solution (
  <a rid="r12" ref-type="bibr" href="#r12">12</a>) to derive the time–mean transport matrix and GFs (
  <span class="italic">GF Reconstruction: OHC and Thermosteric Sea Level</span>). The ECCO-GODAE solution combines a state-of-the-art ocean general circulation model, the MITgcm (
  <a rid="r45" ref-type="bibr" href="#r45">45</a>), at a 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="i60" class="math">
    <span mathvariant="normal" class="mn">1</span>
    <span class="mo">°</span>
   </div>
  </div> horizontal resolution and an adjoint-based assimilation with all available global ocean datasets over the period ranging from 1992 to 2004. The domain extends from 80 °S to 80 °N. To compare our GF-based OHC estimates with direct observations, we use the following data products. From the National Centers for Environmental Information (NCEI), we use the global analyzed gridded fields of OHC from 1955 to 2017. We use yearly averaged fields for the depth range 0–700 m and pentadal averages for 0–2,000 m (
  <a rid="r2" ref-type="bibr" href="#r2">2</a>, 
  <a rid="r46" ref-type="bibr" href="#r46">46</a>). From the Institute of Atmospheric Physics (IAP) and the objective analysis of Ishii et al. (
  <a rid="r20" ref-type="bibr" href="#r20">20</a>), we use the yearly average ocean temperatures from the 41 vertical levels down to 2,000 m between 1940 and 2016 (
  <a rid="r1" ref-type="bibr" href="#r1">1</a>) and between 1955 and 2017, respectively. All datasets are gridded products with 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="i61" class="math">
    <span mathvariant="normal" class="mn">1</span>
    <span class="mo">°</span>
   </div>
  </div> latitude–longitude horizontal resolution. For the upper 700 m, we also used the global updated OHC estimates from Domingues et al. (
  <a rid="r21" ref-type="bibr" href="#r21">21</a>, 
  <a rid="r22" ref-type="bibr" href="#r22">22</a>). The SST datasets used as surface boundary conditions (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1808838115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S1
  </span>) are from The Met Office Hadley Center’s Sea Ice and Sea Surface Temperature Dataset HadISST, which combines fields of SST on a 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="i62" class="math">
    <span mathvariant="normal" class="mn">1</span>
    <span class="mo">°</span>
   </div>
  </div> latitude–longitude grid from 1871 to 2017. We use both HadISST v1 (
  <a rid="r13" ref-type="bibr" href="#r13">13</a>) and v2.0 (
  <a rid="r47" ref-type="bibr" href="#r47">47</a>); the latter offers a 10-member ensemble, which is used as part of the uncertainty quantification of our OHC estimates.
 </p>
</sec>
