<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Permafrost changes during the 21st century</div>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figure 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a> shows the present (1986–2005) permafrost extent estimated from the reanalysis data and the MME of the 17 CMIP5 models. Both estimations are in good agreement with the International Permafrost Association (IPA) data in most regions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>
  </span>. Discrepancies between simulated and observed permafrost distributions are mainly located in northern Europe, southern west Siberia and the southern permafrost boundary in North America. The two datasets underestimate the permafrost area in western Siberia and the northern margin of Europe but overestimate the permafrost area on the southern Qinghai–Tibet Plateau and in northern Mongolia. Comparing the permafrost extent estimated by the two datasets, the estimations based on the MME showed a better performance in the northern islands of North America than the estimations based on the reanalysis data. However, the estimations based on the MME underestimate the permafrost in southern North America, which may be related to the difference in permafrost extent between the two datasets. The permafrost areas in the NH estimated from the reanalysis datasets and climate model data are about 15.61 × 10
  <span class="sup">6</span> and 16.24 × 10
  <span class="sup">6</span> km
  <span class="sup">2</span>, respectively. The latter is closer to IPA’s estimate of 16.2 × 10
  <span class="sup">6</span> km
  <span class="sup">2</span>. However, because the 16.2 × 10
  <span class="sup">6</span> km
  <span class="sup">2</span> figure excludes isolated and sporadic permafrost, the actual permafrost area in the NH is likely to be greater than 16.2 × 10
  <span class="sup">6</span> km
  <span class="sup">2</span>.
  <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>The permafrost extent in Northern Hemisphere during the period of 1986–2005 estimated by Kudryavtsev method (
     <span class="bold">a</span>) reanalysis datasets (
     <span class="bold">b</span>) CMIP5 models. (Gray region represent the observed permafrost extent from Brown 
     <span class="italic">et al</span>.
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>
     </span>; Orange region represent the region where permafrost is overestimated by CLM4.5) (The NCAR Command Language (Version 6.3.0) [Software]. (2016). Boulder, Colorado: UCAR/NCAR/CISL/TDD. http://dx.doi.org/10.5065/D6WD3XH5).
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_39942_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e1053" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figure 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a> shows the active layer thickness (ALT) in NH permafrost regions during the 1986–2005 period, estimated from CMIP5 data. Results indicate that the ALT deepens from high latitude to low latitude and that deeper ALTs (e.g. &gt;225 cm) are mainly located in the Mongolian Plateau and Greater Khingan. Considering the calculation of mean bias, correlation coefficient and regression coefficient under different ALT estimation methods, the Kudryavtsev method could well reflect the correlation between simulation and observation. The correlation coefficient and regression coefficient, both statistically significant at the 
  <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.001 level, are 0.53 and 0.17, respectively. The mean bias in the Kudryavtsev method is relatively small (23.55 cm), implying the high performance of the Kudryavtsev method for permafrost simulation.
  <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>The distribution of ALT (unit: cm) in permafrost region over NH during 1986–2005 simulated by Kudryavtsev method. The black dot represents the 52 observations from GTN-P. ‘R’ is correlation coefficient; ‘a’ is regression coefficient and ‘MB’ represents mean bias between simulation and observation. (The NCAR Command Language (Version 6.3.0) [Software]. (2016). Boulder, Colorado: UCAR/NCAR/CISL/TDD. http://dx.doi.org/10.5065/D6WD3XH5).</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_39942_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e1070" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The response of the components of the cryosphere to global warming is a slow process with gradients
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>
  </span> and hysteresis. We define the initial year of five consecutive years when global mean surface temperature meets thresholds of 1.5 °C and 2.0 °C, then the subsequent 10 years are regarded as the period that meets the thresholds of 1.5 °C and 2.0 °C. Figure 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a> shows the projected change in permafrost extent under the three RCP scenarios for temperature rises of 1.5 °C and 2.0 °C compared to pre-industrial levels. The southern permafrost boundary shifts northwards by 1° to 4° latitude under the three RCPs between the 1.5 °C and 2 °C levels. Compared with the historical period (1986–2005), significant degradation occurs in northern Mongolia and southern Russia. When the global mean surface temperature reaches the 1.5 °C threshold, the MME (Table 
  <a rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" href="#Tab2">2</a>) shows that the permafrost extent in the NH would be 12.81 ± 3.31 × 10
  <span class="sup">6</span>, 12.33 ± 4.46 × 10
  <span class="sup">6</span> and 12.09 ± 3.31 × 10
  <span class="sup">6</span> km
  <span class="sup">2</span>, respectively, under RCP2.6 (2027–2036), RCP4.5 (2026–2035) and RCP8.5 (2023–2032). Relative to the historical period, these represent reductions in permafrost extent of 23.58%, 24.10% and 25.55%, respectively. However, uncertainty is evident because of the large discrepancies among the models’ performance on temperature simulation over cold regions. When the global mean surface temperature reaches the 2 °C threshold, permafrost areas in the NH would be 10.38 × 10
  <span class="sup">6</span> and 10.13 × 10
  <span class="sup">6</span> km
  <span class="sup">2</span>, respectively, in RCP4.5 (2046–2055) and RCP8.5 (2037–2046). These would, respectively, constitute reductions relative to the historical period of 36.08% and 37.62%, respectively, for RCP4.5 and RCP8.5. Compared to the historical period, the most obvious degradation occurs in northern Mongolia and southern Russia, and the southern permafrost boundary moves northwards by about 3° to 4° between the 1.5 °C and 2 °C thresholds under RCP4.5. It must be noted that the global mean surface temperature under RCP2.6 does not rise by 2 °C until the end of the 21
  <span class="sup">st</span> century. The extent of the permafrost in the NH in 2100 is about 12.65 × 10
  <span class="sup">6</span> km
  <span class="sup">2</span>, a reduction of 22.11% relative to the historical period. This reduction shows the southern permafrost boundary in Canada and the United States to move northwards and the area of the permafrost in northern Mongolia to decrease slightly. The projected reductions in permafrost area under the three RCPs vary between 23% and 26% at the 1.5 °C threshold and range from 36% to 38% at the 2.0 °C threshold. Relative to the 1.5 °C threshold, the permafrost area at the 2 °C threshold would be reduced by 1.95 × 10
  <span class="sup">6</span> km
  <span class="sup">2</span> (i.e. 15.8%) and 1.96 × 10
  <span class="sup">6</span> km
  <span class="sup">2</span> (i.e. 16.2%), respectively, under RCP4.5 and RCP8.5.
  <div id="Fig4" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>The extent of permafrost in Northern Hemisphere when global average surface temperature rises to 1.5 and 2 °C above pre-industrial (1861–1880) under RCPs. (The orange and blue shaded regions represent the permafrost extent in 1986–2005 and the period corresponding to the certain threshold, respectively). (The NCAR Command Language (Version 6.3.0) [Software]. (2016). Boulder, Colorado: UCAR/NCAR/CISL/TDD. http://dx.doi.org/10.5065/D6WD3XH5).</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_39942_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e1139" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <div id="Tab2" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>The permafrost area, absolute change (AC) and relative change (RC) in Northern Hemisphere under global warming.</p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th rowspan="2">Region</th>
      <th rowspan="2">Type</th>
      <th colspan="3">1.5 °C</th>
      <th colspan="3">2 °C</th>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <th>RCP2.6</th>
      <th>RCP4.5</th>
      <th>RCP8.5</th>
      <th>RCP2.6</th>
      <th>RCP4.5</th>
      <th>RCP8.5</th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td rowspan="3">Northern Hemisphere (16.24)</td>
      <td>Area (×10
       <span class="sup">6</span> km
       <span class="sup">2</span>)
      </td>
      <td>12.81 ± 3.2</td>
      <td>12.33 ± 3.2</td>
      <td>12.09 ± 2.9</td>
      <td>12.65</td>
      <td>10.38</td>
      <td>10.13</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>AC (×10
       <span class="sup">6</span> km
       <span class="sup">2</span>)
      </td>
      <td>3.43 ± 3.2</td>
      <td>3.91 ± 3.2</td>
      <td>4.15 ± 2.9</td>
      <td>3.59</td>
      <td>5.86</td>
      <td>6.11</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>RC (%)</td>
      <td>21.12 ± 17.8</td>
      <td>24.1 ± 17.6</td>
      <td>25.55 ± 15.9</td>
      <td>22.11</td>
      <td>36.08</td>
      <td>37.62</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
   <div class="table-wrap-foot">
    <p>Note: In RCP2.6, the global average surface temperature will not reach the 2 °C. 12.64 is the permafrost area in Northern Hemisphere in 2100. The value in bracket represents the decreased permafrost area relative to 1986–2005.</p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
