<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par7">As we all know, WPSH is a multi-dimensional climate system, its temporal and spatial circulation characteristics are more complex, so it is often simplified by one dimension monitoring index to analyze its effect on ozone. Five operational indices of WPSH based on the 5880 geopotential height (gpm) at 500 hPa, including the area, intensity, ridge lines, northern extension, and western boundaries are announced monthly by the National Climate Center (NCC) in China to describe the WPSH’s evolution
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>
 </sup>. But the correlations between ozone concentrations in Shanghai and indices on a monthly scale is very poor, Consequently, it is necessary to develop a new objective index, which is not only with clear physical meanings to objectively describe the location and intensity of the WPSH, but also has significant associations with surface ozone in Shanghai. Figure 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> shows the distribution of correlation coefficients between monthly mean MAD8 O
 <sub>3</sub> in Shanghai and the 500 hPa geopotential height over Eastern Asia during late-summer from 2013 to 2017. To obtain correlation analysis data as more as possible, monthly mean data are used rather than late-summer mean data. Correlations between ozone concentrations and 500 hPa geopotential height are positive in most parts of Eastern Asia. The significant positive correlation coefficients with 500 hPa geopotential height (exceeding the 95% confidence level based on student-t test) are located over eastern ocean of China. The significant correlation coefficients related to the geopotential height averaged over the key area region (122.5°E-135°E, 27.5°N-35°N) at 500 hPa shows a maximum positive correlation coefficient (0.78). Thus, we define geopotential height averaged over the key area region at 500 hPa as the new definition index of WPSH’s effect on ozone (called WPSH_SHO
 <sub>3</sub>). It not only represents the activity center and intensity of the WPSH over the key area region, but also it has high positive correlation with the surface ozone concentration in Shanghai.
</p>
