<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The majority (97.5%) of diet plants in this study were C
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> food plants, followed by C
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> (1.25%) and CAM (1.25%) plants. Previous research has shown that expansion of C
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> plants with low nutrient availability might have led to the extinction and contraction of distributional range of herbivorous mammals which were dependent on C
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> plants during late Miocene (Cerling, Ehleringer, &amp; Harris, 
 <xref rid="mec14842-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1998</xref>; Ehleringer, Cerling, &amp; Dearing, 
 <xref rid="mec14842-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2002</xref>; Ge et al., 
 <xref rid="mec14842-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>; MacFadden &amp; Ceding, 
 <xref rid="mec14842-bib-0071" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1994</xref>; Osborne, 
 <xref rid="mec14842-bib-0083" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>; Osborne &amp; Beerling, 
 <xref rid="mec14842-bib-0084" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>). The prehistoric distribution of pikas was closely associated with distribution of their preferred C
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> food plants, such as those with high protein and moisture content (Ge et al., 
 <xref rid="mec14842-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). Climate change has also been found to alter the distribution and abundance of alpine plants based on their temperature sensitivity (Scherrer &amp; Körner, 
 <xref rid="mec14842-bib-0095" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>). Replacement of C
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> plants by C
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> plants across large landscapes during the late Miocene resulted in the extinction of a high number of pika species (Ge et al., 
 <xref rid="mec14842-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). Gottfried et al. (
 <xref rid="mec14842-bib-0044" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>) suggested that the thermophylization process could lead to the replacement of cold and moist environment plant species (e.g., C
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> plants) with an abundance of warm and dry environment plant species, (e.g., C
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> and CAM plants). Given that the Royle's pika diet consists of C
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> plant species (e.g., 
 <italic class="italic">Potentila</italic>,
 <italic class="italic"> Anaphalis</italic>), the increase in temperature and rainfall patterns is bound to influence the distribution range of plant species as well as pikas. In the past 25 years (1982–2006), the Himalayan arc has experienced significant decreases in winter precipitation (17 mm), which has resulted in an increase in mean annual (0.04–0.08°C per year), spring (0.02–0.08°C per year) and winter temperatures (0.03–0.04°C per year; Shrestha, Gautam, &amp; Bawa, 
 <xref rid="mec14842-bib-0100" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). This continued increase in temperature could have a significant effect on the distribution dynamics of C
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> species and potentially influence plant–herbivore interactions at a microhabitat level.
</p>
