<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1.3. Feed Additives</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Feed additives can be used to inhibit CH
  <sub>4</sub> production in a variety of species. However, some dietary additives that are being tested have potential animal health concerns. For example, 
  <span class="italic">in vitro</span> studies have shown that fumarate can work as an alternative to CH
  <sub>4</sub> as a sink for H
  <sub>2</sub> in the rumen, but feeding fumarate in its free acid form can lower rumen pH and inhibit fiber digestion, while feeding it in salt form can induce toxicity. Effective doses may well exceed current dietary recommendations [
  <a rid="B40-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40-animals-05-00361">40</a>]. Especially in low protein diets, nitrates are also potential CH
  <sub>4</sub> mitigation agents. However, the intermediate product from nitrate metabolism, nitrite, is toxic, and so feeding it requires a gradual acclimation to a high dietary intake in order to avoid nitrite toxicity [
  <a rid="B10-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10-animals-05-00361">10</a>,
  <a rid="B41-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41-animals-05-00361">41</a>]. Another proposed supplement, sulfate, has been linked to sulphur-induced polioencephalomalacia, a condition in US feedlot cattle associated with excessive production of H
  <sub>2</sub>S in the rumen from diets high in distillers grains—co-products from the ethanol industry, which are high in sulfate [
  <a rid="B10-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10-animals-05-00361">10</a>,
  <a rid="B42-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42-animals-05-00361">42</a>]. The FAO cautions that more research is needed [
  <a rid="B10-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10-animals-05-00361">10</a>]. Mitigation strategies should steer clear of feeding substances that might endanger the animals, either outright or in the absence of highly skilled management.
 </p>
</sec>
