<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1.1. Grain Finishing Feedlot Cattle</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One strategy for mitigating methane emissions with feed changes is by including more concentrates in addition to, or in place of, a proportion of dietary forage. Although emissions per animal may rise as productivity improves, there is generally a reduction in the greenhouse gases released on a per kg-product produced basis [
  <a rid="B10-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10-animals-05-00361">10</a>,
  <a rid="B13-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13-animals-05-00361">13</a>]. In intensive production systems, grain feeding of livestock often entails removing cattle raised for beef from pastures to provide the finishing ration in a feedlot. This is a common system in the United States and is being emulated in other parts of the world, such as Latin America. In Brazil, the practice of finishing cattle in feedlots increased 50% (from two to three million animals) from 2003 to 2010 [
  <a rid="B14-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14-animals-05-00361">14</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The digestive system of cattle is best adapted to roughage provided by grass-based diets [
  <a rid="B15-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-animals-05-00361">15</a>], and the natural behavior of cattle is to graze throughout the day. However, the typical routine in feedlots is to gradually reduce the proportion of forage in the ration over time, eventually reaching diets that can be as high as 90% grain [
  <a rid="B16-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16-animals-05-00361">16</a>]. In enlarging Brazilian feedlots, the expected trend is a decrease in the amount of roughage in feedlot diets, with an already observed reduction from 29% in 2009 to 21% in 2011 [
  <a rid="B17-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17-animals-05-00361">17</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In cattle feeding systems with high ratios of concentrate to forages, digestive problems are common. The starches in this concentrated diet are quickly digested and fermentation acids can build up disrupting the normal function of the rumen [
  <a rid="B16-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16-animals-05-00361">16</a>]. Abnormal rumen function and digestive disorders can lead to acidosis, bloat, and if persistent, liver abscesses, and even the foot disorder laminitis [
  <a rid="B15-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-animals-05-00361">15</a>,
  <a rid="B18-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-animals-05-00361">18</a>,
  <a rid="B19-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-animals-05-00361">19</a>]. Maintaining normal rumen function on these diets is a constant challenge for the feedlot industry; one quarter of cattle mortality in feedlots can be attributed to digestive disorders [
  <a rid="B20-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-animals-05-00361">20</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For both acidosis and bloat, increasing the amount of forage in the diet can stimulate chewing and promote saliva production, which have a buffering effect, and thus reduce the likelihood of a sinking pH level and destabilization of the microbial population in the rumen [
  <a rid="B16-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16-animals-05-00361">16</a>,
  <a rid="B21-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21-animals-05-00361">21</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Finishing calves in a feedlot usually involves transporting them from their natal pastures. In the United States, nearly two-thirds (63%) of cattle and calves raised for beef are sold through an auction barn after leaving the farm [
  <a rid="B22-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-animals-05-00361">22</a>], thus, many calves are moved twice before arrival at a feedlot.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Transport takes a physical and psychological toll on animals. Stressors include unfamiliar surroundings, novelty, noise, vibration, social regrouping, loading and unloading, and feed and water deprivation [
  <a rid="B23-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-animals-05-00361">23</a>,
  <a rid="B24-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-animals-05-00361">24</a>,
  <a rid="B25-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25-animals-05-00361">25</a>], although many factors, such as preconditioning [
  <a rid="B26-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26-animals-05-00361">26</a>] and location in the vehicle during the journey [
  <a rid="B27-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27-animals-05-00361">27</a>] can alter the effect. The stress of transport can lead to immunosuppression and an increase in disease susceptibility, including the ubiquitous Bovine Respiratory Disease (RBD) problem [
  <a rid="B25-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25-animals-05-00361">25</a>,
  <a rid="B28-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-animals-05-00361">28</a>,
  <a rid="B29-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29-animals-05-00361">29</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
