<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.4. Reduced Animal Numbers</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The demand for meat and dairy products is rapidly growing. This demand is attributable to the growing world population, urbanization and increasing affluence in emerging economies [
  <a rid="B200-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B200-animals-05-00361">200</a>]. The projected global growth in annual consumption of meat and milk is 5.41% and 3.43%, respectively. In Asia this growth is projected to be even greater, at 7.99% and 11.85% [
  <a rid="B201-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B201-animals-05-00361">201</a>]. Meat consumption is expected to continue to grow in developing countries until they meet the levels of developed countries, with poultry accounting for around 50% of the increase [
  <a rid="B202-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B202-animals-05-00361">202</a>]. If this demand is met, the growing number of animals will substantially increase the problem of climate change [
  <a rid="B203-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B203-animals-05-00361">203</a>], even if production efficiencies per unit of product produced are realized.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The growing demand for animal-based protein is usually presented as inevitable. While the general trajectory seems certain, the call to fill this demand in every case is not necessarily prudent. Reducing animal numbers could come, in part, with changes in production efficiency, as mentioned previously [
  <a rid="B2-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-animals-05-00361">2</a>]. However, these production-side efficiency approaches seem, in some ways, to avoid the heart of the problem.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Feeding animals grain to produce animal-based food is inherently inefficient. For every kg of chicken live weight gain, 1.7 kg is required in feed, and chicken is the most highly feed efficient species; the ratio of feed to gain for pigs is 2.4 to 1 and for cattle it is as high as 10 to 1 [
  <a rid="B204-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B204-animals-05-00361">204</a>]. The production of feed for animals can have a larger environmental impact in terms of energy use and global warming, than the management of those same animals and their manure on the farm [
  <a rid="B205-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B205-animals-05-00361">205</a>,
  <a rid="B206-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B206-animals-05-00361">206</a>]. Using IPCC figures, Garnett (2011) estimates that the reductions achievable for agriculture mitigation options amount to only about 30% of the total impact [
  <a rid="B207-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B207-animals-05-00361">207</a>]; following this she argues: “[h]ence the conclusion that we need also to moderate our consumption of livestock products seems inescapable.”
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One approach to this is to address the immense amount of food that is wasted. This category is broad, including waste at harvest, storage, processing, and a number of post-consumer pathways [
  <a rid="B208-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B208-animals-05-00361">208</a>]. The inefficiencies above suggest that waste of animal-based foods carries a particularly high environmental cost. The FAO has estimated global food waste at about 1/3, with waste of meat products of about 20% [
  <a rid="B209-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B209-animals-05-00361">209</a>]. Smith 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span> (2013) found savings of about 6% in food crop area, and 13%–47% GHG savings in 2050 through waste reduction compared to the reference case [
  <a rid="B210-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B210-animals-05-00361">210</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another approach focuses specifically on consumption, particularly in developed countries and in populations that face chronic disease due to overconsumption. Many studies show that reducing consumption of animal products would have a substantial effect on reducing GHG emissions, and the IPCC recognized this potential in their Fifth Assessment Report [
  <a rid="B4-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4-animals-05-00361">4</a>]. Smith 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span> (2013) found greater mitigation potential in the Agriculture, Forestry, and Other Land Use (AFOLU) sector on the consumption rather than production side, when incorporating associated benefits in spared land use (e.g., afforestation and bioenergy) [
  <a rid="B210-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B210-animals-05-00361">210</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While variables such as energy used in transport, processing and refrigeration do not permit blanket statements about animal products over alternatives, meat, seafood, and some dairy products tend to have large GHG emissions per kg of product at the checkout as compared to most plant-based foods [
  <a rid="B211-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B211-animals-05-00361">211</a>]. Some analyses show that vegetarian and vegan diets have potential GHG savings of 22% and 29% in the UK and US, respectively [
  <a rid="B212-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B212-animals-05-00361">212</a>,
  <a rid="B213-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B213-animals-05-00361">213</a>]. However, a 2014 study conducted in the UK found that dietary GHG emissions for meat-eaters were approximately twice as high as those of vegans [
  <a rid="B214-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B214-animals-05-00361">214</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Vegan and vegetarian diets also have lower environmental impact including less land use [
  <a rid="B215-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B215-animals-05-00361">215</a>], water [
  <a rid="B216-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B216-animals-05-00361">216</a>], and fossil fuel requirements [
  <a rid="B217-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B217-animals-05-00361">217</a>]. Reducing climate change mitigation costs [
  <a rid="B215-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B215-animals-05-00361">215</a>], as well as potential to improve public health [
  <a rid="B218-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B218-animals-05-00361">218</a>], have also been cited as a co-beneficial effects.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Substantial effects could be realized even by simply reducing meat consumption, such as through efforts like the Meatless Monday campaign [
  <a rid="B219-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B219-animals-05-00361">219</a>], or partial substitution of plant protein in ground and processed meats [
  <a rid="B200-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B200-animals-05-00361">200</a>]. Another potential future alternative is cultured meat production. Cultured meat is laboratory produced using 
  <span class="italic">in vitro</span> tissue engineering techniques, and initial LCA estimates show that it could lead to 78%–96% lower GHG emissions than conventionally produced European meat [
  <a rid="B220-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B220-animals-05-00361">220</a>], while simultaneously avoiding all of the animal welfare impacts of intensive production.
 </p>
</sec>
