<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1. Feed Changes</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Given that feed production accounts for about 47% of livestock emissions [
  <a rid="B2-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-animals-05-00361">2</a>] (p. 18), it is a key target for mitigation. However, there are a number of welfare concerns with some of the current proposals to reduce emissions using feed alterations.
 </p>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1.1. Grain Finishing Feedlot Cattle</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One strategy for mitigating methane emissions with feed changes is by including more concentrates in addition to, or in place of, a proportion of dietary forage. Although emissions per animal may rise as productivity improves, there is generally a reduction in the greenhouse gases released on a per kg-product produced basis [
   <a rid="B10-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10-animals-05-00361">10</a>,
   <a rid="B13-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13-animals-05-00361">13</a>]. In intensive production systems, grain feeding of livestock often entails removing cattle raised for beef from pastures to provide the finishing ration in a feedlot. This is a common system in the United States and is being emulated in other parts of the world, such as Latin America. In Brazil, the practice of finishing cattle in feedlots increased 50% (from two to three million animals) from 2003 to 2010 [
   <a rid="B14-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14-animals-05-00361">14</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The digestive system of cattle is best adapted to roughage provided by grass-based diets [
   <a rid="B15-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-animals-05-00361">15</a>], and the natural behavior of cattle is to graze throughout the day. However, the typical routine in feedlots is to gradually reduce the proportion of forage in the ration over time, eventually reaching diets that can be as high as 90% grain [
   <a rid="B16-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16-animals-05-00361">16</a>]. In enlarging Brazilian feedlots, the expected trend is a decrease in the amount of roughage in feedlot diets, with an already observed reduction from 29% in 2009 to 21% in 2011 [
   <a rid="B17-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B17-animals-05-00361">17</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In cattle feeding systems with high ratios of concentrate to forages, digestive problems are common. The starches in this concentrated diet are quickly digested and fermentation acids can build up disrupting the normal function of the rumen [
   <a rid="B16-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16-animals-05-00361">16</a>]. Abnormal rumen function and digestive disorders can lead to acidosis, bloat, and if persistent, liver abscesses, and even the foot disorder laminitis [
   <a rid="B15-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15-animals-05-00361">15</a>,
   <a rid="B18-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B18-animals-05-00361">18</a>,
   <a rid="B19-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19-animals-05-00361">19</a>]. Maintaining normal rumen function on these diets is a constant challenge for the feedlot industry; one quarter of cattle mortality in feedlots can be attributed to digestive disorders [
   <a rid="B20-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20-animals-05-00361">20</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For both acidosis and bloat, increasing the amount of forage in the diet can stimulate chewing and promote saliva production, which have a buffering effect, and thus reduce the likelihood of a sinking pH level and destabilization of the microbial population in the rumen [
   <a rid="B16-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16-animals-05-00361">16</a>,
   <a rid="B21-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21-animals-05-00361">21</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Finishing calves in a feedlot usually involves transporting them from their natal pastures. In the United States, nearly two-thirds (63%) of cattle and calves raised for beef are sold through an auction barn after leaving the farm [
   <a rid="B22-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22-animals-05-00361">22</a>], thus, many calves are moved twice before arrival at a feedlot.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Transport takes a physical and psychological toll on animals. Stressors include unfamiliar surroundings, novelty, noise, vibration, social regrouping, loading and unloading, and feed and water deprivation [
   <a rid="B23-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23-animals-05-00361">23</a>,
   <a rid="B24-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24-animals-05-00361">24</a>,
   <a rid="B25-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25-animals-05-00361">25</a>], although many factors, such as preconditioning [
   <a rid="B26-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26-animals-05-00361">26</a>] and location in the vehicle during the journey [
   <a rid="B27-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27-animals-05-00361">27</a>] can alter the effect. The stress of transport can lead to immunosuppression and an increase in disease susceptibility, including the ubiquitous Bovine Respiratory Disease (RBD) problem [
   <a rid="B25-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25-animals-05-00361">25</a>,
   <a rid="B28-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B28-animals-05-00361">28</a>,
   <a rid="B29-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29-animals-05-00361">29</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1.2. Concentrated Diets for Pigs</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In cases where intensification of animal agriculture is accompanied by better access to resources, then there may be benefits for welfare in terms of providing more nutritionally complete rations. However, pigs are also often fed highly concentrated grain-based diets in intensive production. Concentrated diets may be fed to pigs in a finely ground or pelleted ration and are expected to reduce GHG emissions due to their high digestibility. For example, in a case study of intensive pig production in East and South East Asia, the FAO explored changes to swine diets as a potential mitigation strategy, including increased digestibility of feed. In intermediate (not fully industrialized) systems, by changing the feed along with other management changes, emissions could be reduced by 32% to 38% [
   <a rid="B2-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B2-animals-05-00361">2</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Pigs’ stomachs are biologically designed for numerous, small meals throughout the day of high fiber feedstuffs [
   <a rid="B30-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30-animals-05-00361">30</a>]. However, in intensive production, they have little access to roughage. Feed processing improves feed-to-gain efficiency, but it is also associated with intestinal problems. These low fiber diets can impact mucosa integrity leaving pigs prone to gastric ulcers in the pars esophageal region of the stomach [
   <a rid="B31-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31-animals-05-00361">31</a>]. This is a problem worldwide. Reports vary, with incidence of pigs showing distinct signs of ulceration between farming operations ranging from zero to nearly 90% [
   <a rid="B32-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32-animals-05-00361">32</a>,
   <a rid="B33-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33-animals-05-00361">33</a>,
   <a rid="B34-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34-animals-05-00361">34</a>,
   <a rid="B35-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35-animals-05-00361">35</a>,
   <a rid="B36-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B36-animals-05-00361">36</a>]. For pigs in the growing/finishing stages of production, ulceration is a common cause of mortality [
   <a rid="B37-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37-animals-05-00361">37</a>]. The production systems in which most pigs are kept appear to have a large impact on the incidence of these ulcers, as pigs with access to straw, sawdust, or outdoor paddocks have fewer ulcers than those confined on bare, solid or slatted concrete floors [
   <a rid="B32-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32-animals-05-00361">32</a>,
   <a rid="B38-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38-animals-05-00361">38</a>,
   <a rid="B39-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39-animals-05-00361">39</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1.3. Feed Additives</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Feed additives can be used to inhibit CH
   <sub>4</sub> production in a variety of species. However, some dietary additives that are being tested have potential animal health concerns. For example, 
   <span class="italic">in vitro</span> studies have shown that fumarate can work as an alternative to CH
   <sub>4</sub> as a sink for H
   <sub>2</sub> in the rumen, but feeding fumarate in its free acid form can lower rumen pH and inhibit fiber digestion, while feeding it in salt form can induce toxicity. Effective doses may well exceed current dietary recommendations [
   <a rid="B40-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40-animals-05-00361">40</a>]. Especially in low protein diets, nitrates are also potential CH
   <sub>4</sub> mitigation agents. However, the intermediate product from nitrate metabolism, nitrite, is toxic, and so feeding it requires a gradual acclimation to a high dietary intake in order to avoid nitrite toxicity [
   <a rid="B10-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10-animals-05-00361">10</a>,
   <a rid="B41-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41-animals-05-00361">41</a>]. Another proposed supplement, sulfate, has been linked to sulphur-induced polioencephalomalacia, a condition in US feedlot cattle associated with excessive production of H
   <sub>2</sub>S in the rumen from diets high in distillers grains—co-products from the ethanol industry, which are high in sulfate [
   <a rid="B10-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10-animals-05-00361">10</a>,
   <a rid="B42-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42-animals-05-00361">42</a>]. The FAO cautions that more research is needed [
   <a rid="B10-animals-05-00361" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10-animals-05-00361">10</a>]. Mitigation strategies should steer clear of feeding substances that might endanger the animals, either outright or in the absence of highly skilled management.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
