<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par28">The flood vulnerability assessment is one of the key non-structural measures against flood damage by climate change, a more serious threat in coastal areas than in inland regions due to regional climatic and topographic features. Base on the IPCC’s conceptual framework comprising exposure, sensitivity, and coping components
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>
 </sup>, the vulnerability assessments to climate change have been conducted in various fields, such as human health, ecosystem, water, agriculture, fishery, etc., including floods. This study has therefore assessed the influence of frameworks and utility function forms for constructing a composite indicator on measuring the overall vulnerability to climate change. In the framework for the three vulnerability assessment components in the IPCC TAR
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>
 </sup>, the exposure and sensitivity components have a positive elasticity to the vulnerability, while the vulnerability decreases with the increasing coping score that needs to function as a subtrahend in additive multi-attribute utility forms and a divisor in multiplicative multi-attribute utility forms. Thus, lack of coping with a positive elasticity to the vulnerability like other two components can be used in the opposite concept to coping in the construction framework for composite indicators. The vulnerability ranking orders based on composite indicators 
 <italic>VA</italic>
 <sub>1</sub> and 
 <italic>VA</italic>
 <sub>2</sub> derived by the two additive aggregation forms are completely coincident regardless of the use of coping or lack of coping component. The two outcome values of 
 <italic>VA</italic>
 <sub>1</sub> and 
 <italic>VA</italic>
 <sub>2</sub> will naturally differ, but the magnitude sequences are nevertheless unchanged in each vulnerability indicator. However, the volatility of rankings and rank reversals occur in some vulnerability outcomes by a multiplicative multi-attribute utility function with a denominator coping component, since low level coping values will generate abnormally large composite outcomes and middle level coping values will underestimate the vulnerability numerically. Hence, for robustness and confidence in obtaining the vulnerability outcomes by a multiplicative composite indicator, all the assessment components need to have the same directional elasticity to vulnerability. There are also obvious differences in some vulnerability ranking orders between the two composite indicators from additive and multiplicative aggregations. This is due to the fact that additive multi-attribute utility functions will generate composite indicators with higher compensability of attribute components, while multiplicative multi-attribute utility forms will induce one of the low score components to reduce the composite indicator drastically
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>
 </sup>. In the framework for the use of potential impact as a composite component of exposure and sensitivity, the vulnerability indicator may provide misleading information in assigning more weights to the coping component, although these issues can be somewhat mitigated by the use of proper weighting methods as presented in some literature
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
