<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s4b" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Aviary experiment</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To test if one (or two) long days initiate gonadal growth, we caught 15 wild female great tits at the end of November 2008 around the Netherlands Institute of Ecology, Heteren (The Netherlands; 51°57′20″N–5°44′34″E). All females were housed in one large outdoor aviary under natural light and temperature conditions and 
  <span class="italic">ad libitum</span> food and water. Six days before the light treatment (December 5
  <span class="sup">th</span> 2008), length of the largest ovarian follicle of all females was measured during laparotomy without knowledge of the treatment each female would be assigned to. To measure follicle development, a small incision was made between the last two ribs on the left side. By parting the ribs slightly, length of the largest follicle was measured to the nearest 0.1 mm with an ocular scale. When the length of the largest follicle was too small to be measured (significantly smaller than 0.1 mm) we reported a length of 0.05 mm (
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 3 in December). All laparotomies were carried out by SVS under light Isoflurane anesthesia. Follicle volume was calculated as V = 4/3 · π · a
  <span class="sup">3</span> where 
  <span class="italic">a</span> is ½ the length of the follicle.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the first photostimulation treatment (December 11
  <span class="sup">th</span> 2008), all females were moved indoors after sunset into individual cages in two separate rooms (see 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0035617-g003" href="#pone-0035617-g003">Fig. 3</a> for a schematic overview of the treatments). Ten females in one room were exposed to light for 20 hours (7AM–3AM), then dark for four hours, after which the lights were turned on again at 7AM the following day. Five control females in the second room were kept under the natural light regime (light from 8:40AM to 4:30PM). All females were returned to the outdoor aviary the day after the photostimulation treatment. Seven days later (December 18
  <span class="sup">th</span> 2008), five of the 10 photostimulated females were photostimulated again using the same protocol, while the other five photostimulated females and five control birds were also kept indoors but under natural photoperiod. Thus, the aviary experiment consisted of three treatment groups, each containing five birds: (i) natural short photoperiod (ii) one long day and (iii) two long days with an interval of one week in between. One month after the first photostimulation (January 15
  <span class="sup">th</span> 2009) the length of the largest follicle was measured again for each female. One week after the last laparotomy all 15 females were released into the wild at the catching location (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0035617-g003" href="#pone-0035617-g003">Fig. 3</a>).
 </p>
 <div id="pone-0035617-g003" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0035617.g003</span>
  <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Schematic overview of the photostimulation treatment for both the aviary and the field experiment.</div>
   <p>For the experiment in captivity (December 2008), females were moved from the outdoor aviary to our indoor facilities after sunset, where a part of the females were kept under natural day length and a part were kept in a different room under a long day length (20L∶4D). Females were moved to their outdoor aviary in the morning of day three. For the field experiment (March 2009 and 2010), females were brought from the field into out indoor facilities for a similar treatment. On the morning of day three, all females were released in the field at the location where they were caught. Grey bars resemble darkness while open bars represent light periods; numbers in the bar are the hours of the day.</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pone.0035617.g003" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
