<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">A key uncertainty in C substrate and temperature sensitivity models is the additional inclusion of the effects from other resources. With globally increasing rates of N availability, an evaluation of a potential N effect on R
 <sub class="sub">soil</sub> may be important for predicting soil climate feedbacks. As found across previous studies
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">6</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">18</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">30</xref>
 </sup>, we likewise observed variable influences of N availability. In general N availability reduced R
 <sub class="sub">soil</sub> emissions at both ambient and saturating substrate concentrations, consistent with the nitrogen mining hypothesis (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref>). However, we observed some evidence of N limitation that, when alleviated, increased R
 <sub class="sub">soil</sub> capacity. Our findings were consistent with the variable CUE hypothesis, which predicts increasing N leads to greater conservation of available C through decreased respiratory loss
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>
 </sup>. Furthermore, in the N addition plots, differences in V
 <sub class="sub">max</sub> associated with available soil N resulted in greater V
 <sub class="sub">max</sub> in the Mid N soil compared to the control, but lower V
 <sub class="sub">max</sub> in the High N plot compared to the control (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2f</xref>). This pattern corresponds to a shift from N limitation in the low N soil, to balanced C:N availability, and then C limitation in the highest available N soil, consistent with shifts in CUE regulating R
 <sub class="sub">soil</sub> as previously observed from laboratory incubations from dryland ecosystems
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">18</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" class="xref">31</xref>
 </sup> and that we extend to tests from more mesic environments and through the use of field experiments.
</p>
