<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Historically, flatwoods salamanders occurred across southern Alabama, the panhandle and north central regions of Florida, southern Georgia, and South Carolina (Palis &amp; Means, 
 <xref rid="ece35277-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2005</xref>). In recent years, however, and despite intense efforts to monitor and locate new populations, the two flatwoods salamander species have collectively experienced an 86.8% loss of populations (Semlitsch et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35277-bib-0048" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>). The primary threats currently affecting flatwoods salamanders are changes in habitat (loss, fragmentation, and degradation), climate (particularly drought and variation in the timing of rainfall), and interactions between these threats (Figure 
 <xref rid="ece35277-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref>). Extreme precipitation events, resulting in drought and flooding, along with hurricane‐induced storm surge (Lin, Lane, Emanuel, Sullivan, &amp; Donnelly, 
 <xref rid="ece35277-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>), can potentially impact amphibians that use freshwater coastal wetlands (Walls, Barichivich, &amp; Brown, 
 <xref rid="ece35277-bib-0069" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). Moreover, phenological shifts in the timing of key climatic events (e.g., pond‐filling and drying) can have significant consequences for individual survival and species persistence (Walls et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35277-bib-0069" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>, and references therein). Lastly, sea level rise threatens coastal freshwater wetlands, their surrounding upland habitats, and landscape connectivity (Benscoter et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35277-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Leonard et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35277-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>; Tebaldi, Strauss, &amp; Zervas, 
 <xref rid="ece35277-bib-0056" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>; Wahl, Calafat, &amp; Luther, 
 <xref rid="ece35277-bib-0068" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; Woodruff, Irish, &amp; Camargo, 
 <xref rid="ece35277-bib-0071" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). Because of proximity to the Gulf of Mexico and potential exposure to hurricane‐related storm surge and sea level rise, the St. Marks Unit of the Refuge (approximately 2.4 m above sea level) harbors the most susceptible 
 <italic class="italic">A. cingulatum</italic> Critical Habitat Units (Units FFS‐3A and FFS‐3B; Figure 
 <xref rid="ece35277-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3</xref>). The use of sea level rise and marsh mitigation data from National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA, 
 <xref rid="ece35277-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2018a</xref>) in a SLOSH (Sea, Lake, and Overland Surges from Hurricanes) model (NOAA, 
 <xref rid="ece35277-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2018b</xref>) predicts that, in a Category 1 storm, maximum storm surge could inundate all but a couple of breeding sites in FFS‐3A and FFS‐3B (Figure 
 <xref rid="ece35277-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3</xref>a). In a Category 3 storm, maximum storm surge could completely inundate all breeding sites in FFS‐3A and FFS‐3B and could approach the southern boundary of Critical Habitat Unit FFS‐3C (located north of the Refuge; Figure 
 <xref rid="ece35277-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3</xref>b). In more intense storms (Categories 4 and 5), the maximum surge level could completely inundate FFS‐3C as well (not shown).
</p>
