<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">From 16 October to 30 November 2018, we measured specific conductance (SpC) using a HydroLab Quanta water quality meter during each visit to each wetland according to standard USGS protocols (USGS, 
 <xref rid="ece35277-bib-0065" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1997</xref> to present). We report the median of five water quality readings at each site (Table 
 <xref rid="ece35277-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S1</xref>). We identified overwashed wetlands by comparing poststorm SpC levels to prestorm levels (before the storm, a single measurement of SpC was taken per site each spring). As defined by Gunzburger et al. (
 <xref rid="ece35277-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>), overwashed wetlands had higher specific conductance than non‐overwashed wetlands by several orders of magnitude (Figure 
 <xref rid="ece35277-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" class="xref">4</xref>). In March and April 2018, SpC (µS/cm) of 27 breeding ponds known to be used by 
 <italic class="italic">A. cingulatum</italic> ranged from 75 to 445 µS/cm across all ponds. Soon after the storm (16–29 October), SpC of these same ponds ranged from 80 to 23,100 µS/cm (Figure 
 <xref rid="ece35277-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" class="xref">4</xref>; Table 
 <xref rid="ece35277-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S1</xref>). For the 17 ponds that were overwashed, conductivity increased by  a factor of 11.2–216.7 (mean ± 1 
 <italic class="italic">SD</italic> = 92.8 ± 65.2) per pond, whereas it only changed by a factor of 0.8–2.0 (mean ± 1 
 <italic class="italic">SD </italic>= 1.2 ± 0.4) for the remaining 10 ponds that were not overwashed (Table 
 <xref rid="ece35277-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S1</xref>). For ponds sampled more long‐term (from April 2013 to March/April 2018), mean per‐season SpC (for overwashed and non‐overwashed ponds combined) ranged from a low of 88 µS/cm to a high of 150 µS/cm. But, in October 2018, the mean median value increased to  7,556 µS/cm, a 50‐ to 86‐fold overall increase for all ponds combined. A map of poststorm SpC values reveals the spatial extent of storm surge for ponds inhabited by 
 <italic class="italic">A. cingulatum</italic> (Figure 
 <xref rid="ece35277-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>). This map provides a refinement of the actual spatial extent of saltwater intrusion as well as a basis to compare predictions from SLOSH models for this area (Figure 
 <xref rid="ece35277-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3</xref> a,b).
</p>
