<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">After the hurricane, we opportunistically observed (during systematic trapping and assessments of storm damage) both terrestrial and wetland‐associated species and noted their status (alive or dead). We confined our observation period of dead individuals to 15 ‐ 19 October 2018 to avoid potentially double counting individuals, to infer that the cause of death was possibly storm‐related, and because after this time dead animals were scavenged or otherwise significantly less identifiable. Except for 
 <italic class="italic">A. cingulatum</italic>, for which we report captures through 10 December, we recorded observations of live individuals through 26 October, with most individual amphibians observed during a nocturnal search on 25 October. We observed numerous unidentified individual fishes (both alive and dead), live crayfish, and 15 species of both amphibians and reptiles (live and dead combined; Table 
 <xref rid="ece35277-tbl-0001" ref-type="table" class="xref">1</xref>). We searched for 
 <italic class="italic">A. cingulatum</italic> at two breeding sites that did not get inundated by storm surge and continued to monitor three sites that are part of a long‐term capture‐mark‐recapture study. Prior to the storm, these latter sites were equipped with partial drift fences and funnel traps designed to intercept salamanders migrating to and from breeding ponds. For all three sites combined, a marked population of 888 individuals (including 442 head‐started metamorphs) existed as of May 2018. All three existing study sites were inundated by storm surge during Hurricane Michael, and the storm destroyed or severely damaged most of the drift fences, compromising our ability to detect migrating salamanders. Nevertheless, we erected partial, temporary fences and set out traps (wire‐mesh funnel traps) along them at all five sites (two new sites and three existing ones), checking them daily to determine whether salamanders were still present at these sites.
</p>
