<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The most important locations chosen by respondents living in Jonstorp are more often threatened by sea level rise than the locations chosen by respondents living in Höganäs according to the flooding model we have used (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0210426.g001" class="xref">Fig 1</xref>) (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0210426.s006" class="xref">S6 Fig</xref>). Many of the most important locations chosen by the respondents are found in or in the vicinity of Höganäs and Jonstorp urbanised areas with Jonstorp to a larger extent than Höganäs being located in low-lying and flooding prone areas (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0210426.g001" class="xref">Fig 1</xref>). Also statistically significantly more respondents from Jonstorp chose the most important locations because of the environmental (ENV) value profile (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0210426.s004" class="xref">S4 Fig</xref>) which was often found in areas of high probability of flooding damage (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0210426.g004" class="xref">Fig 4</xref>). However, the vulnerability of the values by respondents living in Jonstorp is potentially reduced because of their higher preparedness to take measures to adapt compared to respondents from Höganäs (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0210426.g005" class="xref">Fig 5</xref>) (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0210426.s013" class="xref">S3 Table</xref>). This is because respondents from Jonstorp more often strongly believe that they have experienced the effects of climate change. In particular, respondents from Jonstorp more often report having experienced climate change induced coastal erosion (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0210426.s010" class="xref">S10 Fig</xref>). This belief is in agreement with the coastline in the vicinity of Jonstorp being more susceptible to undermining and coastal erosion because of ongoing sea level rise than the coastline in the vicinity of Höganäs [
 <xref rid="pone.0210426.ref028" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>]. Finally, it is noteworthy that citizens who have lived longer in the municipality and presumably have more observational data to rely on significantly less strongly believe in the local effects of climate change and have a weaker strength of belief in having experienced the effects of climate change than the other respondents (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0210426.g005" class="xref">Fig 5</xref>) (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0210426.s013" class="xref">S3 Table</xref>).
</p>
