<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The overall impacts of environmental stress on trees can be summarized with their effects on growth. Tree growth is a key parameter for evaluate the ability of forests to mitigate climate change and provide ecosystem services (Bonan, 
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2008</xref>). Forest health, however, is commonly assessed by means of crown defoliation (Michel and Seidling, 
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>). Defoliation is a visual estimate of the relative amount of foliage loss of the target tree compared with that of the reference standard tree. Crown defoliation has been assessed extensively since the 1980s, and the trends recorded are assumed to be correlated with the effects of environmental stress, such as air pollution and climate change (Van Leeuwen et al., 
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2000</xref>). Although no clear relationships were found between defoliation and ecological factors at European level, local studies evidenced the impacts of ozone pollution (Augustatis and Bytnerowicz, 
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2008</xref>); extreme drought and heat weaves (Carnicer et al., 
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>) and fluctuating climatic conditions (Ferretti et al., 
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>). Intuitively, defoliation may affect growth through the reduction of the photosynthetic surface, but different ecophysiological processes (e.g., better exploitation of sunlight from the foliage in the inner part of the crown, increase of photosynthetic efficiency in the remaining foliage) can compensate for the loss of leaves. Growth reduction has been verified only for the most defoliated pine species (
 <italic class="italic">Pinus sylvestris</italic> L.) in Spain (Sánchez-Salguero et al., 
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>), Italy (Castagneri et al., 
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>), and Lithuania (Augustatis and Bytnerowicz, 
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2008</xref>).
</p>
