<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We re-assessed published data on the relationship among the D
 <sub class="sub">max</sub> (
 <italic class="italic">D</italic>
 <sub class="sub">max</sub>; m), amount of infiltrated water to soil, and amount of snowmelt water during the snow cover manipulation experiment at the Memuro Research Station (Hokkaido Agricultural Research Center, NARO: 143 °05′E, 42 °53′N) in the Tokachi region for over 4 years (2005–06
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30" class="xref">30</xref>, 2006–07
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30" class="xref">30</xref>, 2007–08
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30" class="xref">30</xref>, and 2008–09
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15" class="xref">15</xref>). In these studies, soil frost depth was controlled by removing the snow cover in early winter. The cumulative daily downward water flux at 0.5-m soil depth during the snowmelt period was set to the amount of infiltrated water to soil (
 <italic class="italic">Inf</italic>; mm). Similarly, the cumulative decrease in snow-water equivalent during the snowmelt period was set to the amount of snowmelt water (
 <italic class="italic">SnowMelt</italic>; mm). These values were slightly different from the published data
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15" class="xref">15</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30" class="xref">30</xref> because they were rounded off to the closest whole number to convert to an integer value for statistical modelling (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Table S2</xref>). In addition, the year of study was regarded as an independent study plot. Based on the fact that the amount of infiltrated water to soil was no more than that of snowmelt water, i.e. data 
 <italic class="italic">Inf</italic>/
 <italic class="italic">SnowMelt</italic> were between 0 to 1, we assumed that the observed variations in the 
 <italic class="italic">Inf</italic> follows the binomial distribution of mean 
 <italic class="italic">q</italic> and of the upper limit 
 <italic class="italic">SnowMelt</italic> (
 <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq8" class="xref">eq. 6</xref>). We set 
 <italic class="italic">D</italic>
 <sub class="sub">max</sub> as the explanatory variable in the linear predictor and then applied the logit link function (
 <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq9" class="xref">eq. 7</xref>). The coefficients (
 <italic class="italic">β</italic>
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">q</italic>0
 </sub>, 
 <italic class="italic">β</italic>
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">q</italic>1
 </sub>) in 
 <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq9" class="xref">eq. 7</xref> were estimated using the ‘glm’ function of R software package
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29" class="xref">29</xref>.
</p>
