<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">ORYZA2000 simulates phenology at an hourly timestep and integrates over the day. The ORYZA2000 version used by (Matthews et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb13967-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1995</xref>, 
 <xref rid="gcb13967-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1997</xref>) contained a phenology model in which development rate increases above the base temperature of 8°C and then decreases again above the optimum temperature of 30°C, with no development above the maximum temperature of 42°C. Later studies showed that models with no delay in development above the optimum temperature generally simulate the length growing period more accurately (Van Oort et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb13967-bib-0064" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>; Zhang et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb13967-bib-0076" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). These studies showed that in tropical environments the base temperature is often higher than 8°C. Use of a wrong phenology model can cause significant bias in yield simulations (Van Oort, De Vries et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb13967-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Zhang et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb13967-bib-0077" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>). After fixing the cardinal temperatures (see below) and assuming no photoperiod sensitivity we calibrated development rates for each site and season such that simulated duration from sowing to maturity would match values reported in the RiceAtlas. The 50% flowering date was fixed to occur 30 days before the maturity date (Vergara &amp; Chang, 
 <xref rid="gcb13967-bib-0067" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1985</xref>) in the current climate. In this paper we simulated with a bilinear temperature response phenology model with a base temperature of 14°C, an optimum temperature of 31°C and no delay in development at temperatures above 31°C, with values of 14°C and 31°C based on (Van Oort et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb13967-bib-0064" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>) and (Sanchez, Rasmussen, &amp; Porter, 
 <xref rid="gcb13967-bib-0051" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>).
</p>
