<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Businesses in the transportation sector are particularly targeted by demands for climate change action, as the sector accounts for 22% of global carbon dioxide (CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>) emissions (IPCC, 
 <xref rid="bse1968-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). GHG emissions from this sector are growing at a faster rate than in any other energy end‐use industry. Passenger and freight transport alone is responsible for about three‐quarters of total sector emissions (IEA, 
 <xref rid="bse1968-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). Against this background, various policies such as fuel economy standards and emission‐based taxes on cars aim to reduce CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> emissions from vehicle use, including the CAFE regulations in the US, vehicle taxes in the EU or similar approaches in other major markets such as China and Japan (ICCT, 
 <xref rid="bse1968-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). To achieve emission reduction targets requires the introduction of new technologies (e.g. alternative propulsion systems), new services (e.g. fleet management systems) and different usage patterns of automobiles (e.g. car sharing) (IPCC, 
 <xref rid="bse1968-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). While original equipment manufacturers (OEMs) are mainly held responsible for vehicle emissions, suppliers increasingly play a key role in efforts to cut emissions. Due to increased outsourcing, a large portion of innovation is nowadays done by suppliers (Böttcher and Müller, 
 <xref rid="bse1968-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). In the case of the German automotive industry, for example, suppliers generate about 70% of value added (Di Botonto, 
 <xref rid="bse1968-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). The success of OEMs' responses to climate change is therefore heavily dependent on the performance of their suppliers (Lee, 
 <xref rid="bse1968-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>).
</p>
