<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">To assess the influence of climate parameters on the upslope shift of the El Oro parakeets, we first carried out a linear regression to evaluate the variability in temperature and precipitation anomalies over the study period (temp = temp
 <sub class="sub">0</sub> + α * Δ
 <sub class="sub">Year</sub> and precip = precip
 <sub class="sub">0</sub> + α * Δ
 <sub class="sub">Year</sub>; null hypothesis: no trend in climate parameters over time). We found a positive linear trend in temperature over the years (
 <italic class="italic">R</italic>
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> = 0.730; 
 <italic class="italic">p</italic> &lt; 0.1), but no trend in precipitation (
 <italic class="italic">R</italic>
 <sup class="sup">
  <italic class="italic">2</italic>
 </sup> = 0.484; 
 <italic class="italic">p</italic> &gt; 0.1). Additionally, we assessed the relationships between temperature and precipitation anomalies and the mean altitude of El Oro parakeets for the five years 1985, 1986, 2002, 2011, and 2012 (altitude = altitude
 <sub class="sub">0</sub> + α * Δ
 <sub class="sub">temp</sub> and altitude = altitude
 <sub class="sub">0</sub> + α * Δ
 <sub class="sub">precip</sub>; null hypothesis: no altitudinal trend in climate parameters). Likewise, altitude was positively correlated with temperature (
 <italic class="italic">R</italic>
 <sup class="sup">
  <italic class="italic">2</italic>
 </sup> = 0.742; 
 <italic class="italic">p</italic> &lt; 0.1), but not with precipitation (
 <italic class="italic">R</italic>
 <sup class="sup">
  <italic class="italic">2</italic>
 </sup> = 0.502; 
 <italic class="italic">p</italic> &gt; 0.1). These correlations are consistent with the hypothesis that temperature anomalies are the important drivers of altitude of El Oro parakeets. We hence approximated the situation with a simple model in which temperature alone influences the upslope shift, neglecting uncertainties in altitudes and temperature. All further analyses thus were conducted for temperature anomalies only.
</p>
