<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The results of our field and laboratory experiments suggest that the recent, rapid SST rise may play a key role in the collapse of 
 <italic class="italic">P. lividus</italic> populations along the Israeli Mediterranean coast. Even though this species is known to present strong fluctuations in population size
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25" class="xref">25</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29" class="xref">29</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30" class="xref">30</xref>, we presume that this collapse is unprecedented because such a large scale, long-term (probably more than a decade) decline has not been recorded for this key species anywhere before. The urchins’ mortality in our study was not the result of a distinctive extreme weather event. During the summer of 2012, average daily seawater temperature was above 30 °C for 65 consecutive days including 12 days with temperature higher than 31 °C. The year of 2012 was not unique—the summer peak water temperatures during the last decade have often been higher than the observed lethal temperature of ~30.5 °C
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31" class="xref">31</xref>. Over-harvesting, the main cause for 
 <italic class="italic">P. lividus</italic> population decline elsewhere
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26" class="xref">26</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32" class="xref">32</xref>, is not a factor along the Israeli coastline, since there is no commercial fishing of this species in the region, and poaching is rare. Other documented mortality factors such as predator hyper-abundance, toxic algae blooms, wave action and pollution
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25" class="xref">25</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26" class="xref">26</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30" class="xref">30</xref> have been ruled out as well, since no unusual episodes of these factors have been recorded. The possibility of exclusion by an invasive herbivorous fish, 
 <italic class="italic">Siganus rivulatus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Siganus luridus</italic>, possible resource competitors of 
 <italic class="italic">P. lividus</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33" class="xref">33</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34" class="xref">34</xref>, was recently examined. Results from the field and laboratory experiments showed that reduced food availability can have sub-lethal impacts that may affect fitness in the long-term
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27" class="xref">27</xref>. Therefore, temperature may be the proximal cause while competitive exclusion might play some role in the population collapse on the long-term; however, further work is required in order to determine its scope. Our results therefore provide strong evidence that the current SST temperature during the summer months is above the thermo-tolerance range of this species, and may have greatly contributed to the species near-extirpation in the region.
</p>
