<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Four 
 <italic class="italic">B. belizanus</italic>, collected from the Florida Everglades National Park, four 
 <italic class="italic">C. urophthalmus</italic>, collected from Merritt Island, Florida, and four 
 <italic class="italic">P. volitans</italic>, collected from Port St. Lucie, Florida were acclimated to 20 °C water temperature and trained for high-speed video in the fish ecophysiology laboratory at Florida Institute of Technology for two weeks before the experiment was initiated. Each fish was housed in 38 L filming tanks filled with water that matched their Florida habitats: 0 ppt for 
 <italic class="italic">B. belizanus</italic>; 24 ppt for 
 <italic class="italic">C. urophthalmus</italic>, and 35 ppt for 
 <italic class="italic">P. volitans</italic>. The twelve fishes were subjected to a repeated measures experimental design, in which, each fish was filmed successively in each of the three experimental temperatures 20 °C, 25 °C and 30 °C (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="biology-05-00046-f001" class="xref">Figure 1</xref>). Temperature in each filming tank was raised from 20 °C to the higher filming temperatures at a rate of 1 °C daily using a water heater. Once the experimental temperature was achieved, feeding sessions were recorded every other day from each fish. Each fish was filmed using a RedLake High-Speed Motionscope 2000S camera with a shutter speed of 1/1000 s at 250 frames per second while feeding on live mosquitofish (
 <italic class="italic">Gambusia holbrooki</italic>) prey at 20 °C, 25 °C and 30 °C. Prey was maintained at 20 °C ambient-room temperature. Prey girth was about 80% of peak gape of each fish; previous analyses of feeding kinematics in these fishes indicated that this relative prey-size elicited maximum prey-capture performance in fish [
 <xref rid="B35-biology-05-00046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="B36-biology-05-00046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>,
 <xref rid="B46-biology-05-00046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>]. The effects of temperature on the prey was not investigated in this study. Experimental fish was not fed 1–2 days before each recording session to ensure fish was motivated to eat and exhibit maximum performance during feeding trials [
 <xref rid="B19-biology-05-00046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-biology-05-00046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>].
</p>
