<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">After five generations of selection, we measured the effect of selection for increased heat tolerance on upper lethal limits following Kelly et al. (
 <xref rid="eva12394-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). For each of the heat‐selected lines and unselected controls, we exposed sets of nine mate‐guarding pairs to a target temperature for 1 h, allowed 48 h for recovery, and then assessed survival. We did this for a series of 5–10 temperatures at 0.2°C intervals, spanning from the temperature that produced 90–100% survival to the temperature that produced 90–100% mortality, and then used the mortality at each temperature to estimate LT
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> for each line via logistic regression in the statistical program R (R Development Core Team 
 <xref rid="eva12394-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). For each of the high‐ and low‐salinity selection lines, we measured heat tolerance twice: once for individuals that had been taken from the salinity selection line after five generations of selection, and then held under common garden conditions at ambient (35 ppt) salinity for one generation. Second, we measured heat tolerance for individuals from each selection line at their ‘native’ salinity (70 ppt for high‐salinity lines, 15 ppt for low‐salinity lines) after six generations of selection. This allowed us to separate any evolutionary loss of heat tolerance that might have occurred in the salinity selection lines from the possible synergistic physiological effects of simultaneously tolerating both heat and salinity stress. After estimating LT
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> for each line, we tested for differences in temperature tolerance among treatments in two‐way ANOVAs, with LT
 <sub class="sub">50</sub> estimates for each line × treatment combination as the response variable (R Development Core Team 
 <xref rid="eva12394-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). The first ANOVA tested for effects of heat selection and sex on heat tolerance at generation five of selection. The second ANOVA tested for effects of selection + salinity treatment and sex on heat tolerance at generation six of selection. We performed two separate ANOVAs for this analysis because each experimental test was paired with its relevant unselected control for that generation (five generations of selection for heat tolerance and 6 generations of selection for salinity) to account for minor fluctuations in incubator conditions and food quality, which might affect heat tolerance.
</p>
