<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">There was furthermore no overall direct effect of spatial distance on mitigating motivation, lending support to previous studies (e.g., 
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Schoenefeld and McCauley, 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Brügger et al., 2016</xref>). However, our findings point to a complex interactive effect of spatial distance in that only when consequences were abstractly described did spatial distance demotivate willingness to self-change and repair. According to 
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Rabinovich et al. (2009)</xref>, presenting something as simultaneously concrete and distant or abstract and proximate (i.e., non-fitted descriptions) allows people to think both about concrete steps to take in order to mitigate a problem (cf. 
 <italic class="italic">how</italic>) whilst also think about the importance of mitigating the problem (cf. 
 <italic class="italic">why</italic>). Thus, when we think about climate change consequences as both abstract and distant problems, it could communicate the significance of climate change but fail to motivate self-change and repair because it doesn’t get people thinking about 
 <italic class="italic">how</italic> to take action. Making a spatially distant problem more concrete may then have a positive effect because it informs people how to respond. Conversely, when we think about climate change consequences as spatially proximate and concrete problems, we might recognize action alternatives but fail to recognize the importance of action. That making a spatially proximate problem more abstract did not encourage action may (or may not) support this interaction account. The possibility of a positive effect of non-fitted descriptions was at most hinted at and future research is certainly needed to further explore this possibility. The scale for repair further showed lower reliability (Cronbach’s α = 0.66) than the scale for self-change and distancing, which might help explain why the interaction effect of spatial distance and description abstractness was more pronounced for self-change. Future studies might consider using scales that have already been adapted to the climate change context.
</p>
