<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par21" class="p">The maximum entropy approach
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" class="xref">57</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" class="xref">59</xref>
 </sup> was employed to simulate habitat suitability for giant pandas
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" class="xref">36</xref>
 </sup>. We first used eight bioclimatic variables to model the current distribution probability of 16 bamboo species
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" class="xref">37</xref>
 </sup>, and then we built the distribution model for the giant panda using bamboo suitability, the selected eight bioclimatic variables, and five environmental variables (slope, aspect, distance from residential areas, distance from roads, and land cover) as predictors. We adopted a habitat suitability technique to identify the distributions of different classes of habitat suitability for giant pandas. The habitat suitability mode was constructed based on giant pandas’ habitat selection criteria, including bamboo suitability, land cover, elevation, slope, aspect, distance from residential areas, and distance from roads
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" class="xref">27</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" class="xref">32</xref>
 </sup>. Finally, we reclassified panda habitats into marginally, moderately and highly suitable habitats using standard deviations classification
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" class="xref">32</xref>
 </sup>. The details on the simulation of giant panda habitats and bamboo suitability can be found in two papers
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" class="xref">36</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" class="xref">37</xref>
 </sup>. To investigate the congruence between carbon and biodiversity conservation, Spearman’s rank correlation coefficients were also calculated for the relationships between mean carbon density and habitat suitability index at cell scale and in the whole NR network.
</p>
