<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Definition, observations, and key processes</div>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A marine heat wave is usually defined as a coherent area of extreme warm sea surface temperature (SST) that persists for days to months
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span>. MHWs have been observed in all major ocean basins over the recent decade, but only a few MHWs have been documented and analyzed extensively (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). One of the first MHW that has been characterized in the literature occurred in 2003 in the northwestern Mediterranean Sea with SSTs reaching 3–5 °C above the 1982–2016 reference period
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span>. A MHW with similar intensity occurred off the coast of Western Australia in early 2011, persisting for &gt;10 weeks
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
  </span>. The northeast Pacific Ocean experienced the largest MHW (often called “The Blob”) ever recorded between 2013 and 2015 with maximum SST anomalies of &gt;6 °C off southern California
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
  </span>. Prominent MHWs also include the record high coastal ocean warming in the northwest Atlantic
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>
  </span>, and the MHW in the Tasmanian Sea in 2015/16 that lasted &gt;250 days
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>
  </span>. MHWs also repeatedly occurred over the Western Pacific Warm Pool including the Great Barrier Reef in 1998, 2002, and 2016
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
  </span>.
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Summary of prominent recent marine heat waves that are documented and analyzed in the literature. The figure shows the maximum sea surface temperature anomaly in regions where temperature exceeds the 99th percentile using NOAA’s daily Optimum Interpolation sea surface temperature dataset
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
     </span>. The numbers indicate the year of the MHW occurrence. The 99th percentile is calculated over the 1982–2016 reference period. The map was created using the NCAR Command Language (
     <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ncl.ucar.edu" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.ncl.ucar.edu</span>)
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2018_3163_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e265" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The processes leading to the build-up, persistence and decay of a MHW are in general not well understood. Extreme ocean temperatures at the surface can be caused by large and small-scale oceanic forcing, atmospheric forcing or a combination of both, and the dominant mechanisms also depend on the location and season of occurrence. For example, the 2011 MHW off the coast of Western Australia was caused by predominant La Niña conditions in 2010/11 that drove the relatively warm Leeuwin Current southward along the west coast of Australia
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span>. The northeast Pacific MHW from 2013 to 2015 was attributed to strong positive sea level pressure anomalies across the northeast Pacific that suppressed heat loss from the ocean to the atmosphere and caused anomalous and multi-year persistent high sea surface temperatures
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
</sec>
