<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Impacts on physical, natural, and humans systems</div>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">So far the understanding of the impacts of MHWs on marine ecosystems has been opportunistically gained following a few recent events. Reported biological impacts range from geographical species shifts and widespread changes in species composition to harmful algal blooms, mass stranding’s of mammals and mass mortalities of particular species
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span>. Two of the best studied MHWs with extensive ecological implications are the 2011 Western Australian MHW and the 2013–2015 northeast Pacific MHW. The 2011 Western Australian MHW resulted in an entire regime shift of the temperate reef ecosystem including a reduction in abundance of habitat-forming seaweeds, a subsequent shift in community structure and a southward distribution shift in tropical fish communities
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span>. The warm blob in the northeast Pacific caused increased mortality of sea lions, whales and sea birds, very low ocean primary productivity, an increase in warm-water copepod species in the northern Californian region, and novel species compositions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span>. Another example is the MHW associated with the 2015/16 El Niño, which lead to the third mass coral bleaching event in recorded history with reported bleaching of over 90% of the surveyed reefs on the Great Barrier Reef in 2016
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">MHWs can also lead to significant political and socio-economic ramifications when affecting aquaculture or important fishery species. The MHW in the northwest Atlantic in 2012 has led to altered fishing practices and harvest patterns, price collapses of important fisheries and ultimately to intensified economic tensions between nations
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>
  </span>. The warm blob in the northeast Pacific caused the closing of both commercial and recreational fisheries resulting in millions of dollars in losses among fishing industries
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span>. MHWs can also perturb atmospheric conditions over land via teleconnections that may persist for multiple weeks to months. For example, anomalous high SSTs in the northeast Pacific have increased the probability for occurrence of the three consecutive dry winters in California during 2011–2014
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
  </span>. Therefore, MHWs may also have the potential to influence the predictability of extreme weather events over land.
 </p>
</sec>
