<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Important knowledge gaps</div>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While long-term trends in global sea surface temperatures are relatively well known, an overview of past occurrences of MHWs and a mechanistic understanding of associated processes is currently missing. Notable exceptions are individual studies indicating that the extremely warm SSTs have become more common in more than one-third of the world’s coastal ocean
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span> over the past few decades and that the average interval between coral reef bleaching events globally has been halved over the last 25 years
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
  </span>. In addition, knowledge on the future progression of MHWs under different global warming scenarios and the risk for consecutive MHW events is currently lacking, despite strong evidence that global warming will increase the frequency and magnitude of land-based heat waves
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A thought experiment using observed local daily land and sea surface temperature distributions might provide some guidance about the progression of MHWs under global warming (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>). A simple shift towards a warmer climate of the entire land and sea surface temperature distribution causes an increase in the probability of occurrence of both land-based and marine heat waves. Climate models consistently show that warming is about 1.5 times larger over land (Δ
  <span class="italic">T</span>
  <sub>land</sub> in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>) than over the ocean (Δ
  <span class="italic">T</span>
  <sub>ocn</sub>), independent of the level of global warming
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>
  </span>. Intuitively, this points towards a larger increase in the probability of occurrence of heat waves over land than over the ocean. However, due to the narrow sea surface temperature distribution, the smaller temperature increase at the ocean surface still leads to a disproportionally larger increase in the probability of MHWs than of land-based heat waves. Clearly, changes in the higher moments of the probability temperature distribution like increasing/decreasing variance or skewness can also produce changes in the likelihood of extreme events without changes in the mean, and could modify the conceptual picture drawn in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>.
  <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>The effect of a simple shift towards a warmer climate on the probability of land-based and marine heat waves. 
     <span class="bold">a</span> shows the observed distribution of the linearly detrended and deseasonalized local daily surface air temperature anomalies over land using the CRU-NCEP-v8 data set
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>,
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
     </span>; 
     <span class="bold">b</span> as for 
     <span class="bold">a</span> but for local daily sea surface temperature anomalies using NOAA’s daily Optimum Interpolation sea surface temperature data set
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
     </span>. Solid black lines show the distributions over the 1982–2016 period and solid gray lines indicate the same shape of the distributions, but the land is shifted by Δ
     <span class="italic">T</span>
     <sub>land = </sub>2°C and the ocean by Δ
     <span class="italic">T</span>
     <sub>ocn</sub> = 1.33 °C. Here we assume Δ
     <span class="italic">T</span>
     <sub>land</sub>/Δ
     <span class="italic">T</span>
     <sub>ocn = </sub>1.5
     <span class="sup">20</span>. A heat wave is defined as temperature exceeds the 95th percentile (red and blue shaded areas). The inset highlights the changes in land-based heat waves
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2018_3163_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e416" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Major scientific progress in probabilistic event attribution research makes it now possible to attribute the risk of individual extreme climate events over land to human-induced climate change and past carbon emissions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
  </span>. However, so far only a couple of studies applied an attribution framework to MHWs
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
  </span>. These studies conclude that the severity of all but one MHW was increased due to climate change. One study even concluded that the occurrence of the unusually warm water off the coast of Alaska in 2016 would not have even been possible without climate change. Further research into this attribution field is needed to assign losses and damages associated with MHWs to country-level responsibility
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The vulnerability of marine ecosystems to MHWs depends not only on the duration and magnitude of the extreme event, but also on the sensitivity and adaptive capacity of the ecosystem to these events. Risk assessments for marine ecosystems have focused largely on mean changes in temperature. Notable exceptions are the assessment of risks for coral reef systems. As a result, there is currently limited ability to project the effects of MHWs on the future of marine ecosystems and to advise society on effective adaption strategies.</p>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Observations and model simulations also demonstrate that other factors such as ocean acidification and deoxygenation are putting stress on marine ecosystems. However, little is known about possible ocean “hotspots”, where extreme events in temperature, acidification and oxygen occur at the same time or successively (i.e., compound events).</p>
</sec>
