<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec14" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Analysis</div>
 <p id="Par54" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We analysed changes in the biomass of selected functional groups. These groups were chosen taking into account their inclusion in the time series fitting (see Corrales, 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>
  </span>) and considering their importance (economic and ecological importance, such as commercial species and vulnerable species). In addition, functional groups were aggregated taking into account their ecological role, taxonomy, habitat and between alien and native functional groups. Therefore, we defined separate groups as primary producers, zooplanktonic species, invertebrates, fishes and vulnerable species (which included sea turtles, sea birds and dolphins). Invertebrates and fishes were split into native and alien groups, and fishes were also divided between demersal and pelagic.
 </p>
 <p id="Par55" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition, a selection of ecological indicators was used to evaluate the impacts of ecological changes on the ecosystem over time:
  <div list-type="order" class="list">
   <div class="list-item">
    <p id="Par56">Total biomass (excluding detritus) (t·km
     <span class="sup">−2</span>), which included biomass of all the functional groups excluding detritus (detritus and discards). This indicator was used to quantify changes at the whole ecosystem level
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>
     </span>.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p id="Par57">Forage fish biomass (t·km
     <span class="sup">−2</span>), which included the biomass of benthopelagic fishes, small pelagic fishes, mackerel and horse mackerel. This indicator was analysed to quantify changes in the pelagic compartment
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR111" href="#CR111">111</a>
     </span>.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p id="Par58">Invertebrate biomass (t·km
     <span class="sup">−2</span>), which included biomass of benthic invertebrate groups. This indicator was used to assess the dynamics of benthic invertebrates in the ecosystem, which tends to benefit from reductions in fish and predator biomass
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR112" href="#CR112">112</a>
     </span>.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p id="Par59">Predatory biomass (t·km
     <span class="sup">−2</span>), which included biomass of all the groups with TL ≥4 and tends to decrease with increasing fishing impact in marine ecosystems
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR113" href="#CR113">113</a>
     </span>.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p id="Par60">Kempton’s index, which expresses biomass diversity by considering those organisms with trophic levels ≥3 and tends to decrease with ecosystem degradation
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR114" href="#CR114">114</a>
     </span>.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p id="Par61">Total catch (t·km
     <span class="sup">−2</span>·year
     <span class="sup">−1</span>), which includes the annual catches of the different fleets and provides an idea of total fisheries removals
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR111" href="#CR111">111</a>
     </span>.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p id="Par62">Mean Trophic Level of the catch (mTLc), which expresses the TL of the catch, reflects the fishing strategy of the fleet and is used to quantify the impact of fishing
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR112" href="#CR112">112</a>
     </span>.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p id="Par63">Mean Trophic Level of the community (mTLco), which expresses the Trophic Level (TL) of the whole ecosystem, reflects the structure of the ecosystem and is used to quantify the impact of fishing
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR113" href="#CR113">113</a>
     </span>.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p id="Par64">Total System Throughput (t·km
     <span class="sup">−2</span>·year
     <span class="sup">−1</span>) (TST), which estimates the total flows in the ecosystem and is a measure of ecosystem size
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR115" href="#CR115">115</a>
     </span>.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p id="Par65">Finn’s Cycling Index (FCI, %), which represents the proportion of the TST that is recycled in the system and is an indicator of stress and structural differences
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR116" href="#CR116">116</a>
     </span>.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p id="Par66">Path length (PL), defined as the average number of compartments through which a unit of inflow passes, which is an indicator of stress
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR117" href="#CR117">117</a>
     </span>.
    </p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
