<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Common patterns of future scenarios</div>
 <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In general, primary producers increased in most of the scenarios (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>). This can be attributed to the decrease of zooplanktonic groups in most of the scenarios (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>), which is due to increased predation on these groups. Alien invertebrates decreased in scenarios that only fishing reductions were applied while increasing in the other scenarios (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>). This can be attributed to increasing predation and decreasing predation and competition, respectively. Alien fishes increased in all scenarios due to reductions of competition and predators except in Scn2 (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>), where there is a large decrease in earlier alien demersal fishes attributed to higher predation rates (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). New alien demersal fishes increased in all the scenarios, which may due to fishing reductions and/or the decrease of competition (both native and alien groups). Native fishes decreased in all scenarios except those scenarios where only fishing reductions were applied (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). Specifically, small native demersal fishes decreased in all scenarios. This general pattern is due to unfavorable thermal conditions, while for specific scenarios we can add increasing predation (fishing reductions) and competition for resources (alien species scenarios) or both (cumulative scenarios) as the main drivers of the ecological patterns. Vulnerable species increased in all scenarios that implied reductions in fishing activities (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>), although sea birds decreased in all scenarios (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
