<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cumulative scenarios</div>
 <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When assessing the cumulative effects of new Israeli fishing regulations and an intermediate scenario of an increase in SST, while alien species biomass was not forced (Scn9), the model projected biomass increases for native invertebrates, alien groups (both invertebrates and fishes) and vulnerable species, while the biomass of native fishes (both demersal and pelagic) significantly decreased (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>). For specific groups, the biomass of some significantly increased such as alien shrimps and crabs, goatfishes, new alien demersal fishes, demersal sharks, rays and skates, and turtles (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). In addition, significant increases were observed for hake, large demersal fishes and alien lizardfish, but their recoveries were of a lower magnitude than Scn10 due to the limitation of alien prey (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig7">7b,d,f</a>). In fact, hake declined at the end of the simulation due to sea warming (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig7">7b</a>). In contrast, the biomass of small native demersal fishes, earlier alien demersal fishes and sea birds significantly decreased (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). In addition, the model predicted significant declines in mullets and rocky fishes (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig7">7a,c</a>), although they showed better trajectories than Scn10, due to lower impacts of alien species. Alien herbivores also declined (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig7">7e</a>), due to recoveries of predators (both native and alien) (Figure 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S2b</a>).
  <div id="Fig7" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 7</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Comparison between the predicted (solid lines) and observed (dots) time series of biomass (t·km
     <span class="sup">2</span>), and scenarios results for (
     <span class="bold">a</span>) mullets, (
     <span class="bold">b</span>) hake, (
     <span class="bold">c</span>) rocky fishes, (
     <span class="bold">d</span>) large native demersal fishes, (
     <span class="bold">e</span>) alien herbivores and (
     <span class="bold">f</span>) alien lizardfish under different future scenarios of a combination of stressors for the Israeli Mediterranean continental shelf (ICS) ecosystem model for the period 1994–2060. Black line represents historical model predictions and coloured lines represent different scenarios. Shadows represent the 5% and 95% percentiles obtained using the Monte Carlo routine. Scenarios that include forcing of the biomass are not shown.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2018_32666_Fig7_HTML" id="d29e993" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Under this scenario, total biomass, invertebrate biomass, mTLc and mTLco significantly increased, while forage fish and total catch significantly declined (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>). TST and FCI were projected to increase, while PL declined (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">When assessing the cumulative effects of the new Israeli fishing regulations, the intermediate scenario of sea warming and an increase in alien biomass following current trends (Scn10), the model predicted a significant decreasing pattern of native invertebrates and native fishes (both demersal and pelagic), while vulnerable species significantly increased (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>). Several groups that were negatively affected included small native demersal fishes and sea birds (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). In addition, the model predicted a near collapse of mullets (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig7">7a</a>), despite the reduction of fishing effort, and a significant decline of rocky fishes (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig7">7c</a>). In contrast, demersal sharks, rays and skates and turtles significantly increased (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). In addition, hake and large native demersal fishes were predicted to increase (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig7">7b,d</a>), mainly due to reduced fishing effort and a higher abundance of alien prey (Figure 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S2b</a>), although native prey significantly declined and there was negative impact of SST on hake.
 </p>
 <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Within this scenario, forage fish, invertebrate biomass and Kempton’s index significantly decreased, while predatory biomass, total catch and mTLco significantly increased (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>). FCI and PL were projected to decline significantly, while TST increased (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Finally, under the assessment of the cumulative impact of the new Israeli fishing regulations and the intermediate scenario of sea warming, while keeping the biomass of alien species constant (Scn11), the model highlighted the important effects of alien species. For example, native invertebrates increased more than in Scn9 and native fishes decreased less than Scn9 and Scn10 (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>). For specific groups, small native demersal fishes decreased less than Scn9 and Scn10 (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). Hake presented a better trajectory than Scn9 (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig7">7b</a>). This could be due to a less competition for resources with alien lizardfish, which biomass was kept at constant population levels. However, it presented a worst trajectory than Scn10 (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig7">7</a>), which could be due less prey availability. On the other hand, large native demersal fishes presented a worse trajectory than Scn9 and Scn10 (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig7">7d</a>), which could be also due to less prey availability. Mullets and rocky fishes presented similar trajectories than Scn9 (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig7">7a,c</a>), which may be related to similar predation rates and competition for resources in both scenarios.
 </p>
 <p id="Par28" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Within this scenario, ecological indicators presented similar trends to Scn9 (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>). In several cases slightly better trends than Scn9 were observed, such as in forage fish, Kempton’s index, mTLc and mTLco, while total catch and PL presented slightly worse trends than Scn9 (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
