<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec9" sec-type="discussion" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the current context of global change and ecological crisis, there is an increasing demand for approaches that can forecast potential impacts of human stressors, in addition to environmental pressures
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span>. In this study, we used a temporal dynamic food web model for the Israeli Mediterranean continental shelf that accounted for different environmental and human impacts, such as sea warming, fisheries and alien species, to assess potential futures of marine resources and ecosystem conditions of the Eastern Mediterranean Sea. Despite several limitations, this study represents to our knowledge the first attempt to evaluate potential impacts of future conditions in the Eastern Mediterranean Sea in an ecosystem context combining different global change stressors.
 </p>
 <p id="Par31" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results highlight that under current conditions (the baseline scenario) several species will remain depleted or even greatly decline, due to unfavourable thermal conditions, increasing impacts of alien species, and unsustainable fishing activities. Meanwhile, alien groups will continue to increase in abundance, as many of these species have higher thermal tolerances. This general degradation of the system is also captured by the decline of ecological indicators linked with ecosystem condition, such as mTLc, mTLco and FCI. These results are in line with Corrales, 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>
  </span>, where results indicated a historical degradation pattern of the food web over the last two decades (1990–2010) due to the impacts of alien species, climate change and fishing. However, other ecological indicators increased, such as total biomass, predatory biomass and PL. This could be due to the fact that reductions of native species in terms of biomass and path lengths are compensated by the increase of alien species.
 </p>
 <p id="Par32" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In contrast, when fishing effort for several fleets was reduced, our results highlighted a potential restoration of several exploited groups including commercially important species such as hake, mullets and large native demersal fishes, and some vulnerable species such as sharks and rays and skates. Alien groups (fish and crustaceans) were negatively impacted, mainly due to the recovery of predators, while native groups were positively affected. This overall improvement of some marine resources was captured by several ecological indicators that showed a trend of increasing values, such as the predatory biomass, Kempton’s Index, mTLc, mTLco and FCI.</p>
 <p id="Par33" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fishing has been identified as one of the main stressors on marine ecosystems
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>
  </span>, and studies have shown the potential benefits of fishing reduction
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>
  </span>. Our results highlighted the benefits of reducing fishing activities on the exploited marine organisms and ecosystem in the Eastern Mediterranean Sea, and support the call for a reduction in fishing capacity and exploitation levels worldwide if marine resources are to recover
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par34" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The scenarios of sea warming showed potential detrimental impacts on the food web, with the impacts becoming greater as temperature increased. Within these scenarios, native species were negatively impacted, and we observed some collapses, while alien species were favoured. In line with this, several ecological indicators, including Kempton’s Index, mTLco and FCI suggested a potential degradation of the ecosystem. Predicted collapses of some native species in this study may not indicate a total collapse of the species in the Eastern Mediterranean Sea, but may indicate that if these species are to persist in the ecosystem, they may have to migrate to northern areas or to deeper and cooler waters outside of the modelled area, or they will have to adapt. Shifts in species distributions (latitudinal and bathymetric) in relation to climate change have been observed and predicted in many areas of the world
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>
  </span>. Bathymetric shifts and species collapses have been observed recently in the study area associated with sea warming and the proliferation of alien species
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>
  </span>. In addition, several studies have predicted important changes in species distributions due to sea warming in the Mediterranean Sea
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">59</a>
  </span>. In fact, the increasing importance of alien species (thermophilic biota) concurrent with sea warming has led to the tropicalization of the Mediterranean biota
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par35" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our projections of the impact of sea warming present some limitations. For example, the temperature response/preferences used in our study are subject to uncertainty, as they came from a global database (AquaMaps)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">60</a>
  </span>, although we did incorporate local knowledge to adapt the global responses to local conditions (see Corrales, 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>
  </span> for more details). In addition, due to the lack of information on the responses to the explanatory variable change, our model did not incorporate salinity, which has been suggested as an important environmental factor in the study area
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">61</a>
  </span>. Also, other impacts of climate change were not considered. For example, ocean acidification, which mainly acts on invertebrates and basal species, can have strong impacts on the food web
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" href="#CR62">62</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">63</a>
  </span>. Furthermore, our model does not account for the possible acclimatization, selection, and adaptation of species to climate change. Correctly predicting the impacts of climate change on marine organisms and ecosystems remains challenging due to a general lack of knowledge about the capacity of organisms to adapt to rapid climate change
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" href="#CR64">64</a>
  </span>. In addition, our model is a temporal-dynamic representation of the ecosystem and does not explicitly incorporate spatial dynamics (such as movement of species) and therefore the potential movement of species to deeper waters or latitudinal (northward) shifts are not captured. Within this context, the new habitat foraging capacity model of the spatial-temporal module of EwE, Ecospace
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" href="#CR65">65</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">66</a>
  </span>, has provided a step forward for temporal-spatial modelling by combining species distribution and food web models. As new information becomes available, our modelling exercise should be updated and improved, so model predictions would become increasingly valuable for understanding cumulative impacts within a spatial-temporal dynamic framework.
 </p>
 <p id="Par36" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results highlighted the potential negative impacts of alien species on marine species and food webs, either when extrapolating current trends to the future, or when allowing EwE to predict their future abundance. Alien species proliferation causes the collapse of small native demersal fishes and a degradation pattern in the food web, as shown by different ecological indicators (i.e., predatory biomass, Kempton’s index, mTLco, FCI and PL). Biological invasions are considered a major threat to local biodiversity
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" href="#CR67">67</a>
  </span>. Although no complete extinctions have yet been reported in the Mediterranean Sea as a direct result of alien species, there are many examples of sudden declines and local extirpations of native species concurrent with the proliferation of alien species
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" href="#CR68">68</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par37" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is important to note that our model has a limited capacity to assess the impacts of alien species. Our study only considers alien fish and crustacean (shrimps and crabs) species, since for other groups no information was available to be considered within our temporal modelling approach
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" href="#CR69">69</a>
  </span>. However, the invasion of other organisms seems to be of the same magnitude or even greater
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" href="#CR69">69</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" href="#CR70">70</a>
  </span>. In addition, the information about pelagic fishes were limited and the definition of small and medium pelagic fishes groups within the model includes both native and alien species
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>
  </span>. Finally, several new alien species have invaded the Eastern Mediterranean Sea in recent years and were not included in the model
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span>. One of these species, the lionfish (
  <span class="italic">Pterois miles</span>), has alarmed the scientific community, arriving in the Mediterranean Sea in 1991
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71" href="#CR71">71</a>
  </span> but not recorded again until 2012
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72" href="#CR72">72</a>
  </span>. This species has had detrimental effects on invaded ecosystems, such as the Caribbean Sea
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73" href="#CR73">73</a>
  </span>. It is expected that the current and future enlargement of the Suez Canal and future sea warming will allow the invasion of more species
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74" href="#CR74">74</a>
  </span>, and that the Eastern Mediterranean Sea can become an extension of the Red Sea in terms of species composition, even including reef building corals
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75" href="#CR75">75</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76" href="#CR76">76</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par38" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Under cumulative stressor scenarios, our study showed that the beneficial effects of fisheries reduction could be dampened by the combined impacts of sea warming and alien species. For example, mullets, hake and predators in general may not recover if sea warming and alien species impacts are also at play. These results highlight the need to include stressors other than fisheries, such as climate change and biological invasions, in the assessment of risk and the implementation of an ecosystem-based management approach to correctly assess the future of marine ecosystems. Serpetti, 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>
  </span>, using an EwE model on the west coast of Scotland, highlighted that ocean warming could jeopardize sustainable fisheries practices in the future. Our results are complementary to this study and suggest that regional and global scale impacts such as biological invasions and sea warming can impair, or at least limit, the outputs of local fisheries management measures.
 </p>
 <p id="Par39" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There is an increasing need to identify and quantify the biophysical thresholds that must not be exceeded, so as to prevent catastrophic shifts in ecosystems. Catastrophic shifts can be defined as persistent and substantial reorganizations of the structure and functioning of ecosystems and from which their recovery is difficult or impossible
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77" href="#CR77">77</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78" href="#CR78">78</a>
  </span>. The boundaries of several processes (e.g., climate change and biodiversity loss) define the “safe operating space” for humanity
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78" href="#CR78">78</a>
  </span>. However, crossing certain boundaries may take the ecosystem beyond its “safe operating space”, where the risk of unpredictable and damaging change is very high. Our results highlighted the fact that a reduction in fishing activities promotes the resilience of some species to climate change and the impacts of alien species in the Eastern Mediterranean Sea, with resilience defined as the capacity of species and ecosystems to resist and absorb disturbance and their ability to recover
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79" href="#CR79">79</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80" href="#CR80">80</a>
  </span>. In addition, some native species reacted better to reduced fishing activities when alien species were maintained at constant levels in the absence and presence of sea warming. However, once a boundary is crossed, a species can collapse. In our study, this is the case for mullets and hake. These species have been severely impacted in recent decades by fishing activities, alien species (goatfishes and alien lizardfish, respectively), and sea warming
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" href="#CR68">68</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81" href="#CR81">81</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83" href="#CR83">83</a>
  </span>. In the cumulative impact scenarios, these functional groups initially benefited from reduced fishing effort. However, once the boundary of thermal tolerance was crossed, mullets and hake decreased notably. When we forced an increase in alien species biomass, in addition to sea warming, mullets collapsed due to the additional effects of predation and competition, while hake biomass remained almost constant due to the higher abundance of prey. Our study illustrates that complex dynamics between environmental and ecological processes may interact in the future and it is essential to take them into account.
 </p>
 <p id="Par40" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In recent decades, human activities have exponentially increased
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span>. These include local stressors such as overfishing, habitat destruction and pollution, and regional and global stressors, such as biological invasions and climate change. Such anthropogenic effects impose large impacts on marine organisms and ecosystems, affecting ecosystem structure and services
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" href="#CR67">67</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84" href="#CR84">84</a>
  </span>. Organisms and ecosystems already stressed by fishing are more vulnerable to further impacts such as climate change and biological invasions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85" href="#CR85">85</a>
  </span>. As temperature will increase in the future and options for the management of ocean warming are limited at the local and regional scale, reducing local and regional threats such as overexploitation and biological invasions, may be one of the solutions to promoting resilience to climate change, ensuring the capacity to exploit marine resources safely and preserving ecosystem functions and services
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86" href="#CR86">86</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par41" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Different management actions have been used for reducing the impacts of fisheries, including, among others, the establishment of catch limits, fishing effort reductions, increasing gear selectivity and the implementation of Marine Protected Areas (MPAs)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87" href="#CR87">87</a>
  </span>. MPAs have been suggested as an effective tool to mitigate impacts of climate change and alien species
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88" href="#CR88">88</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89" href="#CR89">89</a>
  </span>, although biological invasions have been largely disregarded in marine conservation plans
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90" href="#CR90">90</a>
  </span> and the effectiveness of MPAs in preventing invasions has been questioned
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91" href="#CR91">91</a>
  </span>. The prevention of new introductions should be a priority in the development of effective policies, followed by early detection, rapid response and possible eradication of alien species
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92" href="#CR92">92</a>
  </span>. In the context of our study area, some authors have suggested installing an environmental barrier in the Suez Canal, such as an hypersaline lock, since it may “reduce the likelihood of species migration through canals”
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93" href="#CR93">93</a>
  </span>. In fact, “the Suez Canal had, for nearly a century, a natural salinity barrier in the form of the high salinity Bitter Lakes”
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93" href="#CR93">93</a>
  </span>. In addition, although eradication is challenging, some countries have initiated eradication programs to minimize the impacts of alien species in the marine environment. For example, in Cyprus, governmental authorities encouraged fishermen to catch alien poisonous pufferfish (
  <span class="italic">Lagocephalus sceleratus</span>)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94" href="#CR94">94</a>
  </span>, which have detrimental effects on native biota and fisheries
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95" href="#CR95">95</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par42" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ecological indicators are quantitative measurements that provide information about key ecosystem characteristics. They are increasingly used to document ecosystem status and to track the effects of anthropogenic and environmental stressors on marine ecosystems, as well as the effectiveness of management measures; making them a valuable tool within the EBM framework
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96" href="#CR96">96</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98" href="#CR98">98</a>
  </span>. We showed that trophic level-based indicators (mTLc and mTLco) were informative about the effects of fishing pressure, as they decreased in the baseline scenario (high fishing pressure) while increasing in all scenarios where fishing reductions were implemented. However, they exhibited opposite trends in sea warming scenarios. The predatory biomass indicator also indicated potential benefits of fishing restrictions, as well as detrimental impacts of sea warming. In addition, Kempton’s index successfully tracked fishing pressure, sea warming and impacts of alien species. Therefore, our study illustrates how several ecological indicators obtained from EwE models can be useful to assess ecosystem status
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99" href="#CR99">99</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100" href="#CR100">100</a>
  </span>, but they may show complex trends to interpret as additional pressures to marine ecosystems are investigated.
 </p>
</sec>
