<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Integrated Vector Management for Dengue Control</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Dengue (DEN) poses a threat to over 3.9. billion people and its re-emergence has become one of the most serious global health threats (
  <a rid="B29" ref-type="bibr" href="#B29">29</a>). However, the more recent spread of Zika virus infections in the world is a more broadly recognized illustration of the re-emergence of mosquito-borne diseases 
  <span class="bold">(SDG 3)</span>. Driven by ever increasing trade and travel, as well as continuous and progressive urbanization 
  <span class="bold">(SDG11)</span>, and possibly climate change 
  <span class="bold">(SDG 13)</span>, the world has been witnessing an increase in diseases that are mainly transmitted by the yellow fever mosquito 
  <span class="italic">Aedes aegypti</span>, notably DEN, chikungunya (CHIK), and Zika (ZIK). As no effective vaccine or medicine is yet available to prevent or cure DEN, CHIK, and ZIK, disease prevention through vector control is a critical component of disease control, albeit a very challenging one.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Aedes aegypti</span>, which thrives primarily in (sub)tropical climate, is a domesticated mosquito species that feeds almost exclusively on humans (
  <a rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" href="#B30">30</a>). After the female 
  <span class="italic">Ae. aegypti</span> has mated and taken a blood-meal, she searches for an aquatic breeding place to lay her eggs. This species lays her eggs preferably in artificial containers, which are often established in urban settings near human habitation (
  <a rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" href="#B31">31</a>, 
  <a rid="B32" ref-type="bibr" href="#B32">32</a>). 
  <span class="italic">Aedes aegypti</span> lays her eggs against the vertical side of various kinds of water holding containers and the eggs will hatch upon flooding. The eggs can survive several months of drought (
  <a rid="B33" ref-type="bibr" href="#B33">33</a>, 
  <a rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34">34</a>), and become cryptic for control.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The availability and density of artificial containers are important indicators for the presence and size of 
  <span class="italic">Ae. aegypti</span> population in a locality (
  <a rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" href="#B35">35</a>–
  <a rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37">37</a>). Satterthwaite showed that the amount of artificial objects can be linked to socio-economic status (
  <a rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38">38</a>) 
  <span class="bold">(SDG 10)</span>. The level of access to safe and affordable (drinking) water 
  <span class="bold">(SDG 6)</span> is inversely proportional to the presence of water storage systems, such as cisterns or rain barrels that are well-known breeding sites of 
  <span class="italic">Ae. aegypti</span>. Further, in low income areas there is generally more garbage lying around than in high income areas. Random garbage accumulation in a neighborhood can lead to more artificial containers suitable as a breeding ground for 
  <span class="italic">Ae. aegypti</span> (
  <a rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39">39</a>, 
  <a rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40">40</a>) 
  <span class="bold">(SDG 11)</span>. Neighborhood cleanup constitutes not only an important prerequisite for starting other measures of integrated 
  <span class="italic">Aedes</span> management, it is to be expected to have a considerable additional positive impact on the health and well-being of the inhabitants. Waste management needs to play a central role in integrated Aedes management that may include chemical control (
  <span class="bold">SDG12</span>) in addition to physical and social control measures. While Integrated Vector Management is a public task, it relies, in part, on people to take individual responsibilities 
  <span class="bold">(SDG 4)</span>. In temperate areas, the risk of establishment of invasive 
  <span class="bold">(SDG 15)</span>
  <span class="italic">Aedes</span> mosquitoes and the pathogens they carry is increasing, due to climate change 
  <span class="bold">(SDG 13)</span>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In brief, integrated vector management for dengue control involves, at least, seven SDGs other than the entry goal, SDG3. Within these goals, we identified a total of nine specific main targets (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Figure 1</a>). Among these main targets, we recognize eight, all positive, key interactions and suggested an appropriate policy option for each (
  <a rid="T1" ref-type="table" href="#T1">Table 1</a>). The interactions between target 3.3 and 3D with target 4.3, 10.1, and 11.6 are bi-directional, but not symmetrical. The two SDG3 targets affect the latter targets less, compared to how these targets affect the two SDG3 targets. More specifically, preventing 
  <span class="italic">Aedes</span>-borne diseases does positively affect attempts of reaching equity, education and livable cities, but we assessed that education (4.3), poverty reduction (10.1) improving urban waste management (11.6) has a more direct and stronger impact on dengue prevention. A complete overview of main targets, key interactions, scores and policy options to reach integrated vector management for dengue control are provided in 
  <a rid="T1" ref-type="table" href="#T1">Table 1</a>.
 </p>
</sec>
