<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Prevention of Lyme Borreliosis</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Lyme borreliosis is a VBD caused by an infection with the spirochete 
  <span class="italic">Borrelia burgdorferi s.l</span>. In Europe, humans primarily become infected through the bite of the sheep tick 
  <span class="italic">Ixodes ricinus</span>. The transmission cycle of Lyme spirochetes in nature is intricate because, in addition to the tick, it involves several vertebrate host species.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Entering a tick's biotope poses a risk for people since they can acquire a tick bite. To reduce the risk of people acquiring a tick bite, a reduction in either the tick density and/or the exposure is necessary. Understanding, which factors drive tick densities, is an important step in assessing disease risk and formulating intervention strategies (
  <a rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15">15</a>) (
  <span class="bold">SDG3</span>). As 
  <span class="italic">I. ricinus</span> spends almost its entire life in vegetation, temperature and relative humidity are key requirements for its development, survival and activity and determine their geographic distribution. In conclusion, drivers of tick densities comprise both biotic and abiotic elements of a tick's environment. Land use changes (
  <a rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41">41</a>) and climate change has had considerable impact on the ticks northern latitude limit (
  <a rid="B42" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42">42</a>–
  <a rid="B45" ref-type="bibr" href="#B45">45</a>) (
  <span class="bold">SDG13, SDG 15</span>). Each of the three active stages (larva, nymph, and adult) of 
  <span class="italic">I. ricinus</span> seeks a different vertebrate host, attaches, and feeds. The tick detaches when replete and finds a resting place after dropping off the host to digest its blood meal. After this blood meal, ticks molt to the next feeding stage or enter diapause depending on the ambient temperature (
  <a rid="B46" ref-type="bibr" href="#B46">46</a>). Adults are the main life stage feeding on (roe) deer, but juvenile ticks (larvae and nymphs) prefer smaller mammals and birds. Although, to some extent, annual fluctuations in rodent densities affect the densities of nymphs the following year, the (local) presence of propagation hosts, mostly (roe) deer, is often the key factor for the presence of moderate tick densities in forested areas (
  <a rid="B47" ref-type="bibr" href="#B47">47</a>). Nature and forest corridors not only increase connectivity for vertebrates, but also for ticks and the pathogens they carry (
  <span class="bold">SDG 15</span>). When (roe) deer are absent there is a measurable change in abundance of ticks (
  <a rid="B48" ref-type="bibr" href="#B48">48</a>), illustrated by significant tick reduction in larger deer exclosures (
  <a rid="B49" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49">49</a>). Urban green areas have relatively low tick densities but pose a high risk because of the high human exposure. Over decades urban green areas have been expanded to create more space for nature but also to counter urban warming (
  <span class="bold">SDG 13</span>) and to enhance human well-being through access to nature (
  <span class="bold">SDG 11</span>) (
  <a rid="B50" ref-type="bibr" href="#B50">50</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Effective prevention of Lyme borreliosis from nature requires a sector-transcending approach. It requires an expansion of the integral health policy on education programs (
  <span class="bold">SDG 4</span>) with nature policy and nature management (
  <a rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15">15</a>) (
  <span class="bold">SDG 15</span>). This is often inadequate because (the implementation of) these policy areas are located at different administrative levels.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In brief, prevention of Lyme borreliosis involves, at least, four SDGs other than the entry goal, SDG3, comprising a total of eight specific main targets (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Figure 1</a>). Among these main targets, we identified six key interactions and suggested an appropriate policy option for each (
  <a rid="T2" ref-type="table" href="#T2">Table 2</a>). As opposed to the previous example of dengue control, all six key interactions here are unidirectional, in which the three targets of SDG3 are in all cases affected by the identified targets of the other SDGs, but not in reverse. In addition, three of these six interactions are assessed to be negative, including two constraining and one counteracting interaction. A complete overview of main targets, key interactions, scores and policy options to reach prevention of Lyme borreliosis are provided in 
  <a rid="T2" ref-type="table" href="#T2">Table 2</a>.
 </p>
</sec>
