<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="introduction" disp-level="1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">INTRODUCTION</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Black carbon (BC) aerosols, originating from incomplete combustion of fossil fuels and biomass, contribute to the increased rates of warming of the Arctic (
  <a rid="R1" ref-type="bibr" href="#R1">
   <span class="italic">1</span>
  </a>–
  <a rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" href="#R3">
   <span class="italic">3</span>
  </a>). Policy-focused research suggests that collaboration and alliances of even small groups of countries could achieve urgently needed, efficient, rapid, and substantial BC mitigation (
  <a rid="R4" ref-type="bibr" href="#R4">
   <span class="italic">4</span>
  </a>). Atmospheric transport models—fundamental for validation of inventories used in climate policy discussions—have difficulties in accurately reproducing Arctic BC concentrations (
  <a rid="R5" ref-type="bibr" href="#R5">
   <span class="italic">5</span>
  </a>–
  <a rid="R7" ref-type="bibr" href="#R7">
   <span class="italic">7</span>
  </a>). Comparison of model predictions with source-diagnostic observations offers a means to better understand the emissions of BC reaching the Arctic (
  <a rid="R8" ref-type="bibr" href="#R8">
   <span class="italic">8</span>
  </a>–
  <a rid="R10" ref-type="bibr" href="#R10">
   <span class="italic">10</span>
  </a>). Source attributions are challenged both by a lack of observational constraints and by large uncertainties in emission inventories, the latter being a key element for modeling transport and climate effects of BC, specifically in the Arctic (
  <a rid="R8" ref-type="bibr" href="#R8">
   <span class="italic">8</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R11" ref-type="bibr" href="#R11">
   <span class="italic">11</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R12" ref-type="bibr" href="#R12">
   <span class="italic">12</span>
  </a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Observation-based Arctic BC studies are scarce and rarely extend over more than 1 year (
  <a rid="R13" ref-type="bibr" href="#R13">
   <span class="italic">13</span>
  </a>–
  <a rid="R15" ref-type="bibr" href="#R15">
   <span class="italic">15</span>
  </a>), especially with regard to data on source-diagnostic dual-isotopic composition (δ
  <span class="sup">13</span>C and Δ
  <span class="sup">14</span>C). Hereafter, BC is used when referring to model results or the aerosol in general, and elemental carbon [EC; the mass-based BC analog (
  <a rid="R16" ref-type="bibr" href="#R16">
   <span class="italic">16</span>
  </a>)] is used when referring specifically to observational data. The present study provides new year-round δ
  <span class="sup">13</span>C/Δ
  <span class="sup">14</span>C-based source apportionment of EC from the Arctic sites Alert (Canadian High Arctic; 
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 9), Zeppelin (Svalbard; 
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 11), and Barrow (north Alaska; 
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 10), covering a period of ~3 years. To provide a comprehensive circum-Arctic perspective (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Fig. 1</a>), these three records are combined with our recently published studies of EC aerosol concentrations and isotopic signatures from two long-term campaigns from Abisko (northern Scandinavia; 
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 17) (
  <a rid="R7" ref-type="bibr" href="#R7">
   <span class="italic">7</span>
  </a>) and Tiksi (northeast Siberia; 
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 17) (
  <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">
   <span class="italic">17</span>
  </a>) and a winter study (
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 6) from Barrow (
  <a rid="R18" ref-type="bibr" href="#R18">
   <span class="italic">18</span>
  </a>). The 
  <span class="sup">14</span>C/
  <span class="sup">12</span>C isotope ratio of an EC sample allows determination of the biomass burning fraction (
  <span class="italic">f</span>
  <sub>bb</sub>; containing contemporary 
  <span class="sup">14</span>C) relative to the fossil fuel combustion fraction (
  <span class="italic">f</span>
  <sub>fossil;</sub> devoid in 
  <span class="sup">14</span>C) (
  <a rid="R19" ref-type="bibr" href="#R19">
   <span class="italic">19</span>
  </a>). The 
  <span class="sup">13</span>C/
  <span class="sup">12</span>C ratio helps to further distinguish between various types of fossil fuel sources [e.g., natural gas, coal, or oil (
  <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">
   <span class="italic">17</span>
  </a>)]. Last, these observations of atmospheric BC are compared with results from an atmospheric transport model, which includes both anthropogenic and natural-fire BC emissions, and has shown great potential to accurately simulate observational data (
  <a rid="R5" ref-type="bibr" href="#R5">
   <span class="italic">5</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R7" ref-type="bibr" href="#R7">
   <span class="italic">7</span>
  </a>).
 </p>
 <div id="F1" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Annual BC emissions and all circum-Arctic sites from emission inventories.</div>
   <p>The five Arctic stations are marked in red: Abisko (Sweden), Alert (Canada), Barrow (United States), Tiksi (Russia), and Zeppelin (Norway). Emission data in the maps are log scale. (
    <span class="bold">A</span>) Fossil fuel BC emissions (ECLIPSEv5 base year 2010). (
    <span class="bold">B</span>) Biofuel BC emissions (ECLIPSEv5 base year 2010). (
    <span class="bold">C</span>) BC emissions from open fires (GFED4.1s data for observational year 2013).
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="aau8052-F1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
