<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="materials|methods" disp-level="1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">MATERIALS AND METHODS</div>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Experimental design</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A homebuilt high-volume aerosol sampler was used at the Dr. Neil Trivett Global Atmosphere Watch Observatory in Alert, Canada [83.2°N, 62.5°W, 210 m above sea level (masl)] to collect 44 samples between 4 February 2014 and 15 April 2015. The sampler was installed at a walk-up deck, about 4 m above the ground. Flow rate was approximately 1.4 m
   <span class="sup">3</span> min
   <span class="sup">−1</span> at standard temperature and pressure condition. Quartz filters (8 in × 10 in; QFF, Millipore, USA) were sampled continuously with sampling times of 7 days from December to April and 14 days from May to November (with one interruption from 30 April 2014 to 5 May 2014). A total of 10 field blanks (roughly one every month) were collected. After sampling, filters were stored (at room temperature ~20°C) in their sampling cartridges (inside sealed plastic bags) at the Alert station and shipped in aluminum boxes (containing five sampling cartridges each) to Stockholm, where they were transferred into precombusted Al foil and stored at −20°C. Air temperatures and pressures have been recorded and averaged over the integrated sampling time, and both were used for final flow rate and total air volume calculation.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A yearlong sampling campaign was conducted at the Department of Energy Atmospheric Radiation Measurement Climate Research Facility, 7.4 km northeast of the village of Utqiaġvik (formerly known as Barrow), AK (71.3°N, 156.6°W, 11 masl), on the North Slope of Alaska from 16 July 2012 to 4 June 2013. Samples were collected continuously with no exclusion based on local wind direction. The campaign was designed to monitor local and regional influences on ambient concentration and physical properties (i.e., sources from the village of Utqiaġvik were not excluded from the study). Particulate matter with an equivalent aerodynamic diameter less than 10 μm (PM
   <sub>10</sub>) was collected on precombusted QFF (20 cm × 25 cm, Tissuquartz Filters 2500 QAT-UP) using a Tisch high-volume PM
   <sub>10</sub> sampler (TE-6070, Tisch Environmental, Cleves, OH). All samples were stored in aluminum foil packets and Ziploc storage bags in a freezer (−10°C) before and after sampling. Filter blanks were collected at least once a month or when sampler maintenance was conducted. All blanks (
   <span class="italic">n</span> = 15) were handled in the same manner as samples.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">High-volume aerosol samples were collected on the roof of the Zeppelin Observatory, Svalbard, Norway (78.9°N, 11.9°E, 478 masl). Aerosol samples (PM
   <sub>10</sub>) were collected on QFF (8 in × 10 in; Millipore, USA) from 16 June 2012 to 30 December 2013, with two 3-day interruptions. A total of 33 filter samples and 11 blanks were collected. Early summer aerosol concentrations were very low; hence, for isotope analysis, a subset from 15 November 2012 to 30 December 2013 (410 days) was selected (table S7). Filters were kept in precombusted Al foil and stored at −20°C.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This temporary Abisko receptor site was located 10 km east of the village and research station of Abisko in northern Sweden (68.4°N, 19.1°E, 359 masl), as previously described (
   <a rid="R7" ref-type="bibr" href="#R7">
    <span class="italic">7</span>
   </a>). Briefly, samples were collected from 29 September 2011 to 27 March 2013 on precombusted QFF filters (8 in × 10 in; Millipore, USA) using a PM
   <sub>2.5</sub> inlet high-volume sampler (model DH77, Digitel AG) with filter-changing intervals of 12 to 28 days, depending on the season and weather conditions.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Tiksi sampling site, Polar Geocosmophysical Observatory (71.4°N, 128.5°E, 35 masl), is situated ~10 km southwest of the Tiksi settlement, has been in operation since 1958, and is run by permanent technical staff from the Russian Academy of Sciences, as previously described (
   <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">
    <span class="italic">17</span>
   </a>). Aerosol sampling of total suspended particles on precombusted QFF filters (8 in × 10 in; Millipore, USA) was performed continuously for ~24 months (16 April 2012 to 7 March 2014) with sample intervals of 15 to 25 days, depending on the weather conditions.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">EC analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The EC and organic carbon (OC) concentrations were determined by a thermal-optical transmission (TOT) analyzer (instrument #227, Sunset Laboratory, Tigard, OR) using the National Institute for Occupational Safety and Health 5040 protocol (
   <a rid="R34" ref-type="bibr" href="#R34">
    <span class="italic">34</span>
   </a>). This method is known to potentially overcorrect charring fraction relative to other methods and to underestimate the EC content (
   <a rid="R35" ref-type="bibr" href="#R35">
    <span class="italic">35</span>
   </a>–
   <a rid="R39" ref-type="bibr" href="#R39">
    <span class="italic">39</span>
   </a>). During charring, parts of the OC could also end up in the EC fraction in the form of pyrogenic carbon, which would then influence the isotopic composition of the EC fraction. This effect was evaluated by a sensitivity analysis in a previous study, which concluded that the radiocarbon-derived fraction of biomass burning could be overestimated by a maximum of 7%, in extreme cases (
   <a rid="R25" ref-type="bibr" href="#R25">
    <span class="italic">25</span>
   </a>). The detection limit for EC was based on the OC concentration of the field blanks, which had ~100 ng C cm
   <span class="sup">−2</span> OC (this roughly translates to 2 ng C m
   <span class="sup">−3</span> for Zeppelin samples, which had the lowest EC concentrations measured). EC could not be detected in any of the blanks.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Annual mean concentrations were calculated as
   <div id="E1" class="disp-formula">
    <div id="m1" class="math">
     <div class="mrow">
      <div class="mrow">
       <div accent="true" class="mover">
        <span class="mtext">EC</span>
        <span stretchy="true" class="mo">¯</span>
       </div>
       <span class="mo">=</span>
       <div class="mfrac">
        <div class="mrow">
         <div displaystyle="true" class="mstyle">
          <div class="msubsup">
           <span stretchy="true" class="mo">∑</span>
           <div class="mrow">
            <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">i</span>
            <span class="mo">=</span>
            <span class="mn">1</span>
           </div>
           <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">n</span>
          </div>
         </div>
         <span class="mtext">EC</span>
         <span stretchy="false" class="mo">(</span>
         <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">i</span>
         <span stretchy="false" class="mo">)</span>
         <span class="mo">⋅</span>
         <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">V</span>
         <span stretchy="false" class="mo">(</span>
         <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">i</span>
         <span stretchy="false" class="mo">)</span>
        </div>
        <div class="mrow">
         <div displaystyle="true" class="mstyle">
          <div class="msubsup">
           <span stretchy="true" class="mo">∑</span>
           <div class="mrow">
            <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">i</span>
            <span class="mo">=</span>
            <span class="mn">1</span>
           </div>
           <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">n</span>
          </div>
         </div>
         <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">V</span>
         <span stretchy="false" class="mo">(</span>
         <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">i</span>
         <span stretchy="false" class="mo">)</span>
        </div>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
    <span class="label">(1)</span>
   </div>where EC is the EC concentration unit (ng C m
   <span class="sup">−3</span>), 
   <span class="italic">V</span> is the volume collected for the respective aerosol filter sample, and 
   <span class="italic">i</span> is the sample index.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Carbon isotope analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Before analysis, the filter samples were acid-fumigated with 12 M HCl (inside a desiccator for 24 hours and subsequently dried at 60°C for 1 hour) to remove carbonates and to prevent their charring effect during pyrolysis (
   <a rid="R19" ref-type="bibr" href="#R19">
    <span class="italic">19</span>
   </a>, 
   <a rid="R25" ref-type="bibr" href="#R25">
    <span class="italic">25</span>
   </a>). The EC fraction, generated through the TOT analyzer, was isolated after CO
   <sub>2</sub> conversion and cryogenically trapped using a modified Sunset Laboratory instrument (
   <a rid="R40" ref-type="bibr" href="#R40">
    <span class="italic">40</span>
   </a>). Offline analysis of the carbon isotopes was conducted using accelerator mass spectrometry (AMS) at the U.S. National Science Foundation National Ocean Science Accelerator Mass Spectrometry (NOSAMS) facility (Woods Hole, MA) (
   <a rid="R41" ref-type="bibr" href="#R41">
    <span class="italic">41</span>
   </a>, 
   <a rid="R42" ref-type="bibr" href="#R42">
    <span class="italic">42</span>
   </a>). The six Barrow winter samples from Barrett 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>. (
   <a rid="R18" ref-type="bibr" href="#R18">
    <span class="italic">18</span>
   </a>) were prepped for radiocarbon analysis using a previous EC isolation method. In this method, the TOT analyzer parameters were truncated to preserve EC on the filter samples rather than being combusted to CO
   <sub>2</sub>. This preserved EC was then sent to NOSAMS, where it was combusted to CO
   <sub>2</sub> and analyzed using the AMS method mentioned above.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The relative contributions of EC to biomass burning 
   <span class="italic">f</span>
   <sub>bb</sub> and fossil fuel combustion (
   <span class="italic">f</span>
   <sub>fossil</sub> = 1 − 
   <span class="italic">f</span>
   <sub>bb</sub>) were calculated using an isotopic mass balance equation (
   <a rid="R19" ref-type="bibr" href="#R19">
    <span class="italic">19</span>
   </a>)
   <div id="E2" class="disp-formula">
    <div id="m2" class="math">
     <div class="mrow">
      <div class="mrow">
       <div class="msup">
        <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">Δ</span>
        <span class="mn">14</span>
       </div>
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">C</span>
       <span class="mo">=</span>
       <div class="msup">
        <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">Δ</span>
        <span class="mn">14</span>
       </div>
       <div class="msub">
        <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">C</span>
        <span class="mtext">bb</span>
       </div>
       <div class="msub">
        <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">f</span>
        <span class="mtext">bb</span>
       </div>
       <span class="mo">+</span>
       <div class="msup">
        <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">Δ</span>
        <span class="mn">14</span>
       </div>
       <div class="msub">
        <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">C</span>
        <div class="mrow">
         <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">f</span>
         <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">o</span>
         <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">s</span>
         <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">s</span>
         <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">i</span>
         <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">l</span>
        </div>
       </div>
       <span stretchy="false" class="mo">(</span>
       <span class="mn">1</span>
       <span class="mo">−</span>
       <div class="msub">
        <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">f</span>
        <span class="mtext">bb</span>
       </div>
       <span stretchy="false" class="mo">)</span>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
    <span class="label">(2)</span>
   </div>where Δ
   <span class="sup">14</span>C represents the radiocarbon signature in the sample, Δ
   <span class="sup">14</span>C
   <sub>bb</sub> is the endmember of the contemporary radiocarbon, and Δ
   <span class="sup">14</span>C
   <sub>fossil</sub> is −1000‰ by definition, as fossil carbon is completely devoid of 
   <span class="sup">14</span>C. The contemporary radiocarbon signature (Δ
   <span class="sup">14</span>C
   <sub>bb</sub>) depends on the biomass type, age, and year of harvest. Current monthly mean Δ
   <span class="sup">14</span>CO
   <sub>2</sub> signatures are below 30‰ (
   <a rid="R43" ref-type="bibr" href="#R43">
    <span class="italic">43</span>
   </a>). In case of the Eurasian Arctic stations (Abisko, Tiksi, and Zeppelin) and Alert, an endmember of +225 ± 60‰ is suggested, representing typical Northern tree species (
   <a rid="R25" ref-type="bibr" href="#R25">
    <span class="italic">25</span>
   </a>), the most common form of biomass burning fuel. Because of the different source origins (North America), the Δ
   <span class="sup">14</span>C endmember used to determine contemporary carbon contributions for the Barrow station was +107.5 ± 50‰ based on wood burning for temperate regions in 2010 (
   <a rid="R18" ref-type="bibr" href="#R18">
    <span class="italic">18</span>
   </a>, 
   <a rid="R44" ref-type="bibr" href="#R44">
    <span class="italic">44</span>
   </a>). These conservative estimates for endmember uncertainty took count of biomass burning sources other than wood [e.g., agricultural waste burning (AWB)] and introduced an additional 
   <span class="italic">f</span>
   <sub>bb</sub> variability of &lt;5%.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Yearly annual mean of the fraction of biomass burning (EC mass-weighted 
   <span class="italic">f</span>
   <sub>bb</sub>) was calculated as
   <div id="E3" class="disp-formula">
    <div id="m3" class="math">
     <div class="mrow">
      <div class="mrow">
       <div accent="true" class="mover">
        <div class="mrow">
         <div class="msub">
          <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">f</span>
          <span class="mtext">bb</span>
         </div>
        </div>
        <span stretchy="true" class="mo">¯</span>
       </div>
       <span class="mo">=</span>
       <div class="mfrac">
        <div class="mrow">
         <div displaystyle="true" class="mstyle">
          <div class="msubsup">
           <span stretchy="true" class="mo">∑</span>
           <div class="mrow">
            <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">i</span>
            <span class="mo">=</span>
            <span class="mn">1</span>
           </div>
           <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">n</span>
          </div>
         </div>
         <div class="msub">
          <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">f</span>
          <span class="mtext">bb</span>
         </div>
         <span stretchy="false" class="mo">(</span>
         <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">i</span>
         <span stretchy="false" class="mo">)</span>
         <span class="mo">⋅</span>
         <span class="mtext">EC</span>
         <span stretchy="false" class="mo">(</span>
         <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">i</span>
         <span stretchy="false" class="mo">)</span>
         <span class="mo">⋅</span>
         <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">V</span>
         <span stretchy="false" class="mo">(</span>
         <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">i</span>
         <span stretchy="false" class="mo">)</span>
        </div>
        <div class="mrow">
         <div displaystyle="true" class="mstyle">
          <div class="msubsup">
           <span stretchy="true" class="mo">∑</span>
           <div class="mrow">
            <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">i</span>
            <span class="mo">=</span>
            <span class="mn">1</span>
           </div>
           <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">n</span>
          </div>
         </div>
         <span class="mtext">EC</span>
         <span stretchy="false" class="mo">(</span>
         <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">i</span>
         <span stretchy="false" class="mo">)</span>
         <span class="mo">⋅</span>
         <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">V</span>
         <span stretchy="false" class="mo">(</span>
         <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">i</span>
         <span stretchy="false" class="mo">)</span>
        </div>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
    <span class="label">(3)</span>
   </div>where EC is the EC concentration, 
   <span class="italic">V</span> the volume collected for the respective sample, and 
   <span class="italic">i</span> is the sample index.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Pooling of samples for isotopic analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Pooling was a necessity to enable year-round radiocarbon analysis, in terms of the collection of enough carbon material, complete the laboratory work in a reasonable time, and stay within a reasonable budget (due to rather costly AMS analysis). A subset of 43 Alert samples (12 February 2014 and 15 April 2015) was pooled into nine composites, considering season and previously analyzed composites at Tiksi (to get two data points of identical start and stop dates). Samples were pooled to achieve 40 to 80 μg of EC, with volume normalized mass from each sample.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Multiple PM
   <sub>10</sub> samples from Barrow were pooled for radiocarbon analysis. This pooling was accomplished considering season and source region. Samples from the same seasons and source regions (Russian Arctic, Canadian Arctic, Arctic Ocean, and interior Alaska) were composited (based on HYSPLIT back-trajectory analysis). Samples were pooled to achieve 60 μg of EC, with volume normalized mass from each sample.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The 24 Zeppelin filters collected during 15 November 2012 and 30 December 2013 were pooled into 11 composites (
   <a rid="R7" ref-type="bibr" href="#R7">
    <span class="italic">7</span>
   </a>). None of the stable carbon data could be obtained; hence, only Δ
   <span class="sup">14</span>C data were reported. Samples were pooled to achieve 40 μg of EC, with volume normalized mass from each sample.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All Abisko samples were pooled into 17 composites/samples. Higher temporal resolution was chosen during Arctic Haze seasons (winter/spring), and lower resolution was chosen for the summer months, as previously described (
   <a rid="R7" ref-type="bibr" href="#R7">
    <span class="italic">7</span>
   </a>). The 17 Tiksi composites were pooled with emphasis on higher temporal resolution during the Arctic haze period, as previously described (
   <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">
    <span class="italic">17</span>
   </a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">FLEXPART-ECLIPSE-GFED model</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the bottom-up estimates of the BC concentrations, the FLEXPART-ECLIPSE-GFED (FEG) model was used, consisting of the atmospheric dispersion model FLEXPART (
   <a rid="R28" ref-type="bibr" href="#R28">
    <span class="italic">28</span>
   </a>, 
   <a rid="R45" ref-type="bibr" href="#R45">
    <span class="italic">45</span>
   </a>), coupled to the ECLIPSE (
   <a rid="R12" ref-type="bibr" href="#R12">
    <span class="italic">12</span>
   </a>) emission inventory and satellite-based open fire emissions by GFED (
   <a rid="R29" ref-type="bibr" href="#R29">
    <span class="italic">29</span>
   </a>). FLEXPART version 9.2 was run in backward mode for the same location and time periods over which the measurements were taken. A logarithmic size distribution with mean particulate diameters of 250 nm was used, with a logarithmic SD of 1.25. Simulations extended over 20 days back in time, which is sufficient to include most emissions injected into an air mass arriving at the station, given a typical BC lifetime of roughly 1 week. The simulations used meteorological analysis data from the ECMWF at a resolution of 1° × 1° latitude/longitude. Data in the summer and fall of 2013 were missing due to ECMWF’s increase of vertical model resolution on 25 June 2013. FLEXPART accounts for dry deposition and wet scavenging, differentiating between below-cloud and in-cloud scavenging. Anthropogenic BC emissions were received from the ECLIPSE version 5 emission inventory (
   <a rid="R12" ref-type="bibr" href="#R12">
    <span class="italic">12</span>
   </a>), which is based on the GAINS (greenhouse gas–air pollution interactions and synergies) model (
   <a rid="R46" ref-type="bibr" href="#R46">
    <span class="italic">46</span>
   </a>). The emissions were available at yearly resolution for the various source types and, in addition, contained an explicit split between biofuel (modern) and fossil fuel emissions.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To estimate the biomass burning contribution from open fires (including wildfires and AWB), the most recent version (4.1s) of GFED was applied (
   <a rid="R29" ref-type="bibr" href="#R29">
    <span class="italic">29</span>
   </a>). This satellite-based emission inventory was used with monthly resolution, and the spatial resolution was changed from 0.25° to 0.5° to match ECLIPSE’s resolution. Emissions from wildfires were not accounted for by the ECLIPSE model. However, AWB is included in ECLIPSE as biofuel. Hence, the AWB fraction of ECLIPSE was removed to avoid double counting.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The yearly mean 
   <span class="italic">f</span>
   <sub>bb</sub> for the available FEG data was calculated as
   <div id="E4" class="disp-formula">
    <div id="m4" class="math">
     <div class="mrow">
      <div class="mrow">
       <div accent="true" class="mover">
        <div class="mrow">
         <div class="msub">
          <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">f</span>
          <span class="mtext">bb</span>
         </div>
        </div>
        <span stretchy="true" class="mo">¯</span>
       </div>
       <span class="mo">=</span>
       <div class="mfrac">
        <div class="mrow">
         <div displaystyle="true" class="mstyle">
          <div class="msubsup">
           <span stretchy="true" class="mo">∑</span>
           <span class="mn">1</span>
           <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">n</span>
          </div>
         </div>
         <div class="msub">
          <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">f</span>
          <span class="mtext">bb</span>
         </div>
         <span stretchy="false" class="mo">(</span>
         <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">i</span>
         <span stretchy="false" class="mo">)</span>
         <span class="mo">⋅</span>
         <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">t</span>
         <span stretchy="false" class="mo">(</span>
         <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">i</span>
         <span stretchy="false" class="mo">)</span>
         <span class="mo">⋅</span>
         <span class="mtext">BC</span>
         <span stretchy="false" class="mo">(</span>
         <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">i</span>
         <span stretchy="false" class="mo">)</span>
        </div>
        <div class="mrow">
         <div displaystyle="true" class="mstyle">
          <div class="msubsup">
           <span stretchy="true" class="mo">∑</span>
           <span class="mn">1</span>
           <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">n</span>
          </div>
         </div>
         <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">t</span>
         <span stretchy="false" class="mo">(</span>
         <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">i</span>
         <span stretchy="false" class="mo">)</span>
         <span class="mo">⋅</span>
         <span class="mtext">BC</span>
         <span stretchy="false" class="mo">(</span>
         <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">i</span>
         <span stretchy="false" class="mo">)</span>
        </div>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
    <span class="label">(4)</span>
   </div>where 
   <span class="italic">f</span>
   <sub>bb</sub> is the model-based fraction of biomass burning BC, BC is the BC concentration, 
   <span class="italic">t</span> is the sampling time for the respective sample, and 
   <span class="italic">i</span> is the sample index. The model-derived 
   <span class="italic">f</span>
   <sub>bb</sub> contains all contemporary fuels (i.e., biofuels, wildfires, and AWB).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The total number of samples and composites are mentioned in each respective section and in the Supplementary Materials for all observatories. The coefficients of determination (
   <span class="italic">R</span>
   <span class="sup">2</span>) used in this work are from linear regression to compare model and observation results. 
   <span class="italic">P</span> values are also reported in the figures, where applicable, and can be evaluated on a case-by-case basis.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
