<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Model performance</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A Lagrangian atmospheric transport model [FLEXible PARTicle dispersion model (FLEXPART) (
  <a rid="R28" ref-type="bibr" href="#R28">
   <span class="italic">28</span>
  </a>)], based on an anthropogenic emission inventory [Evaluating the Climate and Air Quality Impacts of Short-Lived Pollutants (ECLIPSE) (
  <a rid="R12" ref-type="bibr" href="#R12">
   <span class="italic">12</span>
  </a>)] and an open fire emissions inventory [Global Fire Emissions Database (GFED) (
  <a rid="R29" ref-type="bibr" href="#R29">
   <span class="italic">29</span>
  </a>)], was used to simulate BC concentrations at the five measurement sites, enabling the investigation of BC’s geographical origins (fig. S1). Furthermore, simulated BC concentrations were split into anthropogenic (biofuel or fossil fuel) and natural (open fires and wildfires) contributions. There were observation model offsets, with both over- and underestimation in model predictions relative to the observations—both in BC concentrations and especially in the BC source apportionment (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F4" href="#F4">Fig. 4</a>, A to F) (
  <a rid="R7" ref-type="bibr" href="#R7">
   <span class="italic">7</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">
   <span class="italic">17</span>
  </a>). The model performed better for fossil fuel–BC concentrations than for biomass burning–BC (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F4" href="#F4">Fig. 4</a>, G and H). Better performance was achieved for sites (Abisko, Alert, and Barrow) with fully overlapping model and observational data coverage, and where no clear influence of local emissions was observed. The influence of missing local emissions and relatively large discrepancies for BC sources (i.e., fossil fuel versus biomass burning; 
  <span class="italic">f</span>
  <sub>bb</sub>), but otherwise well-simulated BC concentrations, suggests large uncertainties for geographical allocation (i.e., misallocation) and composition of BC sources in the emission inventories. In addition to uncertain emissions, the transport of BC into the deep Arctic is a difficult process to model because it involves complex interactions of dry deposition and precipitation scavenging as well as diabatic transport in the low sunlit Arctic with a strong surface-based inversion (
  <a rid="R5" ref-type="bibr" href="#R5">
   <span class="italic">5</span>
  </a>). The difference between Barrow and other Arctic sites also indicates the importance of accurately modeling orographic impacts on surface concentrations. If global transport models with larger grid sizes (2.5° × 2.5°) are used to simulate regional transport over complex terrain like the Brooks Range, the model will be biased high unless nested grids are incorporated to capture dilution during uplift (
  <a rid="R30" ref-type="bibr" href="#R30">
   <span class="italic">30</span>
  </a>). For example, a recent global-scale GEOS-Chem modeling study suggested high biomass burning contributions for Barrow in the summer; however, parallel measurements did not reflect a similarly large increase in surface BC concentrations (
  <a rid="R27" ref-type="bibr" href="#R27">
   <span class="italic">27</span>
  </a>). There may also be local influence from nearby Utqiaġvik. However, the model skill was influenced by the projected geographical origin of BC, showing better agreement for European sources (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Fig. 5</a>).
 </p>
 <div id="F4" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Alert, Barrow, Zeppelin, and BC of fossil versus BC of biomass burning.</div>
   <p>(
    <span class="bold">A</span> to 
    <span class="bold">F</span>) Observation (black line) and model (red line). EC is used synonymous to BC. Horizontal bars indicate sampling duration. Vertical error bars show observational uncertainties (1 SD). (A) Alert BC concentrations. (B) Alert fraction biomass burning. (C) Zeppelin BC concentrations. (D) Zeppelin fraction biomass burning. (E) Barrow BC concentrations. Data from Barret 
    <span class="italic">et al</span>. (
    <a rid="R18" ref-type="bibr" href="#R18">
     <span class="italic">18</span>
    </a>) are marked with a white asterisk. (F) Barrow fraction biomass burning. Data from Barret 
    <span class="italic">et al</span>. (
    <a rid="R18" ref-type="bibr" href="#R18">
     <span class="italic">18</span>
    </a>) are marked with a white asterisk. The linear fit (
    <span class="italic">R</span>
    <span class="sup">2</span>) and 
    <span class="italic">P</span> value between model and observation are shown in each respective panel. (
    <span class="bold">G</span> and 
    <span class="bold">H</span>) From light to dark: Abisko (squares), Alert (diamonds), Barrow (circles), Tiksi (upward triangles), and Zeppelin (downward triangles). The linear fits (
    <span class="italic">R</span>
    <span class="sup">2</span>) and 
    <span class="italic">P</span> values between mode and observation are shown for all stations in each respective panel. (G) BC fossil (fuel) concentrations are the product of 1 − 
    <span class="italic">f</span>
    <sub>bb</sub> and BC concentration. (H) BC biomass (burning) is the product of 
    <span class="italic">f</span>
    <sub>bb</sub> times BC concentration.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="aau8052-F4" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <div id="F5" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 5</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Model versus observation.</div>
   <p>From light to dark: Abisko (squares), Alert (diamonds), Barrow (circles), Tiksi (upward triangles), and Zeppelin (downward triangles). The linear fits (
    <span class="italic">R</span>
    <span class="sup">2</span>) and 
    <span class="italic">P</span> values for EC and BC are replicated in each panel. The color bar (and gray shaded symbols) represents the fraction of simulated anthropogenic sources (fossil fuel and biofuel) by continent, separated in the three panels. (
    <span class="bold">A</span>) Mass fraction of simulated BC from (North) American sources. (
    <span class="bold">B</span>) Mass fraction of simulated BC from Asian sources. (
    <span class="bold">C</span>) Mass fraction of simulated BC from European sources. (
    <span class="bold">D</span> to 
    <span class="bold">F</span>) Biomass burning fraction of EC, based on radiocarbon measurements versus biomass burning fraction based on FEG model simulations. The linear fits (
    <span class="italic">R</span>
    <span class="sup">2</span>) and 
    <span class="italic">P</span> values for fraction biomass burning from observation (Δ
    <span class="sup">14</span>C) and model (FEG) are replicated in each panel. The color bar (and gray shaded symbols) represents the fraction of simulated anthropogenic sources (fossil fuel and biofuel) by continent, separated in the three panels. (D) Mass fraction of simulated BC from (North) American sources. (E) Mass fraction of simulated BC from Asian sources. (F) Mass fraction of simulated BC from European sources.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="aau8052-F5" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
