<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Combustion sources apportioned by stable carbon isotopes</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition to radiocarbon data, the stable carbon isotopic ratio (δ
  <span class="sup">13</span>C) provides additional insight into source apportionment, especially between different fossil fuel source classes (i.e., coal versus liquid fossil fuel versus gas flaring). Liquid fossil fuel sources can be further deconvoluted with δ
  <span class="sup">13</span>C-EC fingerprinting. EC emissions of Russian origin are more depleted in 
  <span class="sup">13</span>C compared to emissions of Chinese and western European (“regular”) liquid fossil fuels (
  <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">
   <span class="italic">17</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R25" ref-type="bibr" href="#R25">
   <span class="italic">25</span>
  </a>). The most δ
  <span class="sup">13</span>C-depleted annual signature of EC was found in Tiksi, followed by Alert, Barrow, and Abisko (
  <a rid="T1" ref-type="table" href="#T1">Table 1</a>; no δ
  <span class="sup">13</span>C data are available for Zeppelin due to low carbon content). Alert and Tiksi had the narrowest δ
  <span class="sup">13</span>C SD (both ±0.8‰; 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F3" href="#F3">Fig. 3</a>), with a wider SD for Abisko and Barrow (roughly ±1.5‰). Taking into account the uncertainty of the potential sources, distributions smaller than 1‰ can be considered narrow, as the “pure” fossil endmembers (e.g., coal) have an uncertainty range of 1 to 1.8‰; the endmember range for gas flaring is more uncertain (±3‰) (
  <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">
   <span class="italic">17</span>
  </a>). Although narrow ranges in annual δ
  <span class="sup">13</span>C point to well-mixed air masses arriving at a site, influence from local point sources cannot be excluded. Point-source signals are difficult to detect, because of the long consecutive sampling times that had to be used in this study to allow collection of enough carbon material to enable radiocarbon analysis. For the 2 years of Tiksi observations, only spring 2013 showed a clear influence from local liquid fossil fuel emissions of Russian origin (
  <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">
   <span class="italic">17</span>
  </a>). This finding is essential, because significant fossil fuel emissions appear to be absent in the emission inventory within a large radius from Tiksi (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Fig. 1A</a>). In contrast to the radiocarbon data, no distinct seasonality for stable isotopic EC signatures was observed for the circum-Arctic. Gas flaring, which is mostly of Russian origin (
  <a rid="R12" ref-type="bibr" href="#R12">
   <span class="italic">12</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R26" ref-type="bibr" href="#R26">
   <span class="italic">26</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R27" ref-type="bibr" href="#R27">
   <span class="italic">27</span>
  </a>) and was suggested earlier to be a major source of the Arctic BC surface concentration (
  <a rid="R26" ref-type="bibr" href="#R26">
   <span class="italic">26</span>
  </a>), did not appear to be abundant during the observed periods and under the given limitations of the current gas-flaring isotopic endmember (text S1) (
  <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">
   <span class="italic">17</span>
  </a>).
 </p>
 <div id="F3" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Multidimensional source apportionment plot of the Δ
    <span class="sup">14</span>C versus δ
    <span class="sup">13</span>C isotopic signature of samples from all stations.
   </div>
   <p>The colored squares show the endmember ranges for the different EC sources of biomass burning (green) and the fossil fuels: gas flaring (blue), liquid fossil fuels of Russian origin (brown), liquid fossil fuels of “regular” (defined as American, Chinese, and western European emission) origin (dark cyan), and coal (black). Data from Barret 
    <span class="italic">et al</span>. (
    <a rid="R18" ref-type="bibr" href="#R18">
     <span class="italic">18</span>
    </a>) are marked with a black asterisk. From light to dark coloring: Abisko, Alert, Barrow, Tiksi, and Zeppelin. The degree of shading in the circles indicates the EC concentration for each sample (right shading bar). The areas of the circles indicate the sampling time in days from 1 to 120. Samples for which no δ
    <span class="sup">13</span>C data were available (e.g., all Zeppelin data) are placed on the 
    <span class="italic">y</span> axis. Uncertainties and error bars are not shown (can be received from tables in the Supplementary Materials) and are smaller than the diameter of the circles.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="aau8052-F3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
