<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="results" disp-level="1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">RESULTS</div>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">BC concentrations</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All sites displayed a seasonal pattern of low EC concentrations in summer (July to September) and higher concentrations during the rest of the year, peaking in the winter/spring “Arctic haze” (
   <a rid="R20" ref-type="bibr" href="#R20">
    <span class="italic">20</span>
   </a>) period (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">Fig. 2</a>). Annual averages (
   <a rid="T1" ref-type="table" href="#T1">Table 1</a>) were relatively uniform and resulted in an EC value for the circum-Arctic of 28 ± 24 ng C m
   <span class="sup">−3</span>. The observed differences in EC concentrations from one site to the other occur because of different proximity to EC sources, site specificity for various types of carbonaceous sources, and differences in aerosol lifetime. The latter is affected by many factors, including differences in size and mixing state of primary aerosols, air mass transport pathways, wet and dry deposition during transport, and orography of the terrain (
   <a rid="R21" ref-type="bibr" href="#R21">
    <span class="italic">21</span>
   </a>). However, some shorter periods were observed where some of the stations had very similar EC concentrations (table S1). In winter, when BC emissions are increased, differences in BC sources between sites are more pronounced, removal processes are least effective, and transport patterns differ from summer conditions (
   <a rid="R22" ref-type="bibr" href="#R22">
    <span class="italic">22</span>
   </a>); all these factors combine to generate larger local differences in Arctic haze concentration in winter months.
  </p>
  <div id="F2" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <div class="title">Circum-Arctic EC observations between 2011 and 2015.</div>
    <p>From light to dark: Abisko (squares), Alert (upward triangles), Barrow (downward triangles), Tiksi (diamonds), and Zeppelin (circles). Horizontal bars (black) indicate sampling duration. Vertical error bars show observational uncertainties (1 SD). Data from Barret 
     <span class="italic">et al</span>. (
     <a rid="R18" ref-type="bibr" href="#R18">
      <span class="italic">18</span>
     </a>) are marked with white asterisks. (
     <span class="bold">A</span>) EC concentrations. Notice that one high-EC sample from Tiksi (~300 ng C m
     <span class="sup">−3</span>) is off-chart. (
     <span class="bold">B</span>) EC source apportionment expressed as fraction of biomass burning of EC.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="aau8052-F2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <div id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Table 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <div class="title">Annual observational data (selected period) for the Arctic observatories.</div>
    <p>EC concentrations and SDs are volume-weighted, whereas the fraction that is biomass burning (
     <span class="italic">f</span>
     <sub>bb</sub>) and δ
     <span class="sup">13</span>C values (and their SDs) are mass-weighted. For the Arctic mean, a value is given without Barrow due to the shorter (less than one full year) period of the data coverage (table S5).
    </p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <col width="%" span="1"/>
    <col width="%" span="1"/>
    <col width="%" span="1"/>
    <col width="%" span="1"/>
    <col width="%" span="1"/>
    <col width="%" span="1"/>
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
       <span class="bold">Site</span>
      </td>
      <td valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
       <span class="bold">(DD/MM/YY)</span>
      </td>
      <td valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
       <span class="bold">Days</span>
      </td>
      <td valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
       <span class="bold">EC (ng/m
        <span class="sup">3</span>)
       </span>
      </td>
      <td valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
       <span class="bold">
        <span class="italic">f</span>
        <sub>bb</sub> (−)
       </span>
      </td>
      <td valign="top" align="center" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
       <span class="bold">δ
        <span class="sup">13</span>C (‰)
       </span>
      </td>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Alert</td>
      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">05/03/14 to 18/03/2015</td>
      <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">371</td>
      <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36 ± 28</td>
      <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40 ± 0.05</td>
      <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−27.9 ± 0.8</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Abisko</td>
      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20/12/11 to 19/12/12</td>
      <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">363</td>
      <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27 ± 32</td>
      <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.42 ± 0.14</td>
      <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−26.3 ± 1.4</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Barrow</td>
      <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16/07/12 to 04/06/13 (not continuous)</td>
      <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">224</td>
      <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25 ± 20</td>
      <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15 ± 0.13</td>
      <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−27.5 ± 1.5</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tiksi</td>
      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27/02/13 to 07/03/14</td>
      <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">373</td>
      <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38 ± 29</td>
      <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30 ± 0.17</td>
      <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−28.4 ± 0.8</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Zeppelin</td>
      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15/11/12 to 22/11/13</td>
      <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">370</td>
      <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12 ± 11</td>
      <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41 ± 0.09</td>
      <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arctic</td>
      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All above</td>
      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
      <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28 ± 24</td>
      <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29 ± 0.16</td>
      <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−26.8 ± 1.6</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arctic</td>
      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Without Barrow</td>
      <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
      <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31 ± 27</td>
      <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39 ± 0.10</td>
      <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−27.0 ± 1.2</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
  </div>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fossil fuel and biomass burning sources from radiocarbon</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All stations exhibited clear seasonality in BC sources, with a dominant contribution from fossil fuel–based emissions (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">Fig. 2</a>). The annual mean radiocarbon-based “fraction biomass burning” (
   <span class="italic">f</span>
   <sub>bb</sub> = 1 – “fraction fossil fuel”) of EC for the circum-Arctic was 39 ± 10%, excluding Barrow, for which there exists less than a full year’s coverage, and 29 ± 16% including Barrow. The 
   <span class="italic">f</span>
   <sub>bb</sub> values for the single sites ranged from 15 to 42% (
   <a rid="T1" ref-type="table" href="#T1">Table 1</a>). Variations are best described in seasonal patterns (table S1). Northward transport of pollutants carried predominantly fossil fuel emissions in the polluted winter (December-January-February; 
   <span class="italic">f</span>
   <sub>bb</sub> of 10 to 40%), whereas biomass burning sources were relatively more important during the pristine summer months (June-July-August; 33 to 68%) (
   <a rid="R23" ref-type="bibr" href="#R23">
    <span class="italic">23</span>
   </a>). The mean contribution of biomass burning to the Arctic EC was 25 ± 16% in the polluted winter and 42 ± 19% in the much cleaner summer (table S1). Barrow showed the same seasonal variation in 
   <span class="italic">f</span>
   <sub>bb</sub> as Abisko, Tiksi, and Zeppelin sites, but the fossil fuel fraction of BC was generally higher
   <sub>.</sub> The surface boundary layer in Barrow is usually isolated from wildfires in central Alaska by the Brooks Range, separating the leeward tundra and wetland of the North Slope from the rest of boreal Alaska. Biomass burning plumes are lofted at the Brooks Range and do not always descend again to the surface within the North Slope. Most of the stations had relatively long periods of overlapping data, except for Alert. There, only the first two samples (i.e., composites) overlap with the final two Tiksi composites while having almost identical sampling times. In terms of 
   <span class="italic">f</span>
   <sub>bb</sub>, this bridging period shows a consistent transition from the preceding Tiksi into Alert observations. However, the succeeding 
   <span class="italic">f</span>
   <sub>bb</sub> seasonality at Alert (40 ± 5%) is much weaker and oscillates around the annual Arctic mean 
   <span class="italic">f</span>
   <sub>bb</sub> determined in this study (
   <a rid="T1" ref-type="table" href="#T1">Table 1</a>). A possible explanation for Alert’s weak seasonality could be its location, which is furthest from BC sources among the Arctic stations. The low annual variation in accumulation mode particles (
   <a rid="R24" ref-type="bibr" href="#R24">
    <span class="italic">24</span>
   </a>) at the most remote site, Alert, suggests that arriving aerosols are more mixed during their longer transport compared to the other sites, creating a relatively constant 
   <span class="italic">f</span>
   <sub>bb</sub> signal.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Combustion sources apportioned by stable carbon isotopes</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition to radiocarbon data, the stable carbon isotopic ratio (δ
   <span class="sup">13</span>C) provides additional insight into source apportionment, especially between different fossil fuel source classes (i.e., coal versus liquid fossil fuel versus gas flaring). Liquid fossil fuel sources can be further deconvoluted with δ
   <span class="sup">13</span>C-EC fingerprinting. EC emissions of Russian origin are more depleted in 
   <span class="sup">13</span>C compared to emissions of Chinese and western European (“regular”) liquid fossil fuels (
   <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">
    <span class="italic">17</span>
   </a>, 
   <a rid="R25" ref-type="bibr" href="#R25">
    <span class="italic">25</span>
   </a>). The most δ
   <span class="sup">13</span>C-depleted annual signature of EC was found in Tiksi, followed by Alert, Barrow, and Abisko (
   <a rid="T1" ref-type="table" href="#T1">Table 1</a>; no δ
   <span class="sup">13</span>C data are available for Zeppelin due to low carbon content). Alert and Tiksi had the narrowest δ
   <span class="sup">13</span>C SD (both ±0.8‰; 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F3" href="#F3">Fig. 3</a>), with a wider SD for Abisko and Barrow (roughly ±1.5‰). Taking into account the uncertainty of the potential sources, distributions smaller than 1‰ can be considered narrow, as the “pure” fossil endmembers (e.g., coal) have an uncertainty range of 1 to 1.8‰; the endmember range for gas flaring is more uncertain (±3‰) (
   <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">
    <span class="italic">17</span>
   </a>). Although narrow ranges in annual δ
   <span class="sup">13</span>C point to well-mixed air masses arriving at a site, influence from local point sources cannot be excluded. Point-source signals are difficult to detect, because of the long consecutive sampling times that had to be used in this study to allow collection of enough carbon material to enable radiocarbon analysis. For the 2 years of Tiksi observations, only spring 2013 showed a clear influence from local liquid fossil fuel emissions of Russian origin (
   <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">
    <span class="italic">17</span>
   </a>). This finding is essential, because significant fossil fuel emissions appear to be absent in the emission inventory within a large radius from Tiksi (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Fig. 1A</a>). In contrast to the radiocarbon data, no distinct seasonality for stable isotopic EC signatures was observed for the circum-Arctic. Gas flaring, which is mostly of Russian origin (
   <a rid="R12" ref-type="bibr" href="#R12">
    <span class="italic">12</span>
   </a>, 
   <a rid="R26" ref-type="bibr" href="#R26">
    <span class="italic">26</span>
   </a>, 
   <a rid="R27" ref-type="bibr" href="#R27">
    <span class="italic">27</span>
   </a>) and was suggested earlier to be a major source of the Arctic BC surface concentration (
   <a rid="R26" ref-type="bibr" href="#R26">
    <span class="italic">26</span>
   </a>), did not appear to be abundant during the observed periods and under the given limitations of the current gas-flaring isotopic endmember (text S1) (
   <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">
    <span class="italic">17</span>
   </a>).
  </p>
  <div id="F3" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <div class="title">Multidimensional source apportionment plot of the Δ
     <span class="sup">14</span>C versus δ
     <span class="sup">13</span>C isotopic signature of samples from all stations.
    </div>
    <p>The colored squares show the endmember ranges for the different EC sources of biomass burning (green) and the fossil fuels: gas flaring (blue), liquid fossil fuels of Russian origin (brown), liquid fossil fuels of “regular” (defined as American, Chinese, and western European emission) origin (dark cyan), and coal (black). Data from Barret 
     <span class="italic">et al</span>. (
     <a rid="R18" ref-type="bibr" href="#R18">
      <span class="italic">18</span>
     </a>) are marked with a black asterisk. From light to dark coloring: Abisko, Alert, Barrow, Tiksi, and Zeppelin. The degree of shading in the circles indicates the EC concentration for each sample (right shading bar). The areas of the circles indicate the sampling time in days from 1 to 120. Samples for which no δ
     <span class="sup">13</span>C data were available (e.g., all Zeppelin data) are placed on the 
     <span class="italic">y</span> axis. Uncertainties and error bars are not shown (can be received from tables in the Supplementary Materials) and are smaller than the diameter of the circles.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="aau8052-F3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Model performance</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A Lagrangian atmospheric transport model [FLEXible PARTicle dispersion model (FLEXPART) (
   <a rid="R28" ref-type="bibr" href="#R28">
    <span class="italic">28</span>
   </a>)], based on an anthropogenic emission inventory [Evaluating the Climate and Air Quality Impacts of Short-Lived Pollutants (ECLIPSE) (
   <a rid="R12" ref-type="bibr" href="#R12">
    <span class="italic">12</span>
   </a>)] and an open fire emissions inventory [Global Fire Emissions Database (GFED) (
   <a rid="R29" ref-type="bibr" href="#R29">
    <span class="italic">29</span>
   </a>)], was used to simulate BC concentrations at the five measurement sites, enabling the investigation of BC’s geographical origins (fig. S1). Furthermore, simulated BC concentrations were split into anthropogenic (biofuel or fossil fuel) and natural (open fires and wildfires) contributions. There were observation model offsets, with both over- and underestimation in model predictions relative to the observations—both in BC concentrations and especially in the BC source apportionment (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F4" href="#F4">Fig. 4</a>, A to F) (
   <a rid="R7" ref-type="bibr" href="#R7">
    <span class="italic">7</span>
   </a>, 
   <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">
    <span class="italic">17</span>
   </a>). The model performed better for fossil fuel–BC concentrations than for biomass burning–BC (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F4" href="#F4">Fig. 4</a>, G and H). Better performance was achieved for sites (Abisko, Alert, and Barrow) with fully overlapping model and observational data coverage, and where no clear influence of local emissions was observed. The influence of missing local emissions and relatively large discrepancies for BC sources (i.e., fossil fuel versus biomass burning; 
   <span class="italic">f</span>
   <sub>bb</sub>), but otherwise well-simulated BC concentrations, suggests large uncertainties for geographical allocation (i.e., misallocation) and composition of BC sources in the emission inventories. In addition to uncertain emissions, the transport of BC into the deep Arctic is a difficult process to model because it involves complex interactions of dry deposition and precipitation scavenging as well as diabatic transport in the low sunlit Arctic with a strong surface-based inversion (
   <a rid="R5" ref-type="bibr" href="#R5">
    <span class="italic">5</span>
   </a>). The difference between Barrow and other Arctic sites also indicates the importance of accurately modeling orographic impacts on surface concentrations. If global transport models with larger grid sizes (2.5° × 2.5°) are used to simulate regional transport over complex terrain like the Brooks Range, the model will be biased high unless nested grids are incorporated to capture dilution during uplift (
   <a rid="R30" ref-type="bibr" href="#R30">
    <span class="italic">30</span>
   </a>). For example, a recent global-scale GEOS-Chem modeling study suggested high biomass burning contributions for Barrow in the summer; however, parallel measurements did not reflect a similarly large increase in surface BC concentrations (
   <a rid="R27" ref-type="bibr" href="#R27">
    <span class="italic">27</span>
   </a>). There may also be local influence from nearby Utqiaġvik. However, the model skill was influenced by the projected geographical origin of BC, showing better agreement for European sources (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Fig. 5</a>).
  </p>
  <div id="F4" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <div class="title">Alert, Barrow, Zeppelin, and BC of fossil versus BC of biomass burning.</div>
    <p>(
     <span class="bold">A</span> to 
     <span class="bold">F</span>) Observation (black line) and model (red line). EC is used synonymous to BC. Horizontal bars indicate sampling duration. Vertical error bars show observational uncertainties (1 SD). (A) Alert BC concentrations. (B) Alert fraction biomass burning. (C) Zeppelin BC concentrations. (D) Zeppelin fraction biomass burning. (E) Barrow BC concentrations. Data from Barret 
     <span class="italic">et al</span>. (
     <a rid="R18" ref-type="bibr" href="#R18">
      <span class="italic">18</span>
     </a>) are marked with a white asterisk. (F) Barrow fraction biomass burning. Data from Barret 
     <span class="italic">et al</span>. (
     <a rid="R18" ref-type="bibr" href="#R18">
      <span class="italic">18</span>
     </a>) are marked with a white asterisk. The linear fit (
     <span class="italic">R</span>
     <span class="sup">2</span>) and 
     <span class="italic">P</span> value between model and observation are shown in each respective panel. (
     <span class="bold">G</span> and 
     <span class="bold">H</span>) From light to dark: Abisko (squares), Alert (diamonds), Barrow (circles), Tiksi (upward triangles), and Zeppelin (downward triangles). The linear fits (
     <span class="italic">R</span>
     <span class="sup">2</span>) and 
     <span class="italic">P</span> values between mode and observation are shown for all stations in each respective panel. (G) BC fossil (fuel) concentrations are the product of 1 − 
     <span class="italic">f</span>
     <sub>bb</sub> and BC concentration. (H) BC biomass (burning) is the product of 
     <span class="italic">f</span>
     <sub>bb</sub> times BC concentration.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="aau8052-F4" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <div id="F5" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Fig. 5</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <div class="title">Model versus observation.</div>
    <p>From light to dark: Abisko (squares), Alert (diamonds), Barrow (circles), Tiksi (upward triangles), and Zeppelin (downward triangles). The linear fits (
     <span class="italic">R</span>
     <span class="sup">2</span>) and 
     <span class="italic">P</span> values for EC and BC are replicated in each panel. The color bar (and gray shaded symbols) represents the fraction of simulated anthropogenic sources (fossil fuel and biofuel) by continent, separated in the three panels. (
     <span class="bold">A</span>) Mass fraction of simulated BC from (North) American sources. (
     <span class="bold">B</span>) Mass fraction of simulated BC from Asian sources. (
     <span class="bold">C</span>) Mass fraction of simulated BC from European sources. (
     <span class="bold">D</span> to 
     <span class="bold">F</span>) Biomass burning fraction of EC, based on radiocarbon measurements versus biomass burning fraction based on FEG model simulations. The linear fits (
     <span class="italic">R</span>
     <span class="sup">2</span>) and 
     <span class="italic">P</span> values for fraction biomass burning from observation (Δ
     <span class="sup">14</span>C) and model (FEG) are replicated in each panel. The color bar (and gray shaded symbols) represents the fraction of simulated anthropogenic sources (fossil fuel and biofuel) by continent, separated in the three panels. (D) Mass fraction of simulated BC from (North) American sources. (E) Mass fraction of simulated BC from Asian sources. (F) Mass fraction of simulated BC from European sources.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="aau8052-F5" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Geographical BC sources</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Two available outputs from FLEXPART are the “potential emission sensitivity” function and a “source contribution function.” The latter can be obtained when FLEXPART is coupled to an emission inventory, such as ECLIPSE. The potential emission sensitivity is proportional to particles’ residence time, in units of seconds per volume (or area), in a particular model grid cell. Close to the surface (0- to 100-m altitude), the potential emission sensitivity is also called footprint emission sensitivity (
   <a rid="R31" ref-type="bibr" href="#R31">
    <span class="italic">31</span>
   </a>). The source contribution function, with units of mass per second, is a measure for the quantity of how much a source in an emission inventory grid cell would contribute to the total concentration at a receptor site. That way, both the geographical sources and the measured concentrations—the product of potential emission sensitivity and source contribution function—can be simulated for an observational site. Reversely, a latitudinal cutoff can be calculated, pointing to a fraction [e.g., 90% (
   <a rid="R4" ref-type="bibr" href="#R4">
    <span class="italic">4</span>
   </a>)] of BC emissions that come north or south of that boundary. The FLEXPART model indicates that main source regions for 90% of the simulated annual anthropogenic (non-open biomass burning) BC in the circum-Arctic were north of 42° latitude. This includes all Arctic council members (Canada, Denmark, Finland, Iceland, Norway, Russia, Sweden, and the United States), most of Europe, some post-Soviet states (Belarus, Kazakhstan, Moldova, and Ukraine), and northern China. The remaining ~10% BC south of 42°N originated mostly from China. Together, for the selected annual periods and stations, the modeled total BC from anthropogenic and natural sources were 38 ± 25% European (including western Russia), 36 ± 25% Asian, and 3 ± 11% North American, with the remainder (23 ± 24%) coming from global open biomass burning (table S2). Wildfires that affect the Arctic occur to a big part in Asia (
   <a rid="R32" ref-type="bibr" href="#R32">
    <span class="italic">32</span>
   </a>). Barrow was the only receptor site where the transport model projected significant impacts from anthropogenic American sources (17 ± 11%). The influences from Asian emissions were relatively high at Alert (50 ± 16%), Barrow (43 ± 21%), Tiksi (41 ± 25%), and Zeppelin (41 ± 12%), whereas European emissions dominated at Abisko (84 ± 6%) and Zeppelin (57 ± 14%) and were pronounced at Alert (27 ± 10%). By assigning these source contributions, it is also worth noting that the countries and regions mostly responsible for emissions (China, Europe, Russia, and the United States) would also benefit most from mitigation efforts in the short term, with regard to socioeconomic impact (health benefits and avoided crop loss) (
   <a rid="R4" ref-type="bibr" href="#R4">
    <span class="italic">4</span>
   </a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
