<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Here we focus on two chipmunk species within the YNP montane mammal community that show different ecological and phenotypic responses over the last century of climate change (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008119.g001" class="xref">Fig 1</xref>). Western chipmunks have long been considered models for niche partitioning by elevation and habitat type [
 <xref rid="pgen.1008119.ref024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>–
 <xref rid="pgen.1008119.ref026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>]. The alpine chipmunk (
 <italic class="italic">Tamias alpinus</italic>) is an ecological specialist endemic to the high elevation alpine habitats of the Sierra Nevada Mountains. The lodgepole chipmunk (
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">speciosus</italic>) occurs more broadly across mid- to high-elevation subalpine coniferous forests of California. 
 <italic class="italic">Tamias alpinus</italic> has undergone severe range contraction driven by extirpation of lower elevation populations [
 <xref rid="pgen.1008119.ref001" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pgen.1008119.ref020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>] combined with pronounced shifts in diet and cranial morphology [
 <xref rid="pgen.1008119.ref027" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>] across the alpine zone of YNP and elsewhere in the Sierra Nevada mountains. Spatial modeling of current versus historical ranges across YNP suggests that the strong upward contraction of 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">alpinus</italic> is best explained by increases in minimum winter temperatures; competing models including co-occurrence with other species of chipmunks or changes in the distribution of preferred vegetation types did not improve prediction of the observed range contraction in this species [
 <xref rid="pgen.1008119.ref028" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pgen.1008119.ref029" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>]. That increasing minimum temperature alone had the strongest impact makes sense in that there has been little change in vegetation across the high elevation talus slopes preferred by this species. By contrast, range contraction in a mid-elevation chipmunk species, 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">senex</italic>, is best explained by changes in its preferred vegetation types [
 <xref rid="pgen.1008119.ref028" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pgen.1008119.ref029" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>]. For YNP 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">alpinus</italic>, there is also evidence of strong directional selection on skull morphology over the past century [
 <xref rid="pgen.1008119.ref030" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>], whereas the range, diet, and morphology of the partially overlapping lodgepole chipmunk (
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">speciosus</italic>) has remained relatively stable within YNP [
 <xref rid="pgen.1008119.ref020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pgen.1008119.ref027" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pgen.1008119.ref031" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>]. As is generally the case [
 <xref rid="pgen.1008119.ref032" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>], it remains unclear why the montane specialist, 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">alpinus</italic>, has contracted during the past century whereas its more widely-distributed congener, 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">speciosus</italic>, has not.
</p>
