<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Here, we build on these previous works [
 <xref rid="pgen.1008119.ref009" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pgen.1008119.ref033" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>] by generating ~9.4 Mb of targeted exome sequence data from 303 chipmunks (194 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">alpinus</italic>, 100 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">speciosus</italic>, and 9 samples from 4 other species). We used these comparative population genomic data to quantify evolutionary responses over the past century at two scales (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pgen.1008119.g001" class="xref">Fig 1</xref>). First, we sequenced 96 modern (48 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">alpinus</italic> and 48 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">speciosus</italic> collected between 2003–2008) and 108 historic (56 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">alpinus</italic>, 52 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">speciosus</italic> collected in 1915–1916) samples collected across geographic transects in YNP for the focal species. Second, we generated an independent geographic transect of 38 modern (2003–2012) and 52 historic (1911–1916) 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">alpinus</italic> in the Southern Sierras (SS), where this species also shows range contraction [
 <xref rid="pgen.1008119.ref020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>], to test to what extent evolutionary responses across the range of this declining alpine specialist have been consistent. To analyze these temporal data, we developed a novel analytical framework based on Approximate Bayesian Computation (ABC) that allowed us to quantify changes in population sizes and migration rates in the context of demographic history, and then to localize positive selection on standing genetic variation at specific genes. Our results provide new insights into recent evolutionary responses in this system and demonstrate how a genomic time-series approach can be broadly applied to other archived specimens to improve understanding of evolutionary responses over the past few centuries.
</p>
