<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We assessed the consequences of climate change for the migratory process of many species using one of the major global migratory flyways (the Eurasian–African flyway). For over 80% of species that already perform long-distance migration, we project that there will be significant increases in both the distance and time taken to travel between their breeding and non-breeding ranges. One of the greatest predicted increases in migratory distance is for thrush nightingale (
 <italic class="italic">Luscinia luscinia</italic>), which we estimate will have to travel an additional 773 km (±30.3 km) between breeding and non-breeding grounds by 2070. This will add a minimum of five days to the duration of its migratory journey. European bee-eater (
 <italic class="italic">Merops apiaster</italic>) migrations are projected to increase by 1020 km (±19.5 km) and by at least 4.5 days by 2070. A small increase in the duration of the migratory period (i.e. 2–3 days) may not have large impact for some individuals, given the within-species variation in migration duration. Migration, however, is a period of high mortality for birds [
 <xref rid="RSPB20172329C10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSPB20172329C12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSPB20172329C45" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>], potentially as a consequence of increased predation risk [
 <xref rid="RSPB20172329C19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>] or of increased starvation resulting from higher energetic requirements [
 <xref rid="RSPB20172329C38" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSPB20172329C45" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>] and unpredictability in food supply. Any predicted increases to the migratory journey are likely to amplify the exposure of migratory birds to these risks, potentially increasing overall mortality rates and leading to population declines [
 <xref rid="RSPB20172329C11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>].
</p>
