<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The evidence from tracking studies of individual birds generally supported the results from our migration models. At present, the statistical power of these analyses is relatively low, given the paucity of available tracking data, but with further technological advancements this sampling should rapidly improve in future. In two of eight species assessed, there were significant differences between our estimates of the total distance and duration of the migratory journey and observations from individual tracking data. Both of these species follow pronounced non-linear migrations, diverting their spring migrations from Africa through Saudi Arabia and West Africa, respectively, before returning to Europe [
 <xref rid="RSPB20172329C8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSPB20172329C52" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>]. These detours suggest some ecological advantage for deviating from the shortest straight line route, perhaps to avoid crossing extensive ecological barriers, such as the Sahara desert, where refuelling is challenging [
 <xref rid="RSPB20172329C19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>]. Alternatively, detours may be favourable if they enable faster refuelling at stopovers resulting, for example, from pulses in resource availability such as mass insect emergences, or if transport costs are reduced by tail winds [
 <xref rid="RSPB20172329C19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSPB20172329C52" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>]. If migratory species can benefit from enhanced fuel deposition rates, increasing overall migratory performance [
 <xref rid="RSPB20172329C42" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>], longer migratory distances may not necessarily result in longer migration durations. Future research could fruitfully add ecological realism to migration models by linking energetic models, such as those used here, with temporal and spatial resource availability, and weather conditions 
 <italic class="italic">en route</italic>.
</p>
