<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In the following, we use ‘total population’ or ‘population’ to refer to the individuals of a species present across the BCCIL site. Subsets of individuals within climate treatments, blocks or plots are referred to as ‘subpopulations’. We collected leaf tissue samples of each species from control, drought‐treated, warmed, watered, heated‐drought and heated‐watered plots at BCCIL in June 2009 (30 plots in total), after 15 years of experimental treatments (further details are given in Text S2). We sampled 12 individuals of each species from each plot, excluding a 0.3‐m boundary zone at the edge of each plot. We used eight previously established permanent 10 × 10 cm quadrats (Fridley 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="gcb12966-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>) and four newly established quadrats within each plot to guide sampling. Leaf tissue was recovered from the individual that was rooted most closely to the centre of each quadrat (12 samples per plot in total). The spatial locations of both the centre of each quadrat and of the sampled plant relative to this point were recorded to the nearest 5 mm. Soil depth at the 240 existing quadrats was known (Fridley 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="gcb12966-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>). Local soil depths were determined for our newly established quadrats and for any plants rooted outside quadrats (i.e. for plants that were located &gt; 5 cm from the quadrat centre). Our sampling scheme led to a total of 60 samples per climate treatment subpopulation. Samples from each treatment spanned the entire range of soil depths occupied by our study species at the site. Each leaf tissue sample was stored in self‐indicating silica gel (1–3 mm grain size; Merck‐Millipore, Darmstadt, Germany) for genetic analysis. Replicate tissue samples were collected from 40 randomly selected individuals to estimate genotyping error.
</p>
