<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We found that foraging rates decreased, warming and heat loss preventing behaviour increased, and vigilance decreased in response to decreasing temperatures in all the species. As expected, the southern newcomers had lower foraging rates, more frequent warming behaviour, and were less vigilant compared to the better adapted boreal willow tits. It seems that even though wintering in the north is possible in terms of physiological aspects and available food, processing enough food to prevent death due starvation while escaping predation requires adaptations. These mechanisms acting in low temperatures may thus be important determinants of species winter ranges (Zuckerberg et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98" href="#CR98">2011</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Willow tits had higher foraging rates than great tits and the decrease in the foraging rate in relation to lowering temperatures was stronger in the great tit than in the willow tit. In support of this, daily mass gain is the lowest during the coldest mid-winter months in great tits (Lehikoinen 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">1987</a>), whereas willow tits do not show such variation (Broggi et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">2003</a>). While great tits can somewhat benefit from the physiological and thermal benefits of their larger size (Lehikoinen 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">1986</a>), reduced foraging rates can be a strain especially for the great tit which weighs nearly twice that of a willow tit, because energy consumption increases with size of the animal (McNab 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">1971</a>; Calder and King 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">1974</a>). Foraging was disturbed by warming behaviour when temperatures declined in all the species, but this change was stronger among great tits than willow tits. This result provides an explanation for the foraging rate difference in low temperatures, and suggests different seasonal adaptations to heat production in northern species (Carlson et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">1993</a>; Broggi et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">2007</a>; Petit et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71" href="#CR71">2013</a>) or species-specific cold tolerance and insulation properties of their plumage (Saarela et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78" href="#CR78">1995</a>). Indeed, great tits are unable to produce optimal feathers in northern conditions due to time and/or nutrient constraints, and this may lead to a plumage with poorer insulation properties (Broggi et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">2011</a>). Species differences in response to temperature may be evident only in the coldest temperatures as the interaction became less evident with the reduced data. This may also reflect the lack of data (and thus lower statistical power) for the complicated models that include the random effects of site with random slopes for years.
 </p>
 <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While blue tits had lower foraging rates and spent more time warming than willow tits, their responses to temperature were similar. It is possible that these behaviours are somewhat linked to morphology. Willow tits and blue tits have shorter feet and bills than great tits (Partridge 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" href="#CR68">1976</a>; Norberg 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">1979</a>), which may reduce heat loss (Cardilini et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">2016</a>). Shorter legs also enable them to keep their centre of mass closer to the branch, which makes keeping the posture easier (Norberg 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">1979</a>) and allows foraging even when their feet are almost covered by their plumage (own observations).
 </p>
 <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Heat loss preventing behaviour increased in response to cold temperatures similarly in all species. Birds may avoid heat loss preventing postures such as keeping legs within the plumage that can reduce reaction times to predation (Carr and Lima 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">2011</a>), and use them mostly under extreme conditions when maintaining body or peripheral (leg) temperature becomes more important than escaping predation. In line with this, we found a threshold for feet warming (ca. − 20 °C) below which this behaviour increased (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>). Birds have to cover their legs as heat loss becomes too high either for maintaining deep body temperature or for preventing freeze damage via the counter-current heat exchange between the arteries and veins. Energetically, it is cheaper to prevent cold damage by hiding the feet in feathers than by increasing the flow of arterial warm blood as this would further increase heat loss.
 </p>
 <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Vigilance reduced in all species when temperatures decreased. This result was similar to the previous studies (Caraco 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">1974</a>; Hogstad 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">1988a</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">2015</a>; Pravosudov and Grubb 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72" href="#CR72">1995</a>); nevertheless, great tits and blue tits scanned less than willow tits. This may be due to the better cold tolerance and higher foraging rate of willow tits. Information on food hoards may also reduce stress of accessing food, and thereby leave more time for vigilance.
 </p>
 <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results suggest that especially great tits have not fully adapted to the northern conditions, which is consistent with the previous studies on breeding great tits (Veistola et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90" href="#CR90">1995</a>; Rytkönen and Orell 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77" href="#CR77">2001</a>; Krama et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">2013</a>). Birds respond to the cold by increasing metabolism, i.e., basal and summit metabolic rates (e.g., Petit et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71" href="#CR71">2013</a>). Resting great tits, for example, increase their metabolic rate to 3 × BMR at − 20 °C (Broggi et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">2004</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">2007</a>), which requires the consumption of more food. However, during cold spells reaching − 35 °C, their foraging rate was reduced to nearly half. Low foraging rate may, therefore, be detrimental, especially when food is scarce and the day length is short. Great tits also move less during mid-winter in cold temperatures (Pakanen et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">2018</a>), which can make it even more difficult to find enough food. As a result, cold weather may result in starvation, stress, and eventually death (Krams et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">2010</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">2013</a>). This is exacerbated by the poorer and reduced ability to keep vigilant in cold weather, making them vulnerable to predation (Morosinotto et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">2017</a>). It is, therefore, possible that cold temperatures limit success of great tits wintering in northern conditions by increasing mortality (Järvinen 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">1983</a>). This conjecture is supported by an effect of winter temperature on annual survival (Perdeck et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" href="#CR70">2000</a>) and the lower survival of breeding great tits in the north (0.38; Karvonen et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">2012</a>) compared to sympatric willow tits (0.59; Lampila et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">2006</a>) but also compared to great tits breeding in Central and Southern Europe (ca. 0.5; Payevsky 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" href="#CR69">2006</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here, we show that the southern newcomers wintering at high latitudes are not adapted to the cold temperatures in terms of foraging behaviour. Even when fed with supplemental food, their foraging rates and vigilance decreased in cold ambient temperatures and were lower than in a boreal species which is better adapted to the northern conditions. Climate change will undoubtedly help southern species winter at higher latitudes via processes such as earlier arrival of spring, increased proportion of bare ground, and less snow cover. Our results suggest that, if climate change increases winter temperatures and especially reduces the length and severity of cold spells in the northern latitudes, southern species will benefit from increased foraging rates and vigilance. These should result in higher survival, stronger population growth, and consequent range expansion towards the north.</p>
</sec>
