<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Materials and methods</div>
 <sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study populations</div>
  <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Foraging blue tits, great tits, and willow tits were video recorded in northern Finland sites along two temperature isotherms: (1) in Oulu, Hietasaari (65°01′N, 25°28′E), Oulu, Sanginjoki (64°95′N, 26°01′E), and Sonkajärvi (63°40′N, 27°31′E), and (2) at Ranua (65°92′N, 26°56′E) further in the north. Data from Oulu and Sonkajärvi were collected in 2010–2012 and data from Ranua in 2011–2012. Feeding sites were similar in terms of safe areas for reaching the feeders and for foraging. Thus, we consider the feeding sites to be equal in terms of predation risk effects on foraging and vigilance behaviour (Hogstad 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">1988b</a>; Ekman 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">1987</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data collection and analysis</div>
  <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used Canon PowerShot A580 and Panasonic Lumix DMC-FZ18 digital cameras in recording videos of foraging tits, which were supplied with sunflower seeds and peanuts. We prevented disturbance to birds by filming from a car, through house windows or behind natural shelters from a distance of 5–10 m. We filmed foraging during daytime (9:00–15:00) when light conditions allowed filming. Length of the videos included in the study ranged from 10 s to a few minutes. Temperatures varied between 0 °C and − 35 °C. The data consisted of 241 video recordings (Oulu 115, Sonkajärvi 7, Ranua 119). There were videos from 34 blue tits, 152 great tits, and 55 willow tits that were similar in length and in ambient temperatures (Online resource 1). However, the coldest − 35 °C temperatures were recorded only for great tits. We, therefore, reran the statistical models (see below) with data spanning until − 30 °C to see if the coefficients stayed similar.</p>
  <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Videos were analysed using the program Anvil 5 (Kipp 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">2001</a>), which can be used to determine time-budgets and quantify time-coded behavioural events. Starting from the time a bird fetched a seed/nut, we registered and marked the following parameters. (1) 
   <span class="italic">Foraging rate</span> was measured as the proportion of time used in processing seeds from the overall time spent at the feeding site. We registered the starting and ending times of foraging, and the starting and ending times of pauses between foraging. Tits keep the seed in their toes when they process it with their bill (Yince 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96" href="#CR96">1964</a>). (2) 
   <span class="italic">Warming behaviour</span> was measured as the proportion of time that the seed was held in the beak. (3) 
   <span class="italic">Heat loss preventing behaviour</span> was measured by whether the birds kept their feet most of the observed time under their feathers (coded 1) or not (coded 0). We used a dichotomous (0/1) variable, because the distribution was extremely discrete. In cold conditions, tits have to warm their toes inside their plumage (Dawson and Whittow 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">2000</a>), and this was observed to affect foraging, either by totally disrupting it (indicated by holding the seed in the bill), or making it more difficult. (4) 
   <span class="italic">Vigilance</span> was registered in timeline as events when the bird presumably scanned for possible predators by raising its head and stopped foraging activities.
  </p>
  <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used linear mixed models (LMM) in program R (R Development Core Team 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83" href="#CR83">2017</a>) to analyse foraging rates, warming behaviour (the proportion of time seed was kept in the bill) and vigilance, and generalized linear mixed models (GLMM; binomial errors, logit link) to analyse heat loss preventing behaviour (legs hidden among feathers most of the time or not). We included species (willow tit as reference) and temperature during observation as fixed effects. The sites were divided into two temperature isotherms and site was included as a random effect with random annual slopes. We centred continuous variables to enable the proper interpretation of interaction models (Schielzeth 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79" href="#CR79">2010</a>). We constructed several models starting with an intercept-model, and added temperature, species, and their interactions, consecutively, to find the best model explaining the variation in the studied behaviours. Model comparison was based on the Akaike Information Criterion (Burnham and Anderson 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">2002</a>). In all cases, we were able to find the best model that was over two AIC-units better than the next best model. We did not individually mark birds, which meant that we could not include individual as a random factor. However, on the basis of a few colour ringed individuals, we could see that the within-individual variation was clearly larger than the between individual variation in the observed temperature scale. This means that the effect of temperature on behaviour should not be biased, even though some observations were made from the same individuals (Leger and Didrichsons 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">1994</a>). Lack of data prevented us from including dominance rank, sex, or age of individuals in our models, even though they may be linked to vigilance behaviour (Krams 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">1998</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
