<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par2" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate change shifts species distributions polewards in most taxa (Thomas and Lennon 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84" href="#CR84">1999</a>; Parmesan and Yohe 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" href="#CR67">2003</a>; Brommer et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">2012</a>; Lehikoinen and Virkkala 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">2016</a>). To date, most studies have concentrated on breeding season phenological consequences of climate change (e.g., Visser et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR92" href="#CR92">1998</a>; Vatka et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88" href="#CR88">2011</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89" href="#CR89">2014</a>), while wintering ecology is less examined despite shortening winters (Sparks and Menzel 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80" href="#CR80">2002</a>) that warm up the most (Jylhä et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">2009</a>). Warming of winters may be an important factor behind range expansion, because surviving the winter should become easier further north (Maclean et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">2008</a>; Zuckerberg et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98" href="#CR98">2011</a>; Lehikoinen et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">2013</a>; Fraixedas et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">2015</a>), but the ecological mechanisms allowing range expansions are not fully understood (Gaston 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">2009</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Winter is a demanding time in the northern latitudes. At the same time, when food availability is reduced, low temperatures require higher food consumption due to increased energy demands for heat production. For diurnal birds, shortened day lengths limit birds, because they have less time to acquire enough energy for their daily activities and for attaining sufficient fat deposits that ensure survival through the long and cold nights (e.g., Calder and King 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">1974</a>; Biebach 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">1996</a>; Koivula et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">2002</a>; Krams 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">2002</a>; Krams et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">2010</a>). Successful wintering in cold conditions where temperatures can decline below − 30 °C requires morphological, physiological, and behavioural adaptations (e.g., Brooks 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">1968</a>; Biebach 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">1996</a>), and alleviation in temperature should thus help southern species.
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Wintering distributions are restricted to areas where the increased energy requirements of cold weather and metabolic rates do not grow too high (Root 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76" href="#CR76">1988</a>, Meehan et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">2004</a>). Increasing winter temperatures reduce these requirements. Birds maintain their body temperatures partly by a high basal metabolic rate (BMR), which increases during the winter in many species (McKechnie 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">2008</a>). When temperatures decline below the thermoneutral zone, basal metabolism, activity, and the heat increment of feeding do not produce enough heat (Calder and King 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">1974</a>), and body temperatures are maintained by shivering thermogenesis (Hohtola et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">1980</a>; Hohtola 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">2004</a>). Wintering birds use about 20–40% of their daily energy expenditure on heat production (Weathers et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95" href="#CR95">1984</a>; Weathers and Sullivan 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94" href="#CR94">1989</a>). Consequently, wintering small birds are forced to forage large parts of the day (Austin 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">1974</a>; Cooper 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">2000</a>). Therefore, the ability to forage efficiently should be vital for acquiring energy reserves that ensure survival.
 </p>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Winter distributions can be further limited by food availability in cases where physiological limitations do not restrict wintering (Repasky 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75" href="#CR75">1991</a>; Canterbury 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">2002</a>). A natural experiment occurs when winter feeding increases food availability and lures species into wintering in more northern locations than enabled by their adaptations. However, temperature seems to be more important than resources in determining wintering distributions (Zuckerberg et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR98" href="#CR98">2011</a>), and these species of southern origin may still face problems in foraging in the cold environment.
 </p>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Among birds, general adaptations to reduce energy and heat loss during the winter include finding less windy, warmer, and most profitable feeding and roosting sites (Sulkava 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82" href="#CR82">1968</a>; Alatalo 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1982</a>; Wachob 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR93" href="#CR93">1996</a>; Veľký et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR91" href="#CR91">2010</a>), reducing movements (e.g., Pakanen et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">2018</a>), using over-night hypothermia (Haftorn 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">1972</a>; Reinertsen 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73" href="#CR73">1983</a>; McKechnie and Lovegrove 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">2002</a>), ptiloerection, and peripheral vasoconstriction, especially to keep their feet colder than their bodies (Johansen and Bech 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">1983</a>). Unfeathered parts are an important avenue of heat loss in birds (Steen and Steen 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81" href="#CR81">1965</a>, Hill et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">1980</a>, Yorzinski et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97" href="#CR97">2018</a>). Heat loss from legs can be reduced by vasoconstriction, but, at temperatures below freezing, birds have to use postural adjustments to cover the legs with insulating feathers for additional cold defense. This can curtail heat loss by 20–50% (Dawson and Whittow 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">2000</a>). Using ventral plumage for insulation by raising a foot or crouching may also be necessary to avoid cold bites at very low temperatures. However, such heat loss preventing behaviour may reduce foraging efficiency (Grubb 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">1978</a>). This behaviour should increase with decreasing temperature, and be more common in the less adapted southern species.
 </p>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">During daily activities, individuals also need to scan the environment to escape depredation (Lendrem 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">1983</a>; Treves 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85" href="#CR85">2000</a>). However, there is a trade-off between time spent vigilant and foraging, which becomes a problem in cold conditions as birds need to increase foraging to meet their daily and over-night energy requirements (Caraco 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">1974</a>; Hogstad 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">1988a</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">2015</a> Pravosudov and Grubb 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72" href="#CR72">1995</a>; Brodin et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">2017</a>). Reduced vigilance, in turn, may result in increased predation (Lind and Cresswell 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">2005</a>). Therefore, wintering birds need to divide their daily activities between foraging, warming, and vigilance, and species that are best adapted to northern conditions should be better able to maintain foraging rates and vigilance in cold conditions, and allocate less time to warming behaviour.
 </p>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Two temperate species, the great tit (
  <span class="italic">Parus major</span>) and the bue tit (
  <span class="italic">Cyanistes caeruleus</span>), have extended their breeding and wintering distributions to Northern Fennoscandia in the 20th century (Haartman et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">1967</a>; Väisänen et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86" href="#CR86">1998</a>; Valkama et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87" href="#CR87">2011</a>). Great tits reached northern parts of Fennoscandia in the late 1950s (Haftorn 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">1957</a>; Veistola et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR90" href="#CR90">1995</a>). Blue tits were very rare in the latter part of the 19th century being present only in the southernmost parts of Finland but extended their range across Finland during the 20th century (Valkama et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87" href="#CR87">2011</a>), reaching Oulu in greater numbers in the 1990s. While both species breed in northern Scandinavia, their densities are lower than in the south (Valkama et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87" href="#CR87">2011</a>). Winter feeding has influenced the winter distributions of these facultative migrants (Orell 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" href="#CR65">1989</a>; Nowakowski and Vähätalo 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" href="#CR64">2003</a>; Nilsson et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" href="#CR62">2006</a>; Valkama et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87" href="#CR87">2011</a>). They commonly coexist with, and visit the same feeders as the willow tit (
  <span class="italic">Poecile montanus</span>) that are fully adapted to the northern conditions with territorial flocks that store food for the winter (Ekman 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">1989</a>). While all species benefit from supplemental food (Lahti et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">1998</a>; Koivula et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">1996</a>; Jansson et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">1981</a>), the temperate species may be poorer in maintaining foraging rates due to lack of adaptations to the cold temperatures.
 </p>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here, we compared the performances of great tits and blue tits to the willow tit in the conditions of ample food (at feeders) in Northern Finland under temperatures ranging from 0 to − 35 °C. We used video recordings taken at feeders during winter to examine (1) how temperature affects the proportion of time which they can allocate to processing food (i.e. foraging rates), warming, and heat loss preventing behaviour and predator vigilance? We expected these behaviours to be dependent on temperature in all species, but we expected willow tits to have higher foraging rates and predator vigilance but show less warming behaviour. We further asked (2) whether the above species show different responses to temperature in these traits? As a boreal species, willow tits should be better adapted to cold conditions than the temperate species. Hence, they should be more efficient foragers, they should need to spend less time warming, and they should be able to be more vigilant in cold weather compared to the southern newcomers.</p>
</sec>
