<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec019" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Dynamic bioclimate envelope model (DBEM) and input parameters</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results obtained through this analysis are representative of species’ responses to changes in environmental suitability under climate change that have been predicted or observed in the scientific literature [
  <a rid="pone.0145285.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0145285.ref004">4</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0145285.ref007" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0145285.ref007">7</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0145285.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0145285.ref042">42</a>], and are likely conservative given the potential for cumulative impacts that are not included in the present analysis (e.g., acidification, overfishing, habitat loss, etc.)[
  <a rid="pone.0145285.ref070" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0145285.ref070">70</a>]. The DBEM was selected for the purpose of this study due to the model’s capacity to predict large-scale scenarios of ecological change for numerous species given limited biological and ecological data. This global model integrates population and dispersal dynamics, which aid in determining the biogeography of marine systems under scenarios of climate change [
  <a rid="pone.0145285.ref106" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0145285.ref106">106</a>]. Although this version of the DBEM does not explicitly incorporate additional factors such as the influence of trophic interactions, evolutionary change, or fishing pressure, the use of empirically obtained habitat preferences based on species’ current distributions indirectly accounts for a ‘realized’ niche that is constrained by trophic interactions [
  <a rid="pone.0145285.ref107" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0145285.ref107">107</a>]. While the resulting shift in species’ distributions from inclusion of trophic interactions differed only modestly [
  <a rid="pone.0145285.ref107" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0145285.ref107">107</a>], these interactions may play a larger role in coastal regions and at localized scales, potentially leading to greater variation in projected responses to changing environmental conditions.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">SDMs are inherently contingent on our understanding of species’ environmental preferences and capacity to respond to environmental change. For this reason, model certainty is much higher for species of commercial importance, where extensive research has been conducted on life history traits, environmental tolerance limits, and the extent of distributions. A species’ capacity to adapt is sensitive to the time scale over which a change occurs, as well as the magnitude of the change in environmental conditions, both of which can be further exacerbated when faced with multiple stressors. Inclusion of cumulative pressures (e.g., changes in fishing pressure, ocean acidification, habitat loss, changes in predation, etc.) would likely increase the rate and scale of estimated declines, with variation between species. For instance, Lam 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. (2014) used the DBEM to project the impacts of changes in SST, oxygen content (represented by O
  <sub>2</sub> concentration), pH (represented by H
  <span class="sup">+</span> concentration), and other variables such as salinity and ocean currents on the growth and distribution of marine species in the Arctic, and corresponding impacts on commercial fisheries by 2050 [
  <a rid="pone.0145285.ref108" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0145285.ref108">108</a>]. The inclusion of ocean acidification in these climate change projections reduced landings by 11% relative to the ‘climate change only’ scenario, with a corresponding 15% reduction in revenue in the Arctic by 2050 [
  <a rid="pone.0145285.ref108" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0145285.ref108">108</a>]. These projections have particular relevance for the species included in the present study, many of which are vulnerable to ocean acidification (e.g., Pacific halibut, sole, and invertebrates)[
  <a rid="pone.0145285.ref108" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0145285.ref108">108</a>], and suggest that impacts to food and economic security are likely to be more severe than those projected in this study. Ocean acidification has also been implicated in changes in competitive interactions between species, leading to ecosystem phase shifts [
  <a rid="pone.0145285.ref109" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0145285.ref109">109</a>]. Moreover, as this study does not account for all stages within the life cycles of diadromous species such as salmon, sturgeon, and eulachon, anthropogenic or environmental impacts on freshwater systems may also alter the projected results of this study for these species.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study assumes that species’ current distributions are in equilibrium with environmental conditions [
  <a rid="pone.0145285.ref110" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0145285.ref110">110</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0145285.ref111" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0145285.ref111">111</a>], and thereby accurately reflect preferred habitat and environmental tolerance limits. However, given anthropogenic disturbances, it has been argued that ranges used in SDMs do not fully capture species’ historical ranges, which could lead to biases in estimates of species’ current environmental tolerance limits [
  <a rid="pone.0145285.ref084" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0145285.ref084">84</a>]. Within BC’s marine environment, such biases are likely less prominent as the majority of species included in this analysis have maintained their approximate historical range or occupy other areas with similar habitat, despite variations in abundance. Exceptions to this include invasive species, such as manila and varnish clams, and individual stocks of salmon and eulachon that have been extirpated.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Lastly, the use of inputs from different GCMs can yield a key source of uncertainty for DBEMs due to the direct relationship between the initial climate simulation and the estimates derived [
  <a rid="pone.0145285.ref112" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0145285.ref112">112</a>]. To incorporate this uncertainty, multi-model ensembles have been shown to improve projections by accounting for model-selection uncertainty and providing an ensemble of data that tends to agree better with observations [
  <a rid="pone.0145285.ref113" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0145285.ref113">113</a>]. Since this analysis evaluates scenarios generated from one coupled atmosphere-ocean global climate model (GFDL’s ESM2M), the inclusion of additional SDM-GCM combinations would help to further elucidate areas of uncertainty in model outputs, and to explore inter-model variation [
  <a rid="pone.0145285.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0145285.ref036">36</a>]. The resolution of current GCMs is most suited to large-scale analyses due to the intricacies of representing fine-scale ocean dynamics. In particular, there has been a concerted effort towards resolving coastal mixing processes and mesoscale eddies within GCMs [
  <a rid="pone.0145285.ref114" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0145285.ref114">114</a>]. While analyses at the scale of the EEZ can provide greater certainty with respect to regional impacts on fisheries, our understanding of impacts on coastal communities is therefore less certain due to both the complicated dynamics of coastal systems and the finer scale of the analysis.
 </p>
</sec>
