<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec014" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Implications for small-scale fisheries management</div>
 <sec id="sec015" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Spatial trends and regional offsets</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An important concern highlighted by this study is the unequal distribution of relative losses in catch potential associated with regional ecological differences and poleward range shifts. In addition to coastwide declines in catch potential that are suggested when viewing cumulative effects on taxonomic groups (e.g., salmon and clams), species-based estimates reveal a stronger differential that correlates with latitude (i.e., impacts are less severe moving polewards).</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While there is increasing support for establishing equitable resource sharing agreements between Nations [
   <a rid="pone.0145285.ref095" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0145285.ref095">95</a>] that might offer opportunities to offset such declines, the means by which such agreements could be achieved are uncertain [
   <a rid="pone.0145285.ref096" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0145285.ref096">96</a>]. Although appearing feasible in theory, three key issues arise from the prospect of applying these agreements to offset regional impacts: the scale of resource-sharing agreements, the extended time frame, and the requirement of reciprocity.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Firstly, resource sharing agreements have both existed and been discussed primarily in a localized context, such as a single river system [
   <a rid="pone.0145285.ref096" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0145285.ref096">96</a>], rather than at the regional level. For example, reciprocal agreements between First Nations historically allowed for shared use of a harvesting or processing site in exchange for another [
   <a rid="pone.0145285.ref097" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0145285.ref097">97</a>]. Although such resources sharing agreements could aid in increasing First Nations’ participation in commercial harvests for manila clams and geoducks along the North and Central Coasts, where their abundances are projected to sufficiently increase under climate change so as to offset other regional losses, the cost of travelling to these regions may offset the prospective benefits. Similarly, FSC harvests hinge upon the feasibility of accessing resources locally, making trans-regional trips unlikely to prove viable or desirable.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The remaining two issues of time frame and reciprocity are intertwined, and relate to the circumstances that facilitated resource exchanges. Many of the key traditional institutions that generated considerable adaptive capacity for First Nations primarily supported responses to seasonal or inter-annual fluctuations in resource abundance and availability through reciprocity [
   <a rid="pone.0145285.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0145285.ref044">44</a>], or operated as measures to prevent such long-term declines through spatial management [
   <a rid="pone.0145285.ref098" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0145285.ref098">98</a>], selective fishing [
   <a rid="pone.0145285.ref099" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0145285.ref099">99</a>], and forms of mariculture [
   <a rid="pone.0145285.ref100" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0145285.ref100">100</a>], among other strategies. Since reciprocal agreements were intended to provide insurance against future resource scarcity, they inherently pivoted on the exchange of resources or access rights. Given that the scenarios presented in this analysis suggest that all species are likely to exhibit a relative decline in abundance in the southern regions of British Columbia, few arrangements remain where species could be traded or access rights exchanged in accordance with this principle. An exception may occur for commercial fisheries, given the potential increased abundance of warmer-water species (e.g., sardines) that is projected to occur within BC’s waters under climate change.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec016" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Externalized impacts</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In almost all circumstances, scenarios represented in this analysis illustrate outcomes where impacts are externalized, rather than internally resolved. For instance, redistributing access rights to fishing would serve to reallocate, rather than reduce, impacts. Given existing competition and conflict over key resources such as salmon and herring, it is unlikely that further reductions in catch potential associated with climate change will yield equitable outcomes.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Traditional clam beds serve as an ideal example of a method that could be applied to offset climatic impacts through internalized mechanisms, using local cultivation to generate increased productivity by enhancing native habitat rather than redirecting extraction efforts towards other regions or species. Clam gardens constructed in a manner akin to those situated near ancient settlements of the Northern Coast Salish and Laich-kwil-tach First Nations have been found to generate higher clam densities, biomass, and growth rates than non-walled beaches [
   <a rid="pone.0145285.ref100" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0145285.ref100">100</a>]. These benefits were observed for Pacific littleneck clams (
   <span class="italic">Protothaca staminea</span>) and butter clams (
   <span class="italic">Saxidomus giganteus</span>), two clams that are of cultural, economic, and ecological importance to the region [
   <a rid="pone.0145285.ref100" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0145285.ref100">100</a>]. Reinstating clam beds in First Nations’ territorial lands has been suggested as a means of simultaneously achieving local conservation and cultural objectives [
   <a rid="pone.0145285.ref101" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0145285.ref101">101</a>], and may thereby provide a politically and ecologically viable option for mitigating climate-related impacts.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec017" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Joint management frameworks</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Management of salmon and herring stocks has been highly contentious due to the myriad of stakeholders who depend upon them, which include First Nations, recreational fisheries, and commercial fisheries. Therein, each group represents an additional layer of complexity: for example, the Fraser River system is home to nearly 100 First Nation communities, each of which depends upon their legal right to salmon harvests [
   <a rid="pone.0145285.ref096" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0145285.ref096">96</a>]. Aside from fulfilling societal needs, salmon serve as key ecological components of the Pacific Northwest Coast, functioning as the mechanisms by which nutrients are transferred from the ocean to freshwater and terrestrial ecosystems [
   <a rid="pone.0145285.ref102" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0145285.ref102">102</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0145285.ref103" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0145285.ref103">103</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While the projections above suggest the inability to fully offset declines in salmon and herring through a redistribution of fishing effort achieved under resource access agreements exchanged by First Nations, attaining a state of collaboration between First Nations, DFO, and other sectors has the potential to yield beneficial ecological and political results, if implemented correctly [
   <a rid="pone.0145285.ref096" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0145285.ref096">96</a>]. Parallels exist between First Nations’ traditional fisheries management approaches and “modern” approaches (e.g., spatial management, mariculture, selective fishing, fishing closures), with differences arising primarily due to diverging worldviews (see 
   <a rid="pone.0145285.s010" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#pone.0145285.s010">S7 Table</a>). By aligning analogous approaches, local application of traditional management strategies could provide opportunities to collaboratively engage in adaptive ecosystem-based management [
   <a rid="pone.0145285.ref104" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0145285.ref104">104</a>] and to coordinate efforts to attain conservation objectives [
   <a rid="pone.0145285.ref101" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0145285.ref101">101</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Established examples of joint-management initiatives may serve to provide frameworks for furthering conservation objectives and implementing traditional management practices. For instance, Garner and Parfitt (2006) identified three key case studies of joint-management of salmon fisheries on the Pacific Northwest Coast that endeavour to integrate First Nations and TEK into fisheries management decisions [
   <a rid="pone.0145285.ref096" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0145285.ref096">96</a>]. For instance, the Nisga’a Nation have ensured their equal partnership in management by employing traditional fish wheel technology to monitor and assess stocks and by leveraging traditional ecosystem-based management practices that could be applied to plan long-term objectives and management approaches [
   <a rid="pone.0145285.ref105" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0145285.ref105">105</a>]. Through such joint-management regimes, traditional fisheries management strategies could be applied to advance localized research directives and to reduce impacts on stocks under unprecedented environmental change. Moreover, the risk of conflict over declining resources underlines the need to establish common and equitable ground to ensure successful joint management of fisheries, and to leverage collective expertise.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
