<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Plant vascular function explains tree death during drought</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The observation that water flow through plants is vulnerable to blockage under conditions of stress (
  <a rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref38">Tyree and Sperry, 1988</a>) was a transformational discovery that has enabled us the best chance yet to understand and predict the conditions that trigger tree mortality. The process of ‘hydraulic failure’ arises from the fact that plants must draw water from the soil and transport it to leaves to replace water transpired during photosynthesis. Due to the very large volumes of water required to keep leaves hydrated during photosynthesis, plants rely on hollow tubes formed by dead xylem cells that link together to connect photosynthetic tissues with a supply of water in the soil. The process of transport relies on the generation of a substantial tension in the leaves that pulls water from the soil and through the vascular system (
  <a rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref43">Zimmermann, 2013</a>). Water transport by cohesion and tension in the xylem cells works while the vascular system remains hermetically sealed against air entering through the many air/xylem interfaces that exist in a plant, but increasing tension during water stress exposes weaknesses in the membranes of the xylem, ultimately resulting in failures of the hermetic seals between the atmosphere and the xylem conduits (
  <a rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref19">Crombie 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 1985
  </a>). The process of hydraulic failure begins when ‘cavitation’ of the water columns within xylem cells is caused by the entry of minute bubbles dragged across the xylem membrane into the lumen where they expand under the tension (negative pressure) and permanently block the xylem conduits (
  <a rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref36">Sperry and Tyree, 1988</a>). As the xylem becomes progressively blocked, the plant is increasingly separated from water in the soil causing accelerated dehydration, increased xylem damage and a potential feedback known as ‘runaway cavitation’ whereby tissues become completely disconnected from the water supply and quickly lethally dehydrated (
  <a rid="ref38" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref38">Tyree and Sperry, 1988</a>). Although the final, lethal feedback in hydraulic failure loop is very hard to capture experimentally, strong associations between cavitation thresholds and tree mortality point towards this as a primary cause of tree death (see below).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although other drought-related effects such as increased biotic damage can contribute to tree mortality during water stress (
  <a rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref29">McDowell 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2008
  </a>), extensive evidence now points to cavitation and ‘hydraulic failure’ as the primary cause of drought-related mortality (
  <a rid="ref15" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref15">Choat 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2018
  </a>). Clear links between xylem cavitation and plant mortality across a diversity of trees have been established under experimental conditions (
  <a rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref6">Blackman 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2009
  </a>; 
  <a rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref11">Brodribb and Cochard, 2009</a>). In addition, large-scale observations of tree damage and mortality under both natural (
  <a rid="ref4" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref4">Anderegg 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2016
  </a>; 
  <a rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref1">Adams 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2017
  </a>) and artificial (
  <a rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref31">Rowland 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2015
  </a>) drought indicate that hydraulic failure provides the best explanation for patterns of damage and mortality in natural forest systems.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The identification of hydraulic failure as a universal trigger of plant mortality during drought has been a great step forwards because it means that species threatened by mortality can finally be identified by their intrinsic physiology, rather than by traditional methods using climatic niche statistics that may or may not reflect their actual growth limitations. An important feature of xylem cavitation is that the ‘xylem vulnerability’ of different species to cavitation under water stress varies enormously. This variation is widely viewed as being the product of an evolutionary trade-off between the efficiency of water transport versus safety from cavitation (
  <a rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref24">Gleason 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2016
  </a>). Differences in the porosity of membranes between xylem conduits are thought to explain this trade-off, with higher transport efficiency associated with more porous membranes that are less able to resist cavitation (
  <a rid="ref14" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref14">Choat 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2003
  </a>). Despite the existence of a large range of xylem vulnerabilities among species, this trait appears to be relatively conserved within species, thus allowing the species to be characterized by their intrinsic vulnerability to xylem cavitation (
  <a rid="ref42" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref42">Wortemann 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2011
  </a>). Thus, it is possible to measure species-specific vulnerability using excised stems or leaves to quantify the point of failure of the water transport system (
  <a rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref9">Brodersen 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2019
  </a>). Techniques to quantify xylem vulnerability typically involve the dehydration of excised branches while periodically measuring the flow properties of the xylem. Although some of these techniques have recently been shown to produce errors associated with tissue excision (
  <a rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref27">Longepierre 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2014
  </a>; 
  <a rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref37">Torres-Ruiz 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2014
  </a>), new methods have been developed that avoid excision errors by either measuring 
  <span class="italic">in situ</span> on intact plants or by measuring leaf tissue that can be excised without significant perturbation of the vascular system. One of these methods uses x-ray computed tomography (CT) to identify the presence of air in xylem cells (
  <a rid="ref18" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref18">Cochard 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2015
  </a>), while the other uses an optical technique (
  <a rid="f1" ref-type="fig" href="#f1">Fig. 1</a>) to visualize the process of cavitation in xylem tissue (
  <a rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref13">Brodribb 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2016
  </a>). X-ray CT imaging produces a beautifully resolved 3D map of embolism in the xylem, but it is limited by cost and temporal resolution (scans can only be made infrequently during plant dehydration). The optical method by contrast provides very high temporal resolution of cavitation in the sample but lacks the spatial precision of the CT method. However, the simplicity and low cost of the optical method make it highly suitable for relatively high-throughput measurements that could allow the characterization of forest communities (
  <a rid="f1" ref-type="fig" href="#f1">Fig. 1</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
