<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Rising temperature as a driver of damage</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The most damaging impact of rising temperature on plants is unlikely to be the direct effect of leaf warming but rather the consequences of increased transpiration on the depletion of soil water. Although increased global temperatures may increase the growing season at higher latitudes, a potentially more important global impact of greater heat is increased evaporation (
  <a rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref22">Frank 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2015
  </a>). The rate of water loss from leaves is highly sensitive to temperature such that all else being equal the loss of water from a tree doubles if leaf temperature rises from 30 to 45°C. For this reason, warming atmospheric temperature substantially increases the rate of soil dehydration even if rainfall remains static. Drier soil exposes the water transport system of plants to increased water deficit, increasing the risk of catastrophic damage to the vasculature system (see below). Rapid changes in water balance therefore constitute a major problem for plants because the costs and trade-offs associated with the acquisition, conservation and transport of water have been central drivers of terrestrial plant evolution and extinction since the earliest evolution of land plants (
  <a rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref35">Sperry, 2003</a>). Thus, we find that tree species distribute according to their vascular drought resistances (
  <a rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref12">Brodribb and Hill, 1999</a>), and that the safety margins between survival or damage/mortality during drought may be rather small across the spectrum of rainfall from arid to rainforest communities (
  <a rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref16">Choat 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2012
  </a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Increasing reports of the combined effects of extreme drought and heat producing forest mortality across the globe (
  <a rid="ref29" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref29">McDowell 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2008
  </a>) seem to support the notion that the warming climate is likely to drive increased forest mortality into the future. To understand this pattern, it is imperative to understand the cause of mortality during drought.
 </p>
 <div id="f1" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Different species have different vulnerability of xylem tissue to damage by cavitation. The ‘optical method’ (
    <a rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref10">Brodribb 
     <span class="italic">et al.</span>, 2017
    </a>) is a recently developed approach for quantifying the vulnerability of plant tissues to cavitation during water stress. The optical method is applied here in a 
    <span class="italic">Quercus robur</span> plant to visualize cavitation in stem and leaf xylem tissues. (
    <span class="bold">a</span>) Custom-built miniaturized cameras are shown installed on a stem and a leaf of an oak plant to monitor xylem cavitation events during plant dehydration. (
    <span class="bold">b</span>) Colour map depicting the location of xylem cavitation events in leaf veins and the level of water potential that induces those events (colour scale) on a 
    <span class="italic">Q. robur</span> leaf (scale bar, 1 mm). (
    <span class="bold">c</span>) Optical hydraulic vulnerability curve showing the cumulative embolisms visualized against the water deficit (water potential) in the plant. Plants typically die when &gt; 50% of xylem tissue is damaged, so P
    <sub>50</sub> (blue dashed line) and P
    <sub>88</sub> (red dashed line) values (i.e. water potential at which 50% and 88% of xylem vessels are embolized, respectively) describe the range of water potentials (striped grey bar) where plant mortality is likely to occur.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="coz046f1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
