<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Insect Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Insect Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jis</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Insect Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1536-2442</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name><publisher-loc>US</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6397019</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jisesa/iez017</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">iez017</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Conservation Conundrum: At-risk Bumble Bees (<italic>Bombus</italic> spp.) Show Preference for Invasive Tufted Vetch (<italic>Vicia cracca</italic>) While Foraging in Protected Areas</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-0210-5001</contrib-id><name><surname>Gibson</surname><given-names>Shelby D</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1"/><!--<email>shelbydgibson@gmail.com</email>--></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Liczner</surname><given-names>Amanda R</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Colla</surname><given-names>Sheila R</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0001">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="AF0002">2</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="AF0001"><label>1</label>Faculty of Environmental Studies, York University, Toronto, Ontario, Canada</aff><aff id="AF0002"><label>2</label>Department of Biology, York University, Toronto, Ontario, Canada</aff><author-notes><corresp id="c1">Corresponding author, e-mail: <email>shelbydgibson@gmail.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>3</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub" iso-8601-date="2019-03-02"><day>02</day><month>3</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>02</day><month>3</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><!-- PMC Release delay is 0 months and 0 days and was based on the <pub-date pub-type="epub"/>. --><volume>19</volume><issue>2</issue><elocation-id>10</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>12</day><month>10</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of Entomological Society of America.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><license license-type="cc-by-nc" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/"><license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="iez017.pdf"/><abstract><title>Abstract</title><p>In recent decades, some bumble bee species have declined, including in North America. Declines have been reported in species of bumble bees historically present in Ontario, including: yellow bumble bee (<italic>Bombus fervidus</italic>) (Fabricus, 1798), American bumble bee (<italic>Bombus pensylvanicus</italic>) (DeGeer, 1773), and yellow-banded bumble bee (<italic>Bombus terricola</italic>) (Kirby, 1837). Threats contributing to bumble bee population declines include: land-use changes, habitat loss, climate change, pathogen spillover, and pesticide use. A response to the need for action on pollinator preservation in North America has been to encourage &#x02018;bee-friendly&#x02019; plantings. Previous studies show differences in common and at-risk bumble bee foraging; however, similar data are unavailable for Ontario. Our research question is whether there is a difference in co-occurring at-risk and common bumble bee (<italic>Bombus</italic> spp.) floral use (including nectar and pollen collection) in protected areas in southern Ontario. We hypothesize that common and at-risk species forage differently, predicting that at-risk species forage on a limited selection of host plants. We conducted a field survey of sites in southern Ontario, using observational methods to determine bumble bee foraging by species. The results of a redundancy analysis show a difference in foraging between common and at-risk bumblebee species. At-risk bumble bee species show a preference for foraging on invasive, naturalized <italic>Vicia cracca</italic> (tufted vetch). This finding raises the question of how to preserve or provide forage for at-risk bumble bees, when they show an association with an invasive species often subject to control in protected areas.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd><italic>Plant-pollinator Interactions</italic></kwd><kwd>Conservation</kwd><kwd><italic>Restoration</italic></kwd><kwd><italic>Habitat Management</italic></kwd><kwd>Pollination </kwd></kwd-group><counts><page-count count="10"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><p>Bumble bee (<italic>Bombus</italic> spp.) Latreille populations of particular species have declined globally in recent decades (<xref rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr">Williams 1986</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr">Kearns et al. 1998</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">Colla and Packer 2008</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">Bartomeus et al. 2013</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">Beckham and Atkinson 2017</xref>). A portion of North American bumble bee species have been found to be in decline (<xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">Grixti et al. 2009</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0002" ref-type="bibr">Bartomeus et al. 2013</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">Beckham and Atkinson 2017</xref>), including species once abundant in southern Ontario, Canada (<xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">Colla and Packer 2008</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">Colla and Dumesh 2010</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">Colla et al. 2012</xref>). Threats to bumble bee populations include habitat loss and land-use changes, climate change, pathogen spillover from managed bees, and pesticide use (<xref rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr">Thorp and Shepherd 2005</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">Colla 2006</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">Grixti et al. 2009</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0045" ref-type="bibr">Szabo et al. 2012</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0006a" ref-type="bibr">Colla 2016</xref>). A global sense of urgency over the conservation of pollinators has manifested, due to their importance primarily in agricultural systems (<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">CSPNA 2007</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0006a" ref-type="bibr">Colla 2016</xref>). Recently, there has been increased pressure on policymakers, who are faced with addressing growing concerns over pollinators quickly and effectively (<xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">CSPNA 2007</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0006a" ref-type="bibr">Colla 2016</xref>). Most often, however, policies and programs react to the problem of pollinator declines as a whole, which can cause oversight of important species-specific ecological requirements (<xref rid="CIT0006a" ref-type="bibr">Colla 2016</xref>). This is in part due to the documented lack of data available about wild pollinator species, including bumble bees in Ontario and globally (<xref rid="CIT0003a" ref-type="bibr">Berenbaum et al. 2007</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0012" ref-type="bibr">CSPNA 2007</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">Colla and Packer 2008</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr">Grixti et al. 2009</xref>).</p><p>In the field of conservation biology, a variety of strategies have been designed, recommended, and implemented upon various wildlife populations (<xref rid="CIT0015" ref-type="bibr">Ebenhard et al. 1995</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">Primack 2008</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0051" ref-type="bibr">Winfree 2010</xref>), with a focus on habitat establishment and maintenance (<xref rid="CIT0005" ref-type="bibr">Cameron et al. 2011</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr">IUCN 2016</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr">Beckham and Atkinson 2017</xref>). <xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">Primack (2008)</xref> argues that for protected areas management to be successful it must be adaptive to the results of ongoing research. This is described as adaptive management, characterized by managers adjusting their guiding plans based on ever-changing ecological data from both inside and outside of the protected area (<xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">Primack 2008</xref>). Monitoring involves biodiversity data collection, and habitat maintenance involves management to ensure the persistence of the native/natural biodiversity (<xref rid="CIT0039" ref-type="bibr">Primack 2008</xref>). Using data from within the protected areas can also provide information about historical features of local ecosystems for restoration purposes outside of the protected area. For example, key features of a natural ecosystem, such as at-risk species forage availability, may be observed in the protected area and then used elsewhere if appropriate.</p><p>Bumble bee habitat includes nesting resources, overwintering sites, mating sites, and access to appropriate floral resources for nectar and pollen collection (<xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">Brian 1957</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0017" ref-type="bibr">Goulson 2009</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0006a" ref-type="bibr">Colla 2016</xref>). Habitat requirements are likely to vary by species (<xref rid="CIT0006a" ref-type="bibr">Colla 2016</xref>), but little is known about patterns in variation (<xref rid="CIT0004" ref-type="bibr">Brian 1957</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr">Cock 1978</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0006a" ref-type="bibr">Colla 2016</xref>). For example, studies from Europe show that floral use has previously been found to differ at the species-level, especially in uncommon bumble bee species (<xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">Goulson and Darvill 2004</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">Goulson et al. 2005</xref>). These species-specific differences in habitat requirements have important implications for conservation and management efforts as potential differences in resource preferences would need to be considered (<xref rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr">Lye et al. 2012</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0031" ref-type="bibr">Jha et al. 2013</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0044" ref-type="bibr">Saifuddin and Jha 2014</xref>). Differences in proboscis length among bumblebee species support resource partitioning within a community (<xref rid="CIT0027" ref-type="bibr">Heinrich 1976</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">Ranta and Lundberg 1980</xref>). Bumblebee species with longer tongue lengths forage on plants with a long corolla length, while species with shorter tongues forage on plants with a short corolla (<xref rid="CIT0042" ref-type="bibr">Ranta and Lundberg 1980</xref>). In Europe, bumble bees with long tongues that forage on deep-corolla flowers have been asserted to be most in decline (<xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">Goulson et al. 2005</xref>). Long-tongued species have been suggested to have narrower diets; therefore, populations are impacted more by habitat destruction and fragmentation (<xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">Goulson et al. 2005</xref>). The methods for determining evidence for the &#x02018;food-plant specialization hypothesis&#x02019;, studied by <xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">Goulson and Darvill (2004)</xref>, have been challenged by colleagues in the field (<xref rid="CIT0048" ref-type="bibr">Williams 2005</xref>). Williams highlights that rather than floral specialization, there is a correlation between climatic and habitat specialization and niche breadth (and thus decline). It is possible that dietary breadth is misinterpreted as being the main cause of decline in a species, when in fact there is a more complex explanation, such as climatic specialization or some related factor. Nevertheless, data on floral usage for Ontario&#x02019;s at-risk and common bumble bee species can inform conservation decisions. This can be done by determining if there are species or plant families that at-risk bumble bees preferentially forage on and ensure these species and/or families are abundant or even promoted in management efforts. As bumble bees are both an intrinsically valuable species and critically important to natural and agricultural ecosystems, it is important that their populations are preserved.</p><p>The three at-risk bumble bee species studied here are Bombus <italic>fervidus</italic> (Fabricus, 1798)<italic>, Bombus pensylvanicus</italic> (DeGeer, 1773), and <italic>Bombus terricola</italic> (Kirby, 1837)<italic>. Bombus terricola</italic> is of the subgenus <italic>Bombus</italic> sensu stricto, and <italic>B. fervidus</italic> and <italic>B. pensylvanicus</italic> are of the subgenus <italic>Thoracobombus</italic> (<xref rid="CIT0034" ref-type="bibr">Koch 2011</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">Williams et al. 2014</xref>). The yellow-banded bumble bee (<italic>B. terricola</italic>) was assessed as a species of Special Concern in Canada by the Committee on the Status of Endangered Wildlife in Canada (COSEWIC) in May (2015) and listed as Special Concern in Ontario in 2016 and was listed as Vulnerable by the International Union for the Conservation of Nature (IUCN) (<xref rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr">Hatfield et al. 2015a</xref>). Studies have documented a decline of <italic>B. terricola</italic> abundance in areas of southern Canada where it was once very common (<xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">Colla and Packer 2008</xref>). <xref rid="CIT0011" ref-type="bibr">COSEWIC (2015)</xref> lists various potential threats to <italic>B. terricola</italic> populations and causes for decline, including interaction with pesticides, land-use changes, and pathogen spillover from managed bumble bee colonies (see <xref rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr">Colla 2006</xref>). This bumble bee species generally has a short face and a short tongue length (<xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">Williams et al. 2014</xref>). While limited research from Ontario has found that bees with short tongues tend to have access to a smaller diversity of flowers than bees with long tongues (<xref rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr">Harder 1985</xref>), <italic>B. terricola</italic> has been found foraging on a diversity of plant genera (<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">Colla and Dumesh 2010</xref>). More details are needed about the specific foraging requirements and behavior of this species of Special Concern in Ontario as <italic>B. terricola</italic> is an important species to the natural and agroecosystems in which it lives. This species is known to provide valuable pollination services to wild plants and various agricultural crops such as cranberry (<italic>Vaccinium macrocarpon</italic>) and blueberry (<italic>Vaccinium corymbosum</italic>) (<xref rid="CIT0036" ref-type="bibr">Mackenzie and Averill 1995</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0030" ref-type="bibr">Javorek et al. 2002</xref>). Two other at-risk bumble bees included here are the yellow bumble bee (<italic>B. fervidus</italic>), and the American bumble bee (<italic>B. pensylvanicus</italic>). These two species have been assessed by the IUCN to be Vulnerable (<xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">Hatfield et al. 2015b</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">c</xref>) based on information from documented population declines (<xref rid="CIT0007" ref-type="bibr">Colla and Packer 2008</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">Colla et al. 2012</xref>). Further, <xref rid="CIT0010" ref-type="bibr">Colla et al. (2012)</xref> found <italic>B. pensylvanicus</italic> to be one of eastern North America&#x02019;s most sharply declining species. One major conservation action recommended by IUCN involves the creation, protection, and restoration of habitat for <italic>B. fervidus</italic> and <italic>B. pensylvanicus</italic> (<xref rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr">Hatfield et al. 2015b</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr">c</xref>).</p><p>There is a lack of forage resource data available for at-risk bumble bee species, hindering their conservation management in Ontario and abroad. Continued planning for conservation actions and programs without this information could potentially lead to harmful effects on at-risk bumble bee populations. Given the importance of forage in the creation and restoration of habitat, this study aims to investigate whether there is a difference between common and at-risk bumble bee foraging behavior in southern Ontario, Canada. Our main research question is whether there is a difference in at-risk and common bumble bee (<italic>Bombus</italic> spp.) floral usage (including nectar and pollen collection) in southern Ontario. We examine this research question using associations between bumble bee species and plant forage species and families using redundancy analysis, and by comparing the abundance of foraging at-risk and common bumble bee species on the plant families used for nectar or pollen collection.</p><sec sec-type="materials" id="s1"><title>Methods</title><sec id="s2"><title>Site Selection/Transect Design</title><p>Twenty-five sites were selected for surveying across southern Ontario (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). These sites were selected as they had a recent (between 2001 and 2016) record of <italic>B. terricola</italic> and/or <italic>B. pensylvanicus</italic> and we were successful in gaining access. We obtained a &#x02018;Research Authorization for Provincial Parks and Conservation Reserves&#x02019; permit to conduct research in Ontario&#x02019;s protected areas. The selected sites include national and provincial parks, private land, and conservation areas. These sites had mixed landscape types including forests, grasslands, dunes, and urban areas (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). We chose to focus on <italic>B. terricola</italic> and <italic>B. pensylvanicus</italic> records in determining the sites, as these species represent two different subgenera that are in decline, but still present, in southern Ontario. These two species have distinct habitat requirements with <italic>B. terricola</italic> described as a woodland species and <italic>B. pensylvanicus</italic> as a grassland species (<xref rid="CIT0008" ref-type="bibr">Colla and Dumesh 2010</xref>). Sampling areas were designated using the QGIS buffer function at a distance of 1 km away from the location the recent occurrence record. Two 250-m transects were randomly placed using the QGIS random point function within each buffer. The direction of each transect was determined using a random number generator between 0 and 360&#x000b0;. Each site was to be surveyed three times in 2017 (spring/early, mid-summer, and late-summer). The spring surveys took place between April 24 and May 26, the summer surveys between June 19 and July 7, and the late-summer surveys were between August 7 and August 24. Not every site was surveyed in each time-period due to inability to gain access or flooding in the survey area due to a very wet spring season (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>), but each site was surveyed at least once.</p><table-wrap id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1.</label><caption><p>A description of the 25 sites surveyed during 2017 sampling</p></caption><table frame="vsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site name</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Latitude</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Longitude</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">At-risk recent occurrence</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shannon diversity</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bumble bee species surveyed</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site description</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Arrowhead Provincial Park (3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.3917</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;79.1978</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. terricola</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.63</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. bimaculatus</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. griseocolis</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. impatiens</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. perplexus</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. ternarius</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. vagans</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Densely forested, hills, beach.</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Awenda Provincial Park (3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.84871</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;80.0194</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. terricola</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.66</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. bimaculatus</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. griseocolis</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. impatiens</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. perplexus</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. terricola*</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. vagans</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Densely forested, beach, near open water</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Backus Woods (2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.68102</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;80.4739</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. pensylvanicus</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. bimaculatus</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. griseocolis</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. impatiens</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. perplexus</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. terricola*</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. vagans</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forest and grassland patches sandy soil, surrounded by agriculture</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bass Lake Provincial Park (3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.60251</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;79.4867</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. terricola</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. borealis</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forest, beach, near open water, marshy</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bayview Park (3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.38811</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;79.6869</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Both</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.61</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. bimaculatus</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. impatiens</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urban park, lawn and maintained gardens, near open water, scattered trees, urban landscape</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beausoleil Island (1)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.84754</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;79.8605</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. terricola</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. bimaculatus</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. impatiens</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. griseocolis</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forested with some built-up recreational areas, near open water</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Black Creek Provincial Park (3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.96836</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;81.3625</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. terricola</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. bimaculatus</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. borealis</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. griseocolis</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. impatiens</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. ternarius</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dense forest, near open water, beach</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bruce Peninsula National Park (3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.2128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;81.4895</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. terricola</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. bimaculatus</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. griseocolis</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. impatiens</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. vagans</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dense forest, wet soil</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bruce Trail Caledon (3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.8015</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;79.99</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. terricola</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forest, exposed rock, steep rockface</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Central Big Creek Block (3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.64919</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;80.5604</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. pensylvanicus</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.54</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. bimaculatus</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. fervidus*</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. griseocolis</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. impatiens</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. terricola*</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forest and grassland patches, sandy soil, surrounded by agriculture</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forks of the Credit Provincial Park (3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.8249</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;80.004</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Both</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. bimaculatus</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. borealis</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. griseocolis</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. impatiens</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. pensylvanicus*</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. vagans</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grassland and sloping hills some wooded areas</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Guelph Lake Conservation Area (3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.596</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;80.252</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. terricola</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. bimaculatus</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. griseocolis</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. impatiens</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. pensylvanicus*</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. vagans</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Campground surrounded by forest, pollinator garden within a grassland</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Harris Park (3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.983</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;81.25</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. pensylvanicus</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. bimaculatus</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. griseocolis</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. impatiens</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. rufocinctus</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. ternarius</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. vagans</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Urban park, lawn, few scattered trees, urban landscape</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inverhuron Provincial Park (3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.2987</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;81.5944</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. terricola</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.52</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. bimaculatus</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. borealis</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. griseocolis</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. impatiens</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. terricola*</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dense forest, few forest clearings, near open water</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">MacNaughton Trail (3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;81.483</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. pensylvanicus</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. griseocolis</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. impatiens</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. vagans</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forest, surrounded by agriculture, marsh and residential development</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mara Provincial Park (3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.58661</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;79.3571</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. terricola</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.97</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. borealis</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. imaptiens</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. vagans</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forest, beach, near open water, marsh</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Matchedash Bay (3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.75084</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;79.646</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. terricola</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.41</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. bimaculatus</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. borealis</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. citrinus</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. impatiens</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. perplexus</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. rufocinctus</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wetland and forest, surrounded by agriculture</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pinery Provincial Park (2)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.2734</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;81.8183</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. pensylvanicus</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.49</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. bimaculatus</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. citrinus</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. griseocolis</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. impatiens</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. vagans</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forest, dunes, beach, near open water</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pollinators Park (3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.57776</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;80.2331</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Both</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.82</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. bimaculatus</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. borealis</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. fervidus*</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. griseocolis</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. impatiens</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. rufocinctus</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. terricola*</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. vagans</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grassland, surrounded by development</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scotsdale Farm (3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.69024</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;80.0051</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. terricola</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.22</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. bimaculatus</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. borealis</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. griseocolis</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. impatiens</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forest and rangeland, surrounded by agriculture, marsh</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Singing Sands (3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.1912</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;81.5776</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. terricola</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. bimaculatus</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. borealis</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. fervidus*</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beach, dunes, near open water, dense forest</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sulfur Springs Conservation Area (3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.11729</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;81.0035</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. terricola</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.1</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. bimaculatus</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. impatiens</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. perplexus</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Forest and marsh, surrounded by agriculture</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Turkey Point Provincial Park (3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.7279</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;80.3369</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. pensylvanicus</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.69</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. impatiens</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. vagans</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Densely forested, some forest clearings</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">University of Guelph Arboretum (3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">43.54205</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;80.2115</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. terricola</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. bimaculatus</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. griseocolis</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. imaptiens</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. vagans</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maintained gardens, scattered trees, forest, arboretum</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Waubaushene Beaches (3)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">44.75054</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x02212;79.7209</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. terricola</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. bimaculatus</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. impatiens</italic>
<break/>
<italic>B. vagans</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Shrubland meadow, scattered trees, sandy soil</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="fn-0100"><p>The number of times the site was surveyed is given in bracket. The at-risk bumble bee species that was recently observed at each site is given as &#x02018;at-risk recent occurrence&#x02019;. The at-risk bumble bee species that was recently (past ten years) observed at each site and a general description of the site are also given. The Shannon diversity estimate for each site is listed as well as all bumble bee species found during sampling (* denotes at-risk species).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig fig-type="figure" id="F1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 1.</label><caption><p>Map of survey site locations for sampling declining bumblebees in southern Ontario. Site locations were based on historical data of presence of at-risk species: red = <italic>B. terricola</italic>, yellow = <italic>B. pensylvanicus</italic>, orange = both. Twenty-two sites were surveyed three times, two sites were surveyed twice, and one site was surveyed once.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="iez017f0001"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Survey Methods</title><p>Observational survey methods were used to collect bumble bees for this study. Transects were walked once a day at each site and each bumble bee present along the transect foraging on a flower within 2 m on either side was recorded. Foraging bees were collected using a sweep net or by vial collection on the flower (<xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">Kearns and Inouye 1993</xref>). Determination between nectar and pollen foraging was made using a combination of observing bees grooming pollen toward their corbiculae, while on the flower, and presence of pollen sacs, prior to net collection (<xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">Goulson and Darvill 2004</xref>). Bees otherwise on the flower were recorded as collecting nectar. The date, site, time, and host plant (i.e., the forage species) were recorded on the vial for each of the bumble bees, which were then placed inside a small lunch cooler containing freezer packs. The freezer packs help to cool the bumble bees down to the appropriate temperature required for them to stop moving which allows for identification in the field. While the bumble bees were chilled, photos were taken to verify the species-level identification of each bumble bee collected during the study. Photos were also taken of each plant for identification purposes. In most cases, a voucher worker specimen was collected for each bumble bee species recorded and identified using <xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">Williams et al. (2014)</xref>. The majority of bees were released after identification. Only a small number of bees were collected for identification later in the lab. A table was used to record the count and status of bumble bees collected during this survey (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). Voucher specimens and specimens difficult to identify in the field were collected. Collected specimens were frozen in the vial. Each bee was pinned to the right of the center of the thorax using size II BioQuip Insect Pins (<xref rid="CIT0032" ref-type="bibr">Kearns and Inouye 1993</xref>). This collection is being held in Dr. Colla&#x02019;s laboratory at York University, Toronto, Ontario, Canada. Bumble bees were identified according to Bumble Bees of North America (<xref rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr">Williams et al. 2014</xref>). Plants bumble bees were observed foraging on were identified according to Plants of Southern Ontario (<xref rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr">Dickinson and Royer 2014</xref>). Plants were identified to species level when possible and were otherwise identified to family level. Species identification was verified by Dr. Colla and Victoria MacPhail, York University.</p><table-wrap id="T2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2. </label><caption><p>Count of each bumble bee species (<italic>Bombus</italic> spp.) collected during opportunistic sampling along transects in southern Ontario between April and August 2017</p></caption><table frame="vsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bumble bee (<italic>Bombus</italic> sp.) species</th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Count</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. bimaculatus</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">98</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. borealis</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. citrinus</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. fervidus*</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. griseocollis</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">75</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. impatiens</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">179</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. pensylvanicus*</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. perplexus</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. rufocinctus</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. ternarius</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. terricola*</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<italic>B. vagans</italic>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="fn-0101"><p>Species marked with * are at-risk in our study based on declining and vulnerable population trends as assessed by the IUCN Red List.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Statistical Analysis</title><p>The number of host plant species found for a particular number of sites sampled was determined with a species accumulation curve using the <italic>specaccum</italic> function (<xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">Oksanen et al. 2018</xref>) (e.g., <xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">Williams et al. 2009</xref>). The number of resampling events at each site was 999. Redundancy analysis (RDA) was used to determine whether common and at-risk bumble bee species forage on different plant species for mid and late-summer combined, and mid and late-summer analyzed separately. The variables that were included were the forage species and family and the bumble bee species that were observed foraging on these species. The early season was not included in either RDA as we did not find any at-risk species during spring sampling. Collinear variables were identified using variance inflation factors (<italic>vifcor</italic> function in package <italic>usdm</italic>) and all identified collinear variables (<italic>R</italic> = &#x0003e;0.90) were removed as they would introduce redundancy into the model. The list of collinear variables is given in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup2">Supplementary Appendix Table 1</xref>. Redundancy analysis was performed using the <italic>rda</italic> and <italic>enfit</italic> functions (<italic>vegan</italic> package) using the covariance matrix and scaling set to sites (<xref rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr">Naimi et al. 2014</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr">Oksanen et al. 2018</xref>). A redundancy analysis was used as our data are multivariate data and contain both response and explanatory variables (i.e., bumble bee species and forage species/families). The Hellinger transformation was applied to the data prior to running the RDA as the data contained many zeros and to avoid the double-zero effect (<xref rid="CIT0052" ref-type="bibr">Zuur et al. 2007</xref>). Shannon diversity was calculated for the bumble bee species found foraging at all sites using the <italic>diversity</italic> function (<italic>vegan</italic> package). All statistical analyses were performed using R (version 3.4.3. 2017) (<xref rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr">R Core Development Team 2017</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0041" ref-type="bibr">R Documents 2018</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s5"><title>Results</title><p>At-risk species were observed at eight of our study sites (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref>). The sites surveyed ranged in richness from zero to eight bumble bee species and had a Shannon diversity value between 0 and 1.82 (<xref rid="T1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). There were 5 <italic>B. fervidus</italic>, 2 <italic>B. pensylvanicus</italic>, and 13 <italic>B. terricola</italic> individuals recorded foraging during this survey, and a total of 454 individuals of other, not at-risk bumble bees (<xref rid="T2" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). The results of a species accumulation curve showed that increased sampling would have increased the number of host plant species for both common and at-risk species (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup1">Supplementary Appendix Fig. 1</xref>).</p><p>At-risk bumble bee species foraged on different plant families/species than common bee species (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). All three at-risk bumble bee species (<italic>B. fervidus, B. pensylvanicus,</italic> and <italic>B. terricola</italic>) foraged on similar plant species/families when forage data was summarized across the mid and late season (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>) or only in late season when each season was analyzed separately (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). In mid-season, two of three species foraged on similar plants (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). The at-risk bumble bee species were consistently associated with the invasive plant species <italic>V. cracca</italic> Linnaeus (tufted vetch) and <italic>Fabaceae</italic> Linnaeus (legumes) in late-summer (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figs. 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref>). In mid-summer, <italic>B. terricola</italic> was more positively correlated with the family <italic>Fabaceae</italic> than <italic>V. cracca</italic> and was weakly correlated with the other at-risk species <italic>B. fervidus</italic> or <italic>B. pensylvanicus</italic>. In mid-summer, <italic>B. fervidus and B. pensylvanicus</italic> had a strong positive correlation with <italic>V. cracca,</italic> and a weaker but still positive correlation with <italic>Fabaceae</italic>. B<italic>. terricola</italic> was positively correlated with <italic>Trifolium pratense</italic> Fabales:Fabaceae, Linnaeus (red clover) and <italic>Securigera varia</italic> Fabales: Fabaceae, Lassen (crown vetch) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). The at-risk species <italic>B. fervidus</italic> and <italic>B. pensylvanicus</italic> were positively correlated with <italic>V. cracca</italic> for forage in mid-summer. In late-summer, all three at-risk bumble bee species were positively correlated with <italic>Fabaceae</italic>, <italic>V. cracca, T. pratense</italic> (red clover), and <italic>Lespedeza capitata</italic> Fabales: Fabaceae, Michaux (round bush clover) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>).</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 2.</label><caption><p>Redundancy analysis showing the association between at-risk and common bumble bee (<italic>Bombus</italic> spp.) species and host plant for Mid, and Late season foraging in southern Ontario between April and August 2017. Red text indicates the at-risk bumble bee species. The total variance explained is 38.2%.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="iez017f0002"/></fig><fig fig-type="figure" id="F3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 3.</label><caption><p>Redundancy analysis of foraging preferences among at-risk and common bumble bee species from 25 sites across southern Ontario. The top panel is mid-summer and the bottom panel is late-summer foraging observations. Red text denotes the at-risk species. The total variation explained is 44.1% and 41.2% for mid-summer and late-summer, respectively.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="iez017f0003"/></fig><p>Common bee species were found to forage more often on <italic>Asteraceae</italic> (asters), <italic>Solidago</italic> (goldenrod), (<italic>Bombus impatiens, Cresson, Bombus griseocollis, De Geer</italic>), <italic>Lamiaceae</italic> (mints), and <italic>Prunella vulgaris</italic> Lamiales: Lamiaceae, Linnaeus (self-heal) (<italic>Bombus vagans</italic>, Smith, <italic>Bombus rufocinctus</italic>, Cresson, <italic>Bombus ternarius</italic>, Say, <italic>Bombus perplexus</italic>, Cresson) over the whole season (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>). In mid-summer, common bumble bee species were positively correlated with <italic>Lonicera dioica</italic> Dipsacales: Caprifoliaceae, Linnaeus (Twinning honeysuckle) (<italic>Bombus bimaculatus</italic>, Cresson, <italic>B. perplexus</italic>, Cresson) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). In late-summer, common bumble bee species were positively correlated with <italic>Asteraceae</italic> and <italic>Solidago</italic>, (<italic>B. griseocollis</italic>, <italic>Bombus citrinus</italic>, Smith, <italic>B. ternarius</italic>), <italic>Lamiaceae,</italic> and <italic>Prunella vulgaris</italic> (<italic>B. rufocinctus</italic>, <italic>B. impatiens</italic>, <italic>B. perplexus</italic>) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>). Over the whole season, common bumble bees were correlated with <italic>Asteraceae</italic> and <italic>Solidago</italic> (<italic>B. griseocolis</italic>, <italic>B. impatiens</italic>, <italic>B. citrinus</italic>, and <italic>Bombus borealis</italic>), Kirby, <italic>Lamiaceae</italic> and <italic>Prunella vulgaris</italic> (<italic>B. vagans</italic>, <italic>B. rufocinctus</italic>, <italic>B. ternarius</italic>, <italic>B. perplexus</italic>).</p><p>A total of 194 bumble bees were recorded foraging for pollen, and 269 for nectar (some undetermined whether pollen or nectar foraging) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>). Common bumble bee species foraged on 21 plant families and foraged for both pollen and nectar primarily on three plant families, <italic>Asteraceae</italic>, <italic>Fabaceae</italic>, and <italic>Lamiaceae</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>). At-risk bumble bee species foraged on four plant families, including <italic>Fabaceae</italic> and <italic>Rosaceae</italic> for pollen, and <italic>Asteraceae, Fabaceae,</italic> and <italic>Grossulariaceae</italic> for nectar (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>). The majority of at-risk bumble bee species foraging was on <italic>V. cracca</italic> (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup3">Supplementary Appendix Table 2</xref>).</p><fig fig-type="figure" id="F4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 4.</label><caption><p>Count of common (C) and at-risk (AR) bumble bees foraging for nectar (N) and pollen (P) on plant families found during opportunistic field surveys in southern Ontario protected areas during the Early, Mid, and Late seasons, between April and August 2017.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="iez017f0004"/></fig></sec><sec id="s6"><title>Discussion</title><p>The results of our research provide important information which may be used in efforts to restore and conserve bumble bee habitat in Ontario, particularly by influencing decisions on forage plants used in restoration. Our results indicate at-risk and common species use the same plant community in different ways. In particular, we provide evidence of an association between at-risk bumble bee species and the plant family <italic>Fabaceae</italic>, particularly <italic>V. cracca</italic>, which the at-risk bumble bees recorded used for nectar and pollen collection. Land managers in habitat restoration face the challenge of providing both nectar and pollen sources for at-risk bumble bee species. Common bumble bee species were also commonly recorded visiting <italic>V. cracca,</italic> however were not associated with any particular plant species/family. There are some shortcomings in this study, which may restrict its application, however, this work does give us a preliminary understanding which can be used to design further research to understand the ecological requirements of at-risk bumble bees in Ontario. The result of our species accumulation curve shows that we did not sample sufficiently to capture all of the potential forage plants being used by either common or at-risk bumble bee species. Our study, therefore, cannot provide data on dietary breadth for the studied bumble bee species, a limitation also mentioned in previous relevant studies (<xref rid="CIT0018" ref-type="bibr">Goulson and Darvill 2004</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr">Williams et al. 2009</xref>). Another limitation would be the potential inaccuracy of determining between pollen and nectar collection, which is unlikely to be exactly correct.</p><p>In our study, at-risk bumble bees were positively correlated with <italic>V. cracc</italic>a, most often documented collecting pollen on this plant (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="sup3">Supplementary Appendix Table 2</xref>). <italic>Vicia cracca</italic> blooms May&#x02013;July (<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">Aarssen et al. 1986</xref>), which includes most of our study season (late April to late August). The <italic>Fabaceae</italic> &#x02018;pea&#x02019; or &#x02018;bean&#x02019; family (interchangeable with <italic>Leguminosae</italic>) is a large family of flowering plants, many of which are economically important in North America (<xref rid="CIT0001a" ref-type="bibr">APG 2009</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0028" ref-type="bibr">IAPT 2012</xref>). While <italic>Fabaceae</italic> is considered to have worldwide distribution (<xref rid="CIT0001a" ref-type="bibr">APG 2009</xref>), some species within this family are considered invasive species in Ontario. Included in this category is the species <italic>V. cracca</italic> (tufted vetch), which is classified as exotic, invasive, and naturalized in Ontario, and throughout most of Canada (<xref rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr">Aarssen et al. 1986</xref>). <italic>Vicia cracca</italic> is considered a weed by the Ontario Ministry of Agriculture, Food, and Rural Affairs (OMAFRA), and warrants the use of pesticides for control in agricultural areas in Ontario (<xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">Cowbrough 2005</xref>). Pesticides are used to control <italic>V. cracca</italic> mainly in soybean, corn, and winter wheat plantings (<xref rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr">Cowbrough 2005</xref>). This raises a significant conservation conundrum, where at-risk bumble bees have shown a preference for foraging on an invasive plant species that may face extensive eradication protocols including pesticide application. Research from Europe has associated reduction of legume plantings with decreases in certain bumble bee populations (<xref rid="CIT0020" ref-type="bibr">Goulson et al. 2005</xref>). Future research may investigate whether a highly invasive species should be preserved in order to help conserve an at-risk bumble bee species, or perhaps if a similar native plant species could be supplemented for <italic>V. cracca</italic> and used in bee-friendly plantings, particularly when conservation efforts occur in protected areas.</p><p>Another consideration for land managers is the changes that occur in plant availability over the season. Our results show that in mid-season <italic>B. terricola</italic> was more associated with <italic>Fabaceae</italic> than <italic>V. cracca,</italic> whereas <italic>B. fervidus</italic> and <italic>B. pensylvanicus</italic> were more associated with <italic>V. cracca.</italic> There is a difference in tongue length between these species, with <italic>B. terricola</italic> having a short tongue, and <italic>B. fervidus</italic> and <italic>B. pensylvanicus</italic> having long tongues. Perhaps, due to short tongue length, <italic>B. terricola</italic> prefers to forage on short corolla flowers (e.g., crown vetch, red clover), before attempting to forage on <italic>V. cracca</italic> (<xref rid="CIT0006a" ref-type="bibr">Colla 2016</xref>). In the late season, <italic>V. cracca</italic> is not in full bloom, so it is possible that this explains why the at-risk species are less associated with <italic>V. cracca</italic> at this point, however still associated with <italic>Fabaceae</italic>. This indicates that land managers working on habitat restoration must ensure that there is a supply of short and long corolla flowers available at all times throughout the season.</p><p>Our research warrants further study on appropriate methods for habitat restoration and monitoring in the future. Perhaps, <italic>Fabaceae</italic> is more visually attractive to at-risk bumble bees and thus they might show a preference for those plants. Perhaps, at-risk bumble bee populations at our sites have been influenced by the nectar or pollen quality of these preferred plants, as pollen quality is known to differ by plant species (<xref rid="CIT0043" ref-type="bibr">Roulston et al. 2000</xref>, <xref rid="CIT0016" ref-type="bibr">Forcone et al. 2011</xref>). <italic>Fabaceae</italic> may provide important food sources in degraded bumble bee habitat. Where species are experiencing environmental stressors, perhaps they forage on abundant weedy species to minimize energetic and cognitive costs associated with learning different flowers or foraging farther for less abundant species. While bumble bees were mostly found foraging on non-native species of <italic>Fabaceae</italic>, there are many native species within the family that might be used for habitat restoration purposes.</p><p>Many important features are required to provide high-quality bumble bee habitat, including both nectar and pollen forage resources. Populations of bumble bees found to be influenced by various threats, including <italic>B. fervidus</italic>, <italic>B. pensylvanicus,</italic> and <italic>B. terricola</italic>, will require targeted conservation programs to maintain resilience and avoid population declines. Part of this work includes collecting baseline data to ensure that future conservation programs have species-specific data to work with. Here, we present records of foraging behavior for common and at-risk bumble bee species in various protected areas in Ontario, Canada. Common bumble bees did not show such an association with a particular plant family or species but were found foraging on a broad host of plant families and species. At-risk bumble bees show an association with <italic>Fabaceae</italic>, specifically <italic>V. cracca</italic>. Future conservation research should further consider the role of this plant family as an ecological requirement for at-risk bumble bees.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary Material</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sup1"><label>Supplementary Figure 1</label><media xlink:href="iez017_suppl_supplementary_figure_1.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sup2"><label>Supplementary Table 1</label><media xlink:href="iez017_suppl_supplementary_table_1.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="sup3"><label>Supplementary Table 2</label><media xlink:href="iez017_suppl_supplementary_table_2.docx"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We would like to thank Leif Richardson for the development and maintenance of the Bumble Bees of North America database used for site selections in this study. We would like to thank the staff at the Parks Canada, Ontario Provincial Parks, Ontario Ministry of Natural Resources and Forestry, the Nature Conservancy of Canada, Scotsdale Farm, Ausable Bayfield Conservation Authority, Bruce Trail Conservancy, Grand River Conservation Authority, Guelph Lake Conservation Area, Guelph University Arboretum, Matchedash Bay Conservation Association, Pollination Guelph, and Sulphur Springs Conservation Area for allowing us to conduct this study on their property and for providing their expertise, guidance, and assistance when requested. This research was paid for through an NSERC Discovery Grant to S.R.C. and by Wildlife Preservation Canada.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References Cited</title><ref id="CIT0001"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Aarssen</surname><given-names>L. W.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>I. V.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Jensen</surname><given-names>K. I. N.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>1986</year>
<article-title>The biology of Canadian weeds 76. <italic>Vicia angustifolia</italic> L., <italic>V. cracca</italic> L., <italic>V. sativa</italic> L., <italic>V. tetrasperma</italic> (L.) Schreb. and <italic>V. villosa</italic> Roth</article-title>. <source>Can. J. Plant Sci</source>. <volume>66</volume>: <fpage>711</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>737</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0001a"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<collab>Angiosperm Phylogeny Group (APG)</collab>. <year>2009</year>. An update of the Angiosperm Phylogeny Group classification for the orders and families of flowering plants: APG III. Bot. J. Linn. Soc. 161: 105&#x02013;121.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0002"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bartomeus</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ascher</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gibbs</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Danforth</surname><given-names>B. N.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hedtke</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Winfree</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Historical changes in northeastern US bee pollinators related to shared ecological traits</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source><volume>110</volume>: <fpage>4656</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>4660</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23487768</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0003"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Beckham</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Atkinson</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<article-title>An updated understanding of Texas bumble bee (<italic>Hymenoptera: Apidae</italic>) species presence and potential distributions in Texas, USA</article-title>. <source>PeerJ</source><volume>5</volume>: <fpage>e3612</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28828241</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0003a"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Berenbaum, M., P. Bernhardt, S. Buchmann, N. Calderone, P. Goldstein, D. W. Inouye, P. Kevan, C. Kremen, R. A. Medellin, T. Ricketts, et al. 2007. Status of Pollinators in North America, The National Academies Press, Washington, DC.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0004"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Brian</surname><given-names>A. D</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1957</year>
<article-title>Differences in the flowers visited by four species of bumble-bees and their causes</article-title>. <source>J. Anim. Ecol</source>. <volume>26</volume>: <fpage>71</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>98</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0005"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jepsen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Spivak</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Strange</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vaughan</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Engler</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Byers</surname><given-names>O.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<source>North American bumble bee species conservation planning workshop final report</source>. <publisher-name>IUCN/SSC Conservation Breeding Specialist Group</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Apple Valley, MN</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0006"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cock</surname><given-names>M. J. W</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1978</year>
<article-title>The assessment of preference</article-title>. <source>J. Anim. Ecol</source>. <volume>47</volume>: <fpage>805</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>816</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0006a"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">Colla, S. 2016. Status, threats, and conservation recommendations for wild bumble bees (Bombus spp.) in Ontario, Canada: a review for policymakers and practitioners. Nat. Area J. 36: 412&#x02013;426.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0007"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Colla</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Packer</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Evidence for decline in eastern North American bumble bees (<italic>Hymenoptera: Apidae</italic>), with special reference to <italic>Bombus affnis</italic> Cresson</article-title>. <source>Biodivers. Conserv</source>. <volume>17</volume>:<fpage>1379</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1391</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0008"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Colla</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Dumesh</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>The bumble bees of Southern Ontario: notes on natural history and distribution</article-title>. <source>J. Entomol. Soc. Ont</source>. <volume>141</volume>: <fpage>39</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>68</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0009"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Colla</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Otterstatter</surname><given-names>M. C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gegear</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Thomson</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Plight of the bumble bee: pathogen spillover from commercial to wild populations</article-title>. <source>Biol. Conserv</source>. <volume>129</volume>: <fpage>461</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>467</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0010"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Colla</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gadallah</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Gall</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Assessing declines of North American bumble bees (<italic>Bombus</italic> spp.) using museum specimens</article-title>. <source>Biodivers. Conserv</source>. <volume>21</volume>: <fpage>3585</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3595</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0011"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Committee on the Status of Endangered Wildlife in Canada. (COSEWIC)</collab></person-group>
<year>2015</year>
<comment>COSEWIC assessment and status report on the yellow-banded bumble bee <italic>Bombus terricola</italic> in Canada</comment>
<publisher-name>Committee on the Status of Endangered Wildlife in Canada</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Ottawa</publisher-loc> pp. 
<fpage>ix + 60</fpage> Available from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.registrelep-sararegistry.gc.ca/default_e.cfm">www.registrelep-sararegistry.gc.ca/default_e.cfm</ext-link>. Accessed September 2018.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0012"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Committee on the Status of Pollinators in North America National Research Council (CSPNA)</collab></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<source>Status of pollinators in North America</source>. <publisher-name>National Academies Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0013"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Cowbrough</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<comment>Vetch, tufted (<italic>Vicia cracca</italic> L.)</comment>
<publisher-name>Ontario Ministry of Agriculture, Food, and Rural Affairs</publisher-name> Queen&#x02019;s Printer for Ontario. Available from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.omafra.gov.on.ca/english/crops/field/weeds/tufted_vetch.htm">http://www.omafra.gov.on.ca/english/crops/field/weeds/tufted_vetch.htm</ext-link>. Accessed March 2018.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0014"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Dickinson</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Royer</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<source>Plants of Southern Ontario</source>. <publisher-name>Lone Pine Publishing</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Vancouver, BC</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0015"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ebenhard</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1995</year>
<article-title>Conservation breeding as a tool for saving animal species from extinction</article-title>. <source>Trends Ecol. Evol</source>. <volume>10</volume>: <fpage>438</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>443</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21237098</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0016"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Forcone</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Aloisi</surname><given-names>P. V.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ruppel</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Mu&#x000f1;oz</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<article-title>Botanical composition and protein content of pollen collected by <italic>Apis mellifera</italic> L. in the north-west of Santa Cruz (Argentinean Patagonia)</article-title>. <source>Grana</source><volume>50</volume>: <fpage>30</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>39</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0017"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goulson</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<source>Bumble bees: behavior, ecology and conservation</source>. <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>London, UK</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0018"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goulson</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Darvill</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Niche overlap and diet breadth in bumblebees: are rare species more specialized in their choice of flowers?</article-title><source>Apidologie</source><volume>35</volume>: <fpage>55</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>63</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0020"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Goulson</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hanley</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Darvill</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ellis</surname><given-names>J. S.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Knight</surname><given-names>M. E.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Causes of rarity in bumblebees</article-title>. <source>Biol. Conserv</source>. <volume>122</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0022"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Grixti</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>L. T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cameron</surname><given-names>S. A.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Favret</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Decline of bumble bees (<italic>Bombus</italic>) in the North American Midwest</article-title>. <source>Biol. Conserv</source>. <volume>142</volume>:<fpage>75</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>84</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0023"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Harder</surname><given-names>L. D</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1985</year>
<article-title>Morphology as a predictor of flower choice by bumble bees</article-title>. <source>Ecology</source><volume>66</volume>:<fpage>198</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>210</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0024"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hatfield</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jepsen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thorp</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Colla</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2015a</year>
<article-title>Bombus terricola</article-title>. <source>The IUCN Red List of Threatened Species</source><volume>2015</volume>: <fpage>e.T44937505A46440206</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2305/IUCN.UK.2015-2.RLTS.T44937505A46440206.en</pub-id> Available from <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.iucnredlist.org/species/44937505/46440206">https://www.iucnredlist.org/species/44937505/46440206</uri>. Accessed March 2018.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0025"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hatfield</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jepsen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thorp</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Colla</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Foltz Jordan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2015b</year>
<article-title>Bombus pensylvanicus</article-title>. <source>The IUCN Red List of Threatened Species</source><volume>2015</volume>: <fpage>e.T21215172A21215281</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2305/IUCN.UK.2015-4.RLTS.T21215172A21215281.en</pub-id> Available from <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.iucnredlist.org/species/21215172/21215281">https://www.iucnredlist.org/species/21215172/21215281</uri>. Accessed March 2018.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0026"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hatfield</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jepsen</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thorp</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Colla</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Foltz Jordan</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2015c</year>
<article-title>Bombus fervidus</article-title>. <source>The IUCN Red List of Threatened Species</source><volume>2015</volume>: <fpage>e.T21215132A21215225</fpage>. doi:<pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2305/IUCN.UK.2015-4.RLTS.T21215132A21215225.en</pub-id> Available from <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="https://www.iucnredlist.org/species/21215132/21215225">https://www.iucnredlist.org/species/21215132/21215225</uri>. Accessed March 2018.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0027"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Heinrich</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1976</year>
<article-title>Resource partitioning among some eusocial insects: bumblebees</article-title>. <source>Ecology</source><volume>57</volume>: <fpage>874</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>889</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0028"><mixed-citation publication-type="webpage">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>International Association for Plant Taxonomy (IAPT)</collab></person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<comment>Chapter III. Nomenclature of taxa according to their rank</comment> Available from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.iapt-taxon.org/nomen/main.php?page=art18">http://www.iapt-taxon.org/nomen/main.php?page=art18</ext-link>. Accessed September 2018.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0029"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>International Union for the Conservation of Nature (IUCN)</collab></person-group>
<year>2016</year>
<comment>Save our Species (SOS): Five years of conservation action. Report 2011&#x02013;2016</comment> Available from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://portals.iucn.org/library/sites/library/files/documents/2016&#x02013;043.pdf">https://portals.iucn.org/library/sites/library/files/documents/2016&#x02013;043.pdf</ext-link>. Accessed September 2018.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0030"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Javorek</surname><given-names>S. K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>MacKenzie</surname><given-names>K. E.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Vander Kloet</surname><given-names>S. P.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Comparative pollination effectiveness among bees on lowbush blueberry</article-title>. <source>Ann. Entomol. Soc. Am</source>. <volume>95</volume>: <fpage>345</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>351</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0031"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jha</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stefanovich</surname><given-names>L. E. V.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Kremen</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2013</year>
<article-title>Bumble bee pollen use and preference across spatial scales in human&#x02010;altered landscapes</article-title>. <source>Ecol. Entomol</source>. <volume>38</volume>: <fpage>570</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>579</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0032"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kearns</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Inouye</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>1993</year>
<source>Techniques for pollination biologists</source>. <publisher-name>University Press of Colorado</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Niwot, CO</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0033"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kearns</surname><given-names>C. A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Inouye</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Waser</surname><given-names>N. M.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>1998</year>
<article-title>Endangered mutualisms: the conservation of plant-pollinator interactions</article-title>. <source>Annu. Rev. Ecol. Syst</source>. <volume>29</volume>: <fpage>83&#x000d0;112</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0034"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Koch</surname><given-names>J. B</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2011</year>
<source>&#x0201c;The decline and conservation status of North American bumble bees&#x0201d;</source>. All Graduate Theses and Dissertations. Utah State University, Logan, Utah. Paper 1015.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0035"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lye</surname><given-names>G. C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Osborne</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Park</surname><given-names>K. J.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Goulson</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Using citizen science to monitor <italic>Bombus</italic> populations in the UK: nesting ecology and relative abundance in the urban environment</article-title>. <source>J. Insect Conserv</source>. <volume>16</volume>: <fpage>697</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>707</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0036"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>MacKenzie</surname><given-names>K. E.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Averill</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>1995</year>
<article-title>Bee (<italic>Hymenoptera: Apoidea</italic>) diversity and abundance on cranberry in Southeastern Massachusetts</article-title>. <source>Ann. Entomol. Soc. Am</source>. <volume>88</volume>: <fpage>334</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>341</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0037"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Naimi</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hamm</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Groen</surname><given-names>T. A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Skidmore</surname><given-names>A. K.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Toxopeus</surname><given-names>A. G.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Where is positional uncertainty a problem for species distribution modelling</article-title>. <source>Ecography</source><volume>37</volume>:<fpage>191</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>203</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0038"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Oksanen</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Blanchet</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Friendly</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kindt</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Legendre</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McGlinn</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Minchin</surname><given-names>P. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>O&#x02019;Hara</surname><given-names>R. B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Simpson</surname><given-names>G. L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Solymos</surname><given-names>P. M.</given-names></name>, </person-group>
<etal>et al</etal>
<year>2018</year>
<comment>vegan: community ecology package. R package version 2.4&#x02013;6</comment> Available from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=vegan">https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=vegan</ext-link>. Accessed March 2018.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0039"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Primack</surname><given-names>R. B</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<source>A primer of conservation biology</source>, <edition>4th ed</edition>
<publisher-name>Sinauer Associates, Inc.</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Sunderland, MA</publisher-loc> ISBN <isbn>978-0-87893-692-2</isbn>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0040"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>R Development Core Team</collab></person-group>
<year>2017</year>
<source>R: a language and environment for statistical computing</source>. <publisher-name>R foundation for Statistical Computing</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Vienna, Austria</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0041"><mixed-citation publication-type="other">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>R Documents</collab></person-group>
<year>2018</year>
<comment>Fitting generalized linear models</comment> Available from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://stat.ethz.ch/R-manual/R-devel/library/stats/html/glm.html">https://stat.ethz.ch/R-manual/R-devel/library/stats/html/glm.html</ext-link>. Accessed March 2018.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0042"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ranta</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Lundberg</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>1980</year>
<article-title>Resource partitioning in bumblebees: the significance of differences in proboscis length</article-title>. <source>Oikos</source><volume>35</volume>: <fpage>298</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>302</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0043"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Roulston</surname><given-names>T. H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Cane</surname><given-names>J. H.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Buchman</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>What governs protein content of pollen: pollinator preferences, pollen-pistil interactions, or phylogeny?</article-title><source>Ecol. Monogr</source>. <volume>70</volume>: <fpage>617</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>643</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0044"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saifuddin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Jha</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<article-title>Colony-level variation in pollen collection and foraging preferences among wild-caught bumble bees (<italic>Hymenoptera: Apidae</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Environ. Entomol</source>. <volume>43</volume>: <fpage>393</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>401</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24763096</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0045"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Szabo</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Colla</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wagner</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gall</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Kerr</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2012</year>
<article-title>Is pathogen spillover from commercial bumble bees responsible for North American wild bumble bee declines?</article-title><source>Conservation Letters</source><volume>5</volume>: <fpage>322</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>329</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0046"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thorp</surname><given-names>R. W.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Shepherd</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Profile: subgenus <italic>Bombus</italic></article-title>. <italic>In</italic><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name name-style="western"><surname>Shepherd</surname><given-names>M. D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vaughan</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Black</surname><given-names>S. H.</given-names></name></person-group> (eds.), <source>Red list of pollinator insects of North America</source>. CD-ROM version 1 (May 2005). 
<publisher-name>The Xerces Society for Invertebrate Conservation</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Portland, OR</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0047"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>P. H</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1986</year>
<article-title>Environmental change and the distribution of British bumble bees (<italic>Bombus</italic> Latr.)</article-title>. <source>Bee World</source><volume>67</volume>: <fpage>50</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>61</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0048"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Does specialization explain rarity and decline among British bumblebees? A response to Goulson <italic>et al</italic></article-title>. <source>Biol. Conserv</source>. <volume>122</volume>: <fpage>33</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>43</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0049"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Colla</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Xie</surname><given-names>Z.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Bumblebee vulnerability: common correlates of winners and losers across three continents</article-title>. <source>Conserv. Biol</source>. <volume>23</volume>: <fpage>931</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>940</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19245487</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0050"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>P. H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thorp</surname><given-names>R. W.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Richardson</surname><given-names>L. L.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Colla</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2014</year>
<source>The bumble bees of North America: an identification guide</source>. <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Princeton, NJ</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0051"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Winfree</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>The conservation and restoration of wild bees</article-title>. <source>Ann. N. Y. Acad. Sci</source>. <volume>1195</volume>: <fpage>169</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>197</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20536823</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CIT0052"><mixed-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zuur</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ieno</surname><given-names>E. N.</given-names></name>, and <name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>G. M.</given-names></name>. </person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<source>Analyzing ecological data</source>. <publisher-name>Springer Science &#x00026; Business Media, Springer-Verlag New York</publisher-name>. doi:10.1007/978-0-387-45972-1.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>