<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Overall, we recommend that future impact studies model adaptation by absolute threshold shifts and reductions in ERF slope. This should, however, not be done arbitrarily. We suggest that researchers first check the validity of the magnitude of adaptation assumed by exploring the evidence for, and magnitude of, historical adaptation in the chosen location of investigation. This information should yield quantification of shifts in the threshold temperature and declines in slope over the historical period. The analysis should be performed using as long a time series of daily data as possible, ideally spanning 
 <inline-formula class="inline-formula">
  <math id="M124" class="math">
   <mrow class="mrow">
    <mo class="mo">∼</mo>
    <mn class="mn">100</mn>
    <mspace width="0.3em" class="mspace"/>
    <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">y</mi>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> because the most compelling evidence for adaptation over the historical period is from studies that have analyzed data sets of this length (
 <xref rid="c1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Arbuthnott et al. 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="c2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Åström et al. 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="c9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Carson et al. 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="c17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ha and Kim 2013</xref>; 
 <xref rid="c44" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Petkova et al. 2014a</xref>). If adaptation is not observed over the historical period, if there is a lack of available data, or a combination of the two, then it should not be assumed that future adaptation is impossible. Rather, the reasons for this apparent lack of adaptation (or data) should be investigated, and adaptation modeling should be undertaken. We recommend applying a shift in absolute threshold between 
 <inline-formula class="inline-formula">
  <math id="M125" class="math">
   <mrow class="mrow">
    <mn class="mn">1</mn>
    <mo class="mo">°</mo>
    <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">C</mi>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> and 
 <inline-formula class="inline-formula">
  <math id="M126" class="math">
   <mrow class="mrow">
    <mn class="mn">4</mn>
    <mo class="mo">°</mo>
    <mi mathvariant="normal" class="mi">C</mi>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> in such cases because this is broadly within the range of shifts in threshold temperature observed for some locations (
 <xref rid="c3" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Åström et al. 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="c22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Honda et al. 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="c54" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Todd and Valleron 2015</xref>). However, the results should be interpreted within the knowledge that historical adaptation has not occurred, that there were insufficient available data to observe it, or both. Analysis of historical trends in adaptation will indicate whether both the threshold and slope have changed over time, or whether only one has changed. This in turn should inform which method to use in the climate change impact assessment.
</p>
