<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Coastal flooding is likely to be the biggest socioeconomic impact of sea level rise (SLR) in the 21st century (
 <xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">1</italic>
 </xref>–
 <xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">6</italic>
 </xref>). Several U.S. states (including Texas, Louisiana, and Florida, as well as U.S. territories such as Puerto Rico and the Virgin Islands) have just experienced devastation caused by the unprecedented flooding after Hurricane Harvey, Hurricane Irma, and Hurricane Maria. Storm intensity, associated rainfall, and storm surges affecting the coastal area were likely amplified by the elevated ocean temperature caused by ongoing global climate change (
 <xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">7</italic>
 </xref>). Moreover, increasing rates of mean global SLR, coinciding with the global rise in Earth’s temperature, increase the susceptibility of coastal areas to flooding. The increase in the rate of global SLR, from ~1.7 mm/year in the late 20th century to ~3.1 mm/year in the early 21st century, is mostly attributed to accelerated ice mass loss at major glaciers and polar ice caps and to thermal expansion of ocean water (
 <xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">8</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">9</italic>
 </xref>). Although the contribution of these sources to SLR is fairly well understood, the rate of relative SLR (RSLR) can vary significantly due to a number of other processes such as isostatic adjustments, ocean currents, earthquakes, and volcanic episodes, as well as local land subsidence (LLS) associated with sediment and aquifer-system compaction (
 <xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">10</italic>
 </xref>–
 <xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">13</italic>
 </xref>).
</p>
