<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The spatial pattern of SLR in the northeast Pacific is generally affected by climate patterns (such as El Niño and La Niña), changes in gravitational pull due to large glaciers and ice melting, isostatic rebound caused by ice sheet loss, and tectonic processes, including interseismic land uplift and subsidence (
 <xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">8</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">9</italic>
 </xref>). The regional vertical land motion due to current tectonic and nontectonic deformation along the northeast Pacific shorelines varies from uplift of 1.5 to 3 mm/year north of Cape Mendocino to subsidence at a rate of ~1 mm/year to the south (
 <xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">8</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">9</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">20</italic>
 </xref>). Projections of SLR for the northeast Pacific suggested by the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) in 2007 (
 <xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">8</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">9</italic>
 </xref>) predict a rise of 4 to 30 cm by 2030, 12 to 61 cm by 2050, and 42 to 167 cm by 2100, relative to 2000. Considering different emission scenarios, so-called representative concentration pathways (RCPs), and the upgraded rate of Antarctica ice sheet loss in the 21st century (
 <xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">21</italic>
 </xref>), the likely ranges of projected SLR can be much higher than that computed by IPCC (table S1) (
 <xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">2</italic>
 </xref>). The projections provided by the IPCC have already been used to identify areas of potential inundation in coastal regions. These maps are the basis for planning flood resilience strategies for large coastal urban areas such as the SFBA, the greater Los Angeles Basin, and New York (
 <xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">1</italic>
 </xref>). Heberger 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. (
 <xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">22</italic>
 </xref>) consider a 100-year 1.4-m SLR along the entire coast of California and estimate nearly $100 billion in property losses, 8750 km
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> of inundated wetlands, and 480,000 displaced people. These estimates are highly sensitive to the assumed SLR projection (
 <xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">23</italic>
 </xref>) and contributions from spatially variable LLS. Here, we use the SFBA as a case example to develop improved inundation scenarios, integrating high-resolution digital topography, detailed and accurate estimates of coastal LLS, and probabilistic projections of SLR under a wide range of emission and global warming scenarios.
</p>
