<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Multiple pathways can explain how climate change can increase complications of NCDs including cardiovascular, respiratory, cancer, mental health, and injuries. Specific examples include environmental exposures such as air pollution, changes in available diet and its quality, ozone exposure, altered ultraviolet radiation, increased use of herbicides and pesticides, social inequalities due to the scarcity of resources and distribution within and between countries, and extreme weather events leading to injuries and fatalities.[
 <xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>] The relationship between climate change, food consumption, and NCDs needs emphasis because individuals and communities can actively participate to reduce potential adverse outcomes. For example, livestock production at a global level contributes to a sizable proportion (~15%) of greenhouse gas emission and the consumption levels are rising. Can we change our eating habits and reduce meat consumption? Based on data from the WHO,[
 <xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>] six risk factors (high blood pressure, tobacco use, high blood glucose level, physical inactivity, overweight/obesity, and high cholesterol levels) are leading causes of death attributed to CVD, metabolic diseases, and cancer. Therefore, changing dietary habits and increasing physical activity can substantially improve individual as well as population health. The WHO estimates that the life-years that are lost due to disability or premature death (disability-adjusted life years [DALYs]) for causes attributed to climate change would be much higher in the developing regions compared to developed regions of the world.[
 <xref rid="ref12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>] These DALY estimates per million people are 3071.5 in Africa and 1586.5 in Eastern Mediterranean, compared to 8.9 in the developed countries. It should be noted that most of the greenhouse emissions that adversely affect the environment are produced by developed countries.[
 <xref rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]
</p>
