<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par5" class="p">Wooldridge [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>] presented an integrative model for the breakdown of the coral symbiosis, detailing how mutualistic symbionts might shift to parasitism in the warming period preceding bleaching [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>]. The model is based on the need for the coral host to supply exogenous carbon for 
 <italic class="italic">Symbiodinium</italic> photosynthesis. Although CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> can be sourced from host respiration of heterotrophic substrates, in many species the abundant ATP derived from photosynthesis is sufficient to sustain a positive feedback on the activity of carbonic anhydrase, which converts seawater bicarbonate into intracellular CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>. The diversity of active carbon concentrating mechanisms found in corals highlights the importance of this feedback [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">17</xref>]. Provided that symbiont growth is limited by lack of nutrients, cell division is minimized and hosts can accumulate translocated photosynthates as energy reserves to maintain symbiotic homeostasis. However, chronic metabolic imbalances caused by environmental perturbation, particularly eutrophication, but also high 
 <italic class="italic">p</italic>CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> and irradiance favor the proliferation of 
 <italic class="italic">Symbiodinium</italic> within the host [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">18</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>]; Fagoonee 1999). As such, 
 <italic class="italic">Symbiodinium</italic> are predicted to retain more carbon (as molecular skeletons for amino and nucleic acids) in order to sequester more nitrogen for cell division [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" class="xref">19</xref>]. Thus, the flow of energy to the host is lessened, forcing increased respiration of lipid reserves to maintain metabolic functioning.
</p>
