<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par6" class="p">At this point, host investments in supplying exogenous CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> for photosynthesis no longer yield returns as the flow of carbon ends in the 
 <italic class="italic">Symbiodinium</italic> sink. Consequently, the likelihood of bleaching increases as a result of a weakened host unable to tolerate the burgeoning symbiont population which becomes primed for bleaching when temperature and irradiance are high [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">13</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">20</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">22</xref>]. As such, there is a presumption that the mutualistic symbiont has become more parasitic by “cheating” the host of resource subsidies while reducing host fitness. The transition from symbiont to parasite can be defined by increasing costs that exceed benefits gained by the host [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">23</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">24</xref>] and may be more evident in phylotypes that demonstrate “cheating” behaviors. Indeed, Lesser et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">5</xref>] suggested that cheating in corals is evidenced by the observation of the temporary dominance of “infectious” and opportunistic 
 <italic class="italic">Symbiodinium</italic> species such as 
 <italic class="italic">S. trenchii</italic>. The competitive displacement and/or host-modulated winnowing of “inferior” symbionts further suggests that the host can influence this process, perhaps by optimizing subsidies for mutualists or implementing sanctions on parasites [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" class="xref">49</xref>] (McIlroy &amp; Coffroth 2017). These processes are thought to be mediated by symbiont competition, which is predicted to vary with environmental factors such as heat, light, and nutrient stress [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" class="xref">25</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" class="xref">26</xref>]. However, many of these theoretical processes lack empirical data for corals.
</p>
