<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">LD mapping can be classified into two types, including (a) broad genome‐wide studies seeking variation associated with phenotypic diversity and (b) narrower investigations attempting to identify causal genes and mutations in a small number of candidate genes within a specified genomic region (Ross‐Ibarra et al., 
 <xref rid="pce13203-bib-0120" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>). Examples of where LD mapping has been applied for identification of both novel and previously characterized genes responsible for agronomic traits include genome‐wide association studies (GWAS) in model legume 
 <styled-content style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">
  <styled-content style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">Medicago truncatula</styled-content>
 </styled-content> (Stanton‐Geddes et al., 
 <xref rid="pce13203-bib-0136" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>), common bean (Kamfwa, Cichy, &amp; Kelly, 
 <xref rid="pce13203-bib-0071" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Moghaddam et al., 
 <xref rid="pce13203-bib-0099" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>), and soybean (Contreras‐Soto et al., 
 <xref rid="pce13203-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>; Zhou et al., 
 <xref rid="pce13203-bib-0174" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). GWAS has also proven to be successful in identifying candidate genes for ascochyta blight resistance (Li et al., 
 <xref rid="pce13203-bib-0089" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>) and heat and drought tolerant loci in chickpea (Thudi, Upadhyaya, et al., 
 <xref rid="pce13203-bib-0143" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>), and 
 <italic class="italic">Aphanomyces euteiches</italic> resistance in 
 <styled-content style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">
  <styled-content style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">Medicago truncatula</styled-content>
 </styled-content> (Bonhomme et al., 
 <xref rid="pce13203-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). Applying GWAS in a population comprising 292 pigeonpea accessions using data over several years enabled identification of association between candidate genes and traits, including 100‐seed weight, days to 50% flowering, and plant height (Varshney et al., 
 <xref rid="pce13203-bib-0151" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>). Hoyos‐Villegas, Song, and Kelly (
 <xref rid="pce13203-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>) investigated the genetic basis of variation for drought tolerance and related traits in a diversity panel including 96 Middle American genotypes of common bean, and the GWAS analysis allowed identification of significant marker‐trait associations for traits related to drought tolerance and candidate genes associated with wilting.
</p>
