<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="methods" id="s4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec id="s4a" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ethics Statement</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The experiments reported here comply with the current law in The Netherlands and were carried out under licenses of the Animal Ethics Committee of the KNAW (Royal Netherlands Academy of Arts and Sciences, protocol CTE.08.10 &amp; CTE 09.01).</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">Study areas –</span> This study was carried out in two study areas, Hoge Veluwe and Oosterhout (the Netherlands), about 50 km apart. Strong natural selection for early laying females exists in both populations 
   <a rid="pone.0035617-Visser3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0035617-Visser3">[6]</a>. The study sites were chosen for this experiment because food availability in the period before egg laying differs between them. National Park ‘De Hoge Veluwe’ (52° 02′ 07″ N 5° 51′ 32″ E) is a mixed forest on poor sandy soils, while Oosterhout (51° 52′ 22″ N 5° 50′ 22″ E) is a rich deciduous forest on rich river clay. Besides finding food in the rich undergrowth, females of the Oosterhout population regularly fly to the nearby village (maximum distance 1 km) to feed on the abundant supplemented food (observed during radio tracking, unpublished data LtM &amp; MEV). This food was available until most birds laid their eggs and consisted mainly of fat and peanuts. Over the last 25 years, natural selection favored early breeding in 21 of the past 25 years in Oosterhout and in 23 out of 25 years in the Hoge Veluwe 
   <a rid="pone.0035617-Visser2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0035617-Visser2">[4]</a>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s4b" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Aviary experiment</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To test if one (or two) long days initiate gonadal growth, we caught 15 wild female great tits at the end of November 2008 around the Netherlands Institute of Ecology, Heteren (The Netherlands; 51°57′20″N–5°44′34″E). All females were housed in one large outdoor aviary under natural light and temperature conditions and 
   <span class="italic">ad libitum</span> food and water. Six days before the light treatment (December 5
   <span class="sup">th</span> 2008), length of the largest ovarian follicle of all females was measured during laparotomy without knowledge of the treatment each female would be assigned to. To measure follicle development, a small incision was made between the last two ribs on the left side. By parting the ribs slightly, length of the largest follicle was measured to the nearest 0.1 mm with an ocular scale. When the length of the largest follicle was too small to be measured (significantly smaller than 0.1 mm) we reported a length of 0.05 mm (
   <span class="italic">n</span> = 3 in December). All laparotomies were carried out by SVS under light Isoflurane anesthesia. Follicle volume was calculated as V = 4/3 · π · a
   <span class="sup">3</span> where 
   <span class="italic">a</span> is ½ the length of the follicle.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the first photostimulation treatment (December 11
   <span class="sup">th</span> 2008), all females were moved indoors after sunset into individual cages in two separate rooms (see 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0035617-g003" href="#pone-0035617-g003">Fig. 3</a> for a schematic overview of the treatments). Ten females in one room were exposed to light for 20 hours (7AM–3AM), then dark for four hours, after which the lights were turned on again at 7AM the following day. Five control females in the second room were kept under the natural light regime (light from 8:40AM to 4:30PM). All females were returned to the outdoor aviary the day after the photostimulation treatment. Seven days later (December 18
   <span class="sup">th</span> 2008), five of the 10 photostimulated females were photostimulated again using the same protocol, while the other five photostimulated females and five control birds were also kept indoors but under natural photoperiod. Thus, the aviary experiment consisted of three treatment groups, each containing five birds: (i) natural short photoperiod (ii) one long day and (iii) two long days with an interval of one week in between. One month after the first photostimulation (January 15
   <span class="sup">th</span> 2009) the length of the largest follicle was measured again for each female. One week after the last laparotomy all 15 females were released into the wild at the catching location (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0035617-g003" href="#pone-0035617-g003">Fig. 3</a>).
  </p>
  <div id="pone-0035617-g003" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0035617.g003</span>
   <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <div class="title">Schematic overview of the photostimulation treatment for both the aviary and the field experiment.</div>
    <p>For the experiment in captivity (December 2008), females were moved from the outdoor aviary to our indoor facilities after sunset, where a part of the females were kept under natural day length and a part were kept in a different room under a long day length (20L∶4D). Females were moved to their outdoor aviary in the morning of day three. For the field experiment (March 2009 and 2010), females were brought from the field into out indoor facilities for a similar treatment. On the morning of day three, all females were released in the field at the location where they were caught. Grey bars resemble darkness while open bars represent light periods; numbers in the bar are the hours of the day.</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="pone.0035617.g003" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s4c" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Field experiment</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We carried out a field experiment to test if laying dates in the wild are restricted by gonadal development of the females. In the Oosterhout (∼150 nest boxes) and Hoge Veluwe study area (∼440 nest boxes) all nest boxes were checked at night for the presence of female great tits (Oosterhout 2009: February 25
   <span class="sup">th</span>; 2010: March 1
   <span class="sup">st</span>; Hoge Veluwe 2009: March 3
   <span class="sup">rd</span>). All females were banded with a uniquely numbered aluminum ring as well as a unique colour band combination. Of the 103 females encountered, we took 69 females into temporary captivity (Oosterhout: 2009 
   <span class="italic">n</span> = 20, 2010 
   <span class="italic">n</span> = 20, Hoge Veluwe: 2009 
   <span class="italic">n</span> = 29; 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="pone-0035617-t001" href="#pone-0035617-t001">Table 1</a>). Thus, 34 females were not taken into captivity; these control females were put back in the nest box after being ringed and weighed with a pesola spring scale (
   <a ref-type="table" rid="pone-0035617-t001" href="#pone-0035617-t001">Table 1</a>). The females taken into captivity were housed indoor in individual cages with 
   <span class="italic">ad libitum</span> food and water.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Half of the females were kept indoors under a natural light regime (light from 7:30AM to 6:15PM), while the other half were photostimulated (light from 7AM to 3AM; 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0035617-g003" href="#pone-0035617-g003">Fig. 3</a>), and thus experienced an increase in day length of 8 hours and 45 minutes. Thus, we created three experimental groups in this field experiment: (i) photostimulated females in captivity (ii) females which experienced natural day length in captivity and (iii) females which experienced natural day length in the field. We chose not to measure gonadal size of the females in the field after release since disturbance in the period just before egg laying could probably affect the timing of egg laying. All females were released at the field site of capture the day after the treatment (day 3, 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0035617-g003" href="#pone-0035617-g003">Fig. 3</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nest boxes at both study sites were checked once a week from the beginning of April onwards to monitor nest building. Once the bottom of the box was covered with nest material, nests were checked daily to determine the exact laying date (date the first egg was laid). During incubation, females were identified by their unique colour code combination by exposing the colour rings with a pen. Laying dates of three females were excluded since they were likely to be replacement clutches (&gt;30 days after the first egg laying dates in that year of that population) of which we had missed the first clutch (removed laying dates are: Oosterhout 2009: April 40
   <span class="sup">th</span>; Oosterhout 2010: April 34
   <span class="sup">th</span> and April 61
   <span class="sup">st</span>). Results of the analysis did not change after including these data points.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s4d" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analyses</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used a One-sample Wilcoxon signed rank test to test if follicles grew for the photostimulated females in the aviary experiment and a Two-sample Wilcoxon signed rank test to test if gonadal growth was different for females which were photostimulated either once or twice. Statistics presented here were done on the follicle volumes. Results did not change when using follicle length as dependent variable. To test for differences in laying dates in the field experiment we used ANOVAs. Because the experiment was done in Oosterhout in 2009 and 2010 and in the Hoge Veluwe population only in 2009, we divided the analyses of the field experiment in two parts; comparison between study areas in 2009 and comparison between years for the Oosterhout population. All statistics were done using R 2.9.2 
   <a rid="pone.0035617-R1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0035617-R1">[33]</a>.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
