<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Nine planetary boundaries have recently been defined
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1" class="xref">1</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2" class="xref">2</xref> within which we expect that humanity and our societies can operate safely. One of these planetary boundaries addresses the issue of climate change through two thresholds based on the CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> concentration in the atmosphere
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1" class="xref">1</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2" class="xref">2</xref> (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1" class="xref">Fig. 1</xref>) instead of thresholds based on temperature increase. Although temperature increase is directly connected to CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> concentration in the atmosphere and radiative forcing, this relationship is quite uncertain due to, for example, slow feedbacks such as the decrease of ice cover or changes in global vegetation distribution
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1" class="xref">1</xref>. Moreover, reducing atmospheric temperatures alone will not reverse ocean acidification and the associated biodiversity loss
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3" class="xref">3</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4" class="xref">4</xref>. Based on these considerations, the planetary boundary on climate change is framed in terms of atmospheric CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> concentrations rather than temperature. Experts
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b1" class="xref">1</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2" class="xref">2</xref> suggest that “the planet was largely ice free until atmospheric CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> concentrations fell to 450 ppm (±100 ppm), indicating a danger zone when concentrations of CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> rise within the range of 350–550 ppm”
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5" class="xref">5</xref>. This suggests that there are two thresholds of interest: 350 ppm under which the system is considered safe and 550 ppm above which there is a consensus about catastrophic effects in terms of loss of polar ice sheets or freshwater supplies
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5" class="xref">5</xref>.
</p>
