<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Despite some criticisms
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6" class="xref">6</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7" class="xref">7</xref>, the planetary boundary framework is valuable for designing climate policy through the lens of adaptive governance in order to keep the earth within a safe operating space
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8" class="xref">8</xref>. As such, we seek to analyze the characteristics of pathways that comply with planetary climate boundaries and to extract milestones for their integration into future climate policy design. In terms of future pathways, the fifth IPCC’s report (AR5) shows that there is a variety of options for curbing climate change
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9" class="xref">9</xref>, some of which will keep the system within the safe operating space. However, the more we advance in time, the more this variety of options erodes, particularly as governments struggle with a global agreement on the reduction of CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> emissions
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10" class="xref">10</xref>, yielding a delicate balance between the policy lag for reducing greenhouse gas emissions (it is not possible to immediately reduce all CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> emissions) and the lag of global warming (even without additional greenhouse gases from 2000 to 2100, the atmosphere temperature may increase by 0.6 °C
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11" class="xref">11</xref>). To evaluate different policy options and their impact on such climate lags, both the IPCC and policy-makers use integrated assessment models (IAMs) to aid in their decision-making process
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12" class="xref">12</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13" class="xref">13</xref>. Many IAMs are used for optimizing climate policy by maximizing the discounted sum of utilities over the next hundred years
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14" class="xref">14</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15" class="xref">15</xref> or so despite the fact that these optimal trajectories remain contestable because of parameter uncertainties in the long term
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16" class="xref">16</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17" class="xref">17</xref>. In addition, reality has closely tracked the baseline scenario for the past 20 years
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18" class="xref">18</xref> suggesting that these optimal trajectories are not credible. The approach outlined here offers an alternative view. Based on the planetary boundary framework, rather than computing the optimal policy timeline for the coming decades, we aim at assessing the full set of sustainable adaptive pathways that enable the earth to stay within the safe operating space in the face of considerable uncertainty. More specifically, we seek to identify critical boundaries in terms of time (i.e., how long can we postpone an effective global agreement?) and in terms of policy (i.e., what are the minimal policy measures we can take to prevent the crossing of the planetary climate boundaries?). An important message that emerges from the approach we take here is the need to take an adaptive, path-based approach to climate policy design rather than point targets which are meaningless in the face of social and political delays.
</p>
