<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec14" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Details of the observation system simulation experiments</div>
 <p id="Par50" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">During the observation system simulation experiments for the GMST change to melt we use each model’s output as pseudo-observations one-at-a-time. In the first set of experiments we use both SIE mean and SIE sensitivity constraints for years 1979–2017. For each perfect model, we explore the joint pdf specified in the second term of Eq. (
  <a rid="Equ11" ref-type="" href="#Equ11">11</a>) using MCMC. We use 200,000 MCMC samples, with a burn-in of 50,000. We use 
  <span class="italic">f</span> = 3 for the observation system simulation experiments, as this results in reasonable empirical coverage of the 90% posterior credible intervals. For each excluded model we compare the posterior pdf for the GMST change to melt to the value from the true excluded model (Supplementary Figs. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2</a> and 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">3</a>). The GMST change from the true model, and the mean projection exhibit a considerable positive correlation, highlighting the skill of the method at projecting this quantity. We then perform a similar experiment with just the mean SIE constraint for years 1979–2004. Supplementary Figures 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">4</a> and 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">5</a> show validation results for this case.
 </p>
 <p id="Par51" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We test whether the chain length and burn-in settings in the observation system simulation experiments are reasonable. Using such MCMC length in an additional estimation experiment similar to NSIDC_r91_40p.nat, we find that the differences between marginal pdfs for the GMST change in the short and the standard run are small. In addition, chains for all parameters for the short run appear to be reasonably stationary and not unduly influenced by the initial random seed. This suggests that these MCMC settings are reasonable for calibration of the 90% posterior credible interval.</p>
</sec>
