<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">GMST change at which Arctic sea ice will melt</div>
 <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our method provides pdfs for 36 parameters, however of main interest is the GMST change at which the Arctic ice will effectively melt in September. Figure 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4a</a> explores the effect of accounting for the non-exclusivity on the GMST to melt pdfs. It appears that the effect is relatively small for the case of two constraints (HadISST_r51_anthro with and without interactions). Yet, in the NSIDC_mean_only experiment, once the interactions are accounted for, the peak in GMST change to melt between 2 and 2.5 K decreases considerably, while the upper tail of the pdf becomes much fatter. Thus, the effects of accounting for interactions diminish in the case of using two constraints on the models. This is consistent with discussion in the previous section regarding introducing multiple constraints.
  <div id="Fig4" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Probability density functions (pdfs) of global mean surface temperature change required for September Arctic sea ice to effectively vanish. 
     <span class="bold">a</span> Pdfs for runs with and without interactions (to illustrate the effects of accounting for model interactions). 
     <span class="bold">b</span> Pdfs from all runs accounting for interactions, to illustrate the impact of different assumptions. Vertical dotted line: lower desirable warming limit of 1.5° under the Paris agreement. The projections are sensitive to the datasets used, and to the assumptions about the cause of the recent Arctic sea ice decline. There is a distinct probability that keeping global warming below the 1.5° target of the Paris agreement may not be enough to stave off an essential disappearance of summer Arctic sea ice. The figure illustrates the capacity of the method to make predictions of a variable of interest conditioned on a set of non-exclusive hypotheses while accounting for all orders of hypothesis interactions
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2019_10561_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e3889" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par31" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figure 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4b</a> illustrates the differences between the pdfs under different assumptions about the observations, and about the fraction of the recent SIE decline caused by anthropogenic effects. For example, under the assumption of a fully-anthropogenic SIE decline, the HadISST sea ice dataset, and using the 51st realization of HadCRUT4 temperature observations, the pdf is relatively tight with the most likely GMST change to melt (mode) slightly above 2 K, and the 90% credible interval of (1.44, 3.17) K (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>). Keeping the HadISST SIE dataset, but assuming that 40% of the recent SIE decline was natural (HadISST_r51_40p.nat) changes the pdf considerably and results in the second peak above 4 K. This suggests that determining the cause of the recent SIE decline is fundamental in reducing the uncertainty about future GMST to melt projections. Yet, keeping the natural fraction of 40%, but switching to the NSIDC ice dataset and to the 91st realization of temperature observations substantially changes the pdf once again (NSIDC_r91_40p.nat experiment). Specifically, the pdf is shifted to the left, and the second temperature peak between the 4 and 4.5 K is almost completely removed (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>). This illustrates the monumental impact the uncertainties in the observations can have on future Arctic sea ice projections. These effects have been pinpointed in previous work
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
  </span>. Finally, the pdf under the NSIDC sea ice observations, the 47th realization of temperature observations, and a natural fraction of the sea ice decline of 20% (NSIDC_r47_20p.nat), is again tight, with no second peak, a mean of 2.11 K, and the 90% posterior credible interval of (1.35, 2.92) (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>). Removing the sea ice sensitivity constraint results in a wide pdf with a relatively high mean (2.90 K). In most of the experiments, the lower bound of the 90% posterior credible interval is below 1.5 K. This indicates that there is a distinct probability of the Arctic losing essentially all of its summer ice even if we fulfill commitments to the lower 1.5 K warming limit of the Paris agreement. These results are in stark contrast to an almost zero probability of Arctic ice disappearance at 1.5 K warming suggested in previous work
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
  </span>. Yet, that work does not constrain the models by the sea ice sensitivity to temperature. On the other hand, our results broadly agree with a recent study that does use the sea ice sensitivity in correcting climate model biases
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
  </span>. Overall, the mean GMST change to melt for all experiments accounting for non-exclusivity is 2.54 K, with the 90% posterior credible interval from 1.49 to 3.83 K (Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>).
  <div id="Tab1" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Pdf properties of GMST warming to melt</p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th>Experiment</th>
      <th>Mean (K)</th>
      <th>Median (K)</th>
      <th>Mode (K)</th>
      <th>90% credible interval (K)</th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td>NSIDC_mean_only</td>
      <td>2.90</td>
      <td>2.73</td>
      <td>2.51</td>
      <td>(1.60, 4.43)</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>HadISST_r51_anthro</td>
      <td>2.21</td>
      <td>2.16</td>
      <td>2.12</td>
      <td>(1.44, 3.17)</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>NSIDC_r47_20p.nat</td>
      <td>2.11</td>
      <td>2.09</td>
      <td>2.13</td>
      <td>(1.35, 2.92)</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>HadISST_r51_40p.nat</td>
      <td>3.12</td>
      <td>2.87</td>
      <td>2.51</td>
      <td>(1.73, 4.59)</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>NSIDC_r91_40p.nat</td>
      <td>2.35</td>
      <td>2.22</td>
      <td>2.12</td>
      <td>(1.32, 4.05)</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td>Mean of all experiments</td>
      <td>2.54</td>
      <td>2.41</td>
      <td>2.28</td>
      <td>(1.49, 3.83)</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par32" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results have been performed under the assumption of RCP8.5 emissions scenario. However, previous work has found a remarkably linear relationship between temperature and Arctic sea ice in various months in climate models/climate model ensembles
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>
  </span>. Moreover, SIE metrics of individual models (at least for the annual mean), and entire CMIP5 ensemble (for September) have been found to not strongly depend on the driving emissions scenario
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>, and others]
  </span>. Thus suggests that current pdfs may be adequate not just for RCP8.5, but for a range of future emissions scenarios
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
  </span> where GMST monotonically increases with time. Validating our results using other emissions scenarios is subject of future work.
 </p>
</sec>
