<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Used variables were divided into historical and contemporary predictors. Historical predictors include climatic stability
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10" class="xref">10</xref> and accessibility to suitable environments
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b5" class="xref">5</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10" class="xref">10</xref> at the end of the Last Glacial Maximum (LGM; ~21,000 yrs ago). We focus on environmental changes since the LGM climate changes during this period are relatively well known. Also, by focusing on this period, we can focus on evaluating the effects of colonization dynamics and local extirpations without having to consider regional speciation and extinction events. Historical climatic stability was measured as the annual temperature and precipitation velocities (measured in kilometers × decade
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>) from the LGM. As in ref. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b52" class="xref">52</xref>, climate velocities were calculated as the ratio between temporal anomalies (that is the absolute difference between the LGM and current temperature and precipitation) and the spatial gradients (variability in temperature and precipitation during the LGM on a 3 × 3 grid cell neighbourhood). We used climate velocity as a measure of stability as it captures both the changes in climatic conditions over time (temporal anomaly) and the buffering effect of the surrounding area (spatial heterogeneity). Following the approach described in ref. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b2" class="xref">2</xref>, accessibility to postglacial re-colonization from ice-age refugia (measured in kilometers
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>) was estimated as the sum of inverse distances between an AFE grid cell and regions considered to be suitable for cool-temperate trees during the LGM according to ref. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25" class="xref">25</xref> specifications. Historical climate conditions were determined based on three different climatic models (CCSM, MIROC, and MPI) for the last glacial maximum from the Paleoclimate Modelling Intercomparison Project Phase II at a resolution of 5 × 5 arc-minutes, and summarized as the mean within each AFE cell. We focused on both climatic stability and accessibility to refugia as these provide an estimate of the effects of the magnitude of change driving local extirpations and colonization distance for suitable areas at the end of the LGM.
</p>
