<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Management can also be targeted towards specific factors. For example amphibian species richness is largely concentrated along the south-east coastline of Australia, which makes reliance on particular moisture regimes or habitats a significant vulnerability factor there. Species affected by low genetic variation or recent population bottlenecks are prevalent along the coastline of south and south-east Australia, in both fragmented and undisturbed areas (
 <xref rid="pone.0124766.g003" ref-type="fig" class="xref">Fig 3h</xref>). Many species in these regions have undergone major range contractions through habitat destruction and the introduction of invasive species, though their distributions once extended much further north [
 <xref rid="pone.0124766.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. For example, the South Australian glossy black-cockatoo (
 <italic class="italic">Calyptorhynchus lathami halmaturinus</italic>) once occurred in mainland South Australia, but is now restricted to Kangaroo Island owing to mainland habitat clearance [
 <xref rid="pone.0124766.ref052" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>]. Numbers dropped to as low as 158 birds in 1995, though the population had recovered to around 320 birds in 2006, which is suggestive of a recent bottleneck [
 <xref rid="pone.0124766.ref052" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>] potentially increasing its vulnerability to climate change. More generally, dependence on a particular disturbance regime that is likely to change with climate (e.g. fire), is driving climate change vulnerability throughout eastern South Australia, Victoria, western New South Wales and the south coast of Western Australia. In Australia, many species are reliant on appropriate fire regimes for reproduction and habitat. For example, the abundance of the Pilliga mouse (
 <italic class="italic">Pseudomys pilligaensis</italic>) increases fivefold in fire-induced regrowth forest (18–24 months post fire) in comparison with mature forest (&gt;20years) and 28-fold in the intermediate growth stage [
 <xref rid="pone.0124766.ref053" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">53</xref>]. Studies have found that populations peak 20–24 months post fire and following an above average rainfall year, though as with many opportunistic breeders, the population then declines rapidly [
 <xref rid="pone.0124766.ref054" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>]. However, mature forest is required for breeding habitat [
 <xref rid="pone.0124766.ref053" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">53</xref>]. Fires are expected to become more frequent, intense and erratic as a result of climate change in Australia [
 <xref rid="pone.0124766.ref043" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0124766.ref055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0124766.ref057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>]. Reliance on specific moisture regimes is a major factor in north-eastern Queensland and in upper Western Australia and Northern Territory. For example, the western partridge pigeon (
 <italic class="italic">Geophaps smithii blaauwi</italic>) depends on a reliable water source for survival during the late dry season [
 <xref rid="pone.0124766.ref058" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">58</xref>], and reductions in rainfall and increasing temperatures as a result of climate change could pose a serious risk.
</p>
