<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">According to Millar and Stephenson (
 <xref rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>), forest cover under climatic change undergoes a progressive dieback of the crown and mortality of trees. During the period of decline, a regeneration of trees of different species, or of different genotypes of the same species, will occur. The decline of canopies induced by climate change may trigger a vegetational dynamism, with a temporary success of the early-successional tree species. In a longer time span, the regeneration of a “definitive” (mature) tree cover is supposed to be ensured by more xerophytic species coming from proximal areas (e.g., from lower elevation). This new generation of trees is supposed to be better adapted to the environmental condition of the previous one. The functions and services of forests are assumed to decrease during the canopy-decline period, but they are likely to be restored when the “new forest” is well-established. The equilibrium of the forest, adapted to a new environment, implies probably a different level of ecosystem functions and services, with respect to that which is provided by forests before the action of disturbing factors. Adaptation to drier conditions determines slower growth rates, lower foliar mass, reduced regeneration rate, and so on. These processes are ongoing in some parts of Europe and can be observed, for example, in 
 <italic class="italic">P. sylvestris</italic> stands in the Valais (Switzerland) and the Italian Western Alps, where 
 <italic class="italic">Quercus pubescens</italic> Willd. is going to replace 
 <italic class="italic">P. sylvestris</italic> in the driest conditions (Rigling et al., 
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>). The changes in the forest structure and species composition are associated with several events and signals, among which the most significant, due to its consequences, is the drought-induced tree mortality (Allen et al., 
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>) and insect attacks in trees weakened by drought (Wermelinger et al., 
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2007</xref>; Anderegg et al., 
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>).
</p>
