<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The meridional temperature gradient associated with SST feedbacks, coupled with the stronger land cooling, induce significant changes in the local atmospheric overturning circulation. Figure 
 <xref rid="grl56839-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" class="xref">4</xref> shows the 60
 <sup class="sup">∘</sup>E to 140
 <sup class="sup">∘</sup>E averaged vertical motion change for the total (Figure 
 <xref rid="grl56839-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" class="xref">4</xref>a) and fast (Figure 
 <xref rid="grl56839-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" class="xref">4</xref>b) responses. The climatological rising motion (dashed contours) spans a wide latitude band from 10
 <sup class="sup">∘</sup>S to 40
 <sup class="sup">∘</sup>N, representing an expanded cross‐equatorial overturning circulation during the summer monsoon months and the seasonal migration of the Intertropical Convergence Zone (Schneider et al., 
 <xref rid="grl56839-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). The climatological sinking branch (solid contours) is located to the south of 10
 <sup class="sup">∘</sup>S. The AGCMs reproduce well the regional overturning circulation (contours in Figure 
 <xref rid="grl56839-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" class="xref">4</xref>b). The aerosol‐induced total response (shading in Figure 
 <xref rid="grl56839-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" class="xref">4</xref>a) features an overall reduction of the climatological circulation with anomalous sinking motion over most of the climatological convection region and anomalous rising motion south of the equator, consistent with previous studies (Bollasina et al., 
 <xref rid="grl56839-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>; Li et al., 
 <xref rid="grl56839-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). However, the anomalous sinking motion is confined to the north of 20
 <sup class="sup">∘</sup>N in the fast response (shading in Figure 
 <xref rid="grl56839-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" class="xref">4</xref>b), where the major land mass is located (illustrated by the number of land grid points in Figure 
 <xref rid="grl56839-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" class="xref">4</xref>e). There is strong anomalous rising motion between 0
 <sup class="sup">∘</sup> and 20
 <sup class="sup">∘</sup>N over the oceanic regions. The difference between Figures 
 <xref rid="grl56839-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" class="xref">4</xref>a and 
 <xref rid="grl56839-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" class="xref">4</xref>b (Figure 
 <xref rid="grl56839-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" class="xref">4</xref>c, assuming linearity, approximates the “slow response”) shows strong anomalous sinking motion over 0
 <sup class="sup">∘</sup>–20
 <sup class="sup">∘</sup>N and anomalous rising motion south of the equator. The slow response due to aerosol‐induced SST anomaly in CAM5 (Figure 
 <xref rid="grl56839-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" class="xref">4</xref>d) shows very similar patterns to that in Figure 
 <xref rid="grl56839-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" class="xref">4</xref>c. The consistency between Figures 
 <xref rid="grl56839-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" class="xref">4</xref>c and 
 <xref rid="grl56839-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" class="xref">4</xref>d confirms that the anomalous overturning circulation near the equator is predominantly caused by the slow response due to SST feedbacks.
</p>
