<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The annual cycle of changing day length is commonly used as a signal of the approaching and waning seasons. In many vertebrates, photoperiodic information is encoded by the central circadian clock located in the SCN (Hastings and Herzog, 
 <xref rid="ece35537-bib-0049" ref-type="ref">2004</xref>). The SCN regulates the synthesis and release of melatonin from the pineal gland during the night; thus, day length differences are assessed by monitoring night length, which is encoded by the duration of melatonin secretion into the blood and cerebrospinal fluid (Pevet and Challet, 
 <xref rid="ece35537-bib-0096" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>; Reiter, Tan, Kim, &amp; Cruz, 
 <xref rid="ece35537-bib-0105" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>). Relatively long durations of secreted melatonin encode long nights (or short days), whereas relatively short elevations of secreted melatonin encode short nights (or long days). Melatonin targets several brain regions to affect the phase of peripheral circadian clocks, as well as the central clock in the SCN, by altering expression of circadian clock genes (Pevet and Challet, 
 <xref rid="ece35537-bib-0096" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>). Among the target sites of melatonin, the pars tuberalis (PT) of the pituitary stalk plays a key role in the photoperiodic pathway governing seasonal reproduction (Dardente, 
 <xref rid="ece35537-bib-0026" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>). In mammals, a long‐day signal rapidly induces the strong peak of the transcription factor 
 <italic>Eyes absent 3 (Eya3</italic>) in the PT (Dardente et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35537-bib-0027" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>; Masumoto et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35537-bib-0071" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>). EYA3 contributes to thyroid stimulating hormone (TSH) synthesis in the PT by activating transcription of 
 <italic>TSH b subunit</italic> (
 <italic>TSHb</italic>). TSH acts on TSH receptor (TSHR)‐expressing cells in the basal hypothalamus to increase thyroid hormone (T
 <sub>3</sub>) availability. T
 <sub>3</sub> interacts with hypothalamic peptides which eventually control the release of gonadotropins from the adenohypophysis leading to seasonal changes in gonadal size and function, as well as adjustments in body mass (Barrett et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35537-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">2007</xref>). Although environmental factors such as temperature vary from year to year, annual changes in day length follow a predictable and consistent pattern. However, recent urbanization activity by humans has increased the prevalence of artificial light at night, rapidly changing the natural environment to which organisms must adjust (Hölker et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35537-bib-0054" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>). Again, the role of day length in coordinating seasonal phenotypic changes has evolved with precision so that seasonal reproductive function coincides with optimal conditions for offspring and parental survival (Nelson, 
 <xref rid="ece35537-bib-0089" ref-type="ref">1987</xref>). Exposure to light at night alters the daily melatonin cycle and other aspects of the circadian system and affects many photoperiod‐regulated physiological and behavioral responses (Navara and Nelson, 
 <xref rid="ece35537-bib-0088" ref-type="ref">2007</xref>). Both synchronization of circadian clocks and photoperiodic time measurement depend on a distinct demarcation between light and dark. Modern illuminated skies prevent this demarcation (Dominoni, Borniger, &amp; Nelson, 
 <xref rid="ece35537-bib-0034" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>; Dominoni &amp; Nelson, 
 <xref rid="ece35537-bib-0036" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>).
</p>
