<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="eva12678-sec-0007" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">COMMON METHODOLOGICAL APPROACHES IN LANDSCAPE GENETICS AND THEIR USE IN STUDYING PATHOGEN DYNAMICS</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There are a variety of methods available for implementing landscape genetics, some designed specifically for landscape genetics, while others have been adapted from other fields. The rapid development of landscape genetics means that new methods are regularly emerging, and it is difficult to comprehensively review all of them. However, there are some well‐established methodological approaches that have either seen wide use for some time or are becoming increasingly popular at the cutting edge of the field (Balkenhol, Cushman, Storfer, &amp; Waits, 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0007">2016</a>). We describe the approaches (Table 
  <a rid="eva12678-tbl-0001" ref-type="table" href="#eva12678-tbl-0001">1</a>) and discuss their implementation in the study of pathogen transmission and spread.
 </p>
 <div id="eva12678-tbl-0001" xml:lang="en" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Table 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Common landscape genetic approaches and their potential use in pathogen research</p>
  </div>
  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
   <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/>
   <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/>
   <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/>
   <thead valign="top">
    <tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000">
     <th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Landscape genetic approach</th>
     <th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Their potential applications in pathogen research</th>
     <th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pathogen landscape genetic examples</th>
    </tr>
   </thead>
   <tbody>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Landscape genetic simulation modelling</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Predict pathogen spread in future landscape scenarios; predict spread of genes relevant to host–pathogen–vector interactions; test and validate new methods</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rees et al. (
      <a rid="eva12678-bib-0106" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0106">2008</a>), Landguth et al. (
      <a rid="eva12678-bib-0072" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0072">2016</a>), Leo et al. (
      <a rid="eva12678-bib-0082" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0082">2016</a>)
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clustering and assignment methods</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Detect barriers to pathogen spread and infer levels of barrier permeability; detect pathogen or vector environmental niche variation</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Cullingham et al. (
      <a rid="eva12678-bib-0030" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0030">2009</a>), Cote et al. (
      <a rid="eva12678-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0027">2012</a>), Addis et al. (
      <a rid="eva12678-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0001">2015</a>), Brar et al. (
      <a rid="eva12678-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0017">2015</a>)
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Landscape resistance surfaces</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Identify probable transmission routes or corridors; identify hosts and vectors responsible for pathogen spread; predict effects of environmental change on pathogen spread</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Liang et al. (
      <a rid="eva12678-bib-0084" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0084">2014</a>), Streicker et al. (
      <a rid="eva12678-bib-0122" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0122">2016</a>), Lo et al. (
      <a rid="eva12678-bib-0085" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0085">2017</a>), Young et al. (
      <a rid="eva12678-bib-0132" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0132">2017</a>)
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Graph theory and network models</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genetic inference of host contacts; identify key habitat patches/populations contributing to pathogen spread</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Genomic approaches</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Identify associations of known candidate loci with spatial variation in pathogen exposure; infer spatial variation in pathogen exposure in different landscapes using associated loci; identify alleles determining disease susceptibility and incorporate the distribution of these into predictions of future pathogen spread</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Garroway et al. (
      <a rid="eva12678-bib-0056" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0056">2013</a>), Larson et al. (
      <a rid="eva12678-bib-0075" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0075">2014</a>), Roffler et al. (
      <a rid="eva12678-bib-0113" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0113">2016</a>), Wenzel et al. (
      <a rid="eva12678-bib-0130" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0130">2016</a>)
     </td>
    </tr>
   </tbody>
  </table>
  <div class="permissions">
   <span class="copyright-holder">John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd</span>
  </div>
 </div>
 <sec id="eva12678-sec-0008" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.1</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Simulation modelling to test theoretical and predicted scenarios and validate methodology</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In landscape genetics, simulation models are usually agent‐based and spatially explicit (Landguth, Cushman, &amp; Balkenhol, 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0072" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0072">2016</a>). Genetic data are modelled for individuals which have discrete spatial locations with respect to one another and with respect to environmental heterogeneity. Individuals move, behave and reproduce according to their own attributes in response to other individuals and in response to the simulated environment, and the model simulates changes in allele frequencies in response to these parameters. Landscape genetic simulation modelling has been used to test and validate methodological approaches (Cushman, Wasserman, Landguth, &amp; Shirk, 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0031">2013</a>; Zeller et al., 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0133" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0133">2016</a>), address theoretical questions about how and why landscape heterogeneity influences genetics (Landguth et al., 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0073" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0073">2010</a>), and evaluate and explain empirical observations (Shirk, Cushman, &amp; Landguth, 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0116" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0116">2012</a>). Further, simulation modelling can predict how a system might respond to certain changes, such as habitat fragmentation or future management activities.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Simulation modelling has been widely implemented in the study of pathogenic and nonpathogenic disease, beginning with medical research in the 1960s (Elveback &amp; Varma, 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0043">1965</a>). Frequently, epidemiological simulations are used to predict the spread of pathogens and their effect on host populations (Calonnec, Cartolaro, Naulin, Bailey, &amp; Langlais, 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0021">2008</a>). However, the use of landscape genetic simulations in pathogen studies has been relatively limited. Landscape genetic simulations have been used to predict raccoon rabies transmission risk across a river barrier by simulating various rates of host dispersal and comparing these outputs with empirical genetic data from the host (Rees et al., 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0106" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0106">2008</a>). The spread of particular host genes relevant to disease can also be simulated to inform management efforts. For instance, Landguth, Holden, Mahalovich, and Cushman (
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0074" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0074">2017</a>) used landscape genetic simulations to determine optimal planting regimes to maximize the spread of blister rust resistant genes among whitebark pine populations. Such simulations could undoubtedly be applied to vector species in particular, such as predicting the spread of pesticide resistance genes in mosquitos (Chang et al., 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0025">2016</a>) and selecting appropriate sites for introduction of genetically modified vectors (Lavery, Harrington, &amp; Scott, 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0076" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0076">2008</a>). In addition, with the need to develop further landscape genetic frameworks for the study of pathogens, simulation modelling can prove useful in testing and validating these techniques, as it has done in the broader landscape genetics field (Cushman et al., 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0031">2013</a>; Zeller et al., 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0133" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0133">2016</a>). For example, Leo, Gonzalez, Millien, and Cristescu (
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0082" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0082">2016</a>) used landscape genetic simulations to validate their multitaxa integrated landscape genetic framework, which appears to be a promising solution to the challenge of studying pathogens with multiple hosts and/or vectors. Landscape genetic simulations may also include epidemiological parameters such as mortality or activity responses to infection, or limited infectious periods, which may otherwise confound conventional (i.e., nonsimulation) landscape genetic approaches.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="eva12678-sec-0009" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Clustering and assignment methods for quantifying connectivity and identifying transmission origin</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Landscape genetic clustering and assignment methods have largely built upon classical methods from population genetics (e.g., principal components analysis, STRUCTURE, Pritchard, Stephens, &amp; Donnelly, 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0103" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0103">2000</a>) by incorporating spatial information (e.g., GENELAND, Guillot, Mortier, &amp; Estoup, 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0061">2005</a>; sPCA, Jombart, Devillard, Dufour, &amp; Pontier, 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0068" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0068">2008</a>) and environmental heterogeneity (e.g., constrained ordination, Anderson &amp; Willis, 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0005" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0005">2003</a>; POPS, Jay, 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0064" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0064">2011</a>) into estimates of population structure and providing quantitative estimates of ancestry for each individual (François &amp; Waits, 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0052">2016</a>). Clustering methods have been relatively popular in studying pathogens and implemented for the inference of landscape barriers affecting both host (Addis, Lowe, Hossack, &amp; Allendorf, 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0001">2015</a>; Cote, Garant, Robert, Mainguy, &amp; Pelletier, 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0027">2012</a>; Cullingham, Kyle, Pond, Rees, &amp; White, 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0030" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0030">2009</a>; Frantz, Cellina, Krier, Schley, &amp; Burke, 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0053">2009</a>) and microparasite (Brar et al., 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0017">2015</a>; Rieux et al., 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0110" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0110">2011</a>) spatial genetic variation. Edge detection methods, such as Monmonier's maximum difference algorithm, (Monmonier, 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0095" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0095">1973</a>) have also been used to detect landscape barriers to transmission in pathogen studies (Carrel et al., 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0023">2015</a>; Joannon et al., 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0066" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0066">2010</a>). Ancestry estimates from model‐based clustering algorithms can assign individuals to their populations of origin, enabling inference of landscape barrier permeability through the identification of migrants and thus estimation of the risk of pathogen spread across the barrier.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Most of the studies implementing clustering and assignment methods did not use approaches that incorporate environmental data. Instead, spatially or nonspatially explicit methods were typically used to identify genetic discontinuities and relationships with landscape barriers were inferred ad hoc, or analyses proceeded to entirely different methods that explicitly include environmental data. Associations between genetic discontinuities and landscape barriers should be considered with care due to the potential effect of intrinsic isolation mechanisms on genetic structure. For instance, studies on apple scab identified two distantly related lineages that are reproductively isolated through host specificity, but which have formed a narrow secondary contact zone in orchards where multiple host species are cultivated (Lemaire et al., 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0080" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0080">2016</a>; Leroy, Lemaire, Dunemann, &amp; Le Cam, 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0083" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0083">2013</a>). Secondary contact zones occurring at equivalent spatial scales to that of landscape heterogeneity may result in genetic discontinuities resembling a barrier effect and thus be misattributed as such.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Other applications of clustering methods that explicitly integrate landscape variables, such as detecting environmental niche variation (Pease et al., 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0099" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0099">2009</a>) and ancestry–environment relationships (Jay et al., 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0065" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0065">2012</a>), remain relatively unexplored among studies of pathogen dynamics. These applications could translate in infectious organisms to the identification of distinct ecotypes or identify landscape features that coincide with infection foci or sources of pathogen spread. However, it must be noted that many of the genetic clustering and assignment methods presented here rely on classical population genetics models that generally do not apply to microorganisms. Therefore, the use of such methods in the study of pathogens is often limited to the inference of pathogen movement using host gene flow, with the exception of some fungal pathogens (Brar et al., 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0017">2015</a>; Rieux et al., 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0110" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0110">2011</a>). Some recent methods for identifying spatial population structure are free of classical population genetic assumptions, such as LOCALDIFF (Duforet‐Frebourg &amp; Blum, 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0038" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0038">2014</a>), EEMS (Petkova, Novembre, &amp; Stephens, 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0100" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0100">2016</a>) and MAPI (Piry et al., 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0101" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0101">2016</a>), and can be applied to pathogens directly without these potential constraints.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="eva12678-sec-0010" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.3</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Resistance surface modelling can identify transmission pathways and quantify spread by hosts and vectors</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Resistance surfaces are commonly used in landscape genetics for modelling hypotheses concerning the influence of landscape features (from GIS landscape variables) on functional connectivity using techniques such as least‐cost paths (Adriaensen et al., 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0002">2003</a>) or circuit theory (McRae, Dickson, Keitt, &amp; Shah, 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0092" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0092">2008</a>). These techniques produce measures of landscape or “effective” distance among populations or individuals for each hypothesis, which can be tested against observed genetic variation. The primary applications of resistance surface modelling in landscape genetics have been the identification of dispersal corridors and predicting the impacts of landscape and environmental change, such as habitat fragmentation or climate change, on connectivity. Similar to that, landscape genetic resistance surfaces can identify transmission corridors or future patterns of spread (e.g., Streicker et al., 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0122" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0122">2016</a>), and such tools have been identified previously as having great utility for pathogen landscape genetic studies (Biek &amp; Real, 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0014">2010</a>). However, resistance surface modelling remains infrequently applied among pathogen studies. Careful consideration is required for identifying the most relevant landscape variables to be tested and correctly parameterizing (assigning costs to) the resistance surface(s) so that these variables are represented in a biologically meaningful way. Developing landscape resistance hypotheses for transmitted agents may be more difficult as their interactions with the landscape are often indirect, mediated by the ecology of hosts and vectors. Pathogen ecological niche models offer an empirical approach for constructing resistance surfaces based on ecological factors influencing pathogen prevalence (Escobar et al., 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0045" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0045">2017</a>; Fountain‐Jones, Pearse et al., 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0051" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0051">2017</a>), but these also may not adequately represent host/vector movements.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our literature search returned only one study that explicitly modelled landscape resistance based on pathogen‐specific biology, testing elevation (as a proxy for temperature) as a predictor of 
   <span class="italic">Plasmodium</span> spread, in addition to resistance surfaces that modelled human movements and mosquito vector ecology (Lo et al., 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0085" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0085">2017</a>). However, several other studies applied resistance surfaces to hosts and vectors. Young et al. (
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0132" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0132">2017</a>) tested resistance surfaces based on waterbird niche models against genetic data from avian influenza. Two further examples of resistance surface modelling used host genetic data: Liang, Liu, Liao, and Gong (
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0084" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0084">2014</a>) studied landscape resistance of the snail 
   <span class="italic">Oncomelania hupensis</span> to infer transmission of its parasite 
   <span class="italic">Schistosoma japonicum</span>; while Rioux Paquette, Talbot, Garant, Mainguy, and Pelletier (
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0111" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0111">2014</a>) identified likely dispersal corridors for two rabies hosts. Further, Streicker et al. (
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0122" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0122">2016</a>) used resistance surfaces to construct least‐cost pathways predicting future spread of vampire bat rabies, and Barton, Gregory, Davis, Hanlon, and Wisely (
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0011">2010</a>) tested landscape resistance to rabies gene flow among striped skunks using landscape variables believed important for host dispersal, as well as landscape variables found to be relevant to other rabies hosts. Resistance surface modelling has thus demonstrated utility in identifying landscape drivers of functional connectivity that can shape pathogen spread and should see increasing use as frameworks for the integration of host, vector and pathogen data continue to develop.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="eva12678-sec-0011" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.4</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Graph theory and network models—integrating landscape genetic and epidemiological approaches</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Graph theoretical approaches, which describe connections (edges) between discrete objects (nodes) (Newman, 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0097" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0097">2003</a>), are a flexible yet powerful tool for use in landscape genetics (Dyer, Nason, &amp; Garrick, 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0041">2010</a>; Garroway, Bowman, Carr, &amp; Wilson, 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0055">2008</a>). In landscape genetics, nodes can represent individuals, populations or habitat patches, possessing genetic parameters such as diversity measures (Dyer et al., 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0041">2010</a>), or landscape parameters such as percentage habitat or habitat quality (Murphy, Dezzani, Pilliod, &amp; Storfer, 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0096" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0096">2010</a>). Similar to that, edges can represent genetic relationships between nodes such as genetic distances, gene flow or dispersal (Decout, Manel, Miaud, &amp; Luque, 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0033">2012</a>), or spatial/landscape relationships such as geographic distance or landscape resistance (Dyer et al., 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0041">2010</a>). Distinct from other landscape genetic analytical approaches, graphs allow inferences based on the overall shape, or topology, of the network, which can provide unique insights into systemwide processes, such as hierarchical population structure (Dyer &amp; Nason, 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0040">2004</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Network topology may be used to identify populations or habitat patches that form important “stepping stones” for maintaining genetic connectivity across an entire system. Such an approach enables experimental simulation whereby nodes may be selectively removed and the overall effect on the system's topology (e.g., overall connectivity, population structure) assessed. Metrics pertaining to the importance of individual nodes to network topology can be correlated with variables such as landscape to identify important drivers of network processes. Despite their unique applications, graph theory and network approaches are relatively underutilized in landscape genetics compared to methods specifically derived from population genetics and landscape ecology. However, among studies of infectious agents, network approaches in wildlife are becoming increasingly popular (Craft, 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0028">2015</a>; Craft &amp; Caillaud, 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0029">2011</a>). Epidemiological network models are typically based on host contact networks, which are usually constructed using direct observations or indirect techniques such as mark‐recapture, telemetry or proximity loggers, and pathogens are simulated on these contact networks. Such approaches have already incorporated landscape and other environmental features. In addition, the potential for inferring host contacts in network models using pathogen genetic markers (see below) has been acknowledged in recent reviews (Craft, 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0028">2015</a>; Gilbertson, Fountain‐Jones, &amp; Craft, 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0057" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0057">2018</a>; White, Forester, &amp; Craft, 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0131" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0131">2017</a>), and some studies have directly compared host contact network parameters to parasite genotypes (Bull, Godfrey, &amp; Gordon, 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0020">2012</a>). Despite this, to our knowledge, no published studies have used network models to investigate pathogen movement within a landscape genetic framework.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="eva12678-sec-0012" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.5</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Genomic approaches to study microevolutionary responses to pathogens and landscape structure</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While landscape genetics initially was used to investigate spatial genetic patterns using relatively few neutral markers, the more modern advent of landscape genomics allows the study of variation across the entire genome and effectively expands the scope of landscape genetics to include the study of functional, adaptive genetic variation. Next‐generation sequencing (NGS) techniques such as restriction‐site‐associated DNA sequencing (RADseq) require minimal prior knowledge of the genome under study and can genotype thousands of SNPs randomly distributed across the genome. Some of these SNPs will by chance be located within or near (and thus linked to) genes or regulatory regions that are under selection. Genomewide association studies (GWAS) can make use of this information to identify loci linked to phenotypic variation such as disease susceptibility. Genotyping of candidate loci identified using quantitative trait locus mapping and GWAS can be expanded across a large number of individuals using methods such as targeted sequence capture (Grover, Salmon, &amp; Wendel, 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0060" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0060">2012</a>), and these data can be tested in a landscape genomic framework for associations with environmental variables.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Loci exhibiting a signature of selection can be identified using outlier tests (Excoffier, Hofer, &amp; Foll, 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0046" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0046">2009</a>; Luu, Bazin, &amp; Blum, 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0087" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0087">2017</a>), which search for loci with allelic frequencies that are outliers relative to the majority. Such loci are considered potentially under selection and may then be tested 
   <span class="italic">a posteriori</span> for correlations with environmental variables. Newer methods have focused on explicitly incorporating environmental variables into landscape genomic analyses, known as genetic–environment association (GEA) tests (Lotterhos &amp; Whitlock, 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0086" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0086">2015</a>; Rellstab, Gugerli, Eckert, Hancock, &amp; Holderegger, 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0107" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0107">2015</a>). GEA analyses test for correlations between environmental variables and individual genotypes, which eliminates problems due to underlying population structure that must be controlled when using outlier tests. NGS approaches also generate thousands of neutral loci, which provide greater power to detect fine‐scale neutral genetic structure than conventional studies based on relatively few loci (Allendorf, Hohenlohe, &amp; Luikart, 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0003">2010</a>). However, for studies with a particular focus on functional genetic variation, NGS approaches can also be adapted specifically for this purpose through targeted sequencing of the exome (Roffler et al., 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0113" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0113">2016</a>) or transcriptome (de Wit &amp; Palumbi, 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0035">2013</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While genomic technologies are becoming the norm in microbial research, approaches incorporating landscape (i.e., landscape genomics) have yet to see widespread usage. Current examples focus on established candidate loci from the host known to be relevant to immune function from prior research, such as in commercially important salmon (Larson, Seeb, Dann, Schindler, &amp; Seeb, 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0075" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0075">2014</a>; Tonteri et al., 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0126" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0126">2010</a>). Wenzel, Douglas, James, Redpath, and Piertney (
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0130" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0130">2016</a>) used SNPs previously identified to be associated with nematode burden in red grouse (
   <span class="italic">Lagopus lagopus scotica</span>) using GWAS, as well as 
   <span class="italic">F</span>
   <sub>st</sub> outlier loci, to investigate parasite‐driven genetic structure across a landscape. Garroway et al. (
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0056" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0056">2013</a>) used SNPs identified from transcriptome sequencing of great tits (
   <span class="italic">Parus major</span>) to conduct a GEA with respect to avian malaria infection risk and contrasted this with neutral gene flow. Another targeted approach employed exon capture to genotype SNPs that were then subjected to outlier and environmental association tests to investigate variation in pathogen exposure with respect to environment (Roffler et al., 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0113" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0113">2016</a>). The spread of functional alleles has also been incorporated into landscape genetic simulations (Landguth et al., 
   <a rid="eva12678-bib-0074" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0074">2017</a>), enhancing predictions of future pathogen spread and its effects on host populations. This small body of research is promising for expansion of landscape genomic studies designed to couple pathogen‐related functional genetic variation with landscape variables.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
