<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="eva12678-sec-0011" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.4</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Graph theory and network models—integrating landscape genetic and epidemiological approaches</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Graph theoretical approaches, which describe connections (edges) between discrete objects (nodes) (Newman, 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0097" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0097">2003</a>), are a flexible yet powerful tool for use in landscape genetics (Dyer, Nason, &amp; Garrick, 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0041">2010</a>; Garroway, Bowman, Carr, &amp; Wilson, 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0055">2008</a>). In landscape genetics, nodes can represent individuals, populations or habitat patches, possessing genetic parameters such as diversity measures (Dyer et al., 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0041">2010</a>), or landscape parameters such as percentage habitat or habitat quality (Murphy, Dezzani, Pilliod, &amp; Storfer, 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0096" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0096">2010</a>). Similar to that, edges can represent genetic relationships between nodes such as genetic distances, gene flow or dispersal (Decout, Manel, Miaud, &amp; Luque, 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0033">2012</a>), or spatial/landscape relationships such as geographic distance or landscape resistance (Dyer et al., 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0041">2010</a>). Distinct from other landscape genetic analytical approaches, graphs allow inferences based on the overall shape, or topology, of the network, which can provide unique insights into systemwide processes, such as hierarchical population structure (Dyer &amp; Nason, 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0040">2004</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Network topology may be used to identify populations or habitat patches that form important “stepping stones” for maintaining genetic connectivity across an entire system. Such an approach enables experimental simulation whereby nodes may be selectively removed and the overall effect on the system's topology (e.g., overall connectivity, population structure) assessed. Metrics pertaining to the importance of individual nodes to network topology can be correlated with variables such as landscape to identify important drivers of network processes. Despite their unique applications, graph theory and network approaches are relatively underutilized in landscape genetics compared to methods specifically derived from population genetics and landscape ecology. However, among studies of infectious agents, network approaches in wildlife are becoming increasingly popular (Craft, 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0028">2015</a>; Craft &amp; Caillaud, 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0029">2011</a>). Epidemiological network models are typically based on host contact networks, which are usually constructed using direct observations or indirect techniques such as mark‐recapture, telemetry or proximity loggers, and pathogens are simulated on these contact networks. Such approaches have already incorporated landscape and other environmental features. In addition, the potential for inferring host contacts in network models using pathogen genetic markers (see below) has been acknowledged in recent reviews (Craft, 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0028">2015</a>; Gilbertson, Fountain‐Jones, &amp; Craft, 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0057" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0057">2018</a>; White, Forester, &amp; Craft, 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0131" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0131">2017</a>), and some studies have directly compared host contact network parameters to parasite genotypes (Bull, Godfrey, &amp; Gordon, 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0020">2012</a>). Despite this, to our knowledge, no published studies have used network models to investigate pathogen movement within a landscape genetic framework.
 </p>
</sec>
