<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="eva12678-sec-0001" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">INTRODUCTION</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The field of landscape genetics seeks to identify relationships between heterogeneous landscape features and genetic variation in free‐living organisms and has become a popular method for investigating drivers of processes such as gene flow, genetic drift and selection. (Manel &amp; Holderegger, 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0089" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0089">2013</a>; Manel, Schwartz, Luikart, &amp; Taberlet, 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0090" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0090">2003</a>). Landscape genetics has grown substantially since its formal inception in 2003, facilitated by technological advances that have increased the availability of molecular and landscape data in conjunction with more powerful computational and analytical approaches. Landscape genetics is fuelled by a steady stream of new ideas and methodologies, which, while exciting, can contribute to a lack of consensus or consistency in some key aspects. These aspects include the formulation of research questions, sampling strategies, analytical methods (Balkenhol, Waits, &amp; Dezzani, 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0010">2009</a>; Richardson, Brady, Wang, &amp; Spear, 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0108" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0108">2016</a>; Wagner &amp; Fortin, 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0129" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0129">2013</a>) and even the identity of the field itself (Dyer, 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0039">2015</a>; Storfer et al., 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0120" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0120">2007</a>). In fact, landscape genetics has yet to develop its own comprehensive, unifying theory for linking spatial and temporal landscape heterogeneity to genetic variation (Balkenhol, Cushman, Waits, &amp; Storfer, 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0008">2016</a>). While these issues are expected to be remedied as the field matures, many suggestions have been made to facilitate this progress. These have included calls for an increase in cross‐disciplinary collaboration (Balkenhol, Gugerli et al., 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0009">2009</a>) and an expansion of the scope of landscape genetic research beyond its current emphasis on vertebrates (Balkenhol, Cushman, Waits et al., 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0008">2016</a>; Dyer, 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0039">2015</a>) and, particularly, mammals (Kozakiewicz, Carver, &amp; Burridge, 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0071" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0071">2018</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One logical avenue for cross‐disciplinary expansion of landscape genetics is in disease ecology (Biek &amp; Real, 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0014">2010</a>). Elucidating the specific influences of landscape features on pathogen transmission can provide key insights into the processes that affect disease risk and incidence. However, accomplishing this has been a challenge for disease ecologists (Ostfeld, Glass, &amp; Keesing, 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0098" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0098">2005</a>). Indeed, the field of spatial epidemiology has only recently begun to emphasize the use of explicit landscape approaches in studies of spatial heterogeneity in infectious disease (i.e., “landscape epidemiology”; Ostfeld et al., 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0098" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0098">2005</a>; Meentemeyer, Haas, &amp; Václavík, 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0093" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0093">2012</a>). A major challenge for the study of landscape epidemiology, a field which does not traditionally implement genetic approaches, is that it is typically dependent on the ability to identify the location and timing of transmission events such that they can be compared to landscape features of interest. Transmission events are essentially impossible to observe, so disease ecologists often assume that contacts between infected and susceptible individuals are a reasonable proxy for transmission. Such contacts generally must be inferred indirectly using methods such as proximity collars, mark‐recapture or telemetry, often using spatial overlap as a proxy for contact (Craft &amp; Caillaud, 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0029">2011</a>). These methods are logistically challenging to employ, and whether an inferred contact resulted in transmission is uncertain (Craft, 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0028">2015</a>). Further, much landscape epidemiological research uses infection or exposure data to indicate past transmission, but these methods provide static snapshots of pathogen prevalence and may be inappropriate for inferring how transmission or spread has occurred (or is occurring) over time (Meentemeyer et al., 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0093" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0093">2012</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The spatial distribution and movement of hosts are major factors affecting the likelihood, timing and spatial patterns of pathogen transmission and spread (Dougherty, Seidel, Carlson, Spiegel, &amp; Getz, 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0037">2018</a>). Landscape genetics can identify landscape factors that are important drivers of host population structure. These landscape factors can determine the spatial configuration of a population, its density, its connectivity with other populations, its demographic structure and its genetic health—all of which have implications for the dynamics of microorganisms infecting the host species (Ellis, Václavík, &amp; Meentemeyer, 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0042">2010</a>; Prentice, Marion, White, Davidson, &amp; Hutchings, 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0102" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0102">2014</a>; Spielman, Brook, Briscoe, &amp; Frankham, 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0118" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0118">2004</a>). Further, pathogen dynamics can be inferred directly using pathogen genetic data (Archie, Luikart, &amp; Ezenwa, 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0006">2009</a>; DeCandia, Dobson, &amp; vonHoldt, 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0032">2018</a>) and incorporated into landscape genetic analyses. Understanding specifically how infectious agents respond to the influence of landscape factors on hosts enables us to predict how such agents might spread based on present landscape configurations, as well as under potential future landscape scenarios (Real &amp; Biek, 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0104" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0104">2007</a>). This knowledge can subsequently inform management efforts at the population level (such as vaccination targeted at key regions, culling), as well as broader decisions relating to the management of the landscape itself, which is a key aim of landscape genetics generally (Manel &amp; Holderegger, 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0089" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0089">2013</a>; Segelbacher et al., 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0115" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0115">2010</a>). Landscape genetics is being applied by managers at relatively low rates compared to related ecological fields such as landscape ecology, conservation biology and telemetry research (Bowman et al., 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0016">2016</a>). Therefore, studies that contribute to the management of disease agents within populations could increase the practical impacts of landscape genetics significantly. However, the conceptual underpinnings of pathogen landscape genetics are not fully developed, and the methodologies employed are diverse and potentially confusing for new practitioners.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here, we investigate how landscape genetic techniques are being used to better understand dynamics of microorganisms infecting host species. In conducting this review, we aim to both advocate and facilitate landscape genetic research involving disease‐causing organisms. We first evaluate the use of landscape genetics in disease ecology, including the types of questions addressed, the approaches used and the infectious agents studied. We then review established landscape genetic methods and their realized and potential applications to disease ecology. At last, we identify emerging frontiers in the landscape genetic study of pathogens that hold significant potential for advancing research in this field.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Landscape genetics was first implemented in the study of rabies virus by Real et al. (
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0105" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0105">2005</a>), offering an approach to overcome many feasibility issues associated with understanding landscape influences on pathogen transmission. The landscape genetic approach to studying disease was later reviewed by Biek and Real (
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0014">2010</a>), who were optimistic about its growth and future use. In particular, they noted that microparasites, such as viruses, are well‐suited to landscape genetic study due to their rapid mutation rate and potential spatial genetic structure that can be compared to heterogeneous landscape features at fine temporal and spatial scales. Analyses could be conducted using both pathogenic organisms and agents that do not cause significant diseases in their hosts (Biek, Drummond, &amp; Poss, 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0012">2006</a>). They also identified that methodologies such as GIS, which are commonly employed both in the wider landscape genetics literature and in spatial studies of infectious disease, had not been widely implemented in molecular epidemiology (Archie et al., 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0006">2009</a>). Further, other popular landscape genetic tools, such as those focused on differential landscape permeability (e.g., least‐cost paths), were greatly underused despite compatibility with pathogen spatial genetic data.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Similar to landscape genetics, landscape epidemiology is an interdisciplinary field undergoing rapid development driven by technological advancements, and arguably still working to develop clear directions for future research (Meentemeyer et al., 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0093" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0093">2012</a>). It is therefore likely that the interface of these two fields (i.e., where landscape genetics is used in epidemiology) is similarly challenged, perhaps to the extent that its potential is remaining unrealized. We thus believe it is timely to revisit the body of research that combines landscape genetics and landscape epidemiology, leveraging the work done both prior and subsequent to Biek and Real's (
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0014">2010</a>) earlier review into clear directions for future research.
 </p>
</sec>
