<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="eva12678-sec-0006" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.4</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Pathogen genetic variation to quantify pathogen transmission and spread</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Using the sampled disease agent as the source of genetic data is the most direct way to infer pathogen spread across landscapes, but can be challenging to accomplish. Genetic material may be absent from, or uninformative in some infectious agents, such as prions or clonally transmissible cancers, necessitating genetic analysis of the host (Kelly et al., 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0070" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0070">2014</a>; Storfer et al., 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0119" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0119">2017</a>). In addition to the aforementioned difficulties with pathogen diagnosis, pathogen nucleic acid can be difficult to isolate from samples taken from the host or vector and would ideally be present in the blood, saliva or other easily collected sample. Samples may also require enrichment to obtain sufficient quantities of genetic material for analysis, which can be difficult to accomplish for many pathogens, particularly viruses. However, genetic information from viruses may be particularly useful for molecular epidemiologic analyses due to their rapid mutation rate that can closely infer transmission history (Archie et al., 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0006">2009</a>; Brunker, Hampson, Horton, &amp; Biek, 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0018">2012</a>). Further, viruses are prominent emerging pathogens and have relatively small genomes, aiding whole genome‐analysis. Landscape effects on viral transmission are typically studied using phylogenetic approaches (Fountain‐Jones, Craft et al., 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0049">2017</a>; Joannon, Lavigne, Lecoq, &amp; Desbiez, 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0066" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0066">2010</a>; Streicker et al., 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0122" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0122">2016</a>; Young et al., 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0132" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0132">2017</a>). To date, pathogens with larger and more slowly mutating genomes, such as protozoans (Carrel et al., 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0023">2015</a>; Lo et al., 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0085" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0085">2017</a>) and fungi (Brar et al., 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0017">2015</a>; Rieux, De Bellaire, Zapater, Ravigne, &amp; Carlier, 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0109" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0109">2013</a>), have been studied using population genetics‐based methods with highly variable microsatellite and SNP loci. New methods based on next‐generation sequencing technologies such as targeted enrichment techniques (Lee et al., 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0077" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0077">2017</a>) are helping to address challenges with sequencing viruses and other pathogens, facilitating greater use of pathogen genetic data in future landscape genetic studies.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The pathogenicity of an infectious agent and the length of its period of infection are other factors that may determine its utility for landscape genetic study. Highly pathogenic agents (i.e., those that cause a greater severity of disease) are typically of utmost interest due to their potential implications for wildlife conservation, agricultural production and human health. Among the studies identified in our literature search, agents that form chronic infections and have moderate or high pathogenic effects on their sampled host/vector organisms were more frequently investigated (see Supporting Information Appendix 
  <a rid="eva12678-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#eva12678-sup-0001">S1</a>). However, genetically inferring transmission histories of pathogens in host populations experiencing high rates of mortality may be problematic because hosts through which the pathogen has spread may no longer be present in the population and are unable to be sampled. Similarly, acutely infectious agents from which the host recovers after a short period of time may also evade sampling. These characteristics may be less problematic for agricultural populations where morbidity or mortality can be identified and samples collected immediately, but inevitably leave “breaks” in the inferred chain of transmission among wild populations. While complete sampling of wild populations is rarely possible in any case, obtaining adequate sample sizes is easier for apathogenic or low‐pathogenicity agents that form chronic infections and may be sampled at any time postinfection (e.g., feline immunodeficiency virus; Biek et al., 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0012">2006</a>; Lee et al., 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0078" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0078">2012</a>; Fountain‐Jones, Craft et al., 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0049">2017</a>). Landscape genetic study of such “model” infectious agents may be used to target specific ecological questions and provide insights into how similarly transmitted agents with higher pathogenicity might spread in the event of an outbreak.
 </p>
</sec>
