<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="eva12678-sec-0005" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Relating spatial heterogeneity in infection risk with host spatial genetic variation</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Spatial variation in pathogen prevalence or infection risk can be represented in much the same way as any landscape variable (Escobar et al., 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0045" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0045">2017</a>), making spatial data relating to presence of an infectious agent well‐suited for incorporation into host landscape genetic models. While spatial heterogeneity in pathogen prevalence could also be considered a component of the landscape that may influence spatial genetic variation in the host, typically only adaptive loci are investigated in this context. More commonly, host neutral genetic variation is used to explain spatial patterns of infection risk or prevalence. A prominent example is a study of chronic wasting disease (CWD) in white‐tailed deer. Blanchong et al. (
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0015">2008</a>) found that populations with lower CWD prevalence showed higher genetic differentiation from those that had high CWD prevalence. This genetic differentiation was found to be associated with roads and rivers, which were likely barriers to both host gene flow and CWD spread. These inferences have subsequently informed and been verified by additional landscape epidemiological research (Robinson, Samuel, Rolley, &amp; Shelton, 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0112" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0112">2013</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Spatial heterogeneity in pathogen infection risk can also drive microevolutionary responses in the host (Epstein et al., 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0044" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0044">2016</a>; Monello et al., 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0094" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0094">2017</a>). Host species are constantly being challenged by parasitic organisms, which, if not overcome, cause disease and can have fitness consequences. This can create strong selection that acts on various genes, and geographic variation in selection at loci that are known to be associated with adaptive immune genes may reflect variation in pathogen pressure, and individual infection or disease risk (Fumagalli et al., 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0054">2011</a>). This variation may be tested for association with environmental features such as temperature, humidity or urbanization (Tonteri, Vasemägi, Lumme, &amp; Primmer, 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0126" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0126">2010</a>), enabling insights into how future changes in climate or land use might influence overall pathogen prevalence.
 </p>
</sec>
