<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="eva12678-sec-0014" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Simultaneously integrating host, vector and landscape variables into studies of pathogen gene flow</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Studies relating pathogen genetic data directly to the landscape using resistance surfaces are challenged by the mediating influence of distinct host and vector traits, as well as relative differences in the contributions of multiple host and/or vector species to microparasite gene flow. This necessitates frameworks that more holistically incorporate multiple host and vector factors into studies of pathogen gene flow, which can expand the potential insights provided by landscape genetic studies of infectious agents (Figure 
  <a rid="eva12678-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#eva12678-fig-0002">2</a>). Single or multiple host or vector species can be added as “landscape variables” (e.g., as resistance surfaces) in addition to physical landscape and environmental variables to test as factors shaping spatial pathogen genetic structure. Resistance surfaces for tests of microparasite gene flow can represent host/vector distributions or abundance, ideally inferred from empirically derived ecological niche or species distribution models. Optimally, host/vector movement would be represented (Dougherty et al., 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0037">2018</a>), using outputs from agent‐based movement models informed by telemetry or mark‐recapture data, or host/vector landscape genetic data representing spatial patterns of gene flow. We note that the common issue in conventional landscape genetics of spatio‐temporal mismatches between landscape processes and genetic change (Anderson et al., 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0004">2010</a>; Landguth et al., 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0073" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0073">2010</a>) would apply even more strongly here. Researchers must simultaneously consider the potentially different spatial and temporal scales over which host and pathogen genetic changes (and potentially those of additional host/vector species) and landscape changes occur. Nonetheless, with careful study design, such an approach has significant potential to unify hosts/vectors and landscape variables under a single analytical framework for explaining and predicting pathogen transmission and spread. Importantly, it allows a flexible framework for both single and multihost/vector systems.
 </p>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="eva12678-fig-0002" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Schematic indicating the increasing insights that may be gained from using approaches that are able to integrate additional host/vector and pathogen genetic datasets, starting with genetic data from a single host or vector, through to multispecies approaches that integrate multiple host, vector and pathogen datasets. LG: landscape genetic</p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-3" xlink:href="EVA-11-1763-g002" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Approaches integrating multiple host and vector datasets into landscape genetic studies of infectious agent gene flow have been proposed recently. Leo et al. (
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0082" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0082">2016</a>) developed a multitaxa integrated landscape genetic framework for diseases, which simultaneously quantifies the effects of both landscape variables and interspecific codispersal on pathogen gene flow in multi‐host‐vector systems. Few studies include both host and pathogen genetic data in landscape analyses. However, Fountain‐Jones, Craft et al. (
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0049">2017</a>) tested host relatedness, in addition to host demographic and landscape variables, and found this to be an important predictor of pathogen gene flow in a single‐host system of feline immunodeficiency virus in bobcats. A framework for combining multiple host and vector resistance surfaces was recently demonstrated for Chagas disease by Schwabl et al. (
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0114" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0114">2017</a>), involving subsequent validation using landscape genetic simulations. Although their approach does not explicitly include host and vector movement or gene flow, it advocates careful selection of landscape variables based on each host and vector species, informed by previous research. A recent study tested least‐cost path models of water bird movement estimated from ecological niche models, and road networks representing human movement, as potential predictors of avian influenza spread (Young et al., 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0132" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0132">2017</a>). Other studies have investigated landscape genetic structure in multiple hosts of the same pathogens, identifying divergent dispersal patterns that could be integrated into studies of pathogen gene flow under such a framework (Rioux Paquette et al., 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0111" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0111">2014</a>; Vander Wal et al., 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0128" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0128">2013</a>). Approaches that consider whole ecological communities have recently been identified as necessary for advancing our understanding of pathogen dynamics (Fountain‐Jones, Pearse et al., 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0051" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0051">2017</a>; Johnson, de Roode, &amp; Fenton, 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0067" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0067">2015</a>). Studies integrating multiple host and vector species into landscape genetic models of spread of infectious agents represent an important step towards such a paradigm.
 </p>
</sec>
