<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="eva12678-sec-0016" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.3</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The role of phylogenetics in understanding landscape influences on pathogen genetic variation</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Phylogenetic approaches can reconstruct very recent epidemic histories, providing insights into particular transmission events and pathways that may be contextualized temporally and spatially (Corman et al., 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0026">2014</a>; Faria et al., 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0047">2014</a>; Carroll et al., 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0024">2015</a>; Magee, Beard, Suchard, Lemey, &amp; Scotch, 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0088" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0088">2015</a>; Fountain‐Jones, Packer, et al., 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0050" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0050">2017</a>; Fountain‐Jones, Pearse et al., 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0051" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0051">2017</a>). The majority of such work has been conducted on RNA viruses owing to their small, rapidly mutating genomes, requiring relatively little sequencing effort to detect contemporary phylogenetic signals. Other pathogens that evolve more slowly, such as bacteria or fungal pathogens, require the sequencing of larger portions of their genomes to capture equivalent phylogenetic signals (Biek, Pybus, Lloyd‐Smith, &amp; Didelot, 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0013">2015</a>). While this is becoming increasingly feasible (Kao, Haydon, Lycett, &amp; Murcia, 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0069" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0069">2014</a>), more complex computational analysis is required to make meaningful conclusions.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Several approaches may be used for relating phylogenetic information with landscape variables. Neighbour joining trees can identify clusters for quantifying population‐level landscape genetic relationships (Joannon et al., 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0066" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0066">2010</a>). The calculation of genetic distances based on maximum likelihood trees (Carrel, Emch, Tung, Jobe, &amp; Wan, 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0022">2012</a>; Real et al., 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0105" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0105">2005</a>; Young et al., 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0132" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0132">2017</a>) results in distance matrices that can be correlated with landscape resistance matrices using conventional landscape genetic approaches. Relaxed random walk phylogeographic approaches (Lemey, Rambaut, Welch, &amp; Suchard, 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0081" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0081">2010</a>) that can reconstruct pathogen dispersal have been linked to landscape predictors using a “phylogeographic GLM” method (Faria, Suchard, Rambaut, Streicker, &amp; Lemey, 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0048" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0048">2013</a>; Jacquot, Nomikou, Palmarini, Mertens, &amp; Biek, 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0063" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0063">2017</a>). The phylogeographic GLM approach has enabled a better understanding of how landscape and hosts can constrain pathogen spread. For example, using the phylogeographic GLM approach on viral genomic data, roads and rivers, coupled with dog distribution, were found to impact rabies spread in Tanzania (Brunker et al., 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0019">2018</a>). However, this approach is limited to discrete sampling locations and is computationally intensive (Dellicour, Rose, &amp; Pybus, 
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0034">2016</a>). A recent framework by Dellicour et al. (
  <a rid="eva12678-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" href="#eva12678-bib-0034">2016</a>) modifies the phylogeographic GLM approach to use resistance surfaces to efficiently quantify landscape resistance along transmission pathways inferred by continuous phylogeographic analyses. These landscape resistances are then correlated with temporal estimates of transmission along these routes to estimate how the landscape has shaped rates and directions of pathogen spread. Such approaches are yet to be broadly applied, but appear to be important developments that should see increasing application in the future.
 </p>
</sec>
