<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec034" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Biomass</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For all scenarios, the overall biomass decreases, with a stronger signal when there are large reductions in river load. This is in line with the results from [
  <a rid="pone.0199168.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0199168.ref021">21</a>] who used a NPDZ model to show that a reduction in nutrients lead to a decrease in biomass for diatoms, flagellates and zooplankton, with a maximum decrease in primary producers. According to the Atlantis results, there is a bottom-up and cascading effect where the change is observed for all trophic levels [
  <a rid="pone.0199168.ref093" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0199168.ref093">93</a>]. However, there is no consistent pattern found for all functional groups because of the complex foodweb interactions that the model comprehends. The amount of change differs also from polygon to polygon with higher changes in the near coastal ones as they are more directly affected by the river inflow, which is also shown in other studies [
  <a rid="pone.0199168.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0199168.ref021">21</a>]. The changed fish biomass under the scenarios of decreasing fishing mortalities on commercial fish stocks is much smaller than the uncertainty of the model (i.e. difference due to an altered set of initial conditions and uncertainty of the input data). However, the scenario #5 leads to a sprat biomass reduction of 18% and an increased cod biomass levels as was expected. The largest decrease of biomass for scenario #5 was that of the mysids. The mysids react only for the last two scenarios though. This is because of the way they are spatially distributed. Their limited spatial occurrence does not mean that their production is equally limited. Especially because sprat and herring have a broader spatial occurrence and do feed for a large part on the mysids.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Significant changes in Nephrops and detritus biomasses were as expected for the nutrient load reduction scenarios. For scenario #3 and #5, Nephrops decreases around 20% due to a decrease in their main food source, detritus. Labile and refractory detritus are a pool of fixed nutrients from faeces and non-predation mortality products. The decrease of this detritus pool is caused by a decrease of production of the rest of the ecosystem due to the reduced river load. In the scenario following the Baltic action plan, the Nephrops stock is reduced by 11%, less than for other scenarios. Consequently, the model response is proportional to load reduction and shows expected patterns and levels of effects on the different functional groups given current knowledge. This can be seen in context of a general propagation of the effect of the river load reductions through the whole ecosystem. When the small changes in biomass, which are generated in the scenarios, accumulate, then this might lead to a more extensive change of the detritus pool. This in turn can have an effect on those groups feeding on detritus, such as filter feeders, polychaetes, deposit feeders and Nephrops. Those multitudes of interactions is an argument for using an end-to-end ecosystem model to comprehend the more realistic perception of effects of nutrient load reductions taking into consideration the broader and complex biological processes, effects and interactions.</p>
</sec>
