<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec015" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Economic analysis of the Atlantis output in Kattegat-Western Baltic</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The FISHRENT model [
  <a rid="pone.0199168.ref060" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0199168.ref060">60</a>] was used to analyze the final year output of the Atlantis model. FISHRENT is a multi-stock multi-fleet bio-economic model which was developed from best practice knowledge on fisheries gained from similar models used in Europe over the past decade (e.g. [
  <a rid="pone.0199168.ref078" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0199168.ref078">78</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0199168.ref079" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0199168.ref079">79</a>]). FISHRENT enables consideration of a diverse array of policy aims, including Maximum Sustainable Yield (MSY) and Maximum Economic Yield (MEY) goals. The main outputs from FISHRENT describe the likely trajectories and status of the modelled fisheries and fleets over a predetermined time-period given the status of the main fish stocks exploited per area and the policy aims considered. The model contains five modules: biological, economic, market, behavior, and policy (Figure C in 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0199168.s001" href="#pone.0199168.s001">S1 File</a>). A key characteristic of FISHRENT is that the necessary fleet and economic data have been structured in the same way as the data collected on a national basis as part of the EU Data Collection Framework (EU DCF). This enables consistent analysis to be conducted across nations ensuring that best available national data is used. More detailed information about the FISHRENT model and its implementation in the Kattegat and the Western Baltic Sea can be found in section C, Tables J-R in 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0199168.s001" href="#pone.0199168.s001">S1 File</a>. The economic consequences of the nutrient load scenarios two to four are evaluated by the FISHRENT model.
 </p>
</sec>
