<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec033" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nutrient load reduction scenarios</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The nutrient load reduction scenarios allowed us to test our newly developed model in its responsiveness to system disturbances. The nutrient load reduction scenarios where chosen because the Baltic ecosystem is already characterized as a highly eutrophic system [
  <a rid="pone.0199168.ref010" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0199168.ref010">10</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0199168.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0199168.ref016">16</a>]. The scenarios are purely for testing the model though and do not reflect an actual reduction plan. The four different scenarios gradually increase the reduction of nitrogen in the ecosystem. This is done by including more and more river point sources, linked to certain polygons, which carries a reduced amount of nitrogen. Even though the spatial scale of the Atlantis polygons might, to some extent, limit the resolution of fully representing bio-geochemical and primary production responses to changes in eutrophication pressures, it still allows for the separation of different processes in narrow coastal versus larger off-shore polygons (section B.1 in 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0199168.s001" href="#pone.0199168.s001">S1 File</a>). This spatial explicit approach is necessary because the eutrophication issue in the Baltic Sea is on such a large scale. Besides the spatial explicit approach, the interactions of physical with biological processes need to be included to investigate this issue, which is why this end-to-end model is applied.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the model, it is mainly the dietary interactions that determine the response of planktivorous and piscivorous fish biomass for the analyzed nutrient reduction scenarios. However, the model parameterization could not be equally well constrained for all groups and processes. For instance, the prey-predator interactions involving cod, sprat and herring are well informed using abundant field data and robust model results from the Baltic SMS or EwE. On the other hand, there is little data to quantitatively describe the dietary interactions of many benthic animals, or if locally available, the issue of extrapolating accurately over many types of habitats remains. Benthic organisms, especially in the coastal zones, are known to be susceptible to changes in ambient oxygen conditions [
  <a rid="pone.0199168.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0199168.ref023">23</a>], strongly affected by riverine nutrient inputs. As a result, the biomass fluctuations in the nutrient load scenarios of these less constrained groups could strongly affect the development of their predators, such as juvenile cod, or other bottom dwelling fish. (See also section B.2 in 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0199168.s001" href="#pone.0199168.s001">S1 File</a>–Demographic profiles, mortality rates &amp; reproduction functions).
 </p>
 <sec id="sec034" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Biomass</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For all scenarios, the overall biomass decreases, with a stronger signal when there are large reductions in river load. This is in line with the results from [
   <a rid="pone.0199168.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0199168.ref021">21</a>] who used a NPDZ model to show that a reduction in nutrients lead to a decrease in biomass for diatoms, flagellates and zooplankton, with a maximum decrease in primary producers. According to the Atlantis results, there is a bottom-up and cascading effect where the change is observed for all trophic levels [
   <a rid="pone.0199168.ref093" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0199168.ref093">93</a>]. However, there is no consistent pattern found for all functional groups because of the complex foodweb interactions that the model comprehends. The amount of change differs also from polygon to polygon with higher changes in the near coastal ones as they are more directly affected by the river inflow, which is also shown in other studies [
   <a rid="pone.0199168.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0199168.ref021">21</a>]. The changed fish biomass under the scenarios of decreasing fishing mortalities on commercial fish stocks is much smaller than the uncertainty of the model (i.e. difference due to an altered set of initial conditions and uncertainty of the input data). However, the scenario #5 leads to a sprat biomass reduction of 18% and an increased cod biomass levels as was expected. The largest decrease of biomass for scenario #5 was that of the mysids. The mysids react only for the last two scenarios though. This is because of the way they are spatially distributed. Their limited spatial occurrence does not mean that their production is equally limited. Especially because sprat and herring have a broader spatial occurrence and do feed for a large part on the mysids.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Significant changes in Nephrops and detritus biomasses were as expected for the nutrient load reduction scenarios. For scenario #3 and #5, Nephrops decreases around 20% due to a decrease in their main food source, detritus. Labile and refractory detritus are a pool of fixed nutrients from faeces and non-predation mortality products. The decrease of this detritus pool is caused by a decrease of production of the rest of the ecosystem due to the reduced river load. In the scenario following the Baltic action plan, the Nephrops stock is reduced by 11%, less than for other scenarios. Consequently, the model response is proportional to load reduction and shows expected patterns and levels of effects on the different functional groups given current knowledge. This can be seen in context of a general propagation of the effect of the river load reductions through the whole ecosystem. When the small changes in biomass, which are generated in the scenarios, accumulate, then this might lead to a more extensive change of the detritus pool. This in turn can have an effect on those groups feeding on detritus, such as filter feeders, polychaetes, deposit feeders and Nephrops. Those multitudes of interactions is an argument for using an end-to-end ecosystem model to comprehend the more realistic perception of effects of nutrient load reductions taking into consideration the broader and complex biological processes, effects and interactions.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec035" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Oxygen</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Distinct benthic oxygen concentration increases were simulated in many areas according to nutrient load reductions, especially in the Western Baltic and the Baltic proper areas while less distinct in the deeper areas (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0199168.g011" href="#pone.0199168.g011">Fig 11</a>). Oxygen conditions in the bottom water layers improved with up to two to three times the amount of oxygen for scenario #4 and #5 compared with the baseline. Reducing the river load caused a reduced production of biomass which presumably lowered the need for oxygen in order to decompose all the organic matter. It must be emphasized though, that the benthic-pelagic coupling and sediment processes in general require further calibration and validation before we can apply a greater certainty to the above and below model output.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The increase of cod biomass might be linked with the increase in oxygen concentration for two reasons. First of all, benthic invertebrates have a higher survival chance due to the increased oxygen conditions. They are also the main food source for juvenile cod, especially the isopod 
   <span class="italic">Saduria entomon</span> [
   <a rid="pone.0199168.ref084" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0199168.ref084">84</a>]. Secondly, the improved hydrographical conditions in the bottom water layers may have a positive effect on cod egg survival as it increases the reproductive volume [
   <a rid="pone.0199168.ref094" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0199168.ref094">94</a>]. This is the volume of water in which the cod eggs develop and it is the key driver of its recruitment success. The reproductive volume is delimited by a concentration of oxygen &gt;2mL L-1 and a salinity of &gt;11 psu [
   <a rid="pone.0199168.ref094" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0199168.ref094">94</a>–
   <a rid="pone.0199168.ref096" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0199168.ref096">96</a>]. While we didn’t explicitly represent oxygen effects on the egg and larval stage it would affect new settlers so the model captures some of the potential recruitment effects, but not all.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The simulations mainly show an increase for the cod age-groups of 2–4 and rather than in the 1
   <span class="sup">st</span> age group. This implies that the increase in food sources for the juvenile cod has a larger effect than the higher survival of its eggs (Figure L in 
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0199168.s001" href="#pone.0199168.s001">S1 File</a>). So, despite an increased production for the benthic organisms, their total biomass decreased due to accentuated predation by juvenile cod.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Anoxic zones have been known in the Baltic for long time and are severely impacting the ecosystem [
   <a rid="pone.0199168.ref096" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0199168.ref096">96</a>–
   <a rid="pone.0199168.ref100" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0199168.ref100">100</a>], because benthic species are unable to escape. Anoxic zones cause severe losses on entire benthic communities, which are seen as one of the causes for changed levels of fish catches since the 1970s combined hydrographical driven fish recruitment patterns [
   <a rid="pone.0199168.ref101" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0199168.ref101">101</a>–
   <a rid="pone.0199168.ref105" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0199168.ref105">105</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
