<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec009" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Other initial condition values</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The annual average spatial distribution of mysids and gelatinous zooplankton was based on scarce and irregular data maintained in SMHI (Swedish Meteorological and Hydrographical Institute; 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.smhi.se/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.smhi.se</span>) and ICES (International Council for Exploration of the Sea; 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ices.dk/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.ices.dk</span>) databases, and supplemented by the results of an extensive literature review, covering a period from 2003 to 2007. Initial conditions for benthic deposit feeders, polychaetes, soft- and hard-substrate filter feeders came from the compilation of data obtained from SMHI, ICES, DCE (Danish National Center for Environment and Energy; 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.dce.au.dk/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.dce.au.dk</span>) and HERTTA (Finnish Environmental Institute; 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.p2.ymparisto.fi/scripts/oiva.asp" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.p2.ymparisto.fi/scripts/oiva.asp</span>) databases. The data used covered a period from 2003 to 2007. Literature information on coverage and/or biomass was obtained to estimate initial conditions for spatial distribution of macroalgae [
  <a rid="pone.0199168.ref073" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0199168.ref073">73</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0199168.ref075" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0199168.ref075">75</a>] and seagrass [
  <a rid="pone.0199168.ref076" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0199168.ref076">76</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Table C in the 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0199168.s001" href="#pone.0199168.s001">S1 File</a> provides a summary of the sources used to inform the model with the required biological fields, fluxes and parameters for the 2005 initial conditions year for all vertebrate and/or commercially important species (e.g. Nephrops). A distinct spatial distribution was specified for adults and juveniles, and by season (half year), if the data was available. Details of these calculations and considerations for vertebrates and invertebrates can be found in 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0199168.s001" href="#pone.0199168.s001">S1 File</a> section B.2. Because the input information is derived from observed or previously modeled mean annual concentration and biomass levels taken from the 2005 reference year, we can check whether the model is able to reproduce realistic biomass levels for those groups. We do not provide a similar comparison for invertebrates and the lower trophic levels for which we did not have accurate or equivalent data to start with. However, their values are set according to the best available knowledge. Initial values of detrital matter were purposefully set very low for the model initial conditions in order to avoid too strong grazing pressure and in general larger internal model error due to a choice of initial conditions.
 </p>
</sec>
