<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec032" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Spatial distribution of biological functional groups</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The spatial distribution shows no extinctions in any polygon for all the vertebrates, with biomass fluctuating seasonally. The higher fluctuations of the vertebrates represent migrations between spawning and feeding grounds. This is why for instance cod biomass in certain polygons reaches zero (this type of migration is further discussed in section B.2 in 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0199168.s001" href="#pone.0199168.s001">S1 File</a>–Quarterly abundance distribution of vertebrates). The fluctuations of the phytoplankton biomass show a spatial variation in the amplitude of those seasonal biomass peaks. The differences are likely due to the coastal versus off-shore physical conditions. Coastal areas have a continuous high nutrient load due to the riverine inflow all year round and they exhibit the highest variations in temperature with the lowest temperature reaching zero [
  <a rid="pone.0199168.ref056" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0199168.ref056">56</a>]. Off-shore areas also have a continuous N load in the surface areas [
  <a rid="pone.0199168.ref050" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0199168.ref050">50</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0199168.ref090" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0199168.ref090">90</a>] so primary production and standing stock biomass does not go to zero [
  <a rid="pone.0199168.ref056" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0199168.ref056">56</a>], but they show much less temperature fluctuations, especially with respect to the extreme minima. That is why we do not expect as high temperature driven fluctuations in primary production in the off-shore areas as we see in the coastal ones (Figures D and M in 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0199168.s001" href="#pone.0199168.s001">S1 File</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">However, it should be noticed that the limitation of finding vertical/horizontal mixing parameters could lead to a lack of adequately representing the nutrient distribution, stratification and so the primary production, despite extensively testing these parameters. On top of that, there exists only limited knowledge on the spatial distribution of the phytoplankton communities in the Baltic Sea due to the limited spatial and/or temporal coverage of previous research [
  <a rid="pone.0199168.ref091" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0199168.ref091">91</a>]. Similar for the Baltic total zooplankton biomass (microzooplankton, mesozooplankton and gelatinous zooplankton), the grazing and its distribution patterns in the Baltic Sea likely remains the least constrained level of the ecosystem. This is partly due to similar challenges in adequately sampling and monitoring, and partly due to the large fluctuations arising from observed patterns that also show high fluctuations on narrow spatial and temporal scales in different water layers. In the Bornholm Basin there are spectacular shifts in observed zooplankton community composition and grazing pressure (e.g. [
  <a rid="pone.0199168.ref067" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0199168.ref067">67</a>]), and although this area is sampled regularly, it still imposes many difficulties and challenges for model attempts in relation to those specific processes. Future improvements in properly constraining this ecosystem bottleneck will be fundamental to the successful evaluation of ecosystem-wide interactions in the Baltic Sea realm.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another proxy useful for evaluating the geographical distribution of total phytoplankton biomass is the surface Chl-a (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0199168.g004" href="#pone.0199168.g004">Fig 4</a>). The reason why Atlantis seems to overestimate the Chl-a in coastal waters for the Western Baltic, the Gulf of Riga and Gulf of Finland regions, compared to the ERGOM model, could be because of the spatial resolution of the two models, where the ERGOM model has a very fine resolution in comparison with the coarse Atlantis polygon sizes. However, the ERGOM model also tends to underestimate the surface Chl-a concentration when compared to observational data, especially in the offshore Bornholm Basin and Gotland Basin [
  <a rid="pone.0199168.ref056" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0199168.ref056">56</a>] which makes the Atlantis estimates closer to the observations.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the offshore polygons, Atlantis simulates quite similar surface Chl-a concentrations relative to the HBM-ERGOM output, except for the northern Bothnian Sea where Atlantis has a slightly lower estimate of the Chl-a concentration in the off-shore polygon. This may be explained by the lack of cyanobacteria in the Atlantis in comparison with HBM-ERGOM. The current Baltic Atlantis results are calibrated without considering phosphorus and carbon cycling. Consequently, cyanobacteria are not included in the model simulations since they are mostly distinguished from other pelagic primary producers by a higher phosphorus requirement for growth. In the Baltic Sea, nitrogen-fixing cyanobacteria contribute significantly to primary production, especially during the summer months in the northern Baltic Proper and more Northerly Baltic areas (e.g. [
  <a rid="pone.0199168.ref092" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0199168.ref092">92</a>]).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Lack of cyanobacteria probably does not affect the secondary production in the model, because they are not an important food source for zooplankton. Sedimentation and subsequent degradation of cyanobacteria are also not included in Atlantis and may lead to slight underestimation of hypoxia in the open areas of the model. Not accounting for these phenomena is unlikely to compromise the results of the current analyses because the salinities in the Kattegat, Western Baltic regions and southern Baltic proper regions, except in the immediate vicinity of the coast, are beyond the typical &lt;12 salinity range where cyanobacteria appear in the Baltic [
  <a rid="pone.0199168.ref066" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0199168.ref066">66</a>]. Finally, the attenuation of light in the Baltic Atlantis water column accounts for total phytoplankton biomass but does not explicitly represent attenuation due to colored dissolved organic material (CDOM). The potential overestimation of light levels due to lack of CDOM as well as cloud cover effects on light availability are partially offset by adjusting the light attenuation coefficients of phytoplankton groups.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Furthermore, HBM-ERGOM outputs reveal that in Kattegat and the Western Baltic there exist very sharp gradients between very narrow but highly productive zones and offshore areas with low annual average phytoplankton standing stocks. These features are unlikely to be fully captured in Baltic Atlantis without a more detailed map of time-varying riverine and point source inputs to the model, such as the one offered by the DK-QNP model used to force HBM-ERGOM. Although such high spatial resolution details need not be considered to force the dynamics of fisheries, they are more important in better constraining biogeochemical cycling, and its control on seasonal and inter-annual variability in primary production.</p>
</sec>
