<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD with MathML3 v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1-mathml3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="editorial"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Perspect Med Educ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Perspect Med Educ</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Perspectives on Medical Education</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">2212-2761</issn><issn pub-type="epub">2212-277X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Bohn Stafleu van Loghum</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Houten</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6820585</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">541</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s40037-019-00541-8</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Commentary</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>A&#x000a0;call for action: integrating climate change into the medical school curriculum</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Finkel</surname><given-names>Madelon L.</given-names></name><address><email>maf2011@med.cornell.edu</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5386.8</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">000000041936877X</institution-id><institution>Weill Cornell Medicine, </institution></institution-wrap>New York, NY USA </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>9</day><month>10</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>9</day><month>10</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><month>10</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>5</issue><fpage>265</fpage><lpage>266</lpage><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made.</license-p></license></permissions><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><p>The world is experiencing unprecedented changes in the global climate system. The increase in the number of extreme weather events, including rising temperatures, extended heatwaves, hurricanes, flooding, droughts and wildfires, has been steadily increasing in every region of the world since the 1990s [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. The global mean surface temperature has increased and atmospheric concentrations of carbon dioxide and other greenhouse gases (e.g., methane) have risen. Ice caps are melting; sea levels are rising. The 2018 Lancet Countdown report, which monitors the impacts of climate change on health, concluded that many of the global trends identified in its 2015 report (e.g., vulnerability to heat, vectorial capacity for disease, terrestrial and marine food security) have accelerated in terms of the impact of climate change on health [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. The 2018 report ominously concludes that based on analysis of the data, climate change is &#x02018;the biggest global health threat of the 21st&#x000a0;century&#x02019;.</p><p>The implications of extreme weather and climate events on the environment as well as on health status are apparent, with young children, the elderly and patients with comorbid conditions most vulnerable [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Twenty-three percent of global deaths and 22% of global disability adjusted life years (DALYs) were attributable to environmental risks in 2012, and nearly a&#x000a0;quarter of global disease burden could be prevented by reducing environmental risks [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. For example, coal burning power plants spew harmful levels of sulphur dioxide and particulate matter into the air and exposure to ambient air pollution and fine particulate matter have serious implications for respiratory diseases. Air pollution alone contributed to an estimated 6.5&#x000a0;million deaths in 2015 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Heat stress exacerbates kidney and cardiovascular disease, among other conditions. As of 2017, 157 million more people were exposed to heat-related health risks than in 2000 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Further, rising temperatures have implications for the transmission of important vector-borne and water-borne diseases, which have implications for the spread of many infectious diseases. Higher temperatures lead to an increase in mosquitos that transmit the viruses that cause Zika, chikungunya, yellow fever, and dengue. Even small changes in temperature and rainfall can have a&#x000a0;significant effect on the spread of disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. The World Health Organization (WHO) projects that between 2030 and 2050 there will be approximately 250,000 deaths annually due to climate change [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>].</p><p>Climate change also contributes to reduced agricultural yields, which has an impact on food security and food availability. Changes in crop yields linked to climate change lead to food shortages, which can have substantial implications for nutritional status as well as for famines. In addition to its impact on physical health, climate change also affects mental health and wellbeing. As a&#x000a0;result of climate change, there is a&#x000a0;geographic displacement of populations, damage to property, and chronic stress, all of which can negatively affect mental health [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>].</p><p>Some believe that climate change is too narrowly focused. The idea of Planetary Health was introduced in 2015 by The Rockefeller Foundation-Lancet Commission on Planetary Health [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Planetary health aims not only to investigate the effects of environmental change on human health, but also to study the political, economic, and social systems that govern those effects. In addition to assessing the impact on human health, planetary health also takes into account poverty, nutrition, gender equity, water and sanitation, energy, economic growth, industrialization, inequality, urbanization, human consumption and production, climate change, ocean health, land use, peace, and justice. As conceived, planetary health is a&#x000a0;wide-ranging, interdisciplinary subject with a&#x000a0;focus on addressing challenges to maintain and enhance human health in the face of increasingly harmful environmental trends.</p><p>What does this have to do with the medical school curriculum? There is a&#x000a0;growing realization that as we prepare medical students to enter the profession, it is imperative that they graduate with an understanding of the implications of climate change/planetary health on the physical and mental health and well-being of their patients.</p><p>Given the mounting evidence that changes in the climate system have the potential to adversely affect human health, the medical school curriculum should incorporate curricula to reflect the health risks and harms associated with a&#x000a0;changing climate. A&#x000a0;2013 survey found that 34&#x02013;40% of each year&#x02019;s graduating medical students between 2009 and 2013 believed that their instruction in environmental health was inadequate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. The implications of these findings take on added urgency as we learn more about the potential hazards of climate change on the environment and human health. Clearly, medical schools can and should do a&#x000a0;better job of preparing medical students to be cognizant of and to understand the negative effects of climate change on human health.</p><p>The medical school curriculum is not static, evolving over the decades to reflect new ideas and new knowledge. An increasing number of medical schools are implementing changes to their curriculum to incorporate timely and current content. One-third of US medical schools report that they are planning to implement curricula changes in the near future while 31% are in the process of so doing. One fifth have already implemented changes within the past three years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. The potential impact of climate change on human health begs the importance of including the health impacts of climate change in the medical school curriculum. While some medical schools have introduced climate change modules focusing on the role of the environment as a&#x000a0;risk factor for disease, [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>] more widespread action is needed.</p><p>A&#x000a0;decade ago an ad hoc Interagency Working Group on Climate Change and Health prepared a&#x000a0;white paper outlining the human health effects of climate change [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. While some progress has been made to mitigate the situation, much more remains to be done, including preparing medical students to understand the implications of climate change on the health and well-being of their patients.</p></body><back><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Global Climate Change</collab></person-group><source>Vital signs of the planet</source><year>2999</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Watts</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Amann</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Arnell</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The 2018 report of the Lancet Countdown on health and climate change: shaping the health of nations for centuries to come</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2018</year><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(18)32594-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ebi</surname><given-names>KL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ogden</surname><given-names>NH</given-names></name><name><surname>Semenza</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Woodward</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detecting and attributing health burdens to climate change</article-title><source>Environ Health Perspect</source><year>2017</year><volume>125</volume><fpage>085004</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1289/EHP1509</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28796635</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pr&#x000fc;ss-Ust&#x000fc;n</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Wolf</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Corval&#x000e1;n</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Diseases due to unhealthy environments: an updated estimate of the global burden of disease attributable to environmental determinants of health</article-title><source>J Public Health</source><year>2016</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>464</fpage><lpage>475</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Landrigan</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Fuller</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Acosta</surname><given-names>NJR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The Lancet Commission on pollution and health</article-title><source>Lancet</source><year>2018</year><volume>391</volume><fpage>462</fpage><lpage>512</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(17)32345-0</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29056410</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>World Health Organization</collab></person-group><source>Quantitative risk assessment of the effects of climate change on selected causes of death, 2030s and 2050s</source><year>2014</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Planetary Health</collab></person-group><source>Safeguarding both human health and the natural systems that underpin it</source><year>2019</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Association of American Medical Colleges</collab></person-group><source>Medical school graduation questionnaire 2014. All schools summary report</source><year>2999</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Association of American Medical Colleges</collab><collab>Medical School Graduation Questionnaire</collab></person-group><source>All schools summary report</source><year>2013</year></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Walpole</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Vyas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Maxwell</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Building an environmentally accountable medical curriculum through international collaboration</article-title><source>Med Teach</source><year>2017</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>1040</fpage><lpage>1050</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/0142159X.2017.1342031</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28681652</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="editor"><collab>National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences</collab></person-group><source>A human health perspective on climate change. A report outlining the research needs on the human health effects of climate change. The interagency working group on climate change and health</source><year>2010</year></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>