<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Previous studies analyzing variability changes predicted by climate models have focused on changes in variance (
 <xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">12</italic>
 </xref>), mostly in high and mid-latitudes (
 <xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">13</italic>
 </xref>) and the global mean temperature (
 <xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">14</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">15</italic>
 </xref>). Here, we analyze changes in the standard deviation (SD) of monthly temperature anomalies on a local scale, with the aims of (i) identifying regional hotspots where models agree on the largest magnitude changes and (ii) investigating the physical mechanisms behind the identified changes. Because of the variability of climate on multiple time scales, observational time series are usually too short to detect a clear human influence on climate variability (
 <xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">16</italic>
 </xref>–
 <xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">18</italic>
 </xref>). Here, instead, we analyze all available state-of-the art climate models from the Coupled Model Intercomparison Project 5 (CMIP5) (
 <xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">19</italic>
 </xref>), which were used to inform the last report of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change. Our time series consist of the historical simulation starting in 1850, followed by the future scenario with the largest greenhouse gas emissions, RCP8.5 (
 <xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">20</italic>
 </xref>). The 37 models in total are used to calculate changes until the year 2100, and simulations with nine of the models have been extended until the year 2300. In the following, we examine monthly temperature anomalies, where each anomaly value represents the deviation from the 30-year running mean of the same month at a particular grid cell in a model (see Materials and Methods). We then analyze the changes in SD over time that are associated with global warming.
</p>
