<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par2" class="p">Climate models project increases of drought conditions in the southwest and central Great Plains in the late twenty-first century
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">1</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" class="xref">2</xref>
 </sup>, co-located with the major dust sources in the United States (U.S.). If these models are correct, will the level of “unprecedented” aridity in the next half of this century
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" class="xref">2</xref>
 </sup> produce more dust storms in the future? Given the severe health and social impact of the dust storms (e.g., refs 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">3</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">4</xref>) several model studies have attempted to estimate future projections of dust on a global scale, with uncertain results (e.g., refs 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">5</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">6</xref>). Unfortunately, none of these studies provide specific information for the U.S. One reason is the difficulty for models to properly reproduce observed dust variability over North America
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>
 </sup>. Solutions have been proposed, for example, to modulate dust source strength to fit the data
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>
 </sup>. But such method cannot project future dust change. Here we perform a multiple linear regression analysis of key controlling factors of dust activity using satellite data. We then use projected changes of these controlling factors from the Coupled Model Intercomparison Project Phase 5 (CMIP5
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">8</xref>
 </sup>) models to project future dust activity due to climate changes in the late half of the twenty-first century under the Representative Concentration Pathways 8.5 (RCP8.5) scenario
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">9</xref>
 </sup>. The RCP 8.5 scenario represents the upper limit of the projected CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> changes in the twenty-first century and, presumably, would be the worst-case scenario of severe droughts and resultant dust activities.
</p>
