<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Adaptation pathways</div>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Adaptation can be seen as a dynamic, long-term transitional process involving repeated decisions that can be structured using the adaptation pathway approach. Maru and Smith (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">2014</a>) conclude that the development of the concept of adaptation pathways is informed by at least four strands of research, each inspired by different framing of adaptation pathways. The first involves the framing of adaptation pathways in the context of sustainability and development. A second strand responds to deep uncertainties around long-term levels of change in adaptation decision-making. The third strand concerns the depth of change required for robust and equitable adaptation, as observed from studies and theories of change. The fourth and last strand is the need for a detailed causal understanding of how climate change and extreme events lead to impacts and possible adaptation responses.
 </p>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Adaptation pathways provide “an analytical approach for exploring and sequencing a set of possible actions based on alternative external developments over time.” (Haasnoot et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">2012</a>, p. 485). Following the definition of Barnett et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">2014</a>, p. 1103), an “adaptation pathway is a decision strategy that entails a vision for the entity exposed to climate risks, to be met through a sequence of manageable steps over time, each of which is triggered by changing environmental or social conditions.” Main features of the approach are that it takes into account multiple possible futures and that it foresees adjustments of plans as conditions change. It therefore requires a focused monitoring program that is transparently linked to decision-making processes at different regional and temporal scales. The Dynamic Adaptive Pathways Planning (DAPP) approach (Haasnoot et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">2013</a>) has adaptation pathways at its core. DAPP has been used increasingly for implementing climate-resilient pathways for water management.
 </p>
 <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the case of flood risk management, the process of developing an adaptation pathway typically starts with evaluating the current level of flood risk and the standards of protection and mapping future sensitivities to climate change, like (upper bounds of) sea level rise. Known or estimated key thresholds between the present and these upper bounds are assessed in terms of vulnerability to impacts. In the case of a storm surge barrier, a key threshold might be the sea level rise at which the current system will fall below the target protection level. Subsequently, feasible adaptation response options for coping with these thresholds are identified. Interactions with other issues such as development pressures are checked. Route maps of response options that will tackle the thresholds are assembled. Costs and benefits and other criteria (like environmental impacts) of each route are compared under the most likely rate of change in extreme water level. That information is used to recommend the preferred route under the most likely rate of change. Key variables are identified that should be monitored to assess if a switch of route will be needed in the future. In the implementation phase, significant deviations from the expected rate of sea level rise will inform decision-makers about the necessity to delay or accelerate the program.</p>
 <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Even in the adaptation pathways approach, it is possible that actions that seem evident now will turn out to be maladaptative as the actual risk situation reveals itself. But by explicitly taking into consideration a bandwidth of possible futures and by identifying long-term options and guaranteeing as much as possible that they are kept open, the risk of maladaptation is reduced.</p>
 <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Wise et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85" href="#CR85">2014</a>) warn for a too narrow framing of adaptation pathways. They observe a focus on proximate causes and incremental actions and a shortage of more systemic or transformative actions. They attribute this partly to the way the issue of adaptation is framed. Decision-oriented approaches presuppose governments able and willing to effectively address clearly defined unambiguous goals. A broader conceptualization of adaptation pathways inspired by the sustainability domain opens up the search for adequate responses. Aspects that thereby come into view are, e.g., path dependency, interactions between adaptation plans, and situations where values, interests, and institutions constrain societal responses to changing conditions.
 </p>
 <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For example, countries often require a certain cost-benefit ratio to be achieved in order for the (planned) investment adaptation pathways to be considered worthwhile. In theory, all schemes with a cost benefit of greater than 1 should be funded. But in eras of constraints in available investment finance, high ratios can be part of the need to ration the amount of available funding when allocating it to schemes. For instance, the ambition of the Environment Agency of the UK Department for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs for the overall flood investment program was to realize benefit-cost ratios approaching 8:1. Also in the Netherlands, benefit-cost ratios of large-scale public investments are preferably 1 or higher. Political considerations can result in decisions to realize investment projects with lower benefit-cost ratios. The Dutch Central Planning Bureau recently finished their research on the role of cost-benefit analysis and cost-effectiveness studies in decisions on large-scale investments for improving safety against flooding in the last century. The results show that most often, the political decision to realize a certain goal, like the decision to improve safety from flooding by the sea by means of shortening the coastline in the southwest of the Netherlands in 1954, or to improve safety from flooding by the rivers by means of enlarging the room for the rivers in 2005, is taken on political grounds. After that, decisions about how to realize these goals are based on a cost effectiveness study (Bos and Zwaneveld 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">2017</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Adaptation pathways were first applied in practice in developing the Thames Estuary 2100 Plan (Environment Agency UK 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">2012a</a>; Ranger et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">2013</a>; Reeder and Ranger 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" href="#CR67">2011</a>) and in the Dutch Delta Programme on water safety and freshwater supply (Haasnoot et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">2012</a>; Morselt 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">2013</a>; Rijke 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" href="#CR68">2014</a>). It has also been considered in, amongst others, water resource planning for London (Kingsborough et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">2016</a>); coastal planning in England; strategic regional planning on the Eyre Peninsula, Australia (Siebentritt et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75" href="#CR75">2014</a>); coastal planning in Lakes Entrance, Australia (Barnett et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">2014</a>); urban adaptation in New York to hurricane and storm surge risk (Rosenzweig and Solecki 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" href="#CR70">2014</a>); and flood risk management in the Hutt River, New Zealand (Lawrence et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">2013</a>). Recently, adaptation pathways have been constructed for heat-risk management in London (Kingsborough et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">2017</a>). Although for each of these cases, it has been described how the approach could in theory lead to more informed decision-making in the face of deep uncertainty; lessons about its practical applicability have not yet found their way back to the scientific debate.
 </p>
</sec>
