<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec14" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion and conclusions</div>
 <p id="Par92" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The experience in the UK and the Netherlands with applying adaptation pathways in the TE2100 Project and the Dutch Delta Programme has been compared with the “common findings” from recent literature on other applications of adaptation pathways.</p>
 <p id="Par93" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The first common finding from the literature review, that adaptation pathways are effective in informing and mobilizing decision-makers, is in line with our own experiences, as described in Section 
  <a rid="Sec7" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec7">5</a>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par94" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The second ‘thread” through the papers, the strong call for incorporating local information in the design of the adaptation pathways and the third point, which stresses the need of coordination at a higher level to ensure consistency, are both recognized from our own experiences. Both in the UK and the Netherlands, these two points have effectively been addressed in the way the programs were structured and processes were organized. In the process of developing the TE 2100 Plan, local parties were actively involved in inventorying and discussing possible measures, while consistency in building up the plan was secured by the coordination from the level of the City of London. In the Netherlands, the structure of the Delta Programme includes both regional sub-programs, in which municipalities, provinces, water boards, NGOs, and the private sector cooperate with the national government in developing regional strategies and the Delta Commissioner for the central coordination of the program.</p>
 <p id="Par95" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A fourth element that is distilled from the review is the call for periodic updates of the adaptation pathways. This point was also recognized and effectively addressed in both cases. In the UK, this was done by setting up a monitoring program that will inform a scheduled review and re-appraisal of the TE 2100 Plan every 10 years with a mid-term monitoring review to be undertaken every 5 years. The Dutch Delta Programme has chosen a similar approach: a systematic review of all regional strategies are foreseen every 6 years, and every 12 years, practical experience and research results will be analyzed to determine if the new flood safety standards should be revised.</p>
 <p id="Par96" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A fifth common point that arises from the papers is the need to secure the possibility to switch, at some time in the future, from incremental to transformational strategies. The adaptation pathway approach could be improved by making more explicit how such a switch could be facilitated. This point also emerged from the analysis of the two case studies.</p>
 <p id="Par97" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The “threads” 1 and 5 overlap with the experience from the two water management programs. The other three common points that emerged from the literature review (threads 2, 3, and 4) focus on the way the construction of adaptation pathways should be organized. They are in line with the way the two water management programs have operationalized that process.</p>
 <p id="Par98" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Table 
  <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a> summarizes the lessons learned from the analysis.
  <div id="Tab1" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Lessons learned on the application of the adaptation pathways approach</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="11027_2017_9773_Tab1_HTML" id="MO4" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par99" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Lin et al. (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">2017</a>) state that “very little work has been done to evaluate the current use of adaptation pathways and its utility to practitioners and decision makers” (p. 387). By combining the observations from the practical experiences with the results of the literature review, we hope to have made a contribution to filling the observed.
 </p>
 <p id="Par100" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A first conclusion is that the adaptation pathways approach can effectively contribute to pace and quality of decision-making processes that are confronted with large uncertainties about future developments. These positive experiences have led to a broader application of this approach.</p>
 <p id="Par101" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Mayor of London’s infrastructure plan called for the use of adaptation pathways in the development of water resource plans for London (Mayor of London 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">2015</a>). Thames Water and other water companies in the South East have been investigating their use and demonstration pathways have been developed (Kingsborough et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">2016</a>). A pathways approach in response to surface water flooding and heat waves is the subject of ongoing research.
 </p>
 <p id="Par102" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the Netherlands, applications of an adaptive approach are presently being considered in a broad array of policy fields, such as the development of a national strategy for climate mitigation, of a more flexible approach for the national programming of large investments in infrastructural projects, of a national vision on sustainable fuel, of national guidelines for the design and maintenance of tunnels, and of regional strategies for the sustainable use of groundwater reserves.</p>
 <p id="Par103" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A second conclusion is that there are still major challenges for the scientific community in the further development of the approach. These notably include the design of a monitoring and evaluation system that is capable of early detection of tipping points in situations with large natural variability. Another specific challenge concerns the preparation of the switch from incremental to transformational strategies. Research is needed on the possibilities of visualizing if, and precluding that, incremental strategies augment path dependency, thereby complicating this switch, that seems unavoidable in the long term.</p>
 <p id="Par104" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To effectively deal with the challenges, they need to be taken up in national research programs such as those of the UK Natural Environment Research Council (NERC) and the Dutch National Knowledge and Innovation Programme on Water and Climate (NKWK) and in international research programs such as the EU Joint Programming Initiative on “Water challenges for a changing world.” It equally implies that research results and practical experiences in real life applications need to be discussed in international workshops and seminars. Examples range from large-scale international conferences such as the bi-annual conferences organized by the European Climate Change Adaptation (ECCA) Committee and by the Global Programme of Research on Climate Change Vulnerability, Impacts and Adaptation (PROVIA) to more specialized workshops such as organized by the Society for Decision Making under Deep Uncertainty (DMDU).</p>
</sec>
