<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Based on our projections, it seems likely that the appearance of European forests will change remarkably until the end of the 21st century. Most prominent changes are related to the northward migration of the four most abundant species, i.e., Scots pine, Norway spruce, European beech, and English oak and at the same a remarkable decrease in abundance in Central Europe, particularly regarding Norway spruce and Scots pine (Figure 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2" class="xref">2</xref>). Other currently abundant species such as 
 <italic class="italic">Betula pubescens</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Betula pendula</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Q. petraea</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Sorbus aucuparia</italic> featured similar projections (Figure 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3" class="xref">3</xref> and Supplementary Figures 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1" class="xref">S9–S11</xref>). Considering whole Europe, the relative importance of Scots pine and Norway spruce—the currently economically most important tree species—decreased, while for European beech and English oak, the relative importance remained unchanged (Figure 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3" class="xref">3</xref>). Tree species that were projected to partly fill the resulting gaps were 
 <italic class="italic">Q. ilex</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">P. pinaster</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">P. halepensis</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">P. nigra</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">C. sativa</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Q. pubescens</italic> (Figure 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3" class="xref">3</xref> and Supplementary Figures 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1" class="xref">S9–S14</xref>). For large parts of Central and Northern Europe, the currently dominant tree species experienced remarkable reductions in abundance, particularly for RCP 8.5 while for most Mediterranean areas an increase in abundance of the currently dominant species was projected (Figure 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4" class="xref">4</xref>). The projected migrations and changes in abundance resulted in an increasing tree-species diversity in most regions north of the Alps and a decreasing tree-species diversity in the Mediterranean (Figure 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5" class="xref">5</xref>).
</p>
