<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>This study had several limitations. First, it was not possible to consider information about individual factors, such as demographic factors and socioeconomic status, in our analysis because of difficulties in collecting data. Thus, social and economic vulnerabilities were not accounted for in our projections of temperature-related morbidity associations for climate change scenarios. Assessing the association between temperature and diarrhea and stratifying by these factors would provide a better understanding of the future impact of temperature–diarrhea relationships. Additionally, future climate change–related diarrheal disease burden may depend on future emission scenarios as well as alterations in socioeconomic and demographic trends and public health interventions (
 <xref rid="c13" ref-type="bibr">Gething et al. 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="c18" ref-type="bibr">Hodges et al. 2014</xref>). Temperature-related social or behavioral trends, such as treatment-seeking behaviors, the prevalence of coinfections, and infant care practices, may also alter the effect of climate change on the epidemiology of acute infectious gastroenteritis (
 <xref rid="c35" ref-type="bibr">Pitzer et al. 2011</xref>). Therefore, our results should not be interpreted as predictions of future excess morbidity but rather of possible outcomes for each of the specified but theoretical scenarios. Second, our projections are subject to uncertainty due to variation in the climate models and lack of precision in the estimated exposure–response association (
 <xref rid="c2" ref-type="bibr">Benmarhnia et al. 2014</xref>). Moreover, our findings are restricted to the range of observable temperature data for present climate conditions, and a key assumption for the projections of the infectious gastroenteritis burden into the future is that the shape of associations stay the same over time. Although this assumption is likely adequate for short-term estimations of the effect of climate on health, evidence suggests that temperatures will surpass currently observed ranges, the consequences of which on health will be difficult to estimate (
 <xref rid="c27" ref-type="bibr">Mora et al. 2013</xref>). Third, there may be biases in our results because we could not adjust for immunity to and probability of person-to-person transmission and variations of infectious gastroenteritis in the susceptible population. Variations due to immunity to and the transmissibility of infectious diseases in the at-risk population may bias estimates of associations with temperature (
 <xref rid="c19" ref-type="bibr">Imai et al. 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="c20" ref-type="bibr">Imai and Hashizume 2015</xref>). Additionally, poor immunity and the chance of transmissibility could increase in the next decade mainly due to aging of the population, and this effect may offset the effect of the increase in temperature in Japan. These potential biases may affect the interpretation of our results. Additional studies using more precise modeling methods are required to resolve these issues. Future studies should consider these important points.
</p>
