<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Quantifications of drought persistence errors in a model ensemble are themselves subject to several sources of uncertainty, which include (i) uncertainty of the considered observations, (ii) uncertainty of the individual models, (iii) internal variability, and (iv) errors related to the statistical estimation of drought persistence (i.e., finite sample effects). Assessing the relative contribution of each of these sources to the total uncertainty will aid interpretation in a model validation exercise. Uncertainty in the observation‐based data sets generally refers to the combination of observational errors and the uncertainty related to data processing methods which depend on the interpolation scheme, station density, and quality control tools (Xie et al., 
 <xref rid="jgrd54513-bib-0057" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1996</xref>) as well as the subset of selected stations. Previous studies that have assessed global climate models (GCMs) globally usually relied on a single observational data set as a reference and sometimes accounted for observational uncertainty in the analysis by excluding the regions where observations were deemed unreliable. An alternative approach to account for observational uncertainty is to use independent observation‐based data sets for the analysis and to investigate the associated spread. Model uncertainty can be characterized as the spread across different models, mainly generated from the discrepancy in their structure. Internal climate variability (or natural climate variability) corresponds to fluctuations generated in the climate system without changes in external forcing and can thus be approximated from the spread across initial condition ensembles of individual GCMs. Lastly, the fact that model evaluation is based on finite data sources leads to uncertainty in the statistical characterization of model performance. This statistical estimation error is often omitted in model validation studies, although it could affect the robustness of the analysis and hence also the conclusions.
</p>
