<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We used a species distribution map from the International Union for Conservation of Nature (IUCN; McLellan et al 
 <xref rid="ece34645-bib-0045" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>; IUCN &amp; Wildlife Conservation Society, 
 <xref rid="ece34645-bib-0030" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>), to extract brown bear distribution areas (resident) for Asia with the help of ArcGIS. We plotted GPS points of current presence data we obtained and compared with the current IUCN distribution map for ground truthing for validation and correction. We downloaded protected areas of Asia (IUCN &amp; UNEP‐WCMC, 
 <xref rid="ece34645-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>), and based on the literature survey of brown bear presence, we selected areas and overlaid them into the species distribution map. Only the brown bear occurrence points within protected areas were selected for further analysis to model the potentially suitable habitats for brown bear. We removed the unconfirmed brown bear distribution areas (potential distribution) which lay outside of protected areas throughout the range on which we did not have evidence of presence. In this way, we validated brown bear presence points collected from field surveys and from literature and used them for final analysis. We also created 500 presence points within each protected area (one point per 5 km × 5 km cell) that overlaid with the IUCN's brown bear distribution map using Hawth's tools extension in ArcGIS. We verified the randomly generated presence points by brown bear experts from China, Mongolia, Nepal, and India. We did field verification of those randomly generated points in China, and Nepal by consulting with local park authorities to determine the current brown bear presence and removed those points from the analysis where absence was indicated. We also removed duplicate presence points and retained only one presence points per 1‐km
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> grids cells. After validation, verification of presence points and removal of duplicates, we used remaining 209 occurrence points of brown bear presence for further analysis.
</p>
