<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec010" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data analysis</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The influence of location, habitat, prey density and depth on the relative abundance and biomass of reef sharks (as derived from MaxN) was investigated using generalised additive mixed models (GAMMs; [
  <a rid="pone.0200960.ref048" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0200960.ref048">48</a>]). To accommodate for over-dispersion and correlation in the data, we extended the application of this class of models by including sites as a random effect [
  <a rid="pone.0200960.ref049" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0200960.ref049">49</a>]. Model selection was based on Akaike Information Criterion (AIC; [
  <a rid="pone.0200960.ref050" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0200960.ref050">50</a>]) and AIC weights (wAIC; [
  <a rid="pone.0200960.ref051" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0200960.ref051">51</a>]). A full subsets method was used to fit models of all possible combinations up to a maximum of three variables to prevent overfitting. Models containing variables with correlations &gt;0.28 were excluded from the analysis to eliminate strong collinearity in line with recommendations from Graham [
  <a rid="pone.0200960.ref052" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0200960.ref052">52</a>]; this can cause problems with over-fitting and make interpretation of statistical results difficult. Models with AIC values that differ by less than two units show weak evidence for favouring one over the other [
  <a rid="pone.0200960.ref053" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0200960.ref053">53</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0200960.ref054" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0200960.ref054">54</a>]. The best model was therefore the one with the fewest variables (most parsimonious) and within two AIC units of the lowest AIC value [
  <a rid="pone.0200960.ref054" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0200960.ref054">54</a>]. The wAIC, which represents probabilities or weights of evidence for each model, was used to facilitate interpretation of the best models. Relative support for each predictor variable was obtained by calculating the summed wAIC across all subsets of models containing that variable to obtain its relative importance [
  <a rid="pone.0200960.ref054" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0200960.ref054">54</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Prior to analyses, two habitat categories (macroalgae and soft corals) were removed due to their limited coverage, and sand/rubble was excluded due to strong collinearity with the category reef. Models were fitted to untransformed abundance data using a Tweedie error distribution [
  <a rid="pone.0200960.ref055" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0200960.ref055">55</a>]. A Tweedie model is an extension of compound Poisson model derived from the stochastic process where a gamma distribution is used for the counted or measured objects (i.e., number or mass of fish) and has an advantage over delta-type two-step models by handling the zero data in a unified way. All analyses were performed using the R language for statistical computing [
  <a rid="pone.0200960.ref056" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0200960.ref056">56</a>] with the package GAMM4 version 0.2e3 [
  <a rid="pone.0200960.ref057" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0200960.ref057">57</a>]. Because P values derived from GAMMs are usually approximates and typically too low [
  <a rid="pone.0200960.ref058" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0200960.ref058">58</a>], we used a weight of evidence approach to test for significance in the factors identified by the most parsimonious models. Univariate permutational analysis of variance and co-variance (PERMANOVA and PERMANCOVA; with 9999 permutations and dissimilarity matrices constructed with Euclidean distance) was used for significance testing and to explore pairwise comparisons between locations in the PERMANOVA+ add-on to PRIMER [
  <a rid="pone.0200960.ref059" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0200960.ref059">59</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
