<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Marine coastal environments are especially vulnerable to change due to the dual influence of the surrounding terrestrial ecosystems and the connecting water-bodies. Coastal systems are thus highly dynamic and can be strongly influenced by climate change (
 <xref rid="B76" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Stocker et al., 2013</xref>), anthropogenic activities (e.g., pollution), and a combination of the two pressures (
 <xref rid="B63" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Robinson et al., 2004</xref>). Pollutants can have various effects on marine ecosystems, such as direct toxicity, persistent negative effects, or bioaccumulation (
 <xref rid="B36" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kallenborn et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Andersson et al., 2015</xref>). Furthermore, the physicochemical environment can alter the behavior of these substances (
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ripszam et al., 2015a</xref>,
 <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">b</xref>). Moreover, the northern hemisphere is predicted to undergo an increased precipitation regime, leading in turn to higher terrestrial runoff and increased river inflow (up to 15–22%) to the Baltic Sea by the end of the century (
 <xref rid="B51" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Meier et al., 2011</xref>). This increased runoff will transfer terrestrial dissolved organic matter (tDOM) to coastal waters, increasing the concentration of substances such as: dissolved organic carbon (DOC), humic substances, and nutrients (e.g., nitrogen and phosphorus); thereby altering the physicochemical environment (
 <xref rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Figueroa et al., 2016</xref>). Such changes can directly influence the resident biology, particularly at the base of the food web and can influence the partitioning of contaminants (
 <xref rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Cole et al., 1988</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ripszam et al., 2015a</xref>).
</p>
