<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The Sichuan snub‐nosed monkey (
 <italic class="italic">Rhinopithecus roxellana</italic>) is a primate species endemic to China (Li, 
 <xref rid="ece34815-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2004</xref>) and is listed as Endangered by the International Union for Conservation of Nature (Long &amp; Richardson, 
 <xref rid="ece34815-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>). 
 <italic class="italic">R. roxellana</italic> currently occurs in three isolated temperate montane forest regions in China with a total of approximately 22,000 individuals, comprised of approximately 16,000 individuals in the Sichuan‐Gansu population, approximately 5,500 individuals in the Shanxi population, and approximately 1,000 individuals in the Hubei population (Chang, Luo, et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34815-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). 
 <italic class="italic">R. roxellana</italic> has suffered a population decline of more than 50% over the past half‐century (Li, Pan, &amp; Oxnard, 
 <xref rid="ece34815-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2002</xref>). Currently, the major threats to its population are tourism‐related activities and continued habitat loss (Long &amp; Richardson, 
 <xref rid="ece34815-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>). Hubei Province is at the easternmost edge of the species distribution and harbors over 1,000 individuals (Liu et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34815-bib-0030" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). This population is considered as a stand‐alone management unit (Chang, Luo, et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34815-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>), determined to be a group of conspecific individuals among which the degree of connectivity is sufficiently low and thus should be monitored and managed separately (Palsbøll, Bérubé, &amp; Allendorf, 
 <xref rid="ece34815-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>; Taylor &amp; Dizon, 
 <xref rid="ece34815-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1999</xref>). The relatively lower genetic diversity, genetically distinct status and small population size of this population makes it more vulnerable to environmental change than the other two populations (Li et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34815-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>; Luo, Pan, Liu, &amp; Li, 
 <xref rid="ece34815-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>; Pan et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34815-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>). This arboreal species lives in temperate broadleaf and coniferous forests (Chang, Liu, Yang, Li, &amp; Vigilant, 
 <xref rid="ece34815-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>), and the impact of climate change on vegetation is expected to decrease the availability of its suitable habitat (Luo et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34815-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Xiang et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34815-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>). These predicted range reductions will force the Hubei population monkeys to migrate to higher elevations over time (Lou et al., 2015). In addition, there is little research identifying the refugia of 
 <italic class="italic">R. roxellana</italic> and how it may disperse from its currently suitable habitats to future habitats. Identifying the extent to which the 
 <italic class="italic">R. roxellana</italic> could be affected by climate change and the dispersal paths between its current and future habitats are therefore important for effective conservation management.
</p>
