<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Materials and Methods</div>
 <sec id="s2a" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ethics</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Most animals in this study were handled only once (during their first moult) for marking with a subcutaneous transponder tag and measurement of morphological features. A smaller number of individuals had also been previously handled as chicks (in their first month) for marking with a small external plastic pin (Fishtag, Floytag) and blood-sampling. All procedures employed during the field work were approved by the Ethical Committee of the French Polar Institute (Institut Paul Emile Victor – IPEV) and conducted in accordance with its guidelines, also complying with French laws including those relating to conservation and animal welfare. Authorizations to enter the breeding site (permits n° 2005–191 issued on the 21
   <span class="sup">st</span> of November 2005, 2006–67 issued on the 6
   <span class="sup">th</span> of November 2006, 2007–149 on the 24
   <span class="sup">th</span> of October 2007, 2008–98 issued on the 5
   <span class="sup">th</span> of September 2008, 2009–57 issued on the 26
   <span class="sup">th</span> of August 2009, 2010–79 issued on the 3
   <span class="sup">rd</span> of September 2010) and handle birds (permits n° 99/346/AUT issued on the 30th of November 1999, 00/240/AUT issued on the 5
   <span class="sup">th</span> of September 2000, 01/315/AUT issued on the 4
   <span class="sup">th</span> of July 2001, 01/322/AUT issued on the 16
   <span class="sup">th</span> of August 2001, 2003–113 and 2003–114 issued on the 7
   <span class="sup">th</span> of October 2003, 2004–182 and 2004–183 issued on the 14
   <span class="sup">th</span> of December 2004, 2005–203 issued on the 1
   <span class="sup">st</span> of December 2005, 2006–73 issued on the 6
   <span class="sup">th</span> of November 2006, 2007–144 issued on the 24
   <span class="sup">th</span> of October 2007, 2008–71 issued on the 5
   <span class="sup">th</span> of September 2008, 2009–59 issued on the 29
   <span class="sup">th</span> of August 2009, 2010–67 issued on the 3
   <span class="sup">rd</span> of September 2010) were delivered first by the French ‘Ministère de l’Aménagement du Territoire et de l’Environnement’ and then by the ‘Terres Australes et Antarctiques Françaises’ (TAAF). Handled animals were removed from the colony in order to minimize the disturbance to neighbouring birds and carried a few meters away for manipulation. They were hooded to reduce their stress and manipulations lasted between 5 and 10 minutes. The transponder tags weigh 0.8 g and have no known adverse effects. They were shown to have no effect on survival of king penguins 
   <a rid="pone.0114052-Froget1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Froget1">[36]</a> or breeding success, recruitment or survival of great tits (
   <span class="italic">Parus major</span>) 
   <a rid="pone.0114052-Nicolaus1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Nicolaus1">[37]</a>. Furthermore, concerns about infections should be minimal, as transponder tags are kept sealed sterile in iodine capsules (Betadine) and removed from the capsules only by the process of injecting them into the bird. Vétédine soap and alcoholic antiseptic solutions were used to disinfect the skin and the injecting needle before each insertion. Flesh wounds did not appear infected thereafter (personal observations on a sample of recaptured birds). Blood was sampled in small quantities, taking into account the age of the chick (1 mL for fledglings and 100 µL for younger chicks).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2b" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Long-term monitoring and sex-ratio determination</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our study was conducted in the king penguin colony of ‘La Baie du Marin’, on Possession Island, Crozet Archipelago (46°25′S, 51°45′E). From 2000 to 2009, we marked 3787 king penguin chicks that we later monitored using an automatic system (ANTAVIA), based on radio-frequency identification (RFID) of individuals born in a subpart of the colony 
   <a rid="pone.0114052-Gendner1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Gendner1">[38]</a>. Around the peak of fledging, chicks in advanced moult were captured on the edge of the colony and implanted with passive transponder tags under the skin of their leg, without any other external mark. Upon capture, the chick’s head was covered with a hood to keep it calm. A 1-mL blood sample was collected from its marginal flipper and used for sex determination based on genomic DNA (see below). Because those chicks were initially captured right before fledging, we did not know whether they were issued from an early (laying prior to Jan. 1
   <span class="sup">st</span>) or late reproduction 
   <a rid="pone.0114052-Stonehouse1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Stonehouse1">[23]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0114052-Weimerskirch1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Weimerskirch1">[26]</a>. Thus, we captured and marked 200 early and 200 late chicks per year from 2007 to 2009 (∼3–4 week old). Those chicks were temporarily tagged with a small external plastic pin (Fishtag, Floytag). Of those, 225 chicks (198 early chicks and 27 late chicks) survived to fledging and were re-captured, transponder-tagged and blood-sampled at that time. Finally, as part of a separate study, 20 early and 20 late chicks were captured in 2009, and 173 early and 197 late chicks were captured in 2010, right after hatching (∼1 week old). Those were marked with a fishtag, blood sampled (∼100 µL), and used to investigate the changes in sex ratio between hatching and fledging.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chick sex was determined from DNA extracted from blood samples following the protocol described by Sambrook et al. 
   <a rid="pone.0114052-Sambrook1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Sambrook1">[39]</a>. Sex determination relied on polymerase chain reaction (PCR) amplification of two parts of the sex chromosome CHD1 gene, which in birds differs in size between the Z and W chromosomes 
   <a rid="pone.0114052-Griffiths1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Griffiths1">[40]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0114052-Ellegren1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Ellegren1">[41]</a>. Females were characterized by displaying both a W-specific fragment and a Z-specific fragment, while males showed only the shorter Z-fragment. All individuals were tested with primers F1/R1 
   <a rid="pone.0114052-Kahn1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Kahn1">[42]</a>, and in each year, ca. 10% of them were controlled at random using another pair of primers P2/P8 
   <a rid="pone.0114052-Griffiths2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Griffiths2">[43]</a> to confirm sex determinations. Sex ratio was calculated as the proportion of males in the population (given as a %).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2c" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Chick morphological measurements and body condition</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Standardised measurements of flipper length, beak length (±1 mm) and body mass were collected on all but 3 chicks upon capture right before fledging (N = 4101). Flipper and beak lengths are highly repeatable measurements 
   <a rid="pone.0114052-Fahlman1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Fahlman1">[44]</a> and provide good descriptors of structural size. However, because those measurements are correlated (Spearman’s rank correlation; 
   <span class="italic">p</span>&lt;0.001, 
   <span class="italic">rho</span> = 0.32, 
   <span class="italic">N</span> = 4101), we established a Structural Size Index (SSI) using principal component analysis as previously described in 
   <a rid="pone.0114052-Saraux1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Saraux1">[35]</a>. The first principal component of the analyses explained 79% of the variation in bill and flipper length and was retained as the SSI 
   <div class="inline-formula">
    <span xlink:href="pone.0114052.e001.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
   <sub>.</sub>
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Because body mass is highly variable in king penguins and perhaps associated with differences in nutritional status as well as structural size, OLS-regression residuals of body mass on structural size are likely to provide a better reflection of the actual energy stores of the animal 
   <a rid="pone.0114052-SchulteHostedde1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-SchulteHostedde1">[45]</a>. Thus, we calculated body condition as the residuals of an OLS-regression of chicks’ body mass on SSI 
   <a rid="pone.0114052-Saraux1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Saraux1">[35]</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0114052-Dobson1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Dobson1">[46]</a>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To determine if the sexual size dimorphism occurred at hatching or fledging, we also calculated body condition from an OLS regression of body mass on structural size at hatching over 173 early and 197 late-hatched king penguin chicks in 2010 
   <div class="inline-formula">
    <span xlink:href="pone.0114052.e002.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
   <sub>.</sub>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2d" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Life-history determination of transponder-tagged birds</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Once implanted with a transponder tag, chicks are automatically identified throughout their lifetime in the ANTAVIA sub-colony by RFID antennas. Those antennas are buried underground at unique transit pathways in and out of the sub-colony and allow continuous monitoring of bird movements and presence within the colony 
   <a rid="pone.0114052-Gendner1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Gendner1">[38]</a>. Such data have yielded detailed information on individuals’ lives after fledging, including data on first return rates to their natal colony 
   <a rid="pone.0114052-Saraux1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Saraux1">[35]</a>, reproduction 
   <a rid="pone.0114052-Descamps1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Descamps1">[47]</a>–
   <a rid="pone.0114052-Saraux2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Saraux2">[49]</a>, age-specific survival and breeding performances (Le Bohec et al., 
   <span class="italic">unpublished data</span>). Thus, monitoring individuals tagged from fledging allows assessment of changes in sex ratio throughout different life-history stages. This information was used to investigate changes in sex ratio between fledging, first return to the colony, and first reproductive attempt. For this analysis, only the first 4 cohorts of tagged chicks were used, as most of the birds from latter cohorts had not yet started to breed.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2e" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Environmental descriptors</div>
  <sec id="s2e1" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate and oceanographic conditions</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To investigate how sex ratio may be influenced by climatic conditions, we used indicators of processes acting both at local and global scales 
    <a rid="pone.0114052-Stenseth1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Stenseth1">[50]</a>–
    <a rid="pone.0114052-Stenseth2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Stenseth2">[51]</a>. A large-scale climatic index, the Southern Oscillation Index (SOI; calculated on a monthly basis as the fluctuation in the air pressure difference between Tahiti and Darwin) was obtained from the Australian Bureau of Meteorology. Prolonged periods of negative SOI values are usually associated with warm ocean temperatures in our study area, typical of El Niño events 
    <a rid="pone.0114052-Deser1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Deser1">[52]</a>. We used Sea Surface Temperature (SST, in °C), as a local proxy of prey abundance and distribution, a good indicator for marine predators such as king penguins 
    <a rid="pone.0114052-Saraux1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Saraux1">[35]</a>, 
    <a rid="pone.0114052-LeBohec3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-LeBohec3">[53]</a>–
    <a rid="pone.0114052-Pron1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Pron1">[55]</a>. Indeed, by affecting primary production, SST has strong consequences on prey abundance 
    <a rid="pone.0114052-Gregg1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Gregg1">[56]</a>. Monthly SST values were obtained from the National Ocean and Atmospheric Administration of the USA and averaged for the feeding areas (46–60°S, 46–56°E) of king penguins during the summer (Polar Front, PF) and the winter (Marginal Ice Zone, MIZ) 
    <a rid="pone.0114052-Charrassin1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Charrassin1">[57]</a>. We previously found that breeding success in our study colony was mostly affected by the SOI and SST conditions of the same year 
    <a rid="pone.0114052-LeBohec3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-LeBohec3">[53]</a>. However, we tested for SOI and SST effects over four different periods: 6- and 12-mo time-lag prior to laying (prior to the mean annual laying date of early breeders, May–Oct. or Nov.–Oct.), 6-mo time-lag after laying (after the mean annual laying date of early breeders, Nov.–Apr.), and over the entire breeding cycle (from laying to fledging, Nov.–Oct.). The different time-periods yielded similar results, so that results are given only over one period: the summer season, i.e. the 6-mo period following the onset of reproduction (the mean annual laying date of early breeders). Finally, we recorded the mean annual laying date of early breeders from 2004 to 2009 as a proxy of environmental conditions before breeding onset, and calculated the mean annual breeding success of the colony from 2000 to 2009 (Le Bohec et al., 
    <span class="italic">unpublished data</span>) as a proxy of the annual environmental conditions endured during reproduction. Early years and/or years of high breeding success could be viewed as more favourable years of high resource availability.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="s2e2" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Colonial breeding conditions</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Because colony density of king penguins varies to a large extent over the course of a breeding season and may affect the physiological status of breeding parents 
    <a rid="pone.0114052-Viblanc1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Viblanc1">[32]</a>, we considered whether colony density might affect chick sex ratio. Each year, starting in 2004, we calculated yearly colony density indices in the ANTAVIA sub-colony by counting breeding individuals on pictures taken in December (peak density of the breeding season). We further calculated a second annual density index as the proportion of transponder-tagged birds monitored as breeding in a given year among tagged birds alive and of breeding age.
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2f" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistics</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All statistics were run using R v. 2.13.0 
   <a rid="pone.0114052-R1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-R1">[58]</a>. Because chicks were randomly sampled in the absence of their parents, we could not know whether sampled chicks may come from the same breeding pairs from year to year. This prevented us from looking for pseudo-replication in our data and using Generalized Linear Mixed Models (GLMMs) that would take adult identity into account. Yet, it should be noted that no more than 500–600 chicks were marked per year in a part of the colony retaining 
   <span class="italic">ca.</span> 8,000 breeding pairs, so that the probability of pseudo-replication should be low. Therefore, Generalized Linear Models (GLMs; maximum likelihood approach) fitted to a binomial distribution were used to evaluate sex ratio with environmental factors or laying period. As all independent variables (
   <span class="italic">e.g.</span> laying period) were not available for all individuals, we could not run a single general model and use an information theoretical approach to select variables. Instead, we had to compute separate models for different independent variables. Still, in the case of climatic variables, we ran a single global model with SST and SOI as independent variables. The most appropriate models were selected using Akaike’s Information Criterion (AIC). Adjusted R
   <span class="sup">2</span> values are indicated along with p-values. Data were checked for normality and for between-group homoscedasticity and between-year comparisons were performed using Wilcoxon rank-sum tests. Sex-ratio comparisons across life-history stages were performed using a binomial proportion test ('prop.test' package in R). Variables were considered significant for 
   <span class="italic">P</span>&lt;0.05. Bonferroni corrections were considered for multiple testing in three occasions, i.e. comparisons of sex ratio between life-history stages 
   <div class="inline-formula">
    <span xlink:href="pone.0114052.e003.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div> comparisons of body condition between males and females for each year 
   <div class="inline-formula">
    <span xlink:href="pone.0114052.e004.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>, and finally pairwise comparisons of sex ratio between years 
   <div class="inline-formula">
    <span xlink:href="pone.0114052.e005.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>. In the first 2 cases, results were similar regardless of whether the Bonferroni adjustment was applied or not, indicating their robustness. In the last case (pairwise comparison of annual sex ratios), differences appeared. As Bonferroni adjustments are often criticized for being too conservative preventing from detecting significant differences, we decided to present the results without this adjustment on 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0114052-g001" href="#pone-0114052-g001">Figure 1</a>. The number of birds is given as 
   <span class="italic">N</span>.
  </p>
  <div id="pone-0114052-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0114052.g001</span>
   <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <div class="title">Sex ratio of fledging king penguins over a 10-year period.</div>
    <p>Sex ratio is presented as male proportion (%). Dotted lines represent the 95% confidence interval. The grey area of the figure (fledging males &lt;50%) corresponds to female-biased sex ratios, while the white area corresponds to male-biased sex ratios. Points not sharing a common superscript are different for 
     <span class="italic">P</span>&lt;0.05. Sample sizes are given in brackets. The insert shows the average sex ratio over the 10-year study (*significant difference for 
     <span class="italic">P</span>&lt;0.05).
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="pone.0114052.g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </sec>
</sec>
