<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2a" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ethics</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Most animals in this study were handled only once (during their first moult) for marking with a subcutaneous transponder tag and measurement of morphological features. A smaller number of individuals had also been previously handled as chicks (in their first month) for marking with a small external plastic pin (Fishtag, Floytag) and blood-sampling. All procedures employed during the field work were approved by the Ethical Committee of the French Polar Institute (Institut Paul Emile Victor – IPEV) and conducted in accordance with its guidelines, also complying with French laws including those relating to conservation and animal welfare. Authorizations to enter the breeding site (permits n° 2005–191 issued on the 21
  <span class="sup">st</span> of November 2005, 2006–67 issued on the 6
  <span class="sup">th</span> of November 2006, 2007–149 on the 24
  <span class="sup">th</span> of October 2007, 2008–98 issued on the 5
  <span class="sup">th</span> of September 2008, 2009–57 issued on the 26
  <span class="sup">th</span> of August 2009, 2010–79 issued on the 3
  <span class="sup">rd</span> of September 2010) and handle birds (permits n° 99/346/AUT issued on the 30th of November 1999, 00/240/AUT issued on the 5
  <span class="sup">th</span> of September 2000, 01/315/AUT issued on the 4
  <span class="sup">th</span> of July 2001, 01/322/AUT issued on the 16
  <span class="sup">th</span> of August 2001, 2003–113 and 2003–114 issued on the 7
  <span class="sup">th</span> of October 2003, 2004–182 and 2004–183 issued on the 14
  <span class="sup">th</span> of December 2004, 2005–203 issued on the 1
  <span class="sup">st</span> of December 2005, 2006–73 issued on the 6
  <span class="sup">th</span> of November 2006, 2007–144 issued on the 24
  <span class="sup">th</span> of October 2007, 2008–71 issued on the 5
  <span class="sup">th</span> of September 2008, 2009–59 issued on the 29
  <span class="sup">th</span> of August 2009, 2010–67 issued on the 3
  <span class="sup">rd</span> of September 2010) were delivered first by the French ‘Ministère de l’Aménagement du Territoire et de l’Environnement’ and then by the ‘Terres Australes et Antarctiques Françaises’ (TAAF). Handled animals were removed from the colony in order to minimize the disturbance to neighbouring birds and carried a few meters away for manipulation. They were hooded to reduce their stress and manipulations lasted between 5 and 10 minutes. The transponder tags weigh 0.8 g and have no known adverse effects. They were shown to have no effect on survival of king penguins 
  <a rid="pone.0114052-Froget1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Froget1">[36]</a> or breeding success, recruitment or survival of great tits (
  <span class="italic">Parus major</span>) 
  <a rid="pone.0114052-Nicolaus1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Nicolaus1">[37]</a>. Furthermore, concerns about infections should be minimal, as transponder tags are kept sealed sterile in iodine capsules (Betadine) and removed from the capsules only by the process of injecting them into the bird. Vétédine soap and alcoholic antiseptic solutions were used to disinfect the skin and the injecting needle before each insertion. Flesh wounds did not appear infected thereafter (personal observations on a sample of recaptured birds). Blood was sampled in small quantities, taking into account the age of the chick (1 mL for fledglings and 100 µL for younger chicks).
 </p>
</sec>
