<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In animal populations, determinants of adult sex ratio (ASR, i.e. the proportion of male to female adult individuals 
  <a rid="pone.0114052-Mayr1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Mayr1">[1]</a>) are likely to occur before adulthood, due to variations in parental sexual allocation of resources (before and after birth, reviewed in 
  <a rid="pone.0114052-Frank1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Frank1">[2]</a>), and to fluctuations in sex-specific mortality of these offspring before recruitment into the breeding population. According to Fisher 
  <a rid="pone.0114052-Fisher1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Fisher1">[3]</a>, parental investment into male and female offspring should be equal at the termination of parental care, as the production of any zygote requires one mother and father. Thus, the reproductive value of males and females should be equal 
  <a rid="pone.0114052-Fisher1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Fisher1">[3]</a> and any tendency to deviate from a 1∶1 sex allocation should return to equilibrium by frequency-dependent selection 
  <a rid="pone.0114052-Allen1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Allen1">[4]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0114052-Bull1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Bull1">[5]</a>. Nonetheless, Hamilton pointed out that biased sex ratios were likely to occur in natural conditions 
  <a rid="pone.0114052-Hamilton1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Hamilton1">[6]</a>, if the costs of producing male and female offspring were different. In such cases, a bias towards the less costly sex should be expected 
  <a rid="pone.0114052-Fisher1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Fisher1">[3]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0114052-Hamilton1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Hamilton1">[6]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0114052-Charnov1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Charnov1">[8]</a>. In sexually dimorphic species for instance, the higher costs of producing the larger (
  <span class="italic">e.g.</span> male) sex should favour a production bias towards the smaller (
  <span class="italic">e.g.</span> female) one. Additionally, Trivers &amp; Willard 
  <a rid="pone.0114052-Trivers1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Trivers1">[7]</a> hypothesised that mothers in good condition may afford to invest more into the sex with greatest variance in reproductive success, when mothers in poor condition gain more by investing into the sex less affected by poor maternal rearing conditions 
  <a rid="pone.0114052-Trivers1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Trivers1">[7]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0114052-Nager1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Nager1">[9]</a>. This seems to be the case in the red deer (
  <span class="italic">Cervus elaphus</span>) in which high population densities during female pregnancy lead to adverse nutritional stress causing mothers to produce fewer male than female offspring 
  <a rid="pone.0114052-Kruuk1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Kruuk1">[10]</a>. Alternately, sex-ratio bias may also stem from the fitness benefits/costs associated with inter-sexual differences in competition/cooperation, favouring selection for the sex in which competition between parents and offspring is lowest and/or cooperation highest 
  <a rid="pone.0114052-Hamilton1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Hamilton1">[6]</a>. In particular, Clark’s resource competition model (
  <a rid="pone.0114052-Clark1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Clark1">[11]</a>; generalisation of Hamilton’s model) highlights an additional cost of producing offspring for mothers, in that they must later compete for food/mate/reproductive site resources. Consequently, mothers might favour the more dispersive sex. For instance, during years of El Niño events, Northern elephant seal (
  <span class="italic">Mirounga angustirostris</span>) females experience poor foraging conditions and high nutritional stress 
  <a rid="pone.0114052-Crocker1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Crocker1">[12]</a>. Interestingly, offspring production is biased towards males in those years and this male-biased sex ratio has been suggested as an adaptive strategy to decrease later resource competition between mothers and daughters on similar food patches 
  <a rid="pone.0114052-Lee1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Lee1">[13]</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Because it has direct consequences on breeder proportions 
  <a rid="pone.0114052-Keyfitz1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Keyfitz1">[14]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0114052-Caswell1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Caswell1">[15]</a>, understanding the dynamics of ASR and the reasons for its fluctuations is an important perspective in animal ecology (e.g. 
  <a rid="pone.0114052-Trivers2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Trivers2">[16]</a>, see 
  <a rid="pone.0114052-Sheldon1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Sheldon1">[17]</a> for a review in birds). In this study, we used a decade-long dataset to investigate sex-ratio variability in a wild seabird population of king penguins (
  <span class="italic">Aptenodytes patagonicus</span>). In these seasonally monogamous seabirds, bi-parental care is necessary for successful reproduction, so that a biased ASR should produce adults of the supernumerary sex that are unable to find mates and reproduce, resulting in a reduced number of breeders at the population scale with potential consequences on population dynamics. Surprisingly however, male-biased ASRs have been suggested in king penguin populations 
  <a rid="pone.0114052-Bried1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Bried1">[18]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0114052-Olsson1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Olsson1">[21]</a> and so has male-biased mate competition 
  <a rid="pone.0114052-Keddar1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Keddar1">[22]</a>. Yet, the reason for such a bias, and life history stage at which it arises, remains unclear. Therefore, using over more than 4000 king penguins of ‘La Baie du Marin’ colony (Crozet Archipelago; Southern Ocean), we considered fledgling sex-ratio variability and its potential links with environmental parameters. The breeding biology of king penguins imposes strong constraints on parental investment. The absence of a nest 
  <a rid="pone.0114052-Stonehouse1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Stonehouse1">[23]</a> compels breeding birds to navigate through thousands of conspecifics to locate both partners and chicks 
  <a rid="pone.0114052-Nesterova1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Nesterova1">[24]</a>. In addition, chick development from hatching to fledging occurs over an exceptionally long period (over 11 months 
  <a rid="pone.0114052-Stonehouse1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Stonehouse1">[23]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0114052-Barrat1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Barrat1">[25]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0114052-Weimerskirch1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Weimerskirch1">[26]</a>), encompassing the austral winter when chick growth is limited and mortality is high 
  <a rid="pone.0114052-Weimerskirch1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Weimerskirch1">[26]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0114052-Olsson2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Olsson2">[28]</a>, chicks gather in crèches to limit predation pressure 
  <a rid="pone.0114052-LeBohec1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-LeBohec1">[29]</a> and increase thermoregulation 
  <a rid="pone.0114052-Eichhorn1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Eichhorn1">[30]</a>. This long breeding cycle (over a year from courtship to fledging) also results in non-synchronised laying, early and late offspring being reared in highly heterogeneous conditions (i.e. differences in food resources 
  <a rid="pone.0114052-GauthierClerc1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-GauthierClerc1">[31]</a> and bird colony density 
  <a rid="pone.0114052-Viblanc1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Viblanc1">[32]</a>). In particular, early and late chicks are known to differ in their phenotype at hatching 
  <a rid="pone.0114052-Stier1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Stier1">[27]</a> and to exhibit strong differential mortality during the winter 
  <a rid="pone.0114052-Weimerskirch1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Weimerskirch1">[26]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0114052-Olsson2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Olsson2">[28]</a>. Finally, as penguins are state-dependent breeders 
  <a rid="pone.0114052-GauthierClerc2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-GauthierClerc2">[33]</a>, environmental conditions before the onset of breeding might affect parental body condition 
  <a rid="pone.0114052-McNamara1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-McNamara1">[34]</a> and foraging efficiency, with potential consequences on chick growth and survival 
  <a rid="pone.0114052-GauthierClerc2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-GauthierClerc2">[33]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0114052-McNamara1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-McNamara1">[34]</a>. Given the above features, king penguins provide an interesting model to investigate how sex ratio may be modulated by environmental factors and whether biased sex ratio may arise over early life history in this species, either due to differential parental allocation or sex-specific mortality. For instance, sex ratio might change between fledging and adulthood, as male and female juveniles may differ in their return rates to their natal colony 
  <a rid="pone.0114052-Saraux1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0114052-Saraux1">[35]</a>.
 </p>
</sec>
