<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="Fig2">
 <label>Figure 2</label>
 <caption>
  <p>Gradient of selection (top panels, A and B) and stationary distribution (bottom panels, C and D) for the different values of per-capita budget 
   <italic>δ</italic> indicated, using either pure-Reward (
   <italic>w</italic> = 1, left panels) or pure-Punishment (
   <italic>w</italic> = 0, right panels). The black curve is equal on the left and right panels, since in this case 
   <italic>δ</italic> = 0. As 
   <italic>δ</italic> increases, the behaviour under Reward and Punishment is qualitatively similar, by displacing the (unstable) coordination equilibrium towards lower values of 
   <italic>k/Z</italic>, while displacing the (stable) coexistence equilibrium towards higher values of 
   <italic>k/Z</italic>. This happens, however, only for low values of 
   <italic>δ</italic>. Indeed, by further increasing 
   <italic>δ</italic> one observes very different behaviours under Reward and Punishment: Whereas under Punishment the equilibria are further moved apart (in accord with what happened for low 
   <italic>δ</italic>) under Reward the coordination equilibrium disappears, and the overall dynamics becomes characterized by a single coexistence equilibrium which consistently shifts towards higher values of 
   <italic>k</italic>/
   <italic>Z</italic> with increasing 
   <italic>δ</italic>. This difference in behaviour, in turn, has a dramatic impact in the overall prevalence of configurations achieved by the population dynamics, as shown by the stationary distributions: On panel C (pure-Reward) the population spends most of the time on intermediate states of cooperation. On panel D (pure-Punishment) the population spends most of the time on both extremes (high and low cooperation) but especially on low cooperation states. Other parameters: 
   <italic>Z</italic> = 50, 
   <italic>N</italic> = 10, 
   <italic>M</italic> = 5, 
   <italic>c</italic> = 0.1, 
   <italic>B</italic> = 1, 
   <italic>r</italic> = 0.5, 
   <italic>a</italic> = 
   <italic>b</italic> = 1, 
   <italic>β</italic> = 5 and µ = 0.01 (see Methods for details).
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_52524_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e901" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
