<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par17" class="p">Downscaling using a high-resolution climatology is an improvement over the coarse model output, but still does not explicitly account for ocean dynamics at scales smaller than the coarse model resolution. The NOAA Geophysical Fluid Dynamics Laboratory (GFDL) has developed a high-resolution global climate model CM2.6
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" class="xref">57</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" class="xref">58</xref>
 </sup>, which resolves regional scale circulation in the Northeast U.S. that is not captured in coarse resolution models
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">17</xref>
 </sup>. For example, CM2.6 (~10-km horizontal ocean resolution) projects a northwestern shift of the Gulf Stream and a poleward retreat of the Labrador Current, increasing the proportion of warmer and saltier Atlantic Temperate Slope Water entering the Gulf of Maine
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">17</xref>
 </sup>. This model was only run using an 80-year simulation of the transient climate response (TCR), which projects a 1% per year increase in atmospheric CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> such that CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> doubles by year 70. This is not an IPCC RCP scenario, so it was not included in our ensemble projections of 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">finmarchicus</italic>. However, it was still useful to compare the projections between the lower and higher resolution models. The CM2.6 TCR run can be equated to the IPCC’s RCP 8.5 scenario such that a doubling of CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> (or a global surface warming of 2 °C relative to 1986–2005) is projected to occur in the 2060 s
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" class="xref">59</xref>
 </sup>. Therefore, the projections we show for CM2.6 can be roughly linked to the years 2050–2070 under the IPCC’s RCP 8.5 emissions scenario.
</p>
