<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par38" class="p">This review has indicated that climate change may have important consequences for foodborne illness but that these relationships are complex and uncertain. Hence, within the academic literature, there is considerable uncertainty over which foodborne pathogens will be most affected, what the specific effects will be and on what timescales changes might occur. We show that the 10 WHO/Europe Essential Public Health Operations can be used to highlight current capacity and adaptation potential with respect to potential effects of climate change on the food system and foodborne illness. Developments that underpin improved public health operations and hence preparedness for climate change include the following:
 <list list-type="bullet" class="list">
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par39" class="p">Adoption of novel surveillance methods, such as syndromic methods, to speed up detection and increase the fidelity of intervention in foodborne outbreaks</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par40" class="p">Genotype-based approaches to surveillance of food pathogens to enhance spatiotemporal resolution in tracing and tracking of illness</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par41" class="p">Ever increasing integration of plant, animal and human surveillance systems, One Health, to maximise potential for identifying threats</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par42" class="p">Increased commitment to cross-border (global) information initiatives (including big data)</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par43" class="p">Improved clarity regarding the governance of complex societal issues such as the conflict between food safety and food waste</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par44" class="p">Strong user-centric (social) communications strategies to engage diverse stakeholder groups</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
