<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec4.1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.1. Local Community Perceptions on Trends and Causes of Climate Change</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Findings from this study indicate that local communities perceive that rainfall is decreasing whilst temperatures are increasing. Findings are in line with IPCC [
  <a rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40">40</a>] predictions that temperatures across different scales are set to increase whilst rainfall in southern Africa is set to decrease. Results from this study show that scientific rainfall data which show interannual variations and a general decline in rainfall for over the past 30 years corroborate with the people's perception of climate changes. Farmers' perceptions of climate change in the study area are in line with empirical data and other studies on farmers perceptions inhabiting marginal areas in Zimbabwe [
  <a rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23">23</a>, 
  <a rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41">41</a>, 
  <a rid="B42" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42">42</a>]. Findings are also similar to other studies in Zimbabwe such as Guruve District where Gwenzi et al. [
  <a rid="B43" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43">43</a>] and Hwedza and Makoni [
  <a rid="B44" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44">44</a>] have reported unpredictable rainfall, declining rainfall, and increasing temperatures as some of the indicators of climate change. Local ecological knowledge on climate patterns and impacts has been documented in other studies in different parts of Africa [
  <a rid="B45" ref-type="bibr" href="#B45">45</a>–
  <a rid="B48" ref-type="bibr" href="#B48">48</a>]. Using IKS, Nkomwa et al. [
  <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">22</a>] reported that farmers in Malawi observed delayed and unpredictable onset of rainfall, declining rainfall trends, warming temperatures, and increased frequency of dry spells as some of the key indicators of a changing climate. However, there are variations with respect to observed extreme events. In this study, respondents cited frequent droughts and heat waves as the common extreme events. These findings are similar to IPCC [
  <a rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40">40</a>] report, which indicated that persistent droughts and extreme temperatures are some of the indicators of a changing climate. Whilst other studies have observed extreme events such as cyclones and floods [
  <a rid="B49" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49">49</a>–
  <a rid="B51" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51">51</a>], in this study, farmers did not identify such events. In Zimbabwe, two cyclones Elline (experienced in 2000) and Japhet (experienced in 2003) have mainly affected the Manicaland and Masvingo provinces [
  <a rid="B51" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51">51</a>], which the study respondents have not experienced. According to the [
  <a rid="B52" ref-type="bibr" href="#B52">52</a>] the major flood-prone areas in Zimbabwe are selected parts of the southern lowveld and the lower Zambezi valley, that is Muzarabani, Middle Sabi, Tsholotsho, Malipati, Chikwalakwala, and Tuli-Shashe.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this study, farmers attribute climate change to both anthropogenic and spiritual causes. This is in line with findings by [
  <a rid="B53" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53">53</a>] who noticed that farmers in Ghana perceived that disasters such as prolonged droughts are inflicted by spiritual factors such as the gods. Our findings also correspond with the IPCC [
  <a rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40">40</a>] report that combinations of anthropogenic and natural forces are the major cases of climatic changes.
 </p>
</sec>
