<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec4.3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.3. Coping and Adaptation Strategies</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Findings from this study revealed that local communities use LEK on wildlife resources, water conservation, indigenous plant food sources, and alternative income generation as way of adapting and coping with changing rainfall patterns, extreme temperatures, and droughts. Local communities use water harvesting such as digging wells, which collect water within wetlands during the rainy season, as one of the key strategies of coping with water shortages. The water is then used for supplementary irrigation of vegetables and crops during the dry season. Similar observations have been made by Van Campenhout et al. [
  <a rid="B72" ref-type="bibr" href="#B72">72</a>] that, in the dry season, farmers use the water conserved in the wells and basins for irrigation. Home gardens are widely done in southern Africa especially Zimbabwe, Mozambique, Botswana, and South Africa where there is growing of food crops like maize, rice, vegetable, and fruits for barter trading and income generation [
  <a rid="B72" ref-type="bibr" href="#B72">72</a>]. For example, in South Africa, indigenous people grow cash crops like vegetables, tomatoes, and maize in home gardens to increase household income [
  <a rid="B73" ref-type="bibr" href="#B73">73</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study established that illegal harvesting of wildlife and harvesting and consumption of wild fruits and legumes can alleviate food shortages during drought. Similar findings have been observed by [
  <a rid="B74" ref-type="bibr" href="#B74">74</a>, 
  <a rid="B75" ref-type="bibr" href="#B75">75</a>] who noted that off-farm income derived from exploitation of wildlife resources is critical to livelihoods and overall adaptive capacity. In coping with risk due to excessive or low rainfall, drought, and crop failure, some traditional people in Ghana also supplement their food by hunting, fishing, and gathering wild food plants [
  <a rid="B76" ref-type="bibr" href="#B76">76</a>]. Findings from this study on the use of edible tubers from family Dioscoreaceae are similar to findings elsewhere in Africa. Similar sentiments have been expressed by Mortimore and Manvell [
  <a rid="B77" ref-type="bibr" href="#B77">77</a>] who reported that small holder farmers in northern Nigeria making use of biodiversity in cultivated crops and wild plants as one of the adaptation strategies. For example, Bruschi et al. [
  <a rid="B70" ref-type="bibr" href="#B70">70</a>] found that some plant species like 
  <span class="italic">Dioscorea cochleari apiculata</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Dioscorea dumetorum</span> have been collected from a Miombo woodland and eaten as a means of averting food shortages during drought periods in a rural community of Muda-Serraçã, central Mozambique. Similarly, in this study, the same species provide alternative food during drought periods. In addition, both studies acknowledge that utilisation of the tubers requires one to be thoroughly acquainted with the skills and techniques for making some of the poisonous wild plants edible. Apart from southern Africa, the edible legumes are widely known as famine foods in East Africa and have also been reported as cultivated in some parts of West Africa [
  <a rid="B78" ref-type="bibr" href="#B78">78</a>]. Key informants also emphasized that 
  <span class="italic">Dioscorea cochleari apiculata</span> and 
  <span class="italic">D. dumetorum</span> may be eaten only after they have undergone appropriate preparation. Basically, the preparation procedure for the tubers involve the following: peeling the tuber, cutting it into thin slices, dry and wash several hours in a river, always changing the place, and then boil thoroughly for a prolonged period of time till they are cooked. Failure to do this may cause vomiting and even death as revealed by observations from East Africa [
  <a rid="B79" ref-type="bibr" href="#B79">79</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this study, few individuals indicated that they resort to production of handcrafts for sale as a strategy to increase household income. Mogotsi et al. [
  <a rid="B80" ref-type="bibr" href="#B80">80</a>] concurs that local communities have engaged in different living strategies like producing crafts for selling for income generation in order to reduce poverty and starvation during drought periods. For example, in Zimbabwe and South Africa, they use murara (
  <span class="italic">Hyphanate petersiana</span>) leaves for basket weaving and production of wine from the sap [
  <a rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24">24</a>, 
  <a rid="B81" ref-type="bibr" href="#B81">81</a>]. In Zimbabwe, njemani production has become a source of living for many people in Sengwe area and some of people no longer get involved in farming [
  <a rid="B82" ref-type="bibr" href="#B82">82</a>]. Similarly, in this study, some farmers indicated that they used local plant resources to weave mats, curve wood crafts, and brew beer for selling to boost household income but still engage in farming. However, unlike other communities who use grass plants like 
  <span class="italic">Hyphanate petersiana</span> to brew local beer [
  <a rid="B82" ref-type="bibr" href="#B82">82</a>], in this study, they used legume 
  <span class="italic">Rhynchosia venulosa</span> to brew beer.
 </p>
</sec>
