<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4. Discussion</div>
 <sec id="sec4.1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.1. Local Community Perceptions on Trends and Causes of Climate Change</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Findings from this study indicate that local communities perceive that rainfall is decreasing whilst temperatures are increasing. Findings are in line with IPCC [
   <a rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40">40</a>] predictions that temperatures across different scales are set to increase whilst rainfall in southern Africa is set to decrease. Results from this study show that scientific rainfall data which show interannual variations and a general decline in rainfall for over the past 30 years corroborate with the people's perception of climate changes. Farmers' perceptions of climate change in the study area are in line with empirical data and other studies on farmers perceptions inhabiting marginal areas in Zimbabwe [
   <a rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" href="#B23">23</a>, 
   <a rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41">41</a>, 
   <a rid="B42" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42">42</a>]. Findings are also similar to other studies in Zimbabwe such as Guruve District where Gwenzi et al. [
   <a rid="B43" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43">43</a>] and Hwedza and Makoni [
   <a rid="B44" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44">44</a>] have reported unpredictable rainfall, declining rainfall, and increasing temperatures as some of the indicators of climate change. Local ecological knowledge on climate patterns and impacts has been documented in other studies in different parts of Africa [
   <a rid="B45" ref-type="bibr" href="#B45">45</a>–
   <a rid="B48" ref-type="bibr" href="#B48">48</a>]. Using IKS, Nkomwa et al. [
   <a rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" href="#B22">22</a>] reported that farmers in Malawi observed delayed and unpredictable onset of rainfall, declining rainfall trends, warming temperatures, and increased frequency of dry spells as some of the key indicators of a changing climate. However, there are variations with respect to observed extreme events. In this study, respondents cited frequent droughts and heat waves as the common extreme events. These findings are similar to IPCC [
   <a rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40">40</a>] report, which indicated that persistent droughts and extreme temperatures are some of the indicators of a changing climate. Whilst other studies have observed extreme events such as cyclones and floods [
   <a rid="B49" ref-type="bibr" href="#B49">49</a>–
   <a rid="B51" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51">51</a>], in this study, farmers did not identify such events. In Zimbabwe, two cyclones Elline (experienced in 2000) and Japhet (experienced in 2003) have mainly affected the Manicaland and Masvingo provinces [
   <a rid="B51" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51">51</a>], which the study respondents have not experienced. According to the [
   <a rid="B52" ref-type="bibr" href="#B52">52</a>] the major flood-prone areas in Zimbabwe are selected parts of the southern lowveld and the lower Zambezi valley, that is Muzarabani, Middle Sabi, Tsholotsho, Malipati, Chikwalakwala, and Tuli-Shashe.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this study, farmers attribute climate change to both anthropogenic and spiritual causes. This is in line with findings by [
   <a rid="B53" ref-type="bibr" href="#B53">53</a>] who noticed that farmers in Ghana perceived that disasters such as prolonged droughts are inflicted by spiritual factors such as the gods. Our findings also correspond with the IPCC [
   <a rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40">40</a>] report that combinations of anthropogenic and natural forces are the major cases of climatic changes.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec4.2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.2. Local Ecological Knowledge on the Impacts of Climate Change</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study found that community members agreed that extreme events related to climate change such as prolonged dry periods and excessive temperatures have affected agricultural activities and the biophysical environment. Nyikahadzoi et al. [
   <a rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25">25</a>] note that climate change is expected to continue to pose a serious threat to agriculture in southern Africa as annual rainfall amounts are expected to decline and temperatures are expected to increase. Climate change has led to highly variable yields in arable agriculture (both rain-fed and irrigated) in African countries [
   <a rid="B54" ref-type="bibr" href="#B54">54</a>]. Findings in this study are in line with the IPCC [
   <a rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40">40</a>] which states that climate change impacts affect both natural and human systems. Respondents indicated that climate change has affected seasonal rainfall patterns by reducing the length of the rainy periods as well as the amount of rain with consequences on crop and livestock production. Similar observations by Chikozho [
   <a rid="B51" ref-type="bibr" href="#B51">51</a>] are that low and erratic rainfall is leading to low and unpredictable levels of crop production in the semidry agroecological zones of Zimbabwe. Study findings revealed that some farmers resorted to stored grain for seed but did not indicate any loss of seed variety impacts associated with climate change. This contrasts with findings by Mburu Gathuru and Kaguna [
   <a rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" href="#B55">55</a>] who revealed that, in Kenya, climate change, mainly reduced rainfall levels, has led to the disappearance of some of the indigenous seed varieties as continued failure of crops is affecting the capacity for production of good seeds. In this study, farmers indicated that the planting season has been shortened due to shifting in the timing of the onset of the rain season. Findings in this study are in line with Mburu Gathuru and Kaguna [
   <a rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" href="#B55">55</a>] who observed that, in Kenya, climate change has caused disruption of the planting calendar such that it has become increasingly difficult for youthful farmers to predict seasonal regimes.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Findings on the negative impacts of climate change on pastures and livestock health concur with those by Hopping et al. [
   <a rid="B56" ref-type="bibr" href="#B56">56</a>] who reported that pastoralists in the Tibetan rangelands, China, have the same opinion that changing climate is driving undesirable trends in grassland and livestock health. Rose et al. [
   <a rid="B57" ref-type="bibr" href="#B57">57</a>] also noted cases of decline in pastures due to low and erratic rainfall. Other authors have also noted that livestock production faces the problem of poor and variable rangeland productivity and desertification processes [
   <a rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24">24</a>, 
   <a rid="B58" ref-type="bibr" href="#B58">58</a>, 
   <a rid="B59" ref-type="bibr" href="#B59">59</a>]. Generally, reduction in fresh water resources affects natural resource and climate-dependent sectors such as forestry, agriculture, water, and fisheries [
   <a rid="B60" ref-type="bibr" href="#B60">60</a>]. Findings from this study indicate that local communities use LEK to detect changes in water resources due to climate change and variability. Respondents indicated that frequent extreme events such as drought and increasing temperatures affect soil moisture and surface water availability for both domestic use and agriculture. This is in line with United Nations Framework on Climate Change [
   <a rid="B61" ref-type="bibr" href="#B61">61</a>] assertion that Africa faces challenges related to water availability and spatial variations in the location and need for water resources. Observations from this study are also similar to those by Taylor et al. [
   <a rid="B62" ref-type="bibr" href="#B62">62</a>] who noticed that more frequent and intense climate extremes such as droughts and floods increase variability in soil moisture and surface water. Observations in this study related to drying up of rivers and poor water quality in surface and groundwater systems coincide with findings by Urama and Ozor [
   <a rid="B63" ref-type="bibr" href="#B63">63</a>] who reported that impacts on water resources act in conjunction with other factors to affect ecosystem health and socioeconomic well-being of human communities. For example, Mburu Gathuru and Kaguna [
   <a rid="B55" ref-type="bibr" href="#B55">55</a>] also noticed that, in Kenya, climate change interacts with anthropogenic activities along rivers to contribute to reduction of river water volume over time and weakening of critical ecosystems like forest watersheds.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Farmers at the agriculture wildlife interface notice impacts of climate change on wildlife resource abundance such as disappearance of wetlands, habitat changes, and changes in the phenology of indigenous tree species. These observations are in line with Dube and Phiri [
   <a rid="B64" ref-type="bibr" href="#B64">64</a>] who reported that climate change is affecting biodiversity in Zimbabwe as indicated by the disappearance of natural habitats, flora, and fauna. In Tanzania, Paavola [
   <a rid="B65" ref-type="bibr" href="#B65">65</a>] also noticed that forests, wildlife, and wetlands are being impacted by climate change. Farmers also reported that although wildlife resources such as fruits are consumed to avert food shortages during drought, their abundance has declined due to climatic changes. Results from this study agree with those by Rurinda et al. [
   <a rid="B44" ref-type="bibr" href="#B44">44</a>], who reported that the availability of wild fruits and social safety nets was affected directly and indirectly by extreme temperatures and increased rainfall variability, impacting on the livelihoods of resource-constrained farmers. Similar observations were also seen in [
   <a rid="B66" ref-type="bibr" href="#B66">66</a>] who noticed that farmers in Makonde district, Zimbabwe, perceived changes in ecosystem productivity, goods, and services as a result of climate-induced factors. Nhemachena et al. [
   <a rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41">41</a>] also indicated that the phenology of indigenous fruit trees and invertebrate species was under threat from climate-induced changes on water availability and wetlands. However, in this study, respondents did not identify any impacts associated with invertebrate species.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The recruitment of plants has been constrained by low rainfall and temperature leading to low productivity [
   <a rid="B67" ref-type="bibr" href="#B67">67</a>]. Low productivity of primary producers (plants) had severe cascading effects on both domestic and wildlife species along the food chain. Climate change has led to creation of strong tensions between humans and wildlife species due to shortage of resources (especially food and water). Occurrence of habitat patches and invasive species (which are inedible to animals) led to animals exceeding their home-ranges and encroaching human habitats, thereby causing damage to crops and property paving a way to human-wildlife conflict. Climate change has the potential to alter migratory routes (and timings) of species that use both seasonal wetlands (migratory birds) and track seasonal changes in vegetation (herbivores) [
   <a rid="B68" ref-type="bibr" href="#B68">68</a>]. This increase conflicts between people and large mammals such as elephants, particularly in areas where rainfall is low. Change [
   <a rid="B69" ref-type="bibr" href="#B69">69</a>] states that wildlife-farming conflict was potentially exacerbated by climate change, in particular, drought, which encourages wildlife to forage on farmlands.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this study, respondents also noted that climatic parameters interact with other nonclimatic factors such as illegal harvesting and pressure from human population increase also influence the abundance of wildlife resources. For instance, trees belonging to the dominant family within the Miombo region are threatened by other nonclimatic factors such as deforestation. Similar observations have been made in Mozambique where trees associated with Miombo woodland utilised for traditional purposes are declining due to overexploitation and destructive collection [
   <a rid="B70" ref-type="bibr" href="#B70">70</a>]. Mubaya et al. [
   <a rid="B71" ref-type="bibr" href="#B71">71</a>] suggest that although climatic factors are critical in determining production in agroecosystems, multiple stressors interact to influence the abundance and diversity of natural resources.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec4.3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.3. Coping and Adaptation Strategies</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Findings from this study revealed that local communities use LEK on wildlife resources, water conservation, indigenous plant food sources, and alternative income generation as way of adapting and coping with changing rainfall patterns, extreme temperatures, and droughts. Local communities use water harvesting such as digging wells, which collect water within wetlands during the rainy season, as one of the key strategies of coping with water shortages. The water is then used for supplementary irrigation of vegetables and crops during the dry season. Similar observations have been made by Van Campenhout et al. [
   <a rid="B72" ref-type="bibr" href="#B72">72</a>] that, in the dry season, farmers use the water conserved in the wells and basins for irrigation. Home gardens are widely done in southern Africa especially Zimbabwe, Mozambique, Botswana, and South Africa where there is growing of food crops like maize, rice, vegetable, and fruits for barter trading and income generation [
   <a rid="B72" ref-type="bibr" href="#B72">72</a>]. For example, in South Africa, indigenous people grow cash crops like vegetables, tomatoes, and maize in home gardens to increase household income [
   <a rid="B73" ref-type="bibr" href="#B73">73</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study established that illegal harvesting of wildlife and harvesting and consumption of wild fruits and legumes can alleviate food shortages during drought. Similar findings have been observed by [
   <a rid="B74" ref-type="bibr" href="#B74">74</a>, 
   <a rid="B75" ref-type="bibr" href="#B75">75</a>] who noted that off-farm income derived from exploitation of wildlife resources is critical to livelihoods and overall adaptive capacity. In coping with risk due to excessive or low rainfall, drought, and crop failure, some traditional people in Ghana also supplement their food by hunting, fishing, and gathering wild food plants [
   <a rid="B76" ref-type="bibr" href="#B76">76</a>]. Findings from this study on the use of edible tubers from family Dioscoreaceae are similar to findings elsewhere in Africa. Similar sentiments have been expressed by Mortimore and Manvell [
   <a rid="B77" ref-type="bibr" href="#B77">77</a>] who reported that small holder farmers in northern Nigeria making use of biodiversity in cultivated crops and wild plants as one of the adaptation strategies. For example, Bruschi et al. [
   <a rid="B70" ref-type="bibr" href="#B70">70</a>] found that some plant species like 
   <span class="italic">Dioscorea cochleari apiculata</span> and 
   <span class="italic">Dioscorea dumetorum</span> have been collected from a Miombo woodland and eaten as a means of averting food shortages during drought periods in a rural community of Muda-Serraçã, central Mozambique. Similarly, in this study, the same species provide alternative food during drought periods. In addition, both studies acknowledge that utilisation of the tubers requires one to be thoroughly acquainted with the skills and techniques for making some of the poisonous wild plants edible. Apart from southern Africa, the edible legumes are widely known as famine foods in East Africa and have also been reported as cultivated in some parts of West Africa [
   <a rid="B78" ref-type="bibr" href="#B78">78</a>]. Key informants also emphasized that 
   <span class="italic">Dioscorea cochleari apiculata</span> and 
   <span class="italic">D. dumetorum</span> may be eaten only after they have undergone appropriate preparation. Basically, the preparation procedure for the tubers involve the following: peeling the tuber, cutting it into thin slices, dry and wash several hours in a river, always changing the place, and then boil thoroughly for a prolonged period of time till they are cooked. Failure to do this may cause vomiting and even death as revealed by observations from East Africa [
   <a rid="B79" ref-type="bibr" href="#B79">79</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this study, few individuals indicated that they resort to production of handcrafts for sale as a strategy to increase household income. Mogotsi et al. [
   <a rid="B80" ref-type="bibr" href="#B80">80</a>] concurs that local communities have engaged in different living strategies like producing crafts for selling for income generation in order to reduce poverty and starvation during drought periods. For example, in Zimbabwe and South Africa, they use murara (
   <span class="italic">Hyphanate petersiana</span>) leaves for basket weaving and production of wine from the sap [
   <a rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" href="#B24">24</a>, 
   <a rid="B81" ref-type="bibr" href="#B81">81</a>]. In Zimbabwe, njemani production has become a source of living for many people in Sengwe area and some of people no longer get involved in farming [
   <a rid="B82" ref-type="bibr" href="#B82">82</a>]. Similarly, in this study, some farmers indicated that they used local plant resources to weave mats, curve wood crafts, and brew beer for selling to boost household income but still engage in farming. However, unlike other communities who use grass plants like 
   <span class="italic">Hyphanate petersiana</span> to brew local beer [
   <a rid="B82" ref-type="bibr" href="#B82">82</a>], in this study, they used legume 
   <span class="italic">Rhynchosia venulosa</span> to brew beer.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
