<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">To determine the flowering and seed dispersal times of 23 common Nunavut Arctic plant species (Table 
 <xref rid="ece32702-tbl-0001" ref-type="table-wrap" class="xref">1</xref>) over the past 120 years, we examined herbarium specimens collected from across Nunavut, Canada, from 1896 to 2015 (Table S1). We also included in the dataset flowering and seed dispersal times from field observations at both Lake Hazen, Quttinirpaaq National Park, Ellesmere Island, and Iqaluit, Baffin Island, Nunavut, in 2013–2015 (Panchen, 
 <xref rid="ece32702-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>; Panchen &amp; Gorelick, 
 <xref rid="ece32702-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>) and photographs from the Canadian Museum of Nature's photographic collection and private photographic collections (Table S1). We excluded from the dataset herbarium specimens and photographs that were any of the following: south of the tree line, west of longitude 111°W, duplicate herbarium specimens or photographs, or any records of plants not in flower or not dispersing seed. For each herbarium specimen, field observation, or photograph (henceforth referred to as a collection data point), we recorded the phenological state (flowering or dispersing seed), collection date representing the time of flowering or time of seed dispersal in number of days from 1st January (henceforth referred to as flowering day of year [DOY] or dispersing seed DOY), year of collection, and latitude and longitude of the collection data point location. The sample size for all collection data points was 3,795, with 3,353 in flower and 442 dispersing seed. For the field observations, the population's mean peak flowering or peak seed dispersal date at a site was used as the collection date. The “flowering” phenology state was when the petals were open, i.e., not in a bud, the petals looked fresh and were not wilted or discoloured, and the stigmas and anthers were visible. The “dispersing seed” phenology state was when the fruit had dehisced or the styles were extended and untwisted (
 <italic class="italic">Dryas integrifolia</italic> L.) or the capitulum had formed into a spherical seed head (
 <italic class="italic">Asteraceae</italic> species). There were no dispersing seed collection data points for 
 <italic class="italic">Diapensia lapponica</italic> L., 
 <italic class="italic">Saxifraga cernua</italic> L., and 
 <italic class="italic">Tofieldia pusilla</italic> (Michx.) Pers. In order to compare the phenological sensitivity to temperature in different parts of Nunavut and at different spatial scales, we classified each collection data point by region (Nunavut mainland or Nunavut archipelago), by island (for Nunavut archipelago collection data points only), and by locale (for Lake Hazen or Iqaluit collection data points only; Figures 
 <xref rid="ece32702-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref> and 
 <xref rid="ece32702-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref>). Islands north of Hudson Bay, and Boothia and Melville Peninsulas were classified as Nunavut archipelago. Islands further south and in Hudson Bay were classified with the latitudinally and climatically comparable Nunavut mainland (Canadian Ice Service, 
 <xref rid="ece32702-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2002</xref>).
</p>
