<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div id="Fig4" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
 <div class="caption">
  <p>Potential methane hydrate reserves beneath present and former ice sheets. Data presented includes minimum, mid-range and maximum estimates of carbon reserves. East Antarctic Ice Sheet sedimentary basin methane hydrate + free gas (AIS hydrate, minimum and maximum values taken from ref. 
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96" href="#CR96">96</a>
   </span>, with mid-range values as the average between the two), West Antarctic Ice Sheet sedimentary basin methane hydrate + free gas (WAIS hydrate, minimum and maximum estimates taken from ref. 
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR96" href="#CR96">96</a>
   </span>, with mid-range values as the average between the two), the SW Barents Sea LGM hydrate
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR165" href="#CR165">165</a>
   </span> (mid-range values are the average of the minimum and maximum published values from ref. 
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR165" href="#CR165">165</a>
   </span>), Laurentide and Fennoscandian Ice Sheet estimates of potential methane hydrate (minimum and mid-range estimates from estimates of methane hydrate carbon modelled in ref. 
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
   </span>. and maximum estimates taken from calculations in ref. 
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
   </span>) (LIS/FIS LGM), Total LGM subglacial (SG) hydrate + free gas (sum of all data presented, with SW Barents Sea estimates scaled to the entire formerly glaciated Barents Sea Shelf
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR165" href="#CR165">165</a>
   </span> hydrate scaled to the entire shelf), global present day marine methane hydrate, mid-range estimates (2500 Pg C) from ref. 
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR173" href="#CR173">173</a>
   </span>, minimum and maximum estimates from ref. 
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR174" href="#CR174">174</a>
   </span> (170–12,700 Pg C)
  </p>
 </div>
 <div xlink:href="41467_2019_11394_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e2618" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</div>
