<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3" class="p">While global climate models (GCMs) show obvious capabilities in projecting future climate, model parameters may have large uncertainties which depend on space and the forecast time horizon
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">13</xref>
 </sup>. The uncertainties are due to the nature of the climate system itself with complex behaviors and large internal variability
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">1</xref>
 </sup>. From a global perspective, the CMIP5 models well replicate the general feature
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">14</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">15</xref>
 </sup>. At the regional scale, climate change effects are more complex, particularly at different environments and climate conditions. Such predictions are available from GCMs, but there exits large uncertainties from the model uncertainty, scenario uncertainty and internal variability
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>
 </sup>. Apart from the uncertainty caused by CMIP5 data, the topography of study area may result in the performances for precipitation by CMIP5 data
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" class="xref">2</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">17</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">20</xref>
 </sup>. Jiang, 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">18</xref>
 </sup> concluded that most GCMs have topography-related cold biases and excessive precipitation. Su, 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" class="xref">2</xref>
 </sup> discussed the relation between the elevation of the study area and precipitation, temperature simulated by multi-model ensemble, who pointed out that the ensemble of CMIP5 underestimates the actual temperature and overestimates the actual precipitation in higher altitude regions over Indus River Basin. In this study, we focus on the influence of the topography of study area while simulating precipitation, particularly in elevation and relief amplitude.
</p>
