<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par3" class="p">Climate change and the intensification of agricultural food production pose threats to water quality and aquatic ecosystem functions and services
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">1</xref>
 </sup>. Biogeochemical flows, specifically phosphorus (P) and the one-way flow
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" class="xref">2</xref>
 </sup> of P from mineral reserves to farms and into oceans, are already considered to be beyond the safe operating space for sustainable human development
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">3</xref>
 </sup>. Although intensification of food production may well be necessary from the standpoint of human demand and sustainable human development, this should also take account of societal concerns about resource use and eutrophication. Predicting future nutrient transfers into rivers, lakes and groundwater, for evaluating nutrient abatement strategies, is challenging, due to the complexity of the landscape processes involved and the uncertainties in the input data, model structures and calibration data. Previous studies on the effects of climate and land use change on water quality have been limited by inadequate data resolution, lack of appropriate P data, limited model comparison, and lack of uncertainty analysis
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">4</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>
 </sup>. Here, we overcome these limitations by combining new high-resolution catchment discharge and total P (TP) data and climate projections with two models of contrasting complexity (process-based Hydrological Predictions for the Environment (HYPE)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">8</xref>
 </sup> and a Data-Based Mechanistic (DBM)
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">9</xref>
 </sup> model) for three diverse agricultural catchments across the UK. The Eden, Cumbria (predominantly livestock), the Wensum, Norfolk (predominantly arable) and the Avon, Hampshire (mixed farming) are representative of the country’s different climatic conditions, soil types, hydrology and farming systems. We determine possible future agricultural management options by consultation with stakeholders in the three catchments. We estimate future P export loads under combined agricultural intensification and future climate using projections from a new high-resolution (1.5 km grid) regional climate model (RCM-1.5 km) for the UK
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>
 </sup> and from the UK Climate Projections 2009 Weather Generator
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">11</xref>
 </sup> (UKCP09-WG). RCM-1.5 km is able to simulate sub-daily precipitation characteristics better than coarser resolution climate models, particularly for short-duration, summer convective storms
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>
 </sup>, and makes a more realistic estimate of the intensity and duration of extreme events
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">12</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">13</xref>
 </sup> which have previously been shown to transfer a large proportion of the annual total P load
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">14</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">15</xref>
 </sup>. We assess what scale of agricultural change would be needed to mitigate the transfers predicted under climate change. Michalak
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">1</xref>
 </sup> notes that climate research and water quality research are usually conducted entirely separately, partly due to the often differing scales of interest, and recommends that for better understanding of climate change effects, we need to bring together the two disciplines. Our integrated, multi-disciplinary study follows these recommendations, with the potential to contribute to the understanding of likely future P losses. We show that the predicted increase in winter P loads due to climate change (up to 30% by 2050s) is greater than the technically feasible reduction from mitigation measures estimated in previous studies
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>
 </sup>. Our study suggests that only large-scale agricultural changes (e.g., 20–80% reduction in P inputs) will limit the projected impacts of climate change on P loads in these catchments.
</p>
