<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec014" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.3.3 Low Latitudes</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As in the other latitudinal bands, the carbon lost by vegetation due to tree removal over the low latitudes enters the atmosphere, generating a rapid increase in CO
  <sub>2</sub> concentrations proportional to the extent of deforestation (7 to 127 ppmv). Due to the larger quantity of trees removed in the low latitudes, this initial CO
  <sub>2</sub> increase is higher than what is seen in the high and mid latitudes combined (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0153357.g013" href="#pone.0153357.g013">Fig 13</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This increase is followed by a period of diminishing CO
  <sub>2</sub>, with the rate of decrease proportional to the deforestation fraction caused mostly by oceanic absorption of CO
  <sub>2</sub>. Atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub> values in the 75% and 100% scenarios fall relatively quickly, and for the duration of the experiments, remain below those of the initial peak. This is not the case for the other scenarios, where by no later than the mid 21
  <span class="sup">
   <span class="italic">st</span>
  </span> century, the atmosphere holds more carbon than it had at the peak of the post deforestation pulse (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0153357.g013" href="#pone.0153357.g013">Fig 13</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The low latitudes had the same initial soil carbon response to deforestation as the high and mid latitudes, with a small initial decrease over the first few years followed by a rapid increase (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0153357.g014" href="#pone.0153357.g014">Fig 14</a>). As with the mid latitudes, the changes in soil carbon are explained by continuous increase in carbon density over non-deforested areas and a mixed response in the deforested bins. The largest soil carbon losses occur in the intermediary deforestation fractions, where soils are warmer and not as dry. Different from the high and mid latitudes, these losses resulted in periods where some intermediary fractions, like the 25% scenario, exhibited global changes soil carbon near zero. Again as seen in the high and mid latitudes, the experiments with the smaller soil carbon anomalies are the ones which show the largest concentrations of atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub>. Increases in NPP, relatively colder temperatures and drier conditions lead to large soil carbon gains by deforested bins in the higher fraction deforestation scenarios. Similarly to the mid latitudes, the deforested bins of the 75% and 100% simulations hold the majority of the global soil carbon by the end of the experiments.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ocean carbon response to low latitude deforestation is very similar to the high and mid latitudes, where ocean carbon to a certain degree mirrors atmospheric carbon. In the low latitudes we do not see the same level of post initial pulse reduction in atmospheric carbon as was observed in the high and mid latitudes, and the ocean carbon also shows this, as there is less variation in total ocean carbon between the simulations, due to the oceans slower response to atmospheric carbon change (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0153357.g014" href="#pone.0153357.g014">Fig 14</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
