<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Previous studies have shown that shallow‐water settings are numerically dominated by abundant, eurytopic, geographically widespread, and geologically long‐lived species, whereas offshore faunas tend to be dominated by species that are less abundant, more stenotopic, geographically restricted, and geologically short‐lived (e.g. Jackson 
 <xref rid="pala12278-bib-0057" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1974</xref>, Jablonski &amp; Valentine 
 <xref rid="pala12278-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1981</xref>, Kammer 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="pala12278-bib-0060" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1997</xref>). Somewhat paradoxically, taxonomic extinction (Sepkoski 
 <xref rid="pala12278-bib-0100" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1987</xref>) and origination (Kiessling &amp; Aberhan 
 <xref rid="pala12278-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>) rates increase onshore. These apparently conflicting observations are reconciled by a model in which preferential onshore extinction leads to the accumulation of extinction‐resistant clades (i.e. eurytopic, geographically widespread) that spread offshore over macroevolutionary timescales (Sepkoski 
 <xref rid="pala12278-bib-0099" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1981</xref>). The cause of enhanced onshore extinction has been attributed to greater short‐term environmental variability (Sepkoski 
 <xref rid="pala12278-bib-0100" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1987</xref>) and to greater onshore variability in habitat area during relative sea‐level changes (Holland &amp; Christie 
 <xref rid="pala12278-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). Biofacies composition and change in the Sundance Seaway follows these same patterns, with onshore faunas characterized by abundant and long‐lived species relative to those offshore. Thus, in the Sundance biofacies show relatively greater turnover in the offshore than the onshore. These results emphasize the contrast between taxon‐based approaches, which indicate greater extinction and turnover onshore, and ecological approaches based on relative abundance, which show greater turnover offshore. These results match well previous studies that have shown how ecologically‐based analyses of macroevolutionary patterns differ from taxonomically‐based analyses (Boucot 
 <xref rid="pala12278-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1983</xref>; McGhee 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="pala12278-bib-0075" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2004</xref>; Christie 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="pala12278-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Dineen 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="pala12278-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). Tomašových 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. (
 <xref rid="pala12278-bib-0108" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>) found no consistent onshore–offshore patterns of turnover within Eocene and Pliocene stages, but elevated onshore turnover from the Eocene to the Pliocene that was driven by selectivity in onshore regions, underscoring that global macroevolutionary patterns are driven by regional‐scale patterns of selectivity whose effects accumulate over long spans of time.
</p>
