<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par20" class="p">Contrary to the expectations under the “nowhere to go” hypothesis
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">3</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">4</xref>
 </sup>, most 
 <italic class="italic">Rhodiola</italic> species broadened their geographic ranges rather than contracting with future climate warming (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3</xref>; Supplementary Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S9</xref>; Supplementary Figs 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S2</xref>–
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S4</xref>). DeChaine 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" class="xref">32</xref>
 </sup> and Forester 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" class="xref">33</xref>
 </sup> found that 
 <italic class="italic">R. integrifolia</italic> exhibited a similar pattern of range expansion in North America. Other QTP plants, such as 
 <italic class="italic">Hippophae gyantsensis</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">H. rhamnoides</italic> ssp. 
 <italic class="italic">yunnanensis</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">H</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">neurocarpa</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Eriophyton wallichii</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Thalictrum squamiferum</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Paraquilegia microphylla</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Allium przewalskianum</italic> also tend towards range expansion with climate warming
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">38</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" class="xref">40</xref>
 </sup>. Such patterns may be explained by a number of factors. First, these species have relatively small contemporary geographical ranges. For instance, 
 <italic class="italic">Rhodiola</italic> is mainly distributed in the eastern and southern regions of the QTP while the more extensive areas available above 4000 m above sea level (asl) in the northern and western parts of the QTP remain uncolonized. Second, warmer temperatures and higher precipitation under future warming conditions could transform unsuitable regions, such as those currently with permafrost, into suitable habitats for 
 <italic class="italic">Rhodiola</italic> at higher latitudes and elevations. Moreover, increased vegetation coverage could also play a role in expansion of 
 <italic class="italic">Rhodiola</italic> species ranges. Cannone 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" class="xref">41</xref>
 </sup> reported that vegetation coverage, particularly that of shrubs, increased dramatically in the alpine belt of Italian Central Alps from 1952 to 2003, coincident with higher precipitation and diminution of permafrost. The extent of shrub coverage has also increased in the Arctic over the past 50 years
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" class="xref">42</xref>
 </sup>. 
 <italic class="italic">Rhodiola</italic> species typically co-occur with shrubs
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">15</xref>
 </sup>, and thus we predict that areas suitable for colonization by 
 <italic class="italic">Rhodiola</italic> will be increasingly available as shrub vegetation expands in the QTP and environs. Overall then, our results provide evidence that vascular plant species richness in montane communities will increase with climate warming
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">9</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
