<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The identification of molecular markers linked to tolerance to climate change becomes essential to efficiently drive breeding projects targeting Mediterranean crops. Quantitative Trait Loci or QTLs analysis and genetic association studies are based on genetic linkage (low recombination rate) of marker genes to genes directly involved in phenotype diversity. In contrast to QTL, analysis in sexual recombining populations, genome-wide association studies (GWAS) allow exploring linkage associations in more diverse germplasms and the identification of key genes that should be monomorphic in a single hybrid population. It also poses the advantage of bypassing the construction of designed segregating populations saving time and work, constituting a serious alternative in perennial fruit crop breeding programs where breeding materials are derived from many parental combinations. As a result, the usage of GWAS in fruit crops increased during the last 2 years (
 <xref rid="B136" ref-type="bibr">Iwata et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B90" ref-type="bibr">Farneti et al., 2017</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B177" ref-type="bibr">Minamikawa et al., 2017</xref>). However, its applicability depends greatly on the genetic structure of the considered germplasm and particularly the decay of the linkage disequilibrium (LD) with the genetic distance. The LD decay can be strongly affected by the evolution history of the gene pool as observed in Citrus (
 <xref rid="B102" ref-type="bibr">Garcia-Lor et al., 2012</xref>). Genomic selection (GS) is a more recent approach, initially developed for animal breeding to make an improved use high throughput molecular in marker assisted selection. It is based on modelization of the phenotypic value from high density marker information over the whole genome (
 <xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr">Desta and Ortiz, 2014</xref>). Previous studies on animals and plants highlighted the interest of GS, especially for capturing small-effect quantitative trait loci. GS is now routinely applied in animal breeding (
 <xref rid="B173" ref-type="bibr">Meuwissen et al., 2016</xref>). Its application resulted in increased genetic gain in dairy cattle breeding where the reliability of genomic prediction exceeds 0.8 for production traits and 0.7 for fertility and other traits (
 <xref rid="B164" ref-type="bibr">Lund et al., 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B266" ref-type="bibr">Wiggans et al., 2011</xref>). In Canada, for example, the rate of genetic gain has approximately doubled since GS was introduced. In plants, promising results were obtained, particularly in cereals with genetic gain of GS higher than that of MAS or conventional pedigree breeding (
 <xref rid="B263" ref-type="bibr">Wang X. et al., 2018</xref>). The combined analysis of multiple traits and/or multiple environments will be important for improving the accuracy of prediction and to promote the use of GS in plant breeding projects.
</p>
