<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Ethnobiology and Ethnomedicine</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1746-4269</issn><publisher><publisher-name>BioMed Central</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">5599890</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">181</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13002-017-0181-8</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Sharing fishers&#x000b4; ethnoecological knowledge of the European pilchard (<italic>Sardina pilchardus</italic>) in the westernmost fishing community in Europe</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Braga</surname><given-names>Heitor de Oliveira</given-names></name><address><email>heitorob@gmail.com</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pardal</surname><given-names>Miguel &#x000c2;ngelo</given-names></name><address><email>mpardal@uc.pt</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Azeiteiro</surname><given-names>Ulisses Miranda</given-names></name><address><email>ulisses@ua.pt</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9511 4342</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.8051.c</institution-id><institution>Centre for Functional Ecology - CFE, Department of Life Sciences, </institution><institution>University of Coimbra, </institution></institution-wrap>Cal&#x000e7;ada Martins de Freitas, 3000-456 Coimbra, Portugal </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 9738 4872</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.452295.d</institution-id><institution>CAPES Foundation, Ministry of Education of Brazil, </institution></institution-wrap>Caixa Postal 250, Brasilia, DF 70040-020 Brazil </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000000123236065</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.7311.4</institution-id><institution>Department of Biology &#x00026; CESAM - Centre for Environmental and Marine Studies, </institution><institution>University of Aveiro, </institution></institution-wrap>3810-19 Aveiro, Portugal </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>9</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>14</day><month>9</month><year>2017</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2017</year></pub-date><volume>13</volume><elocation-id>52</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>13</day><month>7</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>3</day><month>9</month><year>2017</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s). 2017</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p>
<bold>Open Access</bold>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/">http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/</ext-link>) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><sec><title>Background</title><p id="Par1">With the present difficulties in the conservation of sardines in the North Atlantic, it is important to investigate the local ecological knowledge (LEK) of fishermen about the biology and ecology of these fish. The ethnoecological data of European pilchard provided by local fishermen can be of importance for the management and conservation of this fishery resource. Thus, the present study recorded the ethnoecological knowledge of <italic>S. pilchardus</italic> in the traditional fishing community of Peniche, Portugal.</p></sec><sec><title>Methods</title><p id="Par2">This study was based on 87 semi-structured interviews conducted randomly from June to September 2016 in Peniche. The interview script contained two main points: Profile of fishermen and LEK on European pilchard. The ethnoecological data of sardines were compared with the scientific literature following an emic-etic approach. Data collected also were also analysed following the union model of the different individual competences and carefully explored to guarantee the objectivity of the study.</p></sec><sec><title>Results</title><p id="Par3">The profile of the fishermen was investigated and measured. Respondents provided detailed informal data on the taxonomy, habitat, behaviour, migration, development, spawning and fat accumulation season of sardines that showed agreements with the biological data already published on the species. The main uses of sardines by fishermen, as well as beliefs and food taboos have also been mentioned by the local community.</p></sec><sec><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par4">The generated ethnoecological data can be used to improve the management of this fishery resource through an adaptive framework among the actors involved, in addition to providing data that can be tested in further ecological studies. Therefore, this local knowledge may have the capacity to contribute to more effective conservation actions for sardines in Portugal.</p></sec><sec><title>Electronic supplementary material</title><p>The online version of this article (10.1186/s13002-017-0181-8) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></sec></abstract><kwd-group xml:lang="en"><title>Keywords</title><kwd>Ethnoecology</kwd><kwd>Folk knowledge</kwd><kwd>Fishermen</kwd><kwd>European pilchard</kwd><kwd>Participatory management</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution>CAPES Foundation - Ministry of Education of Brazil </institution></funding-source><award-id>BEX: 8926/13-1</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2017</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1"><title>Background</title><p id="Par12">Human populations have forced marine coastal ecosystems to differ from their historical states, which were characterized by diversified and productive communities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. One of the biggest human impacts has been overfishing, which has progressively reduced stocks, geographically expanded its range and disguises itself through new and improved technologies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>].</p><p id="Par13">In marine ecosystems, pelagic fish are recognized as abundant in productive fishing areas, both on a large scale and on a small scale [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>], and are characterized by a history of large fluctuations in their populations, both due to overfishing as well as environmental factors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Within this group of fish, we have small pelagic species, such as sardines and anchovies, which are abundant in several productive regions of the ocean and are found mainly in areas of coastal and oceanic upwelling [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. These clupeoid fishes are recognized mainly as having a low trophic level in the food web, early reproduction age and rapid growth, all of which make them more vulnerable to different environmental factors and climate change [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>].</p><p id="Par14">In the central, eastern, and northeastern Atlantic, the European pilchard <italic>Sardina pilchardus</italic> (Walbaum, 1792) stands out among the pelagic fish for fisheries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. At the moment in Iberian waters, this species exhibits low biomass stocks at age 1 and a decrease in the stock of old fish and low recruitment rates [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. In Portugal, European pilchard are one of the most important species to fishing fleets using purse seines and are recognized for their socio-economic values and traditional uses among the Portuguese [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>].</p><p id="Par15">With all these processes occurring, it is important to understand both the perceptions of local fishery managers and users of local resources and to provide strategies for avoiding conflicting shared perceptions among the stakeholders involved in fisheries management [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. In small-scale fisheries, for example, local fishermen are in many cases disadvantaged in relation to the actors belonging to large-scale fisheries due to their marginal political power, lack of infrastructure and their typical remoteness [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>].</p><p id="Par16">However, it is known that support from the general public for the management of natural resources is fundamental for long-term sustainability [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Discussions should be initiated with these local communities as a way of transferring responsibility and regulatory power over available environmental resources [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>].</p><p id="Par17">The local ecological knowledge (LEK) in this context serves as an effective tool for monitoring and assisting in the planning of depleted resources, for the conservation of biodiversity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>], and for conducting more reasonable and culturally sensitive research and management plans [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. This knowledge can be understood as the lay or experiential knowledge of an individual about the environment based on daily observations, practical experiences in nature and learned scientific knowledge [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>].</p><p id="Par18">To better understand recent history of artisanal fishing and the deterioration of the standard of living of the dependents of this resource [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>], we can employ ethnoecology, which according to Marques (2001) can be understood as the scientific study of traditional ecological knowledge (knowledge, behaviour, feelings, and beliefs that influence all interactions between humans and the ecosystem) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. More specifically within ethnozoology, we have ethnoichthyology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>], which aims to report the knowledge that fishermen have about fish biology and ecology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>], and the understanding of interactions between humans and ichthyological resources encompassing the cognitive and behavioural aspects supported by conservation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>].</p><p id="Par19">From this perspective, extracting ethnoecological data about European pilchard from the fishing community of Peniche, as well as the knowledge passed from generation to generation by the more experienced fishermen, can be important strategies for the conservation of this fishing resource. This type of ethnoecological survey emphasizes the cultural knowledge of fishermen, favours their dialogue with environmental managers and researchers, and contributes to the improvement of participatory management of natural resources by increasing the acceptance of management rules [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>].</p><p id="Par20">Thus, the aim of this study was to record the ethnoecological knowledge of the fishing village of Peniche, Portugal, about the ecology and biology of <italic>S. pilchardus. T</italic>he fishermen&#x02019;s profiles and the likely human uses, beliefs and taboos related to European pilchard (also known as the Atlantic sardine, European sardine, or sardine) were also explored. The ethnoecological data provided by the fishermen who are in agreement with the published biological data were interpreted and discussed in the present study.</p></sec><sec id="Sec2"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec3"><title>Study area</title><p id="Par21">This study was based on interviews with artisanal fishermen from the fishing community of Peniche, on the coast of the western sub-region of Portugal (39&#x000b0; 21&#x02032; 32&#x02033; N, 9&#x000b0; 22&#x02032; 40&#x02033; W; Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). This city has 27,628 inhabitants with an area of approximately 77,55&#x000a0;km2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. The climate is temperate with rainy winters and dry and somewhat hot summers (K&#x000f6;ppen type Csb) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>].<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Map of the study area, highlighting the fishing port and the city center of Peniche where the interviews were conducted in Portugal. Credits: B Zucherato</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13002_2017_181_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par22">One of the world&#x02019;s first Portuguese protected areas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>] is located approximately 5.7&#x000a0;miles from Peniche (Cape Carvoeiro) in the Atlantic Ocean [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Formed by an archipelago of islands (Berlenga Grande, Estela and Farilh&#x000f5;es), this marine protected area is located in the transition zone between the Mediterranean and European sub-regions, specifically at the top of the escarpment of the Nazar&#x000e9; Canyon [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. The Berlengas Marine Natural Reserve (MNR) is renowned for its great marine biological diversity, archaeological features, insular ecosystem specificities and is importance in the life cycle of the marine avifauna [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Fishing community</title><p id="Par23">The fishing port of Peniche is recognized as one of the main ports of the country [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>] according to fishing indicators for the average value of fish unloaded in this area [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. The economic and social development of the city is directly linked to the fishing activity of this port, which is one of the busiest in Portugal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>].</p><p id="Par24">This fishing community is considered a local symbol with remarkable prestige throughout the municipality [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. In the maritime captaincy of Peniche, there are approximately 1105 registered fishermen, with 996 conducting marine fishing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Polyvalent and seine fishing are predominant in this area, with sardines being one of the three main target species for fishing according to the data on the nominal catch landed in Portugal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec5"><title>Fishermen&#x02019;s Interviews</title><p id="Par25">Semi-structured interviews [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>] were conducted from June to September 2016 to obtain data on LEK about the European pilchard. The state-owned company Docapesca - Portos e Lotas granted permission for administering the interviews to the fishermen of Porto de Peniche. Fishermen were interviewed over successive visits in the fishing warehouses of the Port of Peniche and at the main meeting points of the fishing community. Brook and McLachlan (2008) sees this type of involvement with the community as indispensable [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>].&#x000a0;The objectives of the work and the statement of informed consent to participate in the research were provided to the fishermen through the Statement of Informed Consent (IC) [see Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>].</p><p id="Par26">The interviews were mainly conducted through manual transcription and occasionally with a digital audio recorder. The interviews with fishermen were conducted randomly - always before or after the arrivals and departures of the fishing teams and when they were doing net and fishing gear repairs. The interview script [see Additional&#x000a0;file&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media">2</xref>] was structured in 2 parts: Profile of fisherman (age, schooling, fishing time, time of residence in Peniche, income source, type and length of boat, fishing time at sea and time to catch sardines) and LEK of European pilchard (folk taxonomy, habitat, behaviour and migration, development of sardines, spawning, fat accumulation season and uses, beliefs and food taboos). The educational profile of the interviewees followed the Portuguese educational classification: A (1st Cycle: 1&#x02013;4&#x000a0;years of study), B (2nd Cycle: 5&#x02013;6&#x000a0;years of study), C (3rd Cycle: 7&#x02013;9&#x000a0;years of study) and D: (Secondary Education: 10&#x02013;12&#x000a0;years of study).</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Data analyses</title><p id="Par27">A respect for the stakeholders and communities, the clarification of data collection objectives, the interactive approach and the recognition of information limitations were used as a basis for analysing the data acquired [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. All the information provided through the surveys was analysed following the union model of the different individual competences [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. The LEK about sardine was analysed through an emic-etic approach [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>], and the data generated by the community were compared with the scientific literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. The wealth of information and depth of perceptions in the data collected were analysed through careful coding and cross-checking to ensure the objectivity of the study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. Species nomenclature data were analysed following the Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations (FAO) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>], the International Union for Conservation of Nature (IUCN) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>], and Fish Base [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. The data obtained in the interviews were stored and standardized in EXCEL and analysed (descriptive statistics) in the R Project for Statistical Computing version 3.3.2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec7"><title>Results</title><sec id="Sec8"><title>Descriptive statistics of fishermen&#x02019;s profiles</title><p id="Par28">A total of 87 interviews were conducted in the fishing community of Peniche. The interview sites were predominantly in the Port of Peniche (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>) (<italic>N</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;71) followed by the city centre (<italic>N</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;16). The average age of the respondents was 58.25&#x000a0;years, with a minimum of 25&#x000a0;years and a maximum of 76&#x000a0;years. More than half of the interviewees (<italic>N</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;59) were born in Peniche and are active (<italic>N</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;49) in the fishing currently. According to the Portuguese educational classification, 58 individuals belonged to the 1st Cycle, 19 to the 2nd Cycle, 5 to the 3rd Cycle and 5 to Secondary Education. There were no illiterates or individuals with higher education in the sample. The fishing experience varied from 3 to 60&#x000a0;years, but fishing experience average was 39.08&#x000a0;years. The average monthly income source related to fishing, including retirees, is 810.5 Euros, ranging from 208.0 to 3000.0 Euros. A total of 50 fishermen interviewed supplement their income with income from other activities. Of these fishermen, 31 informants do so through work related to fishing (maintenance of fishing nets) and the rest in other autonomous activities.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>
<bold>a</bold> Main area of the fishing port of Peniche, Portugal where the interviews with the fishermen were carried out. <bold>b</bold> A fisherman doing maintenance of purse seine nets. Credits: HO Braga. (Images published under previous consent of the participants)</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13002_2017_181_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig>
</p><p id="Par29">The main types of boats mentioned by the fishermen were: trawlers, artisanal fishing boats, trawl nets, coastal boats, and sports boats. Trawlers were further sub-classified by fishermen into trawlers (larger boats) and &#x0201c;rapa&#x0201d; (smaller boats). Boats were measured 93 times during the interviews. Of these, the boats mentioned were as follows: trawlers (35), artisanal fishing boats (38), &#x0201c;rapa&#x0201d; (14), trawl nets (3), coastal boats (2) and sport boats (1). Six Fishermen have said they have fished in more than one type of boat, those being 3 in both artisanal fishing boats and trawlers and 3 in artisanal fishing boats and trawl nets. Only 17 of the fishermen interviewed are boat owners.</p><p id="Par30">The fishermen interviewed were questioned about their preferred schedule of sardine capture during the fishing campaigns<italic>.</italic> A cycle called "It is six in the morning and six in the afternoon" was the most cited by fishermen (<italic>N</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;27). Other respondents mentioned both sunrise and sunset (<italic>N</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;17), day and night (<italic>N</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;16), preferably day (N&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;16), preferably night (<italic>N</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;9), and only at sunset (N&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;2).</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Local ecological knowledge of sardines</title><sec id="Sec10"><title>Folk taxonomy</title><p id="Par31">In Peniche, besides the name sardine, the artisanal fishermen attributed popular names to small sardines. A total of 82 fishermen attributed the name &#x0201c;petinga&#x0201d; or &#x0201c;esquilha&#x0201d; to juvenile sardines. One fishermen mentioned the name &#x0201c;real&#x0201d; sardine and another fishermen &#x0201c;sueste&#x0201d; fish. In this community, only two fishermen mentioned the scientific name (Linnaean).</p></sec><sec id="Sec11"><title>Habitat, behaviour and migration</title><p id="Par32">When questioned about the preferential habitat of sardines, 40 of the fishermen indicated coasts and high sea, 39 only on the coast, 6 more often on the coast, one only on the high sea and one did not answer this question. The informants highlighted some specific habitats (rocky seabeds, areas where the river empties into the sea carrying food, clean seabeds, more temperate waters, and sandy seabed to escape from common dolphin (<italic>Delphinus delphis</italic> Linnaeus, 1758) attacks.</p><p id="Par33">In relation to the most common depth of the sardine in the sea, 32 informants indicate a forage interval of 0&#x02013;50&#x000a0;m, 40 between 0 and 100&#x000a0;m and 11 between 0 and 200&#x000a0;m. Two fishermen did not know how to answer this question and two others just said they were deep-sea fish.</p><p id="Par34">The locomotion of sardines in the sea, according to all fishermen, is carried out in shoals. Some fishermen (<italic>N</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;15) specified that the schools are enormous. Two other fishermen referred to a phenomenon that makes sardines stick together. One informant said that sardines usually come together to protect themselves from common dolphins, and the other informant said that common dolphins make them stay together to feed.</p><p id="Par35">The following types and patterns of sardine migration have been mentioned by fishermen in the fishing community of Peniche: the migration comes from the South (13 times), comes from the North (18 times), comes from the South and North (32 times), occurs with the tides (3 times), occurs according to the seasons of the year - summer and winter (15 times) and migrant/pelagic/moving fish (14 times). Only 7 respondents did not respond to this part of the interview.</p><p id="Par36">Local fishermen also mentioned the probable areas of sardine displacement along the Portuguese Coast that passes through Peniche (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The areas most cited by respondents were Figueira da Foz (27 times), Algarve (25 times), Nazar&#x000e9; (19 times), Ericeira (15 times), Sesimbra (12 times) and Sines (11 times). Other areas of Portugal, such as Aveiro, Set&#x000fa;bal and Portim&#x000e3;o (8 times), Cape Roca (7 times), S&#x000e3;o Pedro de Moel and Matosinhos (4 times), Viana de Castelo, P&#x000f3;voa de Varzim, Olh&#x000e3;o and Santa Cruz (3 times) and Cascaiz and Leix&#x000f5;es (2 times). Foz do Minho Beach, Vila do Conde, Caparica Coast, Porto Beach, Mira Beach, Tocha Beach, Sagres and Lisbon were mentioned only once in the interviews.<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Probable areas of sardines displacement along the Portuguese Coast according to the fishermen of Peniche</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Fishing spots in Portugal</th><th>Number of times cited by fishermen</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Figueira da Foz</td><td>27</td></tr><tr><td>Algarve</td><td>25</td></tr><tr><td>Nazar&#x000e9;</td><td>19</td></tr><tr><td>Ericeira</td><td>15</td></tr><tr><td>Sesimbra</td><td>12</td></tr><tr><td>Sines</td><td>11</td></tr><tr><td>Aveiro, Set&#x000fa;bal and Portim&#x000e3;o</td><td>8</td></tr><tr><td>Cape Roca</td><td>7</td></tr><tr><td>S&#x000e3;o Pedro de Moel and Matosinhos</td><td>4</td></tr><tr><td>Viana de Castelo, P&#x000f3;voa de Varzim, Olh&#x000e3;o and Santa Cruz</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>Cascaiz and Leix&#x000f5;es</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Foz do Minho Beach, Vila do Conde, Caparica Coast, Porto Beach, Mira Beach, Tocha Beach, Sagres and Lisbon</td><td>1</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec12"><title>Development of sardines</title><p id="Par37">In the development section, the fisherman was asked about the time of sardine growth. According to 57 of respondents, sardines showed rapid growth, 16 said they were slow growing, 3 indicated intermediate growth (neither slow nor fast) and 11 did not know how to answer this question. The vast majority of respondents (<italic>N</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;85) said that the sardine exhibit only the roe phase during their development. One fisherman mentioned both the larval stage and the roe phase, and another fisherman did not know how to answer this question.</p><p id="Par38">Only 19 of respondents said that sardine mature after 1&#x000a0;year of age, and 24 did not know how to respond. The rest of the interviewees (<italic>N</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;44) said that the sardine is able to reproduce within a range of 3&#x02013;7&#x000a0;months old.</p></sec><sec id="Sec13"><title>Spawning and fat accumulation season</title><p id="Par39">The answers about the spawning time of sardines varied among fishermen. Most informants cited the spawning months as the answer to this question. The spawning time ranged from one to 8&#x000a0;months (72 citations). There was 1 response for 8&#x000a0;months, 2 for 4&#x000a0;months, 3 for 6&#x000a0;months and 3 for 7&#x000a0;months, 7 responses for 5&#x000a0;months, 16 for 4&#x000a0;months, 17 for 3&#x000a0;months and 20 for 2&#x000a0;months. The rest of the respondents (<italic>N</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3) did not report any months.</p><p id="Par40">According to respondents, spawning occurs mainly in the months of January and February (20 times). December was quoted 19 times, November and March 15 times and October 12 times. The months of April (9 times), May and September (6 times), June (5 times), July and August (4 times) were the least mentioned by fishermen in Peniche (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>The sardines spawning period according to the fishermen interviewed</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Sardines spawning period</th><th>Number of times cited by fishermen</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="2">
<italic>Months</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;January and February</td><td>20</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;December</td><td>19</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;November and March</td><td>15</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;October</td><td>12</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;April</td><td>9</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;May and September</td><td>6</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;June</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;July and August</td><td>4</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Seasons</italic>
</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Winter</td><td>12</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;Summer</td><td>8</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Time per year</italic>
</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;2 times</td><td>4</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;2&#x02013;3 times</td><td>4</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;3 times</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;3&#x02013;4 times</td><td>1</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par41">Other fishermen still specified the occurrence of spawning seasons. Along these lines, there were citations only for winter (<italic>N</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;12) and summer (<italic>N</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;8). There were also fishermen who reported the number of times (2&#x000d7; a year&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;4 citations, 2-3&#x000d7;&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;4 citations, 3&#x000d7;&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;3 citations and 3-4&#x000d7;&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1 citation) that they spawn each year (Table <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).</p><p id="Par42">The fishermen interviewed in Peniche provided some information from this part of the questionnaire below:<list list-type="order"><list-item><p id="Par43">
<italic>&#x0201c;The water becomes creamy and milky when the sardine spawns&#x0201d;.</italic>
</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par44">
<italic>"From 100% of the spawn, 90% live and 10% die".</italic>
</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par45">
<italic>&#x0201c;The sardine buries itself in the sand to spawn and escape predators&#x0201d;.</italic>
</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par46">
<italic>&#x0201c;The sardine goes to the rocks to scratch its belly when it is pregnant&#x0201d;.</italic>
</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par47">
<italic>&#x0201c;Outside the summer, the sardines are thin and run away&#x0201d;.</italic>
</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par48">
<italic>&#x0201c;The sardine passes its belly through the sand to spawn and leaves the eggs for the sea to take later&#x0201d;.</italic>
</p></list-item></list>
</p><p id="Par49">The informants mentioned the months of the years when the sardines accumulate (April to December). The months of June (56 times), July (75 times), August (68 times), September (47 times) and October (34 times) are the most remembered by the fishermen. (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Some local sayings were recorded in the interview as:<list list-type="order"><list-item><p id="Par50">"<italic>In July, the sardine already drips on bread</italic>".</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par51">
<italic>"The sardine grows earlier in the Algarve (Portugal) because of the warm waters".</italic>
</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par52">
<italic>&#x0201c;The more rain, the more the sardine gets fat&#x0201d;.</italic>
</p></list-item><list-item><p id="Par53">
<italic>"In June and July, they are fatter, just like the Christmas sardine".</italic>
</p></list-item></list>
<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>The period of fat accumulation of sardines according to the respondents</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Sardines accumulation season</th><th>Number of times cited by fishermen</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="2">
<italic>Months</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;June</td><td>56</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;July</td><td>75</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;August</td><td>68</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;September</td><td>47</td></tr><tr><td>&#x02003;October</td><td>34</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec14"><title>Trophic ecology: Predators and prey</title><p id="Par54">The LEK of the fishermen of the Port of Peniche showed important aspects of the sardine food chain, indicating the main predators and prey according to fishing experiences along the Portuguese coast. The main predators according to the fishermen (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>) are dolphins (<italic>atuninha</italic> or <italic>toninha</italic>), sharks and whales (generally), conger eel (<italic>safio</italic>) and yellowfin tuna (<italic>atum-albacora</italic>).<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table 4</label><caption><p>The correspondence between the Portuguese folk names of the <italic>S. pilchardus</italic> predators and the scientific classification (Linnaean)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Folk taxonomy</th><th>Scientific names (Linnaean)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Atuninha or toninha</td><td>
<italic>Delphinus delphis</italic> Linnaeus, 1758</td></tr><tr><td>Sharkes</td><td>Generally</td></tr><tr><td>Whales</td><td>Generally</td></tr><tr><td>Safio</td><td>
<italic>Conger conger</italic> (Linnaeus, 1758)</td></tr><tr><td>Albacora</td><td>
<italic>Thunnus albacares</italic> (Bonnaterre, 1788)</td></tr><tr><td>Robalo</td><td>
<italic>Dicentrarchus labrax</italic> (Linnaeus, 1758)</td></tr><tr><td>Cherne</td><td>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://researcharchive.calacademy.org/research/ichthyology/catalog/fishcatget.asp?genid=911"><italic>Polyprion</italic></ext-link>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://researcharchive.calacademy.org/research/ichthyology/catalog/fishcatget.asp?spid=19728"><italic>americanus</italic></ext-link> (Bloch &#x00026; Schneider, 1801)</td></tr><tr><td>Pargo</td><td>
<italic>Pagrus pagrus</italic> (Linnaeus, 1758)</td></tr><tr><td>Cavala</td><td>
<italic>Scomber japonicus</italic> Houttuyn, 1782</td></tr><tr><td>Espada-preto</td><td>
<italic>Aphanopus carbo</italic> Lowe, 1839</td></tr><tr><td>Polvo-comum</td><td>
<italic>Octopus vulgaris</italic> Cuvier, 1797</td></tr><tr><td>Goraz</td><td>
<italic>Pagellus bogaraveo</italic> (Br&#x000fc;nnich, 1768)</td></tr><tr><td>Pescada-branca</td><td>
<italic>Merluccius merluccius</italic> (Linneaus, 1758)</td></tr><tr><td>Abr&#x000f3;tea</td><td>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://researcharchive.calacademy.org/research/ichthyology/catalog/fishcatget.asp?genid=9303"><italic>Phycis</italic></ext-link>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://researcharchive.calacademy.org/research/ichthyology/catalog/fishcatget.asp?spid=12055"><italic>phycis</italic></ext-link> (Linnaeus, 1766)</td></tr><tr><td>Sarraj&#x000e3;o or serraj&#x000e3;o</td><td>
<italic>Sarda sarda</italic> (Bloch, 1793)</td></tr><tr><td>Raias</td><td>
<italic>Raja</italic> spp<italic>.</italic>
</td></tr><tr><td>Cantarilho</td><td>
<italic>Helicolenus dactylopterus</italic> (Delaroche, 1809)</td></tr><tr><td>Tamboril branco</td><td>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://researcharchive.calacademy.org/research/ichthyology/catalog/fishcatget.asp?genid=112"><italic>Lophius</italic></ext-link>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://researcharchive.calacademy.org/research/ichthyology/catalog/fishcatget.asp?spid=12993"><italic>piscatorius</italic></ext-link>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carl_Linnaeus">Linnaeus</ext-link>, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://researcharchive.calacademy.org/research/ichthyology/catalog/getref.asp?id=2787">1758</ext-link>
</td></tr><tr><td>Espadarte</td><td>
<italic>Xiphias gladius</italic> Linnaeus, 1758</td></tr><tr><td>Carapau</td><td>
<italic>Trachurus trachurus</italic> (Linnaeus, 1758)</td></tr><tr><td>Corvina</td><td>
<italic>Argyrosomus regius</italic> (Asso, 1801)</td></tr><tr><td>Sargo-leg&#x000ed;timo</td><td>
<italic>Diplodus sargus</italic> (Linnaeus, 1758)</td></tr><tr><td>Sarda</td><td>
<italic>Scomber scombrus</italic> Linnaeus, 1758</td></tr><tr><td>Faneca</td><td>
<italic>Trisopterus luscus</italic> (Linnaeus, 1758)</td></tr><tr><td>Mor&#x000e9;ia-preta</td><td>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://researcharchive.calacademy.org/research/ichthyology/catalog/fishcatget.asp?genid=111"><italic>Muraena</italic></ext-link>
<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://researcharchive.calacademy.org/research/ichthyology/catalog/fishcatget.asp?spid=58892"><italic>augusti</italic></ext-link> (Kaup, 1856)</td></tr><tr><td>Peixe-lua</td><td>
<italic>Mola mola</italic> (Linnaeus, 1758)</td></tr><tr><td>Tainhas</td><td>
<italic>Mugil</italic> spp.</td></tr><tr><td>Gaivota</td><td>
<italic>Larus michahellis</italic> J. F. Naumann, 1840</td></tr><tr><td>Albatroz</td><td>Generally</td></tr><tr><td>Birds</td><td>Generally</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par55">The fishermen also mentioned the following: sea bass (<italic>robalo</italic>), wreckfish (<italic>cherne-leg&#x000ed;timo</italic>), red porgy (<italic>pargo-leg&#x000ed;timo</italic>), chub mackerel (<italic>cavala</italic>), black scabbardfish (<italic>espada-preto</italic>), common octopus (<italic>polvo-comum</italic>), blackspot seabream (<italic>goraz</italic>), European hake (<italic>pescada-branca</italic>), forkbeard (<italic>abr&#x000f3;tea</italic>), Atlantic &#x0201c;bonito&#x0201d; (<italic>sarraj&#x000e3;o</italic> or <italic>serraj&#x000e3;o</italic>), raja rays nei (<italic>raias</italic>), blackbelly rosefish (<italic>cantarilho</italic>), monkfish (<italic>tamboril branco</italic>) and swordfish (<italic>espadarte</italic>).</p><p id="Par56">The following species were cited only once in the interviews: horse mackerel (<italic>carapau</italic>), meagre (<italic>corvina</italic>), white seabream (<italic>sargo-leg&#x000ed;timo</italic>), Atlantic mackerel (<italic>sarda</italic>), pouting (<italic>faneca</italic>), black moray eels (<italic>mor&#x000e9;ia-preta</italic>) and ocean sunfish (<italic>peixe-lua</italic>). The &#x0201c;<italic>tainha</italic>&#x0201d; was also mentioned in the study in a generalized way. Birds were generally cited as sardine predators. The yellow-legged gull (<italic>gaivota-de-patas-amarelas</italic>) and albatross (<italic>albatroz)</italic> and were also mentioned within this group.</p><p id="Par57">According to the ethnoecological data obtained from the fishing community have a diet (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>) based on plankton (<italic>N</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;56), algae called &#x0201c;limo&#x0201d; (<italic>N</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;30), small shrimp (<italic>N</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;13), &#x0201c;comedias&#x0201d; or &#x0201c;comedorias&#x0201d; (<italic>N</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;12), the spawn of other fish species (<italic>N</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;8) their own spawn (<italic>N</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;6). The fishermen also said that the sardine feed on krill (N&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;5), sediments accumulated after rainfall (N&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;5), sea impurities (N&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1), and remnants of other fish species (N&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1). &#x0201c;Comedorias&#x0201d; or &#x0201c;Comedias&#x0201d; in this study was defined by fishermen as a mixture of small fish, small prawns, the roe of other species of fish and sardine roe.<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>Number of citations of <italic>S. pilchardus</italic> food items by fishermen in the fishing community of Peniche, Portugal</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="13002_2017_181_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig>
</p></sec><sec id="Sec15"><title>Human uses, beliefs, and food taboos about European pilchard</title><p id="Par58">The sardine is greatly important to the fishermen interviewed. According to the majority of the interviewees (<italic>N</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;81), sardines have a high economic importance in the region of Peniche. Another 4 fishermen said that the importance of it is average and 2 other respondents have said that the importance is low. The summer (<italic>N</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;21) is cited as the time when the sardine is more important to the population of Peniche. The main uses of this pelagic species are as bait for another species (<italic>N</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;85 fishermen), in the canning industry (<italic>N</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;53), for one&#x02019;s own food (<italic>N</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;50) and the fish meal industries (<italic>N</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;10). Local commerce (N&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;2) and tourism (N&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;2) were also identified by Fishermen.</p><p id="Par59">Some informants (<italic>N</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;6) from this community mentioned sardine food taboos. Fish that are restricted were locally termed &#x0201c;raimoso&#x0201d;. A change in the restriction of this fish was observed over time. Twenty-three percent of fishermen said that the sardine was once &#x0201c;raimosa&#x0201d; in the past and 61 % of the fishermen said it was not &#x0201c;raimosa&#x0201d;. Two informants said that the sardine was little &#x0201c;raimosa&#x0201d; and that sick people could not eat it. There were 3 respondents who said that if the joint between the sardine skins is removed, it is no longer a restricted food. The fat found in sardines was recognized as a source of omega 3 by fishermen (<italic>N</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;9), aiding in the medical treatment of people with problems with cholesterol or in the treatment of heart disease patients.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec16"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="Sec17"><title>Folk taxonomy</title><p id="Par60">Local knowledge related to the naming of fish species is an inherent part of fishermen&#x02019;s trade and can be considered as proof of ability in these communities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. In Ericeira, Portugal, the local community also calls the juveniles of this species &#x0201c;petinga&#x0201d; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. In the Autonomous Region of the Azores in Portugal, the sardine is also called by the same vernacular name [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. The designation of sardines as &#x0201c;esquilha&#x0201d; (small fish), &#x0201c;sueste&#x0201d; and &#x0201c;real&#x0201d; are new to the scientific literature.</p></sec><sec id="Sec18"><title>Habitat, behaviour and migration</title><p id="Par61">According to the ethnoecological data extracted from the interviews, sardine is a predominantly coastal species and prefers sites near river mouths in the sea. The fishermen reported that sardines are distributed vertically, predominantly between the depths between 0 to 100&#x000a0;m. In the scientific literature, similar information was found indicating that this species is predominantly found in coastal shelf waters [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>] and prefers areas of great productivity near the mouths of rivers and estuaries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. In a study on the modelling of habitat suitability for juveniles of <italic>S. pilchardus</italic>, the results showed that sardines in the growth phase, in search of food and in the spawning process can be closely linked to sites that provide nutrient sources that increase productivity, such as local upwelling or river runoff [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. Di Natale and collaborators (2011) report in the IUCN Red List of Threatened Species 2011 that European pilchard can usually be found at depths of up to 100&#x000a0;m, reaching a lower depth limit of 180&#x000a0;m [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. The PECH Committee of the European Parliament for the sardine fishery shows that this species can range down to 150&#x000a0;m [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>], and in a study of sardine habitat to the west of Portugal showed that this species has a preference for waters with depths of up to 100&#x000a0;m [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>] (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>).<table-wrap id="Tab5"><label>Table 5</label><caption><p>Matrix cognition compared between the fishers&#x000b4; LEK and the scientific literature on the biology and ecology of European pilchard in Peniche, Portugal</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Topics</th><th>Fisherman&#x02019;s citation</th><th>Scientific literature</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>
<italic>Habitat</italic>
</td><td>&#x0201c;Coastal species and prefers sites near river mouths in the sea&#x0201d;.<break/>&#x0201c;Depths between 0 to 100&#x000a0;m&#x0201d;.</td><td>Coastal shelf waters [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>];<break/>Areas of great productivity near the mouths of rivers and estuaries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]; Area of local upwelling or river runoff [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>].<break/>Depths of up to 100&#x000a0;m, reaching a lower depth limit of 180&#x000a0;m [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]; Preference for waters with depths of up to 100&#x000a0;m [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>].</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Behaviour</italic>
</td><td>&#x0201c;Migration carried out in shoals&#x0201d;.<break/>&#x0201c;Ability to school as a way to ward off<break/>predators&#x0201d;.</td><td>Migratory behaviour, a high dispersal capacity and schooling<break/>behaviour similar to other pelagic fish [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>].<break/>Competitors or predators may change the direction or influence the<break/>intensity of these migrations in schooling [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>].</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Migration</italic>
</td><td>&#x0201c;Mainly Figueira da Foz and Algarve&#x0201d;.<break/>&#x0201c;P&#x000f3;voa de Varzim, Lisbon...&#x0201d;.</td><td>P&#x000f3;voa de Varzim, Figueira da Foz and Lisbon [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>];<break/>Algarve (Southern Portion of Portugal), this pelagic fish is found in greater quantities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>].</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Development</italic>
</td><td>&#x0201c;Rapid growth&#x0201d;.<break/>&#x0201c;Sardine reach sexual maturity at 1&#x000a0;year&#x0201d;; &#x0201c;from 3 to 7&#x000a0;months of age&#x0201d;.</td><td>Very fast growth rate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>].<break/>Matures early [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>].</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Spawning</italic>
</td><td>&#x0201c;The main months of spawning are also December, January and February&#x0201d;.<break/>&#x0201c;Spawn time can range from one to 8&#x000a0;months&#x0201d;.<break/>&#x0201c;In the winter, the sardine spawns more&#x0201d;;<break/>&#x0201c;The spawning occurs 2 to 4 times a year&#x0201d;.</td><td>October to April [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]; mainly between December and February along the Portuguese coast [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">57</xref>].<break/>Ranging from 3&#x000a0;months per year up to 8&#x000a0;months [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>].<break/>Sardines exhibit a prolonged spawning period during the year, with more pronounced spawning mainly in the colder months of the year [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>].</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Fat accumulation season</italic>
</td><td>&#x0201c;June through October&#x0201d;.</td><td>Late summer and autumn [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>].<break/>Late spring to autumn [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>].</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Predator</italic>
</td><td>&#x0201c;Mainly dolphins (atuninha or toninha), &#x0201c;sharks, whales, conger eel (safio) and yellowfin tuna (albacora)&#x0201d;; &#x0201c;yellow-legged gull (gaivota)&#x0201d;, albatross and other birds&#x0201d;.</td><td>Common dolphin (<italic>D. delphis</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>]; species of demersal fish, seabirds and marine mammals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>].</td></tr><tr><td>
<italic>Prey</italic>
</td><td>&#x0201c;Plankton, algae called &#x0201c;limo&#x0201d;, small shrimp, krill, the spawn of other fish species and their own spawn&#x0201d;.</td><td>Zooplankton as their energy source [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>]; Phytoplankton [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>]; fish eggs and crustaceans [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>].<break/>Sardines may predate on their own eggs in winter [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>].</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap>
</p><p id="Par62">European pilchard show migratory behaviour, a high dispersal capacity and schooling behaviour similar to other pelagic fish [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. In the present study, respondents exclusively reported this type of behaviour pattern. There was an account of a fisherman who referred to this ability to school as a way to ward off predators. Neilson and Perry (1990) show that the presence of competitors or predators may change the direction or influence the intensity of these migrations in schooling [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>] (Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>).</p><p id="Par63">In Portugal, the geographic distribution of this pelagic fish covers the entire coastline, Madeira Island and the Azores [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. However, sardine migration patterns are not yet well understood [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. There are indications of seasonal migrations along the Portuguese Coast [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>], and fifteen interviewees mentioned this information.</p><p id="Par64">According to acoustic campaigns performed in April and May of 2015 by the Portuguese Sea and Atmosphere Institute (IPMA), the abundance of sardines decreased from the north to the south of Portugal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. Regarding sardine migrations, it is known that they occur during the growth phase and towards the north coast of Spain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. During the collection of ethnoecological data in this part of the interview, it was observed that there was a variation in the responses among the interviewees. There were 18 fishermen who said that the sardines come from the north of Portugal and another 32 fishermen who say that they come from the north and the south of Portugal. This pattern of responses among fishermen reinforces the need to investigate and explore the studies on the migratory behaviour of sardines in the Iberian Peninsula.</p><p id="Par65">The European pilchard show migratory behaviour, a high dispersal capacity and schooling behaviour similar to other pelagic fish is distributed mainly near P&#x000f3;voa de Varzim and Figueira da Foz in the northwestern region of Portugal and near Peniche and Lisbon in the southwestern region [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. In the Algarve (Southern Portion of Portugal), this pelagic fish is found in greater quantities in Lagos, Portim&#x000e3;o and between Faro and Vila Real de Santo Ant&#x000f3;nio [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. According to the fishermen of Peniche&#x02019;s LEK, the Figueira da Foz region and the Algarve were cited the most frequently when asked about where the sardine is on the coast after passing through Peniche (Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>). The regions of Portim&#x000e3;o, S&#x000e3;o Pedro de Manoel, Olh&#x000e3;o, Tocha Beach and Sagres were identified by the fishermen in the southern portion of Portugal, which are included in or near the range of greater distribution found during the last acoustic campaign by the IPMA. None of the respondents specifically mentioned V. Real de Santo Ant&#x000f4;nio.</p></sec><sec id="Sec19"><title>Development of sardines</title><p id="Par66">The sardines show a very fast growth rate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>], growing to approximately 90% of their full size in 2&#x000a0;years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. Most fishermen in the community of Peniche (<italic>N</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;57) corroborate the scientific research in relation to rapid growth (Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>). In relation to the stages of development of this species, the fishermen only mentioned the egg phase as constituting the whole sardine life history. However, it is known that the larval stage is one of the development stages of this pelagic fish [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>].</p><p id="Par67">The European pilchard matures early [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">53</xref>]. Individuals are largely mature at 1&#x000a0;year of age, and all individuals are reproductively mature at 2&#x000a0;years of age [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">52</xref>]. In the present study, only 19 of fishermen said that sardine reach sexual maturity at 1&#x000a0;year of age and 44 of respondents mentioned that they are ready to reproduce from 3 to 7&#x000a0;months of age (Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec20"><title>Spawning and fat accumulation season</title><p id="Par68">Regarding reproduction, spawning of sardines occurs in batches of eggs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">54</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55">55</xref>]. The spawning of the Atlantic sardines occurs mainly on the western coast of Portugal between the Nazar&#x000e9; Canyon and the Minho river and in the Cantabrian Sea [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. Along the western Iberian coast, the spawning season of this pelagic species ranges from September to May, with spawning peaking in November to the north of Portugal from October to April [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">56</xref>]. Nunes and collaborators (2011) showed that the spawning peak occurs mainly between December and February along the Portuguese coast. According to fishermen from Peniche, the main months of spawning are also December, January and February. This period as a whole (from October to April) included the months most cited by the respondents (Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>).</p><p id="Par69">There is a variation in the duration of spawning times in the European waters of the North-East Atlantic, ranging from 3&#x000a0;months per year up to 8&#x000a0;months to the south and west of the Iberian Peninsula for large fish [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. A similar pattern was found in responses of our interviewees from Peniche, in which 72 fishermen said that the Atlantic sardine spawn time can range from one to 8&#x000a0;months (Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>).</p><p id="Par70">The winter was cited by 12 fishermen as being the season during which sardine spawn the most along the Portuguese Coast, and others (<italic>N</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;12) said that the spawning occurs 2 to 4 times a year. This point aligns with the scientific information that Atlantic sardines exhibit a prolonged spawning period during the year, with more pronounced spawning mainly in the colder months of the year [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>] (Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>).</p><p id="Par71">
<italic>S. pilchardus</italic> begins to store fat reserves before the breeding season between late summer and autumn [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>]. However, sardines can also accumulate fat from late spring to autumn [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. Most months cited by fishermen (June through October) fit the range of months for the accumulation of fat found in the scientific literature (Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec21"><title>Trophic ecology: Predator and prey</title><p id="Par72">The sardine is one of the main prey species of the common dolphin (<italic>D. delphis</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>]. It also serves as a food base for several species of demersal fish, seabirds and marine mammals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>]. These animals were also cited by fishermen during the interviews (Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>). The common dolphin stood out among all the other predators [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">59</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>]. Along the Portuguese Coast specifically, <italic>S. pilchardus</italic> was the most important species in the common dolphin diet in a study in which the stomach contents of this animal were examined during accidental catch and when they were stranded [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>]. It is also known that the common dolphin is an opportunistic predator of small epipelagic fish [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>], usually in places with moderate or high productivity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>] where sardines seek their energy sources [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. Given the current population decline in the sardine population on the Iberian coast [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>], attention should be given to the conservation of the common dolphin along the Portuguese coast, as this is one of the main predators of this clupeoid fish [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>].</p><p id="Par73">Sardines primarily seek zooplankton as their energy source [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">68</xref>]. Phytoplankton are also an integral part of the diet of this species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>]. Among the zooplankton, we should highlight copepods, decapods and cirripeds [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>], fish eggs and crustaceans [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>]. During the winter spawning months, sardines may exhibit cannibalistic behaviour in which they predate on their own eggs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">69</xref>]. Respondents describe a foraging behaviour similar to that reported in the investigative work on European sardine prey (Table <xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>). In general, it is also observed that fishermen in the fishing village of Peniche show sardines with migratory behaviour, high dispersal capacity, prey and school behaviour similar to other pelagic fish.</p></sec><sec id="Sec22"><title>Human uses, beliefs and food taboos about European pilchard</title><p id="Par74">The great majority of fishermen (<italic>N</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;81) in our ethnoecological study indicated the great economic importance of Iberian sardines, <italic>S. pilchardus,</italic> to the local community of Peniche. According to data from the Statistics Yearbook of the Central Region of 2015 made by Portugal&#x02019;s National Statistical Institute (INE), sardine fisheries officially yielded approximately 1223 tons of fish and 3517 thousand Euros for the municipality of Peniche in 2015 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. This fact proves the strength of this economic activity for this region.</p><p id="Par75">The summer was highlighted among the respondents as being the most important season for sardine fishing, local commerce and tourism. In this season, the sardines are in the fattening stage [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">58</xref>], and their fat content is high [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>]. The sardine in this period has a flavour and aroma that is more appreciated by the consumers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">71</xref>], which makes this species more economically profitable. When the fat content is low (2&#x02013;5%), this fish is less preferred by consumers and is normally sent to the canning and fish meal industries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">70</xref>]. In other seasons, sardines are primarily used as baitfish for demersal fishing or for the canning industry [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">72</xref>]. All sardine uses known to the scientific literature were also mentioned by the fishermen during the interviews.</p><p id="Par76">Taboos are unwritten social rules that regulate human behaviour and can both govern and affect human social life and serve to manage a local biological resource [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73">73</xref>]. In the local community of Peniche, there were no significant taboos or food aversions regarding sardines by fishermen (<italic>N</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;6). In local communities of the Amazon and in the Atlantic Forest in Brazil, taboos and aversions were also not associated with herbivorous fish or invertebrate eaters [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>]. According to Begossi (2004), this can be an adaptive strategy of local inhabitants to fish of higher trophic levels that can more easily accumulate toxins by eating a variety of prey (plants, invertebrates and other fish) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74">74</xref>]. This may be one of the reasons that there are few fishermen with taboos or sardine aversions. Another hypothesis is that these social rules may be losing strength over the years due to the exodus of fishermen to other economic activities, many of whom leave due to the low economic profitability of this profession and the difficulties imposed by European Union legislation on Portuguese artisanal fisheries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75">75</xref>].</p><p id="Par77">Regarding medicinal purposes, 9 fishermen indicated that sardine can treat high cholesterol levels and patients with cardiac problems. In a study about the fauna and the role of taboos in the conservation of animals in a forest reserve in southeastern Cameroon [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76">76</xref>], sardine (<italic>Sardina sp.</italic>) are used medicinally to treat cardiovascular diseases, which was also indicated in our survey by some fishermen (<italic>N</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;9). In the Sierra de Segura (Albacete, Spain), <italic>S. pilchardus</italic> is used for medicinal purposes in the treatment of sore feet and blisters in modern times and is marketed in the Spanish markets as food [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77">77</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="Sec23"><title>Conservation concerns and co-management</title><p id="Par78">There is a growing interest in LEK research in order to provide complementary data for several small-scale fishery species [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78">78</xref>]. With the difficulties and vulnerability of the marine ecosystem, LEK correctly acquired and aggregated at appropriate spatial-temporal scales becomes an important marine species conservation tool [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79">79</xref>]. The management of these coastal resources in fishing villages can also be better achieved by exploring data of this nature, which provide information on the ecology, behaviour and presence of these species in the environment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80">80</xref>].</p><p id="Par79">In the present work, we present LEK data on the ecology of sardines that corroborated scientific research. Other data generated in the interviews that were not validated by the scientific literature can be tested and incorporated into new hypotheses before carrying out a scientific study. According to Drew (2005), an analysis of the components of traditional ecological knowledge can reveal new information and thus contribute to the formulation of testable hypotheses in order to improve scientific infrastructure. Silva et al. (2014) also reveal the importance of generating new scientific questions through ethnoecological data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81">81</xref>]. The LEK about sardines acquired here may complement pre-existing scientific data. Due to the high cost and lack of resources for investments in traditional samplings, data of this nature become important for conservation practices and development [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR82">82</xref>].</p><p id="Par80">Given the low stock levels of the sardine population in the Iberian Region [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>], participation among the actors involved in fishing regulations should be carried out in an interactive manner [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR83">83</xref>]. Ecological knowledge data on spawning and the time of fat accumulation may provide researchers an additional source of data to better understand the reproductive behaviour of this species from the fishermen&#x02019;s point of view. Analysing this knowledge can contribute to a better understanding and reduction of internal conflicts between fishing managers, politicians and the community about the correct time for harvesting this species. In addition, LEK data acquired from these traditional communities are important because it reveals the most recent changes in environmental processes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84">84</xref>].</p><p id="Par81">The new data (trophic ecology, habitat and behaviour) that emerged during the interviews can serve as a starting point for research on the population structure of sardines. On a larger spatial scale, this kind of data, with adequate treatment, becomes important in the construction of management and conservation plans for sardines. Finally, we can note that the LEK of the sardines in Peniche should (and did) treat all stakeholders as being within a continuously adaptive framework [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85">85</xref>].</p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec24"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par82">The socioeconomic profile of the fishermen of Peniche was described in this ethnoecological research. Respondents provided detailed informal data on the taxonomy, ecology and biology of <italic>Sardina pilchardus</italic>. This informal knowledge showed agreements with the scientific literature. We suggest the use of non-corresponding data with formal knowledge to aid in the construction of testable hypotheses for new investigative work on sardines. The data generated here can be used to try to improve the understanding of the fishermen&#x02019;s knowledge of the European pilchard by managers and conservationists. This approach requires the use of an adaptive framework, which contributes to an improvement in the relations between the actors involved with the resource. The food taboos and social rules about European pilchard were not relevant to conservation in this community. This species, which is mainly used as baitfish for other fishes and in the canning and fish meal industries, provides a great economic value for the fishing community studied here.</p><p id="Par83">Finally, our results highlighted that artisanal fishermen from Peniche show ethnoecological data about European pilchard that can support scientific knowledge, as well as collaborate with future initiatives in pursuit of viable conservation goals for sardines on the coast of Portugal.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Additional files</title><sec id="Sec25"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="13002_2017_181_MOESM1_ESM.docx"><label>Additional file 1:</label><caption><p>Statement of Informed Consent (IC) and agreement to participate in the research. (DOCX 16 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM2"><media xlink:href="13002_2017_181_MOESM2_ESM.docx"><label>Additional file 2:</label><caption><p>Script of interview. (DOCX 14 kb)</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><glossary><title>Abbreviations</title><def-list><def-item><term>FAO</term><def><p id="Par5">Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IC</term><def><p id="Par6">Statement of Informed Consent</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>INE</term><def><p id="Par7">Portugal&#x02019;s National Statistical Institute</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IPMA</term><def><p id="Par8">Portuguese Sea and Atmosphere Institute</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>IUCN</term><def><p id="Par9">International Union for Conservation of Nature</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>LEK</term><def><p id="Par10">local ecological knowledge</p></def></def-item><def-item><term>MNR</term><def><p id="Par11">Berlengas Marine Natural Reserve</p></def></def-item></def-list></glossary><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Electronic supplementary material</bold></p><p>The online version of this article (10.1186/s13002-017-0181-8) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p></fn></fn-group><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We are also grateful to Henrique M. F. de Oliveira and Bruno Zucherato who collaborated in the production of this paper. We also thank the members of the fishing community of Peniche who took part in this study by providing interviews. A special thank you goes to Dr. Paulo Maranh&#x000e3;o and Jo&#x000e3;o G. Carneiro for the initial support given to the data collection process in Peniche.</p><sec id="FPar1"><title>Funding</title><p id="Par84">The fieldwork was sponsored by the CAPES Foundation - Ministry of Education of Brazil (BEX: 8926/13&#x02013;1).</p></sec><sec id="FPar2"><title>Availability of data and materials</title><p id="Par85">Not applicable.</p></sec></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Authors&#x02019; contributions</title><p>HOB &#x02013; Collected and analyzed data and drafted the manuscript; MAP and UMA &#x02013; Reviewed the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><sec id="FPar3"><title>Ethics approval and consent to participate</title><p id="Par86">The objectives of the work and the statement of informed consent to participate in the research were provided to the fishermen through the Statement of Informed Consent (IC) [see Additional file <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">1</xref>]. No further Research Ethics Committee approval was required in Portugal.</p></sec><sec id="FPar4"><title>Consent for publication</title><p id="Par87">Not applicable.</p></sec><sec id="FPar5"><title>Competing interests</title><p id="Par88">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p></sec><sec id="FPar6"><title>Publisher&#x02019;s Note</title><p id="Par89">Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></sec></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lotze</surname><given-names>HK</given-names></name><name><surname>Lenihan</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Bourque</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bradbury</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooke</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name><name><surname>Kay</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Depletion, degradation, and recovery potential of estuaries and coastal seas</article-title><source>Science</source><year>2006</year><volume>312</volume><fpage>1806</fpage><lpage>1809</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1128035</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16794081?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16794081</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pauly</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Christensen</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Gu&#x000e9;nette</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Pitcher</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Sumaila</surname><given-names>UR</given-names></name><name><surname>Walters</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Towards sustainability in world fisheries</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>2002</year><volume>418</volume><fpage>689</fpage><lpage>695</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature01017</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 12167876?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12167876</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Teixeira</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><name><surname>Gamito</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Leit&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Murta</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Cabral</surname><given-names>HN</given-names></name><name><surname>Erzini</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Environmental influence on commercial fishery landings of small pelagic fish in Portugal</article-title><source>Reg Environ Chang</source><year>2016</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>709</fpage><lpage>716</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10113-015-0786-1</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cury</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Bakun</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Crawford</surname><given-names>RJM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jarre</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Qui&#x000f1;ones</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Shannon</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Small pelagics in upwelling systems: patterns of interaction and structural changes in &#x0201c;wasp-waist&#x0201d; ecosystems</article-title><source>ICES J Mar Sci</source><year>2000</year><volume>57</volume><fpage>603</fpage><lpage>618</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/jmsc.2000.0712</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Checkley D, Alheit J, Oozeki Y, Roy C. Climate change and small pelagic fish [Internet]. Cambridge University Press Cambridge; 2009 [cited 2017 Feb 27] Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Juergen_Alheit2/publication/266567677_Climate_Change_and_Small_Pelagic_Fish/links/54b5057c0cf26833efd05664.pdf">https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Juergen_Alheit2/publication/266567677_Climate_Change_and_Small_Pelagic_Fish/links/54b5057c0cf26833efd05664.pdf</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Atarhouch</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>R&#x000fc;ber</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonzalez</surname><given-names>EG</given-names></name><name><surname>Albert</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rami</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Dakkak</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Signature of an early genetic bottleneck in a population of Moroccan sardines (Sardina Pilchardus)</article-title><source>Mol Phylogenet Evol</source><year>2006</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>373</fpage><lpage>383</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ympev.2005.08.003</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 16216537?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16216537</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">INE. Statistical Yearbook of Centro Region 2015. Statistics Portugal INE, I. P. Anu&#x000e1;rio Estat&#x000ed;stico da Regi&#x000e3;o Centro 2015 [Internet]. Lisboa, Portugal: Instituto Nacional de Estat&#x000ed;stica, I.P; 2015 [cited 2016 Nov 16] Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.ine.pt/ngt_server/attachfileu.jsp?look_parentBoui=279965601&#x00026;att_display=n&#x00026;att_download=y">https://www.ine.pt/ngt_server/attachfileu.jsp?look_parentBoui=279965601&#x00026;att_display=n&#x00026;att_download=y</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McClanahan</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Maina</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Davies</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Perceptions of resource users and managers towards fisheries management options in Kenyan coral reefs</article-title><source>Fish Manag Ecol</source><year>2005</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>105</fpage><lpage>112</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2400.2004.00431.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jacquet</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Pauly</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Funding priorities: big barriers to small-scale fisheries</article-title><source>Conserv Biol</source><year>2008</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>832</fpage><lpage>835</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1523-1739.2008.00978.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 18637910?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18637910</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fiallo</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jacobson</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Local communities and protected areas: attitudes of rural residents towards conservation and Machalilla National Park</article-title><source>Ecuador Environ Conserv</source><year>1995</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>241</fpage><lpage>249</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S037689290001064X</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>de Boer</surname><given-names>WF</given-names></name><name><surname>Baquete</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Natural resource use, crop damage and attitudes of rural people in the vicinity of the Maputo elephant reserve</article-title><source>Mozambique Environ Conserv</source><year>1998</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>208</fpage><lpage>218</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0376892998000265</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pitt</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Baldwin</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Lipscomb</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawley</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Allard-Keese</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>The missing wetlands: using local ecological knowledge to find cryptic ecosystems</article-title><source>Biodivers Conserv</source><year>2012</year><volume>21</volume><fpage>51</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10531-011-0160-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Drew</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Use of traditional ecological knowledge in marine conservation</article-title><source>Conserv Biol</source><year>2005</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1286</fpage><lpage>1293</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1523-1739.2005.00158.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Yli-Pelkonen V, Kohl J. The role of local ecological knowledge in sustainable urban planning: perspectives from Finland. Sustain Sci Pract Policy. 2005;1:1. Available at SSRN:&#x000a0;<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://ssrn.com/abstract=2384833">https://ssrn.com/abstract=2384833</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pinto</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name><name><surname>J da S</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>RRN</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ethnotaxonomical considerations and usage of ichthyofauna in a fishing community in Cear&#x000e1; State, Northeast Brazil</article-title><source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source><year>2013</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>17</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-4269-9-17</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 23497491?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23497491</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Marques JGW. Pescando pescadores: Ci&#x000ea;ncia e Etnoci&#x000ea;ncia em uma Perspectiva Ecol&#x000f3;gica. S&#x000e3;o Paulo USPNUPAUB. 2001;258p.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Alves RRN, Souto WMS. Ethnozoology: a brief introduction. Ethnobiol Conserv. [Internet]. 2015 [cited 2017 Mar 24];4 Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ethnobioconservation.com/index.php/ebc/article/view/63">http://www.ethnobioconservation.com/index.php/ebc/article/view/63</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Begossi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Salivonchyk</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Lopes</surname><given-names>PFM</given-names></name><name><surname>Silvano</surname><given-names>RAM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fishers&#x02019; knowledge on the coast of Brazil</article-title><source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomed</source><year>2016</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>20</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/s13002-016-0091-1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 27245047?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27245047</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marques</surname><given-names>JGW</given-names></name></person-group><source>Pescando Pescadores. Etnoecologia Abrangente no Baixo S&#x000e3;o Francisco</source><year>1995</year><publisher-loc>NUPAUB/USP</publisher-loc><publisher-name>S&#x000e3;o Paulo</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR20"><label>20.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silvano</surname><given-names>RAM</given-names></name><name><surname>Begossi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Local knowledge on a cosmopolitan fish: Ethnoecology of Pomatomus Saltatrix (Pomatomidae) in Brazil and Australia</article-title><source>Fish Res</source><year>2005</year><volume>71</volume><fpage>43</fpage><lpage>59</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fishres.2004.07.007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR21"><label>21.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Monteiro</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#x000e9;braud</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chafsey</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Poeta</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Igrejas</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>How different is the proteome of the extended spectrum &#x003b2;-lactamase producing Escherichia Coli strains from seagulls of the Berlengas natural reserve of Portugal</article-title><source>J Proteome</source><year>2016</year><volume>145</volume><fpage>167</fpage><lpage>176</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jprot.2016.04.032</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR22"><label>22.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mendes</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Marques</surname><given-names>SC</given-names></name><name><surname>Azeiteiro</surname><given-names>UM</given-names></name><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez-G&#x000f3;mez</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Galindo Villardon</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Maranh&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Zooplankton distribution in a marine protected area: the Berlengas natural reserve (western coast of Portugal)</article-title><source>Fresenius Env Bull</source><year>2011</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>496</fpage><lpage>505</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR23"><label>23.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Jacinto D, Cruz T, Silva T, Castro JJ. Management of the stalked barnacle (Pollicipes pollicipes) fishery in the Berlengas nature reserve (Portugal): evaluation of bag and size limit regulation measures. Sci Mar. 2011;75:439&#x02013;445.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR24"><label>24.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Viegas V, Azeiteiro UM, Alves F. Fostering Resilience Among Artisanal Fishers in Peniche (Portugal): An Exploratory Study. Clim. Change Adapt. Resil. Hazards [Internet]. Springer; 2016 [cited 2017 Jan 17]. p. 305&#x02013;327. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-319-39880-8_19">http://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1007/978-3-319-39880-8_19</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR25"><label>25.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>AJFR</given-names></name><name><surname>Azeiteiro</surname><given-names>UM</given-names></name><name><surname>F de</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of knowledge and the way of life of local inhabitants in sustainable development: an exploratory study on the impact of the natural Reserve of the Berlengas Islands (Portugal) on the life of its local fishing community</article-title><source>Rev Gest Costeira Integrada</source><year>2012</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>429</fpage><lpage>436</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5894/rgci321</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR26"><label>26.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Queiroga H, Le&#x000e3;o F, Coutinho M. Candidatura das Berlengas a Reserva da Biosfera da UNESCO." Vers&#x000e3;o para consulta p&#x000fa;blica. IDAD, Aveiro. 2008 [cited 2015 Apr 6]; Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cm-peniche.pt/_uploads/PDF_Berlengas_Laboratorio/Dossier_Berlengas_Cons_publica.pdf">http://www.cm-peniche.pt/_uploads/PDF_Berlengas_Laboratorio/Dossier_Berlengas_Cons_publica.pdf</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR27"><label>27.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Newing H. Conducting research in conservation: social science methods and practice: Routledge; 2010.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR28"><label>28.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Albuquerque</surname><given-names>UP</given-names></name><name><surname>Lucena</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Cunha</surname><given-names>LV</given-names></name><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>RRN</given-names></name></person-group><source>Methods and techniques in ethnobiology and ethnoecology</source><year>2014</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR29"><label>29.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brook</surname><given-names>RK</given-names></name><name><surname>McLachlan</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Trends and prospects for local knowledge in ecological and conservation research and monitoring</article-title><source>Biodivers Conserv</source><year>2008</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>3501</fpage><lpage>3512</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10531-008-9445-x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR30"><label>30.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Bunce L, Townsley P, Pomeroy R, Pollnac R, others. Socioeconomic manual for coral reef management. Australian Institute of Marine Science. 2000 [cited 2017 Jan 18]; Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.socmon.org/pdf/GCRMN_Manual.pdf">http://www.socmon.org/pdf/GCRMN_Manual.pdf</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR31"><label>31.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Marques JGW. Aspectos ecol&#x000f3;gicos na etnoecologia dos pescadores do complexo estuarino-lagunar Munda&#x000fa;-Manguaba, Alagoas. PhD thesis. [Campinas, S&#x000e3;o Paulo, Brazil]: Universidade Estadual de Campinas, Biosciences Institute; 1991.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR32"><label>32.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>History and significance of the emic/etic distinction</article-title><source>Annu Rev Anthropol</source><year>1976</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>329</fpage><lpage>350</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.an.05.100176.001553</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR33"><label>33.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">FAO. Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations: Fisheries and aquaculture department nations. [Internet]. 2017 [cited. Nov 22. 2016; Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fao.org/home/en/">http://www.fao.org/home/en/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR34"><label>34.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">IUCN. The International Union for Conservation of Nature and Natural Resources Red List of Threatened Species. Version 2016.3. [Internet]. 2016 [cited. Feb 2. 2017; Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.iucnredlist.org">http://www.iucnredlist.org</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR35"><label>35.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Fishbase. Froese, R. e D. Pauly. Editors. 2016. FishBase. World Wide Web electronic publication. Version (10/2016). [Internet]. 2016 [cited. Sep 4. 2015; Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.fishbase.org/">www.fishbase.org</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR36"><label>36.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Development Core Team R. R: A language and environment for statistical computing. R version 3.3.2 (Sincere Pumpkin Patch). 2016 [cited 2016 Nov 28]; Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://cran.r-project.org/src/base/R-3/">https://cran.r-project.org/src/base/R-3/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR37"><label>37.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Masski</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Ait</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fish names variability traces the geo-historical dynamics of Moroccan fishermen communities</article-title><source>J Ecol Anthropol</source><year>2016</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>8</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR38"><label>38.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vale</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Sampayo</surname><given-names>MAM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Domoic acid in Portuguese shellfish and fish</article-title><source>Toxicon</source><year>2001</year><volume>39</volume><fpage>893</fpage><lpage>904</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0041-0101(00)00229-4</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 11137551?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11137551</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR39"><label>39.</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brito</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><source>Catalogo de los pesces de las Islas Canarias</source><year>1991</year><publisher-loc>Tenerife, Spain</publisher-loc><publisher-name>La Laguna</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR40"><label>40.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Di Natale A, Molinari A, Oral M, Kada O, Golani D. Sardina pilchardus. The IUCN Red List of Threatened Species 2011: e.T198580A9039349 [Internet]. 2011 [cited. Aug 12. 2017; Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.iucnredlist.org/details/198580/3">http://www.iucnredlist.org/details/198580/3</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR41"><label>41.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Silva A, Moreno A, Riveiro I, Santos B, Pita C, Garcia Rodrigues J, et al. Research for pech committee-sardine fisheries: resource assessment and social and economic situation. 2015 [cited 2017 Feb 8]; Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00300/41109/">http://archimer.ifremer.fr/doc/00300/41109/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR42"><label>42.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">IPMA. Instituto Portugu&#x000ea;s do Mar e da Atmosfera. Sardinha &#x02013; Sardina pilchardus [Internet]. 2016 [cited 2016 Dec 21] Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ipma.pt/pt/pescas/recursos/sardinha/?print=true">http://www.ipma.pt/pt/pescas/recursos/sardinha/?print=true</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR43"><label>43.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zwolinski</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name><surname>Quintino</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Stratoudakis</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sardine potential habitat and environmental forcing off western Portugal</article-title><source>ICES J Mar Sci</source><year>2010</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>1553</fpage><lpage>1564</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/icesjms/fsq068</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR44"><label>44.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giannoulaki</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pyrounaki</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Liorzou</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Leonori</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Valavanis</surname><given-names>VD</given-names></name><name><surname>Tsagarakis</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Habitat suitability modelling for sardine juveniles (Sardina Pilchardus) in the Mediterranean Sea</article-title><source>Fish Oceanogr</source><year>2011</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>367</fpage><lpage>382</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2419.2011.00590.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR45"><label>45.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jemaa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Bacha</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Khalaf</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Dessailly</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Rabhi</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Amara</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>What can otolith shape analysis tell us about population structure of the European sardine, Sardina Pilchardus, from Atlantic and Mediterranean waters</article-title><source>J Sea Res</source><year>2015</year><volume>96</volume><fpage>11</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.seares.2014.11.002</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR46"><label>46.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Neilson</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>RI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diel vertical migrations of marine fishes: an obligate or facultative process?</article-title><source>Adv Mar Biol</source><year>1990</year><volume>26</volume><fpage>115</fpage><lpage>168</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0065-2881(08)60200-X</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR47"><label>47.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Parrish</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Serra</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Grant</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The monotypic sardines, Sardina and Sardinops: their taxonomy, distribution, stock structure, and zoogeography</article-title><source>Can J Fish Aquat Sci</source><year>1989</year><volume>46</volume><fpage>2019</fpage><lpage>2036</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/f89-251</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR48"><label>48.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Monteiro PV. The purse seine fishing of sardine in Portuguese waters: a difficult compromise between fish stock sustainability and fishing effort. Rev Fish Sci Aquac. 2017:1&#x02013;12.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR49"><label>49.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">IPMA. Relat&#x000f3;rio de campanha Ac&#x000fa;stica PELAGO15 (Abr/Mai. 2015). Instituto Portugu&#x000ea;s do Mar e da Atmosfera. [Internet]. 2015 [cited 2017 Feb 13] Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ipma.pt/export/sites/ipma/bin/docs/relatorios/pescas.mar/CampPELAGOS-2015.pdf">http://www.ipma.pt/export/sites/ipma/bin/docs/relatorios/pescas.mar/CampPELAGOS-2015.pdf</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR50"><label>50.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Carrera</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Mass&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Uriarte</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Geographic variability of sardine growth across the northeastern Atlantic and the Mediterranean Sea</article-title><source>Fish Res</source><year>2008</year><volume>90</volume><fpage>56</fpage><lpage>69</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fishres.2007.09.011</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR51"><label>51.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Fogarty MJ, Moksness E. Fish reproductive biology: implications for assessment and management: John Wiley &#x00026; Sons; 2016.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR52"><label>52.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Caneco</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Pestana</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Porteiro</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Carrera</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Temporal and geographic variability of sardine maturity at length in the northeastern Atlantic and the western Mediterranean</article-title><source>ICES J Mar Sci</source><year>2006</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>663</fpage><lpage>676</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.icesjms.2006.01.005</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR53"><label>53.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blaxter</surname><given-names>JHS</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunter</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The biology of the clupeoid fishes</article-title><source>Adv Mar Biol</source><year>1982</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>223</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0065-2881(08)60140-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR54"><label>54.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zwolinski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Stratoudakis</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Sares</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Intra-annual variation in the batch fecundity of sardine off Portugal</article-title><source>J Fish Biol</source><year>2001</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>1633</fpage><lpage>1645</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1095-8649.2001.tb02318.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR55"><label>55.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ganias</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Somarakis</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Machias</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Theodorou</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pattern of oocyte development and batch fecundity in the Mediterranean sardine</article-title><source>Fish Res</source><year>2004</year><volume>67</volume><fpage>13</fpage><lpage>23</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fishres.2003.08.008</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR56"><label>56.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Garc&#x000ed;a-Garc&#x000ed;a LM, Ruiz-Villarreal M, Bernal M. A biophysical model for simulating early life stages of sardine in the Iberian Atlantic stock. Fish Res 2016;173, Part 3:250&#x02013;272.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR57"><label>57.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nunes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ganias</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The use of hepatic and somatic indices and histological information to characterize the reproductive dynamics of Atlantic sardine Sardina Pilchardus from the Portuguese coast</article-title><source>Mar Coast Fish</source><year>2011</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>127</fpage><lpage>144</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/19425120.2011.556911</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR58"><label>58.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Garrido S, Rosa R, Ben-Hamadou R, Cunha ME, Ch&#x000ed;charo MA, Lingen CD van der. Spatio-temporal variability in fatty acid trophic biomarkers in stomach contents and muscle of Iberian sardine (Sardina Pilchardus) and its relationship with spawning. Mar Biol 2008;154:1053.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR59"><label>59.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><name><surname>Saavedra</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Pierce</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantifying the predation on sardine and hake by cetaceans in the Atlantic waters of the Iberian peninsula. Deep Sea res. Part II top. Stud</article-title><source>Oceanography</source><year>2014</year><volume>106</volume><fpage>232</fpage><lpage>244</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR60"><label>60.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Certain</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Masse</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Canneyt</surname><given-names>O</given-names></name><name><surname>Petitgas</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Doremus</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Investigating the coupling between small pelagic fish and marine top predators using data collected from ecosystem-based surveys</article-title><source>Mar Ecol-Prog Ser</source><year>2011</year><volume>422</volume><fpage>23</fpage><lpage>39</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3354/meps08932</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR61"><label>61.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ca&#x000f1;adas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hammond</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Abundance and habitat preferences of the short-beaked common dolphin Delphinus Delphis in the southwestern Mediterranean: implications for conservation</article-title><source>Endanger Species Res</source><year>2008</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>309</fpage><lpage>331</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3354/esr00073</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR62"><label>62.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diet of common dolphins, Delphinus Delphis, off the Portuguese continental coast</article-title><source>J Mar Biol Assoc U K</source><year>1999</year><volume>79</volume><fpage>531</fpage><lpage>540</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0025315498000654</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR63"><label>63.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Preciado</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Velasco</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Olaso</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of pelagic fish as forage for the demersal fish community in the southern Bay of Biscay</article-title><source>J Mar Syst</source><year>2008</year><volume>72</volume><fpage>407</fpage><lpage>417</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jmarsys.2007.04.007</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR64"><label>64.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Garrido</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Ben-Hamadou</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>PB</given-names></name><name><surname>Cunha</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Ch&#x000ed;charo</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>van der Lingen</surname><given-names>CD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diet and feeding intensity of sardine Sardina Pilchardus: correlation with satellite-derived chlorophyll data</article-title><source>Mar Ecol Prog Ser</source><year>2008</year><volume>354</volume><fpage>245</fpage><lpage>256</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3354/meps07201</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR65"><label>65.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jefferson</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name><name><surname>Fertl</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Bola&#x000f1;os-Jim&#x000e9;nez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Zerbini</surname><given-names>AN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Distribution of common dolphins Delphinus spp. in the western Atlantic Ocean: a critical re-examination</article-title><source>Mar Biol</source><year>2009</year><volume>156</volume><fpage>1109</fpage><lpage>1124</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00227-009-1152-y</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR66"><label>66.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">ICES. ICES Advice on fishing opportunities, catch, and effort Bay of Biscay and the Iberian Coast Ecoregion. 7.3.27 Sardine (Sardina pilchardus) in Divisions VIIIc and IXa (Cantabrian Sea, Atlantic Iberian Waters) [Internet]. 2016. Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ices.dk/sites/pub/Publication%20Reports/Advice/2015/2015/sar-soth.pdf">http://www.ices.dk/sites/pub/Publication%20Reports/Advice/2015/2015/sar-soth.pdf</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR67"><label>67.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moura</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Sillero</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Rodrigues</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Common dolphin (Delphinus Delphis) habitat preferences using data from two platforms of opportunity</article-title><source>Acta Oecol</source><year>2012</year><volume>38</volume><fpage>24</fpage><lpage>32</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.actao.2011.08.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR68"><label>68.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Garrido S, Van der Lingen CD. Feeding Biology and Ecology. GaniasK Ed Biol. Ecol. Sardines Anchovies. 2014. p. 122.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR69"><label>69.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Costalago</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Garrido</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Palomera</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparison of the feeding apparatus and diet of European sardines Sardina Pilchardus of Atlantic and Mediterranean waters: ecological implications</article-title><source>J Fish Biol</source><year>2015</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>1348</fpage><lpage>1362</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/jfb.12645</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 25846858?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">25846858</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR70"><label>70.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mendes</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Vital</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Bandarra</surname><given-names>NM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of a vacuum-leaching technology on the proteins and lipids of lean sardine (Sardina Pilchardus) mince</article-title><source>Eur Food Res Technol</source><year>2000</year><volume>212</volume><fpage>31</fpage><lpage>38</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s002170000185</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR71"><label>71.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zlatanos</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Laskaridis</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Seasonal variation in the fatty acid composition of three Mediterranean fish&#x02013;sardine (Sardina Pilchardus), anchovy (Engraulis Encrasicholus) and picarel (Spicara Smaris)</article-title><source>Food Chem</source><year>2007</year><volume>103</volume><fpage>725</fpage><lpage>728</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.foodchem.2006.09.013</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR72"><label>72.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">V&#x000e1;zquez-Rowe I, Villanueva-Rey P, Hospido A, Moreira MT, Feijoo G, others. Environmental sustainability pathways based on a single raw material: European pilchard (Sardina pilchardus) in NW Spain. Proc. 9th Int. Conf. Life Cycle Assess. Agri-Food Sect. LCA Food 2014 San Franc. Calif. USA 8&#x02013;10 Oct. 2014. American Center for Life Cycle Assessment; 2014. p. 1462&#x02013;1470.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR73"><label>73.</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Colding J, Folke C. The relations among threatened species, their protection, and taboos. Conserv. Ecol. [Internet]. 1997 [cited 2017 Feb 18];1 Available from: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ecologyandsociety.org/vol1/iss1/art6/">http://www.ecologyandsociety.org/vol1/iss1/art6/</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="CR74"><label>74.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Begossi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanazaki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Ramos</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Food chain and the reasons for fish food taboos among Amazonian and Atlantic Forest fishers (brazil)</article-title><source>Ecol Appl</source><year>2004</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>1334</fpage><lpage>1343</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1890/03-5072</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR75"><label>75.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Santos</surname><given-names>MPN</given-names></name><name><surname>Seixas</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Aggio</surname><given-names>RBM</given-names></name><name><surname>Hanazaki</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schiavetti</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>A Pesca enquanto Atividade Humana: Pesca Artesanal e Sustentabilidade</article-title><source>Rev Gest Costeira Integrada</source><year>2012</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>405</fpage><lpage>427</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5894/rgci385</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR76"><label>76.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bobo</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Aghomo</surname><given-names>FFM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ntumwel</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Wildlife use and the role of taboos in the conservation of wildlife around the Nkwende Hills Forest reserve South-west Cameroon</article-title><source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomedicine</source><year>2015</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>2</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-4269-11-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR77"><label>77.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Vallejo</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name><name><surname>Gonz&#x000e1;lez</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Fish-based remedies in Spanish ethnomedicine: a review from a historical perspective</article-title><source>J Ethnobiol Ethnomedicine</source><year>2014</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>37</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1746-4269-10-37</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR78"><label>78.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silvano</surname><given-names>RAM</given-names></name><name><surname>Valbo-J&#x000f8;rgensen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Beyond fishermen&#x02019;s tales: contributions of fishers&#x02019; local ecological knowledge to fish ecology and fisheries management</article-title><source>Environ Dev Sustain</source><year>2008</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>657</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10668-008-9149-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR79"><label>79.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beaudreau</surname><given-names>AH</given-names></name><name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Advancing the use of local ecological knowledge for assessing data-poor species in coastal ecosystems</article-title><source>Ecol Appl</source><year>2014</year><volume>24</volume><fpage>244</fpage><lpage>256</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1890/13-0817.1</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 24689138?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24689138</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR80"><label>80.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rasalato</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Maginnity</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Brunnschweiler</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Using local ecological knowledge to identify shark river habitats in Fiji (South Pacific)</article-title><source>Environ Conserv</source><year>2010</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>90</fpage><lpage>97</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0376892910000317</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR81"><label>81.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>JS</given-names></name><name><surname>El-Deir</surname><given-names>ACA</given-names></name><name><surname>Moura</surname><given-names>GJB</given-names></name><name><surname>Alves</surname><given-names>RRN</given-names></name><name><surname>Albuquerque</surname><given-names>UP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Traditional ecological knowledge about dietary and reproductive characteristics of Tupinambis Merianae and Hoplias Malabaricus in semiarid northeastern Brazil</article-title><source>Hum Ecol</source><year>2014</year><volume>42</volume><fpage>901</fpage><lpage>911</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10745-014-9698-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR82"><label>82.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Anad&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Gim&#x000e9;nez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Ballestar</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>P&#x000e9;rez</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Evaluation of local ecological knowledge as a method for collecting extensive data on animal abundance</article-title><source>Conserv Biol</source><year>2009</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>617</fpage><lpage>625</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1523-1739.2008.01145.x</pub-id><?supplied-pmid 19183211?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19183211</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR83"><label>83.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Heck</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Dearden</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Carver</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Developing MPA performance indicators with local stakeholders&#x02019; input in the Pacific rim National Park Reserve</article-title><source>Canada Biodivers Conserv</source><year>2011</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>895</fpage><lpage>911</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10531-011-0002-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR84"><label>84.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cosham</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Beazley</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><name><surname>McCarthy</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Local knowledge of distribution of European green crab (Carcinus Maenas) in southern Nova Scotian coastal waters</article-title><source>Hum Ecol</source><year>2016</year><volume>44</volume><fpage>409</fpage><lpage>424</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10745-016-9825-x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR85"><label>85.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Raakj&#x000e6;r</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Degnbol</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Local ecological knowledge and practical fisheries management in the tropics: a policy brief</article-title><source>Mar Policy</source><year>2006</year><volume>30</volume><fpage>794</fpage><lpage>801</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.marpol.2006.02.004</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>