<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Parasites and diseases have the potential to reduce host fitness by their consumption of host resources. The effect of endoparasites on host fitness has often focused on survival or lifespan of the host and relatively less attention has been given to the influence on host reproduction (see [
  <a rid="pone.0125773.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0125773.ref001">1</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0125773.ref003" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0125773.ref003">3</a>]). If the strategy of the parasite does not utilize the reproductive stage of a host to its own benefit (e.g. transmission), the parasite may evolve mechanisms to limit host reproduction [
  <a rid="pone.0125773.ref003" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0125773.ref003">3</a>]. A parasite may achieve this by consuming energy that the host would otherwise have allocated to reproduction [
  <a rid="pone.0125773.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0125773.ref001">1</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0125773.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0125773.ref004">4</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0125773.ref005" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0125773.ref005">5</a>]. Parasite-induced reduction in host reproduction may be particularly favoured by parasites with a predominantly horizontal transmission (i.e. between individual hosts within a generation), allowing parasites to maximize the amount of energy consumed from the host without severely compromising host survival [
  <a rid="pone.0125773.ref003" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0125773.ref003">3</a>]. By minimizing the negative effect on host survival, parasites may also allow time and opportunity for the host to come into contact with potential new hosts before it dies.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The parasite may have an immediate effect on host reproduction in a given year or season (e.g. [
  <a rid="pone.0125773.ref006" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0125773.ref006">6</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0125773.ref007" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0125773.ref007">7</a>]). Alternatively, there may be a cumulative effect of parasites on the host’s lifetime reproductive success (e.g. [
  <a rid="pone.0125773.ref008" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0125773.ref008">8</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0125773.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0125773.ref009">9</a>]). However, the host may mount defences or allocate energy differently in response to parasite infection to compensate and minimize the cost of the infection in terms of host fitness [
  <a rid="pone.0125773.ref002" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0125773.ref002">2</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0125773.ref010" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0125773.ref010">10</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0125773.ref011" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0125773.ref011">11</a>]. For example, the host may delay current reproduction in favour of longer lifespan and a chance to compensate later in life [
  <a rid="pone.0125773.ref002" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0125773.ref002">2</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0125773.ref011" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0125773.ref011">11</a>]. Thus the “arms race” between the host and the parasite may lead to a complex set of mechanisms with different strategies or trade-offs depending on the life history traits of the species. Theoretical population models also indicate that if a parasite affects host reproduction more than host survival, this may have destabilizing effects on the host-parasite dynamics and may increase the probability of extinction [
  <a rid="pone.0125773.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0125773.ref012">12</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Life history theory suggests that negative effects (due to biotic and/or abiotic factors) suffered by individuals early in life may cause reduced reproductive success later in life [
  <a rid="pone.0125773.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0125773.ref013">13</a>]. For example, female red deer (
  <span class="italic">Cervus elaphus</span>) on the Isle of Rum, Scotland, born in years with high population densities start reproduction at a later age compared to females born in years with low population densities [
  <a rid="pone.0125773.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0125773.ref014">14</a>]. However, few studies have investigated if parasite infection may have similar long term negative effects on reproductive success in wild populations (but see [
  <a rid="pone.0125773.ref008" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0125773.ref008">8</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0125773.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0125773.ref009">9</a>]).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition to possible effects of parasites on host reproduction, there may be several other important factors which affect individual host reproductive success (e.g. age or morphology), that should be accounted for in studies of potential effects of parasites on host fitness. For example, the reproductive success of individuals may decrease as they age (i.e. senescence) [
  <a rid="pone.0125773.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0125773.ref015">15</a>] or larger individuals may produce larger clutches [
  <a rid="pone.0125773.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0125773.ref016">16</a>]. Controlling for such effects requires detailed information on each individual included in the study. In addition, obtaining precise estimates of individual reproductive success in wild populations may be challenging. However, one study system which has managed to obtain estimates of several individual reproductive fitness components (clutch size, fledging failure and total number of recruits produced in a lifetime) is a metapopulation of house sparrows (
  <span class="italic">Passer domesticus</span>) on the coast of Helgeland in northern Norway [
  <a rid="pone.0125773.ref017" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0125773.ref017">17</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0125773.ref019" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0125773.ref019">19</a>]. In this system, data collected from both parents and offspring have made it possible to obtain different estimates of individual reproductive success along with individual covariates (age, morphology etc.). Our aim for this study was to investigate the relationship between individual maternal infection of the parasite 
  <span class="italic">Syngamus trachea</span> in a given year and reproductive success. We also investigated the relationship between parasite infection (measured in faeces samples) when females were juveniles and their subsequent lifetime reproductive success.
 </p>
</sec>
