<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec009" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Lifetime reproductive success and juvenile infection</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our second section of analyses investigated the relationship between female lifetime reproductive success (LRS) and their infection status or FEC as a juvenile. In these analyses we used our second dataset (see above) which was collected from captured female juveniles and only included female juveniles that survived to become adults. None of these individuals were observed or captured in 2013 and were assumed to be dead after 2012. Previous analyses [
  <a rid="pone.0125773.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0125773.ref021">21</a>] have found a very high mean resighting probability (~ 0.9) on Hestmannøy. Accordingly, we assumed that the estimated total number of recruits produced per female 2007–2012 represented an estimate of the LRS for these individuals. For these analyses we used generalized linear models (function = glm, family = poisson, link = log) with LRS as the response variable. As explanatory variables we used FEC, infection status and juvenile morphology (BC, bill depth, bill length, tarsus length and wing length). In addition we included the lifespan (number of years) and the hatch year of individuals as explanatory variables.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All candidate models were ranked using Akaike information criterion corrected for small sample sizes (AIC
  <sub>C</sub>), which penalizes models with a high number of parameters relative to sample size [
  <a rid="pone.0125773.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0125773.ref035">35</a>]. We also calculated the Akaike weights [
  <a rid="pone.0125773.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0125773.ref035">35</a>] of all candidate models. Estimates from candidate models are reported as mean ± 1 standard error. In order to prevent any problems due to multicollinearity, all explanatory variables were assessed for collinearity visually, by the use of Pearson’s correlation coefficient (r
  <sub>p</sub>) and variance inflation factors (VIF). Models with higher-order terms also included the respective main effects (e.g. age and age
  <span class="sup">2</span>). To avoid overparametrization [
  <a rid="pone.0125773.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0125773.ref035">35</a>], we did not include models with a sample size to variable ratio &lt; 10 (i.e. never less than 10 samples per variable). Due to the relatively small size of our datasets, we did not include interactions between explanatory variables in any models. We also did not allow FEC and infection status to feature together in the same candidate model(s) due to their collinearity.
 </p>
</sec>
