<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec008" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Maternal infection and current breeding attempt</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We first investigated the relationship between maternal infection and reproductive success measured as either clutch size (number of eggs), fledging failure or recruitment failure (first dataset, see above). To test if there was a mean difference between infected/non-infected mothers or a linear relationship with faecal egg count (FEC), we used maternal infection status (no/yes) or FEC as explanatory variables. We included females which had been captured and sampled during the period when their nest contained eggs or chicks. This period corresponds to hatch date ± 14 days, as egg laying and incubation may take 14 days [
  <a rid="pone.0125773.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0125773.ref028">28</a>] and chicks generally leave the nest when they are 14 days old [
  <a rid="pone.0125773.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0125773.ref028">28</a>]. In addition to infection status and FEC, we included clutch number, clutch size, hatch day, hatch day
  <span class="sup">2</span>, calendar year (as a factor) and the mothers; age, age
  <span class="sup">2</span> and morphology (BC, bill depth, bill length, tarsus length and wing length) as explanatory variables. Because 6 birds appeared as mothers more than once in our dataset, we used maternal identity as a random factor in all models in order to avoid pseudoreplication.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The first analysis focused on the relationship between clutch size (measured as the number of eggs laid by a female) and infection. In this analysis we used the clutch size as the response variable in generalized linear mixed models (package lme4, function = glmer, family = poisson, link = log). In the second part of our first section, we investigated the probability of fledging failure measured as the proportion of eggs in a nest that failed to develop into fledglings (nestlings with age 9–13 days) by using generalized linear mixed models (package lme4, function = glmer, family = binomial, link = cloglog). In these models, we also included the age of fledglings (9–13) as an offset in all models to account for differences in survival intervals from egg to fledgling [
  <a rid="pone.0125773.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0125773.ref034">34</a>]. We also weighted the proportion of fledgling failure in a given nest by the number of eggs present in the nest (i.e. number of trials). Lastly in our first section, we investigated the probability of fledglings failing to become recruits (i.e. probability of fledglings in a given nest that failed to survive their first winter) by using generalized linear mixed models (package lme4, function = glmer, family = binomial, link = cloglog). We only included nests that produced fledglings (n = 51). We also weighted the proportion of recruitment failure in a given nest by the number of fledglings present in the nest (i.e. number of trials). We thus investigated if maternal infection could have a delayed relationship with mortality of offspring after fledging.
 </p>
</sec>
