<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="Fig2" class="fig">
 <label class="label">Fig. 2</label>
 <caption class="caption">
  <p class="p">Central Pacific relative sea surface temperature (SST) response to the Pinatubo eruption in IPSL-CM5B ensemble simulations. Niño3.4 relative SST (in °C) anomalies, relative to the climatology for the control (
   <italic class="italic">black</italic>) and Pinatubo ensemble mean (
   <italic class="italic">purple</italic>) from January of the year of the eruption (labelled year 0) to August 32 months later, for ocean–atmosphere conditions leading to 
   <bold class="bold">a</bold> La Niña, 
   <bold class="bold">b</bold> El Niño and 
   <bold class="bold">c</bold> neutral ENSO state at the end of the eruption year in the unforced control run, based on the warm water volume (WWV) content. The WWV corresponds to the volume of water above the 20 °C isotherm between 5 °N–5 °N and 120 °E–80 °W and is a good precursor of the upcoming ENSO phase in nature
   <sup class="sup">
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">4</xref>
   </sup>. This is also the case in our model as demonstrated by a peak correlation of 
   <italic class="italic">r</italic> = 0.7 when the Niño 3.4 SST index lags the WWV in May by 6 months in the IPSL-CM5B CMIP5 historical simulation
   <sup class="sup">
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" class="xref">54</xref>
   </sup>. Anomalies are obtained by removing the Niño3.4 relative SST mean seasonal cycle over the 30 years of historical simulations that precede the start of each model ensemble. The 
   <italic class="italic">colour shading</italic> indicates the ensemble spread, based on a 90% confidence interval from two-tailed Welch’s 
   <italic class="italic">t</italic>-test. The 
   <italic class="italic">vertical dashed line</italic> in each panel indicates the date of the eruption
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="41467_2017_755_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e776" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
