<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="Fig1" class="fig">
 <label class="label">Fig. 1</label>
 <caption class="caption">
  <p class="p">Observed and CMIP5 relative sea surface temperature (SST) response to the five main eruptions with stratospheric aerosol injection during 1870–2010. 
   <bold class="bold">a</bold> Evolution of the composited Niño3.4 (5 °S–5 °N, 170 °W–120 °W) relative SST anomalies (SSTA) over a 2-year period following the five largest volcanic eruptions during 1870–2010 in HadISST observations
   <sup class="sup">
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" class="xref">46</xref>
   </sup> (
   <italic class="italic">black line</italic>). The 
   <italic class="italic">red dots</italic> denote when the 5 events (
   <italic class="italic">colour lines</italic>) have anomalies of the same sign. An 
   <italic class="italic">arrow</italic> indicates the dates and relative magnitude (based on Aerosol Optical Depth provided by Gao et al.
   <sup class="sup">
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" class="xref">51</xref>
   </sup>) of the selected eruptions. 
   <bold class="bold">b</bold> Same as 
   <bold class="bold">a</bold> but shown as a longitude-time section. The 
   <italic class="italic">black rectangle</italic> denotes the Niño3.4 region during October–November–December. 
   <italic class="italic">Stippling</italic> highlights times and locations where the 5 eruptions display anomalies of the same sign and the 
   <italic class="italic">contour</italic> corresponds to the 90% significance level of this anomaly according to a two-tailed Student’s 
   <italic class="italic">t</italic>-test. The composited anomalies are relative to the preceding 5-year climatology. 
   <bold class="bold">c</bold> Anomalous percentage of CMIP5 historical simulation members with an El Niño occurrence for the entire historical period (136 years). The anomalous percentage is given relative to the climatological rate over the entire period. El Niño events are defined as Niño3.4 positive relative SST anomalies exceeding 1/2 standard deviation. The 
   <italic class="italic">vertical coloured lines</italic> localize each eruption date and the 
   <italic class="italic">pink shading</italic> a period of 2 years following the eruption. 
   <italic class="italic">Continuous</italic> and 
   <italic class="italic">dashed horizontal lines</italic> indicate one and two standard deviations respectively. The 
   <italic class="italic">red shading</italic> outlines one standard deviation from the mean of the ensemble
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="41467_2017_755_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e629" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
