<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par49" class="p">A starting point on this hierarchy of simulations would be to use a dry dynamical model in the Held-Suarez configuration [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR127" class="xref">127</xref>] with localized thermal forcings systematically applied at different latitudes and pressure levels. This approach would construct response functions for ITCZ width and strength analogous to those being used to understand the sensitivities of mid-latitude dynamics and the Hadley circulation to internal climate variability and external forcings [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR128" class="xref">128</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR130" class="xref">130</xref>]. Response functions would show the broad range of possible ITCZ width and strength responses in the absence of processes such as latent heating and radiative transfer which play important but complicating roles in ITCZ dynamics in comprehensive models and in Earth’s climate. Moving up the model hierarchy, moist aquaplanet models with simplified gray radiation schemes are ideal tools with which to assess how latent heating and surface fluxes couple to the ITCZ, and have been used extensively in tropical atmospheric dynamics research [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">14</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" class="xref">19</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" class="xref">36</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR131" class="xref">131</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR132" class="xref">132</xref>]. Moist aquaplanets with prescribed surface, atmospheric, and TOA thermal forcings—analogous to those described above for a dry model—would establish a basic understanding for whether ITCZ width and strength are more sensitive to local or extratropical forcing, or to heating in the lower or upper troposphere. Aquaplanet simulations using the “radiation-locking” technique [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR121" class="xref">121</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR133" class="xref">133</xref>] could further be used to decompose how radiative effects associated with CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>, aerosols, water vapor and clouds control the ITCZ response to climate change. The ITCZ is a region of frequent moist convection and a computational hierarchy to understand ITCZ sensitivity should include a model with the capability to explicitly simulate deep convection. Limited-domain, fixed-SST, convection-permitting simulations are becoming increasingly feasible, and novel “aquachannel” configurations have recently been used to study the climatological ITCZ [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR134" class="xref">134</xref>]. Performing analogous convection-permitting simulations with a range of SSTs would be a first step towards accounting for the role of explicit atmospheric convection in modulating the ITCZ response to climate change.
</p>
