<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Based on the “in the meantime updated SRES emission scenarios” an increase in the globally averaged (land only) number of HWs between 4 and 12 depending on the emission scenario was simulated [
 <xref rid="B48-ijerph-16-03959" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Although there is not much difference in the number of heat waves between the two scenarios, the number of days’ contribution to heat waves each year with reference to the 30-year period 1971–2000 increases significantly following the projected general increase in air temperature. It is worth noticing, that the arithmetic mean of the HW-N anomalies for Rome in the RCP8.5 scenario for the far future is lower (+4.0 HW) than that for London (+4.1 HW) and Luxembourg (+4.2 HW) and additionally, the increase for the far future is less pronounced here than for the other indices. This could be explained by the fact that the increased number of days that contribute to HWs prolonged the length of the HWs substantially, so that few but very long HWs occur in all three cities every year at the end of this century. This is reconfirmed by the results presented in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-16-03959-f005">Figure 5</xref>. The HW-D index—describing the length of the longest HW per year—shows overall positive anomalies with the most pronounced positive trends for the far future. For both RCPs for Rome, the highest anomalies were projected for the far future. This index only describes the most extreme event per year, but is important for the health aspects because the longer the heat waves last, the more pronounced heat-related illnesses are. For Mumbai (India) an increase of one day in the duration of an HW was associated with a 4.9% increase in the estimated association between HWs and mortality [
 <xref rid="B49-ijerph-16-03959" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. The detected increase in the duration of heat waves in the future are similar to those presented for Eastern Europe or northern Russia [
 <xref rid="B50-ijerph-16-03959" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>].
</p>
