<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Species living in the warmer areas close to the coast seem to be most vulnerable, as temperature for these areas is predicted to be around 20 °C in 2080 (see 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Supplementary Fig. S4</xref>). This is close to the estimated upper limit of their fundamental climatic niche
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22" class="xref">22</xref> thus limiting their thermal safety margin. In general, conservation recommendations related to climate change are mostly strategies based on the selection of protected areas and measures to increase habitat connectivity
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30" class="xref">30</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31" class="xref">31</xref>. However, for cave species, as happens for other species with poor dispersal capabilities, the concentration of conservation efforts in actual localities (i.e., 
 <italic class="italic">in situ</italic> management) could be a more efficient and practical strategy. Although these measures are recommended for species living in the central Pyrenees (i.e. those with wider TSM), they seem insufficient for species and populations highly vulnerable to climatic change, such as those living in the coast. At present it is not know whether the situation of the coastal species of 
 <italic class="italic">Troglocharinus</italic> is common among the subterranean fauna or a unique situation consequence of their peculiar evolutionary history
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32" class="xref">32</xref>. Despite the long fascination by the peculiarities of typical subterranean organisms
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33" class="xref">33</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34" class="xref">34</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b35" class="xref">35</xref> there is a general lack of knowledge of most subterranean groups worldwide. Subterranean biodiversity has been largely neglected in conservation programs worldwide, even if it has been estimated a total of 50,000–100,000 obligate subterranean species
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b36" class="xref">36</xref>, with a high level of local endemism
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b37" class="xref">37</xref>.
</p>
