<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par2" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">ENSO is a major source of variability in global precipitation and temperature on 2–8 year time scale. Recent studies have suggested that global climate extremes could be amplified by the combined influence of ENSO and PDO
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span>, however, depending on their phase relationship. Antarctic climate might be sensitive to these tropical changes due to Southern Hemispheric teleconnections
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span>. However, it is not yet well understood that how these changes in tropical oscillations and associated climate extremes influence Antarctic climate through space and time particularly in the backdrop of continuing global warming since the industrial era ~1850 Common Era (CE).
 </p>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To reconstruct past ENSO behavior and predict its future trend, several attempts have been made based on model simulations and proxy records. Results of long term predictions of ENSO in Coupled Model Intercomparison Project phase-5 (CMIP5) show contradictory results
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
  </span>. A number of attempts have already been made based on tree ring
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>
  </span> and coral
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span> records to understand decadal to centennial scale variability of ENSO and PDO. These records show good agreement in shorter reconstructions; however, they differ in case of longer records
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>
  </span>. In addition, there are few important caveats attached to tree ring-based reconstruction such as changes in sample depth, tree size, and chronology—some of which coincide with variance changes and hence, they often misrepresents climate signal
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span>. Further, such ENSO reconstructions are mostly from the ENSO regions in tropics/subtropics and therefore may not necessarily reflect changes in ENSO influencing beyond the Niño regions. Though ENSO signals (in temperature and precipitation) are recorded in the Antarctic ice sheet, however, due to non-stationary nature
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span> and poor understanding of transfer functions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span>, it becomes difficult to infer about the changes in ENSO behaviour based on multiple ice core records. In present study, we have reconstructed Antarctic surface air temperature (SAT) for the last five centuries from East and West Antarctica ice core records and investigated temperature signals in ENSO and PDO bands to examine long-term variability in their influence on Antarctic SAT. This long-term reconstruction would enable us to discern their trend during the pre- and post-industrial greenhouse warming and examine their phase relationship.
 </p>
</sec>
