<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0190">The results show that information from the media, particularly, television and radio are significantly less likely to influence farmers' perception of climate change. This is partly due to the mistrust among smallholder farmers on the information from the media. In Ghana, 
 <xref rid="bib37" ref-type="bibr">Hirons et al. (2018)</xref> found that smallholder farmers in cocoa growing areas do not trust information from the media. Similar results were also reported by 
 <xref rid="bib20" ref-type="bibr">Chepkoech et al. (2018)</xref> who noted that smallholder farmers in Kenya have mistrust in climate information from the media. Nevertheless, 
 <xref rid="bib27" ref-type="bibr">Elum et al. (2017)</xref> reveal that climate change perception of smallholder farmers in South Africa is shaped by the media. The results from the analysis also show that information from family and friends, and government significantly influence farmers' perception. This might be due to their experience of climate change and proximity to smallholder farmers. For instance, family and friends who experience climate change are more likely to share or exchange information on the observed changes in climate with other members, which influence their perception. Similarly, the government, in this case local administration including extension officers also influence the perception of smallholder farmers. For instance, extension officers educate smallholder farmers on changing climate, which influence their perception (
 <xref rid="bib5" ref-type="bibr">Aemro et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib10" ref-type="bibr">Asare-Nuamah et al., 2019</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bib25" ref-type="bibr">Debela et al., 2015</xref>). Implicitly, smallholder farmers trust information from the people close to them, thereby influencing their perception of climate change. Personal experience also showed positive in influencing the perception of smallholder farmers, although the result was not significant. Studies have reported that personal experience significantly influence farmers’ perception of climate chang (
 <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Hitayezu et al., 2017</xref>), even though 
 <xref rid="bib38" ref-type="bibr">Hitayezu et al. (2017)</xref> assert that personal experience leads to bias in the perception of smallholder farmers.
</p>
