<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div id="Tab3" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <span class="label">Table 3</span>
 <div class="caption">
  <p>Key literature and results on primary, secondary and tertiary effects of climate change to Sápmi region and Saami people</p>
 </div>
 <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
  <thead>
   <tr>
    <th>Article</th>
    <th>Primary effects</th>
    <th>Secondary effects</th>
    <th>Tertiary effects</th>
    <th>Mitigation</th>
    <th>Adaptation</th>
   </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
   <tr>
    <td>Dobler et al. Regional climate change projections for the Barents region. Earth System Dynamics Discussions: 2016: 1–22. DOI:10.5194/esd-2016-27.</td>
    <td>Projections on temperature, cloudiness and precipitation in the Barents region</td>
    <td/>
    <td/>
    <td/>
    <td/>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Furberg et al. Facing the limit of resilience: perceptions of climate change among reindeer herding Sami in Sweden. Global Health Action 2011: 4: 1–11. DOI:10.3402/gha.v4i0.8417.</td>
    <td>Perception of primary effects of climate change to winter conditions</td>
    <td/>
    <td>Adverse mental health and cultural effects of climate change</td>
    <td/>
    <td>Flexibility and technology means for adaptation</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Lof A. Examining limits and barriers to climate change adaptation in an Indigenous reindeer herding community. Clim Dev 2013: 5(4): 328–339. DOI:10.1080/17565529.2013.831338.</td>
    <td>Perception of primary effects of climate change to winter conditions</td>
    <td/>
    <td/>
    <td/>
    <td>Governance limits possibilities for adaptation</td>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Pape R. and Loffler J. Climate change, land use conflicts, predation and ecological degradation as challenges for reindeer husbandry in northern Europe: what do we really know after half a century of research? Ambio 2012: 41(5): 421-434DOI:10.1007/s13280-012-0257-6</td>
    <td>Projected effects of climate change to conditions relevant for reindeer herding</td>
    <td/>
    <td/>
    <td>Adaptation possibilities</td>
    <td/>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Parkinson A.J. and Evengård B. Climate change, its impact on human health in the Arctic and the public health response to threats of emerging infectious diseases. Global Health Action 2009: 2: 88–90.</td>
    <td>Risk for accidents and health threats from extreme weather events</td>
    <td>Potential changes in vector-borne and infectious diseases</td>
    <td>Adverse mental health effects and diet and lifestyle changes increasing risk for lifestyle diseases</td>
    <td/>
    <td/>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Tryland M. Are we facing new health challenges and diseases in reindeer in Fennoscandia? Rangifer 2012: 32(1): 35–47.</td>
    <td>Effects of changing climate to reindeer demography, pastures and condition</td>
    <td>Reindeer parasite and diseases outbreaks</td>
    <td/>
    <td>Adaptation in reindeer herding with supplementary feeding and technology</td>
    <td/>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Vowles et al. Expansion of deciduous tall shrubs but not evergreen dwarf shrubs inhibited by reindeer in Scandes mountain range. Journal of Ecology 2017: 105(6): 1547–1561. Doi:10.1111/1365-2745.12753.</td>
    <td>Effects of climate change to vegetation (shrubification)</td>
    <td/>
    <td/>
    <td>Herbivore is potentially of great importance for shaping arctic shrub expansion and its associated ecosystem effects</td>
    <td/>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Eliasson et al. Identification of development areas in a warming Arctic with respect to natural resources, transportation, protected areas, and geography. Futures 2017: 85: 14–29. Doi:10.1016/j.futures.2016.11.005.</td>
    <td/>
    <td/>
    <td>Opening of new development areas in warming climate</td>
    <td/>
    <td/>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Willox et al. Examining relationships between climate change and mental health in the Circumpolar North. Reg Environ Change 2015: 15(1): 169–182. DOI:10.1007/s10113-014-0630-z.</td>
    <td/>
    <td/>
    <td>Climate change is likely an emerging mental health challenge for Circumpolar Indigenous populations</td>
    <td/>
    <td/>
   </tr>
   <tr>
    <td>Cohen et al. Effect of reindeer grazing on snowmelt, albedo and energy balance based on satellite data analyses. Remote Sens Environ 2013: 135: 107–117 Doi: /10.1016/j.rse.2013.03.029.</td>
    <td/>
    <td/>
    <td/>
    <td>Summer reindeer herding can delay snowmelt, increase surface albedo and to decrease the ground heating in the snowmelt season.</td>
    <td/>
   </tr>
  </tbody>
 </table>
</div>
