<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Darwin (
 <xref rid="pce13203-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1859</xref>) considered domestication as a model of adaptation from which the nature of variation and selection could be inferred. Domestication of plants has been crucial to the development of human civilization by enabling an abundance of food (Diamond, 
 <xref rid="pce13203-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2002</xref>). However, as a consequence of this human intervention and historic population bottlenecks associated with it, the genetic diversity of most domesticated crops has been vastly reduced compared with their wild progenitors (Diamond, 
 <xref rid="pce13203-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2002</xref>; Gepts, 
 <xref rid="pce13203-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>; Glémin &amp; Bataillon, 
 <xref rid="pce13203-bib-0045" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>). Reduction in genetic diversity of cultivated legumes compared with their wild relatives and ancestors has been discussed for different plants such as common bean (Bellucci et al., 
 <xref rid="pce13203-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; Bitocchi et al., 
 <xref rid="pce13203-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Gepts, 
 <xref rid="pce13203-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1990</xref>), soybean (Hyten et al., 
 <xref rid="pce13203-bib-0064" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>; Lam et al., 
 <xref rid="pce13203-bib-0085" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>), narrow‐leafed lupin (
 <styled-content style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">
  <styled-content style="italic-in-any-context" class="styled-content">Lupinus angustifolius</styled-content>
 </styled-content>; Berger, Buirchell, Luckett, &amp; Nelson, 
 <xref rid="pce13203-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>), and chickpea (Varshney et al., 
 <xref rid="pce13203-bib-0152" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). Interestingly, a study illustrated that reduction in genetic diversity as a result of domestication could go beyond the plant itself, as lower sequence variation was observed in rhizobia from domesticated chickpea compared with those from the wild type, which may suggest the potential negative impact of chickpea domestication on symbiosis (Kim et al., 
 <xref rid="pce13203-bib-0076" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). Shifts in genetic variation as a result of domestication, crop expansion, and breeding highlight the need for conserving and management of genetic resources for future breeding attempts.
</p>
