<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Genome sequencing, assembly and annotation</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We selected a male great tit (hereafter the reference bird) from a recent captive population (four generations in captivity) in the Netherlands for genome sequencing and 
  <span class="italic">de novo</span> assembly (see Methods and 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">Supplementary Information</a> for a detailed description of genome assembly and annotation). We generated a total of 114 Gb of Illumina HiSeq sequence data; after gap-filling and removal of adaptor sequences, the assembly consisted of a total of 2,066 scaffolds with an N50 scaffold length of over 7.7 Mb and an N50 contig length of 133 kb. Taken together, the assembled contigs span 1.0 Gb. We were able to assign 98% of the assembled bases to a chromosomal location using the recently described high-density linkage map
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b19" href="#b19">19</a> (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">Supplementary Data 1</a>). The total number of chromosomes covered by the assembly is 29 with three additional linkage groups (Chr25LG1, Chr25LG2 and LGE22). The assignment of chromosomal locations to the majority of the assembly resulted in a very high quality reference genome and enabled detailed comparisons with other bird genomes. A comparison between the genomes of the great tit and zebra finch (
  <span class="italic">Taeniopygia guttata</span>)
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b20" href="#b20">20</a> (see 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">Supplementary Fig. 1</a>) showed only intra-chromosomal inversions, and not a single inter-chromosomal rearrangement, confirming high synteny in birds. For the genome annotation step, we combined RNA sequencing data from eight different tissues of the reference bird with gene models from chicken (
  <span class="italic">Gallus gallus</span>)
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b21" href="#b21">21</a> and zebra finch
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b20" href="#b20">20</a>. The final annotation resulted in a total of 21,057 transcripts for 13,036 high-confidence gene predictions.
 </p>
</sec>
