<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methylation is correlated with rates of molecular evolution</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To investigate the potential adaptive and evolutionary role of DNA methylation, we first assessed the methylation patterns of selective sweep genes in the brain. We observed higher CpG methylation at sweep gene bodies (Linear Mixed effect Model, LMM; 
  <div id="d33e950" class="inline-formula">
   <span id="d33e951" xlink:href="ncomms10474-m1.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>, 
  <span class="italic">P</span>=9.2 × 10
  <span class="sup">−88</span>) and in regions upstream (LMM; 
  <div id="d33e959" class="inline-formula">
   <span id="d33e960" xlink:href="ncomms10474-m2.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>, 
  <span class="italic">P</span>=3.0 × 10
  <span class="sup">−34</span>) and downstream (LMM; 
  <div id="d33e969" class="inline-formula">
   <span id="d33e970" xlink:href="ncomms10474-m3.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>, 
  <span class="italic">P</span>=1.8 × 10
  <span class="sup">−65</span>) of gene bodies compared with the same regions in genes outside sweep regions (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f4" href="#f4">Fig. 4d</a>). In addition, lower non-CpG methylation in sweep gene bodies (LMM; 
  <div id="d33e981" class="inline-formula">
   <span id="d33e982" xlink:href="ncomms10474-m4.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>, 
  <span class="italic">P</span>=4.0 × 10
  <span class="sup">−14</span>) and in regions upstream (LMM; 
  <div id="d33e991" class="inline-formula">
   <span id="d33e992" xlink:href="ncomms10474-m5.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>, 
  <span class="italic">P</span>=0.001) and downstream (LMM; 
  <div id="d33e997" class="inline-formula">
   <span id="d33e998" xlink:href="ncomms10474-m6.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>, 
  <span class="italic">P</span>=1.64 × 10
  <span class="sup">−8</span>) of gene bodies was observed compared with the same regions in genes outside sweep regions (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f4" href="#f4">Fig. 4e</a>). These patterns are not due to systematic differences in expression levels between sweep and non-sweep genes because the observed CpG and non-CpG methylation differences are in opposing directions. In addition, although the overall expression profiles reveal a higher proportion of non-sweep genes with no or low expression (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">Supplementary Fig. 4e</a>), differences seen between CpG and non-CpG methylation in sweep gene regions were also observed when comparing genes with similar expression levels (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">Supplementary Fig. 4a–d</a>). While previous studies in chickens and humans have also shown altered CpG methylation in regions under selective pressure
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b36" href="#b36">36</a>, it is unclear what causes the observed higher CpG and lower non-CpG methylation in great tit sweep regions. In addition, lowly methylated genes in the brain were found to evolve significantly slower in comparison with highly methylated genes as shown by differences in the rate of nonsynonymous mutations between the two groups of genes (
  <span class="italic">P</span>&lt;0.001 for all pairwise comparisons, 
  <span class="italic">U</span>-test, 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">Supplementary Fig. 5</a>). This pattern was observed for both CpG and non-CpG methylation at TSS and within gene bodies. Overall these results not only show, for the first time, conserved neuronal non-CpG methylation patterns between birds and mammals, but also extend them by showing that methylation is correlated with rates of molecular evolution, thereby suggesting an important role for DNA methylation in evolution.
 </p>
</sec>
