<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methylation analysis</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Blood and brain DNA libraries were constructed according to the Epitect whole-genome bisulfite sequencing workflow (Illumina) with 18 PCR cycles. Whole-genome sequencing data were generated using the Illumina HiSeq 2,500 platform at Business Unit Bioscience, Wageningen UR. The number of paired-end reads (101 bp) were 358M and 292M for the brain and the blood, respectively. Raw sequencing reads were trimmed for quality (⩾20) and adaptor sequence using trim_galore v.0.1.4 (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/trim_galore/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/trim_galore/</span>). The methylation data has been submitted to NCBI with accession numbers SRR2070790 and SRR2070791 for the brain and the blood, respectively. Trimmed sequences were aligned to the reference genome using BSseeker2 v2.0.6 (ref. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b63" href="#b63">63</a>) with Bowtie2 v.2.1.0 (ref. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b44" href="#b44">44</a>) in the local alignment mode. A total, 97.63% and 99.93% of the genome was covered to an average depth of 31.88 × and 33.04 × in brain and blood, respectively. Methylation levels for each site were determined using the BSseeker2 methylation call script. All the analyses were done using sites covered by a minimum of 10 reads in both the samples. Only genes found to be 1:1:1 orthologues with chicken and zebra finch were used for methylation analysis. Gene bodies (annotated gene boundaries excluding the 5′ 5% of genes) and TSS (300 bp upstream to 50 bp downstream of the annotated starting position of each gene) for which we had information from at least 50% of the potential methylation sites were used in the dN/dS and expression correlation analysis. Average methylation levels for TSS and gene bodies were calculated for each individual gene. The upper (highly methylated) and lower (lowly methylated) quartiles were compared for differences in their evolutionary rates (dN/dS) using a Mann–Whitney 
  <span class="italic">U</span>-test. Correlations between the average methylation level of a given region (TSS or gene body) per gene with expression were performed using Spearman's rank correlation. A sliding window approach was used to infer differences in methylation levels between sweep and non-sweep gene regions. Non-sweep genes located on scaffolds were not included in the analysis, as these regions were not tested for sweeps. For this, genes were divided into different regions: the gene body (described above), 10 kb upstream and 10 kb downstream of the gene body and the TSS region (described above). Each gene body was subdivided into 40 bins, with the length of each bin therefore depending on the length of the gene. We calculated the mean methylation levels of these 40 bins with an overlap between neighbouring bins of 250 bp. Upstream and downstream regions were divided into bins of exactly 250 bp with an overlap of 125 bp between consecutive bins.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To compare TSS methylation between sweep and non-sweep genes, we conducted a 
  <span class="italic">t</span>-test with equal variance assumed. Only TSS regions with a minimum of 10 covered sites were used for comparative analysis. To compare methylation levels between sweep and non-sweep genes for other gene regions, we conducted LMM analyses with methylation level as the dependent variable, sweep (yes or no) as a fixed factor and bin as a random factor. A likelihood-ratio test was conducted comparing the model with and without sweep as a fixed factor. All criteria were met for conducting parametric analyses.
 </p>
</sec>
