<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">RNA sequencing and assembly</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">RNA was extracted from eight tissues (bone marrow, homogenized half of the brain, breast filet, higher intestine, kidney, liver, lung and testis) from the reference bird and was then used to prepare tissue-specific tagged Illumina sequencing libraries. The tagged libraries were pooled and sequenced using five lanes on one flowcell of Illumina HiSeq 2000 (same run on the machine). This resulted in 100 bp paired-end unstranded RNA sequencing data. The number of reads per tissue ranged from 98 to 229 million with a total number of 1.25 billion paired-end reads (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">Supplementary Data 7</a>). The sequence reads were checked for quality with FastQC (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/fastqc/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/fastqc/</span>) and low-quality sequences were trimmed with Fastq-Mcf
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b41" href="#b41">41</a> resulting in a final number of 1,096,140,415 paired-end reads that were used for the annotation. The RNA sequencing data per individual tissue has been submitted to Genbank (GT_BoneMarrow SRS863935, GT_Brain SRS866013, GT_BreastFilet SRS86603, GT_HigherIntestine SRS866033, GT_Liver SRS866035, GT_Kidney SRS866036, GT_Lung SRS866044, GT_Testis SRS866048).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The combined 1 billion reads from all eight tissues were simultaneously 
  <span class="italic">de novo</span> assembled using the Trinity software package
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b42" href="#b42">42</a> v. r2013-02-25. Because of the high depth of the RNA sequencing data, we first normalized the data. Following the normalization, the Trinity assembly was subsequently run using the default settings. We obtained a total of 101,289 assembled transcripts ranging in size from 201 to 16,061 bp, with an average size of 1,335 bp. We also did a reference-based RNA assembling by using the normalized RNA sequencing data in Tophat version v2.0.10 (ref. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b43" href="#b43">43</a>; Bowtie v2.1.0 (ref. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b44" href="#b44">44</a>)).
 </p>
</sec>
