<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Selective sweep detection</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We scanned the genome for target regions of positive selection using Sweepfinder
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b55" href="#b55">55</a> which uses local deviations of the site frequency spectrum (SFS) compared with a standard neutral model or chromosome/genome-wide reference to infer the action of positive selection. We used SNP calls from the ANGSD pipeline to construct SFS. ANGSD assumes that each variable position is biallelic and determines allele frequencies based on the genotype likelihoods
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b56" href="#b56">56</a>. Whole-genome alignments constructed with MAUVE
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b57" href="#b57">57</a> for zebra finch
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b20" href="#b20">20</a>, flycatcher
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b47" href="#b47">47</a>, ground tit
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b48" href="#b48">48</a> and chicken
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b21" href="#b21">21</a> were used to infer the ancestral state based on maximum parsimony. Sites for which the ancestral state could not be reconstructed with confidence were included in the analysis as folded sites (unpolarized). The chromosome-wide SFS was used as reference for each chromosome as recommended by Sweepfinder, which helps to reduce false positives caused by past demographic changes. We used a dense grid size of 100 bp and extracted sweep targets that had a composite likelihood score (CLR) within the top 1%. Neighbouring sweep targets were merged to sweep regions, with the total CLR score of a sweep region being the sum of the CLR score of each sweep target. The top 3% of genes that overlapped with or were near (within 5 kB flanking the sweep region) sweep regions larger than 300 bp were extracted (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">Supplementary Data 4</a>). Targets for positive selection included the low diversity region of chromosome 3, 6 and Z. Further details of the Sweepfinder pipeline can be found in the 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">Supplementary Materials and Methods</a>.
 </p>
</sec>
