<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">For animals, but not for plants, our results support the first hypothesis that species with narrow climatic niches are biotic specialists. Different, not mutually exclusive, explanations are consistent with this finding. First, animal species with wide distribution ranges and climatic niches are usually locally abundant
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b19" class="xref">19</xref> and are therefore likely to locally interact with more plant partners than rare species. In contrast, the relationship between range size and local abundance is usually more variable for plants
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b20" class="xref">20</xref>. Second, species traits that favour biotic generalization, for example, large body size
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b21" class="xref">21</xref>, may also favour the widespread distribution of animal species across a wide climatic range
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22" class="xref">22</xref>. Thus, climatic niche breadth and biotic specialization may be indirectly linked via species traits. Third, realized climatic niche breadth and biotic specialization will be directly linked if the distribution of specialized animal species is constrained by that of their resource plants, which has been demonstrated for antagonistic plant–animal interactions of butterflies and other phytophagous insects
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7" class="xref">7</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23" class="xref">23</xref>, but not yet for animal species linked to plants by mutualistic interactions. In contrast to animals, plants may depend less on their animal partners because pollination and seed dispersal by animals are characterized by a high degree of animal redundancy
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b24" class="xref">24</xref> and because many plants have evolved alternative regeneration loops, such as clonal propagation, autonomous self-pollination or the maintenance of persistent seed banks
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25" class="xref">25</xref>.
</p>
