<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In contrast to the robustness of plants to animal extinction, our simulation model shows that plant extinctions could trigger bottom-up trophic cascades
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13" class="xref">13</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26" class="xref">26</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27" class="xref">27</xref>. We found a high risk of animal coextinction, especially in simulations where animals were rather inflexible in choosing their plant partners. Apparently, the higher sensitivity of mutualistic networks to plant than to animal extinction disappeared only in simulations where species could freely reallocate at least 50% of their lost interactions to all persisting species in the network (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3" class="xref">Fig. 3f</xref>). Empirical studies have shown a high variability of mutualistic plant–animal interactions across years
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30" class="xref">30</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31" class="xref">31</xref>, suggesting a high flexibility in these networks. In contrast, recent studies have highlighted the importance of partner fidelity in both antagonistic and mutualistic ecological networks
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32" class="xref">32</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33" class="xref">33</xref> that might be associated with a high degree of trait matching between interacting species in these networks
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34" class="xref">34</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b35" class="xref">35</xref>. According to these studies, the flexibility of interactions will be constrained in ecological networks under future conditions, suggesting that unconstrained rewiring of interactions is unlikely even for generalized mutualistic networks. This notion is corroborated by a substantial loss of interactions in a plant–pollinator network during the past century, although rewiring of interactions mitigated the loss of pollinator function in the novel community
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b36" class="xref">36</xref>.
</p>
