<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Energy is the driving force of existence and is required for agricultural production systems. Studies on energy and greenhouse gas (GHG) emissions are key for analyzing the structure and function of agricultural production systems (
  <a rid="ref-54" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-54">Ren, Lin &amp; Wei, 2009</a>). As agricultural production depends heavily on fuel energy and other energy resources, it has a major impact on GHG emissions. This has led to serious environmental problems such as global warming, which has affected the stability and sustainability of agricultural ecosystem, consequently threatening global food security and ecological security (
  <a rid="ref-31" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-31">Khoshnevisan et al., 2014</a>). The net energy ratio (NER) is one of the key indicators for developing more sustainable agricultural practices (
  <a rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-16">Ghorbani et al., 2011</a>). High NER in conjunction with low energy use will conserve natural resources, reduce environmental damage, and promote the sustainable development of agriculture. Increasing energy use efficiency are vital for ensuring food and ecological security (
  <a rid="ref-71" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-71">Yuan et al., 2018</a>). The NER has been widely used to accurately evaluate energy use and energy use efficiency in various production systems to identify or develop more energy-efficient crop management practices or cropping system at regional, national, and global scales (
  <a rid="ref-71" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-71">Yuan et al., 2018</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Agriculture is considered one of the most important global emitters of GHG (
  <a rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-10">Cheng et al., 2011</a>). With the population growth and the large food demand in China, the challenge of reducing GHG emissions is huge. The main sources of GHG emissions are the use of fertilizer and fossil fuel in crop production, and enteric methane and manure management in livestock production. The GHG emissions in China accounted for a large proportion of global emissions in 2014 (
  <a rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-27">Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC), 2014</a>). Similar to other countries, the agricultural emissions mitigation policy in China faces a range of challenges due to the biophysical complexity and heterogeneity of farming systems, as well as other socioeconomic barriers (
  <a rid="ref-62" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-62">Wang et al., 2014</a>). At present, the large population and food demand are the main challenges in China. With the rapid development of society, the change in the food structure, and the increase in the quantity of animal-derived food, GHG emissions will increase in China (
  <a rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-12">Dong et al., 2008</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Generally, there are three categories for studying energy balances and GHG emissions from global agricultural production (
  <a rid="ref-23" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-23">Hou et al., 2008</a>), that is, crop production, livestock production only, and the combination of crop and livestock production. There is little information available on energy balances and GHG emissions in agricultural production systems in oases in arid regions of China based on production type. Arid regions cover ∼40% of the Earth’s land surface (
  <a rid="ref-53" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-53">Reichmann &amp; Sala, 2015</a>). Drying trends may occur most significantly in semi-arid and arid regions as a result of global warming (
  <a rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-24">Huang et al., 2016</a>). The mountain-oasis-desert coupling ecological system is widely distributed in inland areas of the world (
  <a rid="ref-55" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-55">Ren &amp; Wan, 1994</a>). Oasis and desert are the dominant ecological landscapes in arid regions of the world, in which water comes from rivers originating from high mountains.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Agricultural production systems in Minqin Oasis surrounded by the Tengger and Badain Jeran Deserts vary greatly in different regions, mainly due to the distribution of water sources located in the Shiyang River, the geography, and other environmental conditions (
  <a rid="ref-20" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-20">He et al., 2004</a>). The process and control of desertification in Minqin Oasis are principal modes of action in China and even the world (
  <a rid="ref-22" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-22">Hou, Chang &amp; Nan, 2009</a>). Over the past 2,000 years, agricultural production has relied on an extensive grazing system. In history, there are three periods of the opening up of grasslands for planting that resulted in soil desertification in Minqin Oasis. The succession order of agricultural systems in Minqin Oasis is extensive livestock production (grazing) (EGLP), integrated crop–livestock production (ICLP), and intensive crop production (ICP). Agricultural activities of Minqin Oasis, located in northwestern China, are commonly categorized into four contrasting systems: ICP, ICLP, intensive livestock production (confined feeding) (IFLP), and EGLP (
  <a rid="ref-22" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-22">Hou, Chang &amp; Nan, 2009</a>). The ICP and IFLP are practiced in well-watered center of Minqin Oasis. The ICLP system is located close to the desert. Grazing in the EGLP system, which is located in the desert, is the main production model (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1" href="#fig-1">Fig. 1</a>). However, there is no information available on the NER and GHG emissions in Minqin Oasis.
 </p>
 <div id="fig-1" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.7717/peerj.6890/fig-1</span>
  <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Satellite map of study site at Minqin Oasis, China.</div>
   <p>(A) Locations of Minqin Oasis; (B) location of study site at Minqin Oasis.</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="peerj-07-6890-g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The objectives in this study were to evaluate the difference in energy balances and GHG emissions form 4 contrasting agricultural production systems in Minqin Oasis of China using the life cycle assessment (LCA) technique. These data can offer key information for pursuing low-carbon agriculture and for adjusting the agricultural structure in northwestern China.</p>
</sec>
