<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Agricultural production systems in Minqin Oasis</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Minqin Oasis, located in northwestern China (103°05′E, 38°38′N), covers an area of 1.59 × 10
  <span class="sup">6</span> hectares (
  <a rid="ref-20" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-20">He et al., 2004</a>). Minqin Oasis has a continental arid climate, and the mean annual temperature, annual frost-free days, and annual rainfall are 7.6 °C, 175 days, and 110.7 mm, respectively. The mean annual rainfall and temperature over the 20-year period from 1997 showed respective decreasing and increasing trends (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2" href="#fig-2">Fig. 2</a>). Shiyang River, which originates in Qilian Mountain, is the economic lifeblood of Minqin Oasis. The IFLP system has a rich underground water source upstream of Shiyang River for livestock production. However, two of the systems, ICP and ICLP, mainly depend on irrigation, which enables a high input and output of crop production. There was no grazing in the ICLP, and forage fed to livestock was maize, alfalfa hay, and crop straw. Grazing and rangeland are the main production modes at the bottom of the Shiyang River.
 </p>
 <div id="fig-2" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.7717/peerj.6890/fig-2</span>
  <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Annual mean temperature and rainfall from 1997 to 2017 in Minqin Oasis.</div>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="peerj-07-6890-g002" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To facilitate a comparison of energy balances and GHG emissions from crop and livestock production among the four systems in Minqin Oasis, two typical towns were selected from each production mode to represent the average condition of agricultural production, namely, Caiqi and Chongxing for IFLP; Suwu and Daba for ICLP; Dongba and Shuangzike for ICP; and Hongshagang and Beishan for EGLP (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1" href="#fig-1">Fig. 1</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
