<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Energy balances and net energy ratio of agricultural production systems</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The energy balance of agricultural production systems can be influenced by variations in farm input and output capacities, including family population, production systems, environmental conditions, management regimes, and input capacity. It is known that the evaluation of energy balances is related to the variability of computed energy parameters. The parameters of energy and GHG emissions in this study were collected from literature in similar research sites. For example, the energy parameters of herbicides and insecticides selected in this study are higher than that reported by 
  <a rid="ref-50" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-50">Pishgar-Komleh, Ghahderijani &amp; Sefeedpari (2012b)</a>. The present carbon balances for agricultural production are comparable to those published elsewhere. For example, our NER for wheat and maize production are similar to those in Iran (2.09 vs. 2.13 GJ/ha, 2.63 vs. 2.67 GJ/ha, respectively) (
  <a rid="ref-32" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-32">Khoshroo, 2014</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-70" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-70">Yousefi, Damghani &amp; Khoramivafa, 2014</a>). However, our input energy and output energy of maize production (76.7 and 201.1 GJ/ha, respectively) are much higher than those (50.5 and 134.9 GJ/ha, respectively) estimated using LCA in Iran (
  <a rid="ref-70" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-70">Yousefi, Damghani &amp; Khoramivafa, 2014</a>). Our input energy for cotton production (50.2 GJ/ha) is much higher than that (31.2 GJ/ha) in Iran (
  <a rid="ref-51" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-51">Pishgar-Komleh, Sefeedpari &amp; Ghahderijani, 2012a</a>). The present NER of ICP (1.04) and IFLP (0.63) are within the range of crop production (0.5–2.1 GJ/farm) and livestock production (0.5–1.0 GJ/farm) of eastern Gansu in China, respectively (
  <a rid="ref-68" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-68">Xu et al., 2010</a>). Our NER for tomato production (0.63) is similar to that (0.6) in India (
  <a rid="ref-44" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-44">Nautiyal et al., 2007</a>). However, the NER of wheat production (2.09) in this study is higher than that in Pakistan (
  <a rid="ref-1" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-1">Abbas et al., 2017</a>), and the corresponding value of maize and cotton production in our study are much lower than that (2.63 vs. 5.52) in Turkey and (1.40 vs. 2.27) in India, respectively (
  <a rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-4">Baran &amp; Gokdogan, 2016</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-7">Channagouda, Babalad &amp; Patil, 2017</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The nature of agricultural production systems is the flow and circulation of matter and energy (
  <a rid="ref-57" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-57">Sere, Steinfeld &amp; Groenewold, 1996</a>). Energy is the foundation of the development of agricultural systems. ICP, which is an open system in Minqin Oasis, depends on high inputs with fertilizer, plastic mulch, and machinery accounting for 99% the total inputs. The large input of inorganic energy has improved the living standards of local farmers, however, the inorganic energy, especially, chemical fertilizer, pesticide and plastic mulch have yielded negative effect on local environment. It is a sustainable mode of agricultural development to enlarge the alfalfa planting area and to breed numerous sheep in Minqin Oasis.
 </p>
</sec>
