<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par22" class="p">
 <italic class="italic">Macrosiphum euphorbiae</italic> nymphs were able to survive high day-night temperatures although at a reduced rate. Direct impact of high temperatures can affect aphid mitochondrial processes such as respiration, oxidative phosphorylation, as well as denaturation of proteins and enzymes, resulting in altered functions and cell death
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" class="xref">49</xref>
 </sup>. Survival at high temperatures may be attributed to changes in metabolic rates and cellular and physiological processes triggering the production of heat shock proteins, which aid aphids in tolerating temperatures above 27 °C
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" class="xref">33</xref>
 </sup>. Furthermore, fluctuating day-night temperatures could also increase survival due to the recovery period from heat stress during cooler conditions at night
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">30</xref>
 </sup>. In keeping with the findings of Barlow
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>
 </sup> and Nguyen, 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" class="xref">33</xref>
 </sup>, no nymphs of 
 <italic class="italic">M. euphorbiae</italic> survived to the adult stage in the laboratory at a constant 30 °C (Beetge, unpublished data). However, while aphids may have recovered when exposed to cooler night temperatures during high-temperature periods in the current study, high day-night temperatures still negatively affected nymphal survival and reproduction. Although aphids may be able to adapt to high temperatures to some extent, Hoffmann, 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" class="xref">50</xref>
 </sup> suggest that terrestrial ectotherms have a limited ability to change their upper thermal limits.
</p>
