<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>It is likely that alterations in performance will be most apparent when temperature changes occur over a short time period (i.e. acute), while acclimation can compensate for the effect of temperature on escape swimming to a large degree when temperatures change slowly, such as during seasonal temperature shifts in mean temperature (
 <xref rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr">Beddow 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 1995
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref91" ref-type="bibr">Johnson and Bennett, 1995</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref176" ref-type="bibr">Temple and Johnston, 1998</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref194" ref-type="bibr">Wilson 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2010
 </xref>). The extent of this compensation depends on the duration of the acclimation, is largely species and habitat specific, and is related to thermal tolerance ranges, such that species with a wide thermal range (e.g. goldfish 
 <italic>Carassius auratus</italic>) tend to show greater compensation in escape swimming (e.g. speed, distance travelled, turning rates) than species with a narrow thermal range (e.g. killifish 
 <italic>Fundulus heteroclitus</italic>) after 4 weeks of acclimation (
 <xref rid="ref91" ref-type="bibr">Johnson and Bennett, 1995</xref>). Similarly, in Trinidad guppies (
 <italic>Poecilia reticulata</italic>) and Mediterranean grey mullets (
 <italic>Liza aurata)</italic>, the escape speeds of fish acclimated (for 70 days and 1 month, respectively) to each temperature did not differ, as a result of complete compensation (
 <xref rid="ref122" ref-type="bibr">Muñoz 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref95" ref-type="bibr">Killen 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2015
 </xref>). In common carp (
 <italic>Cyprinus carpio</italic>), 2 weeks of acclimation can induce changes at the anaerobic muscle fibre level and extend the range of temperature for escape swimming but do not result in full compensation (
 <xref rid="ref183" ref-type="bibr">Wakeling 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000
 </xref>). In golden perch (
 <italic>Macquaria ambigua)</italic> tested within a range of 10–25°C after 3 weeks of acclimation, escape swimming performance decreased significantly at temperatures below approximately 15°C but was relatively constant between 15 and 25°C (
 <xref rid="ref106" ref-type="bibr">Lyon 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2008
 </xref>). The strength of the acclimation response can also be associated with seasonal variation in temperature, especially during development (
 <xref rid="ref183" ref-type="bibr">Wakeling 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2000
 </xref>). In mosquitofish, (
 <italic>Gambusia holbrooki</italic>) escape speeds did not differ between spring and summer fish at their natural water temperatures of 15 and 25°C, respectively (
 <xref rid="ref164" ref-type="bibr">Seebacher 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2014
 </xref>). While temperature acclimation in adults and juveniles is reversible, temperature effects during the early developmental stages can have more long-term effects on physical traits (
 <xref rid="ref92" ref-type="bibr">Johnston and Temple, 2002</xref>) and can be reflected in burst swimming performance (
 <xref rid="ref9" ref-type="bibr">Batty 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 1993
 </xref>).
</p>
