<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ack id="grl59251-sec-0010" class="ack">
 <title class="title">Acknowledgments</title>
 <p class="p">Free accessibility of the EC‐Earth SPHINX data to the climate user community is granted through a dedicated THREDDS Web Server hosted by CINECA (
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://sphinx.hpc.cineca.it/thredds/sphinx.html" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://sphinx.hpc.cineca.it/thredds/sphinx.html</ext-link>). Further details on the data accessibility and on the Climate SPHINX project itself are available on the official website of the project (
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.to.isac.cnr.it/sphinx/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.to.isac.cnr.it/sphinx/</ext-link>). The SPHINX data were generated with computing resources provided by CINECA and LRZ in the framework of Climate SPHINX and Climate SPHINX reloaded PRACE projects. The MRI model integrations were performed using the Earth Simulator under the Development of Basic Technology for Risk Information on Climate Change of the SOUSEI Program of the Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology (MEXT) of Japan. The model data were submitted as part of CMIP5 and is available on the CMIP5 data archive (
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://cmip.llnl.gov/cmip5" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://cmip.llnl.gov/cmip5</ext-link>). The UPSCALE data set was created by P. L. Vidale, M. Roberts, M. Mizielinski, J. Strachan, M. E. Demory, and R. Schiemann using the HadGEM3 model, with support from NERC and the Met Office and the PRACE Research Infrastructure resource HERMIT. We thank the large team of model developers, infrastructure experts, and all the other essential components required to conduct such a large‐scale simulation campaign, in particular the PRACE infrastructure and the Stuttgart HLRS supercomputing center, as well as the STFC CEDA service for data storage and analysis using the JASMIN platform, where the data are publicly available. This work was supported by the Joint U.K. DECC/Defra Met Office Hadley Centre Climate Programme (GA01101). P. L. Vidale acknowledges the National Centre for Atmospheric Science Climate directorate (NCAS‐Climate; Contract R8/H12/83/001) for the High Resolution Climate Modelling (HRCM) program. We acknowledge the contribution of the C3S 34a Lot 2 Copernicus Climate Change Service project, funded by the European Union, to the development of software tools used in this work. The clustering algorithm used to process the geopotential height fields, written with this support, is publicly available at 
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/IreMav/WRtool" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://github.com/IreMav/WRtool</ext-link>. The scripts used to plot the processed data are publicly available at 
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/KristianJS/regimes-grl" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://github.com/KristianJS/regimes-grl</ext-link>. We especially thank Federico Fabiano (ISAC‐CNR) for his contribution to the clustering software and for doing some supporting computations involving all 10 EC‐Earth ensemble members. Jost von Hardenberg acknowledges support from the European Union's Horizon 2020 Research and Innovation Programme under Grant Agreement 641816 (CRESCENDO). Susanna Corti, Irene Mavilia, and Kristian Strommen acknowledge support by the PRIMAVERA project, funded by the European Commission under Grant Agreement 641727 of the Horizon 2020 research program.
 </p>
</ack>
