<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">For each of the 5 SDMs we projected the final current-climate SDM for vampire bats into future climate projections for North America using the World Research Programme’s most current Coupled Model Intercomparison Project set of future climate projections for year 2070 (CMIP5; [
 <xref rid="pone.0192887.ref037" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>]), and the RCP8.5 representative concentration pathway emissions scenario and climate projections. The RCP8.5 representative concentration pathway is the potential climate pathway that is expected to result in the most significant changes in climate forcing relative to the climate of the recent past [
 <xref rid="pone.0192887.ref037" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>]. We used the RCP8.5 projections because this represents the largest change from current climate of the four representative concentration pathway scenarios. Since it is currently unclear which future climate model provides the best predictions for our area of interest (especially the México-U.S. borderlands), we extrapolated each of the 5 final current-climate SDMs for vampire bats into each of the 17 future climate projections derived from global circulation models (RCP8.5 GCMs), representing 9 national climate change research centers produced by climate scientists in 7 nations (
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0192887.t002" class="xref">Table 2</xref>). Each of these future climate models produced a binary estimate of habitat suitability for year 2070 for each cell on our North American template. We then created a grand ensemble future climate map by combining in one map the binary results for each of the 5 SDM results applied to each of the 17 future climate models. This approach combined 85 models (5 SDM approaches x 17 GCM future climate projections) into a final grand ensemble map, based on the average of the binary estimates (0 or 1) for all model runs for each cell on the template. Given that our goal in this project was to consider “worst-case” influences of a changing climate on vampire bat distributions in North America, we decided not to complete the runs required for the other emission pathways, which would have required roughly 17 × 3 = 51 additional dedicated computer days, given the resources we had available at the time of this analysis. A data and code package used in this analysis are available in a GitHub repository (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://github.com/mark-a-hayes/Hayes-Piaggio-2017" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://github.com/mark-a-hayes/Hayes-Piaggio-2017</ext-link>). This repository includes geographic locations in decimal degrees of the occurrence data used in the analysis.
</p>
