<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As one can note, for this particular climate scenario RCP 8.5, the augment of daily maximum temperature along the future years is projected to occur with more intensity in the climate regions: Northern Rockies &amp; Plains, Upper Midwest, Ohio Valley and South. Nevertheless, the amount of thermal stresses developed into the bridge superstructure when expansion joints are clogged do not depend on those future temperatures only, but also on the temperature at the time of construction of the bridge. In other words, the induced thermal stress is a function of the temperature variation and not of the absolute temperature value for which the bridge is subjected. This temperature variation is calculated as the difference between the future daily maximum temperatures projected by the climate model (2040, 2060, 2080 and 2100) and the temperature of the bridge at the time of construction (see 
 <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec004">Materials and methods</xref>). Since the only available information in 2017 NBI [
 <xref rid="pone.0223307.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>] is the year in which construction was concluded, the temperature during bridge construction at the stage of expansion joints installation is considered according to four possible scenarios: average of minimum temperatures in the winter (Scenario 1), spring (Scenario 2), summer (Scenario 3) and fall (Scenario 4) for the respective year of each bridge construction conclusion. Each scenario can be interpreted as a hypothetical temperature condition, where Scenario 1 (winter) is the worst case, Scenario 3 (summer) is the most optimistic and Scenarios 2 and 4 present intermediate ranges of temperature (see 
 <xref ref-type="sec" rid="sec004">Materials and methods</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0223307.s001">S1 Appendix</xref>). In addition, bridges are classified to belong to one of the nine U.S. climate regions: Northwest, Northern Rockies &amp; Plains, Upper Midwest, Ohio Valley, Northeast, West, Southwest, South and Southeast (see 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0223307.s001">S1 Appendix</xref>). Using this classification, the average of minimum temperatures of each season scenario is taken from the historical NOAA Regional Time Series [
 <xref rid="pone.0223307.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>] and attributed to each bridge in the inventory according to its respective year of construction and its regional location (see 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0223307.s001">S1 Appendix</xref>). Hence, the temperature range that each bridge is subjected to depends on of the year in which it was built, its geographical location and the future projected temperature.
</p>
