<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par15" class="p">O
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> is strongly correlated with temperature [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" class="xref">31</xref>] due to associations of increased temperature with enhanced O
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> photochemical reaction rates, as well as with stagnation events (discussed below), and with elevated natural emissions from biogenic and wild fire sources. In particular, several studies highlight that higher temperatures enhance rates of peroxyacetylnitrate (PAN) decomposition [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" class="xref">32</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" class="xref">34</xref>] leading to local NO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> and O
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> increases in polluted emission regions. A number of these factors were also established as the cause of high levels of O
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> during the 2003 heatwave (see above). Natural emissions of isoprene strongly increase with increasing temperature (but also decrease with increasing atmospheric carbon dioxide CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>). Several authors have highlighted the crucial role of the temperature sensitivity of isoprene emission, finding this to be the dominant mechanism for increasing O
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> levels in polluted regions [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" class="xref">33</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" class="xref">34</xref>]. However, CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> inhibition of isoprene emissions in a future higher CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> climate may offset temperature-driven emission increases [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" class="xref">35</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" class="xref">40</xref>]. In addition, Ito et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" class="xref">41</xref>] and Fiore et al. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>] suggest the O
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> response to temperature depends on the amount of recycling of NO
 <sub class="sub">x</sub> from isoprene nitrates. Sustained elevated temperatures can lead to reduced soil moisture, which decreases dry deposition of O
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> through plant stomata, and to increased wildfires which contribute to O
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> precursor emissions. Another important global O
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> precursor, methane (CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub>), has a large natural emissions source from wetlands; these emissions are likely to increase under climate change along with CH
 <sub class="sub">4</sub> emissions from other sources as a result of climate feedbacks (e.g. permafrost thaw) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" class="xref">42</xref>]. Forkel and Knoche [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" class="xref">43</xref>] also suggest that elevated temperatures increase soil NO
 <sub class="sub">x</sub> emissions, which they found increased summer daily maximum surface O
 <sub class="sub">3</sub> concentrations slightly in agricultural areas in Europe.
</p>
