<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece31915-sec-0001" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Many biological invaders contribute to biodiversity loss by causing the extinction of native species (Sax et al. 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0040">2002</a>). An invasive species is an introduced or non‐native species that becomes established and spread outside its native range (Sax et al. 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0040">2002</a>). Invasive species are seen as one of the key drivers of change in island ecosystems and a major threat to native island biodiversity (Reaser et al. 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0038" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0038">2007</a>; Ricciardi 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0039">2007</a>). Island ecosystems are highly susceptible to biological invasions (Mueller‐Dombois and Fosberg 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0030" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0030">1998</a>). The Pacific region includes three of the 35 global biodiversity hotspots (East Melanesian Islands, New Caledonia and Polynesia‐Micronesia) with numerous endemic and native species (Myers et al. 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0031">2000</a>). Habitat destruction and invasive species are reported as the two main causes of species' extinctions in this region (Sherley et al. 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0042">2000</a>). These non‐native species often have highly detrimental impacts on native biota, leading to alterations at the community, the ecosystem, and the landscape levels (Vitousek et al. 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0052">1996</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Merremia peltata</span> (L.) Merrill (Convolvulaceae) is a woody vine with a geographical range extending from East Africa to Tahiti (Whistler 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0054">1995</a>; Master et al. 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0026">2013</a>). It is considered native to Madagascar, Mauritius, La Réunion, Tanzania (Pemba Island), Indonesia, Malaysia, the Philippines and Australia (northern Queensland) (Paynter et al. 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0033">2006</a>). The islands of the Pacific region have been included within its native area; however, its status in this region is uncertain (Meyer 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0027">2000</a>, Space and Flynn 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0044" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0044">2002</a>; Whistler 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0055">2002</a>; PIER, 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0036">2009</a>) (Fig. 
  <a rid="ece31915-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#ece31915-fig-0001">1</a>). In the Pacific, it has been suggested as a native to some countries such as Samoa, Cook Islands, Federated States of Micronesia (FSM), Fiji, French Polynesia, the Solomon Islands and Niue (PIER, 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0036">2009</a>). On the other hand, it has been identified as an invasive species of environmental concern in several other Pacific island countries such as some islands of American Samoa, Marshall Islands, Papua New Guinea (PNG) and Vanuatu (Meyer 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0027">2000</a>; Space and Flynn 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0044" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0044">2002</a>; Whistler 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0055">2002</a>; PIER, 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0036">2009</a>) while its status is uncertain in New Caledonia (PIER, 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0036">2009</a>) (Fig. 
  <a rid="ece31915-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#ece31915-fig-0002">2</a>). The resolution of this uncertain status requires an understanding of the biogeography of 
  <span class="italic">M. peltata</span> and genetic studies using molecular markers are useful for this (Palmer et al. 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0032">2010</a>). This genetic information should underpin management options for this species in the Pacific region.
 </p>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece31915-fig-0001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Photograph of 
    <span class="italic">Merremia peltata</span> on a roadside on the island of Espiritu Santo, Vanuatu. Photo credit: Subhashni Taylor.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-3" xlink:href="ECE3-6-742-g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece31915-fig-0002" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Pacific island countries where 
    <span class="italic">M. peltata</span> is present and is native (N), native invasive (
    <span style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">NI</span>) and introduced invasive (
    <span style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">II</span>). Status data are adapted from PIER (
    <a rid="ece31915-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0036">2009</a>). Broken lines show the extent of the three biodiversity hotspots in the region.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-5" xlink:href="ECE3-6-742-g002" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">M. peltata</span> is a common species found in dry lowland and mesic inland vegetation types in the Pacific region (Meyer 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0027">2000</a>); however, in Samoa, it has been noted as a dominant species on the landscape only during the past two decades (Kirkham 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0021">2005</a>). It reproduces both vegetatively and by seed; however, the seed viability rates are reported to be low (Bacon 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0002">1982</a>). Viable seeds can be transported by sea to new islands (Hacker 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0013">1990</a>) but the distance and duration that seeds can travel is largely unknown. Dispersal by sea may have led to its presence on the remote islands of the Pacific region. It is not known whether animals play a role in pollination and dispersal of this species as according to Kirkham (
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0021">2005</a>), in Samoa, “ants were observed in the corolla of the 
  <span class="italic">M. peltata</span> flowers, but never bees or wasps that were frequently seen on flowers of other species”.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In parts of the Pacific region, 
  <span class="italic">M. peltata</span> is considered a troublesome weed, capable of smothering trees up to 20 m tall (GBIF, 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0011">2010</a>). It commonly occurs in plantations and forest clearings where it often suppresses other important vegetation and regeneration of native species (Bacon 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0002">1982</a>; Bakeo and Qarani 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0003">2005</a>; Kiapranis and Nimiago 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0019">2005</a>; Wood 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0056" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0056">2012</a>). Many local and academic experts consider it to be a serious threat to the native ecosystems of the Pacific islands (Meyer 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0027">2000</a>). Furthermore, a weed risk assessment undertaken for this species for Australia and Hawaii resulted in a rating of “high risk” indicating that 
  <span class="italic">M. peltata</span> posed a high risk of becoming a serious pest (PIER, 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0036">2009</a>). It has also been suggested as a serious weed for which biological control should be explored in this region (Dovey et al. 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0009">2004</a>). However, any uncertainty associated with the status of a species needs to be resolved through investigations into its genetics (Dodd and Hayes 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0007">2009</a>, 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0008">2010</a>; Paynter et al. 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0034">2009</a>). Biological control should not be suggested for management of any species within its native range because their regulating natural enemies are already present and they may have expanded their range due to other factors such as overgrazing (Pemberton 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0035">1984</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Some researchers argue that 
  <span class="italic">M. peltata</span> is native to the region (Space and Flynn 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0044" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0044">2002</a>; Whistler 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0055">2002</a>). In countries such as Samoa, frequent disturbance caused by hurricanes or shifting cultivation can increase its distribution. In Samoa, it also appeared to play an important role in rainforest regeneration and attempts to control it could promote other invasive species (Kirkham 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0021">2005</a>). Kirkham (
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0021">2005</a>) found that 
  <span class="italic">M. peltata</span> behaved differently depending on whether it occurred in the forest canopy or as ground cover. It was found to suppress species diversity when acting as ground cover and also aided the spread of other invasive vines such as 
  <span class="italic">Mikania micrantha</span>; however, it seemed to support species diversity when occurring in the forest canopy. The dominance of 
  <span class="italic">M. peltata</span> is driven by fluctuating patterns of disturbance on the landscape, both anthropogenic and natural. The anthropogenic disturbance has been mainly caused by changes in land‐use due to increase in agriculture, while disturbances caused by tropical cyclones also have an effect on the dominance of 
  <span class="italic">M. peltata</span> (Kirkham 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0021">2005</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The lack of agreement regarding the status of 
  <span class="italic">M. peltata</span> throughout the region is problematic in terms of control strategies (PIER, 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0036">2009</a>; Dodd and Hayes 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0008">2010</a>). Manual control is difficult given its predominantly vegetative mode of reproduction since root fragments re‐sprout and stem fragments readily take root (Paynter et al. 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0033">2006</a>). Chemical control using glyphosate has proved to be effective against 
  <span class="italic">M. peltata</span> in forestry plantations in some countries like the Solomon Islands (Miller 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0028">1982</a>). Biological control has been proposed although the controversial issue of its native/invasive status in the Pacific region has complicated matters (Dovey et al. 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0009">2004</a>; Dodd and Hayes 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0008">2010</a>). Native weed species have an important ecological role and reduction of these species could have a destabilizing impact on ecosystems. Thus, in the case of 
  <span class="italic">M. peltata</span> it would be prudent to undertake further research to ascertain its status to assess the suitability of biological control. It is also important that any control strategies for 
  <span class="italic">M. peltata</span> are underpinned by information describing its potential distribution. Climate change will add to the complications of managing such a species because changes in climate may lead to shifts in the climatic limits that usually constrain its range (Taylor et al. 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0050" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0050">2012a</a>). An estimate of how the potential range of 
  <span class="italic">M. peltata</span> is likely to shift under climate change would contribute to an understanding of the potential impact of the species in the Pacific region.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To this end, CLIMEX, a popular species distribution modeling software for undertaking risk assessments for weeds (Chejara et al. 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0005" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0005">2010</a>; Taylor and Kumar 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0048" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0048">2013a</a>,
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0049">b</a>), was used to develop a model of the climate responses of 
  <span class="italic">M. peltata</span>. A range of information, such as experimental observations of its growth response to temperature and soil moisture, current distribution, and seasonal phenology, were used in model development. This model was then used to examine its potential current distribution and future distribution under climate change on some of the main archipelagos in the South Pacific. Despite rapid advances in the development of gridded data sets for global climate normals (Hijmans et al. 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0015">2005</a>; Mitchell and Jones 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0029">2005</a>), these datasets are still inappropriate for very small islands because they are unlikely to reflect the variations in climate that can occur over small distances on mountainous islands (Taylor and Kumar 
  <a rid="ece31915-bib-0048" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31915-bib-0048">2013a</a>). Hence, results are only presented for the following archipelagos: Fiji, Hawaii, New Caledonia, Papua New Guinea, Solomon Islands and Vanuatu.
 </p>
</sec>
