<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Phenological mismatch may be especially apparent in the highly seasonal arctic environment, which is experiencing the effects of climate change more so than any other region, resulting in earlier, warmer, and longer summers (Callaghan et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33517-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2005</xref>; Hodgkins, 
 <xref rid="ece33517-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; Serreze &amp; Francis, 
 <xref rid="ece33517-bib-0060" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>). Shorebirds comprise a large portion of the avian fauna breeding in the Arctic and are an ideal taxa to investigate phenological mismatch, as they time their long‐distance migrations using a combination of endogenous and photoperiod cues (Karagicheva et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33517-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>; Piersma, Brugge, Spaans, &amp; Battley, 
 <xref rid="ece33517-bib-0050" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>), but rely on a short pulse of abundant food whose emergence is dictated by local climatic conditions on the breeding grounds (Bolduc et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33517-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Danks, 
 <xref rid="ece33517-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1999</xref>; Tulp &amp; Schekkerman, 
 <xref rid="ece33517-bib-0067" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>). Upon arrival, shorebirds use the presence of snow to time egg laying, as egg laying is inhibited until enough snow‐free land is present (Grabowski, Doyle, Reid, Mossop, &amp; Talarico, 
 <xref rid="ece33517-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Green, Greenwood, &amp; Lloyd, 
 <xref rid="ece33517-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1977</xref>; Liebezeit, Gurney, Budde, Zack, &amp; Ward, 
 <xref rid="ece33517-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; Meltofte, 
 <xref rid="ece33517-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1985</xref>; Meltofte, Høye, Schmidt, &amp; Forchhammer, 
 <xref rid="ece33517-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>; Smith, Gilchrist, Forbes, Martin, &amp; Allard, 
 <xref rid="ece33517-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>). By doing so, shorebirds may be able to accurately time hatch with peak food availability, as timing of snowmelt, along with temperatures after snowmelt, influences insect emergence (Bolduc et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33517-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Danks, 
 <xref rid="ece33517-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1999</xref>; Høye &amp; Forchhammer, 
 <xref rid="ece33517-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>; Tulp &amp; Schekkerman, 
 <xref rid="ece33517-bib-0067" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>). However, with earlier and warmer summers, decoupling of this synchronization may occur if (1) shorebirds fail to advance arrival dates, arriving after snow has already melted, or (2) the time between snowmelt and insect emergence shortens (due to warmer temperatures), but shorebird incubation periods remain the same (Saalfeld et al. unpublished data). Such a decoupling has the potential to greatly impact shorebird populations, as prey availability directly influences juvenile growth and survival rates (McKinnon, Nol, &amp; Juillet, 
 <xref rid="ece33517-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; McKinnon, Picotin, Bolduc, Juillet, &amp; Bêty, 
 <xref rid="ece33517-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>; Pearce‐Higgins &amp; Yalden, 
 <xref rid="ece33517-bib-0048" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2004</xref>; Reneerkens et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33517-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>; Schekkerman, Tulp, Piersma, &amp; Visser, 
 <xref rid="ece33517-bib-0058" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2003</xref>; Senner, Stager, &amp; Sandercock, 
 <xref rid="ece33517-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). Therefore, understanding the ability of species, as well as the life‐history characteristics that enable a species to adapt to environmental change, is crucial for determining long‐term population viability in the face of a changing climate. However, few studies have investigated phenological advancement in laying dates in multiple shorebird species at the same site over a long period of time, allowing for direct comparisons among species under the same environmental conditions (Pearce‐Higgins, Yalden, &amp; Whittingham, 
 <xref rid="ece33517-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2005</xref>; Gill et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33517-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; but see Høye, Post, Meltofte, Schmidt, &amp; Forchhammer, 
 <xref rid="ece33517-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>; McKinnon et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33517-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>; Grabowski et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33517-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Liebezeit et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33517-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). Thus, our objectives for this study were to determine (1) the level of phenotypic plasticity in nest initiation dates in relation to snowmelt in eight arctic‐breeding shorebird species nesting over a 14‐year period, and (2) how a species’ migration pattern, timing of nesting, and settlement strategy (and by association an individual's mate and site experience) relate to their ability to adjust egg laying in response to earlier onset of summer.
</p>
