<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We estimated the species richness of saturniids on BCI with two methods. First, we estimated the total number of species likely to be present in the understorey of BCI forests by randomizing 100 times the cumulative number of species collected/observed during 32 surveys performed during 2009–2016 by ForestGEO (i.e., 640 trap‐nights) and calculating the Incidence Coverage‐based Estimator (ICE) with EstimateS 8.20 (Colwell, 
 <xref rid="ece33515-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>). Although light traps were located in the undestorey, the accumulation of saturniid species during the study period (Results, Fig.S2a) suggests that the canopy stratum was also well sampled, presumably because saturniid moths are strong fliers that can be attracted to the lower strata. Second, we fitted a nonlinear regression with the software CurveExpert (Hyams, 
 <xref rid="ece33515-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>) to the cumulative number of individuals sequenced against the cumulative number of cryptic species discovered, in order to appreciate how many cryptic species remain to be discovered on BCI. We choose the best model according to the highest 
 <italic class="italic">R</italic>
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> and the lowest corrected Akaike's Information Criterion (AIC). We also used nonmetric multidimensional scaling (NDMS) to compare the faunal composition of the key datasets and years of our compilation (Table 
 <xref rid="ece33515-tbl-0001" ref-type="table-wrap" class="xref">1</xref>): Dyar, Blest, Aiello, and ForestGEO, years 2009 to 2016 (matrix of 80 species × 9 datasets; Bray–Curtis distance). The similarity of assemblage composition among collecting years was estimated with the Morisita–Horn index, comparing abundance data, routinely used in entomology (Magurran &amp; McGill, 
 <xref rid="ece33515-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>), and calculated with the R‐language function vegdist of the vegan library (Oksanen et al., 
 <xref rid="ece33515-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>). We attempted to explain the signification of the NDMS axes for ForestGEO data with correlation between the scores of Years and the abundance of all species collected per year or the abundance of certain subfamilies collected per year. We obtained DNA barcodes from 58 of the 72 saturniid species recorded in the study for inclusion in our phylogenetic analysis. Together, these 58 species represent 95% of individuals observed on BCI. We used a tree‐grafting approach to estimate a community‐level phylogeny. Details about the software used for these various analyses are indicated in Appendix 
 <xref rid="ece33515-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S1</xref>.
</p>
