<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par18" class="p">There are many foodborne pathogens, and we have so far illustrated several mechanisms through which climate change may affect pathogen levels in food. The complexity of the food system, combined with the diversity of pathogens potentially affected, ensures risk prioritisation is challenging [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">21</xref>]. Several studies discuss the likely impact of climate change upon specific foodborne pathogens, but there are few attempts to highlight the significant vulnerabilities [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">5</xref>]. One attempt [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">22</xref>] is based upon a systematic assessment of academic papers to assess reported links between pathogens and climate sensitivity across Europe. From this assessment, we have extracted those pathogens that are foodborne (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" class="xref">1</xref>). This list includes 19 of 22 enteric pathogens considered by a recent WHO review of the global burden of disease, to be of global importance [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">3</xref>]. Factors included as climate drivers included altitude, climate change, extreme weather events, moisture, oscillations, particle matter, rainfall, salinity, temperature, vegetation and wind. Pathogens in the table are ordered according to their H-index, which the authors argue is a measure related to current disease severity. A pathogen with an H-index of 
 <italic class="italic">x</italic> has been included in 
 <italic class="italic">x</italic> papers (productivity measure); each of which has been cited by other papers (impact measure) more than 
 <italic class="italic">x</italic> times. However, many of these pathogens have multiple transmission pathways, including food, but the relative importance of food in comparison to other pathways is not stated. In addition, research on many pathogens has multiple drivers and the relative importance of climate, in comparison to others, is not quantified. For example, other authors argue that the links between 
 <italic class="italic">Listeria monocytogenes</italic> (near the top of the list) and climate are relatively weak [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">23</xref>]. The same paper argues that conversely, 
 <italic class="italic">Salmonella</italic> (near the bottom of the list) demonstrates strong relationships with climate. For many pathogens, although strong associations with climate exist, the mechanisms are poorly understood. This makes it difficult to assess the likely impact of climate change. One example is infections with 
 <italic class="italic">Campylobacter</italic> which has a strong seasonality and associations with weather, but the mechanisms are poorly understood [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">9</xref>].
</p>
