<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="methods" id="S0003" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec id="S0003-S20001" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study population</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This cross-sectional study was conducted between July and September 2012 in seven districts of Bangladesh that are prone to cyclone, flood, and salinity (
   <a rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0023">23</a>). The targeted study population was the total community of the vulnerable seven districts, that is, Bagerhat, Barguna, Cox's Bazar, Faridpur, Khulna, Satkhira, and Sirajganj comprising a population of 19,228,598. Multistage cluster sampling was used for recruiting the study population. We randomly selected four upazilas (sub-districts) from each district, resulting in a total of 28 upazilas as the primary sampling units. Then, four unions (lowest administrative unit) per upazila were selected randomly, resulting in a total of 112 unions. Finally, two villages from each union were selected randomly, reaching a total of 224 villages. From each selected village, we randomly selected 30 households using the Bangladesh Bureau of Statistics (BBS) household numbers. Therefore, a total of 6,720 households were surveyed in rural areas. From each household, we selected the head of the household as an eligible adult participant providing written consent or thumb impression; in the absence of the head of the household (mostly male), we interviewed the next seniormost female household member as the respondent. Information on other household members was collected from the respondent.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="S0003-S20002" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data collection</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">After obtaining written informed consent, information was collected using a pretested, structured, interviewer-administered questionnaire. The questionnaire was developed by the investigators and finalized after pretesting in a similar rural setting outside the study area. A week-long training was provided to the interview team prior to data collection. The trained 28 interviewers collected data through door-to-door visits at household level under the direct supervision of 14 field supervisors. The interviewers and supervisors had completed bachelor degrees and had experience in conducting national-level surveys using the census method. The quality control team formed by the investigators monitored the performance of field members through regular observation at the household level and regular checks of data for completeness. In 5% of study participants (
   <span class="italic">n</span>=336), the quality control team independently repeated data collection. The investigators checked each questionnaire to ensure that no information was missing; any error detected was corrected immediately at the field.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We have also collected secondary data of weather variables (rainfall, average temperature, maximum temperature, minimum temperature, and relative humidity) since 1970 to 2010 from the Bangladesh Meteorological Department (BMD).</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="S0003-S20003" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Interview questions</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition to socio-demographic variables (family size, education, occupation, source of drinking water, total family income, duration of stay, etc.) and climate-related variables, we collected household data on malaria, dengue, pneumonia, and diarrhoeal diseases from every member of the household. Height and weight of the respondents were measured to obtain body mass index (BMI) for nutritional assessment. Other relevant information on primary health care facilities, school health promotion, and health system response were also collected through face to face interview.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Dengue and malaria were self-reported by survey participants with a review of written history of diagnosis by a general practitioner or village doctor. In extreme weather events (flood, cyclone, storm surge, and drought), snakes lose their normal habitat and come out from their hideouts and move towards the households. Therefore, incidence of morbidity and mortality from snake bites increases during extreme weather events. We have compared our findings with the national-level household survey data of snake bites. The number of snake bites received by any household member for the past 12 months was recorded. Death from drowning increases during flood, cyclone, storm surge, and so on, which are related to extreme weather events. Mortality from drowning and snake bites is an important health indicator during extreme weather events. The number of deaths from drowning and snake bites during extreme weather events was quantified for the past 10 years preceding the interview. Household incidence of diarrhoea and pneumonia in children aged under-5 years was collected as number of episodes (at least one) for the last 12 months and for the last 1 month preceding the interview date. One episode of diarrhoea was defined as acute watery stool passed more than three times in 24 h or diagnosed by a registered physician. One episode of pneumonia (acute respiratory illness) was defined as fever, running nose, and/or cough, with shortness of breath and increased respirations (in drawing of ribs on observation) or diagnosed by a registered physician.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Regarding the diseases, respondents were asked about total family members’ outcome inclusive of his/her own. Female members of the family contributed to the response by reporting children's disease outcomes.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="S0003-S20004" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analysis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Collected data were initially entered into computer using the Statistical Package for Social Sciences (SPSS), version 21. Data were validated by a series of logical and range checks, producing summary statistics and tables. Data were immediately copied onto the hard disks of two computers as soon as data verification was completed and a copy was sent to the principal investigator at the University of Newcastle, Australia. Data were then transferred and analysed using STATA 13.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The summary statistics were reported as means, with standard deviations (SD) for continuous variables or percentages, with 95% confidence intervals (CI) for categorical variables. Socio-demographic variables and participants’ responses were summarized and presented using frequency tables. We estimated the incidence of climate-sensitive diseases (e.g. dengue, malaria) by fitting intercept only Poisson model using total number of household members as the offset. We estimated the incidence of different health events (e.g. diarrhoea) among under-five children adopting the same methods as described above using the total number of under-five children in each house as the offset. To adjust for the design effect of multistage sampling, we created sampling weights and incorporated them in the analyses using ‘svy’ command in Stata for all the analyses. We calculated sampling weights in four stages (i.e. the selection of upazila, union, village, and household) taking the inverse of the sampling fraction. The base weight was calculated by multiplying weights from all the four stages and was used in the ‘svy’ command.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="S0003-S20005" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ethical approval and consent</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The study protocol was approved by the Bangladesh Medical Research Council and Human Research Ethics Committee of the University of Newcastle, Australia (H2012-0163). Participants were provided with information note about the study before obtaining written consent.</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
