<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par10" class="p">We used hindcast SST and prescribed AOD data from the HadCM3, CM2.1, CCSM4, and MIROC5 ESMs. Table 
 <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" class="xref">1</xref> summarizes major attributes of these models and the CMIP5 decadal hindcast experiments carried out with them. In the CMIP5 hindcast experiments, the CM2.1 used a fully-coupled initialization scheme (Zhang et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" class="xref">2007</xref>), the MIROC5 used an ocean-only initialization scheme (Tatebe et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" class="xref">2012</xref>), the CCSM4 used initial ocean and sea ice conditions from a historical forced experiment (Yeager et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" class="xref">2012</xref>), and the HadCM3 was initialized by relaxation to analyzed ocean and atmosphere observations (Smith et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" class="xref">2007</xref>). In all CMIP5 experiments, Northern Hemisphere and Southern Hemisphere time series of AOD, based on observations (Ammann et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">2003</xref>) in the NCAR ESM, and Sato et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">1993</xref>) and Hansen et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">2002</xref>) in the other three ESMs), were specified. These data sets provide zonal-average, vertically-resolved AOD for visible wavelengths and column-average effective radii of aerosols (Stenchikov et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" class="xref">2006</xref>). We also combined hindcast data from the four ESMs in a multi-model ensemble (MME). The MME in this study is the average of the ensemble-average data from each ESM with generally different numbers of ensemble members. In this way, all ESMs are treated equally in forming the MME. We used the Extended Reconstructed SSTs (ERSST; Reynolds et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" class="xref">2002</xref>) from 1961 to 2010 for evaluating hindcast skills.
</p>
