<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece31848-sec-0023" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Behavior observations</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We found pika activity was lowest when temperatures were highest, which is consistent with the literature (e.g., Barash 
  <a rid="ece31848-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0002">1973</a>; MacArthur and Wang 
  <a rid="ece31848-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0031">1974</a>; Smith 
  <a rid="ece31848-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0052">1974</a>). Niche Mapper identified a limiting temperature threshold of 20°C for a 150 g pika with summer fur, above which we observed restrictions in most above‐talus behaviors (Fig. 
  <a rid="ece31848-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#ece31848-fig-0004">4</a>). We found no correlation between behavior and temperature below this threshold, suggesting that other factors may exert stronger influences on behavior below 20°C. For example, the predominance of short activity bouts may play a role in predator avoidance. Pika calls, which were negatively correlated with temperature, probably serve as a conspecific territorial defense mechanism and a predator alarm (Conner 
  <a rid="ece31848-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0014">1983</a>), but may also increase individual predation risk by revealing the caller's location (Smith and Ivins 
  <a rid="ece31848-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0053">1983</a>). Our results suggest that temperature may modulate an individual's cost–benefit curve for making vocalizations as well as restrict above‐talus activity.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Behavioral observations revealed that, in addition to temperature, site elevation and aspect combined to impact pika activity in complex ways. Pikas at higher elevations and north‐facing slopes were generally most active (Fig. 
  <a rid="ece31848-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#ece31848-fig-0003">3</a>). While high elevations and north‐facing slopes may contribute to the cooler conditions preferred by pikas, they also may contribute to differences in seasonality and phenology that are more pronounced at high latitudes. Later snowmelt and earlier, more frequent snowfall at high‐elevation north‐facing sites may constrain or shift the timing of the growing season, which could limit food availability. Pikas inhabiting such sites may be compelled to increase foraging and/or haying bouts per unit time relative to other sites to meet caloric demands for metabolic maintenance, reproduction, and food caching.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The seasonality of haying and breeding activities in pikas may have considerable impacts on observations of their behavior. Compared to higher elevations, pikas at lower elevations start and cease haying sooner, and breed up to 6 weeks sooner (Smith 
  <a rid="ece31848-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0052">1974</a>), which could be driven by elevational gradients in vegetation senescence (Smith 
  <a rid="ece31848-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0052">1974</a>; Huntly et al. 
  <a rid="ece31848-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0024">1986</a>). Additionally, pikas change their preferred forage throughout the season in response to changes in plant toxins and protein content, which may compel them to accelerate haying at different times (Dearing 
  <a rid="ece31848-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0016">1997</a>). We conducted our field observations during a 10‐day period to reduce behavioral changes due to seasonality. However, spatial differences in seasonality across sites may have contributed to the support for elevation, aspect, and elevation × aspect terms as predictors of pika activity (Fig. 
  <a rid="ece31848-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#ece31848-fig-0003">3</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
