<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece31848-sec-0002" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Material and methods</div>
 <sec id="ece31848-sec-0003" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Building and validating the biophysical model</div>
  <sec id="ece31848-sec-0004" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Microclimate data</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We deployed AQA 8000 Series LogTag
    <span class="sup">™</span> data loggers (
    <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.logtagrecorders.com" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.logtagrecorders.com</span>) at sites occupied by pikas in two stages. In the first stage, we used the loggers to estimate an altitudinal lapse rate for interpolating the elevation–temperature relationship across GNP. In June and July 2008, we placed seven loggers in protected crevices 1–2 m below the talus surface adjacent to a pika's food cache (or “hay‐pile”), one at each of seven sites with varying slope aspects and elevations ranging from 1512 to 2274 m. Two of these loggers at intermediate elevations were placed within 100 m of each other to assess small‐scale and potential logger variability. The loggers recorded temperature and relative humidity at 15‐min intervals. We calculated the lapse rate by fitting a linear regression to the instantaneous morning (07:00), midday (14:00), and evening (20:00) temperatures at each of the sites at one‐week intervals from July 28 to September 15.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the second stage, we used four loggers to measure the thermal refuge provided by the talus by measuring above‐ and below‐talus temperature at two locations representing elevation extremes (1056 m and 2521 m). At both sites, one logger was placed, unshaded, on top of the talus. The other was placed under the same rock and next to a hay‐pile. These loggers recorded temperature and relative humidity at 20‐min intervals. We did not deploy loggers at all behavioral observation sites, so in order to interpolate above‐ and below‐talus temperatures at those sites, we applied our estimated lapse rate of −8°C/km (from stage one) to the stage‐two thermal refuge data. Our estimated lapse rate fell within the range considered appropriate for GNP (Ray et al. 
    <a rid="ece31848-bib-0046" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0046">2010</a>).
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="ece31848-sec-0005" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Pika physical parameters</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The pika physical properties used for biophysical modeling (see below) were either measured directly using a preserved pika specimen from the University of Wisconsin‐Madison Zoology Museum (with summer pelage, obtained in Colorado) or gleaned from the literature. We directly measured fur length and reflectivity for dorsal and ventral sections of the torso and legs. We assumed that winter fur was 50% longer than summer fur (Howell 
    <a rid="ece31848-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0022">1924</a>), and that fur depth was always 50% of fur length. Animal model inputs are summarized in Table S1 of the Supporting Information.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="ece31848-sec-0006" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mechanistic model simulations</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Niche Mapper is described in detail elsewhere (Porter and Mitchell 
    <a rid="ece31848-bib-0044" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0044">2006</a>; Mathewson and Porter 
    <a rid="ece31848-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0032">2013</a>). In brief, Niche Mapper consists of two submodels: a microclimate model and an endotherm model. The microclimate model computes the hourly values of local air temperature at animal height, ground surface temperatures, below ground soil temperatures, local wind speed and relative humidity, and direct and diffuse solar radiation in the sun and shade. The endotherm model numerically solves for metabolic rates that allow an animal to maintain its core temperature within a defined range under the computed environmental conditions. To do so, both models solve the generic heat balance model, 
    <span class="italic">Q</span>
    <sub>in</sub>
    <span class="italic"> + Q</span>
    <sub>gen</sub>
    <span class="italic"> = Q</span>
    <sub>out </sub>
    <span class="italic">+ Q</span>
    <sub>st</sub>; where heat in (
    <span class="italic">Q</span>
    <sub>in</sub>) comes from solar and infrared radiation; 
    <span class="italic">Q</span>
    <sub>gen</sub> is metabolic heat generated (set to zero for the microclimate model); heat out (
    <span class="italic">Q</span>
    <sub>out</sub>), is infrared radiation from the surface (ground or fur–air interface), convective heat loss, and evaporative heat loss; and stored heat (
    <span class="italic">Q</span>
    <sub>st</sub>), which is set to zero in the endotherm model for steady‐state simulations. Niche Mapper solves these equations for each hour of the day, enabling analyses such as how many hours of a month's “average” day a model animal will be either heat or cold stressed when trying to maintain a given activity level (quantified as a multiple of BMR). If the metabolic rate that solves the heat balance equation is below the target activity level, the animal is predicted to overheat if active in those conditions and thus activity is not possible.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We tested Niche Mapper's ability to predict metabolic rates as a function of ambient air temperature prior to field simulations of pikas in GNP by simulating the metabolic chamber experiments of MacArthur and Wang (
    <a rid="ece31848-bib-0030" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0030">1973</a>), using the same mean pika mass (109 g) and constant wind speed (0.1 m/s) used in the experiments. We also conducted a series of sensitivity analyses to determine the influence of various animal and environmental properties on the model's metabolic rate predictions.
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece31848-sec-0007" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Field observations of pika activity in GNP</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We observed pika activity at eight sites in GNP from 15 to 24 July, 2009. We chose sites that had relatively high pika densities across a broad range of elevations and slope aspects. We conducted twelve separate 3‐h observations per site during the following intervals: morning (05:15–08:15), midday (13:00–16:00), and evening (19:00–22:00). We conducted observations over a 10‐day span to reduce the effect of seasonality; pikas are more active in late summer when caching food (Smith and Weston 
   <a rid="ece31848-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0055">1990</a>). Morning observations commenced ~45 min prior to sunrise and evening observations concluded ~30 min after sunset. We observed pika activity passively from a high vantage point, because pikas pay little attention to quiet observers (Conner 
   <a rid="ece31848-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0014">1983</a>). Trained observers continuously scanned the talus using the naked eye or 7 × 35 binoculars, and recorded the time of all visual and audible evidence of pika activity. Observers worked in pairs, but recorded data from nonoverlapping areas (~40 m radius) of the same talus patch, assigning pikas temporary ID numbers and sketching maps of their whereabouts to distinguish the activity of individuals (sensu Barash 
   <a rid="ece31848-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0002">1973</a>). A single pika call or sighting was considered a “unique event”. Additional calls or sightings of the same individual within 30 sec were recorded, but not considered new unique events. In this way, we categorized brief flourishes of activity as single events. We identified the type of observed behavior under the following nonmutually exclusive categories: haying (collecting or carrying vegetation in the mouth), foraging (directly consuming vegetation), moving fast, moving slow, and vigilant (stationary). We assumed that imperfect detection of pikas played a relatively small role in data collection, because pikas are highly detectable (85–95%) and relatively easy to identify for a stationary observer (Beever et al. 
   <a rid="ece31848-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0007">2010</a>; Moyer‐Horner et al. 
   <a rid="ece31848-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0040">2012</a>).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used multiple regression to associate minimum above‐talus temperature (
   <span class="italic">t</span>) and two site‐level variables (elevation, 
   <span class="italic">e</span>; slope aspect, 
   <span class="italic">a</span>) with aggregate above‐talus pika activity observations to understand whether field observations were generally congruent with predictions from our biophysical model. We only modeled pika activity with minimum above‐talus temperature because of moderate to high collinearity with other temperature measurements (0.55 &lt; 
   <span class="italic">r </span>&lt;
   <span class="italic"> </span>0.99) and because minimum above‐talus temperature best explained variability in pika activity in preliminary analysis (see Table S2). There was no strong collinearity detected among the remaining predictor variables (
   <span class="italic">r </span>=
   <span class="italic"> </span>0.06–0.26). We developed a set of 10 a priori hypotheses relating minimum above‐talus temperature, elevation, and slope aspect to observed pika activity (see Table S3) and evaluated relative empirical support for these hypotheses using AIC
   <sub>C</sub> (Burnham and Anderson 
   <a rid="ece31848-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0012">2002</a>). We derived parameter estimates that accounted for model selection uncertainty by performing model averaging among models with &gt;10% AIC weight and without uninformative parameters (Burnham and Anderson 
   <a rid="ece31848-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0012">2002</a>; Arnold 
   <a rid="ece31848-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0001">2010</a>). We log‐transformed the response variable (per capita pika sightings) to approximate a normal distribution (Ives 
   <a rid="ece31848-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0025">2015</a>). Log‐linear forms of 
   <span class="italic">e</span>,
   <span class="italic"> a</span>, and 
   <span class="italic">t</span> outperformed linear and quadratic forms in preliminary analysis (see Fig. S1); therefore, we used log‐linear forms of our predictor variables in the final analysis. We fit models and performed model selection using the package ‘AICcmodavg’ (Mazerolle 
   <a rid="ece31848-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0033">2013</a>) in R version 3.1.1 (R Core Development Team).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece31848-sec-0008" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Field simulations</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Niche Mapper field simulations were conducted using a diurnally active, ellipsoidal (2.25 a:b ratio) pika and a wind velocity at pika height (9 cm) varying diurnally from 0.1 to 4.0 m/s. Hair lengths and depths were scaled according to the total mass of the modeled animal, for example, a 120 g pika had 20% shorter and shallower hair than a 150 g pika. Climate and weather data were retrieved from the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration website (
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.noaa.gov" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.noaa.gov</span>) for Kalispell International Airport ([KIA] elevation 961 m), which is located ~30 km from Glacier National Park. When appropriate, we used a lapse rate of −8°C/km to derive mean monthly maximum and minimum temperatures (see below). In addition, we conducted sensitivity analyses to test Niche Mapper's robustness to input variable uncertainty (see Tables S1 and S4) and also compared its calculated above‐ and below‐talus temperatures to those we measured in the field. For simulations used as direct comparisons to field observations, we used site‐specific parameters, such as aspects and elevations of those sites, along with adjusted KIA temperatures from those days. For all other simulations, we used an eastern aspect, a 15° slope, GNP‐relevant elevations of 1500–2500 m, and long‐term (1981–2010) monthly averages from KIA.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We simulated a conservative warming scenario for 2100 of +5.0°C for all elevations (McWethy et al. 
   <a rid="ece31848-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0034">2010</a>). We used daily temperature ranges of 20°C, typical for summer months in GNP. The lowest temperature range (−10–10°C) is typical for June or September above 2500 m elevation. July and August temperature ranges at the lowest elevations in GNP (1500 m) are typically 4–22°C. We interpreted the ratio of the field metabolic rate over the BMR (FMR/BMR) to determine when pikas could be active above the talus. If an FMR/BMR ratio below 1.5 was required to remain below the animal's upper critical temperature, activity would probably be infeasible (Nagy 
   <a rid="ece31848-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0041">1987</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
