<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece31848-sec-0020" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our understanding of animal species' resilience to warming temperatures is a critical component of our ability to predict future range shifts and extirpations, and conserve biodiversity. Animals employ an array of behavioral strategies to avoid hyperthermia, such as changing body posture, seeking cooler microhabitats, reducing locomotion, and decreasing energy intake (Terrien et al. 
  <a rid="ece31848-bib-0057" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0057">2011</a>). Mammals in particular have the ability to regulate body temperature through fur properties, for example, by changing their seasonal molt timing. We examined some of these factors by presenting a coupled biophysical endotherm and microclimate model and comparing the results to empirical temperature and behavior data for a species, the American pika, whose ability to persist under future climate warming is unclear.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although recent work has shown that pika extirpations during the past 35–55 years in the Great Basin were correlated with high mean summer temperatures and both extreme heat in the summer and extreme cold in the winter (Beever et al. 
  <a rid="ece31848-bib-0005" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0005">2003</a>, 
  <a rid="ece31848-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0007">2010</a>), the mechanisms driving these losses are unclear. A critical gap exists regarding our understanding of how climate and pika physiology interact to affect behavior. Thus, it is unclear how pika physiological tolerances and behavioral flexibility will impact their individual and population‐level responses to rapid climate change. To date, the most thorough studies of pika behavior relative to temperature found that pikas were less active during midday, especially at lower elevation sites (Smith 
  <a rid="ece31848-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0052">1974</a>), and that activity durations were short. It was presumed that pikas used short activity bouts to limit heat accumulation and used the sub‐talus microclimate to dissipate heat (MacArthur and Wang 
  <a rid="ece31848-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0031">1974</a>). Others have reported midday activity decreases in GNP (Barash 
  <a rid="ece31848-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0002">1973</a>), as well as the Sierra Nevada (Severaid 
  <a rid="ece31848-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0049">1955</a>) and Great Basin (Hall 
  <a rid="ece31848-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0021">1946</a>). However, research in Colorado (Broadbooks 
  <a rid="ece31848-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0011">1965</a>; Krear 
  <a rid="ece31848-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0029">1965</a>), and the high Sierra (Grinnell and Storer 
  <a rid="ece31848-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0019">1917</a>) suggested that pikas remained active throughout the day. Thus, analysis of the mechanisms driving pika extirpations requires a greater biophysical understanding of pikas as well as their capacity to behaviorally thermoregulate.
 </p>
 <sec id="ece31848-sec-0021" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Microclimate data</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Uncertainty in a temperature‐occupancy threshold for pikas in the literature (e.g., Beever et al. 
   <a rid="ece31848-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0007">2010</a>; Millar and Westfall 
   <a rid="ece31848-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0036">2010</a>; Smith and Nagy 
   <a rid="ece31848-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0054">2015</a>) may stem from a reliance on broad‐scale weather data in place of pika‐relevant microclimate data (Potter et al. 
   <a rid="ece31848-bib-0045" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0045">2013</a>). Mean free atmospheric lapse rates are too coarse to accurately characterize temperature over complex terrain and at fine spatial scales (Minder et al. 
   <a rid="ece31848-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0037">2010</a>). Instead, regional monthly and daily surface temperature lapse rates such as those we calculated are more appropriate (Blandford et al. 
   <a rid="ece31848-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0009">2008</a>), especially when combined with a microclimate model such as Niche Mapper's. We identified relatively large variation in the relationship between the microclimates available to pikas and elevation in GNP; when consistent, this lapse rate had a 1–3°C greater magnitude than expected for the region (Ray et al. 
   <a rid="ece31848-bib-0046" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0046">2010</a>). Pikas could potentially exploit this variability during warmer summers by increasing their activity during short periods of favorable conditions or even increasing nocturnal activity (Severaid 
   <a rid="ece31848-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0049">1955</a>; Smith 
   <a rid="ece31848-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0052">1974</a>). We recommend caution when applying large‐scale climate data and model predictions, such as lapse rate estimates, in mountainous terrain.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The thermal refuge beneath the talus plays a critical role in pika thermoregulation. We found that it provided a buffer of up to 20°C during the hottest times of day, which is consistent with the literature (MacArthur and Wang 
   <a rid="ece31848-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0031">1974</a>; Varner and Dearing 
   <a rid="ece31848-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0059">2014</a>), although it can be more pronounced in the presence of subsurface ice features (Wilkening et al. 
   <a rid="ece31848-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0062">2015</a>). This buffer allows pikas to remain active under the talus surface and avoid acute heat stress or death on hot days (Fig. 
   <a rid="ece31848-fig-0006" ref-type="fig" href="#ece31848-fig-0006">6</a>). However, our simulations showed that relatively shallow talus may provide insufficient thermal refuge during heat waves, especially in the late afternoon and early evening, such that microclimates become unsuitable both above and below the talus.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece31848-sec-0022" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Metabolic chamber simulations</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We demonstrated that Niche Mapper accurately predicted pika metabolic rates from metabolic chamber experiments across a wide range of temperatures (Fig. 
   <a rid="ece31848-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#ece31848-fig-0002">2</a>). Sensitivity analyses revealed that fur properties, animal size, and ambient wind speed had relatively large physiological, and thus behavioral, consequences. These factors are rarely considered in studies of pika behavior and occurrence, but our work suggests that they may play a critical role in pika persistence in a warming climate.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece31848-sec-0023" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Behavior observations</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We found pika activity was lowest when temperatures were highest, which is consistent with the literature (e.g., Barash 
   <a rid="ece31848-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0002">1973</a>; MacArthur and Wang 
   <a rid="ece31848-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0031">1974</a>; Smith 
   <a rid="ece31848-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0052">1974</a>). Niche Mapper identified a limiting temperature threshold of 20°C for a 150 g pika with summer fur, above which we observed restrictions in most above‐talus behaviors (Fig. 
   <a rid="ece31848-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#ece31848-fig-0004">4</a>). We found no correlation between behavior and temperature below this threshold, suggesting that other factors may exert stronger influences on behavior below 20°C. For example, the predominance of short activity bouts may play a role in predator avoidance. Pika calls, which were negatively correlated with temperature, probably serve as a conspecific territorial defense mechanism and a predator alarm (Conner 
   <a rid="ece31848-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0014">1983</a>), but may also increase individual predation risk by revealing the caller's location (Smith and Ivins 
   <a rid="ece31848-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0053">1983</a>). Our results suggest that temperature may modulate an individual's cost–benefit curve for making vocalizations as well as restrict above‐talus activity.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Behavioral observations revealed that, in addition to temperature, site elevation and aspect combined to impact pika activity in complex ways. Pikas at higher elevations and north‐facing slopes were generally most active (Fig. 
   <a rid="ece31848-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#ece31848-fig-0003">3</a>). While high elevations and north‐facing slopes may contribute to the cooler conditions preferred by pikas, they also may contribute to differences in seasonality and phenology that are more pronounced at high latitudes. Later snowmelt and earlier, more frequent snowfall at high‐elevation north‐facing sites may constrain or shift the timing of the growing season, which could limit food availability. Pikas inhabiting such sites may be compelled to increase foraging and/or haying bouts per unit time relative to other sites to meet caloric demands for metabolic maintenance, reproduction, and food caching.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The seasonality of haying and breeding activities in pikas may have considerable impacts on observations of their behavior. Compared to higher elevations, pikas at lower elevations start and cease haying sooner, and breed up to 6 weeks sooner (Smith 
   <a rid="ece31848-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0052">1974</a>), which could be driven by elevational gradients in vegetation senescence (Smith 
   <a rid="ece31848-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0052">1974</a>; Huntly et al. 
   <a rid="ece31848-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0024">1986</a>). Additionally, pikas change their preferred forage throughout the season in response to changes in plant toxins and protein content, which may compel them to accelerate haying at different times (Dearing 
   <a rid="ece31848-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0016">1997</a>). We conducted our field observations during a 10‐day period to reduce behavioral changes due to seasonality. However, spatial differences in seasonality across sites may have contributed to the support for elevation, aspect, and elevation × aspect terms as predictors of pika activity (Fig. 
   <a rid="ece31848-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#ece31848-fig-0003">3</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece31848-sec-0024" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Field simulations and activity observations</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used simulations to demonstrate pika physiological activity constraints over a range of temperatures, elevations, and fur properties. The metabolic consequences of thermoregulation are reflected in the FMR/BMR ratio, which constrains animals at low and high temperature extremes. Pikas must maintain an FMR of at least 1.5 ×  BMR to remain active above the talus, but as low as possible above this threshold to conserve energy. While our summer‐month simulations produced FMR/BMR ratios no greater than 3.0, higher ratios could occur in winter when pikas face hypothermia.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We demonstrated that fur properties, molt timing, and animal size have significant metabolic impacts on pikas, thereby constraining activity time (Fig. 
   <a rid="ece31848-fig-0007" ref-type="fig" href="#ece31848-fig-0007">7</a>). The role of fur properties in pika behavior, morphology, and physiology has, to date, been unexamined. To our knowledge, only three studies have documented pika fur properties. Krear (
   <a rid="ece31848-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0029">1965</a>) and Howell (
   <a rid="ece31848-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0022">1924</a>) documented two annual molts, noting that summer pelage is generally worn for &lt; 2 months and that winter fur is up to twice the length of summer fur, while Severaid (
   <a rid="ece31848-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0049">1955</a>) examined the effect of reproductive status on molt timing. However, the extent to which subpopulations inhabiting disparate climatic regions (or microclimates on the same mountain) vary in fur properties and molt timing is not well known. Our simulations suggested that plasticity in molt timing, to a certain degree, may reduce activity restrictions predicted under future warming scenarios. In particular, pikas that shed their winter pelage sooner could be less restricted in early growing season activity.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Geographic variation in size and pelage can have substantial biophysical impacts on endotherms (Briscoe et al. 
   <a rid="ece31848-bib-0010" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0010">2014</a>). Range‐wide variation in pika body size is poorly documented, yet we demonstrated that body size could affect potential activity time under climate change. Smith and Weston (
   <a rid="ece31848-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0055">1990</a>) reported interpopulation variation in pika mean body mass ranging from 121 to 176 g, but their sample was relatively limited in size and geographic extent. In addition to limiting activity (Fig. 
   <a rid="ece31848-fig-0007" ref-type="fig" href="#ece31848-fig-0007">7</a>), animal size may interact with temperature to impact dispersal. Smith (
   <a rid="ece31848-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0052">1974</a>) suggested that pikas at low elevations were limited primarily by low colonization success associated with higher temperatures, and that furthermore these pikas were forced to disperse during the hottest times of the season. However, smaller dispersing juveniles (Millar and Tapper 
   <a rid="ece31848-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0035">1973</a>) can dissipate heat more efficiently and remain active at higher temperatures (Fig. 
   <a rid="ece31848-fig-0007" ref-type="fig" href="#ece31848-fig-0007">7</a>). More range‐wide data on variation in fur properties, molt timing, and animal size, especially for at‐risk subpopulations, is critical to improve our understanding of pika thermoregulation and potential responses to future warming.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The nocturnal activity of pikas warrants further investigation, especially at warmer low‐elevation sites (e.g., Beever et al. 
   <a rid="ece31848-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0006">2008</a>). Little is known about nocturnal activity in pikas; nocturnal activity may be restricted to certain regions and subpopulations, or may be a behavioral adaptation available to all pikas. While several occurrences of nocturnal activity and vocalizations have been documented in the Sierra Nevada and GNP (Smith 
   <a rid="ece31848-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0052">1974</a>; LMH 
   <span class="italic">pers. obs</span>.), Krear (
   <a rid="ece31848-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0029">1965</a>) observed no nocturnal activity during extensive observations in Colorado. The risk of depredation by efficient nocturnal predators such as owls and weasels could play a role in restricting pika nocturnal activity.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results presented here combine mechanistic biophysical and empirical correlative approaches to investigate the temperature‐limitations of American pikas. The approaches complemented one another, and together formed a more complete understanding of pika heat tolerance and thermoregulatory options. The empirical observations and correlative analyses provided critical support for the mechanistic model's predictions while also identifying important factors, in this case elevation, aspect, and possibly seasonality that were not modeled biophysically. In turn, the biophysical model provided mechanistic support for our understanding of the drivers of pika behaviors observed by us and other researchers. Future research could evaluate allowable activity time across the pika's range to model spatial patterns of occupancy and extirpation.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Niche Mapper simulations allowed us to identify additional significant factors and generate hypotheses for investigation by future empirical studies. In the case of American pikas, the complex relationship between fur properties, body size, behavior, and microclimate structure may be critical to species persistence. For instance, we found that smaller pikas with shorter fur were better able to tolerate higher temperatures and remain active longer than larger pikas with thicker fur. Rising temperatures will present selective pressures on pika populations relative to the characteristics that we identified. Approaches that combine correlative and mechanistic analyses are becoming increasingly necessary in an age of rapid climate change.</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
