<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece31848-sec-0009" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results</div>
 <sec id="ece31848-sec-0010" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Building and validating the biophysical model</div>
  <sec id="ece31848-sec-0011" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Microclimate data</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The observed altitudinal lapse rate varied depending on the prevailing daily weather patterns and time of day. Temperature inversions were more frequent during mornings (07:00) and in September (see Tables S5–7). We measured a consistent lapse rate (
    <span class="italic">R</span>
    <span class="sup">2 </span>&gt; 0.75) during seven of 24 measurements, for which the mean lapse rate was −9.46°C/km. The midday (14:00) mean for July and August measurements was −8.08°C/km.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The difference between below‐ and above‐talus temperature varied considerably depending on the time of day, and generally below‐talus temperatures were less variable than above‐talus temperatures. In the mornings (05:15–08:15), temperatures below the talus were slightly warmer than above‐talus conditions, with higher minimum (mean°C below talus – mean°C above talus [standard deviation]: +2.50°C [1.69°C]), and maximum temperatures (+2.62°C [1.69°C]). During the warmest part of the day (13:00–16:00), the temperature‐damping effects of the below‐talus thermal refuge were most pronounced, exhibiting substantially lower minimum (−13.08°C [2.42°C]) and maximum temperatures (−15.44°C [1.94°C]). The evenings (19:00–21:00) produced higher minimum temperatures below‐talus (+2.75°C [1.95°C]), but lower maximums (−3.75°C [1.78°C]).</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sensitivity analyses of Niche Mapper's microclimate model revealed sufficient stability in response to input variability within ranges expected in the field, consistent with previous tests (Kearney et al. 
    <a rid="ece31848-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0027">2014a</a>,
    <a rid="ece31848-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0028">b</a>). Varying the specific heat of the talus by up to 30% (700–1000 J/kg K) produced a maximum 12% change in modeled surface temperatures and 10% change in temperatures 15 cm below the surface. Increasing wind speed from 0.1 to 1.5 m/sec decreased modeled temperatures at animal height (9 cm) by a maximum of 15%; further increases from 1.5 to 9 m/sec produced at most a 10% temperature decrease. Modifying cloud cover from 0 to 100% and aspect from south to north produced a maximum 9% and 2.5% decrease in temperature at animal height, respectively. The remaining inputs produced &lt;2% changes in modeled temperature when varied within expected ranges.
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The microclimate model also produced relatively robust estimates of above‐ and below‐talus temperatures when compared to field measurements (see Figs. S2–S5). Surface temperature estimates most closely matched observed when a −8°C/km altitudinal lapse rate was used to estimate air temperature and when wind speed was allowed to vary diurnally from 0 to 4 m/sec. Below‐talus temperature estimates fit field measurements closest using a modeled depth of 20 cm for the 1056 m site and 15 cm for the 2521 m site. The microclimate model assumed a solid below‐surface substrate (in contrast to porous talus deposits); thus, simulated depths were 100–200% less than the size of the rocks under which the loggers were placed.</p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece31848-sec-0012" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Metabolic chamber simulations</div>
  <sec id="ece31848-sec-0013" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sensitivity analyses for key animal model inputs</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The effect of ambient temperature on metabolic rate was most heavily influenced by the core temperature, body posture, size, and fur properties of the modeled pika. Increasing core temperature from 38 to 43°C produced 8–25% higher metabolic demands (W/g), depending on ambient temperature. Changing posture from a 3:2 to 3:1 ellipsoid produced ~10% higher metabolic demands in a 150 g pika at temperatures ranging from −15 to 30°C. At cooler temperatures, pikas with lower mass (e.g., 109 g), and thus smaller volume, were at an energetic disadvantage because they were required to generate proportionally more metabolic heat to maintain core temperatures. However, above 22°C, smaller pikas had an energetic advantage in that they were able to avoid overheating at higher temperatures. Additionally, summer fur allowed pikas of all sizes to stay in their thermal neutral zone at temperatures 4°C higher than those with winter fur (see Fig. S6). Increasing fur density from 250 to 3000 hairs/cm
    <span class="sup">2</span> produced 61% lower metabolic rates at 0°C; further increases from 3000 to 15,000 hairs/cm
    <span class="sup">2</span> produced 15% lower rates. Increasing O
    <sub>2</sub> extraction efficiency from 5 to 30% produced up to 6% lower metabolic rates, while increasing flesh thermal conductivity from 0.5 to 2.8 (W/mK) increased metabolic rates by up to 13%. Finally, when we modeled a constant solar input of 500 W/m
    <span class="sup">2</span> directly overhead, increasing pelt reflectivity from 15 to 90% produced 15% higher metabolic rates.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="ece31848-sec-0014" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Comparison to metabolic chamber measurements</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Metabolic rate simulations for 109 g pikas fell within the range empirically derived by MacArthur and Wang (
    <a rid="ece31848-bib-0030" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0030">1973</a>) for a variety of body postures and fur properties (Fig. 
    <a rid="ece31848-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#ece31848-fig-0002">2</a>). Niche Mapper simulated an upper critical temperature threshold (FMR = BMR) of ~25°C, which is similar to observed values (MacArthur and Wang 
    <a rid="ece31848-bib-0030" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0030">1973</a>; Smith 
    <a rid="ece31848-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0052">1974</a>).
   </p>
   <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece31848-fig-0002" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Niche Mapper simulations of American pika metabolic rate (W) in a metabolic chamber at a range of temperatures, animal shape (ellipsoid a:b ratio 1.5 and 2.25) and fur properties. Solid lines represent the range of empirical minimum metabolic rates for pikas measured by MacArthur and Wang (
      <a rid="ece31848-bib-0030" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0030">1973</a>). The dashed lines represent the target 
      <span style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">BMR</span> range of 0.923 W ± 5%.
     </p>
    </div>
    <div id="nlm-graphic-5" xlink:href="ECE3-5-5810-g002" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece31848-sec-0015" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Field observations of pika activity in GNP</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There were three closely competing models within 0.4 AIC that combined for ~90% of the total AIC weight; the top model, {ln(
   <span class="italic">e</span>) + ln(
   <span class="italic">a</span>) + ln(
   <span class="italic">t</span>) + [ln(
   <span class="italic">e</span>) × ln(
   <span class="italic">a</span>)]}, contained all covariates that were considered and therefore had the most parameters (
   <span class="italic">k</span> = 5), followed by more parsimonious models [ln(
   <span class="italic">e</span>) + ln(
   <span class="italic">a</span>) + ln(
   <span class="italic">t</span>)] and [ln(
   <span class="italic">a</span>) + ln(
   <span class="italic">t</span>)] (see Table S8). We calculated model‐averaged regression coefficients and unconditional 85% confidence intervals for parameters in these models to reduce model selection bias (Burnham and Anderson 
   <a rid="ece31848-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0012">2002</a>; Arnold 
   <a rid="ece31848-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0001">2010</a>) and produce conservative estimates of effect sizes (Fig. 
   <a rid="ece31848-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#ece31848-fig-0003">3</a>A and B) because some estimates varied to an appreciable extent among models (Fig. 
   <a rid="ece31848-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#ece31848-fig-0003">3</a>C and E). Model‐averaged parameter estimates suggested that pikas were generally more active at higher elevations (
   <div id="nlm-math-1" class="math">
    <div class="msub">
     <div accent="true" class="mover">
      <div accent="true" class="mover">
       <div class="mrow">
        <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">β</span>
       </div>
       <div class="mrow">
        <span stretchy="false" class="mo">¯</span>
       </div>
      </div>
      <span stretchy="false" class="mo">^</span>
     </div>
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mtext">ln</span>
      <span stretchy="false" class="mo">(</span>
      <span class="mi">e</span>
      <span stretchy="false" class="mo">)</span>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div> = 0.36, SE = 0.35), on north‐facing slopes (
   <div id="nlm-math-2" class="math">
    <div class="msub">
     <div accent="true" class="mover">
      <div accent="true" class="mover">
       <div class="mrow">
        <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">β</span>
       </div>
       <div class="mrow">
        <span stretchy="false" class="mo">¯</span>
       </div>
      </div>
      <span stretchy="false" class="mo">^</span>
     </div>
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mtext">ln</span>
      <span stretchy="false" class="mo">(</span>
      <span class="mi">a</span>
      <span stretchy="false" class="mo">)</span>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div> = 0.96, SE = 1.00), and when minimum above‐talus temperatures were cooler (
   <div id="nlm-math-3" class="math">
    <div class="msub">
     <div accent="true" class="mover">
      <div accent="true" class="mover">
       <div class="mrow">
        <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">β</span>
       </div>
       <div class="mrow">
        <span stretchy="false" class="mo">¯</span>
       </div>
      </div>
      <span stretchy="false" class="mo">^</span>
     </div>
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mtext">ln</span>
      <span stretchy="false" class="mo">(</span>
      <span class="mi">t</span>
      <span stretchy="false" class="mo">)</span>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div> = −0.76, SE = 0.22) (Fig. 
   <a rid="ece31848-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#ece31848-fig-0003">3</a>A). Elevation and aspect were linked by a negative interaction (
   <div id="nlm-math-4" class="math">
    <div class="msub">
     <div accent="true" class="mover">
      <div accent="true" class="mover">
       <div class="mrow">
        <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">β</span>
       </div>
       <div class="mrow">
        <span stretchy="false" class="mo">¯</span>
       </div>
      </div>
      <span stretchy="false" class="mo">^</span>
     </div>
     <div class="mrow">
      <span stretchy="false" class="mo">[</span>
      <span class="mtext">ln</span>
      <span stretchy="false" class="mo">(</span>
      <span class="mi">e</span>
      <span stretchy="false" class="mo">)</span>
      <span class="mo">×</span>
      <span class="mtext">ln</span>
      <span stretchy="false" class="mo">(</span>
      <span class="mi">a</span>
      <span stretchy="false" class="mo">)</span>
      <span stretchy="false" class="mo">]</span>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div> = −0.35, SE = 0.59), which suggested that pikas on south‐facing slopes were less active at low elevations than at high elevations, but pikas were more active above the talus on north‐facing slopes regardless of elevation (Fig. 
   <a rid="ece31848-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" href="#ece31848-fig-0003">3</a>A).
  </p>
  <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece31848-fig-0003" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Relationship between field‐based observations of pika activity, minimum above‐talus temperature, elevation, and slope aspect. The top graph (A) shows model‐averaged predicted regression surfaces at three temperatures: 25% quartile, mean, and 75% quartile. Beta coefficients and 85% confidence intervals (Arnold 
     <a rid="ece31848-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0001">2010</a>) are shown (B) following model averaging, and for the (C) top‐ranked model, (D) second‐ranked model, and (E) third‐ranked model.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div id="nlm-graphic-7" xlink:href="ECE3-5-5810-g003" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition to our model selection‐based approach evaluating aggregate pika activity in relation to minimum above‐talus temperature and site‐level variables, we used an ANOVA‐based approach to evaluate whether minimum above‐talus temperature and time of day were significantly related to specific pika behaviors. We found that pikas were significantly more active in all behavior categories (except for haying) when minimum above‐talus temperature was below 20°C (all 
   <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.01), which corresponded with a metabolic threshold predicted by Niche Mapper (Fig. 
   <a rid="ece31848-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#ece31848-fig-0004">4</a>). Calls per occupant were influenced by time of day and temperature; there were 14.7 fewer calls per occupant during midday than during morning or evening (
   <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.01) and 0.5 fewer calls per occupant for every 1°C (
   <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.01, 
   <span class="italic">R</span>
   <span class="sup">2 </span>= 0.08). Data were also collected on whether or not pikas were exposed to direct sunlight while making short or long call vocalizations. Long calls are typically made by males and probably related to mating (Smith and Weston 
   <a rid="ece31848-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0055">1990</a>). Only one of 149 (0.67%) recorded long calls and 400 of 6699 (6%) of short calls were made while pikas were exposed to direct sunlight.
  </p>
  <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece31848-fig-0004" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Figure 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>The top panel (A) shows 
     <span style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">FMR</span>/
     <span style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">BMR</span> ratios across a range of temperatures. The red vertical line denotes the temperature threshold at which modeled 150 g pikas could not maintain an 
     <span style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">FMR</span>/
     <span style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">BMR</span> above 1.5. The bottom panel (B) shows the per capita frequency of pika behaviors when minimum above‐talus temperature was above or below 20°C during field observations in 
     <span style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">GNP</span>. Error bars represent ±1 
     <span style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">SE</span>. *Denotes a significant difference between the two groups.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div id="nlm-graphic-9" xlink:href="ECE3-5-5810-g004" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece31848-sec-0016" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Field simulations</div>
  <sec id="ece31848-sec-0017" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Comparing modeled and observed behavior</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Niche Mapper's activity level predictions were similar to observations at field sites in GNP. Predicted activity levels, quantified by the ratio of maximum allowable FMR to BMR, were lowest when temperatures were high and increased as temperatures dropped. Above 20°C, modeled 150 g pikas began physiologically thermoregulating (vasodilation, raising body temperature) in order to maintain a target metabolic rate of 1.5 ×  their BMR, which corresponds to the minimum value necessary for activity (Fig. 
    <a rid="ece31848-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#ece31848-fig-0004">4</a>A). Additionally, increasing predicted allowable activity levels corresponded to the highest rates and variance of observed per capita pika activity (Fig. 
    <a rid="ece31848-fig-0005" ref-type="fig" href="#ece31848-fig-0005">5</a>).
   </p>
   <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece31848-fig-0005" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <span class="label">Figure 5</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Comparison of Niche Mapper predicted maximum allowable activity at field sites (
      <span class="italic">x</span>‐axis) with observed pika activity frequency at those same sites in the field (
      <span class="italic">y</span>‐axis).
     </p>
    </div>
    <div id="nlm-graphic-11" xlink:href="ECE3-5-5810-g005" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Using 1.5 FMR/BMR as the minimum metabolic ratio for activity, a simulated 120 g pika in GNP was able to remain active above the talus during all available diurnal hours of the day (June and July = 21, August = 19 h), regardless of elevation or pelage (summer vs. winter). However, a 150 g pika with winter pelage faced physiological limitations that reduced allowable activity time by 19.0% in July at 1500 m, 4.8% in July at 1750 m, and 15.8% in August at 1500 m.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="ece31848-sec-0018" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Simulating the below‐talus thermal refuge</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We simulated a heat wave with temperatures ~10°C higher than current July means at low elevations in GNP to explore how the talus might buffer a pika from acute heat stress. For several consecutive hours in the middle of the day, the model pika was unable to maintain even its BMR without overheating, suggesting death from hyperthermia. However, at sufficient depth below the surface, the model pika could retreat and maintain its BMR for all hours of the day without overheating (Fig. 
    <a rid="ece31848-fig-0006" ref-type="fig" href="#ece31848-fig-0006">6</a>).
   </p>
   <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece31848-fig-0006" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <span class="label">Figure 6</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Niche Mapper simulations of 
      <span style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">FMR</span>/
      <span style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">BMR</span> for a pika at three depths (surface, 15 cm below‐surface, and 20 cm below‐surface) during a heat wave. Activity cannot occur below 1.5 
      <span style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">FMR</span>/
      <span style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">BMR</span>.
     </p>
    </div>
    <div id="nlm-graphic-13" xlink:href="ECE3-5-5810-g006" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </sec>
  <sec id="ece31848-sec-0019" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Simulations under a future warming scenario</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A 2100 warming scenario of +5°C resulted in restrictions in allowable activity time (diurnal + crepuscular hours) for simulated pikas in GNP, especially when pikas had a higher body mass and thicker fur. Simulations suggested that allowable activity time for a 120 g pika with summer fur in year 2100 will decline by 9.5%, but only in July and at a low elevation (1500 m). However, allowable activity time for a 150 g pika with summer fur declined by 10.5–23.8% in July and August at both 1500 m (Fig 
    <a rid="ece31848-fig-0007" ref-type="fig" href="#ece31848-fig-0007">7</a>A) and 1750 m elevation sites.
   </p>
   <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece31848-fig-0007" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <span class="label">Figure 7</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Niche Mapper simulations of percent (%) change in metabolically allowable daily above‐talus activity time by year 2100 for a pika at 1500 m elevation in Glacier National Park, 
      <span style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">MT</span>, for (A) a 150 g pika during summer months in summer fur and winter fur and (B) for different sizes of pikas with varying fur depths, during the month of August.
     </p>
    </div>
    <div id="nlm-graphic-15" xlink:href="ECE3-5-5810-g007" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">With winter fur, potential activity time for a 150 g pika declined under the future warming scenario at elevations below 2500 m. In June, when many pikas may still have winter fur, allowable activity time declined by 23.8% and 4.8% at 1500 m and 1750 m, respectively. Further investigation of the impacts of interactions between body size and fur properties on allowable activity for a pika at low elevation (1500 m) in GNP in year 2100 revealed no activity restrictions for a 120 g pika with 30% shorter and shallower fur (compared to the measured specimen), but 37% fewer activity hours for a 180 g pika with 20% longer and thicker fur (Fig. 
    <a rid="ece31848-fig-0007" ref-type="fig" href="#ece31848-fig-0007">7</a>B).
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
</sec>
