<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece31848-sec-0021" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Microclimate data</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Uncertainty in a temperature‐occupancy threshold for pikas in the literature (e.g., Beever et al. 
  <a rid="ece31848-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0007">2010</a>; Millar and Westfall 
  <a rid="ece31848-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0036">2010</a>; Smith and Nagy 
  <a rid="ece31848-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0054">2015</a>) may stem from a reliance on broad‐scale weather data in place of pika‐relevant microclimate data (Potter et al. 
  <a rid="ece31848-bib-0045" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0045">2013</a>). Mean free atmospheric lapse rates are too coarse to accurately characterize temperature over complex terrain and at fine spatial scales (Minder et al. 
  <a rid="ece31848-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0037">2010</a>). Instead, regional monthly and daily surface temperature lapse rates such as those we calculated are more appropriate (Blandford et al. 
  <a rid="ece31848-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0009">2008</a>), especially when combined with a microclimate model such as Niche Mapper's. We identified relatively large variation in the relationship between the microclimates available to pikas and elevation in GNP; when consistent, this lapse rate had a 1–3°C greater magnitude than expected for the region (Ray et al. 
  <a rid="ece31848-bib-0046" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0046">2010</a>). Pikas could potentially exploit this variability during warmer summers by increasing their activity during short periods of favorable conditions or even increasing nocturnal activity (Severaid 
  <a rid="ece31848-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0049">1955</a>; Smith 
  <a rid="ece31848-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0052">1974</a>). We recommend caution when applying large‐scale climate data and model predictions, such as lapse rate estimates, in mountainous terrain.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The thermal refuge beneath the talus plays a critical role in pika thermoregulation. We found that it provided a buffer of up to 20°C during the hottest times of day, which is consistent with the literature (MacArthur and Wang 
  <a rid="ece31848-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0031">1974</a>; Varner and Dearing 
  <a rid="ece31848-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0059">2014</a>), although it can be more pronounced in the presence of subsurface ice features (Wilkening et al. 
  <a rid="ece31848-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" href="#ece31848-bib-0062">2015</a>). This buffer allows pikas to remain active under the talus surface and avoid acute heat stress or death on hot days (Fig. 
  <a rid="ece31848-fig-0006" ref-type="fig" href="#ece31848-fig-0006">6</a>). However, our simulations showed that relatively shallow talus may provide insufficient thermal refuge during heat waves, especially in the late afternoon and early evening, such that microclimates become unsuitable both above and below the talus.
 </p>
</sec>
