<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="supplementary-material" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Supporting information</div>
 <div content-type="local-data" class="supplementary-material" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <div class="caption">
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Figure S1.</span> Graphical representations of the supported log‐linear relationships between environmental variables and field‐based observations of pika activity in Glacier National Park, MT during the summers of 2008 and 2009.
   </p>
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Figure S2</span>. Comparison of NicheMapper microclimate model surface temperature estimates to measured surface temperatures in GNP at 1056 m elevation, between July 15–July 24, 2009.
   </p>
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Figure S3</span>. Comparison of NicheMapper microclimate model surface temperature estimates to measured surface temperatures in GNP at 2521 m elevation, between July 15–July 24, 2009.
   </p>
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Figure S4</span>. Comparison of NicheMapper microclimate model below‐talus temperature estimates to measured below‐talus temperatures in GNP at 1056 m elevation, between July 15–July 24, 2009.
   </p>
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Figure S5</span>. Comparison of NicheMapper microclimate model below‐talus temperature estimates to measured below‐talus temperatures in GNP at 2521 m elevation, between July 15–July 24, 2009.
   </p>
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Figure S6</span>. Niche Mapper simulations of an American pika (
    <span class="italic">Ochotona princeps</span>) in a metabolic chamber, across a range of temperatures, varying the size and fur properties of the animal.
   </p>
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Table S1.</span> Properties used to parameterize the biophysical model for an American pika (
    <span class="italic">Ochotona princeps</span>).
   </p>
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Table S2.</span> Model selection results for the relationship between relevant temperature covariates and field‐based observations of pika activity in Glacier National Park, MT during the summers of 2008 and 2009.
   </p>
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Table S3.</span> Set of 10 a priori hypotheses relating a suite of environmental variables (
    <span class="italic">e</span>, elevation; 
    <span class="italic">a</span>, aspect; 
    <span class="italic">t</span>, minimum above talus temperature) to field‐based observations of pika activity in Glacier National Park, MT during the summers of 2008 and 2009.
   </p>
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Table S4.</span> Standard microclimate model inputs for Niche Mapper simulations of American pikas (
    <span class="italic">Ochotona princeps</span>) in Glacier National Park, Montana, USA.
   </p>
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Table S5.</span> Temperature (°C) data from time 0700 on the dates indicated in 2008, 1 m below the talus surface at seven sites in Glacier National Park, Montana.
   </p>
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Table S6.</span> Temperature (°C) data from time 1400 on the dates indicated in 2008 and 1 m below the talus surface at seven sites in Glacier National Park, Montana.
   </p>
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Table S7.</span> Temperature (°C) data from time 2000 on the dates indicated in 2008 and 1 m below the talus surface at seven sites in Glacier National Park, Montana.
   </p>
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Table S8.</span> Model selection results for analysis of field‐based observations of pika behavior (per capita pika activity) in Glacier National Park, Montana during the summers of 2008 and 2009.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="ECE3-5-5810-s001.docx" class="media" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Click here for additional data file.</p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </div>
</sec>
