<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Population structure can create spurious associations between genotypes and phenotypes (false positives). Nevertheless, when population structure covaries with adaptive genetic variation as in 
 <italic class="italic">P. strobus</italic> (Nadeau 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="nph14968-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>), over‐adjustment for population structure may decrease power and result in false negatives (Sork 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="nph14968-bib-0074" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). Therefore, three models were tested with 
 <sc class="sc">tassel</sc>: no correction (i.e. omitting the population structure and kinship effects); correction for population structure (
 <italic class="italic">
  <bold class="bold">Q</bold>
 </italic> model, i.e. omitting the kinship effects); and correction for population structure and for kinship (
 <italic class="italic">
  <bold class="bold">Q</bold>
 </italic> + 
 <italic class="italic">
  <bold class="bold">K</bold>
 </italic> model, i.e. full model). To obtain the population membership matrix (
 <italic class="italic">
  <bold class="bold">Q</bold>
 </italic>), we performed a discriminant analysis of principal components (DAPC; Jombart 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="nph14968-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>) using all 225 genotyped trees from this study and 821 additional trees (133 provenances) sampled across the entire range and genotyped on the same set of 128 SNPs taken from Nadeau 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. (
 <xref rid="nph14968-bib-0058" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). DAPC maximizes among‐population genetic variation while minimizing within‐group genetic variation. Therefore, this method is well suited for GPA analyses because population structure is removed by including the group memberships identified by DAPC as covariates in the 
 <sc class="sc">tassel</sc> model (Jombart 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="nph14968-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>). A complete description of the DAPC method can be found in Fig. 
 <xref rid="nph14968-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S5</xref>. We used the membership probabilities for 
 <italic class="italic">k</italic> = 3 clusters (
 <italic class="italic">k </italic>− 1 = 2 covariates) as the 
 <italic class="italic">
  <bold class="bold">Q</bold>
 </italic> matrix to correct for population structure in the 
 <sc class="sc">tassel</sc> analyses (Fig. 
 <xref rid="nph14968-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S5</xref>b). The three clusters detected were similar to those in Nadeau 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. (
 <xref rid="nph14968-bib-0058" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>): a southern and a northern group with weak west to east differentiation (Fig. 
 <xref rid="nph14968-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S5</xref>c). To summarize results from the three models (no correction, 
 <italic class="italic">
  <bold class="bold">Q</bold>
 </italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">
  <bold class="bold">Q</bold>
 </italic> + 
 <italic class="italic">
  <bold class="bold">K</bold>
 </italic>), each SNP–phenotype association was classified as follows: ‘very likely’ when significant (
 <italic class="italic">P </italic>&lt;
 <italic class="italic"> </italic>0.05) for all three models; ‘likely’ when significant for two out of the three models; ‘uncertain’ when significant for only one model; and ‘no evidence’ when not significant in the three models (Girardin 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="nph14968-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). While summarizing results across models may help controlling for errors, the likelihood of false discoveries is significantly raised under multiple testing. Because we tested a small number of SNPs (128), we preferred to reduce the risk of false negatives (i.e. not detecting true associations) by using 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>‐values that were not corrected for multiple testing. Instead, the cross‐validation of the SNPs detected by 
 <sc class="sc">tassel</sc> with the 21 candidate SNPs found in Nadeau 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. (
 <xref rid="nph14968-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>), which used independent samples and different methods, should reduce false positives and make a stronger case for those candidate genes. GPAs excluding the two southern group populations (
 <italic class="italic">n </italic>=
 <italic class="italic"> </italic>221) gave similar results (Table 
 <xref rid="nph14968-sup-0003" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S4</xref>).
</p>
