<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName A++V2.4.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.4?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName springer2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Rep</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientific Reports</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-2322</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Nature Publishing Group UK</publisher-name><publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6629672</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">46646</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-019-46646-2</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Enhancement of light emission in Bragg monolayer-thick quantum well structures</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-9840-7364</contrib-id><name><surname>Pozina</surname><given-names>Galia</given-names></name><address><email>galia.pozina@liu.se</email></address><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Ivanov</surname><given-names>Konstantin A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-0051-0823</contrib-id><name><surname>Morozov</surname><given-names>Konstantin M.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Girshova</surname><given-names>Elizaveta I.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Egorov</surname><given-names>Anton Yu.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-4792-7738</contrib-id><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>Stewart J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kaliteevski</surname><given-names>Mikhail A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref></contrib><aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 2162 9922</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.5640.7</institution-id><institution>Department of Physics, Chemistry and Biology (IFM), </institution><institution>Link&#x000f6;ping University, </institution></institution-wrap>S-581 83 Link&#x000f6;ping, Sweden </aff><aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0001 0413 4629</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.35915.3b</institution-id><institution>ITMO University, </institution></institution-wrap>Kronverkskiy pr. 49, 197101 St., Petersburg, Russian Federation </aff><aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>St-Petersburg Academic University, Khlopina 8/3, 194021 St., Petersburg, Russian Federation </aff><aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0004 0548 8017</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.423485.c</institution-id><institution>Ioffe Institute, </institution></institution-wrap>Politekhnicheskaya 26, 194021 St., Petersburg, Russian Federation </aff><aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="ISNI">0000 0000 8700 0572</institution-id><institution-id institution-id-type="GRID">grid.8250.f</institution-id><institution>Department of Physics, </institution><institution>Durham University, </institution></institution-wrap>South Road, Durham, DH1 3LE UK </aff></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>15</day><month>7</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="pmc-release"><day>15</day><month>7</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>9</volume><elocation-id>10162</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>1</day><month>11</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>28</day><month>6</month><year>2019</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019</copyright-statement><license license-type="OpenAccess"><license-p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the article&#x02019;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/</ext-link>.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract id="Abs1"><p id="Par1">Control over spontaneous emission rate is important for improving efficiency in different semiconductor applications including lasers, LEDs and photovoltaics. Usually, an emitter should be placed inside the cavity to increase the spontaneous emission rate, although it is technologically challenging. Here we experimentally demonstrate a phenomenon of super-radiance observed in a cavity-less periodic Bragg structure based on InAs monolayer-thick multiple quantum wells (MQW). The collective super-radiant mode shows enhanced emission rate for specific angles and frequencies. This behaviour correlates with the calculations demonstrating individual spots of the enhanced Purcell coefficient near the Bragg condition curve. This study provides a perspective for realization of surface emitting cavity-less lasers with distributed feedback.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="npg-subject"><title>Subject terms</title><kwd>Nanophotonics and plasmonics</kwd><kwd>Photonic crystals</kwd><kwd>Nonlinear optics</kwd><kwd>Electronic properties and materials</kwd><kwd>Polaritons</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="FundRef">https://doi.org/10.13039/501100006769</institution-id><institution>Russian Science Foundation (RSF)</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>16-12-10503</award-id><award-id>16-12-10503</award-id><award-id>16-12-10503</award-id><award-id>16-12-10503</award-id><principal-award-recipient><name><surname>Ivanov</surname><given-names>Konstantin A.</given-names></name><name><surname>Morozov</surname><given-names>Konstantin M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Girshova</surname><given-names>Elizaveta I.</given-names></name><name><surname>Kaliteevski</surname><given-names>Mikhail A.</given-names></name></principal-award-recipient></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name><meta-value>&#x000a9; The Author(s) 2019</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction"><title>Introduction</title><p id="Par2">Mastering the modification of the radiation emission rates paves the way to a realization of new functionality in optoelectronic devices. The principal way to enhance these rates is to place an emitter in a strongly structured optical medium, which leads to the alteration of the photon density of states (DOS). A direct consequence of this, as follows from the Fermi&#x02019;s golden rule, is the so-called Purcell effect<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref></sup>. Purcell suggested that the control of the spontaneous emission rate of a quasi-monochromatic dipole can be done in a cavity<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref></sup>. Then the spontaneous emission rate at the resonance frequency with the cavity mode will be enhanced, while emission at other non-resonance frequencies will be suppressed. However, the technological challenge is to integrate such resonators in devices demonstrating considerable output power since experimental realization requires cavities with high Q-factors and small mode volumes.</p><p id="Par3">On the other hand, the spectacular phenomena of the super-radiance (SR) requires no cavity but only an ensemble of two-level atoms occurring in symmetric Dicke states to obtain an enhanced emission rate<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref></sup>. Remarkably, atoms in these states show a rate of spontaneous emission proportional to the square of the number of emitters N. Such super-radiant behaviour of the emission is a result of the strong quantum correlations among the emitters occurring in symmetric Dicke states<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref></sup>. However, it is difficult to prepare a highly entangled states for a large number of particles. From this point of view, a revolutionary technological breakthrough can be achieved for multiple quantum well (MQW) structures based on mature III-V semiconductors. Theoretically it was shown by Ivchenko <italic>et al</italic>.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref></sup> that such interaction can occur for the Bragg arrangement of MQW structures, when the period of the structure <italic>d</italic> is coupled to the exciton emission frequency <italic>&#x003c9;</italic> by the Bragg condition,<disp-formula id="Equ1"><label>1</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$n\omega d\,\cos \,\phi =\pi c$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M2" display="block"><mml:mi>n</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003c9;</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mspace width=".25em"/><mml:mi>cos</mml:mi><mml:mspace width=".10em"/><mml:mi>&#x003d5;</mml:mi><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c0;</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_46646_Article_Equ1.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>where <italic>&#x003c6;</italic> is the angle of propagation in the structure, and <italic>n</italic> is the refractive index of the structure. The angle of emission into the vacuum <italic>&#x003b8;</italic> is described by<disp-formula id="Equ2"><label>2</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\omega d\sqrt{{n}^{2}-{\sin }^{2}\theta }=\pi c$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M4" display="block"><mml:mi>&#x003c9;</mml:mi><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:msqrt><mml:mrow><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>n</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mo>&#x02212;</mml:mo><mml:msup><mml:mrow><mml:mi>sin</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mn>2</mml:mn></mml:msup><mml:mi>&#x003b8;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msqrt><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c0;</mml:mi><mml:mi>c</mml:mi></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_46646_Article_Equ2.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par4">The first experiments with Bragg MQWs have demonstrated the resonant reflection coefficient of ~7%<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref></sup>, while for the same but single semiconductor QW the magnitude of the exciton resonance in reflection spectra was less than 1%<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref></sup>. Advances in epitaxial technology have allowed fabrication of highly coherent III-V semiconductor-based Bragg MQW structures demonstrating excitonic reflection above 50%<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. Recent studies of luminescence properties in Bragg MQW structures grown by molecular beam epitaxy (MBE), formed by InAs monolayers confined in GaAs matrix, has demonstrated a clear appearance of an additional blue-shifted collective emission mode revealing a super-radiant behaviour. It was preliminary assigned to the super-radiant emission of coherently coupled individual quantum well excitons<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par5">However, to make a decisive conclusion about the nature of the additional mode observed<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>, we prove here that the new mode with super-radiant behaviour is in fact the result of coherent interference between the emissions from individual quantum wells and is not associated with the recombination of hot nonequilibrium carriers. Furthermore, we give insight into fundamental problems regarding the modification of the spontaneous emission rate in InAs single monolayer MQWs with GaAs barriers using a detailed analysis of a modification of the spontaneous emission rate in such systems. Our experimental and theoretical results lead not only to an understanding of the optical properties in Bragg MQW structures but also pave the way to novel potential applications, ranging from optical logic devices and optical switches to the realization of highly interesting surface emitting cavity-less lasers with distributed feedback. These also combine advantages such as low divergence typical for VCSEL<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref></sup> with high monochromatic properties typical for distributed feedback lasers<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref></sup>.</p><sec id="Sec2"><title>Mixing of exciton states in the triple monolayer QW structure</title><p id="Par6">The structure for the experimental studies is illustrated in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. Also, the geometry of the excitation and detection of the emission is indicated. The sample grown by MBE consists of 60 triple InAs monolayer quantum wells, where InAs monolayers are separated by 10&#x02009;nm of GaAs, while the triple quantum wells are separated from each other by 102&#x02009;nm of GaAs. The eigenenergies and wavefunction of electron localized at the InAs monolayer have been calculated using density functional theory (DFT)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup> implemented in the CASTEP computer code<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref></sup>. For more details about the experiment conditions, the structure preparation and the calculations see Methods.<fig id="Fig1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Schematic drawing of the experimental structure and the measurements of photoluminescence (top). The Bragg structure is represented by 60-periods of InAs triple monolayers of InAs (red lines) separated by 107-nm-thick GaAs barriers (blue colour), as shown on the bottom left panel. The distance between the monolayers is 10&#x02009;nm, as shown on the bottom right panel.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_46646_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e484"/></fig></p><p id="Par7">First, we consider the carrier localization in the InAs monolayer embedded in the GaAs matrix. In such QW system, the localization energy for electrons and holes is 16&#x02009;meV and 19&#x02009;meV, respectively. Thus, for the exciton localized at the single InAs monolayer QW the energy in the ground state is 1.480&#x02009;eV at temperature of 4&#x02009;K. The charge density is shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2a,b</xref> (top) with corresponding profiles (bottom) of the probability density for the holes and electrons localized at one monolayer of InAs confined by GaAs, respectively. It can be seen that for electrons, the localization length (<italic>a</italic>) along z-direction is about 10&#x02009;nm, while for the hole it is 5&#x02009;nm. Thus, due to a relatively long localization length of electrons we have an overlapping of the wave function of electrons in the triple QWs, which will result in a triplet structure of the exciton mode with eigen frequencies near 1.471&#x02009;eV, 1.482&#x02009;eV and 1.492&#x02009;eV as described in details in<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup>. Such mixing of exciton states can be seen as a peculiar triplet structure in the both experimental (blue line) and modelled (red line) reflection&#x000a0; spectra&#x000a0; of the Bragg monolayer QW structure shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>.<fig id="Fig2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Calculated charge density. Averaged in the plane of InAs monolayer charge density of holes (<bold>a</bold>) and electrons (<bold>b</bold>) localized at InAs monolayer confined by GaAs. The coordinate z corresponds to the structure growth axis. On the top - images of charge density are shown.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_46646_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e514"/></fig><fig id="Fig3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Reflection for the studied sample. Calculated reflection coefficient as a function of incidence angle and photon energy for (<bold>a</bold>) TE &#x02013; polarization and (<bold>d</bold>) for TM- polarization. Bragg condition is shown by the magenta solid line. Vertical dashed lines in (<bold>a</bold>,<bold>d</bold>) indicate the angle of incidence of 45&#x000b0;, 65&#x000b0; and 72&#x000b0; (Brewster angle). Experimentally measured (blue lines) and calculated (red lines) spectra in TE -polarization for an incidence angle of 45&#x000b0; (<bold>b</bold>) and 65&#x000b0; (<bold>c</bold>). Experimental (blue lines) and calculated (red lines) reflection spectra in TM-polarization for the angles of 45&#x000b0; (<bold>e</bold>) and 65&#x000b0; (<bold>f</bold>). These calculations are based on the transfer matrix method, see Supplementary Equations (<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S9</xref>) with parameters given in Supplementary Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_46646_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e557"/></fig></p><p id="Par8">Peculiarities in the reflection spectra have been studied with respect to the dependence on light polarization for different incidence angles. The reflection coefficient calculated as a function of incidence angle and photon energy for the Bragg MQW structure is shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a,d</xref> for TE and TM-polarization, respectively. Bragg conditions are indicated by a solid magenta line. The dashed lines in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3a,d</xref> correspond to the incidence angles of 45&#x000b0; and 65&#x000b0;, close to Brewster angle of ~72&#x000b0; for GaAs. A comparison of the calculated reflection curves with experimental reflection spectra for both TE and TM polarizations is done for 45&#x000b0; and 65&#x000b0; as shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3b,c,e,f</xref>, respectively. The features in the experimental and calculated spectra correlate very well and the energy position of the peaks follow Bragg conditions.</p></sec><sec id="Sec3"><title>Additional super-radiant emission mode</title><p id="Par9">Results of the time-resolved photoluminescence (TRPL) measured from the top of the sample has shown that as pumping increases an additional mode appears with a peak energy depending on the angle. The dependence of the intensity of this mode is proportional to nearly the squared pumping power<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref></sup>, therefore, this mode is likely originated because of SR<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par10">Also, the time delay between the central mode (X1) and the SR mode is very clear with the increase of excitation power, while the recombination time became much faster. At the same time, measurements performed on the edge of the structure do not show the appearance of the additional mode. We demonstrate this in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> for the TRPL measured at different power for an angle of 40&#x000b0; (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a&#x02013;c</xref>) and compare to the same measurements performed at the edge of the structure (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4d&#x02013;f</xref>).<fig id="Fig4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>Transient photoluminescence pattern. (<bold>a</bold>&#x02013;<bold>c</bold>) measurements from the surface of the sample at the emission angle of 40&#x000b0;, (<bold>d</bold>,<bold>e</bold>,<bold>f</bold>) measurements from the edge of the sample. Pumping power P used 0.3&#x02009;mW (<bold>a</bold>,<bold>d</bold>); 3&#x02009;mW (<bold>b</bold>,<bold>e</bold>); and 27&#x02009;mW (<bold>c</bold>,<bold>f</bold>). Horizontal dashed lines indicate an example of interval of integration in time (200&#x02013;300 ps). Examples of PL spectra taken at different delay time are shown in Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_46646_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e642"/></fig></p><p id="Par11">We point out the following features in the case of emission from the edge: there is only a strong emission line corresponding to ground state exciton (X1) with the peak energy of ~1.47&#x02009;eV; there is no change in the delay between the exciting pulse and luminescence for different excitation powers; and there is no change in the luminescence decay time for different excitation powers. All these results indicate that there is no super-radiance or non-linear effects in the emission taken from the edge. In contrast, the emission from the top of the sample significantly changes with increasing emission power (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4a&#x02013;c</xref>).</p><p id="Par12">To understand the properties of the SR mode, it is convenient to perform a quantitative comparison of the emission pattern from the top and from the edge of the sample. For this purpose, we have measured the TRPL for different angles in the interval between 15&#x000b0; and 85&#x000b0; with the step of 2&#x000b0; (see examples of experimental data taken for different angles in Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S3</xref>). The peak position of the SR mode varies in time due to a change of the refractive index of the material caused by the recombination of non-equilibrium electrons and holes generated by the excitation pulse.</p><p id="Par13">In order to make a quantitative analysis of influence of the Bragg arrangements of quantum wells on the probability of spontaneous emission, we have applied the following procedure:<list list-type="simple"><list-item><label>(i)</label><p id="Par14">we integrated the signal of TRPL <italic>F</italic> over time within a specific time interval (as shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4c,f</xref> by horizontal lines) to obtain time-integrated intensities for the emission taken from the sample top:<disp-formula id="Equ3"><label>3</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M5">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${I}_{s}(\omega ,\theta )=\int {F}_{s}(\omega ,t,\theta )dt$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M6" display="block"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c9;</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b8;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x0222b;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c9;</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b8;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_46646_Article_Equ3.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>and from the edge of the sample:<disp-formula id="Equ4"><label>4</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M7">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${I}_{e}(\omega )=\int {F}_{e}(\omega ,t)dt.$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M8" display="block"><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c9;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mo>&#x0222b;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>F</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c9;</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>t</mml:mi><mml:mo>.</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_46646_Article_Equ4.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p></list-item><list-item><label>(ii)</label><p id="Par15">we then obtained normalized intensities<disp-formula id="Equ5"><label>5</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M9">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\tilde{{I}_{s}}(\omega ,\theta )={I}_{s}(\omega ,\theta )/\,\int {I}_{s}(\omega ,\theta )d\omega $$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M10" display="block"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">&#x002dc;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c9;</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b8;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c9;</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b8;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="-.5em"/><mml:mo>&#x0222b;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c9;</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b8;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003c9;</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_46646_Article_Equ5.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula>and<disp-formula id="Equ6"><label>6</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M11">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$\tilde{{I}_{e}}(\omega )={I}_{e}(\omega )/\,\int {I}_{e}(\omega )d\omega ;$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M12" display="block"><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">&#x002dc;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c9;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c9;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mspace width="-.5em"/><mml:mo>&#x0222b;</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c9;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mi>d</mml:mi><mml:mi>&#x003c9;</mml:mi><mml:mo>;</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_46646_Article_Equ6.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p></list-item><list-item><label>(iii)</label><p id="Par16">and finally, we got the ratio:</p></list-item></list><disp-formula id="Equ7"><label>7</label><alternatives><tex-math id="M13">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$$P(\omega ,\theta )=\tilde{{I}_{s}}(\omega ,\theta )/\tilde{{I}_{e}}(\omega )$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M14" display="block"><mml:mi>P</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c9;</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b8;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>=</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>s</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">&#x002dc;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c9;</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003b8;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo><mml:mo>/</mml:mo><mml:mover accent="true"><mml:mrow><mml:msub><mml:mrow><mml:mi>I</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mrow><mml:mi>e</mml:mi></mml:mrow></mml:msub></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">&#x002dc;</mml:mo></mml:mover><mml:mo stretchy="false">(</mml:mo><mml:mi>&#x003c9;</mml:mi><mml:mo stretchy="false">)</mml:mo></mml:math><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_46646_Article_Equ7.gif" position="anchor"/></alternatives></disp-formula></p><p id="Par17">The procedure of integration over a finite time interval is required to smooth the noise in the TRPL signal. Since the emission from the edge of the sample is not affected by the Bragg arrangement of monolayer quantum wells, <italic>P</italic>(<italic>&#x003c9;</italic>, <italic>&#x003b8;</italic>) is the experimental counterpart of the ratio of spontaneous emission rates for a particular direction for the emitter placed into the structure and for the emitter in free space (i.e. the modal Purcell factor)<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>.</p><p id="Par18">Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> shows the pattern of <italic>P</italic>(<italic>&#x003c9;</italic>, <italic>&#x003b8;</italic>) for different time integration intervals, where time starts from the excitation laser pulse. The Bragg condition (solid magenta line) is shown on each pattern for comparison. Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5a</xref> shows <italic>P</italic>(<italic>&#x003c9;</italic>, <italic>&#x003b8;</italic>) for the time integration interval from 0 to 700&#x02009;ps, which corresponds to the time of existence of the SR mode in the spectra. <italic>P</italic>(<italic>&#x003c9;</italic>, <italic>&#x003b8;</italic>) is enhanced for the frequency of light corresponding to the ground state of exciton and also along the Bragg condition line. Since the peak position of the SR mode is shifted with time, it is convenient to reduce the time integration interval. Thus, Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5b</xref> corresponds to the time integration interval between 100&#x02009;ps and 200&#x02009;ps, when only the SR mode exists in the spectra (see Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4c</xref>). It is clearly seen, especially in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5b</xref>, that the enhancement of the emission occurs only for some spots along the Bragg condition line. For the time integration interval between 200&#x02009;ps and 300&#x02009;ps (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5c</xref>) and between 300&#x02009;ps and 400&#x02009;ps (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5d</xref>) the spotted pattern of <italic>P</italic>(<italic>&#x003c9;</italic>, <italic>&#x003b8;</italic>) along the Bragg condition is conserved, however the spots become less pronounced and instead the feature corresponding to the X1 line appears. For the integration intervals between 500&#x02009;ps and 600&#x02009;ps and also between 600&#x02009;ps and 700&#x02009;ps shown in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5e,f</xref>, respectively, the SR mode decays and the enhancement of the emission along Bragg condition vanishes.<fig id="Fig5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>Dependence of the ratio of time &#x02013;integrated emission spectra taken from surface and from the edge of the sample (<inline-formula id="IEq1"><alternatives><tex-math id="M15">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
				\usepackage{amsmath}
				\usepackage{wasysym} 
				\usepackage{amsfonts} 
				\usepackage{amssymb} 
				\usepackage{amsbsy}
				\usepackage{mathrsfs}
				\usepackage{upgreek}
				\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
				\begin{document}$${\rm{P}}({\rm{\omega }},{\rm{\theta }})$$\end{document}</tex-math><mml:math id="M16"><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">P</mml:mi><mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">(</mml:mo><mml:mrow><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003c9;</mml:mi><mml:mo>,</mml:mo><mml:mi mathvariant="normal">&#x003b8;</mml:mi></mml:mrow><mml:mo stretchy="true">)</mml:mo></mml:mrow></mml:math><inline-graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_46646_Article_IEq1.gif"/></alternatives></inline-formula>) obtained by Eq. (<xref rid="Equ3" ref-type="">3</xref>) for different time integration intervals: (<bold>a</bold>) 0&#x02013;700 ps; (<bold>b</bold>) 100&#x02013;200 ps; (<bold>c</bold>) 200&#x02013;300 ps; (<bold>d</bold>) 300&#x02013;400 ps; (<bold>e</bold>) 500&#x02013;600 ps; and (f) 600&#x02013;700 ps. Time interval is calculated from the start of excitation pulse. Time-integrated PL spectra measured for different angles are shown in Supplementary Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S2</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_46646_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e1128"/></fig></p></sec><sec id="Sec4"><title>Modal purcell factor calculations</title><p id="Par19">The spotted structure in the emission enhancement pattern is the most intriguing and counter&#x02013;intuitive finding of this work: the enhancement of spontaneous emission due to super-radiance is expected to occur for all directions and frequencies of the emission coupled to the Bragg condition Eq. (<xref rid="Equ1" ref-type="">1</xref>). Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5b,c</xref> shows that the enhancement of the emission occurs only for discrete periodically placed spots near the Bragg condition.</p><p id="Par20">Insight into such unusual behaviour can be obtained by analysis of the modal Purcell factor<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup>. Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref> shows examples of the modal Purcell factor calculated for different positions of the emitter placed inside the structure. It can be seen that there is an area of the enhancement of the modal Purcell factor near the bottom of the Bragg condition curve. Also, there are individual spots of the enhancement of the Purcell factor positioned near the Bragg condition curve at the frequencies corresponding to the triplet exciton states. Such behaviour correlates with the experimental pattern of the emission enhancement. Thus, the observed spotted TPRL pattern results from the combination of several effects: (i) the Purcell enhancement of the spontaneous emission rate; (ii) super-radiance; (iii) spatial diffusion, and (iv) the relaxation of non-equilibrium electrons and holes.<fig id="Fig6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Dependence of calculated modal Purcell factor on the angle and photon energy for TE-polarization when emitter is placed in (<bold>a</bold>) central monolayer in the 1<sup>st</sup> period; (<bold>b</bold>) central monolayer in the 5th period; (<bold>c</bold>) central monolayer in the 10th period. Vertical dashed lines indicate the interval of angles from 15&#x000b0; to 85&#x000b0;, for which the experimental dependences of the emission in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> are shown. Calculations are based on S-quantization formalism (Methods), (for details see Supplementary Equations (<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S10</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S41</xref>)).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="41598_2019_46646_Fig6_HTML" id="d29e1179"/></fig></p></sec></sec><sec id="Sec5" sec-type="conclusion"><title>Conclusions</title><p id="Par21">A Bragg quantum well structure based on MBE-grown InAs monolayers with GaAs barriers has been fabricated and studied. Eigenenergies and wavefunctions of electrons and holes localized on InAs monolayers have been calculated by a density functional theory approach. Time-resolved photoluminescence of the Bragg quantum well structure has been measured from the edge of the sample (where light emission is not affected by Bragg arrangement of quantum wells) and from the surface of the sample for different emission angles. We have shown that emission from the edge of the sample is represented by one line corresponding to the ground state exciton, while for the emission from the top of the sample an additional line appears and the angle of emission and the frequency of light for this line corresponds to Bragg conditions. The ratio of time-integrated emission intensities from the surface of the sample for different angles and from the edge of the samples as a function of frequency of light that has been obtained, showing the pattern of this ratio has a spot-like structure, where spots are located near the Bragg condition. Such behaviour correlates with the calculated dependence of the modal Purcell factor on the frequency and angle of emission, which also demonstrates individual spots of an enhanced Purcell coefficient near the Bragg condition curve.</p></sec><sec id="Sec6"><title>Methods</title><sec id="Sec7"><title>Sample growth</title><p id="Par22">The Bragg structure contained 60 triple QWs based on monolayer-thick InAs separated by GaAs layers. The thickness of layers was chosen to satisfy the Bragg conditions for the emission wavelength corresponding to the exciton emission at 5&#x02009;K in the single monolayer InAs QW with GaAs barriers. This matches to the peak photon energy of 1.48&#x02009;eV, while the optical thickness of the period in the Bragg structure is 418&#x02009;nm. Each triple QWs was separated by the 102 nm-thick undoped GaAs layer, while the spatial separation between individual InAs monolayers in the triple QW was 10&#x02009;nm. The sample was fabricated under rotation using the molecular beam epitaxy growth chamber Riber 49. (100)-GaAs was used as the substrate. High energy electron diffraction was used to control <italic>in-situ</italic> the growth rate. The thickness of the GaAs cap layer was about 100&#x02009;nm to provide a matching of the antinodes of the electric field of the collective mode. The part of the GaAs cap layer near the sample surface was doped in order to avoid the GaAs excitonic reflection feature from the surface of the sample.</p></sec><sec id="Sec8"><title>Characterization</title><p id="Par23">Time-integrated and time-resolved photoluminescence was studied under excitation by a Ti: sapphire femtosecond pulsed laser with a frequency of 75&#x02009;MHz. The excitation wavelength was ~800&#x02009;nm having a maximum average power density of 100&#x02009;W/cm<sup>2</sup>. The excitation pulse duration was ~150&#x02009;fs. The observed results of TRPL are not affected by a small variation of the pulse duration as well as by turning of the excitation wavelength from 780&#x02009;nm to 800&#x02009;nm.</p><p id="Par24">A Hamamatsu syncroscan streak camera with a temporal resolution of ~20&#x02009;ps was employed to acquire the TRPL signal. The sample was cooled down to 5&#x02009;K using a liquid-He cryostat. The angle of emission was tuned by rotating the sample holder.</p></sec><sec id="Sec9"><title>Modelling</title><p id="Par25">The calculated dependence of the reflection coefficient on the angle of emission and frequency of light was obtained using transfer matrix method, detailed description of the method is provided in<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref></sup> (see also Supplementary Equations (<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S1</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S9</xref>)). Dependence of probability density of spontaneous emission on the angle of emission and frequency of light was obtained by S-quantization formalism described in detail in<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref></sup> and in Supplementary Equations (<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S10</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media">S41</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="Sec10"><title>Electronic structure calculations</title><p id="Par26">The electronic structure calculations were performed using the CASTEP code<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref></sup> which uses the plane wave density functional formalism within the generalised gradient approximation.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material"><title>Supplementary information</title><sec id="Sec11"><p>
<supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="MOESM1"><media xlink:href="41598_2019_46646_MOESM1_ESM.pdf"><caption><p>Supplementary information</p></caption></media></supplementary-material>
</p></sec></sec></body><back><fn-group><fn><p><bold>Publisher&#x02019;s note:</bold> Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p></fn></fn-group><sec><title>Supplementary information</title><p><bold>Supplementary information</bold> accompanies this paper at 10.1038/s41598-019-46646-2.</p></sec><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>The work has been supported by Russian Science Foundation Grant 16-12-10503. SJC acknowledges Durham&#x02019;s Hamilton and UK&#x02019;s Archer supercomputer facilities for the DFT calculations.</p></ack><notes notes-type="author-contribution"><title>Author Contributions</title><p>G.P., M.A.K. designed the research idea. G.P. performed optical measurements. K.A.I., K.M.M., M.A.K., A.Y.E. contributed to the design of the sample. E.I.G., K.A.I., S.J.C. and K.M.M. contributed to numerical modelling of the results. All authors contributed to analysis of the results. G.P., K.A.I., M.A.K. wrote the manuscript. All authors have given approval to the final version of the manuscript.</p></notes><notes notes-type="data-availability"><title>Data Availability</title><p>All data generated and/or analysed during this study are available from the corresponding author on reasonable request.</p></notes><notes notes-type="COI-statement"><title>Competing Interests</title><p id="Par27">The authors declare no competing interests.</p></notes><ref-list id="Bib1"><title>References</title><ref id="CR1"><label>1.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kleppner</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibited spontaneous emission</article-title><source>Phys. Rev. Lett.</source><year>1981</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>233</fpage><lpage>236</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevLett.47.233</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR2"><label>2.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Purcell</surname><given-names>EM</given-names></name><name><surname>Torrey</surname><given-names>HC</given-names></name><name><surname>Pound</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Resonance Absorption by Nuclear Magnetic Moments in a Solid</article-title><source>Physical Review</source><year>1946</year><volume>69</volume><fpage>37</fpage><lpage>38</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRev.69.37</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR3"><label>3.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>G&#x000e9;rard</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Enhanced spontaneous emission by quantum boxes in a monolithic optical microcavity</article-title><source>Phys. Rev. Let.</source><year>1998</year><volume>81</volume><fpage>1110</fpage><lpage>1113</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevLett.81.1110</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR4"><label>4.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dicke</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Coherence in spontaneous radiation processes</article-title><source>Phys. Rev.</source><year>1954</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>99</fpage><lpage>110</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRev.93.99</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR5"><label>5.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rehler</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name><name><surname>Eberly</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Superradiance</article-title><source>Phys. Rev. A</source><year>1971</year><volume>3</volume><fpage>1735</fpage><lpage>1751</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevA.3.1735</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR6"><label>6.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Haroche</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Superradiance: An essay on the theory of collective spontaneous emission</article-title><source>Phys. Reports</source><year>1982</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>301</fpage><lpage>396</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0370-1573(82)90102-8</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR7"><label>7.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ivchenko</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Nesvizhskii</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jorda</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Bragg reflection of light from quantum-well structures</article-title><source>Phys. Sol. State</source><year>1994</year><volume>36</volume><fpage>1156</fpage><lpage>1161</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR8"><label>8.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kochereshko</surname><given-names>VP</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Giant exciton resonance reflectance in Bragg MQW structures</article-title><source>Superlat. Microstr.</source><year>1994</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>471</fpage><lpage>473</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/spmi.1994.1090</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR9"><label>9.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ivchenko</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Reflection in the exciton region of the spectrum of a structure with a single quantum well. Oblique and normal incidence of light</article-title><source>Sov. Phys. Semicond.</source><year>1988</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>495</fpage><lpage>498</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR10"><label>10.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>H&#x000fc;bner</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Optical Lattices Achieved by Excitons in Periodic Quantum Well Structures</article-title><source>Phys. Rev. Let.</source><year>1999</year><volume>83</volume><fpage>2841</fpage><lpage>2844</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1103/PhysRevLett.83.2841</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR11"><label>11.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Chaldyshev</surname><given-names>VV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Optical lattices of InGaN quantum well excitons</article-title><source>Appl. Phys. Let.</source><year>2011</year><volume>99</volume><fpage>251103</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1063/1.3670499</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR12"><label>12.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pozina</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Super-radiant mode in InAs&#x02014;monolayer&#x02013;based Bragg structures</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2015</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>14911</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/srep14911</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">26456523</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR13"><label>13.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pozina</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Nonlinear behavior of the emission in the periodic structure of InAs monolayers embedded in a GaAs matrix</article-title><source>Phys. Stat. Sol. b</source><year>2017</year><volume>254</volume><fpage>1600402</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pssb.201600402</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR14"><label>14.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Khurgin</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative analysis of spasers, vertical-cavity surface-emitting lasers and surface-plasmon-emitting diodes</article-title><source>Nature Phot.</source><year>2014</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>468</fpage><lpage>473</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nphoton.2014.94</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR15"><label>15.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Turitsyn</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Random distributed feedback fibre laser</article-title><source>Nature Phot.</source><year>2010</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>231</fpage><lpage>235</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nphoton.2010.4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR16"><label>16.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Room-temperature InP distributed feedback laser array directly grown on silicon</article-title><source>Nature Phot.</source><year>2015</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>837</fpage><lpage>842</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nphoton.2015.199</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR17"><label>17.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>First principles methods using CASTEP</article-title><source>Z. Kristal.</source><year>2005</year><volume>220</volume><fpage>567</fpage><lpage>570</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR18"><label>18.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Milman</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Electron and vibrational spectroscopies using DFT, plane waves and pseudopotentials: CASTEP implementation</article-title><source>J. Molec. Struc.: THEOCHEM</source><year>2010</year><volume>954</volume><fpage>22</fpage><lpage>35</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.theochem.2009.12.040</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="CR19"><label>19.</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gubaydullin</surname><given-names>AR</given-names></name><etal/></person-group><article-title>Enhancement of spontaneous emission in Tamm plasmon structures</article-title><source>Sci. Rep.</source><year>2017</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>1914</fpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/s41598-017-09245-7</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28507299</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>