<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The global distribution of arboviruses has received considerable attention from public health organizations after recent emergence events in several parts of the world [
  <a rid="pone.0150489.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0150489.ref001">1</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0150489.ref002" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0150489.ref002">2</a>]. Bluetongue virus (BTV) is an arboviral disease in ruminants [
  <a rid="pone.0150489.ref003" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0150489.ref003">3</a>], caused by a member of the genus 
  <span class="italic">Orivirus</span> in the family 
  <span class="italic">Reoviridae</span>. The disease is transmitted among ruminants by the bites of biting midges of the genus 
  <span class="italic">Culicoides</span> [
  <a rid="pone.0150489.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0150489.ref004">4</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">BTV has been responsible for massive sheep mortality; for example, outbreaks in the Mediterranean region since 1998 resulted in deaths of over 800,000 sheep [
  <a rid="pone.0150489.ref005" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0150489.ref005">5</a>]. A single strain of BTV in Belgium disrupted animal trade and killed animals with a market value of UK £180 million during a 2006–2007 outbreak [
  <a rid="pone.0150489.ref006" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0150489.ref006">6</a>]. In the United States, BTV causes losses of US $125 million yearly [
  <a rid="pone.0150489.ref007" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0150489.ref007">7</a>]. Previous reports have discussed early introduction of infected sheep into South Africa 125 years ago [
  <a rid="pone.0150489.ref008" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0150489.ref008">8</a>], but others identified South Africa as the origin of the infection [
  <a rid="pone.0150489.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0150489.ref009">9</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">BTV geography was long limited to a range between 40°N and 35°S [
  <a rid="pone.0150489.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0150489.ref001">1</a>]. Recently, however, several BTV strains began to spread worldwide [
  <a rid="pone.0150489.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0150489.ref001">1</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0150489.ref010" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0150489.ref010">10</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0150489.ref011" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0150489.ref011">11</a>], including to more northern parts of Europe, in 1998 [
  <a rid="pone.0150489.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0150489.ref004">4</a>]. The expansion and the potential for susceptibility of new vector species to the virus raises concerns of broader BTV spread [
  <a rid="pone.0150489.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0150489.ref004">4</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0150489.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0150489.ref012">12</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0150489.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0150489.ref014">14</a>]. BTV is transmitted by several vector species: 
  <span class="italic">Culicoides imicola</span> Kieffer, 1913 (Diptera: Ceratopogonidae) is the most significant vector in the Old World [
  <a rid="pone.0150489.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0150489.ref015">15</a>], but three other species serve as vectors in the United Sates alone [
  <a rid="pone.0150489.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0150489.ref016">16</a>]. The distribution and movement of hosts has also been identified as a limiting factor for BTV spread; although BTV is known to have infected several ruminants, cattle and sheep are identified as primary reservoirs in several endemic areas worldwide [
  <a rid="pone.0150489.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0150489.ref001">1</a>]. The combination of climate, presence of susceptible host, and presence of competent vectors marks areas where BTV can circulate in the long term among livestock.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Previous studies have mapped BTV risk based on occurrence data from single countries [
  <a rid="pone.0150489.ref017" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0150489.ref017">17</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0150489.ref019" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0150489.ref019">19</a>]; others included vector distributions in mapping efforts [
  <a rid="pone.0150489.ref005" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0150489.ref005">5</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0150489.ref018" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0150489.ref018">18</a>]. One study explored the global distribution and possible future shifts in the distribution of 
  <span class="italic">C</span>. 
  <span class="italic">imicola</span> across the world [
  <a rid="pone.0150489.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0150489.ref015">15</a>]. Ecological niche models provide a robust approach by which to assess and evaluate distribution of disease risk [
  <a rid="pone.0150489.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0150489.ref020">20</a>]: this approach has been used in mapping everything from fungal to arboviral diseases in several recent analyses [
  <a rid="pone.0150489.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0150489.ref021">21</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0150489.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0150489.ref022">22</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here, we developed a comprehensive database of BTV case occurrences, and estimated the global potential distribution of BTV under both current and future climate conditions. The study used outputs from 62 general climate models (GCMs) and four representative concentration pathway (RCP) scenarios from the Fifth Assessment Report (AR5) of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) to estimate the future potential distribution of the virus. Finally, we tested niche similarity between several vector species and BTV case distribution in different geographic areas to provide some level of assessment of the role of particular potential vector species in BTV transmission.</p>
</sec>
