<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec006" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Niche overlap of bluetongue virus and its vectors</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We tested the niche similarity between each potential vector species and BTV using the background similarity test implemented in ENMTools version 1.4.4 [
  <a rid="pone.0150489.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0150489.ref034">34</a>]. We developed a specific 
  <span class="bold">M</span> hypothesis [
  <a rid="pone.0150489.ref031" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0150489.ref031">31</a>] for each vector species as follows: 
  <span class="italic">C</span>. 
  <span class="italic">imicola</span>, a vector of BTV in the Old World [
  <a rid="pone.0150489.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0150489.ref001">1</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0150489.ref005" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0150489.ref005">5</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0150489.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0150489.ref035">35</a>], so we estimated a broad accessible area (
  <span class="bold">M</span>) that included all of Europe, Asia, and Africa for that species. 
  <span class="italic">Culicoides insignis</span> is reported from North, Central, and South America [
  <a rid="pone.0150489.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0150489.ref036">36</a>], so its 
  <span class="bold">M</span> was estimated to include all of the Americas. The 
  <span class="bold">M</span> hypotheses for 
  <span class="italic">C</span>. 
  <span class="italic">variipennis</span> and 
  <span class="italic">C</span>. 
  <span class="italic">sonorensis</span> were estimated as all of North and Central America. 
  <span class="italic">Culicoides brevitarsis</span> was restricted to East Asia and Australia, and 
  <span class="italic">C</span>. 
  <span class="italic">occidentalis</span> was limited to the southern United States and Central America.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The background similarity test assessed whether vector and BTV niches are less similar than expected given the “background” similarity manifested across the accessible areas of each [
  <a rid="pone.0150489.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0150489.ref034">34</a>]. We compared niche model similarity values based on actual occurrences of each species, with distributions of background similarity based on comparison of the niche of one species with “niche” models based on random points from across the 
  <span class="bold">M</span> of the other species. We used numbers of random points equal to the number of actual occurrences for the other species. The null hypothesis of niche similarity was rejected if the observed 
  <span class="italic">D</span> or 
  <span class="italic">I</span> values for the BTV and vector species in question fell below the 5
  <span class="sup">th</span> percentile in the random-replicate distribution.
 </p>
</sec>
