<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The results presented here are dependent on the ability of the models used to represent the observed natural variability. Global‐scale information on variability derived from satellite data is only available for SST and chlorophyll concentration (and derived products, such as PP). Overall, the models represent the natural variability in SST very well, although it is underestimated in the Arctic (Fig. S4). For chlorophyll, observed variability is generally larger than modelled in the coastal and polar regions (Fig. S5). Typically, modelled variability is lower than observed variability, particularly in biogeochemical parameters (e.g. Cadule 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="gcb13152-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>; Laepple &amp; Huybers, 
 <xref rid="gcb13152-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). Generally, we find a similar pattern, although with some exceptions such as chlorophyll in the oligotrophic gyres in the HadGEM models (see Fig. S5). Increased levels of variability would result in weaker signal to noise ratio, and thus longer 
 <italic class="italic">n*</italic>. Note also that the observations do not represent purely natural variability as they contain responses to both natural and anthropogenic forcing. The modelled spatial footprints are similar to those calculated from observed SST and chlorophyll (Fig. S6, compare to Fig. 
 <xref rid="gcb13152-fig-0003" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3</xref>b, f). For SST, the pattern and shape of the footprints are very similar in observations and models, although they are slightly larger in the observations so that 18% of the ocean is covered by BGC‐SOs (13% for models). In chlorophyll, results are mixed with the size, shape and isotropy of the footprints being similar in observations and models for some BGC‐SOs, for example BATS and PAP, but not in others, for example OOI‐Argentine. Both observations and models suggest that 12% of the ocean is represented by BGC‐SOs for chlorophyll, although the distribution of coverage is slightly different.
</p>
