<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The extinction risk of a meta‐population or (sub)species depends in part on the degree of population synchrony, and thereby the strength of climate as a synchronizing agent (Engen et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0018" ref-type="ref">2002</xref>; Heino et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0034" ref-type="ref">1997</xref>; Ranta et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0066" ref-type="ref">1995</xref>). The estimated regional level of synchrony of Svalbard reindeer dynamics was high for single vital rates, but this was less apparent in the population growth rates, which are more strongly influenced by sampling error. However, as expected based on the observed pattern of autocorrelation in ROS (Figure 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S4</xref>), synchrony declined with distance for all these population parameters. Uboni et al. (
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0081" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>) found no such pattern of spatial scaling in their pairwise population correlations in population growth rates across large distances (up to ~7,000 km) in Eurasian reindeer, but for our range of distances (up to ~324 km) their average regional synchrony (ca. 0.24) was very similar to ours (
 <italic>ρ</italic>
 <sub>R</sub> = 0.23). Their lack of evidence for climate effects on population dynamics and synchrony could, at least in part, be a result of not accounting for local variation in density dependence and climate–density interactions, the importance of which has been clearly demonstrated here. Thus, even in ‘simple’ trophic systems such as Svalbard, where the influence of human presence is low and where few external factors other than weather fluctuations are expected to influence annual reindeer population fluctuations (Ims &amp; Ehrich, 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0037" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>; Tyler et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0079" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>), it has proven crucial to account for density dependence in studies of population dynamics (Aanes et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0001" ref-type="ref">2000</xref>; Albon et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>; Hansen et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0027" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>; Tyler et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0079" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>). In this study, direct density dependence was generally present across populations and population parameters, but there was little evidence of a consistent pattern of ROS–density interaction effects (as found in Hansen et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0029" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>) across the 10 populations. The contribution of this interaction effect to population synchrony was therefore not huge; its synchronizing effect was significant for mortality, yet negligible for fecundity (which seemed better explained by an additive ROS effect), and, thereby, only close to significant for population growth rates. This lack of significance, and the local variation across Svalbard in estimated effects of ROS, and its interaction with density, could in part also be due to the slightly ‘noisy’ and short datasets used for this analysis. Furthermore, the Svalbard‐scale ROS variable probably reflected local conditions better for some populations (close to one or more weather stations) than others, e.g. the remote Svenskøya population in eastern Svalbard (Figure 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Nevertheless, the in‐depth analysis of the two high‐quality datasets confirmed that important local differences in density regulation indeed occur. Accordingly, when density dependence and its potential interaction with climate effects differ locally, the assumption of the Moran effect that there is a similar (log‐linear) density dependence among populations does not hold. Contrasting density dependence desynchronizes population dynamics (Engen et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>) and should clearly be accounted for in the analysis of climate effects on population synchrony.
</p>
