<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>One major reason for the overall poor understanding of density‐dependent and ‐independent drivers of Arctic ungulate population dynamics, and how they vary in space, is that time series of population monitoring data are notoriously discontinuous (Mallory, Campbell, &amp; Boyce, 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0053" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>; Uboni et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0081" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>; Vors &amp; Boyce, 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0086" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>). This complicates any attempt to quantify how climate change shapes the dynamics and trends at the level of population/herd, meta‐population, and subspecies, as well as patterns of spatial population synchrony. The accuracy of ‘total population count’ data is also rarely assessed, but aerial counts are often assumed to be uncertain and underestimates of the actual population sizes (Poole, Cuyler, &amp; Nymand, 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0059" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>). We have no reason to believe that the helicopter counts used here differ in that sense; however, ground counts appear highly accurate (Le Moullec et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0048" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>). Uncertain aerial counts contribute to noise in the dataset, reducing the measured level of population synchrony and the ability to detect effects of climate on population growth rates and their spatial synchrony. However, because of the solitary, non‐migratory behaviour of Svalbard reindeer, and the rather small, well‐defined study areas in open tundra landscapes, we believe that these helicopter counts generally captured major changes occurring from year to year, as well as the long‐term trends. This is especially the case for the vital rates, which were highly correlated across relatively nearby populations, as also indicated in other subspecies of 
 <italic>Rangifer</italic> (Hegel, Verbyla, Huettmann, &amp; Barboza, 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0033" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>).
</p>
