<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The results from this study have ecological implications far beyond the levels of population, meta‐population and subspecies. Like many other deer species (Côté, Rooney, Tremblay, Dussault, &amp; Waller, 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">2004</xref>), Svalbard reindeer play a key role in the ecosystem through top‐down and bottom‐up effects of trophic interactions. Impacts of grazing, trampling and high nutrient turnover rates resulting from increased reindeer densities may cause vegetation state transitions from lichen‐ to moss‐ and graminoid‐dominated vegetation (Hansen et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">2007</xref>; Van der Wal, 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0082" ref-type="ref">2006</xref>). Thus, similar or contrasting long‐term trends in abundance between reindeer populations, distributed across large areas, may influence the spatial autocorrelation in vegetation structure, with implications for other herbivores and ecosystem components (Ims &amp; Ehrich, 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0037" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>). Importantly, reindeer carcasses represent a major food source for the Svalbard population of Arctic fox (
 <italic>Vulpes lagopus</italic>), and stochastic ROS events therefore cause lagged synchrony in the two species’ population growth rates (Hansen et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>). The Arctic fox does not kill reindeer but is the most important predator of the other overwintering herbivore, the Svalbard rock ptarmigan (
 <italic>Lagopus muta hyperborea</italic>), as well as migratory birds. This key ecosystem role of 
 <italic>Rangifer</italic> through trophic interaction effects is not unique to Svalbard (Ims &amp; Ehrich, 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0037" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>; Legagneux et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0049" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>). Thus, how future climate change affects the level and spatial scaling of abundance synchrony in caribou and reindeer and, in turn, their food plants and consumers, are likely to impact spatiotemporal ecological dynamics occurring at the entire tundra community level.
</p>
