<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The resulting changes in transport performance and mileage by transport mode as specified by the Transport Modelling Tool (1) enter into the transport Network Emission Model (NEMO) [
 <xref rid="B28-ijerph-15-00880" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>] (2a in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-15-00880-f001" class="xref">Figure 1</xref>) which calculates road transport emissions (exhaust and non-exhaust) using detailed data on fleet composition (category, fuel types, emission classes etc.) and on road network (section lengths, gradients). These calculated road transport emissions, combined with meteorological data, comprise the input for the Lagrangian Dispersion Model GRAL [
 <xref rid="B29-ijerph-15-00880" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>], which is used to model concentration levels of pollutants for each scenario [
 <xref rid="B30-ijerph-15-00880" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>] (2b in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-15-00880-f001" class="xref">Figure 1</xref>). Different diurnal and seasonal cycles are used to consider variability of pollutant sources. Changes in the annual mean of specific pollutants are calculated and matched with population data on the district level to determine the number of people affected by a specific change in exposure to specific pollutants. 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-15-00880-f003" class="xref">Figure 3</xref> illustrates spatially-explicit modelled concentration levels for the city of Vienna at high resolution (10 m × 10 m). Air pollution (annual mean for PM
 <sub class="sub">2.5</sub> concentration) is exemplified by different colors for different concentration levels of pollutants for the baseline case and the three scenarios. Detailed concentration level maps for all cities and considered pollutants are given in 
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-ijerph-15-00880" class="xref">Figures S3–S5</xref> in the 
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app1-ijerph-15-00880" class="xref">Supplementary Material</xref>.
</p>
