<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Marine systems have been and will continue to be impacted by climate change across all habitats, latitudes, and trophic levels (Hoegh-Guldberg and Bruno 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">2010</a>; Richardson et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88" href="#CR88">2012</a>; Poloczanska et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86" href="#CR86">2013</a>; Rhein et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87" href="#CR87">2013</a>). These impacts trickle up to the fisheries that humans depend upon via alterations in primary productivity (Poloczanska et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86" href="#CR86">2013</a>), food webs (Edwards and Richardson 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">2004</a>), and community structure (Barange and Perry 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">2009</a>). These ecological shifts will produce both positive and negative impacts (Cheung et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">2012</a>), but are expected to affect fishers and fishing communities via altered fishing revenues, increased costs per unit effort, higher insurance costs, and/or changes in international fishing agreements, among others (Adger et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">2009</a>; Badjeck et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">2010</a>; Sumaila et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR97" href="#CR97">2011</a>). Thus, there is a need for fisheries management that promotes resilient social and ecological systems in order to ensure long-term sustainability (Adger et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">2009</a>; Grafton 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">2009</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While ecological resilience is traditionally defined as the 
  <span class="italic">resistance</span> of ecosystems or species to disturbance, and the speed of 
  <span class="italic">recovery</span> following disturbance (Holling 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">1973</a>); in social systems resilience is related to the disturbance, reorganization, and renewal of communities and institutions (Grafton 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">2009</a>). Here we define socio-ecological resilience as the ability of a SES to absorb disturbances while retaining the same basic structure and ways of functioning, the capacity for self-organization, and the capacity to adapt to stress and change (IPCC 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">2007</a>, Davidson et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">2013</a>). Social–ecological resilience refers to people and nature as inter-dependent systems (Folke et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">2010</a>), where changes in ecological resilience affect social resilience and vice versa.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We define a SES as a coupled and integrated system that encompasses social and ecological components that interact closely (López-Angarita et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71" href="#CR71">2014</a>). Fisheries SES are regulated in diverse ways including community management, co-management, and strong top-down control rules (e.g., limited licensing of vessels). Fisheries regulatory regimes also vary in the extent of rights allocated to fishers (e.g., access rights, property rights) and regulations stemming from conservation measures that might be in place (e.g., marine protected areas). These institutional and regulatory characteristics can have important implications for how a fishery SES responds to climate change. For example, protecting particular age classes by using more selective gear (Cinner et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">2009b</a>; Grafton 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">2009</a>) or protecting key habitat by implementing no-take marine reserves (Allison et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">2003</a>; Gaines et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">2010</a>) can buffer stocks against climatic shocks, helping fishers and communities to adapt. Similarly, promoting long-term resource stewardship, for instance via property rights, may provide incentives to fishers to apply more precautionary or adaptive management approaches in the face of looming climate change.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Many fisheries regulatory strategies may be ill prepared to protect or enhance resilience to climate change (McClanahan 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75" href="#CR75">2008</a>). There is a growing body of research that addresses the question of resilience to climate change from different angles: by looking at climate change adaptation and resilience in specific fisheries SES (Cinner et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">2009a</a>; Lopes et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" href="#CR70">2011</a>; Pinsky and Mantua 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84" href="#CR84">2014</a>; Maldonado and Moreno-Sánchez 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73" href="#CR73">2014</a>) by assessing the adaptive capacity of fisheries SES to confront climate change (Leith et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">2014</a>; López-Angarita et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71" href="#CR71">2014</a>; Rivera et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR89" href="#CR89">2014</a>); and by identifying attributes that safeguard economic (van Putten et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100" href="#CR100">2013</a>) and ecological resilience for a given fishery (McClanahan et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76" href="#CR76">2012</a>). However, no studies have suggested broadly applicable criteria for assessing socio-ecological resilience of fisheries. Moreover, the implications of different regulatory systems for fisheries’ resilience to climate change is yet unknown (Smit et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94" href="#CR94">2001</a>; Folke 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">2006</a>; Pinsky and Mantua 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR84" href="#CR84">2014</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This paper addresses this gap by conceptualizing resilience in fisheries management systems by identifying nine resilience criteria. We then explore four fisheries regulatory systems (individual transferable quotas—ITQs; territorial use rights for fisheries—TURFs; limited entry; and open access) in terms of their capacity for social and ecological resilience to climate change based on these criteria, examining evidence in the literature. Our aim is to provide a framework for understanding the effects of fisheries regulatory regimes under a resilience perspective. Our preliminary assessment of the resilience potential of these regulatory approaches suggests important research directions to promote fisheries able to adapt to impending climate change.</p>
</sec>
