<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Here, we used a systematic web‐based literature search to further narrow this group of candidate species to those particularly relevant in the context of both invasion and hybridization. We used all possible combinations of the following keywords in the Web‐of‐Science (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://apps.webofknowledge.com" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://apps.webofknowledge.com</ext-link>): #hybridization, #hybridisation, #invasion, #alien, #invasive species, #plant. The records were subsequently limited to the following categories: agriculture, biodiversity, conservation, ecology, environmental sciences, evolutionary biology and reproductive biology. We screened the abstracts of the 1,220 papers found and finally identified 66 plant genera that fulfil the following criteria: (1) interspecific hybridization has been documented and (2) they contain invasive species (even if these are not identical with the hybrids or if only intraspecific hybrids have so far been reported to be invasive, for example in 
 <italic class="italic">Pyrus</italic> (Hardiman &amp; Culley, 
 <xref rid="ddi12578-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>)). Twenty‐three of these genera were represented by at least one species in the list of Dullinger et al. (
 <xref rid="ddi12578-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>), of which 18 were also represented by at least one species (native and naturalized) in the flora of Europe (Tutin et al., 
 <xref rid="ddi12578-bib-0079" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1964–1980</xref>). From these, we discarded the genera 
 <italic class="italic">Rosa</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Rubus</italic> because of taxonomic difficulties with a large number of apomictic species. As a result of these consecutive filtering steps, we ended up with 16 genera. These 16 genera contain 34 alien plants currently cultivated in Europe with the potential to escape into the wild (indicated by their naturalization in other continents) and at least one congeneric species in the native and naturalized flora of Europe which shares the same life form (assuming that only mating partners of the same life form are likely to produce viable hybrid offspring; see Tables 
 <xref rid="ddi12578-sup-0003" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ddi12578-sup-0003" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S3</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ddi12578-sup-0003" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S6</xref>). Most of these species are planted for ornamental purposes only, but some, like 
 <italic class="italic">Chenopodium quinoa</italic> or several 
 <italic class="italic">Eucalyptus</italic> spp., are also of commercial interest beyond horticulture. After a final screening in GBIF for those species with more than 50 occurrence records (see Table 
 <xref rid="ddi12578-sup-0003" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S2</xref>), the group of congeneric species within Europe contained 133 native and 40 alien naturalized spp (see Table 
 <xref rid="ddi12578-sup-0003" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S6</xref>).
</p>
