<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The MaxEnt output maps show the changes in bioclimatic suitability within the study area. Nonetheless, it is known that the absence of adequate soil conditions would make the true suitability zero in most of the territory. To assess suitability in the gypsiferous areas, we need to know their locations. Outcrops of this type do not commonly cover large extensions and over the scale of the variables used, most of these outcrops would appear as mere points. Therefore, to trace the areas with gypsum soils we chose to use records of the presence of a gypsum indicator plant, 
 <italic class="italic">Ononis tridentata</italic>
 <bold class="bold">[
  <xref rid="pone.0218160.ref024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>,
  <xref rid="pone.0218160.ref068" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">68</xref>–
  <xref rid="pone.0218160.ref069" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">69</xref>]
 </bold>. This species was used as sole gypsum soils indicator for the several reasons: it is one of the most abundant gypsophyles in the Iberian Peninsula and this species thrives in a wide range of bioclimatic stages and gypsum soils. This species can be found on the Thermomediterranean (TMM), Mesomediterranean (MSM) and Supramediterranean (SPM) stages. It is also present on all types of gypsum soils, including crusts, saccaroid soils and gypsum marls, sometimes with low gypsum content. 
 <italic class="italic">O</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">tridentatata</italic> is the gypsophile with the lowest of gypsum content requirements and, as such, it can be present even in some washed soils of the Supramediterranean (SPM) stage. Again, we used QuantumGIS 
 <bold class="bold">[
  <xref rid="pone.0218160.ref067" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">67</xref>]
 </bold> to represent the georeferenced presence of 
 <italic class="italic">O</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">tridentata</italic> and the pattern of the data obtained coincided perfectly with the published maps of Iberian gypsum soils 
 <bold class="bold">[
  <xref rid="pone.0218160.ref024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>]
 </bold>. Subsequently, we obtained the suitability values from the models for those locations at three points in time: now, 2050 and 2070. Again, these values were color coded in the maps and through box-plots.
</p>
