<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Within the ABC framework, two classes of model parameters were used to characterize the phylogeographic hypotheses described above: effective population sizes (Ne), and divergence times (
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>). We performed two rounds of modeling: (a) a preliminary round with broad priors, and (b) the final round with narrower priors (Supporting Information Table S4.5). Briefly, all competing scenarios had two divergence events: any two of 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>
 <sub class="sub">N</sub>, 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>
 <sub class="sub">C</sub> or 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>
 <sub class="sub">S, </sub>(where the subscript is the first letter abbreviation of the new cluster, i.e., Northern, Central, or Southern), the prior range for the more recent event encompassed the MH and the LGM whereas priors for the older event ranged from the LGM to the LIG assuming a 1‐year generation time for 
 <italic class="italic">R. flavipes</italic>. Full details of ABC priors on Ne and T parameters are given in Supporting Information Appendix 
 <xref rid="ece35065-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S4</xref>. We set the mtDNA mutation rate priors from 5.0 × 10
 <sup class="sup">−9</sup> to 5.0 × 10
 <sup class="sup">−7</sup>, a broad range encompassing the Brower (
 <xref rid="ece35065-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1994</xref>) and Luchetti et al. (
 <xref rid="ece35065-bib-0066" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2005</xref>) rates (see Section 2—Step 2). Similarly, since no rates were available for the nDNA locus in 
 <italic class="italic">Reticulitermes</italic>, we used broad priors for this locus, from 5.0 × 10
 <sup class="sup">−10</sup> to 2.5 × 10
 <sup class="sup">−8</sup>. Thus, the mean nDNA rate was an order of magnitude slower than the mean mtDNA rate, despite some overlap at the upper end of nDNA and lower end of mtDNA prior ranges.
</p>
