<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0195">As above, ‘success’ may come through Fukuoka's early adoption of climate change and adaptation-related policies, especially the specificity with which these are considered within greenspace and urban plans. In Japan, existing urban policies developed for areas such as disaster risk reduction and environmental management may mean that cities are already relatively well-prepared for climate change adaptation and may not require new areas of policy or planning to deal with weather and climate risks (
 <xref rid="bb0165" ref-type="bibr">Hijioka et al., 2016</xref>). Indeed, as per 
 <xref rid="t0010" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>, Hiroshima City Government explicitly states that climate adaptation is considered within wider disaster risk reduction measures. What is perhaps distinctive about Fukuoka is therefore the 
 <italic>explicit</italic> focus on climate change within greenspace- and urban planning measures. Fukuoka City produced its first climate change plan in 1994, placing it ahead of other local governments developing similar plans (e.g. Hiroshima, Kobe, Kyoto, Osaka) by several years. In comparison to other Japanese city contexts, Fukuoka's greenspace planning has also made rigorous attempts to consider climate change, the urban thermal environment and to work towards understanding the city's greenspace in terms of a city-wide green network, supported by research from within the government and by local institutions (
 <xref rid="bb0050" ref-type="bibr">Fukuoka City, 1999</xref>, 
 <xref rid="bb0065" ref-type="bibr">Fukuoka City, 2009c</xref>). The city's support for research into localised heat island effects, and subsequent utilisation of these findings to inform decisions on development of a grass area outside Fukuoka City Hall (
 <xref rid="bb0300" ref-type="bibr">Tanaka et al., 2009</xref>), indicates there is a willingness within government to consider urban climate issues within their governance of the built environment. Moreover, although at an early stage, it is significant that 
 <xref rid="bb0135" ref-type="bibr">Fukuoka Prefecture's Climate Change Countermeasures Action Plan (2017)</xref> identifies the need to understand green infrastructure and ecosystem services across the Fukuoka area from now into the future.
</p>
