<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The carbon fluxes of the alpine grassland in the Tibetan Plateau were stimulated to be strongly influenced by the climate change and elevated CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> concentrations [
 <xref rid="pone.0215261.ref003" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0215261.ref005" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>]. Over the 21st century, the Tibetan Plateau grassland NPP and Rh were projected to significantly increase, at rates of 0.35 ~ 1.52 g C m
 <sup class="sup">-2</sup> yr
 <sup class="sup">-1</sup> and 0.49 ~ 1.62 g C m
 <sup class="sup">-2</sup> yr
 <sup class="sup">-1</sup>, respectively, under the three scenarios. These increases in NPP and Rh were primarily due to the effects of warming and elevated CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> concentrations, while the positive impact of precipitation became stable (Figs 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0215261.g005" class="xref">5</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0215261.g006" class="xref">6</xref>). The enhanced vegetation production in future projections was consistent with the model estimations of Gao et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0215261.ref007" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>] and Jin et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0215261.ref030" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>]. The dynamics of decadal carbon fluxes (ΔNPP and ΔRh) were predicted to decrease with precipitation and temperature under RCP2.6, and with temperature in a relatively stable precipitation scenario under RCP4.5 (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0215261.g005" class="xref">Fig 5</xref>). Across all scenarios, the partial correlation (R) between the carbon fluxes (NPP and Rh) and T
 <sub class="sub">mean</sub> (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0215261.g004" class="xref">Fig 4A–4F</xref>) were higher than those with precipitation (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0215261.g003" class="xref">Fig 3A–3F</xref>), except for the Rh in RCP4.5. These results suggested that the carbon cycle in the alpine region may be primarily controlled by the temperature increase. However, the partial correlation between carbon sink (NEP) and T
 <sub class="sub">mean</sub> was predicted to decrease from 0.14 in RCP2.6 to -0.09 in RCP8.5 under a warmer scenario (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0215261.g004" class="xref">Fig 4G and 4I</xref>). The partial correlation of NEP with precipitation were equal to 0.07 and 0.08 in RCP4.5 and RCP8.5 (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0215261.g003" class="xref">Fig 3H and 3I</xref>), which were higher than with T
 <sub class="sub">mean</sub> (0.04 and -0.09, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0215261.g004" class="xref">Fig 4H and 4I</xref>). Furthermore, the decadal carbon fluxes were predicted to decrease with decreasing precipitation, albeit increasing temperature under RCP8.5 during the 2040s ~ 2060s (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0215261.g005" class="xref">Fig 5</xref>). The role of precipitation was becoming increasingly important in carbon uptake of the Tibetan Plateau grassland. The seasonal dynamics of carbon exchange in alpine grassland under warming were likely to be modulated by water availability [
 <xref rid="pone.0215261.ref036" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>]. Similar results were found in Inner Mongolia [
 <xref rid="pone.0215261.ref052" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>], the central and eastern United States [
 <xref rid="pone.0215261.ref053" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">53</xref>], and California [
 <xref rid="pone.0215261.ref054" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>], which indicated that grass production would largely decrease under warmer and drier climate scenarios. The warming accelerated the evapotranspiration and then changed the soil water availability [
 <xref rid="pone.0215261.ref055" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0215261.ref056" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">56</xref>]. When the soil water availability became limited, the vegetation production might decrease due to suppressed photosynthesis [
 <xref rid="pone.0215261.ref057" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>] and also reduce root biomass [
 <xref rid="pone.0215261.ref058" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">58</xref>]. Shen et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0215261.ref006" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>] and Shen et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0215261.ref059" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">59</xref>] further indicated that the precipitation may regulate the response of vegetation phenology and soil respiration to climatic warming on the Tibetan Plateau. The water availability became an increasingly important factor on carbon dynamics on the Tibetan Plateau grasslands, particularly under a warmer climate scenario. These results highlight the significance of accurate projection of precipitation (i.e. the amounts and distributions) under three RCP scenarios, which should be considered in estimates of the carbon fluxes.
</p>
