<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Pure citation counts of papers are not meaningful, because they depend not only on the importance of research (for the research of other researchers than the authors), but also on the subject category and the publication year of the papers [
 <xref rid="pone.0160393.ref019" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>]. For example, one can expect more citations on average for papers in biology than for papers in the social sciences (using citation data from WoS). Therefore, we present citation impact scores in this study which are normalized concerning the particular publication year and WoS subject category [
 <xref rid="pone.0160393.ref020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. The normalization is done in our in-house database as follows: The proportion of papers of a given publication set A (e.g. a journal or a country) which belong to the most frequently cited papers in the corresponding WoS subject categories and publication years has emerged as the most robust normalized impact score [
 <xref rid="pone.0160393.ref021" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0160393.ref022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>]. In order to ascertain the proportion of papers, for every paper in A the reference set with comparable papers is composed. The comparable papers consist of papers belonging to the same subject category and publication year as the paper from A. The papers in the reference sets are sorted in descending order by their citation counts and the most frequently cited papers are identified. Then, either a paper from A belongs to the most frequently cited papers in the corresponding reference set (P
 <sub class="sub">Ai</sub> = 1) or not (P
 <sub class="sub">Ai</sub> = 0). Only some papers from A are fractionally assigned to the most frequently cited papers, if their citation counts position them at the threshold which is used to separate the most frequently cited papers from the rest in the reference set [
 <xref rid="pone.0160393.ref023" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>]. Based on this value for every paper i in A (0, …, 1), the proportion of papers in A is calculated which belongs to the most frequently cited papers in their set of comparable papers. In the case that a paper belongs to multiple subject categories, impact values are calculated for such papers in each subject category and average values are used for impact values on a paper basis.
</p>
