<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The use of climate velocity and MCE should be done in a manner that is cognizant of the tension between species-specific approaches, which have greater data needs but account for individual species responses to climate change, and coarse-filter approaches that are applied independently of species-specific data, such as the metrics presented here. Distance-based velocity implicitly assumes negligible thermal tolerances or adaptive capacity of local populations and thus represents an upper limit for migration requirements for climate-sensitive biota
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11" class="xref">11</xref>. In contrast, sites comprised of organisms with more broadly defined climate tolerances will have lower MCE and velocity values because more of the neighbouring landscape will be suitable for these organisms. This is demonstrated in 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Supplementary Table 1</xref>; mean velocity and MCE decrease as climate bin width increases. Fine-filter approaches that model potential migration paths for individual species have also been developed. For example, circuit theory has been applied to modelling faunal movement routes that track climate changes
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29" class="xref">29</xref>. In addition, both distance- and gradient-based approaches for calculating velocity have been adapted to account for individual species climate tolerances; so-called biotic velocity estimates the direction and rate at which a given species must move to track its climatic niche
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11" class="xref">11</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b30" class="xref">30</xref>. Biotic velocity suffers from the same limitations we identify here; it may not reflect the extent to which potential migration routes expose species to dissimilar climate. Nonetheless, the methods we employ can be applied to the calculation of biotic velocity and for estimating species-specific MCE.
</p>
