<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Mountains support roughly a quarter of the globe's terrestrial biodiversity, contain 32% of protected areas and nearly half of the world's biodiversity hotspots
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b31" class="xref">31</xref>. In light of this, our results raise a logical question of how to reconcile the notion of mountains as refugia under changing climate versus mountains as areas of high climatic resistance to movement. Climate change adaptation strategies are often predicated on the former notion which assumes that spatial variability in climate may allow for short distance dispersal to ameliorate climate change impacts
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14" class="xref">14</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15" class="xref">15</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16" class="xref">16</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b32" class="xref">32</xref>. This paradigm underlies approaches for reserve design
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b33" class="xref">33</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b34" class="xref">34</xref> and methods for identifying microrefugia
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9" class="xref">9</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16" class="xref">16</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b35" class="xref">35</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b36" class="xref">36</xref>. Nonetheless, an important and sometimes overlooked consideration is whether sites are accessible to migrating organisms
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b37" class="xref">37</xref>. Accessibility is partly a function of climatic connectivity to a given site
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4" class="xref">4</xref>. For example, velocity
 <sub class="sub">MED</sub> and MCE calculated for ‘reverse' climate trajectories (
 <italic class="italic">sensu</italic> ‘reverse velocity'
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b4" class="xref">4</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11" class="xref">11</xref>) provide two measures of climatic accessibility (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f5" class="xref">Fig. 5</xref>). Accessibility will also depend on physical barriers to movement, habitat fragmentation, land use and land cover change, among other factors. Temporal scale is another important consideration when trying to reconcile these two viewpoints. Velocity
 <sub class="sub">MED</sub> and MCE depend in part on the magnitude of climate shifts (a function of time) relative to the range or extent of the local spatial gradient in climate. Over short time intervals (or in places with sharp climate gradients) local dispersal, within the range of a local monotonic spatial climate gradient, may allow an organism to keep pace with climate change without exposure to dissimilar climates (for example, simple upslope movement; 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1" class="xref">Fig. 1b</xref>, path 1). However when the magnitude of climate change exceeds the extent of the local spatial gradient in climate, MCE (and potentially MED) will increase sharply as organisms are required to traverse unsuitable climates en route to a future climate analogue (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1" class="xref">Fig. 1b</xref>, path 2). This implies that at certain spatial and temporal scales, montane sites will act as climate refugia. Beyond these spatio-temporal domains, these sites will provide only temporary holdout habitat (
 <italic class="italic">sensu</italic>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b36" class="xref">36</xref>).
</p>
