<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par19" class="p">Other studies have suggested an alternative mechanism for the influence of volcanically induced land cooling on ENSO. The larger landmass in the Northern Hemisphere for instance may induce a large cooling over Asia and weakening of the Asian monsoon, inducing a southward Intertropical Convergence Zone (ITCZ) shift in boreal summer and fall, and westerly anomalies over the Pacific
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">21</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">24</xref>
 </sup>. This mechanism however does not apply in our experiments: the tropical cooling is rather symmetrical with respect to the equator in boreal fall after the eruption (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" class="xref">4</xref>), because the Pinatubo aerosol cloud is still mostly confined within the tropics at that time. Another work has underlined the potential role of the maritime continent cooling in generating the Pacific westerly wind anomalies
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" class="xref">19</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" class="xref">25</xref>
 </sup>. Our experiments do not yield any significant summer–fall Asian monsoon weakening or southward ITCZ shift (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" class="xref">4</xref>). Experiments with volcanically induced land cooling only applied over Southeast Asia, the maritime continent or the extra-tropics do not display any summer–fall westerly wind anomaly in the western Pacific (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" class="xref">5c</xref>). Our modelling results support a different mechanism from those invoked previously, in which the cooling of tropical landmasses, especially Africa, induces boreal summer–fall Pacific westerly wind anomalies that favour a Pacific warming (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" class="xref">7</xref>). This mechanism will however have to be tested in a wider variety of climate models.
</p>
