<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We conducted an on-farm experiment to evaluate the nitrate retention in the surface soil after snowmelt at fields with different annual maximum soil frost depths (
 <italic class="italic">D</italic>
 <sub class="sub">max</sub>; m). The snow cover manipulation experiment was conducted at two experimental fields at the Memuro Research Station. The soil type is classified as Andisols derived from volcanic ash, which is the major soil type in the Tokachi region. Soil nitrate content at 0–0.40 m depth (kg N ha
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>) before snowfall and after snowmelt was set to 
 <italic class="italic">AutumnN</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Spring N</italic>, respectively (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Table S3</xref>). For the statistical modelling, the year of study and experimental field examined were regarded as an independent study plot. Next, because nitrate content is a continuous value and should not have negative values, we assumed that the variations in the observed nitrate content in the surface soil after snowmelt follows the Gamma distribution of shape parameter 
 <italic class="italic">s</italic> and rate parameter 
 <italic class="italic">r</italic> (
 <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq10" class="xref">eq. 8</xref>), which are related to the mean 
 <italic class="italic">μ</italic> with 
 <italic class="italic">s</italic>/
 <italic class="italic">r</italic> and the variance with 
 <italic class="italic">s</italic>/
 <italic class="italic">r</italic>
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>. According to the definition of the dispersion parameter ϕ, these parameters are related to the variance with 
 <italic class="italic">μ</italic>
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>ϕ; thus, 
 <italic class="italic">s</italic> is 1/ϕ and 
 <italic class="italic">r</italic> is 1/ϕ
 <italic class="italic">μ</italic>. We set 
 <italic class="italic">D</italic>
 <sub class="sub">max</sub> as the explanatory variable and 
 <italic class="italic">AutumnN</italic> as the offset term in the linear predictor. Subsequently, the log link function was applied to the linear predictor (
 <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq11" class="xref">eq. 9</xref>). The parameters in 
 <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq10" class="xref">eq. 8</xref> (
 <italic class="italic">s, r</italic>) and the coefficients in 
 <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="eq11" class="xref">eq. 9</xref> (β
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">N</italic>1
 </sub>, β
 <sub class="sub">
  <italic class="italic">N</italic>2
 </sub>) were estimated using the ‘glm’ function of R software package
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29" class="xref">29</xref>.
</p>
