<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">A combination of a high temperature (27/30 °C) and recurrent drought at the seedling and tillering stages (which might be a predicted climate change scenario for lowland valleys of Rwanda) showed the most severe results for the plant development and yield, with no panicles plant
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup> resulting in zero yield for all cultivars. However, for the rest of the combinations of drought and temperature treatments, the different cultivars reacted differently. Differences among cultivars towards drought conditions may be the result of a range of various characters in the plant, including both root and leaf characters [
 <xref rid="B36-ijerph-16-01043" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>]. Thus, cultivars capable of extracting more water from the soil and maintaining a good water status in the tissues are able to withstand drought and to produce grains. The cultivar ‘Zong geng’ showed the most severe reaction regarding panicles plant
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>, resulting in a total absence after most of the treatments. This genotype is both taller and later flowering than the other cultivars when grown during field conditions (
 <xref rid="ijerph-16-01043-t001" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref>), which might explain part of its sensitivity to drought conditions, although additional studies are needed for a full understanding of variations in the reactions from the different genotypes. In addition, cultivar interactions with the soil water content and the time course of its’ changes may contribute to an understanding of drought treatments on various cultivars. The course of soil water content for each individual plants, cultivars, and treatments was not measured in the present study, and such interactions are an option for further studies. However, previous studies have indicated that leaf characteristics of rice, including leaf water status and leaf elongation rate, are limitedly sensitive to soil water content and deficits; instead, the root character was proposed as the main character related to drought sensitivity [
 <xref rid="B37-ijerph-16-01043" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>]. Furthermore, panicle exertion and abortion of secondary rachis branches has been reported as the major causes of yield reduction in rice under drought stress [
 <xref rid="B38-ijerph-16-01043" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>], which correspond to the results in the present study. The severe reduction in the number of panicles plant
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup> and, consequently, reduction in grain yield in the present study indicate that a high temperature and recurrent drought at the seedling and tillering stages were severe for the rice plants. Drought conditions and the cultivation of rice in the present study were based on methodology developed at IRRI [
 <xref rid="B23-ijerph-16-01043" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>]. The high temperature combined with recurrent drought at the seedling and tillering stages might have resulted in more severe drought responses in rice than is normally found while rice is grown during field conditions. At present, rice is most likely not recommended to be grown at conditions with severe recurrent drought conditions at a high temperature. However, the severe drought responses from the rice in the present study might also be due to differences in growing conditions in the biotron compared to in field conditions. It is well known that biotron or green-house cultivations are not perfectly comparable to cultivation in field conditions. In the biotron, the rice plants were grown in pots, not allowing the roots to extract water deep in the soil; in addition, microbiota and other biotic factors are known to be different. Despite the fact that biotron conditions are not totally comparable to field conditions, our results predict a high risk of large reduction in rice yield in the predicted climate change scenarios. In previous studies, spikelet sterility has consistently been reported as an indicator of sensitivity to drought around flowering [
 <xref rid="B39-ijerph-16-01043" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>] and is directly associated with leaf water potential. However, in the present study, spikelet sterility was mainly found to be correlated to the temperature of rice cultivation and, to a lesser degree, to the drought treatments. The fact that spikelet sterility was not seen as correlated with drought treatments thereby verifies drought treatments as not being severe enough to result in differences in leaf water potential. Extreme temperatures have been found to affect spikelet fertility by causing poor anther dehiscence, pollen grains deficiency, and failure of pollen germination on stigmas [
 <xref rid="B40-ijerph-16-01043" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="B41-ijerph-16-01043" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>]. Our results primarily showed high spikelet sterility at a low temperature, which has also been shown in other studies [
 <xref rid="B42-ijerph-16-01043" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>]. Spikelet sterility under the low temperature regime is a sign of this temperature being in the lower edge of the optimal range. However, we found comparable yields in high and low temperatures treated rice due to an increased spikelet fertility compensating for the low number of panicles plant
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup> at a high temperature.
</p>
