<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Rossby wave train during September–October 2016</div>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The lower level atmospheric circulation anomalies during Sep–Oct 2016 appear as a wave train arcing across the mid-high latitudes (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2a</a>), with a close correspondence between the variations in Antarctic sea-ice, represented by sea-ice concentration (SIC) (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2b</a>), and the meridional wind anomalies (shading in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2a</a>). SIC decreases in conjunction with anomalous northerlies and increases in conjunction with southerlies through associated anomalous poleward heat advection and sea ice drift. SIC anomalies were negative over the west Pacific to west Ross Sea sector, Bellingshausen and Amundsen Seas sector, and to lesser extent over the western Indian Ocean sector
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
  </span>.
  <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Atmospheric circulation and sea-ice concentration during September to December 2016. 
     <span class="bold">a</span> Sep–Oct 850 hPa wind anomaly (vectors, scale in upper right, m s
     <span class="sup">−1</span>); Shading is meridional wind component with northerly coloured in reds and southerly coloured in blues (interval 1.5 m s
     <span class="sup">−1</span>); 
     <span class="bold">b</span> Sep–Oct Antarctic sea-ice concentration (SIC) anomaly (shading; interval 0.05); the 0.15 contour is highlighted with red dashed curve. For clarity, SIC anomaly is only displayed in the latitudes poleward of 50
     <span class="bold">°</span>S. 
     <span class="bold">c</span>, 
     <span class="bold">d</span> are the same as 
     <span class="bold">a</span>, 
     <span class="bold">b</span>, respectively, but for Nov–Dec 2016. The shading in 
     <span class="bold">c</span> is zonal wind component with easterly coloured in reds and westerly coloured in blues (interval 3 m s
     <span class="sup">−1</span>). Plots were generated using the NCAR Command Language version 6.4.0 (
     <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncl.ucar.edu" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.ncl.ucar.edu</span>)
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2018_7689_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e551" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Rossby wave theory suggests that changes in tropical convection and corresponding anomalous diabatic heating can excite Rossby wave trains that teleconnect the region of tropical forcing to the extratropics
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
  </span>. In the SH, the Rossby wave response to tropical convective forcing manifests as a stationary wave train propagating poleward and eastward from the source, thereby resulting in persistent circulation anomalies that can influence surface thermal conditions and sea-ice across most sectors surrounding the Antarctic
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">During Sep–Oct 2016, weak La Niña conditions were developing in the Pacific (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1c</a>), while a record strong negative IOD had reached its mature stage in the tropical Indian Ocean as reflected by the IOD Mode Index (DMI)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
  </span> (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1d</a>). The anomalous SST patterns associated with this La Niña and negative IOD favoured a tri-pole pattern of suppressed-enhanced-suppressed convection in western Indian Ocean through to the western Pacific Oceans (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3a</a>, shading). An index representing this tropical convective anomaly (Methods) exhibited a record value in Sep–Oct 2016 (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1e</a>).
  <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Rossby wave train and source during September–October 2016. 
     <span class="bold">a</span> 200 hPa divergent wind anomaly (vectors, scale in upper right, m s
     <span class="sup">−1</span>), Rossby wave source (RWS, magenta contours, positive (anticyclonic) solid and negative (cyclonic) dashed, zero line omitted; interval 4 × 10
     <span class="sup">−11</span>s
     <span class="sup">−2</span>, see Methods) and outgoing longwave radiation (OLR) anomaly (shading; interval 4 Wm
     <span class="sup">−2</span>) for Sep–Oct 2016. 
     <span class="bold">b</span> 200 hPa eddy streamfunction anomaly (shading; interval 3 × 10
     <span class="sup">6</span> m
     <span class="sup">2</span>s) and anomalous wave activity flux (WAF, vectors, m
     <span class="sup">2</span> s
     <span class="sup">−2</span>) for Sep–Oct 2016. 
     <span class="bold">c</span>–
     <span class="bold">f</span> are same as 
     <span class="bold">a</span>, 
     <span class="bold">b</span> but displayed fields are derived by multiple linear regression onto the DMI index (
     <span class="bold">c</span>, 
     <span class="bold">d</span>) and Nino34 SST index (
     <span class="bold">e</span>, 
     <span class="bold">f</span>) using historical data for the period 1979–2015 (see Methods). The anomalies in 
     <span class="bold">c</span>, 
     <span class="bold">d</span> and 
     <span class="bold">e</span>, 
     <span class="bold">f</span> are scaled by the observed magnitude of the DMI and Nino34 index, respectively, in Sep–Oct 2016. Contouring/shading is as in 
     <span class="bold">a</span> and 
     <span class="bold">b</span>, except RWS interval is 2 × 10
     <span class="sup">−11</span> s
     <span class="sup">−2</span>, and eddy streamfunction interval is 1 × 10
     <span class="sup">6</span> m
     <span class="sup">2</span>s. Anomalies and regression coefficients are shown only for 
     <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.10 using two-sided 
     <span class="italic">t</span>-test. For clarity, divergent wind weaker than 0.8 ms
     <span class="sup">−1</span> in 
     <span class="bold">a</span>, and weaker than 0.3 ms
     <span class="sup">−1</span> in 
     <span class="bold">c</span> and 
     <span class="bold">e</span>, WAF weaker than 0.8 m
     <span class="sup">2</span>s
     <span class="sup">−2</span> in 
     <span class="bold">b</span>, and weaker than 0.1 m
     <span class="sup">2</span>s
     <span class="sup">−2</span> in 
     <span class="bold">d</span> and 
     <span class="bold">f</span> are masked. In the Southern Hemisphere, negative streamfunction anomaly corresponds to positive geopotential height anomaly and thus is coloured in reds; similarly, positive streamfunction anomaly is coloured in blues. Plots were generated using the NCAR Command Language version 6.4.0 (
     <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ncl.ucar.edu" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.ncl.ucar.edu</span>)
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2018_7689_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e733" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">These record anomalies in tropical convection forced anomalous divergent outflow and inflow in the upper troposphere (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3a</a>, vectors), which act as an effective Rossby wave source (RWS; Methods) in the subtropics by anomalously advecting the mean meridional gradient of absolute vorticity that maximises along about 25°S
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span>. An anticyclonic RWS emerges off the west coast of Australia in association with the southward divergent flow from the enhanced convection in the eastern Indian Ocean (purple contours lettered “H” in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3a</a>). Similarly, the anomalous northward divergent in-flow driven by suppressed convection in the western Indian Ocean and more pronouncedly in the western Pacific produced cyclonic RWS centred approximately at 65°E (“L1”) and 165°E (“L2”), respectively.
 </p>
 <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The anticyclonic RWS in the eastern Indian Ocean (“H” in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3a</a>) appears to drive an anticyclonic streamfunction anomaly off the northwest coast of Australia (“A1” in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3b</a>), and the cyclonic RWS off the northeast coast of Australia (“L2” in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3a</a>) drives a cyclonic streamfunction anomaly (“C” in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3b</a>). These subtropical streamfunction anomalies are then associated with wave trains that arc poleward and eastward into the SH higher latitudes. Wave activity flux anomalies (vectors in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3b</a>; Methods), which track the group velocity of the Rossby wave train, indicate that the RWS in the eastern Indian Ocean is the source of the wave train that arcs poleward to the west of Australia, and then eastward across the Southern Ocean along the waveguide of the high latitude westerly jet
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>
  </span>. The cyclonic RWS in the western Pacific is similarly associated with a wave train that propagates poleward and eastward in the western Pacific, avoiding the region around New Zealand where meridional gradient of absolute vorticity becomes negative (Supplementary Figure 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2</a>) and so prohibits Rossby wave propagation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
  </span>. This wave train perhaps is partially refracted back to the tropics in the eastern Pacific (indicated by the equatorward pointing wave activity flux vectors). However, the two wave trains appear to constructively add to the cyclonic-anticyclonic anomalies to the southwest and southeast of South America, thus contributing to the zonal wavenumber 3 pattern along 60°S. Divergence of wave activity flux in the southern Indian Ocean indicates an additional anticyclonic source of the extratropical Rossby wave train (labelled “A2” in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3b</a>). This additional wave source has previously been shown to typically develop during negative IOD years, resulting from feedback of altered transient eddies in the high latitude storm track onto the seasonal mean anomalous circulation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The extratropical circulation anomalies are similarly signed throughout the depth of the troposphere (i.e. compare Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3b</a> with the implied circulation centres near the surface from Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2a</a>), consistent with theoretical considerations for forcing of extratropical circulation anomalies by tropical convection
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
  </span>, and so are indicative of the anomalous winds at the surface that would directly impact sea ice.
 </p>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The role played by IOD and ENSO in promoting the Rossby wave trains that affected SIE during Sep–Oct 2016 is clarified by multiple regression of winds, outgoing longwave radiation (OLR) and streamfunction onto indices of the IOD (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a> middle panels) and ENSO (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a> bottom panels) using the historical record 1979–2015. For display, the resulting regressions are scaled by the magnitude of the IOD and ENSO indices in 2016 (Methods). This method successfully isolates the anomalous convection, RWS, and wave train emanating from the tropical Indian Ocean associated with the IOD and from the tropical Pacific associated with ENSO. During 2016, the wave train emanating from the Indian Ocean has stronger amplitude and spans both the eastern and western hemispheres compared to the wave train emanating from the Pacific associated with La Niña. The sum of these two patterns explains about half of the high latitude anomalies observed during Sep–Oct 2016 (figure not shown). The other half plausibly comes from internal variability that cannot be described by the simple regression model.
 </p>
 <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The analysis presented in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a> indicates that the record negative IOD played a key role in generating the wave-3 pattern at high latitudes that affected SIE around the breadth of Antarctica during Sep–Oct 2016. The weak La Nina conditions in the Pacific played a more secondary role by contributing constructively to the anomalous circulation to the south of South America. The stronger forcing from the tropical Indian Ocean is supported by comparable regression results using reforecasts from a coupled model (Supplementary Figure 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">3</a>). The results are also consistent with that obtained with an atmosphere-only model experiment with a specified convective heating representing precipitation anomaly in September–November 2016 in the eastern Indian/western Pacific Ocean
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
</sec>
