<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Invasive alien species are considered the second biggest threat to global biodiversity, after habitat degradation (Gurevitch and Padilla, 
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2004</xref>; Powell et al., 
 <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>). Invasive plant species alter the dynamics of plant communities and thus threaten the stability and functioning of established ecosystems by affecting nutrient cycles and net primary productivity, affecting soil health by increasing soil acidity, posing risk for pollinators, inhibiting regeneration of native species, and competing with native flora (Manchester and Bullock, 
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2000</xref>; Ehrenfeld, 
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2003</xref>; Snowdonia Rhododendron Partnership, 
 <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>; Tiedeken and Stout, 
 <xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>). Plant invasion causes significant economic losses to crop and livestock farmers around the world (Peterson et al., 
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2008</xref>). Various studies estimate that the global monetary value of direct damage and associated control of invasives exceeds $100 billion per annum (Pimentel et al., 
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2005</xref>). However, since there are many invasive species with no recorded damage costs, the true figure is likely to be many times higher than these estimates (Bradshaw et al., 
 <xref rid="B68" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>). Several studies have highlighted the potential impacts of global climate change on population dynamics of invasive species, with secondary effects on host plant communities and ecosystems (Chapin et al., 
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2000</xref>; Peterson et al., 
 <xref rid="B58" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2008</xref>). During the last century, global average temperatures have increased by 0.85°C above pre-industrial levels and are expected to further increase by 0.3–4.8°C by 2100 (IPCC, 
 <xref rid="B42" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>). Changes in climatic conditions may render some regions more or less suitable for invasive plants thus increasing or decreasing their range (Bradley et al., 
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>). Effects of climate change on invasiveness of alien species must be considered and any prediction of future distribution should include a range of climate change scenarios.
</p>
