<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In Europe, 
 <italic class="italic">Rhododendron ponticum</italic> (L.) is an invasive plant species that was introduced to the United Kingdom in the eighteenth century as an ornamental plant. It is a perennial, evergreen shrub that generally invades woodlands (Tiedeken and Stout, 
 <xref rid="B77" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>), although it has been shown to colonize other types of habitats too. The main ancestor is reported to be the population of 
 <italic class="italic">R. ponticum</italic> resident at the southern tip of Spain. The successful invasion of 
 <italic class="italic">R. ponticum</italic> in the UK is attributed to a range of its ecological and biological characteristics: it produces great amounts of seeds which are wind-dispersed, can tolerate shade and thus outcompetes flora under closed canopies and can easily colonize low-nutrient sites (Dehnen-Schmutz and Williamson, 
 <xref rid="B24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2006</xref>). It often prevents germination of native plant species by casting a dense shade and by releasing toxins into the soil (Stephenson et al., 
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2006</xref>). Germination of 
 <italic class="italic">R. ponticum</italic> seeds may occur on a number of substrates, including tree stumps and mosses covering bare ground (Cross, 
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1981</xref>) The UK invasion by this shrub has been more intense in Western and North Western parts, which are the comparatively cooler and wetter areas of Britain. A genetic analysis of the British population of 
 <italic class="italic">R. ponticum</italic> has confirmed the presence of genes from 
 <italic class="italic">R. catawbiense</italic> (Michx), suggesting past hybridization between the two species. 
 <italic class="italic">R. catawbiense</italic> is a species native to North America and characterized by greater cold tolerance (Erfmeier et al., 
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>; Snowdonia Rhododendron Partnership, 
 <xref rid="B66" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>; Die et al., 
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2017</xref>), a trait that may increase invasiveness of 
 <italic class="italic">R. ponticum</italic> in the UK. However, an in-depth analysis is still required to identify the other key environmental factors responsible for colonization and spread of this species. Of the various parts of U.K. invaded by 
 <italic class="italic">R. ponticum</italic>, Wales is one of the worst affected regions. In this study, we focus on the Snowdonia National Park in Wales where 
 <italic class="italic">R. ponticum</italic> is identified as a major invasive species affecting large areas of the National Park (Jackson, 
 <xref rid="B44" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2008</xref>) indicating that current environmental, topographic and land cover conditions in Snowdonia represent a range of conditions very suitable for 
 <italic class="italic">R. ponticum</italic>.
</p>
