<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The type and timing of climatic extremes may be crucial for the dynamics and range expansion of plant communities. Drought or extreme rainfall may occur before or during the growing season, and their effects on plant community composition can differ. In a greenhouse study (
 <xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>27</italic>
 </xref>), plant species that expanded their range from southern Europe (warm and dry) toward northern Europe (currently warming) were grown in mixed communities with their congeneric relatives that were native to northern Europe. The soils in that study had been subjected to preseason drought, preseason rainfall, and combined conditions and were then brought back to control soil water conditions. Preseason drought increased the proportional contribution of range-expanding plant species to community composition, whereas preseason rainfall had smaller effects (
 <xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>27</italic>
 </xref>). These effects corresponded to the increased abundance of the so-called “drought response types” or “wet response types” among both bacteria and fungi (
 <xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>36</italic>
 </xref>). Furthermore, a recent outdoor mesocosm study (
 <xref rid="R61" ref-type="bibr">
  <italic>61</italic>
 </xref>) compared the current climatic situation with three future scenarios: range shifts of plants but not soil biota, range shifts of soil biota but not plants, and range shifts of both plants and soil biota. During the growing season, half of the mesocosms were exposed to drought, while the other half was provided with the 30-year average water conditions of nondrought years. During extreme drought, decomposition was strongly reduced in all four types of mesocosms. After rewetting the soil, however, decomposition with plants in temperate zones recovered 2 weeks faster than that with range-shifted plants that originated from a region characterized by severe summer droughts.
</p>
