<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">For genotyping, DNA from each of the 233 sampled trees was extracted from foliage using the protocol described by Nadeau 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. (
 <xref rid="nph14968-bib-0058" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). Leaf sampling was conducted independently from the sampling of Nadeau 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. (
 <xref rid="nph14968-bib-0058" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>, 
 <xref rid="nph14968-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>): only 21 out of 133 populations sampled in Nadeau 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. (
 <xref rid="nph14968-bib-0058" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>, 
 <xref rid="nph14968-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>) are common to both datasets (16%), and samples within populations are largely different (
 <italic class="italic">c</italic>. 4% in common). The 233 trees were genotyped on the same set of 153 SNP markers as in Nadeau 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. (
 <xref rid="nph14968-bib-0058" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>) previously developed in a Sequenom iPlex Gold MassARRAY (Agena Bioscience, San Diego, CA, USA). This array included SNPs from 52 candidate genes for growth and phenology previously identified in 
 <italic class="italic">Picea glauca</italic> and 68 noncandidate genes randomly distributed across the genome (for more details see Nadeau 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="nph14968-bib-0058" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>, 
 <xref rid="nph14968-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). Using this array and an independent set of populations distributed across the range of 
 <italic class="italic">P. strobus</italic>, Nadeau 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. (
 <xref rid="nph14968-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>) identified 26 candidate SNPs for local adaptation using GEAs and 
 <italic class="italic">F</italic>
 <sub class="sub">ST</sub> outlier tests. In this study, eight trees and six SNPs failed during the genotyping step and were discarded from subsequent analyses. SNPs with a minor allele frequency &lt; 0.03 were also discarded. This resulted in 225 trees and 128 SNPs successfully genotyped (SNP genotyping call rate: min. = 90.7%, mean = 98.9%), including 21 of the candidate SNPs identified by Nadeau 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. (
 <xref rid="nph14968-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). All of the 21 candidate SNPs were detected by at least one GEA method, and two SNPs were 
 <italic class="italic">F</italic>
 <sub class="sub">ST</sub> outliers (Nadeau 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="nph14968-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>; Table 
 <xref rid="nph14968-sup-0002" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S3</xref>). No trees were discarded based on the genotyping call rate (min. = 78.9%; mean = 98.9%). GenBank accession numbers of the genes containing the 128 SNPs are given in Table 
 <xref rid="nph14968-sup-0002" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S3</xref>.
</p>
