<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Altered body growth and reproductive performance among individual fish are important impacts of climate change as variation in energy use of ectothermic animals is inherently driven by differences in ambient temperature (Brown, Gillooly, Allen, Savage, &amp; West, 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2004</xref>; Magnuson, Crowder, &amp; Medvick, 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0138" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1979</xref>). Decreased size and age of sexual maturation with increasing temperature are widely reported for freshwater fish across contrasting climate regions, including populations inhabiting the subarctic (Blanck &amp; Lamouroux, 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>; Daufresne, Lengfellner, &amp; Sommer, 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>; Griffiths, 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0068" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0069" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>; Heibo, Magnhagen, &amp; Vøllestad, 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0085" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2005</xref>; Lappalainen, Tarkan, &amp; Harrod, 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0127" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>). In contrast to decreasing body size of parental fish, individual egg size increases with increasing temperature in autumn‐spawning brown trout (
 <italic class="italic">Salmo trutta</italic>) and Atlantic salmon (
 <italic class="italic">S</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">salar</italic>; Jonsson &amp; Jonsson, 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0111" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>), yet decreases in spring‐spawning roach (Lappalainen et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0127" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>). In spring‐spawning European perch, the gonadosomatic index (the proportion of gonad to total body mass) increases with temperature (Heibo et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0085" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2005</xref>), and individual fecundity of roach peaks in mid‐latitude regions throughout their range (Lappalainen et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0127" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>). These findings suggest that temperature increases will lead to higher reproductive output for spring‐spawning invasive species (e.g., roach and European perch), potentially enhancing their invasion success in subarctic regions.
</p>
