<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We used 10.0 arc-minute current and future datasets for the environmental layer input of the species distribution model (
 <xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Araújo et al., 2011</xref>). We obtained nine bioclimatic variables with 10.0-arc-minute spatial resolution (the same as future bioclimatic variables) from the WorldClim database (averages from 1950 to 2000 were used as current bioclimatic variables; 
 <uri xlink:href="http://www.worldclim.org" class="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.worldclim.org</uri>; 
 <xref rid="ref-44" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hijmans et al., 2005</xref>). The nine bioclimatic variables are shown in 
 <xref rid="table-1" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref>. 
 <xref rid="ref-44" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hijmans et al. (2005)</xref> presented detailed information for bioclimatic variables. The nine bioclimatic variables were selected because they are related to distributions of IPS at global scales and can indicate the maximum, minimum, mean, and variance of temperature and precipitation (
 <xref rid="ref-86" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Thuiller et al., 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-66" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Petitpierre et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bellard et al., 2013</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>). We tested multi-collinearity for the layers of above-mentioned bioclimatic variables using Pearson’s correlation coefficient (
 <italic class="italic">r</italic> ≤ ±0.85) for further analysis (
 <xref rid="ref-18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Briscoe et al., 2016</xref>). We relied on data from the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change Fifth Assessment Report as a reference for modelling the changing trends of IPS invasions (
 <xref rid="ref-83" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Stocker, 2014</xref>; 
 <uri xlink:href="http://www.ipcc.ch/" class="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.ipcc.ch/</uri>). To model the future potential distribution of IPS in the 2080s (2071–2099), we used the maps of four global climate models (GCMs; i.e. bcc_csm1_1, csiro_mk3_6_0, gfdl_cm3, and mohc_hadgem2_es downloaded from 
 <uri xlink:href="http://www.ccafs-climate.org/" class="uri" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.ccafs-climate.org/</uri>), which successfully reproduce the general features of temperature structure in terms of vertical, annual, and inter-annual variation (
 <xref rid="ref-86" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Thuiller et al., 2005</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bellard et al., 2013</xref>, 
 <xref rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kishore et al., 2016</xref>). We averaged the pixel values of bioclimatic data based on these four GCMs (
 <xref rid="ref-50" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Läderach et al., 2017</xref>). Representative concentration pathways (RCPs) 4.5 and 8.5 were used in our study (
 <xref rid="ref-77" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Rogelj, Meinshausen &amp; Knutti, 2012</xref>).
</p>
