<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">For each of the three 
 <italic class="italic">R. flavipes</italic> genetic groups, we assessed evidence for population size changes versus stability by calculating Tajima's 
 <italic class="italic">D</italic>, and Fu and Li's 
 <italic class="italic">D</italic>* and 
 <italic class="italic">F</italic>* (Fu &amp; Li, 
 <xref rid="ece35065-bib-0030" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1993</xref>) from the mtDNA data, in DnaSP. To identify cases of departure from the null hypothesis of constant size, 
 <italic class="italic">p</italic>‐values for these statistics were obtained by computing 10,000 coalescent simulations based on 
 <italic class="italic">θ</italic> from the observed data and assuming no recombination. We also calculated Ramos‐Onsins and Rozas' (
 <xref rid="ece35065-bib-0084" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2002</xref>) 
 <italic class="italic">R</italic>
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> statistic for which significantly small values indicate population growth, whereas significantly large 
 <italic class="italic">R</italic>
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> values indicate size reduction. Statistical significance of deviation from the null hypothesis of constant population size was assessed by performing 10,000 coalescent simulations in DnaSP. To complement the above analyses, we also estimated mismatch distributions, where a unimodal distribution indicates growth, whereas a multimodal distribution is indicative of size constancy (Rogers &amp; Harpending, 
 <xref rid="ece35065-bib-0087" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1992</xref>). Given that signatures of selection can mimic those of population size changes and therefore complicate interpretation of the above summary statistics, we examined evidence for nonneutrality using compound tests (Zeng, Shi, &amp; Wu, 
 <xref rid="ece35065-bib-0111" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>). We performed the compound tests using the program DH (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://zeng-lab.group.shef.ac.uk/wordpress" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://zeng-lab.group.shef.ac.uk/wordpress</ext-link>). The significance (
 <italic class="italic">α</italic> = 0.05) of each test was determined using 100,000 simulations.
</p>
