<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s7" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">7.</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results</div>
 <sec id="s7a" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(a)</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Seed dispersal events</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Overall, the seed rain was highly heterogeneous, with 215 (77%) seed-plots receiving no 
   <span class="italic">T. baccata</span> seeds; 47 (17%) receiving less than 10 seeds; and only 15 (5%) receiving 10 or more seeds (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTB20150280F2" href="#RSTB20150280F2">figure 2</a>
   <span class="italic">a</span>). Additionally, all seeds were collected in the southern half of the fenced population, in the vicinity of yew trees (figures 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTB20150280F1" href="#RSTB20150280F1">1
    <span class="italic">b</span>
   </a> and 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTB20150280F2" href="#RSTB20150280F2">2</a>
   <span class="italic">a</span>), highlighting a spatially constrained seed dispersal pattern. 
   <div id="RSTB20150280F2" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Figure 2.</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Empirical observations from our study system. (
      <span class="italic">a</span>) Seed rain of 
      <span class="italic">T. baccata</span>. Squares represent seed-plots and are proportional to the number of yew seeds collected; dots represent seed-plots that did not receive 
      <span class="italic">T. baccata</span> seeds. (
      <span class="italic">b</span>) Distribution of observed flight distances to first perch of frugivorous birds feeding on 
      <span class="italic">T. baccata</span>. Grey bars represent short-distance seed dispersers, which include 
      <span class="italic">Coccothraustes coccothraustes</span>, 
      <span class="italic">Erithacus rubecula</span>, 
      <span class="italic">Phoenicurus ochruros</span>, 
      <span class="italic">Sylvia atricapilla</span> and 
      <span class="italic">Turdus merula</span>. White bars represent long-distance seed dispersers, which include 
      <span class="italic">Turdus viscivorus</span>, 
      <span class="italic">T. philomelos</span> and 
      <span class="italic">T. torquatus</span>. (
      <span class="italic">c</span>) Frequency distribution of the dispersal distances of seeds from known origin. All the seeds but three (indicated by an arrow) came from a source tree inside the fence. (
      <span class="italic">d</span>) Frequency distribution of the minimum dispersal distance of the seeds from unknown sources, i.e. the minimum distance between the seed-plot containing the immigrant seed and the limit of the complementary area explored (dotted line in the electronic supplementary material, figure S1).
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="rstb20150280-g2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The 254 seed endocarps analysed were distributed in 59 seed-plots, thus encompassing the spatial variability of the seed rain. From those endocarps, 172 (67.7%) matched a mother tree inside the fenced area, 3 (1.2%) matched a mother tree outside the fence and 79 (31.1%) originated from unknown sources (electronic supplementary material, tables S2 and S4). For clarity, we will refer to the seeds that originate from a mother tree inside the fence as the local seed pool, and from a mother tree outside the fence as the immigrant seed pool (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTB20150280F3" href="#RSTB20150280F3">figure 3</a>
   <span class="italic">b</span>). Ten (42%) female trees contributed to the local seed pool, out of the 20 censused inside the fenced area. As for the immigrant seed pool, 1 of the 6 additional female trees sampled contributed 3 (4%) seeds, and 51 unidentified source trees—thus located outside our extended sampling area (electronic supplementary material, figures S1 and S3)—contributed the remaining 79 (96%) seeds. 
   <div id="RSTB20150280F3" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Figure 3.</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Spatial information of the seed-plots receiving bird-dispersed seeds. The size of the node is proportional to the total number of seeds analysed within each seed-plot (as in the regional network, 
      <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTB20150280F4" href="#RSTB20150280F4">figure 4</a>
      <span class="italic">b</span>). (
      <span class="italic">a</span>) Microhabitat of the seed-plots. N, non-fleshy-fruited tree; F, fleshy-fruited tree; P, pine tree; S, shrub; R, rock; TF, 
      <span class="italic">T. baccata</span> female tree; TM, 
      <span class="italic">T. baccata</span> male tree (see the electronic supplementary material, SI-1 for a detailed description of the microhabitats). (
      <span class="italic">b</span>) Maternal origin of the seed pool analysed from each seed-plot. Local: seed-plots where all the seeds were from local mother trees; outside: seed-plots where all the seeds were from mother trees outside the fenced area; mixed: seed-plots receiving seeds from mother trees both inside and outside the fenced area.
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="rstb20150280-g3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Seed dispersal distances of seeds from a mother tree within the fenced area and from outside of it have different frequency distributions (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTB20150280F2" href="#RSTB20150280F2">figure 2</a>
   <span class="italic">c,d</span>). Dispersal events inside the fence largely occur at very short distances (less than 50 m), in the vicinity of the source trees. Contrastingly, the seeds originating from outside the fence, and from unknown origin, displayed much longer dispersal distances (most of them greater than 300 m), especially because these distances are most probably underestimated (closest population located at 1.5 km; electronic supplementary material, figure S3).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There was an equal number of seed-plots, 25 (42%), receiving either strictly locally dispersed seeds or both locally dispersed and immigrant seeds (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTB20150280F3" href="#RSTB20150280F3">figure 3</a>
   <span class="italic">b</span>). Only 9 (15%) seed-plots received immigrant seeds exclusively. No clear spatial pattern of the seed-plots depending on the origin of the seeds emerged, but we observed a tendency for the seed-plots with mixed seed origin to receive a greater number of seeds.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The immigrant seed pool displayed a higher mean allelic richness than the local seed pool (
   <a rid="RSTB20150280TB1" ref-type="table" href="#RSTB20150280TB1">table 1</a>), which probably reflects the larger number of mother trees (52 versus 10). Nonetheless, the lower observed heterozygosity, 
   <span class="italic">H</span>
   <sub>o</sub>, among the immigrant seed pool suggests that they originate from genetically depauperate sources. 
   <div id="RSTB20150280TB1" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="table-wrap">
    <span class="label">Table 1.</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Summary genetic data for the dispersed seeds. 
      <span class="italic">n</span>, sample size; 
      <span class="italic">N</span>
      <sub>m</sub>, number of identified mother trees; 
      <span class="italic">A</span>, mean allelic richness; 
      <span class="italic">H</span>
      <sub>E</sub>, Nei's unbiased expected heterozygosity; 
      <span class="italic">H</span>
      <sub>O</sub>, observed heterozygosity. Standard deviations are reported in brackets.
     </p>
    </div>
    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
     <colgroup span="1">
      <col align="left" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" span="1"/>
     </colgroup>
     <thead valign="bottom">
      <tr>
       <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">seed-pool
        <span class="sup">a</span>
       </th>
       <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="italic">n</span>
       </th>
       <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="italic">N</span>
        <sub>m</sub>
       </th>
       <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="italic">A</span>
       </th>
       <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="italic">H</span>
        <sub>E</sub>
       </th>
       <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
        <span class="italic">H</span>
        <sub>O</sub>
       </th>
      </tr>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <tr>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">all</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">254</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">62</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.0</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.713 (0.131)</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.522 (0.217)</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">local</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">172</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.375</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.687 (0.161)</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.542 (0.250)</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">immigrant</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">82</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.375</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.720 (0.087)</td>
       <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.478 (0.165)</td>
      </tr>
     </tbody>
    </table>
    <div class="table-wrap-foot">
     <fn class="fn" xmlns="">
      <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
       <span class="sup">a</span>Groups of seeds that originate either from a source tree inside, 
       <span class="italic">local</span>, or outside, 
       <span class="italic">immigrant</span>, the fenced area.
      </p>
     </fn>
    </div>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s7b" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(b)</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Frugivorous birds</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">During the 5 years of bird censuses, we identified eight bird species feeding on yew, four of them being thrushes (
   <span class="italic">Turdus</span> spp.). The frequency distributions of flight distances of individual bird species suggested two main foraging behaviours (electronic supplementary material, figure S4). On the one hand, we observed frequency distributions skewed towards short distances (less than 50 m) for 
   <span class="italic">Coccothraustes coccothraustes</span>, 
   <span class="italic">Erithacus rubecula</span>, 
   <span class="italic">Phoenicurus ochruros</span>, 
   <span class="italic">Sylvia atricapilla</span> and 
   <span class="italic">Turdus merula</span>. On the other hand, 
   <span class="italic">T. viscivorus</span>, 
   <span class="italic">T. philomelos</span> and 
   <span class="italic">T. torquatus</span> displayed kernels with longer tails. As these similarities are in agreement with the results of previous studies on similar assemblages of species [
   <a rid="RSTB20150280C17" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20150280C17">17</a>,
   <a rid="RSTB20150280C18" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20150280C18">18</a>,
   <a rid="RSTB20150280C23" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20150280C23">23</a>], we regrouped the data in two categories: small-sized birds and medium-sized birds. A Kolmogorov–Smirnov test confirmed that the flight distance kernels of these two groups were indeed significantly different (
   <span class="italic">D</span> = 0.8426, 
   <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.001).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In 2006, the year of the seed sampling, 
   <span class="italic">C. coccothraustes</span>, 
   <span class="italic">T. torquatus</span> and 
   <span class="italic">T. philomelos</span> were not observed at the study site. Nonetheless, we observed these species only three, one and nine times, respectively, over the 5 years (from 125 records in total), and their absence might not affect the overall shape of the flight distance kernels of the two groups.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Frugivorous birds visited some of the female trees more often (electronic supplementary material, table S4), which might indicate a selective behaviour. Also, the most visited trees appear to contribute the highest number of seeds to the seed-plots. The results point towards an active selection of not only the microhabitat type but also individual source trees.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s7c" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(c)</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Seed dispersal network</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">By comparing the modular structure of the set of nodes common to the two networks (10 trees and 49 seed-plots), we indirectly estimated how regional dispersal events (82 seeds) modify the spatial structure of the local seed rain. The analysis revealed a modular organization for the two networks (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTB20150280F4" href="#RSTB20150280F4">figure 4</a>). However, the regional network was relatively more modular than the local network (
   <span class="italic">Q</span> = 0.583, 
   <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.001 for the regional network, 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTB20150280F4" href="#RSTB20150280F4">figure 4</a>
   <span class="italic">b</span>; 
   <span class="italic">Q</span> = 0.387, 
   <span class="italic">p</span> = 0.015 for the local network, 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTB20150280F4" href="#RSTB20150280F4">figure 4</a>
   <span class="italic">a</span>) and had a much larger number of modules (14 for the regional network versus 6 for the local network). 
   <div id="RSTB20150280F4" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Figure 4.</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Modular organization of the seed dispersal network of 
      <span class="italic">Taxus baccata</span>. Nodes represent mother trees (squares) and seed-plots (circles). The size of the node is proportional to the number of seeds either received, for seed-plots, or contributed, for mother trees. Arrows indicate seed dispersal events mediated by birds and are directed from the source, mother trees, to the destination, seed-plots. The same set of nodes is represented in both panels and include 10 mother trees and 49 seed-plots. Each colour represents a module, i.e. a group of non-overlapping highly connected mother trees and seed-plots detected by the QuanBiMo algorithm; 
      <span class="italic">n</span> indicates the corresponding number of modules. (
      <span class="italic">a</span>) Modular organization of the local network (locally dispersed seeds). (
      <span class="italic">b</span>) Modular organization of the regional network (all seeds); black arrows indicate the nodes that have changed module assignment when incorporating regional dispersal events.
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="rstb20150280-g4" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">So far, we have just compared the overall modularity of the local and regional networks. Two identical values of modularity, however, could be reached by different distributions of nodes into the different modules. Next, we quantified to what degree the ascription of nodes to modules changes once immigrant seeds are taken into account. Therefore, we explored whether two nodes belonging to the same module in the local network also belong to the same module in the regional network. The probability for two female trees within the same module in the local network to be assigned to the same module in the regional network was high (
   <span class="italic">V
    <sub>m</sub>
   </span> = 0.098). The equivalent probability of two seed-plots remaining in the same module after incorporating immigrant seeds was slightly lower (
   <span class="italic">V
    <sub>s</sub>
   </span> = 0.193), but still indicative of a similar organization of modules.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Once we compared the modular organization between the local and regional networks, we turned to the potential ecological correlates of this modular organization. Specifically, one could expect that nodes located within the same module belong to the same microhabitat type and/or are geographically closer. Regarding microhabitat, we did not find a tendency for the seed-plots receiving seeds from the same mother trees to be located in the same microhabitat, either for the local network (
   <span class="italic">V</span>
   <sub>hl</sub> = 0.577) or the regional network (
   <span class="italic">V</span>
   <sub>hr</sub> = 0.601). Regarding geographical distance, we compared the distribution of distances between seed-plots within a module with that among any two seed-plots within the entire network. Mann–Whitney 
   <span class="italic">U</span> tests did not reveale significant differences in the local network (
   <span class="italic">W</span> = 321 610, 
   <span class="italic">p</span> = 0.21), or the regional network (
   <span class="italic">W</span> = 335 270, 
   <span class="italic">p</span> = 0.69). These results suggest that neither microhabitat type nor distance explain the observed modular organization of seed dispersal.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
