<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s7b" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(b)</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Frugivorous birds</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">During the 5 years of bird censuses, we identified eight bird species feeding on yew, four of them being thrushes (
  <span class="italic">Turdus</span> spp.). The frequency distributions of flight distances of individual bird species suggested two main foraging behaviours (electronic supplementary material, figure S4). On the one hand, we observed frequency distributions skewed towards short distances (less than 50 m) for 
  <span class="italic">Coccothraustes coccothraustes</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Erithacus rubecula</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Phoenicurus ochruros</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Sylvia atricapilla</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Turdus merula</span>. On the other hand, 
  <span class="italic">T. viscivorus</span>, 
  <span class="italic">T. philomelos</span> and 
  <span class="italic">T. torquatus</span> displayed kernels with longer tails. As these similarities are in agreement with the results of previous studies on similar assemblages of species [
  <a rid="RSTB20150280C17" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20150280C17">17</a>,
  <a rid="RSTB20150280C18" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20150280C18">18</a>,
  <a rid="RSTB20150280C23" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20150280C23">23</a>], we regrouped the data in two categories: small-sized birds and medium-sized birds. A Kolmogorov–Smirnov test confirmed that the flight distance kernels of these two groups were indeed significantly different (
  <span class="italic">D</span> = 0.8426, 
  <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.001).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In 2006, the year of the seed sampling, 
  <span class="italic">C. coccothraustes</span>, 
  <span class="italic">T. torquatus</span> and 
  <span class="italic">T. philomelos</span> were not observed at the study site. Nonetheless, we observed these species only three, one and nine times, respectively, over the 5 years (from 125 records in total), and their absence might not affect the overall shape of the flight distance kernels of the two groups.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Frugivorous birds visited some of the female trees more often (electronic supplementary material, table S4), which might indicate a selective behaviour. Also, the most visited trees appear to contribute the highest number of seeds to the seed-plots. The results point towards an active selection of not only the microhabitat type but also individual source trees.</p>
</sec>
