<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s9" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">9.</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Prospects for the future</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The previous case study was missing a proper assignment of individual contributions for each seed dispersed. So far, genetic markers were used to determine distance from the mother tree. But we were lacking a specific assignment of frugivorous species to each event of seed dispersal. Thus, we relied on independent flight distance observations. This represents a first step, and in this paper, we argue that it may point towards the identification of two major functional groups. Nevertheless, we cannot unambiguously identify a frugivorous species behind each dispersal event. How to circumvent this? One formidable possibility is provided by the use of DNA barcoding [
  <a rid="RSTB20150280C68" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20150280C68">68</a>]. This technique, introduced as a fast way to identify species by taking advantage of the diversity among DNA sequences, has most recently been used to unravel trophic interactions between species [
  <a rid="RSTB20150280C69" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20150280C69">69</a>,
  <a rid="RSTB20150280C70" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20150280C70">70</a>]. Samples of the dispersed seed could then not only identify the mother tree as here illustrated but also contain biological samples of the dispersal vector. This technique has already been proven to shed light on basic questions such as how species can coexist by partitioning their feeding niches [
  <a rid="RSTB20150280C70" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20150280C70">70</a>]. More recently, DNA barcoding was developed to identify seed dispersers [
  <a rid="RSTB20150280C71" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20150280C71">71</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">With an extension of DNA barcoding, therefore, one could unambiguously determine the bird species behind each dispersed seed. One could further characterize the functional diversity of a dispersal guild. The integration of molecular techniques to determine dispersal distances from mother trees, molecular techniques to identify the species dispersing this seed, and quantitative methods to describe the spatial mapping of seed dispersal can engender a true understanding of the spatial structuring of seed dispersal and how this is shaped by the functional diversity of frugivorous birds.</p>
</sec>
