<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Quantifying dispersal distances</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the last few years, ecologists have used molecular markers to unambiguously determine dispersal distances. This has resulted in a more detailed description of the dispersal kernel. In particular, the reported dispersal kernels are characterized by long tails [
  <a rid="RSTB20150280C18" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20150280C18">18</a>]. This is reminiscent of power law distributions in complex systems where there is no dominant scale. This can be seen explicitly by considering a power law of the form: 
  <div id="RSTB20150280M2.1" class="disp-formula">
   <span class="label">2.1</span>
   <div xlink:href="rstb20150280-e1.jpg" position="float" orientation="portrait" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>where 
  <span class="italic">p</span>(
  <span class="italic">k</span>) is the probability of a seed reaching a distance 
  <span class="italic">k</span> in arbitrary units, and 
  <span class="italic">γ</span> is a critical exponent. The above relationship is called ‘scale free’ because the relationship between 
  <span class="italic">k</span> and 
  <span class="italic">p</span>(
  <span class="italic">k</span>) is not defined on a particular scale [
  <a rid="RSTB20150280C26" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20150280C26">26</a>]. For example, if we represent the previous relationship on a log–log plot, the relationship appears as a straight line. It is invariant to a change in coordinates. The same relationship appears for small scales and for large scales. This does not happen for other types of relationships, such as an exponential one.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Examples of scale-free distributions include the frequency distribution of earthquakes releasing a particular energy. This relationship, known as the Gutenberg–Richter law, has a clear implication: we do not need mechanisms to explain small earthquakes different from those used to explain large ones. In seed dispersal studies, authors have used the distinction between short- and long-distance dispersal with different meanings and spatial scales in mind. Part of the confusion stems from the artificial distinction between these two scales. A dispersal kernel with long tails is indicative of the absence of a characteristic scale.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The above refers to the proper characterization of dispersal kernels. And yet this is only a simplified description of the services provided by frugivorous animals, as the process of seed dispersal takes place on both dimensions of the plane. In short, it is also important to understand the spatial pattern of seed dispersal. For example, is seed dispersal homogeneous in space? Does it tend to follow a major direction? Does it create seed aggregates? And if so, what are the determinants of such aggregates? To address these questions, we need a quantitative approach to map the spatial details of seed rain. Finally, if we want to unravel the differential contribution of different species in an attempt to estimate the functional diversity of seed dispersal, we need to identify the species responsible for each dispersal event.</p>
</sec>
