<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s7c" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(c)</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Seed dispersal network</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">By comparing the modular structure of the set of nodes common to the two networks (10 trees and 49 seed-plots), we indirectly estimated how regional dispersal events (82 seeds) modify the spatial structure of the local seed rain. The analysis revealed a modular organization for the two networks (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTB20150280F4" href="#RSTB20150280F4">figure 4</a>). However, the regional network was relatively more modular than the local network (
  <span class="italic">Q</span> = 0.583, 
  <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.001 for the regional network, 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTB20150280F4" href="#RSTB20150280F4">figure 4</a>
  <span class="italic">b</span>; 
  <span class="italic">Q</span> = 0.387, 
  <span class="italic">p</span> = 0.015 for the local network, 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTB20150280F4" href="#RSTB20150280F4">figure 4</a>
  <span class="italic">a</span>) and had a much larger number of modules (14 for the regional network versus 6 for the local network). 
  <div id="RSTB20150280F4" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 4.</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Modular organization of the seed dispersal network of 
     <span class="italic">Taxus baccata</span>. Nodes represent mother trees (squares) and seed-plots (circles). The size of the node is proportional to the number of seeds either received, for seed-plots, or contributed, for mother trees. Arrows indicate seed dispersal events mediated by birds and are directed from the source, mother trees, to the destination, seed-plots. The same set of nodes is represented in both panels and include 10 mother trees and 49 seed-plots. Each colour represents a module, i.e. a group of non-overlapping highly connected mother trees and seed-plots detected by the QuanBiMo algorithm; 
     <span class="italic">n</span> indicates the corresponding number of modules. (
     <span class="italic">a</span>) Modular organization of the local network (locally dispersed seeds). (
     <span class="italic">b</span>) Modular organization of the regional network (all seeds); black arrows indicate the nodes that have changed module assignment when incorporating regional dispersal events.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="rstb20150280-g4" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">So far, we have just compared the overall modularity of the local and regional networks. Two identical values of modularity, however, could be reached by different distributions of nodes into the different modules. Next, we quantified to what degree the ascription of nodes to modules changes once immigrant seeds are taken into account. Therefore, we explored whether two nodes belonging to the same module in the local network also belong to the same module in the regional network. The probability for two female trees within the same module in the local network to be assigned to the same module in the regional network was high (
  <span class="italic">V
   <sub>m</sub>
  </span> = 0.098). The equivalent probability of two seed-plots remaining in the same module after incorporating immigrant seeds was slightly lower (
  <span class="italic">V
   <sub>s</sub>
  </span> = 0.193), but still indicative of a similar organization of modules.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Once we compared the modular organization between the local and regional networks, we turned to the potential ecological correlates of this modular organization. Specifically, one could expect that nodes located within the same module belong to the same microhabitat type and/or are geographically closer. Regarding microhabitat, we did not find a tendency for the seed-plots receiving seeds from the same mother trees to be located in the same microhabitat, either for the local network (
  <span class="italic">V</span>
  <sub>hl</sub> = 0.577) or the regional network (
  <span class="italic">V</span>
  <sub>hr</sub> = 0.601). Regarding geographical distance, we compared the distribution of distances between seed-plots within a module with that among any two seed-plots within the entire network. Mann–Whitney 
  <span class="italic">U</span> tests did not reveale significant differences in the local network (
  <span class="italic">W</span> = 321 610, 
  <span class="italic">p</span> = 0.21), or the regional network (
  <span class="italic">W</span> = 335 270, 
  <span class="italic">p</span> = 0.69). These results suggest that neither microhabitat type nor distance explain the observed modular organization of seed dispersal.
 </p>
</sec>
