<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s4a" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(a)</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Species and study site</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The evergreen, non-resinous gymnosperm 
  <span class="italic">T. baccata</span> L., the common yew, is a dioecious wind-pollinated tree growing across Europe [
  <a rid="RSTB20150280C33" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20150280C33">33</a>]. Embryos are protected by pseudobayes composed of a seed partially covered by a red and fleshy aril (‘fruit’ hereafter, for simplicity). Fruits ripen asynchronously from late summer (August) to late autumn (November), but can remain on trees until late winter when not consumed by seed dispersers [
  <a rid="RSTB20150280C19" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20150280C19">19</a>]. Yew relies essentially on avian frugivores for seed dispersal, especially on thrushes, 
  <span class="italic">Turdus</span> spp., that feed on fruits directly from branches [
  <a rid="RSTB20150280C19" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20150280C19">19</a>,
  <a rid="RSTB20150280C34" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20150280C34">34</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The study population is located in Nava de las Correhuelas (37°55′ N, 2°51′ W, Parque Natural de las Sierras de Cazorla, Segura y las Villas) in the autonomous community of Andalusia, south-east Spain, at 1615 m a.s.l. elevation (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTB20150280F1" href="#RSTB20150280F1">figure 1</a>; electronic supplementary material, figures S1 and S3). The site vegetation is dominated by grassland with scattered woody deciduous patches, with gravelly soil or rock outcrops covered by shrubs (e.g. 
  <span class="italic">Juniperus</span> spp., 
  <span class="italic">Rosa</span> spp.) or small isolated trees. Some pine stands (
  <span class="italic">Pinus nigra</span> subsp. 
  <span class="italic">salzmannii</span> (Dunal) Franco) also occur on rocky slopes. The site is protected by a fence to exclude large mammals, and thus the grazing pressure is low. At this site, the yew grows as a secondary species and is found almost exclusively on rocks, aggregated in clusters. The highly fragmented landscape offers a rich mosaic of habitats at the local scale therefore providing an adequate system to study seed dispersal in heterogeneous conditions. 
  <div id="RSTB20150280F1" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 1.</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Geographical details of the study site. (
     <span class="italic">a</span>) Location of the study site in the Iberian Peninsula (black dot). (
     <span class="italic">b</span>) Map of the study site indicating the location of the 
     <span class="italic">Taxus baccata</span> trees sampled within the fenced area (dotted line). White circle: 
     <span class="italic">Taxus baccata</span> female trees; white triangle: 
     <span class="italic">Taxus baccata</span> male trees; black cross: non-reproductive 
     <span class="italic">T. baccata</span> individuals. (
     <span class="italic">c</span>) Mistle thrush (
     <span class="italic">Turdus viscivorus</span> handling a yew fruit, picture by Ralph Hancock).
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="rstb20150280-g1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The field study was conducted from August to December 2006.</p>
</sec>
