<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ack class="ack">
 <title class="title">Acknowledgments</title>
 <p class="p">
  <bold class="bold">Funding:</bold> The contribution of M.S. was funded by NSF grants EAR-1357079 and EAR-1735630 and NASA grants 80NSSC170567 and NNX17AD98G, and R.B. acknowledges support by NASA grant NNX12AQ32G and by Point Blue Conservation Science. Radar data were provided by the Alaska Satellite Facilities. We thank UNAVCO for the operation and maintenance of the PBO GNSS stations and data archiving. These data and services are provided by the UNAVCO Facility with support from the NSF and NASA under NSF Cooperative agreement no. EAR-0735156. Additional GNSS data for this study come from the BARD network, doi: 
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.7932/BARD" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">10.7932/BARD</ext-link>, operated by the University of California, Berkeley Seismological Laboratory, which is archived at the Northern California Earthquake Data Center (NCEDC), doi: 
  <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.7932/NCEDC" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">10.7932/NCEDC</ext-link>. The LiDAR data were collected through a collaboration among the California Ocean Protection Council, the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration Coastal Services Center, and the U.S. Geological Survey. 
  <bold class="bold">Author contributions:</bold> M.S. led the analysis. R.B. assisted with the interpretation of the results. All authors contributed to the theory and to the writing of the paper. 
  <bold class="bold">Competing interests:</bold> The authors declare that they have no competing interests. 
  <bold class="bold">Data and materials availability:</bold> All data needed to evaluate the conclusions in the paper are present in the paper and/or the Supplementary Materials. Additional data related to this paper may be requested from the authors.
 </p>
</ack>
