<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Large-scale anthropogenic climatic change has been documented since the mid-20th century and average global temperature has increased by 0.7°C over the past 100 years 
  <a rid="pone.0068037-Solomon1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0068037-Solomon1">[1]</a>. Although climate has been continuously changing throughout the planet’s history, forcing species to adapt or to go extinct, the current pace of climate change is particularly threatening to biodiversity because climate is changing at a rate much faster than most species can adapt 
  <a rid="pone.0068037-Thomas1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0068037-Thomas1">[2]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0068037-Wormworth1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0068037-Wormworth1">[3]</a>. Recent, rapid climate change and future projections of human-induced climate change indicate that biological diversity and habitats worldwide are likely to be drastically affected in the near future 
  <a rid="pone.0068037-Hughes1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0068037-Hughes1">[4]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0068037-ekerciolu1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0068037-ekerciolu1">[7]</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate change has vital implications for biodiversity. It has an effect on a wide variety of organisms with diverse geographical distributions, affecting their physiology, distributions, phenology, and behavior. Furthermore, climate change can render species’ ranges unsuitable and force populations to move from their current locations to new and unoccupied areas. During this transition, populations may become highly fragmented and local extinctions may occur 
  <a rid="pone.0068037-Hughes1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0068037-Hughes1">[4]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0068037-Root1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0068037-Root1">[5]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0068037-McCarty1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0068037-McCarty1">[8]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0068037-Chen1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0068037-Chen1">[10]</a>. However, species do not necessarily ‘go without a fight’; they may adapt themselves to these changes either ecologically 
  <a rid="pone.0068037-Wormworth1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0068037-Wormworth1">[3]</a> or evolutionarily 
  <a rid="pone.0068037-ekerciolu1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0068037-ekerciolu1">[7]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0068037-Skelly1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0068037-Skelly1">[11]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0068037-Bradshaw1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0068037-Bradshaw1">[12]</a>. Nevertheless, species and/or populations that cannot exhibit adequate levels of adaptation will probably go extinct, either locally or globally. Species with limited climatic tolerance and specialized habitat requirements, limited dispersal abilities and thermal physiology are more likely to be affected this way 
  <a rid="pone.0068037-Thomas1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0068037-Thomas1">[2]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0068037-ekerciolu1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0068037-ekerciolu1">[7]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0068037-Walther1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0068037-Walther1">[9]</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Birds have been increasingly documented to be shifting their elevational ranges and colonizing new localities due to climate change 
  <a rid="pone.0068037-Peterson1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0068037-Peterson1">[13]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0068037-ekerciolu2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0068037-ekerciolu2">[15]</a>. For instance, Tingley 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. 
  <a rid="pone.0068037-Tingley1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0068037-Tingley1">[16]</a> found that 48 out of the 53 species in the Sierra Nevada mountains of California shifted their average bioclimatic range over 100 years. Phenological shifts in relation to climate change have also been documented. For instance, some populations of songbirds (passerines, order Passeriformes) have decreased as a consequence of climate change, since the phenology of their main food supplies such as flowers, seeds and insects during breeding has advanced faster than birds’ breeding periods, resulting in phenological mismatch 
  <a rid="pone.0068037-Wormworth1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0068037-Wormworth1">[3]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0068037-ekerciolu1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0068037-ekerciolu1">[7]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0068037-Marra1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0068037-Marra1">[17]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0068037-Both2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0068037-Both2">[20]</a>. Other changes associated with climate change include changes in abundance, interactions with habitat fragmentation, and changes in the timing of lifecycle events, such as hibernation and estivation 
  <a rid="pone.0068037-Menzel1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0068037-Menzel1">[21]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0068037-Sinervo1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0068037-Sinervo1">[22]</a>. The interactions of these effects further contribute to disruptions in species’ population dynamics, potentially leading to additional changes in distribution 
  <a rid="pone.0068037-Sinervo1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0068037-Sinervo1">[22]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0068037-Jankowski1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0068037-Jankowski1">[23]</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As a consequence of its geographic, topographic, and climatic diversity, Turkey hosts exceptionally rich biodiversity that is increasingly threatened 
  <a rid="pone.0068037-Eken1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0068037-Eken1">[24]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0068037-Sekercioglu1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0068037-Sekercioglu1">[25]</a>. Three out of 34 “biodiversity hotspots” in the world meet in Turkey: Mediterranean, Caucasus, and Irano-Anatolian 
  <a rid="pone.0068037-Sekercioglu1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0068037-Sekercioglu1">[25]</a>. Turkey is also home to a range of terrestrial biomes, including Mediterranean forests, woodlands, and shrublands, temperate broadleaf and mixed forests, temperate coniferous forests, montane grasslands and shrublands, temperate grasslands, semi-deserts, and xeric shrublands 
  <a rid="pone.0068037-Eken1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0068037-Eken1">[24]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0068037-Olson1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0068037-Olson1">[26]</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Such biome diversity contributes to high plant and animal diversity in Turkey, and birds provide a good example. Anatolia hosts a diverse bird fauna of 470 species that is steadily increasing with more research 
  <a rid="pone.0068037-Sekercioglu1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0068037-Sekercioglu1">[25]</a>. Turkey is also an important region for the study of geographical variation in the bird populations of the Western Palearctic region 
  <a rid="pone.0068037-Roselaar1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0068037-Roselaar1">[27]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0068037-Kirwan1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0068037-Kirwan1">[28]</a>. Even though the distributions of most bird species in Turkey are relatively well known, to our knowledge there has not been a study on how climatic change will shape the future distributions of Turkey’s birds. The effects of climate change on the distributions of lesser-known bats have been modelled 
  <a rid="pone.0068037-Bilgin1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0068037-Bilgin1">[29]</a>, and we have substantially more data for birds. In this study, we evaluate the potential impact of climate change on the distributions of Turkey’s songbirds in the 21st century, using data from Turkey’s most extensive citizen science project 
  <a rid="pone.0068037-Kubank1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0068037-Kubank1">[30]</a>. We have created species richness maps based on songbirds’ current distributions and projected their future distributions to understand the trends in resident and migratory species’ ranges over time. In addition to improving our understanding of the current and future distributions of Turkey’s songbirds and their responses to climate change, our modeling approach also helps highlight effective strategies to maximize avian conservation efforts in the study region.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our study is also an excellent model for using high-quality citizen science biodiversity data for understanding how species’ distributions will respond to global change 
  <a rid="pone.0068037-Hurlbert1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0068037-Hurlbert1">[31]</a>. As funding for biodiversity research becomes increasingly scarce and amateur naturalists’ numbers grow rapidly, data collected by citizen scientists are becoming increasingly important for global change research 
  <a rid="pone.0068037-Hurlbert1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0068037-Hurlbert1">[31]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0068037-Monahan1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0068037-Monahan1">[33]</a>. This is particularly the case for ornithology, where millions of birdwatchers have made significant contributions to avian research for centuries 
  <a rid="pone.0068037-Wormworth1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0068037-Wormworth1">[3]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0068037-Ramirez1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0068037-Ramirez1">[34]</a>. The role of citizen scientists is especially important in developing countries like Turkey where there are few professional ornithologists, no funding for long-term bird monitoring programs, and a rapidly growing number of experienced and dedicated amateur ornithologists. Our study is based on a citizen ornithology program in Turkey (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.kusbank.org" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.kusbank.org</span>) 
  <a rid="pone.0068037-Kubank1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0068037-Kubank1">[30]</a> that is similar to e-bird (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebird.org" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.ebird.org</span>) 
  <a rid="pone.0068037-Wood1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0068037-Wood1">[32]</a>. Our findings show the value of citizen science data for global change research and provide a good model for similar studies, particularly in biodiverse developing countries with few professional field biologists and inadequate biodiversity research 
  <a rid="pone.0068037-ekerciolu1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0068037-ekerciolu1">[7]</a>.
 </p>
</sec>
