<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The maximum concentration of chlorophyll-
 <italic class="italic">a</italic> presented a distribution pattern similar to calcite and was also strongly affected by coastal processes, mainly big river discharges, which fertilize the sea and enhance primary production. From satellite data, chlorophyll-
 <italic class="italic">a</italic> cannot be distinguished from dissolved organic matter (DOM) without an algorithm specific to each region (
 <xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Ali et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-45" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Liew, Chia &amp; Kwoh, 2001</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-89" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Vazyulya et al., 2014</xref>). Away from river discharges, chlorophyll-
 <italic class="italic">a</italic> can be re-suspended back into the water column by wind, currents, and waves, and is therefore correlated with suspended sediment (
 <xref rid="ref-93" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Walsh, Dieterle &amp; Esaias, 1987</xref>). The values of chlorophyll-
 <italic class="italic">a</italic> data used in this study are relative to its maximum concentration over several years. Hence, it is likely that these values are the sum of all processes listed above: river discharge, new production, and re-suspension. 
 <italic class="italic">P. caribaeorum</italic> inhabits coastal regions with high chlorophyll-
 <italic class="italic">a</italic> concentrations, but when these concentrations are related to river discharge, the regions lose habitat suitability due to lower salinity and pH values. This can indicate that despite the low salinity, chlorophyll-
 <italic class="italic">a</italic> and turbidity can be important factors for the species’ niche. This information corroborates previous studies (
 <xref rid="ref-75" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Segal &amp; Castro, 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref-80" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Steiner et al., 2015</xref>), which suggested that low salinity was an exclusion factor for 
 <italic class="italic">P. caribaeorum</italic>. However, it is difficult to decouple the influence of variables related to water quality from demands related more to depth and substrate in coastal areas, as both are intrinsically linked in continental shores. For instance, 
 <italic class="italic">P. caribaeorum</italic> is quite abundant around remote oceanic islands where eutrophication, turbidity, and other processes typical of continental shores are not present. However, 
 <italic class="italic">P. caribaeorum</italic> seems to be more common in regions influenced by coastal processes with high turbidity along the Brazilian coast (I Cruz, pers. obs., 2015).
</p>
