<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par24" class="p">
 <italic class="italic">Bicyclus anynana</italic> inhabits a strongly seasonal savannah environment, with vastly differing food availability and reproductive opportunities between the dry and wet seasons, making it crucial to produce the right phenotype at the right moment. In Nkhata Bay in Malawi, source of the laboratory population
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">24</xref>
 </sup>, transitions between the seasons are highly predictable, with a strong positive correlation between monthly averaged precipitation and minimum temperature in the previous month
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" class="xref">45</xref>
 </sup> (
 <italic class="italic">ρ</italic>
 <sub class="sub">pearson</sub> = +0.85; Supplementary Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">15</xref>). This puts a premium on a single-reaction norm optimally tuned to the specific temperature cue predicting seasonal transitions. Alternative reaction norms, producing the wrong phenotype, would lead to a maladaptive mismatch between seasonal environment and expressed phenotype
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" class="xref">37</xref>
 </sup>. Given the vastly contrasting selective pressures across the seasons, reaction norms producing such mismatches would likely be strongly selected against. This ongoing purifying selection should deplete genetic variation for plasticity, without affecting overall levels of genetic variation for expression. Consistent with this, we find relatively few genes showing gene-by-environment interaction in expression, and those that do show GxE have an excess of rare mutations (i.e., low Tajima’s D), consistent with increased purifying selection. Additional analyses of these GxE genes revealed that they neither exhibit patterns of pairwise diversity consistent with recent gene duplication events
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" class="xref">40</xref>
 </sup>, nor are enriched for novel genes. Finally, we assessed the patterns of genetic variation in the orthologs of these GxE genes in 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">rapae</italic>, a temperate butterfly species without strong seasonal polyphenism, and found them to be more polymorphic than the rest of the genome, suggestive of a relaxation of purifying selection. This latter finding is consistent with considerable to high levels of gene-by-environment interaction in the transcriptome among many species that lack seasonal polyphenism, including 
 <italic class="italic">Drosophila</italic>
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" class="xref">46</xref>
 </sup>, 
 <italic class="italic">Caenorhabditis elegans</italic>
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" class="xref">47</xref>
 </sup>, yeast
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" class="xref">48</xref>
 </sup>, butterflies
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">15</xref>
 </sup>, sticklebacks
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>
 </sup> and other fish
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" class="xref">49</xref>
 </sup>. However, not all species show these patterns, and they vary with the type of environmental treatment and whether laboratory or wild populations were assayed (e.g.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" class="xref">50</xref>
 </sup>). Unfortunately, most studies focus on genetic variation in plasticity across multiple populations (but see refs. 
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">15</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" class="xref">49</xref>
 </sup>), and data on species in strongly seasonal environments is particularly lacking. Future analyses focused upon gene turnover and evolutionary rates within a phylogenetic framework, comparing species differing in seasonal and/or thermal plasticity, are likely to shed important light on the evolutionary forces acting on regulators of plasticity compared to the rest of the genome.
</p>
