<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">To analyze the change in the degree of favorable climatic conditions for the extrinsic development of the malaria parasite, we used long-term observational data from 16 weather stations, which are operated under the standards of World Meteorological Organization (WMO). Three of them are located in Moscow city, including Balchug station (WMO ID 27605), which is located in a densely built area just in the city center, VDHKh station (WMO ID 27612), which is located in a park area nine km to the north from the city center, and the meteorological observatory of Lomonosov Moscow State University (MSU), which is located in another park area 7.5 km to the southwest from the city center. These three stations represent the climate of the urban environment affected by the urban heat island effect. The annual mean temperature anomaly (deviation from the mean rural value) is 2 °C for Balchug station and about 1 °C for the park stations MSU and VDHKh [
 <xref rid="B24-ijerph-16-00694" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>]. According to the recent detailed studies of Moscow climate features [
 <xref rid="B21-ijerph-16-00694" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>,
 <xref rid="B23-ijerph-16-00694" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>], the temperature observations at Balchug station are representative of the whole central part of the city, and of some especially densely built areas beyond. Most of the other built areas within the city are typically cooler than the city center, but warmer than the urban parks, and, moreover, rural areas. For rural areas, we use data for 13 weather stations that are located in Moscow 
 <italic class="italic">oblast</italic>’ or in the neighboring parts of Vladimir 
 <italic class="italic">oblast</italic>’ and Kaluga 
 <italic class="italic">oblast</italic>’: Volokolamsk (WMO ID 27502) Klin (27417), Dmitrov (27419), Pavlovsky Posad (27523), Cherusti (27538), New Jerusalem (27511), Mozhaisk (27509), Naro-Fominsk (27611), Serpukhov (27618), Kolomna (27625), Maloyaroslavets (27606), Aleksandrov (27428), and Petushki (27526). Listed stations are located in rural areas or at the edges of the small towns, so they represent almost natural environments in different parts of the Moscow region.
</p>
