<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec7" sec-type="results" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results</div>
 <sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Correlations between life history traits and temporal and latitudinal trends</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The average advancement of mean flight date of all 66 butterfly species was 0.36 days/year during the last two decades. Moreover, the mean flight date of the same investigated butterfly species showed a positive correlation with latitude (mean value is 1.20 days/degree of latitude). The advancement in mean flight date as well as the seasonal advancement at lower latitudes was both greater in 
   <span class="italic">A. cardamines</span> than in the vast majority of other butterfly species in the region. It has advanced its mean flight dates during the last two decades with a mean value of 1.02 days/year, which is among the top three of all investigated butterfly species (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>). In addition, there are only 2 out of 66 species that show a steeper relationship between mean flight date and latitude than 
   <span class="italic">A. cardamines</span> (3.41 days/degree of latitude).
   <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>The relationship between mean flight date and yearly change in flight date in a set of butterfly species in Sweden during 1991–2010, 
      <span class="italic">r</span> = 0.49, 
      <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.001 (cf. Table 1 in Karlsson 
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">2013</a>), 
      <span class="italic">symbols</span> represent overwintering stage; 
      <span class="italic">squares</span> adult, 
      <span class="italic">diamonds</span> pupal, 
      <span class="italic">crosses</span> larval, and 
      <span class="italic">dots</span> egg. The focal butterfly species, 
      <span class="italic">Anthocharis cardamines</span>, in this study is marked with an 
      <span class="italic">arrow</span>. The different overwintering stages differ significantly in respect to degree of yearly change in flight date, 
      <span class="italic">F</span>(3,62) = 5.779, 
      <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.0015. Redrawn from Karlsson (
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">2013</a>)
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="13280_2014_602_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Correlations between temporal and spatial trends were also evident in terms of a significant correlation between the yearly change in flight date and the dependence of flight date on latitude in the 66 species of butterflies investigated (
   <span class="italic">r</span> = −0.36, 
   <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.015; cf. Fig. 5 in Karlsson 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">2013</a>). In univoltine species overwintering as pupae, like 
   <span class="italic">A. cardamines</span>, this relationship still holds true (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>). This suggests that spatial and temporal variations are partly caused by the same factors and that investigations of latitudinal trends should be useful to predict expected future temporal trends in butterfly species.
   <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>The relationship between yearly change in mean flight date and latitudinal change in mean flight date for all 7 species of butterflies in the dataset that overwinter as pupae and have an univoltine life cycle, 
      <span class="italic">r</span> = −0.77, 
      <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.04. 
      <span class="italic">Anthocharis cardamines</span> is second from the right
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="13280_2014_602_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Since 
   <span class="italic">A. cardamines</span> is a univoltine species throughout its geographic range, it is of interest to restrict the comparison to species sharing this characteristic. Among the 66 species investigated by Karlsson (
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">2013</a>), univoltine species generally have significantly later flight dates compared to bivoltine species (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>) (and also compared to adult overwintering species where adults appear two times per season but with generally only one cohort of larvae developing each year) (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>). 
   <span class="italic">Anthocharis cardamines</span> has a relatively early flight also when compared only to other univoltine butterfly species; only 2 out of 46 investigated Swedish univoltine species fly at earlier dates than 
   <span class="italic">A. cardamines</span>. To summarize, our focal species appears early in the season and much earlier at southern than at northern latitudes, and has advanced its flight dates in response to climate warming more strongly than most other butterfly species in the same area.
   <div id="Fig4" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Comparison of mean flight date among univoltine (U, 
      <span class="italic">n</span> = 46), bivoltine (B, 
      <span class="italic">n</span> = 13), and adult overwintering (A, 
      <span class="italic">n</span> = 7) butterfly species. Mean and SD, 
      <span class="italic">F</span>(2,63) = 30.9, 
      <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.001. Mean flight date is from Karlsson (
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">2013</a>), and overwintering stage is from Eliasson et al. (
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">2005</a>)
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="13280_2014_602_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Latitudinal variation in use of host plant species</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A comparison with the records of 
   <span class="italic">A. cardamines</span> during 2010 registered in the Swedish Species Gateway indicated that our census periods occurred 4–6 days after the peak flight period in all three regions (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). Together with the results of previous studies showing that the egg stage in the field lasts 7–10 days (Wiklund and Åhrberg 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">1978</a>) and that ca. 80% of the eggs are laid during the first half of the flight season (Wiklund and Friberg 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">2009</a>), this strongly suggests that our census provided accurate assessments of host use in all regions.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The mean number of eggs per plant (number of eggs/number of plants in each plot) varied among host species (Table 
   <a rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" href="#Tab2">2</a>; Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>). However, host use differed among the three regions (significant interaction region × species in Table 
   <a rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" href="#Tab2">2</a>). In the south region, the most used species for oviposition was 
   <span class="italic">C. paludosa</span>, in the central region it was 
   <span class="italic">C. pratensis</span>, and in the north region, 
   <span class="italic">A. glabra</span> was the most attacked species (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>). From the butterfly’s perspective, there was a difference between regions concerning which host plant was most used for oviposition (Table 
   <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>).
   <div id="Tab2" class="table-wrap">
    <span class="label">Table 2</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Effects of region, host species identity, and population density on the mean number of eggs per plant individual in each plot. Analysis of deviance with region and host species as factors and host plant density as a covariate</p>
    </div>
    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
     <thead>
      <tr>
       <th align="left" rowspan="2">Source of variation</th>
       <th align="left" colspan="3">Number of eggs per plant</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <th align="left">
        <span class="italic">df</span>
       </th>
       <th align="left">
        <span class="italic">F</span>
       </th>
       <th align="left">
        <span class="italic">P</span>
       </th>
      </tr>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">Region</td>
       <td char="." align="char">2</td>
       <td char="." align="char">1.816</td>
       <td char="." align="char">0.274</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">Species</td>
       <td char="." align="char">6</td>
       <td char="." align="char">5.8058</td>
       <td char="." align="char">
        <span class="bold">0.001</span>
       </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">Density</td>
       <td char="." align="char">1</td>
       <td char="." align="char">6.88</td>
       <td char="." align="char">0.081</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left">Region × species</td>
       <td char="." align="char">9</td>
       <td char="." align="char">3.983</td>
       <td char="." align="char">
        <span class="bold">&lt;0.001</span>
       </td>
      </tr>
     </tbody>
    </table>
    <div class="table-wrap-foot">
     <p>Effects significant at 
      <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.05 are in bold
     </p>
    </div>
   </div>
   <div id="Fig5" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 5</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Mean number of eggs per plant (±SE) for seven different host plant species and three different regions along a latitudinal gradient. Means among species with different letter are significantly different (Tukey multiple Comparisons, 
      <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.05). 
      <span class="italic">NA</span> indicates that no populations of a host species were found in a region. The 
      <span class="italic">asterisk</span> denotes that only one population was found. Species abbreviations: arth = 
      <span class="italic">Arabidopsis thaliana</span>), thca = 
      <span class="italic">Thlaspi</span>
      <span class="italic">caerulescens</span>, cabu = 
      <span class="italic">Capsella</span>
      <span class="italic">bursa</span>-
      <span class="italic">pastoris</span>, capr4 = 
      <span class="italic">Cardamine pratensis</span>), capr8 = 
      <span class="italic">Cardamine paludosa</span>, arhi = 
      <span class="italic">Arabis hirsuta</span>, and argl = 
      <span class="italic">Arabis glabra</span>
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="13280_2014_602_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Plant phenology and selection of host plants within species</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Among-individual differences in plant resistance to oviposition were related to phenology and size, but relationships differed among species and among regions (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6</a>; Table 10.1007/s13280-014-0602-7 in Electronic Supplementary Material). Plants in more advance phenological stages were significantly more attacked in 
   <span class="italic">A. thaliana</span>, 
   <span class="italic">T. caerulescens</span>, 
   <span class="italic">C. pratensis</span>, 
   <span class="italic">A. hirsuta</span>, and 
   <span class="italic">A. glabra</span>, while the opposite was true in 
   <span class="italic">C. paludosa</span>. However, the effects of phenology significantly differed among regions for several species (significant effects of region × phenology in two species and of region × size × phenology in two additional species, Table 10.1007/s13280-014-0602-7). In 
   <span class="italic">T. caerulescens</span>, late-flowering individuals were more attacked in the north, but there was no significant effect of phenology in the central region. In 
   <span class="italic">C. pratensis</span>, late-flowering individuals were more attacked in the south region but there was no effect of phenology in the other regions. On average, butterflies preferred larger plants in all host species except for 
   <span class="italic">T. caerulescens</span> (Fig. 10.1007/s13280-014-0602-7). However, in five of seven species, the effects of size differed along the latitudinal gradient (significant effects of region × size or region × size × phenology in Table 10.1007/s13280-014-0602-7). There were also significant effects of the interaction size × phenology in four of seven species.
   <div id="Fig6" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 6</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>
      <span class="italic">Box-plots</span> showing the mean phenology (second axis from a PCA, see text) for plant individuals of seven different species and from three different regions that were either oviposited on by the butterfly 
      <span class="italic">Anthocharis cardamines</span> (1) or that escaped attack (0). The seven host plant species were arth = 
      <span class="italic">Arabidopsis thaliana</span>), thca = 
      <span class="italic">Thlaspi caerulescens</span>, cabu = 
      <span class="italic">Capsella bursa</span>-
      <span class="italic">pastoris</span>, capr4 = 
      <span class="italic">Cardamine pratensis</span>), capr8 = 
      <span class="italic">Cardamine paludosa</span>, arhi = 
      <span class="italic">Arabis hirsuta</span>, and argl = 
      <span class="italic">Arabis glabra</span>. The three regions were: south (S), central (C), and north (N). Significant differences between groups are indicated by 
      <span class="italic">asterisks</span> (*
      <span class="italic">P</span> ≤ 0.05, 
      <span class="italic">**P</span> ≤ 0.01, ***
      <span class="italic">P</span> ≤ 0.001). Note that scales differ among species
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="13280_2014_602_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
