<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Plant phenology and selection of host plants within species</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Among-individual differences in plant resistance to oviposition were related to phenology and size, but relationships differed among species and among regions (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6</a>; Table 10.1007/s13280-014-0602-7 in Electronic Supplementary Material). Plants in more advance phenological stages were significantly more attacked in 
  <span class="italic">A. thaliana</span>, 
  <span class="italic">T. caerulescens</span>, 
  <span class="italic">C. pratensis</span>, 
  <span class="italic">A. hirsuta</span>, and 
  <span class="italic">A. glabra</span>, while the opposite was true in 
  <span class="italic">C. paludosa</span>. However, the effects of phenology significantly differed among regions for several species (significant effects of region × phenology in two species and of region × size × phenology in two additional species, Table 10.1007/s13280-014-0602-7). In 
  <span class="italic">T. caerulescens</span>, late-flowering individuals were more attacked in the north, but there was no significant effect of phenology in the central region. In 
  <span class="italic">C. pratensis</span>, late-flowering individuals were more attacked in the south region but there was no effect of phenology in the other regions. On average, butterflies preferred larger plants in all host species except for 
  <span class="italic">T. caerulescens</span> (Fig. 10.1007/s13280-014-0602-7). However, in five of seven species, the effects of size differed along the latitudinal gradient (significant effects of region × size or region × size × phenology in Table 10.1007/s13280-014-0602-7). There were also significant effects of the interaction size × phenology in four of seven species.
  <div id="Fig6" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 6</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>
     <span class="italic">Box-plots</span> showing the mean phenology (second axis from a PCA, see text) for plant individuals of seven different species and from three different regions that were either oviposited on by the butterfly 
     <span class="italic">Anthocharis cardamines</span> (1) or that escaped attack (0). The seven host plant species were arth = 
     <span class="italic">Arabidopsis thaliana</span>), thca = 
     <span class="italic">Thlaspi caerulescens</span>, cabu = 
     <span class="italic">Capsella bursa</span>-
     <span class="italic">pastoris</span>, capr4 = 
     <span class="italic">Cardamine pratensis</span>), capr8 = 
     <span class="italic">Cardamine paludosa</span>, arhi = 
     <span class="italic">Arabis hirsuta</span>, and argl = 
     <span class="italic">Arabis glabra</span>. The three regions were: south (S), central (C), and north (N). Significant differences between groups are indicated by 
     <span class="italic">asterisks</span> (*
     <span class="italic">P</span> ≤ 0.05, 
     <span class="italic">**P</span> ≤ 0.01, ***
     <span class="italic">P</span> ≤ 0.001). Note that scales differ among species
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="13280_2014_602_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
