<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="grl57348-sec-0006" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Summary and Discussion: Relevance to Future Warming</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results here give new observational support to positive local SST‐LCC feedback with characteristic spatial patterns that can be decomposed into familiar IPO and AMO modes. Current models can capture the IPO SST‐LCC coupling pattern rather well, but their feedback magnitudes are weaker than those inferred from observations. The SST‐LCC feedback strength as measured by the regression slope between them is important in determining model simulated magnitude and patterns of internal variability. Models with stronger SST‐LCC feedback tend to have better representation of internal variability patterns and larger amplitudes. The patterned coupling between SST and LCC fields may serve as a holistic constraint for model evaluation.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Similar physics will operate in the global warming context with regard to SST‐LCC feedback. Analyses of CO2 quadrupling experiments have demonstrated that implied climate sensitivity generally increases with time. It happens when forced SST warming eventually overwhelms SST cooling due to internal variability or ocean heat uptake in the upwelling regions, which gets further amplified by positive cloud feedback (Andrews et al., 
  <a rid="grl57348-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" href="#grl57348-bib-0003">2015</a>). We refer to this warming as latent warming here. Intriguingly, the spatial pattern of additional cloud feedback that drives the latent warming (Figures 4 and 5 in Andrews et al., 
  <a rid="grl57348-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" href="#grl57348-bib-0003">2015</a>), that is, the delayed warming that is amplified by cloud feedbacks, matches the leading LCC pattern reported here (Figure 
  <a rid="grl57348-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#grl57348-fig-0002">2</a>b). This pattern also bears resemblance to the slow warming pattern in the Pacific from another state‐of‐the‐art model (Held et al., 
  <a rid="grl57348-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" href="#grl57348-bib-0020">2010</a>). Our observational analysis when considered together with these modeling results implies stronger latent warming and possibly higher climate sensitivity than current estimates for many models because the SST‐LCC feedback of current models is too weak. SST‐LCC feedback being too weak in many models suggests that a higher equilibrium climate sensitivity might be more realistic (see Klein et al., 
  <a rid="grl57348-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" href="#grl57348-bib-0023">2017</a>, and references therein). Indeed, we find that models capturing better the SST‐LCC coupling, as measured by the spatial correlation, have higher values of equilibrium climate sensitivity (Figure 
  <a rid="grl57348-supitem-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#grl57348-supitem-0001">S7</a>), which may be a result of both stronger overall positive cloud feedback and stronger latent warming. For example, HadGEM2‐ES, the best overall performing model using our metric, has one of the highest climate sensitivities and strong latent warming (Andrews et al., 
  <a rid="grl57348-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" href="#grl57348-bib-0003">2015</a>). Since the remote effect of SST‐LCC feedback is not separated out and it would likely offset part of the local SST‐LCC feedback discussed here, a complete understanding of the overall impact of SST‐LCC on climate sensitivity requires separate understanding of both effects, which will be left for a future study.
 </p>
</sec>
