<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="ece34006-abs-0001" class="abstract">
 <title class="title">Abstract</title>
 <p class="p">Thermal acclimation is hypothesized to offer a selective advantage in seasonal habitats and may underlie disparities in geographic range size among closely‐related species with similar ecologies. Understanding this relationship is also critical for identifying species that are more sensitive to warming climates. Here, we study North American plethodontid salamanders to investigate whether acclimation ability is associated with species’ latitudinal extents and the thermal range of the environments they inhabit. We quantified variation in thermal physiology by measuring standard metabolic rate (
  <styled-content style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">SMR</styled-content>) at different test and acclimation temperatures for 16 species of salamanders with varying latitudinal extents. A phylogenetically‐controlled Markov chain Monte Carlo generalized linear mixed model (
  <styled-content style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">MCMC</styled-content>glmm) was then employed to determine whether there are differences in 
  <styled-content style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">SMR</styled-content> between wide‐ and narrow‐ranging species at different acclimation temperatures. In addition, we tested for a relationship between the acclimation ability of species and the environmental temperature ranges they inhabit. Further, we investigated if there is a trade‐off between critical thermal maximum (
  <styled-content style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">CTM</styled-content>ax) and thermal acclimation ability. 
  <styled-content style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">MCMC</styled-content>glmm results show a significant difference in acclimation ability between wide and narrow‐ranging temperate salamanders. Salamanders with wide latitudinal distributions maintain or slightly increase 
  <styled-content style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">SMR</styled-content> when subjected to higher test and acclimation temperatures, whereas several narrow‐ranging species show significant metabolic depression. We also found significant, positive relationships between acclimation ability and environmental thermal range, and between acclimation ability and 
  <styled-content style="fixed-case" class="styled-content">CTM</styled-content>ax. Wide‐ranging salamander species exhibit a greater capacity for thermal acclimation than narrow‐ranging species, suggesting that selection for acclimation ability may have been a key factor enabling geographic expansion into areas with greater thermal variability. Further, given that narrow‐ranging salamanders are found to have both poor acclimation ability and lower tolerance to warm temperatures, they are likely to be more susceptible to environmental warming associated with anthropogenic climate change.
 </p>
</abstract>
