<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Inter-model differences</div>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The model spread between the contributions of individual SEB terms is represented by the inter-model standard deviation in Table 
  <a rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM2">1</a>. LWCS and HSTOR exhibit the largest annual mean, domain-averaged standard deviation, 1.4 K and 1.2 K, respectively. Considering percent differences however, the HSTOR inter-model spread is 400%. Clouds represent the second largest percentage spread at ~125%. Different from other feedbacks, the ±1 standard deviation bounds for these two feedbacks includes zero indicating that models disagree on the annual mean magnitude and sign of these contributions.
 </p>
 <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The strong seasonality of the PTCs renders the annual mean picture potentially misleading. Despite a modest annual mean inter-model spread (~40%), the SAF shows the widest inter-model range in any month, between +2 to +13 K in July (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3a</a>). A strong correlation (
  <span class="italic">R</span> = −0.89) is found between annual mean albedo changes (peaking in summer) and AA (peaking in winter) even though the SAF seasonal cycle is out-of-phase with the maximum warming. The inter-model range in HSTOR (from −2 to −11 K) also maximizes in summer, aligning with the SAF inter-model spread. The inter-model spread in the CRE PTCs is the largest in fall (from +1 to +7 K) and smallest during summer. Models with the largest summer SAF do not exhibit the largest negative CRE PTC and therefore do not compensate for sea ice loss by simulating more reflective clouds. HFLUX exhibits its largest inter-model spread in winter (from −1 to −7 K) and smallest spread in summer (from −1 to +0.5 K). Seasonal cycles of the PTCs exhibit greater amplitude over ocean than land as in Laîné et al.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span> (not shown), with HSTOR and HFLUX over the ocean having the largest inter-model range in winter of ~11 K between models. The SAF and HSTOR over the ocean show the largest inter-model range in summer of 18 K and 15 K, respectively.
 </p>
</sec>
