<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The process of Arctic amplification</div>
 <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Synthesis of our results and previous work paints a picture of AA whereby increased downwelling LW radiation (LWDN) dominates Arctic warming
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>
  </span>. Observational evidence corroborates this model behavior demonstrating a significant contribution to recent Arctic warming and fall sea ice variability from LWDN
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>
  </span>. Understanding the drivers of AA then reduces to quantifying the processes driving changes in LWDN.
 </p>
 <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figure 
  <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6</a> illustrates two primary process loops contributing to increased LWDN: remote and local mechanisms. In the remote mechanism, changes in the non-polar (tropical and mid-latitude) circulation increase atmospheric poleward heat transport (APHT) into the Arctic and warm, moisten, and produce a cloudier Arctic atmosphere, increasing LWDN. Proposed processes facilitating the increased APHT include mid-latitude circulation changes such as increased moisture intrusions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>
  </span> and teleconnections with the tropical climate
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>
  </span>. Atmospheric energy convergence from midlatitude moisture fluxes into the Arctic has increased LWDN and contributed to observed Arctic temperature trends between 1989 and 2009
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">51</a>
  </span>.
  <div id="Fig6" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 6</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Local and remote Arctic amplification processes. The local and remote mechanisms represent two process loops that contribute to Arctic amplification. In the remote mechanism, changes in the non-polar circulation increase atmospheric poleward heat transport warming, moistening, and producing a cloudier Arctic, increasing longwave downward radiation. The local mechanism represents the combined surface albedo (radiative) and ice-insulation (non-radiative) feedbacks whereby a less sea ice covered Arctic stores more sunlight in the ocean in summer supporting increased surface turbulent fluxes in fall/winter, which warms, moistens, and produces cloudier conditions and increases longwave downward radiation. The common influence of both the local and remote mechanisms on longwave downward radiation links the two mechanisms facilitating constructive interference and makes them challenging to separate. A line connecting warmer Arctic temperatures with non-polar circulation changes suggests a potential feedback, however the dashed line is used to indicate the current lack of consensus on the magnitude and influence of Arctic temperature changes on the mid-latitude circulation</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2018_7061_Fig6_HTML" id="d29e1253" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The local mechanism represents the combined surface albedo (radiative) and ice-insulation (non-radiative) feedbacks whereby a warmer Arctic with less sea ice stores more energy in the ocean in summer via the SAF supporting increased HFLUX in fall/winter. The increased absorbed radiation is not immediately radiated away but stored and transferred from summer to fall/winter delaying fall sea ice freeze-up and providing an energy source to the atmosphere
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>
  </span>. Increased HFLUX subsequently warms, moistens, and increases clouds, contributing to increased LWDN
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
  </span>. Increased LWDN and warmer Arctic temperatures in fall/winter promote thinner sea ice and further sea ice loss
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>
  </span>, reinforcing the feedback loop by increasing the potential for ocean heat storage
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ocean mixed layer processes and heat transport modulate the local and remote mechanisms. The summer SAF warms the upper ocean making it less dense and more stably stratified. Heat entering the ocean is trapped near the surface, where it melts and thins sea ice [Graham et al. 2013]. Sea ice melt freshens the mixed layer and increases stratification encouraging the development of a near-surface temperature maximum
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>
  </span> —a layer of warm water below the shallow summer ocean mixed layer (OML). In fall, the OML cools, deepens, and transfers heat to the atmosphere via HFLUX and longwave radiation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">59</a>
  </span>. More ice-free ocean supports greater upper ocean mixing by atmospheric winds, which can entrain warm water from the near-surface temperature maximum layer and delay fall sea ice freeze-up
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>
  </span>. However, this process is likely poorly represented across CMIP5 models due to insufficient upper ocean vertical mixing
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">60</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ocean heat transport into the Arctic influences temperature and sea ice, passes energy to the atmosphere via HFLUX, and modifies the Arctic circulation. Reconstructions of long-term records
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>
  </span> and model output point to ocean heat transport as a potential source of AA and inter-model spread
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">61</a>
  </span>. Oceanic heat transport into the Barents Sea influences Arctic climate variability and the North Atlantic Oscillation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" href="#CR62">62</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">63</a>
  </span> by reducing sea ice, enhancing HFLUX, and lowering the local atmospheric pressure. However, ocean heat transport in CMIP5 models contributes little to projected warming over 21
  <span class="sup">st</span> century
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span>. These interactions suggest that changes in the position and intensity of the jet stream and frequency of synoptic cyclones can modulate the local and remote mechanisms by influencing sea ice, HFLUX, and the OML, representing a process link between the two mechanisms.
 </p>
 <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The fact that the remote and local mechanisms contribute to AA via increased LWDN (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6</a>) also links these two mechanisms
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" href="#CR64">64</a>
  </span>. It is clear that the remote forcing mechanism can accelerate the local mechanism by increasing LWDN and influencing sea ice
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>
  </span>. It is an open question if changes in the Arctic drive changes in the mid-latitude circulation (dashed line in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6</a>)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" href="#CR65">65</a>
  </span>. Zappa et al.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">66</a>
  </span> suggest that sea ice loss in CMIP5 models influences the position of the midlatitude westerly jet, promoting an equatorward shift and consistent with previous work
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" href="#CR67">67</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" href="#CR68">68</a>
  </span>. These links suggest the potential for constructive and destructive interference between these mechanisms, however it is unclear how this interference influences the inter-model spread and cannot be assessed from the current methodology. We hypothesize that quantifying the strength of interactions between the local and remote mechanisms in observations is key to determining if the largest projected AA is likely. This is an important area for future work.
 </p>
</sec>
