<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par26" class="p">There is substantial evidence that climate change is having an impact at multiple levels of the Arctic food chain from several species of ice algae all the way up to the top predator Atlantic cod (
 <italic class="italic">Gadus morhua</italic>). Warmer water is likely to change the availability of melting floating ice, which could influence primary producers’ composition in the Arctic waters, in particular ice algae. These changes could trigger a decrease in 
 <italic class="italic">Calanus glacialis</italic>, the dominant (80%) zooplankton species to the advantage of 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">finmarchicus</italic> (Ellingsen et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">2008</xref>). 
 <italic class="italic">C. glacialis</italic> is a much more lipid-rich species and this change would have direct negative impacts on higher trophic levels (Falk-Petersen et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">2009</xref>) like herrings (
 <italic class="italic">Clupea harengus</italic>), which in turn are essential prey fish for higher trophic levels. In contrast, inflow of warm water to the Barents Sea favours herring recruitment (Sætre et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" class="xref">2002</xref>). Changes in currents and water masses could also influence capelin (
 <italic class="italic">Mallotus villosus</italic>) distribution and migration (Bogstad et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">2000</xref>). Collapses in the capelin stock may result from increased food competition and herring predation on capelin larvae (Gjøsæter et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">2015</xref>). Sea temperature and other oceanographic changes are also likely to directly affect recruitment and growth of Atlantic cod, the main predator of capelin (Ottersen et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" class="xref">1998</xref>).
</p>
