<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In the United States, conservatives and Republicans are relatively likely to see climate change as unimportant and to doubt the veracity of climate science [
 <xref rid="pone.0181401.ref035" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0181401.ref036" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>]. Gauchat [
 <xref rid="pone.0181401.ref037" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>] finds that although the public’s trust in science has remained largely stable in the U.S. over the past 40 years, conservatives’ trust in science has dropped within that period. At the same time, Hamilton [
 <xref rid="pone.0181401.ref038" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>] finds that liberals are more inclined to trust scientific conclusions, even when they conflict with their existing political views. Because information processing is biased toward one’s existing beliefs [
 <xref rid="pone.0181401.ref039" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>], individuals may construct counterarguments against information that contradicts their preconceptions [
 <xref rid="pone.0181401.ref040" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>], and they may even bolster their existing beliefs through this counterargumentative process [
 <xref rid="pone.0181401.ref041" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>]. Hart and Nisbet [
 <xref rid="pone.0181401.ref042" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>] find evidence of such a dynamic with regard to the likelihood that individuals identify with potential victims of climate change, and Petrovic et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0181401.ref015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>] find similar evidence with regard to the likelihood that individuals agree with a statement about the harmful effects of air pollution. Severson and Coleman [
 <xref rid="pone.0181401.ref019" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>] and Wiest et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0181401.ref020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>] find that the ideological divide with regard to climate change is strengthened by certain issue frames and attenuated by others.
</p>
