<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<list list-type="order" class="list">
 <list-item class="list-item">
  <p class="p">
   <bold class="bold">In what ways can public understanding of climate change be strengthened by an interdisciplinary collaboration in a museum setting?</bold> The pre- and post-event survey results indicate that, through interactive activities, it is possible to increase public understanding of the effects of climate change. Statistically significant change can be seen on some topics, but public opinion is still reluctant to change overall.
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item class="list-item">
  <p class="p">
   <bold class="bold">To what extent can climate science misconceptions be clarified through interactions with researchers in a museum educational exhibit?</bold> Although the visitors’ opinions on common misconceptions about the cause and impact of climate change changed from the pre-survey to the post-survey, the changes were slight and not statistically significant. This is likely due to the fact that the activities focused on specific topics related to climate change (awareness, preparedness, and communication) rather than directly confronting the misconceptions surrounding climate change.
  </p>
 </list-item>
 <list-item class="list-item">
  <p class="p">
   <bold class="bold">How can an interdisciplinary collaboration in a museum setting encourage evidence-based decision-making in relation to climate change and disaster response?</bold> The participants’ willingness to alter personal living habits through awareness, preparedness, and communication are not directly measurable by surveys completed during this event, since any changes would occur after data collection ended. However, the participants’ willingness to engage in discussion with the researchers, their acceptance of take-home material to share with others, and their reported willingness to change suggests that the event provided the visitors with information to better make evidence-based decisions in the future.
  </p>
 </list-item>
</list>
