<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We hypothesize that the relationship between Spectacled Eider survival and low‐ice conditions can be explained in large part by energetics. The energetic cost in aquatic birds of having full contact with water (swimming) is substantially greater than having no contact (roosting; De Vries &amp; Van Eerden, 
 <xref rid="ece34637-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1995</xref>). For Spectacled Eiders, respiratory studies on captive birds indicate that the cost of thermoregulation is reduced when birds have access to a platform to rest on between foraging bouts (Lovvorn et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34637-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>). Therefore, when ice is present, eiders can survive with less food because their energetic demands are lower. Ice cover also suppresses wave height, providing a favorable environment for feeding (Divoky, 
 <xref rid="ece34637-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" class="xref">1981</xref>), and can passively transport eiders to new foraging areas within the core wintering area (Petersen &amp; Douglas, 
 <xref rid="ece34637-bib-0044" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2004</xref>). Lastly, the presence of sea ice in the Bering Sea is linked to spring algal blooms, which cause carbon to be deposited in the benthic zone, in turn enhancing biological productivity (Brown &amp; Arrigo, 
 <xref rid="ece34637-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Cooper et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34637-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>). Therefore, moderate amounts of ice may be a key habitat feature that reduces energetic costs of Spectacled Eiders, dampens wave action, and increases the productivity of benthic feeding areas. Exactly how much ice is required to achieve these conditions is unknown. We defined “minimal ice cover” as concentrations below 15%, as defined by Wang and Overland (
 <xref rid="ece34637-bib-0065" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>); however, it is possible that higher concentrations are needed to provide suitable overwintering conditions for eiders.
</p>
