<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">According to GCM projections, the Bering Sea core wintering area is likely to experience a decline in sea ice concentrations over the next several decades that may result in a shift in the factors limiting Spectacled Eider populations. We acknowledge that GCMs project sea ice at a fairly coarse resolution relative to the size of the Spectacled Eider wintering area. Our goal was to understand, broadly, how sea ice concentrations are expected to change in the region that is important to overwintering eiders. GCMs projected minimal ice days to increase from an average of 56 days during our study period (1992–2015) to approximately 100 at the end of the century under RCP 4.5 and 175 days under RCP 8.5. These results agree with a CMIP5 GCM study of future sea ice cover in the Alaskan Arctic (Wang &amp; Overland, 
 <xref rid="ece34637-bib-0065" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>) that reported projections of ice‐free waters in the Bering Sea by the end of the century under RCP 8.5. Contingent on projections of sea ice, estimated Spectacled Eider survival remained fairly high (0.88) until mid‐century and then declined to 0.82 (RCP 4.5) and 0.77 (RCP 8.5) in 2100. Stochastic population models indicated that these changes in survival have pronounced effects on eider population size. Projections differed markedly between the two climate change scenarios, with a net increase in population size in 2100 under RCP 4.5 due to moderate conditions favoring high survival until 2069 versus a decline to near extirpation by 2100 under RCP 8.5. These stochastic population models resulted in highly variable population estimates due to the incorporation of two major sources of uncertainty: (a) uncertainty associated with the relationship between eider survival and minimal ice days, and (b) uncertainty about future sea ice conditions, resulting in dramatically different outcomes for RCP 4.5 and 8.5. Additional survival data from years with minimal ice cover and further refinement of GCM models and will reduce this uncertainty.
</p>
