<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">At the beginning of the breeding season (late February 2014), all fish were measured (standard length) in three consecutive days and the sex of individuals was determined by male sexual coloration (
 <italic class="italic">n </italic>= 474 males; 
 <italic class="italic">n </italic>= 429 females). In this population, all males express red throat colour at this time of the year, although the full colouration on the lateral body surface appears later in the season in most males. All fishes were monitored daily to record the survival. The survival of males for a year from the beginning of the 2014 breeding season was analysed to test the effect of the temperature treatment by using a Cox proportional hazard model as follows: λ(
 <italic class="italic">t</italic>)
 <italic class="italic"> </italic>= λ
 <sub class="sub">0</sub>(
 <italic class="italic">t</italic>)∙e
 <sup class="sup">
  <italic class="italic">T+f</italic>
 </sup>, where λ(
 <italic class="italic">t</italic>) is time‐dependent mortality rate
 <italic class="italic">,</italic> λ
 <sub class="sub">0</sub> is a baseline hazard, 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic> is the fixed effect of treatment and 
 <italic class="italic">f</italic> is the random effect of family. The area of red ornament coloration was measured in a randomly selected subsample of male breeders (104 controls and 105 warm‐treated males, one or two males per each growth tank; for details, see Kim et al., 
 <xref rid="eva12487-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). The selected males were allocated into individual tanks containing nesting materials and shown a gravid female for 5 min twice a week to prompt expression of nuptial colour. They were photographed on their lateral side every 2 weeks during the 6 months of breeding season. The area of red ornament coloration (hue: 1–60 and 340–359; saturation: 50–255; intensity: 0–255) was determined from the digital image, and relative size of the red area was calculated as a percentage of the total lateral body area. Relative size of red area (i.e., standardized size of red area by size of the fish) in the early territorial period (i.e., 2 weeks after the allocation into an individual tank) and individual peak coloration (i.e., individual maximum colouration during the breeding season) were used in this study.
</p>
