<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The MUPT spans five DO cycles approximately between Greenland Interstadial 12 (GI12) and Greenland Stadial 8 (GS8) (
 <xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>) for which climate change over continental Europe is poorly constrained. The paleoclimatic and environmental context is known with sufficient resolution and age-control only along the continent’s western and southern fringe. In the Aegean and Black Sea region, records of sea surface temperature (
 <xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>), coastal ice-rafted detritus (IRDc) (
 <xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>), pollen assemblages (
 <xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>
 <xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref"/>
 <xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref"/>–
 <xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>), and stable isotopes in speleothems (
 <xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>) suggest a DO-type response without the clear prominence of ice-rafting intervals (Heinrich stadials) seen in the Atlantic domain (
 <xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>). Forest was generally more abundant in Europe during interstadials, while steppe landscape advanced during stadials (
 <xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>). A taiga and tundra shrub/forest landscape covered the eastern European plains, with some loess deposition east of the Carpathians (
 <xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>). The middle and lower Danube Plain was a steppe landscape with continuous loess deposition (
 <xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>). A temperate open forest in the mountains of the southern Balkan passed into a xerophytic steppe toward the Aegean Sea (
 <xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>). Boreal forest with birch and pine trees was present at 50° N in Western Europe (Eifel maar lakes) but began to degrade after GI12, ∼44.5 ka cal BP (
 <xref rid="r21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>). Two sparsely dated records from the Western Carpathians (Safarka, Jablunka) suggest a dense taiga forest landscape (
 <xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>). For the upper Danube Plain, pollen (Füramoos) and loess/paleosol profiles (Willendorf II, Nussloch) suggest a cold steppe environment with few conifers during interstadials, and a tundra landscape with cryosoil formation during stadials (
 <xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>). During GIs, a temperate forest-steppe prevailed west (marine records) and south of the Alps (Monticchio, Castiglione, and Lagaccione) (
 <xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>). Dust deposition in the Eifel maar lakes and speleothem carbon isotopes from Villars Cave suggest increasing aridity in Western Europe across the MUPT (
 <xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>).
</p>
