<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par16" class="p">We conclude that the details of precipitation changes in response to QCO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> are not directly linked by large-scale east–west-coupling across the tropical Pacific basin. By calculating water vapor transport (
 <bold class="bold">Q</bold>) and the effective boundary-layer wind (
 <bold class="bold">V</bold>
 <sub class="sub">E</sub>), we proposed that regionally different responses of the Walker and Hadley circulations to increasing CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> tend to shape the details of the spatial pattern of precipitation in the tropical Pacific. Therefore, regional scales of atmospheric circulation over the tropical Pacific basin should be understood to correctly project the precipitation changes in response to increasing CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> in a warmer climate. Precipitation changes over the western equatorial Pacific seem to be more related to the Indian Ocean and the tropical Atlantic Ocean, when the eastward shift of the Walker circulation is considered. On the other hand, most central-to-eastern equatorial Pacific regions depict an increase of local Hadley-type circulation in a warmer climate, suggesting that the conventional east–west Walker circulation in the same regions is less sensitive to CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> increases. In other words, the change in total precipitable water in the central-to-eastern tropical Pacific is largely controlled by the local Hadley circulation, consistent with intensified subtropics and a narrowing of ITCZ under the global warming condition. This somewhat contradicts the previous literature, which emphasizes the respective role of Walker circulation and Hadley circulation change in a warmer climate. In the Darwin area, for example, the change in the atmospheric circulation and the total precipitable water is greatly linked to the Indian Ocean where divergence can be expected, whereas in Tahiti, the atmospheric circulations leading to the change in the total precipitable water are nearly in the north–south direction (Supplementary Fig. 
 <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media" class="xref">10</xref>). Thus, in many previous studies
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">38</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" class="xref">41</xref>
 </sup>, the difference of SLP between two regions may not be interpreted as a Walker circulation change. The present study emphasizes the regulation of regional atmospheric circulation controlling the precipitation changes in response to QCO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> in a warmer climate.
</p>
