<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par34" class="p">Future projections suggest that wild dogs will be less active and travel less far under future climate change, particularly in the denning period. Recent climate assessments have suggested that the best case scenario is unlikely, and therefore, future increases in temperature are likely to be higher than those used in our best case scenario predictions (Cox et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">2018</xref>). This would mean that when wild dogs are denning average decreases in activity of greater than the 3% per 24 h and decreases in distances traveled of greater than 6% per 24 h, as predicted in the best case scenario, are likely by the year 2070. As demographic effects are already apparent at high temperatures under the current climate regime (Woodroffe et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" class="xref">2017</xref>), the impact of the consistently higher temperatures projected for 2070 on wild dog demography is likely to be marked. As African wild dogs’ hunting strategy relies on covering large distances to consume enough prey to maintain their energy balance (Hubel et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" class="xref">2016</xref>), they potentially have greater energy expenditure than many other species (Gorman et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">1998</xref>). Reduced activity and distances traveled at high temperatures are likely to have an impact on food intake, and hence may exacerbate the impacts of temperature on recruitment already observed in the field (Woodroffe et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" class="xref">2017</xref>). Outside the denning period, while 24-h activity and distance traveled might change little, the shift from day-time to night-time hunting, with around 5–10% of their activity shifting from day to night, might decrease wild dog hunting success as a result of a greater percentage of hunts occurring at low light levels, as well as putting wild dogs at greater risk of predation by lions and hyaenas.
</p>
