<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Analytic strategy</div>
 <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used confirmatory factor analysis (CFA) to measure the hypothesized components of resilience, as well as resilience itself. CFA is a theory-driven analysis of the relationships between observed variables that tests whether the covariance matrix of the observed data matches the covariance matrix of a hypothesized model (Schreiber et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">2006</a>). Using this approach, it is possible to estimate exogenous latent constructs that are shared by a set of observed variables, which are considered endogenous or determined by the latent construct. In a structural equation modeling framework (SEM), CFA is also called a measurement model. Besides measurement models, SEM also allows the estimation of structural models, which estimate relationships between latent and observed variables using regression. The goal of measurement and structural models in SEM is to minimize the difference between the covariance matrix of the hypothesized model and the actual covariance matrix of the observed data. In addition to allowing us to model the complex relationships hypothesized in our model, SEM also allows us to estimate unbiased coefficients despite potential multicollinearity (see Appendix Table 
  <a rid="Tab5" ref-type="table" href="#Tab5">5</a> for the correlation matrix). SEM models require sufficient sample size, with a minimum of 10 observations for each estimated parameter (Schreiber et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">2006</a>). In our most complex model, we estimate 74 parameters. With a sample size of 1010, we have a ratio of observations to parameters of 13.7:1.
 </p>
 <p id="Par31" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We followed a two-step process to develop a comprehensive measure of resilience using CFA. First, we estimated first-order measurement models for each multi-item construct that was hypothesized to be a component of resilience (i.e., 
  <span class="italic">social cohesion–participation; natural resource protection attitudes; food security and livelihoods and assets; water, sanitation, and hygiene; and climate change awareness</span>). We repeated the same process to create a measurement model of 
  <span class="italic">family planning and access to MCH care</span>. Second, we estimated a second-order measurement model that incorporates the aforementioned first-order measurement models of the components of resilience, as well as three observed variables (i.e., adult use of mosquito bed nets, women’s highest education level, and changed behavior due to climate change).
 </p>
 <p id="Par32" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Once satisfactory measurement models had been fitted, we used SEM to examine the association between 
  <span class="italic">resilience</span> and 
  <span class="italic">family planning and access to MCH care</span>. We also tested the hypothesized structural model with the inclusion of all covariates. Finally, we examined the direct association between 
  <span class="italic">family planning and access to MCH care</span> and each individual component of resilience to assess whether an association with a particular component of resilience is driving the overall relationship.
 </p>
 <p id="Par33" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All measurement and structural models were estimated using Mplus 6.1 (Muthén and Muthén 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">2012</a>) with maximum likelihood estimation using weighted least squares estimators using a diagonal matrix with robust standard errors and the Satorra–Bentler chi-squared test for model fit. This estimation approach is most appropriate for models that include binary or ordered categorical dependent variables, as well as non-normally distributed continuous data, as is the case in our models (Brown 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">2006</a>; Savalei 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">2014</a>). Pairwise deletion was used to address missing data, which uses information from any observation with available data for both variables in a pair to estimate the correlation matrix. While pairwise deletion results in different numbers of observations being used for different parts of a model, this approach maximizes the data available. This approach is adequate when data are missing at random (MAR), that is, when missingness is explained by observed variables (Allison 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">2001</a>). Given that the vast majority of missingness is related to whether households participated in the reproductive health section, this is a reasonable assumption.
 </p>
 <p id="Par34" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For all measurement and structural models, model fit was evaluated using a combination of three model fit statistics, since each goodness-of-fit statistic operates on different assumptions (Hoyle and Panter 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">1995</a>). The comparative fit index (CFI; Gentler 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">1990</a>) ranges from 0 to 1, with 1 indicating a perfectly fitted model. Values of 0.9 or higher signify good model fit (Bollen 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">1989</a>; Hoyle and Panter 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">1995</a>). The root mean square error of approximation (RMSEA) was also used in this study, and values below 0.05 are considered evidence of good model fit (Browne and Dudek 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">1993</a>). Also presented here is the 
  <span class="italic">χ</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> statistic; a non-significant value indicates good model fit. However, the 
  <span class="italic">χ</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> statistic is sensitive to sample size and the large sample size of this study renders this statistic largely undiagnostic. Therefore, the 
  <span class="italic">χ</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> ratio (
  <span class="italic">χ</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span>/df) is also presented, as this adjusts for sample size. Good fit is indicated by a 
  <span class="italic">χ</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> ratio between 1 and 3 (Arbuckle and Wothke 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">1999</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
