<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec16" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p id="Par48" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This paper presents results of a first-of-its-kind effort to define and measure resilience within the context of PHE multisectoral programming and identify and quantify the link between resilience and family planning combined with use of maternal and child health facilities. The analysis, using data from a 2016 survey in the Tuungane Project in western Tanzania, confirms that resilience can be measured in PHE and other integrated community-based development programming. These measures of resilience can help direct programming. This paper provides evidence that family planning with access to MCH care is positively associated with resilience, a link that had been posited previously but lacked sufficient quantitative evidence.</p>
 <p id="Par49" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on the literature on resilience and interviews with PHE practitioners, questions related to broad components of resilience were included in the 2016 survey. Among a number of indicators that were hypothesized to comprise resilience, the following multi-item components of resilience emerged: 
  <span class="italic">social cohesion–participation</span>; 
  <span class="italic">natural resource protection attitudes</span>; 
  <span class="italic">food security</span> and 
  <span class="italic">livelihoods and assets</span>; 
  <span class="italic">water</span>, 
  <span class="italic">sanitation</span>, 
  <span class="italic">and hygiene</span>; and 
  <span class="italic">climate change awareness</span>. We added an additional three observed variables to the model of resilience: adult use of mosquito bed nets (as a proxy for health behavior), women’s highest education level (as a proxy for education), and changed behavior due to climate change (as an added dimension of climate change). The strength of these factor loadings reflects the relative importance of each of these components to the core construct of resilience. All factor loadings were significant; among these, 
  <span class="italic">social cohesion</span>–
  <span class="italic">participation</span> had the highest factor loading on resilience, followed by 
  <span class="italic">natural resource protection attitudes</span>, 
  <span class="italic">climate change awareness</span>, and 
  <span class="italic">water</span>, 
  <span class="italic">sanitation</span>, 
  <span class="italic">and hygiene.</span> This finding makes theoretical sense given that the literature on resilience highlights the primacy of social capital in dealing with adverse weather events, the need for natural resources as a means of rebounding from negative environmental change, and the need for maintaining public health and access to clean water (Meyers and Hardee 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">2017</a>). While adjustments were made based on available variables from the dataset and on model fit, seven of the eight original components of resilience identified in the literature and in the expert consultation conducted to inform the 2016 survey fit in the final model.
 </p>
 <p id="Par50" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">After including 
  <span class="italic">family planning/access to MCH care</span> in the model, all factor loadings remained significant, and a positive and strong association between 
  <span class="italic">resilience</span> and 
  <span class="italic">family planning/access to MCH care</span> was found, both before and after the inclusion of a range of control variables. Moreover, results using an alternative specification of family planning that excludes the maternal and child health care component of this factor confirms that the association between resilience and 
  <span class="italic">family planning/access to MCH care</span> is not driven by the inclusion of health care access measures. Thus, there is a strong and significant association between resilience and family planning alone.
 </p>
 <p id="Par51" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results also show that there is an association between 
  <span class="italic">family planning/access to MCH care</span> and the individual components of resilience, with the exception of 
  <span class="italic">food security and livelihoods and assets</span>. These results suggest the association between 
  <span class="italic">family planning and access to MCH care</span> and 
  <span class="italic">resilience</span> is not driven by an association with only one or two specific components of resilience. That 
  <span class="italic">food security and livelihoods and assets</span> were not significantly associated with 
  <span class="italic">family planning/access to MCH care</span> was surprising and needs more exploration, given the strong theoretical link between food availability and number of mouths to feed in a family (Bremner 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">2012</a>; Smith and Smith 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">2015</a>; Borwankar and Amieva 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">2015</a>).We hypothesize that the theoretical family planning and food security/nutrition links are not reflected in our data because our family planning factor does not reflect reduced fertility, which is an important driver in these theoretical pathways, and we did not measure all food security and nutritional aspects (e.g., stunting). Another possible reason for the lack of association could be temporal: that 
  <span class="italic">family planning and access to MCH care</span> is significantly associated with future, but not concurrent, 
  <span class="italic">food security and livelihoods and assets.</span> Additional research is necessary to further explore the temporal variations in the relationships between all components of 
  <span class="italic">resilience</span> and 
  <span class="italic">family planning/access to MCH care</span>. Attention to better measurement of food security and livelihoods and assets is also warranted.
 </p>
 <p id="Par52" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study had some limitations. Because it was the first of its kind, the components used to define resilience may not be complete. Furthermore, the questions asked in the survey about the components of resilience were not always satisfactory to measure the constructs in the model. For example, we had to use mosquito bed net use as a proxy for health behavior because other questions asked about health behavior did not perform well in the analysis, including questions about general disease prevalence, malaria incidence, and measles immunization for children. We decided to keep the bed net measure in the model because health is a recognized component of resilience (NBSB, 2014), and we did not want our model to imply that health is not important for resilience. Future surveys should include a wider range of questions on health behavior. We also suggest further work on measuring food security and livelihoods and assets. Additionally, because two of the latent constructs in the final model are measured using only three observed variables, it is possible that these factors are too perfectly reflective of the unique variation and relationships reflected in this particular dataset and that the results of these models may not generalize to other populations. Therefore, it is possible that the associations between resilience and family planning and access to maternal and child health care and, indeed, the nature of resilience may differ in other samples. For that reason, replication of these measures with other data sources and their further refinement is a necessary step for future research.</p>
 <p id="Par53" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is also possible that, because the majority of missing data is due to households not having an eligible respondent for the reproductive health section, the results are biased because of the selectivity of the reproductive health section sample. Only households with eligible respondents who were available provided information for several variables in the model that come from this section (e.g., adult use of mosquito bed nets, use of family planning, and visits to a health facility). These households had a younger head of household and had more children than households that did not participate in the reproductive health section. The women in these households are also more educated on average. Therefore, because our model estimation relies more heavily on these younger and more educated households for the associations and covariances of several family planning variables and for mosquito net use, it is possible that we overestimate the role of education and mosquito net use in resilience and, thus, their association with family planning and maternal health care. Finally, a limitation of SEM models is that they do not allow for causal inference, and the association between family planning and access to maternal and child health care and resilience can reflect a relationship that goes in either direction. Therefore, additional research on the directionality of this relationship is needed.</p>
 <p id="Par54" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Given the complexity of the models, there was insufficient power to conduct sub-analyses of the findings by group (e.g., female vs. male heads of household), which would show whether the components of resilience have a different configuration for different sub-groups and whether the association between resilience and family planning and access to MCH care varies among different groups. However, by controlling for a set of demographic, socioeconomic, and other household variables, it was possible to assess which characteristics are likely associated with differential levels in each of the components of resilience. Being a “model household” was associated with higher values on 
  <span class="italic">family planning and access to MCH care</span>; 
  <span class="italic">social cohesion–participation</span>; and 
  <span class="italic">water, sanitation, and hygiene</span>. This suggests that the Tuungane Project’s model households are reflecting the desired behavior changes. Yet, the association between resilience and 
  <span class="italic">family planning and access to MCH care</span> is significant for all households, including those that did not receive specific training on health, hygiene, and the environment. Additionally, being a female-headed household was associated with lower values of 
  <span class="italic">social cohesion–participation</span>, 
  <span class="italic">natural resource protection attitudes</span>, 
  <span class="italic">food security and livelihoods and assets</span>, and 
  <span class="italic">climate change awareness</span>, which suggests that female-headed households are likely less resilient on average than male-headed households. Together, these results are suggestive of sub-group differences in resilience; further research is warranted to investigate the extent of these differences. Additional analysis of other demographic factors, including length of time in the village, migration history, and marital status, would be beneficial.
 </p>
 <p id="Par55" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Moreover, this study has only used indicators of resilience that were collected at household level. While some of these in part also reflect community properties, such as the indicators included in the social cohesion component, our measure of resilience cannot fully capture all its facets, as vulnerability to shocks and changes is determined at multiple levels and varies according to local community characteristics or even the quality of national governance. It would be hard for PHE projects to measure resilience at all these levels, but testing how resilience is measured at the household level could be combined with community-level indicators to create a more encompassing measurement of resilience and would be an interesting addition to the research presented here.</p>
 <p id="Par56" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Finally, in factor analysis, certain variables are excluded if they do not fit together well in a single factor. Therefore, our constructs do not include all the data collected in the survey. For example, in food security/nutrition, we created two indicators showing partially conflicting results: (1) a food consumption score showing the households overall had good nutritional values and (2) diet diversity indicating a generally low diet diversity in the study area. Only the former of these indicators fit well within the food security and livelihoods and assets factor, and therefore, the factor does not reflect the full nutritional picture of the area because of the required conditions for factor analysis. Thus, the constructs are sometimes narrower than their factor titles might suggest, and when interpreting the results, it is important to keep in mind which variables comprise each factor. We have listed all variables that were looked at in the analysis in Table 
  <a rid="Tab2" ref-type="table" href="#Tab2">2</a> since some that did not fit the data from the Tuungane survey might perform better with data from other settings.
 </p>
 <p id="Par57" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Acknowledging these limitations, this study represents a start in the identification of resilience indicators that can be incorporated into the project design and measured within PHE projects as well as other integrated multisectoral development projects to measure resilience, with adaptations for particular project settings. The study also provides evidence of the importance of including family planning and access to maternal and child health care among the components of programming to strengthen resilience. Measuring these indicators over time can help assess whether social resilience is increasing in project areas. This information can be analyzed in conjunction with data on natural resources management and climate change, including gradual change and sudden shocks. In addition, this analysis can inform the design and implementation of holistic programs to strengthen resilience. This analysis can also inform the design and implementation of integrated multisectoral programs to strengthen resilience, helping communities meet multiple development needs―including reproductive health―and cope with climate and environmental shocks.</p>
</sec>
