<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Identifying components of resilience relevant for PHE and integrated development programming</div>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To understand better which components contribute to building resilience in the context of PHE programming, we conducted an extensive literature review and interviewed PHE practitioners (Meyers and Hardee 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">2017</a>; PRB 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">2016</a>). Based on these reviews and a 2016 expert meeting held in Arusha, Tanzania, we identified a number of broad components of resilience for which questions can be added to quantitative and qualitative surveys conducted as part of PHE projects. We sought to quantify resilience to shocks that households in economically and geographically isolated regions adjacent to protected areas typically face and often have to resolve on their own: health crises (e.g., cholera outbreaks), food insecurity, and natural resources management within the context of climate change. Because this research was linked to the Tuungane Project’s planned 2016 household survey, we focused on indicators of resilience that can be measured at the family or household level. We were interested in how people cope with environmental change. Eight initial components and their hypothesized linkages to resilience in the context of integrated PHE programming were social capital/social cohesion (engagement, participation, trust, and support); natural resources management (protecting and rebuilding resources); livelihoods and food security (multiple income sources, caloric intake, food reserves); water, sanitation, and hygiene (WASH) (public health infrastructure); health (physical ability to respond to a crisis); education (information access and processing); knowledge of and experience with climate change (increasing adaptive capacity); and attitudes toward population growth (perceived population pressure on ecological sustainability and community wellbeing).
 </p>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on the literature, we hypothesized that there would be a positive link between resilience and family planning plus access to reproductive health care.</p>
</sec>
