<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Survey and sample</div>
 <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data come from a 2016 cross-sectional survey of 1010 households in 16 villages near the Mahale Mountains National Park in western Tanzania along the coastline of Lake Tanganyika (Hess et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">2017</a>). The 16 villages formed the survey sample frame, and the sample division over these villages was proportional to the village size (number of households). Tanzanian villages are administratively divided into sub-villages, and for logistical and cost reasons, two sub-villages were selected per village (each village had between three and eight sub-villages). If a village directly bordered Lake Tanganyika, one lake side and one inland sub-village were selected, with the village sample divided over the selected sub-villages proportional to the combined population size of all coastal and inland sub-villages in that village. Complete household lists of the selected sub-villages were drawn up from which households were randomly selected.
 </p>
 <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the purpose of this research, a household was defined as a group of people who live together and usually share their food. The average household size was 6.2 people, and 17% of households were female headed. Children under age 15 comprised 52% of the household population in the sample. A majority of household heads (60%) completed primary school or more, while nearly a quarter (22%) of household heads did not have any formal education.</p>
 <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Interviews were conducted using computer-aided personal interviewing (CAPI). The survey instrument included an overall household section and a reproductive health section. The former was answered by one adult household member, preferably the household head, with sufficient knowledge about the household. Nearly half the respondents to this section were male (49%); at the time of the interview, they were 39 years old on average; respondents were the household head (in 60% of the interviews), his or her spouse (31%), a child of the household head (6%), or another household member (3%). The reproductive health section was answered by one female household member between 18 and 49 years old, if present in the household and available. The reproductive health section was completed in 767 households (76% of the sample); respondents were the spouse of the household head (74%), the household head herself (9%), a child of the household head (10%), or another household member (7%). Sometimes, the same respondent answered both sections of the questionnaire. Most of the households without reproductive health section interviews had no eligible female household members (61%). For the remainder, the reasons for not conducting the section interview were not documented. Because refusal rates for the overall interview were very low (1%), it is assumed that refusal was rare and the unavailability of eligible female household members was the primary reason. As much as possible, the interviews were conducted privately to avoid bias, especially the reproductive health section. Enumerators recorded that 95% of these section interviews were not overheard.</p>
</sec>
