<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Five different methods were employed for determining antioxidant potential of 
 <italic class="italic">Aloe vera</italic> leaf extracts. DPPH radical scavenging method is an extensive procedure to evaluate the free radical scavenging ability of various samples [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" class="xref">47</xref>]. The effect of antioxidants on DPPH radical scavenging was supposed to be due to their hydrogen- donating ability. Hydrogen peroxide is generally not very reactive, but it can sometimes be toxic to cell because it can give rise to hydroxyl radicals in the cells. Thus, the removal of H
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>O
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> is essential for antioxidant defence in cell or food systems. In general, the reducing properties are associated with the presence of reductones, which have been shown to exert antioxidant action through breaking the free radical chain by donating a hydrogen atom [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" class="xref">48</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" class="xref">49</xref>]. In the reducing power assay, the presence of reductants in the sample would result in the reduction of Fe
 <sup class="sup">3+</sup> to Fe
 <sup class="sup">2+</sup> by donating an electron [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" class="xref">50</xref>]. Metal chelating activity is based on chelation of Fe
 <sup class="sup">2+</sup> ions in a quantitative manner by the reagent ferrozine, which results to the formation of a complex with Fe
 <sup class="sup">2+</sup> ions [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" class="xref">51</xref>]. So the chelating ability influences other scavenging activities of free radicals which protect the organisms against oxidative damage. Mechanism of β carotene bleaching is a free radical mediated phenomenon resulting from the formation of hydroperoxides from linoleic acid oxidation. The presence of antioxidant extracts can hinder the extent of β carotene bleaching by acting on the linoleate- free radical and other formations of free radicals in the system [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" class="xref">52</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" class="xref">53</xref>].
</p>
