<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par32" class="p">In the Netherlands, where sea level rise constitutes an existential risk, there has been a paradigm shift from predicting to exploring the future, which has increased the opportunity for robust decision-making (Haasnoot and Middelkoop 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">2012</xref>). The Delta Commission of the Netherlands addressed the challenge of high-end, long-range sea level change by deconstructing all the components of sea level rise and building plausible accounts of how each might evolve under extreme global mean warming (Katsman et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">2011</xref>). In this study, each source of information, whether climate model output, palaeoclimatic data, observations or expert elicitation, is presented in a transparent and auditable format that is open to challenge and revision as scientific understanding grows. This field of expertise is developing rapidly, and frequently, new insights on major contributors to sea level rise are explored (e.g. DeConto and Pollard 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">2016</xref>), which trigger scientific and public debates on the severity of the risks for extreme sea level rise. Using a similar process-based decomposition method, Le Bars et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" class="xref">2017</xref>) presented projections of sea level rise exceeding those of Katsman et al. (
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">2011</xref>), which triggered the Dutch Delta Programme to commission a new study on potential consequences of these projections for the safety of the Netherlands. Such a concept of ‘adaptive delta management’ as applied in the Netherlands is based on the principle that new insights or events may trigger the need to change the defence strategy, and relies heavily on its ability to monitor and digest new evidence and information offered by consecutive storylines of major climatic phenomena (Haasnoot et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">2018</xref>).
</p>
