<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Shorebirds are important components of the ecosystems in which they live, they are valued by the general public, can exhibit extremely large and impressive aggregations during migration, and they can act as sentinels of global environmental change 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Brown1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Brown1">[1]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Piersma1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Piersma1">[3]</a>. There also is a growing demand to move beyond evaluating climate change impacts on single species or habitats and to evaluate expected broad scale ecological impacts on communities and ecosystems 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Russel1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Russel1">[4]</a>. Consequently, we are concerned about the current documented widespread declines of many species of North American shorebirds 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Brown1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Brown1">[1]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-International1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-International1">[5]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Bart1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Bart1">[8]</a>, particularly the recent steep declines in Atlantic populations of Red Knots (scientific names of North American shorebirds are given below) 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Morrison2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Morrison2">[9]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Federal1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Federal1">[10]</a> and Semipalmated Sandpipers 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Jehl1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Jehl1">[11]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Morrison3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Morrison3">[12]</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service currently lists three North American shorebirds as Threatened or Endangered 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-US1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-US1">[13]</a>. IUCN lists five shorebird species in North America as Near Threatened or at higher risk, and four additional species in these categories for the Western Hemisphere 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-International2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-International2">[14]</a>. The causes of these declines are not well understood but most likely include loss of breeding, migration, and wintering habitats, and disturbance and exploitation 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Brown1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Brown1">[1]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Howe1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Howe1">[15]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Austin1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Austin1">[17]</a>. It should be recognized, however, that the factors causing such changes could be global, since population reductions have been seen in virtually all shorebird flyways from North and South America, to East Africa, to Asia and Australia, e.g., 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Milton1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Milton1">[18]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Stroud1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Stroud1">[19]</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Global climate change is an anthropogenic stressor that could adversely affect shorebird populations across species' ranges. Shorebirds that breed and/or winter at high latitudes may be among the most sensitive of bird species to this stressor because this is where climate change is expected to be most severe 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Parry1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Parry1">[20]</a>. They also have several additional risk factors, including lengthy, energetically expensive migrations where they may be vulnerable to changes in wind patterns, dependence upon coastal migration stopover sites that are vulnerable to sea level rise, and dependence upon ecological synchronicities that may be disrupted by a changing climate 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-GrattoTrevor1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-GrattoTrevor1">[16]</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Galbraith1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Galbraith1">[21]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Colwell1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Colwell1">[23]</a>. Small–Lorenz 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span>
  <a rid="pone.0108899-SmallLorenz1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-SmallLorenz1">[24]</a> point out that assessments of vulnerability to climate change often ignore problems associated with a migratory life–history, causing them to underestimate vulnerabilities. Shorebirds are already in a vulnerable condition and climate change may exacerbate this.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">If we are to understand what may happen to shorebirds in the near future and initiate appropriate conservation measures it is essential that we be able to predict the likely vulnerabilities of shorebird species to various aspects of the changing climate, cf. 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Lee1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Lee1">[25]</a>. To be useful for conservation, predictive frameworks should be based on the ecologies and life histories of the species, should incorporate what we know about how the planet's climate will alter, and should generate at least qualitative estimates of species vulnerabilities, e.g. 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Galbraith2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Galbraith2">[26]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Lee2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Lee2">[27]</a>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Categorizing vulnerability to extinction based on a suite of characteristics, such as population size and rate of decline, is used widely e.g. 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Millsap1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Millsap1">[28]</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Gardali1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Gardali1">[31]</a>. The best known models are those of Partners in Flight and IUCN (also used by BirdLife International) 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Panjabi1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Panjabi1">[32]</a>. Their categorization approach to vulnerability also can be used to evaluate species' changes in vulnerability as ecosystems change over time, e.g. 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Higdon1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Higdon1">[33]</a>. Partners in Flight (PIF) uses a model to assess vulnerability based on population trend, relative abundance, threats during the breeding and non–breeding seasons, and breeding and non–breeding range sizes. For each category, each species receives a score of 1 to 5, with 5 associated with greatest risk. These scores are summed using several different formulas, each of which is used to determine species of conservation concern for particular reasons. A similar system was developed based on the same set of basic variables for the U.S. Shorebird Conservation Plan 
  <a rid="pone.0108899-Brown1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0108899-Brown1">[1]</a>, although the resulting risk categories are defined somewhat differently. None of these systems includes risk due to climate change. In this paper, it was our overarching goal to determine the degree to which climate change will alter the extinction risk level assigned to shorebird species in the U.S. Shorebird Conservation Plan, and for this method to be compatible with the PIF ranking system.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We approached our reconsideration of risks under climate change by developing an assessment framework, and then used it to evaluate the vulnerabilities to climate change of North American (north of Mexico) shorebird species, whose life histories extend across wide ecological and behavioral spectra. Specifically, we (1) identified risk factors, (2) created a framework for quantifying the change in risk due to climate change for each of the factors, including the possibility of decreased extinction risk due to climate change, (3) identified the effects climate change would have on the risk factors, (4) reviewed the literature on each shorebird species we assessed to determine species–specific risk for each factor, and (5) assigned species to their new extinction–risk categories. We also (6) did a sensitivity analysis to determine how the results were affected by different decision rules for changing PIF risk categories.</p>
</sec>
