<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In the Kumaon region, farming is largely practised on terraced rainfed upland fields and lowland fields irrigated with traditional channels. In this region, the study was conducted in two sites, in the districts of Nainital and Bageshwar. According to our sample (see Table 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s13280-016-0833-2" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">S1</ext-link> in 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s13280-016-0833-2" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Supplementary material 1</ext-link>), most of farmers (72 % in Nainital and 85 % in Bageshwar) are marginal farmers with less than 0.4 ha of agricultural land. In Nainital, a small percentage of farmers (6.5 %) own 33 % of the land. Two main cropping systems coexist: (i) in the lowlands (prevalent in the Bageshwar site), farmers alternate irrigated rice (
 <italic class="italic">kharif</italic> season, from June to October) with wheat and barley (
 <italic class="italic">rabi</italic> season, from October to April); (ii) in the upland fields (prevalent in the Nainital site), farmers cultivate dry rice, millets (i.e. finger millet, pearl millet, foxtail millet, barnyard millet) and pulses (i.e. 
 <italic class="italic">horsegram</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">black soybean</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">kidney beans</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">black gram</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">pigeon pea</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">soy bean</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">lentils</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">mung bean</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">rice bean</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">simi</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">pea</italic>) in the 
 <italic class="italic">kharif</italic> season, in rotation with wheat and barley in the 
 <italic class="italic">rabi</italic> season. Farmers in the two sites grow multiple crops through polyculture, including intercropping, crop rotation and the use of locally adapted and traditional varieties (i.e. landraces).
</p>
