<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Abiotic interactions are not alone in modulating plant performance. A large number or studies have shown that biotic interactions such as competition and herbivory can have significant effects on plant performance [
 <xref rid="pone.0164844.ref024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0164844.ref025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. Furthermore, the impacts of biotic interactions can change along environmental gradients. Fungal endophytes are ubiquitous plant symbionts that can strongly influence plant physiological performance, particularly under stressful conditions [
 <xref rid="pone.0164844.ref026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>]. They can confer fitness benefits to host plants including tolerance to herbivory, heat, salt, disease and drought, amongst other stress factors (e.g. [
 <xref rid="pone.0164844.ref027" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0164844.ref030" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>]). However, despite their known potential to drive the ability of plants to cope with stressful environmental conditions, little is known about how climate change might affect plant performance through modifications of symbiotic interactions (but see [
 <xref rid="pone.0164844.ref026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>]). Symbiotic interactions between fungi and higher plants and liverworts in the Antarctic environment have been demonstrated [
 <xref rid="pone.0164844.ref031" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0164844.ref034" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>]. Recent reports have focused on the occurrence, type of association, diversity and possible ecological roles of mycorrhizal and dark septate endophytic fungal interactions with vascular plants. Only two native vascular plants, both occurring on the Antarctic Peninsula, are exposed to the extreme environmental conditions of the Antarctic [
 <xref rid="pone.0164844.ref004" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0164844.ref035" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>]. Upson et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0164844.ref032" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0164844.ref036" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>] and Rosa et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0164844.ref033" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0164844.ref034" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>] described the root-fungal associations of both plants along a latitudinal transect in the Antarctic, demonstrating that root endophytes were able to mineralize peptides and amino acids in the rhizosphere, increasing nitrogen availability to the roots of plants. Further study is clearly required to understand the potential role of these positive interactions in the adaptation of plants to environmental stresses and changes in the Antarctic ecosystem. Increased understanding of the role of root endophytes in the establishment process and subsequent survival is also paramount for understanding and predicting the future spread of these vascular plants under current climate change scenarios.
</p>
