<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec14" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Origin of model biases</div>
 <p id="Par41" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In polar regions, many studies have identified model strengths and weaknesses in reproducing observations
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR99" href="#CR99">99</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR100" href="#CR100">100</a>
  </span>. Yet, perhaps the most important challenge is identifying the climate system processes that must be represented in order to consider a model realistic enough for mechanistic studies and projections. More generally, simple comparisons between model results and observations do not allow estimating the origin of model biases or their impact. Process-based model evaluation offers the possibility of exploring the causes of discrepancies more deeply, identifying the links between various variables and ultimately suggesting model improvements
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR101" href="#CR101">101</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR103" href="#CR103">103</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par42" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To illustrate this point, we compare the ice production–entrainment feedback in three existing simulations for all the sectors of the Southern Ocean with estimates derived from observations and a reanalysis (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>). A clear link is found between the value of the feedback factor and the amplitude of the seasonal cycle of ice volume: since the ice production–entrainment feedback is negative, it tends to damp the seasonal cycle; i.e., a stronger feedback corresponds to a weaker seasonal cycle. The spread across simulations and Antarctic sea ice regions in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a> stresses the large sensitivity of the feedback to the ocean properties. As many climate models suffer from large biases in their representation of the vertical structure of the Southern Ocean, they are unlikely to predict this feedback accurately. For instance, the overestimation of the amplitude of the seasonal cycle of sea ice volume in the model CCSM4 is likely related to a too weak negative feedback and improvements in the representation of ocean properties, in particular of temperature and salinity below the surface layer, would reduce this bias.
  <div id="Fig4" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Amplitude of the sea ice volume seasonal cycle versus the ice production-entrainment feedback factor. The ice production-entrainment feedback factor 
     <span class="italic">γ</span>
     <sub>
      <span class="italic">θ</span>
     </sub> is defined as the ratio of the melting due to warm water entrainment to the initial ice formation
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">50</a>
     </span>. The values are estimated over 1990–2005 for a standardized perturbation corresponding to an increase of 10 cm of sea ice. For both observational and model datasets, the evaluation of 
     <span class="italic">γ</span>
     <sub>
      <span class="italic">θ</span>
     </sub> is performed on the basis of temperature and salinity profiles in the Southern Ocean, averaged over January–February for the period 1990–2005. Values are represented by five crosses corresponding to five sectors of the Southern Ocean
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR111" href="#CR111">111</a>
     </span>. Results for NEMO-LIM
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR112" href="#CR112">112</a>
     </span>, CCSM4
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR113" href="#CR113">113</a>
     </span>, and IPSL
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR114" href="#CR114">114</a>
     </span> models are in colors. Estimates are given in black based on oceanic observations
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR115" href="#CR115">115</a>
     </span> and the sea ice volume derived from a reanalysis
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR116" href="#CR116">116</a>
     </span>. For all datasets, the plain circles correspond to the average of 
     <span class="italic">γ</span>
     <sub>
      <span class="italic">θ</span>
     </sub> and of the amplitude of the ice volume seasonal cycle over all sectors, and 
     <span class="italic">ρ</span> is the correlation coefficient between these two quantities
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2018_4173_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e1833" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
