<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece32400-sec-0015" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The effects of aquatic prey on reproductive success of riparian consumers have been largely ignored. Our study demonstrates that aquatic prey subsidies may influence nestling growth and condition in a passerine species. Variation in aquatic and terrestrial resources was observed in the prothonotary warbler nestling diet, and higher brood growth rates were found in a habitat with greater mayfly availability and use. Interestingly, at the site with low aquatic prey availability (Presquile), nests that were fed mayfly prey had higher brood growth rates than nests fed solely terrestrial prey, further demonstrating the importance of this resource.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The timing of peak caterpillar emergence did not overlap with the timing of greatest warbler nestling demand. Caterpillars were most available just prior to maximum egg production, and least available during the nestling period of both early and late clutches. While this pattern could be interpreted as poor timing when compared with other studies assessing caterpillar availability and avian nesting phenology (Van Noordwijk et al. 
  <a rid="ece32400-bib-0051" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32400-bib-0051">1995</a>; Dias and Blondel 
  <a rid="ece32400-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32400-bib-0014">1996</a>; Seki and Takano 
  <a rid="ece32400-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32400-bib-0042">1998</a>; Naef‐Daenzer et al. 
  <a rid="ece32400-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32400-bib-0029">2000</a>; Tremblay et al. 
  <a rid="ece32400-bib-0048" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32400-bib-0048">2003</a>), it is not uncommon in other migrant species. Maziarz and Wesolowski (
  <a rid="ece32400-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32400-bib-0026">2010</a>) observed that the date of maximum nestling demand for wood warblers, 
  <span class="italic">Phylloscopus sibilatrix</span>, occurred 15–16 days after the peak in caterpillar abundance. Similarly, in a West Virginia forest, caterpillar density was higher earlier and later in the season, and lowest during the nestling period for red‐eyed vireos, 
  <span class="italic">Vireo olivaceus</span> (Marshall and Cooper 
  <a rid="ece32400-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32400-bib-0024">2004</a>). Our results are concordant with these studies, and seem to suggest that caterpillars could be an important energy resource for early season egg production in many migratory songbirds. A different trend was observed for aquatic prey where the maximum nestling demand occurred just after peak mayfly emergence, and mayflies remained abundant throughout the nestling period of both early and late clutches. Prothonotary warblers, similar to other migratory riparian species (Nakano and Murakami 
  <a rid="ece32400-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32400-bib-0032">2001</a>), may time their breeding so that mayflies are available during the energetically demanding nestling period.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We observed a seasonal shift in diet to include more caterpillars as mayfly availability decreased (Fig. 
  <a rid="ece32400-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#ece32400-fig-0004">4</a>) at the site with higher mayfly availability. Likewise, other studies have shown that birds switch to alternative prey sources when preferred prey are less available (Blondel et al. 
  <a rid="ece32400-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32400-bib-0006">1991</a>; García‐Navas and Sanz 
  <a rid="ece32400-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32400-bib-0017">2011</a>); and similar seasonal diet shifts have been documented in the lesser spotted woodpecker, 
  <span class="italic">Picoides minor</span> (Rossmanith et al. 
  <a rid="ece32400-bib-0038" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32400-bib-0038">2007</a>) and wood warbler (Maziarz and Wesolowski 
  <a rid="ece32400-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32400-bib-0026">2010</a>) from caterpillars to aphids and winged insects, respectively, as caterpillar abundance declined. However, no changes were observed in diet at the site with lower mayfly availability; nestlings were fed caterpillars consistently throughout the breeding season despite the seasonal variation in availability detected in our sampling. This site also had a more diverse diet, suggesting that prothonotary warblers opportunistically feed on a variety of prey types.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Despite the fact that warblers generally fed mayflies in relation to their abundance, our data indicate that mayfly resources may be sought out when in low abundance. Mayflies were not found in the vicinity of our nest boxes at Presquile, likely due to severe channel sedimentation and lack of suitable aquatic burrowing substrate, yet low numbers of mayflies were observed being fed to nestlings at this site (33% of boxes, 14 of 43), suggesting that parents travelled off territory to get these resources. Indeed, mayflies were observed in large numbers on the west side of the island (a distance ranging from 650 m to &gt;1 km from the nest boxes) (Dodson and Moy pers. obs.) where there was suitable rocky substrate for 
  <span class="italic">Hexagenia</span> spp. At the site with high mayfly availability, emergence near riverfront boxes occurred 2 weeks prior to that in the smaller creek, although we observed parents feeding mayflies at nest boxes prior to mayfly emergence in that location. This suggests that individuals may seek out valuable resources when they are nearby. Indeed, it has been documented that parent blue tits, 
  <span class="italic">Cyanistes caeruleus</span>, will expand their foraging radius to acquire preferred caterpillar prey in habitats of low caterpillar availability (Tremblay et al. 
  <a rid="ece32400-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32400-bib-0049">2005</a>). Although there is much to learn about extraterritorial movements in songbirds related to foraging, a recent study showed that we likely underestimate the area used by territorial songbirds during the breeding season (Streby et al. 
  <a rid="ece32400-bib-0046" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32400-bib-0046">2012</a>). A study with Wilson's warblers, 
  <span class="italic">Cardellina pusilla</span>, showed that males will leave their territory, often in pursuit of extra‐pair copulations, and frequently move 0.5 km and up to 2.5 km in search of these reproductive opportunities (Norris and Stutchbury 
  <a rid="ece32400-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32400-bib-0034">2001</a>). Similar extraterritorial movements are possible for birds seeking foraging opportunities; however, they are expensive and not likely common during the demanding time of nestling feeding.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Other studies of riparian passerine species have observed the preference of aquatic prey in the nestling diet. Aquatic Diptera, particularly adult chironomids, were selectively fed to 8‐day‐old broods of yellow warbler nestlings, 
  <span class="italic">Setophaga petechia</span> (Biermann and Sealy 
  <a rid="ece32400-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32400-bib-0004">1982</a>), and Mengelkoch et al. (
  <a rid="ece32400-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32400-bib-0027">2004</a>) observed 90–98% of the biomass fed to nestling tree swallows, 
  <span class="italic">Tachycineta bicolor</span>, was of aquatic origin, primarily Odonates and aquatic Dipterans. Although our sampling efforts focused on mayflies in this study, the light traps also captured large numbers of other aquatic prey, primarily smaller aquatic species including Diptera (Nemotocera) and Trichoptera. It is possible that these smaller aquatic species were provisioned to prothonotary warbler nestlings, and we were unable to identify them in the videos due to their small size and coloration similar to the prothonotary warbler beak. As such, other types of aquatic prey, particularly chironomids, found as important components of the diet for other riparian species (Biermann and Sealy 
  <a rid="ece32400-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32400-bib-0004">1982</a>; Mengelkoch et al. 
  <a rid="ece32400-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32400-bib-0027">2004</a>), may be excluded from our results due to identification bias. Future studies of nestlings diet in this species may consider alternatives to video observation (i.e., crop flushing, collaring, or DNA in fecal material) to better understand the importance of smaller, less conspicuous, and readily available prey items.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Despite potential identification bias of some aquatic prey types, whether or not mayflies were fed to nestlings seemed to influence growth rate such that nestlings fed mayflies had faster mean growth rates than nestlings that were not. This relationship is not seen at our site with higher overall and aquatic prey availability, likely due to the superabundance of food (Tremblay et al. 
  <a rid="ece32400-bib-0048" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32400-bib-0048">2003</a>). Reproductive performance only responds to increases in available food supply up to a certain threshold (Maziarz and Wesolowski 
  <a rid="ece32400-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32400-bib-0026">2010</a>), beyond which parameters such as fledgling mass can be independent of food supply (Tremblay et al. 
  <a rid="ece32400-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32400-bib-0049">2005</a>). In the habitat with greater food availability, mayfly abundance may have passed the saturation threshold (Maziarz and Wesolowski 
  <a rid="ece32400-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32400-bib-0026">2010</a>), such that the relationship between nestling growth and the amount of mayfly prey in the diet was decoupled. However, at a site under the saturation threshold, the relationship between mayfly prey and reproductive parameters is more apparent; parents who were able to acquire mayflies had faster growing nestlings.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is not surprising that nestling provisioning and diet would be related to measures of fitness, including growth rate and body condition (Tremblay et al. 
  <a rid="ece32400-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32400-bib-0049">2005</a>). Ideally, parents feed nestlings resources that will promote rapid growth (to fledge as early as possible and avoid predation) and fledging at a larger mass (to promote postfledging survival). Our results indicate that this high‐quality resource may be of aquatic origin for the prothonotary warbler. To our knowledge, the only other bird study to assess the relationship between aquatic prey and fitness measures found more emerging aquatic prey led to higher pied flycatcher (
  <span class="italic">Ficedula hypolueca</span>) nestling survival rates along free‐flowing rivers compared to regulated rivers (Strasevicius et al. 
  <a rid="ece32400-bib-0045" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32400-bib-0045">2013</a>). Aquatic prey has also been documented as an important resource for growth in riparian lizards; Sabo and Power (
  <a rid="ece32400-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32400-bib-0039">2002</a>) found that growth rates were seven times higher in subsidized habitats during the early summer when emergence was highest. Additionally, within the watershed, lizard growth rates were positively correlated with the abundance of aquatic insects, further emphasizing the importance of aquatic subsidies for riparian predators. More studies are needed that assess fitness responses to spatial and temporal variations in emerging aquatic prey resources. This is particularly important because the timing of pulses in aquatic prey is regulated by temperature (Watanabe et al. 
  <a rid="ece32400-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32400-bib-0052">1999</a>; Harper and Peckarsky 
  <a rid="ece32400-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32400-bib-0020">2006</a>) and recent warming trends may lead to shifts in the timing of breeding in relation to prey abundance (i.e., a mismatch of prey supply and nestling demand) similar to those observed with caterpillars and the bird species that depend on them (Miller‐Rushing et al. 
  <a rid="ece32400-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32400-bib-0028">2013</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although we found differences in nestling growth rate between habitats, diet differences do not appear to be affecting overall reproductive success, specifically the number of young fledged per female. Similarly, in the study of pied flycatchers that compared sites with high and low aquatic prey resources (Strasevicius et al. 
  <a rid="ece32400-bib-0045" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32400-bib-0045">2013</a>), there was no difference in occupation rate, clutch size, or number of successfully hatched juveniles between habitats. In our system, we postulate that birds at the site with low mayfly availability (Presquile) make up for this deficit by spending more time in the nest; nestlings may benefit from a slower growth rate due to greater physiological development, greater flight ability, and better fledgling condition (Bosque and Bosque 
  <a rid="ece32400-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32400-bib-0007">1995</a>). Nestlings could then leave the nest at an equivalent developmental stage and condition as nestlings from Deep Bottom where growth rates are faster. A tradeoff of this strategy is increased exposure to nest predators; however, in our study system, nest predation rates are low (boxes placed on poles over water) reducing the selective pressure for early fledging. We did find clutch initiation date to be earlier at the site with faster growth rates. Earlier breeding birds tend to be more successful as food availability generally decreases throughout the season (Daan et al. 
  <a rid="ece32400-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32400-bib-0012">1989</a>; Bulluck et al. 
  <a rid="ece32400-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32400-bib-0009">2013</a>), and studies have demonstrated that birds will delay initiation of nesting when food resources are low (Marshall et al. 
  <a rid="ece32400-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32400-bib-0025">2002</a>; Strasevicius et al. 
  <a rid="ece32400-bib-0045" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32400-bib-0045">2013</a>). As such, it appears that emerging aquatic insects may be key subsidies that are most important for early nesting birds.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As this was an observational study from only 1 year, we are cautious in our interpretation of the results and future work is recommended to understand the mechanisms responsible for nestling growth rates and to determine potential differences in nutritional content of caterpillars, mayflies, and other important aquatic prey items. Carbon‐to‐nitrogen ratios of invertebrates have been used to indicate relative amounts of chitin (Sullivan et al. 
  <a rid="ece32400-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32400-bib-0047">2014</a>), a structural carbohydrate indigestible to birds. As such, it can be an indicator of food quality, where a greater proportion of chitin (or greater C:N) indicates lower quality (Sullivan et al. 
  <a rid="ece32400-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32400-bib-0047">2014</a>). We found that mayflies had a lower (mean ± SD) C:N value (4.37 ± 0.28) than caterpillars (5.56 ± 0.07), which may in part explain the nutritional benefits of aquatic prey. In addition to C:N ratios, our results are also supported by potential nutritional differences in fatty acid content. Most recently, the literature has highlighted the dichotomy between omega‐3 long‐chain poly unsaturated fatty acid (LC‐PUFA) production between aquatic and terrestrial systems as a possible mechanism to explain food quality limitation in natural ecosystems. LC‐PUFAs are readily available in aquatic food webs as aquatic primary producers have high synthesis capacity (Hixson et al. 
  <a rid="ece32400-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32400-bib-0021">2015</a>). However, terrestrial primary producers are not able to synthesize all of these fatty acids or their precursors, creating a fatty acid limitation in terrestrial‐based food (Hixson et al. 
  <a rid="ece32400-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32400-bib-0021">2015</a>). Gladyshev et al. (
  <a rid="ece32400-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32400-bib-0018">2013</a>) estimated that terrestrial carnivores may not be able to obtain sufficient amounts of omega‐3 highly unsaturated fatty acid (
  <span class="italic">ω</span>‐3 HUFA) consuming terrestrial‐based foods alone, and emergent aquatic insects may transport some 
  <span class="italic">ω</span>‐3 HUFAs to terrestrial consumers, including riparian birds (Gladyshev et al. 
  <a rid="ece32400-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32400-bib-0018">2013</a>). The clearest direct effect of 
  <span class="italic">ω</span>‐3 HUFA limitation for an individual consumer is decreased growth (Twining et al. 
  <a rid="ece32400-bib-0050" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32400-bib-0050">2015</a>), which could explain why nestlings at the site with few mayflies had slower growth rates. This suggests that relative differences in fatty acid content between terrestrial and aquatic resources could play an important role in nestling fitness in riparian species. Future work is recommended to determine differences in fatty acid content between caterpillars and mayflies.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our findings support previous research that suggests aquatic resources are important subsidies for riparian species. Unlike previous studies that show changes in abundance, distribution, or migratory stopover refueling benefits related to pulses of emerging aquatic resources, our study is the first documentation of how aquatic subsidies in the nestling diet influence growth and condition in an avian species. Notably, aquatic resource availability and use did not seem to influence the annual reproductive success (number of young fledged) of individual birds. However, there could be “downstream” effects of differing food quality that were not measured in this study, such as fledgling survival and recruitment. Our results suggest that the interdependence between aquatic subsidies and riparian terrestrial consumers is crucial to understanding the breeding ecology of riparian species and that more study is needed in these complex systems.</p>
</sec>
