<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece32400-sec-0004" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nestling field surveys</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A total of 110 nest boxes were monitored in 2014: 63 boxes at Deep Bottom Park and 47 boxes at Presquile NWR. Mean yearly temperature and total precipitation were consistent with climate data for this area (mean 15°C and 90.7 cm total rainfall). All boxes were positioned on metal conduit poles approximately 30 m apart over water at high tide and were checked 2–3 times each week during the breeding season (late April–mid‐July). Nest contents were recorded to determine dates for nest initiation (first egg), hatching, and completion for each clutch. As a species and population that often double broods (Bulluck et al. 
  <a rid="ece32400-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32400-bib-0009">2013</a>), there is a natural lull in hatching dates during the season between the early and later clutches. This lull occurred on May 28 such that nests with eggs that hatched prior to this date were classified as early clutches, and those nests whose eggs hatched after 28 May were classified as late clutches.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nestlings were carefully removed from the nest box (Fig. 
  <a rid="ece32400-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#ece32400-fig-0001">1</a>) and fitted with a unique numbered aluminum band (USGS). We measured the mass and tarsus length of each nestling on two occasions between hatching and fledging (mean age of first weighing was 3–4 days, range 2–8 days, mean age of second weighing was 7–8 days, range 5–10 days, with hatch day = 0). We were not able to standardize the ages for these measurements due to the logistics of accessing the sites and boxes. Tarsus length was measured to 0.1 mm using dial calipers, and mass was measured to 0.1 g using a digital scale. Mean growth rates per brood were calculated as the change in mean mass between the first and second weighing dates, standardized by the number of days between measurements. Nestling body condition was calculated as the residuals from a regression of tarsus and mass at the second measurement, and was calculated for each age class separately (Schulte‐Hostedde et al. 
  <a rid="ece32400-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32400-bib-0041">2005</a>). All applicable institutional and/or national guidelines for the care and use of animals were followed. All research was approved by the Virginia Commonwealth University's Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee (IACUC, protocol #AM10230) as well as the VA Department of Game and Inland Fisheries (permit #053965) and the US Department of Interior (USGS Bird Banding Laboratory permit #23486).
 </p>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece32400-fig-0001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Nine‐day‐old prothonotary warbler nestlings removed from their nest box for measuring (photograph taken by L. Bulluck).</p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-3" xlink:href="ECE3-6-7462-g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
