<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece32400-sec-0007" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Quantifying nestling diet</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nestling diet was quantified using video observations. A Canon FS400 handheld standard‐definition camera (min/max focal length = 2.6/96.2 mm) was placed 2–4 m from the nest box with a clear view of the nest box opening for at least 1.09 h (mean video length was 2.55 h, range 1.09–3.75 h). All video observations were conducted in the mornings (6:00–12:30) when the nestlings were 6–9 days old. We observed no difference in feeding behavior in the presence of the video cameras (e.g., prolonged nest vigilance or excessive chipping around nest or camera), and cameras have been successfully used to quantify nestling provisioning in other warbler species (Stodola et al. 
  <a rid="ece32400-bib-0044" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32400-bib-0044">2010</a>). Videos were reviewed by four observers for the identification of food items brought to the nest. All observers were initially trained by watching and scoring the same video and then discussing any interobserver differences, and regular meetings were held to discuss identification of any questionable prey items. For each visit, we recorded the number and size of food item(s) as well as parent sex using plumage characteristics and color band combinations. When possible, food items were identified to one of the following orders: Lepidoptera (caterpillar – terrestrial), Ephemeroptera (mayfly – aquatic), Araneae (spider – terrestrial), Orthoptera (grasshopper – terrestrial), Odonata (dragonfly – aquatic), other terrestrial (i.e., Coleoptera larvae or pupae), or unknown.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The length (size) of food was estimated relative to the parents' bill (1 = smaller than bill, 2 = same size as bill, 3 = larger than bill) following Beck (
  <a rid="ece32400-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32400-bib-0003">2010</a>) and Stodola et al. (
  <a rid="ece32400-bib-0044" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32400-bib-0044">2010</a>). These size estimations were used to calculate a food score. A food score was calculated for each visit as the food size multiplied by the number of items. These food scores were totaled for each prey type and for each nest. If the item size could not be estimated because the item was too small (e.g., inside the beak), it received a size of one. If an item could not be identified due to visual obstruction, it was classified as a nonvisualized unknown prey item and did not receive a size score. In these cases, we assumed that nonvisualized prey items were consistent with the sizes of identified items, and calculated an adjusted food score estimate. To calculate the adjusted food score estimate, the number of visits with nonvisualized prey items was multiplied by the average food score per visualized item for that parent. These values provided an estimated food score of the nonvisualized unknown item(s). This was performed for males and females separately and added to the total food score, creating a total adjusted food score for that nest. When an item was not visualized but a parent displayed normal feeding behaviors such as perching on the box entrance and lowering its head and neck into the box, it was assumed one item was being fed. All diet variables were standardized by number of nestlings and video length (chick
  <span class="sup">−1</span>·h
  <span class="sup">−1</span>).
 </p>
</sec>
