<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0240" class="p">Mention should be made of a number of possible limitations and their ensuing biases. Firstly, with reference to the quality and consistency of the data analysed, there may be misclassification of the cause of mortality or admission, or errors related to the lack of data on environmental variables. Secondly, with respect to methodological limitations, essentially two should be highlighted: the shortcomings inherent in a statistical method that works with a high number of variables at a 95% confidence level. The fact that this is an ecological study means that inferences cannot be made at an individual level, since these would be exposed to the appearance of the ecological fallacy due to the use of aggregate data. It is only possible to show the existence of a statistical association between the variables analysed. Factors favouring the existence of a real, as opposed to a spurious-relationship, are the high correlation index, increasing dose-response relationship, absence of temporal ambiguity, biological plausibility of the effect shown in clinical studies, and consistency of results obtained by previous studies. Furthermore, in the case of estimates of the impact of temperatures on mortality, various hypotheses were postulated, including the assumption of mortality being constant over time, the related attributable risk remaining similarly constant, as well as the mortality threshold temperature associated with the extreme temperatures. In addition, there are great uncertainties inherent to population projections, including migration, age structure and mortality rates, albeit these may arguably be more acceptable than the obvious alternative of assuming a constant population or a simplified model. Also, our models did not account for potential changes in air pollution and urban heat related to changes in traffic policy (e.g. the establishment of a low emission zone) and in urban green (e.g. replacement of large old city trees by new trees).</p>
