<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0245" class="p">There are various ways to design and implement effective prevention against the health impacts of heat. A common template to organize such prevention is a Heat-health action plan (
 <xref rid="bb0305" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">WHO, 2008</xref>) in which a set or core elements and agencies hierarchically act upon and respond to heat warnings. Many prevention plans were formulated following the European heatwave in 2003. Currently various plans and additional activities are in place to tackle the issues related to heat in the Antwerp area. The Belgian National Heatwave plan defines a heatwave as a period of at least three consecutive days where the mean maximum temperature exceeds 30ʡC and the mean minimum temperature exceeds 18ʡC. The plan contains two warning levels: Level one is activated when two days with temperatures exceeding those mentioned have occurred. Level two is activated when the definition of a heatwave is fulfilled. Warnings are prepared during level one. The effectiveness of this action plan has been examined and improvements considered (
 <xref rid="bb0295" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">van Loenhout et al., 2016</xref>). In addition to the National plan, the Flemish Region authorities have designed and are in the process of implementing a regional heat health action plan. In the proposed Flemish heat action plan the level two warning level is activated when a cumulative indicator of temperature, 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>
 <sub class="sub">cumul</sub>, equals or exceeds 17ʡC. 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>
 <sub class="sub">cumul</sub> is calculated as the sum of all degrees centigrade higher than 25ʡC of the expected maximum temperature in a time window of five days. This method would allow activation of heat action plans three days in advance of an expected heatwave. The level two warning level stays active until the maximum temperature expected is lower than 25ʡC. A sensitivity analysis of this new threshold showed that the new method resulted in longer activation periods of warning level two compared to the heat plan active at present, but the frequency of activation of level two did not differ between the two methods (
 <xref rid="bb0050" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bustos-Sierra et al., 2016</xref>). Moreover, the municipality of Antwerp itself plans and runs every year a number of preventive activities. The results of this study can help calibrate these preventive efforts, and put a long term perspective on heat-health prevention in a changing climate.
</p>
