<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par2" class="p">Dietary deficiencies of micronutrients such as iron and zinc constitute major public health problems globally, particularly amongst women and children in sub-Saharan Africa
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">1</xref>
 </sup>. While micronutrient supplementation and food fortification are important for improving delivery of micronutrients, staple food crop biofortification through breeding provides an additional route for increasing the supply of key micronutrients (iron, zinc, vitamin A) from staple crops to the diets of poorer communities in developing countries
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" class="xref">2</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">5</xref>
 </sup>. The level of micronutrients (e.g. iron, zinc) in staple crops and foods is one of the key determinants of the extent of uptake of dietary micronutrients
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">6</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>
 </sup>. However, the presence and levels of anti-nutritionals, in particular phytic acid and polyphenols, can inhibit bioavailability and hence the level of uptake of such micronutrients
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">8</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">15</xref>
 </sup>. The consideration of anti-nutritionals in biofortification breeding programs is important to ensure that efforts to increase the levels of micronutrients (e.g. iron) in crops are not compromised by inadvertent increases in levels of anti-nutritionals (such as phytic acid and/or polyphenols) that could arise from breeding efforts
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">9</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">11</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">13</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">15</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>
 </sup> or from environmental stresses.
</p>
