<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>As mentioned above, previous descriptive studies on the tundra vegetation of the Changbai Mountains indicated that the tundra vegetation has changed significantly over the last 30 years. However, there is a lack of quantitative study on the composition and spatial distribution of tundra vegetation. Several surveys in the tundra were conducted, but the exact locations investigated were not well documented [
 <xref rid="B23-plants-08-00370" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-plants-08-00370" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], and, thus, a comparable re-investigation is impossible. In the early 1980s, the tundra community is nearly purely composed of shrubs [
 <xref rid="B23-plants-08-00370" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-plants-08-00370" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>]. Recently, some studies found that eight plant species dominated the tundra, including two shrub species (
 <italic>R. chrysanthum</italic> and 
 <italic>V. uliginosum</italic>) and six herb species (
 <italic>C. angustifolia, Geranium baishanense, Ligularia jamesii, Sanguisorba parviflora, Sanguisorba stipulata</italic>, and 
 <italic>Saussurea tomentosa</italic>) [
 <xref rid="B38-plants-08-00370" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="B39-plants-08-00370" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. These herb species previously either occurred in the mountain birch forests at a lower elevation or were occasionally observed in the tundra [
 <xref rid="B39-plants-08-00370" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>]. The distribution patterns of these eight dominant species belong to the aggregated distribution, but the aggregate intensity varies among species. The aggregate intensity of 
 <italic>R. chrysanthum</italic> is the weakest, while the aggregate intensity of herbs is usually stronger. Moreover, the associations among six dominant herbs are different and their associations are low [
 <xref rid="B37-plants-08-00370" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>]. This phenomenon indicates that there may be differences in habitat selection among dominant herbs and, thus, they may occupy various spatial locations. However, the variation characteristics and differences in the spatial distribution of dominant plants in that tundra remain unknown.
</p>
