<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our study clearly demonstrates that reducing the ambient temperature can increase the predation of toxic prey by avian predators. This is the first time that an abiotic environmental factor has been shown to affect predatory decisions on signalling prey known to contain toxins. While previous experiments have shown that birds increase their overall dietary intake, particularly of energy-rich foods, at lower temperatures (
  <a rid="bib46 bib18 bib63" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib46 bib18 bib63">Prince et al. 1965; Chaffee &amp; Roberts 1971; Sprenkle &amp; Blem 1984</a>; 
  <a rid="bib73" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib73">Wansik &amp; Tinbergen 1994</a>), this is the first demonstration that birds eat more toxic prey as temperature decreases. This is most likely to be in response to an increased need for energy at lower temperatures, which increases the benefits of eating the nutrients relative to ingesting the toxins (see also 
  <a rid="bib5 bib6" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib5 bib6">Barnett et al. 2007, 2012</a>). Our results suggest that selection pressures on insect defences could vary with temperature across days, seasons or environmental climes, such as latitude and elevation. Temperature-dependent predation on toxic prey is predicted to change the costs and benefits to warning coloration and investment in defences in prey.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">First, decreasing temperature will increase the costs of being conspicuous for aposematic prey. Conspicuous coloration already carries a significant detectability cost, although this can potentially be offset by predators learning to associate conspicuous coloration with toxicity more quickly with conspicuous compared to cryptic signals (e.g. 
  <a rid="bib29 bib2 bib37" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib29 bib2 bib37">Gittleman &amp; Harvey 1980; Alatalo &amp; Mappes 1996; Lindström et al. 1999</a>). Our results suggest that if predators more readily ingest toxic prey at low temperatures, warning coloration will become even more costly as temperature decreases. This could lead to selection for less conspicuous warning signals in colder environments, for example, through the evolution of patterns that make prey cryptic at a distance (
  <a rid="bib67" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib67">Tullberg et al. 2005</a>) or by a reduction in the size or coloration of the colour signal. While increasing latitude tends to be associated with smaller or duller signals in aposematic prey, this is generally ascribed to the thermoregulatory benefits of increasing the amount of melanin in the signal (
  <a rid="bib36 bib41" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib36 bib41">Lindstedt et al. 2009; Mochida 2011</a>; 
  <a rid="bib72" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib72">Hegna et al. 2013</a>). However, detectability costs could also be important in selection for less colourful signals, particularly for prey for which the costs of predation increase more rapidly than the benefits of thermoregulation with decreasing temperature (Hegna et al. 2013).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Second, increased predation of toxic prey at lower temperatures could also select for increased toxicity of aposematic prey. This is likely to evolve only if the benefits from the associated reduction in predation outweigh any costs of increased toxicity, for example, reduced growth rates or lower fecundity (
  <a rid="bib43 bib21 bib50 bib71" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib43 bib21 bib50 bib71">Pasteels et al. 1983; Cohen 1985; Rowell-Rahier &amp; Pasteels 1986; Zalucki et al. 2001</a>). However, there appear to be some insect species for which the costs of possessing toxins appear minimal (
  <a rid="bib34" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib34">Kearsley &amp; Whitham 1992</a>), suggesting that increased toxicity could be selected for in at least some cases. An alternative strategy would be to aggregate in colder weather in order to pool defences to saturate a predator's detoxification pathways. Some aposematic insects, such as seven-spot ladybirds, 
  <span class="italic">Coccinella septempunctata</span>, and monarch butterflies, often aggregate in winter (
  <a rid="bib14 bib33" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib14 bib33">Brower &amp; Calvert 1985; Holloway et al. 1991</a>), a strategy that is known to enhance individual survival (
  <a rid="bib2 bib48 bib26" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib2 bib48 bib26">Alatalo &amp; Mappes 1996; Riipi et al. 2001; Finkbeiner et al. 2012</a>). Perhaps this strategy is particularly effective at lower temperatures when predators are more willing to ingest toxic prey, since it ensures that a predator's toxin burden is reached, allowing the majority of individuals to survive.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Finally, our results also suggest that the costs and benefits of mimicry may change with temperature. For example, in Batesian or quasi-Batesian mimicry, where a visual mimic has a parasitic relationship with a more toxic model (
  <a rid="bib7 bib61" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib7 bib61">Bates 1862; Speed 1993</a>), the benefits to the mimic may rapidly decrease with decreasing temperature. This is because the benefits of looking the same as a toxic model will be much reduced and predators will be less likely to reject a model or a mimic upon encounter. If Batesian model–mimic complexes become more acceptable as food at lower temperatures, the cost of the mimic on the model may also increase at lower temperatures. To our knowledge, there has been no investigation of how the costs and benefits to mimicry might change with temperature, but it provides an interesting avenue for future research, both in the laboratory and in the field.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although we found a main effect of temperature on the predation of toxic prey, our birds varied in their sensitivity to decreasing temperature. We found that heavier birds (and/or possibly those in better body condition) increased their ingestion of defended prey more rapidly than lighter birds. One possible explanation for this is that heavier individuals had a higher BMR and that their need for nutrients was higher than that of individuals with lower body mass (
  <a rid="bib52 bib60 bib10" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib52 bib60 bib10">Selman et al. 2001; Speakman et al. 2004; Boratyński &amp; Koteja 2009</a>). However, heavier individuals did not have higher dietary intake than lighter individuals. Perhaps instead, these birds were more sensitive to the food deprivation period prior to the start of experimental sessions (possibly owing to a higher BMR), and that this increased their motivation to acquire nutrients. Although it seems likely that foraging decisions were based upon changes in the energetic requirements of birds, we cannot rule out the possibility that the heavier birds were somehow better able to process toxins at lower temperatures compared to lighter birds, although the possible mechanisms by which this would occur are not clear. Given that our study was purely behavioural, we are unable to discriminate between these different possibilities at this stage.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although we found an effect of body mass on the birds' sensitivity to ingest toxic prey with decreasing temperature, we found no effect of either body mass, condition, dietary intake or fat scores on the number of defended prey eaten by an individual when at asymptote during the learning phase the learning phase. This is perhaps surprising given that we would expect energetic state to be important in an individual's decision to eat toxic prey (
  <a rid="bib5 bib6" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib5 bib6">Barnett et al. 2007, 2012</a>). Although the sample size was small in this experiment, we have been unable to find an effect of body mass or condition on the number of defended prey eaten at asymptote in a larger sample of birds used in a previous experiment (
  <span class="italic">N</span> = 33 birds; C. G. Halpin &amp; C. Rowe, unpublished data, from 
  <a rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib31">Halpin et al. 2012</a>). There are two possible reasons for this. First, our measures do not reliably measure energetic state, and other factors that we did not measure could be affecting nutrient requirements, for example, age, health or gut microflora (see 
  <a rid="bib42" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib42">Murphy 1996</a> for full list). Second, it could be that factors other than energetic state are also involved in determining birds' decisions to forage on toxic prey. Perhaps the most obvious is birds' abilities to detoxify ingested toxins. Brower's work on blue jays, 
  <span class="italic">Cyanocitta cristata</span>, showed that individual birds within a population varied in their ability to cope with ingested cardenolides from monarch butterflies (
  <a rid="bib16 bib15" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib16 bib15">Brower et al. 1968; Brower &amp; Glazier 1975</a>). It is therefore entirely possible that our starlings also differed in their abilities to detoxify quinine, because of either genetic variation or exposure to toxins prior to capture. Clearly, we are only just beginning to understand the mechanisms underlying birds' decisions to eat toxic prey, and future experiments could build on our findings to explore the interaction between genetic, physiological and cognitive factors in how predators decide to forage on toxic prey.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While our experiment has focused on the predation of toxic prey by avian predators, two studies have explored how temperature affects mammalian herbivores grazing on plants containing PSMs. In contrast to our own findings, neither of these studies found that herbivores increased their ingestion of toxic plant material when the ambient temperature was reduced below their TNZ (
  <a rid="bib64 bib23" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib64 bib23">Stapley et al. 2000; Dearing et al. 2008</a>). Because of the paucity of studies investigating how ambient temperature affects animals foraging on toxic foods, it is hard to know whether the differences between our study on avian predators and those on mammalian herbivores are due to comparing across taxa, foraging modes or different laboratory protocols. Clearly, a better understanding of the relationship between temperature, toxicity and energetics is required if we are to understand selection pressures acting on toxic animals and plants (see also 
  <a rid="bib23" ref-type="bibr" href="#bib23">Dearing et al. 2008</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Of course, any study investigating how foraging decisions change with temperature is potentially relevant for understanding how climate change may affect predator–prey dynamics and animal populations. While our study is perhaps limited in that we only manipulated temperature over several weeks, it does suggest that long-term changes in temperature may also affect selection pressures acting on aposematic prey and their mimics. Our results suggest that ambient temperature affects the evolutionary dynamics of prey defences, and raises interesting future avenues for research in aposematism and mimicry.</p>
</sec>
