<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="appsec1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Appendix: Body condition measurements</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The time points during the experiment at which we collected data on body mass, dietary intake and fat stores differed. For consistency, we compared data collected at 20 °C and 6 °C; however, here we report the full data collection methods and the data collected at all sampling points for each of our three measures.</p>
 <sec id="appsec1.1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Body Mass</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Since measuring the birds' masses could disrupt their behaviour, we took measures during the learning phase at 20 °C (days 2 and 5), and three in the temperature manipulation phase on experimental days 17 (10 °C), 20 (8 °C) and 21 (6 °C). These latter measurements also ensured that our birds were not rapidly losing weight in response to decreasing temperature. The data from all days are presented in Fig. A1. To compare whether birds' masses differed between 20 °C and 6 °C, we compared the data between day 5 (the last measure at 20 °C prior to the temperature manipulation) and day 21 (the only measure at 6 °C).</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="appsec1.2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Dietary Intake</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We took daily measures of the total mass of food eaten by birds during the learning phase at 20 °C and the temperature manipulation phase as the temperature was reduced from 20 °C to 6 °C (days 1–22). The data from all days are presented in Fig. A2. To compare whether birds' intake differed between 20 °C and 6 °C, we compared the data between day 8 (the last measure at 20 °C prior to the temperature manipulation) and day 22 (the last measure at 6 °C).</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="appsec1.3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fat Scores</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To maximize the opportunity for detecting changes in fat storage, we fat scored the birds on day 8 (20 °C) and day 22 (6 °C) which reduced handling and potential stress to the birds. The data are presented in Fig. A3.
   <div id="undfig1" position="anchor" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Figure A1</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>The mean ± SE mass of the birds taken as the temperature was reduced from 20 °C to 6 °C.</p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="fx1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
   <div id="undfig2" position="anchor" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Figure A2</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>The mean ± SE daily dietary intake of birds on experimental days 1–22. Vertical lines denote a change in temperature.</p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="fx2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
   <div id="undfig3" position="anchor" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Figure A3</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>The mean ± SE fat score of the birds at 20 °C (day 8) and 6 °C (day 22).</p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="fx3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
