<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec1.1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Subjects and Housing</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A group of 50 European starlings were caught in the nonbreeding season (September/October 2011) in Northumberland under licence (Natural England 20113759) using a baited whoosh net. The birds (juveniles and adults) were immediately transported to the laboratory by car (a 30 min drive) and kept in two indoor aviaries (215 × 340 cm and 220 cm high) at Newcastle University. Each aviary had bark chippings on the floor, and ropes, boxes and branches for perches and cover. Birds were fed ad libitum poultry diet, mixed fruit and mealworms (mealworms were scattered into the bark chippings to promote natural foraging behaviour). Birds had constant access to drinking water and were provided with bathing water daily. The temperature of the aviary ranged between 15 °C and 18 °C, and was kept under a 14:10 h light cycle under high flicker rate (100 Hz) fluorescent lighting. Birds were individually marked using plastic colour rings, and were weighed each week and visually inspected daily by a trained technician during their time in captivity to ensure that they remained in good health.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nine days before the start of the experiment, eight birds (four female and four male) were selected at random as experimental subjects and transferred to a climate-controlled chamber at 20 °C. Birds were individually housed in cages measuring 75 × 45 cm and 45 cm high with a flap facing the front through which prey could be presented. Although housed individually, birds were not visually or acoustically isolated from the other birds in the room, except during test sessions (see below). The cages were enriched with a bowl of water used for bathing, a litter tray containing wood chips for foraging and branches as perches. Birds were maintained on a 14:10 h light:dark photoperiod under high flicker rate (100 Hz) fluorescent lighting. Enriched vitamin water and a poultry maintenance diet were provided ad libitum except during experimental periods (see below). A piece of apple was also given at the end of each daily session. At the end of the experiment (April 2012), birds were returned to free-flight aviaries before being health checked by a vet, BTO ringed and released back to the wild at their site of capture. Although we were unable to monitor the birds following their release and subsequent dispersal, we have seen and recaught birds that we have previously released, demonstrating their ability to survive in the wild. The experiments were conducted under local ethical approval from Newcastle University (ERC Project ID No. 266).</p>
</sec>
