<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate Model Experiments.</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We compare the Historical and Natural climate model simulations from the CMIP5 archive (
  <a rid="r20" ref-type="bibr" href="#r20">20</a>). As in Burke et al. (
  <a rid="r14" ref-type="bibr" href="#r14">14</a>), we analyze the subselection of CMIP5 realizations analyzed by the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) (
  <a rid="r31" ref-type="bibr" href="#r31">31</a>). For the Natural experiment, this includes one realization each from 21 of the participating global climate models, which are paired with the 21 corresponding Historical realizations. Note that although the socioeconomic data are available through 2010, the CMIP5 experimental protocol for the Historical and Natural experiments ends in 2005. Thus, as in Burke et al. (
  <a rid="r14" ref-type="bibr" href="#r14">14</a>), we use the IPCC’s 20-y historical baseline period (1986–2005) as the baseline period for climate model bias correction.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For each country, we create 21 counterfactual historical temperature timeseries 
  <span class="italic">T</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">NoAnthro</span>
  </sub>, which remove the influence of anthropogenic forcing simulated by each of the 21 climate models. Our approach to creating the counterfactual timeseries follows the widely applied “delta method” of climate model bias correction, in which the model-simulated change in the mean is applied to the observed timeseries. For each country 
  <span class="italic">c</span>, we first calculate the observed country-level population-weighted mean annual temperature timeseries 
  <span class="italic">T</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">Obs</span>
  </sub> for the 1961–2010 time period covered by the socioeconomic data, following Burke et al. (
  <a rid="r14" ref-type="bibr" href="#r14">14</a>). Then, for each country 
  <span class="italic">c</span> and climate model 
  <span class="italic">m</span>, we calculate the difference in country-level population-weighted mean temperature between the Historical and Natural CMIP5 simulations, both for the 20-y period centered on the beginning of the socioeconomic data (1951–1970), and for the 20-y historical baseline period used by the IPCC (1986–2005). We then linearize the difference between the Historical and Natural simulations over the 1961–2010 period, such that the difference in 1961 is equal to the difference in the Historical and Natural means during the 20-y period centered on 1961 (1951–1970), and the difference in 2010 is equal to the difference in the Historical and Natural means during the IPCC’s 20-y baseline period (1986–2005). Finally, for each year 
  <span class="italic">t</span> in the 1961–2010 observed temperature timeseries, we add the linearized 
  <span class="italic">Natural</span> minus 
  <span class="italic">Historical</span> difference ∆
  <span class="italic">T</span> for that year:
  <div id="uneq1" class="disp-formula">
   <div id="me1" class="math">
    <div class="mrow">
     <div class="msub">
      <span class="mi">T</span>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">NoAnthro</span>
      </div>
     </div>
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mo">[</span>
      <span class="mi">t</span>
      <span class="mo">]</span>
     </div>
     <span class="mo">=</span>
     <div class="msub">
      <span class="mi">T</span>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">Obs</span>
      </div>
     </div>
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mo">[</span>
      <span class="mi">t</span>
      <span class="mo">]</span>
     </div>
     <span class="mo">+</span>
     <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">Δ</span>
     <span class="mi">T</span>
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mo">[</span>
      <span class="mi">t</span>
      <span class="mo">]</span>
     </div>
     <span class="mo">.</span>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p content-type="flushleft" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This process generates, for each country, an ensemble of 21 counterfactual timeseries 
  <span class="italic">T</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">NoAnthro</span>
  </sub>. This 21-member ensemble reflects a combination of uncertainty in the climate response to external forcings and uncertainty arising from internal climate system variability, but removes biases in the climate model simulation of the absolute temperature magnitude and of the interannual temperature variability. [The 
  <span class="italic">T</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">NoAnthro</span>
  </sub> timeseries corresponds to the counterfactual timeseries used in Diffenbaugh et al. (
  <a rid="r21" ref-type="bibr" href="#r21">21</a>) to calculate the contribution of the observed trend to the extreme event magnitude, except that in this case the magnitude of the counterfactual trend is calculated from the CMIP5 Natural forcing simulation.]
 </p>
</sec>
