<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>We projected future temperature-related infectious gastroenteritis under four climate change scenarios according to models of climate change and morbidity. We acquired climate historical and projected time-series data for average daily temperatures from the database developed by the Inter-Sectoral Impact Model Intercomparison Project (ISI-MIP). This database includes time series of modeled average daily temperatures for historical (1960–2005) and projected (2006–2099) periods (
 <xref rid="c48" ref-type="bibr">Warszawski et al. 2014</xref>). Historical and projections of average daily temperatures were developed according to GCMs (
 <xref rid="c48" ref-type="bibr">Warszawski et al. 2014</xref>). We used the four RCP scenarios (RCP2.6, RCP4.5, RCP6.0, and RCP8.5), as detailed in the fifth IPCC report (
 <xref rid="c44" ref-type="bibr">van Vuuren et al. 2011a</xref>). The ISI-MIP used five publicly available representative GCMs (GFDL-ESM2M, HadGEM2-ES, IPSL-CM5A-LR, MIROC-ESM-CHEM, and NorESM1-M) to reconstruct daily temperature series under each GCM, and these models were chosen as the representatives of the various GCMs developed in the fifth phase of the Climate Model Intercomparison Project (CMIP5) (
 <xref rid="c39" ref-type="bibr">Taylor et al. 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="c48" ref-type="bibr">Warszawski et al. 2014</xref>). GCMs were developed by considering the differences in the impact of climate change at varying levels of global warming according to the four RCPs to produce the highest and lowest end-of-century forcings (
 <xref rid="c48" ref-type="bibr">Warszawski et al. 2014</xref>). The model outputs are adjusted for bias and reduced to 
 <inline-formula>
  <math id="m15">
   <mrow>
    <mn>0.5</mn>
    <mo>°</mo>
    <mo>×</mo>
    <mn>0.5</mn>
    <mo>°</mo>
   </mrow>
  </math>
 </inline-formula> spatial resolution (
 <xref rid="c48" ref-type="bibr">Warszawski et al. 2014</xref>). The modeled daily temperature time series for each prefecture in the projection period 1990–2099 was obtained by linking the coordinates with the appropriate grid cells containing the climate projections. From the daily mean temperature time series, we also derived the weekly average of mean temperature. When the modeled weekly temperature series are applied to exposure–response relationships estimated using observed weekly time series for average daily mean temperature, deviations between the modeled and observed weekly temperature series may produce biased results in the impact projections. Thus, we corrected the modeled daily temperature series using the bias-correction method, which recalibrated using the monthly mean observed daily temperature series (
 <xref rid="c17" ref-type="bibr">Hempel et al. 2013</xref>). This bias-correction approach preserves the long-term absolute temperature change in the simulations (
 <xref rid="c17" ref-type="bibr">Hempel et al. 2013</xref>). We computed the projected weekly time series of infectious gastroenteritis cases, showing the average weekly observed number across each year of the projection period (1990–2099).
</p>
