<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec011" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our use of a minimally realistic ecosystem model [
  <a rid="pone.0191011.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191011.ref013">13</a>] to assess the marginal impacts of one potential consequence of climate change and fishing on the krill-centric ecosystem in the Scotia Sea has several main outcomes. First, the effects of warming on krill growth have implications for krill biomass and the abundances of dependent predators. Second, evaluating aggregated responses across the ecosystem is likely to downplay smaller-scale impacts on some predators, especially penguins. Third, differences in predator responses across SSMUs suggest that some predators and locations may be more vulnerable to changes in the future, and may need specific consideration in management strategies aimed at balancing ecosystem services. Finally, the results indicate that fishing as we implemented it may compound the impacts of warming, and that stopping fishing could help to offset the modeled risks associated with warming for predators in some, but not all, areas.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Growth in marine species is often temperature-dependent and, therefore, one of the major mechanisms by which ocean warming driven by climate change could impact biomass [
  <a rid="pone.0191011.ref026" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191011.ref026">26</a>]. Our results suggest that warming impacts on krill growth are likely to have negative effects for both the biomass of krill and the abundances of their predators. Current krill catches remain below 50% of the conservative catch limit, yet CCAMLR needs to anticipate a future in which climate change affects the ecosystem and the services it provides. For example, our results demonstrate that the risk of CCAMLR failing to meet a key technical objective for krill (maintaining biomass above 75% of its unimpacted level [
  <a rid="pone.0191011.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191011.ref014">14</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0191011.ref027" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191011.ref027">27</a>], represented here as the expected biomass in the absence of both climate change and fishing) could increase to c. 25% under RCP 8.5, even in the absence of fishing. Consequently, the risks of seal and penguin populations being depleted below 75% of their unimpacted levels could also increase to c. 10% and c. 51%, respectively. Fishing at 100% of the catch limit, as modeled here, would likely exacerbate those risks.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">These aggregated results de-emphasize important outcomes at smaller spatial scales, in this case SSMUs, where fishing, warming, or both might have greater impacts. This finding echoes other work (e.g. [
  <a rid="pone.0191011.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191011.ref014">14</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0191011.ref027" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191011.ref027">27</a>]), and is an important motivation for using spatially-explicit models like the one here. However, management of marine ecosystems is often focused on larger spatial scales, as it is in the Southern Ocean, because aggregation can simplify both the translation of science to management advice and the implementation of resulting management action. It is therefore important to check whether trends at smaller spatial scales are captured at larger spatial scales. Our results suggest that smaller scale responses to climate change impacts, like ocean warming, can be lost with aggregation. For example, we find spatial separation at the SSMU scale between the strongest effects on krill and the strongest impacts on penguins, even in the absence of fishing. These outcomes arise from the spatial processes represented in the model, including movement (or lack thereof) of krill, and seasonal differences in the foraging distributions of predators. This is a useful demonstration that local food-web structure is affected by processes operating at multiple scales, including global climate change and changes elsewhere in the same ecosystem [
  <a rid="pone.0191011.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191011.ref028">28</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We also found differences between species groups in our simulations, with whales and fish largely unaffected by warming effects on krill growth, and penguins the most sensitive. Even RCP 2.6, which includes a return to radiative forcing similar to that for 2020 by the end of the 21st century, increased the estimated risks for penguins by c. 12%. Previous analysis using the model here indicates that penguin population responses tend to magnify modelled perturbations [
  <a rid="pone.0191011.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191011.ref020">20</a>] due to depensatory dynamics [
  <a rid="pone.0191011.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191011.ref013">13</a>]. This formalizes a clear hypothesis that depensatory dynamics might make penguins particularly vulnerable to changes in krill biomass. Identifying whether this is an accurate representation of penguin population dynamics should be a research priority. Other work supplies some evidence that certain species and populations will be more sensitive than others to the effects of ocean warming and changes in krill biomass (e.g. [
  <a rid="pone.0191011.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191011.ref029">29</a>]), with penguins particularly susceptible (e.g. [
  <a rid="pone.0191011.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191011.ref030">30</a>]).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">More broadly, our results have implications for similar ecosystems where dynamics are strongly impacted by a single trophic level, such as that occupied by krill in the Southern Ocean. Previous research demonstrates krill predators tied to land-based breeding colonies may be more vulnerable if changes in available prey occur during the breeding season, as this may cause declines in breeding success [
  <a rid="pone.0191011.ref031" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191011.ref031">31</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0191011.ref032" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191011.ref032">32</a>]. Outcomes may also be exacerbated for krill-dependent predators who forage in areas temporally or spatially disparate from breeding areas (e.g. some cetaceans and seals [
  <a rid="pone.0191011.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191011.ref033">33</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0191011.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191011.ref034">34</a>]), and those that require continual and immediate feeding while rearing young (e.g. marine mammals and seabirds, [
  <a rid="pone.0191011.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191011.ref035">35</a>]). These examples from the Antarctic demonstrate the potential for ecosystem consequences of changes in one critical prey species, with implications for other similar, or potentially “wasp-waist” [
  <a rid="pone.0191011.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191011.ref036">36</a>], ecosystems.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Comprehensive evaluation of all possible climate change impacts on an ecosystem is currently impractical. We have reduced this complexity by focusing on the marginal impacts of a single process, the potential for warming to reduce krill growth. In reality, krill are affected by a range of physical drivers that may be altered by climate change, such as sea-ice extent and temperature [
  <a rid="pone.0191011.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191011.ref037">37</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0191011.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191011.ref038">38</a>], as well as increased UV exposure and ocean acidity [
  <a rid="pone.0191011.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191011.ref029">29</a>]. Our work does not address these additional drivers; we assumed they would remain unchanged. This will likely not be the case, and alterations in these drivers may have additional effects. For example, changes in primary production might be important for future krill production as well [
  <a rid="pone.0191011.ref010" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191011.ref010">10</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0191011.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191011.ref012">12</a>]. Climate change will also likely influence krill through processes beyond growth such as recruitment and natural mortality (e.g. [
  <a rid="pone.0191011.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191011.ref009">9</a>]), and outcomes may differ across life-history stages [
  <a rid="pone.0191011.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191011.ref029">29</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition, climate change may have direct impacts on the krill-dependent predators themselves, potentially via a variety of physical drivers, such as changes in sea ice (e.g. [
  <a rid="pone.0191011.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191011.ref030">30</a>]), snowfall [
  <a rid="pone.0191011.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191011.ref039">39</a>], and warmer conditions (e.g. [
  <a rid="pone.0191011.ref040" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191011.ref040">40</a>]), with consequences for life history and behavior (e.g., [
  <a rid="pone.0191011.ref032" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191011.ref032">32</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0191011.ref041" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191011.ref041">41</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0191011.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191011.ref042">42</a>]). Outcomes are likely to vary by species and location, will depend on the ability of a species to adapt, and may be confounded by current or previous human harvesting [
  <a rid="pone.0191011.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191011.ref029">29</a>]. Overall, climate-change outcomes will be more complicated than those we project here, and are likely to be generally negative for krill-dependent ecosystems [
  <a rid="pone.0191011.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191011.ref009">9</a>] (but see [
  <a rid="pone.0191011.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191011.ref012">12</a>]).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In terms of fishing, simulated here at the current catch limit and the recent spatial distribution of effort, overall estimated risks were low, on par with those for RCP 2.6. The main exception was for seals, which had zero depletion risk attributable to RCP 2.6 but c. 8% attributable to fishing. The longer fishing period and more recent effort distribution we modelled resulted in higher average risks to penguins and seals than those estimated by Watters et al. [
  <a rid="pone.0191011.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191011.ref013">13</a>]. In addition, for penguins, we found nonlinear interactions between fishing and the effects of warming when both were implemented in our model, with results indicating a greater increase in depletion risk than in the overall depletion of abundance (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="pone.0191011.t002" href="#pone.0191011.t002">Table 2</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As the outcomes of climate change and fishing are important drivers of change in marine ecosystems, there is great potential for the former to compound the consequences of the latter. Reducing fishing is an important means by which management can reduce this potential in fully- or over-exploited marine ecosystems [
  <a rid="pone.0191011.ref005" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191011.ref005">5</a>]. We explored this issue by investigating whether total cessation of fishing in an underexploited fishery [
  <a rid="pone.0191011.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191011.ref014">14</a>] could offset some of the risks to predators resulting from ocean warming. Total cessation of fishing is a blunt tool to partially mitigate the effects of climate change, with significant costs in terms of lost provisioning services (i.e. fisheries revenue, employment opportunities, and food security). Our results at the system-wide scale suggest fishing cessation would not reduce the risk of CCAMLR failing to meet its technical objective for krill following ocean warming under severe climate change (RCP 8.5). However, simulated stoppages reduced compounded risks to some krill predators, with earlier stoppages resulting in greater risk reductions. The extent of the risk reduction varied with species group and location at smaller spatial scales, where stoppage reduced risk by 20% to 30% for some penguin populations, but made little difference to others.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Whether or not curtailing fishing is an effective mitigation measure depends on the time an ecosystem takes to recover from the effects of fishing. Previous simulations with this model suggest that different species groups recover at different rates following the cessation of krill fishing [
  <a rid="pone.0191011.ref027" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191011.ref027">27</a>]. Our projections to the end of the current century also suggest such outcomes (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0191011.s004" href="#pone.0191011.s004">S4 Fig</a>). Fish quickly returned to unimpacted levels following a cessation of fishing, but end points for penguins varied depending on when fishing stopped. It is unclear how long it might take all predator groups to recover fully, but our results suggest the potential for lasting effects that compound outcomes of warming long after fishing has ended. This is an area for future research.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The current krill catch limit and spatial distribution of fishing effort imply risk to some krill predators even in the absence of warming, but many predator populations were unaffected by simulated fishing. This suggests that maintaining the current catch limit and preventing any further spatial concentration of effort would help to balance ecosystem services and avoid exacerbating the ecosystem impacts of warming. Regardless, our results provide several insights for managing fishing in the face of future climate change. First, effective management needs to address a range of spatial scales [
  <a rid="pone.0191011.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191011.ref043">43</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0191011.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191011.ref044">44</a>]. Second, there is a need to identify vulnerable predator populations, for example using remote sensing of penguin colonies [
  <a rid="pone.0191011.ref041" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191011.ref041">41</a>], and devise targeted management measures to protect them. Finally, disparity in both the risks posed by fishing and the potential for a cessation of fishing to reduce risks indicates that spatially structured management may simultaneously mitigate risks for the most vulnerable populations while relaxing constraints on the krill fishery where populations are more robust. Doing so might provide flexibility for balancing trade-offs between ecosystem services that regional-scale policies may not.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">CCAMLR’s management approach includes spatial measures and a desire for feedback-management [
  <a rid="pone.0191011.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191011.ref014">14</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0191011.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191011.ref015">15</a>], tactics that exemplify best practices in regional fisheries management [
  <a rid="pone.0191011.ref045" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191011.ref045">45</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0191011.ref046" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0191011.ref046">46</a>]. Targeted actions might therefore include fine-scale catch restrictions, which could vary in response to ecosystem monitoring data. As predator populations are influenced by processes occurring elsewhere in the Antarctic ecosystem and beyond, further investigation will be necessary to identify the appropriate locations for such targeted measures. These investigations might also identify locations where catch limits can be relaxed without increasing risks to predators. However, our results also imply that the risks for krill and their predators resulting from ocean warming cannot fully be offset by stopping fishing.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We aimed to understand how a warming global ocean under climate change may influence a regional social-ecological system, and conclude that future management of such systems must account for spatial heterogeneity in risk. Our results point to the potential utility of spatial and feedback management to mitigate outcomes for the most vulnerable populations, while maintaining other ecosystem services important for people. Management under shifting conditions in the future will be challenging, but current mandates, governance structures, and research in the Antarctic support novel endeavors to ensure management effectiveness, and CCAMLR has an opportunity to lead the way on effectively balancing ecosystem services in a changing climate.</p>
</sec>
