<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In the Mediterranean, coralligenous assemblages are one of the most affected habitats by climate change. Coralligenous assemblages are biogenic formations built by the growth of crustose coralline algae and diverse calcareous macroinvertebrates at low irradiance levels and are characterized by their great structural complexity and species richness (harbouring ~10% of marine Mediterranean species) (Ballesteros, 
 <xref rid="ece35045-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2006</xref>). Most of the structural species of these habitats exhibit slow population dynamics and long life spans (+100 years; Garrabou &amp; Harmelin, 
 <xref rid="ece35045-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2002</xref>; Linares, Doak, Coma, Diaz, &amp; Zabala, 
 <xref rid="ece35045-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>; Teixidó, Garrabou, &amp; Harmelin, 
 <xref rid="ece35045-bib-0064" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>); therefore, they are very sensitive to disturbances, including climate change (Balata, Piazzi, &amp; Benedetti‐Cecchi, 
 <xref rid="ece35045-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>; Ferrigno, Appolloni, Russo, &amp; Sandulli, 
 <xref rid="ece35045-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2018</xref>; Garrabou et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35045-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>; Montero‐Serra et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35045-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). In fact, more than 30 coralligenous species from different phyla and different structural roles have been affected in various mass mortality events (hereafter MMEs) associated with Mediterranean heat waves, suffering extensive tissue necrosis (partial and total mortality) and long‐term population declines (Cerrano et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35045-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2000</xref>; Crisci, Bensoussan, Romano, &amp; Garrabou, 
 <xref rid="ece35045-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>; Garrabou et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35045-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>; Garrabou, Perez, Sartoretto, &amp; Harmelin, 
 <xref rid="ece35045-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2001</xref>; Linares et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35045-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2005</xref>). Moreover, for some key habitat‐forming species, these population declines have been shown to potentially drive detrimental effects at the community level, such as the reduction of structural complexity and resilience (Linares et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35045-bib-0038" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2017</xref>; Ponti et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35045-bib-0056" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). However, while some species have been massively and recurrently affected during these warming events, other taxonomically and morpho‐functionally related organisms seem to remain unaffected, triggering the question of whether there could be different levels of thermal sensitivity within these communities in the context of climate change. This could have further implications for the future composition of these habitats and the loss (or maintenance) of the many associated functions and services they provide.
</p>
