<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="gcb13988-fig-0001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
 <label class="label">Figure 1</label>
 <caption class="caption">
  <p class="p">Clarifying land‐use terminology. Clarifying basic terminology in terms of land‐use change and land‐cover change is essential given that these terms are not always used consistently in the climate change and land system science communities. Land cover is defined as the sum of all land surface properties at a given location (e.g., biophysical, morphological, topographical) and typically described by vegetation and soil characteristics at that location. Land cover is often categorized in broad land‐cover classes (e.g., forest, grassland, bare ground), which can be subdivided into more detailed classes (e.g., deciduous forest, coniferous forest, mixed forest). Land‐cover maps can provide one class label or a continuous class proportion (e.g., % tree cover) for each gridcell. Land use relates to the purposes or functions that humans assign to a given location and how humans interact with the land. Land use is also typically categorized in broad classes (e.g., forestry, grazing, cropping). Land management refers to the land‐use practices that take place within these broader land‐use classes (e.g., sowing, fertilizing, weeding, harvesting, thinning, clear‐cutting). Land‐use change over time then refers to either (a) conversions among broad land‐use classes (e.g., agricultural expansion) or (b) changes in land management within these classes (e.g., agricultural intensification). Importantly, both types of land‐use changes can result in either (i) land‐cover conversion from one class to another (e.g., forest loss), or (ii) in more subtle changes in ecosystem properties (e.g., forest degradation), denoted as land‐cover modifications. Some previous studies and reviews (e.g., Erb, Luyssaert, et al., 
   <xref rid="gcb13988-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>; Luyssaert et al., 
   <xref rid="gcb13988-bib-0069" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>) used simplified terminology, assuming that land‐use conversion always lead to land‐cover conversion, and land management changes to land‐cover modifications. While this is often the case, it is important to note that the terms land cover and land use are not congruent, as land management can lead to land‐cover conversions (e.g., wood harvesting resulting in the full clear‐cutting of forest), and land‐use conversion can happen without drastic changes in land cover (e.g., putting livestock on natural grasslands)
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic id="nlm-graphic-3" xlink:href="GCB-24-1470-g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
