<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In order to explore whether the structure of the anuran beta diversity is expected to change under climate change, we decomposed the Jaccard dissimilarity coefficient into replacement and nestedness components (i.e., the replacement and nestedness index of the Baselga‐family, presence‐absence data, sensu Legendre, 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0030" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). Therefore, we aimed to check whether and which of the beta diversity components (the species turnover among sites or the nested pattern characterized by the species at a site being a strict subset of the species at a richer site) are presumed to vary in future climate change scenarios. Since the replacement (Repl) and nestedness (Nes) indices equal the dissimilarity (D) index, and that the similarity (S) index equals 1 – D, we are following Podani and Schmera (
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0048" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>) and Podani, Ricotta, and Schmera (
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>) and are representing the triplets of values (S, Repl, Nes) in a triangular graph for each time slice and hotspot (see also Legendre, 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0030" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). Each triplet sums to 1 and the central dot is the centroid of the points, so the graphics illustrate the main beta diversity component structuring the anuran community at each time slice. The determination of LCBD indices and decomposition of beta diversity into replacement and nestedness components were performed in R with the scripts provided by Legendre and De Cáceres (
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>) and Legendre (
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0030" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>), whereas the triangular graphs were generated using the ade4 package (Chessel, Dufour, &amp; Thioulouse, 
 <xref rid="ece34357-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2004</xref>).
</p>
