<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The downscaled climate projections on a daily scale were further temporally aggregated on a monthly timescale, and then spatially interpolated by considering the proximity to the ocean, and other geographic influences on climate to a spatial resolution of 10 x 10 km. The information from the spatial interpolations was aggregated at the administrative unit (department and province). To link the climatological information with the household information, average values at the province level were ultimately used. In the simulations of vulnerability with climate change, average values for the 5 years centered around 2050 (2048–2052) were used to capture climate trends and not inter-annual climate variability. Therefore, the correct interpretation of the simulations is: What would the impact on food vulnerability be in Peru if it faces today the climate that we expect to see towards 2050? In the exposition below, we present the tables of modeling and simulations derived from the CanESM2 climate model and for the RCP 4.5 and 8.5 scenarios of moderate and high GHG emissions growth. However, all six models and their related tables are available in supplementary tables (see 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0222483.s010">S9</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0222483.s011">S10</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0222483.s012">S11</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0222483.s013">S12</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0222483.s014">S13</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0222483.s015">S14</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0222483.s016">S15</xref> Tables), and; also below, we present mean and inter-model variability, across the six climate scenarios, for the main results discussed. Further, climate estimates towards 2050 for all three ESMs are also available in the 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0222483.s007">S6</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0222483.s008">S7</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0222483.s009">S8</xref> Tables.
</p>
