<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In China, desertification area survey was conducted once every five years since 1994. Desertification lands occupy an area about 2.61 million km
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> and spread across 18 provinces accounting for 27.20% of the country’s land area by 2014
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12" class="xref">12</xref>. This survey takes a lot of manpower, material and financial resources with a lack of sequential dynamic monitoring. In this study, a remote sensing method was used to obtain the aeolian desertification land distribution in northern China. A new spectral index called Normalized Difference Desertification Index (NDDI) derived from MODIS surface reflectance data was used to acquire the aeolian desertification land distribution. Results will provide a basis for combating desertification. In northern China, natural vegetation is being transformed into agricultural lands at a faster rate, endangering ecosystem services and increasing soil-loss potential, which may trigger land degradation. This region is sensitive to climate change and human intervention. It becomes an original region of sandstorms. To alleviate the multifaceted environmental degradation, Chinese government has implemented several ecological restoration programs that have deeply affected the structure and function of grassland ecosystems. Understanding desertification processes and causes are important to provide reasonable and effective control measures for preventing desertification. The study area of this paper is located in northern China (31°09′N- 53°23′N, 73°40′E- 126°04′E) (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1" class="xref">Fig. 1</xref>). It includes Xinjiang Uyghur Autonomous Region, Qinghai Province, Gansu Province, Ningxia Hui Autonomous Region and Inner Mongolia Autonomous Region with eight famous deserts in China. Generally, a semi-arid or desert climate prevails in Xinjiang. The entire region is marked by great seasonal differences in temperature. This region includes Gurban Tunggut Desert, Taklamakan Desert and Kumtag Desert. Qinghai has quite cold winters, mild summers, and a large diurnal temperature variation. Significant rainfall occurs mainly in summer, while precipitation is very low in winter and spring, and is generally low enough to keep much of the province semi-arid or arid. This region includes Qaidam Basin Desert. Gansu generally has a semi-arid to arid continental climate with warm to hot summers and cold to very cold winters. Most of the limited precipitation is delivered in the summer months. This region includes Badain Jaran Desert, Tengger Desert and Kumtag Desert. Ningxia Hui Autonomous Region has a continental climate with average summer temperatures rising to 17 to 24 °C in July and average winter temperatures dropping to between −7 to −15 °C in January. Annual rainfall averages from 190 to 700 millimetres, with more rain falling in the south of the region. This region includes Tengger Desert in Shapotou. Inner Mongolia has a wide variety of regional climates. The winters in Inner Mongolia are very long, cold and dry. The spring is short, mild and arid, with large, dangerous sandstorms, whilst the summer is very warm to hot and relatively humid except in the west where it remains dry. Autumn is brief and sees a steady cooling, with temperatures below 0 °C reached in October in the north and November in the south. It includes Badain Jaran Desert, Tengger Desert, Kubuqi Desert and Ulan Buh Desert.
</p>
