<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">From 2012 through fall of 2018, 13 New Hampshire surveys with a combined total of 7,707 interviews carried the renewable-energy question, as did four northeast Oregon surveys (2011–2018) with 3,782 interviews. 
 <bold class="bold">
  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217608.g005" class="xref">Fig 5</xref>
 </bold> tracks these regional-survey results, along with results on the same question from the POLES and North Country surveys. Unlike Figs 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217608.g001" class="xref">1</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217608.g004" class="xref">4</xref> which depict only the most recent years of each project, 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217608.g005" class="xref">Fig 5</xref> and subsequent graphs employ all available data for the analysis shown. The number of observations fluctuates, because some questions were not asked on some surveys. The upper line in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0217608.g005" class="xref">Fig 5</xref>, drifting up about 21 points, tracks the percentage of New Hampshire respondents who prioritize renewable energy. The lower line shows an upward drift of about 14 points among northeast Oregon respondents. Nationwide results from the POLES surveys (1,411 interviews) appear slightly lower than contemporary New Hampshire results; North Country results (1,650 interviews) match New Hampshire almost exactly. Error bars depict the 95 percent confidence intervals for each survey. We see minor survey-to-survey variations, within the range of sampling error, but the main visual impression is how stable percentages appear, from one survey to the next. Their short-term stability reflects use of consistent sampling and interview methods, repeating a straightforward question. An earlier paper based on Oregon data through 2015 and New Hampshire through 2017 observed similar upward trends,[
 <xref rid="pone.0217608.ref023" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>] which are now seen continuing in these longer time series.
</p>
