<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2.1.</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Areas of Endemism at Subregional Scale</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The general topology based on distributions of the 105 species revealed three main branches: the DXMS, the Palaearctic subregions, and the Oriental subregions. Among them, the DXMS has only the one species, 
  <span class="italic">Garrulax davidi</span>. It is very probable that such little information caused this branch to separate from the other Palaearctic subregions. Except this branch, the subregional topology generally reflects the accepted division between the Palaearctic and Oriental realms in China [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b3-ijms-11-02097" href="#b3-ijms-11-02097">3</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b4-ijms-11-02097" href="#b4-ijms-11-02097">4</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">By using the PAE method, four avian AOEs at subregional level, 
  <span class="italic">i.e.,</span> the Qinghai-Zangnan Subregion (AOE1), the Southwest Mountainous Subregion (AOE2), the Hainan Subregion (AOE3), and the Taiwan Subregion (AOE4) were identified (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f1-ijms-11-02097" href="#f1-ijms-11-02097">Figure 1</a>). The Qinghai-Zangnan Subregion extends from the north Qilianshan mountains of northeastern Qinghai Province southward to Changdu and encompasses central and eastern regions of the Himalayan Mountains, including the Yaluzangbu valley of Tibetan Autonomous Region. Typical habitats in this area are montane forest (coniferous and broad-leaved), meadow and meadow-steppe. The Southwest Mountainous Subregion encompasses the western areas of Yunnan and Sichuan provinces and mostly covers the Hengduan mountain areas. Its typical habitats are mountain meadow and mountain forest with obvious altitudinal variation. The Hainan Subregion is confined to the Hainan Island. The typical habitat is tropical monsoon rain forest. The Taiwan Subregion is confined to the Taiwan Island and its offshore islands. Typical habitats are tropical monsoon rain forest and subtropical ever-green broad-leaved forest.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although the Qinghai-Zangnan Subregion and the Southwest Mountainous Subregion are geographically contiguous on the southeast Tibetan Plateau, they are in two distinct separated branches in the tree, which is consistent with the division between the Palaearctic and Oriental realms [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b3-ijms-11-02097" href="#b3-ijms-11-02097">3</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b4-ijms-11-02097" href="#b4-ijms-11-02097">4</a>]. The Qinghai-Zangnan Subregion is a mountainous area with habitats ranging from high mountain forests to meadow and steppe [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b4-ijms-11-02097" href="#b4-ijms-11-02097">4</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b32-ijms-11-02097" href="#b32-ijms-11-02097">32</a>]. Apart from the local endemics, which defined this AOE, 
  <span class="italic">G. sukatschewi</span>, 
  <span class="italic">K. roborowskii</span>, 
  <span class="italic">B. koslowi</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Urocynchramus pylzowi</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Emberiza koslowi</span> are also mostly restricted to this subregion. The Southwest Mountainous Subregion is also a mountainous area in the subtropical zone with high mountain ranges and deep valleys such as the Yaluzangbu Valley [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b3-ijms-11-02097" href="#b3-ijms-11-02097">3</a>]. Besides the endemics restricted to this AOE, 
  <span class="italic">A. rufipectus</span>, 
  <span class="italic">M. poecilotis</span>, 
  <span class="italic">G. bieti</span>, 
  <span class="italic">L. omeiensis</span>, 
  <span class="italic">P. zappeyi</span>, 
  <span class="italic">P. emeienses</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Arborophila rufipectus</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Lophophorus sclateri</span>, 
  <span class="italic">Crossoptilon harmani</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Moupinia poecilotis</span> are also mostly confined to this subregion. AOEs are important areas for understanding fauna evolution, which has been determined by historical and ecological factors. For these two adjacent AOEs, they have related but discrepant geological history. As part of the uplift of the Tibetan Plateau and the Himalayas region, which began in the Late Cenozoic [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b32-ijms-11-02097" href="#b32-ijms-11-02097">32</a>], the Qinghai-Zangnan region has been formed due to the recent and violent uplift (less than 2.5 million years ago). Harsh environmental pressures during this uplift mainly determined the fauna evolution in this region [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b15-ijms-11-02097" href="#b15-ijms-11-02097">15</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b33-ijms-11-02097" href="#b33-ijms-11-02097">33</a>]. However, the Southwest Mountainous region has much longer geological history and was more stable during this geological event [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b4-ijms-11-02097" href="#b4-ijms-11-02097">4</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b32-ijms-11-02097" href="#b32-ijms-11-02097">32</a>]. The differences between geological history, topography and ecological factors may determine this different endemic avian fauna of the two AOEs, with the inferred hypothesis that historical and ecological vicariant events may act as important factors in shaping this deep divergence between the two AOEs.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The other two AOEs, the Hainan and Taiwan subregions, are islands with typical mountainous habitats in the southern subtropical, northern and middle tropical zones. Mountains in the Hainan subregion are relatively low, the highest peak, Wuzhishan, is less than 2,000 m, and the average temperature is &gt;25 °C. The Taiwan Subregion is more geographically isolated by the wider Taiwan Strait. Its western coastal areas are plains, but eastern and central parts are mountainous, with the highest mountain in southeastern China, Mt Yushan (3,997 m) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b3-ijms-11-02097" href="#b3-ijms-11-02097">3</a>]. Fifteen endemic species restricted to this region defined this AOE. For these two AOEs, especially for the Taiwan subregion, species diversification after geological isolation from the mainland may contribute to its current endemic avian fauna. Grey-cheeked Fulvetta (
  <span class="italic">Alcippe morrisonia</span>) populations [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b34-ijms-11-02097" href="#b34-ijms-11-02097">34</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b35-ijms-11-02097" href="#b35-ijms-11-02097">35</a>] and Hwamei (
  <span class="italic">Garrulax canorus</span>) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b36-ijms-11-02097" href="#b36-ijms-11-02097">36</a>], for example, are well confirmed due to this isolation between island and mainland through a phylogeographical approach.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All the four AOEs have large part of mountainous habitats, which suggests that mountainous environment may act as “historical and ecological barriers” preventing population gene flow, promoting speciation and maintaining a high endemism [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b5-ijms-11-02097" href="#b5-ijms-11-02097">5</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b37-ijms-11-02097" href="#b37-ijms-11-02097">37</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b38-ijms-11-02097" href="#b38-ijms-11-02097">38</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
