<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The species list was derived from those recorded in Carajás, currently one of the biologically best known areas in the SE Amazonia due to over three decades of periodic inventories and sporadic observations [
 <xref rid="pone.0215229.ref029" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0215229.ref030" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>]. It was updated from Vale’s internal database (
 <italic class="italic">bdbio</italic>), internet repositories (e.g., 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://wikiaves.com.br" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://wikiaves.com.br</ext-link> and 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://xeno-canto.org" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://xeno-canto.org</ext-link>) and Museu Paraense Emilio Goeldi ornithological collection, achieving 620 species. The projections and analysis focuses mainly on SE Amazonia, an area between the right margin of Tapajós and Juruena Rivers (59°W) and the Amazonia east limit (44°W), and from Marajó island (0°) to the Amazonia south limit (14°S). The south and east limits of this area correspond to the Amazonia-Cerrado transition zone, encompassing FT and OAV environments, and it is naturally close to the climatic limit of tropical forests [
 <xref rid="pone.0215229.ref031" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0215229.ref032" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>]. In fact, several climate model simulations confirm that SE Amazonia is the most sensitive region to global climate change [
 <xref rid="pone.0215229.ref033" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0215229.ref034" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>] and it has the most deforested area and the highest deforestation rates considering all Amazonia [
 <xref rid="pone.0215229.ref022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>]. It is important to mention that our set of species corresponds to 
 <italic class="italic">ca</italic>. 63% of the total known avian taxa of the focal area, and, although some avifauna turnover may occur between the interfluves of major rivers, most species have wide distributions and less than 1% represent taxa exclusively endemic to the respective interfluves. In addition, the list includes FT and OAV species, which allow testing if and how these groups will potentially respond differently to climate changes. Moreover, to assess changes in ecosystem functioning, we also assign each species to one of three trophic guilds based on the main diet of the species [
 <xref rid="pone.0215229.ref028" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>]: frugivores (FR [seed dispersion]), insectivores (IN [pest control]) and nectarivores (NE [pollination]). Species with other diets (e.g., omnivores, granivores, carnivores, and scavengers) were assigned as "others" (OT).
</p>
