<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p content-type="flushleft" class="p">Satellite altimeter data collected since 1993 have measured a rise in global mean sea level (GMSL) of ∼3 ± 0.4 mm/y (
 <xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>), resulting in more than 7 cm of total sea-level rise over the last 25 y. This rate of sea-level rise is expected to accelerate as the melting of the ice sheets and ocean heat content increases as greenhouse gas concentrations rise. Acceleration of sea-level rise over the 20th century has already been inferred from tide-gauge data (
 <xref rid="r3" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>
 <xref rid="r4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref"/>–
 <xref rid="r5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>), although sampling and data issues preclude a precise quantification. The satellite altimeter record of sea-level change from TOPEX/Poseidon, Jason-1, Jason-2, and Jason-3 is now approaching 25 y in length, making it possible to begin probing the record for climate-change–driven acceleration of the rate of GMSL change (
 <xref rid="r6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>). Unlike tide-gauge data, these retrievals sample the open ocean and allow for precise quantitative statements regarding global sea level. However, detecting acceleration is difficult because of (
 <italic class="italic">i</italic>) interannual variability in GMSL largely driven by changes in terrestrial water storage (TWS) (
 <xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>
 <xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref"/>–
 <xref rid="r9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>), (
 <italic class="italic">ii</italic>) decadal variability in TWS (
 <xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>), thermosteric sea level, and ice sheet mass loss (
 <xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>) that might masquerade as a long-term acceleration over a 25-y record, (
 <italic class="italic">iii</italic>) episodic variability driven by large volcanic eruptions (
 <xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>), and (
 <italic class="italic">iv</italic>) errors in the altimeter data, in particular, potential drifts in the instruments over time (
 <xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>). With careful attention to each of these issues, however, a preliminary satellite-based estimate of the climate-change–driven acceleration of sea-level rise can be obtained. This estimate is useful for understanding how the Earth is responding to warming, and thus better informs us of how it might change in the future.
</p>
