<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Finally, we must also consider the impact of decadal variability in GMSL on acceleration estimates derived from a 25-y record. While estimates of the impact of decadal variability on the 25-y-long time series are difficult to obtain (
 <xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>), satellite altimetry is far less sensitive to decadal variability than tide-gauge measurements (
 <xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>) because of its superior global coverage. Estimates of decadal variability from tide-gauge data (
 <xref rid="r18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>) are uncertain due to their poor geographic sampling and other effects, so estimates must be assembled from measurements of the contributions to GMSL including TWS (
 <xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>), the cryosphere (
 <xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>), and thermosteric sea-level change (
 <xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>). We have removed most of the impact of changes in TWS, but allow 0.01-mm/y
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> residual impact on the acceleration (based on ref. 
 <xref rid="r10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>). Estimates of the decadal variability in ice sheet mass loss (
 <xref rid="r11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>) suggest the impact on acceleration estimates is ∼0.014 mm/y
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> for a 25-y time series, in the absence of rapid dynamical changes in the ice sheets. The impact of decadal variability in thermosteric sea level was estimated at 0.01 mm/y
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> using a control run for the National Center for Atmospheric Research (NCAR) Large Ensemble (LE) (
 <xref rid="r21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>). We also include an estimate from the NCAR LE of the impact of decadal variability in precipitable water in the atmosphere, which can impact GMSL. Therefore, a conservative estimate of the total impact of decadal variability on our acceleration estimate is the root sum square (RSS) of these contributions, which is 0.017 mm/y
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>.
</p>
