<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Many plant species are migrating in response to ongoing changes in climate and additional shifts in geographic ranges are expected in the future, though the rates of movement will likely vary substantially with growth form (e.g., herbaceous vs. woody plants; 
 <xref rid="B45" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">IPCC, 2014</xref>). For species in montane environments, recent climate change-induced shifts in species distributions toward higher elevations have been documented in temperate and tropical locations (
 <xref rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Benavides et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Dolezal et al., 2016</xref>). Over the past 100–200 years, many non-native (i.e., introduced or alien) species have colonized high altitude environments (
 <xref rid="B72" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Pyšek et al., 2011</xref>) and in several temperate mountain ranges in North America and Europe, non-native species appear to be migrating to higher elevations to a greater degree than native species (
 <xref rid="B100" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Wolf et al., 2016</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Dainese et al., 2017</xref>). These findings suggest that, at least along elevation gradients, non-native species have higher migration potentials than native species, though this may depend upon levels of disturbance and local habitat heterogeneity (
 <xref rid="B88" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Suding et al., 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Averett et al., 2016</xref>). This upward migration of species inevitably exposes plants to novel combinations of biotic and abiotic environmental conditions, including ultraviolet (UV) radiation (280–400 nm), with the potential for significant negative impacts on native alpine biodiversity (
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Chapin and Körner, 1994</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B83" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Savage and Vellend, 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Cuyckens et al., 2016</xref>).
</p>
