<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Leishmaniasis is transmitted by the bite of Phlebotomine sandflies and is caused by obligate parasite protozoa of the genus 
 <italic class="italic">Leishmania</italic> [
 <xref rid="pone.0183583.ref018" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>]. These parasites have complex life cycles involving multiple insect vectors and mammalian reservoir species [
 <xref rid="pone.0183583.ref018" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0183583.ref019" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>]. Infection results in wide ranging symptoms, dependent on 
 <italic class="italic">Leishmania</italic> species, with the two main outcomes being cutaneous leishmaniasis (CL, 0.7–1.2 million annual cases, [
 <xref rid="pone.0183583.ref020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]) where skin lesions develop around the bite site and visceral leishmaniasis (VL, 0.2–0.4 million annual cases, [
 <xref rid="pone.0183583.ref020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]) that affects the spleen, liver and other lymphoid tissues and can be fatal if left untreated. A particularly debilitating cutaneous form is mucosal or mucocutaneous leishmaniasis (~4% of cutaneous cases in the Americas [
 <xref rid="pone.0183583.ref021" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>]) which attacks the mucous membranes of the nose, mouth and throat cavities and surrounding tissues and can cause mutilation, disabilities and livelihood impacts if not treated in a timely manner. Collectively, the leishmaniases have huge impact, ranking ninth amongst individual infectious disease burdens globally, with around a 10% death rate [
 <xref rid="pone.0183583.ref020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>]. In particular, VL ranks third amongst vector-borne diseases in the number of Disability Adjusted Life Years (number of years lost due to ill-health, disability or early death from a disease) attributed to it (2005 and 2013, [
 <xref rid="pone.0183583.ref022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>])
</p>
