<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In the Americas, VL is linked with zoonotic peri-domestic cycles with dogs as the main reservoir and foxes and jackals as a sylvatic reservoir [
 <xref rid="pone.0183583.ref023" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>] [
 <xref rid="pone.0183583.ref024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>]. CL is linked to zoonotic, sylvatic cycles involving a wide diversity of wild mammal reservoirs (rodents and large mammals) and sandfly species [
 <xref rid="pone.0183583.ref019" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0183583.ref023" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>]. Socio-economic factors and ecosystem changes have been linked to impacts of both disease forms, including urbanisation, deforestation, agricultural intensification (dams and irrigation, new crops), human settlement (including migration from rural to urban areas), poverty [
 <xref rid="pone.0183583.ref015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>] and marginalisation [
 <xref rid="pone.0183583.ref023" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0183583.ref025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0183583.ref030" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>]. The precise roles of wild and domestic hosts and different sandfly species in transmission is unquantified for most 
 <italic class="italic">Leishmania</italic> parasites and contexts [
 <xref rid="pone.0183583.ref018" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0183583.ref019" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>]. However, Wood et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0183583.ref006" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>] cite the New World 
 <italic class="italic">Leishmania</italic> species causing the cutaneous disease form (e.g. 
 <italic class="italic">Leishmania braziliensis</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Leishmania guayanensis</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Leishmania</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">panamensis</italic>), as examples of parasites that are associated geographically with undisturbed ecosystems because they depend on reservoir mammal hosts that are more abundant in undisturbed than in disturbed habitats. By contrast, the visceral leishmaniasis parasite in the Americas, 
 <italic class="italic">Leishmania infantum</italic>, was originally a zoonotic rural infection but has spread into urban and peri-urban areas because of both domestic dog reservoirs and the adaptable sandfly vector, 
 <italic class="italic">Lutzomyia longipalpis</italic>, can utilise anthropogenic habitats [
 <xref rid="pone.0183583.ref025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. Wood et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0183583.ref006" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>] thus predict that cutaneous leishmaniasis impacts will be positively associated with intact ecosystems and biodiversity whilst the converse will be true of visceral leishmaniasis.
</p>
