<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec014" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Supplemental feeding is about increasing food availability at a local level and is often targeted for particular species, like the Buff-throated Partridge. Our goal was to assess the effects of year-round supplemental feeding on the breeding ecology and reproductive success of the Buff-throated Partridges fed at the Tibetan sacred site on Pamuling Mountain.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The single most common effect of supplemental feeding is earlier breeding, an advancement of laying dates, which effectively increases the length of the breeding season [
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref013">13</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref014">14</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref016">16</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref018" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref018">18</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref020">20</a>]. The fed partridges we studied showed a significant shift to early breeding (
  <a rid="pone.0146568.t001" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0146568.t001">Table 1</a>) with a mean advancement of 19 days over nonfed groups with 
  <span class="italic">all</span> the fed groups laying earlier than 86% of the nonfed groups. Compare this with a four-year study of Tibetan Eared Pheasants (
  <span class="italic">Crossoptilon harmani</span>) which received supplemental food (highland barley) from late autumn until the start of incubation in late spring at a Buddhist nunnery near Llasa, Tibet [
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref005" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref005">5</a>]. Compared to nonfed pheasants living in the same area, the fed pheasants showed an average advancement of laying dates of only two days, which was not significant [
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref005" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref005">5</a>]. Early laying “buys more time” for second clutches, such as renesting after clutch failure [
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref016">16</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref022">22</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref023">23</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref030">30</a>]. For the fed partridges, the six females with failed clutches all renested compared to one out of five for nonfed groups (
  <a rid="pone.0146568.t001" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0146568.t001">Table 1</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Early laying can lead to an early finish of the breeding season, which would give the parents more time to molt and recover fat reserves before winter [
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref018" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref018">18</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref021">21</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref022">22</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref071" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref071">71</a>]. We observed that out of the 27 fed groups, the 18 groups (67%) that bred early and did not renest had significantly more time than nonfed groups, thus giving the fed female breeders the time and resources for a complete molt before winter. In contrast, a late breeding female may have to shorten her molting period, which may leave her with a cheap, poorly insulated ‘coat’, which will generate increased thermoregulatory costs and, therefore, greater risk of mortality as this bird moves into winter [
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref018" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref018">18</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref071" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref071">71</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Perhaps, the most compelling advantage of early laying is that 
  <span class="italic">fledglings produced by early breeders survive better than fledglings produced later</span> [
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref024" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref024">24</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref072" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref072">72</a>]. The increasing mortality rate of young hatched later in the season suggests strong selection for early nesting [
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref044">44</a>]. Young hatched early in the season are likely to be larger and more experienced and, therefore, often dominant over later hatched young, and will likely have an advantage competing for resources and for positions in winter groups [
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref018" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref018">18</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref022">22</a>]. Offspring from first nests would be the oldest members of their cohort and could establish a level of dominance that promotes their ascendancy to breeder status [
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref030">30</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref073" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref073">73</a>]. The high reproductive value of early hatched young selects for early laying [
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref018" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref018">18</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref020">20</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref022">22</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Young hatching earlier have a much higher chance of surviving and demonstrate greater reproductive value [
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref022">22</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref024" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref024">24</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref030">30</a>]; therefore, a more useful statistic is the relative number of independent young hatched earlier from fed versus nonfed groups. The earlier breeding fed groups not only produced significantly more young, but the most important difference was that 80% of fed young hatched earlier than any nonfed young (
  <a rid="pone.0146568.t008" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0146568.t008">Table 8</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">What are the limits of earlier advancement of laying? If early laying buys time, what does it cost? On Pamuling Mountain, even with supplemental food, attempting to lay in early April or into March is moving into the end of winter, when it is still quite cold and late snowstorms still happen. We examined the reproductive costs of pushing the limits of how early the partridge bred by comparing success among four different sets of groups: the earliest fed groups (Mar 27-Apr 11); the later laying fed groups (Apr 12–19); the earliest laying nonfed groups (Apr 13–26); and the later laying nonfed groups (Apr 27-May 12). We focused on hatching rates because that stage was most likely to be affected by the conditions during incubation. Because the earliest fed groups suffered more losses and lower hatching rates than the later fed groups and were not clearly any more successful than the earliest nonfed groups, was their higher effort and risk worth it? The benefits of an early timing of breeding can be quantified only when considering also the post-fledging period [
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref074" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref074">74</a>]. We do know that the four fed groups with clutch failures all renested with three producing independent young and that the 12 early independent young hatched in the earliest breeding fed groups may well have had greater reproductive value than the later hatched young of all the later laying groups [
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref044">44</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Lack of available food is most likely the greatest constraint against early breeding [
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref014">14</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref021">21</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref022">22</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref030">30</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref032" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref032">32</a>]. Due to the length and cold of the high altitude winter, the availability of natural foods is low in winter, and high protein foods are likely to be at their lowest at the end of winter and beginning of spring just when early partridge breeders would face their greatest needs.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For precocial species like the partridge, the highest energy and nutritional demands are during egg-laying when their daily expenditure for the production of clutches is greater than for altricial species [
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref016">16</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref025" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref025">25</a>]. The high energy demands of laying are followed next by incubation when the breeding females must spend nearly all of their time at the nest sitting on the clutch to protect the eggs from cold and predators. While they are incubating, they have little time to forage, relying instead on their fat reserves [
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref016">16</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref037">37</a>]. To be able to provide that high level of energy into the first two stages of breeding, female pheasant species, such as grouse, ptarmigans, and these partridges, need to be in good condition with sufficient fat reserves 
  <span class="italic">before</span> they begin to lay their first clutch in early spring [
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref016">16</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref037">37</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref075" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref075">75</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref076" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref076">76</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Along with stimulating early breeding in birds, supplemental feeding before and during the breeding season may lead to production of larger clutches and larger eggs [
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref022">22</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref030">30</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref077" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref077">77</a>]. Both represent greater investments by the female breeder to increase the number and survivability of the young. The fed female partridge breeders significantly increased clutch size more often from three to four (
  <a rid="pone.0146568.t003" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0146568.t003">Table 3</a>) and significantly increased the size of their eggs (
  <a rid="pone.0146568.t004" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0146568.t004">Table 4</a>). The greater investment in clutch size and, particularly, in egg size showed that the resources available were abundant enough to support those investments. In particular, the relatively consistent amount of the increase in egg size may have been to improve the size and survivability of their chicks which would be hatching under less than favorable environmental conditions of early spring at that high altitude [
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref028">28</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref044">44</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The first clutch sizes of fed and nonfed birds did not decline over the laying period of the first clutches (Mar 27-May 12)(
  <a rid="pone.0146568.g002" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0146568.g002">Fig 2</a>). The mean egg weight per group did show a slight decline from early to late laying dates for both fed and nonfed groups, but the R
  <span class="sup">2</span> values were very low (
  <a rid="pone.0146568.g002" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0146568.g002">Fig 2</a>). In contrast, the fed partridges’ six renesting clutches were all significantly smaller with smaller egg weights (
  <a rid="pone.0146568.t005" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0146568.t005">Table 5</a>). The reduced sizes of these replacement clutches do appear to fit into the general pattern of seasonal decline in clutch size [
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref024" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref024">24</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref026" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref026">26</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref028">28</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref077" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref077">77</a>]. Larger egg size can produce a larger hatchling, which may give a better chance to survive [
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref028">28</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref044">44</a>]. Smaller egg sizes, in contrast, allow the chick to hatch earlier and may reduce the cost to females [
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref026" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref026">26</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Supplemental feeding also carries some risk associated with a higher density of birds near feeding sites, which is likely to increase competition and may attract predators and increase the risk of predation [
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref013">13</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref014">14</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref030">30</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref049" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref049">49</a>]. The few cases of predation on adult partridges we recorded were at nests, not at feeding sites, and we found no significant difference between fed and nonfed groups.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">With predation being a major risk for ground-dwelling gamebirds [
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref015">15</a>], the partridges in our study engaged in several behaviors to reduce risks from predators. One was communal roosting in trees, in which all members of a group roost together in dense conifer trees, which gives them protection from predators and thermoregulatory benefits through cold nights [
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref052" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref052">52</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref054" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref054">54</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref057" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref057">57</a>]. Another was nesting in trees. While roosting in trees occurs in many gallinaceous species, nesting in trees has been reported only in the Buff-throated Partridge and in the five species of tragopans (
  <span class="italic">Tragopan</span>) [
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref050" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref050">50</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref055" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref055">55</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref056" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref056">56</a>]. In our study, most of the nests were on the ground with just over one-fifth found in trees. Although we found no difference in the use of tree nesting by fed and nonfed groups, we were able to show the first evidence that hatching success of groups that nested in trees was significantly greater than for those groups that nested on the ground (all groups combined, 
  <a rid="pone.0146568.t006" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0146568.t006">Table 6</a>), and the groups nesting in trees showed significantly greater hatching rates compared to groups nesting on the ground both within nonfed groups and within fed groups (
  <a rid="pone.0146568.t006" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0146568.t006">Table 6</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Supplemental feeding increases survival of fed birds; the increase in food availability may free more time for vigilance and reduce exposure to predation [
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref013">13</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref018" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref018">18</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref033">33</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref035">35</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref036">36</a>] as well as more time for resting and preening [
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref005" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref005">5</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref018" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref018">18</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref036">36</a>]. Winter food supplementation increases rates of winter survival of game birds [
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref038">38</a>]. Winter feeding for songbirds (often from fall into early spring) increases productivity in the subsequent breeding season [
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref036">36</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref042">42</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref078" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref078">78</a>]. For populations of two 
  <span class="italic">Parus</span> species in Sweden, food supplementation in autumn and winter improved winter survival, which led to a doubling of the fed breeding populations the following spring [
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref035">35</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Young adult partridges remaining with their parents within the safety of their known territory can gain greater security and experience [
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref078" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref078">78</a>]. At the same time, these young adults benefit the breeding pair by assisting in territorial defense and vigilance for predators and joining in communal roosting [
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref054" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref054">54</a>]; this is the basis of the cooperative breeding shown by Buff-throated Partridges [
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref051" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref051">51</a>]. The mutual fitness benefits of breeding cooperatively are likely to stem from group living per se rather than from alloparental effects [
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref079" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref079">79</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref081" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref081">81</a>], which is why solitary male partridges often join as a helper to a territorial breeding pair [
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref051" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref051">51</a>], and, in addition to the benefits of group living, unrelated male helpers also increase their chances of becoming the dominant breeding male [
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref082" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref082">82</a>]. Such promotion occurred in two of the seven year-to-year cases of fed groups with marked individuals (described in Methods above). Ours is the first study of these cooperative breeding partridges to show that cooperative breeding groups (i.e., breeding groups with adult helpers) experience greater reproductive success than single pairs. Groups with helpers were significantly more likely to produce independent young compared to single pair groups (
  <a rid="pone.0146568.t008" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0146568.t008">Table 8</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Among the partridge cooperative breeding groups, helpers have been observed to contribute to vigilance and territorial defense [
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref051" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref051">51</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref054" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref054">54</a>]. Such assistance by partridge helpers may give the breeding female more time to feed and accumulate greater resources to lay earlier and to invest more in their clutches [
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref078" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref078">78</a>]. We were able to show that among the supplemental fed groups, breeding groups with helpers produced significantly greater mean egg weights compared to single pair groups (
  <a rid="pone.0146568.t009" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0146568.t009">Table 9</a>); however, nonfed groups with helpers did not show a significant difference compared to single pair groups (
  <a rid="pone.0146568.t009" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0146568.t009">Table 9</a>). We suggest that the combined benefits of supplemental feeding and assistance of adult helpers work together to further reduce the workload of a fed female breeder and to increase her time and resources compared to fed single pairs or to nonfed female breeders with helpers.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A related study of cooperative breeding in Arabian babblers (
  <span class="italic">Turdoides squamiceps</span>) showed that helpers with access to supplemental food were able to spend longer periods on sentinel duty without a loss in body mass [
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref083" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref083">83</a>]. That example shows further how the benefits of supplemental feeding can serve to enhance the benefits provided by helpers in a cooperative breeding group. We suggest that for partridge fed groups, supplemental feeding may reduce feeding time for all adult members of cooperative groups, which may further increase vigilance of helpers, thereby further reducing the risk of predation [
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref054" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref054">54</a>]. For a fed female breeder with helpers, the combined benefits may allow her to invest even more in her offspring without significantly increasing her reproductive costs, as shown by the significantly larger eggs produced by fed females in cooperative groups compared to fed females in single pair groups [
  <a rid="pone.0146568.t009" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0146568.t009">Table 9</a>]. We suggest that a more detailed study of vigilance and foraging behaviors of fed cooperative breeding partridge groups would be valuable in many ways.
 </p>
</sec>
