<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec006" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Selection of study groups and possibility of pseudoreplication</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Longitudinal observational studies, such as ours, raise the possibility of pseudoreplication from year to year [
  <a rid="pone.0146568.ref070" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0146568.ref070">70</a>], which assumes “the same groups occur in the same treatments year after year”. Although 35 fed partridges were banded as part of several overlapping field studies, only eight banded birds occurred in fed groups of this study. Those eight were distributed among six fed nesting groups. None of the eight banded birds were present in a breeding group in more than two consecutive years, although identification of repeat individuals allowed one group to be identified in a third year. Therefore, we could confirm that six fed groups were directly related to seven later groups, which involved a total of 13 groups, 48% of the 27 fed groups. For the nonfed groups, no birds were banded; however, two groups were identified from individual characteristics of group members to have been the same group in a subsequent year, which involved only four groups, 19% of the 21 nonfed groups.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Examination of the seven cases among the fed groups where we knew that a group in one year was present in the following year, the seven cases showed a total of 13 important changes: 3 changed group size, 5 new adult male helpers appeared of which 4 came from other groups (only one new male helper was recruited from the progeny of that group), 2 breeding males were replaced the following year by an outside male that previously had been a helper in that group, and 3 changed their nest type (2 tree to ground nest; 1 ground to tree nest). Similarly, for nonfed groups, the two cases identified also showed important changes: one with a change in group size, the other with a replacement of a male helper with a male from another group. The prevalence of these year-to-year changes among the breeding groups of those nine cases diminishes the concern about pseudoreplication.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Also, in addition to the observed year-to-year changes in group sizes and composition, we never found a breeding group using the same nest site the following year; therefore, locations of the nest sites discovered each year all differ from the previous year's nest sites (see the locations of all the nesting sites in 
  <a rid="pone.0146568.g001" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0146568.g001">Fig 1</a>). This means that 1) each group changed its nest site from year to year, and 2) it was often not possible to find the nest of the same group each year. The result is that there were many cases where group nesting sites from a given year, say 2006, did not show any nearby nesting sites for the next year (i.e., 2007 in this example), in which case, it is unlikely that those breeding groups were represented in the following year.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The search in early spring each year to locate nesting sites was spread across different areas. Note in the map in 
  <a rid="pone.0146568.g001" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0146568.g001">Fig 1</a> how the locations of nesting sites for fed groups are well distributed over the central sacred site (light gray area), and the nonfed groups are widely distributed in the neighboring areas surrounding the central sacred site (gray hatched area). The relatively wide scattering of the nesting sites each year acted to increase the likelihood of including a broader, non-selective sampling of the groups within the study area. Given these points, we conclude that the possible problem of pseudoreplication is small and very likely outweighed by the changes in group size and composition and in nest type and location as well as by other factors and chance occurrences related to weather, predation, etc.
 </p>
</sec>
