<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" sec-type="discussion" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We have shown that the pale speckled form (
  <span class="italic">typica</span>) of the peppered moth has a close match to lichen covered bark for both colour and lightness, whereas the melanic (
  <span class="italic">carbonaria</span>) form is poorly matched and closer in lightness to plain bark. Therefore, to avian vision, the 
  <span class="italic">typica</span> form is indeed better hidden against lichen covered trees than 
  <span class="italic">carbonaria</span>. Crucially, this translates into a strong survival advantage, with replica models of 
  <span class="italic">typica</span> being much less likely to be discovered by wild birds when on lichen covered backgrounds. These two components provide substantial direct support for the role of camouflage and differential avian predation in driving the rises and falls of polymorphic frequencies, and specifically the documented increases in 
  <span class="italic">typica</span> during the post-industrial era
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In our assessment of camouflage, the match of 
  <span class="italic">typica</span> to lichen was very close using a model of avian vision, with values around 2–3 JNDs. Instead, 
  <span class="italic">carbonaria</span> was a close match to plain bark for luminance, although not colour. In contrast, all moths had JNDs of around 7–9 for both colour and luminance against their incorrect background, indicating a substantially poorer match and diminished camouflage. These data are already in very close accordance with our predictions, but in addition, we used museum specimens and the resulting match between fresh specimens resting on in situ lichen under natural lighting may be closer. We also took average matches over the entirety of the moth wing patterns, which may produce a lower match (and a more conservative camouflage estimate) than between specific patches of colour on the moths to the background. In addition to the above considerations, it should be noted here that we have not tested how closely 
  <span class="italic">carbonaria</span> would resemble trees covered with a fine layer of soot; most likely, the match would be even closer. However, conducting such an experiment would present two key issues that are hard to resolve. First, it is unclear as to how much soot should be applied to the bark samples because too little or too much may skew the results substantially. One would have to rely on historical accounts of how much soot was around in polluted woodland, and this would not necessarily have been accurately recorded or replicable. Second, as the soot during the Industrial Revolution was deposited from the settling of particulates from the atmosphere, it would be difficult to correctly replicate this natural scenario through artificial application. Liebert and Brakefield
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span> noted that Kettlewell documented soot particulates being built up on trees based upon patterns of drainage, and so an effective replication of this would need information about the type of drainage pattern on the trees involved in Kettlewell’s and others’ experiments, for which we are not aware of any information. Finally, the plain bark we use here is an appropriate comparison in many regards, since in many polluted areas it is not necessarily the presence of soot that matters, but pollution killing off lichen rendering the tree bark bare.
 </p>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although the colour match of our artificial prey pastry bodies to the target wings and relevant natural background was not close for the 
  <span class="italic">carbonaria</span> models compared to the 
  <span class="italic">typical</span> ones (see “Methods” section), this is highly unlikely to explain our results and detection should primarily be based on the wing coloration, for several reasons. First, as discussed elsewhere
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span>, the overall area of the wings is many times greater than that of the body (here, seven times larger: 442 mm
  <span class="sup">2</span> for wings vs. 60 mm
  <span class="sup">2</span> for the body), and a key predictor of detection is object size. In addition, the prey bodies only touch the background bark at the top and bottom of the targets, and so this small area of contrast with the bark background is unlikely to be important (though body-wing contrast may have more influence). Second, numerous past experiments have investigated the effect of an edible body vs. target appearance on detection / predation, and repeatedly shown no or minimal effect of body presence or appearance. These experiments have, for example, compared detection and attack rates on targets with camouflage or eyespot markings against birds, whereby an edible body (a dead mealworm larvae or pastry body, often mismatching the main target) was placed either directly on top of the wings or underneath, partly projecting out
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
  </span>. In addition, studies have compared results of computer experiments with human subjects searching for computer-generated prey lacking edible bodies with work using the same stimuli types in field experiments
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
  </span>. In all these studies, results are entirely consistent regardless of the placement and presence/absence of a body component. Finally, the detection of small targets and of texture is mediated primarily by luminance rather than colour contrast
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>
  </span>, and in this regard for both morphs the bodies were a close and similar match to the wings and natural background. Therefore, we are highly confident that our results are fully or largely explained by model wing appearance against the background.
 </p>
 <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Kettlewell
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
  </span> showed that morphs of the peppered moth choose backgrounds to rest on that more closely resemble their appearance (e.g. 
  <span class="italic">carbonaria</span> on black stripes, 
  <span class="italic">typica</span> on white stripes). This was also confirmed in later work, although it is not straightforward as there can be variation among individuals, especially melanic ones, and the mechanisms underlying choices are unresolved
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>
  </span>. Work on other species has shown that individual moths have a remarkable ability to adjust their resting orientation and location to improve their own individual-specific, rather than species- or morph-specific, match to the background
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
  </span>. Such behavioural approaches to facilitate camouflage have also been demonstrated in birds and lizards, among other taxa
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>
  </span>. Consequently, real live peppered moths may be able to further improve their match to appropriate backgrounds through behavioural responses to ultimately confer a greater survival advantage. While recent work has largely resolved the issue of where these moths rest (lower branch surfaces and trunks
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span>), more work is also needed on the fine-scale background resting locations of each morph, including with regards to lichen types. Current work, as here, has focused on crustose lichens rather than foliose species
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>
  </span>. This is partly because the use of crustose lichen is consistent with information on chosen resting positions of moths, and because crustose lichen has been shown to reflect UV in a similar manner to 
  <span class="italic">typica</span> moths, in comparison to foliose lichen, which absorbs UV creating a poor match with 
  <span class="italic">typica</span>
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While industrial melanism provides an important example of evolution, it is also an early demonstration of how anthropogenic changes affect species and their interactions with their environment. More recent work has investigated if and how camouflaged animals will be affected by climate change
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>
  </span>, with coral bleaching through ocean acidification already seemingly having an impact on the camouflage of some fish
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">47</a>
  </span>. It is possible that in industrially developing nations with high pollution levels, there are parallel examples to that of the peppered moth occurring at present. Advancing this understanding not only demonstrates evolution but illustrates the impact that humans can have on species interactions and fundamental biological processes, such as those between predators and prey.
 </p>
</sec>
