<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Museum collection photography</div>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Photographs of peppered moth (
  <span class="italic">Biston betularia</span>) specimens were required for digital image analysis. Photographic data were obtained from three museums in the south of England: Bristol Museum and Art Gallery, the Exeter Ark of the Royal Albert Memorial Museum and Art Gallery, and Oxford University Museum of Natural History. The Oxford collections are noteworthy as they contain the specimens collected by Kettlewell for his original bird predation and breeding experiments. Access was permitted to the specimen drawers for selection of the most intact 
  <span class="italic">typica</span> and 
  <span class="italic">carbonaria</span> forms of both sexes for sampling, with selection based on wing completeness. Due to the age and fragility of such specimens, care in handling the pinned insects was paramount.
 </p>
 <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used a Nikon D7000 DSLR camera that had previously undergone a quartz conversion (Advanced Camera Services Limited, Norfolk, UK) by replacement of the internal UV filter with a transparent quartz sheet, as per previous studies
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" href="#CR48">48</a>
  </span>. This allowed for full spectral sensitivity throughout the avian-visible spectrum. A CoastalOpt 105 mm UV Macro APO interchangeable lens was attached whereby photographs in the human-visible spectrum were taken with a Baader UV-IR blocking filter (transmitting 400–700 nm) and ultraviolet (UV) photographs were taken using a Baader UV pass filter (transmitting 315–400 nm)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
  </span>. All images were taken in RAW format. An area within the collections was selected with a minimal amount of natural and artificial light so not to interfere with the lighting equipment, which consisted of an Iwasaki EYE Colour Arc lamp connected to a Ventronic ballast, mounted onto a PhotxPro photographic lighting stand with an attached Elinchrom umbrella. The arc lamp was left to warm-up for 15 min to allow the bulb to reach at least 90% of its full light output. Prior to use, the UV blocking filter applied over the arc lamp was removed using a steel brush bit as to allow for a full spectrum of wavelengths. A cylindrical sheet of PTFE was placed around the bulb, or around the specimen(s) to be photographed if accessible, to evenly diffuse the light.
 </p>
 <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">If appropriate, a moth was removed from the specimen drawer and pinned onto a neutral grey foam background. A maximum of three specimens per shot were photographed to ensure they were all uniform in size and wings were not out of the frame. To remove any effect of lighting variability, a light (95%) and dark (5%) reflectance standard (Labsphere, Congleton, UK) was included along with a scale bar positioned on the side closest to the specimens. The camera was positioned directly above using either a copy stand or a tripod with a flexible head, before being focused to obtain optimal sharpness. The exposure time was selected dependent on whether photographing with the visible or UV filter and optimised for correct exposure and to prevent saturation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49" href="#CR49">49</a>
  </span>. A camera shutter remote was used to minimise unnecessary noise or movement.
 </p>
</sec>
