<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The main climate engineering imaginary analyzed in this article is here dubbed ‘Reluctant Geoengineering’. It broadly posits the desirability of a research program into climate engineering technologies framed as a ‘Plan B’ – that is, as a fallback option or second-best option rather than as a preferred option or replacement for mitigation (which remains ‘Plan A’). Reluctant Geoengineering depicts, via modeling and scenarios, certain technologies as possible means to avoid or deal with the dystopian vision of rapid or dangerous climate change in a future suffering from increasing climatic instability and continually failing or inadequate global efforts to curb emissions of greenhouse gases. It is ‘reluctant’ in that climate engineering is advanced in a ‘worth a try’ style of argumentation that tends not to hide uncertainties and (environmental) risks. ‘Plan B/insurance’ is the most commonly used metaphor among experts and in the media (
 <xref rid="bibr10-0967010617704142" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bellamy et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bibr27-0967010617704142" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Corner et al., 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bibr63-0967010617704142" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Luokkanen et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bibr76-0967010617704142" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Nerlich and Jaspal, 2012</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bibr96-0967010617704142" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Scholte et al., 2013</xref>). In a survey of metaphors, 
 <xref rid="bibr76-0967010617704142" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Nerlich and Jaspal (2012</xref>: 141) report that they
 <disp-quote class="disp-quote">
  <p class="p">found one master argument, according to which geoengineering is the only option to avoid a planetary catastrophe. This is linked more or less directly to two main metaphors according to which geoengineering is the only Plan B we have and the only insurance policy we have for this planet.</p>
 </disp-quote>
</p>
