<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par37" class="p">This paper focuses on the priorities, barriers and enablers in Asian cities to develop the governance capacity necessary to address their challenges related to water, waste and climate change. The results show a great variety in performances and capacities reflected by the high variation of the BCI scores of Asian cities varying from 2.0 to 8.1. This large variation emphasises their learning and transformation potential, provided that cities exchange knowledge, experiences and best practices. Cities with more social, environmental and financial pressures were found to have lower water management performances. On the other hand, the cities of Seoul (BCI 7.3) and Singapore (BCI 8.1) are world leading examples of water conservation, circular urban water management and climate robustness. The main priorities observed in Asian cities were water scarcity, water leakage, flood and heat risk, wastewater treatment and solid waste collection and recycling (Table 
 <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table" class="xref">3</xref> and Figs. 
 <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref> and 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3</xref>). The main barriers observed were adequate education and good governance (Tables 
 <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table" class="xref">3</xref> and 
 <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table" class="xref">4</xref>). Our study shows that there are several options for improvement:
 <list list-type="bullet" class="list">
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par38" class="p">The main enablers reside in adequate education and good governance: ‘before fixing the urban water pipes, fix the institutions.' (OECD 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" class="xref">2016</xref>). In Asia, this specifically includes the need for proper monitoring, cross-stakeholder learning, implementation and enforcement as well as sufficient room for new initiatives (Table 
    <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table" class="xref">4</xref>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par39" class="p">This study in Asian cities reconfirms our earlier observations that water challenges form a cross-cutting issue that require a holistic rather than a sectorial approach in order to create co-benefits and win-wins (Koop and Van Leeuwen 
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" class="xref">2017</xref>). Defragmentation of institutions may play a key role again.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par40" class="p">Based on the governance capacity analysis of flood risk management in the cities of Ahmedabad, Bandung and Taipei, we conclude that improvements in both the statutory compliance and policy evaluation processes can be considered as key priorities as well.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par41" class="p">Proper IWRM is often hindered by low performance in solid waste collection and recycling leading to clogging of sewers, and subsequently to high risks of both flooding (after heavy rain events) and water scarcity (as water reuse requires proper collection and treatment of wastewater). Thus, proper IWRM should encompass adequate solid waste management.</p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p id="Par42" class="p">IWRM in slum areas is of particular importance for Asia’s rapidly expanding cities. Here, citizen engagement is an important precondition for their sustainability and resilience. Improvements can only be realised through inclusive local decision-making and long-term commitment. In particular, access to basic water services, solid waste management and various forms of centralised and decentralised wastewater treatment can be considered as focal areas.</p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
