<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Finally, predation pressure has also been shown to drive differences in both size at maturity and overall body size via phenotypic or genetic processes. For instance, elevated predation intensity from natural predators or commercial harvesting can drive declines in body size at reproductive maturity (e.g. [
 <xref rid="pone.0176263.ref027" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0176263.ref045" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>] but see [
 <xref rid="pone.0176263.ref050" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>] for an exception). Our tethering trials indicated that predation potential on 
 <italic class="italic">A</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">pisonii</italic> was almost twice as high on large individuals than small individuals in the representative mixed marsh habitat. Conversely, there was no evidence of size-specific predation in the representative mangrove habitat. Because large crabs are not present in salt marsh habitats, all of the large crabs used in the tethering trials were collected from mangrove habitats. Although we previously established that large crabs are capable of climbing cordgrass in the salt marsh, individual inexperience in the salt marsh may have contributed to the increased predation on large individuals. Additionally, habitat may influence prey palatability, and predator preferences may have been impacted by the inclusion of only small crabs collected from the salt marsh in the tethering study. Finally, predator community composition may differ between the two habitat types, which could also impact predation patterns. Nevertheless, even the slight size-specific predation discrepancy noted between large and small individuals in novel habitats could drive the observed decrease in body size and size at reproduction (e.g. [
 <xref rid="pone.0176263.ref027" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>]). Thus, the life history patterns associated with 
 <italic class="italic">A</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">pisonii</italic>’s range expansion are consistent with multiple mechanisms presented here, and we are currently unable to tease apart the relative influence of these explanations.
</p>
