<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Studying the warming conditions of the last years, from monitoring stations of Northern Europe it emerges that 
 <italic class="italic">Alnus</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Betula</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Corylus</italic> generally have an early pollination start. As 
 <italic class="italic">Betula</italic> lives at low temperatures in mid to high latitude countries, data from Central Europe suggest that an increase in temperature could limit the physiological performance of birch species, including the production of pollen [
 <xref rid="B32-plants-05-00042" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>]. European data, however, reveal that 
 <italic class="italic">Alnus</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Betula</italic>, and 
 <italic class="italic">Corylus</italic> trees are more associated with high latitudes and low temperatures than others, and their annual concentrations have a negative correlation with temperature that could reflect the limited presence of these species at warmer sites [
 <xref rid="B33-plants-05-00042" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>]. In Italy, moving to different local geobotanical features, in the last years the pollination start tends to become delayed in winter-blooming plants (
 <italic class="italic">Alnus</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">Corylus</italic>) while the most important tendency to an early pollination occurs in spring-blooming trees (
 <italic class="italic">Betula</italic>) [
 <xref rid="B6-plants-05-00042" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-plants-05-00042" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>]. Our data add information about the behavior of the last day of pollination periods. Pollen monitoring suggests that there is a tendency of 
 <italic class="italic">Alnus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Corylus</italic> to behave as winter-blooming trees thus anticipating the end (earlier last day) of their pollen seasons. Contrarily, the spring-blooming 
 <italic class="italic">Betula</italic> trees tend to delay the end of the pollen season. Comparing these results, we can conclude that the pollen season of alder and hazelnut trees tends to be shorter, meanwhile the season of birch becomes longer. This seems to demonstrate that warm climate, as the current environmental conditions are, may be generally unfavorable to the winter-blooming trees that have a later pollination after exceptionally warm autumn temperatures [
 <xref rid="B27-plants-05-00042" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>].
</p>
