<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="editorial"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.0 20120330//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Scientifica (Cairo)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Scientifica (Cairo)</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SCIENTIFICA</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Scientifica</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2090-908X</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Hindawi</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6437751</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1155/2019/1573593</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Editorial</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Wildlife Conservation in Tropical Savanna Ecosystems</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0003-0708-350X</contrib-id><name><surname>Gandiwa</surname><given-names>Edson</given-names></name><email>egandiwa@gmail.com</email><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="false">http://orcid.org/0000-0001-7512-0697</contrib-id><name><surname>Muboko</surname><given-names>Never</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mupangwa</surname><given-names>John F.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="I2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="I1">
<sup>1</sup>School of Wildlife, Ecology and Conservation, Chinhoyi University of Technology, Chinhoyi, Zimbabwe</aff><aff id="I2">
<sup>2</sup>Department of Animal Science, Faculty of Agriculture and Natural Resources, University of Namibia, Neudamm Campus, Windhoek, Namibia</aff><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2019</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>3</month><year>2019</year></pub-date><volume>2019</volume><elocation-id>1573593</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>12</month><year>2018</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>16</day><month>12</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2019 Edson Gandiwa et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2019</copyright-year><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions></article-meta></front><body><p>The objective of this special issue is to address the diverse issues and developments related to wildlife conservation in tropical savanna ecosystems, given the challenges related to climate change, habitat fragmentation, illegal hunting and trade in wildlife products, and sustainable utilization. Many papers were submitted, and after a thorough peer-review process, six papers, i.e., five original research papers and one review paper, were selected to be included in this special issue. These research studies provide invaluable insights into understanding contemporary issues in wildlife conservation and scientific evidence for adaptive management and sustainable conservation.</p><p>The paper by V. K. Munyaka and E. Gandiwa presents an assessment of how the giraffe species (<italic>Giraffa camelopardalis</italic>) acclimatizes to a new ecosystem after introduction and which forage species it selects using the focal observation method.</p><p>The paper by T. Chigonda reviews the relationships between human livelihoods and biodiversity conservation in the rural areas of a semi-arid savanna and highlights the need for complete devolution of natural resource ownership and management to the grassroots levels in order to fully realise social and ecological sustainability.</p><p>The paper by G. Matseketsa et al. proposes a more socially and economically inclusive management approach, based on a stakeholder-driven access and benefit sharing framework, as essential in promoting a more positive form of reciprocity towards protected areas and nature conservation.</p><p>The paper by E. Mufandaedza et al. highlights variability in the influence of soil parameters (i.e., soil texture, soil pH, and available nitrogen (N) and phosphorus (P)) and level of tannins in tree barks in the distribution of mopane worms (<italic>Imbrasia belina</italic>) in savanna ecosystems.</p><p>The paper by C. Mutengu and W. Mhlanga analyses fish health and water quality and proposes the importance of long-term monitoring of freshwater ecosystems for sustainable fisheries management.</p><p>The paper by O. L. Kupika et al. illuminates the importance of local ecological knowledge held by rural communities adjacent to large protected areas on climate change- and ecosystem-based adaptation strategies and how this facilitates resilience in a changing environment.</p></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We are very grateful to all the authors who contributed to this special issue and our expert reviewers who provided vital constructive feedback and criticism throughout the review process.</p><p content-type="signature-group">
<named-content content-type="signature">
<italic>Edson Gandiwa</italic>
</named-content>
<named-content content-type="signature">
<italic>Never Muboko</italic>
</named-content>
<named-content content-type="signature">
<italic>John F. Mupangwa</italic>
</named-content>
</p></ack><sec><title>Conflicts of Interest</title><p>The editors declare that they have no conflicts of interest.</p></sec></back></article>