<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec006" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our result that reproductive output was greater in nest boxes than tree cavities suggests that nest boxes offer a reproductive advantage even when no attempts are made to prevent ectoparasitism or nest predation. We suggest, therefore, that installing nest boxes could be an effective strategy for bolstering populations of Tree Swallows.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Interspecific competition for tree cavities that leads to later settlement may help explain why Tree Swallow clutches in cavities were smaller than those in nest boxes. Researchers in Ontario suggested that interspecific competition from earlier breeding European Starlings, the most abundant competitor, led to later and smaller Tree Swallow clutches in tree cavities [
  <a rid="pone.0204226.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0204226.ref013">13</a>]. In that study, the high densities of Tree Swallows (6.6 pairs/ha) occupying the tree cavity sites likely contributed to high competition for cavities [
  <a rid="pone.0204226.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0204226.ref013">13</a>]. Likewise, during our study, Tree Swallow pairs (N = 112 pairs) had to compete for breeding sites with more dominant species of comparable abundance (84 Mountain Bluebird; 
  <span class="italic">Sialia currucoides</span> pairs, 114 European Starling pairs and 130 Northern Flicker pairs; K. Martin unpublished data) that initiated nesting early [
  <a rid="pone.0204226.ref057" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0204226.ref057">57</a>]. In a separate study at our study site, Tree Swallows proved to be an inferior nest-site competitor, initiating clutches 7–14 days later at cavities in years and areas with breeding European Starlings and Mountain Bluebirds present. Additionally, changes in nest-site supply occurred with a separate study in which cavities were removed and added at our study area during 2002–2004 [
  <a rid="pone.0204226.ref007" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0204226.ref007">7</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0204226.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0204226.ref009">9</a>]. In this other study, cavities were removed (blocked) at some sites [
  <a rid="pone.0204226.ref007" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0204226.ref007">7</a>] and added at other sites in 2002 and 2003 [
  <a rid="pone.0204226.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0204226.ref009">9</a>]. At sites where cavities were removed, we suspect that Tree Swallows used cavities of lesser quality resulting in small clutches but exhibited no site-level changes in population densities [
  <a rid="pone.0204226.ref007" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0204226.ref007">7</a>]. At sites where nests were added, Tree Swallows used only a very small proportion of the new nest sites and therefore likely still had to compete for cavities with the inflated densities of competitors [
  <a rid="pone.0204226.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0204226.ref009">9</a>]. Thus, the smaller clutches and broods in tree cavities were apparently correlated with an increase in competition for nest-sites, and swallows nesting in boxes were able to maintain larger clutches.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Tree Swallows preferentially selected and were more successful in smaller cavities produced by Red-naped Sapsuckers (
  <span class="italic">Sphyrapicus nuchalis</span>) whereas bluebirds and starlings preferred larger cavities excavated by Northern Flickers [
  <a rid="pone.0204226.ref049" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0204226.ref049">49</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0204226.ref057" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0204226.ref057">57</a>]. This may help to explain why our results differed from a similar study in the same region in British Columbia, which found no difference in reproductive output of Tree Swallows nesting in boxes and cavities [
  <a rid="pone.0204226.ref045" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0204226.ref045">45</a>]. The other British Columbia study [
  <a rid="pone.0204226.ref045" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0204226.ref045">45</a>] examined nests in boxes that were erected for ducks, which had large cavity entrances. In our study, nest boxes had much smaller cavity entrances, therefore swallows that used boxes avoided competition with starlings and flickers, and produced larger and more successful clutches and broods. Nest boxes were 60% larger in volume, and 1.8 cm wider internally than tree cavities used by Tree Swallows. Other researchers [
  <a rid="pone.0204226.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0204226.ref013">13</a>] found positive correlations between cavity floor area and clutch size and between cavity floor area and probability of fledging young of Tree Swallows. We found that clutch size marginally declined with increasing tree cavity entrance area, but found no evidence of a relationship with internal cavity size. Further, we were unable to examine the correlation between clutch size and nest box volume due to the lack of variation in nest box size. Future work to test the hypothesis that nest volume influences clutch size should involve supplementation of nest boxes with a wide range in internal volume. It is important to note, however, that cavity entrance should be kept small to restrict larger bodied competitors and predators.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We found a greater number of nests later in the season in boxes, particularly in 2001 (Figs 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0204226.g001" href="#pone.0204226.g001">1</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0204226.g002" href="#pone.0204226.g002">2c</a>), and due to logistical constraints during the study we were unable to confirm nest success or failure in these later nests. Nonetheless, fledging success was consistently higher in nest boxes across all three years of our study, including the year before nest-site removal and supplementation (2001), suggesting that competition for tree cavities alone cannot explain higher nest success in boxes. Our results differ from another study on Great Crested Flycatchers (
  <span class="italic">Myiarchus crinitus</span>) in northern Florida that found high annual variation in nest success in cleaned nest boxes but consistent nest success in tree cavities, which they attributed to different nest predator species depredating the two nest types [
  <a rid="pone.0204226.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0204226.ref020">20</a>]. We found on multiple occasions that grass nests were built by small mammals inside cavities and boxes, indicating that nest predators frequently occupied both nest types. In our long-term study of the cavity-nesting community, the most abundant predators for nests in trees were red squirrels (
  <span class="italic">Tamiasciurus hudsonicus</span>; [
  <a rid="pone.0204226.ref058" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0204226.ref058">58</a>]). Others have shown nest predation rates of Tree Swallows to increase in cavities closer to the ground [
  <a rid="pone.0204226.ref024" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0204226.ref024">24</a>]. Relative to tree cavities, our nest boxes lacked predator guards, had the same range of potential nest predators, and were closer to the ground.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The presence of ectoparasites was likely similar in cavities and boxes, since we did not remove nest material between seasons and the colonization rate of ectoparasites in the study area was found to be very consistent across cavities by another researcher [
  <a rid="pone.0204226.ref059" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0204226.ref059">59</a>]. Thus, we hypothesize that nest predation risk and ectoparasitism rates likely did not differ between tree cavities and nest boxes in our study. We did not directly test the hypothesis that cleaning nest boxes influences fledging success but future work should compare uncleaned and cleaned boxes to determine how the practice of cleaning nest boxes interacts with ectoparasitsm and nest predation to influence fledging success.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Other investigators have found that older females tend to nest in boxes and have larger clutches than younger females that use tree cavities [
  <a rid="pone.0204226.ref003" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0204226.ref003">3</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0204226.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0204226.ref013">13</a>]. Some females were likely included twice in the study within and across nest types, but due to the sparsity of demographic data we were unable to account for this source of variation. In addition, we cannot rule out the possibility that females occupying the two nest types differed in terms of breeding age and/or experience. Our evidence supports the hypothesis that swallows preferred boxes perhaps because of their larger interior dimensions, and later-arriving and/or less competitive individuals (e.g., younger/less experienced individuals) were forced to nest in tree cavities. Thus it remains unknown how much of the difference in reproduction in boxes and cavities was due to the type of nest site versus the nature of birds using those nest sites. Further study is needed to examine how nest predation risk, predator types, nest box characteristics, and demographic variables might influence reproductive output in nest boxes versus tree cavities.
 </p>
</sec>
