<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Within the economics literature, CEs have become an established valuation method (Bateman et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">2002</xref>; Hensher et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">2005</xref>) and have lately been applied to the evaluation of ecosystem services (de Groot and Hein 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">2007</xref>). Despite a higher cognitive burden, the multiattribute approach of CEs is still advantageous, as (1) economic values are not elicited directly but are inferred, which decreases strategic response behavior when it comes to payments (Van Beukering and Cesar 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77" class="xref">2004</xref>); (2) the incidence of ethical protesting seems to be lower (Hanley et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" class="xref">2001</xref>); (3) they excel in measuring nonuse values (Adamowicz et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">1998</xref>); (4) they allow for a deeper understanding of trade-offs between different attributes (Adamowicz et al. 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">1998</xref>), and as (5), in the context of nonmarket ecosystem service valuation, individuals can evaluate nonmarket benefits or hypothetical futures and options in an intuitive and meaningful way (Van Beukering and Cesar 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77" class="xref">2004</xref>). In addition, the choice experiment permits a combined analysis of multiple aspects of hypothetical (future) attributes and scenarios (e.g., impact of funding). Thus, CEs are deemed particularly suitable for the application in climate change research, as currently nonexisting criteria and scenarios (i.e., increased yield through prolonged cultivation periods and new types of funding schemes and subsidies) can easily be integrated alongside existing adaptation strategies into the survey and subsequent analyses. Finally, the method can also accommodate risks and uncertainties into the evaluation and trade-offs.
</p>
