<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par14" class="p">The Miami model-simulated NPP
 <sub class="sub">P</sub> is only influenced by climatic factors and has been regarded as the maximum NPP of an ecosystem
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>
 </sup>. In an arid and semi-arid region, the vegetation NPP is more sensitive to precipitation and vulnerable to climate warming
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" class="xref">27</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>
 </sup>. According to the fifth report of IPCC, in the past three decades, global temperatures and precipitation have shown an increasing trend. Gao 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" class="xref">28</xref>
 </sup>, compared the average annual values of the normalized difference vegetation index (NDVI) with theoretical NPP values based on Miami Model to determine the effect of historic climate change on global grassland productivity from 1982 to 2011. They found an increase in most of the grassland NPP
 <sub class="sub">P</sub>, and concluded the global grassland areas have been significantly affected by climate change. In this study, the grassland NPP
 <sub class="sub">P</sub> in Xinjiang also showed an overall increasing trend. The increase may be related to the fact that, in the past ten years, the average annual temperature and precipitation in Xinjiang have increased, showing an overall trend of warm - wet climate
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">17</xref>
 </sup>. Chen 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., analyzed the impact of climate change and anthropogenic activities on alpine grassland over the Qinghai-Tibet Plateau from 1982 to 2011, and found an increasing trend of NPP
 <sub class="sub">A</sub> for the entire period, while an increasing trend of NPP
 <sub class="sub">P</sub> during 1982 to 2001 and decreasing trend of NPP
 <sub class="sub">P</sub> during 2001 to 2012. As the annual precipitation is the main driving force of the alpine grassland NPP
 <sub class="sub">P</sub> , the NPP
 <sub class="sub">P</sub> decline since 2000 was due to the rainfall decrease
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>
 </sup>. This further indicates that, the variability in actual and potential productivity may different throughout the global grassland ecosystems, and may show various trends in different grassland regions, since human activities and climate change present various contributions to the productivity of grassland in different regions.
</p>
