<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Seedlings were planted at plots near the eight microclimate monitoring stations. Plots approximately 20 x 20 m in size were sprayed with imazapyr herbicide to kill invasive grasses in July‒August 2015, and again with glyphosate herbicide in January 2016. A total of 322 liters of herbicide mixture was used for the first round of grass control, and a follow-up effort used another 116 liters. Seedlings of three native plant species were hardened in a greenhouse at KBC beginning October 12, 2015: 480 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">oahuense</italic>, 350 
 <italic class="italic">D</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">viscosa</italic>, and 115 
 <italic class="italic">S</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">chrysophylla</italic>. Nineteen 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">oahuense</italic>, 22 
 <italic class="italic">D</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">viscosa</italic>, and two 
 <italic class="italic">S</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">chrysophylla</italic> seedlings died before being outplanted. Seedlings of each species were equally distributed for outplanting among all eight plots, and planting order within plots was randomized. Number of seedlings planted, by species and plot, is available in 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0218516.s001" class="xref">S1 Table</xref>. All seedlings were outplanted among the eight study sites February 29–March 2, 2016. Seedlings were planted approximately 1 m apart, thoroughly watered, coconut core substrate added when necessary, and amended with Nutricote 13-11-11 fertilizer. Seedling height was measured to the nearest mm in the greenhouse prior to out-planting, and three times after out-planting: during March three weeks after outplanting, June and July 2016. March measurements were used as the initial height value in subsequent analyses. While not initially part of the experiment design, invasive grasses and weeds were manually removed from plots throughout the 2016 growing period to minimize seedling mortality from competition. Heavy herbivory and substantial seedling mortality was caused by non-native game birds at Plot 2, and data from that plot were eliminated from statistical analyses.
</p>
