<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">After laboratory acclimation, four different groups (with 5 to 7 individuals) of 
 <italic class="italic">S</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">carolitertii</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">S</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">torgalensis</italic> were gradually acclimated to four different conditions (
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone.0181325.t001" class="xref">Table 1</xref>): i) control; ii) warming; iii) acidification and iv) combined warming and acidification condition. Within these experimental conditions, we planned to simulate a moderate climate change scenario by increasing the temperature in +3°C and applying a ΔpH = -0.4, under a 2x2 factorial design. During the acclimation and experimental periods, fish were fed daily (ad libitum) with bloodworms (TMC Iberia, Portugal), white mosquito larvae (TMC Iberia, Portugal) and 
 <italic class="italic">Spirulina</italic> spp. flake food (Ocean nutrition, Belgium). Overhead tank illumination was provided, according to prevailing natural light conditions, under a 12:12 (day: night) light regime. Ammonia, nitrite and nitrate levels were monitored daily (Salifert Profi Test, Holland) and kept always below detectable levels. Normoxic conditions were maintained and pH values were monitored and adjusted automatically by means of a computerized controlling system (Profilux 3.1N, GHL, Germany) connected to individual oxygen and pH probes (GHL, Germany), respectively. Monitoring was performed every 2 seconds and pH values were adjusted through injection of N
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>/CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> (Air Liquide, Portugal) and upregulated by aeration with CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> filtered air (soda lime, Sigma-Aldrich). Conductivity was individually monitored (Profilux 3.1N, GHL, Germany) and kept between 400–500 μS/cm. Automatic dosing systems (TMC Iberia, Portugal), linked to the Profilux system, enabled inflow of freshwater (300 or 600 μS/cm), in order to lower or raise conductivity values (culture tanks), within desired interval (400–500 μS/cm). After 30 days of experimental exposure, five to seven individuals of each treatment and species were euthanized (with spinal transection followed by immediate brain removal), during early morning period. Experimental procedures used in this research were in accordance with the requirements imposed by the Directive 2010/63/EU of the European Parliament and of the Council of 22 September 2010 on the protection of animals used for scientific purposes (reviewed and approved by the animal ethics committee ORBEA–Animal Welfare Body of FCUL Statement 5/2016).
</p>
