<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec9" sec-type="discussion" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The optimal Bayesian data-driven model derived here from the LR04 stack shows that strong nonlinear feedbacks in climate, gradual trends of global cooling, stochastic and insolation (obliquity) forcings are all important for various aspects of the MPT. From a dynamical point of view, the MPT is shown to be generated due to a long-term trend in climate leading to a noise-induced nonlinear oscillation build-up. This trend makes the warm steady states less stable and hence allows the climate to reach colder states. As a result, the slow onset/rapid termination glacial-interglacial climate oscillations of large amplitude became more approachable in the late Pleistocene; this gives indication that the large glaciations started to be triggered at higher temperatures than in the pre-MPT epoch. This conclusion supports indirectly the hypothesis put forth in ref.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
  </span> about the leading role of a gradual deep ocean cooling in the MPT, through decreasing the ocean heat capacity and hence allowing sea ice to grow at higher atmospheric temperatures.
 </p>
 <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">However, the strongly nonlinear relaxation oscillations responsible for the large sawtooth glacial-interglacial cycles cannot arise in our model without energetic millennial (and/or centennial) climate variability, represented by a stochastic process. So, the data-driven modeling of such short-scale variability (e.g. Dansgaard-Oeschger, Heinrich, Bond oscillations), with connection to large glacial-interglacial cycle models, could be helpful for further clarification of the mechanisms underlying the Pleistocene dynamics.</p>
 <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Regarding the insolation forcing, we have found that only the insolation gradient, driven primary by the obliquity oscillations, is important for the Pleistocene dynamics. For the pre-MPT 41 kyr world the principal role of insolation gradient was explained in ref.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>
  </span>, but the physical mechanism for its dominance in the late Pleistocene (shown by our model) is not presently clear. Accordingly to ref.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
  </span>, the glacial oscillation is phase locked with the Milankovitch forcing via the high-latitude insolation: lower insolation leads to larger glacier growth and makes the sea ice switches (rapid expansions of sea ice) followed by the deglaciation stages more probable than at higher insolation values. But the high-latitude insolation signal is dominated by the precession rather than obliquity oscillation, whereas our analysis uncovers that the impacts of both precession and eccentricity forcings are negligible. To reconcile these differences, we conjecture here that the tropical insolation can be also important in this mechanism. Above the average tropical insolation in combination with the low high-latitude insolation may result in an intensification of moisture transport to high latitudes and a related increase in the ice accumulation rate. The latter prolongs the stability of continental ice allowing temperatures to reach much lower values through the ice-albedo feedback. Eventually, all behavior explained in refs
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
  </span> still happens – the low temperatures, large sea ice extent, reducing precipitations followed by retreating of the glaciers, but the deglaciation stage starts from much colder conditions yielding higher amplitudes of the glacial cycles. Thus, the major deglaciations are tied to the positive phase of the low-high latitude insolation difference (i.e. the insolation gradient) oscillation, providing a phase locking of the climate cycles with the obliquity cycles. Probably, this is the direction the conceptual models could be modified in.
 </p>
 <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All the conclusions we made in this work are inferred by the analysis of the LR04 stack which only represents the global climate changes during the Pleistocene. Therefore the dynamical model derived from this data set can only describe the salient properties of the climate system and necessarily lacks potentially important regional details. In particular, it was shown
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span> that the Ocean Drilling Program records in the Southwest Pacific Ocean – an important region for studying the global ocean circulation – indicate a much more abrupt change in 
  <span class="italic">δ</span>
  <span class="sup">18</span>O from 950 ka to 870 ka compared to much smoother globally-averaged changes. No doubt, differences in regional climate variability can be important for more detailed studies of glacial mechanisms, and future works on data-driven modeling of paleoclimate would be focused on the analysis of multivariate time series over the globe.
 </p>
 <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another question beyond the scope of this work concerns the reversibility of the MPT: whether is it possible to bring the climate back to the 41-kyr world by reversing the long-term trend in the system? In principle, the dynamics of the model obtained here is reversible in this sense: if we initialize the model by current conditions and launch the sequence {
  <span class="italic">t</span>
  <sub>
   <span class="italic">n</span>
  </sub>} in Eq. 
  <a rid="Equ1" ref-type="" href="#Equ1">1</a> backward, we get the completely reversed scenario of the MPT, as shown in Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S8</a>. This means that structurally, there is no hysteresis, or multistability, in the model on the time interval corresponding to the MPT. But the problem is that the LR04 time series does not provide sufficient information for identification of the physical processes contributing to the trend itself, whereas some of them may be irreversible, e.g. glacial erosion of regolith which has been suggested as a primary factor for large glaciations
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span>. Further understanding and modeling the causes of such long-term changes of the system may shed new light on this task.
 </p>
</sec>
