<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The impact of stochastic forcing</div>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To study the role of the random fluctuations (noise) in the model, which represent the sub-grid millennial and centennial climate variability, we compare outputs of the model in three variants: (i) the full model containing all the forcings, (ii) the model without the insolation forcing, in which both forcing time series entering 
  <span class="bold">q</span> are set to their mean values, and (iii) the noise-free model with 
  <span class="italic">g</span> = 0. We find that the stochastic forcing is a crucial factor for the frequency-band change associated with the MPT: the transition to the 100 kyr scale occurs in the same way in the model without any insolation signal, whereas the model with insolation forcing only and no noise only exhibits a response to the obliquity 41 kyr oscillations through the entire Pleistocene (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1(D,E)</a>). Thus, the model internal dynamical properties, short-scale climate fluctuations and the model nonstationarity induce together the frequency shift in the 
  <span class="italic">δ</span>
  <span class="sup">18</span>O variations; by contrast, the variability in insolation is not instrumental in the MPT.
 </p>
 <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The resulting probability distribution of noise in the model Eq. 
  <a rid="Equ1" ref-type="" href="#Equ1">1</a> is not constant in time due to the state-dependence of the noise amplitude 
  <span class="italic">g</span>. The ratio of the “instantaneous” noise variance 
  <span class="italic">g</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> to the variance of the LR04 time series is marked by color in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3(A)</a>, where the time series from a single randomly chosen model run is plotted. The increase in the millennial variability in colder climate seen in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3(A)</a> coincides well with findings of refs
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>
  </span> showing an amplification of the millennial-scale climate variability amplitude with an increasing of the continental ice mass. As shown below, such an increase in the sub-grid fluctuations may contribute to but does not play a central role in the MPT mechanism.
  <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Deterministic and stochastic model specifics. (
     <span class="bold">A</span>) An example of model time series (the same time series is used in Fig. 
     <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S1</a>) colored in accordance with the noise power: color represents the values of the “instantaneous” noise variance 
     <span class="italic">g</span>
     <span class="sup">2</span> in Eq. 
     <a rid="Equ1" ref-type="" href="#Equ1">1</a> normalized to the variance of the LR04 stack. (
     <span class="bold">B</span>) Deterministic model’s (see the text) steady states at different insolation gradient forcing levels (colors correspond to the insolation gradient values). The stable and unstable steady states are shown by thick and thin lines respectively.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_43867_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e727" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
