<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par43" class="p">The importance of global cooperation to achieve carbon emissions reduction is underlined by a recent Price Water Cooper report
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" class="xref">47</xref>
 </sup>. The failure of even-handedness in sharing the cost of reducing carbon is evident. Some countries are dealing with the problem. Australia, for example, has reduced carbon emissions by 7.2% between 2012 and 2013. Certain countries such as the U.K., Italy, and even China have all managed impressive decarbonization rates between four and five percent. Other countries, including the U.S., have increased their carbon emissions. The study indicates the trend “[f]or the sixth year running, the global economy has missed the decarbonization target needed to limit global warming to 2 °C. Confronted with the challenge in 2013 of decarbonizing at 6% a year, we managed only 1.2%“
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" class="xref">47</xref>
 </sup>. A’climate’ of non-cooperation seems to be the route the US is taking since 2017 as is evidenced by it’s withdrawal from the Paris Climate Agreement
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" class="xref">48</xref>
 </sup>. Consistent with this study, we highlight the concept that when pollution does not directly affect the individual (or polluter) at least directly (spatially detached) or right now (temporarily detached), the results are, on a global scale, inaction. This reality is analogous to the concept “Not In My Back Yard” (NIMBY) or in this context, 
 <italic class="italic">My Neighbor’Oughta’ Pay</italic> (MNOP). This action, or lack thereof, perhaps cynical, can be viewed as a self-interest scenario and is rational, at least in the short-term. In this scenario, the pollution problem is ignored until the cost of impact is sufficiently large, that action must then be taken. This reasoning is consistent with the cost analysis of other anthropogenic pollution issues in the past.
</p>
