<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par34" class="p">Total Hg was measured on one complete back cover feather (abbreviated BF hereafter) or one complete throat feather (abbreviated HF hereafter) using an advanced Hg analyzer spectrophotometer (Altec AMA 254) as described in Bustamante 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR94" class="xref">94</xref>
 </sup>. Hg in little auk BF reflect the amount of Hg accumulated by birds during the previous breeding season spent in East Greenland (year preceding the sample), while Hg in HF reflect the amount of Hg accumulated during the previous winter (see Fort 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" class="xref">37</xref>
 </sup>). Hence, BF collected from 2007 to 2016 were analyzed for comparison with the biological time-series. Previous studies showed that &gt;90% of Hg in seabird feathers is methyl-Hg (Me-Hg), the most toxic form of Hg
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR95" class="xref">95</xref>
 </sup>. Total Hg measured in feathers is thus considered as an indicator of bird exposure to Me-Hg. Hg concentrations measured in bird feathers are also an indicator of the contamination level of the food chain on which birds feed during both seasons
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" class="xref">37</xref>
 </sup>. Analyses were repeated two or three times (two or three feathers) for each bird and feather type until the relative standard deviation for two samples was &lt;10%; samples not meeting this criterion were excluded from the analysis. The mean Hg concentrations for those two or three measurements were then considered for statistical analyses. To ensure the accuracy of measurements, a certified reference material (CRM) was used [Lobster Hepatopancreas Tort-2; NRC, Canada; Hg concentration of 0.27 ± 0.06 µg.g
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup> of dry weight (dw)]. The CRM was measured every 10 samples and the average measured value was 0.26 ± 0.01 µg.g
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup> dw (n = 113). Additionally, blanks were run at the beginning of each sample set. The detection limit of the method was 0.005 µg.g
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup> dw.
</p>
