<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par5" class="p">Global environmental change, including climate change, first engaged public health interest in the late twentieth century (e.g. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>–
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">13</xref>]). In the UK, for example, the public health discourse on climate change, was conducted, initially at least, with a clear focus on environmental change taking place, or imminently anticipated, in that country. From the outset, concern centered on what the greater incidence and severity of flooding or more extreme weather in the UK would mean for the health of UK citizens [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">14</xref>]. In this paper, we propose the term 
 <italic class="italic">proximal</italic> pathway to describe the process where a population’s health is imminently threatened or undermined through climate-related environmental change within its locality or within the borders of its own country and in ways readily comprehensible to that population (including its policy makers). Expressed in another way, from a national perspective, the 
 <italic class="italic">proximal</italic> pathway is about the “here and now”. We recognize that the health effects arising in any country from the 
 <italic class="italic">proximal</italic> pathway closely align with the direct health effects described by McMichael et al. in 1996 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">15</xref>] and explored further by Butler and colleagues when first introducing four classifications of adverse health effects from climate change [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>]. These broad classifications were reflected in later work [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">17</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">18</xref>]. The International Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">1</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" class="xref">19</xref>] has predominantly highlighted such direct impacts. The 2015 Lancet Commission [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">20</xref>] emphasizes the complexity of relationships between climate-related changes and health [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" class="xref">19</xref>], distinguishing between direct and indirect impacts.
</p>
