<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par2" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">During the last glacial period the many regions experienced large variations in climate that were first identified in ice cores from central Greenland
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>
  </span>. Known as Dansgaard-Oeschger (D
  <span class="italic">-</span>O) cycles, these climate oscillations have subsequently been recognized across the globe in places such as the monsoon regions of Asia
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span>, parts of the Southern Hemisphere
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>
  </span>, and the North Pacific
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>
  </span>. The mechanisms of these abrupt warmings and intervening coolings (including ice-rafting events) remain a heavily researched topic in the paleoclimate community
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Some sediment cores from the North Pacific have a sufficiently high resolution and extend back far enough to provide evidence of D
  <span class="italic">-</span>O cycles
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>
  </span>, which are most prominent beyond 30,000 yr BP. In some cases there is good agreement between these marine proxy data and the Greenland ice-core data (e.g.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>), supporting the idea of a teleconnection between the North Atlantic realm and the North Pacific. However, lack of suitable terrestrial samples at higher latitudes (&gt;55°N) in the Pacific realm prevent this comparison. A robust and independent chronology of D
  <span class="italic">-</span>O cycles at high-latitude sites in North Pacific is therefore needed to further test the presence of teleconnections between these regions during the last glacial period. Here we present a speleothem record from Alaska that covers much of Marine Isotope Stage (MIS) 3, and provides a precise and independent chronology of short-lived warm intervals in Alaska. The robust dating of the speleothem record allows for a rigorous test of the temporal relationship of the observed warm phases in Southeastern Alaska with the D
  <span class="italic">-</span>O cycles observed in the North Atlantic.
 </p>
</sec>
