<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec14" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Speleothem EC-16-5-F was cut in half and polished. The orientation of the main growth axis changed several times in the speleothem during its growth (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>). Total length was measured at 140.5 mm. Thin sections were made and examined using optical microscopy, including blue-light epifluorescence.
 </p>
 <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A total of 21 powdered calcite samples were manually drilled for U-Th dating under a laminar flow hood. An additional 452 samples were collected for stable isotope analyses using a Merchantek micromill every 0.3 mm from 0 to 133.5 mm and every 1 mm from 133.5 to 140.5 mm. All distances are measured from the top of the stalagmite (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">U-Th samples were processed at the University of Minnesota Trace Metal Isotope Geochemistry Lab and analyzed using a ThermoFisher Neptune Plus multi-collector inductively coupled plasma mass spectrometer equipped with an Aridus desolvation nebuliser, following the method of Shen 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>.
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
  </span>. Ages are reported with 2σ errors in years before present, i.e. before the year 1950 A.D. A time-depth model was created in OxCal 4.3 using the Bayesian approach
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>
  </span>, with a variable “k” parameter of 0.1–0.2 mm
  <span class="sup">−1</span> (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>). The duration of the hiatuses were estimated using the time-depth model (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Stable isotope samples were analyzed at the University of Innsbruck using a ThermoFisher Delta V isotope ratio mass spectrometer equipped with a Gasbench II
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>
  </span>. Stable isotopes are reported in per mil relative to Vienna Peedee Belemnite (VPDB). Long-term analytical precision is better than 0.08‰ for both δ
  <span class="sup">13</span>C and δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O (1 σ). The stable isotopes were incorporated into the OxCal 4.3 time-depth model.
 </p>
</sec>
