<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Petrography</div>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Speleothem EC-16-5-F is composed of a translucent compact-columnar calcite fabric (Suppl. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>). Crystal length and width range from 0.5 to 6 mm and 0.6 to 2 mm, respectively. Individual crystals show even extinction under cross-polarized light and contain few solid and liquid inclusions. The stalagmite is segmented by distinct petrographic boundaries at 27.4, 42.5, 65, 80.9, 124.3, and 133.9 mm (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>). Crystal growth came to a halt at four of the hiatuses. In the other two cases large columnar crystals continued to grow in optical continuity across the hiatus (Suppl. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>). All hiatuses are marked by a 5 to 100 µm thin layer of micrite. Only the hiatus at 27.4 mm shows indication of slight corrosion (Suppl. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>). There is no petrographic evidence of detrital sediment present at these hiatuses, which likely rules out flooding of the cave as a cause for these interruptions of growth. Most parts of this stalagmite reveal regular A-B-type epifluorescence banding, which most likely reflects seasonally-controlled influx of soil-derived fulvic and humic acids into the epikarst.
  <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Polished slab of speleothem EC-16-5-F showing U-Th sampling locations and petrographic hiatuses. Note the presence of a cryptic hiatus (see text) represented by the dashed green line. Also shown is the time-depth model using OxCal 4.3. Note that the cryptic hiatus is incorporated into the age model (red boxes with dashed lines).</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_44231_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e469" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
