<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Speleothem deposition at El Capitan Cave</div>
 <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Deposition of speleothem EC-16-5-F occurred in stepwise fashion, growing at ~0.02 mm/yr within each growth segment (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>). As no sulfides are present in the host rock to allow for sulfuric acid dissolution of the limestone in the absence of soils
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>
  </span>, speleothem growth at this site most likely took place when soil was present in the catchment, thereby promoting the production of soil carbon dioxide and carbonic acid dissolution of the carbonate bedrock. It is likely that permafrost, had it existed, would have effectively shut down the infiltration of water and therefore prevented calcite deposition. The growth segments recorded in the stalagmite therefore most likely represent intervals of relatively mild climate when MAAT was above freezing.
 </p>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The intervals of non-deposition range from 1,000 to 28,000 years in duration (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>). In total, six distinct hiatuses and one cryptic hiatus (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>) define the boundaries of the growth segments. The latter occurs between 59,300 ± 787 and 57,970 ± 777 yr BP. Upon visual inspection, this growth segment appears continuous (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>); however, oxygen and carbon isotope values change sharply (by 0.4‰ and 3.9‰, respectively) at 128.5 mm. If we assume continuous deposition between the two dated samples, stalagmite growth slowed considerably to 0.004 mm/yr, inconsistent with typical values of ~0.02 mm/yr. We therefore suggest a cryptic hiatus at 128.5 mm (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>). Applying the growth rate of 0.02 mm/yr, a period of growth occurred for ~450 years between 59,750 ± 421 and 59,300 ± 787 yr BP. The cryptic hiatus after 59,300 ± 840 yr BP spans ~1,300 yr. Growth re-commenced between 58,000 ± 782 and 57,596 ± 797 yr BP (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The hiatuses recorded in speleothem EC-16-5-F could represent hydrological re-routing or blockage, as noted in speleothem studies elsewhere
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>
  </span>. However, these processes tend to be permanent
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>
  </span>, and are therefore not consistent with the continued growth of speleothem EC-16-5-F after each hiatus. Alternatively, periodic flooding of the cave could produce the observed hiatuses. However, there is no evidence of high-water marks or fine-grained slackwater deposits in the passageway where the speleothem was collected, or such detrital materials in the speleothem itself. Hiatuses could also form as a result of climate changes such as increased aridity
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>
  </span> or permafrost, preventing water flow and calcite deposition
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span>. As the MAAT at the site is presently about 5 °C, it is plausible that the MAAT during stadials was at or below 0 °C, and may have resulted in the development of discontinuous permafrost. Temperatures within the cave were also likely to be at or below 0 °C, as interior cave air temperatures closely correspond to the MAAT. A drop of 5 °C has been reported in Pacific marine cores during interstadial/stadial transitions
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span>. Glaciation may have also been a contributing factor in the formation of hiatuses by removing soils important for carbonate dissolution and speleothem deposition. However, the study of the glacial history in southeast Alaska/northern coastal British Columbia prior to the Last Glacial Maximum is still in its infancy. No glacial records in the region currently exist beyond the Last Glacial Maximum, which occurred between 17,000 to 22,000 yr BP
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span>. Because of the uncertainty of glacial advances in the region, we prefer to use a more conservative approach and consider permafrost development to be a principal mechanism for hiatus formation in EC-16-5-F. U-Th ages constraining the individual growth phases and the intervening hiatuses are thus used to establish a record of mild and cold climate episodes in SE Alaska.
 </p>
</sec>
