<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Synchronicity between high-latitude North Pacific and North Atlantic regions</div>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Currently there are no well-dated continuous terrestrial records from high-latitude sites in the North Pacific region that span the full interval of MIS 3, when D-O cycles are most prominent. In order to attempt to determine any apparent synchronicity between high-latitude North Pacific and North Atlantic regions, we compare episodic pulses of growth from speleothem EC-16-5-F with Greenland ice-core data.</p>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Greenland ice-core record serves as a Northern Hemisphere reference for alternating warm (Greenland interstadials, GI) and cold (Greenland stadials, GS) events during the last glacial period. We use the NGRIP record and the spliced GICCO5/ss09sea age model
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
  </span> and follow the INTIMATE event stratigraphy
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span> (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>) in our comparison with the growth record of speleothem EC-16-5-F.
  <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>(
     <span class="bold">A</span>) Timing of Marine Isotope Stages 5a to 1
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45" href="#CR45">45</a>
     </span>. (
     <span class="bold">B</span>) El Capitan Cave speleothem EC-16-5-F carbon and oxygen isotope record. Black bars show 2σ errors of the speleothem U-Th ages with corresponding sample numbers in Table 
     <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>. (
     <span class="bold">C</span>) NHSI (Northern Hemisphere summer insolation, 21 July) at 65°N
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
     </span>. (
     <span class="bold">D</span>) NGRIP oxygen isotope record
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
     </span>. (
     <span class="bold">E</span>) Color B* spectral analyses from core S0201-2-85KL
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
     </span>. Yellow vertical bars are used to highlight speleothem EC-16-5-F growth intervals.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_44231_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e1506" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Growth phases recorded in speleothem EC-16-5-F are synchronous (within 2σ error of the time-depth model) with GI events
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span> (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>) providing strong evidence for D-O cycles in Alaska. However, difference between the records are also evident. Differences are initially seen in the termination of growth episodes in EC-16-5-F, marked by the presence of hiatuses. The termination of growth in EC-16-5-F is not always synchronous with GS events
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span>. Calcite deposition at the end of GI-16.1a, GI-14b, and GI-12c stopped prior to the onset of the subsequent stadials in the Greenland record
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span> (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>). The modest discrepancies between records could possibly be due to permafrost sensitivity in Southeastern Alaska. Permafrost in the region may have developed with just a slight drop in MAAT, halting speleothem growth. This slight drop in temperature may only be subtle in the Greenland record, precluding it from being designated a GS event, but could have been significant enough to initiate the development of permafrost, resulting in the aforementioned hiatuses in EC-16-5-F. This demonstrates the high sensitivity of speleothem EC-16-5-F to changes in the MAAT, through the hypothesized linkage to permafrost development.
 </p>
 <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">GIs 2
  <span class="italic">–</span>9, 13, 15, 18, and 19 are not recorded by speleothem EC-16-5-F. GI-13 has been reported as a minor interstadial in Greenland
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span>. It is also poorly developed in the stalagmite records from Kleegruben Cave in the Austrian Alps
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
  </span> and in Crag Cave in Ireland
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
  </span>, sites which reflect the North Atlantic climate. GI-15, represented by GI-15.1 and GI-15.2, may also reflect minor interstadials, with GI-15.1 only being only 100 years long
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span>. The absence of GI′s 2
  <span class="italic">–</span>9, 18, and 19 in our speleothem record may reflect lower summer insolation during this overall time frame
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>
  </span> (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>). It is possible that permafrost persisted through these missing GI events in Southeastern Alaska. Permafrost has many complex interactions with the surrounding landscape, involving slope, aspect, soil conditions, vegetation, and snow cover, which can allow it to persist at MAATs as high as 2 °C
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
  </span>. However, even with the complexities of permafrost, the overall evidence suggests synchronicity between the high-latitude North Pacific and North Atlantic climates.
 </p>
 <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The atmospheric teleconnection observed between the Greenland record and speleothem EC-16-5-F is also observed in oceanic processes in marine core S0201-2-85KL in the western Bering Sea
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>. The marine core has a similar high-latitude as El Capitan cave at 57°30.30′N. The proxy used in core S0201-2-85KL as an age control beyond ~30,000 yr BP is color B* spectral analyses (sediment color analyses used as a proxy for diatom content vs. detrital input)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>, in part due to its similar fluctuations with the NGRIP δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O record
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
  </span> (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>). Increasing color B* indicates more diatoms
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
  </span>, and in core SO201-2-85KL are considered brief intervals of enhanced marine productivity, sudden sea-ice melt associated with the subsequent release of ice-rafted debris, and a higher bottom water calcite saturation state, and may be related to D-O cycles observed in the NGRIP record
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>. Color B* spectral analyses was therefore chosen as the principle proxy to correlate with growth phases recorded in speleothem EC-16-5-F to determine if they were synchronous (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Growth phases in speleothem EC-16-5-F are synchronous, within 2σ error, with increases in color B* during Greenland interstadial (GI) events 10, 11, 12c, 14b
  <span class="italic">–</span>e, and 20c
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span> (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>). GI events 16.1a and 17.2
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span>, which are observed in speleothem EC-16-5-F, and are notable peaks in the Greenland INTIMATE chronology
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span> (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>), are not prominent in color B* in core S0201-2-85KL
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
  </span>. Color B* may not be a suitable proxy to show these events. Alternatively, there may be an error with wiggle-matching color B* in core S0201-2-85KL with the NGRIP record, or these two events are not well-expressed in all North Pacific marine records.
 </p>
</sec>
