<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s9" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Method</div>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Participants</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Forty-seven undergraduate and graduate students from a large West Coast University in the United States participated in this study. All participants were recruited from the Department of Communication's research participant pool and received class credit for participating.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ages ranged from 18 to 28 (Median = 20 y) and 29 subjects were female. Many participants reported prior immersive VR experience (over 90%), curbing any concern that a first-time immersive VR task may impede learning potential (Bricken, 
   <a rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" href="#B9">1991</a>). Random assignment was indeed successful as participant age [
   <span class="italic">t</span>
   <sub>(45)</sub> = −0.47, 
   <span class="italic">p</span> = 0.64] and gender [
   <div class="inline-formula">
    <div id="M1" class="math">
     <div class="msubsup">
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mo">χ</span>
      </div>
      <div class="mrow">
       <div class="mrow">
        <span stretchy="false" class="mo">(</span>
        <div class="mrow">
         <span class="mn">1</span>
        </div>
        <span stretchy="false" class="mo">)</span>
       </div>
      </div>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mn">2</span>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div> = 1.18, 
   <span class="italic">p</span> = 0.28] were evenly distributed across conditions.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Materials</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Consistent with the previous experiment, the immersive virtual experience placed participants underwater on a simulated Mediterranean reef. Depending on condition, participants had one of two different self-avatars: (1) a roughly humanoid-shaped coral, or (2) a scuba diver. The apparatus for this study were consistent with Study 1; both head rotation and head translation were tracked.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Procedure</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Participants were randomly assigned to one of two self-avatar conditions (Coral avatar 
   <span class="italic">n</span> = 24, Scuba Diver avatar 
   <span class="italic">n</span> = 23). Besides this change, all experimental conditions were identical (Figure 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F4" href="#F4">4</a> depicts a participant in each experimental condition).
  </p>
  <div id="F4" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Figure 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>A participant experiencing the virtual environment. 
     <span class="bold">(A)</span> The participant wears an Oculus Development Kit 2 (DK2) VR display, whose internal accelerometer and gyroscope track 3-degrees of orientation for the user's head. 
     <span class="bold">(B)</span> The Oculus near infrared (IR) camera tracks IR sensors embedded in the DK2 headset to allow for translational tracking. The IR camera combined with the DK2's accelerometer allows for 6 degrees of freedom tracked on the user's head. 
     <span class="bold">(C)</span> In the Scuba Diver condition, the user embodies a scuba diver to visit the virtual rocky reef. 
     <span class="bold">(D)</span> In the Coral Condition, the user embodies a piece of coral that lives on the rocky reef.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="fpsyg-09-02364-g0004" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <sec class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Pre-test</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Prior to entering the virtual world, participants took a survey consisting of the 14-item Connectedness to Nature Scale (CNS; Mayer and Frantz, 
    <a rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34">2004</a>), which measures the magnitude of emotional connection to nature and the environment on a scale of (1) strongly disagree, to (7) strongly agree. The seven-point NEP scale from Study 1 (Dunlap et al., 
    <a rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19">2000</a>), six short answer questions on the causes and effects of ocean acidification, and several demographic measures were also evaluated. Participants were allowed as much time as needed for the pre-test.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Immersive VR experience</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">After the pre-test, participants were introduced to the VR hardware and the remainder of the experiment. The researcher helped participants put on the HMD and headphones, made adjustments to ensure comfort and A/V clarity, and the VR experience began. Participants were standing for the duration of the experiment. The researcher stayed close to the participant and wore headphones to monitor the person's progress through the VR experience.</p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the virtual world, participants experienced synchronous environmental feedback designed to make them feel more connected to their self-avatars. Participants saw a fish swim up to their bodies in the virtual world that would begin to repeatedly bump against them. Concurrently, the researcher used a plastic fish on a stick to gently tap the participant on his or her physical body in the same location on their torso as in the virtual world (Figure 
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">5</a>). These taps continued for ~30 s, then the fish swam away. Participants heard an audible “tap” sound as the fish bumped them. This synchronized sensory feedback aims to make participants feel a greater sense of embodiment in their self-avatars (Botvinick and Cohen, 
    <a rid="B8" ref-type="bibr" href="#B8">1998</a>; Ehrsson, 
    <a rid="B20" ref-type="bibr" href="#B20">2007</a>; Slater et al., 
    <a rid="B56" ref-type="bibr" href="#B56">2010</a>). No additional interaction with the researcher occurred. Similar to Study 1, participants did not move or swim in the environment. Participants' position was tracked in the virtual space using the external Rift infrared sensor but they did not physically walk around.
   </p>
   <div id="F5" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
    <span class="label">Figure 5</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>
      <span class="bold">(A)</span> The researcher uses a wooden dowel to tap the participant gently in the abdomen. This haptic feedback corresponds with a simultaneous bumping action that occurs in the virtual environment. 
      <span class="bold">(B)</span> A fish approaches the participant's virtual body and bumps it repeatedly. The fish's bumping action coincides with the researcher's gentle tapping action in the real world.
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="fpsyg-09-02364-g0005" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The entire virtual experience took ~6 1/2 min and then participants removed the HMD and headphones. Once subjects confirmed they were not motion sick or otherwise uncomfortable from the virtual experience (none were), they continued to the post-test.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Post-test</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Participants completed the post-test survey on a computer in the experiment room with no time limit. Post-test measures included a presence questionnaire (adapted from Bailenson and Yee, 
    <a rid="B3" ref-type="bibr" href="#B3">2008</a>), the CNS scale, the NEP scale, and six questions from the pre-test about ocean acidification knowledge.
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Measures</div>
  <sec class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ocean acidification knowledge</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Responses to questions concerning ocean acidification knowledge were independently scored by two coders, blind to participant condition. Significant differences between graders' scores were rare but resolved after discussion, leading to a high inter-rater reliability (Table 
    <a rid="T1" ref-type="table" href="#T1">1</a>). In instances where the scores of two raters differed, the average score was used. Scores were summed for each participant, leading to an overall knowledge measure out of twelve possible points.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Environmental attitude</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Responses to the NEP scale were averaged to create an overall measure of environmental concern (Dunlap et al., 
    <a rid="B19" ref-type="bibr" href="#B19">2000</a>).
   </p>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Items from the CNS scale (Mayer and Frantz, 
    <a rid="B34" ref-type="bibr" href="#B34">2004</a>) were highly correlated (Table 
    <a rid="T1" ref-type="table" href="#T1">1</a>) and averaged. Higher scores reflect more connectedness to nature.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Presence</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Responses to 9 presence questions were averaged to create an overall presence measure in the virtual environment. Overall, participants reported a moderate level of presence in immersive VR, [(
    <span class="italic">M</span> = 5.09, 
    <span class="italic">SD</span> = 0.73), min = 3.56, max = 6.89].
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
</sec>
