<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Measures</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Consistent with our prior studies, we asked questions about ocean acidification and administered the CNS, NEP, and presence scales. We also evaluated the total distance traveled underwater as a gauge of interactivity in the virtual environment. Finally, other exploratory measures such as the perceived room temperature and ratings of simulator sickness (Kennedy et al., 
  <a rid="B26" ref-type="bibr" href="#B26">1993</a>) were investigated (for these ancillary measures, see Appendix 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1" href="#SM1">D</a>).
 </p>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ocean acidification knowledge</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Participants answered three questions about ocean acidification and their responses were judged by three blind raters. The questions asked, “What is ocean acidification?,” “What are the causes of ocean acidification?,” and “What are the predicted effects of ocean acidification?” Following the procedure established in Study 1, questions received grades of 0, 1, or 2 based on their response accuracy. Questions were randomized in the judgment process to control for order effects. Ideal answers are located in Appendix 
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1" href="#SM1">E</a>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Attitude</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Participants responded to two primary attitude questions. The first question asked how far away the consequences of ocean acidification felt, on a scale from (1) extremely far, to (5) extremely close [(
   <span class="italic">M</span> = 3.33, 
   <span class="italic">SD</span> = 1.02), min = 1.0, max = 5.0]. The second question consisted of six items where on five-point scales, participants responded to the consequences of ocean acidification, ranging from (a) unimportant to important (b), of no concern to of concern (c), irrelevant to relevant (d), means nothing to means a lot (e), doesn't matter to matters a lot (f), uninvolving to involving (Cronbach's α = 0.94). Overall, participants reported an above-average level of concern for ocean acidification, [(
   <span class="italic">M</span> = 4.05, 
   <span class="italic">SD</span> = 0.74), min = 1.67, max = 5.0]. These two measures were evaluated separately and also averaged to create an overall attitude score toward ocean acidification [(
   <span class="italic">M</span> = 3.69, 
   <span class="italic">SD</span> = 0.80), min = 1.83, max = 5.0; Cronbach's α = 0.78].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">CNS and NEP scales</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Participants responded to the CNS, [(
   <span class="italic">M</span> = 3.36, 
   <span class="italic">SD</span> = 0.53), min = 2.36, max = 4.79], and NEP scales, [(
   <span class="italic">M</span> = 3.72, 
   <span class="italic">SD</span> = 0.58), min = 2.33, max = 4.80]. For this study, the CNS and NEP scales were measured from (1) strongly disagree to (5) strongly agree.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Presence</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Self-reported presence was the averaged response to five, five-point Likert scale questions, [(
   <span class="italic">M</span> = 3.16; 
   <span class="italic">SD</span> = 0.92), min = 1.60, max = 4.80] in the post-survey that measured the degree to which participants felt surrounded by the virtual environment.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Total number of snails found</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We tracked the number of snails found in the 
   <span class="italic">High pH</span> and 
   <span class="italic">Medium pH</span> zones as an indicator of activity level. On average, participants found over 23 snails across the two zones combined, [(
   <span class="italic">M</span> = 23.74; 
   <span class="italic">SD</span> = 3.87), min = 13.0, max = 29.0].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Distance traveled underwater</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We also tracked the participants' viewpoint through the virtual world, which let us calculate the total distance traveled underwater across three zones, [(
   <span class="italic">M</span> = 128.12 m; 
   <span class="italic">SD</span> = 37.17 m), min = 45.49 m, max = 193.26 m].
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
