<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s13" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results and discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We assessed attitude toward ocean acidification and inquisitiveness based on head and hand movements, which are evaluated as separate predictors. We used movement to predict attitude and inquisitiveness because we were interested in exploring physical actions that may be indicative of environmental concern and if people who move more in the virtual space are also likely to express greater interest in environmental issues (Clark, 
  <a rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" href="#B14">1997</a>; Gallagher, 
  <a rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" href="#B21">2005</a>). For each regression model, we include physical movement and physical rotation of the head and hands as separate predictors because changes to these body parts are often concurrent. That is, movement of the head and hands is also accompanied by rotation of the head and hands (ρ = 0.64, 
  <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.001; Table 
  <a rid="T4" ref-type="table" href="#T4">4</a>).
 </p>
 <div id="T4" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Table 4</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Correlation Matrix: Study 3 (Two-tailed, 
    <span class="italic">N</span> = 167).
   </p>
  </div>
  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
   <thead>
    <tr>
     <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
     <th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
      <span class="bold">Inquisitiveness</span>
     </th>
     <th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
      <span class="bold">Attitude</span>
     </th>
     <th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
      <span class="bold">Total movement</span>
     </th>
     <th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
      <span class="bold">Total rotation</span>
     </th>
     <th valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
      <span class="bold">Search activity</span>
     </th>
    </tr>
   </thead>
   <tbody>
    <tr>
     <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Inquisitiveness</td>
     <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
     <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19
      <a ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN3" href="#TN3">
       <span class="sup">*</span>
      </a>
     </td>
     <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td>
     <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.05</td>
     <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Attitude</td>
     <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19
      <a ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN3" href="#TN3">
       <span class="sup">*</span>
      </a>
     </td>
     <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
     <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.05</td>
     <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.10</td>
     <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.10</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total movement</td>
     <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.10</td>
     <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.05</td>
     <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
     <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64
      <a ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN4" href="#TN4">
       <span class="sup">***</span>
      </a>
     </td>
     <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34
      <a ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN4" href="#TN4">
       <span class="sup">***</span>
      </a>
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total rotation</td>
     <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.05</td>
     <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.10</td>
     <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64
      <a ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN4" href="#TN4">
       <span class="sup">***</span>
      </a>
     </td>
     <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
     <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47
      <a ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN4" href="#TN4">
       <span class="sup">***</span>
      </a>
     </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Search Activity</td>
     <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td>
     <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">−0.10</td>
     <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34
      <a ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN4" href="#TN4">
       <span class="sup">***</span>
      </a>
     </td>
     <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47
      <a ref-type="table-fn" rid="TN4" href="#TN4">
       <span class="sup">***</span>
      </a>
     </td>
     <td valign="top" align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">—</td>
    </tr>
   </tbody>
  </table>
  <div class="table-wrap-foot">
   <p>
    <span class="italic">Correlations were computed using Spearman's rho</span>.
   </p>
   <fn id="TN3" class="fn" xmlns="">
    <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">*</span>
    <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
     <span class="italic">p &lt; 0.05</span>,
    </p>
   </fn>
   <fn id="TN4" class="fn" xmlns="">
    <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">***</span>
    <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
     <span class="italic">p &lt; 0.001. Inquisitiveness was a dichotomous variable (1 = would like more information, 0 = would not like more information). Search activity is a standardized index of the grabbed and collected biodiversity during the species count</span>.
    </p>
   </fn>
  </div>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used a layered analytic approach to isolate if movement or rotation predict attitude and inquisitiveness. First, we combined the total movement of the head and two hands into a single predictor, 
  <span class="italic">total physical movement</span>, and the total rotation of the head and two hands into a single predictor, 
  <span class="italic">total physical rotation</span>. If statistically significant, these global variables were then isolated by body part (head, two separate hands) to discover how movement and rotation of specific body features predict attitude and inquisitiveness.
 </p>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Attitude</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Total physical movement and total physical rotation did not predict participants' attitude toward the immediacy of ocean acidification [
   <span class="italic">p</span>'s &gt; 0.40]. Therefore, we did not inspect this effect further.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Inquisitiveness</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A logistic regression model predicting participant inquisitiveness (1 = would like more information, 0 = would not like more information) with total physical movement and total physical rotation as standardized predictors showed a significant effect of total physical movement [(β = 0.45, 
   <span class="italic">SE</span> = 0.23); Wald = 3.90, 
   <span class="italic">p</span> = 0.048, Exp(β) = 1.57; 95% CI for Exp(β) [1.00, 2.47], but no effect of total physical rotation [
   <span class="italic">p</span> = 0.12, Exp(β) &lt; 1; 95% CI for Exp(β) [0.44, 1.10], Nagelkerke 
   <span class="italic">R</span>
   <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.03].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Consistent with our layered analytic approach, we then ran three separate logistic regression models for each body part's movement (e.g., head, left hand, right hand) and concurrent rotation as independent predictors. The data revealed that the total physical movement of the participant's right hand, proxied by the movement of the virtual right-hand model, significantly predicted inquisitiveness [(β = 0.54, 
   <span class="italic">SE</span> = 0.25); Wald = 4.74, 
   <span class="italic">p</span> = 0.029, Exp(β) = 1.71; 95% CI for Exp(β) [1.06, 2.77]. Physical total rotation of the right hand was marginally associated with inquisitiveness, [
   <span class="italic">p</span> = 0.069, Exp(β) = 0.64; 95% CI for Exp(β) [0.39, 1.04], Nagelkerke 
   <span class="italic">R</span>
   <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.04]. Movement and rotation of the left hand were not significant predictors of inquisitiveness [
   <span class="italic">p</span>'s &gt; 0.19, Exp(β) &lt; 1.32; Nagelkerke 
   <span class="italic">R</span>
   <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.02], and neither were movement or rotation of the head [
   <span class="italic">p</span>'s &gt; 0.18, Exp(β) &lt; 1.27; Nagelkerke 
   <span class="italic">R</span>
   <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.02].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">Post-hoc</span> correlations
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on the prior evidence suggesting that right-hand movements can predict inquisitiveness, we analyzed the data for other 
   <span class="italic">post-hoc</span> relationships. The point-biserial correlation between inquisitiveness and attitude toward the closeness of ocean acidification revealed a positive relationship (ρ = 0.19, 
   <span class="italic">p</span> = 0.014). The exact direction of this effect is unclear, however, because it is plausible that the more people believe climate change is an immediate threat, the more they may be interested in learning about the issue. On the other hand, if people report being inquisitive about climate change, they may also feel like the issue is impending. Further research is required to understand this effect more clearly. Finally, we found that participants' total body movement (ρ = 0.34, 
   <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.001) and rotation (ρ = 0.47, 
   <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.001) were significantly correlated with total search activity (e.g., total species grabbed and collected in the species count). All correlations for this study's key variables are located in Table 
   <a rid="T4" ref-type="table" href="#T4">4</a>.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The data suggest that participant right hand movements can predict if people want to learn more about climate change. How can right hand movements predict inquisitiveness? Prior work suggests that people often process information differently based on the side of their physical body that is completing an action (Casasanto, 
   <a rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" href="#B12">2011</a>; Bailey et al., 
   <a rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" href="#B4">2016</a>). This idea is called processing fluency (Reber et al., 
   <a rid="B50" ref-type="bibr" href="#B50">2004</a>), with evidence suggesting that making one hand inaccessible (e.g., wearing a bulky ski glove on one hand) changes how people perceive the space (e.g., the side that is accessible is viewed more positively than the side that is inaccessible; Casasanto and Chrysikou, 
   <a rid="B13" ref-type="bibr" href="#B13">2011</a>). It is plausible that people with more right-handed movements also were inquisitive because they enjoyed the virtual experience and formed a positive association with it. This contention is worth exploring more directly in future work.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There are two primary limitations of this study worth noting. First, we did not gauge handedness of the participants. Second, people at the Tribeca Film Festival paid $40 to get into the VR arcade and stood in line for our immersive VR booth throughout the week-long festival. This information suggests that subjects who participated in our study may therefore have been extrinsically motivated to acquire knowledge about novel experiences in general. Given that we have some evidence that movement can predict interest in learning about climate change, albeit data from an uncontrolled field study, we tested the robustness of these effects in a more sterile laboratory environment with university undergraduates.</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
