<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s12" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Method</div>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Participants</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the 5 days of the Tribeca Film Festival, 488 people participated the immersive VR experience either wholly or partially, and several participant exclusion criteria were used. First, we discarded data collected from the 1st day due to general technical failures. Data from participants were also excluded if the individual did not comply with the study's task (e.g., if he or she swam so far outside the simulated reef that they missed the interactive simulation). Finally, we excluded participants who failed to respond to our attitude prompts in the post-underwater experience. This reduced our sample size to 167 participants, though this number remains large enough to possibly detect an effect of physical movements on interest in learning about ocean acidification.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Due to time constraints set by the festival—to have an exhibit, virtual experiences were required to be &lt;10 min long—we did not formally measure demographics of participants. In general, however, there was greater age and demographic variance in this study than a typical sample of university undergraduates.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Materials</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For this study, we used the HTC Vive with a resolution of 2160 × 1200 and an update rate of 90 Hz (e.g., 90 frames per second, per eye), tracked at a 22 ms latency rate. Two tracking base stations provided a six degrees-of-freedom control each for the head (through sensors embedded inside the Vive) and the two hands (through hand controllers; 120 Hz update rate, 8.333 ms latency). Participants also received audio feedback provided by stereo headphones. We used Worldviz's Vizard for developing the VR experience and used the 3D models developed by Worldviz around Italy's Ischia Reef. The 3D environment modeled the Mediterranean rocky reefs located off the coast of Ischia, Italy, which were simulated in Studies 1 and 2. The virtual environment in Study 3 was similar, but not identical to the virtual environment in Study 2. Slight modifications were made to the virtual environment due to affordances granted by more advanced hardware and computing power. The modifications included: increasing the fidelity of the graphics and the size of the virtual space that could be explored (e.g., participants could move and interact more within the environment).</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The immersive VR stations were 10' × 10' booths with four curtained walls. It should be noted, however, that the size of the virtual space exceeded physical space limitations. We encouraged participants to stand in one place, swim by moving their arms in a breaststroke motion, and rotate to change their direction.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Procedure</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The experiment, including consent procedure, was a self-contained 8 min experience. The embedded informed consent procedure was approved by our university's Institutional Review Board. Pre-recorded narratives for this field trip, recorded by an expert voice-actor, were played through noise-canceling stereo headphones and guided the participants throughout the experience. To display text and visual information, we used virtual information boards. Participants responded to the experimental questions by placing their hands inside virtual choice-boxes and clicking a button on the HTC Vive controllers to select answers to written prompts that appeared within the virtual environment.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The VR experience began on a virtual boat floating above an Ischian Reef (see Figure 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="F6" href="#F6">6</a>). Participants first viewed and responded to the informed consent. A series of narratives and infographics then trained each participant on their task, which was to swim underwater by moving their arms in a breaststroke motion and find marine life to measure the biodiversity of the reef. The immersive VR scene brought participants to the first underwater zone, modeled around a healthy rocky reef. Participants were asked to locate three different underwater animal species (snails, octopi, and eel) as part of a “species count,” an activity modeled after biodiversity assessments that marine biologists conduct in the field. For the next 2 min, participants used their arms to swim around the virtual underwater reef looking for the species of animals and collecting as many as they could find by picking them up with their hand controllers and placing them into a bucket located at the reef's center. A dive slate—modeled after the slates used by marine biologists—attached to each participant's virtual left wrist, displayed the remaining time, and how many of each species had been collected.
  </p>
  <div id="F6" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Figure 6</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>
     <span class="bold">(A)</span> The participant begins the experience by listening to an introductory narration and watching short tutorials that describe how he will interact with objects in the underwater environment. 
     <span class="bold">(B)</span> The participant engages in a “species count.” He refers to the dive slate attached to his virtual left wrist to see which species are on the list, how many he has found already, and how much time is left. The participant is given 2 min to find species in the first healthy underwater zone. 
     <span class="bold">(C)</span> The participant is transported to an unhealthy zone with higher levels of acidity. He is given another 2 min to conduct a species count in this area.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="fpsyg-09-02364-g0006" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">After 2 min, participants were moved to an acidified zone and asked to perform the same species collection task, however, the acidified zone only contained grass and degraded snails. This subtly communicated the message about the ill effects of ocean acidification, implying that the healthy species could no longer survive in an acidified environment. After counting species in the acidified zones, participants returned to the boat and compared the number and the variety of species in the two zones on an infographic. The narration then told participants about the general consequences of ocean acidification around the world. Participants then responded to an attitude and inquisitiveness question related to ocean acidification, which were presented inside the VR world, and then the experience ended with credits and acknowledgments.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Measures</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Given that the measures for this study were administered during the immersive VR experience and the focus of the venue was not on experimental studies, we avoided standardized questionnaires such as those used in our previous experiments. Instead, we created two simpler dependent variables to measure each participant's attitude toward the immediacy of ocean acidification and inquisitiveness about the issue at large.</p>
  <sec class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Movement</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We tracked the head and hand movements of participants during the species count, which included working with the virtual slate, to discover if the amount of movement predicted attitude or inquisitiveness. Descriptive statistics for head and hand movements are located in Appendix 
    <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="SM1" href="#SM1">C</a>.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Attitude</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">After the immersive VR experience ended, participants responded to the question, “How far away do the consequences of ocean acidification feel to you?” with five answer choices: (1) extremely far, (2) far, (3) reasonable time remains, (4) close, and (5) extremely close. The median response was higher than the midpoint (4), with a slightly smaller mean level of concern for the consequences of ocean acidification [(
    <span class="italic">M</span> = 3.53, 
    <span class="italic">SD</span> = 0.97), min = 1.0, max = 5.0].
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Inquisitiveness</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">After the attitudinal question, participants answered yes or no to the question, “Would you like us to send you more information about ocean acidification?” Approximately one-third of participants asked for more information (53/167; 31.7%).</p>
  </sec>
  <sec class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Species count and search activity</div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We counted the number of species that each participant grabbed during the underwater experience [(
    <span class="italic">M</span> = 10.22; 
    <span class="italic">SD</span> = 14.17), min = 0, max = 116.0]. This measure differed, however, from the number of species that participants put into their collection buckets [(
    <span class="italic">M</span> = 3.90; 
    <span class="italic">SD</span> = 3.57), min = 0, max = 21]. These items were highly correlated (ρ = 0.74, 
    <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.001) and we therefore combined these scores into a standardized index called 
    <span class="italic">search activity</span> to evaluate participant overall interactivity level during the species count.
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
</sec>
