<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s7" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results and discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The data were analyzed using hierarchical linear mixed models with a random effect for participant to account for multiple, non-independent observations by each student. Note, data and experimental scripts are available from the authors upon request.</p>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ocean acidification knowledge</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As expected, there was a significant effect of time on knowledge about ocean acidification, [
   <span class="italic">F</span>
   <sub>(4, 69.08)</sub> = 18.85, 
   <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.001, η
   <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.50]. Table 
   <a rid="T2" ref-type="table" href="#T2">2</a> displays the trend of knowledge gain over time and a crucial increase in ocean acidification knowledge after the immersive VR intervention (from Time 2 to Time 3). 
   <span class="italic">Bonferroni</span>-corrected adjustments support this pattern as ocean acidification knowledge was significantly higher for all time points from Time 3 onward, compared to Times 1 and 2 [
   <span class="italic">p</span>'s &lt; 0.001].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Considering students who participated in at least one of the open-water dives during the study's time period, we observed a significant Dive Trip (trip 1, trip 2) X Time (first, second, third, fourth, fifth meeting) interaction, 
   <span class="italic">F</span>
   <sub>(4, 46.21)</sub> = 2.85, 
   <span class="italic">p</span> = 0.034. Further inspection of this pattern revealed that only during the last session (Time 5), students who went on the first open-water dive reported significantly more ocean acidification knowledge than participants who went on the second dive (
   <span class="italic">p</span> = 0.009). This suggests that a physical-world experience may have a positive impact on learning about complex marine phenomena if it precedes the virtual world. The effect is downstream and not immediate, however. We interpret these data with caution because this study was not a controlled experiment and there may be other factors accounting for the difference between the diving conditions.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Environmental attitude</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There was no effect of environmental attitude over time or between dive trips [
   <span class="italic">p</span>'s &gt; 0.15, η
   <span class="sup">2</span> &lt; 0.01].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Presence</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There was no difference in reported levels of presence for participants who went scuba diving before (
   <span class="italic">M</span> = 4.05, 
   <span class="italic">SD</span> = 2.03) or after (
   <span class="italic">M</span> = 5.87, 
   <span class="italic">SD</span> = 0.77) the immersive VR experience, [Welch's 
   <span class="italic">t</span>
   <sub>(3.35)</sub> = −1.74, 
   <span class="italic">p</span> = 0.17, 
   <span class="italic">d</span> = 1.18].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study provides evidence that students in a high school classroom setting can learn about marine science in immersive VR. As expected, overall student knowledge about ocean acidification was low at the beginning of the program. The relatively stable knowledge gain, weeks after the immersive VR field trip, demonstrates the potential of using this technology to facilitate learning over time. An initial open-water scuba dive seems to have increased the effectiveness of the virtual experience, while the exact mechanism remains unclear and our relatively small sample prevents broad conclusions to be made from these data. Finally, we observed a null effect for changes in environmental attitudes and presence. These patterns may be genuine or perhaps an artifact of an underpowered design. We therefore continue to explore these dimensions in future studies.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We also report that no pragmatic issues occurred when deploying an immersive VR experience outside of the lab. Students did not get sick, nor did they find the immersive VR experience disruptive in their learning experience. These outcomes were not empirical certainties and should not be overlooked.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There are important limitations to this experiment that we address in Study 2. First, we transition the experimental design to a controlled lab setting that allows for a tighter manipulation of the immersive VR experience. Our high school sample was also admittedly small. In Study 2, we recruit a larger number of university undergraduates to participate in our experiment and perform an exploratory study to investigate if different avatar embodiment may affect knowledge gain and how people feel about ocean acidification. Embodiment is often an important method to induce attitude change and behavior (Kilteni et al., 
   <a rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" href="#B27">2012</a>), but has seldom been applied to learning about climate change. We therefore position this study as exploratory to investigate how different avatar embodiment affects learning.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
