<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Participants</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Forty-four students from a large West Coast University in the United States participated in the experiment for course credit. One participant was excluded due to hardware failures, leaving 24 females and 19 males in the final sample.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A total of 21 participants swam using the remote control, henceforth called the Joystick condition, and 22 participants swam using their physical gestures, henceforth called the Gestures condition. Figure 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F7" href="#F7">7</a> shows a participant in each condition. Random assignment was indeed successful for this study as participant age [
  <span class="italic">t</span>
  <sub>(41)</sub> = −0.78, 
  <span class="italic">p</span> = 0.44] and gender [
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="M5" class="math">
    <div class="msubsup">
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mo">χ</span>
     </div>
     <div class="mrow">
      <div class="mrow">
       <span stretchy="false" class="mo">(</span>
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mn">1</span>
       </div>
       <span stretchy="false" class="mo">)</span>
      </div>
     </div>
     <div class="mrow">
      <span class="mn">2</span>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div> = 0.29, 
  <span class="italic">p</span> = 0.86] were evenly distributed across conditions.
 </p>
 <div id="F7" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 7</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>
    <span class="bold">(A)</span> In the Gestures condition, the participant is outfitted with Worldviz PPT-E infrared sensors attached to her wrists, to allow her to swim through the virtual ocean. The participant moves her arms in a breast-stroke-like motion to swim forward through the environment and turns her head to change direction. 
    <span class="bold">(B)</span> In the Joystick condition, the participant uses a Wiimote controller to swim through the environment. She presses the arrow keys on the Wiimote controller to control the direction in which she swims and can turn her head to change directions.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="fpsyg-09-02364-g0007" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
