<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Virtual reality and science education</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Since the 1990's VR has been tested and used as a tool for Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics (STEM) education. According to Salzman et al. (
  <a rid="B52" ref-type="bibr" href="#B52">1999</a>), learning in VR is possible because VR systems produce highly engaging experiences, which can lead to greater focus on the learning topic (Bricken and Byrne, 
  <a rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" href="#B10">1993</a>). VR puts users within a virtual learning environment that reflects the topic of interest (e.g., placing students within a cell if they are learning about human biology), which can offer perspectives that are difficult to realize in other learning settings (see Johnson et al., 
  <a rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" href="#B25">2002</a>). VR can be effective for learning because it enables “users to interact with spatial representations” from many frames of reference (Salzman et al., 
  <a rid="B52" ref-type="bibr" href="#B52">1999</a>, p. 294). Finally, the addition of auditory, haptic, and other sensory feedback allows users participate in a world that feels unmediated. Such features provide a multidimensional experience that can aid in cognitive processing and information retention (Ragan et al., 
  <a rid="B48" ref-type="bibr" href="#B48">2012</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A classic example of VR developed for learning about science was created by Dede (
  <a rid="B16" ref-type="bibr" href="#B16">2009</a>), who designed a desktop VR program called River City (see Clarke and Dede, 
  <a rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" href="#B15">2009</a>). The program's goal is to teach students about the scientific method by progressing through different parts of the city. Students develop research questions about why River City is experiencing health issues or why people are getting sick at uneven rates. Participants move through the curriculum by collecting, analyzing, and interpreting science data.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An extensive review of the research on educational virtual environments by Mikropoulos and Natsis (
  <a rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38">2011</a>) suggests that most VR programs are consistent with River City, using desktop or non-immersive technology for learning (e.g., computers, styluses, joysticks). For example, Minogue et al. (
  <a rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39">2006</a>) gave middle school students a desktop VR program to explore the details of a cell. In the treatment group, students received visual and haptic feedback as they explored a virtual cell and the control group only received visual feedback. The data revealed positive learning effects for students in both groups after comparing pre- to post-test knowledge scores about cells. Haptic feedback improved knowledge scores for some low-achieving students, but overall, it did not lead to learning differences between groups.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The prior patterns have been summarized at scale in a recent meta-analysis that evaluated the effect of desktop VR instruction on learning and knowledge gain (Merchant et al., 
  <a rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37">2014</a>). Across nearly 30 studies, Merchant et al. (
  <a rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" href="#B37">2014</a>) observed that desktop VR interventions produce a significant, positive effect on leaning outcomes and knowledge gain in K-12 higher education. We use this meta-analytic evidence as support for the idea that instruction through predominantly desktop VR is effective and can lead to positive knowledge gain for many science topics. It is still unclear, however, if immersive VR can facilitate learning about complex social and environmental issues.
 </p>
</sec>
