<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par32" class="p">Our results indicate climate change will cause large declines in 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">finmarchicus</italic>, especially in the Gulf of Maine and Georges Bank. This decline is projected for both RCP scenarios at a similar rate through 2041–2060. After that, densities in the RCP 4.5 scenario decrease at a much slower rate, while populations continue to decrease under the RCP 8.5 scenario. The Gulf of Maine and Georges Bank rely on 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">finmarchicus</italic> as a crucial link in the food web, transferring energy from phytoplankton through the marine food web and into vital fisheries species, such as larval cod and haddock
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">6</xref>
 </sup>. 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">finmarchicus</italic> is the primary prey of the North Atlantic right whale (
 <italic class="italic">Eubalaena glacialis</italic>), which is endangered with an estimated 526 individuals cataloged by the North Atlantic Right Whale Consortium in 2014
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73" class="xref">73</xref>
 </sup>. North Atlantic right whales have shown extremely slow recovery since the 1931 commercial fishing ban, possibly indicating that fluctuating food availability is contributing to their limited population growth
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR74" class="xref">74</xref>
 </sup>, although incidental anthropogenic interference (e.g. entanglements, ship strikes) is still a significant source of mortality
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR75" class="xref">75</xref>
 </sup>. These whales require ~500 kg of 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">finmarchicus</italic> per day to sustain themselves
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76" class="xref">76</xref>
 </sup>. As a result, calving success is correlated with 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">finmarchicus</italic> concentration even at regional scales
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">9</xref>
 </sup> despite right whales requiring small (10 s of m), extremely dense patches of 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">finmarchicus</italic>
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77" class="xref">77</xref>
 </sup>. Although our model did not resolve these smaller spatial scales, we do show that the large-scale conditions for 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">finmarchicus</italic> are going to become less favorable under climate change. These conditions are likely to negatively affect 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">finmarchicus</italic> size as well as density
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78" class="xref">78</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR80" class="xref">80</xref>
 </sup>, potentially having a severe negative effect on right whales and the rest of the food web.
</p>
