<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par34" class="p">In other niche models
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">20</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" class="xref">35</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" class="xref">38</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR81" class="xref">81</xref>
 </sup>, SST was determined to be an extremely important component in determining probability of occurrence. However, SST was the only variable we used that was deemed insignificant by the GAM. This is due to our inclusion of BT, without which SST is highly significant. This could indicate that BT is a better variable to use in modelling 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">finmarchicus</italic>, or that dynamics are different when attempting to model the entire North Atlantic instead of just the Northwest Atlantic studied here. Additionally, BT could be a more important factor in determining density, but likelihood of occurrence can be modelled using only surface variables. This model is only a proxy for the different effects of changing conditions, so the exact physiological and life history mechanisms being disrupted by climate change are uncertain. Because depth is static, BT is the most important variable in our study driving the declines of 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">finmarchicus</italic> with climate change. Increasing temperature can affect 
 <italic class="italic">C</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">finmarchicus</italic> populations in a variety of ways including decreasing body size
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR78" class="xref">78</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR79" class="xref">79</xref>
 </sup>, egg production
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">23</xref>
 </sup>, or available nutrients and dissolved oxygen
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" class="xref">48</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
