<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Maxent (ver.3.3.3k; 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cs.princeton.edu/~schapire/maxent/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.cs.princeton.edu/~schapire/maxent/</ext-link>) was used to model spatial distributions and produce habitat suitability maps of the AIWs for the present‐day scenarios based on bioclimatic variables and occurrence records (Merow et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32684-bib-0044" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). For the modeling, we accounted for occurrence records in both the invasive and native ranges because it improves the performance of ecological niche modeling (Merow et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32684-bib-0044" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Mainali et al., 
 <xref rid="ece32684-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Shabani &amp; Kumar, 
 <xref rid="ece32684-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; Figure 
 <xref rid="ece32684-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1</xref>). In our study, three models were built using the occurrence records of native, invasive, and both native and invasive ranges, respectively. A fourfold cross‐validation approach was used to estimate the uncertainties in the response curves and occurrence predictions. The occurrence records were divided into four approximately equal random partitions. In turn, three of the partitions were used to train the model, while the fourth was used to generate the SDM estimate for its validation (each run used a different random sample points). Detailed information on the dataset of input occurrence records was shown for each AIW in Table S1. The maximum number of background points was set to 10,000. The convergence threshold was set to 0.0001. The regularization multiplier was fixed at two to generate a smooth and general response that could be modeled in a biologically realistic manner (Radosavljevic &amp; Anderson, 
 <xref rid="ece32684-bib-0052" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). The maximum number of iterations was fixed to 500. All other parameters for Maxent were consistent with those of Phillips and Dudík (
 <xref rid="ece32684-bib-0050" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>) and Elith et al. (
 <xref rid="ece32684-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>).
</p>
