<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In addition to volunteer potato management, soil frost control is thought to have multiple effects on agriculture in cold regions
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b6" class="xref">6</xref>. For centuries, soil frost has been considered to have adverse effects on agriculture, such as soil erosion during the snow-melting period
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b7" class="xref">7</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b8" class="xref">8</xref> and delays in the initiation of agricultural activity because of the excessive wetting of soil in the early spring. Recently, there are concerns of temporarily large emissions of a greenhouse gas (nitrous oxide) immediately after snowmelt during soil thaw
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9" class="xref">9</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b10" class="xref">10</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b11" class="xref">11</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b12" class="xref">12</xref>. In addition, snowmelt water is known to immediately infiltrate the soil when the soil frost depth becomes shallow
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13" class="xref">13</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14" class="xref">14</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b15" class="xref">15</xref>, leading to an increased risk of water pollution by the leaching of residual nitrate in the surface soil
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b16" class="xref">16</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b17" class="xref">17</xref>. These events caused by climate change suggest that a new optimum soil frost depth needs to be determined to avoid the negative effects on local agriculture and environment. In this study, we analysed the results obtained during field studies conducted in the Tokachi region to estimate an optimum soil frost depth. The suppression of volunteer potatoes was considered as the intended positive effect of the soil frost control, whereas smaller ratio of snowmelt water infiltration and increased nitrate loss from the surface soil were considered as the adverse effects. Because the majority (52%) of global potato production area is located between 44°N to 58°N
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b18" class="xref">18</xref> and the Tokachi region is located around the southern boundary of the zone, our findings might help overcome the volunteer potato problem in the potato-producing cold regions, while avoiding the negative consequences.
</p>
