<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In terms of the nature of the system, resilience can be categorized in a number of ways. Following Checkland and Scholes [
 <xref rid="B70-ijerph-13-01211" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">70</xref>] and Handmer and Dovers [
 <xref rid="B55-ijerph-13-01211" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>], we can distinguish between resilience of hard, soft, and mixed systems (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-13-01211-f001" class="xref">Figure 1</xref>). As mentioned earlier, resilience of hard systems can be characterized as descriptive, non-normative [
 <xref rid="B37-ijerph-13-01211" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>], tangible, precisely defined, and quantitatively measurable [
 <xref rid="B55-ijerph-13-01211" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>]. The major systems that have this type of resilience include physical–mathematical, engineering, and ecological systems. In physical and mathematical sciences, resilience is viewed as a part of stability analysis and synonymously with elasticity. Resilience of a material or system is linked with its dynamic behavior to return to the original point of equilibrium. Resilience can be defined as the speed with which a system returns to equilibrium after displacement, irrespective of the number of oscillations required [
 <xref rid="B56-ijerph-13-01211" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">56</xref>]. The more a system is resilient, the more displacement force is required to destabilize it. Structural and engineering science borrows the original meaning of resilience from physical–mathematical sciences. Engineering resilience is focused on “efficiency, control, constancy, and predictability—all attributes at the core of desires for fail-safe design and optimal performance” [
 <xref rid="B71-ijerph-13-01211" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">71</xref>]. In one of its applied levels, engineering resilience, as the concept of seismic resilience of buildings, denotes the following properties of the system: “reduced failure probabilities; reduced consequences from failures, in terms of lives lost, damage, and negative economic and social consequences; and reduced time to recovery” [
 <xref rid="B72-ijerph-13-01211" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">72</xref>]. While both physical–mathematical and engineering resilience emphasize on a system’s capacity to return to the original state, ecological or ecosystem resilience focuses on the system’s ability to absorb changes. Ecological resilience can be defined as the buffer capacity of ecosystems to absorb externally caused perturbation, maintain robust functions, and survive systemic shocks [
 <xref rid="B6-ijerph-13-01211" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>,
 <xref rid="B73-ijerph-13-01211" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">73</xref>]. In this approach, ecosystems are viewed as constantly changing systems and entities. Thus, maintaining ecosystems functions is a dynamic process of renewal and reorganization. In this sense, ecological resilience shifts from the original mathematical-engineering idea of single equilibrium to multiple points of stability of a system [
 <xref rid="B45-ijerph-13-01211" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>]. 
</p>
