<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">How might individuals respond in our task to achieve the economic goal of doubling the size of the economy by the end of the experiment? How might people’s response strategies be affected by causal knowledge of the system variables? Because people in our task have an explicit economic goal to achieve (i.e., doubling the size of the economy) and a clear means of achieving that goal (i.e., responding by setting large economic growth targets), we assume that people will tend to adopt a means-ends approach to the task. That is, we expect people to set economic growth targets that will promote rapid growth of the economic index, given the absence of relevant causal knowledge. Because of the time delays involved in warming driven by accumulated CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> (Eqs 
 <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0184480.e003" class="xref">3</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0184480.e004" class="xref">4</xref>), this pattern of responding will promote positive interim outcomes—rapid progress toward achieving the economic goal of the task. Accordingly, it would be predicted on the basis of instance theories[
 <xref rid="pone.0184480.ref033" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>], hypothesis-testing perspectives[
 <xref rid="pone.0184480.ref034" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>], as well as causal model-based theories[
 <xref rid="pone.0184480.ref035" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>], that people would favor responding in this way for the duration of the task. Once warming increases to the point where economic growth is harmed—or even prevented—the predictions from these theories become less clear. Under instance theory, people will not have a bank of similar trial instances to retrieve once economic growth targets fail to achieve growth on a given trial, and so it is possible that people might persist in setting high growth targets. Under a hypothesis-testing framework, people may similarly be expected to persist in setting high growth targets, as doing otherwise would result in moving people away from achieving the economic goal (i.e., setting 
 <italic class="italic">negative</italic> growth targets would reduce the economic index). However, because high levels of warming would prevent even high growth targets from increasing the economic index (
 <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0184480.e002" class="xref">Eq 2</xref>), people might attempt to change their response pattern by inferring from feedback, that their current strategy is ineffective. Under a causal model-based approach, we would expect people to have developed a mental model of the task that incorporates a strong positive relationship between growth targets and approach toward the economic goal. Accordingly, people would be expected to persist in setting high growth targets even after high levels of warming begin to limit increases to the economic index (
 <xref ref-type="disp-formula" rid="pone.0184480.e002" class="xref">Eq 2</xref>).
</p>
