<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>One of the best examples of the effects of acute temperature on locomotor performance and behaviour is the fight or flight response observed in some lizard species. At higher temperatures, such lizards will tend to flee from perceived predation risk. However, as environmental, and hence body, temperature decreases, it becomes increasingly likely that an individual will act aggressively and may attempt to bite the predator rather than run away (
 <xref rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr">Hertz 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 1982
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">Crowley and Pietruszka, 1983</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref62" ref-type="bibr">Mautz 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 1992
 </xref>). Sprint performance in lizards has high thermal sensitivity, with maximal and near maximal performance occurring over a narrow range of relatively high temperatures (
 <xref rid="ref10" ref-type="bibr">Bennett, 1980</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref43" ref-type="bibr">Huey and Kingsolver, 1989</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref92" ref-type="bibr">Swoap 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 1993
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">Herrel 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007
 </xref>). In contrast, the maximal bite force produced by 
 <italic>Trapelus pallida</italic>, a species of agamid lizard that exhibits this temperature-related shift between fight and flight behaviour, is relatively independent of temperature (
 <xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">Herrel 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007
 </xref>). Herrel 
 <italic>et al,</italic> (2007) demonstrated that the thermal sensitivity of the mechanical performance of muscle could explain the effects of temperature on bite force and running performance measured in this species. Isolated jaw muscle from 
 <italic>T. pallida</italic> exhibited almost no change in maximal isometric force production between test temperatures of 20°C and 40°C, whereas caudofemoralis, a large muscle that retracts the femur, reduced in maximal isometric force by 20% between 35°C and 20°C (
 <xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">Herrel 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007
 </xref>). However, while isometric force production is important for jaw muscles during biting, the caudofemoralis muscle is likely to act primarily to produce power during sprinting. The maximal power produced by isolated caudofemoralis muscle during work loops decreased by more than 40% between 35°C and 20°C (
 <xref rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr">Herrel 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007
 </xref>); other previous work on the desert iguana, 
 <italic>Dipsosaurus dorsalis</italic>, has also found that isolated limb muscle power output, determined by work loops, has a high thermal sensitivity (
 <xref rid="ref92" ref-type="bibr">Swoap 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 1993
 </xref>). Overall, previous findings indicate that at least in these species studied, the acute thermal effects on the mechanical performance of skeletal muscle cause large changes in sprint performance but not bite force, due to the type of muscle activity being undertaken, as well as the differing intrinsic properties of the muscles involved. These thermal effects on sprint performance drive the observed shift from escape behaviour to aggressive behaviour at lower temperature in such lizard species. However, in some species of lizard, such as the Jamaican Grey anole 
 <italic>Anolis lineatopus</italic>, individuals start their escape response from predators sooner at lower temperatures, rather than using any form of defensive behaviour, presumably as a different strategy to account for lower mechanical performance of limb muscle at reduced temperatures (
 <xref rid="ref75" ref-type="bibr">Rand, 1964</xref>).
</p>
