<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par15">Comparing the two multiplicative composite indicators 
 <italic>VM</italic>
 <sub>1</sub> and 
 <italic>VM</italic>
 <sub>2</sub>, some reference cases of the three attribute components show inconsistent outcomes in 
 <italic>VM</italic>
 <sub>1</sub>, which incorporated the coping component as a divisor. The composite indicator outcomes are expected to be identical for the reference cases that comprise the three components of the same score levels in different orders, such as cases (3) and (2) with H-H-M(M) and H-M-H(L), cases (9) and (10) with H-L-M(M) and M-L-H(L), cases (13) and (12) with M-L-M(M) and M-M-L(H), and cases (17) and (16) with L-L-M(M) and M-L-L(H), respectively. However, the vulnerability outcome of each of the former cases is much lower than that of the latter (i.e. cases (3) &lt; (2), (9) &lt; (10), (13) &lt; (12), and (17) &lt; (16)) as presented in Table 
 <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> and Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. The vulnerability in reference cases (3), (9), (13), and (17) would be underestimated in 
 <italic>VM</italic>
 <sub>1</sub> as a result of a multiplicative aggregation function using a divisor component of coping in Eq. (
 <xref rid="Equ4" ref-type="">4</xref>). On the other hand, the multiplicative form for 
 <italic>VM</italic>
 <sub>1</sub> produces much higher vulnerability in case (5), with M-M-H(L), than case (4), with H-M-M(M) (an equivalent combination to the case (5)) and case (3), with H-H-M(M) (a higher level combination than the case (5)). This is due to the fact that the multiplicative composite indicator 
 <italic>VM</italic>
 <sub>1</sub> would generate the overestimated outcomes in such combinations as in case (5), including a low denominator of coping without any comparable low numerators of exposure or sensitivity that cannot cancel out each other. Abnormally large outcomes could lead to ranking reversals in vulnerability assessments measured by 
 <italic>VM</italic>
 <sub>1</sub>. Such large vulnerability outcomes are also generated in cases (1) and (2), but ranking reversals might not occur since these cases have higher score levels than other reference cases. Note that as shown in Table 
 <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> and Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, other composite indicators, such as 
 <italic>VA</italic>
 <sub>1</sub>, 
 <italic>VA</italic>
 <sub>2</sub>, and 
 <italic>VM</italic>
 <sub>2</sub> produce the same vulnerability outcomes between each of the two cases in the above five sets of reference cases, such as cases (2) &amp; (3), (4) &amp; (5), (9) &amp; (10), (12) &amp; (13), and (16) &amp; (17), while there is a difference between each of the two cases in 
 <italic>VM</italic>
 <sub>1</sub> outcomes only. Consequently, the vulnerability outcomes 
 <italic>VM</italic>
 <sub>1</sub> aggregated from the IPCC’s components 
 <italic>E</italic>, 
 <italic>S</italic>, and 
 <italic>C</italic> by the well-known form of a multi-attribute utility function in Eq. (
 <xref rid="Equ4" ref-type="">4</xref>) might cause volatility of rankings and rank reversals in decision making.
</p>
