<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="discussion" disp-level="1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">DISCUSSION</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In contrast with the 1PCTCO2 simulations, the RCP 8.5 projections (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F3" href="#F3">Fig. 3</a>) show no clear pattern of polar amplification of summer warming. This effect is particularly pronounced in the AIE simulations (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F3" href="#F3">Fig. 3</a>, A and B). Only 46% of the multimodel simulations (less than half) and an even lower 32% (less than a third) of the AIE simulations exhibit positive polar amplification. This underappreciated feature of the climate projections is readily understood as a consequence of projected changes in anthropogenic aerosol forcing.
 </p>
 <div id="F3" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Analysis of RCP8.5 future projections (JJA seasonal means).</div>
   <p>Included are both (
    <span class="bold">A</span> to 
    <span class="bold">C</span>) full multimodel ensemble and (
    <span class="bold">D</span> to 
    <span class="bold">F</span>) AIE-only sub-ensemble (JJA seasonal means). (A and D) Time series of multimodel average zonal mean temperature anomalies. (B and E) Comparison of multimodel mean midlatitude (25°N to 60°N) and high-latitude (65°N to 75°N) mean temperature anomalies. (C and F) AA index defined as high-latitude minus midlatitude series (colored curves, individual simulations; black curves, multimodel mean).
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="aat3272-F3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There is a marked decrease in summer season aerosol forcing over the early 21st century as aerosols ramp down sharply, the response to which is especially large during the summer season when solar insolation is high and especially pronounced in midlatitudes where aerosol production takes place. This positive trend in radiative forcing in midlatitudes during the first half of the 21st century is of similar magnitude to the positive greenhouse forcing trend (~1 W/m
  <span class="sup">2</span>) and yields prominent warming in the midlatitudes relative to subpolar latitudes, i.e., an Arctic de-amplification. Over the latter half of the 21st century, as the aerosol trend is minimal, greenhouse forcing dominates, and the trend returns toward AA. This effect is seen as an inflection in the AA index in the mid-21st century (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F3" href="#F3">Fig. 3C</a>). We can also see this effect in the spatial pattern of first-half 21st century surface temperature trends, which displays especially prominent warming over the midlatitude continents in the ensemble mean and especially in the subset of models that are most negative QRA trending (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F4" href="#F4">Fig. 4</a>).
 </p>
 <div id="F4" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Mean surface temperature trend patterns (JJA seasonal means) over 2006–2050.</div>
   <p>(
    <span class="bold">A</span>) multimodel ensemble, (
    <span class="bold">B</span>) most negative QRA-trending ensemble members, and (
    <span class="bold">C</span>) most positive QRA-trending ensemble members (“most” is defined as upper 10th percentile of multimodel ensemble).
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="aat3272-F4" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We are now in a position to understand the behavior observed in the QRA fingerprint series (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Fig. 5</a>). For the full multimodel ensemble mean, we see a slowdown in the increasing trend over the first half of the 21st century, followed by an acceleration in the late 21st century. In the case of the AIE subset, we see a flat (actually, very slightly negative) trend over the first half of the 21st century, followed by a very rapid increase over the latter 21st century. A slim majority (59%) of the multimodel simulations exhibit an increase in the QRA fingerprint during the first half of the 21st century, while there is an equal split (50%) between increasing and decreasing QRA among the AIE simulations.
 </p>
 <div id="F5" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 5</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">QRA fingerprint series for RCP8.5 future projections.</div>
   <p>Both (
    <span class="bold">A</span>) full multimodel ensemble and (
    <span class="bold">B</span>) AIE-only sub-ensemble. Conventions are as in 
    <a ref-type="fig" rid="F3" href="#F3">Fig. 3D</a>. The historical QRA series calculated from [Goddard Institute for Space Studies Surface Temperature Analysis (GISTEMP)] surface temperature observations from 1894 to 1916 (cyan) and the actual series of annual QRA event counts (green) from 1979 to 2015 (as diagnosed from ERA reanalysis data; see Materials and methods for further details) are shown for comparison.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="aat3272-F5" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">These trends reflect a competition between the overall influence of greenhouse warming on QRA, which, as we have seen before (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">Fig. 2</a>), is a steady increase in QRA, and the mitigating effects of decreasing aerosol forcing, which dominates in the first half of the 21st century and is most prominent in the AIE-only simulations. The models that exhibit the greatest decline in the QRA fingerprint series during the first half of the 21st century are the models that display especially pronounced midlatitude warming during that period (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F4" href="#F4">Fig. 4</a>) from decreasing aerosols.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In both cases, however, by the end of the 21st century, the impact of greenhouse warming is dominant, and we observe an increase in 64% of the full multimodel ensemble simulations and 74% of the AIE-only simulations (the number is higher in this case because many of the models must recover from a prominent aerosol-induced decrease during the first half of the century). In terms of the actual number of QRA events, we project an average increase from the current historical level of ~7.5 events/year to ~11 events/year, i.e., a roughly 50% increase in the annual number of events, for the full multimodel ensemble. In some individual models, however, the increase is far greater (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Fig. 5</a>), i.e., more than a tripling by 2100 (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F5" href="#F5">Fig. 5</a>). These models tend (see 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F4" href="#F4">Fig. 4C</a>) to be those where greenhouse-induced high-latitude amplification dominates. It is apparent that the treatment of anthropogenic aerosols plays a key role in determining the pathway of QRA changes over the next century.
 </p>
</sec>
