<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="results" disp-level="1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">RESULTS</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here, we extend the M17 analysis by examining the behavior of the QRA fingerprint in future climate projections (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Fig. 1</a>). The fingerprint (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Fig. 1A</a>) exhibits negative values in the subtropics, increases to near-neutral values at 40°N, a decline toward more negative values through 50°N, and pronounced positive values again at higher subpolar latitudes. The JJA meridional temperature profiles associated with several prominent recent QRA-influenced extreme weather events (2003 European heat wave, 2010 Russian wildfires/Pakistan floods, and 2011 Oklahoma/Texas heat wave and drought) are also shown (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Fig. 1A</a>) along with the large-scale 300-hPa meridional wind fields, zonal wave number spectra, and zonal mean zonal wind profiles associated with the three events, each of which exhibits the expected QRA features (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Fig. 1B</a>; note, for example, the spectral peaks in the 
  <span class="italic">k</span> = 6/7/8 range and the double-peaked latitudinal structure in the zonal winds).
 </p>
 <div id="F1" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">QRA fingerprint and QRA event signatures.</div>
   <p>(
    <span class="bold">A</span>) JJA 1000-hPa meridional temperature anomalies over the extratropical region 25°N to 75°N associated with QRA-favorable conditions (i.e., QRA fingerprint) based on composite of events from ERA reanalysis data (1979–2015) along with the actual JJA meridional surface temperature anomalies corresponding to three selected QRA events (July/August 2003, July/August 2010, and August 2010). (
    <span class="bold">B</span>) Upper-troposphere (300 hPa) meridional wind, zonal wave number spectra (computed for the meridional average over 37.5°N to 57.5°N; the climatological mean spectra and associated 1.5σ upper limit are shown for comparison by red solid and red dashed curves, respectively), and zonal mean zonal wind profiles associated with each of the three aforementioned events.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="aat3272-F1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We see how each of the three events is associated with a prominent wave 6/7/8 pattern, and a summer mean meridional temperature profile that projects substantially onto the QRA fingerprint. The correlations with the fingerprint are 
  <span class="italic">r</span> = 0.79, 
  <span class="italic">r</span> = 0.63, and 
  <span class="italic">r</span> = 0.41, respectively, which are statistically significant at the 
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.001, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.02, and 
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.1 levels, respectively. Superimposed on the seasonal mean temperature profiles is considerable intraseasonal variation, and the positive projection of the seasonal mean temperature profiles onto the QRA fingerprint substantially increases the likelihood of daily-to-weekly temperature profiles that closely resemble the QRA fingerprint.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Arctic-amplified warming projects onto this latitudinal anomaly pattern. However, the fingerprint has considerably more latitudinal structure than a simple index (65N to 75N mean minus 25N to 60N mean temperatures) of AA (see 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Fig. 1A</a>). Thus, while we might expect some broad similarity in the behavior of the QRA fingerprint and AA index, we might also expect some significant differences. The anomalous meridional temperature gradient associated with the QRA profile is characterized by a large positive peak in the midlatitude zone of 50°N to 65°N, which, via thermal wind, implies a more-pronounced minimum in the zonal mean zonal wind. More poleward (i.e., beyond 65°N), the reduction in the temperature gradient (and thus a stronger negative gradient) implies stronger westerlies in subpolar regions. As noted earlier, these are precisely the double-peaked jet conditions associated with QRA.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The next step in the analysis involves projecting the CMIP5 simulation meridional temperature profiles onto the QRA fingerprint (see 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F1" href="#F1">Fig. 1A</a>) using linear regression (see Materials and methods). In assessing the impact of projected future climate change on the conditions favoring QRA, it is instructive to first examine the simple case (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">Fig. 2</a>) of linearly increasing greenhouse forcing with no other changes in external forcing. We use steady CO
  <sub>2</sub> increase experiments of the CMIP5 ensemble (
  <span class="italic">N</span> = 35 simulations, 
  <span class="italic">M</span> = 26 models; see table S2 for details), which are initialized by a preindustrial control and subject to a 1%/year increase in CO
  <sub>2</sub> (henceforth “1PCTCO2”).
 </p>
 <div id="F2" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Analysis of 1PCTCO2 experiments (JJA seasonal means).</div>
   <p>(
    <span class="bold">A</span>) Time series of multimodel average zonal mean temperature anomalies. (
    <span class="bold">B</span>) Comparison of multimodel average midlatitude (25°N to 60°N) and high-latitude (65°N to 75°N) mean temperature anomalies. (
    <span class="bold">C</span>) AA index defined as high-latitude minus midlatitude series including individual simulations shown (colored curves) and multimodel mean (black solid curve), along with linear trend (black dashed lines). (
    <span class="bold">D</span>) QRA series for individual series and multimodel mean [conventions as in (C); see Materials and methods for details on scaling of QRA]. (
    <span class="bold">E</span>) Projection of the QRA fingerprint onto zonal wind anomalies.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="aat3272-F2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Examining the multimodel ensemble mean JJA surface temperatures, we see the expected polar amplification of warming with latitude (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">Fig. 2A</a>), with summer (JJA) warming in the high-latitude zone (65°N to 75°N) substantially exceeding that for the midlatitude zone (25°N to 60°N) (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">Fig. 2B</a>). The multimodel mean AA index (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">Fig. 2C</a>) shows a nearly linear increase over time. There is spread within the multimodel ensemble [with two-thirds (67%) of the ensemble members displaying AA]. We next examine the QRA fingerprint series [
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">Fig. 2D</a>; the unitless QRA index has been scaled against the actual historical series of annual QRA event numbers (see Materials and methods) for the purpose of defining the vertical scale]. This series displays an even more robust positive trend [in this case, more than three-fourths (76%) of the ensemble members display a positive trend], consistent with the hypothesis (see M17) that climate change attributes other than AA—particularly the enhanced land/ocean contrast and perhaps changing snow cover (
  <a rid="R8" ref-type="bibr" href="#R8">
   <span class="italic">8</span>
  </a>), as expressed in the corresponding zonal means—also project positively onto the QRA fingerprint. The projection of the 300-hPa 
  <span class="italic">U</span> field (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">Fig. 2E</a>) onto the QRA series shows the expected (M17) anomaly pattern of weakened midlatitude westerlies and strengthened subpolar and subtropical westerlies indicative of the double-peaked jet associated with QRA-favorable conditions. The observed ~2 m/s peak-to-peak amplitude of the response is consistent with a simple calculation based on the thermal wind approximation (see Materials and methods).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We then examined the CMIP5 future (2006–2100) projections (see Materials and methods for details). We focus on the RCP (Representative Concentration Pathway) 8.5 experiments (
  <span class="italic">N</span> = 73 simulations, 
  <span class="italic">M</span> = 39 models; see table S3), which reflect a “business-as-usual” scenario of steadily increasing carbon emissions through the end of the 21st century, but with a sharp drop-off in anthropogenic sulfate aerosol production over the next half century (reflecting the assumption of a transition to “cleaner” coal burning in the developing world). Results for the RCP 2.6 scenario (table S4), which reflects more ambitious carbon emission reductions, yield qualitatively similar results but with substantially smaller future projected changes (see figs. S2 and S3).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We combine the projections and the previously assessed (M17) CMIP5 historical (1880–2005) simulations (
  <span class="italic">N</span> = 164, 
  <span class="italic">M</span> = 48; see table S1) to provide a historical context for the future projections. We analyze both the full multimodel ensembles and the aerosol indirect effects (AIE) subsets of the ensembles consisting only of models that include both aerosol first and second indirect effects (
  <span class="italic">N</span> = 46 historical simulations and 
  <span class="italic">N</span> = 28 future simulations) to better assess the potentially important role played by anthropogenic aerosols.
 </p>
</sec>
