<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">QRA fingerprint</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To define the QRA meridional temperature fingerprint, we used the QRA detection scheme developed by Kornhuber 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. (
  <a rid="R26" ref-type="bibr" href="#R26">
   <span class="italic">26</span>
  </a>) applied to temperature profiles as in M17 using the JJA 1979–2015 ERA interim reanalysis (2.5° × 2.5°). Near-surface atmospheric temperature profiles were calculated using 
  <span class="italic">z</span> = 1000 hPa daily data over the full Northern Hemisphere (0°N to 90°N) in 37 steps (2.5°). We focused on long-duration (≥10 days) wave number 7 events to define QRA-favorable time intervals and confined zonal mean profiles to the latitude range (25°N to 75°N) of interest. The fingerprint was interpolated to a 5° latitude to be consistent with the grid of the model simulations and observational datasets (see below) and centered on zero. This yields an 11-element zero-centered row vector that defines the QRA fingerprint.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The QRA fingerprint is found to be robust with respect to sampling considerations. Calculating the fingerprint based on either the first half (1979–1997) or second half (1998–2015) of the full ERA dataset yields profiles that are very similar to those based on the full (1979–2015) data interval (fig. S4).</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The projection of other fields onto the QRA fingerprint was estimated in both CMIP5 simulated (see below) and observational (see below) datasets by calculating the linear inner product of those fields and the QRA fingerprint defined above.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We also calculated the time series of observed annual QRA events using the set of all QRA events, with wave numbers 6 to 8 detected in the ERA reanalysis dataset over 1979–2015 (
  <a rid="R14" ref-type="bibr" href="#R14">
   <span class="italic">14</span>
  </a>). Owing to the noisy nature of this count series, it was smoothed using an interannual smoothing filter (
  <span class="italic">f</span> = 0.2 cycle/year cutoff) for the purpose of comparison with other calculated QRA series. We used mean and variance matching with this series to scale the observational and model-based QRA fingerprint series in dimensions of equivalent annual number of QRA events.
 </p>
</sec>
