<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Personality traits explain some differences in individual actions under similar situations and can be used as predictors of individual behavior. The Big Five Inventory of personality [
 <xref rid="B54-ijerph-14-01472" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>] comprises the dimensions of neuroticism (in the current study this was called emotional stability), agreeableness, conscientiousness, openness to experience and extraversion, it seems personality traits are a multi-dimensional construct [
 <xref rid="B54-ijerph-14-01472" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>,
 <xref rid="B55-ijerph-14-01472" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>]. In addition, the second-order construct (personality traits) is a linear combination of five first order factors and the first-order factors themselves have reflective indicators; when consequences of the latent construct are included, the formative model can be estimated. Wood [
 <xref rid="B56-ijerph-14-01472" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">56</xref>] argued that sustainable behavior may not immediately affect or stop GCC and that a person’s irresponsible behaviors are mainly due to personality traits. Milfont and Sibley [
 <xref rid="B57-ijerph-14-01472" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>] found that agreeableness and conscientiousness influenced self-reported energy-saving behavior and environmental commitment. Hirsh [
 <xref rid="B58-ijerph-14-01472" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">58</xref>] indicated that higher environmental concern is significantly associated with higher levels of agreeableness, openness, stability and conscientiousness, with no significant association observed for extraversion. An individual’s personality traits may be a positive catalyst that enhances the effect perceived risk of GCC on pro-environmental behavior. These previous findings lend support to the assertion that the Big Five personality traits moderate the antecedent variables that influence pro-environmental attitude. Therefore, drawing from these previous findings, the following predictions were made: 
 <statement class="statement">
  <label class="label">
   <bold class="bold">Hypothesis</bold> 
   <bold class="bold">6.</bold>
  </label>
  <p class="p">
   <italic class="italic">The relationship between sustainability value and pro-environmental attitude is moderated by level of personality traits. That is, the relationship is weaker with lower levels of personality traits and stronger with higher levels of personality traits.</italic>
  </p>
 </statement>
 <statement class="statement">
  <label class="label">
   <bold class="bold">Hypothesis</bold> 
   <bold class="bold">7.</bold>
  </label>
  <p class="p">
   <italic class="italic">The relationship between social norm and pro-environmental attitude is moderated by level of personality traits.</italic>
  </p>
 </statement>
 <statement class="statement">
  <label class="label">
   <bold class="bold">Hypothesis</bold> 
   <bold class="bold">8.</bold>
  </label>
  <p class="p">
   <italic class="italic">The relationship between environmental concern and pro-environmental attitude is moderated by level of personality traits.</italic>
  </p>
 </statement>
 <statement class="statement">
  <label class="label">
   <bold class="bold">Hypothesis</bold> 
   <bold class="bold">9.</bold>
  </label>
  <p class="p">
   <italic class="italic">The relationship between perceived risk and pro-environmental attitude is moderated by level of personality traits.</italic>
  </p>
 </statement>
</p>
