<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The second dataset was from demersal fish trawling surveys in the southern North Sea—part of the North Sea International Bottom Trawl Survey coordinated by the International Council for the Exploration of the Sea [
 <xref rid="pone.0184275.ref032" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>], made available through International Council for the Exploration of the Sea DATRAS database (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ices.dk/marine-data/data-portals/Pages/DATRAS.aspx" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.ices.dk/marine-data/data-portals/Pages/DATRAS.aspx</ext-link>). We used catch per unit effort collected during winter (Jan to March) during 1980–2013 in “area 6”. We focused on relatively well-observed demersal species seen in at least 25% of the census years, comprising 34 species. One species was removed (
 <italic class="italic">Syngnathus acus</italic>) because it alone caused a strong increase in the CTI in the last census year and therefore could give a misleading picture—but its exclusion does not affect the general results (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0184275.s003" class="xref">S3 Fig</xref> shows the analysis including this species). Temperature preference was calculated as the average annual temperature over each species range [distribution data: Ocean Biogeographic Information System/Global Biodiversity Information Facility; temperature data: bottom temperature from Aquamaps, which is based on the 2001 World Ocean Atlas annual means between 1990 and 1999 [
 <xref rid="pone.0184275.ref033" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>], projected onto a 50 km grid. We also compiled species information on maximum body length [
 <xref rid="pone.0184275.ref034" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>] and whether the species were exploited using the fishbase database [
 <xref rid="pone.0184275.ref035" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>], which could relate to the fishing pressure each species had experienced.
</p>
