<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Recent rapid regional warming along the Antarctic Peninsula (AP) has driven massive loss of ice shelves and retreat of tidewater glaciers, together with a reduction of seasonal sea-ice extension (
 <xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">1</italic>
 </xref>–
 <xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">3</italic>
 </xref>). Surface waters at the Western AP have warmed by almost 1°C in the latter half century and strong surface salinity changes, especially in coastal areas during summer (
 <xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">4</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">5</italic>
 </xref>). Biological responses are increasingly being predicted from single species to ecosystem levels, including changes in abundance, diversity, and assemblage structure (
 <xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">6</italic>
 </xref>–
 <xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">10</italic>
 </xref>). However, shifts have been reported particularly in the pelagic system, in phytoplankton with cross-food web links from krill to penguins (
 <xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">11</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">12</italic>
 </xref>). Although by far most Antarctic species occur in the benthos, to date observed responses from abundant and diverse communities on the seabed have been restricted to only a few species (
 <xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">13</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">14</italic>
 </xref>). Most of the reported shifts in benthic species were related to catastrophic events, such as ice-shelf collapses, or to the colonization of newly ice-free areas (
 <xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">15</italic>
 </xref>–
 <xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">21</italic>
 </xref>). Whereas only one taxon, bryozoans, was reported to be affected by the gradual change of a factor driven by climatic change, exhibiting a linear relationship with the increment of ice disturbance (
 <xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">13</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">14</italic>
 </xref>), major effects at the community level remain unknown (
 <xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">13</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">14</italic>
 </xref>).
</p>
