<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">
 <named-content content-type="taxon-name" class="named-content">
  <named-content content-type="suborder" class="named-content">Oniscidea</named-content>
 </named-content> originate from marine ancestors and there is a distinctive gradient within the taxon of increased adaptation to land conditions so that a variety of climatic components could be identified as determinants of species’ occurrence, establishment, survival, or prosperity (
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hornung 2011</xref>). In addition, the degree of dependence on such climatic factors may vary through different scales (biomes through regions, to habitats and microhabitats). In general, though, the most critical factors determining terrestrial isopod establishment, existence and survival at any given locality are temperature and humidity. Microclimatic tolerance, niche dimensions of single species or species assemblages are central topics of isopod studies since the turnout of woodlice ecology (e.g., see the works of 
 <xref rid="B91" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Miller 1938</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Edney 1954</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B31" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1958</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B148" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Warburg 1965</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B150" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1987</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B153" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Warburg et al. 1984</xref>) in the last century. Certain species are differently sensitive to environmental conditions and this broad range of evolutionary adaptation is coupled with a wide range of ecomorphological and life history strategies (
 <xref rid="B103" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Schmalfuss 1984</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B131" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Sutton et al. 1984</xref>). This variety involves considerable distinct values of desiccation resistance among species (
 <xref rid="B151" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Warburg 1993</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Dias et al. 2013</xref>). Protection against desiccation evolved along different routes, such as physiological, ecomorphological and/or behavioral pathways. Evolutionary changes in respiration and respiratory organs, changes in cuticle structure and morphology, conglobation mechanisms and tendency towards aggregation, are all parts of terrestrial adaptations promoting fine and large-scale dispersal (
 <xref rid="B150" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Warburg 1987</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B43" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hassall et al. 2010</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hornung 2011</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Broly et al. 2013b</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>).
</p>
