<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The US National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA) and National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA) both recently reported that 2016 was the warmest year on record (Potter et al. 
 <xref rid="bib47" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>), followed by 2015 and 2014. Currently, 2017 is on track to be the second warmest year after 2016. The vast majority of scientists agree that most of the warming since the Industrial Revolution is explained by rising atmospheric greenhouse gas (GHG) concentrations (Doran and Zimmerman 
 <xref rid="bib19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>, Cook et al. 
 <xref rid="bib12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>, Stenhouse et al. 2014, Carlton et al 
 <xref rid="bib11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>, Verheggen et al. 
 <xref rid="bib58" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>), that the frequency of extremely warm years will increase in a future of continually rising GHG levels, and that the harmful effects of anthropogenic global warming (AGW) on natural and managed ecosystems across the biosphere (Stocker et al. 
 <xref rid="bib55" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>) will escalate. However, much of the public remains unconvinced of the human influence on climate, as has been described by Working Groups 1 and 2 of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC), and believes scientists continue to debate AGW causes or even process (Lewandowsky et al. 
 <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>). This chasm between public opinion and scientific agreement on AGW is now commonly referred to as the 
 <italic class="italic">consensus gap</italic> (Lewandowsky et al. 
 <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>). Several factors contribute to the consensus gap. For example, some media outlets consistently misrepresent our fundamental understanding of AGW. This may be partially because framing AGW as a “scientific controversy,” with “opinions on both sides,” may be more profitable than differentiating unsubstantiated opinions of climate-change deniers from the broad and evidence-based “scientific consensus” (Oreskes and Conway 
 <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>, Dunlap 
 <xref rid="bib21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>, Lewandowsky et al. 
 <xref rid="bib31" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>). Also, the corporate media may not wish to overemphasize the significance of AGW if this conflicts with the interests of advertisers (Anderson 
 <xref rid="bib3" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>). Many elected politicians further confuse the public by denying—or expressing unwarranted skepticism about—AGW (Oreskes and Conway 
 <xref rid="bib39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>).
</p>
