<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s4" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Reframing the question</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">If the construction of regional climate information inevitably involves ethical choices, then those choices should be made by the users of the climate information, based on their values. If the uncertainties in the climate information involve a significant epistemic component, then subjectivity is inevitable and the epistemic uncertainties similarly need to be understandable and assessable by the users of the climate information, within their particular context. Both imperatives move the climate risk problem outside the domain of pure climate science. Moreover, the recognition that epistemic uncertainties are deterministic removes the impulse to provide probabilities, which can give the illusion of objectivity and thereby reduce transparency. Instead, epistemic uncertainty can be represented through a discrete set of (multiple) storylines—physically self-consistent, plausible pathways, with no probability attached [
  <a rid="RSPA20190013C11" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPA20190013C11">11</a>,
  <a rid="RSPA20190013C36" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPA20190013C36">36</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Rather than asking what will happen (as in the traditional, scenario-driven approach), which we may not be able to answer with any confidence, storylines allow us to ask what would be the effect of particular interventions—e.g. different climate forcing scenarios, or different adaptation measures—across a range of plausible futures. The latter questions are in any case the societally relevant ones. This reframing of the climate risk question from the prediction space to the decision space avoids the confidence straightjacket. Storylines have much in common with scenario planning and other methods of robust decision-making under uncertainty [
  <a rid="RSPA20190013C37" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPA20190013C37">37</a>,
  <a rid="RSPA20190013C38" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPA20190013C38">38</a>]. What is novel is their application to physical climate science, where, perhaps because the system obeys known physical laws, the operative paradigm up to now has been probabilistic, which gives the impression of objectivity.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The different uncertainties that are relevant to climate risk, and the different human decision points, can be broadly represented as follows. There is uncertainty in the future climate forcing, which is mainly anthropogenic in origin, and represents the mitigation options. This combines with the epistemic uncertainty in climate sensitivity to determine the global-mean warming level. While there is some aleatoric uncertainty in the global-mean warming, it is small compared with the forced response on decadal or longer time scales. A given global-mean warming level will be associated with distinct patterns of regional warming (e.g. land warms more than ocean, the Arctic warms more than lower latitudes during the winter season), including changes in lapse rate [
  <a rid="RSPA20190013C39" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPA20190013C39">39</a>]. These regional warming patterns are largely explainable from thermodynamic principles and thus are fairly well understood, though they have substantial quantitative epistemic uncertainty (including the possibility of tipping points). A given global-mean warming level will also be associated with particular dynamical conditions in any specific region (including the circulation effects of coupled atmosphere–ocean variability), which have a very large aleatoric component but whose forced changes are also highly uncertain. The regional warming patterns and dynamical conditions together produce hazards such as weather or climate extremes, which then combine with the non-climatic anthropogenic factors of vulnerability and exposure to create climate impacts.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This representation of the climate risk problem provides a natural framework for storyline approaches. For example, from the perspective of the Paris Agreement, one may ask the question of what the climate impacts would be at different levels of global-mean warming, and what different mitigation pathways would lead to those warming levels [
  <a rid="RSPA20190013C40" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPA20190013C40">40</a>]. The epistemic uncertainty in climate sensitivity now no longer affects the estimation of climate impacts, but is instead relevant to the carbon budget allowed by the given level of warming. The epistemic uncertainty in future dynamical conditions (for a given level of global-mean warming) can then be managed via storylines, the simplest of which is that the changes in hazard are dominated by the thermodynamic effects arising from the regional temperature changes, with the forced changes in dynamical conditions assumed to be negligible. Given the large uncertainties in the forced dynamical changes, this can be considered a reasonable null hypothesis for climate change [
  <a rid="RSPA20190013C41" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPA20190013C41">41</a>,
  <a rid="RSPA20190013C42" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPA20190013C42">42</a>], and it is far from uninformative. It is in fact the basis for all of the predicted changes in extremes shown in table SPM.1 of the IPCC WGI Fifth Assessment Report [
  <a rid="RSPA20190013C2" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPA20190013C2">2</a>]. It also underlies the ‘surrogate climate change’ (also known as ‘pseudo-global warming’) methodology [
  <a rid="RSPA20190013C39" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPA20190013C39">39</a>,
  <a rid="RSPA20190013C43" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPA20190013C43">43</a>], which is widely used in regional climate change simulations, and the circulation-analogue methodology [
  <a rid="RSPA20190013C44" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPA20190013C44">44</a>], which is widely used in extreme-event attribution. However, specific storylines of forced circulation change can also be considered [
  <a rid="RSPA20190013C16" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPA20190013C16">16</a>,
  <a rid="RSPA20190013C42" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPA20190013C42">42</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Reframing the climate risk question in this way increases the signal-to-noise ratio of the climate information by explicitly accounting for the correlated nature of epistemic uncertainty. An example is provided in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSPA20190013F2" href="#RSPA20190013F2">figure 2</a>. The Mediterranean region receives most of its precipitation during the winter season, so the predicted wintertime drying of the region, which is a robust feature of climate model projections (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSPA20190013F1" href="#RSPA20190013F1">figure 1</a>), has important consequences. The extent of the drying will depend on the global warming level, and it is relevant to ask, for instance, what would be the difference between 1.5°C and 2.0°C of global warming. However, the extent of the drying will also depend on the pattern of circulation change in the region—an epistemic uncertainty—which can be characterized by physically coherent storylines [
  <a rid="RSPA20190013C16" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPA20190013C16">16</a>]. Considering just the range between the low-impact and high-impact storylines shown in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSPA20190013F2" href="#RSPA20190013F2">figure 2</a>, the difference in drying between 1.5°C and 2.0°C of global-mean warming under the standard probabilistic framing is the difference between 0.09 [0.04 to 0.15] and 0.12 [0.05 to 0.20] mm d
  <span class="sup">−1</span> (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSPA20190013F2" href="#RSPA20190013F2">figure 2</a>
  <span class="italic">a</span>), which would be considered indeterminate within the stated uncertainties. The storyline framing of the difference is, by contrast, a deterministic 0.04 versus 0.05 for the low-impact circulation storyline, 0.09 versus 0.12 for the median storyline and 0.15 versus 0.20 for the high-impact storyline (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSPA20190013F2" href="#RSPA20190013F2">figure 2</a>
  <span class="italic">b</span>). This is a more informative way of representing the uncertainty, because it quantifies different plausible outcomes. For reference, 0.08 mm d
  <span class="sup">−1</span> corresponds to a change that is statistically detectable, and 0.19 to one standard deviation of the interannual variability—quite a large change, probably requiring significant adaptation measures. The distinction between the two approaches is analogous to that between accuracy and precision; sometimes, the latter is all that is needed for decision-making. 
  <div id="RSPA20190013F2" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 2.</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Projected average wintertime precipitation change (in mm d
     <span class="sup">−1</span>) over the Mediterranean basin plotted as a function of global warming level (in °C) relative to 1960–1990 and a ‘storyline index’ that represents the uncertainty in the pattern of circulation change in the region. The high-impact storyline corresponds to the combination of strong tropical upper tropospheric amplification of surface warming and a strengthening of the stratospheric polar vortex, and the low-impact storyline to weak tropical upper tropospheric amplification of surface warming and a weakening of the polar vortex. The light blue dashed line represents a magnitude of change that is statistically detectable, and the dark blue dashed line corresponds to one standard deviation of the interannual variability. (
     <span class="italic">a</span>) The standard representation of the difference between global warming levels of 1.5°C and 2.0°C is shown, taking the low- and high-impact storylines as spanning a range of uncertainty. (
     <span class="italic">b</span>) Differences are shown conditioned on different storylines. Adapted from [
     <a rid="RSPA20190013C16" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPA20190013C16">16</a>]. (Online version in colour.)
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="rspa20190013-g2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Storylines are ideal vehicles for quantifying the impacts of climate change and adaptation measures. They provide a way of dealing with singular historical events, which within the probabilistic framework are merely accidents within a phase space of unrealized possibilities, yet often provide benchmarks for resilience; and with the local context, where the human element becomes part of the analysis rather than a confounding factor. For example, rather than seeking to determine the recurrence likelihood of a particularly damaging storm (an inherently fuzzy question since every storm is unique), one can ask how much worse the flooding would be in a warmer, moister climate [
  <a rid="RSPA20190013C41" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPA20190013C41">41</a>], or under a particular urban development scenario. Such conditioning of the question enormously reduces the dimension of the problem and thereby allows the use of much more realistic modelling tools, which users of climate information can relate to. In this way, the storyline approach addresses the needed reframing of the climate risk problem while representing the epistemic uncertainties in a traceable manner.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">That there is relevant information concerning climate risk contained even in single historical events is illustrated in 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSPA20190013F3" href="#RSPA20190013F3">figure 3</a>, which shows a small region in central France during one day in August 2000 and another day in August 2003 during the severe heat wave that affected Europe that summer [
  <a rid="RSPA20190013C45" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPA20190013C45">45</a>]. From a statistical perspective, it may seem meaningless to compare two single days because they will each be strongly influenced by synoptic variability. However, the images show that the crops and grasses in the agricultural plots died out during the 2003 heat wave, and the surface temperature difference between the 2 days over those parts of the scene was 20°C, versus only 11°C in the forested region. Since a difference of 9°C over a distance of several hundred metres cannot be explained by synoptic variability (which has much larger correlation scales), this clearly shows the impact of land cover on the climate risk from heat waves. (Moreover, the average temperature difference in the agricultural plots rises to 24°C if the hedgerows are excluded, and the temperature difference in fields that were bare in both 2000 and 2003 is 11°C.) While it may not be possible to predict the future statistics of heat waves in this region, it is possible to make informative statements about how those heat waves would be affected by land cover and thus inform adaptation strategies. 
  <div id="RSPA20190013F3" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 3.</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Surface conditions derived from infrared remote sensing for a small region in central France, for 1 August 2000 (left panels) and 10 August 2003 (right panels). The top panels show the normalized difference vegetation index (NDVI), with the red colours indicative of vegetation. The lower panels show the radiometric temperature, with the colour scale at the bottom. The distance scale is shown in the lower right panel, and the values given in the right panels indicate the average differences in those parts of the scene between the left and right panels. Adapted from [
     <a rid="RSPA20190013C45" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPA20190013C45">45</a>]. (Online version in colour.)
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="rspa20190013-g3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The tension between global and local descriptions (in time or space) is not unique to climate science, of course. It arises in any scientific context where statistical power is achieved by aggregation over an inhomogeneous population, and thus blurs information. There is a growing move in many fields towards analysis methods that aim to consider information in context rather than in aggregate, especially when that information is sparse (e.g. safety in healthcare [
  <a rid="RSPA20190013C46" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPA20190013C46">46</a>]). Storyline approaches to climate risk can be seen as part of that movement.
 </p>
</sec>
