<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Phenotypic plasticity plays a significant role in the responses of both plants and animals to environmental change (De Witt and Scheiner 
 <xref rid="b83" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2004</xref>; Ellers and Stuefer 
 <xref rid="b96" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>; Nicotra et al. 
 <xref rid="b207" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>). The extent to which plasticity promotes longer-term adaptation may vary, however, ranging from cases where it promotes adaptation through to those where it might inhibit adaptation. The outcome depends on a range of circumstances, including the extent and form of environmental predictability, the extent of dispersal and the genetic variance in new environments (Chown and Terblanche 
 <xref rid="b63" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2007</xref>; Ghalambor et al. 
 <xref rid="b120" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2007</xref>; Scoville and Pfrender 
 <xref rid="b261" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>; Chevin et al. 
 <xref rid="b60" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>). Nonetheless, currently, it appears that phenotypic plasticity can play a major role in species responses to climate change, such as in changing the timing of breeding in birds (Gienapp et al. 
 <xref rid="b122" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2008</xref>) and responses of plants along climate gradients (Matesanz and Valladares 
 <xref rid="b186" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>; McLean et al. 
 <xref rid="b192" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>). Some evidence also exists suggesting that invasive species have advantages over indigenous ones as a consequence either of the extent or form of their plasticity (Stachowicz et al. 
 <xref rid="b274" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2002</xref>; Chown et al. 
 <xref rid="b64" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2007</xref>; Kleynhans et al. 
 <xref rid="b159" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>). Given that at least some evidence supports the idea that phenotypic plasticity may enhance the success of nonindigenous species as climates change, an understanding of the genomic basis of plasticity may improve forecasts of where such advantage should be expected and what form it should take.
</p>
