<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Another challenge is to consider plastic changes across generations as well as within them. Epigenetic modifications such as DNA methylation and histone modifications can be induced by environment and influence gene expression and transposable element activity, with direct effects on the phenotype (Glastad et al. 
 <xref rid="b123" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>; Herrera et al. 
 <xref rid="b135" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>; Zhang et al. 
 <xref rid="b332" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013c</xref>). In plants, methylation can also be inherited through multiple generations, thus partly acting like heritable genetic variation. There are several examples of invasive species where epigenetic variation far exceeds standing genetic variation (Richards et al. 
 <xref rid="b236" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>; Liebl et al. 
 <xref rid="b177" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>). Genomics is integral to the field of ecological epigenetics. Whole-genome bisulphite sequencing can reconstruct entire methylation profiles (Schmitz et al. 
 <xref rid="b258" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>; Wang et al. 
 <xref rid="b310" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>) while reduced-representation genomic methods and genetic methods such as MS-AFLP can enable quantification of the extent of epigenetic compared to genetic variation within and among populations (Pérez et al. 
 <xref rid="b215" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2006</xref>). The hypothesis that epigenetic variation is important to invasion in some cases is intriguing, and a handful of studies exist directly linking epigenotype to phenotypic means, plasticities and environmental tolerance (Herrera et al. 
 <xref rid="b135" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>; Zhang et al. 
 <xref rid="b332" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013c</xref>), but in general, few data have been collected that examine adaptive and heritable epigenetic effects (Furrow and Feldman 
 <xref rid="b111" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>).
</p>
