<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec11" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Impact of Self-Amplification</div>
 <p id="Par38" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition to changes in the external forcing and internal variability, also a possible self-amplification of the ice loss has been suggested to contribute to the substantial ice loss in recent years. This has often been framed in the context of nonlinear threshold behavior of the ice cover, also referred to as “tipping points.” The main mechanism that has been suggested to possibly give rise to such “tipping” of the ice cover has been the ice-albedo feedback.</p>
 <sec id="Sec12" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Past Evolution of the Sea-Ice Cover</div>
  <p id="Par39" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The observed evolution of the Arctic sea-ice cover is inconsistent with the possible existence of a tipping point arising from self-amplification of the ice cover. First, the evolution has remained linearly linked to the long-term rise in global-mean temperature as outlined above. Second, the 1-year lag autocorrelation of year-to-year changes in summer sea-ice coverage is negative (around − 0.5, see also [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>]), implying that after a summer with a particularly strong ice loss, the ice cover usually recovers somewhat in the following year. If indeed self-amplification played a significant role in the observed evolution of the ice cover, one would expect both an increasing failure of the linear relationship with rising temperature and an even more substantial ice loss after a year with a substantial ice loss.
  </p>
  <p id="Par40" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Several stabilizing feedbacks during winter contribute to the lack of self-amplification even in light of the ice-albedo feedback [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">53</a>]: First, any ice-free parts of the Arctic Ocean more effectively lose their heat to the atmosphere than those parts that remained ice-covered during winter [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>]. Second, thin ice grows much faster than thick ice in response to the same external forcing, allowing for some recovery of total sea-ice volume after any record ice loss during summer [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>]. And third, the later the ice cover forms, the thinner will be its isolating snow cover during winter [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>].
  </p>
  <p id="Par41" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Note that all these stabilizing feedbacks are only active during winter. Throughout summer of a given year, any small perturbation of the ice cover will be effectively amplified. For example, the observed progressively earlier melt onset translates directly to more absorption of solar heat, and thus to a more substantial ice loss during summer and a later onset of autumn freeze-up. This behavior has been found in the observational record [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>] and can be used to estimate the timing of freeze onset at the end of the summer [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>].
  </p>
  <p id="Par42" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The observed lack of self-amplification of the ongoing ice loss is consistent with the behaviour of the Arctic sea-ice cover in large-scale climate models. In contrast, simplified models of the sea-ice cover often show instabilities [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">59</a>]. This behavior has been explained by the lack of meridional heat transport and a lack of a seasonal cycle in these simplified models [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">60</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec13" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Future Evolution of the Sea-Ice Cover</div>
  <p id="Par43" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Also for the future, no substantial self amplification of the summer ice loss is expected. In particular, in all models that participated in CMIP5, the linear relationship between Arctic sea-ice cover and global-mean temperature holds until all sea ice is lost. This behavior already takes into account that in many regions, the ice-free duration during summer is becoming longer and longer, and that the ice cover as a whole is getting thinner. These factors are apparently not sufficient to overcome the stabilizing feedbacks and do not cause an acceleration of the summer sea-ice loss.</p>
  <p id="Par44" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In contrast, the pace of winter sea-ice loss accelerates once the total area covered in summer approaches nearly ice-free conditions, both in idealized studies [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">61</a>] and in many CMIP5 models [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" href="#CR62">62</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">63</a>]. This behavior has recently been explained by geometric reasons, since the winter sea-ice covering the Arctic Ocean after the loss of summer sea ice will have a rather small homogeneous thickness and can thus be removed quickly [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">63</a>, 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" href="#CR64">64</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
