<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Past Evolution of the Sea-Ice Cover</div>
 <p id="Par33" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The observed evolution of the Arctic sea-ice cover is well described by the linear combination of an externally forced trend and superimposed internal variability [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>]. However, estimating the true impact of internal variability in particular on the rapid ice loss in recent years is challenging, as the external forcing is changing rapidly. Hence, it is difficult to estimate the true internal variability of the sea-ice cover directly from the observational record. The pre-satellite record of sea-ice coverage from 1953 to 1979 as summarized in the HadISST record is assumed to be rather reliable [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>] and does not show a strong trend. It provides a standard deviation of year-to-year changes in September sea-ice area from internal variability of 
  <span class="italic">σ</span> = 0.36 million km
  <span class="sup">2</span> [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par34" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">CMIP5 models display on average a similar variability. In their pre-industrial control simulations, the average standard deviation of September sea-ice area is 
  <span class="italic">σ</span> = 0.43 ± 0.12 million km
  <span class="sup">2</span> [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>]. Hence, based on a 2
  <span class="italic">σ</span> 95% confidence interval, the models and the observations suggest a maximum impact of internal variability on September sea-ice coverage of less than ± 1 million km
  <span class="sup">2</span> for any given year for pre-industrial ice coverage. The internal variability depends on the sea-ice-covered area and reaches in model simulations a maximum at a sea-ice extent of around 3 million km
  <span class="sup">2</span> [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>]. With a further decrease in sea-ice cover, internal variability decreases towards pre-industrial values and eventually drops to zero as ice-coverage drops to zero [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>]. As in the following, we are primarily interested in internal variability for low ice coverage, we take the pre-industrial value as a conservative estimate for the relevant internal variability of a future low ice state. This is in line with the finding that the long-term mean variability for the decreasing ice coverage of a high-emission scenario is across the CMIP5 models very similar to the pre-industrial long-term mean variability [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par35" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Examining the observed and modeled trends, a number of studies have found that a range of internal variability of ± 1 million km
  <span class="sup">2</span> is sufficient to explain much of the biases in modeled sea-ice trends over the past few decades [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>]. Given that most models underestimate the observed sea-ice loss, this finding suggests that the observed ice loss has recently been amplified by internal variability [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>]. This is in line with a more process-oriented study examining the link between atmospheric variability and the resulting evolution of the sea-ice cover [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>]. This might also explain why sea-ice loss has slowed down during summer since 2012, as the ice cover is ”recovering” from an extreme-event ice loss to the long-term trend line provided by the external forcing. A possible explanation for this behavior relates to changes in ocean circulation arising from internal variability [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
