<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2b" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(b)</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Salmon data</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Adult Atlantic salmon in the Burrishoole river system are anadromous and typically return to freshwater between June and September and spawn the following December. At this latitude (53°59′ N), juveniles generally spend three winters in freshwater, including the winter when eggs are in the gravel, before migrating to sea as smolts in April and May (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="RSPB20090799C31" href="#RSPB20090799C31">Metcalfe &amp; Thorpe 1990</a>). A total trapping system for the counting of returning adults and migrating smolts has been operated at Burrishoole since 1969 at two locations above the tide (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSPB20090799F1" href="#RSPB20090799F1">figure 1</a>), allowing both the quantification of all fish entering and leaving the system and the estimation of egg numbers (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSPB20090799F2" href="#RSPB20090799F2">figure 2</a>
  <span class="italic">a</span>). The number of adult wild salmon spawning in the system during the period of the study ranged from 203 to 1485 individuals. Total estimates of egg input into the wild includes a variable proportion, 1–60%, of eggs deposited by adult salmon from an experimental captive breeding and smolt release (ranching) programme (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSPB20090799F2" href="#RSPB20090799F2">figure 2</a>
  <span class="italic">b</span>). The number of salmon bred in captivity spawning naturally in the system has varied between 8 and 608 fish. The captive breeding programme for salmon was established from wild fish collected from the catchment between 1960 and 1964. Additional wild fish were included in the breeding stock between 1970 and 1975. The breeding population has been effectively closed since that time with brood fish being selected from returning ranched fish. The Burrishoole hatchery population fish are referred to as ranched fish.
 </p>
 <div id="RSPB20090799F2" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 2.</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Smolt and egg numbers and winter temperatures at Burrishoole since 1972. (
    <span class="italic">a</span>) smolt numbers ('000, open circle) and egg numbers (million, filled circle) for that smolt cohort plotted against smolt migration year, 1972–2006; (
    <span class="italic">b</span>) egg to smolt per cent survival (filled circle) and the percentage of ranched eggs (open circle) in that egg cohort plotted against smolt migration year, 1972–2006; (
    <span class="italic">c</span>) mean winter (DJF) SWT (°C) in Lough Feeagh, 1972–2006.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="rspb20090799f02" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The estimated fecundities for this analysis of both Burrishoole wild and ranched females are based on values previously reported in 1974 of 4000 eggs for one sea winter fish and 6000 eggs for two sea winter fish (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="RSPB20090799C42" href="#RSPB20090799C42">Salmon Research Trust/Agency of Ireland including the Marine Institute 1955–2006</a>). The sex ratio of 55 per cent female for one sea winter wild fish is based on the average value reported between 1963 and 1974. A value of 70 per cent female is calculated for two sea winter wild fish based on observations on fish captured in the Burrishoole river traps. All ranched fish spawning in the wild are assumed to be one sea winter fish. All smolts are assumed to be 2 years old (time from emergence to smoltification). The percentage survival to smolt stage was calculated from these data and is referred to as egg-to-smolt survival. The value for 2001 was exceptionally high (3.5 times the s.d.) and was considered to be an outlier and omitted from the analysis. The number of ranched eggs contributing to the total number of eggs in any year was expressed as a proportion (ranched eggs/all eggs).
 </p>
</sec>
