<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s4b" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(b)</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The possibility that adaptation to environmental change in the wild is constrained by gene flow from the hatchery</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results clearly demonstrate that hatchery fish spawning in the wild can impact negatively on freshwater survival chances in natural populations. The study provides some clues as to one specific cause and effect. However, in addition to the winter temperature effects postulated, captively bred fish in other studies have shown increased metabolic rates and food conversion efficiency (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="RSPB20090799C46" href="#RSPB20090799C46">Thodesen 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>. 1999
  </a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="RSPB20090799C18" href="#RSPB20090799C18">Handeland 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>. 2003
  </a>), higher growth rates (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="RSPB20090799C11" href="#RSPB20090799C11">Fleming &amp; Einum 1997</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="RSPB20090799C29" href="#RSPB20090799C29">McGinnity 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>. 1997
  </a>), to be more aggressive (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="RSPB20090799C7" href="#RSPB20090799C7">Einum &amp; Fleming 1997</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="RSPB20090799C11" href="#RSPB20090799C11">Fleming &amp; Einum 1997</a>) and less risk averse to predators compared with wild fish (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="RSPB20090799C7" href="#RSPB20090799C7">Einum &amp; Fleming 1997</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="RSPB20090799C11" href="#RSPB20090799C11">Fleming &amp; Einum 1997</a>). These are all characteristics that have proven to be maladaptive in the wild. Without tangible gene flow from the hatchery to the river, the differential response of the progeny of wild and hatchery fish to higher winter temperature could account for the variation in survival observed with respect to the proportion of hatchery fish in the spawning population. Yet this is of little consequence to the evolutionary trajectory of the wild population unless there is a direct genetic interaction by inter-breeding between wild and ranched adults either in the parental F1 or subsequent generations. A direct interaction would lead to a change in the genetic composition of the wild population by the addition or incorporation of a ‘genetic load’ carried over from the hatchery into the wild that might subsequently affect its productivity. This ‘load’ or degree of maladaptation to the existing natural environment occurs because hatchery populations (where food is available ad libitum) do not experience the continuous evolutionary adjustment possible in the wild, and therefore they do not have the benefit of a history of natural selection experienced by the wild population. Consequently, the mismatch between the hatchery fish and the natural environment will increase. In addition, domestication selection in the hatchery population, such as for reduced fear of predators, will exacerbate these differences over time. Illustrating this possibility empirically (McGinnity 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="RSPB20090799C29" href="#RSPB20090799C29">1997</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="RSPB20090799C30" href="#RSPB20090799C30">2003</a>), it has been shown that hybrid progeny of local wild salmon and farm escape salmon parents have, when compared under natural conditions, intermediate fitness to their parents. This lower fitness in hybrids was found to be accompanied by a reduction in the productive potential of the hybridized population. It is known that ranched and wild salmon at Burrishoole interbreed in the wild (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="RSPB20090799C48" href="#RSPB20090799C48">Thompson 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>. 1998
  </a>), gene flow primarily occurring by fertilization of eggs of ranched females by wild mature male parr. Although not usually to the same extent, it has also been shown in this and other studies that substantial levels of gene flow also occurs via captive bred males to wild females (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="RSPB20090799C12" href="#RSPB20090799C12">Fleming 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>. 2000
  </a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="RSPB20090799C50" href="#RSPB20090799C50">Weir 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>. 2004
  </a>). The extent of the gene flow between ranched males and wild females might be expected to be a function of the proportion of captive bred fish in the spawning population. We might conclude therefore that some of the HiLo effect on egg-to-smolt survival pertains to both the progeny of the hatchery fish and the F(n) hybrid progeny of wild and hatchery reared fish.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We interpret our results as being consistent with the predictions of general theoretical demographic-evolutionary models (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="RSPB20090799C6" href="#RSPB20090799C6">Burger &amp; Lynch 1995</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="RSPB20090799C17" href="#RSPB20090799C17">Gomulkiewicz &amp; Holt 1995</a>; 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="RSPB20090799C28" href="#RSPB20090799C28">Kirkpatrick &amp; Barton 1997</a>). These models suggest that each time a population undergoes an evolutionary adjustment in response to variations in the environment through natural selection, a demographic penalty, such as a higher rate of mortality is incurred. In our study, the demographic penalty associated with increases in winter temperature or high summer precipitation is a reduction in egg-to-smolt survival. Though the relationship between natural selection and environmental change and the demographic response have been modelled extensively, there are very few empirical examples under natural conditions (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="RSPB20090799C16" href="#RSPB20090799C16">Grant &amp; Grant 2002</a>). The end product of these adjustments should be a population that is better adapted to its local environment and consequently is increasing in size towards its carrying capacity (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="RSPB20090799C28" href="#RSPB20090799C28">Kirkpatrick &amp; Barton 1997</a>). However, what is also suggested from our results is that the potential to adapt to environmental change can be thwarted by concurrent and recurrent genetic changes in the wild population following hybridization with captive bred animals, which are subject to domestication and possibly directional selection. Also they will not be not subject to natural selection in benign hatchery environments and as a consequence are less well adapted to life in the wild. This would counteract any positive adaptive response in the wild population to environmental change and increase the demographic costs imposed by natural selection.
 </p>
</sec>
