<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s3b" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(b)</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Concealment</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Contrary to our predictions, hares did not seek higher concealment with increasing colour contrast; rather, the level of concealment was mostly affected by season and site. First, we detected habituation to human observers, as concealment began to significantly decrease with number of location attempts when hares were located more than nine times. Therefore, we truncated the dataset to include only the first nine observations per hare which yielded a total of 731 observations from 139 radiocollared individuals at the two sites. Each individual was observed an average of 6.4 occasions (s.d. = 2.9).</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The best model included season, site and quadratic form of colour contrast at 1 m (see the electronic supplementary material, S2, for the set of best models tested). The other three best models included one additional term each: snow at 10 m, whiteness, and snow at 1 m (in order) that had positive effects on concealment, but their 95% HPD intervals included zero. The significant quadratic relationship of contrast on concealment was in the opposite direction than expected, with highest concealment at medium levels of positive colour contrast and reduced concealment at high negative and high positive contrasts (
  <span class="italic">β</span>
  <sub>Contrast</sub> = 0.0051, s.d. = 0.0021; 
  <span class="italic">β</span>
  <sub>Contrast</sub>
  <span class="sup">2</span> = −0.000085, s.d. = 0.000026; see the electronic supplementary materials, S3 and S4). Concealment varied seasonally, and hares were on average concealed by 25% more in the summer and 8% more in the autumn than in the winter, but not significantly different in the spring than in the winter. Concealment was significantly different at the two sites; hares at the Seeley Lake site were on average 11% more concealed than at the Gardiner site.
 </p>
</sec>
