<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="discussion" id="s4" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Across a wide range of snow conditions and two study sites, snowshoe hares demonstrated little plasticity for modifying coat colour moult phenology or behaviours to track seasonal snowpack. The fixed initiation dates of coat colour moults are consistent with a photoperiod modulator of timing, as occurs for other circannual processes [
  <a rid="RSPB20140029C33" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20140029C33">33</a>–
  <a rid="RSPB20140029C35" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20140029C35">35</a>]. We observed no plasticity in the rate of the autumn brown-to-white moult on both the population (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSPB20140029F1" href="#RSPB20140029F1">figure 1</a>) and individual level (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSPB20140029F2" href="#RSPB20140029F2">figure 2</a>). Consistent with the findings of [
  <a rid="RSPB20140029C13" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20140029C13">13</a>], we found plasticity in the rate of the spring white-to-brown moult with mean completion dates shifted by 19 days across two years of different snowpack. Additionally, we observed plasticity in the individual rate of moult in the spring. The one hare which was observed over two springs at the Gardiner site displayed different moult phenology each year, with a difference in spring moult rates nearly as large as observed across all of the six individuals over multiple autumn moults (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSPB20140029F2" href="#RSPB20140029F2">figure 2</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The mechanisms for a fixed autumn moult phenology and only limited plasticity in the spring rate are unclear. One explanation for plasticity in the spring moult could be an elevated predation rate in the spring [
  <a rid="RSPB20140029C36" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20140029C36">36</a>], placing higher selection pressure to adjust the rate of the spring moult as a means of optimizing camouflage against immediate snow conditions. Further, hares might simply be able to trace the change in the snow conditions better in the spring than in the autumn. Over three years and two study sites, we observed four substantial snow fluctuations (more than 30% and in the opposite direction of the seasonal change) in the weekly average snow cover around hares in the autumns and only one such fluctuation in the springs. Thus, the spring change in the snow conditions might be more predictable compared with autumn snow change, where early snowfalls are often followed by full melt-out before continuous winter snow cover builds up.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We did not detect any strong variables influencing the rate of the spring white-to-brown moult. Despite the more consistent snow change in the spring, our change point analysis indicated that snow cover explained only about a three-day shift in the average spring completion date. Temperature also was not a strong regulator of the spring moult rate as it only explained a one-day shift in the completion date. Finally, the rate of moult in the spring was not significantly influenced by sex, with females completing the spring moult on average two days earlier than males. The faster colour moult for females is consistent with previous observations [
  <a rid="RSPB20140029C13" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20140029C13">13</a>,
  <a rid="RSPB20140029C37" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20140029C37">37</a>,
  <a rid="RSPB20140029C38" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20140029C38">38</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The spring and autumn moults across the different study sites were similar in duration, each lasting about 40 days. Despite this similarity in moult length and limited coat colour plasticity within sites, natural selection appears to have aligned the moult phenology to correspond to average local climate at each site. Although the Gardiner site is slightly south of the Seeley Lake site, and therefore has a similar or slightly longer photoperiod, the higher elevation of the Gardiner site leads to considerably longer lasting snowpack. As might be expected with the longer snowpack, hares in the higher elevation Gardiner site obtained their white coats sooner in the autumn and retained them longer in the spring. Elevational and latitudinal gradients have been shown to affect the timing of the moults in several leporid species. Watson [
  <a rid="RSPB20140029C15" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20140029C15">15</a>] showed that mountain hares (
  <span class="italic">Lepus timidus</span>) occupying high elevations became white earlier, turned dark later, and became whiter in winter than those at low elevations. Similarly, latitudinal differences were observed in museum specimens [
  <a rid="RSPB20140029C39" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20140029C39">39</a>], where snowshoe hares from northern latitudes moulted from brown to white earlier in the autumn and retained the white coat longer.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We found that hares did not modify their hiding behaviour in a manner that reduced colour contrast at either the 1- or 10-m radius scale. If our assessment of the range at which predators visually perceive hares is correct, then hares mismatched to their surroundings within a radius of up to 10 m (an area of 314 m
  <span class="sup">2</span>) are more vulnerable to detection. The relationship between concealment and colour contrast suggested that hares most concealed themselves by vegetation when their coats were about 40% whiter than their immediate (1-m radius) background (40% contrast) and least when brown hares were on snowy backgrounds (−100% contrast; see the electronic supplementary material, S3). Because the effect size was small, this relationship may represent weak biological importance. Overall, concealment levels of hares seemed to be most affected by season and site, which may be good proxies for available vegetation cover. Hares were more concealed in the summer and autumn when leafy vegetation in the understory provided more horizontal cover than in the winter and spring when leafy vegetation was either absent or covered by snow.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Second, we did not find evidence for hares responding to colour contrast at either the 1- or 10-m radius scale by fleeing at a farther distance from a potential threat. FID of positively mismatched hares (white hares on brown background) was no different than for matched hares; negatively mismatched hares (brown hares on snowy background) consistently had the shortest FID. On the contrary, concealment had a strong effect on FID; hares that were most concealed stayed still longest. Shorter FIDs when concealment was high likely represented decreased perceptions of risk, as has been reported, for example, for pygmy rabbits (
  <span class="italic">Brachylagus idahoensis</span>; [
  <a rid="RSPB20140029C22" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20140029C22">22</a>]). Seasonally, hares fled at longer distances in the summer than in the winter, consistent with our field observations that hares seemed to be more active in the summer (see also [
  <a rid="RSPB20140029C40" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20140029C40">40</a>], who observed lowest activity for hares in winter). Longer flight distance in summer is also consistent with the general expectation that prey flee at farther distances when in better body condition [
  <a rid="RSPB20140029C21" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20140029C21">21</a>]. Indeed, our personal field observations of hares during winter are that they generally appear calmer when approached, flee less even if they are fully exposed and often have their eyes closed, perhaps a strategy to save energy during winter periods of food limitation. Additionally, hares might perceive less predation risk in winter as their low foot loading provides a likely escape advantage from potential carnivores on snow [
  <a rid="RSPB20140029C41" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20140029C41">41</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Lastly, we found no evidence of hares preferring resting spots with colour background that would reduce colour contrast. On the contrary, hares were more likely to be found at spots within their immediate surroundings that increased their colour contrast with the background within 10-m radius. This is likely result of their overall preference to rest at spots with little snow cover. We noted this behaviour during field observations; when snow cover was heterogeneous on the landscape, hares were located at non-snowy spots such as under logs or in tree wells. Thermoregulation may therefore be playing an important role in resting spot choice.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Finally, we note several caveats and assumptions. First, our choices of 1- and 10-m radius of snow cover around hares might not represent the spatial scale of perceived colour contrast for hares and/or their predators. We did not consider larger areas than 10-m radius for estimating colour contrast based on the assumption that visual detection of hares by predators at such scales was unlikely in these relatively dense forests. Second, because little is known about the drivers of the circannual rhythm of the moult, our measurements of moult regulators (e.g. snow cover, cumulative sum of temperature degree days) may not capture the correct regulators of colour moult phenology in the wild. Likewise, hares may be pursuing behavioural strategies to reduce colour contrast that we did not measure. Hares and many of their predators are primarily crepuscular and nocturnal, and thus hares could be deploying anti-predatory strategies that minimize colour contrast during the main periods of activity. For example, hares could be foraging during the night preferentially at areas that match their coat colour or they could be modifying their FID in response to colour contrast during those times of the day. Finally, our use of human observers as a proxy for predators assumes that FID response to humans is the same as to hares’ natural terrestrial predators.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nevertheless, across multiple years, two study sites, a wide range of snow conditions, and nearly 200 hares monitored in the wild, we find no evidence that hares perceive coat colour mismatch and act to shift hiding or flight behaviours or immediate microsite choice. We also confirm that moult initiation dates are fixed across years of different snowpacks, even as the moult phenology is locally shaped within regions by a combination of photoperiod and climate. Given the prospect for substantially decreased snowpack duration in the future due to climate change [
  <a rid="RSPB20140029C13" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20140029C13">13</a>,
  <a rid="RSPB20140029C42" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSPB20140029C42">42</a>], it seems that the most likely avenue for reducing camouflage mismatch or its potential predation consequences in local populations is evolutionary shifts in moult phenologies, anti-predatory behaviours or in phenotypic plasticity.
 </p>
</sec>
