<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s3c" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(c)</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Flight initiation distance</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hares did not flee at farther distances with increasing mismatch as we predicted, but rather their concealment level, season and site variables played important roles in predicting their FID. We detected habituation to human observers, as FID began to significantly decrease with number of location attempts when hares were located more than five times. Therefore, we truncated the dataset to include only the first five observations per hare which yielded a total of 367 observations from 104 radiocollared individuals. Each individual was located on average 4.1 occasions (s.d. = 1.3).</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our set of best models included concealment, site, season, sex and either contrast or mismatch (see the electronic supplementary material, S5, for the set of best models tested). The model results can be interpreted as the increase in probability of flight initiation throughout the distance within which we measured the FID response (=20 m). Our first, second and sixth best model included mismatch at 10 m. Hares matched with their background were 5.6 times more likely to flee than brown hares on snowy background (hazard ratio
  <sub>Negative Mismatch</sub> = 5.62, s.e. = 1.72), but there was no difference for white hares on brown background (hazard ratio
  <sub>Positive Mismatch</sub> = 1.62, s.e. = 1.39; see the electronic supplementary material, S6, for a list of coefficients from the best model). A similar trend was observed in the fourth and fifth best model that included absolute mismatch at 10 m scale, where matched hares were about two times (fourth best model: hazard ratio
  <sub>Abs Mismatch</sub> = 2.02, s.e. = 1.33; fifth best model: hazard ratio
  <sub>Abs Mismatch</sub> = 1.87, s.e. = 1.33) more likely to flee than mismatched hares. The third best model included a linear relationship with colour contrast at 1 m. Hares were 0.77% more likely to flee with each 1% decrement in colour contrast (hazard ratio
  <sub>Contrast</sub> = 1.01, s.e. = 1.00).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Concealment significantly decreased flight distance; with each 25% increment in body concealed hares were 26% less likely to flee. There was a significant difference in FID at the two sites; hares at the Gardiner site were 89% more likely to flee than hares at the Seeley Lake site. Season appeared in all best models but only summer was significantly different from winter; hares were 21% more likely to flee in summer than in winter. Sex was present in all best models as it improved model fit but was not significant in any of them. Similarly, snow at 1 m around hares and whiteness were present in three models of the best models set but their effects were not significant in any. According to the score tests and scatterplots of scaled Schoenfeld residuals, there was no evidence of non-proportional hazards in any of the terms in the best models.</p>
</sec>
