<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this paper, we applied ENM to develop three hypotheses about genetic structure and population demography and tested the hypotheses by analyzing two genetic data sets in a phylogeographical framework. Below, we discuss these hypotheses in the light of our a priori expectations and the observed results.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A shallow divergence pattern between northern and southern populations was revealed by mitochondrial DNA, but no such pattern was found in nuclear DNA, which instead showed a widely shared ancestral haplotype (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f4" href="#f4">Fig. 4</a>). Such discordances between mitochondrial and nuclear data might result from a variety of factors, such as incomplete lineage sorting of ancestral polymorphism, potentially sex-biased dispersal or the different evolutionary rates of different markers
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b10" href="#b10">10</a>. Firstly, if incomplete lineage sorting leads to the observed mitochondrial DNA pattern, we would anticipate a less shallow divergence pattern in the nuclear DNA, since the relatively larger effective population size would result in a longer sorting time
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b21" href="#b21">21</a>. However, analysis of the nuclear DNA data did not reveal any genetic divergence in the populations, suggesting that incomplete lineage sorting was not likely to be the main reason. Secondly, since sex-biased dispersive behavior influencing the phylogeographical structure had been studied in many animals
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b22" href="#b22">22</a>, we hypothesized that if females possessed native philopatry and males displayed high dispersal capacity, it would show that a significant IBD pattern detected in the mitochondrial DNA and a nonsignificant IBD pattern in nuclear DNA
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b23" href="#b23">23</a>. Interestingly, this hypothesis was in accordance with our IBD results (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">Fig. S2</a>), which did not reject the possibility that a higher male dispersal ability was responsible for incongruence between mitochondrial DNA and nuclear DNA. However, there were no direct evidences in the literature for 
  <span class="italic">M. horvathi</span> to testify whether the different sexes showed different dispersal capacity, which should be studied further through ecological and biological observations or experiments in the future. Thirdly, the reconstructed palaeodistribution from ENM prediction might show that the discordance patterns observed in mitochondrial DNA and nuclear DNA were most likely explained by the different evolutionary rates of these two markers. The ENM indicated a potentially largely continuous range in subtropical China during the LIG period with relatively high temperature than now
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b24" href="#b24">24</a>, but in the LGM period, the most suitable habitats contracted into two main refugia (the Sichuan Basin space and a space from northern Vietnam to northern Guangxi). Under the CCSM model, we suggested that the glacially-induced population isolation was sustained only long enough for divergence in mitochondrial DNA, which possesses a relatively fast mutation rate, and in a small effective population size, but not enough for divergence in the nuclear gene (ITS), with a slower evolutionary rate and a larger effective population size. Based on the molecular evidence, the divergence in mtDNA accumulated during the LGM had not entirely disappeared though the northern and southern populations came into contact with gene exchange during the LGM to current transition. Geographical barriers and ecological factors likely inhibited or slowed down the homogenizing gene flow between the northern and southern populations, which shaped the currently shallow divergence pattern. This accorded with Hypothesis 2 above.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It has been also demonstrated that mountains, as geographical barriers, played a key role in speciation and lineage differentiation by obstructing or slower migration/gene flow between populations
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b25" href="#b25">25</a>. Many previous studies had paid close attention to the effects of very large mountain systems such as the Hengduan and Qinling Mts., but less attention had been paid to the effect of the smaller mountain systems in subtropical China. In the Miocene and Pliocene, intensive tectonic activity had already begun in subtropical China
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b15" href="#b15">15</a>. Today, the north-south fauna dividing line in subtropical China was associated with a dramatic series of east-west trending mountain ridges reaching elevations of over 2000 m above sea level and differences between valleys and ridges extending 500 m above sea level in elevation. The Wuyi, Nanling and Xuefeng Mts were characteristic in this respect. The Wuyi and Nanling Mts. acted as protective barriers against the inflow of cold air from the northwest and retained warm moist air originating from the sea, resulting in a humid climate with high rainfall
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b26" href="#b26">26</a>. The Xuefeng Mountains ran northeast to southwest and acted as a protective barrier against different climate environments on the eastern edge of the Guizhou Plateau. These three east-west trending mountains were an important faunal dividing line between the Palaearctic Realm and the Oriental Realm
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b27" href="#b27">27</a>. We suggested that gene flow between the northern and southern populations was likely to be influenced by these mountains. Our molecular data confirmed hypothesis 2, showing that 
  <span class="italic">M. horvathi</span> was genetically and geographically divided into north-south clades (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f1" href="#f1">Fig. 1</a>, clade I and clade II). The haplotypes of clade I were widespread in the north and the haplotypes of clade II were mainly restricted to the narrow south areas. For example, some haplotypes were confined to the north or south, a haplotype h1 pattern which was found in 21 populations mostly distributed in the north of the mountains. A similar north-south geographical differentiation had been observed in previous studies, including the Chinese canopy tree 
  <span class="italic">Eurycorymbus cavaleriei</span>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b28" href="#b28">28</a> and the small freshwater fish 
  <span class="italic">Squalidus argentatus</span>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b29" href="#b29">29</a>. Therefore, we speculated that the Wuyi, Nanling and Xuefeng Mts. might have acted as geographical barriers preventing or slowing down gene flow between the northern and southern populations, resulting in lineage differentiation especially during the inter-glacial periods. Further, these mountains areas commonly identified as biodiversity hotspots
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b30" href="#b30">30</a> and acted as important refugia during Pleistocene glacial periods because of the extremely topographical complexity which could provide different suitable stable microclimates for many species to survive during the glacial period, harboring high diversities of haplotypes and lineages. Our molecular data supported this idea; the GZYH, GXME, JXLN, GDBL, ZJTS and FJSW populations of 
  <span class="italic">M. horvathi</span> were entirely located in the Wuyi, Nanling and Xuefeng Mts., and occupied very high haplotype diversities relative to the other populations (e.g. 
  <span class="italic">Hd</span>
  <sub>GZYH</sub> = 0.844, 
  <span class="italic">Hd</span>
  <sub>GXME</sub> = 0.900, 
  <span class="italic">Hd</span>
  <sub>JXLN</sub> = 0.972, 
  <span class="italic">Hd</span>
  <sub>FJSW</sub> = 0.917), and all these populations also showed haplotype diversities both from clade I and clade II (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f1" href="#f1">Fig. 1</a>). Thus, we suggested that these mountain areas were refugia for 
  <span class="italic">M. horvathi</span> during the glacial period. In the LGM prediction under the CCSM model, one refugium was identified in northern Guangxi extending to northern Guangdong (areas of Nanling and Xuefeng Mts.) (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f2" href="#f2">Fig. 2</a>). In conclusion, the Wuyi, Nanling and Xuefeng mountains not only as geographical barriers, obstructing or slowering gene flow between northern and southern populations and promoting to lineage differentiation, but also as potentially suitable areas during the glacial period, preserving the very high genetic diversities and diverse genetic lineages.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The geographical distribution of species was also affected by both historical and present-day ecological factors. Current ecological factors were clearly important in maintaining divergence of the genetic lineages of 
  <span class="italic">M. horvathi</span>. This conclusion was based on the relatively strong coincidence between the northern and southern structural groups and zoogeographical fauna in subtropical China
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b27" href="#b27">27</a>, which revealed that the two groups occupied different climatic regimes (the Palaearctic Realm and Oriental Realm). In this case, the effects of ecological factors might be much more prominent for lineage differentiation. The Palaearctic Realm and Oriental Realm in subtropical China showed rather prominent difference in many environmental variables, such as temperature, precipitation, elevation and vegetation types. In the Palaearctic Realm of subtropical China, 
  <span class="italic">M. horvathi</span> inhabited temperate deciduous forest and evergreen broad-leaved forest. In contrast, in the Oriental Realm, it mostly inhabited monsoon rain forest, evergreen broad-leaved forest and island monsoon rain forest, which were warmer and had more precipitation during the year. Among many present-day ecological factors, SEEVA analysis (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">Table S3</a>, 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f6" href="#f6">Fig. 6</a>) showed that temperature and vegetation type greatly contributed to the phylogenetic split between the north and south lineages. The cooler northern region and warmer southern region might have easily affected the physiological activity of 
  <span class="italic">M. horvathi</span>, gradually shaping the different temperature tolerance in the different lineages. However, the precipitation had less influence on the north-south lineage differentiation in subtropical China than expected, given that 
  <span class="italic">M. horvathi</span> was a semi-aquatic species dependent on a water habitat for survival. It was reasonable to assume that 
  <span class="italic">M. horvathi,</span> as a very small insect, only needed minor water microhabitats, and that large-scale precipitation might probably destroy microhabitats including small rain pools, ditches, and swampy ground. Therefore, the main ecological constraint on local lineages could be temperature, with the genetic differentiation resulting from Pleistocene climatic fluctuations being more or less maintained. However, to clarify how different lineages of 
  <span class="italic">M. horvathi</span> adapted to local ecological niches, we still need to further explore the evidence, including studies of the function- related protein-coding genes.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Estimating divergence time derived from the mitochondrial data in BEAST and IMa2 indicated that diversification of 
  <span class="italic">M. horvathi</span> was fairly recent. The north-south differentiation probably occurred during the transition from the LIG to the LGM. In the MJ haplotypes network, four starlike shapes in the south region and one relatively large starlike shape in the north region (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f4" href="#f4">Fig. 4a</a>) suggested that 
  <span class="italic">M. horvathi</span> experienced more population expansion events in the south region than in the north region. The molecular result of neutrality tests (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="t2" href="#t2">Table 2</a>) and the Bayesian skyline plot (BSP) (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f3" href="#f3">Fig. 3c</a>) all indicated that historical population expansion happened after the LGM period. These results were in line with the spatial prediction of ENM (Hypothesis 3) (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f2" href="#f2">Fig. 2</a>). From the LIG to LGM period, when the weather gradually became increasingly dryer and colder, potential spaces for 
  <span class="italic">M. horvathi</span> contracted and were gradually isolated into two largely separate northern and southern refugia (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f2" href="#f2">Fig. 2</a>), after which populations in the isolated refugia had less gene exchange and accumulated major divergence. After the LGM period, when the weather turned warm and moist, the two formerly separate groups expanded and a significantly suitable range increased into the current predicted space (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f2" href="#f2">Fig. 2</a>). These two independent hindcasting methods (phylogeograpic analysis and ENM) achieved a similar historical demographic change pattern. Interestingly, this result was contradictory to the previous phylogeographic studies in 
  <span class="italic">Microvelia douglasi douglasi</span>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b12" href="#b12">12</a>, although these two species both belong to the same genus. We speculated that the main reason for the contradictory patterns might be differences in the ecologic requirements of these two species. 
  <span class="italic">M. douglasi douglasi</span> was widely distributed in the east and southeastern Asia today, but 
  <span class="italic">M. horvathi</span> was mainly confined to subtropical China. The wide distributional range meant that 
  <span class="italic">M. douglasi douglasi</span> exhibited much higher genetic diversity, with the potential to adapt to diverse environments easily. Secondly, in the potential LGM distribution predicted by ENM, 
  <span class="italic">M. dougalsi douglasi</span> inhabited connected and relatively large areas in subtropical China and tropical Asia including Vietnam and Indonesia, while 
  <span class="italic">M. horvathi</span> only inhabited segregated, narrow and discontinuous areas in subtropical China (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f2" href="#f2">Fig. 2</a>). Therefore, we proposed that 
  <span class="italic">M. horvathi</span> might be less adapted to the whole range of local environments in subtropical China than 
  <span class="italic">M. douglasi dougalsi</span>, with relatively lower ecological tolerance, and was particularly sensitive to population changes driven by Pleistocene climatic fluctuations.
 </p>
</sec>
