<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Genetic polymorphism and phylogenetic analysis</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the mitochondrial data, 1405 bp of protein-coding regions of mitochondrial genome were obtained from 250 individuals, including sections of the COI (726 bp) and COII (679 bp) genes. Ninety unique haplotypes were derived among all individuals. The 96 polymorphic sites included 67 singleton variable and 29 parsimony informative sites. The nucleotide diversities and haplotype diversities ranged from 0.00057 to 0.00360 with an average of 0.00262, and 0.378 to 1.000 with an average of 0.845, respectively (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="t1" href="#t1">Table 1</a>). NJ analyses produced tree topology based on combined mitochondrial sequences (COI + COII) (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f3" href="#f3">Fig. 3a</a>). The whole haplotypes were shallowly separated into two supported major clades, clade I and clade II. The haplotype frequencies of clade I and clade II were shown in a pie graph revealing that the geographical distributions of the two monophyletic clades were uneven (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f1" href="#f1">Fig. 1</a>). Most haplotypes of clade I were located widely in the northern region of subtropical China, whereas most haplotypes of clade II were commonly found in the narrower southern region (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f1" href="#f1">Fig. 1</a>). Interestingly, the intermediate populations (ZJTS, JXLN and GZYH) living between the northern and southern regions simultaneously possessed the haplotype diversities of both lineages. The network analysis based on all ninety haplotypes showed the same pattern, with two well-defined independent haplogroups (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f3" href="#f3">Figs 3</a>b and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f4" href="#f4">4</a>a). In the haplotype network (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f4" href="#f4">Fig. 4a</a>), h1, h12, h15 and h25 were the four most frequent haplotypes, characterizing 37.6%, 6%, 3.2% and 9.6% of individuals respectively. The h1 ancestral haplotype was mostly found in the northern region, whereas h12, h15 and h25 were the ancestral haplotypes found in the southern region (
  <a ref-type="table" rid="t1" href="#t1">Table 1</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the nuclear sequencing data, 1039 bp fragments were successfully obtained from 237 individuals, including ITS1, 5.8S and ITS2 genes. 19 unique haplotypes were derived among all individuals. The 19 polymorphic sites included 16 singleton variable and 3 parsimony informative sites. The nucleotide diversities and haplotype diversities ranged from 0 to 0.00123 with an average of 0.00055, and 0.000 to 0.833 with an average of 0.478, respectively (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">Table S1</a>). The mitochondrial DNA structure of lineage differentiation in 
  <span class="italic">M. horvathi</span> was not apparent in the nuclear data (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f4" href="#f4">Fig. 4b</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
