<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Historical demographic changes based on mitochondrial data</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used three neutrality tests, the Tajima’s 
  <span class="italic">D</span>, Fu and Li’s 
  <span class="italic">D</span>* and Fu’s Fs tests, implemented in DNASP 4.0
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b33" href="#b33">33</a> or Arlequin 3.5
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b39" href="#b39">39</a>, to detect deviations from the mutation-drift equilibrium that would be indicative of changes in historical demography and natural selection. We used BEAST 1.8.2
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b41" href="#b41">41</a> to estimate divergence time for the mitochondrial lineages obtained. The best fit nucleotide substitution model GTR + G + I was estimated by Modeltest 3.7
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b42" href="#b42">42</a>. Divergence time was estimated with an uncorrelated lognormal relaxed clock with the mutation rate 0.4–0.8%/Myr for 
  <span class="italic">M. horvathi</span>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b43" href="#b43">43</a>. We adopted one year as seven generation for 
  <span class="italic">M. horvathi</span>
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b44" href="#b44">44</a>, using a coalescent tree prior model with the chains run for 100 million generations, checked to make sure the ESS was more than 200 and then discarded the first 10% as burn-in. We also estimated divergence time using the isolation-with-migration model implemented in IMa2
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="b45" href="#b45">45</a>. The HKY model and 0.25 as inheritance scalar were used. We set the upper prior bounds to 80 for the population size (q), 32 for the divergence time (t) and 0.125 for the migration rate (m). Final runs consisted of 1 × 10
  <span class="sup">8</span> steps with a burn-in of 1 × 10
  <span class="sup">7</span> steps, with the lowest ESS among the parameters at least above 50.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Then two methods were used to estimate population expansion time. One approach used 
  <span class="italic">t</span> = 
  <span class="italic">τ</span>/2
  <span class="italic">u</span> (where 
  <span class="italic">τ</span> is the crest of mismatch distribution, 
  <span class="italic">u</span> is the mutation rate per generation for the whole sequence, and 
  <span class="italic">t</span> is the expansion time in number of generations; the value 
  <span class="italic">u</span> was calculated using the formula 
  <span class="italic">u</span> = 
  <span class="italic">μk</span> (
  <span class="italic">μ</span> is the mutation rate per nucleotide and 
  <span class="italic">k</span> is the number of nucleotides). The other approach used a Bayesian coalescent-based method (Bayesian Skyline Plot, BSP) in BEAST 1.8.2. A relaxed uncorrelated lognormal molecular clock was applied. We ran the chains for 100 million generations, and checked to make sure the ESS was more than 200, after which the first 10% were discarded as “burn-in”.
 </p>
</sec>
