<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Phylogeographic structure and hierarchical partitioning of genetic structure</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">SAMOVA showed a maximum value in 
  <span class="italic">F</span>
  <sub>CT</sub> of 
  <span class="italic">K</span> = 2 (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f5" href="#f5">Fig. 5</a>). The two groups corresponded genetically and geographically (i.e. north and south populations) in subtropical China. Zones of genetic discontinuities identified by Barrier 2.2 showed the potential geographical barriers associated with the genetic abruption (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">Fig. S1</a>). The bold lines mainly divided the entire sampling region into a northern and a southern subregion, reflecting significant genetic/geographical isolation between them. Isolations between the northern and southern subregions (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">Fig. S1</a>) were mostly consistent with the results of SAMOVA. The nuclear sequencing data showed much lower genetic diversities than the mitochondrial data, and revealed no distinct phylogeographical structure pattern (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f4" href="#f4">Fig. 4b</a>). Therefore SAMOVA and Barrier analysis were not implemented in nuclear data.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">AMOVA analysis showed a relatively significant genetic variance between the northern and southern groups in mitochondrial DNA data (48.45%, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.05) (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">Table S2</a>). However, the same analyses of nuclear DNA data attributed most genetic variance (83.69%) to differentiation among individuals within populations (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">Table S2</a>). The Mantel tests revealed a significant positive relationship in the mitochondrial DNA (r = 0.5590, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.001), but not in nuclear DNA (r = −0.0478, 
  <span class="italic">P</span> = 0.3120) (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">Fig. S2a,b</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
