<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Over the past decade, the Pacific Northwest of North America has experienced a significant warming trend (roughly 0.5–1.5°C; [
 <xref rid="pone.0142110.ref022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>]). Temperatures are predicted to continue to warm across all seasons at rates comparable to or higher than current rates, with variable predictions for precipitation [
 <xref rid="pone.0142110.ref023" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>]. Such changes will accelerate woody vegetation growth in former alpine tundra; for instance, Flower 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="pone.0142110.ref024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>] predict rapid upward shifts in elevational range for both Douglas Fir (
 <italic class="italic">Pseudotsuga menziesii</italic>) and spruce (
 <italic class="italic">Picea</italic> spp.) in British Columbia, and Laroque 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="pone.0142110.ref025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>] used dendroclimatological analysis to document climate-related pulses of tree establishment at high elevations on southern Vancouver Island during the 20
 <sup class="sup">th</sup> century. They predicted rapid infilling of alpine meadow sites within 10–20 years, with negative consequences for montane meadow-dependent wildlife. Subsequent research has shown that infilling by trees and shrubs at high elevations occurred on Vancouver Island between 1962 and 2005 [
 <xref rid="pone.0142110.ref026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>]. Such expansion of woody vegetation leads not only to loss of suitable habitat for alpine species but also to habitat fragmentation and loss of connectivity. Most studies investigating potential climate-induced range changes for wildlife focus primarily on habitat loss and shifting climate envelopes, but fragmentation may also play a crucial role, particularly for alpine species with limited room “at the top” for tracking climate envelopes upward in elevation.
</p>
