<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="other5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Intervention Approach</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Healthy Communities Coalition members and program staff members worked through a collaborative needs assessment process to identify local resources, including existing food stores. In some cases, coalition members introduced LSU AgCenter staff to local food store owners. If contact was more difficult to make, the program staff conducted outreach to food stores and invited store owners to attend Healthy Communities Coalition meetings. In one Healthy Communities Coalition, the store owner regularly attended coalition meetings. Owners from at least one major food store, grocery, or convenience store were recruited in each parish. To improve the intervention’s reach, our approach was geared toward engaging owners of local stores recommended by community members as being locations where they frequently shopped. All store owners who were invited to participate agreed to do so. In total, 5 stores (3 grocery stores and 2 convenience stores) across the 3 parishes became Healthy Communities Partner Stores.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In June 2017, store owners received technical assistance through in-person site visits regarding strategies to promote healthy food items from a consultant with The Food Trust, a national healthy food access organization. Store owners were asked to provide input on available marketing materials that worked best for their store, were given shelving and cooler infrastructure, and asked about aesthetic preferences. Store owners selected the most applicable and feasible interventions to improve healthy food access and awareness in their store. All stores chose to participate in in-store marketing and nutrition education, and LSU AgCenter program staff members led implementation to minimize the burden on the food store staff. Although no monetary incentives were provided, store owners did receive marketing materials at no cost. The marketing materials were provided by the LSU AgCenter and valued at $1,000 per store. Store owners were also encouraged to stock healthy items; however, this was voluntary. One store used a merchandising store “reset” (large scale rearrangement of a store’s products) as an opportunity to integrate healthy food products into their store.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In-store marketing included shelf banners and signage that used a traffic-light concept to help customers identify healthy and unhealthy options. Green signals “Go,” indicating the healthiest foods; yellow signals “Caution,” indicating somewhat healthy foods; and red signals “Stop and Think,” indicating the least healthy foods (
  <a rid="T1" ref-type="table" href="#T1">Table 1</a>). Marketing was installed throughout partner stores in produce, dairy, and meat departments and on aisles of canned and frozen goods, bread, pasta, and cereal. Grab-and-go coolers with beverages and snack items were also targeted. In-store marketing was installed in all partner stores over a 4-month period (September–December 2017). The in-store marketing exposure period ranged from 8 to 12 months (August 2017–August 2018). LSU AgCenter staff members conducted in-store nutrition education lessons, including food demonstrations and healthy food taste tests, on at least a quarterly basis during the intervention period.
 </p>
 <div id="T1" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Table 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">In-store Marketing Using Traffic Light Concept to Indicate Healthy Foods, Louisiana 2017–2018</div>
  </div>
  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
   <col width="65" span="1"/>
   <col width="115" span="1"/>
   <col width="143" span="1"/>
   <col width="143" span="1"/>
   <thead>
    <tr>
     <th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1"> </th>
     <th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Green – Go: Healthiest</th>
     <th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Yellow – Caution: Somewhat Healthy</th>
     <th valign="top" align="left" scope="col" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Red – Stop: Least Healthy</th>
    </tr>
   </thead>
   <tbody>
    <tr>
     <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fruits and vegetables</td>
     <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fresh fruits and vegetables</td>
     <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canned or frozen fruits and vegetables with less than 290 mg sodium and no added sugar</td>
     <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Canned or frozen fruits and vegetables with more than 290 mg sodium or with added sugar</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Grains</td>
     <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Whole grains listed as the first ingredient: pasta, rice, bread, flour</td>
     <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Refined and whole grain: whole grain is not listed as first ingredient</td>
     <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">White refined: whole grain not listed as an ingredient</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proteins</td>
     <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lean and low-fat fish, poultry, eggs, beef, pork</td>
     <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Non-lean meat: steak, ground beef, poultry with skin</td>
     <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Processed meats: high sodium or high fat meats – bacon, deli meat, sausage</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td valign="top" align="left" scope="row" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beverages</td>
     <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">No sugar added, water, fat-free, or 1% low-fat milk</td>
     <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">100% juice, diet drinks, low-fat chocolate milk</td>
     <td valign="top" align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Soda, fruit drinks, sport drinks, iced tea, lemonade</td>
    </tr>
   </tbody>
  </table>
 </div>
</sec>
