<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Understanding how animals respond to temperature is key to predicting the consequences of climate change. Since ectotherms are unable to regulate their body temperature as effectively as endotherms they have adapted to develop and function within temperature ranges that are typical for their habitat. However, there is little information regarding the regulation of the thermal limits of a species or how they respond to a different temperature range. Terrestrial ectotherms are likely to face increased periods of heat stress as mean temperatures and temperature variability are predicted to increase over the next few decades (
 <xref rid="msy132-B48" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kharin et al. 2007</xref>; 
 <xref rid="msy132-B83" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Smith et al. 2015</xref>). On one hand, there is growing evidence that small aquatic ectotherms with shorter generation times are able to rapidly adapt to climate change. For example, the water flea (
 <italic class="italic">Daphnia magna</italic>) in the UK and oceanic phytoplankton in the Gulf of Cariaco, Venezuela, have adapted to an increase in temperature over several years by increasing their thermal niche (
 <xref rid="msy132-B25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Geerts et al. 2015</xref>; 
 <xref rid="msy132-B42" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Irwin et al. 2015</xref>). On the other hand, many organisms respond to climate change by altering their geographic range. Both vertebrate and invertebrate species have moved towards higher latitudes over a circa 25 year period, presumably following the thermal optima to which they are already adapted (
 <xref rid="msy132-B34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hickling et al. 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="msy132-B13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Chen et al. 2011</xref>). Analysis of 612 crop pests and pathogens established a global move poleward since the 1960s for some organisms but not for either of the potato cyst nematode (PCN) species 
 <italic class="italic">Globodera pallida</italic> or 
 <italic class="italic">G. rostochiensis</italic> in the Northern hemisphere (
 <xref rid="msy132-B6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bebber et al. 2013</xref>).
</p>
