<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The PCN 
 <italic class="italic">G. pallida</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">G. rostochiensis</italic> are major pests of the potato crop in cool-temperate areas of the world. PCN is indigenous to South America (
 <xref rid="msy132-B20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Evans et al. 1975</xref>; 
 <xref rid="msy132-B70" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Plantard et al. 2008</xref>) but has been introduced to Europe and subsequently is now found in all major potato growing regions of the world (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.cabi.org/isc/datasheet/27033" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.cabi.org/isc/datasheet/27033</ext-link> and 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cabi.org/isc/datasheet/27034" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.cabi.org/isc/datasheet/27034</ext-link>, last accessed September 14, 2017) where it causes losses to potato harvests of up to 50% (
 <xref rid="msy132-B86" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Trudgill 1986</xref>). PCN are host-specific parasites that coevolved over 15–21 My with wild potato species (
 <italic class="italic">Solanum</italic> L. section Petota Dumort.) in the cool-temperate climate of the Andean highlands. The two species are estimated to have diverged ∼18 Ma and display a shift in thermal range (
 <xref rid="msy132-B70" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Plantard et al. 2008</xref>). 
 <italic class="italic">Globodera pallida</italic> is adapted to high altitudes and is considered to have undergone an expansion northwards within the current day Peru, Ecuador and Columbia as the Andean chain rose in that region during the Miocene. 
 <italic class="italic">Globodera rostochiensis</italic> is hypothesised to originate from where uplift of the paleo-Andes was less extreme and therefore the climate is slightly warmer. However, the boundaries of the native geographical ranges for the two species, both at recent and geological time scales, are uncertain (Oro et al. 2014).
</p>
