<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">As the result of feed intake, concentrate could be fed at 0.5% BW with SG-based when compared to 1.0% BW with RS-based in heifer feeding. It appears that SG could reduce the use of concentrate supplementation without negative effect on the amount of feed uptake, nutrient digestibility and intake of nutrients. These results are in accordance with previous experiments which showed that SG was a high quality roughage, especially as it has the lowest content of NDF and ADF when compared to Ruzi, Guinea and Napier Pakchong1 grass at a similar age of regrowth. This resulted in having the highest degradability and accumulated gas production, using 
 <italic class="italic">in vitro</italic> gas production technique. Moreover, it was found that higher quality roughage could decrease levels of concentrate supplementation [
 <xref rid="b10-ajas-31-12-1890" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>]. The results of this experiment confirmed that voluntary feed intake of roughage, nutrient digestibility and nutrients intake were significantly related to the quality of roughage as NRC, [
 <xref rid="b14-ajas-31-12-1890" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>] presented that NDF and ADF content were highly related to DM intake and digestibility of roughage. The current results were according to those of previous studies which showed feeding higher quality roughage could increase feed efficiency in ruminants [
 <xref rid="b5-ajas-31-12-1890" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="b24-ajas-31-12-1890" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>–
 <xref rid="b26-ajas-31-12-1890" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>]. Corea et al [
 <xref rid="b26-ajas-31-12-1890" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>] also found that using Cow-pea as a high quality roughage could reduce the CP content in concentrate from 17.0% to 15.5% without altering the feed digestibility, milk production, and milk components of lactating dairy cows. It also agreed with the findings of Wanapat et al [
 <xref rid="b5-ajas-31-12-1890" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>] that higher quality roughage achieved using the tropical legume (
 <italic class="italic">Phaseolus calcaratus</italic>) mixed with Ruzi grass could improve DM intake, nutrient digestibility and milk production. Moreover, it could be used to reduce the amount of concentrate supplementation without adversely effect on rumen fermentation characteristics and milk production in tropical dairy cows. Therefore, quality of roughage is very important to the improvement of feed intake and feed utilization efficiency in ruminant feeding to ensure efficient rumen fermentation and production.
</p>
