<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par11" class="p">The cold stress temperature threshold (TTCS) sets the extreme low temperatures, below which the species cannot survive. TTCS is a weekly average of minimum temperatures that are accumulated at a specific rate, known as the cold stress temperature rate (THCS). Maize does not tolerate low temperatures and dies just below the freezing point
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">5</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">13</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" class="xref">52</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" class="xref">53</xref>
 </sup>. Low temperatures affect germination, emergence and vegetative growth. The intensity of the damage will depend on the air temperature and duration of the stress exposure. Maize plants are sensitive to cold temperatures, and frost is detrimental at all stages of plant development, except as dry seed (0 to 6 °C); young plants can be killed at 1 °C
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" class="xref">53</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" class="xref">54</xref>
 </sup> or from the severe cold stress that occurs at 0 °C
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">5</xref>, 
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" class="xref">55</xref>
 </sup>. A group of cold-induced maize genes (
 <italic class="italic">ZmCOI</italic>) that may affect abiotic stresses was isolated from maize exposed to 6 °C
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" class="xref">56</xref>
 </sup>. A review by Garcia and Lopez
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>
 </sup> found that maize can tolerate temperatures as low as −2 and −3.5 °C, but they did not mention the acceptable duration of low temperatures. Thus, the TTCS was adjusted to 7 °C with a THCS of −0.00007 week
 <sup class="sup">−1</sup>, to allow for the existence of the coldest current locations, such as Norway, Sweden, Finland and northeastern China, but to avoid survival scenarios in Northern Russia.
</p>
