<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName archivearticle3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Ecol Evol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Ecol Evol</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="doi">10.1002/(ISSN)2045-7758</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">ECE3</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Ecology and Evolution</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2045-7758</issn><publisher><publisher-name>John Wiley and Sons Inc.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Hoboken</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4930994</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ece3.2204</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">ECE32204</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Original Research</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Weighing the relative potential impacts of climate change and land&#x02010;use change on an endangered bird</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="left-running-head">B. A. Bancroft <italic>et&#x000a0;al</italic>.</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="ece32204-cr-0001" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Bancroft</surname><given-names>Betsy A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="ece32204-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="ece32204-curr-0001">
<sup>3</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="ece32204-cr-0002" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lawler</surname><given-names>Joshua J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="ece32204-aff-0001">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib id="ece32204-cr-0003" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Schumaker</surname><given-names>Nathan H.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="ece32204-aff-0002">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="ece32204-aff-0001"><label><sup>1</sup></label><named-content content-type="organisation-division">School of Environmental and Forest Sciences</named-content><institution>University of Washington</institution><named-content content-type="city">Seattle</named-content><named-content content-type="country-part">Washington</named-content></aff><aff id="ece32204-aff-0002"><label><sup>2</sup></label><named-content content-type="organisation-division">Western Division</named-content><institution>United States Environmental Protection Agency</institution><named-content content-type="city">Corvallis</named-content><named-content content-type="country-part">Oregon</named-content></aff><aff id="ece32204-curr-0001"><label><sup>3</sup></label>Present address: <named-content content-type="organisation-division">Departments of Biology and Environmental Studies</named-content><institution>Gonzaga University</institution><named-content content-type="city">Spokane</named-content><named-content content-type="country-part">Washington</named-content></aff><author-notes><corresp id="correspondenceTo"><label>*</label><bold>Correspondence</bold><break/>
Betsy A. Bancroft, Department of Biology, Gonzaga University,<break/>
502 E. Boone Avenue, Spokane, WA, 99258.<break/>
Tel: 509&#x02010;313&#x02010;5607<break/>
Fax:509&#x02010;313&#x02010;5804<break/>
E&#x02010;mail: <email>bancroft@gonzaga.edu</email><break/></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>08</day><month>6</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>7</month><year>2016</year></pub-date><volume>6</volume><issue>13</issue><issue-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/ece3.2016.6.issue-13</issue-id><fpage>4468</fpage><lpage>4477</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>19</day><month>11</month><year>2015</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>18</day><month>4</month><year>2016</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>04</day><month>5</month><year>2016</year></date></history><permissions><!--<copyright-statement content-type="issue-copyright"> &#x000a9; 2016 Published by John Wiley & Sons Ltd. <copyright-statement>--><copyright-statement content-type="article-copyright">&#x000a9; 2016 The Authors. <italic>Ecology and Evolution</italic> published by John Wiley &#x00026; Sons Ltd.</copyright-statement><license license-type="creativeCommonsBy"><license-p>This is an open access article under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution</ext-link> License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="file:ECE3-6-4468.pdf"/><abstract id="ece32204-abs-0001"><title>Abstract</title><p>Climate change and land&#x02010;use change are projected to be the two greatest drivers of biodiversity loss over the coming century. Land&#x02010;use change has resulted in extensive habitat loss for many species. Likewise, climate change has affected many species resulting in range shifts, changes in phenology, and altered interactions. We used a spatially explicit, individual&#x02010;based model to explore the effects of land&#x02010;use change and climate change on a population of the endangered Red&#x02010;cockaded Woodpecker (<styled-content style="fixed-case">RCW</styled-content>;<italic> Picoides borealis</italic>). We modeled the effects of land&#x02010;use change using multiple scenarios representing different spatial arrangements of new training areas for troops across Fort Benning. We used projected climate&#x02010;driven changes in habitat and changes in reproductive output to explore the potential effects of climate change. We summarized potential changes in habitat based on the output of the dynamic vegetation model <styled-content style="fixed-case">LPJ</styled-content>&#x02010;<styled-content style="fixed-case">GUESS</styled-content>, run for multiple climate change scenarios through the year 2100. We projected potential changes in reproduction based on an empirical relationship between spring precipitation and the mean number of successful fledglings produced per nest attempt. As modeled in our study, climate change had virtually no effect on the <styled-content style="fixed-case">RCW</styled-content> population. Conversely, simulated effects of land&#x02010;use change resulted in the loss of up to 28 breeding pairs by 2100. However, the simulated impacts of development depended on where the development occurred and could be completely avoided if the new training areas were placed in poor&#x02010;quality habitat. Our results demonstrate the flexibility inherent in many systems that allows seemingly incompatible human land uses, such as development, and conservation actions to exist side by side.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author-generated"><kwd id="ece32204-kwd-0001">Development</kwd><kwd id="ece32204-kwd-0002">environmental stress</kwd><kwd id="ece32204-kwd-0003">habitat change</kwd><kwd id="ece32204-kwd-0004">habitat loss</kwd><kwd id="ece32204-kwd-0005">HexSim</kwd><kwd id="ece32204-kwd-0006"><italic>Picoides borealis</italic></kwd><kwd id="ece32204-kwd-0007">population model</kwd><kwd id="ece32204-kwd-0008">precipitation</kwd><kwd id="ece32204-kwd-0009">Red&#x02010;cockaded Woodpecker</kwd><kwd id="ece32204-kwd-0010">spatially explicit individual&#x02010;based model</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>Strategic Environmental Research and Development Program (SERDP)</funding-source><award-id>RC&#x02010;1541</award-id></award-group></funding-group><funding-group><award-group><funding-source>US Environmental Protection Agency</funding-source></award-group></funding-group><counts><page-count count="10"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>source-schema-version-number</meta-name><meta-value>2.0</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>component-id</meta-name><meta-value>ece32204</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>cover-date</meta-name><meta-value>July 2016</meta-value></custom-meta><custom-meta><meta-name>details-of-publishers-convertor</meta-name><meta-value>Converter:WILEY_ML3GV2_TO_NLMPMC version:4.9.1 mode:remove_FC converted:03.07.2016</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec id="ece32204-sec-0001"><title>Introduction</title><p>Climate change and land&#x02010;use change are likely to be two of the most important drivers of environmental change over the coming century (Sala et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0038" ref-type="ref">2000</xref>). The best&#x02010;documented changes in biota in response to climate change are shifts in species distributions and changes in phenology. However, for many animal species, changes in climate are likely to lead to changes in habitat, food availability, and altered predator&#x02013;prey and competitive relationships (Schneider et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0042" ref-type="ref">2007</xref>). Species with specialized habitat requirements, narrow environmental tolerances, specific environmental triggers for phenological events, dependencies on species interactions, and poor dispersal abilities may be more susceptible to climatic changes (Foden et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0019" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>).</p><p>Much of the Earth's surface has already been converted from its natural state for human uses (Kareiva et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">2007</xref>), including the conversion of over 50% of the Earth's land surface for food production (Millenium Ecosystem Assessment <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0030" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>). Habitat loss and fragmentation (driven by land&#x02010;use change) have been the leading causes of species loss and decline over the last century (Wilcove et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0053" ref-type="ref">1998</xref>; Carlson <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0003" ref-type="ref">2000</xref>; Lawler et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0027" ref-type="ref">2002</xref>; Dirzo and Raven <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">2003</xref>; Stuart et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0047" ref-type="ref">2004</xref>). More specifically, habitat loss affects many aspects of biodiversity, including species richness (Findlay and Houlahan <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0018" ref-type="ref">1997</xref>), population abundance and distribution (Schmiegelow and M&#x000f6;nkk&#x000f6;nen <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0041" ref-type="ref">2002</xref>), genetic diversity (Lindsay et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0029" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>), and population growth (Harper et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0022" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>). However, changes in land use can result in habitat destruction or habitat creation, and the effects of land&#x02010;use change can vary by species and by the nature of the change. Thus, habitat loss can reduce the likelihood of population persistence for species with specialized habitat or diet requirements.</p><p>Together, climate change and land&#x02010;use change have the potential to significantly alter ecosystems, communities, and populations. Moreover, these two global changes can interact, resulting in greater alterations and positive feedback (Riordan and Rundel <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0036" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>). At large spatial scales, climate change and land&#x02010;use change have negative effects on species including birds (Barbet&#x02010;Massin et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0001" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>; Kampichler et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0024" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>). Despite these large&#x02010;scale trends, climate change and land&#x02010;use change may influence populations and species differently, such that some populations may be primarily threatened by climate change, while others are more susceptible to land&#x02010;use change. For managers, understanding which threat is preeminent for a given population, in addition to understanding the potential interaction among stressors, is vital to creating successful conservation plans. Here, we explore how both climate change and land&#x02010;use change may influence an endemic, endangered US species.</p><p>The Red&#x02010;cockaded Woodpecker (RCW, <italic>Picoides borealis</italic>) was listed as an endangered species in 1970, largely due to widespread habitat loss (US Fish and Wildlife Service <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0048" ref-type="ref">2003</xref>). RCWs are dependent on mature, open, pine woodlands maintained by frequent fire. These pine ecosystems have suffered widespread declines due to logging for timber and agriculture, coupled with fire suppression (US Fish and Wildlife Service <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0048" ref-type="ref">2003</xref>). The majority of remaining RCW populations are found on federal lands, and consequently, the Red&#x02010;cockaded Woodpecker Recovery Plan identifies national forests and military installations as critical for recovery (US Fish and Wildlife Service <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0048" ref-type="ref">2003</xref>). Although US military installations provide sanctuary for many threatened and endangered species, training of military troops frequently requires intensive alteration of the landscape, often in ways that are not compatible with habitat and foraging needs of the various species living on the installation. Furthermore, these installations will be as susceptible to the impacts of climate change as other parts of the landscape. Climate&#x02010;driven changes in the pine forests of the southeastern USA have the potential to eliminate what remains of suitable RCW habitat (Hansen et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0021" ref-type="ref">2001</xref>). Furthermore, changes in precipitation could alter insect availability or foraging behavior. Thus, this RCW population is likely threatened by both climate change and land&#x02010;use change despite their protected status as a listed species.</p><p>Here, we use a spatially explicit, individual&#x02010;based population model to explore the relative effects of climate change and land&#x02010;use change on the RCW population on Fort Benning, located near Columbus, Georgia, USA. Fort Benning has fewer than 300 RCW clusters &#x02013; RCWs breed in small cooperative groups that use a cluster of cavity trees &#x02013; and is designated as a primary core recovery population (US Fish and Wildlife Service <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0048" ref-type="ref">2003</xref>). The installation's recovery goal is 351 potential breeding pairs across the approximately 74,000&#x02010;ha installation. The installation is dominated by loblolly pine (<italic>Pinus taeda</italic>), but historically was likely dominated by longleaf pine (<italic>P.&#x000a0;palustris</italic>). Forestry practices have varied since the founding of the installation (reviewed in Doresky et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0014" ref-type="ref">2003</xref>); however, current forest management includes prescribed burns on an approximate 3&#x02010;year cycle and planting longleaf pine seedlings. We compare the impacts of multiple spatial arrangements of land&#x02010;use change, climate&#x02010;driven changes in vegetation, and the potential for climate&#x02010;driven changes in reproduction on population dynamics over a 100&#x02010;year period.</p></sec><sec id="ece32204-sec-0002"><title>Methods</title><sec id="ece32204-sec-0003"><title>Habitat model</title><p>We used random forests (Breiman <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0002" ref-type="ref">2001</xref>), an ensemble classification technique, to build predictive models of habitat probability using data on forest composition and structure at Fort Benning, GA (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32204-tbl-0001" ref-type="table-wrap">1</xref>). We divided known presence and absence data into training and test data sets by randomly withholding one&#x02010;third of presences and one&#x02010;third of absences (90 points each) to serve as test data. The remaining data were used to train the models. We used the R statistical package RandomForest to build model predictors. For each model, we built 500 trees using two randomly selected variables of the three total predictor variables as candidates for each split in the tree. This habitat map correctly identified active clusters in the test data 81% of the time and correctly identified absences in the test data 88% of the time. Although including more parameters may have increased the overall accuracy of the habitat map, all parameters in the model could be projected under future conditions. This baseline habitat map was the foundation for all further habitat maps generated under the scenarios described below. This map and all other spatial layers were developed on a grid of 50&#x02010;m&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;50&#x02010;m cells.</p><table-wrap id="ece32204-tbl-0001" xml:lang="en" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Environmental variables used in constructing Red&#x02010;cockaded Woodpecker habitat probability models. Data were derived from forest inventory data collected in 2003 at Fort Benning, Georgia, USA</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><thead valign="top"><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Type</th><th align="char" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Range of values</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average age<xref ref-type="fn" rid="ece32204-note-0002">a</xref> of trees within stand is greater than or equal to 30, or less than 30&#x000a0;years old</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Categorical</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
&#x02265;30<break/>
&#x0003c;30
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Average age<xref ref-type="fn" rid="ece32204-note-0002">a</xref> of trees within stand is greater than or equal to 60, or less than 60&#x000a0;years old</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Categorical</td><td align="char" char="." rowspan="1" colspan="1">
&#x02265;60<break/>
&#x0003c;60
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The functional type of the dominant species in the stand</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Categorical</td><td align="char" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
Conifer<break/>
Hardwood
</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="ece32204-note-0002"><label>a</label><p>Age parameters were adjusted to reflect current age of stands.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap></sec><sec id="ece32204-sec-0004"><title>Simulating land&#x02010;use change</title><p>At military installations such as Fort Benning, land&#x02010;use change occurs primarily through the development of training areas. To simulate land&#x02010;use change, a map of proposed training areas was used as a baseline of future development (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32204-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>A). These areas do not necessarily represent actual development on the installation, but are useful to estimate the land area that might change due to additional training needs. The training areas range in size from 0.02&#x000a0;ha to 1107.98&#x000a0;ha (median: 9.00). The training areas shown in Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32204-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>A were added to the baseline landscape by reducing the habitat quality within each area according to the estimated impact of each development on RCW habitat (M. Barron, pers. comm.). For example, areas designated as buffer zones around firing ranges had less impact (habitat quality reduced by 50%) on habitat than did the large area that was to be clear&#x02010;cut and used for tank training (habitat quality reduced by 90%). Each pixel within each development was multiplied by the value shown in Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32204-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>A, such that a development with a rating of 0.1 would reduce the existing habitat to 10% of the original habitat probability. This new habitat map with the developed areas in place, hereafter &#x0201c;baseline development map&#x0201d; (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32204-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>B), reflects a current plan for base development, and thus, land&#x02010;use change to which the base is already largely committed. We developed three development scenarios that built off of this baseline development map. In these three development scenarios, three or four new areas were developed every 10&#x000a0;years during the 100&#x02010;year simulations. The area of additional development in the scenarios is equal to the area shown in Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32204-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>A, and thus, by the end of the 100&#x000a0;years, the area of new development will be twice that shown in Figure&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32204-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>A (total new development equal to 8.6% of the land area).</p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece32204-fig-0001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>(A) Map of training ranges added to the landscape at Fort Benning. This map formed the baseline range development scenario from which all other range development scenarios were generated. Values indicate the effect of each range on Red&#x02010;cockaded Woodpeckers (RCW). The habitat ratings in the initial habitat probability map were multiplied by the values shown to downgrade habitat quality where new ranges were placed. Lower values indicate a larger negative effect of the range on <styled-content style="fixed-case">RCW</styled-content> habitat. (B) Baseline development habitat map for <styled-content style="fixed-case">RCW</styled-content> using proposed training ranges shown in A. Each range shown in A was placed on the landscape in the location shown in A and habitat within the range was reduced based on estimated impact of the range on Red&#x02010;cockaded Woodpecker habitat quality. Values in the legend represent likelihood of <styled-content style="fixed-case">RCW</styled-content> presence, where higher values indicate higher likelihood of <styled-content style="fixed-case">RCW</styled-content> presence.</p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-3" xlink:href="ECE3-6-4468-g001"/></fig><p>We generated three development scenarios (Conservation, Convenience, and Worst&#x02010;case) with three replicate landscapes for each (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32204-tbl-0002" ref-type="table-wrap">2</xref>). In the Conservation scenario, new developments were placed in poor&#x02010;quality habitat (below 0.57, Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32204-tbl-0002" ref-type="table-wrap">2</xref>). In the Convenience scenario, developments were placed within 400&#x000a0;m of a road. In the Worst&#x02010;case scenarios, developments were all placed within RCW habitat. For each scenario, developments (drawn at random without replacement from the set of development areas depicted in Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32204-fig-0001" ref-type="fig">1</xref>A) were placed randomly within constraints listed above (which varied by scenario, Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32204-tbl-0002" ref-type="table-wrap">2</xref>) and habitat quality was reduced accordingly. Three replicate landscapes were generated for each of the three scenarios with a different random placement of the development areas. Maps were generated for each 10&#x02010;year increment, reflecting that decade's new developments, plus any previous decade's developments so that by year 2090, all new areas were in place on the final map for each scenario. All mapping and scenario building was completed in ArcGIS 9.3.1 (ESRI <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0016" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="ece32204-tbl-0002" xml:lang="en" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 2</label><caption><p>Description of land&#x02010;use change scenarios used to generate alternate future landscapes for Fort Benning, <styled-content style="fixed-case">GA</styled-content>
</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><thead valign="top"><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Scenario class</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Goal</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rules</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Conservation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Minimize land&#x02010;use change in RCW habitat</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">The habitat model was converted into a binary model (habitat/not habitat) using the MaxKappa function in the PresenceAbsence package in R (Freeman and Moisen <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0020" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>). Habitat below the threshold (0.57) was designated as &#x0201c;non&#x02010;RCW habitat&#x0201d; and available for development</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Convenience</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Land&#x02010;use change based on location of roads on the installation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Using ArcMap 9.3 (ESRI <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0016" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>), current roads on Fort Benning were buffered with a 400&#x02010;m buffer. This buffer area was available for development</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Worst&#x02010;case</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Land&#x02010;use change only in RCW habitat</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Habitat above the probability threshold calculated using MaxKappa (as above in Conservation scenarios) was designated as &#x0201c;RCW habitat&#x0201d; and available for development</td></tr></tbody></table><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap></sec><sec id="ece32204-sec-0005"><title>Simulating climate change</title><p>The potential effects of climate change on the RCW population at Fort Benning were assessed in two ways. First, we assessed the effect of future climate change on vegetation using the outputs of an ecosystem model, LPJ&#x02010;GUESS (ver. 030124; Smith et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0046" ref-type="ref">2001</xref>). Vegetation projections were run for nine different future projected climates from three general circulation models (GCMs): CCSM3 (Collins et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0004" ref-type="ref">2006</xref>), CGCM3.1(T47) (Scinocca et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0044" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>), and UKMO&#x02010;HadCM3 (Pope et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0034" ref-type="ref">2000</xref>) run for three emissions scenarios (B1, A1B, and A2 (Nakicenovic et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">2000</xref>) (Shafer et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0045" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>)). LPJ&#x02010;GUESS simulates vegetation in the form of plant functional types, such as broad&#x02010;leaved evergreens or grasses. These plant functional types can be combined to represent major biomes and habitat types (e.g., forest, grassland). LPJ&#x02010;GUESS also simulates changes in the fire regime and response of the vegetation to that change and to increased atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations. Following an 800&#x02010;year spin&#x02010;up period, LPJ&#x02010;GUESS was run for the years 1901&#x02013;2100.</p><p>Second, future climate projections were used to model the potential effects of precipitation on RCW reproduction. Previous work suggested that spring precipitation may influence reproductive output in this species, primarily through reduced foraging activity by adults in heavy rain (Neal et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0032" ref-type="ref">1993</xref>). In the current population, a significant negative relationship between RCW reproductive success (mean fledglings produced per nest attempt) and April precipitation was detected (<italic>R</italic>
<sup>2</sup>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;0.62, <italic>P&#x000a0;</italic>&#x0003c;<italic>&#x000a0;</italic>0.01, <italic>y</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;1.819&#x000a0;&#x02212;&#x000a0;0.0024&#x000a0;&#x000d7;&#x000a0;mean April precipitation). This relationship was used to project the effects of future climate on RCW reproduction. We extracted April precipitation from the nine future climate projections (Shafer et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0045" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>) and mapped those projections for each year. The precipitation projections in these layers were then used to influence reproduction in the population model using the empirical relationship described above.</p></sec><sec id="ece32204-sec-0006"><title>Population simulations in HexSim</title><p>We used the HexSim modeling platform (version 1.4; Schumaker <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0043" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>) to build a population model for simulating the impacts of land&#x02010;use change and climate change on the RCW population at Fort Benning. HexSim is a spatially explicit individual&#x02010;based modeling framework that simulates population dynamics over time given spatial data layers and population parameters. HexSim is a framework in which simulation models are constructed. HexSim itself contains no embedded parameters, equations, or specific processes that must be incorporated into its models. HexSim models are normally designed around available data, with poorly understood processes being left out, represented probabilistically, or explored via sensitivity analysis.</p><p>The population model followed the yearly cycle of events typical for RCWs (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32204-fig-0002" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). HexSim was parameterized using data from the literature (Walters et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0051" ref-type="ref">1988</xref>; Walters <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0050" ref-type="ref">1990</xref>; DeLotelle and Epting <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0010" ref-type="ref">1992</xref>; LaBranche and Walters <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0026" ref-type="ref">1994</xref>; Engstrom and Sanders <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0015" ref-type="ref">1997</xref>; Conner et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0005" ref-type="ref">1999</xref>, <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">2004</xref>; Daniels and Walters <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0009" ref-type="ref">2000</xref>; Doresky et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0013" ref-type="ref">2001</xref>; Leonard et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0028" ref-type="ref">2003</xref>). Although HexSim makes constructing extremely complex models possible, we attempted to build the simplest defensible model that captures the essential aspects of RCW biology. As reproductive output for a population of RCW is limited by the number of females of reproductive age (Conner et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>), we modeled females only. Females are rarely helpers in cooperatively breeding RCW clusters; thus, the helper class was not modeled (Conner et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>). Females without established clusters were modeled as a separate floater class. This floater class moved through the landscape and settled available territories vacated after&#x000a0;the death of the previous female, or areas that were not part of another female's territory. Floaters did not reproduce.</p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece32204-fig-0002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Red&#x02010;cockaded Woodpecker annual cycle as implemented in HexSim. At the beginning of each year, 1&#x000a0;year was added to the age of each individual present in the landscape (&#x0201c;increment age&#x0201d;). All movement routines, survival, and reproductive rates were modeled using the values described in the text and Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32204-tbl-0003" ref-type="table-wrap">3</xref>. In these scenarios, &#x0201c;adults&#x0201d; are individuals surviving the first year.</p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-5" xlink:href="ECE3-6-4468-g002"/></fig><p>We parameterized HexSim to start with 800 RCWs (ages 0&#x02013;14&#x000a0;years) placed randomly in the landscape. This number was selected to be far above the potential carrying capacity of the population to ensure that the simulated woodpeckers had an opportunity to become established throughout the landscape. After a 50&#x02010;year initialization period, the model stabilized at approximately 290 RCW breeding pairs on the landscape in the baseline scenario, which is similar to the current number of RCW pairs present at Fort Benning (~280 breeding pairs).</p><p>The maximum age for any RCW on the landscape was 14&#x000a0;years, which when coupled with the adult survival rate (74% for adults on a territory, 25% for adult floaters), allowed for birds older than 10&#x000a0;years in the landscape, but birds in these older age classes were relatively rare. Fledgling survival was set at 45% (Walters et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0051" ref-type="ref">1988</xref>; Walters <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0050" ref-type="ref">1990</xref>).</p><p>We parameterized the model so that quality of a cluster was based on total habitat quality (sum of all hexagons in the cluster). Target quality for establishing a cluster was set such that the spatial occupancy of the modeled population reflected current spacing and density of RCWs at Fort Benning. Any hexagon with a habitat quality of at least 1% of maximum was eligible for inclusion in RCW home ranges. Thus, RCW home ranges could include areas of low&#x02010;quality habitat, including fragmented areas, provided enough high&#x02010;quality habitat was present to meet the minimum range value. In addition, home ranges in our model can vary in size widely based on quality of available habitat, allowing for higher density in areas of high&#x02010;quality habitat. Any RCW that did not find a home range that met the minimum range quality became a floater without a home range. These floaters would move again in the next yearly cycle to try to establish a home range, following the movement routine (Table&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32204-tbl-0003" ref-type="table-wrap">3</xref>). As young female RCW do not typically stay in their natal territory (Conner et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>), all juvenile birds (fledglings) became floaters in their first year and moved to establish a new home range.</p><table-wrap id="ece32204-tbl-0003" xml:lang="en" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Table 3</label><caption><p>Parameters used to model adult and fledgling Red&#x02010;cockaded Woodpeckers at Fort Benning in HexSim</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/><thead valign="top"><tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000"><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Category</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Parameter</th><th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Reproduction</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Expected rate</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.61 offspring/cluster (range 0&#x02013;6)</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Territory assessment</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Range dynamics</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Improve deficient ranges</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Floater creation</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% Resource target</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Float if cluster resources are &#x0003c;90% of target</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="6" colspan="1">Adult movement</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strategy</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exploration<xref ref-type="fn" rid="ece32204-note-0003">a</xref> then dispersal</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximum number of explorations</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximum explored area</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">500 hexagons, adaptive<xref ref-type="fn" rid="ece32204-note-0004">b</xref>
</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean path lengths for dispersal (log normal distribution, in hexagons)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;5 SD</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Path length bounds</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02013;1000 hexagons</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stopping criteria</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stop dispersal if mean resource quality of 60 is experienced over 100 hexagons</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="6" colspan="1">Fledgling movement</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Strategy</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Exploration then dispersal</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximum number of explorations</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Maximum explored area</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">800 hexagons, adaptive</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Mean path lengths for dispersal (log normal distribution, in hexagons)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">130&#x000a0;+&#x000a0;10 SD</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Path length bounds</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10&#x02013;1000 hexagons</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stopping criteria</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">None</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><fn id="ece32204-note-0003"><label>a</label><p>Exploration simulates an intensive search for resources in a surrounding area.</p></fn><fn id="ece32204-note-0004"><label>b</label><p>Adaptive strategy simulates limited knowledge of surroundings in RCW.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot><permissions><copyright-holder>John Wiley &#x00026; Sons, Ltd</copyright-holder></permissions></table-wrap><p>Yearly spatial RCW population data do not exist for this population, so we were unable to compare modeled and actual population distribution as a method of model evaluation (i.e., hindcasting). We ran the model 20 times for each replicate development scenario (nine different series of landscapes) and climate change scenarios (nine different climate scenarios). The spatial data layers (described above) were incorporated into the simulations at 10&#x02010;year (land&#x02010;use) or 1&#x02010;year (climate) intervals to explore the effects of two factors on the RCW population.</p></sec><sec id="ece32204-sec-0007"><title>Statistical analysis</title><p>Final population size (number of potential breeding pairs) was compared among the scenario classes (<italic>n</italic>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;three per class, 20 replicate simulations per scenario) or climate scenario (<italic>n&#x000a0;</italic>=<italic>&#x000a0;</italic>20 per climate scenario) using analysis of variance (ANOVA), followed by a post hoc test for least significant differences using a Tukey's HSD test. Data were assessed for normality prior to analysis using normal Q&#x02013;Q plots. All analyses were conducted in R version 2.13.0 (R Core Team <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0035" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="ece32204-sec-0008"><title>Results</title><p>The effects of development of new training areas on the RCW population strongly depended on which development scenario was applied (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32204-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>, <italic>P&#x000a0;</italic>&#x0003c;<italic>&#x000a0;</italic>0.001, <italic>F</italic>
<sub>2,8</sub>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;82.8). Under the Conservation scenario, the population was relatively stable over the 100&#x02010;year simulation period (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32204-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>A). Conversely, the population declined slightly under the Convenience scenario (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32204-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>B) and declined strongly under the Worst&#x02010;case scenario (Fig.&#x000a0;<xref rid="ece32204-fig-0003" ref-type="fig">3</xref>C). By the year 2100, the RCW population was on average 26 breeding pairs (9%) smaller in the Worst&#x02010;case scenario than in the Conservation scenario. The final population size was different among the three development scenarios (<italic>P&#x000a0;</italic>&#x0003c;<italic>&#x000a0;</italic>0.05 for all pairwise comparisons).</p><fig fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece32204-fig-0003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Red&#x02010;cockaded Woodpecker (<styled-content style="fixed-case">RCW</styled-content>) population projections under three scenarios and baseline conditions. Lines represent means of 20 replicate model runs plus 1 standard error. (A) Conservation land&#x02010;use scenarios. <styled-content style="fixed-case">RCW</styled-content> population projections are not different from baseline development (no further development) in all Conservation scenarios. (B) Convenience land&#x02010;use scenarios. Population projections are slightly lower than baseline development simulations (no further development) in all Convenience scenarios. (C) Worst&#x02010;case land&#x02010;use scenarios. Population projections are much lower than baseline (no further development) in all Worst&#x02010;case scenarios.</p></caption><graphic id="nlm-graphic-7" xlink:href="ECE3-6-4468-g003"/></fig><p>No changes in the dominant vegetation were projected for Fort Benning under any climate model or emissions scenario. The LPJ&#x02010;GUESS model outputs suggested that the study area would remain suitable for needle&#x02010;leaved evergreen trees, the primary habitat type of RCW. Thus, as we modeled it, climate change had no impact on RCW habitat at Fort Benning. Similarly, our simulations showed little impact of changes in April precipitation on the final number of potential RCW breeding pairs at Fort Benning. Population trends resulting from the simulations using the projected future climates were not different from those resulting from simulations run with a constant (current) climate (<italic>P&#x000a0;</italic>&#x0003e;<italic>&#x000a0;</italic>0.05).</p></sec><sec id="ece32204-sec-0009"><title>Discussion</title><p>Our findings suggest that habitat loss (modeled here through land&#x02010;use change) may be a more important threat to some species than climate change. Similar patterns have been found for birds at a global scale (Jetz et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0023" ref-type="ref">2007</xref>) and several other organisms. For example, a recent study found that high&#x02010;elevation Andean plant species were highly susceptible to human land&#x02010;use change, while climate change in the absence of land&#x02010;use change had a smaller negative effect on these plants (Feeley and Silman <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0017" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>). Similarly, extinction risk for three Mexican cloud forest species was low despite projected climate change when the remaining cloud forest was protected from land&#x02010;use change, largely because dispersal was sufficient to prevent extinction when the landscape was relatively intact (Ponce&#x02010;Reyes et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0033" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>). Thus, RCW, like many other species, may be more susceptible to land&#x02010;use change than climate change.</p><p>Our finding of a strong effect of a reduction of habitat quality for RCW in high&#x02010;quality areas is not particularly surprising, given this species' very specific habitat requirements. RCWs are dependent on mature pine savanna habitat, particularly longleaf pine systems (Walters <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0050" ref-type="ref">1990</xref>). Indeed, declines in this species have been attributed primarily to habitat loss (US Fish and Wildlife Service <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0048" ref-type="ref">2003</xref>). Some evidence suggests that RCW home ranges tend to be smaller when they include high&#x02010;quality habitat (Engstrom and Sanders <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0015" ref-type="ref">1997</xref>; Convery and Walters <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0008" ref-type="ref">2003</xref>). Thus, areas with higher quality habitat could support more RCW clusters. These studies combined with the results of the current study suggest that providing more high&#x02010;quality habitat will help increase the number of RCW on the landscape in areas that are not developed.</p><p>Even in the baseline development scenario, which included only planned developments that have either already occurred or are slated to occur in the near future, the installation did not meet its recovery goal of 351 breeding pairs, suggesting that without additional management, the installation will not meet the recovery goal. Most of this observed population growth on Fort Benning in the past several years was likely driven by successful cavity creation (Doresky et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0014" ref-type="ref">2003</xref>). However, it remains to be seen whether artificial cavity creation can sustain population growth in the face of landscape changes that include new development for training. Indeed, the United States Fish and Wildlife Service issued a Biological Opinion stating that the planned land&#x02010;use changes used as our baseline development scenario would jeopardize RCW recovery (US Fish and Wildlife Service <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0049" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>).</p><p>Climate change had little effect on RCW habitat in our ecosystem models. Although other broad&#x02010;scale studies have projected potential changes for the vegetation of much of the southwestern USA, the vegetation projections that we used showed little change in the general type of forest at Fort Benning over the coming century (Shafer et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0045" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>). While these models give some idea of the basic vegetation types that will dominate an area, they do not provide projections of which plant species will dominate or whether the structure of the forest will change in more subtle ways. Although our models did not indicate a change in forest cover, if climate change results in an increase in the hardwood midstory, RCW may be negatively affected. Presence of hardwood midstory vegetation is associated with cluster abandonment in RCW and low habitat suitability (Conner et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0007" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>). Thus, increases in hardwood midstory would either reduce the habitat suitability for RCW, or require expensive manual removal of hardwoods from RCW habitat.</p><p>Changes in precipitation due to climate change did not result in reduced numbers of potential RCW breeding pairs. This result was surprising given the projected increase in spring precipitation (range: +1% to +27%) for the Fort Benning study area (Shafer et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0045" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>). However, precipitation as high as 300&#x000a0;mm for the month of April did not result in mortality of all fledglings within a cluster, suggesting that although high levels of precipitation may reduce the overall number of fledglings that successfully fledge, each cluster is still able to produce at least one fledgling. Because each cluster is still reproducing, it is possible that the population as a whole is still buffered from years of low reproduction due to the floater class of older but unreproductive females. The results suggest that RCW may be less vulnerable to climate change than other species because of the floater class, which also buffers RCW populations against demographic stochasticity (Walters et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0052" ref-type="ref">2002</xref>). Furthermore, evidence suggests that RCW may respond to changes in climate by laying eggs earlier (Schiegg et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0040" ref-type="ref">2002</xref>), suggesting that RCW may be phenotypically plastic in response to some aspects of climate change.</p><p>Although we did not observe any effects of climate change on RCW as simulated here, it is important to note that our study only addressed two potential ways in which climate change could affect the population. The empirical relationship between April precipitation and reproduction from Ft. Benning that we used in our simulations has been noted elsewhere and it is hypothesized that it is driven by decreases in the number of foraging bouts by adults (Neal et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0032" ref-type="ref">1993</xref>). If the overall increase in precipitation projected for the area reduces the number of foraging bouts such that individual body condition declines, mortality rates in adults or young may increase in addition to the decrease in fecundity that has been observed. There are myriad potential effects that climate change may have on this and other species. For example, climate change may affect the population dynamics of cavity competitors, diseases, and parasites, or the distribution or abundance of nest predators. The interaction among insects and plants may also be influenced by climate change (DeLucia et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>). If insect abundance decreases or the timing of insect population growth (i.e., larval development for many species) changes as a result of climate perturbations, then food availability for animals such as the RCW may be negatively influenced. Furthermore, our models did not include the well&#x02010;documented phenomenon of loblolly pine decline observed at Fort Benning. In a recent study, loblolly decline was related to water stress (Ryu et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0037" ref-type="ref">2013</xref>), suggesting that loblolly pines might be more susceptible to decline under changing climates. Thus, climate change should not be discounted as a threat to this species, and future work should focus on how climate change will influence the entire ecosystem upon which this species depends.</p><p>Our findings suggest that prioritizing habitat conservation may enhance the resilience of many systems to climate change. A recent analysis found that for temperate deciduous forest and warm mixed forest biomes, land conversion due to agriculture and timber expansion is expected to have a much larger effect on biodiversity loss than climate change, while the tundra, savannas, boreal forest, and cool conifer biomes are expected to be more impacted by climate change (Sala et&#x000a0;al. <xref rid="ece32204-bib-0039" ref-type="ref">2005</xref>). Targeting conservation actions by identifying which systems are primarily threatened by each stressor could increase the return on investment for conservation dollars, as land&#x02010;use change could be restricted in those areas highly susceptible to development and those systems where dispersal through intact habitat may counteract the negative effects of climate change, while climate adaptation and management activities could focus on those ecosystems with higher susceptibility to climate perturbations.</p><p>Our results stress the importance of land&#x02010;use change even in the face of large projected shifts in environmental conditions, such as those associated with climate change. Perhaps more importantly, although tempered by the caveats above, this is a positive message. Despite the fact that land&#x02010;use change is a formidable threat that has already caused the extinction of many species, it is a threat for which there are clear solutions. Climate change is a far less manageable challenge, many of the true solutions to which will require coordinated action on a global scale.</p></sec><sec id="ece32204-sec-0011"><title>Conflict of Interest</title><p>None declared.</p></sec></body><back><ack id="ece32204-sec-0010"><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>We would like to thank M. Barron, R. Bancroft, S. Bancroft, A. Bancroft, C. B. Wilsey, J. R. Ramos, S. Shafer, and E. Girvetz for assistance. Funding was provided by the Strategic Environmental Research and Development Program (SERDP), grant RC&#x02010;1541 and the US Environmental Protection Agency. The information in this document has been funded wholly (or in part) by the US Environmental Protection Agency. It has been subjected to review by the National Health and Environmental Effects Research Laboratory's Western Ecology Division and approved for publication. Approval does not signify that the contents reflect the views of the Agency, nor does mention of trade names or commercial products constitute endorsement or recommendation for use.</p></ack><ref-list content-type="cited-references" id="ece32204-bibl-0001"><title>References</title><ref id="ece32204-bib-0001"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32204-cit-0001">
<string-name>
<surname>Barbet&#x02010;Massin</surname>, <given-names>M.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>W.</given-names>
<surname>Thuiller</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>F.</given-names>
<surname>Jiguet</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2012</year>
<article-title>The fate of European breeding birds under climate, land&#x02010;use and dispersal scenarios</article-title>. <source>Glob. Change Biol.</source>
<volume>18</volume>:<fpage>881</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>890</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0002"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32204-cit-0002">
<string-name>
<surname>Breiman</surname>, <given-names>L.</given-names>
</string-name>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Random forests</article-title>. <source>Mach. Learn.</source>
<volume>45</volume>:<fpage>5</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>32</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0003"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32204-cit-0003">
<string-name>
<surname>Carlson</surname>, <given-names>A.</given-names>
</string-name>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>The effect of habitat loss on a deciduous forest specialist species: the White&#x02010;backed Woodpecker (<italic>Dendrocopos leucotos</italic>)</article-title>. <source>For. Ecol. Manage.</source>
<volume>131</volume>:<fpage>215</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>221</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0004"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32204-cit-0004">
<string-name>
<surname>Collins</surname>, <given-names>W. D.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>C. M.</given-names>
<surname>Bitz</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M. L.</given-names>
<surname>Blackmon</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>G. B.</given-names>
<surname>Bonan</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>C. S.</given-names>
<surname>Bretherton</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J. A.</given-names>
<surname>Carton</surname>
</string-name>, et&#x000a0;al. <year>2006</year>
<article-title>The Community Climate System Model Version 3 (CCSM3)</article-title>. <source>J. Clim.</source>
<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>2122</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2143</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0005"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32204-cit-0005">
<string-name>
<surname>Conner</surname>, <given-names>R. N.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>D. C.</given-names>
<surname>Rudolph</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>R. R.</given-names>
<surname>Schaefer</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
<surname>Saenz</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>C. E.</given-names>
<surname>Shackelford</surname>
</string-name>. <year>1999</year>
<article-title>Relationships among red&#x02010;cockaded woodpecker group density, nestling provisioning rates, and habitat</article-title>. <source>Wilson Bull.</source>
<volume>111</volume>:<fpage>494</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>498</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0006"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32204-cit-0006">
<string-name>
<surname>Conner</surname>, <given-names>R. N.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
<surname>Saenz</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>R. R.</given-names>
<surname>Schaefer</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J. R.</given-names>
<surname>McCormick</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>D. C.</given-names>
<surname>Rudolph</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>D. B.</given-names>
<surname>Burt</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2004</year>
<article-title>Group size and nest success in red&#x02010;cockaded woodpeckers in the West Gulf Coastal Plain: helpers make a difference</article-title>. <source>J. Field Ornithol.</source>
<volume>75</volume>:<fpage>74</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>78</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0007"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="ece32204-cit-0007">
<string-name>
<surname>Conner</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>D. C.</given-names>
<surname>Rudolph</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>J. R.</given-names>
<surname>Walters</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2010</year>
<source>The red&#x02010;cockaded woodpecker: surviving in a fire&#x02010;maintained ecosystem</source>. 400&#x000a0;pp. <publisher-name>Univ. of Texas Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Austin, TX, USA</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0008"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="ece32204-cit-0008">
<string-name>
<surname>Convery</surname>, <given-names>K. M.</given-names>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>J. R.</given-names>
<surname>Walters</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2003</year>
<chapter-title>Red&#x02010;cockaded woodpecker home ranges and foraging partitions</chapter-title> Pp. <fpage>526</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>535</lpage>
<italic>in</italic>
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> and <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Daniels</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name></person-group>, eds. <source>Red&#x02010;cockaded woodpecker: road to recovery</source>. <publisher-name>Hancock House</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Blaine, WA, USA</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0009"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32204-cit-0009">
<string-name>
<surname>Daniels</surname>, <given-names>S. J.</given-names>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>J. R.</given-names>
<surname>Walters</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2000</year>
<article-title>Between&#x02010;year breeding dispersal in red&#x02010;cockaded woodpeckers: multiple causes and estimated cost</article-title>. <source>Ecology</source>
<volume>81</volume>:<fpage>2473</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2484</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0010"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32204-cit-0010">
<string-name>
<surname>DeLotelle</surname>, <given-names>R. S.</given-names>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>R. J.</given-names>
<surname>Epting</surname>
</string-name>. <year>1992</year>
<article-title>Reproduction of the red&#x02010;cockaded woodpecker in central Florida</article-title>. <source>Wilson Bull.</source>
<volume>104</volume>:<fpage>285</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>294</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0011"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32204-cit-0011">
<string-name>
<surname>DeLucia</surname>, <given-names>E. H.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>P. D.</given-names>
<surname>Nabity</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J. A.</given-names>
<surname>Zavala</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>M. R.</given-names>
<surname>Berenbaum</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2012</year>
<article-title>Climate change: resetting plant&#x02010;insect interactions</article-title>. <source>Plant Physiol.</source>
<volume>160</volume>:<fpage>1677</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1685</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22972704</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0012"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32204-cit-0012">
<string-name>
<surname>Dirzo</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>P. H.</given-names>
<surname>Raven</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2003</year>
<article-title>Global state of biodiversity and loss</article-title>. <source>Annu. Rev. Environ. Resour.</source>
<volume>28</volume>:<fpage>137</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>167</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0013"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32204-cit-0013">
<string-name>
<surname>Doresky</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>K.</given-names>
<surname>Morgan</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
<surname>Ragsdale</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
<surname>Townsend</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Barron</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>West</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2001</year>
<article-title>Effects of military activity on reproductive success of red&#x02010;cockaded woodpeckers</article-title>. <source>J. Field Ornithol.</source>
<volume>72</volume>:<fpage>305</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>311</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0014"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="ece32204-cit-0014">
<string-name>
<surname>Doresky</surname>, <given-names>J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Barron</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>P. K.</given-names>
<surname>Swiderek</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2003</year>
<chapter-title>Landscape scale restoration and red&#x02010;cockaded woodpecker recovery?</chapter-title> Pp. <fpage>127</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>133</lpage>
<italic>in</italic>
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group> and <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Daniels</surname><given-names>S. J.</given-names></name></person-group>, eds. <source>Red&#x02010;cockaded woodpecker: road to recovery</source>. <publisher-name>Hancock House</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Blaine, WA, USA</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0015"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32204-cit-0015">
<string-name>
<surname>Engstrom</surname>, <given-names>R. T.</given-names>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>F. J.</given-names>
<surname>Sanders</surname>
</string-name>. <year>1997</year>
<article-title>Red&#x02010;cockaded woodpecker foraging ecology in an old&#x02010;growth longleaf pine forest</article-title>. <source>Wilson Bull.</source>
<volume>109</volume>:<fpage>203</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>217</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0016"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="ece32204-cit-0016">
<collab collab-type="authors">ESRI</collab>
. <year>2009</year>
<source>ArcGIS</source>. <publisher-name>ESRI</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Redlands, CA</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0017"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32204-cit-0017">
<string-name>
<surname>Feeley</surname>, <given-names>K. J.</given-names>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>M. R.</given-names>
<surname>Silman</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2010</year>
<article-title>Land&#x02010;use and climate change effects on population size and extinction risk of Andean plants</article-title>. <source>Glob. Change Biol.</source>
<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>3215</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3222</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0018"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32204-cit-0018">
<string-name>
<surname>Findlay</surname>, <given-names>C. S.</given-names>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Houlahan</surname>
</string-name>. <year>1997</year>
<article-title>Anthropogenic correlates of species richness in southeastern Ontario wetlands</article-title>. <source>Conserv. Biol.</source>
<volume>11</volume>:<fpage>1000</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1009</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0019"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="ece32204-cit-0019">
<string-name>
<surname>Foden</surname>, <given-names>W.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
<surname>Mace</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J.&#x02010;C.</given-names>
<surname>Vi&#x000e9;</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Angulo</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Butchart</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>L.</given-names>
<surname>DeVantier</surname>
</string-name>, et&#x000a0;al. <year>2008</year>
<chapter-title>Species susceptibility to climate change impacts</chapter-title> Pp. <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11</lpage>
<italic>in</italic>
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Hilton&#x02010;Taylor</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group>, <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Stuart</surname><given-names>S. N.</given-names></name></person-group> and <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Vi&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>J.&#x02010;C.</given-names></name></person-group>, eds. <source>The 2008 review of the IUCN red list of threatened species</source>. <publisher-name>IUCN</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Gland, Switzerland</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0020"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32204-cit-0020">
<string-name>
<surname>Freeman</surname>, <given-names>E. A.</given-names>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
<surname>Moisen</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2008</year>
<article-title>PresenceAbsence: an R package for presence absence analysis</article-title>. <source>J. Stat. Softw</source>
<volume>23</volume>:<fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>31</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0021"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32204-cit-0021">
<string-name>
<surname>Hansen</surname>, <given-names>A. J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>R. P.</given-names>
<surname>Neilson</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>V. H.</given-names>
<surname>Dale</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>C. H.</given-names>
<surname>Flather</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>L. R.</given-names>
<surname>Iverson</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>D. J.</given-names>
<surname>Currie</surname>
</string-name>, et&#x000a0;al. <year>2001</year>
<article-title>Global change in forests: responses of species, communities, and biomes interactions between climate change and land use are projected to cause large shifts in biodiversity</article-title>. <source>Bioscience</source>
<volume>51</volume>:<fpage>765</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>779</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0022"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32204-cit-0022">
<string-name>
<surname>Harper</surname>, <given-names>E. B.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>T. A. G.</given-names>
<surname>Rittenhouse</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>R. D.</given-names>
<surname>Semlitsch</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2008</year>
<article-title>Demographic consequences of terrestrial habitat loss for pool&#x02010;breeding amphibians: predicting extinction risks associated with inadequate size of buffer zones</article-title>. <source>Conserv. Biol.</source>
<volume>22</volume>:<fpage>1205</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1215</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18717698</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0023"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32204-cit-0023">
<string-name>
<surname>Jetz</surname>, <given-names>W.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>D. S.</given-names>
<surname>Wilcove</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>A. P.</given-names>
<surname>Dobson</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2007</year>
<article-title>Projected impacts of climate and land&#x02010;use change on the global diversity of birds</article-title>. <source>PLoS Biol.</source>
<volume>5</volume>:<fpage>e157</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17550306</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0024"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32204-cit-0024">
<string-name>
<surname>Kampichler</surname>, <given-names>C.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>C. A. M.</given-names>
<surname>van Turnhout</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>V.</given-names>
<surname>Devictor</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>H. P.</given-names>
<surname>van der Jeugd</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2012</year>
<article-title>Large&#x02010;scale changes in community composition: determining land use and climate change signals (ed Siepielski A)</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>7</volume>:<fpage>e35272</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22523579</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0025"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32204-cit-0025">
<string-name>
<surname>Kareiva</surname>, <given-names>P.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Watts</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
<surname>McDonald</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>T.</given-names>
<surname>Boucher</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2007</year>
<article-title>Domesticated nature: shaping landscapes and ecosystems for human welfare</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>316</volume>:<fpage>1866</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1869</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17600209</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0026"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32204-cit-0026">
<string-name>
<surname>LaBranche</surname>, <given-names>M. S.</given-names>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>J. R.</given-names>
<surname>Walters</surname>
</string-name>. <year>1994</year>
<article-title>Patterns of mortality in nests of red&#x02010;cockaded woodpeckers in the sandhills of southcentral North Carolina</article-title>. <source>Wilson Bull.</source>
<volume>106</volume>:<fpage>258</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>271</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0027"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32204-cit-0027">
<string-name>
<surname>Lawler</surname>, <given-names>J. J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S. P.</given-names>
<surname>Campbell</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A. D.</given-names>
<surname>Guerry</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M. B.</given-names>
<surname>Kolozsvary</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>R. J.</given-names>
<surname>O'Connor</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>L. C. N.</given-names>
<surname>Seward</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2002</year>
<article-title>The scope and treatment of threats in endangered species recovery plans</article-title>. <source>Ecol. Appl.</source>
<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>663</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>667</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0028"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="ece32204-cit-0028">
<string-name>
<surname>Leonard</surname>, <given-names>D. L. J.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>R. S.</given-names>
<surname>DeLotelle</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>R. J.</given-names>
<surname>Epting</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2003</year>
<chapter-title>Factors contributing to variation in fledgling production in central Florida red&#x02010;cockaded woodpeckers</chapter-title> Pp. <fpage>593</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>602</lpage>
<italic>in</italic>
<source>Red&#x02010;cockaded woodpecker: road to recovery</source>. <publisher-name>Hancock House</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Blaine, WA, USA</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0029"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32204-cit-0029">
<string-name>
<surname>Lindsay</surname>, <given-names>D. L.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>K. R.</given-names>
<surname>Barr</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>R. F.</given-names>
<surname>Lance</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S. A.</given-names>
<surname>Tweddale</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>T. J.</given-names>
<surname>Hayden</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>P. L.</given-names>
<surname>Leberg</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2008</year>
<article-title>Habitat fragmentation and genetic diversity of an endangered, migratory songbird, the golden&#x02010;cheeked warbler (<italic>Dendroica chrysoparia</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Mol. Ecol.</source>
<volume>17</volume>:<fpage>2122</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2133</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18397218</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0030"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="ece32204-cit-0030">
<collab collab-type="authors">Millenium Ecosystem Assessment</collab>
. <year>2005</year>
<source>Ecosystems and human well&#x02010;being: biodiversity synthesis</source>. <publisher-name>World Resources Institute</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0031"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="ece32204-cit-0031">
<string-name>
<surname>Nakicenovic</surname>, <given-names>N.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Alcamo</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
<surname>Davis</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
<surname>De Vries</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Fenhann</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Gaffin</surname>
</string-name>, et&#x000a0;al. <year>2000</year>
<source>Special report on emissions scenarios</source>. <publisher-name>Cambridge Univ. Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0032"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32204-cit-0032">
<string-name>
<surname>Neal</surname>, <given-names>J. C.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>D. A.</given-names>
<surname>James</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>W. G.</given-names>
<surname>Montague</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>J. E.</given-names>
<surname>Johnson</surname>
</string-name>. <year>1993</year>
<article-title>Effects of weather and helpers on survival of nestling&#x000a0;red&#x02010;cockaded woodpeckers</article-title>. <source>Wilson Bull.</source>
<volume>105</volume>:<fpage>666</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>673</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0033"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32204-cit-0033">
<string-name>
<surname>Ponce&#x02010;Reyes</surname>, <given-names>R.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
<surname>Nicholson</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>P. W. J.</given-names>
<surname>Baxter</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>R. A.</given-names>
<surname>Fuller</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>H.</given-names>
<surname>Possingham</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2013</year>
<article-title>Extinction risk in cloud forest fragments under climate change and habitat loss</article-title>. <source>Divers. Distrib.</source>
<volume>19</volume>:<fpage>518</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>529</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0034"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32204-cit-0034">
<string-name>
<surname>Pope</surname>, <given-names>V. D.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M. L.</given-names>
<surname>Gallani</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>P. R.</given-names>
<surname>Rowntree</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>R. A.</given-names>
<surname>Stratton</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2000</year>
<article-title>The impact of new physical parameterizations in the Hadley Centre climate model: HadAM3</article-title>. <source>Clim. Dyn.</source>
<volume>16</volume>:<fpage>123</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>146</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0035"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="ece32204-cit-0035">
<collab collab-type="authors">R Core Team</collab>
. <year>2011</year>
<source>R: a language and environment for statistical computing</source>. <publisher-name>R Foundation for Statistical Computing</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Vienna, Austria</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0036"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32204-cit-0036">
<string-name>
<surname>Riordan</surname>, <given-names>E. C.</given-names>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>P. W.</given-names>
<surname>Rundel</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2014</year>
<article-title>Land use compounds habitat losses under projected climate change in a threatened California ecosystem (ed Bond&#x02010;Lamberty B)</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>
<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>e86487</fpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24466116</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0037"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32204-cit-0037">
<string-name>
<surname>Ryu</surname>, <given-names>S. R.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>G. G.</given-names>
<surname>Wang</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>J. L.</given-names>
<surname>Walker</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2013</year>
<article-title>Factors influencing loblolly pine stand health in Fort Benning, Georgia, USA</article-title>. <source>For. Sci. Technol.</source>
<volume>9</volume>:<fpage>137</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>146</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0038"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32204-cit-0038">
<string-name>
<surname>Sala</surname>, <given-names>O. E.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>F. S.</given-names>
<surname>Chapin</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J. J.</given-names>
<surname>Armesto</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
<surname>Berlow</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Bloomfield</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>R.</given-names>
<surname>Dirzo</surname>
</string-name>, et&#x000a0;al. <year>2000</year>
<article-title>Global biodiversity scenarios for the year 2100</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>287</volume>:<fpage>1770</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1774</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10710299</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0039"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="ece32204-cit-0039">
<string-name>
<surname>Sala</surname>, <given-names>O. E.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
<surname>van Vuuren</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>H. M.</given-names>
<surname>Pereira</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
<surname>Lodge</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Alder</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
<surname>Cumming</surname>
</string-name>, et&#x000a0;al. <year>2005</year>
<chapter-title>Biodiversity across scenarios</chapter-title> Pp. <fpage>375</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>408</lpage>
<italic>in</italic>
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Carpenter</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name></person-group>, <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Pingali</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name></person-group>, <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Bennet</surname><given-names>E. M.</given-names></name></person-group> and <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Zurek</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>, eds. <source>Ecosystems and human well&#x02010;being: scenarios: findings of the scenarios working group</source> Vol. <volume>2</volume>
<publisher-name>Island Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0040"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32204-cit-0040">
<string-name>
<surname>Schiegg</surname>, <given-names>K.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>G.</given-names>
<surname>Pasinelli</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J. R.</given-names>
<surname>Walters</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>S. J.</given-names>
<surname>Daniels</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2002</year>
<article-title>Inbreeding and experience affect response to climate change by endangered woodpeckers</article-title>. <source>Proc. Biol. Sci.</source>
<volume>269</volume>:<fpage>1153</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1159</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12061959</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0041"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32204-cit-0041">
<string-name>
<surname>Schmiegelow</surname>, <given-names>F. K. A.</given-names>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>M&#x000f6;nkk&#x000f6;nen</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2002</year>
<article-title>Habitat loss and fragmentation in dynamic landscapes: avian perspectives from the boreal forest</article-title>. <source>Ecol. Appl.</source>
<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>375</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>389</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0042"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="ece32204-cit-0042">
<string-name>
<surname>Schneider</surname>, <given-names>S. H.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>S.</given-names>
<surname>Semenov</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Patwardhan</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>I.</given-names>
<surname>Burton</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>C. H. D.</given-names>
<surname>Magadza</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Oppenheimer</surname>
</string-name>, et&#x000a0;al. <year>2007</year>
<chapter-title>Assessing key vulnerabilities and the risk from climate change</chapter-title> Pp. <fpage>779</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>810</lpage>
<italic>in</italic>
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Parry</surname><given-names>M. L.</given-names></name></person-group>, <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Canziani</surname><given-names>O. F.</given-names></name></person-group>, <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Palutikof</surname><given-names>J. P.</given-names></name></person-group>, <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>van der Linden</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name></person-group> and <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Hanson</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name></person-group>, eds. <source>Climate change 2007: impacts, adaptation and vulnerability. Contribution of Working Group II to the Fourth Assessment Report of the Intergovernmental Panel&#x000a0;on Climate Change</source>. <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Cambridge, UK</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0043"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="ece32204-cit-0043">
<string-name>
<surname>Schumaker</surname>, <given-names>N. H.</given-names>
</string-name>. <year>2015</year>
<source>HexSim</source>. <publisher-name>United States Environmental Protection Agency, Environmental Research Laboratory</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Corvallis, OR, USA</publisher-loc> Available at: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.hexsim.net">www.hexsim.net</ext-link>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0044"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32204-cit-0044">
<string-name>
<surname>Scinocca</surname>, <given-names>J. F.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>N. A.</given-names>
<surname>McFarlane</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>M.</given-names>
<surname>Lazare</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Li</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
<surname>Plummer</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2008</year>
<article-title>Technical Note: The CCCma third generation AGCM and its extension into the middle atmosphere</article-title>. <source>Atmos. Chem. Phys.</source>
<volume>8</volume>:<fpage>7055</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7074</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0045"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="ece32204-cit-0045">
<string-name>
<surname>Shafer</surname>, <given-names>S. L.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Atkins</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>B. A.</given-names>
<surname>Bancroft</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>P. J.</given-names>
<surname>Bartlein</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J. J.</given-names>
<surname>Lawler</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>B.</given-names>
<surname>Smith</surname>
</string-name>, et&#x000a0;al. <year>2012</year>
<article-title>Projected climate and vegetation changes and potential biotic effects for Fort Benning, Georgia; Fort Hood, Texas; and Fort Irwin, California</article-title>. <publisher-name>US Geological Survey</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Reston, VA</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0046"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32204-cit-0046">
<string-name>
<surname>Smith</surname>, <given-names>B.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>I. C.</given-names>
<surname>Prentice</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>M. T.</given-names>
<surname>Sykes</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2001</year>
<article-title>Representation of vegetation dynamics in the modelling of terrestrial ecosystems: comparing two contrasting approaches within European climate space</article-title>. <source>Glob. Ecol. Biogeogr.</source>
<volume>10</volume>:<fpage>621</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>637</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0047"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32204-cit-0047">
<string-name>
<surname>Stuart</surname>, <given-names>S. N.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J. S.</given-names>
<surname>Chanson</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>N. A.</given-names>
<surname>Cox</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>B. E.</given-names>
<surname>Young</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A. S. L.</given-names>
<surname>Rodrigues</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>D. L.</given-names>
<surname>Fischman</surname>
</string-name>, et&#x000a0;al. <year>2004</year>
<article-title>Status and trends of amphibian declines and extinctions worldwide</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>306</volume>:<fpage>1783</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1786</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15486254</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0048"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="ece32204-cit-0048">
<collab collab-type="authors">US Fish and Wildlife Service</collab>
. <year>2003</year>
<source>Recovery plan for the red&#x02010;cockaded woodpecker (Picoides borealis): second revision</source>. <publisher-name>United States Fish and Wildlife Service</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Atlanta, GA, USA</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0049"><mixed-citation publication-type="miscellaneous" id="ece32204-cit-0049">
<collab collab-type="authors">US Fish and Wildlife Service</collab>
. <year>2009</year>
<article-title>Biological Opinion on the US Army Maneuver Center of Excellence at Fort Benning, Georgia</article-title>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0050"><mixed-citation publication-type="book" id="ece32204-cit-0050">
<string-name>
<surname>Walters</surname>, <given-names>J. R.</given-names>
</string-name>
<year>1990</year>
<chapter-title>Red&#x02010;cockaded Woodpeckers: a &#x0201c;primitive&#x0201d; cooperative breeder</chapter-title> Pp. <fpage>69</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>99</lpage>
<italic>in</italic>
<person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Stacey</surname><given-names>P. B.</given-names></name></person-group> and <person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Koenig</surname><given-names>W. D.</given-names></name></person-group>, eds. <source>Cooperative breeding in birds: long&#x02010;term studies of ecology and behavior</source>. <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>, <publisher-loc>Cambridge, MA, USA</publisher-loc>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0051"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32204-cit-0051">
<string-name>
<surname>Walters</surname>, <given-names>J. R.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>P. D.</given-names>
<surname>Doerr</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>J. H.</given-names>
<surname>Carter</surname>
</string-name>. <year>1988</year>
<article-title>The cooperative breeding system of the red&#x02010;cockaded woodpecker</article-title>. <source>Ethology</source>
<volume>78</volume>:<fpage>275</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>305</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0052"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32204-cit-0052">
<string-name>
<surname>Walters</surname>, <given-names>J. R.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>L. B.</given-names>
<surname>Crowder</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>J. A.</given-names>
<surname>Priddy</surname>
</string-name>. <year>2002</year>
<article-title>Population viability analysis for red&#x02010;cockaded woodpeckers using an individual&#x02010;based model</article-title>. <source>Ecol. Appl.</source>
<volume>12</volume>:<fpage>249</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>260</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="ece32204-bib-0053"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal" id="ece32204-cit-0053">
<string-name>
<surname>Wilcove</surname>, <given-names>D. S.</given-names>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>D.</given-names>
<surname>Rothstein</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>J.</given-names>
<surname>Dubow</surname>
</string-name>, <string-name>
<given-names>A.</given-names>
<surname>Phillips</surname>
</string-name>, and <string-name>
<given-names>E.</given-names>
<surname>Losos</surname>
</string-name>. <year>1998</year>
<article-title>Quantifying Threats to Imperiled Species in the United States Assessing the relative importance of habitat destruction, alien species, pollution, overexploitation, and disease</article-title>. <source>Bioscience</source>
<volume>48</volume>:<fpage>607</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>615</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>