<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In the context of the Coupled Model Intercomparison Project Phase 3 and 5 (CMIP3 (Meehl et al., 
 <xref rid="B119" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2007</xref>) and CMIP5 (Taylor et al., 
 <xref rid="B186" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>), respectively, a World Climate Research Programme (WCRP, 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wcrp-climate.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.wcrp-climate.org/</ext-link>) standard experimental protocol for studying the output of coupled atmosphere-ocean GCMs, climate variability in West Africa is extensively studied, with promising but still unsatisfying results. Specifically, state-of-the-art climate models in both CMIP3 and CMIP5 exercises show low skill in simulating the observed WAM variability (amplitude, phases, and trends), and sizable uncertainties affect projections in the twenty-first century, ranging from dry to wet conditions in the Sahel (Biasutti, 
 <xref rid="B17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>). Although coupled models generally well reproduce the relationship between the regional atmospheric circulation and the monsoonal precipitation, during both the twentieth and the twenty-first century, the same models show discrepancies in future projections (Biasutti et al., 
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>). Therefore, model shortcomings can be firstly related to the ability in reproducing the large scale mechanisms which influence the regional atmospheric circulation, and especially the teleconnections with the global SST teleconnections (Biasutti et al., 
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>; Rowell, 
 <xref rid="B165" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>). An important source of uncertainty in the modeling of climate change in West Africa is also the model responses to the direct and indirect CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> radiative forcing in the atmosphere: the former rapidly warms the continental surface, inducing a positive response in the WAM precipitation; the latter slowly warms the ocean surface, inducing dry conditions (Giannini, 
 <xref rid="B67" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>). It has been shown that wet and dry model biases over West Africa may be related to an unbalanced model response to the direct and indirect CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> forcing (Gaetani et al., 
 <xref rid="B62" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>). At a regional scale, limitations in the model representation of SST in the Tropical Atlantic (Roehrig et al., 
 <xref rid="B154" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>), surface heat fluxes (Xue et al., 
 <xref rid="B211" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>), vegetation feedback (Kucharski et al., 
 <xref rid="B96" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>), land use (Bamba Sylla et al., 
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>), and mineral dust atmospheric concentration (Tompkins et al., 
 <xref rid="B192" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2005</xref>) are sources of incorrect simulations of the temporal and spatial variability of the WAM precipitation. Finally, the coarse resolution typical of GCMs limits the model ability to simulate the intense and organized convection characterizing the WAM (Vellinga et al., 
 <xref rid="B204" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>). The assessment of model performances is critical to understand the sources of errors and limit uncertainties, but an overall and objective evaluation is a particularly difficult task, because results may differ depending on the specific variable analyzed and the metrics used. In the CMIP5 archive, a discrimination in the model performances for the historical climate may be achieved, but uncertainty in the projections is not reduced when skillful models are selected (Rowell et al., 
 <xref rid="B164" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>). This suggests that the underlying assumption relating the model shortcomings in simulating past, present and future climate in West Africa is incorrect, being the assumption that the same modeled processes lead to errors in the simulation of the historical climate and uncertainty in projected change (Rowell et al., 
 <xref rid="B164" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>). Therefore, further research, based on the understanding of the mechanisms that drive the errors and uncertainty in projected changes, is needed to discriminate model performances.
</p>
