<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In the framework of the Coordinated Regional Climate Downscaling Experiment (CORDEX, 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cordex.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.cordex.org/</ext-link>), a WCRP initiative for the assessment and comparison of RCM skills in diverse regions, CORDEX-Africa provides a set of state-of-the-art simulations and predictions for the West African climate at high resolution (Nikulin et al., 
 <xref rid="B132" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>). The availability of reliable climate simulations at high spatial-temporal resolution is crucial for a robust assessment of climate impacts at regional scale, and the CORDEX-Africa exercise shows encouraging results for West Africa. The dynamical downscaling of GCMs, operated at higher resolution by the RCMs, leads to improvements in the simulation of the atmospheric circulation, temperature and precipitation climatology, as well as the occurrence of wet and dry spells, the frequency of heavy rain events, and the drought geographical distribution (Laprise et al., 
 <xref rid="B97" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>; Bucchignani et al., 
 <xref rid="B22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>; Buontempo et al., 
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>; Diasso and Abiodun, 
 <xref rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>; Dosio et al., 
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>), although the biases in the lateral boundary conditions provided by the driving GCMs may significantly affect the RCMs outputs (Laprise et al., 
 <xref rid="B97" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>; Dosio et al., 
 <xref rid="B48" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>). Being the GCM biases more pronounced over the Tropical Atlantic, the RCM performances are in general better over the Sahel than in the Guinean coast, which is more influenced by the local SST variability (Paxian et al., 
 <xref rid="B142" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>). Uncertainties in the simulation of daily precipitation are also observed, mainly related to the diverse convection schemes utilized in the CORDEX-Africa models (Klutse et al., 
 <xref rid="B91" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>). However, the spread in the individual model performances is substantially improved when the ensemble mean is computed (Klutse et al., 
 <xref rid="B91" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2016</xref>).
</p>
