<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s3d" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.4.</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nestling condition</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The top model to explain variation in nestling condition only included climate variables from the autumn: the frequency of freeze–thaw events and mean temperature. Consistent with both the brood size and nest success models, the frequency of autumn freeze–thaw events was negatively correlated with nestling condition (−0.70 (−1.08–−0.33); 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS181754F4" href="#RSOS181754F4">figure 4</a>
  <span class="italic">a</span>). Mean autumn temperature, however, was positively correlated with nestling condition (0.32 (0.091–0.54); 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS181754F4" href="#RSOS181754F4">figure 4</a>
  <span class="italic">b</span>). As expected, there was evidence for a negative correlation between lay date and nestling condition (−0.47 (−0.77–−0.17); 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS181754F4" href="#RSOS181754F4">figure 4</a>
  <span class="italic">c</span>). Nestling condition was also negatively correlated with brood size, suggesting that lower nestling condition was also associated with a higher number of siblings in the nest (−0.74 (−1.08–−0.41); 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS181754F4" href="#RSOS181754F4">figure 4</a>
  <span class="italic">d</span>). 
  <div id="RSOS181754F4" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 4.</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Climatic and non-climatic predictors of nestling condition in Canada jays. Nestling condition of Canada jays was negatively correlated with the frequency of autumn freeze–thaw events (
     <span class="italic">a</span>), lay date (
     <span class="italic">c</span>) and brood size (
     <span class="italic">d</span>). Nestling condition was positively correlated with mean autumn temperature (
     <span class="italic">b</span>). The shaded area around each line represents a 95% confidence interval. Each line is taken from the top model as determined through model selection using AICc.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="rsos181754-g4" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
