<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2b" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2.</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Reproductive performance</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We considered three metrics of reproductive performance: 
  <div list-type="simple" class="list">
   <div class="list-item">
    <span class="label">(1)</span>
    <p>‘Brood size’: the total number of nestlings in a nest at the time of banding (excluding nests that failed prior to nestlings being banded and measured). We did not use clutch size as a metric of reproductive performance because, logistically, we were unable to access nests multiple times throughout the reproductive period. However, we believe that, for the vast majority of nests, our brood size and clutch size were the same because there were very few cases where we observed additional eggs at the time of banding.</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <span class="label">(2)</span>
    <p>‘Nest success’: whether the first nest attempt of the year had young in the nest at the time they were banded and measured. We acknowledge that this may not be a true representation of fledging success because nestlings were banded and measured halfway through the nestling period. However, for a subset of nests that we monitored after banding, we observed few predation events, which suggests that the presence of nestlings at the time the nest was accessed was a good indicator that they will fledge from the nest.</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <span class="label">(3)</span>
    <p>‘Nestling condition’: mass given body size of a nestling at the time it is banded and measured in the nest (typically ∼ 11 days after hatching). Nestling condition was calculated following Derbyshire 
     <span class="italic">et al</span>. [
     <a rid="RSOS181754C30" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS181754C30">30</a>] by first estimating body size using a principal component analysis (PCA; [
     <a rid="RSOS181754C31" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS181754C31">31</a>,
     <a rid="RSOS181754C32" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS181754C32">32</a>]) on a correlation matrix of tarsus, seventh primary and bill length measurements. This estimate was then regressed against mass using an asymptotic exponential model and residuals from this model were considered to be an estimate of body condition [
     <a rid="RSOS181754C30" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS181754C30">30</a>]. Negative residuals represent individuals that weighed less than expected for a given body size and therefore were assumed to be in below-average condition, while individuals with positive residuals weighed more than expected for a given body size and were assumed to be in above-average condition. We assumed that our condition estimate was a good estimate of body condition at the time of measurement, but have not formally investigated the downstream consequences of our condition estimates on survival. In total, 1263 nestlings from 718 nests were used in the analysis.
    </p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
