<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2e" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.5.</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analysis</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To understand how the frequency of freeze–thaw events and mean temperature during the autumn and pre-breeding periods influenced reproductive performance, we constructed a series of generalized mixed effect models for each response variable (brood size: Poisson distribution; nest success: binomial distribution; nestling condition: Gaussian distribution). All models predicting brood size excluded failed nests (brood size = 0) because we were interested in variation in brood size of nests that had young at the time of banding. For each model series, we considered four climate variables: the frequency of freeze–thaw events during the autumn (Freeze-Autumn), the frequency of freeze–thaw events during the pre-breeding period (Freeze-Pre), mean temperature during the autumn (Temp-Autumn) and mean temperature during the pre-breeding period (Temp-Pre). Each series of models, including the base model without climate variables, included the following fixed effects: supplementation (whether individuals on specific territories were regularly fed by park visitors; see Derbyshire 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. [
  <a rid="RSOS181754C30" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS181754C30">30</a>]), male age, female age and first egg date (the date at which females began incubating). Each fixed effect was included based on previous evidence suggesting that it influences reproductive performance (supplementation [
  <a rid="RSOS181754C30" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS181754C30">30</a>]; male age [
  <a rid="RSOS181754C28" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS181754C28">28</a>]; female age [
  <a rid="RSOS181754C29" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS181754C29">29</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS181754C15" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS181754C15">15</a>]; lay date [
  <a rid="RSOS181754C35" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS181754C35">35</a>]). For the nestling condition model, brood size was also included as a fixed effect. All models also included year and male and female identity as random effects because many individuals bred in multiple years. For each response variable, we constructed models with single climate variables as well as all possible combination of climate variables in addition to the fixed effects in the base model. We also included an interaction between first egg date and freeze–thaw events or temperature because we were interested in examining whether the possible negative effects of these climate variables were stronger for pairs that nested later in the season given that (i) there is evidence that later nesting birds have lower reproductive success [
  <a rid="RSOS181754C28" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS181754C28">28</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS181754C30" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS181754C30">30</a>] and (ii) later nesting birds would retrieve caches that have been stored for longer periods of time to feed their young compared to earlier nesting birds.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Akaike's information criterion corrected for small sample sizes (AICc) was then used to rank competing models [
  <a rid="RSOS181754C36" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS181754C36">36</a>]. All models within ΔAICc ≤ 2 were considered as competing to describe variation in reproductive performance [
  <a rid="RSOS181754C35" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS181754C35">35</a>] and Akaike weights provided the cumulative support for a model given all competing models. All statistical tests and calculations were performed in R v. 3.3.2 [
  <a rid="RSOS181754C37" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS181754C37">37</a>] using the lme4 [
  <a rid="RSOS181754C38" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS181754C38">38</a>] and AICcmodavg [
  <a rid="RSOS181754C39" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS181754C39">39</a>] packages. Visreg [
  <a rid="RSOS181754C40" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS181754C40">40</a>] was used to visualize regression lines and confidence intervals for each regression line were estimated using bootpredictlme4 [
  <a rid="RSOS181754C41" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS181754C41">41</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fixed effects in each model predicting brood size, nest success or nestling condition were not highly correlated (
  <span class="italic">r</span> &lt; 0.3).
 </p>
</sec>
