<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Species perceived as threatened</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Galliformes and raptors were the two groups perceived to be most threatened, both in terms of individual (NMDS) and group-level (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig-4" href="#fig-4">Fig. 4</a>) analyses. Both of these groups are quite sensitive to disturbance (e.g., 
  <a rid="ref-2" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-2">Arlettaz et al., 2007</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-49" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-49">Watson, 2010</a>) and are also often killed either for, respectively, food (grouse, 
  <a rid="ref-50" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-50">Watson &amp; Moss, 2008</a>) or illegal shooting (raptors, 
  <a rid="ref-37" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-37">Pedrini &amp; Sergio, 2001</a>). Historically, it seems likely that raptor populations in the Alps have been limited by persecution, although this threat has declined in recent years (e.g., 
  <a rid="ref-18" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-18">Fasce et al., 2011</a>). Furthermore, large raptors are likely to be relatively vulnerable to collisions with wind turbines (e.g., 
  <a rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-27">Madders &amp; Whitfield, 2006</a>; 
  <a rid="ref-3" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-3">Bellebaum et al., 2013</a>), hence changes in energy generation are considered a threat. Neither 
  <span class="italic">Hunting</span> nor 
  <span class="italic">Energy</span> were perceived as the commonest overall threats, but they clearly were perceived as being very important for particular species groups.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Other species groups (passerines and other non-passerines) had on average much lower threat scores, with many not being considered as threatened by many of the factors considered. In terms of habitat groups, this was also true for generalists (often widespread adaptable species found in small numbers at the limit of their altitudinal range in our study) and forest species. Open habitat species were perceived as the most threatened habitat group overall, although this was largely driven by a relatively small number of raptors and Galliformes. When these were removed, the remaining species (including high altitude specialists such as Alpine Chough 
  <span class="italic">Pyrrhocorax graculus</span> and Alpine Accentor 
  <span class="italic">Prunella collaris</span>) were considered not highly threatened. There were higher scores for species associated with mosaic habitats close to the treeline, such as Red-backed Shrike, Whinchat and Yellowhammer, reflecting perceived threats of land abandonment and grazing intensity (e.g., 
  <a rid="ref-6" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-6">Brambilla, Rubolini &amp; Guidali, 2007</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The experts were requested to rank each species on the basis of likely future impacts using a simple 4-level ranking. Whilst other similar surveys have used far more detailed rankings (e.g., up to 10 levels—
  <a rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-16">Donlan et al., 2010</a>), we adopted a deliberately simple approach in the hope of maximising participation. Whilst the experts showed good levels of consistency in their interpretation of the different ranks, there remain two potential drawbacks with the approach. First, there was no scope for including an unknown category in the scoring system. We cannot therefore discount that a zero rank may have represented an unknown effect rather than no effect, but we still feel that the method identifies the species that are currently considered as priorities.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Second, the approach adopted focussed on perceived negative effects. However, some of the drivers identified may also have positive effects for some species. Both climate change and land abandonment may have positive effects for forest species due to forest expansion (e.g., 
  <a rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-12">Chamberlain et al., 2013</a>). Here, for the most part, forest species had low threat scores, so positive effects in these species do not affect the conclusions concerning the majority of threatened species identified (although it should be noted the 
  <span class="italic">Forestry</span> had relatively low concordance). Similarly, urbanization may benefit some generalist species, but again, these were species with low or zero threat scores and typically generalists more usually associated with lower altitudes. Increased hunting pressure, whilst disproportionately affecting grouse and raptors, may nevertheless have positive effects on some, particularly prey, species. In general, whilst we acknowledge that some positive effects may cancel out or exceed negative effects in some species, such effects are likely to be more relevant to generalist and/or lower altitude species (i.e., forest species)—the key species groups identified as being under threat are unlikely to show any compensatory positive effects from any of the threats considered.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In general, the perception of the level of threat identified in the survey was in accord with the conservation status of the species considered, in that species classified as of conservation concern by BirdLife International had higher 
  <span class="italic">T</span>
  <sub>mean</sub> (see 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="supp-4" href="#supp-4">Table S1</a> for SPEC classifications of the species considered). Therefore in general, the experts were identifying those species of most current concern as having higher levels of perceived threat. There may of course be some effect of prior knowledge of the experts, i.e., they may have been more likely to consider a species as threatened if they knew it was already classified as of conservation interest. Nevertheless, there were also 25 species with no SPEC listing that were identified as facing some threat (i.e., that appeared in 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="table-2" href="#table-2">Table 2</a>). Of particular interest are those species that are not currently classified as SPECs, but which had relatively high threat scores (e.g., Buzzard, Peregrine Falcon, Ptarmigan, Whinchat and Yellowhammer). Whilst some of these species may not be of conservation concern at present, they may be species that should be considered as higher priorities for research and conservation actions before problems arise in the future.
 </p>
</sec>
