<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">
 <bold class="bold">Female movements—</bold>Previous theoretical and empirical studies demonstrated that foragers of a wide spectrum of species usually display movement patterns in accordance with a correlated random walk (CRW) [
 <xref rid="pone.0173797.ref045" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">45</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0173797.ref046" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>] and showed that grey seals movements were consistent with the correlated random walk for 48% of the seals tracked by satellite [
 <xref rid="pone.0173797.ref047" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>]. We compared autocorrelations between angles of simulated trajectories and trajectories obtained by satellite tracking (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0173797.s004" class="xref">S2A Fig</xref>). In each case we found significant positive correlations between angles of successive time steps (0.302 for simulated trajectories and 0.218 for satellite tracking), but no correlation between angles recorded over wider intervals. Moreover, we implemented a pure random walk and preliminary simulations showed that mortality of both females and pups were so high that the results were incompatible with the persistence of populations (data not shown). We therefore retained the CRW as a reasonable assumption, using a constant swimming speed of 2.11 m s
 <sup class="sup">-1</sup> [
 <xref rid="pone.0173797.ref027" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>] when the female moves horizontally. However, horizontal displacements were considered as negligible when the female was fishing (see Fishing or moving section below), resulting in a lower overall average speed within the foraging areas. A correlated random walk allows the female to estimate prey abundance in each of the cells visited and thus to determine whether there is a gradient between two contiguous visited cells. The female then uses this information to make a decision regarding which direction to go (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0173797.s001" class="xref">S1C Text</xref>). At the very beginning of the simulation (
 <italic class="italic">i</italic>.
 <italic class="italic">e</italic>., the first hour of the prenatal period) the direction was chosen randomly, simulating the behavior of a naïve female.
</p>
