<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">These remarks show that broad comparisons of the results of different vulnerability studies are a risky task in the face of the profusion of concepts and complexity surrounding the theme, which favors the proliferation of approaches without methodological and/or conceptual uniqueness [
 <xref rid="pone.0190808.ref009" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0190808.ref102" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">102</xref>]. However, Cannon et al [
 <xref rid="pone.0190808.ref097" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">97</xref>] demonstrated the applicability of a method called the analysis of capacities and vulnerabilities (CVA), which was proposed by a non-governmental institution in 1980. The CVA has since then been absorbed by other methodological approaches, mainly in the Philippines, where it was progressively revised and applied for more than a decade to the theme of disasters. In addition, these authors also showed that although the focus and availability of data in each study using CVA varied greatly, the method was able to assess the vulnerability and capabilities of the populations studied with considerable breadth and depth. Likewise, in Brazil, there are studies applying and improving the same conceptual model of vulnerability proposed, initially, to evaluate the vulnerability of the municipalities of the state of Rio de Janeiro to climate [
 <xref rid="pone.0190808.ref002" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>], to other regions of the country, such as the municipalities of the state of Minas Gerais [
 <xref rid="pone.0190808.ref028" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0190808.ref058" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">58</xref>] and the Paraguay River Basin [
 <xref rid="pone.0190808.ref058" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">58</xref>]. Although several methodologies are available to carry out vulnerability assessments (i.e. qualitative diagnostics, future model simulations, statistical analysis), indicators-based approach have been presenting satisfactory results in evaluating the vulnerability of specific sectors (i.e. agriculture) and populations to climate change [
 <xref rid="pone.0190808.ref071" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">71</xref>]. In a review of 35 vulnerability case studies carried out across the globe at different scales using the indictors-based approach, Sabelli [
 <xref rid="pone.0190808.ref071" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">71</xref>] demonstrated that this kind of evaluation is useful in countries with significantly lack of data, and technical and financial resources to undertake more complex modeling simulations, mainly at small scales, showing the practical application of this approach.
</p>
