<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Throughout this paper, we will use the term ‘provenance’ when referring to the geographic and climatic origin of a population, and the term ‘population’ when referring to the trees grown from seed sampled at the provenance (one population per provenance; McLane 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>., 
 <xref rid="nph14968-bib-0056" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>). A list of definitions for abbreviations used throughout this paper is given in Table 
 <xref rid="nph14968-tbl-0001" ref-type="table" class="xref">1</xref>. We studied 
 <italic class="italic">P. strobus</italic> L. trees from 38 provenances planted in a common garden experiment. Provenances were selected to cover the majority of the species’ range from Canada and the US (Fig. 
 <xref rid="nph14968-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" class="xref">2</xref>; Supporting Information Table 
 <xref rid="nph14968-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S1</xref>) to maximize the representativity of the intraspecific genetic variability. Nadeau 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. (
 <xref rid="nph14968-bib-0058" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>) identified two main genetic groups (southern and northern) probably resulting from separate glacial refugia. Thirty‐six provenances were part of the northern genetic group and two provenances were from the southern group (provenances 12 and 13). Seeds were collected between 1976 and 1986 in natural stands, stored at −18°C, germinated in a glasshouse and cultivated for 3 yr in a tree nursery before their establishment in the common garden experiment at the Valcartier arboretum (Quebec, Canada; 46.94886°N, 71.4962°W) in 1989. The experiment was designed as two randomized complete blocks, with up to 
 <italic class="italic">n</italic> = 16 trees per seedlot and blocks arranged in four‐tree row plots. Spacing between trees was 2.0 × 1.5 m (thinned to 2.0 × 3.0 m after the 2002 growing season) in block 1, and 2.0 × 2.0 m in block 2. On average, three trees (SD = 0.96) per population were sampled in each block. A total of 233 trees were sampled, representing two to ten trees per population (mean = 6.13, SD = 1.51), depending on the population survival rate (Table 
 <xref rid="nph14968-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" class="xref">S1</xref>).
</p>
