<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Regular seasonal weather patterns (i.e. rainfall, temperature and humidity) are closely associated with rotational movement of the Earth around the Sun. We therefore used harmonic mathematical functions to represent annual, biannual, quarterly and three-monthly regular components of variation in incidence. All the variables representing weather conditions were considered for inclusion in the model as anomalies, i.e. departures from expectation for the month in question, again using harmonic mathematical functions to describe their expected patterns of seasonal variation. This use of anomalies, rather than actual values, of weather-related variables enabled us to evaluate the effects of weather conditions independently of other seasonally varying factors with which they would otherwise have been confounded.
 <xref rid="dyy188-B33" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">33</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup class="sup">,</sup>
 <xref rid="dyy188-B34" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">34</sup>
 </xref> Therefore, the purely seasonal effects in the model (sine and cosine terms) can be considered as proxies for seasonally varying 
 <italic class="italic">expected</italic> weather and agricultural patterns, and 
 <italic class="italic">weather anomaly</italic> effects as weather effects that cannot be explained by the purely seasonal pattern. After accounting for the purely seasonal weather pattern, snakebites showed association with maximum ambient relative humidity, but not with rainfall or temperature.
 <xref rid="dyy188-B35" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">35</sup>
 </xref> Monthly average maximum relative humidity showed the lowest coefficient of variation among the meteorological variables and exhibited more pronounced changes over time than either temperature or rainfall. Thus, maximum relative humidity can be considered as a better representative of relevant monthly weather conditions in our study. A positive correlation between rainfall and snakebite has been shown in a number of studies,
 <xref rid="dyy188-B36" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">36–38</sup>
 </xref> but it is possible that these reported correlations could be due to the rainfall acting as a proxy for the combined effects of unmeasured social and environmental factors.
</p>
