<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Snakebite patterns coincide with the agricultural seasons, with high numbers of snakebites observed at the beginning and end of the agricultural seasons corresponding to cultivation and harvesting times. The ‘Maha’ season is the main agricultural season in the country, starting during November–December. This explains the associated high snakebite burden during this time compared with the much lower incidence in the ‘Yala’ season that starts around May, when agricultural activities are largely confined to areas fed with irrigated water. On the other hand, heavy physical farming activities, leading to greater human interaction with the environment, are usually over before the onset of heavy rains during the agricultural seasons and a correspondingly low snakebite incidence can be observed during the mid-seasons. Subsequently, harvesting starts after the heavy rains and high snakebite incidence can again be observed towards the end of farming seasons.
 <xref rid="dyy188-B6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">6</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup class="sup">,</sup>
 <xref rid="dyy188-B7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">7</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup class="sup">,</sup>
 <xref rid="dyy188-B16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">16</sup>
 </xref> Lower relative-humidity levels are expected at the beginning and end of each agricultural season compared with mid-season when rainfall is generally heaviest, and this is reflected in the estimated snakebite pattern during an agricultural season. In 1978, the Accelerated Mahaweli Programme deforested nearly 130 000 hectares of land in the country and settled farming communities in the dry zone. Subsequently, rodents, lizards and other potential snake-prey populations increased near human dwellings, especially during the harvesting seasons, predisposing to snakebites.
 <xref rid="dyy188-B29" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">29</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup class="sup">,</sup>
 <xref rid="dyy188-B41" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">41</sup>
 </xref> Also, outdoor activities take place during the dry warmer months, leading to high snakebite incidence during such months.
 <xref rid="dyy188-B42" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">42</sup>
 </xref>
 <sup class="sup">,</sup>
 <xref rid="dyy188-B43" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">43</sup>
 </xref>
</p>
