<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ack class="ack">
 <title class="title">Acknowledgements</title>
 <p class="p">We thank Graeme Brown (Sydney School of Veterinary Science, University of Sydney), Lee-Anne Kingston (Southside Veterinary Surgery), Jess Wargent (Southside Veterinary Surgery), Paul Matthews (Redlynch Valley Vets), Siobhan Kehoe (Pyramid Veterinary Surgery) as well as veterinarians and veterinary nurses that donated the specimens.</p>
 <sec id="FPar1" class="sec">
  <title class="title">Funding</title>
  <p id="Par34" class="p">This study was supported by the Sydney School of Veterinary Science, University of Sydney, through the internal support for the honours project of NC.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar2" sec-type="data-availability" class="sec">
  <title class="title">Availability of data and materials</title>
  <p id="Par35" class="p">Nucleotide sequence data from this study are available in the GenBank (National Center for Biotechnology Information, NCBI) database under accession numbers MK093987-MK094067. The datasets analysed during the present study are available in the LabArchives repository, 
   <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.25833/ncjt-eh29" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://dx.doi.org/10.25833/ncjt-eh29</ext-link>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar3" class="sec">
  <title class="title">Authors’ contributions</title>
  <p id="Par36" class="p">NC and JŠ participated in the study design. NC performed DNA isolation, performed the conventional PCR, analysed the data and wrote the draft. NC and JŠ edited the manuscript. Both authors read and approved the final manuscript.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar4" class="sec">
  <title class="title">Ethics approval and consent to participate</title>
  <p id="Par37" class="p">Not applicable. Parasites were provided by the veterinary practitioners once removed as part of routine veterinary practice and approval was not applicable.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar5" class="sec">
  <title class="title">Consent for publication</title>
  <p id="Par38" class="p">Not applicable.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar6" sec-type="COI-statement" class="sec">
  <title class="title">Competing interests</title>
  <p id="Par39" class="p">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar7" class="sec">
  <title class="title">Publisher’s Note</title>
  <p id="Par40" class="p">Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p>
 </sec>
</ack>
