<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec013" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Multivariate statistical analysis</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Many distinct mathematical and statistical models have been applied into fisheries data. Among them, the multivariate regression analysis like the Autoregressive Integrated Moving Average (ARIMA) and the General Linear model (GLM) are highly recommended [
  <a rid="pone.0157050.ref046" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0157050.ref046">46</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0157050.ref053" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0157050.ref053">53</a>]. Some authors also employ efficiency models relating fish production with some environmental variables [
  <a rid="pone.0157050.ref054" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0157050.ref054">54</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0157050.ref056" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0157050.ref056">56</a>]. The Redundancy Analysis (RDA) is also a model largely employed in ecological studies to analyse data time series. This method when applyed to fisheries studies empirically assums that the several environmental variables regulate the fishery resources' dinamics as much as the fishery effort do [
  <a rid="pone.0157050.ref045" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0157050.ref045">45</a>]. This kind of analysis assumes a linear behavior for the variables studied allowing that the unkown variables fit into a linear regression model.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For all the variables analysed here, tests for normality were conducted and the data homocedasticity was analysed using the Shapiro-Wilk and Bartlett tests, respectively, accepted for the significant level of p &lt; 0.05. The Analysis of Variance (ANOVA) test was applied aiming to test the variance in the monthly average CPUE according to the taxonomic family of the most abundant fish species in the Lower Amazon region. For the ANOVA, the factors established were the taxonomic families, the fisheries region, the months and the years of the fisheries.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ordination was made for the three fishing grounds studies here (Óbidos, Santarém and Monte Alegre) as well as for their respective fishery environments (river and floodplain lakes) using the Detrended Correspondence Analysis (DCA) of the monthly averaged CPUE [
  <a rid="pone.0157050.ref057" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0157050.ref057">57</a>]. The CPUE values analysed here were logarithmically transformed before proceeding with the analysis [
  <a rid="pone.0157050.ref058" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0157050.ref058">58</a>]. DCA is a statistical tool mainly used to explore the data and show initial relationships in one source of data, although it can also be used to choose between linear or unimodal ordination methods [
  <a rid="pone.0157050.ref059" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0157050.ref059">59</a>]. This analysis made possible to graphically visualize the variation in the associations between our variables.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The relationships between the monthly averaged CPUE related to the taxonomic family and the environmental variables were analyzed using the RDA and the multiple regression. RDA was also employed using a matrix of explanatory variables (environmental variables) to quantify the variation in a matrix of response variables (CPUE), assuming linear relationships between all variables [
  <a rid="pone.0157050.ref060" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0157050.ref060">60</a>]. RDA is a tool that has been extensively used to analyze ecological relationships, e.g. between abundance data and environment variables. Environmental data are used to extract patterns from the explained variation only. RDA was he linear gradient analysis method. The focus scaling was on inter-species correlations and species score was divided by standard deviation. We also applied a fourth root transformation into our species data which were previously normalized and standardized. The forward selection of environment variables was made by manual selection with the best K of 24 variables and using Monte Carlo permutation tests with 9999 unrestrict permutations. The data set was then randomized and each variable was analyzed on its own.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The multiple regression method used here was the Backward Stepwise Method applied to a confidence level of 2 (F Fisher-Snedecor value). The dependent variables were the CPUE while the independent variables were the environmental variables and the market index. The fisheries data were transformed through the fourth root transformation. All regressions significant to p &lt; 0.05 were considered here for future analysis. All the statistical analysis from the ANOVA and the multiple regression tests were made using the STATISTICA7.0
  <span class="sup">®</span> software resulting in several statistical models which relate CPUE with the environmental variables and the market index. When performing the DCA we used the PCORD software run at the Natural Sciences Museum in Madrid, Spain. The RDA was run using the Canoco program for Windows 4.54 [
  <a rid="pone.0157050.ref060" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0157050.ref060">60</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
