<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">
 <italic class="italic">K</italic>- and 
 <italic class="italic">r-</italic>strategies can impact emissions through different investment pathways. 
 <italic class="italic">K</italic>-strategies produce larger energy investments 
 <italic class="italic">per capita</italic>, both within parents and offspring, and high 
 <italic class="italic">per capita</italic> CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> emissions nationally [
 <xref rid="RSOS160470C4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="RSOS160470C50" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>]. By contrast, 
 <italic class="italic">r-</italic>strategies are associated with lower 
 <italic class="italic">per capita</italic> carbon emissions, but greater offspring quantity, increasing an individual's ‘carbon legacy’, defined as the expected future emissions produced by a parent and their surviving offspring. Carbon legacies can have a much larger impact on emissions relative to current investment changes (e.g. buying a hybrid car) [
 <xref rid="RSOS160470C5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>]. Countries associated with 
 <italic class="italic">K</italic>-strategies (i.e. most high-income countries) have substantially larger carbon legacies than those countries exhibiting 
 <italic class="italic">r</italic> strategies (i.e. many low-income countries) [
 <xref rid="RSOS160470C51" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">51</xref>]. A woman in Bangladesh, for example, would need to have 74 children before her carbon legacy equalled that of an American woman with one child (calculated from data in [
 <xref rid="RSOS160470C5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>]). In LHT, these emission disparities can be conceived as the historical products of low risk environments that allow future benefits of increased embodied and parental investments to accrue [
 <xref rid="RSOS160470C9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>]. In particular, the advances in healthcare and sanitation associated with industrialization lower mortality rates [
 <xref rid="RSOS160470C52" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>–
 <xref rid="RSOS160470C54" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>]. Lower mortality rates make it more likely that the increased levels of parental investment associated with other correlates of industrialization, such as access to education, will ultimately result in fitness benefits. It is this positive feedback between industrialization and decreased mortality that favours 
 <italic class="italic">K</italic>-strategies and the inverse relationship between population growth and carbon emissions. Here, we demonstrate that national CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> emissions are positively correlated with components of 
 <italic class="italic">K-</italic>strategies, including increased parental investment levels and future orientation.
</p>
