<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Leishmaniasis, a neglected tropical disease, constitutes a major public health threat to the Moroccan nation (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="ijerph-15-01542-f001" class="xref">Figure 1</xref>). Specifically, it severely impedes economic development by affecting poor rural populations [
 <xref rid="B24-ijerph-15-01542" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>]. The cutaneous forms of the disease represent a major socio-economic constraint among women and children by curtailing, through aesthetic disfigurement, the possibility of normal interpersonal relations, whereas the visceral form, which mainly affects children, is fatal if untreated [
 <xref rid="B25-ijerph-15-01542" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. Over the past decade, the analysis of epidemiological data has highlighted a geographic expansion to previously leishmaniasis-free areas in conjunction with the emergence of new foci in several provinces of Morocco [
 <xref rid="B26-ijerph-15-01542" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>]. In terms of the total number of registered leishmaniases cases, 24,804 cases due to 
 <italic class="italic">L. major</italic> CL, 16,852 cases due to 
 <italic class="italic">L. tropica</italic> CL and 1366 cases caused by 
 <italic class="italic">L. infantum</italic> VL were recorded between 2004 and 2013 in Morocco [
 <xref rid="B16-ijerph-15-01542" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B26-ijerph-15-01542" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>]. For the 1990–1999 period, the Moroccan Ministry of Health reported 10,366 cases of 
 <italic class="italic">L. major</italic> CL, 488 cases of 
 <italic class="italic">L. tropica</italic> CL, and 539 cases of 
 <italic class="italic">L. infantum</italic> VL [
 <xref rid="B27-ijerph-15-01542" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>]. In terms of geographic distribution, a migration of 
 <italic class="italic">L. major</italic> (ZCL) cases from the southeast to the northeast of Morocco was observed. Cases of cutaneous lesions caused by 
 <italic class="italic">L. tropica</italic> (ACL) became more common and overlapped with foci of 
 <italic class="italic">L. infantum</italic> (VL) [
 <xref rid="B28-ijerph-15-01542" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>]. Moreover, and unexpectedly, in Southern Morocco, visceral leishmaniasis caused by 
 <italic class="italic">L. infantum</italic> appeared more frequently [
 <xref rid="B14-ijerph-15-01542" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. In Morocco, malaria was eradicated after 2004. Since then, the Ministry of Health halted the fight against 
 <italic class="italic">Anopheles</italic> (the insect vector of the malaria parasite) via dichloro-diphenyl-trichloroethane (DDT) use. The absence of such previously common DDT use may favor sand fly proliferation; however, climate change should also be suspected of being a driver of disease spread [
 <xref rid="B13-ijerph-15-01542" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-ijerph-15-01542" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>].
</p>
