<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The impact of climate change, particularly changes in temperature, affects the distribution of leishmaniases via sand fly abundance or via the effect of temperature on the parasite development process as its vector has been stressed as early as 2008 [
 <xref rid="B21-ijerph-15-01542" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>]. The Phlebotomine sand fly distribution is limited to areas with temperatures above 15.6 °C for at least three months of the year [
 <xref rid="B30-ijerph-15-01542" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>]. Below 10 °C, sand flies must enter a dormant state to survive winter [
 <xref rid="B31-ijerph-15-01542" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>]. Experimental laboratory data demonstrated that ambient temperature significantly impacts various metabolic and digestive processes that affect the developmental life cycle of sand flies [
 <xref rid="B32-ijerph-15-01542" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>]. Nevertheless, if ambient temperature directly affects sand fly development, its impact on the expansion range in natura is less clear because of the likely influence of the photoperiod on the overwintering diapause that acts as a confounding cofactor [
 <xref rid="B33-ijerph-15-01542" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>]. Bounoua et al., (2013) proposed that the increase in ZCL cases reported is related to an increase in the minimum temperature, which allowed sand fly larvae to survive winters, thereby creating conditions suitable for an endemicity that did not previously exist [
 <xref rid="B13-ijerph-15-01542" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. The impact of climate change on parasite development within its vector has received little attention, although it is demonstrated that 
 <italic class="italic">L. infantum</italic> develops better at higher temperatures in the digestive tract of 
 <italic class="italic">P. ariasi</italic> [
 <xref rid="B34-ijerph-15-01542" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>], and this was further investigated in other 
 <italic class="italic">Leishmania</italic> species [
 <xref rid="B29-ijerph-15-01542" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>]. 
 <italic class="italic">Leishmania</italic> parasites developed faster at higher temperatures only during the early stages of sand fly gut colonization [
 <xref rid="B29-ijerph-15-01542" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>]. If the transmission of 
 <italic class="italic">Leishmania</italic> by sand flies is sensitive to temperature change, many other factors may also play a role in the modulation of its spread. Of these, some are linked to the host (immune, nutritional or genetic status of the host) [
 <xref rid="B35-ijerph-15-01542" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>], the parasite (virulence and drug resistance) [
 <xref rid="B36-ijerph-15-01542" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>], and socio-economical determinants (travel and migration of human populations, urbanization, demographic, lifestyle, and availability of health services) [
 <xref rid="B3-ijerph-15-01542" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="B24-ijerph-15-01542" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B25-ijerph-15-01542" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. Regarding cutaneous leishmaniases, social stigma was shown to reinforce poverty in affected individuals and, thus, is of great concern [
 <xref rid="B25-ijerph-15-01542" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>]. Moreover, there is a continuation of psychological morbidity because lesion visibility is an important risk factor for depression in dermatological conditions [
 <xref rid="B37-ijerph-15-01542" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>]. In Southeast Morocco, women suffer from the long-term stigmatizing effects of inactive CL scarring, creating a feeling of shame, and this suggests that the disease is a large-scale social health problem [
 <xref rid="B24-ijerph-15-01542" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>]. Therefore, this is a real social problem, and women affected need psychological monitoring as well as awareness campaigns. These campaigns are required to explain the global context of disease transmission and its cycle, symptoms, treatment, and prophylaxis.
</p>
