<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The study was carried out in two nature reserves 145 km apart in Central Norway (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0211272.g001" class="xref">Fig 1</xref>), the coastal Tågdalen reserve in Surnadal and the inland Sølendet reserve in Røros (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0211272.s001" class="xref">S1 Table</xref>). Both areas lie at the transition between the middle and northern boreal vegetation zones (zonation according to [
 <xref rid="pone.0211272.ref025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0211272.ref026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>]), and are characterized by a short growing season lasting from late May to late August. The areas are dominated by base-rich bedrocks such as grey-green phyllite, mica schist and greenstone [
 <xref rid="pone.0211272.ref027" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>]. The bedrocks and the moraine yield a base-rich, fine-grained soil that is readily waterlogged, leading to paludification (peat formation). The study areas are dominated by sloping fens (slope &gt; 3°; generally steeper at the oceanic site (up to &gt;20°) than at the continental site) and birch woodland, with rich fens covering large areas [
 <xref rid="pone.0211272.ref007" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0211272.ref011" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>]. Rich fens are peat-forming and with characteristic vegetation dominated by brown mosses (species in Amblystegiaceae and Calliergonaceae), reflecting a supply of base-rich water (pH most often &gt; 6). Poor fens have a lower pH and are dominated by bog mosses (
 <italic class="italic">Sphagnum</italic> species) in the ground layer. The fens analysed consist of carpet and lawn communities of fen expanses, and fen margin communities [
 <xref rid="pone.0211272.ref011" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0211272.ref028" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>]. At both sites, the vegetation is dominated by 
 <italic class="italic">Trichophorum cespitosum</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">M</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">caerulea</italic>, several 
 <italic class="italic">Carex</italic> species, and 
 <italic class="italic">Campylium stellatum</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">Scorpidium cossonii</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Thalictrum alpinum</italic> are also very common. The continental site includes some alpine/continental species, such as 
 <italic class="italic">Equisetum variegatum</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Pedicularis oederi</italic>, whereas lowland/oceanic species such as 
 <italic class="italic">Schoenus ferrugineus</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Narthecium ossifragum</italic> characterise the oceanic site. These rich fens were used for haymaking for centuries until traditional mowing ceased around 1950. Although only one site of each type (continental and oceanic) were compared, these sites are nevertheless representative of fens in those climatic regions, and represent important case study areas for this vegetation type. In the phytosociological classification system of fen vegetation [
 <xref rid="pone.0211272.ref029" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>], the vegetation plots mainly belong to the alliances Caricion atrofusco-saxatilis (upper boreal/alpine/arctic rich fens; Sølendet) and Caricion davallianae (mainly nemoral-lower boreal rich fens; Tågdalen). A few plots may be classified to the alliances Sphagno-Tomentypnion (Sphagnum-brown-moss dominated rich fen) and Stygio-Caricion limosae (boreal carpet rich fen). Further descriptions of the study areas, vegetation types and environmental data is found in [
 <xref rid="pone.0211272.ref007" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0211272.ref011" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0211272.ref025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>].
</p>
