<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fig id="Fig6" class="fig">
 <label class="label">Fig. 6</label>
 <caption class="caption">
  <p class="p">Illustration of sigma dissimilarity for direct probabilistic comparison between anomalies of different dimensionality. 
   <bold class="bold">a</bold> The effect of dimensionality on the probabilities of distances can be visualized using a sample from a standard bivariate normal distribution. In any one dimension, there is a 68% probability that an observation will be within one standard deviation (
   <italic class="italic">z</italic>-score) of the mean. In two dimensions, the probability that an observation will fall within a distance of one from the centroid is reduced to 39%. 
   <bold class="bold">b</bold>–
   <bold class="bold">d</bold> As dimensionality increases, the mean distance to observations increases, and even the observation closest to the mean becomes distant. This effect of dimensionality on the probability density of distances in multivariate normal data is described by the chi distribution (
   <italic class="italic">χ</italic>) with degrees of freedom (
   <italic class="italic">ν</italic>) equaling the dimensionality of the data
   <sup class="sup">
    <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" class="xref">51</xref>
   </sup>. The sigma dissimilarity metric is a re-expression of chi percentiles using the terminology of univariate 
   <italic class="italic">z</italic>-scores; i.e., 1, 2, and 3 sigma (
   <italic class="italic">σ</italic>) for the 68th, 95th, and 99.7th normal percentiles, respectively. The chi distribution in one dimension is a half-normal distribution, and the sigma levels correspond to distance. This result is expected because Mahalanobis distances in one dimension are the absolute values of 
   <italic class="italic">z</italic>-scores. At increasing dimensionality, the sigma levels shift away from the origin. For example, 2
   <italic class="italic">σ</italic> (the 68th percentile) occurs at Mahalanobis distances of 2, 2.5, and 4.0 in one, two, and eight dimensions, respectively. By extending sigma levels into multiple dimensions, sigma dissimilarity serves as a multivariate 
   <italic class="italic">z</italic>-score
  </p>
 </caption>
 <graphic xlink:href="41467_2018_3132_Fig6_HTML" id="d29e932" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</fig>
