<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece32718-sec-0005" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Scoring of tree phenology</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Observations of leaf development for the focal trees were conducted in 2013 and 2014 (March–May). Observations began when leaf buds started to swell and continued at 3‐day intervals until all shoots on the tree had developed small, unfolded leaves (see Hinks et al., 
  <a rid="ece32718-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32718-bib-0021">2015</a>; Wesołowski &amp; Rowiński, 
  <a rid="ece32718-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32718-bib-0061">2006</a>). Developing buds were scored using a key of phenological stages ranging from “dormant buds” to “visible unfurled leaves.” We used a seven‐stage key for oaks developed by Hinks et al. (
  <a rid="ece32718-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32718-bib-0021">2015</a>), where 1 = small dormant buds, 2 = larger, slightly elongated buds, 3 = larger, loosened greenish brown buds, 4 = further elongated buds with leaves starting to erupt (i.e., budburst), 5 = leaves emerging but still tight, 6 = leaves loosening and extending outwards, and 7 = leaves fully emerged and unfurled (see Figure 
  <a rid="ece32718-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#ece32718-fig-0001">1</a>b). We created additional five‐stage keys for each of the other species, where one corresponded to stage 1 on the oak scale (i.e., dormant bud), three corresponded to stage 4 on the oak scale (i.e., budburst), and five corresponded to stage 7 (i.e., leaves fully out). Stage 2 described elongated/swollen buds, and stage 4 described leaves emerging and extending outwards (see keys in supplementary material). These five‐stage keys were used because the five distinct stages could be easily observed for all six species. All scores were then normalized to have a range 0–1 and therefore were comparable across species. For each visit to a tree, a leaf development score was calculated by averaging visual scores for 12 sections of the canopy (three equal‐sized vertical sections, each split into four quarters). Any dead parts of the canopy were omitted from this calculation. All observations over the 2 years were carried out by five observers. The 825 trees were divided into nine “rounds,” which were split between three observers each year. Rounds were allocated so that each observer covered a similar range of habitats and altitudes. Before starting data collection, observers scored multiple trees together to minimize observer differences. They then met once a week throughout the scoring period to score a sample of trees together and compare measures to prevent divergence of scoring techniques. “Observer” was also controlled for in analyses (see below).
 </p>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece32718-fig-0001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Scoring tree phenology: (a) two neighboring oak trees with contrasting leaf budburst timing, (b) seven‐stage phenological key used to score oak bud development, and (c) leaf emergence trajectory for three oak trees in 2014 (symbols show field observations of bud stage, the dashed line indicates the point of budburst of each tree). Leaf emergence stage, ranging from 0 (dormant buds) to 1 (fully emerged leaves, was measured via visual inspection of the buds throughout early spring (see 
    <a rid="ece32718-sec-0002" ref-type="sec" href="#ece32718-sec-0002">Methods</a> section). Budburst date (bb) and development rate (slope of curve at budburst) for the three example trajectories are shown in the figure
   </p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-3" xlink:href="ECE3-7-1135-g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
