<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec012" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Compensation distribution</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The pattern of compensation distribution in the study area does not strongly reflect the stated social goals of the compensation scheme for hilsa conservation, indicating that it is not targeting its resources as effectively as it could be, or that real objectives may differ from stated objectives. Although the DoF claims to target jatka fishers and those who are fully dependent on fishing, living inside sanctuary areas, evidence only weakly supported the jatka claim and was contrary to the fishing dependence claim. For households outside of Chandpur, living in a sanctuary area had a negative influence on compensation distribution–a result which reflects the fact that Chandpur is both a sanctuary area and has the highest compensation coverage of any district. There was some evidence that larger households with a higher level of food insecurity were more likely to receive compensation, which is coherent with the goals of the VGF programme, but support for these effects was weak. Contrary to expectations, involvement in fisher associations had a negative influence on compensation distribution. Yet, this result should be interpreted with caution since fishing households are known to be largely disorganised in south east Bangladesh [
  <a rid="pone.0197809.ref063" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0197809.ref063">63</a>], overall involvement with fisher associations in the study area was low (6%), and there is evidence to suggest that those which do exist are non-functional [
  <a rid="pone.0197809.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0197809.ref033">33</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The lack of clarity in the scheme’s targeting criteria makes it difficult to draw conclusions on actual levels of inclusion or exclusion error. Both the proportions of non-fisher and non-hilsa fisher respondents receiving compensation–and the proportions of respondents who were officially listed as recipients but said that they did not receive compensation–were very low. But if the error rates were to be measured through other factors in line with the rationale of the scheme (fishing dependence, income level, or jatka fishing), their lack of influence in statistical models indicates that the error is much higher. For example, although the scheme is aimed at jatka fishers, a similar proportion of recipients and non-recipients said that they target jatka. There is, however, a risk that strategic bias may be driving responses to some questions. It is possible that many more households did not fish, or did not fish hilsa, but declined to volunteer the information due to their understanding of the scheme. Moreover, eliciting honest answers about sensitive behaviours such as illegal resource use is challenging [
  <a rid="pone.0197809.ref064" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0197809.ref064">64</a>] and so it is possible that bias was introduced by concern about the consequences of admitting to the practice of jatka fishing. In this case though, respondents seemed very willing to volunteer the information, and local knowledge suggests that the proportions of jatka fishers and non-jatka fishers in the sample are representative (BH, personal observation).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">What this study did reveal is a strong spatial pattern in compensation distribution. Households were significantly more or less likely to receive compensation in some districts than others. Households in Chandpur had the greatest probability of receiving compensation, once other variables were taken into account, a result in line with the fact that all households in Chandpur are eligible for compensation. A range of factors might explain this higher coverage: Chandpur is the district where the scheme was first established and it is considered to be an important landing site for hilsa, so receives a great deal of media attention and relatively good monitoring. It is also thought to be the site of the largest riverine nursery ground for hilsa [
  <a rid="pone.0197809.ref026" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0197809.ref026">26</a>], so it could be argued that, by focusing on this district, ecological objectives are prioritised–assuming the scientific basis for this nursery ground is reliable. It is also possible that households in the coastal districts of Bhola and Patuakhali are less likely to receive compensation because they have less political influence. Moreover, within districts, some villages have more organised and more powerful local councils, and thus more influence in the distribution process. Due to the subjectivity of this process, officials are free to use it for political gain, which has anecdotally been linked to the appearance of non-target recipients on compensation lists, or more than one record per recipient [
  <a rid="pone.0197809.ref026" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0197809.ref026">26</a>]. However, the key role of Chandpur in driving the spatial pattern is demonstrated by the reduced importance of fixed effects (particularly district) when Chandpur households were excluded from model runs.
 </p>
</sec>
