<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Almost all risk factors, which have been identified in the literature, have been covered in the presented interviews, when considering the answers of all GPs (see 
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="ijerph-15-00843-t0A2" class="xref">Table A2</xref> in the 
 <xref ref-type="app" rid="app2-ijerph-15-00843" class="xref">Appendix A</xref>). Yet, within the category of pre-existing diseases most GPs focused on cardiovascular disease, while areas such as respiratory disease and diabetes were often neglected. Many studies report that cardiovascular diseases (CVD) in general or specific CVDs, such as coronary heart disease, conduction disorders or congestive heart failure, increase the risk of heat-related mortality [
 <xref rid="B14-ijerph-15-00843" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B56-ijerph-15-00843" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">56</xref>,
 <xref rid="B57-ijerph-15-00843" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>]. Yet there is also some conflicting evidence. For instance, Schifano et al. found that previous hospitalization for cardiovascular disease had a protective effect in heat waves [
 <xref rid="B16-ijerph-15-00843" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. Neuropsychological or mental diseases were consistently found to be a risk factor for heat-related mortality and are even found to pose a greater risk than cardiovascular disease [
 <xref rid="B14-ijerph-15-00843" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-ijerph-15-00843" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. Still, most GPs named cardiovascular risk factors while only a quarter of them mentioned neuropsychological diseases as a risk factor. Also other diseases were hardly mentioned by GPs but have been found to increase heat related mortality. For instance, Zanobetti et al. showed that higher temperature in summer time led to shorter survival time in elderly patients with COPD (chronic obstructive pulmonary disease) and diabetes in a time series study with four cohorts from 135 US cities [
 <xref rid="B57-ijerph-15-00843" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">57</xref>].
</p>
