<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">An earlier model of environmental behavior [
 <xref rid="B14-ijerph-14-01472" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>], which considered three factors of knowledge, awareness (or attitude) and behavior, proposed that increasing an individual’s knowledge about environment leads to a change in attitudes, increases the level of awareness and changes the person’s behaviors. Ajzen’s [
 <xref rid="B15-ijerph-14-01472" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>] theory of planned behavior (TPB) explains behavioral intentions using three factors: attitude, subjective norms and perceived behavioral control; this theory suggests that an individual’s prior attitudes towards GCC influence how much the person attempts to change related attitudes and beliefs [
 <xref rid="B4-ijerph-14-01472" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-ijerph-14-01472" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-ijerph-14-01472" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. One demonstrable method of influencing pro-environmental behaviors is a norms-based intervention. Norms may influence the behavioral intention of undergraduate students, particularly with regard to highly valued behaviors. Thus, according to the TPB, individuals holding positive attitudes toward pro-environmental activism have normative support for pro-environment behavioral intentions. Shove [
 <xref rid="B18-ijerph-14-01472" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>] asserted that the ABC paradigm (attitude, behavior and choice) within the TPB may be useful in explaining the role of attitudes and other relationships of GCC-related behaviors of students. Shove [
 <xref rid="B18-ijerph-14-01472" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>] also examined the extent to which environmental beliefs can be used to help encourage support for action against climate change. Ajzen [
 <xref rid="B15-ijerph-14-01472" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B19-ijerph-14-01472" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>] demonstrated that behaviors are manifestations of the values and final attitudes of individuals. Mancha and Yoder [
 <xref rid="B20-ijerph-14-01472" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>] reported on antecedent beliefs and their related behavioral intentions.
</p>
