<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Most studies [
 <xref rid="B28-ijerph-14-01472" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>,
 <xref rid="B29-ijerph-14-01472" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>,
 <xref rid="B30-ijerph-14-01472" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>] of pro-environmental behavior that use VBN theory have found a positive relationship between the degree of environmental concern and willingness to enact pro-environment attitude. Inherent to the idea of environmental concern is the recognition of people in relation to nature and of the reciprocal threats of environmental deterioration and ecological catastrophe. People who are concerned both for the welfare of others and for biospheric values tend to engage in pro-environmental attitudes because they believe that protecting the environment is the right thing to do [
 <xref rid="B24-ijerph-14-01472" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>,
 <xref rid="B31-ijerph-14-01472" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">31</xref>,
 <xref rid="B32-ijerph-14-01472" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">32</xref>]. Empirical evidence validates the claim that environmental value and environmental concern have significant influences on explaining specific beliefs and behaviors and may, therefore, be predictors for various variables, such as pro-environmental attitude. Sustainability values could be depicted using three core values-economics, society and environment [
 <xref rid="B33-ijerph-14-01472" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">33</xref>]. The economic value pertained to materialism [
 <xref rid="B34-ijerph-14-01472" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">34</xref>], the environmental value pertained to environmentalism and the social value pertained to equity [
 <xref rid="B35-ijerph-14-01472" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>]. The equity value stated to how actions of adaptation strategies affect social welfare and surrounding communities [
 <xref rid="B35-ijerph-14-01472" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">35</xref>]. As respondents in this study are undergraduate students and therefore they lack a clear and deep understanding of equity, this latent variable was not measured in this study. Sustainability value in this study was hence composed of environmentalism and materialism. Therefore, the following hypotheses were made: 
 <statement class="statement">
  <label class="label">
   <bold class="bold">Hypothesis</bold> 
   <bold class="bold">1.</bold>
  </label>
  <p class="p">
   <italic class="italic">An individual’s sustainability value is positively related to pro-environmental attitude.</italic>
  </p>
 </statement>
 <statement class="statement">
  <label class="label">
   <bold class="bold">Hypothesis</bold> 
   <bold class="bold">2.</bold>
  </label>
  <p class="p">
   <italic class="italic">An individual’s social norms are positively related to their pro-environmental attitude.</italic>
  </p>
 </statement>
 <statement class="statement">
  <label class="label">
   <bold class="bold">Hypothesis</bold> 
   <bold class="bold">3.</bold>
  </label>
  <p class="p">
   <italic class="italic">An individual’s environmental concerns are positively related to their pro-environmental attitude.</italic>
  </p>
 </statement>
</p>
