<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par6" class="p">One technique suggested for monitoring the lowest altitudes of the D-region, but not undertaken until now, is the analysis of very low frequency (VLF) radio wave propagation over very long distances
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">9</xref>
 </sup>. The advantage of the VLF technique over many of the others comes about because of the long distance integration of the measurement compared to relatively small-scale coverage by rocket, optical cameras, and higher frequency radio wave observations. A technique has been identified
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" class="xref">20</xref>
 </sup> of investigating the characteristics of the nighttime D-region using the timing of abrupt decreases in signal amplitude (‘fading’) of man-made transmitter signals caused by mode conversion
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">21</xref>
 </sup> associated with the passage of the sunrise terminator
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" class="xref">22</xref>
 </sup>. The timing of each amplitude fade is related to the specific location in the upper altitudes of the Earth-ionosphere waveguide (60–80 km) where destructive interference takes place, producing a modal minima
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">23</xref>
 </sup>. The positions of these modal minima locations are determined by the underlying nighttime electron density profile characteristics of the D-region, typically for reflecting electron number densities of &lt;300 el/cm
 <sup class="sup">3</sup> (75–85 km at night
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">24</xref>
 </sup>). The advantage of investigating long-term trends in the nighttime D-region comes from the lack of the direct influence of solar EUV on the behavior of the electron density profile, thereby increasing the sensitivity of the analysis to any anthropogenic changes. In this study we develop the amplitude ‘fading’ technique, and use it to compensate for many of the instrumental/experimental factors that can make long-term comparisons so problematic.
</p>
