<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In veterinary parasitology, the work of Ollerenshaw and Rollands on 
 <italic class="italic">Fasciola hepatica</italic>, the sheep liver fluke, in Wales is a prime example of the impact of weather and climate on the dynamics of parasitic worms. The parasite develops on wet grassland, and then infects an intermediate snail host, before being ingested by a ruminant. 
 <italic class="italic">F. hepatica</italic> then migrates to the bile duct and liver of the host, before releasing eggs which are excreted by the animal onto pasture. The free‐living stages of the parasite and the snails themselves are favored by wet and mild/warm climatic conditions on grassland.
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0172" ref-type="ref" class="xref">172</xref> Transmission of the parasite in most countries is seasonal; it takes approximately three months for parasite stages to develop from eggs and for the release of infective metacercariae onto pasture to occur via the intermediate snail host.
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0172" ref-type="ref" class="xref">172</xref> Liver fluke causes severe morbidity in sheep, reduced milk yield in dairy cattle, reduced growth rates, and liver condemnation; consequently, it has large cost implications for the farming industry. Ollerenshaw and Rollands developed an empirical model to forecast the risk of acute fluke infections in sheep during the late 1950s. This model relies on the frequency of rainy days, evapotranspiration, and temperature from spring to early fall to forecast acute disease burden in sheep the following winter; the model takes advantage of the time lag associated with the life cycle of the parasite. The model was able to successfully forecast epidemics of liver fluke in sheep in Anglesey, Wales in the late 1950s. The model is now used operationally by the National Animal Disease Information Service to provide regional risk forecasts to UK farmers.
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0173" ref-type="ref" class="xref">173</xref> Other spatial risk models based on evapotranspiration data from satellite have been subsequently developed to model the risk posed by liver fluke.
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0174" ref-type="ref" class="xref">174</xref>
</p>
