<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Kutz and others have extensively studied the ecology of host–parasite interactions in the Arctic environment.
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0184" ref-type="ref" class="xref">184</xref>, 
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0185" ref-type="ref" class="xref">185</xref>, 
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0186" ref-type="ref" class="xref">186</xref>, 
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0187" ref-type="ref" class="xref">187</xref> The Artic provides interesting insights into potential changes in future host–parasite systems. Helminth parasites (the lungworm 
 <italic class="italic">Umingmakstrongylus pallikuukensis</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">Varestrongylus eleguneniensis</italic>) affecting muskoxen and caribou and their gastropod intermediate hosts have rapidly extended their range at high latitudes in the central Canadian Arctic. These parasites were found in the late 2000s on Victoria Island. Their spread perfectly coincided with accelerated warming across the region. Cool climatic conditions before the 2000s may have restricted establishment of lungworms and intermediate hosts on the island. The spread of these parasites by migratory caribou is very likely, and this was further facilitated by rapidly changing environmental conditions. This is also consistent with faster warming occurring at high latitudes and altitudes; unfortunately, climate models show that similar trends are likely in future. Furthermore, muskoxen were severely hit by the direct impacts of climate change on their environment in 2018.
 <xref rid="nyas13950-bib-0202" ref-type="ref" class="xref">202</xref> Rising temperatures now favor rainfall instead of snowfall at high latitudes. Once rainfall reaches the surface, it rapidly freezes, encasing the plants in ice and making them inaccessible to the animals that feed on them. Similar trends have been reported in the Southern Hemisphere, in East Antarctica, where a colony of about 40,000 Adélie penguins died from starvation in 2017. More recently, in 2016, an outbreak of anthrax, a bacteria present in soil, affected reindeer en masse in Siberia. Anthrax spores can survive in frozen animal and human cadavers for hundreds of years. Following the 2016 reindeer outbreak, 72 nomadic herders, including 41 children, were hospitalized due to subsequent infection by the bacteria, also known as Siberian plague; one child died. Experts related this catastrophic event to unusually warm weather conditions; the Russian authorities subsequently culled the reindeer population to limit further spread of anthrax.
</p>
