<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Current and future distribution of common reed germination grounds</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The grid used for modeling reduced the level of accuracy in assessing areas that were (or were likely to be) invaded, because common reed stands in the field were generally smaller than the polygons in which they were found. However, the model made no distinction between a polygon containing a small common reed stand and one completely covered. Therefore, when the model grid was applied to predict the current (2010) field situation, the surface area of common reed stands was inevitably overestimated. As such, due to the modeling scale used, common reed stands in 2010 were predicted to occupy 49 ha in Lake St. Louis (when in fact there were only 38 ha), 262 ha in the Boucherville Islands (vs. 86 ha), 100 ha in the Contrecœur Islands (vs. 34 ha), and 135 ha in Lake St. Pierre (vs. 52 ha), respectively.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In all sectors, germination ground maps (Fig. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">2</a>) indicate that the common reed has probably not yet invaded all sites favorable to its establishment by seed. For example, in the Boucherville Islands, for the 1980–2009 period, 648 ha of wetlands having suitable conditions for the germination and survival of common reed seedlings was not yet invaded. In the other sectors and for the same period, surface areas not yet invaded totaled 1270 ha in Lake St. Louis, 1068 ha in Contrecœur Islands, and 13,118 ha in Lake St. Pierre, respectively. In other words, even though 29% (262 ha invaded out of a possible 910 ha) of suitable areas were already invaded in the Boucherville Islands, this proportion was much lower in Lake St. Louis (4%), the Contrecœur Islands (9%), and Lake St. Pierre (1%).
 </p>
 <div id="fig02" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Spatial distribution of common reed (
    <span class="italic">Phragmites australis</span>) stands identified in four St. Lawrence River sectors by remote sensing images (2010) and modeled spatial distribution of germination grounds suitable for the species that have not yet been invaded. Germination grounds vulnerable to a common reed invasion are cumulated for the 1980–2009 period.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="ece30005-3421-f2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The method used for modeling the distribution of germination grounds of the common reed under future climate conditions also resulted in a loss of accuracy. For most years (86%), results produced with the COMP hydrologic series were less accurate than those from the MEAS series, all of which were obtained using quarter-monthly time steps. Differences between the COMP and MEAS series ranged from 3% to 35% for a given year; COMP values for total area of wetlands suitable for common reed germination and seedling survival were in almost all cases below MEAS values.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the St. Lawrence River section between Lake St. Louis and Lake St. Pierre, hydrologic and temperature changes, associated with the two selected climate change scenarios, increased the surface area for the establishment of the common reed in wetlands (Table 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="tbl2" href="#tbl2">2</a>). Under climate conditions associated with the WAWE (wetter) and WADR (drier) scenarios, germination grounds covered 23% more surface area than those modeled with the COMP (reference) data (1961–1989). The difference was particularly high in Lake St. Louis (up to 50% increase) and in the Contrecœur Islands (up to 41%). There was little difference between the results of the WAWE scenario and those of the WADR scenario, except in Lake St. Louis, where the WADR scenario predicted greater surface areas. Under climate change conditions, sites conducive to common reed seed germination and seedling survival were found on a much larger portion of the floodplain and extended further from the bank toward the centre of the river (Fig. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">3</a>). In Lake St. Louis, new sites were present in the lake centre. In Lake St. Pierre, the formation of new common reed stands, extending from the lake banks to its centre, was especially notable.
 </p>
 <div id="tbl2" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Table 2</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Total wetland area potentially suitable for the establishment of the common reed (
    <span class="italic">Phragmites australis</span>) through sexual reproduction in four sectors of the St. Lawrence River as estimated by an ecohydrological model and for three climate scenarios (COMP: present-day climate 1961–1989; WAWE: warmer and wetter climate predicted for 2040–2069; WADR: warmer and drier climate predicted for 2040–2069). The area potentially conducive to common reed establishment by seed is cumulated for the time period considered.
   </p>
  </div>
  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
   <thead>
    <tr>
     <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
     <th align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Total wetland area suitable for common reed establishment (ha)
      <span class="hr"/>
     </th>
     <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
     <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sector</th>
     <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">COMP</th>
     <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WAWE</th>
     <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WADR</th>
     <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Difference WAWE versus COMP (%)</th>
     <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Difference WADR versus COMP (%)</th>
    </tr>
   </thead>
   <tbody>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lake St. Louis</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1486</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1944</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2228</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+31</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+50</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Boucherville Islands</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">963</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1113</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1098</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+16</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+14</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Contrecœur Islands</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1014</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1432</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1400</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+41</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+38</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lake St. Pierre</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13,935</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16,876</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16,660</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+21</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+20</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All sectors</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18,560</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22,879</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22,911</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+23</td>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+23</td>
    </tr>
   </tbody>
  </table>
 </div>
 <div id="fig03" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Spatial distribution of common reed (
    <span class="italic">Phragmites australis</span>) stands identified in four St. Lawrence River sectors by remote sensing images (2010) and modeled spatial distribution of germination grounds suitable for the species that have not yet been invaded, for three climate scenarios (COMP: the present-day climate 1961–1989; WAWE: warmer and wetter climate predicted for 2040–2069; WADR: warmer and drier climate predicted for 2040–2069). Germination grounds vulnerable to a common reed invasion are cumulated for the time period considered.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="ece30005-3421-f3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
