<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="results" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results</div>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Distribution of common reed stands</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In 2010, common reed stands covered 212 ha in the entire study area, as revealed by the satellite images. Common reed covered 40 ha in Lake St. Louis, 86 ha in the Boucherville Islands (by far the most invaded sector), 34 ha in the Contrecœur Islands, and 52 ha in Lake St. Pierre, respectively. Mean common reed stand size was 14 m
   <span class="sup">2</span> for the entire study area. In the Lake St. Pierre sector, it was only 3 m
   <span class="sup">2</span>, near the spatial resolution limit of pixels from the satellite images used. In Lake St. Pierre, 41% of common reed stands were small (≤10 m
   <span class="sup">2</span>), while in the other sectors, they were larger and in most cases ≥50 m
   <span class="sup">2</span> (69% of reed stands in the Boucherville and Contrecœur Islands, and 57% in Lake St. Louis, respectively). Field mapping validation showed an increase in interpretation accuracy with common reed stand size. Small stands (≤10 m
   <span class="sup">2</span>) had a greater margin of error (21% were incorrectly identified) than medium (11–50 m
   <span class="sup">2</span>; 6%) and large (≥51 m
   <span class="sup">2</span>; 4%) stands. Overall, for all sectors and common reed stand sizes combined, the species identification at the stand level was correct in 88% of the cases. Reed canary grass and cattails (
   <span class="italic">Typha</span> spp.) were the other plant species involved in identification errors.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Common reed model parameters and performance</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The model which identified, on an annual basis, polygons from the IERM grid with potential for common reed seed germination and seedling survival, performed best using three parameters, that is, (1) temperature; (2) water level; and (3) wetland class. However, it is important to note that water level had a much greater influence on the model performance than the two other parameters combined. Removing these two parameters had virtually no impact on the model performance (0.05% decline in overall rate of correct classification). Nevertheless, because the three parameters collectively improved the model, they were all retained.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Comparing the actual distribution of common reed stands from 1980 to 2009 in the Boucherville Islands with the distribution of germination grounds produced using the model for the same period gave a correct (i.e., a stand occurred in a germination ground) classification rate of 57% (Table 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="tbl1" href="#tbl1">1</a>). The model sensitivity was 87%, while its specificity was only 49%. The best overall performance for the entire study area was in Lake St. Louis (65%). For all sectors, the model sensitivity clearly outperformed its specificity; for example, sensitivity reached 97% in the Contrecœur Islands, compared to 49% for specificity.
  </p>
  <div id="tbl1" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Table 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Performance of the common reed (
     <span class="italic">Phragmites australis</span>) model that was developed to simulate the distribution of germination grounds of the species in wetlands in four sectors of the St. Lawrence River. Numbers are the proportion of polygons for which there is a match between the simulation of the model (presence of a germination ground) and the actual distribution of the common reed stands.
    </p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sector</th>
      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sensitivity (%)</th>
      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Specificity (%)</th>
      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rate of correct classification (%)</th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lake St. Louis</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">65</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Boucherville Islands</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Contrecœur Islands</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lake St. Pierre</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Approximately 62% of the polygons identified as germination grounds for the common reed in the Boucherville Islands, but containing no reed (according to the analysis of satellite images taken in 2010) and visited for validation purposes in 2012, contained at least one new reed stand. These new stands were generally small with only a few stems not connected to nearby stands; as a result, they were not detected on the 2010 satellite images, either due to their small size or because they were initiated in 2011 or 2012. The model performance increased considerably once these new small stands were included: The rate of correct classification for the validated subsector of the Boucherville Islands increased from 59% to 75%.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Current and future distribution of common reed germination grounds</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The grid used for modeling reduced the level of accuracy in assessing areas that were (or were likely to be) invaded, because common reed stands in the field were generally smaller than the polygons in which they were found. However, the model made no distinction between a polygon containing a small common reed stand and one completely covered. Therefore, when the model grid was applied to predict the current (2010) field situation, the surface area of common reed stands was inevitably overestimated. As such, due to the modeling scale used, common reed stands in 2010 were predicted to occupy 49 ha in Lake St. Louis (when in fact there were only 38 ha), 262 ha in the Boucherville Islands (vs. 86 ha), 100 ha in the Contrecœur Islands (vs. 34 ha), and 135 ha in Lake St. Pierre (vs. 52 ha), respectively.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In all sectors, germination ground maps (Fig. 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">2</a>) indicate that the common reed has probably not yet invaded all sites favorable to its establishment by seed. For example, in the Boucherville Islands, for the 1980–2009 period, 648 ha of wetlands having suitable conditions for the germination and survival of common reed seedlings was not yet invaded. In the other sectors and for the same period, surface areas not yet invaded totaled 1270 ha in Lake St. Louis, 1068 ha in Contrecœur Islands, and 13,118 ha in Lake St. Pierre, respectively. In other words, even though 29% (262 ha invaded out of a possible 910 ha) of suitable areas were already invaded in the Boucherville Islands, this proportion was much lower in Lake St. Louis (4%), the Contrecœur Islands (9%), and Lake St. Pierre (1%).
  </p>
  <div id="fig02" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Spatial distribution of common reed (
     <span class="italic">Phragmites australis</span>) stands identified in four St. Lawrence River sectors by remote sensing images (2010) and modeled spatial distribution of germination grounds suitable for the species that have not yet been invaded. Germination grounds vulnerable to a common reed invasion are cumulated for the 1980–2009 period.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="ece30005-3421-f2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The method used for modeling the distribution of germination grounds of the common reed under future climate conditions also resulted in a loss of accuracy. For most years (86%), results produced with the COMP hydrologic series were less accurate than those from the MEAS series, all of which were obtained using quarter-monthly time steps. Differences between the COMP and MEAS series ranged from 3% to 35% for a given year; COMP values for total area of wetlands suitable for common reed germination and seedling survival were in almost all cases below MEAS values.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For the St. Lawrence River section between Lake St. Louis and Lake St. Pierre, hydrologic and temperature changes, associated with the two selected climate change scenarios, increased the surface area for the establishment of the common reed in wetlands (Table 
   <a ref-type="table" rid="tbl2" href="#tbl2">2</a>). Under climate conditions associated with the WAWE (wetter) and WADR (drier) scenarios, germination grounds covered 23% more surface area than those modeled with the COMP (reference) data (1961–1989). The difference was particularly high in Lake St. Louis (up to 50% increase) and in the Contrecœur Islands (up to 41%). There was little difference between the results of the WAWE scenario and those of the WADR scenario, except in Lake St. Louis, where the WADR scenario predicted greater surface areas. Under climate change conditions, sites conducive to common reed seed germination and seedling survival were found on a much larger portion of the floodplain and extended further from the bank toward the centre of the river (Fig. 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">3</a>). In Lake St. Louis, new sites were present in the lake centre. In Lake St. Pierre, the formation of new common reed stands, extending from the lake banks to its centre, was especially notable.
  </p>
  <div id="tbl2" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Table 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Total wetland area potentially suitable for the establishment of the common reed (
     <span class="italic">Phragmites australis</span>) through sexual reproduction in four sectors of the St. Lawrence River as estimated by an ecohydrological model and for three climate scenarios (COMP: present-day climate 1961–1989; WAWE: warmer and wetter climate predicted for 2040–2069; WADR: warmer and drier climate predicted for 2040–2069). The area potentially conducive to common reed establishment by seed is cumulated for the time period considered.
    </p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <thead>
     <tr>
      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
      <th align="left" colspan="3" rowspan="1">Total wetland area suitable for common reed establishment (ha)
       <span class="hr"/>
      </th>
      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
      <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sector</th>
      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">COMP</th>
      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WAWE</th>
      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">WADR</th>
      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Difference WAWE versus COMP (%)</th>
      <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Difference WADR versus COMP (%)</th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lake St. Louis</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1486</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1944</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2228</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+31</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+50</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Boucherville Islands</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">963</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1113</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1098</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+16</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+14</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Contrecœur Islands</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1014</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1432</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1400</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+41</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+38</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lake St. Pierre</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13,935</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16,876</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16,660</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+21</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+20</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">All sectors</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18,560</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22,879</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22,911</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+23</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">+23</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
  </div>
  <div id="fig03" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Spatial distribution of common reed (
     <span class="italic">Phragmites australis</span>) stands identified in four St. Lawrence River sectors by remote sensing images (2010) and modeled spatial distribution of germination grounds suitable for the species that have not yet been invaded, for three climate scenarios (COMP: the present-day climate 1961–1989; WAWE: warmer and wetter climate predicted for 2040–2069; WADR: warmer and drier climate predicted for 2040–2069). Germination grounds vulnerable to a common reed invasion are cumulated for the time period considered.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="ece30005-3421-f3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </sec>
</sec>
