<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Step 3: Structure of the common reed model</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The common reed model was developed within the infrastructure of the 
  <span class="italic">Integrated Ecosystem Response Model</span> (IERM), a high-resolution spatial database developed by Environment Canada to evaluate the impact of water level fluctuations and flow regulation on the St. Lawrence River ecosystems (Morin et al. 
  <a rid="b63" ref-type="bibr" href="#b63">2005</a>; Morin and Champoux 
  <a rid="b61" ref-type="bibr" href="#b61">2006</a>). IERM has been successfully used to predict the impact of water level changes on fish and bird reproduction, and on wetland vegetation (Desgranges et al. 
  <a rid="b18" ref-type="bibr" href="#b18">2006</a>; Morin et al. 
  <a rid="b64" ref-type="bibr" href="#b64">2006</a>; Mingelbier et al. 
  <a rid="b59" ref-type="bibr" href="#b59">2008</a>). The methodology used to build the basic datasets and to run IERM is described in Morin and Champoux (
  <a rid="b61" ref-type="bibr" href="#b61">2006</a>) and Morin et al. (
  <a rid="b64" ref-type="bibr" href="#b64">2006</a>). In summary, IERM is based on a spatial grid whose nodes are 20–80 m apart in shallow water areas and 160 m apart in the navigation channel. Several information layers measured in the field or modeled (topography, bathymetry, substratum, water level, current velocity, aquatic vegetation, emergent vegetation) are associated with each node. IERM not only models fluvial physics, but also simulates the spatiotemporal development of ten wetland vegetation classes (Desgranges et al. 
  <a rid="b18" ref-type="bibr" href="#b18">2006</a>; Morin et al. 
  <a rid="b64" ref-type="bibr" href="#b64">2006</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The location of a common reed stand did not necessarily correspond to the exact location of a node of the IERM grid. The IERM node network was therefore transformed into a square polygon grid with surface areas varying from 0.04 to 2.56 ha, depending on the distance between nodes in the original grid. The information associated with the central node of each polygon was then applied to the entire polygon. The presence of at least one common reed stand in a polygon was enough to consider this polygon as conducive to the establishment of the invader. The spatially explicit information layers used in this study were topography, water level, and wetland class. Air temperature data, available at only one station, were extracted from the historical series measured at the Montréal Airport (Dorval-Trudeau; Environment Canada, 
  <a rid="b23" ref-type="bibr" href="#b23">2013</a>). This series is the longest (1953–2012) and most complete available in the study area. These values were also used as references for the entire area (Morin et al. 
  <a rid="b63" ref-type="bibr" href="#b63">2005</a>). Temperature data were thus not spatially distributed: they were associated with each node (polygon), but were the same for all the nodes of the modeling domain. The other data, measured or simulated for each node (polygon) of the grid, were extracted from the models developed by Morin et al. (
  <a rid="b63" ref-type="bibr" href="#b63">2005</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The parameters conducive to common reed seed germination and seedling survival, as presented above (step 2), were integrated into IERM in the form of an algorithm. This algorithm was used to query the geodatabase on a daily basis (for a given year), which then returned all sites whose attributes were within the required parameters, thus identifying potential common reed germination grounds. For example, to verify the presence of an appropriate water level, which required that a site not be flooded at the beginning of the growing season, the water level was examined (based on IERM data) for all polygons each day of a given year. A count began as soon as all conditions conducive to common reed seed germination and seedling survival were met in a polygon. If there were nonflooded conditions, the other parameters conducive to germination were met, and the seedlings had at least 120 days of appropriate growing conditions (no frost), the polygon was identified as a potential site for common reed establishment. Data on temperature and water level measurements were available on daily means, while the wetland classes were reassessed yearly based on environmental conditions observed the previous years. Data related to land use and topography were kept constant.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A daily time step was used for the historical series analysis. However, a quarter-monthly time step was used for the climate change simulations, because the water level series for the St. Lawrence River were available only in quarter-monthly means. The quarter-monthly time step divides time into 7- or 8-day blocks, for a total of 48 quarter-monthly time steps per year. Using quarter-monthly time steps permits the comparison of individual quarter-monthly time steps across years and has the advantage of not being influenced by the number of days in a year (Morin et al. 
  <a rid="b65" ref-type="bibr" href="#b65">2009</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
