<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Step 4: Calibration of the common reed model</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The invasion stage, which reflects the proportion of invaded to invadable areas, directly impacts the ability of a model to predict areas vulnerable to invasion (Václavík and Meentemeyer 
  <a rid="b78" ref-type="bibr" href="#b78">2012</a>). If the invasion is advanced, one can presume that the species occupies most of the sites that foster its establishment; it is then easy to establish a correlation between site conditions and their likelihood of being invaded. It is much more difficult to establish such a correlation if the invasion is still in the early stages: the invader absence at a given site does not necessarily correspond to unfavorable local conditions. Thus, the accuracy of the parameters associated with common reed germination and seedling survival was verified in the Boucherville Islands, that is, in the sector of the river containing one of the oldest populations of the plant, the greatest surface area of common reed stands, and a well-documented invasion history. To do so, the common reed distribution, as simulated by IERM, was compared to the real distribution (see step 1). The simulated distribution was generated from 1980 (beginning of the common reed invasion in this sector) to 2009 and took into account the historical environmental data integrated into IERM. Given that satellite images were taken during the 2010 growing season, the period used for modeling ended in 2009.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The comparison was made using a confusion matrix (Fielding and Bell 
  <a rid="b25" ref-type="bibr" href="#b25">1997</a>), which helped to determine (1) the number of polygons with successful common reed seedling establishment and that were also identified by IERM as potential establishment sites between 1980 and 2009 (true positives); (2) the number of polygons with seedling establishment but that were not identified as such by IERM (false negatives); (3) the number of polygons with no seedling establishment but where the common reed should have established stands according to IERM (false positives); and (4) the number of polygons with no seedling establishment and that were also identified by IERM as not being conducive to the emergence and survival of common reed seedlings (true negatives). To improve the model performance, various combinations of parameters were tested, for example, the inclusion or exclusion of the average daily temperature, daily temperature amplitude, water level, and wetland class. Once calibrated, the common reed model was applied to the entire study area.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Given that the common reed invasion in the Boucherville Islands is relatively recent and still ongoing, we hypothesized that the polygons identified as false positives, while having a high germination potential, had not yet been invaded either as a result of insufficient time or the random dispersal of seeds. It was also possible that stand size within a false-positive polygon was simply too small to be detected via satellite imagery. To confirm this hypothesis, 213 of the 317 false-positive polygons (randomly selected) in the Boucherville Islands sector were visited between October 1 and 5, 2012. Each polygon was verified by an observer on foot. Searching continued until either common reed was found or the entire polygon had been covered. If common reed stems were found, their origin (from seed – not connected by rhizomes or stolons to adjacent stands – or from vegetative propagation) was noted.</p>
</sec>
