<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Step 2: Parameters conducive to common reed establishment</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One of the challenges in modeling common reed establishment in a natural environment resides in the fact that it is extremely difficult to determine the exact moment of seed germination, because there is always a lag of a few years between seed germination and the formation of a reed stand (of about 5 m
  <span class="sup">2</span>) that can be detected on aerial photographs or satellite images. It was thus impossible to characterize conditions conducive to seed germination and seedling establishment based on historical data. As a result, the model could only be developed using a deductive approach (Ottaviani et al. 
  <a rid="b68" ref-type="bibr" href="#b68">2004</a>) and was essentially based on the most current knowledge regarding the biology of the common reed.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Bare, wet (not flooded) soils are necessary for a new common reed stand to develop from a seed (Galinato and van der Valk 
  <a rid="b27" ref-type="bibr" href="#b27">1986</a>; Coops and Van der Velde 
  <a rid="b15" ref-type="bibr" href="#b15">1995</a>; Hudon et al. 
  <a rid="b36" ref-type="bibr" href="#b36">2005</a>). Such exposure conditions are present along the St. Lawrence River during summer-long episodes of low water levels or in areas with anthropogenic disturbance (Hudon 
  <a rid="b34" ref-type="bibr" href="#b34">1997</a>, 
  <a rid="b35" ref-type="bibr" href="#b35">2004</a>; Hudon et al. 
  <a rid="b36" ref-type="bibr" href="#b36">2005</a>). These nonflooded conditions must be present at the beginning of the growing season. Seedlings need at least 120 days of growth; otherwise, they are not able to accumulate sufficient reserves, which will hamper their survival the following year, particularly during spring floods and frosts (Haslam 
  <a rid="b31" ref-type="bibr" href="#b31">1971</a>; Weisner and Ekstam 
  <a rid="b84" ref-type="bibr" href="#b84">1993</a>; Ekstam and Forseby 
  <a rid="b20" ref-type="bibr" href="#b20">1999</a>). Furthermore, common reed seed germination occurs at a mean daily air temperature of ≥10°C (Haslam 
  <a rid="b32" ref-type="bibr" href="#b32">1972</a>; Ekstam and Forseby 
  <a rid="b20" ref-type="bibr" href="#b20">1999</a>) and a daily temperature range of ≥10°C (Ekstam and Forseby 
  <a rid="b20" ref-type="bibr" href="#b20">1999</a>). However, very early germination is not necessarily beneficial because seedling risk exposure to late spring frosts (Weisner and Ekstam 
  <a rid="b84" ref-type="bibr" href="#b84">1993</a>). We thus considered that germination and subsequent seedling growth periods could not start until the first day of the year when mean daily temperatures reached 10°C (and were not followed by temperatures below 0°C) until the first autumn frost.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Light conditions also influence common reed germination and seedling survival (Haslam 
  <a rid="b32" ref-type="bibr" href="#b32">1972</a>), and a dense tree cover can strongly reduce seedling establishment and growth (Mal and Narine 
  <a rid="b54" ref-type="bibr" href="#b54">2004</a>; Lelong et al. 
  <a rid="b49" ref-type="bibr" href="#b49">2009</a>; Albert et al. 
  <a rid="b2" ref-type="bibr" href="#b2">2013</a>). Therefore, a robust common reed model must also consider the various classes of wetlands that can be present in a study area, each with their particular tree cover. For this study, we used the ten classes defined specifically for the St. Lawrence River by Desgranges et al. (
  <a rid="b18" ref-type="bibr" href="#b18">2006</a>), but only the three classes associated with the presence of trees (open treed swamp, closed treed swamp, and damp forest) were considered obstacles to common reed germination and seedling survival (no establishment).
 </p>
</sec>
