<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Step 1: Distribution of common reed stands</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data on the historical distribution of common reed stands were gathered through aerial photographs. It is possible to distinguish stands of a certain size (≥5 m
  <span class="sup">2</span>) in black and white or infrared photographs at a scale ≤1:15,000 (Warren et al. 
  <a rid="b82" ref-type="bibr" href="#b82">2001</a>; Wilcox et al. 
  <a rid="b88" ref-type="bibr" href="#b88">2003</a>; Hudon et al. 
  <a rid="b36" ref-type="bibr" href="#b36">2005</a>; Maheu-Giroux and de Blois 
  <a rid="b53" ref-type="bibr" href="#b53">2005</a>). This work was performed for the only sector in which common reed stands were both abundant and old enough to build a valid historical reconstruction, that is, the Boucherville Islands. The database used is based on a mapping carried out by Hudon et al. (
  <a rid="b36" ref-type="bibr" href="#b36">2005</a>), which covered 1980 (1 ha of common reed stands) to 2002 (33 ha). Using a geographic information system, the centroid of each large common reed stand, which was primarily circular in shape, was georeferenced when first detected. The most recent genetic data gathered at Boucherville Islands (Albert et al. 
  <a rid="b3" ref-type="bibr" href="#b3">2015</a>) indicated that each stand was monoclonal, created through the germination of a single seed, followed by the extension of rhizomes and stolons in every direction. The centroid of a common reed stand therefore roughly corresponds to the location of the germination bed that permitted successful reed stand establishment.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Current distribution of common reed stands was mapped through remote sensing using high-definition WorldView–02 and QuickBird–02 satellite images taken between August 15 and September 18, 2010. A configuration of four multispectral bands (near infrared, red, green and blue) was used, providing a spatial resolution of approximately 2.4 m. Common reed stands were identified and delineated using spectral signatures developed by Létourneau and Jean (
  <a rid="b51" ref-type="bibr" href="#b51">2005</a>) based on training areas located in the St. Lawrence River wetlands. Because the spectral signature of the common reed is somewhat similar to that of the reed canary grass (
  <span class="italic">Phalaris arundinacea</span> L.), a plant species also commonly found in the St. Lawrence River floodplain, the map created from satellite images was validated in the field from helicopter (October 18, 2011) and by foot (September 13 and 14, 2011). In all, 240 previously mapped common reed stands were visited for validation, primarily in the Lake St. Louis, Boucherville Islands, and Lake St. Pierre sectors. These stands were selected through a stratified random sampling, which enabled us to confirm the presence of the common reed based on a range of stand areas (0–10 m
  <span class="sup">2</span>, 11–50 m
  <span class="sup">2</span>, ≥51 m
  <span class="sup">2</span>). The map was then adjusted based on results obtained during validation. The centroid of each common reed stand retained on the validated map was localized using the same method used for the historical distribution data.
 </p>
</sec>
