<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study area</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The impact of climate change on the spread of the common reed was assessed for the St. Lawrence River wetlands, in a section of the river 150 km long (Fig. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" href="#fig01">1</a>), from Lake St. Louis (45°19′N; 73°56′W) to Lake St. Pierre (46°16′N; 72°38′W). The St. Lawrence River flow is fed by the Great Lakes and Ottawa River watersheds, which drain an area of 917,000 km
  <span class="sup">2</span>. Variations in river flow can largely be attributed to fluctuations in precipitation. However, the Moses-Saunders Dam (Cornwall, Ontario) regulates the flow to minimize extreme fluctuations in water level, both along the Great Lakes and the river. Spring floods normally increase water flow in Lake St. Pierre to 13,000 m
  <span class="sup">3</span>sec
  <span class="sup">−1</span> in April, while it might only reach 9000 m
  <span class="sup">3</span>sec
  <span class="sup">−1</span> during the low flow periods in August and January. The vast majority of wetlands (nearly 90%) are located in the Lake St. Pierre sector (Jean and Létourneau 
  <a rid="b37" ref-type="bibr" href="#b37">2011</a>). In the other sectors (Lake St. Louis, Boucherville Islands, Contrecœur Islands), wetlands cover smaller areas and are mainly found near islands. Overall, wetlands of the St. Lawrence River are made up by high marshes (55% of the total surface area), low marshes (26%), and swamps (19%; Létourneau and Jean 
  <a rid="b50" ref-type="bibr" href="#b50">1996</a>).
 </p>
 <div id="fig01" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Map of the study area (St. Lawrence River, Québec, Canada). The four sectors of the river under study are delineated by gray boxes.</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="ece30005-3421-f1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
