<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par24" class="p">In contrast to other similar ecosystems, alpine grasslands are mainly distributed within high-altitude zones and cover only about 3% of global land area. These systems are therefore extremely sensitive to human interference
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" class="xref">67</xref>
 </sup>; although exploitation and anthropogenic interventions can damage alpine vegetation within just a few seconds, restoration can take several decades
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" class="xref">68</xref>
 </sup> and the available range of approaches that can be applied to such systems remains relatively small
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68" class="xref">68</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" class="xref">69</xref>
 </sup>. At the moment, payments for ecosystem services and governance interventions remain the main ways in which alpine grasslands are restored
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" class="xref">65</xref>
 </sup>. Previous research has also shown that both the abiotic and biotic constraints of ecological environments influence plant growth and succession during restoration irrespective of whether short- or long-term tactics are adopted to restore ecosystem resilience and adaptability
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" class="xref">70</xref>
 </sup>. Grassland ecosystems within the TRHR provide one representative example of such a system from the high altitude cold environment of the QTP
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71" class="xref">71</xref>
 </sup>. The results of this study provide clear evidence that vegetation growth and the restoration of alpine ecosystems are severely limited by both abiotic and biotic constraints, including climatic and topographical factors, soil nutrient conditions, and grassland types. The outcomes of this research also imply that the heterogeneity determined by different structures and compositions of abiotic and biotic factors can explain grassland NPP variation. Results imply that large-scale abiotic and biotic changes can substantially influence grassland restoration; measures of heterogeneity should therefore also be incorporated as components of future grassland restoration programs
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72" class="xref">72</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
