<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec004" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data collection</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As above mentioned almost all species analysed present wide distributions, thus the total known distribution area of each species in the Neotropics was used and then later projected to the focal area. Our occurrence data were compiled from the open access platform Global Biodiversity Information Facility (available from 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbif.org" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://gbif.org</span>; accessed 19 July 2017), using the R package rgbif [
  <a rid="pone.0215229.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215229.ref035">35</a>]. We applied a quality control to minimize sample bias by using only georeferenced data, ensuring a minimum distance of 10 km between consecutive presence records (lower spatial aggregation). We also excluded dubious/disparate records, i.e., those that were clearly outside the expected bird distribution, grounding our decision in the Handbook of the Birds of the World and BirdLife International [
  <a rid="pone.0215229.ref017" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215229.ref017">17</a>]). Our database includes 228,298 nonduplicate presence records (ranging from 9-1297/taxa) for 547 species (introduced, migratory and aquatic species were excluded). Of these species, 23 are Brazilian endemic, 49 are facing some degree of threat [
  <a rid="pone.0215229.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215229.ref036">36</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0215229.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215229.ref038">38</a>] and only four species have a limited availability of occurrence data (&lt;15 records; all endemic and/or rare). Species taxonomy follows the latest updated checklist of the Brazilian Ornithological Records Committee [
  <a rid="pone.0215229.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215229.ref039">39</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Current climate data and projections for 2050 and 2070 were obtained from the WorldClim database (available at: 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://worldclim.org" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://worldclim.org</span>; accessed 24 November 2016) at a resolution of 5 arcmin (~10km at the equator) for the Neotropical region (spatial limits of 110° to 30°W; 25°N to 60°S). This resolution was chosen due to the high computational power demanded for modelling such a high number of species, their broad distributional area and high number of scenarios. After performing a pairwise Pearson correlation test for all 20 variables (19 bioclimatic and altitude) to remove those that were highly correlated (r&gt;0.85), we selected 11 as our predictors: annual mean temperature, mean diurnal range, temperature seasonality, temperature annual range, mean temperature of warmest quarter, annual precipitation, precipitation of driest month, precipitation seasonality, precipitation of warmest quarter, precipitation of coldest quarter and altitude. Future climatic projections were derived from general circulation model (GCM) simulations from the Community Climate System Model (CCSM4), a well-known and frequently used GCM (e.g., [
  <a rid="pone.0215229.ref040" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215229.ref040">40</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0215229.ref041" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215229.ref041">41</a>]). In addition, among the various GCMs, the Amazonia rainfall and its seasonality have highly variable bias (which account to the uncertainty in forecasting future atmospheric CO2 concentration and climate change), yet the CCSM4 is one of the models that best represent the main climatic drivers on the region [
  <a rid="pone.0215229.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215229.ref042">42</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0215229.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215229.ref043">43</a>]. Three representative concentration pathway scenarios (RCPs 2.6, 6.0 and 8.5) were projected, representing a broad range of climate outcomes from the most to the least optimistic scenario.
 </p>
</sec>
