<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec002" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Material and methods</div>
 <sec id="sec003" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study system</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The species list was derived from those recorded in Carajás, currently one of the biologically best known areas in the SE Amazonia due to over three decades of periodic inventories and sporadic observations [
   <a rid="pone.0215229.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215229.ref029">29</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0215229.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215229.ref030">30</a>]. It was updated from Vale’s internal database (
   <span class="italic">bdbio</span>), internet repositories (e.g., 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://wikiaves.com.br" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://wikiaves.com.br</span> and 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://xeno-canto.org" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://xeno-canto.org</span>) and Museu Paraense Emilio Goeldi ornithological collection, achieving 620 species. The projections and analysis focuses mainly on SE Amazonia, an area between the right margin of Tapajós and Juruena Rivers (59°W) and the Amazonia east limit (44°W), and from Marajó island (0°) to the Amazonia south limit (14°S). The south and east limits of this area correspond to the Amazonia-Cerrado transition zone, encompassing FT and OAV environments, and it is naturally close to the climatic limit of tropical forests [
   <a rid="pone.0215229.ref031" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215229.ref031">31</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0215229.ref032" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215229.ref032">32</a>]. In fact, several climate model simulations confirm that SE Amazonia is the most sensitive region to global climate change [
   <a rid="pone.0215229.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215229.ref033">33</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0215229.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215229.ref034">34</a>] and it has the most deforested area and the highest deforestation rates considering all Amazonia [
   <a rid="pone.0215229.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215229.ref022">22</a>]. It is important to mention that our set of species corresponds to 
   <span class="italic">ca</span>. 63% of the total known avian taxa of the focal area, and, although some avifauna turnover may occur between the interfluves of major rivers, most species have wide distributions and less than 1% represent taxa exclusively endemic to the respective interfluves. In addition, the list includes FT and OAV species, which allow testing if and how these groups will potentially respond differently to climate changes. Moreover, to assess changes in ecosystem functioning, we also assign each species to one of three trophic guilds based on the main diet of the species [
   <a rid="pone.0215229.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215229.ref028">28</a>]: frugivores (FR [seed dispersion]), insectivores (IN [pest control]) and nectarivores (NE [pollination]). Species with other diets (e.g., omnivores, granivores, carnivores, and scavengers) were assigned as "others" (OT).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec004" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data collection</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As above mentioned almost all species analysed present wide distributions, thus the total known distribution area of each species in the Neotropics was used and then later projected to the focal area. Our occurrence data were compiled from the open access platform Global Biodiversity Information Facility (available from 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://gbif.org" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://gbif.org</span>; accessed 19 July 2017), using the R package rgbif [
   <a rid="pone.0215229.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215229.ref035">35</a>]. We applied a quality control to minimize sample bias by using only georeferenced data, ensuring a minimum distance of 10 km between consecutive presence records (lower spatial aggregation). We also excluded dubious/disparate records, i.e., those that were clearly outside the expected bird distribution, grounding our decision in the Handbook of the Birds of the World and BirdLife International [
   <a rid="pone.0215229.ref017" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215229.ref017">17</a>]). Our database includes 228,298 nonduplicate presence records (ranging from 9-1297/taxa) for 547 species (introduced, migratory and aquatic species were excluded). Of these species, 23 are Brazilian endemic, 49 are facing some degree of threat [
   <a rid="pone.0215229.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215229.ref036">36</a>–
   <a rid="pone.0215229.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215229.ref038">38</a>] and only four species have a limited availability of occurrence data (&lt;15 records; all endemic and/or rare). Species taxonomy follows the latest updated checklist of the Brazilian Ornithological Records Committee [
   <a rid="pone.0215229.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215229.ref039">39</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Current climate data and projections for 2050 and 2070 were obtained from the WorldClim database (available at: 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://worldclim.org" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://worldclim.org</span>; accessed 24 November 2016) at a resolution of 5 arcmin (~10km at the equator) for the Neotropical region (spatial limits of 110° to 30°W; 25°N to 60°S). This resolution was chosen due to the high computational power demanded for modelling such a high number of species, their broad distributional area and high number of scenarios. After performing a pairwise Pearson correlation test for all 20 variables (19 bioclimatic and altitude) to remove those that were highly correlated (r&gt;0.85), we selected 11 as our predictors: annual mean temperature, mean diurnal range, temperature seasonality, temperature annual range, mean temperature of warmest quarter, annual precipitation, precipitation of driest month, precipitation seasonality, precipitation of warmest quarter, precipitation of coldest quarter and altitude. Future climatic projections were derived from general circulation model (GCM) simulations from the Community Climate System Model (CCSM4), a well-known and frequently used GCM (e.g., [
   <a rid="pone.0215229.ref040" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215229.ref040">40</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0215229.ref041" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215229.ref041">41</a>]). In addition, among the various GCMs, the Amazonia rainfall and its seasonality have highly variable bias (which account to the uncertainty in forecasting future atmospheric CO2 concentration and climate change), yet the CCSM4 is one of the models that best represent the main climatic drivers on the region [
   <a rid="pone.0215229.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215229.ref042">42</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0215229.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215229.ref043">43</a>]. Three representative concentration pathway scenarios (RCPs 2.6, 6.0 and 8.5) were projected, representing a broad range of climate outcomes from the most to the least optimistic scenario.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec005" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Species distribution modelling</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The SDMs were estimated by running two different algorithms within the biomod2 package on R [
   <a rid="pone.0215229.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215229.ref044">44</a>]: generalised linear models (GLM [
   <a rid="pone.0215229.ref045" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215229.ref045">45</a>]) and maximum entropy (Maxent [
   <a rid="pone.0215229.ref046" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215229.ref046">46</a>]). We generated three sets of pseudo-absence data containing ten times the number of presence data points randomly distributed for each species [
   <a rid="pone.0215229.ref047" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215229.ref047">47</a>]. The data sets were then partitioned so that 80% were used to calibrate the models, while the remaining 20% were used for the evaluation. Model performance was assessed with the True Skill Statistics (TSS; threshold-dependent [
   <a rid="pone.0215229.ref048" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215229.ref048">48</a>]) and the receiver operating characteristic curve analysis (ROC; threshold-independent [
   <a rid="pone.0215229.ref046" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215229.ref046">46</a>]), this procedure was repeated ten times for cross-validation, and the models with poor performance (TSS&lt;0.5) were eliminated from the ensemble process. We also report sensitivity (percentage of true positives), specificity (percentage of true negatives) and assessed the predictor variable importance using the tables of permutation importance.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Finally, we summarized the ensemble of predicted species distributions (two algorithms x three pseudo-absences x models with TSS&gt;0.5) using the committee average method, where probabilities from different models were first transformed into binary according to a threshold (here, the TSS cut-off threshold) and then averaged [
   <a rid="pone.0215229.ref044" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215229.ref044">44</a>]. In the end, seven consensual maps were generated per species (one for each scenario: current, and RCPs 2.6, 6.0, 8.5 for 2050 and 2070).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec006" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Analyses</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">First, our continuous probability consensual maps were converted into a binary classification by selecting threshold values that maximized the TSS (cutoff; 
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0215229.s002" href="#pone.0215229.s002">S1 Table</a>). The projected occurrence area was calculated by multiplying the cell area (10x10 = 100km
   <span class="sup">2</span>) with the cell count. Species with projected current occurrence areas &lt;100 grid cells were excluded from the analyses, to avoid overestimating the predicted effects within the focal area. Therefore, the final dataset included 501 species and 199,250 records (
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0215229.s002" href="#pone.0215229.s002">S1 Table</a>). Our data include species that occur in both FT and OAV environments, and we treat them separately. The total species richness (SR) was computed by stacking the maps of all individual species for each scenario (and for each algorithm to estimate uncertainties, see next). Uncertainties were calculated as the contribution of different sources (here, the algorithms and future scenarios) to variation around the consensus maps, through the proportional sum of squares of each cell in relation to the total sum of squares using the SR maps as response [
   <a rid="pone.0215229.ref049" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215229.ref049">49</a>]. We estimated the species range change dynamics (in terms of area gain/loss) based on the differences between the projected area for each future climate scenario and current. To highlight the impact on ecosystem functioning, these results were grouped by the trophic guild (see above) to reflect the most affected function in the study area. We also assessed the future effectiveness of current PAs by accounting for the differences in the estimated SR in each PA over the different climate scenarios. Although there are 57 PAs (37 CUs and 20 ILs) in the focal area, we grouped them in 13, since they form continuous blocks of protected area and were considered together. Thus, for this analysis we kept only blocks with an area greater than 1,000 km
   <span class="sup">2</span> (
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0215229.s003" href="#pone.0215229.s003">S2 Table</a>; data for Brazilian PAs available from Instituto Chico Mendes de Conservação da Biodiversidade: 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://icmbio.gov.br" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://icmbio.gov.br</span>). Finally, for the FT species only, we calculated the size of climatically stable areas considering grid cells containing at least 20% of each trophic guild and with an increment of +10% (until 80%) in each scenario. We first stacked each series of percentage/guild on one binary map, and stacked this map with each scenario to show the suitable habitats across scenarios. Areas were considered climatically stable if the guilds were predicted to be present in six to seven out the seven scenarios. Also, a deforestation layer (data for Amazon for the year 2015 available from Instituto Nacional de Pesquisas Espaciais [
   <a rid="pone.0215229.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215229.ref022">22</a>]: 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.obt.inpe.br" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.obt.inpe.br</span>) was downscaled from the original resolution (60 m) to the topoclimatic variables resolution (10 km) and then, overlaid to create a final decision-making oriented map. The climatically stable areas, outside PAs, that potentially will maximize suitable habitats for biodiversity and having natural vegetation were considered important to conservation, and the same areas with no natural vegetation, important for restoration programs. All analyses were performed using R [
   <a rid="pone.0215229.ref050" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215229.ref050">50</a>] and QGIS [
   <a rid="pone.0215229.ref051" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0215229.ref051">51</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
