<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We use a simple statistical analysis method to quantify the contribution of climate extremes to climate-induced air pollution and its associated health impacts. The statistical analysis is conducted by replacing the pollutant concentrations in extreme event days with the average concentrations in nonextreme event days over a 90-d window (45 d before and after the extreme event day, approximately at seasonal scales). Any other extreme events in the 90-d window are also excluded to avoid contaminating the mean climate signal. We average the pollutant concentration over the nonextreme 90-d window and treat this as the mean climate component on that given extreme event day. We then subtract the mean climate component from the pollutant concentration during the extreme event and treat that as the climate extreme component. Therefore, we are able to assess the air quality without climate extremes as well as the contribution of climate extremes. Thus, total concentration changes in a changing climate can be further divided into 2 parts: changes in mean climate state (excluding extremes) and extreme-induced additional changes. The contribution of climate extremes to climate-induced air pollution-related health impacts is estimated based on the extremes’ contribution to climate-induced total changes in annual (for PM
 <sub class="sub">2.5</sub>) or seasonal (for ozone) mean concentrations (results are shown in 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1812881116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <italic class="italic">SI Appendix</italic>, Fig. S6
 </ext-link>). We replace the pollutant concentrations in all of the extreme event days in the year with the nonextreme mean calculated over the 90-d window; thus, we are able to calculate the annual/seasonal mean concentration without extremes. We then compare the annual/seasonal mean concentration with and without extremes to get the contribution of extremes in annual or seasonal mean concentrations. We have added sensitivity studies instead using 60- and 120-d windows around the extreme event. The results show that extreme-induced mortality is relatively insensitive to the length of the window (results are shown in 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1812881116/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <italic class="italic">SI Appendix</italic>, Fig. S8
 </ext-link>).
</p>
