<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract id="ece35113-abs-0001" class="abstract">
 <title class="title">Abstract</title>
 <p class="p">Northwestern China has a wealth of endemic species, which has been hypothesized to be affected by the complex paleoclimatic and paleogeographic history during Quaternary. In this paper, we used 
  <italic class="italic">Gymnocarpos przewalskii</italic> as a model to address the evolutionary history and current population genetic structure of species in northwestern China. We employed two chloroplast DNA fragments (
  <italic class="italic">rps</italic>16 and 
  <italic class="italic">psb</italic>B‐
  <italic class="italic">psb</italic>I), one nuclear DNA fragment (ITS), and simple sequence repeat (SSRs) to investigate the spatial genetic pattern of 
  <italic class="italic">G. przewalskii</italic>. High genetic diversity (cpDNA: 
  <italic class="italic">h</italic>
  <sub class="sub">S</sub> = 0.330, 
  <italic class="italic">h</italic>
  <sub class="sub">T</sub> = 0.866; ITS: 
  <italic class="italic">h</italic>
  <sub class="sub">S</sub> = 0.458, 
  <italic class="italic">h</italic>
  <sub class="sub">T</sub> = 0.872) was identified in almost all populations, and most of the population have private haplotypes. Moreover, multimodal mismatch distributions were observed and estimates of Tajima's 
  <italic class="italic">D</italic> and Fu's 
  <italic class="italic">FS</italic> tests did not identify significantly departures from neutrality, indicating that recent expansion of 
  <italic class="italic">G. przewalskii </italic>was rejected. Thus, we inferred that 
  <italic class="italic">G. przewalskii</italic> survived generally in northwestern China during the Pleistocene. All data together support the genotypes of 
  <italic class="italic">G. przewalskii</italic> into three groups, consistent with their respective geographical distributions in the western regions—Tarim Basin, the central regions—Hami Basin and Hexi Corridor, and the eastern regions—Alxa Desert and Wulate Prairie. Divergence among most lineages of 
  <italic class="italic">G. przewalskii</italic> occurred in the Pleistocene, and the range of potential distributions is associated with glacial cycles. We concluded that climate oscillation during Pleistocene significantly affected the distribution of the species.
 </p>
</abstract>
