<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate change is one of the largest threats to biodiversity and to natural systems in general 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-1" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-1">1</a>, 
   <a rid="ref-2" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-2">2</a>
  </span>. Recent changes in climate are driving shifts in the timing of ecological events 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-3" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-3">3</a>
  </span>, the distribution of species 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-4">4</a>, 
   <a rid="ref-5" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-5">5</a>
  </span>, and the functioning of ecosystems 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-6" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-6">6</a>
  </span>. Models project even greater changes for the future 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-7">7</a>– 
   <a rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-10">10</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">These climate-driven changes challenge the way the planning and practice of conservation have traditionally been done. Most conservation has been predicated on the fact that the environment is relatively stable over the time frames of management planning (generally less than 50 years). However, projected changes in species distributions and ecosystem functions present obvious challenges to this assumption. Over the last decade, there has been a growing literature on what climate change means for biodiversity 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-11" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-11">11</a>
  </span> and the implications this has for conservation planning and action 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-12">12</a>
  </span>. As a consequence, there have been some notable shifts in the way conservation is being conducted, from the goals and structure of conservation organizations to the planning and execution of conservation projects on the ground 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-12">12</a>, 
   <a rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-13">13</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate change is increasingly integrated into the daily operations of conservation organizations. The anticipated impacts of climate change have driven planners and managers to consider longer time horizons and to anticipate the potentially synergistic effects of climate change and other threats and the need to address them quickly. Likewise, conservation biologists have begun to acknowledge the importance of planning for extreme weather events in addition to slow, long-term climatic change. These shifts have led to new perspectives on, and alterations to, approaches used to conserve biodiversity. Here, we describe some of the more prominent changes in the approaches conservation planners and practitioners have taken to help address the threat of climate change. Some of these approaches, such as restoration and the prioritization of species for conservation actions, have been around for quite some time but needed reframing as a consequence of the likely impacts of climate change. Others, such as assisted colonization, are new twists on old practices and have arisen directly out of the challenges posed by climate change.</p>
</sec>
