<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Rethinking restoration</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Restoration is one of the basic tools of a conservation practitioner. It has traditionally involved returning a system to its state prior to some disturbance 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-14">14</a>
  </span>. However, climate change challenges the very nature of restoration based on such a definition 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-15">15</a>
  </span>. It brings into question the utility of historical benchmarks as restoration targets, the species or seed sources to be used, and the time frame for planning.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Rethinking how restoration efforts are applied in light of climate change has led to shifts in thinking as well as in practice. Most fundamentally, practicing restoration in a changing climate requires embracing uncertainty and accepting that the goals of a project may need to change over time 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-16">16</a>
  </span>. Instead of relying on historical benchmarks, restoration efforts will likely need to look into the future and anticipate change—perhaps relying on a dynamic reference process that accounts for variability in reference ecosystems 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-16">16</a>, 
   <a rid="ref-17" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-17">17</a>
  </span>. Looking forward will also include rethinking the mix of species to be planted and potentially focusing on ecosystem function rather than particular assemblages of species. Restoration efforts have begun to make use of the same niche modelling methods that have been used to assess potential species responses to climate change 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-18" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-18">18</a>
  </span>, but there is clear recognition that better models are needed 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-19" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-19">19</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Many recent climate-adaptation efforts have involved restoration. Of the projects funded by the Wildlife Conservation Society’s Climate Adaptation Fund, at least 70% have involved restoration 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-20" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-20">20</a>
  </span>. These projects have included riparian restoration to enhance connectivity, coastal restoration to prevent storm damage, forest restoration to reduce fire risk, and prairie restorations to enhance watershed function. In addition to the projects that clearly engage in restoration, several projects are aimed at converting one type of ecosystem to another—not necessarily restoring a historical condition but preparing an ecosystem to function differently in a future climate. An example of this type of project involved converting forested areas to grasslands to facilitate marsh establishment in the face of sea-level rise. Whether such actions are classified as restoration could be debated, but clearly the lessons learned from decades of restoration will be essential to these new types of adaptation projects.
 </p>
</sec>
