<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Since prior experience of weather events is intrinsically related to the region in which one lives, geographic location is another factor with the strong possibility of affecting psychological distance to climate change. In particular, in the present paper we focus on proximity to the coastline. Although all types of regions will experience climate changes of varying levels of severity, an IPCC report suggests that, in addition to mountain settlements and megacities, coastal communities are particularly vulnerable to the impacts of climate change 
 <xref rid="pone.0103180-IPCC1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[35]</xref>, possibly because they must bear the brunt of sea-level rise, changing wind patterns, and/or increasingly severe tropical storms 
 <xref rid="pone.0103180-Nicholls1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[36]</xref>. Thus, coastal dwellers' experience of current climate change impacts may be increased, and this may in turn lower their psychological distance to climate change––that is, they may take warnings of climate change more seriously because they feel they are beginning to experience it themselves. Accordingly, some studies have already focused on perceptions of risk near the coastline. For example, Brody et al. 
 <xref rid="pone.0103180-Brody2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[37]</xref> showed in a U.S. study that risk from climate change is perceived to be significantly lower for respondents located farther away from the coastline. Indeed, among the other geo-physical variables considered in this study (e.g., relative elevation, sea-level rise/inundation risk, temperature trend), distance to the coast had the strongest association with climate change risk perception. Further, in another national sample of U.S. residents, Brody et al. 
 <xref rid="pone.0103180-Brody1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">[29]</xref> found proximity to the coast to be significantly and positively related to willingness to reduce personal emissions.
</p>
