<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In a recent paper, Tayleur et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0184275.ref021" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>] analyzed changes in the CTI of bird communities across Sweden and controlled for habitat type using a land cover map, but they did not control for any effects of 
 <italic class="italic">change</italic> in habitat type, probably due to a general lack of long-term annual land cover data. Similarly, other proposed climate change indicators, such as the climate impact indicator [
 <xref rid="pone.0184275.ref022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>], also do not consider potential effects of other drivers. We propose a novel model-based approach that uses regression to separate the effects of temperature preference from the effects of other species attributes, such as habitat preference, on population abundances, before the CTI is calculated. First, we use a simulation model to highlight the problem of the original CTI approach and to show how our proposed approach overcomes this. We then apply our approach to long-term population datasets of breeding birds in Denmark and demersal marine fish in the North Sea. Previous analysis indicates that abundance trends of European birds and North Sea fish are affected by climate change [
 <xref rid="pone.0184275.ref005" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0184275.ref023" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>] but in both cases additional factors are likely involved (agricultural intensification for birds; exploitation by fisheries for fish) and these factors may additionally affect the trends in the CTI. We compare the temporal trends in the CTI with the original and our new approach to examine the consequences for the interpretation of species response to climate change. Although we focus our approach on the CTI, we note that in fact it could be applied to other indices based on community weighted means, such as the community specialization index [
 <xref rid="pone.0184275.ref024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>] or community weighted nutrient preferences [
 <xref rid="pone.0184275.ref025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>].
</p>
