<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par30" class="p">To summarize the role of climate in F
 <sc class="sc">orClim</sc>, climatic conditions and annual weather variability directly control tree establishment (in addition to other factors), strongly influence tree growth, and have an indirect effect on survival (i.e., via growth). Regarding growth, cold and dry conditions limit individual productivity (with an intensity that depends on species characteristics – see Table 
 <xref rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" class="xref">S2</xref>), whereas trees are close to their optimal growth under moist and warm conditions (obviously without taking into account the effect other factors such as light availability across the canopy). A more detailed description of the model and its development over time can be found in several publications
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" class="xref">53</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" class="xref">54</xref>
 </sup>. F
 <sc class="sc">orClim</sc> has evolved from a simulator of forests in the Swiss Alps to a general model that is applicable to temperate forests of central Europe
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" class="xref">53</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" class="xref">58</xref>
 </sup>, eastern North America
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" class="xref">58</xref>
 </sup>, the Pacific Northwest of the US
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" class="xref">59</xref>
 </sup>, northeastern China
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" class="xref">60</xref>
 </sup> and the Colorado Front Range of the Rocky Mountains
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" class="xref">61</xref>
 </sup>. To our knowledge 
 <sc class="sc">ForClim</sc> is a forest succession model that has been demonstrated to be applicable “out of the box”, 
 <italic class="italic">i.e</italic>. without any re-parameterization, across widely different climates while still keeping a species resolution, which supports its generality. Note that using a succession model to explore the diversity-productivity relationship differs from previous modelling studies
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" class="xref">62</xref>
 </sup> because: (i) we used a multi-trait model that takes into account observed trade-offs in species biology (e.g. growth/shade tolerance), as the F
 <sc class="sc">orClim</sc> parameters are mostly derived from observed/measured traits; and (ii) the model has originally not been developed to study diversity-productivity questions, and can thus be viewed as an independent tool, as illustrated in former studies
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" class="xref">29</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">30</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
