<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div class="ack" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <div class="title">Acknowledgments</div>
 <p>We are grateful to all scientists and support staff involved in the collection and analysis of samples, both at sea and on shore, especially K. Speer, chief scientist of the I06S line occupied as part of the U.S. CLIVAR repeat hydrography program, and H. Venables and P. Abrahamsen for their work on the ANDREX cruises. We are grateful to two anonymous reviewers, whose contributions improved the quality of this manuscript. 
  <span class="bold">Funding:</span> The ANDREX project was supported by the National Environmental Research Council (NE/E01366X/1 and NE/E013538/1). G.A.M. acknowledges support from NERC, the U.K. Met Office, and a Radcliffe-Graduate scholarship from University College, Oxford. A.C.N.G. acknowledges the support of a Philip Leverhulme Prize, the Royal Society, and the Wolfson Foundation. M.P.M. acknowledges support from NERC via awards NE/N018095/1 and NE/E013368/1. P.J.B. acknowledges support from NERC via award NE/N018095/1. 
  <span class="bold">Author contributions:</span> G.A.M. performed the analysis (except those aspects noted below), produced the figures, and wrote the manuscript. A.C.N.G. conceived the experimental approach and contributed to the writing of the manuscript. P.J.B. assisted with carbon budget calculations and performed the satellite-based primary production calculations. L.J. evaluated the original inversion-derived velocity field. S.B., D.C.E.B., M.H., M.P.M., and S.T.-V. were all involved in the original data collection. All authors contributed to revising draft manuscripts. 
  <span class="bold">Competing interests:</span> The authors declare that they have no competing interests, financial or otherwise. 
  <span class="bold">Data and materials availability:</span> Data for the Weddell Gyre sections are available from the CLIVAR and Carbon Hydrographic Data Office (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://cchdo.ucsd.edu" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://cchdo.ucsd.edu</span>). SOSE data are available from 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://sose.ucsd.edu" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://sose.ucsd.edu</span>. Ocean color data (used in 
  <a rid="F1" ref-type="fig" href="#F1">Fig. 1</a>) are available from 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.esa-oceancolour-cci.org" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.esa-oceancolour-cci.org</span>. MATLAB scripts for reproducing the analysis are available at 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://github.com/gmacgilchrist" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://github.com/gmacgilchrist</span> or by request to the author.
 </p>
</div>
