<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Assessing the drivers of horizontal carbon transport</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The drivers of the carbon enrichment experienced by CDW as it circulates horizontally through the Weddell Gyre can be assessed with the use of a carbon partitioning approach, in which the properties of the carbon field along the Gyre’s edge are attributed to a range of physical and biogeochemical processes (see Materials and Methods) (
  <a rid="R24" ref-type="bibr" href="#R24">
   <span class="italic">24</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R25" ref-type="bibr" href="#R25">
   <span class="italic">25</span>
  </a>). The carbon concentration contributed by the remineralization of organic matter (C
  <sub>soft</sub>) is overlain on the distribution of C
  <sub>T</sub> in 
  <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2E</a> (pink contours at 80, 90, and 100 μmol kg
  <span class="sup">−1</span>, with progressively increasing thickness). Within CDW, the coincident patterns of C
  <sub>Τ</sub> and C
  <sub>soft</sub> indicate that the enrichment of carbon observed across the center of the northern section relative to carbon levels in the ASF at the Gyre’s eastern boundary is caused by the remineralization of organic matter. By contrast, the other constituents of the carbon partitioning formulation (fig. S2) do not follow this pattern. This pool of biologically enriched carbon concentration in CDW has been consistently observed in the Gyre’s center (
  <a rid="R26" ref-type="bibr" href="#R26">
   <span class="italic">26</span>
  </a>), where sinking organic matter from biological production in the central gyre region has been documented to remineralize at relatively shallow depths (
  <a rid="R27" ref-type="bibr" href="#R27">
   <span class="italic">27</span>
  </a>), leading to an accumulation of carbon in CDW within the Gyre’s inner reaches. The relevance of this mechanism to explain our observations is reaffirmed by the correspondence of the maximum in C
  <sub>soft</sub> along the northern section (
  <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2E</a>) with a minimum in chlorofluorocarbon-11 (fig. S3), a tracer of recent atmospheric contact. This supports the conclusion that the elevated levels of C
  <sub>T</sub> at the Gyre’s northern boundary arise from biological processes operating in the central region of the Gyre, as opposed to being a signature that was transported from the well-ventilated shelf-sea waters along the Gyre’s rim.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We quantify the contribution of the biological pump to carbon uptake in the Weddell Gyre by examining the transport of each carbon constituent across the region’s boundaries. The horizontal components of these transports (having again applied the decomposition of 
  <a ref-type="disp-formula" rid="E2" href="#E2">Eq. 2</a>) are shown in 
  <a rid="F3" ref-type="fig" href="#F3">Fig. 3C</a>. As expected from the preceding discussion, the export of carbon from the Gyre via the horizontal circulation of CDW is found to be overwhelmingly associated with the transport of C
  <sub>soft</sub> out of the region. This contribution to the regional biological carbon pump (~80 Tg C year
  <span class="sup">−1</span>, summing 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="m11" class="math">
    <div class="mrow">
     <div class="mrow">
      <div class="msubsup">
       <span class="mi">T</span>
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">C</span>
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">h</span>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div> for C
  <sub>soft</sub> in the three layers of CDW) compares favorably with independent estimates derived from upper-ocean nutrient budgets (~110 Tg C year
  <span class="sup">−1</span>) (
  <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">
   <span class="italic">17</span>
  </a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The prevalence of open-ocean biological processes in the drawdown of carbon in the Weddell Gyre is somewhat unexpected in light of the more modest chlorophyll-a concentrations observed in the Gyre interior relative to that near the Antarctic continental shelves (
  <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2A</a>)—likely the result of greater iron limitation in the central region (
  <a rid="R18" ref-type="bibr" href="#R18">
   <span class="italic">18</span>
  </a>). However, satellite-derived estimates of net primary production integrated across the Weddell Gyre (120 to 190 Tg C year
  <span class="sup">−1</span>; see Materials and Methods) indicate that as much as 80% occurs in the vast central gyre region. Sinking and remineralization of this organic matter can, therefore, completely account for the export of C
  <sub>soft</sub> in CDW, assuming sinking efficiencies within the measured range (
  <a rid="R27" ref-type="bibr" href="#R27">
   <span class="italic">27</span>
  </a>). Together, these results suggest that open-ocean primary production is more effective at carbon drawdown than shelf-sea biological processes, making it the primary driver of regional carbon sequestration.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Cyclonic gyres such as the Weddell Gyre are a dominant feature of the horizontal circulation in the subpolar Southern Ocean. As noted above, horizontal carbon export from the Weddell Gyre arises from the accumulation of carbon within the recirculating waters of the central gyre. Hence, it is highly plausible that the same mechanism operates in the other cyclonic gyre systems of the subpolar Southern Ocean, such as that spanning the Ross Sea. This expectation is endorsed by biogeochemical measurements along a section crossing the Ross Gyre, for which application of our carbon partitioning approach reveals the occurrence of a pool of elevated C
  <sub>soft</sub> within CDW with concentrations comparable to and exceeding those in the Weddell Gyre (fig. S4). While a circumpolar quantification of horizontal carbon transports is not possible at present, it is reasonable to expect that the mechanism of carbon uptake here identified in the Weddell Gyre will be relevant across the other cyclonic gyres that make up the subpolar Southern Ocean.
 </p>
</sec>
