<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Carbon partitioning formulation</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Carbon concentration in a water parcel can be separated into constituent parts using coincidentally measured hydrographic and chemical data (
  <a rid="R24" ref-type="bibr" href="#R24">
   <span class="italic">24</span>
  </a>). We provide a summary of the partitioning here and refer to MacGilchrist 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span> (
  <a rid="R25" ref-type="bibr" href="#R25">
   <span class="italic">25</span>
  </a>) for full details. The primary separation is between preformed carbon—the concentration present in the water parcel on leaving the surface—and regenerated carbon—carbon added to the water parcel since leaving the surface ocean. The carbon partitioning is written as
  <div id="E3" class="disp-formula">
   <div id="m12" class="math">
    <div class="mrow">
     <div class="mrow">
      <div class="msub">
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">C</span>
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">T</span>
      </div>
      <span class="mo">=</span>
      <div class="munder">
       <div class="mrow">
        <div accentunder="true" class="munder">
         <div class="mrow">
          <div class="msubsup">
           <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">C</span>
           <span class="mtext">sat</span>
           <span class="mtext">pi</span>
          </div>
          <span class="mo">+</span>
          <div class="mover">
           <div class="mrow">
            <div accent="true" class="mover">
             <div class="mrow">
              <div class="msubsup">
               <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">C</span>
               <span class="mtext">sat</span>
               <span class="mtext">ant</span>
              </div>
              <span class="mo">+</span>
              <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">Δ</span>
              <span class="mi">C</span>
             </div>
             <span stretchy="true" class="mo">⏞</span>
            </div>
           </div>
           <div class="msub">
            <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">C</span>
            <span class="mtext">res</span>
           </div>
          </div>
         </div>
         <span stretchy="true" class="mo">⏟</span>
        </div>
       </div>
       <span class="mtext">preformed</span>
      </div>
      <span class="mo">+</span>
      <div class="munder">
       <div class="mrow">
        <div accentunder="true" class="munder">
         <div class="mrow">
          <div class="msub">
           <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">C</span>
           <span class="mtext">soft</span>
          </div>
          <span class="mo">+</span>
          <div class="msub">
           <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">C</span>
           <span class="mtext">carb</span>
          </div>
         </div>
         <span stretchy="true" class="mo">⏟</span>
        </div>
       </div>
       <span class="mtext">regenerated</span>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
   <span class="label">(3)</span>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The saturated component (
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="m13" class="math">
    <div class="mrow">
     <div class="mrow">
      <div class="msubsup">
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">C</span>
       <span class="mtext">sat</span>
       <span class="mtext">pi</span>
      </div>
      <span class="mo">+</span>
      <div class="msubsup">
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">C</span>
       <span class="mtext">sat</span>
       <span class="mtext">ant</span>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div>) is a measure of the carbon concentration that would have been present in the water at the surface were it at equilibrium with the overlying atmosphere. It is separated into “preindustrial” and “anthropogenic” components to account for the changing levels of atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub> since the industrial revolution. The preindustrial saturated component, 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <div id="m14" class="math">
    <div class="mrow">
     <div class="mrow">
      <div class="msubsup">
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">C</span>
       <span class="mtext">sat</span>
       <span class="mtext">pi</span>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>
  </div>, is determined from potential temperature, salinity, and preformed alkalinity (see below) and was evaluated using the CO2SYS MATLAB program (
  <a rid="R42" ref-type="bibr" href="#R42">
   <span class="italic">42</span>
  </a>), assuming a preindustrial atmospheric CO
  <sub>2</sub> level of 278 ppm. We did not attempt to evaluate the anthropogenic saturated component directly but instead included it in a residual C
  <sub>res</sub> along with the disequilibrium component, ΔC, which accounts for the extent to which the water parcel was out of equilibrium with the overlying atmosphere when it left the surface ocean. The regenerated component comprises contributions from the remineralization of soft tissue organic matter, C
  <sub>soft</sub>, and the dissolution of hard shell carbonates, C
  <sub>carb</sub>. The soft tissue component is established from the apparent oxygen utilization (AOU), itself derived from an estimate of the preformed oxygen concentration: AOU = O
  <sub>2</sub> − O
  <sub>2,pre</sub>. We used a carbon-to-oxygen ratio of 117:−170 (
  <a rid="R43" ref-type="bibr" href="#R43">
   <span class="italic">43</span>
  </a>). The dissolved carbonate contribution is established from the difference between the measured alkalinity and its preformed value—a function of the surface (upper 100 dbar) salinity-alkalinity relationship (fig. S5). The primary uncertainties in the carbon partitioning formulation relate to the estimation of regenerated carbon and nutrients, both in the necessity to assume a level of oxygen saturation and in the prescription of fixed stoichiometric ratios. In addition, the salinity-alkalinity relationship in the surface ocean can vary widely (
  <a rid="R44" ref-type="bibr" href="#R44">
   <span class="italic">44</span>
  </a>). We adopted the simplest approximations possible (100% oxygen saturation, standard stoichiometric ratios, and the local salinity-alkalinity relationship), accepting that there could be quantitative differences in the results if other values were used.
 </p>
</sec>
