<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Circulation and carbon uptake in the Weddell Gyre</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Using sections of hydrographic stations that enclose the Weddell Gyre (
  <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2A</a>), the circulation in the region was quantified using inverse techniques (
  <a rid="R11" ref-type="bibr" href="#R11">
   <span class="italic">11</span>
  </a>). The horizontal circulation (
  <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2B</a>; presented as a cumulative sum moving clockwise around the section, with negative values indicating export of water from the region) is dominated by the cyclonic Gyre, characterized by a volume transport of 40 to 50 Sv (1 Sv = 10
  <span class="sup">6</span> m
  <span class="sup">3</span> s
  <span class="sup">−1</span>). There is also a substantial horizontal throughflow of 13 ± 4 Sv, with water entering the region primarily across the eastern boundary, in the Antarctic Slope Front (ASF; 
  <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2B</a>, station pairs 110 to 123), and leaving across the northern section (station pairs 50 to 75). The vertical circulation in the Gyre (
  <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2C</a>) exhibits the expected dual-overturning cell structure, with water imported in mid-depth layers (CDW and upper layers of AABW) and exported within both the surface waters and lower layers of AABW. Combining the inversion-derived velocity field with coincident measurements of total dissolved inorganic carbon (C
  <sub>T</sub>; 
  <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2E</a>) yields a residual transport of −53 ± 10 Tg C year
  <span class="sup">−1</span> directed out of the Gyre (
  <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">
   <span class="italic">17</span>
  </a>) that is representative of a multi-annual, summertime mean state (see Materials and Methods). The residual transport reflects the regional air-sea carbon flux, indicating that the Weddell Gyre is an important summertime sink of carbon from the atmosphere, with an estimated air-sea CO
  <sub>2</sub> uptake rate of 58 ± 10 Tg C year
  <span class="sup">−1</span> after accounting for dissolved inorganic carbon accumulation [through the uptake of anthropogenic carbon (
  <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">
   <span class="italic">17</span>
  </a>)] within the box. This uptake rate is consistent with that diagnosed from two other approaches (
  <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">
   <span class="italic">17</span>
  </a>), as well as with estimates from previous studies (
  <a rid="R10" ref-type="bibr" href="#R10">
   <span class="italic">10</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R19" ref-type="bibr" href="#R19">
   <span class="italic">19</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R21" ref-type="bibr" href="#R21">
   <span class="italic">21</span>
  </a>). These studies show that summertime uptake overcomes wintertime outgassing to sustain the Weddell Gyre as a substantial sink of CO
  <sub>2</sub> from the atmosphere over an annual cycle (
  <a rid="R10" ref-type="bibr" href="#R10">
   <span class="italic">10</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">
   <span class="italic">17</span>
  </a>).
 </p>
 <div id="F2" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Circulation and carbon in the Weddell Gyre.</div>
   <p>(
    <span class="bold">A</span>) Location of the Weddell Gyre and hydrographic sections. On the right panel, contours of mean dynamic topography (MDT) are plotted, revealing the cyclonic gyre circulation (contours every 0.1 m). These data are the June-July-August mean in 2005, taken from the Southern Ocean State Estimate (
    <a rid="R41" ref-type="bibr" href="#R41">
     <span class="italic">41</span>
    </a>). The 2008 annual mean chlorophyll-a concentration, derived from satellite measurements of ocean color, is also plotted (green shading) (
    <a rid="R47" ref-type="bibr" href="#R47">
     <span class="italic">47</span>
    </a>). (
    <span class="bold">B</span>) Cumulative horizontal circulation around the boundary of the Weddell Gyre, derived from the inversion (
    <a rid="R11" ref-type="bibr" href="#R11">
     <span class="italic">11</span>
    </a>). Volume transports for each station pair are integrated from left to right. Note the reversed direction of the 
    <span class="italic">y</span> axis such that export is upward. (
    <span class="bold">C</span>) Overturning circulation in the Weddell Gyre, derived from the inversion, in neutral density layers. Bars correspond to the volume transport in each layer ([v]
    <span class="italic">
     <span class="sup">i</span>
    </span>). The center location and thickness of each bar correspond to the mean depth and thickness of that layer. Horizontal dotted lines denote the interfaces between major water masses. (
    <span class="bold">D</span>) Area-weighted mean carbon concentration in each layer 
    <div class="inline-formula">
     <div id="m1" class="math">
      <div class="mrow">
       <div class="mrow">
        <span stretchy="false" class="mo">(</span>
        <div class="msup">
         <div class="mrow">
          <div accent="true" class="mover">
           <div class="msub">
            <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">C</span>
            <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">T</span>
           </div>
           <span stretchy="true" class="mo">¯</span>
          </div>
         </div>
         <span class="mi">i</span>
        </div>
        <span stretchy="false" class="mo">)</span>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>. (
    <span class="bold">E</span>) Carbon concentration, C
    <sub>T</sub>, around the Weddell Gyre. As for (C) and (D), dotted lines denote the interfaces between the major water masses. Pink contours correspond to the concentrations (80, 90, and 100 μmol kg
    <span class="sup">−1</span>) of the remineralized organic matter component (C
    <sub>soft</sub>) of the carbon partitioning formulation (see Materials and Methods), with thicker contours denoting greater concentration.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="aav6410-F2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
