<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="materials|methods" disp-level="1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">MATERIALS AND METHODS</div>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hydrographic and biogeochemical data</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data were collected on three oceanographic transects, plotted in 
   <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2A</a>, that took place over a period of 2 years between 2008 and 2010. Two of the cruises were conducted as part of the Antarctic Deep Water Rates of Export (ANDREX) project in December 2008 to January 2009 and March to April 2010, from the Antarctic Peninsula to 30°E around the northern rim of the Weddell Gyre (
   <a rid="R36" ref-type="bibr" href="#R36">
    <span class="italic">36</span>
   </a>, 
   <a rid="R37" ref-type="bibr" href="#R37">
    <span class="italic">37</span>
   </a>). A third cruise was completed as part of the U.S. CLIVAR (Climate Variability and Predictability) program in February to March 2008 along the quasi-meridional I6S section at 30°E (
   <a rid="R38" ref-type="bibr" href="#R38">
    <span class="italic">38</span>
   </a>). Temperature and salinity were measured in 2-dbar pressure bins across the full depth range at each station. Water was collected at an array of depths for onboard measurement of a number of chemical species. Relevant to this study are total dissolved inorganic carbon, total alkalinity, dissolved oxygen, chlorofluorocarbon-11, silicate, and phosphate. For the budget analysis, bottle measurements were optimally interpolated (
   <a rid="R39" ref-type="bibr" href="#R39">
    <span class="italic">39</span>
   </a>) onto the hydrographic data points. Full details of the procedure for hydrographic and chemical measurements can be found in the cruise reports, as well as in the studies of Jullion 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span> (
   <a rid="R11" ref-type="bibr" href="#R11">
    <span class="italic">11</span>
   </a>) and Brown 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span> (
   <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">
    <span class="italic">17</span>
   </a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Inverse model solution</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The velocity field used in this analysis was derived by Jullion 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span> (
   <a rid="R11" ref-type="bibr" href="#R11">
    <span class="italic">11</span>
   </a>) via a box inversion. Box inverse modeling facilitates the estimation of large-scale ocean circulation from observations, within a theoretical framework in which conservation of mass, heat, salt, and any other measured tracers can be imposed. Observations of potential temperature, salinity, and pressure, from which potential density is calculated, are used to derive the vertical shear of the cross-section velocity through thermal wind balance. The box inverse method allows the estimation of reference velocities (for each hydrographic station pair) that achieve conservation of heat, freshwater, and mass (equivalently temperature, salinity, and volume, assuming incompressibility) across the full depth and within each of the model layers, with the minimal perturbation (in a least-squares sense) to an a priori estimate. Jullion 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span> (
   <a rid="R11" ref-type="bibr" href="#R11">
    <span class="italic">11</span>
   </a>) used 10 vertical layers based on neutral density (
   <a rid="R40" ref-type="bibr" href="#R40">
    <span class="italic">40</span>
   </a>), chosen to delineate the major water masses in the Weddell Gyre. In this inversion, an additional constraint was placed on the net volume and salinity transport of the ACC (0 ± 5 Sv for each), which crosses the corner of the box between stations 82 and 111, to improve the solution. The solution also accounts for the transport of volume, temperature, and freshwater by eddying motions. These terms were derived from time averaging of the Southern Ocean State Estimate (
   <a rid="R41" ref-type="bibr" href="#R41">
    <span class="italic">41</span>
   </a>) at the location of the hydrographic sections. In this study, we applied a small correction to the solution of Jullion 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span> (
   <a rid="R11" ref-type="bibr" href="#R11">
    <span class="italic">11</span>
   </a>) to impose full-depth conservation of mass as opposed to volume (the previous solution assumed incompressibility). In applying this correction, we constrained the full-depth carbon transport so that it remained consistent with that of Brown 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span> (
   <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">
    <span class="italic">17</span>
   </a>). The correction invoked minimal change in the velocity field, but mass conservation is important for the decomposition of the contributions to carbon transport from the overturning and horizontal circulations.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Uncertainties in carbon transports were determined using Monte Carlo simulations of the inversion-derived velocity field and carbon concentration section. Reference velocities for the inversion were perturbed on the basis of 5-day variability of the velocity field in the Southern Ocean State Estimate (
   <a rid="R41" ref-type="bibr" href="#R41">
    <span class="italic">41</span>
   </a>). Carbon concentrations were perturbed within measurement uncertainty (±2 to 3 μmol kg
   <span class="sup">−1</span>) (
   <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">
    <span class="italic">17</span>
   </a>). The comparatively small uncertainty in the full-depth integral (relative to that of individual layers; see 
   <a rid="F3" ref-type="fig" href="#F3">Fig. 3A</a>, taking note of the different 
   <span class="italic">x</span>-axis ranges) arises from the integral constraints (full-depth mass and salt conservation) applied in the inverse model, which establish statistical dependence of the layer-wise uncertainties. For example, when the sensitivity of the solution is tested to increased inflow (within local uncertainty) in a shallow layer, there must (by conservation of mass and/or salinity) be a corresponding increase of outflow in a deeper layer. Further details can be found in the study of Jullion 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span> (
   <a rid="R11" ref-type="bibr" href="#R11">
    <span class="italic">11</span>
   </a>) and references therein.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Despite being derived from “snapshot” observations, the velocity field is representative of a multi-annual mean state. This follows from the fact that the inverse model was designed to have uncertainties that represent deviations from a long-term mean, as discussed extensively by Jullion 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span> (
   <a rid="R11" ref-type="bibr" href="#R11">
    <span class="italic">11</span>
   </a>). Because of the seasonality of upper ocean biogeochemistry, carbon transports in the surface water and winter water layers are representative of a summertime mean state, described in detail by Brown 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span> (
   <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">
    <span class="italic">17</span>
   </a>). Biogeochemical properties in intermediate and deep layers are stable over the seasonal cycle such that their transports represent a long-term, annual-mean signal. The representativeness of our carbon measurements (and resultant carbon transports) was assessed by Brown 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span> (
   <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">
    <span class="italic">17</span>
   </a>) by substituting the modern observations in the inverse model with an alternative, temporally separated section of measurements, thereby directly testing the effect of interannual variability in the carbon field. The carbon transports were found to be robust to such changes, implying that for temporally separated data of the same season, it is the circulation scheme that ultimately sets the state of the carbon residual.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Carbon partitioning formulation</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Carbon concentration in a water parcel can be separated into constituent parts using coincidentally measured hydrographic and chemical data (
   <a rid="R24" ref-type="bibr" href="#R24">
    <span class="italic">24</span>
   </a>). We provide a summary of the partitioning here and refer to MacGilchrist 
   <span class="italic">et al.</span> (
   <a rid="R25" ref-type="bibr" href="#R25">
    <span class="italic">25</span>
   </a>) for full details. The primary separation is between preformed carbon—the concentration present in the water parcel on leaving the surface—and regenerated carbon—carbon added to the water parcel since leaving the surface ocean. The carbon partitioning is written as
   <div id="E3" class="disp-formula">
    <div id="m12" class="math">
     <div class="mrow">
      <div class="mrow">
       <div class="msub">
        <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">C</span>
        <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">T</span>
       </div>
       <span class="mo">=</span>
       <div class="munder">
        <div class="mrow">
         <div accentunder="true" class="munder">
          <div class="mrow">
           <div class="msubsup">
            <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">C</span>
            <span class="mtext">sat</span>
            <span class="mtext">pi</span>
           </div>
           <span class="mo">+</span>
           <div class="mover">
            <div class="mrow">
             <div accent="true" class="mover">
              <div class="mrow">
               <div class="msubsup">
                <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">C</span>
                <span class="mtext">sat</span>
                <span class="mtext">ant</span>
               </div>
               <span class="mo">+</span>
               <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">Δ</span>
               <span class="mi">C</span>
              </div>
              <span stretchy="true" class="mo">⏞</span>
             </div>
            </div>
            <div class="msub">
             <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">C</span>
             <span class="mtext">res</span>
            </div>
           </div>
          </div>
          <span stretchy="true" class="mo">⏟</span>
         </div>
        </div>
        <span class="mtext">preformed</span>
       </div>
       <span class="mo">+</span>
       <div class="munder">
        <div class="mrow">
         <div accentunder="true" class="munder">
          <div class="mrow">
           <div class="msub">
            <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">C</span>
            <span class="mtext">soft</span>
           </div>
           <span class="mo">+</span>
           <div class="msub">
            <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">C</span>
            <span class="mtext">carb</span>
           </div>
          </div>
          <span stretchy="true" class="mo">⏟</span>
         </div>
        </div>
        <span class="mtext">regenerated</span>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
    <span class="label">(3)</span>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The saturated component (
   <div class="inline-formula">
    <div id="m13" class="math">
     <div class="mrow">
      <div class="mrow">
       <div class="msubsup">
        <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">C</span>
        <span class="mtext">sat</span>
        <span class="mtext">pi</span>
       </div>
       <span class="mo">+</span>
       <div class="msubsup">
        <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">C</span>
        <span class="mtext">sat</span>
        <span class="mtext">ant</span>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>) is a measure of the carbon concentration that would have been present in the water at the surface were it at equilibrium with the overlying atmosphere. It is separated into “preindustrial” and “anthropogenic” components to account for the changing levels of atmospheric CO
   <sub>2</sub> since the industrial revolution. The preindustrial saturated component, 
   <div class="inline-formula">
    <div id="m14" class="math">
     <div class="mrow">
      <div class="mrow">
       <div class="msubsup">
        <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">C</span>
        <span class="mtext">sat</span>
        <span class="mtext">pi</span>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div>, is determined from potential temperature, salinity, and preformed alkalinity (see below) and was evaluated using the CO2SYS MATLAB program (
   <a rid="R42" ref-type="bibr" href="#R42">
    <span class="italic">42</span>
   </a>), assuming a preindustrial atmospheric CO
   <sub>2</sub> level of 278 ppm. We did not attempt to evaluate the anthropogenic saturated component directly but instead included it in a residual C
   <sub>res</sub> along with the disequilibrium component, ΔC, which accounts for the extent to which the water parcel was out of equilibrium with the overlying atmosphere when it left the surface ocean. The regenerated component comprises contributions from the remineralization of soft tissue organic matter, C
   <sub>soft</sub>, and the dissolution of hard shell carbonates, C
   <sub>carb</sub>. The soft tissue component is established from the apparent oxygen utilization (AOU), itself derived from an estimate of the preformed oxygen concentration: AOU = O
   <sub>2</sub> − O
   <sub>2,pre</sub>. We used a carbon-to-oxygen ratio of 117:−170 (
   <a rid="R43" ref-type="bibr" href="#R43">
    <span class="italic">43</span>
   </a>). The dissolved carbonate contribution is established from the difference between the measured alkalinity and its preformed value—a function of the surface (upper 100 dbar) salinity-alkalinity relationship (fig. S5). The primary uncertainties in the carbon partitioning formulation relate to the estimation of regenerated carbon and nutrients, both in the necessity to assume a level of oxygen saturation and in the prescription of fixed stoichiometric ratios. In addition, the salinity-alkalinity relationship in the surface ocean can vary widely (
   <a rid="R44" ref-type="bibr" href="#R44">
    <span class="italic">44</span>
   </a>). We adopted the simplest approximations possible (100% oxygen saturation, standard stoichiometric ratios, and the local salinity-alkalinity relationship), accepting that there could be quantitative differences in the results if other values were used.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Satellite-derived net primary production</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Monthly estimates of net primary production were retrieved at 1/6° × 1/6° latitude-longitude resolution across the area enclosed by the ANDREX-I6S Weddell Gyre sections between 2003 and 2014 from the Ocean Productivity website (
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://science.oregonstate.edu/ocean.productivity/index.php" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://science.oregonstate.edu/ocean.productivity/index.php</span>). Net primary production was calculated from chlorophyll-a, sea surface temperature (both derived from the Aqua-MODIS satellite data), and photosynthetically active radiation (derived from the SeaWiFS satellite data). Calculations were done using three independent models: the standard and Eppley applications of the Vertical General Productivity Model (
   <a rid="R45" ref-type="bibr" href="#R45">
    <span class="italic">45</span>
   </a>) and the Carbon-based Production Model (
   <a rid="R46" ref-type="bibr" href="#R46">
    <span class="italic">46</span>
   </a>). The value presented in the main text is the time-mean net primary production for the full time series, with the range representing the spread from the different model calculations.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
