<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="introduction" disp-level="1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">INTRODUCTION</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The subpolar Southern Ocean, south of the Antarctic Circumpolar Current (ACC), is arguably the most important region on Earth for the cycling of carbon on centennial to millennial time scales (
  <a rid="R1" ref-type="bibr" href="#R1">
   <span class="italic">1</span>
  </a>). Atmospheric carbon dioxide (CO
  <sub>2</sub>) exhibits strong sensitivity to the physical and biogeochemical dynamics of the region in paleoclimatic observations (
  <a rid="R2" ref-type="bibr" href="#R2">
   <span class="italic">2</span>
  </a>), low-complexity box models (
  <a rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" href="#R3">
   <span class="italic">3</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R4" ref-type="bibr" href="#R4">
   <span class="italic">4</span>
  </a>), and fully three-dimensional numerical simulations (
  <a rid="R5" ref-type="bibr" href="#R5">
   <span class="italic">5</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R6" ref-type="bibr" href="#R6">
   <span class="italic">6</span>
  </a>). Furthermore, in the present day, the regional uptake of anthropogenic carbon is a major contributor to its storage in the deep ocean (
  <a rid="R7" ref-type="bibr" href="#R7">
   <span class="italic">7</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R8" ref-type="bibr" href="#R8">
   <span class="italic">8</span>
  </a>). Consequently, understanding the dynamics and variability of the subpolar Southern Ocean carbon cycle, and the system’s susceptibility to change, is a fundamental challenge facing modern climate research.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The significance of the subpolar Southern Ocean in the global carbon cycle stems from its unique connection to the lower cell of the global overturning circulation (
  <a rid="R1" ref-type="bibr" href="#R1">
   <span class="italic">1</span>
  </a>). The vast carbon content of this lower cell, which occupies the deep and abyssal layers in most of the world ocean, is gradually built up by the remineralization of sinking organic matter (
  <a rid="R9" ref-type="bibr" href="#R9">
   <span class="italic">9</span>
  </a>), with some moderation by the slow upward mixing of carbon across the cell’s upper density interface associated with small-scale turbulence (
  <a rid="R6" ref-type="bibr" href="#R6">
   <span class="italic">6</span>
  </a>). In the subpolar Southern Ocean, the dense waters of the lower cell are exposed directly to the ocean’s surface layers, allowing their carbon to be rapidly exchanged with the atmosphere. The dynamics of the carbon cycle in the region thus determine the degree to which the large carbon pool of the lower cell is able to escape to the atmosphere—in effect, whether the lid of the lower cell is open (net outgassing) or closed (net uptake) (
  <a rid="R1" ref-type="bibr" href="#R1">
   <span class="italic">1</span>
  </a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Understanding of the subpolar Southern Ocean carbon cycle has traditionally been considered in terms of a two-dimensional latitude-depth framework, shown schematically in 
  <a rid="F1" ref-type="fig" href="#F1">Fig. 1</a>. This framework reflects the most conspicuous features of the regional circulation, which is characterized by intense water mass transformations and vertical overturning. Water transported across the ACC in mid-depth layers, known as Circumpolar Deep Water (CDW), is rich in dissolved inorganic carbon and is both upwelled to the surface through wind-driven divergence (
  <a rid="R10" ref-type="bibr" href="#R10">
   <span class="italic">10</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R11" ref-type="bibr" href="#R11">
   <span class="italic">11</span>
  </a>) and conveyed to the abyss through entrainment by dense waters cascading off the continental shelf, forming Antarctic Bottom Water (AABW) (
  <a rid="R11" ref-type="bibr" href="#R11">
   <span class="italic">11</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R12" ref-type="bibr" href="#R12">
   <span class="italic">12</span>
  </a>). Carbon stored within the inflowing CDW may thus be partly outgassed to the atmosphere or transferred to the deep ocean, making these water mass transformations potentially critical to the partitioning of carbon between the atmospheric and oceanic reservoirs. This overturning-centric perspective and, in particular, the transformation of CDW into AABW have traditionally underpinned investigations of the role of the Southern Ocean carbon cycle in global climate (
  <a rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" href="#R3">
   <span class="italic">3</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R6" ref-type="bibr" href="#R6">
   <span class="italic">6</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R13" ref-type="bibr" href="#R13">
   <span class="italic">13</span>
  </a>), while observational campaigns have largely focused on the areas of the most intense water mass transformations, biological activity, and sea-ice dynamics: the continental shelves around Antarctica (
  <a rid="R14" ref-type="bibr" href="#R14">
   <span class="italic">14</span>
  </a>–
  <a rid="R16" ref-type="bibr" href="#R16">
   <span class="italic">16</span>
  </a>).
 </p>
 <div id="F1" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Two-dimensional framework for the subpolar Southern Ocean carbon cycle.</div>
   <p>Schematic illustration of the conventional, two-dimensional, overturning-centric framework for the subpolar Southern Ocean carbon cycle. Dotted lines delineate surface water (SW), CDW, and upper and lower layers of AABW.</p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="aav6410-F1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Increasingly, key features of the subpolar Southern Ocean carbon cycle are being found to be inconsistent with this two-dimensional framework. Extensive observations of elevated concentrations of carbon in inflowing CDW relative to concentrations in outflowing surface waters and AABW (
  <a rid="R15" ref-type="bibr" href="#R15">
   <span class="italic">15</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">
   <span class="italic">17</span>
  </a>) imply that, in a two-dimensional frame, the region should be a net source of carbon to the atmosphere. This is at odds with a number of recent studies, based both on budget analyses and on in situ measurements of the carbonate system, which find the subpolar Southern Ocean to be an oceanic carbon sink (
  <a rid="R10" ref-type="bibr" href="#R10">
   <span class="italic">10</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R14" ref-type="bibr" href="#R14">
   <span class="italic">14</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R16" ref-type="bibr" href="#R16">
   <span class="italic">16</span>
  </a>–
  <a rid="R19" ref-type="bibr" href="#R19">
   <span class="italic">19</span>
  </a>). A possible explanation for this fundamental discrepancy is the role played by biogeochemical processes in the open ocean—that is to say, away from the shelf seas—and the regional horizontal circulation (
  <a rid="R20" ref-type="bibr" href="#R20">
   <span class="italic">20</span>
  </a>), which in the subpolar Southern Ocean is primarily characterized by large cyclonic gyres. In the present study, we test this proposition by considering the cycling of carbon in the Weddell Gyre, an important and representative region of the subpolar Southern Ocean with respect to water mass transformation (
  <a rid="R12" ref-type="bibr" href="#R12">
   <span class="italic">12</span>
  </a>) and carbon drawdown (
  <a rid="R7" ref-type="bibr" href="#R7">
   <span class="italic">7</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R10" ref-type="bibr" href="#R10">
   <span class="italic">10</span>
  </a>).
 </p>
</sec>
