<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hydrographic and biogeochemical data</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data were collected on three oceanographic transects, plotted in 
  <a rid="F2" ref-type="fig" href="#F2">Fig. 2A</a>, that took place over a period of 2 years between 2008 and 2010. Two of the cruises were conducted as part of the Antarctic Deep Water Rates of Export (ANDREX) project in December 2008 to January 2009 and March to April 2010, from the Antarctic Peninsula to 30°E around the northern rim of the Weddell Gyre (
  <a rid="R36" ref-type="bibr" href="#R36">
   <span class="italic">36</span>
  </a>, 
  <a rid="R37" ref-type="bibr" href="#R37">
   <span class="italic">37</span>
  </a>). A third cruise was completed as part of the U.S. CLIVAR (Climate Variability and Predictability) program in February to March 2008 along the quasi-meridional I6S section at 30°E (
  <a rid="R38" ref-type="bibr" href="#R38">
   <span class="italic">38</span>
  </a>). Temperature and salinity were measured in 2-dbar pressure bins across the full depth range at each station. Water was collected at an array of depths for onboard measurement of a number of chemical species. Relevant to this study are total dissolved inorganic carbon, total alkalinity, dissolved oxygen, chlorofluorocarbon-11, silicate, and phosphate. For the budget analysis, bottle measurements were optimally interpolated (
  <a rid="R39" ref-type="bibr" href="#R39">
   <span class="italic">39</span>
  </a>) onto the hydrographic data points. Full details of the procedure for hydrographic and chemical measurements can be found in the cruise reports, as well as in the studies of Jullion 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span> (
  <a rid="R11" ref-type="bibr" href="#R11">
   <span class="italic">11</span>
  </a>) and Brown 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span> (
  <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">
   <span class="italic">17</span>
  </a>).
 </p>
</sec>
