<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec disp-level="2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Inverse model solution</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The velocity field used in this analysis was derived by Jullion 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span> (
  <a rid="R11" ref-type="bibr" href="#R11">
   <span class="italic">11</span>
  </a>) via a box inversion. Box inverse modeling facilitates the estimation of large-scale ocean circulation from observations, within a theoretical framework in which conservation of mass, heat, salt, and any other measured tracers can be imposed. Observations of potential temperature, salinity, and pressure, from which potential density is calculated, are used to derive the vertical shear of the cross-section velocity through thermal wind balance. The box inverse method allows the estimation of reference velocities (for each hydrographic station pair) that achieve conservation of heat, freshwater, and mass (equivalently temperature, salinity, and volume, assuming incompressibility) across the full depth and within each of the model layers, with the minimal perturbation (in a least-squares sense) to an a priori estimate. Jullion 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span> (
  <a rid="R11" ref-type="bibr" href="#R11">
   <span class="italic">11</span>
  </a>) used 10 vertical layers based on neutral density (
  <a rid="R40" ref-type="bibr" href="#R40">
   <span class="italic">40</span>
  </a>), chosen to delineate the major water masses in the Weddell Gyre. In this inversion, an additional constraint was placed on the net volume and salinity transport of the ACC (0 ± 5 Sv for each), which crosses the corner of the box between stations 82 and 111, to improve the solution. The solution also accounts for the transport of volume, temperature, and freshwater by eddying motions. These terms were derived from time averaging of the Southern Ocean State Estimate (
  <a rid="R41" ref-type="bibr" href="#R41">
   <span class="italic">41</span>
  </a>) at the location of the hydrographic sections. In this study, we applied a small correction to the solution of Jullion 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span> (
  <a rid="R11" ref-type="bibr" href="#R11">
   <span class="italic">11</span>
  </a>) to impose full-depth conservation of mass as opposed to volume (the previous solution assumed incompressibility). In applying this correction, we constrained the full-depth carbon transport so that it remained consistent with that of Brown 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span> (
  <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">
   <span class="italic">17</span>
  </a>). The correction invoked minimal change in the velocity field, but mass conservation is important for the decomposition of the contributions to carbon transport from the overturning and horizontal circulations.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Uncertainties in carbon transports were determined using Monte Carlo simulations of the inversion-derived velocity field and carbon concentration section. Reference velocities for the inversion were perturbed on the basis of 5-day variability of the velocity field in the Southern Ocean State Estimate (
  <a rid="R41" ref-type="bibr" href="#R41">
   <span class="italic">41</span>
  </a>). Carbon concentrations were perturbed within measurement uncertainty (±2 to 3 μmol kg
  <span class="sup">−1</span>) (
  <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">
   <span class="italic">17</span>
  </a>). The comparatively small uncertainty in the full-depth integral (relative to that of individual layers; see 
  <a rid="F3" ref-type="fig" href="#F3">Fig. 3A</a>, taking note of the different 
  <span class="italic">x</span>-axis ranges) arises from the integral constraints (full-depth mass and salt conservation) applied in the inverse model, which establish statistical dependence of the layer-wise uncertainties. For example, when the sensitivity of the solution is tested to increased inflow (within local uncertainty) in a shallow layer, there must (by conservation of mass and/or salinity) be a corresponding increase of outflow in a deeper layer. Further details can be found in the study of Jullion 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span> (
  <a rid="R11" ref-type="bibr" href="#R11">
   <span class="italic">11</span>
  </a>) and references therein.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Despite being derived from “snapshot” observations, the velocity field is representative of a multi-annual mean state. This follows from the fact that the inverse model was designed to have uncertainties that represent deviations from a long-term mean, as discussed extensively by Jullion 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span> (
  <a rid="R11" ref-type="bibr" href="#R11">
   <span class="italic">11</span>
  </a>). Because of the seasonality of upper ocean biogeochemistry, carbon transports in the surface water and winter water layers are representative of a summertime mean state, described in detail by Brown 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span> (
  <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">
   <span class="italic">17</span>
  </a>). Biogeochemical properties in intermediate and deep layers are stable over the seasonal cycle such that their transports represent a long-term, annual-mean signal. The representativeness of our carbon measurements (and resultant carbon transports) was assessed by Brown 
  <span class="italic">et al.</span> (
  <a rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" href="#R17">
   <span class="italic">17</span>
  </a>) by substituting the modern observations in the inverse model with an alternative, temporally separated section of measurements, thereby directly testing the effect of interannual variability in the carbon field. The carbon transports were found to be robust to such changes, implying that for temporally separated data of the same season, it is the circulation scheme that ultimately sets the state of the carbon residual.
 </p>
</sec>
