<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">DNA samples were then shipped to Floragenex, Inc. (Eugene, OR, USA) for RAD library preparation, Illumina sequencing, and bioinformatic processing. Briefly, libraries were prepared based on the genome size of this species (Tavares, Carvalho, Aparecida, &amp; Soares, 
 <xref rid="eva12794-bib-0078" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>), digesting genomic DNA with the 
 <italic class="italic">SgrAI</italic> restriction enzyme. The resulting fragments were tagged with individual barcodes, which were then multiplexed and sequenced using 100‐bp single‐end methodology on the HiSeq 2000 platform (Illumina). Libraries were created at the same time and ran on the same sequencing run on two different lanes. Total number of generated reads per individual ranged from ~550,000 to 2.3 million. Samples were then demultiplexed and barcode sequences trimmed to result in final fragment lengths of 92 bp. Quality filtering was done in SAMtools during the genotyping stages, and coverage was limited to loci having less than 500× to limit the incidence of possible contaminants. Stacks was then used to cluster loci from a single individual and generate a RAD reference, allowing two haplotypes from each locus. The de novo clustering of sequences into RAD tags was performed using VELVET (version 1.2.10), considering a minimum cluster depth of 5 and maximum of 1,500, a maximum number of two haplotypes per cluster, and a maximum of three variants per cluster. SNP calling was performed using SAMtools (version 0.1.16), and loci harboring SNPs were included in the final genotype (VCF) table if they had at least 6× individual sequence coverage over at least 75% of the population, individual per locus genotype quality scores of at least 10, a minimum FASTQ quality score of 20, and a minimum distance to other SNPs of 50 bp (average individual Phred score was 60.8, while average individual sequencing coverage was 36.3×). A variant was cataloged when it was present in a single sample (only 3% of loci had minor allele frequencies—MAF—below 0.5, 2% of loci had MAF below 0.3, and 1% of loci had MAF below 0.1.).
</p>
