<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">According to IPCC predictions [
 <xref rid="pone.0146958.ref072" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">72</xref>], mean temperature will increase and precipitation will decrease in the study area over the next few decades. These changes will not be spatially homogeneous in the study area. Some southern sectors will be more affected by changes (
 <xref rid="pone.0146958.g003" ref-type="fig" class="xref">Fig 3</xref>) and, within this latitudinal trend, temperature increases will grow and precipitation loss will decline in the highlands (
 <xref rid="pone.0146958.t004" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 4</xref>). This change has been reported in other studies of the effect of elevation on climate change [
 <xref rid="pone.0146958.ref073" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">73</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0146958.ref074" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">74</xref>]. As a result, and according to the reported effects of winter temperature and precipitation on the meadow pipit and chiffchaff, the models predict two main trends in climate suitability. First, mean climate suitability will improve for the two species in the Iberian Peninsula and the western Maghreb. This change seems to be related to the warming of highlands in a region where 80% of the land is over 300 m and 60% over 600 m a.s.l. (
 <xref rid="pone.0146958.g001" ref-type="fig" class="xref">Fig 1</xref>). In this way, the improvement of winter conditions produced by warming of elevated areas, similar to that reported in northern areas, will provide small birds the possibility to cope with winter conditions more successfully [
 <xref rid="pone.0146958.ref036" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>]. Second, despite the overall improvement of winter conditions, some sectors will be more vulnerable to the damaging effects of climate change in some species. This is true for the warmer lowlands of the south where the predicted decrease in precipitation will reduce the climate suitability for the meadow pipit, a species linked to moist areas (see above). The fate of water resources is a key concern in the drier sectors of the Iberian Peninsula and the Maghreb [
 <xref rid="pone.0146958.ref012" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0146958.ref013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0146958.ref037" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>].
</p>
