<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par48" class="p">In 
 <italic class="italic">Arabidopsis</italic>, the floral transition involves 
 <italic class="italic">FT1</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">LFY</italic> as well as 
 <italic class="italic">AGL14</italic> [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR85" class="xref">85</xref>]. We used putative 
 <italic class="italic">P. trichocarpa</italic> homologues of these genes as indicators of the floral transition. Surprisingly, we found that hyperinduction of 
 <italic class="italic">FT1</italic> during chilling of dormant buds was accompanied by a significant upregulation of the 
 <italic class="italic">AGL14</italic> and 
 <italic class="italic">LFY</italic> homologues in both TBs and AXBs. In contrast, pre-dormancy chilling reduced the expression of 
 <italic class="italic">AGL14</italic> and in particular 
 <italic class="italic">LFY</italic> (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" class="xref">7a, c</xref>). In 
 <italic class="italic">Arabidopsis</italic>, 
 <italic class="italic">AP1</italic> is required for petal and sepal development [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR86" class="xref">86</xref>], while in aspen it is also upregulated under short photoperiod in developing poplar buds [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" class="xref">33</xref>], possibly serving scale formation. Although chilling downregulated 
 <italic class="italic">AP1</italic> expression in dormant buds as well as in chilled pre-dormant buds (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" class="xref">7a, c</xref>), in the latter case 
 <italic class="italic">AP1</italic> transcription remained repressed throughout bud development. In conclusion, chilling of dormant buds promotes the expression of key floral pathway genes, whereas pre-dormancy chilling hampers their transcription (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" class="xref">7a, c</xref>). The implication might be that low temperature in the bud formation phase reduces floral competence. Thus, vernalization-induced flowering might require a previous dormancy phase, the realization of which might help to identify determinants of vernalization.
</p>
