<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par39" class="p">As described in the main text, our method is valid under a few assumptions: first, GMT or SST information is enough for GMT or SST prediction; second, all model trajectories are statistically equivalent; third, the common component of each model reflects its forced component; and fourth, stationarity of the statistics of anomalies in a changing climate scenario (i.e., non-autonomous system). With respect to the first assumption, we acknowledge that further refinement is possible, however, as will be demonstrated, using only globally averaged SAT and SST information is already enough to arrive at a skillful prediction. Assumption 2: Model trajectories are in general not statistically equivalent and maybe severely biased with respect to the real world. For globally averaged temperature, however, the statistical differences are small, and biases for the SST ensemble as a whole have been remedied by scaling the standard deviation. (Rescaling of individual SST trajectories to observation variability does not show improvement in prediction accuracy and shows lost of reliability in comparison with the global ensemble rescaling.) Assumption 3 is clearly incorrect, as long as the ensemble size of each model is finite. However, the error made by this assumption is small enough to allow skillful prediction. Assumption 4 is also not correct, although generally applied in climate science. The general assumption is that the perturbation implied by global warming is too small to fundamentally change the anomalies, or climate variability (i.e., anomalies and perturbation to the background do not affect each other). This might be problematic when studying extreme events, whose occurrences might change in a changing climate. Hence, this assumption is questionable for certain variables that are subject to order one changes under climate change, such as, e.g., the Atlantic Meridional Overturning Circulation, or extremes in the tail of a distribution. However, there is no indication that the assumption is not approximately valid for GMT, whose variability is for a large part dominated by El Nño-Southern Oscillation and the Interdecadal Pacific Oscillation. So, despite these various assumptions, PROCAST is skillful for interannual GMT and (globally averaged) SST prediction, proving that these assumptions although not strictly true are reasonable in the context of our study, because they apply in most cases of variation in GMT and SST.</p>
