<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Our model shows the importance of the distance covered to feed and prey aggregation which are key factors to which animals are highly sensitive. Indeed, a simultaneous increase in distance and aggregation would be of dramatic consequences on the survival of central place forager populations. Such results should be considered within the framework of the environmental modifications likely to be triggered by climate change, as predicted by climatologists (
 <italic class="italic">i</italic>.
 <italic class="italic">e</italic>. a southward shift of the highly productive Polar Front). Several studies have already revealed relationships between oceanographic conditions and the foraging success of marine predators [
 <xref rid="pone.0173797.ref012" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>–
 <xref rid="pone.0173797.ref015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0173797.ref018" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0173797.ref019" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0173797.ref068" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">68</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0173797.ref069" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">69</xref>]. Environmental features and oceanographic cues including temperature, temperature gradients and water turbidity, may be indicative of phytoplankton concentration [
 <xref rid="pone.0173797.ref070" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">70</xref>]. These cues may provide marine predators with elements allowing them to identify the most favorable locations. Thus, in view of the predicted climate change that could lead to critical conditions, the adaptive capacities of central place foragers is of major importance regarding their survival and conservation. Modelling outcomes suggested that only the largest females would be able to rear their newborns successfully if the distance to the resource increases. On the contrary, young (short) females which reach their definitive body length at about 7 years old would be disadvantaged in addition to their inexperience in the foraging activity [
 <xref rid="pone.0173797.ref013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0173797.ref022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0173797.ref026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0173797.ref028" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0173797.ref043" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>]. Consequently, their contribution to successive generations could be increasingly limited in the course of time.
</p>
