<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">INTRODUCTION</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is well documented that nonnative species can have devastating impacts on biodiversity (
  <a rid="CIT0051" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0051">Mack et al. 2000</a>; 
  <a rid="CIT0078" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0078">Simberloff 2005</a>; 
  <a rid="CIT0074" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0074">Shochat et al. 2010</a>; 
  <a rid="CIT0092" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0092">Vilà et al. 2010</a>) but despite extensive research, a high degree of uncertainty still exists with regard to the mechanisms of these impacts on native fauna (
  <a rid="CIT0063" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0063">Perrings et al. 2002</a>; 
  <a rid="CIT0092" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0092">Vilà et al. 2010</a>). Anecdotal evidence and a lack of understanding of the nature and dynamics of the invasion process have contributed to this uncertainty (
  <a rid="CIT0051" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0051">Mack et al. 2000</a>; 
  <a rid="CIT0040" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0040">Gurevitch and Padilla 2004</a>). Knowledge of the behavioral impacts resulting from nonlethal interspecific competition between native and nonnative species can, therefore, give insight into the mechanisms and consequences of invasions (reviewed in 
  <a rid="CIT0013" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0013">Chapple et al. 2012</a>).
 </p>
 <p content-type="indent" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It has been hypothesized that both native and nonnative species which are abundant in urban areas are those that are most adaptable and able to exploit resources in a disturbed environment (
  <a rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0054">McKinney 2006</a>). These “urban adapter” and “urban exploiter” species tend to have broad diets and high behavioral flexibility (
  <a rid="CIT0082" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0082">Sol 2002</a>). These characteristics are likely to increase their potential to compete for food with a variety of species, particularly at supplementary feeding stations (
  <a rid="CIT0074" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0074">Shochat et al. 2010</a>) and displace other species from urban habitats (e.g., 
  <a rid="CIT0061" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0061">Parsons et al. 2006</a>). For instance, increased interspecific competition can result in reduced foraging success of the affected individuals, increased time spent on vigilance, displacement to less high value resources and ultimately result in nonlethal fitness consequences with the potential to indirectly affect population level changes (
  <a rid="CIT0022" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0022">Cresswell 2008</a>). Interspecific competition is widely thought to play a role in the impact of nonnative species (
  <a rid="CIT0066" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0066">Probert and Litvaitis 1996</a>; 
  <a rid="CIT0046" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0046">Kiesecker et al. 2001</a>; 
  <a rid="CIT0093" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0093">Wauters et al. 2002</a>; 
  <a rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0024">Dame et al. 2006</a>; 
  <a rid="CIT0080" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0080">Soares and Serpa 2006</a>) but may be difficult to demonstrate unambiguously (
  <a rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0006">Blackburn et al. 2009</a>) perhaps in part because the ecological impacts of nonnative species can be difficult to distinguish from other potential environmental causes (
  <a rid="CIT0076" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0076">Shochat et al. 2006</a>; 
  <a rid="CIT0029" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0029">Dures and Cumming 2010</a>). It is thought that nonnative species that displace native species are likely to be better able to exploit resources and thus have strong interference effects on native species (
  <a rid="CIT0003" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0003">Amarasekare 2002</a>). There is thus a need for experimental investigation to identify how interspecific interference might lead to behavioral changes driven by nonnative species (
  <a rid="CIT0024" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0024">Dame et al. 2006</a>; 
  <a rid="CIT0087" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0087">Strubbe et al. 2011</a>).
 </p>
 <p content-type="indent" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another factor that requires consideration when studying the potential impact of invasive organisms on the behavior of native species is habituation. It has been suggested that simply the novelty of the invasive species may disrupt normal behavior in native species, by eliciting a neophobic avoidance response (
  <a rid="CIT0053" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0053">McEvoy et al. 2008</a>). Neophobic impacts can be reduced or altered by repeated exposure to the novel species, as shown in cases of habituation in predator–prey interactions (reviewed by 
  <a rid="CIT0009" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0009">Brown and Chivers 2005</a>). It has also been found that bird populations, which establish in urban areas, tend to have higher tolerance for novelty due to higher behavioral flexibility and reduced neophobia (
  <a rid="CIT0052" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0052">Martin and Fitzgerald 2005</a>; 
  <a rid="CIT0049" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0049">Levey et al. 2009</a>; 
  <a rid="CIT0033" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0033">Evans et al. 2010</a>; 
  <a rid="CIT0050" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0050">Lowry et al. 2013</a>). This could mean that birds in urban areas, which share food sources with invasive species, may not be affected as much as bird populations outside urban areas due to a preadaption to cope with an altered environment including altered species presence. However, there has been relatively little work investigating habituation of native species to invasive species and the effects of prior exposure on competitive interactions (but see 
  <a rid="CIT0095" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0095">Webb et al. 2008</a>; 
  <a rid="CIT0001" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0001">Abril and Gómez 2009</a>; 
  <a rid="CIT0057" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0057">Nelson et al. 2011</a>). In this context, rapid ongoing range expansion by exotic populations therefore offer the opportunity to investigate whether native species do habituate to the presence of invasive species (
  <a rid="CIT0037" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0037">Freidenfelds et al. 2012</a>).
 </p>
 <p content-type="indent" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this study, we test for evidence of interference competition with native species and for habituation in the native species to an urban population of the rose-ringed parakeet. This nonnative species is listed as one of the top 100 most invasive alien species in Europe (
  <a rid="CIT0091" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0091">Vilà et al. 2009</a>) and is a common invasive bird species around the world (
  <a rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0035">Feare 1996</a>), particularly in urban areas (
  <a rid="CIT0086" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0086">Strubbe and Matthysen 2009</a>). This study system is ideal because, although locations of establishment of invasive bird populations have been well recorded (
  <a rid="CIT0026" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0026">Duncan et al. 2003</a>), there is little quantitative evidence of their impacts on native faunas (
  <a rid="CIT0006" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0006">Blackburn et al. 2009</a>; 
  <a rid="CIT0087" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0087">Strubbe et al. 2011</a>).
 </p>
 <p content-type="indent" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The high-density populations of the rose-ringed parakeet in urban centers, provides a situation in which interspecific competition for resources with native species might be expected (
  <a rid="CIT0089" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0089">Tayleur 2010</a>). Urban gardens and parks provide alternative food sources such as supplemental feed and nonnative plant species. As such they enable rapid population growth of both native and nonnative adapter species, reflected in their positive association with human population density (
  <a rid="CIT0025" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0025">Daniels and Kirkpatrick 2006</a>; 
  <a rid="CIT0054" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0054">McKinney 2006</a>; 
  <a rid="CIT0038" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0038">Fuller et al. 2008</a>; 
  <a rid="CIT0086" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0086">Strubbe and Matthysen 2009</a>).
 </p>
 <p content-type="indent" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Previous studies on rose-ringed parakeets have been limited to investigating competition for nest sites and have suggested that the impact of this form of competition is likely to be negligible (
  <a rid="CIT0084" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0084">Strubbe et al. 2010</a>; 
  <a rid="CIT0023" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0023">Czajka et al. 2011</a>; 
  <a rid="CIT0058" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0058">Newson et al. 2011</a>). However, the parakeet’s highly varied diet (
  <a rid="CIT0035" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0035">Feare 1996</a>), its ability to eat nonnative plants and human-provided food sources (
  <a rid="CIT0047" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0047">Koutsosms et al. 2001</a>), as well as the fact that individuals have been found to spend half their feeding time at artificial bird feeders (
  <a rid="CIT0014" ref-type="bibr" href="#CIT0014">Clergeau and Vergnes 2011</a>), means that it has potential to compete with a wide variety of native bird species for these resources and particularly with species found in urban gardens.
 </p>
 <p content-type="indent" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Here, we use an experimental approach to address the following questions: 1) Does the presence of a nonnative competitor at a high value food source alter the foraging behavior of native species? 2) Does the native species’ response to the presence of the nonnative competitor differ from that of a similarly dominant native species with which they have coexisted? 3) Is the strength of response to the presence of an establishing nonnative competitor correlated with prior exposure to the nonnative species? 4) If so, is this response indicative of reinforcement of avoidance behavior of the nonnative species, or of habituation to the nonnative species?</p>
</sec>
