<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s4" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Passerine salmonellosis</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Salmonella enterica</span> serovar Typhimurium (definitive phage types (DT)160, 40 and 56 variant) causes salmonellosis in passerine birds and has been reported from various countries since at least the 1950s [
  <a rid="RSTB20170091C46" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20170091C46">46</a>–
  <a rid="RSTB20170091C50" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20170091C50">50</a>]. The disease is characterized by disseminated granulomatous lesions, most commonly affecting the oesophagus, liver, spleen and caecal tonsils. Transmission is faeco-oral and 
  <span class="italic">Salmonella</span> bacteria are capable of persisting for many months within the environment. Incidents of passerine salmonellosis are typically reported in the vicinity of supplementary feeding stations [
  <a rid="RSTB20170091C46" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20170091C46">46</a>–
  <a rid="RSTB20170091C50" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20170091C50">50</a>]. Gregarious and granivorous species in the Fringillidae and Passeridae are most commonly affected by the disease, particularly the greenfinch and house sparrow in GB [
  <a rid="RSTB20170091C48" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20170091C48">48</a>]. Passerine salmonellosis incidents have pronounced winter seasonality in GB, typically peaking in January. The wild bird species that are affected by disease are proposed as the reservoir of these 
  <span class="italic">Salmonella</span> biotypes, which are considered to be host-adapted [
  <a rid="RSTB20170091C51" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20170091C51">51</a>].
 </p>
 <sec id="s4a" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(a)</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Pattern of occurrence of passerine salmonellosis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While the disease is considered to be endemic, with widespread occurrence, in GB, longitudinal studies have shown variation in the spatial distribution of the main phage types in England and Wales with succession of the predominant phage type over time, with shifts from DT160 to DT40 and then DT56(v) [
   <a rid="RSTB20170091C52" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20170091C52">52</a>] (electronic supplementary material, figure S1
   <span class="italic">b</span>). In contrast to the patterns of occurrence of finch trichomonosis and Paridae pox, the number of confirmed passerine salmonellosis incidents has declined markedly over the past decade [
   <a rid="RSTB20170091C52" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20170091C52">52</a>] (electronic supplementary material, figure S1
   <span class="italic">a</span>). The reason for the sharp decline in this endemic disease remains unknown, but we propose two potential hypotheses: first, that the decline in DT56(v) incidents reflects the development of herd immunity to this biotype and the populations are now vulnerable to emergence of a new variant; or, second, that passerine salmonellosis has density-dependent transmission, and the dramatic reduction in greenfinch numbers in garden habitats, due to finch trichomonosis, has had a secondary impact on occurrence of this bacterial disease. Serosurveys of wild bird populations may help elucidate these hypotheses.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s4b" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(b)</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Population impact</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There have been anecdotal reports of temporary, localized reductions in bird numbers following passerine salmonellosis outbreaks [
   <a rid="RSTB20170091C53" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20170091C53">53</a>]. There is, however, no evidence to indicate that passerine mortality caused by salmonellosis occurs at a scale sufficient to cause widespread wild bird population declines in GB.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
