<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Finch trichomonosis</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="italic">Trichomonas gallinae</span> is a protozoan parasite that causes avian trichomonosis, a disease long known to affect columbiforms (pigeons and doves) and birds of prey [
  <a rid="RSTB20170091C27" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20170091C27">27</a>]. The disease is generally characterized by necrotic upper alimentary tract lesions, which often interfere with the ability to swallow. Parasite transmission occurs via fresh saliva during conspecific feeding in courtship or when rearing young, or at shared food and water sources. Birds of prey are exposed to the parasite when they predate or scavenge infected avian hosts. The parasite has short-term environmental persistence and is killed by desiccation.
 </p>
 <sec id="s2a" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(a)</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Pattern of occurrence of finch trichomonosis</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Avian trichomonosis has long been documented sporadically in columbiforms and birds of prey in GB, its widespread distribution being consistent with an endemic disease [
   <a rid="RSTB20170091C28" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20170091C28">28</a>]. Trichomonosis emerged in finch species in GB in spring 2005, with a presentation of necrotic ingluvitis [
   <a rid="RSTB20170091C29" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20170091C29">29</a>]. Since its detection, the disease has been most frequently diagnosed in greenfinch 
   <span class="italic">Chloris chloris</span> and chaffinch 
   <span class="italic">Fringilla coelebs</span>; however, we have also diagnosed fatal trichomonosis in most of the gregarious, seed-eating species that visit garden feeding stations. Epidemic mortality occurs each year with a seasonal peak in late summer (August–September), although incidents continue year-round. Fatalities due to the disease have been recorded infrequently in other common garden birds, probably from spillover at sites where there are high levels of contamination of shared food and water sources and of the ground below bird feeders. Since its emergence, finch trichomonosis has been the most common infectious disease diagnosed for finch species (family Fringillidae), accounting for 87% (372/426) of finch infectious disease diagnoses over the period 2010–2016 inclusive (i.e. since the previous large-scale study on this disease [
   <a rid="RSTB20170091C30" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20170091C30">30</a>]).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While multiple 
   <span class="italic">T. gallinae</span> strains are known to infect pigeons and doves in GB, a single clonal A1 strain is responsible for the trichomonosis epidemic in European finches [
   <a rid="RSTB20170091C31" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20170091C31">31</a>,
   <a rid="RSTB20170091C32" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20170091C32">32</a>]. Although it is possible that this is a recently emerged, highly virulent strain with increased host range, we hypothesize that the epidemic arose from single/multiple spillover events from columbids to finches in GB and has been maintained predominantly by finch to finch transmission [
   <a rid="RSTB20170091C30" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20170091C30">30</a>]. The frequency with which woodpigeon, 
   <span class="italic">Columba palumbus</span>, and collared dove, 
   <span class="italic">Streptopelia decaocto</span>, are reported from gardens has increased markedly since the 1980s, as did greenfinch; indeed, they were among the largest increases at garden feeding stations reported by Chamberlain 
   <span class="italic">et al</span>. [
   <a rid="RSTB20170091C8" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20170091C8">8</a>]. These increases are almost certainly due, in large part, simply to a larger population size; for example, woodpigeon numbers have increased in response to a greater area of oilseed rape cultivation [
   <a rid="RSTB20170091C33" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20170091C33">33</a>]. It is also possible that a widespread change in the nature of garden feeding since the 1970s, with a large variety of food types provided year-round (increasingly presented in multiple feeders), has not only made gardens more attractive as foraging locations, but also increased the frequency of conspecific and interspecific interactions of birds at feeding stations.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Subsequent to its emergence in GB, finch trichomonosis spread to Fennoscandia in 2008 [
   <a rid="RSTB20170091C34" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20170091C34">34</a>], with epidemiological and ring recovery data suggesting the chaffinch as the most likely primary vector [
   <a rid="RSTB20170091C35" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20170091C35">35</a>]. Onward spread of finch trichomonosis has continued in mainland Europe, with molecular studies confirming the same clonal A1 strain of 
   <span class="italic">T</span>. 
   <span class="italic">gallinae</span> to be responsible [
   <a rid="RSTB20170091C36" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20170091C36">36</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="s2b" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(b)</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Population-level impact</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the first year of epidemic mortality (2006), a marked decrease in the number of gardens reporting greenfinches and chaffinches was noted, which was contemporaneous with a late summer peak in reports of the disease [
   <a rid="RSTB20170091C29" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20170091C29">29</a>]. This resulted in a reduction in the breeding population of greenfinches (by 35%) and of chaffinches (by 20%) in the area with the highest frequency of disease reports, but no decrease in dunnock (
   <span class="italic">Prunella modularis</span>) numbers (which represents a rarely affected ‘control’ species [
   <a rid="RSTB20170091C29" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20170091C29">29</a>]). In the years preceding the initial outbreak, all three species were widespread, being reported in approximately 80% of gardens each spring (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTB20170091F1" href="#RSTB20170091F1">figure 1</a>
   <span class="italic">c</span>). In the years following the emergence of finch trichomonosis, dunnocks continued to be reported in a similar proportion of gardens to before, while the number of gardens reported to be visited by chaffinches decreased only slightly. Greenfinches, though, were seen in fewer than half (49%) the number of gardens in 2015/2016 relative to before the disease outbreak. At the same time, a large decrease in the number of greenfinches recorded at garden feeders was noted (from a mean of 5.6 average weekly maximum group size before 2006 to 1.6 in 2015/2016), with a smaller decrease for chaffinch (6.2 to 4.7) and no change was noted for the dunnock (mean = 1.5, 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTB20170091F1" href="#RSTB20170091F1">figure 1</a>
   <span class="italic">b</span>). These changes are reflected at the national level, as the size of the greenfinch (but not chaffinch or dunnock) breeding population has continued to decline markedly (by 66%, 
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTB20170091F1" href="#RSTB20170091F1">figure 1</a>
   <span class="italic">a</span>), from a peak of approximately 4.3 million in 2006 (just before the onset of the epidemic) to approximately 1.5 million individuals in 2016 (i.e. an average reduction of approx. 280 000 individuals per annum). This represents the largest scale infectious disease impact on a European wild bird on record and has led to the inclusion of the British race of Greenfinch, 
   <span class="italic">C. chloris harrisoni</span> on the red list of Birds of Conservation Concern [
   <a rid="RSTB20170091C38" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20170091C38">38</a>]. Furthermore, recent assessment of extinction risk using the International Union for Conservation of Nature Red list guidelines classified the breeding greenfinch population in GB as endangered [
   <a rid="RSTB20170091C39" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20170091C39">39</a>]. It is unclear whether the more recent decline in chaffinch numbers since 2012 (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTB20170091F1" href="#RSTB20170091F1">figure 1</a>
   <span class="italic">a</span>) is a result of finch trichomonosis or other causes. 
   <div id="RSTB20170091F1" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Figure 1.</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Number of greenfinch (red), chaffinch (blue) and dunnock (black). (
      <span class="italic">a</span>) Index of UK breeding population size from the BTO/JNCC/RSPB Breeding Bird Survey [
      <a rid="RSTB20170091C37" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20170091C37">37</a>]; the index is set to 1 in 2006 representing a population size of 4.3 million (greenfinch), 14.3 million (chaffinch) and 4.4 million (dunnock) birds. (
      <span class="italic">b</span>) Mean maximum number of birds recorded each week in winter (October–March) in gardens at feeders from the BTO Garden Bird Feeding Survey. (
      <span class="italic">c</span>) Proportion of gardens in BTO Garden BirdWatch recording each species in winter. In all cases, the vertical dotted line indicates the timing of the initial finch trichomonosis epidemic in 2006.
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="rstb20170091-g1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
