<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s3a" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(a)</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Pattern of occurrence of Paridae pox</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In 2006, a novel and severe form of avian pox affecting Paridae species, most frequently the great tit (
  <span class="italic">Parus major</span>), was diagnosed in southeast England with multiple birds affected in the majority of reported incidents [
  <a rid="RSTB20170091C42" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20170091C42">42</a>]. Reports were received throughout the year, but with a pronounced seasonal peak in the post-breeding period (August/September), when population densities are at their highest following recruitment of naive juveniles, but also coincident with a seasonal peak in the abundance of mosquito vectors. Following the initial cases, there was a marked expansion in the disease range, consistent with epidemic spread from a point source introduction [
  <a rid="RSTB20170091C42" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20170091C42">42</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sequence analysis of the avian poxvirus strains affecting British garden bird species revealed that a single B1 clade virus was responsible for Paridae pox emergence, which was distinct from all other strains except that affecting dunnock, although these might be distinguished as separate strains at higher sequencing resolution [
  <a rid="RSTB20170091C42" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20170091C42">42</a>]. This severe form of pox has been known at an apparently low prevalence in Scandinavia since the 1950s, with incidents seen elsewhere in mainland Europe since 2005 [
  <a rid="RSTB20170091C43" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20170091C43">43</a>]. Analyses of the avipoxvirus 4b core protein gene showed identical DNA sequences to great tits in mainland Europe and GB [
  <a rid="RSTB20170091C42" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20170091C42">42</a>,
  <a rid="RSTB20170091C43" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20170091C43">43</a>]. The spatio-temporal pattern of spread and the same virus strain emerging in great tits in GB and mainland Europe support a hypothesis of disease emergence subsequent to virus incursion, rather than emergence in GB as a result of a spillover event, e.g. from dunnock. As great tits in GB are relatively sedentary, the introduction is likely to have occurred as a result of invertebrate vector movement, perhaps via wind-borne spread or accidental transport [
  <a rid="RSTB20170091C42" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20170091C42">42</a>]. Great tits seem to be particularly susceptible to the disease because other tit species (such as the blue tit 
  <span class="italic">Cyanistes caeruleus</span>) exposed to the same environment are affected much less frequently [
  <a rid="RSTB20170091C44" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20170091C44">44</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Paridae pox incident reports, which have continued to be received (to 2016), demonstrate that the disease has persisted in southeast England and has an expanding range northward and westward across England and Wales; only a few reports have been received from Scotland since the first report from there in 2015 (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSTB20170091F2" href="#RSTB20170091F2">figure 2</a>). 
  <div id="RSTB20170091F2" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 2.</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Records of Paridae pox in great tit submitted in 2006–2009 (red dots), 2010–2013 (purple) and 2014–2016 (blue). Graphs show population growth (mean annual change) for each delineated region for 1994–2005 (black, i.e. before Paridae pox emergence) and 2006–2016 (grey, i.e. after Paridae pox emergence). Points indicate the mean estimate, thicker bars indicate ±1 standard error and thin bars indicate 95% confidence limits. Regions follow the Government Office/NUTS boundaries.</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="rstb20170091-g2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
