<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2a" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">(a)</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Pattern of occurrence of finch trichomonosis</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Avian trichomonosis has long been documented sporadically in columbiforms and birds of prey in GB, its widespread distribution being consistent with an endemic disease [
  <a rid="RSTB20170091C28" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20170091C28">28</a>]. Trichomonosis emerged in finch species in GB in spring 2005, with a presentation of necrotic ingluvitis [
  <a rid="RSTB20170091C29" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20170091C29">29</a>]. Since its detection, the disease has been most frequently diagnosed in greenfinch 
  <span class="italic">Chloris chloris</span> and chaffinch 
  <span class="italic">Fringilla coelebs</span>; however, we have also diagnosed fatal trichomonosis in most of the gregarious, seed-eating species that visit garden feeding stations. Epidemic mortality occurs each year with a seasonal peak in late summer (August–September), although incidents continue year-round. Fatalities due to the disease have been recorded infrequently in other common garden birds, probably from spillover at sites where there are high levels of contamination of shared food and water sources and of the ground below bird feeders. Since its emergence, finch trichomonosis has been the most common infectious disease diagnosed for finch species (family Fringillidae), accounting for 87% (372/426) of finch infectious disease diagnoses over the period 2010–2016 inclusive (i.e. since the previous large-scale study on this disease [
  <a rid="RSTB20170091C30" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20170091C30">30</a>]).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While multiple 
  <span class="italic">T. gallinae</span> strains are known to infect pigeons and doves in GB, a single clonal A1 strain is responsible for the trichomonosis epidemic in European finches [
  <a rid="RSTB20170091C31" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20170091C31">31</a>,
  <a rid="RSTB20170091C32" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20170091C32">32</a>]. Although it is possible that this is a recently emerged, highly virulent strain with increased host range, we hypothesize that the epidemic arose from single/multiple spillover events from columbids to finches in GB and has been maintained predominantly by finch to finch transmission [
  <a rid="RSTB20170091C30" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20170091C30">30</a>]. The frequency with which woodpigeon, 
  <span class="italic">Columba palumbus</span>, and collared dove, 
  <span class="italic">Streptopelia decaocto</span>, are reported from gardens has increased markedly since the 1980s, as did greenfinch; indeed, they were among the largest increases at garden feeding stations reported by Chamberlain 
  <span class="italic">et al</span>. [
  <a rid="RSTB20170091C8" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20170091C8">8</a>]. These increases are almost certainly due, in large part, simply to a larger population size; for example, woodpigeon numbers have increased in response to a greater area of oilseed rape cultivation [
  <a rid="RSTB20170091C33" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20170091C33">33</a>]. It is also possible that a widespread change in the nature of garden feeding since the 1970s, with a large variety of food types provided year-round (increasingly presented in multiple feeders), has not only made gardens more attractive as foraging locations, but also increased the frequency of conspecific and interspecific interactions of birds at feeding stations.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Subsequent to its emergence in GB, finch trichomonosis spread to Fennoscandia in 2008 [
  <a rid="RSTB20170091C34" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20170091C34">34</a>], with epidemiological and ring recovery data suggesting the chaffinch as the most likely primary vector [
  <a rid="RSTB20170091C35" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20170091C35">35</a>]. Onward spread of finch trichomonosis has continued in mainland Europe, with molecular studies confirming the same clonal A1 strain of 
  <span class="italic">T</span>. 
  <span class="italic">gallinae</span> to be responsible [
  <a rid="RSTB20170091C36" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTB20170091C36">36</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
