<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece34882-sec-0005" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.3</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Germination experiment</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Soil seedbanks (approximately 1 L volume per plot) were taken with a 5 cm diameter × 3 cm depth steel coring tool, 16 cores per plot. Live seedlings found growing in soil cores were added to in situ seedling counts, transplanted to 500 ml pots containing equal parts vermiculite and Promix (Premier Tech, Québec, Canada), and grown for identification to species or functional type in the University of Alaska Research Greenhouse (Fairbanks, Alaska). Soil cores were homogenized for each plot and divided into half. Half of each bulk sample was processed immediately for germination; the other half was frozen at −20°C for 16 weeks before germination (vernalization treatment) in order to induce broad‐spectrum germination of species with different requirements for breaking dormancy (Baskin, Thompson, &amp; Baskin, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0004">2006</a>). In both treatments, we concentrated seedbanks by washing them through 4–0.5 mm mesh soil sieves stacked coarse to fine. This method was developed to optimize germination in native soils by eliminating large particles and fine clays that can create uneven light exposure and moisture conditions (Ter Heerdt, Verweij, Bekker, &amp; Bakker, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0079" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0079">1996</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to assess germination, a 0.5 cm layer of concentrated seedbank was poured into 16 oz. plastic cups over moistened Whatman #2 filter paper. Cups were incubated in 20 hr daylight/4 hr night at 23.2°C day/21.4°C night to simulate Arctic summer photoperiod. Cups were randomized on benches weekly and inspected weekly for 12 weeks. Germinants were counted and grown until they were large enough to be identified. Ungerminated seeds were air‐dried, counted, and identified to species or functional type in the laboratory under a dissecting microscope. Counts of seeds or germinants m
  <span class="sup">−2</span> were calculated as the mean number of seeds or germinants/core divided by core area (m
  <span class="sup">2</span>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We found willow seeds only in capsules and inferred that single, ungerminated willow seed decomposes rapidly in contact with the soil. We confirmed this in a seed decay experiment by incubating dwarf birch and tall shrub willow seeds collected from branches of live shrubs in a black spruce bog near Fairbanks, Alaska in October 2013. For each species, 100 seeds were placed onto moistened Whatman #2 filter paper in 8 Petri dishes (25 seeds per dish). Petri dishes were covered and incubated in the University of Alaska Research Greenhouse under the above conditions. No additional moisture was added. Initial germination for both species was not different, but after 7 weeks 58% of the willow seed, both germinated and ungerminated, was decayed by mold, versus 3% of the birch seed. We also found wide variation in willow seed counts in our native soil seedbanks, so we pooled birch and willow data for statistical analysis (“birch + willow”). We considered this method appropriate for comparison with other plant functional types because dwarf birch and willow species represented the majority of the deciduous shrub functional type at our sites.</p>
</sec>
