<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece34882-sec-0001" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">INTRODUCTION</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate warming in the Arctic is likely to increase the frequency of landscape disturbance (IPCC, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0046" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0046">2014</a>), resulting in increased opportunities for seedling recruitment. Seedling recruitment in tundra communities is considered infrequent compared to clonal growth of established individuals (Eriksson, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0029">1989</a>; Rowe, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0067" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0067">1983</a>), due to short growing seasons and lack of suitable microsites. Disturbances such as tundra fires (Bret‐Harte et al., 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0015" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0015">2013</a>), frost boils (Sutton, Hermanutz, &amp; Jacobs, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0075" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0075">2018</a>), and rodent activity (Nystuen, Evju, Rusch, Graae, &amp; Eide, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0061">2014</a>) can stimulate seedling recruitment by reducing competition and altering microsites and may ultimately influence the structure of vegetation communities (Chambers, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0020">1995</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In high‐stress environments, germination and establishment are likely the most limiting phases of a plant's ability to colonize an area (Alsos et al., 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0002">2007</a>; Grime, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0041">1977</a>). Seeds in northern environments typically break dormancy after a cold period, and seedlings must rapidly establish following snowmelt (Billings &amp; Mooney, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0008">1968</a>). Contact with bare soil may be more optimal for root penetration than dense litter layers (Chapin et al., 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0022">2006</a>; Douglas, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0027">1995</a>). Recruitment thus depends on seasonally short windows of suitable microsites and viable seed (Eriksson &amp; Fröborg, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0031">1996</a>). The relationship of increased seedling success in Arctic tundra to disturbance and high‐quality microsites has been supported in other research (Gough, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0038" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0038">2006</a>; Graae et al., 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0040" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0040">2011</a>; Milbau, Shevtsova, Olser, Mooshammer, &amp; Graae, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0055">2013</a>; Munier, Hermanutz, Jacobs, &amp; Lewis, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0056" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0056">2010</a>; Nystuen et al., 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0061">2014</a>; Sutton et al., 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0075" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0075">2018</a>). Increased recruitment can lead to populations with novel combinations of genes that could help plant species adapt to rapid change (Petit, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0062">2004</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Thermal erosion is one disturbance likely to influence tundra plant communities. Since the 1980s, thermal erosion of ice‐rich permafrost soils has been observed with increasing frequency (Belshe, Schuur, &amp; Grosse, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0007">2013</a>; Bowden et al., 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0013">2008</a>). Retrogressive thaw slumps (RTS) are areas of progressive ground collapse due to the melting of subsurface ice; on Alaska's North Slope, they have been observed on hillslopes and lake shores in the northern foothills of the Brooks Range (Bowden et al., 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0013">2008</a>; Gooseff, Balser, Bowden, &amp; Jones, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0037">2009</a>), forming depressions many square meters in area due to mass soil wasting (Figure 
  <a rid="ece34882-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#ece34882-fig-0001">1</a>a,b). Time‐lapse photography of two recent North Slope RTS, the 2010 Horn Lake thermokarst (Godsey, Gooseff, &amp; Lewcowicz, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0036">2010</a>), and the 2014 Wolverine Lake thermokarst (Dobkowski, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0026" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0026">2014</a>) documented the displacement of entire vegetation communities through mass soil wasting within a single summer.
 </p>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece34882-fig-0001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>(a) Overview of a young (1–10 years old) retrogressive thaw slump (RTS) on the south shore of lake NE‐14 in the Alaskan Low Arctic, (b) dead shrub in RTS chute at lake I‐minus 1 caused by mass soil wasting, (c) seedlings on bare soil in young RTS at lake I‐minus 1, and (d) tall shrubs in old (≥30 years old) RTS at NE‐14</p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-3" xlink:href="ECE3-9-1880-g001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Concurrent with increasing thermal erosion, aerial surveys of Alaska's North Slope over 50 years have photographically documented the expansion of deciduous woody shrubs in Arctic tundra (IPCC, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0046" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0046">2014</a>; Sturm, Racine, &amp; Tape, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0073" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0073">2001</a>). Potential feedbacks of a shrubbier Arctic to ecosystem processes include reduced albedo and increased evapotranspiration by shrubs compared to tussock tundra, which can result in greater heat retention (Chapin, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0021">2005</a>; Euskirchen, McGuire, Chapin, Yi, &amp; Thompson, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0032">2009</a>; Sturm et al., 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0074" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0074">2005</a>) and increased destabilization of permafrost soils (Bonfils et al., 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0012">2012</a>; Lawrence &amp; Swenson, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0050" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0050">2011</a>). Deciduous shrubs alter soil properties by depositing leaf litter and trapping snow, both of which can buffer ground temperatures, resulting in a deeper active layer and greater nutrient release over winter (Buckeridge &amp; Grogan, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0016">2010</a>; DeMarco, Mack, &amp; Bret‐Harte, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0025">2011</a>; Schimel, Bilbrough, &amp; Welker, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0069" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0069">2004</a>). Alternatively, predicted positive feedback effects of shrubs could be offset in summer through increased shading and litter deposition, resulting in shallower active layer depths during the growing season (Blok et al., 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0011">2010</a>). Shrubs can also promote herbivore activity, leading to increased shrub sprouting (Tape, Lord, Marshall, &amp; Ruess, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0077" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0077">2010</a>) and to changes in hydrology and permafrost thaw associated with predicted beaver encroachment into willow habitat on Alaska's North Slope (Tape, Jones, Arp, Nitze, &amp; Grosse, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0076" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0076">2018</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Revegetation following thermal erosion in Arctic and subarctic tundra has resulted in thickets of tall willow, dwarf birch, and alder that persist for decades (Lantz, Kokelj, Gergel, &amp; Henry, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0049">2009</a>; Pizano, Barón, Schuur, Crummer, &amp; Mack, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0063" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0063">2014</a>; Schuur, Crummer, Vogel, &amp; Mack, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0070" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0070">2007</a>), though in some cases more heterogeneous plant communities develop (Becker, Davies, &amp; Pollard, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0005" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0005">2016</a>). The contribution of seedlings versus clonal expansion in forming shrub thickets is not well studied, but thermal erosion appears to provide conditions for increased seed production and suitable microsites for the formation of seedbeds and thickets in some sites (Figure 
  <a rid="ece34882-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#ece34882-fig-0001">1</a>c,d; Frost, Epstein, Walker, Matyshak, &amp; Ermokhina, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0034" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0034">2013</a>; Lantz et al., 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0049">2009</a>). In permafrost regions, deeply thawed mineral soils exposed by RTS formation could allow establishment of deep taproots to anchor seedlings against winter freeze–thaw lifting (Billings &amp; Mooney, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0008" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0008">1968</a>), potentially restoring soil stability as plants mature.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Soil seedbanks may be the important sources of colonization where there are sufficient viable seeds and suitable microsites for germination and establishment (Eriksson &amp; Fröborg, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0031" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0031">1996</a>). In general, seedbanks are expected to vary in the number and viability of seeds due to differences in seed longevity, standing vegetation, seed production, topography, disturbance frequency, predation, and local climate (Chambers, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0020">1995</a>; Murdoch &amp; Ellis, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0057" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0057">1992</a>). In tundra, seedbanks may form under mature vegetation (Fox, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0033">1983</a>) and in depressions and sheltered sites that trap seeds dispersed by wind and water (Alsos, Spjelkavik, &amp; Engelskjøn, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0003">2003</a>; Chambers, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0020">1995</a>). In lower latitudes, high disturbance frequency is predicted to select for seeds that persist in the soil as pioneer species to recolonize uncovered ground (Thompson, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0080" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0080">1978</a>). In the Arctic, where disturbance is less frequent and seeds may be more resistant to desiccation (Wyse &amp; Dickie, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0088" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0088">2017</a>), seed persistence may be enhanced by burial in the cold, dry conditions of permafrost soils (McGraw, Vavrek &amp; Bennington, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0053">1991</a>). Seedling recruitment in disturbed Arctic soils has been observed from long‐lived buried seed, primarily sedges in the genera 
  <span class="italic">Carex </span>and 
  <span class="italic">Eriophorum</span> (Ebersole, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0028">1989</a>; Gartner, Chapin, &amp; Shaver, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0035">1983</a>), and from short‐lived seeds of species not present in the seedbank, including 
  <span class="italic">Betula nana</span> and 
  <span class="italic">Salix</span> spp. (Alsos et al., 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0003">2003</a>; Cooper et al., 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0023">2004</a>; Ebersole, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0028">1989</a>). Species requirements for successful germination and growth may be important in determining whether a site is revegetated by uncovered buried seed or recently deposited seed. The dominance of deciduous shrubs in mature RTS in this area suggests that the source of recruitment is recently deposited seed of species with short‐lived seeds rather than older buried seed. If so, we may expect a random sample of recent postdisturbance seedbanks to contain fewer, mostly viable seeds than older sites.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The goal of this study was to assess (a) whether conditions in RTS are more favorable for seedling recruitment than in tundra undisturbed by RTS and (b) how RTS affect seedbank size and viability. We hypothesized first that, all other things being equal, if recruitment depends upon suitable site conditions, recruitment potential will be higher in RTS than in undisturbed tundra, because disturbed ground is free of competing vegetation and may have more space, light, and available nutrients. Second, we hypothesized that if Arctic seedbanks are more dependent upon nearby mature vegetation than upon long‐distance dispersal and entrapment of seed in depressions, there should be a quantity–quality trade‐off in postdisturbance seedbanks over time, because as seeds accumulate under maturing canopies, the proportion of older seed should increase relative to recent seed input, lowering overall seedbank quality. In contrast, immediately following disturbance, the seedbank may be small in quantity, but high in quality, because it would be composed of mostly recent seed rain. Alternatively, if quantity and quality of Arctic seedbanks are independently influenced by factors such as dispersal, entrapment, seed rain, predation, germination, weathering, disease, and burial, this could result in seedbanks of roughly equal size (i.e., seeds per given area) with different levels of viability or in seedbanks of roughly equivalent viability regardless of size.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We compared environmental conditions across two RTS chronosequences on Alaska's North Slope. We compared in situ seedling counts, seedbank size (seeds m
  <span class="sup">−2</span>), and seedbank viability tested in greenhouse germination trials. We predicted that young RTS would have higher in situ seedling counts and smaller but more viable seedbanks. We predicted that due to rebuilding of vegetation canopies and organic layers over time, older RTS would be more similar to undisturbed tundra and show a reverse trend: lower in situ seedling counts and larger seedbanks of lower viability. Finally, we assessed relationships between seedbanks and their environmental conditions to understand whether composition and performance of seedbanks are best explained by RTS age, microsite conditions, location, or some combination of these factors.
 </p>
</sec>
