<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece34882-sec-0016" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.3</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Seedbank characteristics</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The lack of a trade‐off between seedbank size and viability over time in our results suggests these properties are independent. Seedbanks in open tundra environments are expected to form through entrapment of wind‐ and water‐dispersed seed (Alsos et al., 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0003">2003</a>; Chambers, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0020">1995</a>) and from seed rain (Fox, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0033">1983</a>). Although we found RTS to be more collapsed than adjacent undisturbed areas, we found no evidence that RTS sites trapped more seed than the flatter ground of undisturbed tundra. RTS are destructive events, resulting in soil wasting and mixing of soil layers (Pizano et al., 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0063" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0063">2014</a>), and may be composed of combinations of new seed rain and uncovered old seed (Ebersole, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0028">1989</a>; Gartner et al., 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0035">1983</a>; McGraw et al., 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0053" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0053">1991</a>). In partial support of Fox's (
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0033">1983</a>) prediction that seedbank size increases with plant productivity and seed rain, we found most seedbanks associated with plant cover, although seed rain showed no relationship to seedbank size. Our seedbanks ranged from 71 to 10,000 seeds m
  <span class="sup">−2</span> (untransformed count data) and were not different from seedbank sizes reported in studies from temperate and northern latitudes (Alsos et al., 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0003">2003</a>; Cooper et al., 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0023">2004</a>; Ebersole, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0028">1989</a>; Fox, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0033">1983</a>; Thompson, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0080" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0080">1978</a>). The fate of Arctic seeds is therefore likely determined by the same interactive processes that form seedbanks at other latitudes (Chambers, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0020" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0020">1995</a>; Thompson, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0080" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0080">1978</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In contrast to sedge‐dominated seedbanks found in some Alaskan Arctic soils (Ebersole, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0028">1989</a>), the largest seedbanks we found were from NE‐14’s old RTS and undisturbed tundra and were primarily composed of dwarf birch (
  <span class="italic">Betula nana</span>) and evergreen species (mainly 
  <span class="italic">Vaccinium</span> spp. and 
  <span class="italic">Empetrum nigrum</span>). This may be in part due to our goal to sample relatively recent seed input at an average depth of 3 cm, compared to Ebersole's (
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0028">1989</a>) sampling at 10 cm depths, as the latter method likely resulted in greater numbers of buried seed. Dwarf birch seed is common throughout the Arctic, but is considered short‐lived compared to sedge species, many of which are known to survive burial (Ebersole, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0028">1989</a>). Because short‐lived seed may not be adequately represented in studies of soil seedbanks at deeper depths, we felt our sampling method was appropriate in order to understand the relationship of seedbanks to the tall shrub thickets we found in RTS.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Birch and willow seed accounted for over half of some seedbanks, but low percent germination along with higher decay of willow seed in our greenhouse trials suggests recruitment in the field may be lower. Seedbank studies of High Arctic populations (Cooper et al., 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0023" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0023">2004</a>) suggest greenhouse trials may not reflect in situ recruitment; however, Low Arctic populations may not be as seed‐limited as High Arctic populations due to a longer growing season, likely resulting in greater production of viable seed. Ebersole (
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0028">1989</a>) found dwarf birch and willow are common colonizers of disturbed tundra in the Alaskan Low Arctic, and given that birch and willow produce large quantities of seed, in situ germination rates of 1%–6% could be sufficient for recruitment in suitable microsites. It has been estimated that as few as 6–38 seedlings, followed by clonal growth, is sufficient to establish existing populations of these species at the northern limits of their ranges (Alsos et al., 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0002">2007</a>). Perhaps the best evidence that germination rates may be sufficient for shrub establishment in the Toolik Lake area is that the RTS we observed were filled with shrubs within a few decades.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We did not follow the fate of in situ seedlings over time, nor did we account for resprouting vegetative propagules in this analysis (Alsos et al., 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0003">2003</a>). Evidence from temperate and boreal forest fires suggests that seedling counts of woody species are highest within the first 5 years of disturbance and that revegetation occurs within the first decade (Johnstone et al., 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0047">2004</a>; Romme, Turner, Tuskan, &amp; Reed, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0066" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0066">2005</a>; Rydgren, Økland, &amp; Hestmark, 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0068" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0068">2004</a>). Similarly, thermokarst revegetation can occur if exposed soils stabilize within a year after disturbance (Gooseff et al., 
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0037" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0037">2009</a>). Our results agree qualitatively with these, because we saw the most seedlings in the sites aged to within 1 decade old.
 </p>
</sec>
