<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece34882-sec-0004" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Site characterization and observational design</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In July 2012 and 2013, we quantified abiotic and biotic characteristics at each site. We chose the month of July in order to quantify site conditions at midsummer, when most seedlings have germinated, plant canopies are fully expanded, and ground is snow‐free. Abiotic characteristics included elevation and soil variables; biotic characteristics included vegetative cover and seedbank variables. Because we expected the greatest seedling recruitment to occur in the lower portion of the RTS where soil had stabilized, in each RTS age category we ran a single 50 m transect on the lower half of the RTS running upslope, with the transect origin (0–1 m) at the downslope end (Figure 
  <a rid="ece34882-fig-0002" ref-type="fig" href="#ece34882-fig-0002">2</a>e). Transects in undisturbed controls were located within 500 m of the nearest RTS transect. At each transect, we calculated mean elevation (m) and relative change in elevation (highest point ‐ lowest point) from GPS points to account for RTS depressions versus the flatter ground in undisturbed control locations.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Measurements were made inside 1 × 1 m plots along each transect. We measured soil temperature, soil moisture, and active layer depth at 2.5 m intervals (20 plots per transect), plant cover and seedling counts at 5 m intervals (10 plots per transect), soil nutrients from resin bags (five bags per transect), seed rain traps (five traps per transect), and soil seedbanks (3–4 plots per transect). The locations of resin bag, seed rain, and seedbank plots from transect origin were chosen using a random number generator. Seedbank plots were in the same plots or ≤4 m from abiotic and cover measurements described above and thus represent a subsample of plant cover and in situ seedling plots. Active layer depth, soil temperatures, and soil moisture levels were averaged from three sample points measured inside each plot. Active layer depth was measured using a 1.5 m steel thaw probe driven into the ground until rock or ice was struck. To estimate midsummer soil conditions experienced by seedlings, soil temperature (°C) and percent soil moisture at 5 cm depth were measured using handheld probes. We made visual estimates of aerial percent cover of vascular plants, mosses, and lichens identified to genus or species in each sample plot by counting the number of squares filled by each species using a 1 × 1 m grid divided into 10 × 10 cm squares (optical cramming). In each cover plot, we counted the number of live seedlings (assigning a maximum of 100 seedlings to plots with ≥100 seedlings m
  <span class="sup">−2</span>). We recorded the height and width to the nearest 0.1 cm of the tallest shrub and identified shrubs to species or plant functional type. Nomenclature follows Hultén (
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0045" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0045">1968</a>), except where noted. We quantified seed rain by species or functional type by counting the average number of seeds caught over the month of July 2013 in 20 × 20 cm vinyl turf seed traps and dividing by seed trap area (m
  <span class="sup">2</span>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An index of plant‐available soil nutrient levels (NH
  <sub>4</sub>
  <span class="sup">+</span> and NO
  <sub>3</sub>
  <span class="sup">−</span>) was measured using mixed‐bed ion‐exchange resins (IONAC
  <span class="sup">®</span> nm‐60 H+/OH− form, type I beads 16–50 mesh; J.T. Baker, Phillipsburg, New Jersey, USA). Each resin bag was made of nylon mesh acid‐washed in 10% HCl and rinsed with DI water prior to filling with 9 g fresh weight (fw) of resin, then preloaded with 2 M KCl overnight before being placed into the field. One resin bag per plot was placed in the soil at approximately 5 cm depth, in five randomly selected plots per transect, and left in place from July 6 to 31, 2013. Collected resin bags were transported to the laboratory on ice, washed free of soil using millipore‐filtered water, and stored at −20°C until extraction. Each resin bag was extracted in 100 ml of 2 M KCl agitated overnight on a shaker. Extracts were individually filtered using Whatman grade 1 filter paper, stored at −20°C, and then thawed at 4°C prior to analysis. NH
  <sub>4</sub>
  <span class="sup">+</span> and NO
  <sub>3</sub>
  <span class="sup">−</span> concentrations (in μg g
  <span class="sup">−1</span> dw resin) were determined colorimetrically on a Technicon autoanalyzer (Tarrytown, New York, USA) using methods from Whitledge, Malloy, Patton, and Wirick (
  <a rid="ece34882-bib-0087" ref-type="ref" href="#ece34882-bib-0087">1981</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
