<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">A relatively good part of isopod diversity consists of troglobious species, whose distribution patterns might be particularly interesting from the environmental change point of view. In fact, it is believed that climatic changes are among the major selective stresses that lead to adaptation to a life in caves. 
 <xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Manicastri and Argano (1989)</xref> had attempted a global-scale analysis of troglobious species known at the time, and found again that highest diversity is concentrated in circum-Mediterranean countries and at similar latitudes in the New World (southern USA and Mexico), regions near the southern borders of glacial ice cover (
 <xref rid="B61" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Jass and Klausmeier 2006</xref>). Of course, the occurrence of troglobious species is strongly related with the availability of proper geological substrate (e.g., karstic systems), so the respective patterns might reflect the global distribution of caves instead. Furthermore, the structure of karstic systems also affects the degree of endemism, as identified by 
 <xref rid="B85" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Manicastri and Argano (1989)</xref>. For example, troglobious species of Greece are mostly endemic to one or a few neighbouring caves whereas local endemism is much lower for troglobionts of northern Balkans where caves form larger and more inter-connected systems. Nevertheless, this might not always be the case, as shown by the troglobious species of Romania most of which occur in a small number of neighbouring caves (
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Giurginca et al. 2015</xref>). Therefore, explorations on the global-scale distribution of troglobious species should be made among geologically comparable regions. A quarter of a century after this study, though, we still lack data for the isopod fauna of many cave-rich regions of the world (but see 
 <xref rid="B74" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Kováč et al. 2014</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B35" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Giurginca et al. 2015</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B128" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Souza-Silva and Ferreira 2015</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B99" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Reboleira et al. 2015</xref>), so not much can be said regarding global patterns. Terrestrial isopods, though, are among the most frequent and ubiquitous cavernicolous animal groups, even if the representation of different families in caves is highly skewed. At the same time caves provide an important control system in studies on effects of environmental changes, especially climate driven ones, so intensive studies of caves in all parts of the globe are much needed. If increased drought or lowered temperature, or a combination of these factors, has been the main selective pressure on isopods towards a cavernicolous life, it remains to be seen how expected climate change might affect them in the future, given that predictions show increased temperature and drought in many regions that are today rich in troglobious or troglophilous forms (e.g., Greece). Given that temperature in caves is usually very close to the mean temperature of their region, if troglobious species are stenothermal, we might expect increased extinction rates with increasing mean temperature, even though toglobious isopods seem to be more sensitive to humidity variation (see below). In any case, troglobious isopods can provide excellent case studies in modelling cave environments under on-going climate change. In addition, there are also other formations similar to caves, such as sinkholes in karstic regions that provide refugia at a local or regional scale. These habitats provide a ‘negative’ altitudinal gradient in temperature and humidity that effects species distribution. Rare species can be abundant in such formations, possibly able to rescue a valuable species pool under climate change (
 <xref rid="B146" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Vilisics et al. 2008</xref>, 
 <xref rid="B125" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Sólymos et al. 2009</xref>).
</p>
