<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<fn-group>
 <fn id="Fn1">
  <label>1</label>
  <p id="Par3">We use the term “blog” as a short-hand for a variety of social media sites, including for example YouTube, that permit user-generated content and in particular public comments. Those sites that permit generation of user content are collectively also known as Web 2.0 (Kata, 
   <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2012</xref>).
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="Fn2">
  <label>2</label>
  <p id="Par21">Age was self-reported using a slider with end points 15 and 100. The minimum reported age was 18 and the maximum 100, with eight participants reporting an age above 90. Because all participants passed the a priori comprehension criterion, these observations were retained for analysis.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="Fn3">
  <label>3</label>
  <p id="Par29">This variable had one missing observation, which explains why the denominator 
   <italic>df</italic> are different from all the others for this test.
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn id="Fn4">
  <label>4</label>
  <p id="Par39">The difference in perceived consensus between the two types of comments is 16.64, which translates into .74 of a standard deviation. The correlation between 
   <italic>refReadCons</italic> and AGW was 
   <italic>r</italic> = .19, implying that a 1 SD decrease in perceived consensus corresponded to a .19 SD decrease in AGW. Given that the standard deviation of AGW across all participants was .87, the expected shift downward in AGW acceptance as a function of contrarian comments was .74 × .19 × .87, or .13 on the 5-point scale.
  </p>
 </fn>
 <fn>
  <p>The original version of this article was revised: Confidence intervals and regression lines were omitted from Fig. 1 in this article as originally published. This error was introduced during production.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn>
  <p>
   <bold>Publisher’s note</bold>
  </p>
  <p>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations.</p>
 </fn>
 <fn>
  <p>
   <bold>Author Note</bold>
  </p>
  <p>S.L. developed the study concept with assistance from J.C. and N.F. J.C. was responsible for stimulus preparation. G.G. conducted the structural-equation modeling and S.L. performed the remaining analysis. N.F. contributed to the Discussion and theoretical developments. S.L. wrote the first draft and all authors contributed to the approved final version of the manuscript. Preparation of this article was facilitated by a Discovery Grant from the Australian Research Council and an Australian Professorial Fellowship to the first author. During part of this work, the first author was also supported by funding from the Royal Society and from the Psychonomic Society. N.F. was partially funded by the Defence Science and Technology (DST) Group under a Collaborative Agreement 8382.</p>
 </fn>
</fn-group>
