<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Outdoor workers in particular have been considered at high risk of adverse impacts in part because of their increased exposure to heat and humidity and work that may involve heavy exertion.
 <xref rid="cit0013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">[13,14]</sup>
 </xref> The Occupational Safety and Health Administration conducted a limited assessment of outdoor heat-related fatalities and identified 106 deaths in the United States from 2008–2014 (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.osha.gov/SLTC/heatillness/map.html" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.osha.gov/SLTC/heatillness/map.html</ext-link>). In 
 <xref rid="f0001" ref-type="fig" class="xref">Figure 1</xref>, the locations of these deaths are mapped along with the projected number of days/year in 2020 with temperatures that exceed 90°F. The number of days with temperatures above 90°F is projected to increase. Since most fatalities between 2008 and 2014 occurred in areas that are projected to have increased number of days above 90°F it is likely that more fatalities may occur in the future. For workers who may have second jobs or live in homes that lack efficient cooling or have high humidity, heat stress and susceptibility to heat-related illnesses may be even higher, and may be further complicated by the urban heat island effect (i.e., built-up areas releasing heat absorbed during the day and night).
 <xref rid="cit0014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">[14]</sup>
 </xref> Some workers who perform heavy labor in outdoor and indoor hot environments and are paid a piece rate (like many transient or immigrant farm workers), and those who have poor health and economic conditions with few or non-existent bargaining possibilities, may also be particularly vulnerable to adverse effects. These workers may choose to decline rest and water breaks if they negatively affect their income.
 <xref rid="cit0011" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">[11,15]</sup>
 </xref> Also, unacclimatized new workers or workers with less employment tenure have been shown to have proportionally more heat-related illness.
 <xref rid="cit0016" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <sup class="sup">[16]</sup>
 </xref> 
</p>
