<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analysis</div>
 <sec id="FPar1" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Construct validity OTECT</div>
  <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To determine the construct validity of the newly designed questionnaire, an exploratory factor analysis was performed with Varimax rotation. The final amount of data for factor analysis was 140 (excluding missing data), providing a ratio of over three cases per variable. The Kaiser-Meyer-Olkin measure of sampling adequacy was 0.896, which was above the commonly recommended value of 0.6, and Bartlett’s test of sphericity was significant (
   <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.001). The number of factors was forced to 9 from the original version of the questionnaire that contained 9 factors [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>]. Two factors were then eliminated due to them containing items with double loading. Furthermore the Cronbach’s alpha coefficients were calculated to determine the internal consistency of the scales.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar2" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Demographic data</div>
  <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Descriptive statistics were performed on the demographic data.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">OTECT items</div>
  <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Items with negative phrasing were recoded before analyzing the data. The Likert-scale items were analyzed and presented as a mean and a standard deviation and analyzed per professional group. Thereafter analyses were performed on the factor level for each group. To look for differences between professional groups analysis of variance (ANOVA) was performed. The Bonferoni correction was then performed for post-hoc analysis to minimize the type 1 error [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>]. The significant difference was determined at the 
   <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.05 levels.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
