<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec19" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Theme 1: The nature of work in an OT</div>
 <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Characteristics of the OT work environment were the main factor discussed by participants in all three groups. Mainly influencing their learning was 1) the high-stakes nature of the OT and how supervisors deal with it, 2) working with time constraints, and 3) physical discomfort caused by being in the OT.</p>
 <sec id="Sec190" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The high stake nature of the OT and how supervisors deal with it</div>
  <p id="Par31" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All participants indicated that the nature of the learning environment, namely high stakes, negatively influenced the learning experience in the OT. Patient safety always came first, backgrounding their learning process. One anesthesia resident said:
   <div class="disp-quote">
    <p id="Par32">“
     <span class="italic">It is a place where we put a patient between life and death. Yes, we want to learn, but the patient safety always comes first.</span>” (Anesthesia resident, third year.)
    </p>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p id="Par33" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All participants mentioned that how their supervisors dealt with critical situations heavily influenced their learning experiences and the extent to which they felt that the supervisor was a good role-model.
   <div class="disp-quote">
    <p id="Par34">“
     <span class="italic">Once, one of my supervisors used bad words and yelled in my face during a critical period. I know that he was stressed out because he was responsible for the patient safety. But to be honest, I was shocked; I had never expected anyone to act like this in such a tense situation.</span>” (Student nurse anesthetist, first year.)
    </p>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec20" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Working with time constraints</div>
  <p id="Par35" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">How the OT is organized can hinder learning by putting the importance of service ahead of education. The service burden led to a condensed operative list and an increased workload for trainees. It also resulted in a time-constraint issue in the OT as a place to learn. All participants recognized this problem and reported it as affecting their learning. The pressure to utilize resources efficiently combined with tight operating schedules resulted in a sense of continuous rush and hurriedness. Feeling rushed forced the learners to keep up with the OT team instead of taking the time to elaborate and reflect on the knowledge gained and to practice their skills.
   <div class="disp-quote">
    <p id="Par36">“….
     <span class="italic">like when I sent the patient off from the OT to the recovery room, this should be a part of learning to look after the patient in the recovery room as an immediate postoperative care, right? But the next patient on the list had been wheeled in the operating room right after the previous patient was out. And I was the last one running back to the OT with everybody waiting and looking at me as if I was the one who held the team back.</span>” (Anesthesia resident, first year.)
    </p>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p id="Par37" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Participants from AR and SN groups reported that hurriedness sometimes came from co-workers who did not wait for them to practice their skills. This was not an issue in the SR group, who recognized their role and tried to strike a balance between education and service. One participant from the SN group mentioned:
   <div class="disp-quote">
    <p id="Par38">“
     <span class="italic">Some of the co-workers can be very pushy. They don’t want to wait for me to get my job done. Like one time after intubation, I didn’t even put a tape on the tube, but they were ready to turn the patient prone.”</span> (Student nurse anesthetist, first year.)
    </p>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec21" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Physical discomfort caused by being in the OT</div>
  <p id="Par39" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The physical discomfort caused by room temperature and the large amount of sensory information was discussed by all groups. However, participants identified different elements of the physical environment causing discomfort. One participant from the SN group reported that the noisy environment hampered meaningful contact with her supervisor:
   <div class="disp-quote">
    <p id="Par40">“
     <span class="italic">Sometimes, the OT can be very noisy, like the sound of the drilling and hammering in orthopedic theater. I understand that it is unavoidable. But it disturbed me when I tried to elaborate on my discussion with the supervisor.</span>” (Student nurse anesthetist, first year.)
    </p>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p id="Par41" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Participants from the AR group did not mention the noise, but had an issue with the temperature: too cold an operating room made them feel uncomfortable. In contrast, one participant from the SR group reported that quietness was a problem that could raise the stress level of the student; as she said:
   <div class="disp-quote">
    <p id="Par42">“
     <span class="italic">I would like it if my supervisor plays music during the operation, any kind of music would do. It makes the overall environment positive, including learning environment. Imagine when the room is so quiet, and a tense situation occurs, like massive bleeding, the tension in the air will be magnified when it’s too quiet.</span>” (Surgical resident, fourth year.)
    </p>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
