<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Instrument</div>
 <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The learning climate is an intellectual entity which is difficult to be quantitatively measured [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>]. Because there was no previously-available instrument suitable for the operating theater setting and understandable to three different, professional groups (surgery, anesthesiology and nursing), a new questionnaire was created, based on a combination of three instruments aimed at measuring the educational environment: 1) the Dutch Residency Educational Climate Test (D-RECT) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>], 2) the Anesthetic Theatre Educational Environment Measure (ATEEM) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>], and 3) the Surgical Theatre Educational Environment Measure (STEEM) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>]. All three instruments have been previously validated and the permissions to reproduce all instruments were obtained. Items from each instrument were selected by comparing the three instruments to cover the main constructs of the three instruments and create a well-balanced instrument (acceptable in length, without redundancy and sufficient items per construct) that would be usable by trainees from all three professions.
 </p>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This process resulted in the creation of a new questionnaire called the Operating Theater Educational Climate Test (OTECT), consisting of 46 items. Each item was assessed on a five-point Likert scale, where a score of 1 denoted ‘strongly disagree’ and a score of 5 denoted ‘strongly agree’.</p>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The questionnaire was translated into Thai by two separate translators, followed by two separate retranslations back into English. The content validity of the Thai version was tested by piloting the questionnaire with surgical staff (
  <span class="italic">N</span> = 3), anesthesia staff (
  <span class="italic">N</span> = 3), nursing staff (
  <span class="italic">N</span> = 3) as well as trainees from all three groups (
  <span class="italic">N</span> = 15, 5 for each profession). Furthermore, a section was added to the questionnaire to collect demographic data from the participants (age, gender, professional department and level of study). Finally, trainees were asked to rate the overall quality of the learning climate in the operating theater, on a scale of one to five, as well as an open-ended question asking them to describe the factors they felt influenced the learning climate most. See Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>: Appendix 1 for the questionnaire.
 </p>
</sec>
