<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec28" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Supervision &amp; high stakes environment</div>
 <p id="Par60" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results of the OTECT questionnaires and the focus groups both pointed to the importance of the supervisor in the OT for all three groups: Supervisors could make or break the learning climate. The key role of the supervisor in the clinical learning environment is supported by a large body of literature from different health professional contexts and levels of training [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>–
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>]. Olmos-Vega [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>] and Marshall [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>] revealed that balancing between clinical supervision and resident autonomy according to level of training is an important factor to improve residents’ preferences, which could affect the experienced learning climate. Iwaszkiewicz et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>] explored the characteristics of supervisors who were considered good supervisors in the OT as perceived by surgical residents. Good supervisors created a favorable learning climate by being polite and respectful to their colleagues and trainees, staying calm during crisis situations, providing constructive feedback and demonstrating enthusiasm to teach. Our results add to these findings that inappropriate stress-coping mechanisms of supervisors during crisis as well as the impolite and unsafe learning climate sometimes created strongly impact the learning experiences of trainees in that environment.
 </p>
 <p id="Par61" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The high-stakes OT environment affected supervisors and trainees from all three professional groups. Because patient care and safety are the primary goals of the OT, supervisors need to constantly weigh how to ensure patient safety while creating learning opportunities [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>]. Our focus groups results revealed that postgraduate trainees were very aware of the importance of patient safety and did put it ahead of their learning. However, sometimes supervisors responded to high-stakes situations by creating an unsafe learning climate by criticizing, belittling and scolding. Participants from all groups recognized that an unsafe learning climate could be generated by the verbal and nonverbal behavior of their supervisors. Both Lyon [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>] and Flott and Linden [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>] described how the high-stakes nature of the OT environment directly influenced trainees’ ability to learn there. Lyon more specifically indicated how learning in the OT requires a balance between the emotional impact of the high-stakes environment, the purpose of educational tasks in the busy OT, and the social and interprofessional relations [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>]. Ali et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>] and Bragard et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>] studied the stress level of emergency physicians and found high levels of stress caused by the nature of high stake environment as well as the need to supervise trainees. Dependent on the supervisor’s coping style, their expressions of emotion and stress could directly influence the postgraduate trainees. Our study demonstrated that when the supervisors had differing preferences and demanded that their personal preferences were followed, it affected the trainees by creating feelings of ambiguity and hampering their experienced learning climate. The participants in our study coped with the unsafe learning environment by making their learning secondary and being as unobtrusive as possible – they avoided critical thinking, discussing and practicing – in order to avoid worsening the atmosphere. Hoel et al. [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>] point to the fact that it is important to consider how negative feelings caused by supervisors influence the socialization process and potentially stimulates reproduction of this behavior in trainees, producing a chain of unfriendly and negative learning atmosphere in the clinical setting.
 </p>
</sec>
