<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Mechanistic SDMs predict the distribution of habitat suitability through space and time by assessing energy balance. Daily and seasonal fluctuations in the thermal and hydric environment jeopardize energy balance by reducing the rates and durations of activities that supply energy and resources (
 <xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">14</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">15</italic>
 </xref>). Temperature constrains energy intake in plants and animals by reducing the rates of photosynthesis and the capacity to forage and assimilate energy, respectively (
 <xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">16</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">17</italic>
 </xref>). Similarly, the vapor content of the air also influences habitat suitability by limiting the duration of foraging activity and increasing lethal dehydration stress (
 <xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">15</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">16</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">18</italic>
 </xref>). Climate change might further exacerbate hydric stress as warming increases the drying power of the air. Physical expectations indicate that warming will increase evaporation rates by increasing the vapor pressure deficit (VPD), one of the primary forces driving evaporation rates (
 <xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">16</italic>
 </xref>). High VPDs are known to threaten plants as a major driver of mortality events (
 <xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">16</italic>
 </xref>), and the rise in evaporation rates under climate change increases exposure to lethal dehydration events by fourfold in birds (
 <xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">19</italic>
 </xref>). Therefore, ecological predictions require knowledge on the physiological and behavioral strategies that organisms use to minimize thermal and hydric stress.
</p>
