<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par23">To conclude, assessing the vulnerability of islands to climate change represents a first step towards identifying where its impact on biodiversity is most likely to be seen
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">60</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">61</xref>
 </sup>. Importantly, by tackling the crucial challenges to predict and mitigate the effect of climate change on biodiversity, this study contributes to issues of global relevance as defined in the policies of the IPCC
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>
 </sup> and the IPBES
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62">62</xref>
 </sup>. We found that (i) sea level rise, shifts in temperature and shifts in rainfall may not cause high absolute ExpPD
 <italic>loss</italic> at a global scale (ii) however, ExpPD
 <italic>loss</italic> on some vulnerable islands tends to be higher than if extinctions were random (iii) taxa found on vulnerable islands likely capture some deep and/or long phylogenetic branches. The expected significant loss of monocot PD on vulnerable islands is then another warning that climate change will affect human well-being
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">63</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">64</xref>
 </sup>. The results of this study can be used in two ways. First, they can serve as a guide to identify where to act in order to protect the tree of life. While we focused on monocots, other highly diverse insular groups with many endemic species, such as eudicots, would be worth investigated in order to elucidate to which extent these findings can be generalized. Our analysis of islands worldwide provides a chart indicating where to focus to avoid imminent losses. This shows the need of moving from global to local in order to monitor the status of the local populations subtending these evolutionary branches that are under threat, and study ways to avoid their extinctions. The second perspective concerns the synergistic effects of climate change with other threats impacting biodiversity
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">65</xref>
 </sup>. Even on islands not considered to be vulnerable to climate change, other factors, especially human-induced habitat losses and species invasions, may represent an immediate threat to their biodiversity
 <sup>
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">66</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">67</xref>
 </sup>. Future studies should consider the diversity of threats on island biodiversity, including biotic multipliers, and their interactions.
</p>
