<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="S0003-S2003" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Human mental and social health and well-being</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Including the social environment in the One Health paradigm in the North facilitates addressing human health and well-being more holistically at both the individual and community level. The 2004 Arctic Climate Impact Assessment states: “It is more likely that populations living in close association with the land, in remote communities, and those that already face a variety of health-related challenges will be most vulnerable to future climate changes” [
  <a rid="CIT0017" href="#CIT0017">17</a>]. The US Global Change Research Group’s 2018 assessment declares: “Climate change creates new risks and exacerbates existing vulnerabilities in communities across the USA, presenting growing challenges to human health and safety, quality of life, and the rate of economic growth” [
  <a rid="CIT0003" href="#CIT0003">3</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Numerous indicators reflect the elevated mental health stress that northern Indigenous peoples experience, including higher numbers of self-reported poor mental health days for Alaska Native adults, compared with the U.S. average [
  <a rid="CIT0043" href="#CIT0043">43</a>], higher rates of sexual and domestic violence [
  <a rid="CIT0044" href="#CIT0044">44</a>], and most strikingly, elevated rates of suicide [
  <a rid="CIT0018" href="#CIT0018">18</a>,
  <a rid="CIT0045" href="#CIT0045">45</a>]. As leading circumpolar health experts write in the 
  <span class="italic">Circumpolar Health Atlas</span>: “Circumpolar peoples are subject to immense mental stress as their communities undergo profound social and cultural changes. Particularly for Indigenous peoples, the second half of the twentieth century has been a period when the traditional life irrevocably gave way to modern ‘Western’ lifestyles” [
  <a rid="CIT0018" href="#CIT0018">18</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This rapid socio-economic and cultural change of the past three quarters of a century radically altered the social fabric of Indigenous communities. Migrants inadvertently brought infectious diseases that killed large numbers of Indigenous individuals, sometimes nearly destroying whole communities. Christian missionaries introduced a new world view, implicitly and/or explicitly devaluing traditional ways of knowing and being, while they also brought medical care, sanitary practices, and social services that saved lives and improved some health outcomes. Meanwhile, assimilationist educational policies, including English-only rules and boarding schools, deprived Indigenous individuals, families and communities of fluency in their native languages and much other cultural knowledge [
  <a rid="CIT0046" href="#CIT0046">46</a>], resulting in what is now called historical trauma [
  <a rid="CIT0047" href="#CIT0047">47</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">World War II and Cold War construction projects, along with the arrival of government services and transfer payments, generated sweeping socioeconomic changes to rural Alaska and northern Canada in the mid-twentieth century [
  <a rid="CIT0048" href="#CIT0048">48</a>]. In the 1950s the Canadian government encouraged nomadic Inuit to settle in hamlets with offers of housing, education and healthcare [
  <a rid="CIT0049" href="#CIT0049">49</a>]. Employment opportunities drew people from subsistence activities, increasing sedentarism and less healthy diets, while the cash flow enhanced access to alcohol. Transfer payments and education and employment opportunities for both women and men encouraged a shift from subsistence to wage labour, all of which altered gender relations, with males experiencing more negative effects of acculturative stress, including loss of identity and self-esteem [
  <a rid="CIT0018" href="#CIT0018">18</a>,
  <a rid="CIT0050" href="#CIT0050">50</a>,
  <a rid="CIT0051" href="#CIT0051">51</a>]. Social pathologies, including alcohol abuse, sexual and domestic violence, and suicide skyrocketed in the wake of these developments [
  <a rid="CIT0045" href="#CIT0045">45</a>,
  <a rid="CIT0048" href="#CIT0048">48</a>,
  <a rid="CIT0050" href="#CIT0050">50</a>,
  <a rid="CIT0052" href="#CIT0052">52</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In Alaska, suicide rates among Alaska Natives, especially men aged 15–34 years, rose rapidly in the 1960s, the decade following statehood, when infrastructure development and the infusion of federal transfers altered the economic landscape [
  <a rid="CIT0052" href="#CIT0052">52</a>]. The 20
  <span class="sup">th</span> century spike in Alaska Native suicides emerged among Inuit across the Arctic approximately a decade after the period of mid-twentieth century “active colonialism” in each region, when government-sponsored programs dramatically altered traditional lifeways [
  <a rid="CIT0045" href="#CIT0045">45</a>]. Today’s strikingly high suicide rates among young men differ starkly from the rare historical occurrences of suicide by older men in failing health. Of the current pattern among the Inuit, Canadian researcher Jack Hicks writes: “The young Inuit men at greatest risk appear to be those who are situated somewhere between the historical Inuit ‘life script’ and the emerging urban Inuit ‘life script’, in communities and families where unemployment and social dysfunction are more common” [
  <a rid="CIT0045" href="#CIT0045">45</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">High levels of mental stress can also be seen in the rates of sexual and domestic violence in Alaska and northern Canada, that far exceed national averages [
  <a rid="CIT0053" href="#CIT0053">53</a>,
  <a rid="CIT0054" href="#CIT0054">54</a>]. Many historical, social and economic forces are thought to contribute to such violence. The role of Adverse Childhood Experiences (ACEs) in mental and physical health problems later in life is well recognized [
  <a rid="CIT0055" href="#CIT0055">55</a>] and contributes to the cyclical affects of violence in the home that are well documented in the North [
  <a rid="CIT0045" href="#CIT0045">45</a>]. The common factor of alcohol consumption by both perpetrators and victims complicates reporting and prosecution [
  <a rid="CIT0044" href="#CIT0044">44</a>,
  <a rid="CIT0045" href="#CIT0045">45</a>,
  <a rid="CIT0056" href="#CIT0056">56</a>–
  <a rid="CIT0059" href="#CIT0059">59</a>]. Climate change-related disruptions to traditional lifeways and to family and community life can be expected to exacerbate mental stress that contributes to such violence [
  <a rid="CIT0021" href="#CIT0021">21</a>]. Among other effects, Indigenous peoples’ strong attachment to place can lead to elevated anxiety and sense of loss when displacement occurs [
  <a rid="CIT0007" href="#CIT0007">7</a>,
  <a rid="CIT0060" href="#CIT0060">60</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Foreseeable mental health impacts of climate change include: stress on individuals, families and communities related to increased exposure to physical dangers; increased depression, distress, anxiety, and hopelessness; as well as rising rates of alcohol/drug use, violence, and suicide ideation owing to uncertainties and threats to traditional lifeways and food security. Likely indirect effects of climate change on mental health and well-being include the disruption of economic and social networks, mass migration, and the relocation of houses, buildings and even whole villages [
  <a rid="CIT0022" href="#CIT0022">22</a>]. On the other hand, close interpersonal, family and community ties provide a source of strength in the face of such challenges. Community-based research on alcohol abuse and suicide in Alaska Native communities identified an inter-related individual, family and community traits that contribute to resilience associated with lower rates of alcohol abuse and suicide [
  <a rid="CIT0061" href="#CIT0061">61</a>]. The proactive capacity of the One Health paradigm to anticipate these myriad, interrelated effects of climate change, and integrate them to address mental and community health challenges in the North will be a potent factor in this model’s potential to build effective management strategies for these issues.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One example of operationalising One Health in indigenous communities is the health indicators developed by the ﻿Swinomish Indian Tribal Community [
  <a rid="CIT0011" href="#CIT0011">11</a>] to assess human health outcomes in a more culturally appropriate way. An example of effective local collaboration that aligns well with One Health is the 
  <span class="italic">coordinated community response</span>, or Duluth Model, which has shown promise in reducing domestic and sexual violence in Alaskan communities [
  <a rid="CIT0044" href="#CIT0044">44</a>,
  <a rid="CIT0062" href="#CIT0062">62</a>]. The victim-centred concept integrates the efforts of first responders, other service providers, and advocates to encourage reporting and reduce domestic violence. Many Alaskan and northern Canadian localities lack the public safety and medical personnel required to provide such integrated responses, however, which illustrates the need for financial support from national and subnational governments to respond effectively to these and other threats to health and well-being.
 </p>
</sec>
