<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="S0004" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One health in the subsistence context</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this manuscript, subsistence refers to reliance on hunting, fishing, and gathering to obtain a significant portion of one’s food, shelter, clothing, or livelihood. For cultural and nutritional reasons, and due to limited transportation infrastructure and economic opportunities, people continue to live off the land, or live a subsistence lifestyle, in many communities in the far North [
  <a rid="CIT0063" href="#CIT0063">63</a>,
  <a rid="CIT0064" href="#CIT0064">64</a>]. In many regions, subsistence foods provide a large proportion of caloric intake [
  <a rid="CIT0065" href="#CIT0065">65</a>]. Especially in Indigenous communities, subsistence practices hold deep cultural meaning. As Aqqaluk Lynge of Greenland, President of the Inuit Circumpolar Conference (ICC), remarked in 1999: “indeed, hunting, fishing and gathering food is central to all Indigenous peoples’ survival” [
  <a rid="CIT0063" href="#CIT0063">63</a>]. This view of subsistence captures the centrality of peoples’ connection to the land, water, and animals to their health and well-being, and to community well-being.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While subsistence continues to play a vital role in individual nutrition and well-being, and in community food security through traditional sharing practices, multiple forces currently threaten subsistence lifestyles. The cash economy may pose the greatest threat in the early 21
  <span class="sup">st</span> century. Taking part in subsistence activities requires participation in the cash economy, if not by the hunter, fisher or gatherer, then by a family member, to purchase implements such as transportation and hunting equipment, as well as fuel. Meanwhile, wage employment limits the time available to participate in subsistence activities. Therefore, modernity creates a paradox for many subsistence communities: Technology, such as transportation, rifles, and ammunition, has made harvesting resources more efficient, but participating in the cash economy hinders full participation in such culturally and nutritionally important activities owing to the demands it places on the individual’s time and location [
  <a rid="CIT0010" href="#CIT0010">10</a>,
  <a rid="CIT0066" href="#CIT0066">66</a>]. Spending less time “on the land” leads to loss of traditional subsistence skills and knowledge, and it weakens intergenerational bonds [
  <a rid="CIT0010" href="#CIT0010">10</a>,
  <a rid="CIT0067" href="#CIT0067">67</a>]. Moerlein and Carothers found that residents of Noatak and Selawik in northwest Alaska perceived socio-economic changes as a greater threat to subsistence practices and traditional lifeways than environmental change, although they viewed the multiple forces of change holistically [
  <a rid="CIT0010" href="#CIT0010">10</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The impacts of socio-economic change on subsistence practices may be more visible, but environmental change and contamination of traditional foods increasingly threaten traditional lifeways in the North. Climate change alters availability and access to subsistence resources. Climate change impacts are more extreme at high latitudes, with the North showing an average temperature increase 2.5 times the rate of more temperate regions [
  <a rid="CIT0068" href="#CIT0068">68</a>]. Indigenous hunters have identified changing marine ice, river ice, and trail conditions as significant impediments to safety and successful subsistence hunting, and in general as a threat to the availability of subsistence resources [
  <a rid="CIT0021" href="#CIT0021">21</a>,
  <a rid="CIT0023" href="#CIT0023">23</a>]. Furthermore, a warming climate threatens some resource processing and storage practices such as fermenting fish and meat, and storage of food in ice cellars. Thawing permafrost can render traditional ice cellars unusable, leading to food spoilage with obvious food safety and associated health implications, all of which threatens traditional subsistence cultures [
  <a rid="CIT0069" href="#CIT0069">69</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Pollution from industrial production in more southern, populated regions not only contributes to climate change but also releases substances that contaminate resources in far northern communities. Through global atmospheric and oceanographic processes, especially long-lived contaminants accumulate in subsistence resources. The levels of contamination vary greatly by region and among species, as they feed at various levels of the food web. In the Canadian Arctic, the contaminants of greatest concern in subsistence foods are the persistent organic pollutants chlordane and toxaphene, and PCBs, along with mercury and naturally occurring radionuclides [
  <a rid="CIT0070" href="#CIT0070">70</a>]. Bowhead whales show relatively low levels of contaminants, whereas narwhales and other marine mammals that feed at higher levels of the food web have high concentrations of persistent contaminants such as mercury in their tissues [
  <a rid="CIT0071" href="#CIT0071">71</a>–
  <a rid="CIT0074" href="#CIT0074">74</a>]. Arctic residents who consume higher proportions of terrestrial and freshwater foods accrue the highest levels of radionuclides [
  <a rid="CIT0075" href="#CIT0075">75</a>]. Developing human fetusus is at greatest risk from these persistent contaminants [
  <a rid="CIT0070" href="#CIT0070">70</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This variability and the resulting uncertainty for consumers regarding the safety of these resources pose challenges in communicating associated health threats to communities [
  <a rid="CIT0070" href="#CIT0070">70</a>]. The risk of contaminated traditional foods leads not only to direct health consequences through consumer exposure to contaminants, but also to fear of using traditional resources and food insecurity, and to consumption of lower quality store-bought food, which engenders broader health consequences. Commercially produced foods, especially those available in remote northern regions, tend to be less nutritious and have high levels of added sugars and unhealthy fats. Among Arctic residents, days with consumption of subsistence foods have significantly less consumption of fat, saturated fat, sucrose and total carbohydrate than days when subsistence foods are not consumed [
  <a rid="CIT0070" href="#CIT0070">70</a>]. Higher consumption of non-traditional foods, as well as the more sedentary lifestyle that corresponds with movement away from traditional subsistence practices, has been linked to health problems such as obesity, diabetes, colorectal cancer, cardiovascular disease, and developmental disorders [
  <a rid="CIT0065" href="#CIT0065">65</a>,
  <a rid="CIT0070" href="#CIT0070">70</a>,
  <a rid="CIT0076" href="#CIT0076">76</a>,
  <a rid="CIT0077" href="#CIT0077">77</a>] and to nutritional deficiencies. For example, in the Yukon–Kuskokwim Delta of Alaska, a retrospective study of banked samples from young Alaska Native women taken from 1960 to 2010 showed a significant decline in plasma vitamin D concentrations associated with a drop in the consumption of traditional marine foods [
  <a rid="CIT0078" href="#CIT0078">78</a>–
  <a rid="CIT0080" href="#CIT0080">80</a>]. The prevalence of lifestyle-associated diseases has been increasing in remote communities throughout the circumpolar North. Given the health benefits of traditional foods and the wide variability of toxins whose harmful effects could outweigh the nutritional value of specific foods, carefully crafted messaging should be targeted toward specific regions and demographic groups, for instance, women of childbearing age.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Finally, a regulatory threat to subsistence exists throughout the circumpolar North. Many hunting and fishing regulations are based on materialistic and individualistic notions of rights that ignore cultural practices such as sharing and the importance of subsistence in maintaining intergenerational bonds [
  <a rid="CIT0063" href="#CIT0063">63</a>]. Some of these regulatory defects or incongruities are beginning to be addressed through co-management approaches towards subsistence resources. However, competition for limited resources between Indigenous and non-Indigenous northerners, as well as inequitable political influence in many northern regions, can leave Indigenous interests under-represented and thereby threaten Indigenous lifeways and community well-being. The One Health paradigm, in fully engaging Indigenous perspectives and Indigenous knowledge, and in considering both individual and community well-being, holds potential for generating regulatory policies that enhance, rather than threaten, the well-being of northern peoples, animals, and the environment.
 </p>
</sec>
