<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="S0002" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One health’s potential for enhancing well-being in the North</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Research conducted within a broad spectrum of disciplines affirms the interdependence of climate change impacts on physical, biological and social processes in the Arctic and the need for holistic approaches to understand and address these impacts [
  <a rid="CIT0009" href="#CIT0009">9</a>,
  <a rid="CIT0010" href="#CIT0010">10</a>]. The preponderance of Indigenous peoples in large areas of the far North also contributes to the paradigm’s salience in the region. The linkage of human health to environmental and animal health corresponds with a holistic world-view and definitions of health and well-being in many Indigenous cultures [
  <a rid="CIT0011" href="#CIT0011">11</a>–
  <a rid="CIT0013" href="#CIT0013">13</a>]. As Moerlein and Carothers discovered through their ethnographic research in the Inupiat villages of Noatak and Selawik, Alaska in 2010 and 2011, although they sought to limit discussions to their observations of environmental changes, “informants consistently discussed wide-ranging shifts in ecological, social, cultural, political, and economic realms as they are experienced together” [
  <a rid="CIT0010" href="#CIT0010">10</a>]. Similarly, in northern Labrador, Inuit focus groups described the effects of reliable sea ice on health, including mental/emotional, cultural, spiritual, social, physical, and economic well-being [
  <a rid="CIT0014" href="#CIT0014">14</a>]. And a study of Nunavut Inuit youth perspectives on health, well-being and happiness tied these conditions closely to environmental health and their ability to maintain subsistence lifeways that tie them closely with family and community members and with their culture [
  <a rid="CIT0015" href="#CIT0015">15</a>]. These responses indicate a worldview in these communities that aligns with One Health. Importantly, the coordinated, holistic One Health paradigm can enhance surveillance capacity to detect health threats early and increase understanding of their relationship with climate change [
  <a rid="CIT0002" href="#CIT0002">2</a>]. Furthermore, the subsistence lifestyle discussed below inherently uses a One Health approach without using that western terminology.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In June 2015, the Arctic Council’s two health-related expert groups – the Sustainable Development Working Group’s (SDWG’s) Arctic Human Health Expert Group (AHHEG) and the Arctic Monitoring and Assessment Program’s (AMAP’s) Human Health Assessment Group (HHAG) jointly identified One Health as a vital initiative for collaboration. Several conference workshops and other forums focusing on the challenges and opportunities presented by operationalizing One Health in the Arctic followed. In May 2017, at the Arctic Council’s Ministerial Meeting in Fairbanks, the Ministers endorsed the project with the following objective: “To operationalize a One Health approach in the Arctic by forging co-equal, inclusive collaborations across multiple scientific disciplines and Arctic communities, to enhance resiliency of the Arctic inhabitants through an enhanced understanding of climatic change impacts on health risks to people, animals, and the environment” [
  <a rid="CIT0016" href="#CIT0016">16</a>]. The endorsement of Operationalizing One Health in the Arctic by the region’s foremost intergovernmental forum illustrates its view of the relevance of this holistic paradigm, especially as climate change poses unprecedented threats to the region’s ecosystem and the health of its peoples.
 </p>
</sec>
