<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="S0003-S2002" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Zoonotic diseases</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The One Health approach also furthers Western scientific knowledge of disease in a physical sense, most notably perhaps in the field of zoonotic diseases. While species richness is relatively low at high latitudes, including the diversity of infectious agents, zoonoses present significant challenges to health in the North. Examples of zoonotic diseases of concern to public health officials include brucellosis, toxoplasmosis, trichinellosis, protozoan infections, echinococcosis, tularemia, anthrax and rabies [
  <a rid="CIT0038" href="#CIT0038">38</a>]. Logistical impediments, including limited transportation infrastructure and extreme weather conditions in remote communities, pose challenges to surveillance and outreach concerning harvesting-related risks associated with these diseases. Climate change imposes the risk of newly invasive diseases such as those borne by ticks and other vectors that may have enhanced survival and proliferation potential as the Arctic warms. Across the Circumpolar North, the thawing of permafrost may also enhance the risk of exposure to pathogens such as anthrax and influenza. The 2016 death of a child associated with an anthrax outbreak in a reindeer herd in the Yamal region of Russia could be an example of how climate change may influence exposure to zoonotic disease threats [
  <a rid="CIT0039" href="#CIT0039">39</a>,
  <a rid="CIT0040" href="#CIT0040">40</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Coordination among subject matter experts including wildlife biologists, infectious disease researchers, local knowledge holders, and public health officials in both human and veterinary medicine would help address these issues more effectively [
  <a rid="CIT0038" href="#CIT0038">38</a>]. A holistic approach could enhance public health responses across disciplines, especially given the uncertainty associated with predicting changes in infectious disease dynamics in the complex system of the infectious disease triad of host, pathogen, and environment in a rapidly changing North [
  <a rid="CIT0041" href="#CIT0041">41</a>]. One Health provides a functional framework for coordination and collaboration across professional specialities [
  <a rid="CIT0042" href="#CIT0042">42</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
