<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Each article included in the study was grouped on the basis of which environmental factor(s) were assessed in the study, and then placed in a corresponding table of the most prevalent environmental factors that emerged from the systematic review. Articles were placed in multiple tables if they examine multiple environmental variables. For each environmental factor table, we applied a coding framework to quantify the number of articles that demonstrated directional changes (increase, decrease, or no change) of specific tea quality parameters. Specifically, we quantified the following quality parameters: (1) increase, decrease, or no change in catechins and other phenolic compounds with an increase in [environmental factor, i.e., temperature], (2) increase, decrease, or no change in catechins and other phenolic compounds with a decrease in [environmental factor, i.e., temperature], (3) increase, decrease, or no change in caffeine with an increase in [environmental factor, i.e., temperature], (4) increase, decrease, or no change in caffeine with a decrease in [environmental factor, i.e., temperature], (5) increase, decrease, or no change in terpenoids and other volatiles with an increase in [environmental factor, i.e., temperature], (6) increase, decrease, or no change in terpenoids and other volatiles with a decrease in [environmental factor, i.e., temperature], (7) increase, decrease, or no change in amino acids with an increase in [environmental factor, i.e., temperature] and, (8) increase, decrease, or no change in amino acids with a decrease in [environmental factor, i.e., temperature]. Unfortunately, as the studies used different measures of crop quality and variable experimental designs, we were unable to quantitatively compare between studies. Three reviewers (DS, DK, and SA) coded the outcomes for each article to ensure there were no discrepancies. The resulting data were summarized into a narrative synthesis and a quantitative synthesis.</p>
