<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s6" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">6.</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Emission metrics for calculation of ‘CO
  <sub>2</sub> equivalence’
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Emission metrics have traditionally been used in policymaking and climate change assessments for the calculation of ‘equivalent’ amounts of non-CO
  <sub>2</sub> and CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions. The global warming potential (GWP), introduced by the IPCC in 1990, is the most widely used metric to calculate this equivalence. It represents the time-integrated RF from a pulse emission of one mass unit of a GHG or other radiatively active species over a chosen time horizon following its emission, relative to the corresponding impact of the emission of one mass unit of CO
  <sub>2</sub>. Multiplying an emission of gas 
  <span class="italic">i</span> by its GWP, for a chosen time horizon, gives the so-called ‘CO
  <sub>2</sub>-equivalent emission’. Ideally, equivalence should give the same climate impact in a given physical climate variable of interest, and for this emission metric it gives equivalence in terms of integrated RF over the chosen time horizon. The GWP has been subject to criticism (e.g. [
  <a rid="RSTA20160445C22" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160445C22">22</a>]) and regular re-evaluation (e.g. [
  <a rid="RSTA20160445C21" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160445C21">21</a>]). A new application of GWP, denoted here as GWP*, is designed to compare the impact of climate-forcing agents with very different lifetimes on future temperatures [
  <a rid="RSTA20160445C5" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160445C5">5</a>]. It has been shown that conventional GWP values can be used to approximate the relative impact of both long-lived (cumulative) GHGs and SLCFs on global temperatures, requiring only a change in usage, but no new metric values or concepts. This new way of using the traditional GWP metric considers the temperature change due to a sustained increase of one tonne per year in the emission rate of a short-lived component (as proposed in [
  <a rid="RSTA20160445C23" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160445C23">23</a>]) to be approximately equivalent to the temperature change due to a one-off pulse emission of GWP
  <span class="italic">
   <sub>H</sub>
  </span> 
  <span class="italic">×</span> 
  <span class="italic">H</span> tonnes of CO
  <sub>2</sub>, where GWP
  <span class="italic">
   <sub>H</sub>
  </span> is the value of that short-lived component GWP for a time horizon, 
  <span class="italic">H</span> [
  <a rid="RSTA20160445C5" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160445C5">5</a>]. Short- and long-lived components are here distinguished by having characteristic atmospheric residence times less than or greater than 
  <span class="italic">H,</span> respectively.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Various alternative metrics have been proposed in the literature, and among these, the global temperature change potential (GTP) [
  <a rid="RSTA20160445C23" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160445C23">23</a>,
  <a rid="RSTA20160445C24" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160445C24">24</a>] has so far received most attention. The GTP represents the impact of the emission of one mass unit of a GHG on global temperature at a specified point in time after emission, again relative to the corresponding impact of the emission of one mass unit of CO
  <sub>2</sub>. (Both GWP and GTP include natural sinks in their formulations.)
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The INDCs submitted ahead of COP21 referred to different emission metrics—mainly GWPs from various IPCC assessments (Second Assessment Report (SAR), the 3rd Assessment Report (TAR), the 4th Assessment Report (AR4) and the 5th Assessment Report (AR5)), and in a few cases GTP. The text of the Paris Agreement leaves the choice of metric open, and paragraph 31 of the Paris outcome (Decision 1/CP.21) requests that Parties will report emissions and removals using common metrics assessed by the IPCC and adopted by the Conference of the Parties serving as the meeting of the Parties to the Paris Agreement.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another candidate for calculating CO
  <sub>2</sub> equivalence is expressing GHGs in terms of ‘CO
  <sub>2</sub>-forcing-equivalent emissions' (CO
  <sub>2</sub>-fe). The temperature response to aggregate CO
  <sub>2</sub>-fe emissions is, by construction, identical to the response to the equivalent emissions of CO
  <sub>2</sub> only. Net-zero CO
  <sub>2</sub>-fe emissions thus correspond to gradually declining RF and stable temperatures [
  <a rid="RSTA20160445C8" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160445C8">8</a>]. Diagnosing CO
  <sub>2</sub>-fe emissions requires a carbon cycle model, but a simple approximation can also be used to estimate CO
  <sub>2</sub>-fe emissions as they approach zero. Because the forcing integrated over a time horizon 
  <span class="italic">H</span> resulting from a pulse injection of CO
  <sub>2</sub> increases approximately linearly with 
  <span class="italic">H</span> over the range of values of 
  <span class="italic">H</span> typically used in policy calculations (as shown in fig. 8.29 of [
  <a rid="RSTA20160445C21" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160445C21">21</a>]), the rate of CO
  <sub>2</sub>-fe emissions is given, to a good approximation, by the rate of change of RF multiplied by 
  <span class="italic">H</span>/AGWP
  <span class="italic">
   <sub>H</sub>
  </span>(CO
  <sub>2</sub>) [
  <a rid="RSTA20160445C23" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160445C23">23</a>], where AGWP
  <span class="italic">
   <sub>H</sub>
  </span>(CO
  <sub>2</sub>) is the absolute GWP of CO
  <sub>2</sub> for time horizon 
  <span class="italic">H</span> [
  <a rid="RSTA20160445C21" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSTA20160445C21">21</a>]. Hence, to a good approximation, net-zero CO
  <sub>2</sub>-fe emissions corresponds to a combination of residual (positive or negative) CO
  <sub>2</sub> emissions balancing a low rate of change of non-CO
  <sub>2</sub> RF given by 
  <div class="inline-formula">
   <span xlink:href="rsta20160445-i1.jpg" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>, where 
  <span class="italic">E</span> is the emission, 
  <span class="italic">F</span> is the radiative forcing and 
  <span class="italic">t</span> is the time.
 </p>
</sec>
