<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ack class="ack">
 <title class="title">Acknowledgements</title>
 <p class="p">The authors would like to thank SafeWork SA and TAFE SA for providing assistance in the distribution of questionnaires. All survey participants and employers getting involved in this study are greatly appreciated for their contributions. We also thank the reviewers for their valuable comments and suggestions.</p>
 <sec id="FPar1" class="sec">
  <title class="title">Funding</title>
  <p class="p">This manuscript is part of JX's PhD Thesis. There is no funding for this study.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar2" class="sec">
  <title class="title">Availability of data and materials</title>
  <p class="p">Data is not available for online access. Only members of the research team have access to the data, according to the ethics approval (H-200-2011) and information sheet (Additional file 
   <xref rid="MOESM2" ref-type="media" class="xref">2</xref>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar3" class="sec">
  <title class="title">Authors’ contributions</title>
  <p class="p">JX designed and implemented the study, interpreted the results and drafted the manuscript. PB, DP, and AH designed and supervised the study, assisted with questionnaire design, statistical analyses and interpretation of results, reviewed and revised the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final version of the manuscript.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar4" class="sec">
  <title class="title">Competing interests</title>
  <p class="p">The authors declare that they have no competing interests.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar5" class="sec">
  <title class="title">Consent for publication</title>
  <p class="p">This manuscript does not contain any individual person’s data. All participants were informed of the publication of research findings through information sheets. Permission to publish the results from this study was granted by the Human Research Ethics Committee at the University of Adelaide.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="FPar6" class="sec">
  <title class="title">Ethics approval and consent to participate</title>
  <p class="p">Ethics approval was obtained from the Human Research Ethics Committee at the University of Adelaide (H-200-2011). Information sheets were provided to all participants for understanding the research objectives and procedure. Participation was voluntary and strictly confidential. Participants were allowed to withdraw from the study at any time or decline to answer any question. Oral consent was obtained from each participant.</p>
 </sec>
</ack>
