<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Our analysis of a taxonomically and geographically diverse dataset suggests that metabolic constraints provide a viable mechanism for projecting the poleward range boundaries of endotherms. However, estimating metabolic constraints is hindered both by parameter uncertainty and by the many adaptations organisms employ to evade the constraints (Fuller et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34537-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>; Mitchell et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34537-bib-0038" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2018</xref>). The Scholander‐Irving model we employ provides a tractable approximation of metabolic constraints, but we highlight ways that refining metabolic estimates could improve upon the analyses. We estimate metabolic costs assuming homeothermy, but many studies highlight that endotherms exhibit a continuum of heterothermy (Boyles et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34537-bib-0005" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Levesque, Nowack, &amp; Stawski, 
 <xref rid="ece34537-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>). Consideration of the occurrence of torpor/hibernation in the present study only partially accounted for deviations from thermoregulation due to 
 <italic class="italic">T</italic>
 <sub class="sub">b</sub> variation. Many endotherms seasonally acclimatize their insulation, behavior, and physiology (Boyles et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34537-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>; Bozinovic et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34537-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>). Many metabolic estimates in our database are specific to the cold season, but data limitations prevented fully accounting for acclimatization. A comparison of BMR and field metabolic rates (FMR) for small mammals failed to find support for intrinsic limitations on metabolism and low FMRs in very cold climates indicated acclimatization including behavioral avoidance (Humphries et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34537-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2005</xref>). Over longer time periods, adaptation may alter morphology or metabolic constraints (Boyles et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34537-bib-0004" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>). Behavioral strategies for buffering cold include sheltering, huddling, basking, and microclimate selection (Angilletta et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34537-bib-0001" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>). Resource availability may constrain metabolism more strongly than physiology. Despite these complications that introduce variability to estimates of metabolism and should flatten out the distribution of ME
 <sub class="sub">CRB</sub>, we find peaked ME
 <sub class="sub">CRB</sub> distributions that suggest metabolic constraints on poleward range boundaries.
</p>
