<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The positive relationship between the optimal E/SP ratio and female body length (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0173797.g007" class="xref">Fig 7A</xref>) can be interpreted as a positive correlation between the amount of lipids animals can store and their body length, an allometric scaling relating body length to mass. As already shown by Beauplet and Guinet [
 <xref rid="pone.0173797.ref060" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">60</xref>], the longest females are more efficient at exploiting distant food resources. On Amsterdam island (1,500 km north of the Kerguelen islands), where female Subantarctic fur seals (
 <italic class="italic">A</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">tropicalis</italic>) have to perform long foraging trips, body length has been shown to be a critical factor for foraging performance [
 <xref rid="pone.0173797.ref044" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>] and survival [
 <xref rid="pone.0173797.ref060" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">60</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0173797.ref062" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">62</xref>]. Furthermore, a population from South Georgia of 
 <italic class="italic">A</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">gazella</italic> has also been shown to display a similar tendency, associated with decreased availability of Antarctic krill, due to the positive values of the Southern Annular Mode over the last three decades [
 <xref rid="pone.0173797.ref063" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">63</xref>]. At Kerguelen Island depending on the foraging conditions female size were found to have a significant effect on pup growth under poor conditions, while no effect of female size on pup growth could be detected under favorable conditions [
 <xref rid="pone.0173797.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0173797.ref026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0173797.ref064" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">64</xref>]. However, our results are consistent with these observations and show that, under intermediate conditions (particularly Dist = 150 km), the success of female-pup pairs was roughly similar for females’ length ranging between 115 and 145 cm (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0173797.g006" class="xref">Fig 6B</xref>) and it follows that “larger is not always better” [
 <xref rid="pone.0173797.ref060" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">60</xref>].
</p>
