<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The relationship between the E/SP ratio and the average distance to fishing areas is a positive quadratic one (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0173797.g007" class="xref">Fig 7B</xref>). This is not very surprising since the drag force females undergo when they move, and the energy needed for it to be counter-balanced, is a function of the cross-sectional area (m
 <sup class="sup">2</sup>) of the animal. On the other hand, even if the animals can dynamically adopt optimal body lengths, SP evolves in a negative quadratic way (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0173797.g007" class="xref">Fig 7D</xref>), which means that females have more and more difficulties to raise their pup with increasing distances. When looking at the optimal body length in function of Dist, we found a linear relationship (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0173797.g007" class="xref">Fig 7C</xref>). L being the average length of the animals, we obtain: 
 <disp-formula id="pone.0173797.e006" class="disp-formula">
  <alternatives class="alternatives">
   <graphic xlink:href="pone.0173797.e006.jpg" id="pone.0173797.e006g" mimetype="image" position="anchor" orientation="portrait" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   <math id="M6" class="math">
    <mrow class="mrow">
     <mi class="mi">L</mi>
     <mo class="mo">=</mo>
     <mfrac class="mfrac">
      <mrow class="mrow">
       <msub class="msub">
        <mi class="mi">k</mi>
        <mn class="mn">2</mn>
       </msub>
      </mrow>
      <mrow class="mrow">
       <msub class="msub">
        <mi class="mi">k</mi>
        <mn class="mn">1</mn>
       </msub>
      </mrow>
     </mfrac>
     <mo stretchy="false" class="mo">(</mo>
     <mi class="mi">D</mi>
     <mi class="mi">i</mi>
     <mi class="mi">s</mi>
     <mi class="mi">t</mi>
     <mo class="mo">−</mo>
     <msub class="msub">
      <mi class="mi">D</mi>
      <mn class="mn">0</mn>
     </msub>
     <mo stretchy="false" class="mo">)</mo>
     <mo class="mo">+</mo>
     <msub class="msub">
      <mi class="mi">L</mi>
      <mn class="mn">0</mn>
     </msub>
    </mrow>
   </math>
  </alternatives>
 </disp-formula> where D
 <sub class="sub">0</sub> is the initial value of distance, L
 <sub class="sub">0</sub> the initial value of female body length, 
 <italic class="italic">k</italic>
 <sub class="sub">1</sub> and 
 <italic class="italic">k</italic>
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> the speeds at which the fishing areas and the female body length can change respectively (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0173797.s002" class="xref">S2 Text</xref>). Simulations gave similar outcomes (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0173797.g007" class="xref">Fig 7C</xref>), with a slope of 0.128 corresponding to 
 <italic class="italic">k</italic>
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>/
 <italic class="italic">k</italic>
 <sub class="sub">1</sub>. For instance, using a constant speed (3 km year
 <sup class="sup">-1</sup>) for the shift of the polar front, female body length should increase on average by 0.38 cm year
 <sup class="sup">-1</sup> for maintaining the best E/SP ratio. Under a pessimistic scenario in which females fail to modify quickly enough their phenotype (
 <italic class="italic">i</italic>.
 <italic class="italic">e</italic>. 
 <italic class="italic">k</italic>
 <sub class="sub">1</sub>&lt; 0.38 cm year
 <sup class="sup">-1</sup>), while the population has to go farther and farther at sea, the pups will have to fast for longer periods and will be less and less well-fed. In the end, even if the females could adjust their body length from generation to generation, their individual fitness should not evolve in a similar way. To that regards, Beauplet 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. [
 <xref rid="pone.0173797.ref065" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">65</xref>] found that both survival of Subantarctic fur seal pups and post-weaning pup survival were strongly correlated with growth rate during the lactation period. In addition, we could fear that difficulties undergone within the lactation period should hinder pup’s growth resulting into smaller animals, since such a malnourishment leads to a growth delay that cannot be later fully compensated for in mammals [
 <xref rid="pone.0173797.ref066" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">66</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0173797.ref067" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">67</xref>]. Lastly, in most dramatic cases, food distress could possibly lead to the population extinction.
</p>
