<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In further interpreting these results, it is essential that we take into consideration the model assumptions. The bioclimatic models implemented in this study make a number of simplifying assumptions that may bias the projections (Pearson and Dawson, 
 <xref rid="B56" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2003</xref>; Guisan and Thuiller, 
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2005</xref>). There are several factors that would exacerbate the projected impacts of climate change, which our models ignore. These include specialization to restricted soil types (Harrison et al., 
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2006</xref>), the spread of invasive species, which could take over otherwise potentially appropriate habitat (Seabloom et al., 
 <xref rid="B69" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2006</xref>), local adaptation of populations within species, and genetic constraints on evolutionary response to climate change (Etterson and Shaw, 
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2001</xref>). On the other hand, resilience of established plants and seed banks (Chapin and Starfield, 
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1997</xref>), differing population responses at range margins (Hampe and Petit, 
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2005</xref>), and adaptive evolutionary responses might mitigate the influence of climate change. Also, we need to take into consideration the effect of grain size on our models, as there simply are not many types of climate data available for a study area of this size. However, our results point out the value of using regional approaches to understanding climate change effects. Finally, parsing out the regulating effects of climate and land-use change is difficult, particularly in the context of the removal of fire from the landscape and such effects on woody vs. non-woody vegetation (Archer et al., 
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1995</xref>). Both climate and land-use change will affect species distributions (Halpin, 
 <xref rid="B27" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1997</xref>), but it is not clear how the cumulative effects of these dual threats will manifest themselves in terms of future species responses.
</p>
