<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discounting</div>
 <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The RICE model has a discounted utilitarian objective, meaning that for optimal policy calculations, the objective of the model is to maximize the sum of discounted well-being (see Eq. (
  <a rid="Equ1" ref-type="" href="#Equ1">1</a>) of the Methods and associated discussion). The discount rate for consumption is determined via the Ramsey rule, which adds the rate of pure time preference to the product of the elasticity of marginal utility and the economic growth rate. The rate of pure time preference is the rate at which the weight given to future well-being declines over time. The elasticity of marginal utility represents the lesser importance of each additional dollar to well-being as one gets richer. Unless otherwise noted, we assume an elasticity of marginal utility of 1.5, the default in RICE.
 </p>
 <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In all the results presented so far we have used a rate of pure time preference of 1.5% per year, which is the default value RICE, but close to the upper end of the range highlighted by the IPCC (Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
  </span>. This choice puts more weight on near-term impacts compared to those occurring further in the future. As a result, aerosol impacts, which occur more immediately than the climate impacts from CO
  <sub>2</sub>, have a relatively outsized importance. Nevertheless, when we implement a much lower rate that corresponds to a near-zero (0.1%) preference for the present over the future, optimal decarbonization remains substantially higher in RICE + AIR compared to the analogous reference case (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>). (Near-zero time preference is often used in the climate economics literature
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
  </span>, including in the Stern Review
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span>).
  <div id="Fig5" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 5</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>The influence of pure time preference. Optimal decarbonization with low (0.1%), medium (1.5%), and high (3.5%) rates of pure time preference for the reference case (that excludes health co-benefits) and in the full RICE + AIR case (that includes health co-benefits). All runs have a consumption elasticity of marginal utility of 1.5</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2019_9499_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e1041" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conversely, if we increase time preference to 3.5%, which implies a discount rate for consumption of 7%, the difference between RICE and RICE + AIR becomes even more stark. (To calculate the 7% discount rate via the Ramsey rule, we used the economic growth rate in the initial time period. We note that the exact discount rate may change over time due to the effect of climate damages on economic growth; the impact however, is negligible.). We chose the 7% value because it is the highest of the primary discount rates generally used in US federal cost-benefit analyses. (Although most experts consider lower rates to be more appropriate in an intergenerational context such as in the case of climate change-related analyses
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
  </span>, the current US administration has signaled a preference for including the higher 7% rate
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
  </span>.)
 </p>
 <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Such high time preference places so much emphasis on the near-term health benefits associated with reducing CO
  <sub>2</sub> that optimal decarbonization is substantially higher than both the analogous reference case and the reference case with more moderate (1.5%) time preference. These results indicate that even after strongly discounting the future, a robust climate policy is still warranted. In Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">3</a> we present further analyses showing results with a 3% discount rate, which is the lower value generally used for US federal cost-benefit analyses.
 </p>
</sec>
