<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Disentangling such contrasting climate change effects on population dynamics is difficult, regardless of spatial scale (for a simulation study of caribou, see Tews et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0077" ref-type="ref">2007</xref>). Arctic ungulate populations are typically influenced by a variety of other factors, such as hunting, insect harassment, infrastructure development, and predators, and these impacts often vary spatially (Gunn, Russell, White, &amp; Kofinas, 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0026" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>). Poor data quality and discontinuous time series also characterize many monitored populations. Few long‐term, continuous time series have therefore been available with sufficient spatial replication to investigate spatial population synchrony (but see Post &amp; Forchhammer, 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0062" ref-type="ref">2004</xref>, based on harvest records), and the buffering role of spatial heterogeneity, either in the environment or ecological responses. Here, we take advantage of such a rare, spatially replicated dataset, to analyse spatiotemporal patterns of population dynamics in wild Svalbard reindeer (
 <italic>Rangifer tarandus platyrhynchus</italic>) in the high Arctic, a hot‐spot of climate change. We ask: what is the role of the Moran effect in the large‐scale net outcome of recent climate change for this northernmost 
 <italic>Rangifer</italic> subspecies? We assess this by examining (a) local and total population size trends for 10 reindeer populations; (b) how annual fluctuations in weather (i.e. ROS), and their pattern of spatial autocorrelation, synchronize reindeer dynamics in space (Moran, 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0056" ref-type="ref">1953</xref>); and (c) how the effects of this synchronization are moderated by spatial heterogeneity in climate, climate trends (i.e. long‐term changes in weather), and density‐dependent climate responses. In particular, we account for local variation in strength of density dependence and how it may interact with ROS effects on fecundity, mortality and population growth rates (Hansen et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0029" ref-type="ref">2019</xref>).
</p>
