<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>In our study, we can observe multiple trends concerning settlement pattern and human land use in the Western Mediterranean. The number of sites and their distribution in space changes in a diachronic as well as a regional perspective. On the Iberian Peninsula, differences in the settlement pattern between the North and South become visible. The Solutrean in both areas of Iberia is represented by a high number of sites. The stratigraphic composition of these sites is characterized by a slight predominance of single-layered occupations in both areas; this is somewhat stronger in the North [
 <xref rid="pone.0225049.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. This regional balance gives the impression of similar settlement systems in Northern and Southern Iberia, especially in the coastal areas, while the occupation of the Interior is weak [
 <xref rid="pone.0225049.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0225049.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. Although the number of sites is slightly higher in the South, the mean distance of sites from the Nearest Neighbour analysis is somewhat larger. This might point to higher mobility of hunter-gatherer groups and could reflect slight differences in settlement systems in Iberia [
 <xref rid="pone.0225049.ref085" ref-type="bibr">85</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0225049.ref086" ref-type="bibr">86</xref>]. Faunal analyses support differences in the Solutrean of both areas as well [
 <xref rid="pone.0225049.ref087" ref-type="bibr">87</xref>]. The steep curve of the Ripley’ K analysis in the South reinforces this impression and shows patchier settlement in the South than the North. However, in the Kernel Density Estimate, large regions which were inhabited homogeneously can be identified, and the Mating Network Model results in stable social networks and low system vulnerability, despite this patchiness. Solutrean settlement was probably stable in Northern and Southern Iberia, with the exception of the Interior and the North-East.
</p>
