<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par23" class="p">As for why growth variability (MS and SD) is negatively related to forest height, we hypothesis that this is because radial growth will show higher variability when productivity is lower. Forest height is well known to be higher in more productive sites (e.g. ref.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" class="xref">23</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" class="xref">25</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" class="xref">53</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" class="xref">54</xref>
 </sup>), consequently MS and SD are negatively related to tree height (size). Both forest productivity and height decrease with higher altitude on humid mountains but increased on mountains in arid regions. Consequently, MS and SD increased with higher altitude on humid mountains (e.g. this study and ref.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">14</xref>
 </sup>) but decreased on arid mountains
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" class="xref">27</xref>
 </sup>. This hypothesis may also explain why forest height is a better predictor in our study. Forest productivity is affected by a number of factors in addition to climate, e.g. soil fertility and local topography. Meanwhile, forest height is also affected by both these local factors and climate, and thus may a better indicator of productivity than climate indices. Along successional series, forest productivity generally increases from early- to late-successional stages (e.g. ref.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" class="xref">55</xref>
 </sup>), and forest height also increases towards late-successional forests
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">18</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" class="xref">41</xref>
 </sup>. According to our hypothesis, MS and SD should be lower in later-successional forests, and thus lead to a negative relationship of MS and SD with forest height. This prediction is consistent with the findings in Liang 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">18</xref>
 </sup>. Meanwhile, larger-DBH trees (i.e. taller trees) commonly have higher productivity than smaller-DBH (e.g. ref.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" class="xref">55</xref>
 </sup>). Consequently, smaller-DBH trees are expected to have higher MS, which has been reported in previous studies
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" class="xref">21</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" class="xref">51</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" class="xref">52</xref>
 </sup>. Thus, our hypothesis seems to provide an explanation for different situations (altitudinal gradients in humid and arid regions, successional series and different tree sizes).
</p>
