<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec28" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p id="Par91" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Implementation of EBP can be challenging. In particular, the implementation of evidence-based treatment models for PTSD has been described as one of the biggest challenges in psychiatric health care [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">54</a>]. This is underlined by several studies reporting that PTSD interventions are under-utilized and challenging to sustain after initial dissemination [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">55</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>]. Research has pointed to therapists’ concerns about using exposure-based treatment as a barrier to implementation, as they believe it can exacerbate both PTSD and comorbid symptoms [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">57</a>], and that findings from clinical trials may not be representative for their patient population [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58" href="#CR58">58</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par92" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Leaders in the health care system are responsible for providing effective treatments in their services to a certain number of patients within a given time period. In order to increase the probability that patients will receive the most effective care for their symptoms, the leaders have to obtain effective strategies to promote the adoption of the EBP. The LOCI intervention addresses leadership in general, implementation leadership in particular, and organizational strategies in order to support the implementation of EBP and sustainment over time. Available data suggest that LOCI is effective in supporting implementation of EBP through strengthening leadership and a positive implementation climate [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>]. This study will test LOCI in a Norwegian mental health setting. A stepped-wedge design will be used to investigate whether the LOCI will have an effect on leadership, the implementation climate at the clinics, and the clinic’s ability to offer trauma-focused treatments to patients with clinical levels of post-traumatic stress symptoms.
 </p>
 <p id="Par93" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is a strength that the design enables all clinics to receive the same implementation strategy, in addition to examining the effect of the LOCI program. However, the time gap between therapists receiving training in the PTSD treatment interventions and the leaders receiving training in the LOCI program might not be optimal for the implementation of the interventions in the last two cohorts. Moreover, even though clinics were randomized to avoid contamination between them, it might be a small chance of some contamination between clinics that are geographically close to each other.</p>
 <p id="Par94" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The knowledge derived from this study can be used to support the implementation of EBPs for PTSD within mental health systems. Leaders can use strategies to develop system and organizational climates conducive to EBP implementation and sustainment. Hence, knowledge from this project can promote standards for implementation of EBPs in general through enhancing leaders’ competence in how to efficiently implement EBPs, which may increase the use of EBPs and thereby increase the quality and effectiveness of health services. The results can be transferred to health and social services in general, as the innovation can be utilized in all services that are to implement EBPs. Policy-makers and researchers are calling for more and better research in implementation science [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">59</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">60</a>], including the leaders’ role during the implementation process [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>]. This project can hence contribute to raise an under-researched field.
 </p>
</sec>
