<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Setting</div>
 <p id="Par46" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Norway consists of about 5.3 million inhabitants. Of these, 17% are immigrants or with immigrant parents, of which 7% from the European Union/European Economic Area and 4.3% are refugees. The government is responsible for the provision of treatment and the promotion of public welfare and health to everyone, on equal terms and irrespective of income. Coverage is universal and automatic for all residents, and is financed through national and municipal taxes [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>]. The healthcare system is semi-decentralized and distinguishes between specialized and community care. The state is responsible for specialized care, which is administered by four Regional Health Authorities, each responsible for several health trusts that include mental health divisions consisting of both inpatient and outpatient services [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>]. In 2017, 5.1% of the child population and 4.6% of the adult population received treatment in the specialized services [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par47" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The study will take place within Norwegian health trusts’ mental health clinics in both child- and adult-specialized services. Child and youth clinics (
  <span class="italic">Barne</span>- 
  <span class="italic">og ungdomspsykiatrisk poliklinikk</span>, BUP) are outpatient clinics for children up to 18 years and their families. There are about 87 BUPs all over Norway. District psychiatric centers (DPS) include different adult outpatient and inpatient services. Within DPS, mainly general outpatient clinics will be recruited, because patients with PTSD are often referred to these clinics, including those with war and refugee experiences. There are about 75 DPSs all over Norway.
 </p>
</sec>
