<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2.3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">PCR and genotyping</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Genomic DNA was extracted from blood samples using DNeasy Blood and Tissue kits (Qiagen) following manufacturer’s protocol. A total of 14 microsatellite markers were utilized (
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0081365.s002" href="#pone.0081365.s002">Table S1</a>), comprising nine markers developed for this study (Syla1, Syla2, Syla3, Syla12, Syla14, Syla15, Syla18, Syla19, Syla20 [
  <a rid="B38" ref-type="bibr" href="#B38">38</a>]) and five markers previously developed for this species (Syl1, Syl2, Syl6, Syl9, and Syl10 [
  <a rid="B39" ref-type="bibr" href="#B39">39</a>]). Microsatellite loci were amplified with polymerase chain reaction (PCR) for all individuals in 20µl reactions including: 1x Qiagen CoralLoad Concentrate, 1x Qiagen PCR Buffer (containing KCl and (NH
  <sub>4</sub>)
  <sub>2</sub>SO
  <sub>4</sub>), 0.25 µM labeled forward primer, 0.25 µM reverse primer, 200 µM of each dNTP, 1.25 U Qiagen Top Taq DNA polymerase, and 1.0µl DNA template. Mastercycler Gradient Thermocyclers (Eppendorf GmbH, Hamburg Germany) were used to run PCR under the following conditions: initial denaturing at 94 °C for 5 min, followed by 20 cycles of 94°C for 30 s, 60°C for 30 s (decreased by 0.5°C per cycle), and 72°C for 45 s, followed by 15 cycles of 94°C for 30 s, 50°C for 30 s, and 72°C for 45 s with a final extension of 72°C for 3 min. Forward primers were labeled with FAM or HEX florescent dyes (Applied Biosystems), PCR products were genotyped on an ABI3130xl Genetic Analyzer (Applied Biosystems), and genotypes were analyzed with PeakScanner v1.0 software (Applied Biosystems). Raw genotype sizes were rounded and binned according to repeat size using TANDEM [
  <a rid="B40" ref-type="bibr" href="#B40">40</a>]. The mean number of effective alleles (
  <span class="italic">A</span>
  <sub>E</sub>) and observed and expected heterozygosities (
  <span class="italic">H</span>
  <sub>O</sub> and 
  <span class="italic">H</span>
  <sub>E</sub>) were estimated for each population with GenAlEx v6.41[
  <a rid="B41" ref-type="bibr" href="#B41">41</a>]. Deviations from Hardy Weinberg Equilibrium (HWE), genotypic linkage disequilibrium (LD) between loci, and the frequency of null alleles were estimated with Genepop v4.1.2 [
  <a rid="B42" ref-type="bibr" href="#B42">42</a>]. Estimated 
  <span class="italic">P</span>-values from HWE and LD tests were corrected for false discovery rate using the Qvalue program [
  <a rid="B43" ref-type="bibr" href="#B43">43</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
