<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Aquatic surface respiration (ASR) and air breathing (AB) are performed by some fish species in order to avoid hypoxic conditions in the water column (
 <xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr">Domenici 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007b
 </xref>). While ASR can reduce the negative effects of hypoxia on escape response as discussed above, it may also cause additional costs and risks (
 <xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr">Domenici 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007b
 </xref>). Fish performing ASR and AB are at higher risk of predation owing to increased visibility to aerial predators (
 <xref rid="ref98" ref-type="bibr">Kramer, 1987</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr">Domenici 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007b
 </xref>), and the presence of predators can delay the onset of ASR (
 <xref rid="ref169" ref-type="bibr">Shingles 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005
 </xref>). However, when performing ASR and AB, fish can decrease the risk of predation by surfacing with irregular frequency or in synchrony with others (
 <xref rid="ref99" ref-type="bibr">Kramer and Graham, 1976</xref>). Irregularity reduces the predictability of the ASR and AB event, and therefore, the vulnerability to predation and synchronous surfacing was suggested to create sensory confusion in the predator (
 <xref rid="ref99" ref-type="bibr">Kramer and Graham, 1976</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref67" ref-type="bibr">Gee, 1980</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr">Chapman and Chapman, 1994</xref>). Hypoxia is also known to increase the risk of predation by altering efficiency of anti-predator behaviours, such as school cohesiveness in pelagic species (
 <xref rid="ref50" ref-type="bibr">Domenici 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2002
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr">Domenici 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2007b
 </xref>) and crypsis in benthic species via changes in conspicuousness due to hypoxia-dependent increase in ventilation rates (
 <xref rid="ref19" ref-type="bibr">Cannas 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2012
 </xref>).
</p>
