<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Similar to temperature, the effect of hypoxia on predator–prey interactions are taxon specific. Arguably, the effect of hypoxia on fish–fish interactions are likely to differ from those on predator–prey interactions involving fish as prey, and predators that are not affected by hypoxia, such as birds, aquatic mammals, or other hypoxia-tolerant taxa (
 <xref rid="f4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>). If the predators are fish, they are likely to be less hungry and feed less frequently than in normoxia (
 <xref rid="ref145" ref-type="bibr">Poulin 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 1987
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr">Chabot and Dutil, 1999</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref177" ref-type="bibr">Thetmeyer 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 1999
 </xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref59" ref-type="bibr">Engström-Öst and Isaksson, 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="ref150" ref-type="bibr">Ripley and Foran, 2007</xref>), because of the reduced metabolism (
 <xref rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr">Claireaux and Chabot, 2016</xref>) and possibly also decreased sensory performance (
 <xref rid="ref154" ref-type="bibr">Robinson 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2013
 </xref>). On the other hand, water hypoxia will have no effect on birds or marine mammals. As a result, predator pressure is likely to decrease in hypoxia when the predators are fish, while it should not change if the predators are unaffected by hypoxia. While there is both species-specific and methodology-specific (acute versus chronic) differences in the results of the effect of hypoxia on escape performance, most studies show some negative behavioural effects, particularly on directionality and responsiveness, while escape locomotion is affected only in some species (e.g. grey mullet; 
 <xref rid="ref105" ref-type="bibr">Lefrancois 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005
 </xref>). As a result, escape performance may decrease largely because of a decreased non-locomotor performance. Therefore, a potential scenario for fish–fish interactions is that the frequency of predation events should decrease in hypoxia (
 <xref rid="f4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>), with the exception of fish predators that are highly hypoxia tolerant such as certain air-breathing species (
 <xref rid="ref197" ref-type="bibr">Wolf and Kramer, 1987</xref>). This is in line with work based on fish–fish interactions, which shows that the number of fish prey larvae consumed by Spanish mackerel (
 <italic>Scomberomorus niphonius</italic>) (
 <xref rid="ref170" ref-type="bibr">Shoji 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005
 </xref>), as well as by juvenile striped bass (
 <italic>Morone saxatilis</italic>) and adult naked goby (
 <italic>Gobiosoma bosc</italic>) (
 <xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">Breitburg 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 1994
 </xref>) decreased in hypoxia. Conversely, predation by species that are hypoxia independent or highly hypoxia tolerant is expected to increase in low oxygen conditions, because prey escape performance in fish tends to decrease, while hunger in these predators will not be affected (
 <xref rid="f4" ref-type="fig">Fig. 4</xref>). Indeed, works using hypoxia-tolerant predator species such as sea nettle (
 <italic>Chrysaora quinquecirrha</italic>) (
 <xref rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr">Breitburg 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 1994
 </xref>) or moon jellyfish (
 <italic>Aurelia aurita</italic>) (
 <xref rid="ref170" ref-type="bibr">Shoji 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 2005
 </xref>) show that predation on fish increases in hypoxia. Furthermore, aquatic birds such as little egrets (
 <italic>Egretta garzetta</italic>) were observed to take advantage of the ASR behaviour some lagoon fish undertake in the morning, when their surfacing in hypoxic waters (i.e. due to daily fluctuation in oxygen levels) makes them easy prey for birds (
 <xref rid="ref94" ref-type="bibr">Kersten 
  <italic>et al.</italic>, 1991
 </xref>).
</p>
