<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="S3-4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The relationship between beliefs, personal dietary behaviors, and action</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Dietitians were divided when asked if animal products are 
  <span class="italic">essential</span> for a healthy diet. Nearly 42% of survey participants either strongly disagreed or disagreed that animal products are essential for a healthy diet, while 8% are unsure. Almost 50% of survey participants either strongly agreed or agreed that animal products are essential for a healthy diet.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Next, we tested the hypothesis that the variable personal dietary behavior of whether or not vegetarian or whether or not vegan predicts the promotion of diet as a climate change mitigation strategy among registered dietitians. Of note is that more than 10% of survey participants reported being vegetarian, while 2% reported being vegan. Tables 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="T3" href="#T3">3</a> and 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="T4" href="#T4">4</a> show the analysis of the survey participants that engage in activities that promote diet as a climate change mitigation strategy based on the personal behaviors of being vegetarian or vegan, respectively. The corresponding 
  <span class="italic">p</span>-value for both the chi-square test for independence (0.002) and the Fisher’s exact test (0.007) are exceedingly small, indicating that the results are statistically significant. These data suggest that vegetarian and vegan dietitians are significantly more likely than non-vegetarian and non-vegan dietitians to engage in activities that promote diet as a climate change mitigation strategy.
 </p>
 <div id="T3" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Table 3</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Number and percentage of survey participants that engage in activities that promote diet as a climate change mitigation strategy based upon being vegetarian
     <span class="sup">a,b,c</span>
    </span>.
   </p>
  </div>
  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
   <thead>
    <tr>
     <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
     <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vegetarian (yes) (
      <span class="italic">n</span> = 53)
     </th>
     <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vegetarian (no) (
      <span class="italic">n</span> = 341)
     </th>
    </tr>
   </thead>
   <tbody>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number and percentage that engage in activities that promote diet as a climate change mitigation strategy</td>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30 (56.6%)
      <span class="sup">d</span>
     </td>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">162 (34.6%)</td>
    </tr>
   </tbody>
  </table>
  <div class="table-wrap-foot">
   <p>
    <span class="italic">
     <span class="sup">a</span>Difference = 22%; 
     <span class="sup">b</span>95% CI = 7.0–36%; 
     <span class="sup">c</span>Pearson chi-square = 9.9; 
     <span class="sup">d</span>p-value &lt;0.002
    </span>.
   </p>
  </div>
 </div>
 <div id="T4" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Table 4</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Number and percentage of survey participants that engage in activities that promote diet as a climate change mitigation strategy based upon being vegan
     <span class="sup">a,b</span>
    </span>.
   </p>
  </div>
  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
   <thead>
    <tr>
     <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
     <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vegan (yes) (
      <span class="italic">n</span> = 10)
     </th>
     <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Vegetarian (no) (
      <span class="italic">n</span> = 512)
     </th>
    </tr>
   </thead>
   <tbody>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number and percentage that engage in activities that promote diet as a climate change mitigation strategy</td>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8 (80%)
      <span class="sup">c</span>
     </td>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">186 (36.3%)</td>
    </tr>
   </tbody>
  </table>
  <div class="table-wrap-foot">
   <p>
    <span class="italic">
     <span class="sup">a</span>Difference = 43.7%; 
     <span class="sup">b</span>95% CI = 18.5–68.8%; 
     <span class="sup">c</span>Fisher’s exact test, p-value &lt;0.007
    </span>.
   </p>
  </div>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Following this, we tested the hypothesis that the belief that animal products 
  <span class="italic">are not essential for a healthy diet</span> predicts the promotion of diet as a climate change mitigation strategy. The corresponding 
  <span class="italic">p</span>-value (0.013) for the number and percentage of survey participants that engage in activities that promote diet as a climate change mitigation strategy based on the belief that animal products are not essential for a healthy diet is exceedingly small, indicating that the results are statistically significant. These data suggest that those who believe that animal products are not essential for a healthy diet are significantly more likely to engage in activities that promote diet as a climate change mitigation strategy than those who do believe that animal products are essential for a healthy diet.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Lastly, we tested the hypothesis that self-efficacy (comfortable, very comfortable) in promoting solely plant-based (vegan) diets predicts involvement in diet and climate change mitigation strategies. Table 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="T5" href="#T5">5</a> shows the analysis.
 </p>
 <div id="T5" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Table 5</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Number and percentage of survey participants that engage in activities that promote diet as a climate change mitigation strategy based on self-efficacy (comfortable, very comfortable) in promoting a plant-based diet
     <span class="sup">a,b,c</span>
    </span>.
   </p>
  </div>
  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
   <thead>
    <tr>
     <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
     <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-efficacy (yes) (
      <span class="italic">n</span> = 193)
     </th>
     <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Self-efficacy (no) (
      <span class="italic">n</span> = 330)
     </th>
    </tr>
   </thead>
   <tbody>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Number and percentage that engage in activities that promote diet as a climate change mitigation strategy</td>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">93 (48%)
      <span class="sup">d</span>
     </td>
     <td align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">101 (30.6%)</td>
    </tr>
   </tbody>
  </table>
  <div class="table-wrap-foot">
   <p>
    <span class="italic">
     <span class="sup">a</span>Difference = 17.6%; 
     <span class="sup">b</span>95% CI = 8.9–26.2%; 
     <span class="sup">c</span>Pearson chi-square = 16.1; 
     <span class="sup">d</span>p-value &lt; 0.00005
    </span>.
   </p>
  </div>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The corresponding 
  <span class="italic">p</span>-value (0.00005) is exceedingly small and &lt;0.05, indicating that the results are statistically significant. These data suggest that those who report self-efficacy in promoting plant-based (vegan) diets are significantly more likely to engage in activities that promote diet as a climate change mitigation strategy than those who report that they are less comfortable in promoting plant-based diets.
 </p>
</sec>
