<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">
 <list list-type="order" id="ece32982-list-0001" class="list">
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">
    <italic class="italic">What is the role of habitat characteristics (e.g., size, depth, disturbance regime) and landscape (e.g., connectivity) context in the effects of climate change?</italic> In freshwater systems, we have a poor understanding of how ecological effects of climate are mediated by habitat characteristics. Much of this is due to limited replication of studies (sensu Belovsky et al., 
    <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0011" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2004</xref>) across landscapes, species, and habitats. However, there is evidence to suggest that the effects of climate on freshwaters vary on the basis of habitat characteristics (lotic vs. lentic, habitat morphology) and landscape context, and knowledge of these interactions will be useful in future predictive modeling.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">
    <italic class="italic">What are the combined ecological effects of climate change and non‐native invasive species in freshwater ecosystems?</italic> Inadequate consideration of the role of climate in mediating the effects of non‐native species (where invasion is facilitated by climate change) means there is a risk in extrapolating knowledge of invasive species impacts as being consistent under different climate scenarios or along strong climate gradients. This question is important to identify the extent to which non‐native species are drivers, passengers, or “backseat drivers” (sensu MacDougall &amp; Turkington, 
    <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0137" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2005</xref>; Bauer, 
    <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>) of ecological impacts of climate, which is critical for future management options. Because dispersal and invasion of freshwater fish are constrained by hydrological connectivity, freshwater ecosystems are highly relevant to tease apart the effects of these stressors by carefully designed surveys along climate gradients across hydrological networks that vary in the degree to which invasion is possible (due to dispersal barriers constraining range expansions). Thomaz et al. (
    <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0188" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>) determined that the combined use of space‐for‐time and time approaches improves the accuracy of conclusions of the impacts of non‐native species. The use of natural gradients in variables that are expected to change with climate change continues to be an effective basis for predicting future climate change consequences and identify underlying ecological mechanisms (Fukami &amp; Wardle, 
    <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2005</xref>; Woodward et al., 
    <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0205" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>).
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item class="list-item">
   <p class="p">
    <italic class="italic">How do the mechanisms linking climate change with ecological responses determine patterns of freshwater biodiversity across local, landscape, and regional spatial scales?</italic> An extensive body of evidence details how freshwater biodiversity in northern latitude regions is changing in association with climate change (Buisson et al., 
    <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Comte et al., 
    <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Heino et al., 
    <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0089" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2009</xref>; Sharma et al., 
    <xref rid="ece32982-bib-0171" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>). However, the mechanisms through which these changes are occurring are relatively less well known. Subarctic freshwaters are ideal systems to study how changes in biodiversity under current and future climate change will influence trophic interactions, food web structure, ecosystem function, and subsequent consequences for humans.
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
