<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Most modelling studies so far have analyzed the response to large-scale land cover change. In some, deforestation was global or performed over whole latitude bands [
 <xref rid="pone.0153357.ref012" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0153357.ref018" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">18</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0153357.ref020" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0153357.ref024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0153357.ref025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>] while others simulated global historical anthropogenic deforestation [
 <xref rid="pone.0153357.ref021" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0153357.ref026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0153357.ref027" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>]. In general terms, these past simulations show that the temperature response of high latitude deforestation is still dominated by the albedo effect, resulting in a cooler climate. That is, while deforestation causes atmospheric CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> concentrations to increase, the increment in albedo is enough to counteract greenhouse gas warming and yield a reduced surface air temperature (SAT). This cooling is global, and centered over the deforested areas [
 <xref rid="pone.0153357.ref012" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0153357.ref022" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0153357.ref024" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>]. Global temperature changes associated with mid latitude deforestation follow the same trend as for the high latitudes but with temperature changes of smaller magnitude [
 <xref rid="pone.0153357.ref012" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. Contrary to the cooling seen in the mid and high latitudes, simulated low latitude deforestation yields a warmer climate, with the increase in temperature attributed to the reduction in ET, and increased atmospheric CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>, which dominates the temperature signal [
 <xref rid="pone.0153357.ref025" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0153357.ref028" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>]. Some studies have noted that a reduction in cloud cover, and hence, reduced atmospheric albedo over deforested regions was an important contributor to the modelled warming [
 <xref rid="pone.0153357.ref012" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. There have been indications from satellite based observations [
 <xref rid="pone.0153357.ref029" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>] and modeling [
 <xref rid="pone.0153357.ref023" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">23</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0153357.ref030" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>] efforts that the temperature response is dependent on the scale and location of land cover change. According to these studies, in many high latitude and mid latitude areas deforestation would result not in cooling but in net warming or no significant change as the CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> and ET induced energy gain overtakes the albedo induced losses.
</p>
