<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec011" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <sec id="sec012" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Repeatability of body mass, body condition and egg mass</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We found that across years both body mass and body condition were highly repeatable within the same females and males, indicating a high individual consistency of these traits in both sexes. We calculated body condition based on the scaled mass index, currently the best condition index based on mass-length data [
   <a rid="pone.0128776.ref064" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref064">64</a>], and seen as a reliable indicator of body fat [
   <a rid="pone.0128776.ref064" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref064">64</a>]. We therefore assumed that body condition of the birds reflected the energy reserves independently of the structural size of the bird. As repeatability estimates for body mass and body condition were similarly high, we infer that the repeatability in body mass was not primarily caused by consistent between-individual differences in structural size, but more likely caused by other effects. Possibly, the here observed consistent between-individual effects in body mass and reproductive investment could be linked to individually different foraging preferences. Rockhopper penguins are food generalists with a broad prey spectrum [
   <a rid="pone.0128776.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref034">34</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0128776.ref071" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref071">71</a>]. In such generalist species, it is commonly observed that individuals specialize on specific prey or foraging areas [
   <a rid="pone.0128776.ref072" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref072">72</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0128776.ref073" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref073">73</a>], which during winter [
   <a rid="pone.0128776.ref072" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref072">72</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0128776.ref074" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref074">74</a>] could potentially explain the consistent between-individual effects in body mass and also reproductive investment.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Egg mass was also highly repeatable within females, and—to a lesser extent—within males, reflecting an individually consistent investment into egg mass especially in females. In view of the observed variation of body mass in response to Southern Annular Mode (SAM) across the years (see below), this result implies that adults showed a similar response to this environmental variation: Differences in body mass among individual birds were consistently maintained across years, while body mass of all individuals increased under positive SAM (reflecting colder conditions) and decreased under negative SAM (reflecting warmer conditions).</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While structural body size and also body mass may be heritable, which automatically implies significant repeatability (e.g. [
   <a rid="pone.0128776.ref075" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref075">75</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0128776.ref076" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref076">76</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0128776.ref077" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref077">77</a>]), estimates for actual repeatability of body mass within or across years have been rather rarely published. Our estimates for repeatability in body mass are in the same range as those for great tits (
   <span class="italic">Parus major</span>) measured in several winters [
   <a rid="pone.0128776.ref078" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref078">78</a>], and weasels (
   <span class="italic">Mustela nivalis</span>) across a time span of up to 400 days [
   <a rid="pone.0128776.ref079" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref079">79</a>], yet higher than in gray catbirds (
   <span class="italic">Dumetella carolinensis</span>) measured across several breeding seasons [
   <a rid="pone.0128776.ref080" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref080">80</a>]. We obtained higher estimates for repeatability of body condition than were previously reported for breeding upland geese (
   <span class="italic">Chloephaga picta leucoptera</span>) [
   <a rid="pone.0128776.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref023">23</a>], while this trait was not significantly repeatable across years in crimson finches (
   <span class="italic">Neochima phaeton</span>) [
   <a rid="pone.0128776.ref081" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref081">81</a>]. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first study that presents repeatability estimates of body mass or body condition across one year or more in a seabird species.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For egg mass, repeatability estimates within females were in the same range as those from other studies (see review in [
   <a rid="pone.0128776.ref082" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref082">82</a>]). As such, finding significant repeatability of egg mass in males that were paired with the same female over several years was expectable and has also been shown before (e.g. [
   <a rid="pone.0128776.ref065" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref065">65</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0128776.ref083" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref083">83</a>]). Yet, considering that male body mass did not affect egg mass (i.e. females did not invest more into egg mass when paired with a heavy male; see 
   <a rid="sec011" ref-type="sec" href="#sec011">discussion</a> below), we were surprised to still find significant (albeit lower) repeatability estimates for egg mass in males when paired with different females. Indeed, our result contradicts a study by Phillips and Furness [
   <a rid="pone.0128776.ref065" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref065">65</a>] that found clutch volume not to be repeatable for male Arctic skuas (
   <span class="italic">Stercorarius parasiticus</span>) paired with different females. On the other hand, Bańbura and Ziliński [
   <a rid="pone.0128776.ref084" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref084">84</a>] found a similar result as ours, with average egg volume being repeatable for male barn swallows (
   <span class="italic">Hirundo rustica</span>) that paired with different females, and assumed assortative mating according to body condition as the underlying mechanism for this effect. In the framework of this study, we have shown that rockhopper penguins do not mate assortatively according to body mass or body condition (i.e. heavy males do not necessarily pair with heavy females). Nevertheless, other traits besides body mass or body condition may also play a role for reproductive investment, for example the timing of clutch initiation. In birds, early breeders usually lay heavier eggs than late breeders [
   <a rid="pone.0128776.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref023">23</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0128776.ref085" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref085">85</a>]. As such, if rockhopper penguin males that occupy nest sites early mate consistently with early breeding females, and early breeding females lay heavier eggs than late breeding females, this could explain the significant repeatability for egg mass in males. We did not include clutch initiation date into analyses as the focus of this study was on body mass, and we recorded body mass on clutch initiation date. Therefore, investigating the relationships between body mass and clutch initiation date, or between clutch initiation date and egg mass would inevitably have raised problems with circularity.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec013" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Phenotypic plasticity of body mass in response to environmental conditions</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Out of the three temperature-related environmental variables that we included in our analysis to explain annual variation in adult female and male body mass, SAM showed a slightly better model fit than SSTA. SAM also showed a significant effect on body mass, while SSTA did not—although both variables were significantly negatively correlated. SAM is a broad-scale environmental variable that reflects climatic variability in the entire Southern Ocean [
   <a rid="pone.0128776.ref051" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref051">51</a>]. The—relatively—better fit of this broad-scale environmental variable compared to the local one may be due to the fact that southern rockhopper penguins are migratory during winter (e.g. [
   <a rid="pone.0128776.ref086" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref086">86</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0128776.ref087" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref087">87</a>]). They should therefore accumulate their energy reserves for reproduction at wintering grounds or during migration to breeding sites, and thus not in local waters around the Falkland Islands. This result is in line with earlier findings which show a relatively higher importance of broad-scale environmental variables on the breeding behaviour of migratory seabird species compared to resident species [
   <a rid="pone.0128776.ref059" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref059">59</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In agreement with our first prediction, body mass in both sexes increased under positive SAM values, which reflect lower sea surface temperatures and stronger westerly winds, and therefore overall colder conditions and higher primary productivity [
   <a rid="pone.0128776.ref088" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref088">88</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0128776.ref089" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref089">89</a>]. SAM-associated climatic conditions (low SST and increased westerly winds) have already previously been associated with better foraging conditions and higher survival rates in the southern rockhopper penguin [
   <a rid="pone.0128776.ref048" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref048">48</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0128776.ref057" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref057">57</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0128776.ref090" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref090">90</a>]. Furthermore, a recent study identified SAM also as the best explanatory environmental variable for clutch initiation date in rockhopper penguins, with birds breeding earlier under positive SAM and thus colder conditions [
   <a rid="pone.0128776.ref091" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref091">91</a>]. The same study showed that total clutch mass in rockhopper penguins was best explained by local SST, and females laid heavier eggs under lower SST [
   <a rid="pone.0128776.ref091" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref091">91</a>]. Within the marine food web, southern rockhopper penguins are located at a relatively low trophic level position compared to other seabird species [
   <a rid="pone.0128776.ref092" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref092">92</a>], and are therefore likely to benefit rapidly from increased primary productivity. A positive SAM going along with low SST thus implies favourable foraging conditions for southern rockhopper penguins, and under these conditions, rockhopper penguins can reach higher body mass values—and lay heavier eggs. Notably, however, body mass differences among breeding seasons were not very distinct (
   <a rid="pone.0128776.g001" ref-type="fig" href="#pone.0128776.g001">Fig 1</a>), and SAM explained at maximum 3% of the variation of body mass in models, thus much less than individual effects. The overall phenotypic response to SAM in the here analysed time period therefore appeared rather limited, and inter-annual variation in body mass was lower compared to data presented by Crawford et al. [
   <a rid="pone.0128776.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref029">29</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0128776.ref093" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref093">93</a>]. These differences between our study and those by Crawford et al. [
   <a rid="pone.0128776.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref029">29</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0128776.ref093" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref093">93</a>] could, however, be caused by the longer time series and—inevitably—larger environmental variability during their study period. Alternatively, regional differences in the environmental conditions and/or food availability in wintering grounds of rockhopper penguins from Marion Island could be less predictable than those of rockhopper penguins from New Island leading to more variation in body mass among years.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec014" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Effect of body mass on egg mass</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In agreement with the second prediction, A-egg mass and B-egg mass, and consequently overall reproductive investment increased with female body mass. Notably, this effect was stronger for B-eggs than A-eggs. As chicks from A-eggs rarely fledge, they may rather form an “insurance” for the case that the B-egg or chick is lost [
   <a rid="pone.0128776.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref037">37</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0128776.ref094" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref094">94</a>]. Thus, by investing relatively more into B-eggs when being heavy, females selectively increased their investment into those eggs that would most likely produce fledglings while keeping “insurance costs” low. This also agrees with previous findings from the same population of rockhopper penguins which showed that females decrease their relative investment in A-egg mass compared to B-egg mass with increasing (later) laying dates [
   <a rid="pone.0128776.ref091" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref091">91</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In contrast to the effect of female body mass, we could not confirm an effect of male body mass on egg mass—despite the significant repeatability estimates of egg mass for males. These findings are concordant with the literature, in which positive effects of female body mass, body size or a body condition index on egg mass or egg size are well described (e.g. [
   <a rid="pone.0128776.ref017" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref017">17</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0128776.ref095" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref095">95</a>, 
   <a rid="pone.0128776.ref096" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref096">96</a>]). A significant relationship between male mass and egg mass has been shown less frequently (but see [
   <a rid="pone.0128776.ref017" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref017">17</a>]), even when other related parameters like testis size were positively correlated with egg mass [
   <a rid="pone.0128776.ref019" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref019">19</a>]. In line with this and our current results, Poisbleau et al. [
   <a rid="pone.0128776.ref032" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref032">32</a>] did not find an effect of male body mass on total clutch mass (i.e. A-egg mass + B-egg mass) either. Thus, this longer-term study confirmed that female rockhopper penguins do not adapt their overall reproductive investment when paired with a heavy male partner.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
