<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec004" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Field Methods</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fieldwork was done in the “Settlement Colony” on New Island, Falkland Islands / Islas Malvinas (51°43’S, 61°17’W) between 2006 and 2014. The colony held about 5,700 breeding pairs during the first breeding season in 2006/07, and 8,200 breeding pairs during the last breeding season in 2013/14. More specifically, we worked in one part of the Settlement Colony that includes almost one quarter of the nests and is representative in vegetation and topography of the entire colony. In this part, starting in 2006/07, we gradually marked more than 800 adult birds (i.e. three years of age or older) subcutaneously with passive integrated transponders (PITs; 23 mm long, glass-encapsuled, TIRIS, Texas Instruments, USA; [
  <a rid="pone.0128776.ref048" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref048">48</a>]). The sex of the birds was determined from a combination of morphological and behavioural observations; males are larger than females and both have a fixed pattern of nest attendance and incubation shifts [
  <a rid="pone.0128776.ref049" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref049">49</a>]. The breeding cycle of southern rockhopper penguins has been described previously [
  <a rid="pone.0128776.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref037">37</a>]. Briefly, males arrive in breeding colonies in the first week of October, followed by the females a few days later. Both males and females stay ashore and fast during the entire courtship and egg laying period and the first incubation shift. Males leave colonies for a ca. 10-day foraging trip in the middle of November, while females incubate eggs until males return and then leave the colony themselves for foraging.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the framework of an on-going project on maternal investment [
  <a rid="pone.0128776.ref032" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref032">32</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0128776.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref037">37</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0128776.ref050" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref050">50</a>], we collected data on egg mass and female and male body mass across multiple breeding seasons (2006/07–2007/08, 2009/10–2010/11 and 2012/13–2013/14). We visited the colony daily from at least mid-October onwards to follow the egg laying of focal females equipped with a transponder. Transponders were read with a hand-held antenna (Allflex RS320). Clutches were initiated between 25 October and 9 November in all years. We weighed both A- and B-eggs to the closest 0.1 g using a digital balance (Kern CM 320-1N; Kern &amp; Sohn, Germany) on the day when they were first observed. As incubation in rockhopper penguins typically does not start before clutch completion [
  <a rid="pone.0128776.ref026" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref026">26</a>], the A-eggs were not incubated at all and the B-eggs were not incubated for longer than 24 h at weighing. We therefore assumed that embryo development and (potential) change in egg mass (see [
  <a rid="pone.0128776.ref050" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref050">50</a>]) had not yet begun.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We captured males and females on their nests, covered their head to minimize stress and weighed them to the nearest 20 g with an electronic balance following Poisbleau et al. [
  <a rid="pone.0128776.ref049" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref049">49</a>]. We further measured flipper length (using a ruler to the nearest mm), bill depth and bill length (to the nearest 0.1 mm, using callipers). Birds were released after approximately 10 minutes and returned to their partner on the nest. The general procedure was to capture females on their clutch initiation date (= A-egg laying date) and males 5–8 days later. We chose this standardized procedure instead of capturing both partners on the same day in order to minimize the immediate disturbance. However, because of logistic reasons, some females were captured 22–12 days before (N = 36 events; 10%) or 1–23 days after (N = 110 events; 30%) clutch initiation. In order to enable comparisons, we therefore estimated their body mass at clutch initiation by applying a correction by the effect of fasting on body mass. We used 25 females repeatedly (2 or 3 times) weighed in 2010 between their arrival at the colony and the end of their first fasting shift, i.e. the one including egg laying. Female body mass was corrected by removing A-egg mass for captures before clutch initiation and by adding B-egg mass for captures after B-egg laying. We performed a linear mixed effect model with bird identity as random factor and capture date as only explanatory variable. We extracted the estimates (f(x) = 4401.2–33.3*x; marginal R
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.917) and consequently assumed a linear body mass decrease by 33.3 g per fasting day. We followed the same procedure to estimate male body mass at clutch initiation (N = 48 males repeatedly weighed in 2010; f(x) = 4453.8–38.6*x; marginal R
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.793 and body mass decrease of 38.6 g per fasting day). We therefore used these values to back-calculate body mass at clutch initiation for 146 females and all males.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the present study, we included only the nests for which we obtained A-egg mass, B-egg mass, female and male body mass. This resulted in a database of 366 records (between 42 and 86 nests per breeding season) from 202 different females and 222 different males (numbers differed between sexes due to few cases of divorces) represented on average 1.81 ± 1.23 S.D. (min. 1, max. 5) and 1.65 ± 1.07 S.D (min. 1, max. 5) times, respectively across six breeding seasons.</p>
</sec>
