<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec012" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Repeatability of body mass, body condition and egg mass</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We found that across years both body mass and body condition were highly repeatable within the same females and males, indicating a high individual consistency of these traits in both sexes. We calculated body condition based on the scaled mass index, currently the best condition index based on mass-length data [
  <a rid="pone.0128776.ref064" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref064">64</a>], and seen as a reliable indicator of body fat [
  <a rid="pone.0128776.ref064" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref064">64</a>]. We therefore assumed that body condition of the birds reflected the energy reserves independently of the structural size of the bird. As repeatability estimates for body mass and body condition were similarly high, we infer that the repeatability in body mass was not primarily caused by consistent between-individual differences in structural size, but more likely caused by other effects. Possibly, the here observed consistent between-individual effects in body mass and reproductive investment could be linked to individually different foraging preferences. Rockhopper penguins are food generalists with a broad prey spectrum [
  <a rid="pone.0128776.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref034">34</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0128776.ref071" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref071">71</a>]. In such generalist species, it is commonly observed that individuals specialize on specific prey or foraging areas [
  <a rid="pone.0128776.ref072" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref072">72</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0128776.ref073" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref073">73</a>], which during winter [
  <a rid="pone.0128776.ref072" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref072">72</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0128776.ref074" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref074">74</a>] could potentially explain the consistent between-individual effects in body mass and also reproductive investment.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Egg mass was also highly repeatable within females, and—to a lesser extent—within males, reflecting an individually consistent investment into egg mass especially in females. In view of the observed variation of body mass in response to Southern Annular Mode (SAM) across the years (see below), this result implies that adults showed a similar response to this environmental variation: Differences in body mass among individual birds were consistently maintained across years, while body mass of all individuals increased under positive SAM (reflecting colder conditions) and decreased under negative SAM (reflecting warmer conditions).</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While structural body size and also body mass may be heritable, which automatically implies significant repeatability (e.g. [
  <a rid="pone.0128776.ref075" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref075">75</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0128776.ref076" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref076">76</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0128776.ref077" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref077">77</a>]), estimates for actual repeatability of body mass within or across years have been rather rarely published. Our estimates for repeatability in body mass are in the same range as those for great tits (
  <span class="italic">Parus major</span>) measured in several winters [
  <a rid="pone.0128776.ref078" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref078">78</a>], and weasels (
  <span class="italic">Mustela nivalis</span>) across a time span of up to 400 days [
  <a rid="pone.0128776.ref079" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref079">79</a>], yet higher than in gray catbirds (
  <span class="italic">Dumetella carolinensis</span>) measured across several breeding seasons [
  <a rid="pone.0128776.ref080" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref080">80</a>]. We obtained higher estimates for repeatability of body condition than were previously reported for breeding upland geese (
  <span class="italic">Chloephaga picta leucoptera</span>) [
  <a rid="pone.0128776.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref023">23</a>], while this trait was not significantly repeatable across years in crimson finches (
  <span class="italic">Neochima phaeton</span>) [
  <a rid="pone.0128776.ref081" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref081">81</a>]. To the best of our knowledge, this is the first study that presents repeatability estimates of body mass or body condition across one year or more in a seabird species.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For egg mass, repeatability estimates within females were in the same range as those from other studies (see review in [
  <a rid="pone.0128776.ref082" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref082">82</a>]). As such, finding significant repeatability of egg mass in males that were paired with the same female over several years was expectable and has also been shown before (e.g. [
  <a rid="pone.0128776.ref065" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref065">65</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0128776.ref083" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref083">83</a>]). Yet, considering that male body mass did not affect egg mass (i.e. females did not invest more into egg mass when paired with a heavy male; see 
  <a rid="sec011" ref-type="sec" href="#sec011">discussion</a> below), we were surprised to still find significant (albeit lower) repeatability estimates for egg mass in males when paired with different females. Indeed, our result contradicts a study by Phillips and Furness [
  <a rid="pone.0128776.ref065" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref065">65</a>] that found clutch volume not to be repeatable for male Arctic skuas (
  <span class="italic">Stercorarius parasiticus</span>) paired with different females. On the other hand, Bańbura and Ziliński [
  <a rid="pone.0128776.ref084" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref084">84</a>] found a similar result as ours, with average egg volume being repeatable for male barn swallows (
  <span class="italic">Hirundo rustica</span>) that paired with different females, and assumed assortative mating according to body condition as the underlying mechanism for this effect. In the framework of this study, we have shown that rockhopper penguins do not mate assortatively according to body mass or body condition (i.e. heavy males do not necessarily pair with heavy females). Nevertheless, other traits besides body mass or body condition may also play a role for reproductive investment, for example the timing of clutch initiation. In birds, early breeders usually lay heavier eggs than late breeders [
  <a rid="pone.0128776.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref023">23</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0128776.ref085" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0128776.ref085">85</a>]. As such, if rockhopper penguin males that occupy nest sites early mate consistently with early breeding females, and early breeding females lay heavier eggs than late breeding females, this could explain the significant repeatability for egg mass in males. We did not include clutch initiation date into analyses as the focus of this study was on body mass, and we recorded body mass on clutch initiation date. Therefore, investigating the relationships between body mass and clutch initiation date, or between clutch initiation date and egg mass would inevitably have raised problems with circularity.
 </p>
</sec>
