<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div id="Fig6" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <span class="label">Fig. 6</span>
 <div class="caption">
  <p>Variability in contrail optical depth. Probability distributions (PDF) of contrail optical depth, OD, and (top) the cumulative distribution (
   <span class="bold">a</span>) simulated by an idealised contrail model. The model PDF (
   <span class="bold">b</span>) was obtained (i) by solving an equation governing the evolution of the ice crystal size distribution accounting for mixing-induced dilution, shear-induced spreading, sedimentation and growth by vapour uptake and (ii) by imposing on this solution variability in meteorological factors described by probability distributions (inset) of air temperature, 
   <span class="italic">T</span>, ice supersaturation (accounting for unresolved vertical air motion variability), 
   <span class="italic">s</span>
   <sub>i</sub>, vertical shear of horizontal winds, 
   <span class="italic">σ</span>, and thickness of ice supersaturated layers, Δ
   <span class="italic">z</span>, all constrained by atmospheric observations and numerical weather analyses. Simulation results
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" href="#CR65">65</a>
   </span> are compared with satellite observations
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">56</a>
   </span> of contrails over the eastern North Pacific in the year 2001. According to the model analysis
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66" href="#CR66">66</a>
   </span>, the measurements detected only 39% of all contrails over the whole OD range, 49% are subvisible (OD &lt; 0.02) and 11% are not optically thin (OD &gt; 0.3). By comparing simulated and observed PDF, detection efficiencies, 
   <span class="italic">ε</span>, were inferred: 11.5% for data in the range 0&lt; OD ≤ 0.05; 49% for 0.05 &lt; OD ≤ 0.1; 94.5% for 0.1 &lt; OD ≤ 0.2; and 100% for OD &gt; 0.2, partly overlapping with values derived with other methods and in other conditions
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">59</a>
   </span>. After adjusting the model PDF for inefficient detection using these efficiencies (horizontal arrow), it replicates the observed cumulant (stepped curve). Overall, applying the detection efficiency curve is consistent with a single cut-off OD value of 0.04, the upper limit OD value of the hatched area marking undetected (and partly invisible) contrails. The mean OD of all simulated contrails is 0.15, translating into 0.29 when corrected for non-detectable contrails. The corrected OD is roughly in line with the observed mean value, 0.24, that overestimates the model mean value of all contrails by ≈63%
  </p>
 </div>
 <div xlink:href="41467_2018_4068_Fig6_HTML" id="d29e1227" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</div>
