<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div id="Fig7" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <span class="label">Fig. 7</span>
 <div class="caption">
  <p>Global annual mean radiative forcing due to aircraft-induced clouds. RF due to 
   <span class="bold">a</span> persistent contrails alone and 
   <span class="bold">b</span> together with contrail cirrus from selected studies and assessments sorted by publication date since 1999. Purely observational global estimates derive from extrapolating local aircraft and regional satellite data. Pure model estimates are based on or rely upon global model simulations. Uncertainty ranges evaluated across several methodologies are taken from comprehensive assessments. IPCC 1999 assessed persistent contrail RF to be 20 (5–60) mW m
   <span class="sup">−2</span> for air traffic in the year 1992 (ref. 
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
   </span>), followed by two studies summarising knowledge in the subsequent decade
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73" href="#CR73">73</a>
   </span>. A narrower range, 8–20 mW m
   <span class="sup">−2</span>, was provided for the year 2000 after correcting older estimates that include off-line radiative transfer simulations with prescribed contrail coverage and mean optical depth for undetectable contrails
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67" href="#CR67">67</a>
   </span>. Taken together, subsequent climate model simulations and extrapolation from in situ and satellite observations yielded 3–16 mW m
   <span class="sup">−2</span> for air traffic in 2002–2006 (refs. 
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63" href="#CR63">63</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" href="#CR69">69</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71" href="#CR71">71</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR142" href="#CR142">142</a>
   </span>). Relying in part on extrapolation and scaling data from earlier years, the IPCC most recently assessed contrail RF to be 10 (5–30) mW m
   <span class="sup">−2</span> (ref. 
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
   </span>) for 2011. Refs. 
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73" href="#CR73">73</a>
   </span> provided possible RF ranges due to AIC. Ref. 
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
   </span> estimated for the first time global AIC RF to be 38 mW m
   <span class="sup">−2</span> for air traffic in the year 2002 using a climate model that tracks AIC explicitly; an improved model version
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" href="#CR70">70</a>
   </span> estimated 56 mW m
   <span class="sup">−2</span> for 2006. AIC RF values 50 mW m
   <span class="sup">−2</span> and 60 mW m
   <span class="sup">−2</span> were predicted for 2006 based on an off-line model that tracks contrail segments forming along flight tracks in combination with weather forecast and climate host models
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">52</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88" href="#CR88">88</a>
   </span>. In a climate model that regards contrails as a source term for natural clouds, ref. 
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69" href="#CR69">69</a>
   </span> reported a global AIC RF of 13 mW m
   <span class="sup">−2</span> for the same reference year. The IPCC best estimate of global net RF due to AIC for air traffic in the year 2011—associated with low confidence—is 50 mW m
   <span class="sup">−2</span> (ref. 
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>
   </span>), corresponding to more than half of the total aviation RF, with a 90% uncertainty range, 20–150 mW m
   <span class="sup">−2</span>. This most recent best estimate does not include indirect effects of aircraft particle emissions on natural clouds
  </p>
 </div>
 <div xlink:href="41467_2018_4068_Fig7_HTML" id="d29e1389" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</div>
