<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec2" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study design</div>
  <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This exploratory qualitative study consists of focus group discussions and in-depth interviews that were conducted in eight selected primary healthcare clinics within two states (Selangor and Johor) in Malaysia, which were the pilot sites for the EnPHC initiative. Four CFIR domains were used to assess the HCPs’ receptiveness to the proposed change.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study setting and participants</div>
  <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In Malaysia, public primary healthcare clinics provide primary access for curative, preventive and health promotion services to the community. The clinics are categorised according to the population size served and service availability [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>]. Clinics typically consist of a multi-disciplinary team encompassing family medicine specialists (FMS) (in some clinics), general medical practitioners, and paramedics such as nurses and assistant medical officers, physiotherapists, nutritionists, dieticians and occupational therapists. The clinics were purposively sampled from the urban and rural strata, which served a range of 200 to 1000 patients on a daily basis depending on the type of clinics and locations. In all, 106 HCPs from various categories were included to achieve representation across all levels of staff. The focus group discussions were conducted according to their homogenous group to encourage open discussion and freedom of expression towards readiness to change. The participants may have possibly heard about the EnPHC initiative that was to be implemented, but they did not have exact information regarding the proposed interventions. Furthermore, the researchers did not reveal any information on the initiative to eliminate bias in perceptions across all participants, especially since the actual components of the proposed complex intervention package had yet to be finalised at the time of our data collection.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data collection</div>
  <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data were collected between April and May 2017. Overall, 20 focus group discussion (FGD) sessions involving 40 health professionals and 66 paramedics were conducted; each session included six to eight participants. In-depth interviews (IDI) were also conducted with three FMS from selected clinics. The FMS is usually the highest-level authority in the clinic, hence, separate interview sessions were conducted to avoid uneasiness by other clinic members in expressing their views. Information saturation was achieved when no new information can be added to HCPs’ perception of change. For this study, saturation was achieved after 18 FGD whereby all of the identified domains did not have any new information. The additional two FGD were conducted as confirmatory measure to ensure no new information were found. All 106 participants were invited through their heads of clinics. Interviews were conducted at their workplaces (clinic) and during their preferred accommodated times. This approach was adopted to maximise participation and was found to be fruitful as there were no dropouts.</p>
  <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Prior to fieldwork, a comprehensive interview guide with semi-structured questions was developed to assist the interviewers. Topics included openness, perceptions and readiness to change, aside from other general questions such as service duration in the NCD field and the difficulties or challenges faced at their current workplaces. The interview guide underwent revision to include topics such as perception on the need for improvement in NCD care management and triggers for change (Aditional file 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>).
  </p>
  <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The principle investigator (LLL) contacted all medical officers-in-charge of each study clinic, briefed them about the data collection process and scheduled the interview sessions. Eligible participants were briefed prior to their interviews about the study’s purpose, process, confidentiality assurance, voluntary nature of participation and freedom to withdraw from the study at any point in time. Participants were also given the chance to ask questions. Bilingual (English and Malay) participant information sheets were provided. Written consent and permission for audio recording were obtained from all participants prior to interview sessions.</p>
  <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The FGDs and IDIs were conducted by a minimum of two qualitative researchers, one as the moderator and another as the note-taker. All sessions were audio-recorded to ensure data collection accuracy. Each IDI lasted between 30 to 60 minutes, while the FGDs ranged between 60 to 90 minutes. Sessions were carried out either in mono-, bilingual or mixed language, depending on the comfort and fluency of participants and researchers.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Analysis</div>
  <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data transcription and analysis were carried out immediately after each interview. All interviews were transcribed verbatim into Microsoft Word and subsequently transferred to Nvivo11™ to facilitate data management and coding process. Interviews in Malay language were transcribed without translations, but coded in English. The selected quotes in Malay were translated into English for report writing and publication purposes.</p>
  <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An open coding approach was applied to the transcripts at the first order coding before subsequent grouping in second order coding. To imbue sense into the thematic codes, a framework analysis approach guided by CFIR was carried out. A codebook was developed by adopting from CFIR’s website prior to third order coding [
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>]. Initially, all 39 CFIR constructs were included, but the domain ‘Intervention Process’ was deemed irrelevant at the pre-implementation stage. Hence, only the four domains of ‘Intervention Characteristics’, ‘Outer Setting’, ‘Inner Setting’ and ‘Characteristics of Individual’ were used for analysis. Operational definitions for these constructs were developed with regard to EnPHC implementation to capture contextual factors that might influence implementation effectiveness. Coders are members of EnPHC-Process Evaluation team who are familiar with and understand that CFIR constructs were required to strictly adhere to the predetermined operational definition and apply codes without making inferences from the data. However, analysis was not limited only to CFIR constructs because flexibility to create new subdomains and categories that may arise from the data inductively was allowed. The coding process was done independently in pairs, during which the same transcript was read by two persons who coded it separately, followed by consensual validation among the researchers before codes and verbatim quotes were regrouped into major themes. The codebook was continuously revised throughout the data analysis process, during which additional subdomains and their definitions were added or removed.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
