<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The Upper Ouémé watershed in central Benin covers an area of approximately 14,500 km
 <sup class="sup">2</sup> with an estimated population of about 510,000 people [
 <xref rid="pone.0192642.ref026" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">26</xref>] (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0192642.g001" class="xref">Fig 1</xref>). It is located in the sub-humid tropical zone and is characterized by a unimodal rainfall season from May to October with about 1250 mm of precipitation per year. In general, Benin is affected by a seasonal alteration of cool and humid monsoon air mass (originating from the Gulf of Guinea), and hot, dry and dusty Saharan air mass [
 <xref rid="pone.0192642.ref027" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>]. Rainfall anomalies in Benin and West Africa in general have been associated with the northward or southward position of the Inter-Tropical Convergence Zone and the associated low and upper level jet streams [
 <xref rid="pone.0192642.ref027" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">27</xref>]. The natural vegetation of the watershed is a mosaic of savannah woodland and small forest islands. Smallholder rainfed agriculture is the major economic activity. Maize, rice, yam, cassava, sorghum and millet are the most important food crops, with cotton being the major cash crop. The cropping intensity of these staple crops is 1.5 [
 <xref rid="pone.0192642.ref028" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">28</xref>], indicating that a substantial portion of land either devoted to these crops or other crops is harvested twice per year. The irrigation sector is poorly developed and the lack of irrigation water during the dry season is a major problem for many farmers [
 <xref rid="pone.0192642.ref029" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">29</xref>]. Pastoral communities from neighbouring countries such as Nigeria often migrate to this study area, especially for grazing in the dry season when water and food resources are scarce in the less humid zones of the Upper Ouémé to the north [
 <xref rid="pone.0192642.ref030" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>].
</p>
