<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The proposed range of optimum D
 <sub class="sub">max</sub> (0.28–0.33 m) was relatively narrower and shallower than the previously proposed value (0.3–0.4 m)
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b3" class="xref">3</xref> owing to the additional considerations to the possible adverse effects of deep soil frost penetration on agriculture and environment. Higher nitrate retention ratio by deeper soil frost penetration can be an interesting trend, because soil frost control to manage volunteer potatoes could also allow the alleviation of groundwater pollution by nitrate. However, the D
 <sub class="sub">max</sub> shallower than 0.35 m might be preferable to not enlarge the risk in temporarily increasing greenhouse gas (nitrous oxide) emissions from soil immediately after soil thaw
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b9" class="xref">9</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b22" class="xref">22</xref> (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Supplementary Figure 2</xref>). Furthermore, importantly, the proposed D
 <sub class="sub">max</sub> range was determined by our field data, which were mainly obtained at Andisol fields. Because Andisol is characterised by high permeability, the range of D
 <sub class="sub">max</sub> might be similar to those in other fields having, for example, sandy soil. In contrast, soils having lower permeability might show smaller infiltration ratio of snowmelt water to soil even though the D
 <sub class="sub">max</sub> is considerably shallower. The smaller infiltration ratio of snowmelt water to soil can allow higher retention ratio of nitrate at the surface soil layer. Therefore, the deeper limit of the optimum D
 <sub class="sub">max</sub> might be less than 0.33 m as determined in our study (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f3" class="xref">Fig. 3</xref>) in the case of soils having lower water permeability. In other words, our proposed optimum D
 <sub class="sub">max</sub> might be applicable as a reference to achieve volunteer potato control with minimised adverse effects on the soil frost control for different soil types. If the D
 <sub class="sub">max</sub> of 0.28 m is very deep for the fields to infiltrate surface-flooding snowmelt water, the target D
 <sub class="sub">max</sub> should be modified based on the allowable level of volunteer potato emergence for individual farmers. Thus, maintaining the D
 <sub class="sub">max</sub> within the optimum range might allow adaptation to and mitigation of climate change effects. For the extended application of soil frost control as the mitigation measure for climate change, further studies are needed to establish the relationships between seasonal dynamics of greenhouse gas (nitrous oxide) emission and soil management
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b23" class="xref">23</xref>.
</p>
