<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study Site, Sampling, and Chronology</div>
  <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Saleh Cave (3.03220º S, 115.98386º E, 48 m) is located in a tropical karst tower along the eastern edge of South Kalimantan, Indonesia, approximately 25 (200) km from the modern (LGM) coast (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). It is a small shelter extending approximately 500 m into the karst with unidentified insectivorous bats presently inhabiting the cave, and two open chambers each containing a separate and large guano deposits. The nearest deposit to the entrance was very wet and pocketed by drip holes in the surface. We collected from the drier and larger chamber further from the entrance. Surface and ancient ‘rock guano’ (at depth) were collected from a pit excavated through accumulated guano to bedrock at 304 cm depth. Exposed sediments were sampled at 3–5 cm intervals, adjusted where necessary to ensure that sample intervals did not cross stratigraphic boundaries. Samples were irradiated to sterilize, then kept frozen until freeze-dried.
  </p>
  <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A chronology was established by AMS 
   <span class="sup">14</span>C measurements on solvent extracted guano using acid/base/acid treatment (see Supplementary Table 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>). A few samples were problematic, and these were repeated by isolating pyrogenic carbon using hydrogen pyrolysis and submitted for radiocarbon measurement (see Supplementary information). An age model was constructed using Bacon 2.2 which employs Bayesian analysis to reconstruct accumulation rates for depositional sequences, through combining radiocarbon dates with prior information such as accumulation rate and its variability. The output is a probability distribution of calibrated dates with depth (Blaauw and Christen, 2011). Calendar year as a function of depth was plotted using weighted mean age output (Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>). Radiocarbon measurements indicate that guano miners removed much of the Holocene guano. Modern guano contribution to surface samples (down to 20 cm) was estimated via carbon abundances, and guano age to 25 cm was estimated via mass balance between contemporary guano and ancient guano, hence an apparent low accumulation rate above 20 cm.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Determination of Carbon Isotope Composition</div>
  <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Briefly, guano samples were crushed using a mortar and pestle, and lipids were removed by sonicating in 2:1 (v/v) dichloromethane/ methanol 3 times, followed with one rinse in methanol. Solvent extracted guano (SEG) was then washed in 1 M NaOH at 100 °C for 30 minutes, neutralised using DI-water and subsequently washed for 3 hrs in 2 M HCl, and neutralized before freeze-drying again (SEG-BA). Carbon isotope composition was determined using an elemental analyzer (ECS 4010 CHNSO Analyzer; Costech Analytical Technologies INC, Valencia, CA, USA) fitted with a Costech Zero Blank Autosampler coupled via a ConFloIV to a Thermo Scientific Delta V
   <span class="sup">PLUS</span> using Continuous-Flow Isotope Ratio Mass Spectrometry (EA-IRMS) at the Advanced Analytical Centre, James Cook University, Cairns. Calibration curves for elemental abundances were determined for two in-house standards (Chitin and Taipan) and USGS-40 (L-glutamic acid) within the same analysis sequence, and reproducibility was better than ±5% of the value. 
   <span class="italic">δ</span>
   <span class="sup">13</span>C values are reported as per mil (‰) deviations from the VPDB reference scale, using the same reference materials as for elemental abundances. Precisions (S.D.) on internal standards were better than ±0.1‰.
  </p>
  <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">n</span>-alkane fractions were extracted from guano using a CEM MARS (Microwave accelerated reaction system) with 2:1 DCM:MeOH (v/v). Filtered samples were further cleaned using silica gel flash chromatography. The compound-specific carbon isotope composition of 
   <span class="italic">n-</span>alkanes was measured with a Thermo Scientific Trace GC instrument connected to a Thermo Scientific Delta Plus XP isotope ratio mass spectrometer (GC-IRMS), equipped with a DB-5 MS column (30 m × 0.25 mm × 0.25 μm). The injector was set at 300 °C. The GC oven temperature was held at 50 °C for 1 min, then set to 220 °C at 10 °C/min (held 2 min), and then to 300 °C (2 °C/min), and finally to 310 °C (10 °C/min, held for 20 min). He was used as carrier gas (1.4 ml/min). The temperature of the combustion oven was 950 °C. Instrumental performance was verified before and after each sample run using an 
   <span class="italic">n</span>-alkane standard mixture with known 
   <span class="italic">δ</span>
   <span class="sup">13</span>C values (
   <span class="italic">n</span>-C16–
   <span class="italic">n</span>-C30, Indiana University). The relative standard deviation for reference material was better than ±0.5‰, based on a minimum of two analyses. Results are reported as per mil (‰) deviations from the VPDB reference scale.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
