<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par2" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Indo-Pacific Warm Pool is the largest reservoir of warm water on Earth
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>
  </span>. Sea surface temperatures (SSTs) exceed 28 °C, and the IPWP plays a critical role in global climate
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span>. Seasonally, climate is governed by the migration of the Inter-Tropical Convergence Zone (ITCZ), with both the East Asian monsoon (EAM) and the Australian-Indonesian monsoon (AIM) resulting in deep atmospheric convection and high rainfall across the central and northern parts of the region
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span>. This climate leads to generally everwet conditions and lowland dipterocarp rainforest across most of Borneo today
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
  </span> with tropical grass relative abundance encompassing less than 0.1 for the vast majority of the island
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
  </span>. However, abrupt and strong inter-annual variability in SSTs and salinities in the IPWP are associated with ENSO (El Niño-Southern Oscillation) variability that can bring periods of drought
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">During the Last Glacial Period (LGP, c. 110-11.7 kyr ago), reduced global sea level exposed the continental shelf from south of Thailand to Sumatra, Java, and Borneo, revealing the contiguous continent of Sundaland that reached its maximum land area extent during the Last Glacial Maximum (LGM, 26.5-19 kyr ago
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>
  </span>) (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). Such a large change in land/sea area severely impacted the IPWP by reducing its size
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>
  </span> while SSTs 2–4 °C lower than today in the IPWP region would have also served to reduce atmospheric convection
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>
  </span>. It has been proposed that a reduction of rainfall would lead to the development of a ‘savanna corridor’ running north to south/southeast from what is today Peninsula Malaysia across to southern Borneo through the Java Sea
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span> (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). Whether or not open vegetation existed on Sundaland, especially in Borneo, is the subject of intense debate, with significant implications for its biogeography, conservation, LGP carbon storage, and the understanding of early human dispersals through the region
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>
  </span>.
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Current and projected LGM conditions surrounding equatorial Southeast Asia. Diamond showing location of Saleh cave (3.0322°S, 115.9839°E) used for palaeoenvironmental reconstruction. Other cave locations (dots), lake sediments (square), offshore terrestrial (triangles), and Sea Surface Temperature (star) records are indicated. Yellow symbols indicate open vegetation and green symbols indicate closed forest were interpreted for the LGM. (
     <span class="bold">a</span>) Modern mean annual Sea Surface Temperatures
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>
     </span> showing annual averaged 28 °C contours defining the Indo-Pacific Warm Pool. (
     <span class="bold">b</span>) 100 m isobaths indicating approximate shoreline of the Last Glacial Maximum. Also shown are proposed glacial savanna and forest refugia
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
     </span>, −4 mm/day (solid) and −2 mm/day (dash) contours for annual mean 21 k-0 k precipitation difference for the HadCM3M2 –Ocean-Atmosphere experiment
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>
     </span>. Figure was constructed using Ocean Data View
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>
     </span>.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_42670_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e428" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Vegetation models in general simulate tropical rainforest across Sundaland during the LGM, particularly in central Sundaland
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span>. Species distribution models also suggested that rich dipterocarp forests were maintained during the LGM in central Sundaland
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
  </span>, although a few vegetation models have simulated a possible savanna corridor
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>
  </span>. Vegetation simulations are driven ultimately by climate models that simulate a range of ‘dry’ to ‘wet’ conditions during the LGM for Sundaland
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
  </span>. The limited amount of proxy data in the region has enabled the selective interpretation of sites in order to deduce either drier conditions and open vegetation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>
  </span>, or wet conditions and the continued presence of tropical rainforest
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>
  </span> during the LGM.
 </p>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Southern Borneo is ideally placed to test the savanna corridor hypothesis. A few well resolved records in the northern part of Borneo indicate everwet conditions were maintained during the LGP
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">23</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>
  </span>, the southern part of Borneo has produced only limited and equivocal data. Evidence that southern Borneo was everwet and served as a glacial rainforest refugia, or seasonally dry during the LGM have been summarized elsewhere
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span>. A few poorly dated or low resolution pollen records from Kalimantan displayed a ‘graminae’ phase during the LGM that have been interpreted as floating mats of herbaceous vegetation, or as representing more seasonal climatic conditions than today
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>
  </span>, while an offshore biomarker record found no change between LGM and Holocene phenol ratios suggesting the maintenance of rainforest
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Herein, we examine vegetation change over the past 40,000 cal yrs BP using 
  <span class="italic">δ</span>
  <span class="sup">13</span>C values of guano and High Molecular Weight (HMW) 
  <span class="italic">n</span>-alkanes extracted from a 3 m thick guano deposit in South Kalimantan, Indonesia (Saleh Cave, 3.03220°S, 115.98386°E). Faeces (guano) can accumulate in deposits several meters thick in Southeast Asia, providing sedimentary proxy records of environmental change amenable to radiocarbon dating
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span>. Fresh guano is composed dominantly of finely comminuted insect cuticles that are subsequently broken down by bacteria and fungi. These sediments contain multi-proxy information from a variety of sources, but 
  <span class="italic">δ</span>
  <span class="sup">13</span>C values are arguably the most powerful proxy for past environments that can be derived from tropical guano records
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Insect abundance is largely determined by available vegetation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
  </span>, and insect 
  <span class="italic">δ</span>
  <span class="sup">13</span>C values are determined by diet with little fractionation
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
  </span>. Communities of bats and swiftlets generally forage within a 15 km range of the roost
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span> ensuring that a local to regional vegetation signal is captured in the guano deposit
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
  </span>. HMW 
  <span class="italic">n</span>-alkanes represent molecular records from insect cuticles, both from assimilation of plant derived 
  <span class="italic">n</span>-alkanes, and from 
  <span class="italic">de novo</span> synthesis
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
  </span> (see supplemental text). In lowland tropical locations, grasses utilize the C
  <sub>4</sub> photosynthetic pathway, whereas trees use the C
  <sub>3</sub> pathway. The different enzymatic pathways used to fix CO
  <sub>2</sub> results in 
  <span class="italic">δ</span>
  <span class="sup">13</span>C values of C
  <sub>4</sub> plants (−9 to −16‰) and their insect hosts that are substantially different than those of C
  <sub>3</sub> plants (−19 to −34‰)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
  </span>. Hence, both guano and HMW 
  <span class="italic">n</span>-alkanes 
  <span class="italic">δ</span>
  <span class="sup">13</span>C values indicate the abundance of local to regional C
  <sub>4</sub> biomass. As seasonality of precipitation is a strong predictor of vegetation in the Sundaic region
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
  </span>, changing relative abundance of C
  <sub>4</sub> vegetation indicates changing precipitation regimes.
 </p>
</sec>
