<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">We assessed how climate change and other stressors have impacted desert bird populations over the past century by resurveying sites throughout the Mojave Desert that were originally surveyed for avian diversity in the early 20th century by Joseph Grinnell and colleagues. About 85% of desert lands in this region are largely undisturbed and ecologically intact (
 <xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>), allowing for assessment of the impacts of climate change without the confounding effects of land-use change. Nevertheless, structural changes to habitat induced by grazing and increased severity and frequency of fire are potentially important threats to Mojave birds (
 <xref rid="r21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>). Invasive plants occur in the Mojave, but their primary ecological impact has been to increase fire fuel loads and promote recurrent fires (
 <xref rid="r21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>). Thus, we used fire return intervals as a proxy for the primary impact of invasive plants on habitat; see 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1805123115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
  <italic class="italic">SI Appendix</italic>
 </ext-link> for a review of invasive plant impacts in the Mojave. We related changes over the past century in occupancy and richness of the Mojave avian community to changes in climate (annual precipitation, average temperature, and maximum temperature), disturbance (fire and grazing), ecosystem productivity facilitated by actual evapotranspiration (AET) and inhibited by climate water deficit (CWD), and recent weather (precipitation, average temperature, and maximum temperature of the previous year) using a dynamic multispecies occupancy model (
 <xref rid="r22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>). The analysis quantifies species and community change simultaneously, while accounting for species and survey differences in detectability.
</p>
