<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par21">It is well known that WPSH is a strongest subtropical anticyclone high pressure system controlling monthly weather conditions in YRD during late-summer and may intensify in a warming climate background. To systemically study the impact of WPSH on inter-annual variability of ozone pollution in Shanghai under the climate change background, intensive surface measurements of ozone and meteorological data and the NCEP/NCAR re-analyzed meteorological data are used in the analysis. The highlights of this study are as follows:
 <list list-type="order">
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par22">To better understand the relationship between WPSH and O
    <sub>3</sub> in Shanghai, we define geopotential height averaged over a key area (122.5°E-135°E, 27.5°N-35°N) at 500 hPa. In this region, the correlation coefficients between related to ozone concentration in Shanghai shows a maximum positive value (0.78). As a result, the WPSH’s in this region (defined as WPSH_SHO
    <sub>3</sub>) can better represent the effect of WPSH on the O
    <sub>3</sub> concentrations in Shanghai, and are used in this study.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par23">Long-term trend analysis shows that the WPSH_SHO
    <sub>3</sub> index significantly increased from 1960 to 2017, with a rate of 5 gpm decade
    <sup>−1</sup>, resulting from the global climate change.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par24">To quantify the effect of the increasing WPSH_SHO
    <sub>3</sub> on the O3 concentrations in Shanghai, two cases (i.e., a weak WPSH_SHO
    <sub>3</sub> case - occurred in Jul. 2017, and a strong WPSH_SHO
    <sub>3</sub> – occurred in Aug. 2016) are selected and analyzed in this study. The results show that in the strong WPSH_SHO
    <sub>3</sub> case, the lower relative humidity, higher temperature, less cloud, and higher solar radiation produced higher ozone photochemical production than the weak WPSH_SHO
    <sub>3</sub> case. In addition the wind directions in the strong case were dominated by southwest wind. In the contrast, in the weak WPSH_SHO
    <sub>3</sub> case, east and southeast winds were dominated, which transported relative clean air from ocean, resulting in lower O
    <sub>3</sub> concentrations in the weak case.
   </p>
  </list-item>
  <list-item>
   <p id="Par25">Because there are several important factors in controlling the O
    <sub>3</sub> concentrations, such as diffusion (DIF), (b) advection (ADV), and (c) gas-phase chemistry (CHEM), The MOZART model is applied to study the individual contributions to the surface O
    <sub>3</sub> in Shanghai. The results show that in the strong WPSH_SHO
    <sub>3</sub> case, the vertical diffusion produced significant reduction for the O
    <sub>3</sub> concentrations at the surface. This was due to the fact that with less cloud condition, the solar radiation was stronger, producing higher thermal turbulence and vertical diffusion as well as the planetary boundary layer heights. As a result, the surface O
    <sub>3</sub> concentrations were vertical mixed in the upper planetary boundary layer, causing the decrease of O
    <sub>3</sub> concentrations at surface layer in Shanghai.
   </p>
  </list-item>
 </list>
</p>
