<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Studies focusing on vulnerability assessment have so far not been comprehensive or appropriately delineated, especially in the coastal region of Bangladesh. Although a large number of vulnerability studies [
 <xref rid="B27-ijerph-16-04552" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>,
 <xref rid="B34-ijerph-16-04552" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>,
 <xref rid="B35-ijerph-16-04552" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>,
 <xref rid="B38-ijerph-16-04552" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-ijerph-16-04552" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>,
 <xref rid="B44-ijerph-16-04552" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>,
 <xref rid="B45-ijerph-16-04552" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>,
 <xref rid="B46-ijerph-16-04552" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,
 <xref rid="B47-ijerph-16-04552" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>,
 <xref rid="B48-ijerph-16-04552" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>,
 <xref rid="B49-ijerph-16-04552" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>,
 <xref rid="B50-ijerph-16-04552" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>,
 <xref rid="B51-ijerph-16-04552" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,
 <xref rid="B52-ijerph-16-04552" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>,
 <xref rid="B53-ijerph-16-04552" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>,
 <xref rid="B54-ijerph-16-04552" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>,
 <xref rid="B55-ijerph-16-04552" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>] are being conducted, almost none of the previous studies addressed integrated agriculture (i.e., crops, fisheries, and livestock) or took into account the connections between different spatial scales, addressed multiple hazards, or led to the formulation of intervention planning to enhance adaptation capacity. These latter two issues comprise a global research gap [
 <xref rid="B56-ijerph-16-04552" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. Notably, vulnerability assessment of the farming sector was restricted to a localized small area [
 <xref rid="B46-ijerph-16-04552" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,
 <xref rid="B55-ijerph-16-04552" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>] and specialized fields like fisheries [
 <xref rid="B27-ijerph-16-04552" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Hence, the agricultural vulnerability in coastal Bangladesh needs to be assessed by capturing fisheries and livestock along with the crop sector because, in reality, the elements of this tri-economy are invariably mutually dependent and most productive agriculture in the Asian region is located around the river—floodplains, swamp, lakes, and other water reservoirs [
 <xref rid="B57-ijerph-16-04552" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. So these three major farming enterprises deserve to be interconnected [
 <xref rid="B58-ijerph-16-04552" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>] to assess climate change vulnerability for a country like Bangladesh, which is driven by an agro-based economy. Furthermore, vulnerability assessment in coastal Bangladesh should be conducted to the administrative unit (district) at which government agencies allocate resources, which is one mechanism to help ensure that output from vulnerability assessments can be integrated into strategic government plans. Such an assessment at the district level could empower decision-makers and other non-governmental bodies to effectively direct the adaptation investment [
 <xref rid="B59-ijerph-16-04552" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>].
</p>
