<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Barriers associated with ring taxa share topographic features that are rarely found in nature</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">All barriers identified globally by our model are shown in a multivariate topographic space (Figure 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F3" href="#F3">3A</a>), computed using a principal component analysis on the six barrier summary statistics (Table 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="T1" href="#T1">1</a>). Principal component (PC) 1 explained 64% of the variation and loaded most heavily on size (area, perimeter, latitudinal range) and permeability (shape); PC2 explained an additional 19% of the variation and loaded most heavily on position (distance from equator) and permeability (fragmentation; Additional file 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S3" href="#S3">3</a>).
 </p>
 <div id="F3" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Principal component analysis of geographic barriers identified by the topographic ring model. A</span>: Density of all candidate barriers on the planet, with numbers corresponding to reference barriers known to promote ring speciation processes: (1) 
    <span class="italic">Ensatina</span>: Central Valley, California, USA; (2) 
    <span class="italic">Acacia</span>: Drakensberg Massif, South Africa; (3) 
    <span class="italic">Larus</span>: Makarov Basin, Arctic Ocean; (4) 
    <span class="italic">Phylloscopus</span>: Tibetan Plateau, Central Asia; (5) 
    <span class="italic">Phylloscopus</span>: Takla Maka and Gobi Deserts, Central Asia; (6) 
    <span class="italic">Larus</span>: Amundsen and Nansen Basins, Arctic Ocean; (7) 
    <span class="italic">Larus</span>: Canada Basin, Arctic Ocean. Darker red tones correspond to higher barrier density; whitespace identifies areas where barriers are undefined (that is, non-existent). 
    <span class="bold">B</span>: Vertical zoom on numbers 1 to 7 in A, showing in red the 100 closest cohesive candidate barriers (Euclidean distance) to the 
    <span class="italic">Ensatina </span>and 
    <span class="italic">Acacia </span>reference barriers (1 and 2), and the 1,380 cohesive candidate barriers identified for the bird taxa 
    <span class="italic">Larus </span>and 
    <span class="italic">Phylloscopus </span>and used to evaluate candidate composite barriers. Green points show the distribution of barriers where permeability as measured by fragmentation was less than the maximum possible. Lowercase letters show the locations of barriers evaluated in the discussion (b = Baja, c = Costa Rica, i = Iberian Peninsula, m = Madagascar, n = New Guinea). Black contours identify (from left to right) tiers of increasing density.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="1741-7007-10-20-3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Considering all geographic barriers identified globally by our model, most share topographic features that cause them to cluster in two high density peaks of the PCA (Figure 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F3" href="#F3">3A</a>). Meanwhile, the seven reference barriers cluster in a very discrete, low density area of the PCA (Figure 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F3" href="#F3">3B</a>). Despite known species idiosyncrasies, our model is evidently tracking barrier traits that exert effects (Table 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="T1" href="#T1">1</a>) across taxa, since barriers involved in ring diversification in salamander and tree taxa are near one another in multivariate space (points 1 and 2, Figure 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F3" href="#F3">3A</a>), and all individual barriers that comprise composite bird barriers also cluster (points 3 to 7, Figure 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F3" href="#F3">3A</a>). This result indicates that barriers associated with ring taxa share similar topographic features, and that these topographic features are relatively rare on the planet. While our small sample size prevents any formal statistical comparison, the topographic features of the barriers associated with the reference taxa are also distributed along an axis of dispersal behavior (Figure 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F3" href="#F3">3B</a>). As expected, our model shows that ring taxa with higher dispersal (points 3 to 7, Figure 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F3" href="#F3">3B</a>) require larger barriers than lower dispersers (points 1 and 2, Figure 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F3" href="#F3">3B</a>). A better understanding of how characteristics of the barriers scale with the biology of the organism will benefit from the discovery of new ring taxa, which can fill in the biological continuum that is encompassed by the current reference ring taxa, and also expand model predictions.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Compared to the most common barriers on the planet, reference barriers are larger in size (area, perimeter, latitudinal range) and less permeable (shape). These results support initial predictions for four of our six summary statistics (Table 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="T1" href="#T1">1</a>). Notable exceptions include the two summary statistics on PC2: (i) position (distance from equator), where the small number of known ring species prevented us from evaluating whether larger barriers would be required at higher latitudes, and (ii) fragmentation, where we expected more fragmented barriers to allow trans-barrier gene flow and thus prevent ring diversification. In actuality, our measure of fragmentation is reflecting the real topographic complexity of barriers. While small to medium sized barriers (&lt; 50,000 km
  <span class="sup">2</span>) can have lower values for fragmentation (green points in Figure 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F3" href="#F3">3B</a>), larger barriers are more likely to encompass fragmenting features like valleys and ridges, so that fragmentation is maximum for all barriers above 50,000 km
  <span class="sup">2 </span>(Additional file 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S4" href="#S4">4</a>). For the same reason, our model recognizes larger topographic features such as the Arctic Ocean and Central Asia as clusters of individual barriers that are so large that they can no longer remain cohesive. In contrast, permeability of the barrier as measured by shape (perimeter-to-area ratio), which loaded heavily on PC1, fully matched our initial predictions, suggesting that this summary statistic might better reflect trans-barrier dispersal, or that its effect is biologically more meaningful than a finer fragmentation of the barrier. Although shape as computed by a perimeter-to-area ratio scales with size, the reference barriers were some of the most geometrically compact barriers within their respective size classes (low perimeter-to-area ratios in Additional file 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S4" href="#S4">4</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A minimum bounding box around the seven reference barriers (Figure 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F3" href="#F3">3B</a>) encompassed approximately 1% of all candidate barriers on the planet. This statistic taken at face value suggests that geographic barriers with similar topographic characteristics to those that promote ring divergence are exceedingly rare. However, a statistic of 1% also results in about 10,000 individual cohesive barriers that are similar in terms of size, position and permeability to known ring barriers. In agreement with Mayr's [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B8" href="#B8">8</a>] assertion, those topographic conditions are indeed rare when compared to all candidate barriers on the planet, but numerous when considered relative to the handful of ring species that are well-described by science [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B2" href="#B2">2</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B6" href="#B6">6</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B8" href="#B8">8</a>]. This further raises the possibility that a relatively large number of under-studied barriers on the planet may be associated with taxa that are evolving under ring processes of divergence.
 </p>
</sec>
