<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Identification of reference and candidate barriers</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Following development of the topographic model, we identified the barriers associated with our reference taxa ('reference barriers'), and also the other barriers from around the world that were topographically similar to the reference barriers ('candidate barriers').</p>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Reference barriers</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We identified reference barriers by visually inspecting which topographic barriers from the model were circumscribed by the distributions of reference taxa. Data on the distributions of reference taxa were obtained from a combination of georeferenced point localities and range maps and included the following sources: 
   <span class="italic">Ensatina </span>[
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B18" href="#B18">18</a>], 
   <span class="italic">Acacia </span>[
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B27" href="#B27">27</a>], 
   <span class="italic">Phylloscopous </span>[
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B34" href="#B34">34</a>], and 
   <span class="italic">Larus </span>[
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B34" href="#B34">34</a>]. We then used principal components 1 and 2 (PC1, PC2) to extract the locations in multidimensional space of the reference barriers associated with our reference ring taxa. We determined that both 
   <span class="italic">Ensatina </span>and 
   <span class="italic">Acacia </span>encircled single barriers ('cohesive barriers'), while 
   <span class="italic">Larus </span>and 
   <span class="italic">Phylloscopus </span>each encircled clusters of two or three cohesive barriers in close geographic proximity (thus forming 'composite barriers'). For purposes of describing the geography of each cohesive and composite reference barrier, we identified the common names of the topographic features from multiple world and regional maps.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Candidate barriers</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Because geographic species formation depends on the interaction between the 'scale' of the organism and the spatial scale of the barrier associated with it, both the population biology and history of reference and candidate taxa need to be considered when evaluating candidate barriers. Thus, we identified candidate barriers separately with respect to the reference taxa and associated barriers. Because reference barriers were discovered to be either cohesive or composite, we further identified candidate barriers according to two methods.</p>
  <sec class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Candidate cohesive barriers (
    <span class="italic">Ensatina </span>and 
    <span class="italic">Acacia</span>)
   </div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Candidate cohesive barriers are represented in the model by other individual barriers that are topographically similar to the reference barriers in multidimensional barrier space. For this method, we identified candidate cohesive barriers as the 100 nearest neighbors (Euclidean distance) to each reference barrier in the PCA. Yet, other criteria could alternatively be used to define similarity (for example, a Euclidean buffer around reference barriers). For each reference taxon and associated barrier, we mapped the candidates back into geographic space and summed across barriers to detect possible spatial overlap of topographically similar candidates that were not consolidated using our estimate of fragmentation.</p>
  </sec>
  <sec class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Candidate composite barriers (
    <span class="italic">Larus </span>and 
    <span class="italic">Phylloscopus</span>)
   </div>
   <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Composite barriers are represented in the model by groups of other individual cohesive barriers. In addition to the summary statistics characteristic of all barriers, reference composite barriers are described by a particular combination of individual barriers with four criteria: (i) number of barriers, (ii) total area, (iii) geographic proximity to one another, and (iv) the same inflection. Individual barriers were first queried by identifying the 100 nearest neighbors (Euclidean distance) relative to each of the five reference barriers. Because these barriers clustered with respect to both reference bird taxa, we used a minimum convex polygon around the 500 total nearest neighbors to identify 1,380 candidate barriers. As performed for 
    <span class="italic">Ensatina </span>and 
    <span class="italic">Acacia</span>, we mapped the candidates back into geographic space and summed across barriers to detect spatial overlap of topographically similar candidates that were not consolidated using our estimate of fragmentation. We then queried for candidate composite barriers separately in 
    <span class="italic">Larus </span>and 
    <span class="italic">Phylloscopus </span>using the four criteria above, with similarity thresholds set to 5%. In the case of the Arctic Ocean, which was comprised of three individual reference barriers, we employed a two-barrier approximation because 90% of the total area was explained by two reference barriers (the Canada and Amundsen-Nansen Basins).
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
</sec>
