<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Reference ring taxa do not always encircle single topographic barriers</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Using a standardized set of criteria to formally define a barrier, our topographic model identified a total of 952,147 geographically cohesive barriers on the planet. Many of these barriers aligned with ecoregions (Additional file 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" href="#S1">1</a>), suggesting that barriers predicted by our model do indeed delineate areas that represent valid biogeographic barriers. Furthermore, when overlaying the distributions of reference ring taxa, we find that they encircle topographic barriers identified by our model (Figure 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">2</a>). However, contrary to expectations based on both classical [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B2" href="#B2">2</a>,
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B8" href="#B8">8</a>] and recent [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="B6" href="#B6">6</a>] reviews of ring species, at the spatial scale of our analysis not all ring taxa encircle single topographic barriers. While 
  <span class="italic">Ensatina </span>and 
  <span class="italic">Acacia </span>encircle single barriers ('cohesive barriers'; Figure 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">2A, C</a>), the bird taxa 
  <span class="italic">Larus </span>and 
  <span class="italic">Phylloscopus </span>encircle two or more barriers that are in close geographic proximity ('composite barriers'; Figure 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="F2" href="#F2">2B, D</a>). The seven barriers associated with our focal ring taxa align with major topographic features that define important climatic and ecological transitions (numbers correspond to barriers labeled in the PCA, below) are: (1) 
  <span class="italic">Ensatina</span>: Central Valley, California, USA; (2) 
  <span class="italic">Acacia</span>: Drakensberg Massif, South Africa; (3) 
  <span class="italic">Larus</span>: Makarov Basin, Arctic Ocean; (4) 
  <span class="italic">Phylloscopus</span>: Tibetan Plateau, Central Asia; (5) 
  <span class="italic">Phylloscopus</span>: Takla Maka and Gobi Deserts, Central Asia; (6) 
  <span class="italic">Larus</span>: Amundsen and Nansen Basins, Arctic Ocean; (7) 
  <span class="italic">Larus</span>: Canada Basin, Arctic Ocean. The close spatial proximity of the individual barriers associated with the bird taxa (3 to 7) relate to larger topographic features generally known as Central Asia (barriers 4 and 5) and the Arctic Ocean (barriers 3, 6 and 7). In addition to 
  <span class="italic">Larus </span>and 
  <span class="italic">Phylloscopus</span>, these composite barriers have also contributed to ring divergence in three other birds (Additional file 
  <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S2" href="#S2">2</a>).
 </p>
 <div id="F2" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>
    <span class="bold">Reference barriers and reference taxa. A</span>: The salamander species 
    <span class="italic">Ensatina eschscholtzii</span>: Central Valley, California, USA. 
    <span class="bold">B</span>: The bird species 
    <span class="italic">Phylloscopus trochiloides</span>: Central Asia. 
    <span class="bold">C</span>: The tree species 
    <span class="italic">Acacia karroo</span>: Drakensberg Massif, South Africa. 
    <span class="bold">D</span>: The bird species complex 
    <span class="italic">Larus</span>: Arctic Ocean. Barriers are shown by the red polygons, species' distributions by the black points, and global elevations by the shaded topography. Numbers correspond to individual barriers identified in the PCA.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="1741-7007-10-20-2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our finding that composite barriers exist and can promote ring diversification even in taxa that disperse widely is not simply an artifact of the model or the spatial resolution of the data. At different spatial resolutions of topographic slope (30 arc sec to 3 arc degrees) the model still predicted Central Asia and the Arctic Ocean as composite barriers. Furthermore, composite barriers encompass such large geographic areas (millions of km
  <span class="sup">2 </span>and hundreds of different ecoregions) that it is difficult to imagine any univariate or multivariate environmental approximation of a single barrier (for example, Central Asia, which is comprised of the Takla Maka-Gobi deserts and the Tibetan Plateau - large geographic regions that differ dramatically in terms of climate and vegetation). If ring taxa that disperse widely are in fact distributed around composite barriers, then an important implication for ring speciation is that individual barriers in close spatial proximity can interact with one another to form effective barriers to species distribution that are orders of magnitude larger than any single cohesive barrier. More empirical work is required to determine the spatial characteristics of inter-barrier gaps that prevent ring taxa from maintaining genetic connectivity across composite barriers.
 </p>
</sec>
