<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par16" class="p">In Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3(b)</xref> there is a large scatter about the best fit line, with some suggestion of an 11-year solar cycle influence because of the role of scattered Lyman-α and incident galactic cosmic rays on the nighttime D-region electron number density profiles
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">24</xref>
 </sup>. This is consistent with potential solar cycle changes in mesopause temperature
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" class="xref">33</xref>
 </sup>. Systematic increases in fringe distance are observed during the declining phase of some solar cycles (e.g., 1992–1995, and 2012–2016). This solar cycle influence is investigated in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3(c)</xref> when the data points are separated into periods with low monthly average sunspot number (0–35), medium (36–75) and high (&gt;75) solar activity, as given by the International Space Environmental Services (ISES) sunspot number for November in each year. As there were only three data points in the high solar activity category, spanning only 7 years, those results are not shown. The red data points are associated with low solar activity, while the blue data points are from medium activity periods. Standard errors bars are the same as in panel (b). The panel suggests that there is an outward expansion of the fringe pattern with decreasing solar flux, i.e., from medium levels of sunspot activity to low levels of sunspot activity, consistent with increasing LF phase height during solar declining periods
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">18</xref>
 </sup>. Least squares fits are shown (red line for low activity, and blue line for medium solar activity). The results show that contractions of the NAA fringe pattern of ~4.7 km/yr occur during low solar activity periods, and ~4.4 km/yr during medium activity periods. The contraction of a mono-chromatic fringe pattern setup between two parallel reflective surfaces (ground and the ionosphere in this case) is consistent with a reduction of the distance between the surfaces
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" class="xref">34</xref>
 </sup>. Typically the change in fringe pattern with the quasi-11 year solar cycle is ~100 km, whereas the change over the whole dataset is ~200 km. This contrasts with a LF phase height decrease of ~0.6 km over 50 years, a solar cycle influence of ~1 km, and shorter-term fluctuations (such as the QBO) of ~0.1 km
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">18</xref>
 </sup>. The VLF transmitter fringe pattern changes studied here are too sparse to resolve fluctuations associated with the QBO, although we note that these are likely to be in the order of 10% of the solar cycle influence
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">18</xref>
 </sup>, and are therefore ~10 km here, i.e., within the errors bars shown in Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" class="xref">3(a)</xref>.
</p>
