<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Although the primary mission of sun-synchronous, polar-orbiting environmental satellites is weather forecasting, providing most observations used in global forecasting models (
 <xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">1</italic>
 </xref>), polar-orbiting satellites have been playing a vital role in measuring temperature trends during the past few decades (
 <xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">2</italic>
 </xref>–
 <xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">18</italic>
 </xref>) owing to their global coverage and long-term continuity. However, satellite-derived temperature trends have been a subject of debate for nearly three decades. The first attempt to derive satellite-based atmospheric temperature trends was made in the early 1990s using observations from the Microwave Sounding Unit (MSU) onboard the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA) Polar-orbiting Operational Environmental Satellite series (
 <xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">2</italic>
 </xref>). The MSU and its follow-on microwave sounders passively measure the upwelling radiances from the 50- to 60-GHz absorption band of the atmospheric oxygen in discrete frequency channels. The radiance measured by each frequency channel comes from a different layer of the atmosphere, depending on the strength of the absorption at that frequency. The relative contribution of temperatures at individual levels to the measured layer temperature is represented by a vertical weighting function, which is typically a bell-shaped curve peaking at certain level in the height coordinate (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" class="xref">Fig. 1</xref>). The initial study (
 <xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">2</italic>
 </xref>) used MSU channel 2 with a frequency band catered at 53.74 GHz for temperature trend detection in the mid-troposphere. The same group also created a lower-tropospheric temperature time series from differences between the near-nadir and near-limb observations of MSU channel 2 (
 <xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">3</italic>
 </xref>). This study found near-zero trends during 1979–1990 in the lower- and mid-tropospheric temperatures, in contradiction to both the ground-based observational evidence that the surface temperature had been increasing during the same period (
 <xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">4</italic>
 </xref>) and the theoretical prediction that the global temperature near the Earth’s surface shall be increasing due to increasing greenhouse gases such as the carbon dioxide in the atmosphere (
 <xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">19</italic>
 </xref>).
</p>
