<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Global estimates of climate change effects on fishery biomass, harvest, and profits, while useful for understanding the broad implications of climate change and management interventions, may be insufficient for guiding policy and management decisions at the scales where governance institutions operate (typically country level). Gaines et al. find that although global fishery catches and profits can be greater in the future compared to today under moderate climate change, outcomes vary dramatically among different fisheries and regions, suggesting that fishery potential and the appropriate interventions will differ across the globe [
 <xref rid="pone.0222317.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>]. Moreover, simplifications that allow reasonable global estimates of change (e.g., dynamics driven by climate velocity, estimates at the species-level as opposed to the stock-level [
 <xref rid="pone.0222317.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0222317.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]) are unlikely to provide the level of accuracy needed for regional and local decision-making in the face of a broader range of potential climate change threats. More comprehensive analyses that are at appropriate socio-economic and governance scales and incorporate more localized climate effects that are not captured in global models will improve predictions and enable managers to more aptly respond to climate threats [
 <xref rid="pone.0222317.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0222317.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0222317.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Additionally, regional climate change predictions are particularly challenging within data-poor contexts, where there is limited information available regarding stock status and how climate change will impact fishery productivity and spatially shift stocks’ ranges. Unassessed small-scale fisheries are estimated to be in worse condition than those that are assessed, and may be more vulnerable to climate change effects due to limited governance capacity [
 <xref rid="pone.0222317.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0222317.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>].
</p>
