<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Urban air pollution is of increasing global concern as it has great impacts on the environment and public health. China has had a rapid increase in its economy over the past three decades; however, the economic boom also came at a certain cost of depleting air quality. Outdoor air pollution has become a top environmental concern in China (
 <xref rid="B1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>–
 <xref rid="B4" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>). In addition, as the use of motor vehicles has been increasing, air pollutants have shifted from those arising from conventional coal combustion to more emissions from mixed sources (
 <xref rid="B2" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>). In urban areas, emissions from residential energy combustion, transportation, and industry are the main sources of air pollution; while in rural areas, pollution most commonly originates from combustion and solid fuel (
 <xref rid="B5" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>). The burden of air pollution in China has been examined by some studies (
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>–
 <xref rid="B10" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">10</xref>). For example, the effect of air pollutants (PM
 <sub class="sub">10</sub>, ozone, nitrogen dioxide, and sulfur dioxide) per 10-μg/m
 <sup class="sup">3</sup> increases in concentration was found to be significantly correlated with risk of cardiovascular and respiratory morality in three Chinese cities (Hong Kong, Shanghai, and Wuhan) (
 <xref rid="B6" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>), a significant association between air pollution and respiratory mortality in the elderly was observed in a study of 32 Chinese cities by Zhou and colleagues (
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>), and results from China Air Pollution and Health Effects Study showed that a 10-μg/m
 <sup class="sup">3</sup> increase in 2-day moving-average PM
 <sub class="sub">10</sub> was associated with a 0.35% increase of total mortality, 0.44% increase of cardiovascular mortality, and 0.56% increase of respiratory mortality. Females, elderly, and residents with low educational attainment appeared to be more vulnerable to PM
 <sub class="sub">10</sub> exposure (
 <xref rid="B9" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">9</xref>). Findings from these studies highlighted the risk of exposure to air pollutants and human health. However, these studies had limitations of their representativeness due to a small sample size, and data from few selected cities. Furthermore, although it is known that mortality from cardiovascular disease and respiratory diseases significantly increase in winter as compared with the other seasons, limited information is available on the association between climate change and air quality, and their effect on health outcomes. A better understanding of this complex association will help health professionals and policy makers to have a better prevention strategy and approach for air quality control and public health improvement. In this study, we aimed to use large-scale data, with a better representativeness from multiple sources on air quality measures, climate factors, and health outcomes that are collected using standard study design and survey approach, and reported by the Ministry of Environmental Protection of the People’s Republic of China, China Meteorological Data Sharing Service System, and National Health Statistics Center of the People’s Republic of China (
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">11</xref>–
 <xref rid="B14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>). In the study, we had two specific aims (1) to examine the magnitude of air pollution by regions and spatial variation and its association with climatic factors and (2) to examine the association between air quality and health outcomes (assessed by total mortality) among major cities of the country. Findings from the study will not only provide update evidence on the burden of air pollution but also will add new evidence to the body of the literature on the association between air pollution and health outcomes using data from national environmental and health care surveillance systems. Given the data use from the national reports, findings from the study may serve as an important base for further studies.
</p>
