<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec11" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate Change Fatalists</div>
 <p id="Par62" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The fourth group of farmers, the ‘climate change fatalists’, express highly negative feelings about climate change, which are based on only few adverse experiences. They are not aware of effective and efficient adaptation measures, perceive the government and consumers as responsible for action and thus do not form adaptation intention. The farmers also express avoidance, mostly through fatalism.</p>
 <p id="Par63" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Farmers forming part of this group perceive a higher frequency of extreme weather events, rapid changes in weather conditions (warm/cold, dry/wet), and warmer winters. They articulate strongly negative feelings about 
  <span class="bold">changes in regional climate conditions and related impacts</span> even though they report only individual years with lower yield levels, higher pest pressure, or aggravated workflows. The climate change fatalists evaluate the future of agriculture as extraordinary difficult. However, they do not differentiate between climate change and other factors influencing future developments of their farms.
 </p>
 <p id="Par64" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The climate change fatalists 
  <span class="bold">appraise adaptation</span> negatively. They describe their farms as small in size with very low capacity to adapt. More than this, they perceive their farms as globalization victims without chances of long-term survival. The farmers are either not aware of effective adaptation measures, rate established measures as ineffective or too expensive for their farms or perceive the conversion from full- to part-time farming as sole adaptation option for their farm. Furthermore, the climate change fatalists do not perceive self-efficacy and delegate the responsibility to the government, the consumers or to a potential farm successor, as expressed in the following quote:
  <div class="disp-quote">
   <p id="Par65">“We hope to make it until we retire. For the successor – one does not know it yet. They have to know themselves what they want or in which direction, they want to develop.” (M3)</p>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par66" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The farmers of this group do not form 
  <span class="bold">adaptation intentions</span> but express 
  <span class="bold">avoidance</span>, mostly through fatalism. Risk perception combined with the negation of effective adaptation measures turns into resignation and fatalism. For instance, fatalism was expressed by a farmer who is aware of climate change-related risks and has realized that adaptation would be necessary. However, he does not intend to adapt because he is not aware of any viable adaptation measure. Additionally, he seems to be inflexible and unwilling to implement any measure to modernize or change current farming practices. Resignation and fatalism was expressed as follows.
  <div class="disp-quote">
   <p id="Par67">“What can we change?! We are in the downward spiral. That’s sad, […] we don’t know how to proceed, we don’t know how we could survive as farmers.” (S9)</p>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par68" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The 
  <span class="bold">climate change fatalists</span> can be described as conservative, they trust in habits and traditions, show poor skills in problem-solving and innovation, and feel paralyzed because of the negative development of economic, legal, and policy conditions. The climate change fatalists run specialized 
  <span class="bold">farms</span> and perceive their farms as small and experienced impacts as highly adverse. However, the size of their farms is above the Austrian average and the perceived impacts are lower than one would expect from statistical reports. This indicates the relevance of subjective realities for climate change appraisal. 
  <span class="bold">Farm succession</span> is not clear and 
  <span class="bold">regional characteristics</span> do not seem relevant for the farmers’ risk perception, adaptation intentions, and avoidance.
 </p>
 <p id="Par69" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The climate change fatalists do not refer explicitly to 
  <span class="bold">adaptation barriers</span> for their farms. However, they perceive a variety of economic, legal, and policy developments as negative for the development of the agricultural sector and their farms. For instance, they criticize the current growth paradigm, rigorous animal welfare acts, administrative barriers, concentration in the agricultural value chain, low prices of agricultural commodities, and increasing demand for industrially produced food.
 </p>
</sec>
