<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Integrative Adaptors</div>
 <p id="Par40" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The second group of farmers, the ‘integrative adaptors’, continuously adapt to changes—including changes in regional climate conditions—and intend to do so in the future. Adaptation is seen as part of a holistic lifestyle including an environmental-friendly farming practice or as a possibility to improve the resilience of the farm and take advantage of potential emerging opportunities. Some of the farmers also express avoidance, which becomes apparent through denial or religious faith.</p>
 <p id="Par41" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The integrative adaptors address 
  <span class="bold">changes in regional climate conditions</span> such as a gradual temperature increase, a slow ‘disappearance’ of transition periods between seasons, warmer winters with little snow, and more frequent or severe heavy rainfall events. However, they express uncertainty about the relationship between perceived regional climate conditions, global climate change and related impacts by referring to their own experience, which results in ambiguous expectations about future climate conditions. The integrative adaptors frame their observations and perceptions as natural climate variation and refer to human influence as additional driving factor. The following quotes illustrate the equivocal opinion of the farmers forming this group:
  <div class="disp-quote">
   <p id="Par42">“I think, climate change has always existed, as far as we know from history […]. Climate change is happening – caused by nature or, I don’t know, whoever, whatever are causes. But I think humans contribute to it, such that it has reached this speed. […]. But there has always been climate change – we know that. But which factors are related is certainly the big question.” (M10)</p>
  </div>
  <div class="disp-quote">
   <p id="Par43">“We had harsh winters in the past, and we had winters with only little [snow]. We had hot summers in the past … there were wet summers, dry summers, we had all that in the past. So, with my 60 years, I cannot evaluate if anything has changed.” (M2)</p>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par44" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">With respect to 
  <span class="bold">climate change appraisal</span>, the integrative adaptors report risks and opportunities. In terms of risks, they refer to lower yield levels in crop and grassland production, increasing weed and disease pressure, and windfalls in forests. However, farmers attribute experienced negative impacts only partly to variations in regional climate conditions and add other potential causes. For instance, the farmers perceive negative impacts of floods and soil water erosion not only as a result of more frequent or severe heavy rainfall events, but highlight more intensive maize cultivation and rising shares of building land as important causes. Weed and disease pressure are not only attributed to changes in their development cycles but are mostly seen as a consequence of organic production with limited pesticide application. The farmers also reflect on opportunities in the context of climate change. They refer to increasing temperature levels leading to a prolongation of the growing period and the grazing year for livestock.
 </p>
 <p id="Par45" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the context of 
  <span class="bold">adaptation appraisal</span>, the integrative adaptors emphasize that the application of environmental-friendly farming practices, which are adjusted to a farm’s resource base is perfectly adequate for climate change adaptation as well. In particular, the farmers refer to a focus on soil health, humus formation, cultivation of cover crops, the diversification in production activities, and organic production. These adaptation measures are evaluated positively for both, the environment and climate change adaptation. However, the farmers mention strong personal responsibility for natural resources, the environment, God’s creation, and the future generations as well as the desire for economic independence as major stimuli for action whereas climate change is perceived of limited importance. Adaptation costs are only mentioned in the context of savings resulting from circular economy.
 </p>
 <p id="Par46" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="bold">Adaptation intention</span> is expressed as continuation or expansion of environmental-friendly or organic production, which is perceived as the basis for taking advantage of new opportunities. However, the fundamental belief in the effectiveness of the chosen farming practices and production methods for climate change adaptation may lead to overconfidence and thus avoidance. Expressions of 
  <span class="bold">avoidance</span> can be interpreted as religious faith or denial (gallows humor) as illustrated by the following example:
  <div class="disp-quote">
   <p id="Par47">“We won’t be affected very much if temperature increases by two degrees or more. Unless all glaciers melt and the water comes and stays, as floodplain or as a lake for swimming. … In that case, we will build a wine tavern over there (laughs).” (M2)</p>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par48" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Perceived 
  <span class="bold">context factors</span> are summarized as personal, farm, and regional characteristics. The 
  <span class="bold">integrative adaptors</span> are characterized by their deep appreciation of nature, their high environmental awareness, and their desire for independence. This results in a high environmental or sustainability performance of 
  <span class="bold">their farms</span>. The farms are organically certified except in one case. This farmer follows the guidelines for organic production but does not want to forgo the use of chemical pesticides in extreme years. Environmental-friendly production is perceived to decrease the farm’s vulnerability to regional climate change but to increase its susceptibility to pest pressure. Full-time farming is predominant in this group but part-time farming also occurs. With respect to 
  <span class="bold">regional characteristics</span>, integrative adaptors refer to land cover, land use, and landscape patterns because of their effect on soil water erosion and nutrient emissions.
 </p>
 <p id="Par49" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The integrative adaptors do not perceive 
  <span class="bold">adaptation barriers</span> for their farms. However, they are concerned about general developments in the agricultural sector that may decrease the adaptive capacity of the farms. The farmers mention, for instance, low societal appreciation for organic production and thus low prices for agricultural commodities, inflexible regulations and high administrative burden, untargeted subsidies, highly industrialized processes along the agricultural value chain, high emissions, and exploitation of natural resources.
 </p>
</sec>
