<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p id="Par2" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Agriculture is one of the most climate-sensitive sectors and directly affected by changes in physical and chemical climate conditions. Farmers may implement climate change adaptation measures to reduce or avoid adverse developments and take advantage of emerging opportunities. Others may forbear to adapt which results in a lack of timely adaptation. Farmers’ adaptation decisions—such as other human behaviour—underlie perceptual and socio-cognitive processes that are interwoven and refer to selecting, organizing, and interpreting sensory information. Socio-cognitive processes consider that human cognition also depends on the broader socio-environmental context, which may differ by culture and geographic region and may change over time (Grothmann and Patt 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">2005</a>; Kastanakis and Voyer 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">2014</a>; Risbey et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65" href="#CR65">1999</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par3" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The relevance of perceptual and socio-cognitive processes for climate change adaptation in agriculture are underlined by the fact that farmers’ adaptation decisions take place at local level and respond to perceived socio-environmental contexts including, for instance, social and institutional support, cultural values and norms, regional characteristics, and climate-related trigger events (Grothmann and Patt 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">2005</a>; Mitter et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">2018</a>). Against this background, perceptual and socio-cognitive processes have been investigated for farmers working in different cultural contexts and geographic regions, including major farming regions in North America (e.g. Arbuckle Jr et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">2013</a>; Doll et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">2017</a>; Haden et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">2012</a>; Mase et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" href="#CR47">2017</a>; Nicholas and Durham 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59" href="#CR59">2012</a>), South America (e.g. Frank et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">2011</a>), Europe (Alcon et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">2014</a>; Otto-Banaszak et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61" href="#CR61">2011</a>; Woods et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88" href="#CR88">2017</a>), Asia (Abid et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">2015</a>; Burnham and Ma 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">2017</a>; Dang et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">2014</a>; Soriano et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR76" href="#CR76">2017</a>), Africa (Mulenga et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56" href="#CR56">2017</a>), and Australia and New Zealand (Niles et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">2016</a>; Sanderson and Curtis 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" href="#CR70">2016</a>). The empirical results support the necessity to investigate and evaluate these processes within particular cultural and geographic contexts. For instance, Sanderson and Curtis 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70" href="#CR70">2016</a> show that cultural factors influence farmers’ climate change risk perception, which inform their adaptation decisions. Such detailed analyses for specific cultures and regions also contribute to expand and extend the knowledge on climate change adaptation in agriculture and establish the basis for subsequent integrative research.
 </p>
 <p id="Par4" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In our research, we focus on Austrian farmers because of three reasons. First, climate change impacts may threaten Austrian farmers differently than their peers in other agro-environmental zones because climate change projections for the alpine region are particularly uncertain. Such uncertainties can decrease farmers’ intentions to adapt (Spence et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77" href="#CR77">2012</a>) and are mostly due to Austria’s location in a transition zone between rising winter precipitation in northern and declining summer precipitation in southern Europe (Gobiet et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">2014</a>; Haslinger et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">2016</a>; Heinrich et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">2013</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par5" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Second, Austrian agriculture is highly diverse and provides multiple services such as high quality food, fodder, fiber and bioenergy, soil and water quality regulation, carbon sequestration, and landscape esthetics. These multiple services are of relevance for other economic sectors such as energy, water, and tourism indicating potential cross-sectoral impacts of climate change adaptation in agriculture.</p>
 <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Third, scientific knowledge on farmers’ perspectives on climate change adaptation is limited to a small region and selected adaptation measures (Pröbstl-Haider et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" href="#CR64">2016</a>). It lacks on a profound understanding of Austrian farmers’ climate change and adaptation appraisal even though it has been argued that such information could be useful to inform adaptation engagement strategies, outreach efforts, and the design of agricultural and climate policies (Arbuckle et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">2014</a>). Even more, practitioners working in agricultural and environmental organizations, i.e. agricultural knowledge brokers, perceive that Austrian farmers’ adaptation efforts are limited and climate change-related challenges and chances are not fully addressed in different Austrian farming regions (Mitter et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">2018</a>). The farmers’ lack in timely adaptation is evident even though selected adaptation measures have been identified effective for particular farming regions (Kirchner et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">2015</a>; Mitter et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">2015</a>; Schönhart et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR73" href="#CR73">2014</a>), and collaboration between scientists and agricultural stakeholders has been intensified in the context of climate change adaptation (see e.g. Mitter et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">2014</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We aim to explore perceptual and socio-cognitive processes influencing Austrian farmers’ climate change and adaptation appraisal, which are expected to create either agricultural adaptation or avoidance. In our analysis, we consider both response strategies, while previous studies have focused on adaptation intention and mostly ignored avoidance (except for Kuruppu and Liverman 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">2011</a>). In particular, we investigate how farmers’ adaptation intentions and avoidance are formed by considering the following research questions: (i) How do Austrian farmers perceive and appraise climate change? (ii) To what extent are Austrian farmers aware of climate change adaptation measures and how do they appraise their scope of applicability? (iii) How do Austrian farmers’ adaptation intentions develop and how do socio-environmental context factors matter?
 </p>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Despite purposeful selection of farming regions is standard for this type of research (Woods et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR88" href="#CR88">2017</a>), it also means that the research results for Austrian farmers are of limited transferability to other cultural contexts and geographic regions. However, the results may be partially translated to farming regions that share similar cultural values and norms and are located in comparable agro-environmental zones, i.e. continental and alpine south as reported in Metzger et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">2005</a>. Accordingly, we may expect similar response strategies to climate change, i.e. adaptation intention or avoidance, in several farming regions in Central and Eastern Europe, where investigations on farmers’ climate change perceptions and adaptation intentions are limited.
 </p>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The article is structured as follows. First, we provide a review on theories relevant for analyzing perceptual and socio-cognitive processes in agricultural adaptation. Then, we summarize data collection and analysis, and present empirical findings with respect to climate change and adaptation appraisal, agricultural adaptation intention, and avoidance. Finally, we discuss our empirical findings and draw conclusions.</p>
</sec>
