<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec14" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Formation of Adaption Appraisal</div>
 <p id="Par74" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Adaptation appraisal consists of farmers’ perceptions of adaptation efficacy, self-efficacy, and adaptation costs. With regard to adaptation efficacy, the climate change adaptors, the integrative adaptors and the cost-benefit calculators know a bandwidth of effective climate change adaptation measures and have already implemented several of them on their farms. The climate change fatalists are not aware of adaptation measures and have not implemented any on their farms. While climate change adaptors try to balance a broad mix of adaptation measures, integrative adaptors focus on environmental-friendly farming practices adjusted to a farm’s resource base, which they assess to be adequate for climate change adaptation as well. Cost-benefit calculators are continuously taking adaptation measures that bring about slight or moderate changes on their farms. They are also aware of effective adaptation measures that may change the farms’ characteristics or strategic orientation but consider related benefits too low, compared to the costs. These results are in line with previous empirical analyses, which have revealed that preferred adaptation measures differ between groups of farmers sharing, for instance, climate change belief, attitudes, value systems, and perceived risks (Barnes and Toma 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">2012</a>; Hyland et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">2016</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par75" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Perceived self-efficacy and the capacity to respond to climate change-related challenges has received growing attention in the empirical literature suggesting its relevance in the agricultural context (e.g. Arbuckle et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">2014</a>; Duinen et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">2014</a>). In our empirical data, self-efficacy is expressed as the farmers’ sense of personal responsibility for their farms and their perceived capability to act. Except for the climate change fatalists, the farmers show high levels of self-efficacy paired with a high flexibility to respond to changes. While the climate change adaptors and the cost-benefit calculators additionally show a high level of knowledge on climate change, related impacts and potential adaptation measures, perceived self-efficacy of the integrative adaptors is embedded into an environmental-friendly value system. Furthermore, it is notable that farmers belonging to the group of climate change adaptors report personal political engagement in order to increase peoples’ climate change awareness and to evoke adaptation beyond their farms.
 </p>
 <p id="Par76" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The four groups of farmers address adaptation costs differently. While the climate change adaptors consciously accept high costs for successful adaptation, the integrative adaptors emphasize potential savings from measures that yield benefits for both the environmental and adaptation performance of their farms, and the climate change fatalists appraise costs for adaptation measures as too high. The cost-benefit calculators balance expected benefits against adaptation costs, and highlight adaptation costs as major determining factor for implementing long-term adaptation measures. Park et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR62" href="#CR62">2012</a> have come to a similar conclusion showing that adaptation costs are particularly decisive for long-term, transformative adaptation.
 </p>
</sec>
