<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Theoretical Model for the Empirical Analysis</div>
 <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We have chosen the theoretical MPPACC as heuristic for our empirical research, because it is well suited for structuring farmers’ narratives and analyzing farmers’ climate change and adaptation appraisal as well as their effects on adaptation intention and avoidance including socio-environmental context factors. Building on MPPACC, we empirically examine farmers’ individual perceptions towards climate change and adaptation and consider how socio-environmental context factors affect adaptation intention (see Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). We assume that an individual has to perceive and evaluate a certain risk or opportunity in a first step (climate change appraisal), and evaluate his or her subjective capability to deal with this risk or opportunity in a second step (adaptation appraisal). While MPPACC is limited to risks and explicitly excludes opportunities (Grothmann and Patt 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">2005</a>), we consider both risks and opportunities following the commonly accepted definition of climate change adaptation (IPCC 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">2014</a>). Adaptation appraisal consists of three sub-components, i.e. ‘perceived adaptation efficacy’, ‘perceived self-efficacy’, and ‘perceived adaptation costs’, which are closely related and thus added up.
 </p>
 <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Depending on the outcome of the two steps, we consider two socio-cognitive pathways an individual may follow to deal with climate change, i.e. agricultural adaptation intention or avoidance. Agricultural adaptation refers to measures that prevent physical or monetary damage or provide new opportunities, whereas avoidance relates to reactions such as ‘wishful thinking’, ‘denial’, ‘religious faith’, and ‘fatalism’ that typically prevent negative emotional consequences of perceived risks and expected impacts. Climate change appraisal (including risk and opportunity appraisal) and adaptation appraisal (including perceived adaptation efficacy, self-efficacy, and adaptation costs) are assumed to be positively related to adaptation intention (as indicated by the ‘+’ sign in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>). Risk appraisal is assumed to be positively (+) and adaptation appraisal is assumed to be negatively related (−) to avoidance indicating that an individual would respond with ‘avoidance’ if he or she appraises climate change as a risk but is not aware of adaptation measures that are effective, practicable and efficient.
 </p>
 <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">According to MPPACC, adaptation intention is the necessary prerequisite for actual adoption of adaptation measures, while avoidance is discerned as a barrier to adaptation (Grothmann and Patt 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">2005</a>). Additionally and similar to MPPACC, socio-environmental context factors such as farmers’ personal characteristics, farm characteristics including farm succession, regional characteristics, adaptation barriers as well as an individual’s perception thereof are considered. With respect to farmers’ personal characteristics, we follow the classification by Schmitzberger et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71" href="#CR71">2005</a> and consider farmers’ state of knowledge, their age as well as their attitude towards agriculture and the environment. Farm characteristics include farm size, farm type, cultivation system, major production activities, and future perspectives (i.e. farm succession). Criteria related to regional characteristics comprise freshwater availability as well as land cover, land use, and landscape patterns.
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Theoretical model for analyzing farmers’ individual perceptions and cognition towards climate change and adaptation based on the MPPACC by Grothmann and Patt 
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">2005</a>
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="267_2019_1158_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e520" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
