<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Species distribution models (SDMs) are used to guide conservation programs in anticipation of future climate change effects on species [
 <xref rid="pone.0172107.ref003" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">3</xref>]. SDMs capture relationships between a species (occurrence) and its environment. However, some authors recognize that the incomplete coverage of the environmental niche of species is one of the important sources of error when forecasting distributions under climate change, because it does not cover completely the spatial distribution range of species [
 <xref rid="pone.0172107.ref004" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">4</xref>], and/or only consider climatic variables as predictors [
 <xref rid="pone.0172107.ref005" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>]. In addition, forecasts of species distribution under climate change entail an inherent uncertainty such as residual error of models, modeling algorithm and climate scenarios selected [
 <xref rid="pone.0172107.ref006" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>]. Different solutions have been proposed for solving these issues. For example, Gallien et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0172107.ref007" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>] provide a methodological framework where the use of predictions based on a global model to weight pseudo-absences in a regional model significantly improved the predictive performance of regional SDMs. Wenger et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0172107.ref006" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">6</xref>] suggested a Monte Carlo approach that accounts for uncertainty within generalized linear regression models. Finally, the incorporation of other environmental variables (different than climate ones), e.g., land use or ecosystem functioning descriptors such as ecosystem production and seasonality, would improve the reliability of the predictions [
 <xref rid="pone.0172107.ref005" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">5</xref>,
 <xref rid="pone.0172107.ref008" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>]. However, we suggest that it is also necessary to incorporate the uncertainty derived of the future values of projected environmental variables. With this aim, we have developed a remote-sensing based approach.
</p>
