<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Functional attributes derived from VIs are usually expressed as average temporal summaries, such as the annual mean (i.e., surrogate of mean annual primary production) or the seasonal coefficient of variation (i.e., indicator of seasonality or temporal variation within the year) [
 <xref rid="pone.0172107.ref012" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. Of particular note are spectral Vegetation Indices (VIs), such as the Normalized Difference Vegetation Index (NDVI) and the Enhanced Vegetation Index (EVI). Both of these VIs are directly related with the fraction of photosynthetically active radiation (fAPAR) intercepted by green vegetation [
 <xref rid="pone.0172107.ref013" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>]. This relationship allows the derivation of regional maps of primary production from radiation use efficiency values [
 <xref rid="pone.0172107.ref014" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">14</xref>]. Landscape functional heterogeneity has also been suggested as a significant driver of species [
 <xref rid="pone.0172107.ref015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>] and ecosystem diversity [
 <xref rid="pone.0172107.ref012" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>], particularly in the Mediterranean Region. Many animal species have proved to be especially sensitive to spatial heterogeneity [
 <xref rid="pone.0172107.ref016" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. Recent findings suggest that this sensitivity is related more to functional heterogeneity than to structural heterogeneity [
 <xref rid="pone.0172107.ref017" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>]. For instance, Requena-Mullor et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0172107.ref008" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>] found modeled spatial distribution of the European badger (
 <italic class="italic">Meles meles</italic> L.) in SE Spain was significantly improved when augmenting climate variables with EVI-derived functional attributes, (esp. the spatial variability of EVI) rather than land cover and land use variables.
</p>
