<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Although the sensitivity of our results to key assumptions on the implementation of geoengineering technologies (and to effective abatement and damage costs) should make us cautious about translating our quantitative results into decision-making process, this sensitivity can be used to help determine where we should invest in learning and gathering information. However, beyond our quantitative conclusions, our approach may contribute not only towards mapping out all possible options and all possible future trajectories but also towards investigating a wider set of views for designing climate policies for supporting both CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> emission reduction and the development of breakthrough geoengineering technologies in order to keep the planet within the safe operating space. 
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="t1" class="xref">Table 1</xref> summarizes the different windows of opportunity for each of the two planetary boundaries and highlights how they narrow over time. Although emission reduction efforts need to increase as climate policy is delayed, the main result identifies the requirement for carbon neutrality in 2090 (at the latest) for staying under 550 ppm. This objective is consistent with the Paris agreement whose objective is to achieve carbon neutrality during the second half of the 21
 <sup class="sup">st</sup> century. With the recent ratification by the European Union, the Paris agreement enters into effect, making this objective of staying under 550 ppm credible. Recovering the safe planetary boundary of 350 ppm in 2100, on the other hand, requires such efforts in terms of CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> emissions reduction that this is not a credible target if based only on the reduction of CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> emissions. For bouncing back to 350 ppm in 2100, our results emphasize the urgency of the situation and the need to: (1) not delay efficient policies for navigating away from the baseline scenario; and (2) develop and implement geoengineering technologies enabling not only carbon neutrality, but 10% negative emissions before 2060. Reaching this objective of 10% of negative emissions requires the development of new strategies based on innovative geoengineering technologies that can be effective in the short term
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b44" class="xref">44</xref>. Whereas solar radiation management (SRM) may provide a very short-term solution for low cost cooling of the atmosphere, this technology may have a limited effect on ocean acidification
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b45" class="xref">45</xref> and may lead to major political conflicts
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b39" class="xref">39</xref>. Carbon capture and storage (CSS)
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b46" class="xref">46</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b47" class="xref">47</xref> or carbon dioxide removal (CDR)
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b48" class="xref">48</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b49" class="xref">49</xref> technologies may decrease atmospheric CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> concentration by sequestering current CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> from the atmosphere
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b50" class="xref">50</xref> but these technologies are expensive and are not effective today at the global scale. Moreover, even though CSS and CRD (and also SRM) are promising, we stress that geoengineering measures should not be considered as equivalent to CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> emission reduction
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b51" class="xref">51</xref> or as a political panacea that may delay efforts for reducing CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> emissions
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b52" class="xref">52</xref>. Besides, a break in the growth of CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> emissions is immediately required for facing climate challenge, and ocean acidification
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b53" class="xref">53</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b54" class="xref">54</xref>. Finally, because planetary boundaries are entangled in complex ways it is necessary to consider interactions among planetary boundaries, e.g. biodiversity or phosphorous and nitrogen concentrations, in order to capture all the complexity of the dynamics of the planetary boundaries that cannot be reduced to those of climate change. Beyond these specific results we present here, it is necessary to derive adaptive indicators—such as those we propose in 
 <xref ref-type="table" rid="t1" class="xref">Table 1</xref>—in order to fulfill the need for monitoring for facilitating the design of climate policy
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b55" class="xref">55</xref> and to face social and political uncertainties inherent to climate decision process. These indicators have to be dynamical and adaptive by using pathway-based targets instead of single point targets at a given time, the latter being meaningless in case of social or political delays.
</p>
