<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The majority of studies on climate change impacts on biodiversity have focused on direct effects of climate change, that is effects of changes in temperature and precipitation on biodiversity. Fewer works have also investigated indirect effects, such as the effect of climate‐mediated changes in forest structure and composition on species presence and abundance (e.g. De Frenne 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="jpe12644-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>). While forest structure and composition generally respond slowly to environmental changes, they can be altered quickly and profoundly by disturbances, that is pulses of tree mortality caused by agents such as bark beetles, fire and wind. Disturbances are climate sensitive and have already intensified during the last decades (Seidl, Schelhaas &amp; Lexer 
 <xref rid="jpe12644-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>). A further intensification of disturbance regimes in response to ongoing climatic changes is likely (Seidl 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="jpe12644-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>; Millar &amp; Stephenson 
 <xref rid="jpe12644-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). While often regarded as undesirable ‘calamities’ in forest management, the resulting increases in biodiversity (e.g. indicated by the number of species) generally reveal a positive impact of disturbances on biodiversity (Müller 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>. 
 <xref rid="jpe12644-bib-0030" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>; Thom &amp; Seidl 
 <xref rid="jpe12644-bib-0043" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). However, the net effect of changing climate and disturbance regimes on forest biodiversity remains unclear: will intensifying disturbance regimes offset the predicted negative direct effects of climate change on biodiversity? Or will increasing climate and disturbance change threaten the ecological resilience of ecosystems and consequently the habitat quality of forest‐dependent species?
</p>
