<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data pre-processing</div>
 <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A 3-month running mean is taken of all monthly (but not daily) datasets for the period 1970–2016 (1970–2010 for ocean data). N3.4 is the running 3-month mean Niño-3.4 SST anomalies (5°N−5°S, 120°W−170°W). El Niño and La Niña events are selected by a standard used by NOAA (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ggweather.com/enso/oni.htm" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://ggweather.com/enso/oni.htm</span>). Generally, El Niño (La Niña) events are defined as when N3.4 in five consecutive overlapping 3-month periods is at or above (below) the +0.5 °C (–0.5 °C) anomaly. The El Niño (La Niña) developing year is defined as the year (January−December) that El Niño (La Niña) develops from weak to strong, and the El Niño (La Niña) decaying year is defined when El Niño (La Niña) decays from strong to weak. Above-moderate El Niño (La Niña) events (including moderate events) are defined as when five consecutive overlapping 3-month periods are at or above (below) the 1 °C (–1 °C) SST anomaly and the largest N3.4 index value occurs from October to January. Since 1970, 9 El Niño events (1972−1973, 1982−1983, 1986−1987, 1991−1992, 1994−1995, 1997−1998, 2002−2003, 2009−2010 and 2015−2016) and 10 La Niña events (1970−1971, 1973−1974, 1975−1976, 1988−1989, 1995−1996, 1998−1999, 1999−2000, 2007−2008, 2010−2011 and 2011−2012) meet the above criteria, and in this work, unless otherwise specified, El Niño developing years are the developing years of these nine El Niño events. To increase the reliability of our results, monthly composite and regression analyses are employed in this study. The Walker index = 
  <span class="italic">U</span>
  <sub>200</sub> − 
  <span class="italic">U</span>
  <sub>850</sub>, where 
  <span class="italic">U</span>
  <sub>200</sub> and 
  <span class="italic">U</span>
  <sub>850</sub> are the mean (5°S−5°N, 120°W−120°E) zonal wind anomalies at the 200- and 850-hPa levels, respectively.
 </p>
</sec>
