<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Interannual climatic effect of the WNP ACE on El Niño</div>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">On interannual timescale, at 850 hPa (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3d</a>), WNP TCs can lead to anomalous westerlies over 0°–10°N in the tropical western–central Pacific. This might result from tropical semi-geostrophic adjustment processes (see Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">6a</a>), as more intense WNP TCs lead to a broad area of low pressure in the WNP, and the centre of significant zonal wind anomalies is located south of the selected ACE region (this centre is consistent with the main effect of the mean WNP TC genesis position at 12.07°N, 155.36°E). The anomalous westerlies increase the Niño-3.4 SST anomalies. At 200 hPa (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3e</a>), anomalous easterlies resulting from TCs occur from 10°N to 10°S, which do not seem to conform to the ACE locations. The main reason for this is a Hadley-like circulation (20°N−20°S, 135°−170°E) enhanced by the TCs (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3f</a>) on the basis of tropical semi-geostrophic adjustment processes at 200 hPa (see Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">6b</a>). Anomalous northerlies south of the equator enhance the symmetry of the wind field in the upper troposphere with respect to the equator (see Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">6c</a>), intensifying the anomalous upper easterlies over the tropical Pacific. Both the direct effect of asymmetrical anomalous westerlies at lower levels and the indirect effect of the Hadley-like circulation weaken the Walker circulation (5°N−5°S, 120°E−120°W; the Walker index changes from –5.47 to –3.84 m s
  <span class="sup">−1</span>; see Methods) over the equatorial region in J–A–S, further enhancing the equatorial Pacific eastward-flowing currents (see Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">6d</a>), and thereby increasing the Niño-3.4 SST anomalies. The eastward-flowing currents are located north of the equator in J–A–S, which is consistent with lower-level anomalous westerlies. The ACE leads the lower-level westerlies (Walker circulation) in the tropical western–central Pacific by 2 (3) months regardless of whether the proceeding westerlies (Walker circulation) or their simultaneous signals are removed (see Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">7</a>). This lead–lag correlation between the ACE and circulation is in accordance with that between the ACE and N3.4 (see Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2</a>). Through the effect on the Walker circulation, the Niño-3.4 SST anomalies associated with TCs are strongest after 3 months.
 </p>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The evolution of the horizontal wind anomalies is also examined (see Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">8a−c</a>). Compared with the situation in J–A–S, the significant anomalous westerlies related to TCs at 850 hPa shift eastward and become symmetric about the equator in O–N–D, and are accompanied by a significantly weakened Walker circulation. At the upper tropospheric level, the centre of significant anomalous easterlies also shifts eastward. All these effects enhance the eastward-flowing currents, and the centre of the eastward-flowing currents shifts equatorward in O–N–D (see Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">8d</a>), and the Niño-3.4 SST anomalies significantly increase.
 </p>
 <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another possible mechanism is the change in thermocline depth associated with WNP TCs. In J–A–S, TCs can shallow the tropical western Pacific thermocline (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4a</a>). Agreeing with theory, the observed thermocline is shallowed via Ekman pumping associated with the downdrafts over 0°−10°S. However, there are updrafts over 5°−10°N, so theoretically the thermocline in these latitudes should deepen, contrary to what is actually found. One possible reason for this discrepancy is that wind forcing related to TCs excites or amplifies Kelvin waves, further affecting tropical thermocline adjustments
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
  </span>. Another is TC turbulent mixing processes, in which strong surface TC winds cool the surface and warm the subsurface waters
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>
  </span>. This vertical mixing might have a thermodynamic effect on wave formation. Warm water in the tropical western Pacific is carried eastward, in association with enhanced eastward-propagating equatorial Kelvin waves, further deepening the tropical eastern Pacific thermocline and thereby reducing the equatorial Pacific zonal thermocline gradient (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4c</a>). Due to the weakened Walker circulation, the thermocline at 5°S−15°N in the tropical western Pacific is shallower and flatter in O–N–D than in J–A–S, and the equatorial Pacific zonal thermocline gradient becomes smaller (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4b, d</a>), as the Niño-3.4 SST anomalies become stronger. To further investigate the ocean-process effects of WNP ACE on El Niño, the depth–zonal distribution of monthly equatorial potential temperature anomalies averaged between 5°S−5°N during the El Niño developing year is shown in Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">9</a>. At the beginning of the year, the positive potential temperature anomalies begin to emerge in the western Pacific and then propagate eastward along the main thermocline and accumulate in the equatorial eastern Pacific. From June, the negative potential temperature anomalies grow in the western Pacific because of the eastward transport of warm surface water and upward compensation by cold water, which further enhances positive potential temperature anomalies in the equatorial eastern Pacific by transporting warm surface water. After removing the simultaneous TC signals (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5a</a>), this change in the potential temperature anomalies decreases, and can even disappear, particularly during the WNP TC season (May–October; Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5b</a>). In addition, when the proceeding ACE signal is removed, the potential temperature anomalies also decrease, and can even disappear, particularly in the 3 months after the TC season (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">10</a>). All the studied observations indicate that WNP TCs can enhance the transport of warm water from the equatorial western-to-eastern Pacific, thus increasing the Niño-3.4 SST anomalies.
  <div id="Fig4" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Thermocline (20°C isotherm depth, m) during El Niño developing years (1970–2010). 
     <span class="bold">a</span> Meridional distribution (along 135°–170°E) in J–A–S. 
     <span class="bold">b</span> As in 
     <span class="bold">a</span>, but for O–N–D. 
     <span class="bold">c</span>, Zonal distribution (along 5°S–5°N) in J–A–S. 
     <span class="bold">d</span> As in 
     <span class="bold">c</span>, but for O–N–D. The blue dashed line indicates the original thermocline; the red line associated with the preceding WNP ACE signal in J–A–S, and the thicker line indicates significance above the 95% confidence level. An El Niño developing year is defined when the above-moderate El Niño events (including moderate events) develops from weak to strong
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2019_11720_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e823" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <div id="Fig5" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 5</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Composite of the depth–zonal distribution of monthly equatorial potential temperature anomalies averaged between 5°S−5°N (shading; °C) during the El Niño developing years (2004−2016). 
     <span class="bold">a</span> Distribution of monthly equatorial potential temperature anomalies after removing the simultaneous WNP ACE. 
     <span class="bold">b</span> As in 
     <span class="bold">a</span>, but relating to the simultaneous WNP ACE. An El Niño developing year is defined when the above-moderate El Niño events (including moderate events) develops from weak to strong
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2019_11720_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e841" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
