<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec004" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec id="sec005" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study area and environmental setting</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Scotian Shelf (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0205505.g002" href="#pone.0205505.g002">Fig 2</a>) is a wide (up to ~200 km) and long (~700 km) continental margin off Nova Scotia, Canada that is characterized by a number of banks, deep basins, channels, and submarine canyons. It is separated from the Grand Banks in the east by the Laurentian Channel, and from the Gulf of Maine by the Northeast and Fundian Channels in the west. On the central Scotian Shelf lies an area commonly referred to as the ‘Scotian Gulf’, an inlet formed by a cross-shelf channel situated between Emerald and LaHave Banks which opens up into the LaHave and Emerald Basins on the inner shelf (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0205505.g002" href="#pone.0205505.g002">Fig 2</a>). Emerald Basin is composed of two basins. The main part (main basin) is 50 km wide, 100 km long, and nearly 300 m deep at its deepest point. The northern part (northern basin) is 10 km wide, 50 km long, and 230 m deep.
  </p>
  <div id="pone.0205505.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0205505.g002</span>
   <span class="label">Fig 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <div class="title">Distribution of 
     <span class="italic">V</span>. 
     <span class="italic">pourtalesi</span> on the Scotian Shelf and Gulf of Maine off Nova Scotia, Canada.
    </div>
    <p>Data are from the DFO multispecies trawl survey (yellow circles; 2007–2017), DFO benthic science surveys (blue circles; 2001–2017), and commercial bycatch records from the Fisheries Observer Program (red circles; 1997–2007, 2010–2015). Green circles are absence of 
     <span class="italic">V</span>. 
     <span class="italic">pourtalesi</span> from the DFO multispecies trawl survey. The 200-m contour defining Emerald and LaHave Basins is outlined in dark grey. Study area (black outline) is based on DFO’s Maritimes Region administrative boundary clipped to the 2000-m contour. NEC = Northeast Channel.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="pone.0205505.g002" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Scotian Shelf lies at a confluence of two large ocean gyre currents: the subpolar Labrador Current and subtropical Gulf Stream [
   <a rid="pone.0205505.ref053" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref053">53</a>]. The inner shelf is dominated by outflow from the Gulf of St. Lawrence and Labrador Current through Cabot Strait, which bifurcates to feed the Nova Scotia Current that moves westward along the inner shelf and a shelf-edge flow that moves along the western side of the Laurentian Channel and outer shelf [
   <a rid="pone.0205505.ref053" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref053">53</a>]. On the outer shelf the Labrador Current has a more direct influence through flow across the Laurentian Channel from the southern Newfoundland Shelf. Offshore, warm North Atlantic Central Water sits below the cold shelf-edge flow and the warm and cold water masses variously mix to create a region of slope water with identifiable Labrador Slope Water (4–9°C) and Warm Slope Water (9–12°C) signatures [
   <a rid="pone.0205505.ref054" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref054">54</a>]. This warm slope water moves onshore to fill the inner basins of the Scotian Shelf and the Gulf of Maine in the west. Intermittent incursions of Warm Slope Water through the Scotian Gulf result in relatively warm waters in the basins year round compared to the surrounding shelf, with temperatures typically in the range of ~8–10°C below ~100 m depth. The Warm Slope Water entering the basins is not only typically warmer and more saline, but similar to areas of upwelling at the shelf-break front it is also nutrient-rich relative to shelf water [
   <a rid="pone.0205505.ref055" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref055">55</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Emerald and LaHave Basins are also under the intermittent influence of two cold-water currents. The Nova Scotia Current is centred at about 150 m depth and flows over the northern part of Emerald Basin and bends southward to fill LaHave Basin. In addition, an onshore meander of the shelf-edge current flows northward over Western and Emerald Bank to join a weak anti-cyclonic gyre that flows around the inner-shelf basins [
   <a rid="pone.0205505.ref056" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref056">56</a>]. Additionally, Emerald Basin is subjected to high tidal variability and mixing compared to other areas on the shelf [
   <a rid="pone.0205505.ref052" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref052">52</a>]. The possible influence of this tidal mixing on the retention of particles and food in the basins has not been fully described. Azetsu-Scott and colleagues [
   <a rid="pone.0205505.ref057" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref057">57</a>] described the presence of intermittent, intermediate nepheloid layers (i.e. layers of water that contains high amounts of suspended sediment) 10–30 m thick between 140 and 210 m depth in the main basin of Emerald Basin, approximately 90 m above the sea bed. Such nepheloid layers are often caused by biological patchiness in the water column, intrusion of turbid water, turbulence caused by bottom current stress, and/or by internal waves [
   <a rid="pone.0205505.ref057" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref057">57</a>]. Azetsu-Scott and colleagues [
   <a rid="pone.0205505.ref057" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref057">57</a>] suggested that these intermediate layers were caused by resuspension of particles by internal tides along the saddle between Emerald and LaHave Banks, and further transport by variable flows and the mean circulation of the Scotian Gulf. Resuspension by intrusion of slope water was thought to be important during the winter months when strong eastward winds and upwelling events cause strong, onshore flow and significant flushing of Emerald Basin [
   <a rid="pone.0205505.ref050" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref050">50</a>]. This flushing is the likely cause of the disproportionate amount of the organic matter derived from marine, versus terrestrial sources, in Emerald Basin compared to other areas of the shelf [
   <a rid="pone.0205505.ref058" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref058">58</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The surficial geology and sediment stratigraphy of Emerald Basin and the Scotian Shelf has been well described based on acoustic techniques and bottom samples [
   <a rid="pone.0205505.ref059" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref059">59</a>–
   <a rid="pone.0205505.ref061" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref061">61</a>], from which broad-scale categorical maps have been generated [
   <a rid="pone.0205505.ref059" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref059">59</a>]. Generally, the Scotian Shelf is comprised of five sediment formations (Scotian Shelf Drift, Sambro Sand, Emerald Silt, LaHave Clay, and Sable Island Sand and Gravel) that occur as an approximately 50 m-thick surficial succession over the bedrock [
   <a rid="pone.0205505.ref060" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref060">60</a>,
   <a rid="pone.0205505.ref062" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref062">62</a>]. Emerald Basin is overlain by Scotian Shelf Drift (i.e., glacial till), a hard substrate of variable size distribution that occurs in patches over a soft-sediment matrix. Based on 
   <span class="italic">in situ</span> observations and physical collections, the presence of this hard substrate is crucial to the settlement of 
   <span class="italic">V</span>. 
   <span class="italic">pourtalesi</span>, which has been found attached to small pebbles dispersed over soft sediment up to boulder-sized substrate. In the Northeast Channel, 
   <span class="italic">V</span>. 
   <span class="italic">pourtalesi</span> is found on large rocks and boulders down to nearly 500 m depth where it co-occurs with large branching corals 
   <span class="italic">Primnoa resedaeformis</span> and 
   <span class="italic">Paragorgia arborea</span> [
   <a rid="pone.0205505.ref063" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref063">63</a>].
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec006" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Spatial extent of study area</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The study area used for data extraction and modelling (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0205505.g002" href="#pone.0205505.g002">Fig 2</a>) was adapted from the boundary of DFO’s Maritimes Region, one of DFO’s six administrative regions across Canada. This area encompasses the entire Scotian Shelf and is delimited by the 200 nautical mile Exclusive Economic Zone in the south, the Canadian Maritime Boundary to the west in the Gulf of Maine, and DFO’s Newfoundland and Labrador Region’s Placentia Bay–Grand Bank Large Ocean Management Area (LOMA) in the east. The boundary was clipped to the 2000 m isobath, as the deepest known record of 
   <span class="italic">V</span>. 
   <span class="italic">pourtalesi</span> was found &lt; 1000 m depth (845 m off the Azores; [
   <a rid="pone.0205505.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref037">37</a>]), the training data for the current model are &lt;1850 m depth, and previous modelling applications of this species indicated that areas below 2000 m are considered extrapolated [
   <a rid="pone.0205505.ref047" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref047">47</a>]. A 5 km buffer was placed around all land points to avoid their inclusion in the model.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec007" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">Vazella pourtalesi</span> response data
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">V</span>. 
   <span class="italic">pourtalesi</span> presence and absence data (
   <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0205505.g002" href="#pone.0205505.g002">Fig 2</a> and 
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0205505.s001" href="#pone.0205505.s001">S1 Table</a> in supplementary material) were obtained from several different sources: DFO’s multispecies trawl survey conducted in the Maritimes Region between 2007 to 2017 (presences and absences), DFO optical (in-house camera/video and remotely operated vehicle) benthic surveys conducted between 2001 and 2017 (presences only), and commercial bycatch records from the Fisheries Observer Program (FOP) from 1997 to 2007, and 2010 to 2015 (presences only). The DFO multispecies trawl survey is stratified random (by depth) and conducted using primarily Western IIA trawl gear. The average distance of these tows is ~ 3.17 km. Absence records were created from null (zero) catches that occurred in the same surveys. Commercial bycatch data between 1997 to 2007 from the Fisheries Observer Program was further post-processed and validated for accuracy (see [
   <a rid="pone.0205505.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref035">35</a>] for more details), while the data from 2010 to 2015 was extracted directly from the Maritimes Fishery Science Database managed by DFO. Commercial trawls are much longer in duration and may follow bottom contours and/or retrace their footprint through the course of a 10+ km tow. For both the DFO multispecies trawl survey and FOP data, start coordinates were used to represent the tow, whereas for the DFO benthic imagery survey data the actual location of the 
   <span class="italic">V</span>. 
   <span class="italic">pourtalesi</span> record 
   <span class="italic">in situ</span> was used. A 1 x 1 km grid matching that of the environmental data was placed over the study area and the presence-absence data were reduced to one record per cell, with a presence taking precedence over an absence if both occurred in the same cell. This gave a total of 215 presences (102 from the DFO trawl surveys, 47 from DFO benthic science surveys, and 66 from the FOP) and 2867 absences for the model.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The inclusion of response data with different rates of detection or "catchability", spatial bias, and spatial resolution may introduce bias in species distribution models. For instance, the optical surveys used in this study were targeted towards areas of interest (i.e., areas of known sponge distribution), have a high rate of detection, low spatial coverage and high resolution, compared to the RV trawl survey and commercial bycatch data which aggregate the catch across larger areas (i.e., ~3 km and ~10+ km, respectively). Use of null data from the research vessel survey only will introduce another form of bias in terms of false negatives due to poor catchability, but as the absence data dominate the records and are generated from a random stratified survey, we consider any such biases to be negligible compared to those of the presence data. Ideally, models would be conducted with a single data type with random stratification across the study area (i.e. in this instance, using only those records from the RV trawl surveys). Given the scarcity of presences in the trawl survey data and differing spatial coverage from the optical surveys and commercial data, we chose to accept the biases incurred from combining all three datasets. We note however that the resulting predictive surfaces may be driven by such biases, particularly towards areas of aggregation of the optical survey and commercial bycatch data, which are not accompanied by absences records. Similarly, we caution against over-interpreting the boundaries of suitable and unsuitable habitat predicted by the model as a result of this spatial bias.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec008" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ethics statement</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study utilized data on the invertebrate sponge 
   <span class="italic">V</span>. 
   <span class="italic">pourtalesi</span> collected by other research programs or data sources. From those studies, data collected using optical techniques were non-destructive, while data collected by commercial and research trawls involved bringing the sponges on deck where they would have been exposed to air and died. Generally dead sponges collected in the trawls were returned to the sea near the point of sampling. Samples collected by others during the research vessel multispecies surveys conducted by Fisheries and Oceans Canada were done so with authorization to engage in fishing and related activities on the Atlantic coast of Canada subject to the provisions of the Fisheries Act and Regulations bestowed by the Regional Director of Science, Science Branch, Fisheries and Oceans Canada, Maritimes Region, Dartmouth, Nova Scotia, Canada. The field studies did not involve endangered or protected species.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec009" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Environmental data</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A total of 63 environmental data layers were considered as predictor variables in the random forest model. These variables are considered to represent current climate conditions (maximum temporal range is 1990 to 2015) and were derived from various data sources and native spatial resolutions. Variables were chosen based on their availability and assumed relevance to the distribution of 
   <span class="italic">V</span>. 
   <span class="italic">pourtalesi</span>. Biochemical variables such as oxygen, silicate, nitrate, and phosphate, some of which were used to model the glass sponge 
   <span class="italic">Pheronema carpenteri</span> [
   <a rid="pone.0205505.ref064" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref064">64</a>], were considered but rejected due to their poor spatial coverage in this region [
   <a rid="pone.0205505.ref065" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref065">65</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Hydrographic data (e.g. bottom and surface temperature, salinity, current velocity, and bottom shear) were extracted from a North Atlantic model termed BNAM (described in [
   <a rid="pone.0205505.ref066" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref066">66</a>]) developed at the Bedford Institute of Oceanography in Dartmouth, Nova Scotia, Canada. BNAM is based on the NEMO (Nucleus for European Modelling of the Ocean) 2.3 reanalysis model, which includes both an ocean component (OPA, Océan PArallélisé; [
   <a rid="pone.0205505.ref067" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref067">67</a>]) and a sea ice module (LIM, Louvain-la-Neuve Sea Ice Model; [
   <a rid="pone.0205505.ref068" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref068">68</a>]). BNAM has a horizontal resolution of 1/12°, equating to ~ 6 km on the Scotian Shelf. Data from the period 1990 to 2015 were extracted.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Seasonal sea surface chlorophyll 
   <span class="italic">a</span> from 2002 to 2012 and primary production data from 2006 to 2010 were also extracted. Chlorophyll 
   <span class="italic">a</span> was derived from Aqua-MODIS (Moderate Resolution Imaging Spectroradiometer) Case I was processed by the Remote Sensing Unit at the Bedford Institute of Oceanography (RSU-BIO). Specific details on how these data were processed can be found in [
   <a rid="pone.0205505.ref065" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref065">65</a>]. Annual and seasonal averages were computed, with seasons delimited by the following day of year ranges: days 91–181 (spring), 182–273 (summer), and 274–365 (fall). Seasonal (spring, summer, fall) and annual primary production layers were also used in the model, the details of which are summarized in [
   <a rid="pone.0205505.ref065" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref065">65</a>].
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fishing effort from the time period of 2005–2014 from mobile bottom-tending gears was also included as a predictor in the model to ascertain whether fishing effort has shaped the distribution of 
   <span class="italic">V</span>. 
   <span class="italic">pourtalesi</span>. This predictor variable describes the sum of the fishing vessel monitoring system (VMS) ping time (in hours) within each 1 x 1 km grid cell, where a higher number of hours indicates higher effort, and was compiled for an analysis of the overlap between fishing effort and Significant Benthic Areas of cold-water corals and sponges in eastern Canada (see [
   <a rid="pone.0205505.ref069" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref069">69</a>] for more details).
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Emerald Basin is characterized by fluctuations in temperature and salinity that are higher between years than between seasons, and therefore we chose to use metrics of each oceanographic variable type that would describe both mean climate and the variability in oceanographic conditions across its temporal range. For each variable type (e.g., bottom temperature), four different statistical quantities were calculated across its temporal data range: minimum, maximum, mean and range (difference between minimum and maximum). This was done by averaging the minimum, maximum, or mean values between all years of the dataset. All variables except depth and slope were then spatially interpolated across the study area using ordinary kriging in ArcMap 10.2.2 software [
   <a rid="pone.0205505.ref070" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref070">70</a>] to create continuous data surfaces with a ~1 km grid size. All predictor layers were displayed in raster format with geographic coordinates using a WGS 1984 datum and a ~0.012° cell size (approximately equal to 1 km in our study region). Slope was derived from depth projected using the NAD 1983 Zone 20N coordinate system (units in metres), and both depth and slope were re-projected using a WGS 1984 datum and resampled to the 0.012° grid size using the nearest neighbour technique. Averaged bottom temperature and salinity from the BNAM model were additionally used to illustrate the association of 
   <span class="italic">V</span>. 
   <span class="italic">pourtalesi</span> with regional water masses.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Broad-scale categorical maps of the surficial geology of the region have been generated [
   <a rid="pone.0205505.ref059" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref059">59</a>], and as noted above, 
   <span class="italic">V</span>. 
   <span class="italic">pourtalesi</span> attaches to hard substrate. Such categorical data were not included as predictors in our model for several reasons: 1) they did not fully cover the known distribution of 
   <span class="italic">V</span>. 
   <span class="italic">pourtalesi</span> on the Scotian Shelf, 2) random forest has shown bias towards categorical variables with a high number of levels [
   <a rid="pone.0205505.ref071" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref071">71</a>], and 3) patterns in habitat heterogeneity on the Scotian Shelf occur over micro-scales [
   <a rid="pone.0205505.ref072" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref072">72</a>–
   <a rid="pone.0205505.ref073" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref073">73</a>]; therefore such data would not be useful in explaining patterns in the spatial distribution of 
   <span class="italic">V</span>. 
   <span class="italic">pourtalesi</span> with the resolution of our model.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although the performance of classification random forest models are relatively unaffected by the presence of correlated predictor variables [
   <a rid="pone.0205505.ref074" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref074">74</a>], correlated variables may have a significant effect on variable importance measures and ecological interpretation, showing bias towards the most highly correlated predictors [
   <a rid="pone.0205505.ref075" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref075">75</a>]. As most of the variables were moderately or highly correlated, only very strongly correlated variables (Spearman’s rank correlation coefficient 
   <span class="italic">ρ</span> ≥ 0.9; [
   <a rid="pone.0205505.ref076" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref076">76</a>]) were eliminated. Variable elimination was done following the procedure outlined by [
   <a rid="pone.0205505.ref077" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref077">77</a>]. Spearman’s rank correlation coefficients were calculated between predictor variables for each raster grid cell in the study area. The two predictors with the highest correlation were considered and one eliminated based on user-defined criteria. In these criteria, those variables considered more important to the distribution of deep-water sponges (e.g., near-bottom processes over surface) were favoured, as well as those variables considered to have a more direct (e.g. bottom temperature) than proximal (e.g. depth) influence on species’ distributions. The process was repeated until no variables correlated &gt; 0.9 remained. 
   <a rid="pone.0205505.t001" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0205505.t001">Table 1</a> shows the remaining 35 variables used in the random forest model. A depiction of the Spearman’s rank correlation between the 63 original variables used to make this selection can be found in the supplementary material (
   <a ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0205505.s002" href="#pone.0205505.s002">S1 Fig</a>).
  </p>
  <div id="pone.0205505.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pone.0205505.t001</span>
   <span class="label">Table 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <div class="title">Environmental predictor variables remaining after variable elimination and included in the random forest model.</div>
    <p>NA = not applicable.</p>
   </div>
   <div class="alternatives">
    <div id="pone.0205505.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0205505.t001" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
     <colgroup span="1">
      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
      <col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/>
     </colgroup>
     <thead>
      <tr>
       <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Variable</th>
       <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Metric</th>
       <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Unit</th>
       <th align="center" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Native Resolution</th>
      </tr>
     </thead>
     <tbody>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bottom Temperature</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min, Max, Range</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">°C</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/12
        <span class="sup">th</span> degree
       </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bottom Salinity</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/12
        <span class="sup">th</span> degree
       </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bottom Current</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Max, Min</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">m s
        <span class="sup">-1</span>
       </td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/12
        <span class="sup">th</span> degree
       </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Surface Temperature</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Max, Range</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">°C</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/12
        <span class="sup">th</span> degree
       </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Surface Salinity</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Range</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/12
        <span class="sup">th</span> degree
       </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Surface Current</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min, Max</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">m s
        <span class="sup">-1</span>
       </td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1/12
        <span class="sup">th</span> degree
       </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Annual Surface Chlorophyll 
        <span class="italic">a</span>
       </td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Max, Range</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg m
        <span class="sup">-3</span>
       </td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 km</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spring Surface Chlorophyll 
        <span class="italic">a</span>
       </td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min, Max, Mean</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg m
        <span class="sup">-3</span>
       </td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 km</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fall Surface Chlorophyll 
        <span class="italic">a</span>
       </td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min, Max</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg m
        <span class="sup">-3</span>
       </td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2 km</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Annual Surface Primary Production</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min, Max, Mean, Range</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg C m
        <span class="sup">-2</span> day
        <span class="sup">-1</span>
       </td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 km</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Spring Surface Primary Production</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min, Max, Mean, Range</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg C m
        <span class="sup">-2</span> day
        <span class="sup">-1</span>
       </td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 km</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Summer Surface Primary Production</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min, Max, Range</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg C m
        <span class="sup">-2</span> day
        <span class="sup">-1</span>
       </td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 km</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fall Surface Primary Production</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Min, Max, Mean, Range</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">mg C m
        <span class="sup">-2</span> day
        <span class="sup">-1</span>
       </td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9 km</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bottom Fishing Effort</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Percentages</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1 km</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Slope</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NA</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Degrees</td>
       <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 arc-sec</td>
      </tr>
     </tbody>
    </table>
   </div>
  </div>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec010" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Random forest modelling</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Random forest classification [
   <a rid="pone.0205505.ref078" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref078">78</a>] was used to predict the probability of occurrence and range distribution of 
   <span class="italic">V</span>. 
   <span class="italic">pourtalesi</span> based on the 215 presence and 2867 absence records and 35 predictor variables as described above (
   <a rid="pone.0205505.t001" ref-type="table" href="#pone.0205505.t001">Table 1</a>). Random forest is a non-parametric machine learning technique where multiple trees are built using random subsets of the response data. Each tree is fit to a bootstrap sample of these data, and the best predictor at each node is that which splits the response data so that maximum homogeneity is reached in the child nodes. Models were fitted using the ‘randomForest’ package [
   <a rid="pone.0205505.ref079" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref079">79</a>] in the statistical computing software program R version 3.3.1 [
   <a rid="pone.0205505.ref080" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref080">80</a>]. Default values were used for RF parameters, and the default 500 trees were constructed.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Model performance was assessed in R using 10-fold cross validation. In this process the response data are split into 10 folds of equal size, and a model is trained on a combination of 9 folds and validated on the remaining fold. The process is repeated 10 times, giving 10 repetitions for which accuracy measures are derived. Sensitivity (i.e., the proportion of accurately predicted presences) and specificity (the proportion of accurately predicted absences) were derived by summing the predicted outcomes across the 2 x 2 confusion matrices generated for each of the 10 model folds. Low sensitivity represents high omission error (i.e., false negative rate), while low specificity indicates high commission error (i.e., false positive rate). The response dataset for 
   <span class="italic">V</span>. 
   <span class="italic">pourtalesi</span> is characterized by a higher number of absences relative to presences (i.e., unbalanced species prevalence, where prevalence is the proportion of presences in relation to the total dataset). Classification accuracy in random forest is prone to bias when the categorical response variable is highly imbalanced [
   <a rid="pone.0205505.ref081" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref081">81</a>]. This is due to over-representation of the majority class in the bootstrap sample leading to a higher frequency in which the majority class is drawn, therefore skewing predictions in that favour [
   <a rid="pone.0205505.ref082" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref082">82</a>]. Given the highly imbalanced nature of the response dataset, a threshold defining above which a class probability is considered a presence is often used to convert the class probabilities into predicted outcomes that are then summarized in the 2 x 2 confusion matrix. We used prevalence, or the probability of presences in the training dataset, as the threshold defining when a species is considered present [
   <a rid="pone.0205505.ref083" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref083">83</a>–
   <a rid="pone.0205505.ref084" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref084">84</a>]. The discrimination capacity of the training model was determined by calculating the average Area under the Receiver Operating Characteristic (ROC) Curve, or AUC, across all 10 model folds. The AUC is considered threshold-independent and is calculated from a combination of the true positive rate and false positive rate (1-specificity). AUC equals the probability that the model will rank a randomly-chosen presence instance higher than a randomly-chosen absence instance [
   <a rid="pone.0205505.ref085" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref085">85</a>], where values &gt; 0.9 indicate excellent model performance, 0.8–0.9 very good, 0.7–0.8 good, 0.6–0.7 fair, 0.6–0.5 poor, and &lt;0.5 no better than random.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Using R’s ‘predict’ function, a model trained on all of the data (215 presences and 2867 absences) was used to predict the probability of presence of 
   <span class="italic">V</span>. 
   <span class="italic">pourtalesi</span> across the entire study area, creating a 1 x 1 km raster grid surface of predicted presence probabilities. Additionally, the probabilistic map was converted into a discrete map showing areas of suitable and unsuitable habitat using the prevalence threshold, where cells with probabilities less than the threshold were considered unsuitable habitat, and those greater considered suitable. The true skill statistic (TSS), which maximizes the sum of sensitivity and specificity and is considered to have all the advantages of the kappa statistic but is independent of prevalence [
   <a rid="pone.0205505.ref086" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref086">86</a>], was also considered in this study. It was very similar to the prevalence threshold (0.11 versus 0.07 for prevalence) and resulted in only a slightly reduced area predicted as suitable habitat. For 
   <span class="italic">V</span>. 
   <span class="italic">pourtalesi</span>, a long-lived species vulnerable to fishing impacts, our goal was to reduce the omission error (where the model predicts an absence where a presence is located) as much as possible and therefore we applied the prevalence threshold in preference to the TSS.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ecological context of the model was aided by predictor variable importance and response curves (partial dependence plots). The importance of the predictor variables in the classification model was assessed using the ‘importance’ function of package ‘randomForest’, which calculates the Mean Decrease in Gini index, or Gini impurity for each variable. When the response data are split into two child nodes based on a randomly-chosen variable, the data in the two descendent nodes are more homogeneous than that of the parent node. This difference in homogeneity between parent and child nodes is measured by the Gini index, where the increase in homogeneity equals a decrease in Gini value. The sum of all decreases in Gini index for each variable in each tree is averaged across all trees in the model. The variable with the highest mean decrease in Gini value is considered the most important variable in the model.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Response curves showing the partial dependence on the top six predictor variables were generated using the ‘partialPlot’ function in R. For classification random forest, these partial dependence plots show the marginal effect of a predictor variable on the class probability. The other predictor variables are held constant at their mean observed value. Partial dependence plots are useful in showing general trends in model accuracy’s dependence on the predictors [
   <a rid="pone.0205505.ref087" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref087">87</a>]. For classification models, the 
   <span class="italic">y</span> axis ranges from -∞ to ∞ and quantifies the log-odds of a positive classification for the total range of values in 
   <span class="italic">x</span>. Log-odds are logarithmic transformations of the probabilities for values in 
   <span class="italic">x</span> [
   <a rid="pone.0205505.ref088" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref088">88</a>]. These values were transformed to the original presence probability scale using: 
   <span class="italic">p</span> = 
   <span class="italic">exp</span>(
   <span class="italic">y</span>)/(1 + 
   <span class="italic">exp</span>(
   <span class="italic">y</span>)), where p = the probability of presence, and y is the log-odds of presence, the standard output from the partialPlot function.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec011" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fine-scale hydrographic conditions over the 
   <span class="italic">Vazella</span> sponge grounds
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Fine-scale hydrographic and biochemical conditions directly over the 
   <span class="italic">Vazella</span> sponge grounds were examined from four CTD profiles made on July 20, 2016 as part of a DFO science mission to characterize the environmental characteristics of these sponge grounds (see [
   <a rid="pone.0205505.ref089" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref089">89</a>]). Four continuous, full-depth profiles of temperature, salinity, fluorescence, density, and oxygen were made using a CTD and rosette with 24 10-L sampling bottles to collect water samples for the analysis following standard procedures [
   <a rid="pone.0205505.ref090" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref090">90</a>] of silicate, nitrate, and phosphate through the water column to 10 m above the seabed. Note that nutrient data was only acquired for three of the four casts. CTD casts were made in the northeast corner of DFO’s Emerald Basin 
   <span class="italic">Vazella</span> Conservation Area in a gradient from high sponge densities to low. CTD casts were approximately 1 km apart.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="sec012" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climatological trends and inter-annual variability in water mass characteristics over the 
   <span class="italic">Vazella</span> sponge grounds
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Long-term trends in bottom temperature and salinity in Emerald Basin were examined from two different sources: observational data from CTDs and ARGO floats collected in Emerald Basin between 1950 and 2015, and the Simple Ocean Data Assimilation (SODA) version 2.2.4 reanalysis model. The goal of SODA is to reconstruct the historical physical history of the global ocean through the optimization of model physics, forcing, and available ocean data observations. Gridded monthly data were extracted from SODA for the time period 1871 to 2010 from a bounding box with a longitude of -63.5W, -63W by latitude of 43.5N, 44.0N. As the first record of 
   <span class="italic">V</span>. 
   <span class="italic">pourtalesi</span> from the region dates back to 1889 [
   <a rid="pone.0205505.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0205505.ref034">34</a>], this timeframe can be used to describe the variability in conditions experienced by the 
   <span class="italic">V</span>. 
   <span class="italic">pourtalesi</span> population on the Scotian Shelf. Trends in temperature and salinity from SODA were displayed by season (winter: Jan. to Mar., spring: Apr. to June, summer: July to Sept., fall: Oct. to Dec.) and as annual averages.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
