<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Analysis of trends, biases and gaps</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on the categorisation frequencies in 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="T1" href="#T1">Table 1</a> (counts are given in the 
  <span class="italic">n</span> columns adjacent to each category), the “archetypal” highly cited paper in biodiversity and climate change research relies on a database of previously collated information, makes an assessment based on future forecasts of shifts in geographical distributions, is regional in scope, emphasises applied-management outcomes, and uses terrestrial plant species in temperate zones as the study unit.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Many papers also introduced new methodological developments, studied montane communities, took a theoretical-fundamental perspective, and considered physiological, population dynamics, and migration-dispersal aspects of ecological change. Plants were by far the dominant taxonomic group under investigation. By contrast, relatively few of the highly cited paper studies used experimental manipulations or network analysis; lake, river, island and marine systems were rarely treated; nor did they focus on behavioural or biotic interactions. Crucially, none of the highly cited papers relied on paleoclimate reconstructions or genetic information, despite the potential value of such data for model validation and contextualisation 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-12">12</a>
  </span>. Such data are crucial in providing evidence for species responses to past environmental changes, specifying possible limits of adaptation (rate and extent) and fundamental niches, and testing theories of biogeography and macroecology.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">At the time of writing, 5 of the 30 highly cited papers listed in 
  <a ref-type="table" rid="T1" href="#T1">Table 1</a> (16%) also received article recommendations from 
  <span class="italic">Faculty of 1000</span> experts ( 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://f1000.com/prime/recommendations" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">f1000.com/prime/recommendations</span>) 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-9">9</a>, 
   <a rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-13">13</a>– 
   <a rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-16">16</a>
  </span> with none of the most recent (2014) highly cited papers having yet received an F1000 Prime endorsement.
 </p>
</sec>
