<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is now halfway through the second decade of the 21 
  <span class="sup">st</span> century, and climate change impact has emerged as a “hot topic” in biodiversity research. In the early decades of the discipline of conservation biology (1970s and 1980s), effort was focused on studying and mitigating the four principal drivers of extinction risk since the turn of the 16 
  <span class="sup">th</span> century, colourfully framed by Diamond 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-1" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-1">1</a>
  </span> as the “evil quartet”: habitat destruction, overhunting (or overexploitation of resources), introduced species, and chains of extinctions (including trophic cascades and co-extinctions). Recent work has also emphasised the importance of synergies among drivers of endangerment 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-2" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-2">2</a>
  </span>. But the momentum to understand how other aspects of global change (such as a disrupted climate system and pollution) add to, and reinforce, these threats has built since the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change reports 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-3" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-3">3</a>
  </span> of 2001 and 2007 and the Millennium Ecosystem Assessment 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-4">4</a>
  </span> in 2005.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Scientific studies on the effects of climate change on biodiversity have proliferated in recent decades. A 
  <span class="italic">Web of Science</span> ( 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://webofscience.com" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">webofscience.com</span>) query on the term “biodiversity AND (climate change)”, covering the 14 complete years of the 21 
  <span class="sup">st</span> century, shows the peer-reviewed literature matching this search term has grown from just 87 papers in 2001 to 1,377 in 2014. 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="f1" href="#f1">Figure 1</a> illustrates that recent scientific interest in climate change-related aspects of biodiversity research has outpaced—in relative terms—the baseline trend of interest in other areas of biodiversity research (i.e., matching the query “biodiversity NOT (climate change)”), with climate-related research rising from 5.5% of biodiversity papers in 2001 to 16.8% in 2014.
 </p>
 <div fig-type="figure" id="f1" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 1. </span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Relative growth of refereed studies on climate change and biodiversity, compared to non-climate-related biodiversity research.</div>
   <p>Number of refereed papers listed in the 
    <span class="italic">Web of Science</span> database that were published between 2001 and 2014 on the specific topic “biodiversity AND (climate change)” (blue line, secondary y-axis) compared to the more general search term “biodiversity NOT (climate change)”.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="f1000research-4-6984-g0000" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Interest in this field of research seems to have been driven by a number of concerns. First, there is an increasing societal and scientific consensus on the need to measure, predict (and, ultimately, mitigate) the impact of anthropogenic climate change 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-5" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-5">5</a>
  </span>, linked to the rise of industrial fossil-fuel combustion and land-use change 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-6" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-6">6</a>
  </span>. Biodiversity loss and ecosystem transformations, in particular, have been highlighted as possibly being amongst the most sensitive of Earth’s systems to global change 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-7">7</a>, 
   <a rid="ref-8" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-8">8</a>
  </span>. Second, there is increasing attention given to quantifying the reinforcing (or occasionally stabilising) feedbacks between climate change and other impacts of human development, such as agricultural activities and land clearing, invasive species, exploitation of natural resources, and biotic interactions 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-2" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-2">2</a>, 
   <a rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-9">9</a>
  </span>. Third, there has been a trend towards increased accessibility of climate change data and predictions at finer spatio-temporal resolutions, making it more feasible to do biodiversity climate research 
  <span class="sup">
   <a rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-10">10</a>, 
   <a rid="ref-11" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-11">11</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">What are the major directions being taken by the field of climate change and biodiversity research in recent years? Are there particular focal topics, or methods, that have drawn most attention? Here we summarise major trends in the recent highly cited literature of this field.</p>
</sec>
