<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3544717</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">23342048</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-12-30225</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0053959</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Ecology</subject><subj-group><subject>Community Ecology</subject><subj-group><subject>Food Web Structure</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Population Ecology</subject><subject>Spatial and Landscape Ecology</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Population Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Population Dynamics</subject><subj-group><subject>Predator-Prey Dynamics</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Zoology</subject><subj-group><subject>Entomology</subject><subject>Ornithology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Native Birds and Alien Insects: Spatial Density Dependence in Songbird Predation of Invading Oak Gallwasps</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Native Songbird Predation on Alien Insects</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sch&#x000f6;nrogge</surname><given-names>Karsten</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Begg</surname><given-names>Tracey</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>Graham N.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">
<sup>*</sup>
</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1">
<label>1</label>
<addr-line>Centre for Ecology &#x00026; Hydrology, Wallingford, United Kingdom</addr-line>
</aff><aff id="aff2">
<label>2</label>
<addr-line>University of Edinburgh, Institute of Evolutionary Biology, School of Biological Sciences, Edinburgh, United Kingdom</addr-line>
</aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Farwig</surname><given-names>Nina</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">
<addr-line>University of Marburg, Germany</addr-line>
</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">* E-mail: <email>graham.stone@ed.ac.uk</email></corresp><fn fn-type="COI-statement"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: KS TB GNS. Performed the experiments: KS TB. Analyzed the data: KS TB. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: KS TB GNS. Wrote the paper: KS TB GNS.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2013</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>14</day><month>1</month><year>2013</year></pub-date><volume>8</volume><issue>1</issue><elocation-id>e53959</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>2</day><month>10</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>4</day><month>12</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2013 Sch&#x000f6;nrogge et al</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2013</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Sch&#x000f6;nrogge et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are properly credited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Revealing the interactions between alien species and native communities is central to understanding the ecological consequences of range expansion. Much has been learned through study of the communities developing around invading herbivorous insects. Much less, however, is known about the significance of such aliens for native vertebrate predators for which invaders may represent a novel food source. We quantified spatial patterns in native bird predation of invading gall-inducing <italic>Andricus</italic> wasps associated with introduced Turkey oak (<italic>Quercus cerris</italic>) at eight sites across the UK. These gallwasps are available at high density before the emergence of caterpillars that are the principle spring food of native insectivorous birds. Native birds showed positive spatial density dependence in gall attack rates at two sites in southern England, foraging most extensively on trees with highest gall densities. In a subsequent study at one of these sites, positive spatial density dependence persisted through four of five sequential week-long periods of data collection. Both patterns imply that invading galls are a significant resource for at least some native bird populations. Density dependence was strongest in southern UK bird populations that have had longest exposure to the invading gallwasps. We hypothesise that this pattern results from the time taken for native bird populations to learn how to exploit this novel resource.</p></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This work was funded by the UK Natural Environment Research Council (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.nerc.ac.uk/">http://www.nerc.ac.uk/</ext-link>) through grants NER/S/A/2003/11227 and NE/H000135/1. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><page-count count="11"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Understanding the interactions between alien species and native communities is central to understanding the ecological consequences of species range expansions. Biological invasions often disrupt existing networks of biotic interaction among species, with impacts on native species ranging from negative (reduced population densities, extinction) to positive (e.g. through provision of novel food sources <xref rid="pone.0053959-Bartomeus1" ref-type="bibr">[1]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0053959-Skorka1" ref-type="bibr">[3]</xref>. Many aspects of this process have been investigated using natural systems comprising invading herbivorous insects and their parasitoid natural enemies <xref rid="pone.0053959-Hails1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0053959-Schnrogge2" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. In general, however, far less is known about the impact of invading insects on native vertebrate predators, in part because this is often much harder to quantify.</p><p>Here we examine predation by native U.K. insectivorous birds on a group of invading insect herbivores associated with an introduced oak &#x02013; the Turkey oak, <italic>Quercus cerris</italic>. The invaders are <italic>Andricus</italic> wasps (Hymenoptera: Cynipidae) whose lifecycle involves alternation between a sexual generation that galls Turkey oak and an asexual generation that galls native oaks (<italic>Q. petraea</italic> and <italic>Q. robur</italic>). These gallwasps have invaded the UK and northwestern Europe from southern central Europe and the Levant following human dispersal of Turkey oak from Italy and the Balkans <xref rid="pone.0053959-Schnrogge2" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0053959-Stone2" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. While recruitment of parasitoid natural enemies to these invaders has been studied in considerable detail <xref rid="pone.0053959-Schnrogge1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053959-Schnrogge2" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053959-Hails2" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053959-Hayward1" ref-type="bibr">[14]</xref>, much less is known of the development of trophic links with native birds. Native gallwasps are known to be important components in the diets of insectivorous birds in Britain <xref rid="pone.0053959-Betts1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, particularly blue tits (<italic>Parus caeruleus</italic> L.) and great tits (<italic>P. major</italic> L.). and the sexual generation galls of another invader (<italic>Andricus quercuscalicis</italic>) are known to have been systematically exploited by native birds in one UK location <xref rid="pone.0053959-Hails1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>.</p><p>Here we examine bird predation of three further invading <italic>Andricus</italic> gallwasps (<italic>Andricus kollari</italic> (Hartig, 1843), <italic>A. lignicolus</italic> (Hartig, 1843) and <italic>A. corruptrix</italic> (Schlechtendal, 1870)). The sexual generation galls of all three species are small (2&#x02013;3 mm long) and thin-walled, and develop over the winter and early spring concealed within Turkey oak buds. The galls expand to emerge through the bud scales in late March, appearing before any other galls are available on this oak <xref rid="pone.0053959-Schnrogge3" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>. Though the galls are cryptic, individual oaks may bear hundreds of thousands of them (this study). They represent a novel potential food for resident insectivorous birds prior to their breeding season at a time when other early spring foods can be scarce <xref rid="pone.0053959-Jansson1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref>. Small insectivorous birds, particularly blue and great tits, have been observed to open the galls to reach the larvae within <xref rid="pone.0053959-Schnrogge4" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>.</p><p>We assessed native bird responses to these alien gallwasps by analysing spatial patterns in their exploitation across eight sites comprising a north-south transect across the U.K. All of the invading gallwasps first became established in southern England, spreading into Scotland over a period of 40&#x02013;50 years. <italic>Andricus kollari</italic> was introduced to Devon in the 1830s&#x02013;40&#x02032;s <xref rid="pone.0053959-Schnrogge2" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053959-Stone2" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>. <italic>Andricus lignicolus</italic> and <italic>A. corruptrix</italic> were first recorded in Britain in the 1970&#x02019;s, and their expansion through Scotland is ongoing <xref rid="pone.0053959-Schnrogge2" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. Though we do not know the arrival dates of each species at each of our sampling locations, the north-south transect represents a gradient of increasing time of exposure of native birds to invading gallwasps.</p><p>Individual populations of insectivorous birds (including blue tits and great tits) are known to be sensitive to between-tree variation in the density of familiar prey, and forage preferentially in highly rewarding trees, i.e. they show positive spatial density dependence <xref rid="pone.0053959-Betts1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053959-Gibb1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0053959-Tscharntke1" ref-type="bibr">[25]</xref>. Pre-breeding condition has a significant impact on breeding success in insectivorous birds <xref rid="pone.0053959-Lambrechts1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref>. We hypothesise that if alien galls are an important resource for native birds prior to the breeding season, they will also recruit to trees with high gall density, and so show positive spatial density dependence at the scale of trees within sites.</p><p>Detection of spatial density dependence requires a match between the spatial scale of sampling and that at which birds make foraging decisions <xref rid="pone.0053959-Hails1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053959-NaefDaenzer1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053959-Heads1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0053959-Veldtman1" ref-type="bibr">[31]</xref>. In addition to responding to variation in prey density between trees, birds may also respond to variation in prey density at smaller spatial scales, such as branches within trees, or shoots within branches <xref rid="pone.0053959-Heads1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053959-Connor1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053959-Connor2" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. However, such local variation in density is difficult or impossible to estimate for mobile prey. Most studies on tit foraging have used rates of caterpillar frass fall as a surrogate for caterpillar density, but this measure is impossible to estimate for specific branches within the same tree. A major advantage of working with sessile prey (including galling insects) is that their extraction by birds leaves characteristic signs, allowing analysis of patterns at within-tree spatial scales <xref rid="pone.0053959-Schnrogge4" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053959-Connor1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053959-Connor2" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. At each of our 8 sites we therefore analysed bird foraging responses to variation in prey density at three spatial scales: shoots within branches, branches within trees, and trees within sites.</p><p>Previous work has also shown that tit foraging preferences for individual patches and prey types track changes in resource availability over timescales of days <xref rid="pone.0053959-NaefDaenzer1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053959-Gawlik1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>. Each spring, the alien <italic>Andricus</italic> bud galls emerge as a single cohort that once eaten are not replaced, so abundance of this prey declines over time. To study the impact of this change in resource availability, we also tracked week-by-week changes in signatures of density dependence through a single season at a single site. The persistence of any signal of density dependence provides an indication of the attractiveness of this resource to native birds. Our <italic>a priori</italic> expectation was that any signature of density dependence would decline as total gall abundance declines and birds recruit to alternative, more profitable foods <xref rid="pone.0053959-Connor1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053959-Gawlik1" ref-type="bibr">[33]</xref>.</p><p>We thus address the following specific questions. 1) Is there evidence of spatially density dependent predation of alien bud galls by birds, and, if so, at which spatial scale(s)? 2) How do the sign and strength of spatial density dependence at a single site change through a single season? Is there a detectable decline in any signal of density dependence with decreasing resource availability?</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Sampling Methods and Study Locations</title><p>We collected data in 1995 from eight UK locations (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0053959-g001">Fig. 1</xref>) used in previous work on oak gallwasp community dynamics <xref rid="pone.0053959-Schnrogge1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053959-Schnrogge3" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053959-Schnrogge4" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053959-Schnrogge5" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref> whose tree stands and cynipid communities are detailed by Sch&#x000f6;nrogge <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0053959-Schnrogge3" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>. All sites were visited with landowner permission, and no permits for sampling were required. Samples were collected in mid-late April, at an appropriate time to capture all developing galls prior to the ejection of emerged galls by developing buds. At each site we selected 12 <italic>Q. cerris</italic> trees at random or, if fewer than 12 were present, sampled all available trees. We pruned 15 branches (defined as 4 years&#x02019; growth following Sch&#x000f6;nrogge <italic>et al</italic>. <xref rid="pone.0053959-Schnrogge3" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>) from each tree, collected haphazardly from all aspects and heights up to 8.0 m. From each branch, we randomly selected six shoots (defined as one year&#x02019;s growth, identified by ring scars on the bark, following Sch&#x000f6;nrogge <italic>et al.</italic>
<xref rid="pone.0053959-Schnrogge3" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>). The sexual generation bud galls of all three <italic>Andricus</italic> species are conical and small enough that only the tip of a mature gall is visible above the bud scales of the closed buds on <italic>Q. cerris</italic>. To reveal gall density and fate we dissected <underline>all</underline> buds on each sampled shoot in the lab under a dissecting microscope (a total of 11,100 shoots, 33,440 buds and 3,474 galls). Since young galls of the three study species are available simultaneously, contain very similarly-sized larvae and are morphologically indistinguishable, we treated all three species as a single resource. On the basis of adults dissected from galls, we know that in all surveys &#x0003e;50% of the galls were <italic>A. lignicolus</italic>.</p><fig id="pone-0053959-g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0053959.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title>Geographic locations of the eight sampling sites in Britain.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0053959.g001"/></fig><p>Galls attacked by birds show ragged removal of the gall apex, rather than the smooth apertures made by emerging insects. Though we could easily identify galls attacked by birds, we do not attempt to distinguish between galls opened by different bird species.</p><p>In spring 2006, we collected additional data at one location (Puttenham Common; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0053959-g001">Fig. 1</xref>) to allow analysis of temporal patterns of bird predation within a single season. We sampled as above the same twelve <italic>Q. cerris</italic> trees each week for five weeks from March 25, over which period the galls matured and the adults emerged. To identify probable bird species attacking alien galls at this site in this season, we observed six Turkey oaks for one hour in each of weeks 2&#x02013;5. We observed 72 gall predation incidents by a total of seven bird species. Seventy-five percent involved tits, predominantly blue tits (<italic>Parus caeruleus</italic>, 55%) and great tits (<italic>Parus major</italic>, 18%). Other birds observed were Long-tailed tits (<italic>Aegithalos caudatus</italic> (L.), 1.4%), robins (<italic>Erithacus rubecula</italic> (L.), 11.1%), song thrushes (<italic>Turdus philomelos</italic> Brehm, 5.5%), blackbirds (<italic>Turdus merula</italic> L., 6.9%), and green woodpeckers (<italic>Picus viridis</italic> L., 1.4%).</p></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Statistical Methods</title><p>We tested for spatial density dependence using generalised linear model (GLM) analysis of the proportion of predated galls as a function of gall densities per shoot (log(x+1) transformed) using R <xref rid="pone.0053959-R1" ref-type="bibr">[35]</xref> with quasibinomial errors to correct for under-dispersion and a logit link function <xref rid="pone.0053959-Crawley1" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053959-Logan1" ref-type="bibr">[37]</xref>. Separate analyses were carried out at each of three spatial levels, and for each site. First, we examined patterns across shoots (nested within branches within trees). Second, we examined patterns across branches (nested within trees), using mean gall densities and predation rates across shoots within branches to avoid pseudoreplication. Third, we examined patterns across trees, using mean gall densities and predation rates across branches to avoid pseudoreplication. Dunrobin, site 8, was excluded from further statistical analyses because predation of galls was only detected on one shoot. Model terms were tested for significance on deletion and all models were inspected for heteroscedasticity and normality of errors <xref rid="pone.0053959-Crawley1" ref-type="bibr">[36]</xref>.</p><p>Use of separate GLM models for each level in a spatial hierarchy in this way allows us to estimate slopes across sampled units at each level. However, averaging to control for pseudo-replication is sometimes seen as too conservative and the use of mixed models that only estimate variances for the structural factors have become common. We therefore also analysed our data using mixed models to assure ourselves that our results are not unduly influenced by using either method. Mixed effect model analyses were carried out using the R package glmer, library lme4, using the structural variables tree and branch as nested random effects and shoot gall densities as the fixed effect. As the results of the two approaches were very similar, we present the results of the GLMs with quasibinomial errors as the more conservative approach, and highlight the different mixed effect model results as necessary.</p><p>Analysis of gall predation rates over five weeks at Puttenham Common used the same twin approach of GLM&#x02019;s and mixed effect modelling. Each approach was applied separately to the data for each of the five sampling events, with GLM&#x02019;s fitted separately to each level in the spatial hierarchy of shoots within branches, branches within trees, and trees within a sampling event.</p><p>Because our GLM analyses address patterns at three different spatial scales in the data from each sampling site, the issue of significance threshold adjustment for multiple tests needs to be considered. Though threshold significance (alpha) values are routinely adjusted under such circumstances, the application of such procedures remains an area of active debate <xref rid="pone.0053959-Nakagawa1" ref-type="bibr">[38]</xref>. Commonly applied corrections (such as Bonferroni) can be overly conservative and increase the risk of making a type II error. We therefore present the results of our analyses both with unadjusted threshold significance levels (i.e. p&#x0003c;0.05, p&#x0003c;0.01) and indicate those that remain significant after the Dunn-&#x00160;id&#x000e1;k adjustment for three tests <xref rid="pone.0053959-Quinn1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref> of the p&#x0003c;0.05 threshold to p&#x0003c;0.017. We used the Dunn-&#x00160;id&#x000e1;k rather than the Bonferroni correction as this approach slightly improves the power for each comparison <xref rid="pone.0053959-Quinn1" ref-type="bibr">[39]</xref>. Means are given &#x000b1; standard error.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec id="s3a"><title>Variation in Gall Density and Bird Predation</title><p>Gall densities (expressed per shoot throughout) were highly variable at all spatial scales (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0053959-t001">Table 1</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0053959-g002">Fig. 2</xref>, see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0053959.s002">Table S1</xref> for a summary of all site and tree level data). At Silwood Park, for example, while the overall mean gall density was 0.81&#x000b1;0.06 galls/shoot, individual branch means ranged from 0.0&#x02013;7.0 and tree means from 0.0&#x02013;2.44. Equivalent values in the same year for Puttenham Common were 0.39&#x000b1;0.06, 0.0&#x02013;1.5, and 0.01&#x02013;0.79. There was no geographical trend in gall densities, which were highest at Silwood Park in the south and at Dunrobin, the most northern site (see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0053959.s001">Fig. S1</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0053959-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0053959.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Patterns of spatial density dependence among trees at each site.</title><p>Significance levels are indicated by superscripts as follows: ns non significant; * p&#x0003c;0.05, ** p&#x0003c;0.01, *** p&#x0003c;0.001. p&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.05 is equivalent to p&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.017 after Dunn-&#x00160;id&#x000e0;k adjustment (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0053959-t002">Table 2</xref>). Note that the scale of the y-axis is different in for Dunrobin (h).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0053959.g002"/></fig><table-wrap id="pone-0053959-t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0053959.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>Galling and predation rates at the eight locations sampled in 1995.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0053959-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0053959.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site</td><td colspan="6" align="left" rowspan="1">Galling rates</td><td colspan="6" align="left" rowspan="1">Predation rates</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site mean &#x000b1; S.E. (n)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003c3;<sup>2</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Highest tree mean</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003c3;<sup>2</sup>
<sub> h</sub>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lowest tree mean</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003c3;<sup>2</sup>
<sub> l</sub>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Site mean &#x000b1; S.E. (n)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003c3;<sup>2</sup>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Highest tree mean</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003c3;<sup>2</sup>
<sub> h</sub>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lowest Tree mean</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x003c3;<sup>2</sup>
<sub> l</sub>
</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Silwood Park*</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81&#x000b1;0.22 (12)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.59</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.44&#x000b1;0.48 (15)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.48</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00<sub>no galls</sub>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44&#x000b1;0.07 (11)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.86&#x000b1;0.05 (14)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00<sub>no galls</sub>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Puttenham*</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.39&#x000b1;0.06 (12)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79&#x000b1;0.12 (15)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01&#x000b1;0.01 (15)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;0.01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17&#x000b1;0.03 (12)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22&#x000b1;0.09 (15)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00<sub>no pred.</sub> (1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tatton Park</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26&#x000b1;0.05 (12)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46&#x000b1;0.13 (15)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02&#x000b1;0.02 (15)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;0.01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21&#x000b1;0.05 (12)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.66&#x000b1;0.33(3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.33</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00<sub>no pred.</sub> (1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rufford Park</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34&#x000b1;0.06 (12)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57&#x000b1;0.12 (15)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.22</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08&#x000b1;0.04 (15)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32&#x000b1;0.05 (12)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.67&#x000b1;0.10 (15)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00<sub>no pred.</sub> (4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Erskin</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21&#x000b1;0.06 (9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64&#x000b1;0.13 (15)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.27</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02&#x000b1;0.02 (15)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;0.01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57&#x000b1;0.07 (9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79&#x000b1;0.16 (6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.16</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40&#x000b1;0.25 (5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Falkland</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30&#x000b1;0.05 (12)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68&#x000b1;0.13 (15)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01&#x000b1;0.01 (15)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;0.01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.47&#x000b1;0.06 (12)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75&#x000b1;0.07 (13)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00<sub>no pred.</sub> (1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beauly</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40&#x000b1;0.20(10)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.18&#x000b1;0.41 (15)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.52</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02&#x000b1;0.02 (15)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003e;0.01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.12&#x000b1;0.05 (10)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.03</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50&#x000b1;0.50 (2)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00<sub>no pred.</sub> (1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dunrobin</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.23&#x000b1;0.74 (7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.86</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.58&#x000b1;0.67 (15)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.69</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14&#x000b1;0.10 (15)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.15</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.006&#x000b1;0.005 (7)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">&#x02021;</xref>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04&#x000b1;0.04 (9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00<sub>no pred.</sub> (9)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">na</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label/><p>Means (&#x000b1;1standard error) and variances (&#x003c3;<sup>2</sup>) of galling and predation rates, given as the site mean calculated across trees (with shoots and branches averaged within trees). Numbers in brackets give the number of trees contributing to each mean. Highest and Lowest tree means indicate means across branches for the trees with the highest and lowest gall density at each site, respectively. In these columns, the numbers in brackets indicate the number of branches of a total of 15/tree bearing &#x02265;1 galls. Asterisks (*) in the first column indicate locations where spatially density dependent relationships were detected (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0053959-g002">Figure 2</xref>).</p></fn><fn id="nt102"><label>&#x02021;</label><p>Galls on only 1 shoot in the sample from all 7 trees showed signs of predation. Dunrobin was excluded from further statistical analyses.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>Bird predation rates of galls also varied at all spatial scales, and often exceeded 50%. The mean proportion of galls attacked at Silwood Park was 0.44&#x000b1;0.07, where means at branch level ranged from 0.0&#x02013;1.0 and at tree level from 0.0&#x02013;0.86. Equivalent values for Puttenham Common in 1995 were 0.21&#x000b1;0.024, means at branch level ranged from 0.0&#x02013;1.0 and at tree level from 0.0&#x02013;0.35) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0053959-t001">Table 1</xref>; for complete tree level data see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0053959.s002">Table S1</xref>). There was no geographical trend from south to north in predation rates (F<sub>1,6</sub>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.69, p&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.44; see <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0053959.s001">Fig. S1</xref>).</p><p>Nested GLM analysis showed that at all sites more of the variance in bird predation was explained at the level of branches (within trees within sites) (mean&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;51.9%, range: 30.7%&#x02013;67%) than at the level of trees (within sites) (mean&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;16.9%, range: 4.9%&#x02013;36.8%).</p></sec><sec id="s3b"><title>Patterns of Spatial Density Dependence in 1995</title><list list-type="alpha-lower"><list-item><p>Patterns at the scale of shoots (within branches within trees). Significant main effects of gall density on the proportion of galls attacked by birds were found at this scale for five of the seven sites (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0053959-t002">Table 2</xref>), with no significant correlations at the two northern sites (Erskine and Beauly). Significant correlations were highly variable in sign, with the proportion that were positive ranging across the six sites from 0.18&#x02013;0.63 (mean 0.43&#x000b1;0.07).</p></list-item><list-item><p>Patterns at the scale of branches (within trees). At this spatial scale none of the 7 sites yielded significant relationships between the proportion of galls attacked and gall density. Mixed effect models indicated significant correlation at 4 sites (Silwood, Puttenham, Rufford and Falkland), but these remained significant only for Puttenham after Dunn- &#x00160;id&#x000e0;k adjustment (z&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;2.562; p&#x0003c;0.0105).</p></list-item><list-item><p>Patterns at the scale of trees (within sites). GLM models revealed significant positive density dependence at this scale for two southern sites (Silwood, Puttenham) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0053959-t002">Table 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0053959-g002">Fig. 2</xref>).</p></list-item></list><table-wrap id="pone-0053959-t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0053959.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Observed patterns of spatial density dependence in bird predation on <italic>Andricus</italic> bud galls across the UK.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0053959-t002-2" xlink:href="pone.0053959.t002"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Change in Deviance</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">d.f.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall deviance</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">d.f.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% Deviance explained</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F-value</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Significance, P (after Dunn-&#x00160;id&#x000e0;k correctionp<sub>0.05</sub>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.017)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion positive parameterestimates</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="4" align="left" rowspan="1">
<bold>Among shoots (within branches within trees)</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Silwood Park (1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">158.83</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">837.33</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">359</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.71</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P&#x0003c;0.003(*)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.63</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Puttenham (2)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.33</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">365.94</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">235</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.34</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P&#x0003c;0.0008 (*)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.58</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tatton Park (3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26.28</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">164.92</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">123</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.40</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P&#x0003c;0.006(*)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rufford (4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.36</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">401.70</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">179</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.88</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P&#x0003c;0.05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.44</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Erskine (5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.25</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">177.18</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.70</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Falkland (6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74.05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">335.86</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">157</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.60</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P&#x0003c;0.01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beauly (7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19.82</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">112.02</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">108</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="left" rowspan="1">
<bold>Branches (within trees)</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Silwood Park (1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.82</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.44</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">142</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Puttenham (2)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.91</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.86</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">121</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.44</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tatton Park (3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.46</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.02</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.43</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rufford (4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.89</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55.34</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">112</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.37</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Erskine (5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.48</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">62</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.76</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Falkland (6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.16</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.21</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">92</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beauly (7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.50</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="left" rowspan="1">
<bold>Among</bold>
<bold>trees</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Silwood Park (1)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.09</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.68</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33.95</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P&#x0003c;0.0003 (*)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">positive</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Puttenham (2)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">43</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">P&#x0003c;0.05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">positive</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Tatton Park (3)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.23</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.81</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Rufford (4)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.89</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">20</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.70</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Erskine (5)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.004</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.096</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Falkland (6)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.53</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.005</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Beauly (7)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt103"><label/><p>Dunrobin Castle is excluded due to very low predation rates. Analysis summaries are presented at three hierarchical spatial scales: A. Among shoots (within branches within trees); 2. Among branches (within trees); 3. Among trees within sites. Analyses for 2. and 3. were carried out over the averages of gall densities and predation rates at the lower hierarchical levels. Analyses were all generalised linear models with quasibinomial errors and a logit link. Significance levels are shown unadjusted. Significance at P&#x0003c;0.05 after Dunn-&#x00160;id&#x000e0;k adjustment of significance levels for 3 tests are indicated by an asterisk (*). The righthand column shows the proportion of slopes at the hierarchical level analysed showing positive density dependence.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3c"><title>Temporal Patterns in Spatial Density Dependence at Puttenham Common in 2006</title><p>As in 1995, there was considerable among-tree variation in both gall densities and predation rates at this site in 2006 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0053959-g003">Fig. 3</xref>). For example, in week 1 of the five week study period gall densities ranged 20-fold from 0.08 to 1.6/shoot, with corresponding variation in proportions consumed by birds from 0.0&#x02013;0.81. Against the background of this variation, however, there was an overall decline in mean gall density over the five week period, decreasing by a third from 2.8&#x000b1;0.12 to 1.9&#x000b1;0.09 galls per shoot (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0053959-g003">Fig. 3</xref>), probably due to expulsion of emerged/predated galls from opening Turkey oak buds. This decline in gall density was paralleled by a decline in bird predation rates of galls from 27.8&#x000b1;0.02% to 13.5&#x000b1;0.01%.</p><fig id="pone-0053959-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0053959.g003</object-id><label>Figure 3</label><caption><title>Patterns of spatial density dependence through time.</title><p>The figure shows patterns in density dependence among trees over five weeks starting with the last week of March 2006 at Puttenham Common (site 2, Fig. 1). Significance levels are indicated by superscripts as follows: ns non significant; * p&#x0003c;0.05, ** p&#x0003c;0.01, *** p&#x0003c;0.001. p&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.05 is equivalent to p&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.017 after Dunn-&#x00160;id&#x000e0;k adjustment (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0053959-t003">Table 3</xref>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0053959.g003"/></fig><p>Nested GLM analysis of weekly data at the level of shoots (within branches within trees) only revealed a significant main effect of gall density in week 5 (F<sub>27,41</sub>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;1.868, P&#x0003c;0.05). Mixed effect models supported no significant correlation for this week (z&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;1.891, P&#x0003e;0.05). In contrast, mixed effect models indicated significant negative density dependence in weeks 1 and 4 (z&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;2.773, P&#x0003c;0.01, and z&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;2.953, P&#x0003c;0.005 respectively) even after applying Dunn-&#x00160;id&#x000e0;k adjustments. Data for weeks 2 &#x00026; 3 yielded no significant correlation with either method. Models at this spatial scale in general explained a low proportion of deviance (&#x0003c;25%) and correlations were highly variable in sign (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0053959-t003">Table 3</xref>). Analyses at the scale of branches (within trees) explained even less deviance (&#x0003c;20%; <xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0053959-t003">Table 3</xref>), with the single significant effect indicated by nested GLM (for week 3) not supported by the corresponding mixed effect model (z&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.971, P&#x0003e;0.05).</p><table-wrap id="pone-0053959-t003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0053959.t003</object-id><label>Table 3</label><caption><title>Spatial density dependence in bird predation of <italic>Andricus</italic> bud galls at Puttenham Common.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0053959-t003-3" xlink:href="pone.0053959.t003"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Change in Deviance</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">d.f.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Overall deviance</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">d.f.</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">% Deviance explained</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F-value</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Significance, P (after Dunn-&#x00160;id&#x000e0;k adjustment p<sub>0.05</sub>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.017)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Proportion positive parameter estimates</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td colspan="4" align="left" rowspan="1">
<bold>Shoots within branches within trees</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="left" rowspan="1">Week</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.52</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">520.27</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">182</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">19</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.32</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.52</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">53</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">407.42</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">193</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.76</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">344.92</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">188</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">15</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.39</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.27</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">270.83</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">140</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">222.92</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">127</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">23</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.87</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="left" rowspan="1">
<bold>Branches within trees</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Week</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.61</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.39</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.76</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.59</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.35</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.45</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.52</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">058</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.70</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.28</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">66</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.93</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.09</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">59</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">18</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.49</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.40</td></tr><tr><td colspan="4" align="left" rowspan="1">
<bold>Among trees</bold>
</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Week</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.34</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.46</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">74</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27.74</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.001(*)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.26</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.43</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">17.09</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.005(*)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.45</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ns</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">&#x0003c;0.05</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Positive</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt104"><label/><p>Analysis summaries are presented at three spatial scales: 1. Among shoots (within branches within trees); 2. Among branches (within trees); 3. Among trees within sites. Analyses for 2 &#x00026; 3 were carried out over the averages of gall densities and predation rates at the lower levels of nesting. Analyses were all generalised linear models with quasibinomial errors and a logit link. Significance levels are shown unadjusted. Significance at P&#x0003c;0.05 after Dunn-&#x00160;id&#x000e0;k adjustment of significance levels for 3 tests are indicated by an asterisk (*).The right hand column shows the proportion of slopes at the hierarchical level analysed showing positive density dependence.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><p>In contrast, at the scale of trees (within sites) both GLMs and mixed effect models supported significant, positive relationships between gall density and predation rates in weeks 1,2,3 and week 5, in these weeks explaining 41&#x02013;75% of the deviance (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0053959-t003">Table 3</xref>). Rank orders in gall densities and predation rates among trees were positively correlated over the five weeks of the study (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0053959-t004">Table 4</xref>) and with each other (week 1: R<sup>2</sup>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.36, p&#x0003c;0.05; week 2: R<sup>2</sup>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.78, p&#x0003c;0.001; week 3: R<sup>2</sup>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.56, p&#x0003c;0.01; week 4: R<sup>2</sup>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.42, p&#x0003c;0.05; week 5: R<sup>2</sup>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.56, p&#x0003c;0.01; d.f.&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;10 for all analyses), showing not only that bird predation is positively density dependent spatially, but also that this pattern persists over time.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0053959-t004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0053959.t004</object-id><label>Table 4</label><caption><title>Between-week pairwise Spearman Rank Correlation Coefficients (R<sup>2</sup>).</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0053959-t004-4" xlink:href="pone.0053959.t004"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Gall density</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Week 1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Week 2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Week 3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Week 4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Week 5</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Predation rate</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Week 1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.72</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.78</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.73</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Week 2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.83</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.48</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.75</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Week 3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.57</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.55</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.82</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Week 4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.41</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.49</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Week 5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.77</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt105"><label/><p>Matrix values above the diagonal show rank correlations in gall density, while values below the diagonal show rank correlations in predation rates. All correlations had 10 degrees of freedom, and all except one (predation rates between week 1 &#x00026; 2 p&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.052) are significant at p&#x0003c;0.05. All correlations for gall densities are significant at p&#x0003c;0.01.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="s4a"><title>Spatial Density Dependence in Bird Predation of Alien Gallwasps</title><p>Our results show that at the scale of trees within sites, two of seven study sites showing bird predation of alien <italic>Andricus</italic> galls also show significant positive spatial density dependence. This parallels previous studies of birds foraging on native prey that show birds to recruit to rewarding patches at this spatial scale <xref rid="pone.0053959-Gibb1" ref-type="bibr">[19]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053959-Gibb2" ref-type="bibr">[20]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053959-Holmes1" ref-type="bibr">[22]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0053959-Suhonen1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053959-Connor1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053959-Itamies1" ref-type="bibr">[40]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0053959-NaefDaenzer3" ref-type="bibr">[42]</xref>. This sensitivity to prey density shows that even though we do not know the caloric contribution of gallwasps to bird diets, galls are important enough to influence bird foraging behaviour in the early spring. Few alternative protein-rich foods are available at this time <xref rid="pone.0053959-Betts1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053959-Suhonen1" ref-type="bibr">[24]</xref> and because both adult survival <xref rid="pone.0053959-Jansson1" ref-type="bibr">[17]</xref> and breeding success <xref rid="pone.0053959-Lambrechts1" ref-type="bibr">[26]</xref> correlate with pre-breeding adult condition, exploitation of any additional accessible resource is to be expected. Importance of alien gallwasps as a food source is underlined by continuing signatures of positive density dependence across the first three weeks and the fifth week of our five-week sampling period in 2006. We suggest that the observed decline in gall predation rates over the 5 week period may indicate declining dependence on (and hence sensitivity to) this resource as it becomes less abundant <xref rid="pone.0053959-NaefDaenzer1" ref-type="bibr">[23]</xref>. Alternative foods that become increasingly available through May include the Turkey oak catkin galls of two other invaders, <italic>Andricus quercuscalicis</italic> and <italic>A. grossulariae</italic>, which can reach densities of a million galls/tree <xref rid="pone.0053959-Hails1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053959-Schnrogge1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>.</p><p>Variation in prey density among trees &#x02013; and hence spatial patterns in bird foraging -may be driven by bottom-up influences of host oaks on gall densities. Previous work has shown that some trees support consistently higher densities of a given cynipid gall than others <xref rid="pone.0053959-Hails1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053959-Askew1" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0053959-Egan1" ref-type="bibr">[45]</xref>, and evidence is growing that such variation is associated with oak genotype <xref rid="pone.0053959-Eliason1" ref-type="bibr">[46]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053959-Ito1" ref-type="bibr">[47]</xref>. Successful gall induction requires oviposition into host plant tissues at appropriate levels of development, and at least some between-tree variation in gall densities is due to between-tree variation in phenology <xref rid="pone.0053959-Askew1" ref-type="bibr">[43]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053959-Crawley2" ref-type="bibr">[44]</xref>. It is thus possible that once local bird populations have discovered how to exploit alien galls on Turkey oak, they may also learn which trees are consistently more rewarding than others. Bottom-up impacts of host tree genotype on trophic interactions between birds and their insect prey have been demonstrated in other systems <xref rid="pone.0053959-Smith1" ref-type="bibr">[48]</xref>.</p><p>We found no consistent evidence of density dependence at spatial scales within trees. Hails and Crawley <xref rid="pone.0053959-Hails1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref> studied predation rates on the catkin galls of another invading oak gallwasp, <italic>Andricus quercuscalicis,</italic> on Turkey oak in Britain. In experimental treatments involving enhanced gall densities they detected consistently positive spatial density dependence of bird predation at four spatial scales within trees, from within individual catkins to within twigs representing two years of growth. However, at field densities the signs of density dependence at such spatial scales varied within individual trees <xref rid="pone.0053959-Hails1" ref-type="bibr">[4]</xref>, paralleling the lack of consistency at similar spatial scales in our data and in other studies on bird predation of concealed insect prey <xref rid="pone.0053959-Heads1" ref-type="bibr">[27]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053959-Connor1" ref-type="bibr">[28]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053959-Connor2" ref-type="bibr">[32]</xref>. The lack of negative density dependence within branches suggests that at this spatial scale birds have no difficulty in exploiting the highest gall densities they encountered.</p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title>Latitudinal Trends in Spatial Density Dependence</title><p>The signatures of positive spatial density dependence in 1995 were strongest in the two sites in southern England at which the invaders are longest established <xref rid="pone.0053959-Schnrogge2" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053959-Schnrogge5" ref-type="bibr">[34]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053959-Walker1" ref-type="bibr">[49]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053959-Askew2" ref-type="bibr">[50]</xref>. Lack of significant relationships at other sites cannot be attributed to low gall densities, since at these sites gall densities were as high or higher than those showing significant density dependence, and (with one exception) predation rates on individual trees also reached similar levels (see <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0053959-g002">Fig. 2</xref> and <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="pone.0053959.s002">Table S1</xref>). The exception was the most northern site, Dunrobin, which is notable because despite high gall densities there was virtually no predation. The geographic pattern in density dependence leads us to hypothesise that the ability of birds to recognise and effectively exploit this resource may be a function of their exposure to this novel prey type. This hypothesis could be tested using predation data from sites in which dates of first record for each of the invading gallwasps are known. Such a time lag in the recruitment of natural enemies to invading species is not uncommon <xref rid="pone.0053959-Keane1" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0053959-Hawkes1" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>, and is well documented for insect natural enemies (parasitoid wasps) exploiting another invading alien oak gallwasp, <italic>Andricus quercuscalicis,</italic> across continental Europe and Britain <xref rid="pone.0053959-Hails2" ref-type="bibr">[13]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053959-Collins1" ref-type="bibr">[53]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0053959-Schnrogge8" ref-type="bibr">[56]</xref>. Though insectivorous birds, and tits in particular, are able to recruit rapidly to new and rewarding food resources <xref rid="pone.0053959-Sherry1" ref-type="bibr">[57]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053959-Sherry2" ref-type="bibr">[58]</xref>, the alien sexual generation galls do not closely resemble any native galls present at the same time of year and their exploitation may require learning of effective exploitation behaviours by local bird populations. If this hypothesis is correct, then future surveys of bird predation involving the same latitudinal series of bird populations should detect increased spatial density dependence of gall predation at more northern sites.</p><p>An alternative explanation for between-site variation in density dependence is variation in the abundance of bird species able effectively to exploit cynipid galls. Blue tits and great tits vary in abundance across the UK, and while sites in England and southern Scotland have comparable densities of these species, blue tits have only extended their range into northern Scotland during the second half of the 20<sup>th</sup> century <xref rid="pone.0053959-Gibbons1" ref-type="bibr">[59]</xref>. In 1988&#x02013;1991, blue tits were recorded at our two most northern sites (Beauly and Dunrobin) at considerably lower abundance than at sites further south (about 5% of southern densities; see <xref rid="pone.0053959-Gibbons1" ref-type="bibr">[59]</xref> for details). Separating two alternative explanations for variation in exploitation of alien galls &#x02013; variation in gall exploitation ability by <underline>in situ</underline> populations <underline>versus</underline> variation in density of the birds themselves, can be complex, as illustrated by the evolution since 1921 of the ability of blue tits to harvest the cream from foil-covered milk bottles in Britain. It was long believed that this behaviour spread through blue tit populations as a memic wave involving dispersal of expert birds and local mimicry (ringing data show that &#x0003e;10% of recaptured birds fly more than 20 km; <xref rid="pone.0053959-Wernhem1" ref-type="bibr">[60]</xref>). However, recent re-analysis of the mapping data suggests that the behaviour arose multiple times and that spread was more local <xref rid="pone.0053959-Lefebvre1" ref-type="bibr">[61]</xref>. Distinction of these alternatives for exploitation of alien galls will require detailed analyses on a large spatial scale <xref rid="pone.0053959-Schnrogge4" ref-type="bibr">[18]</xref> focussing on the behaviour and population structure of birds themselves.</p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title>The Possible Significance of Alien Galls as a Novel Food Source for Native Birds</title><p>Reproduction of northern temperate insectivorous birds, particularly tit species (<italic>Parus</italic> spp.), is timed to allow nest provisioning during the May peak availability of lepidopteran caterpillars on flushing oak leaves <xref rid="pone.0053959-NaefDaenzer2" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053959-vanNoordwijk1" ref-type="bibr">[62]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053959-Visser1" ref-type="bibr">[63]</xref>. The match between availability of insect prey and nest provisioning strongly influences offspring survival, offspring quality, and parental condition <xref rid="pone.0053959-NaefDaenzer2" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053959-vanNoordwijk1" ref-type="bibr">[62]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053959-Tremblay1" ref-type="bibr">[64]</xref>. Climate change influences the timing of each of tree budburst, caterpillar availability, and egg laying <xref rid="pone.0053959-Visser1" ref-type="bibr">[63]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053959-Both1" ref-type="bibr">[65]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0053959-Visser3" ref-type="bibr">[67]</xref>. While bird responses have tracked resource availability in some populations <xref rid="pone.0053959-McCleery1" ref-type="bibr">[68]</xref>, other bird populations are breeding before there is adequate caterpillar biomass, with significant fitness costs <xref rid="pone.0053959-Visser1" ref-type="bibr">[63]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053959-Thomas1" ref-type="bibr">[69]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053959-Visser4" ref-type="bibr">[70]</xref>. We hypothesise that these changes can only increase the significance for songbirds of foods available before the onset of breeding. These include alien <italic>Andricus</italic> galls on <italic>Q. cerris,</italic> which are increasingly widespread and abundant through much of northern and western Europe <xref rid="pone.0053959-Schnrogge2" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053959-Stone2" ref-type="bibr">[12]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053959-Schnrogge3" ref-type="bibr">[16]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053959-Schnrogge6" ref-type="bibr">[54]</xref>. We suggest that a useful aim for future research will be to quantify the nutritive contribution to native songbirds of these and other invading insects <xref rid="pone.0053959-Girardoz2" ref-type="bibr">[6]</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0053959-Grobler1" ref-type="bibr">[8]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053959-Nash1" ref-type="bibr">[71]</xref>, for example through analyses of foraging time allocated to alternative food sources, or of faecal remains <xref rid="pone.0053959-Jordan1" ref-type="bibr">[72]</xref>.</p><p>Bird exploitation of alien galls has broader implications for oak-associated animal communities. First, positive spatial density dependence in bird predation, combined with the high absolute mortalities observed here, could contribute to top-down regulation of invading gallwasp populations <xref rid="pone.0053959-Keane1" ref-type="bibr">[51]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053959-Hawkes1" ref-type="bibr">[52]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053959-Hassell1" ref-type="bibr">[73]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053959-Holmes2" ref-type="bibr">[74]</xref>. Second, bird predation could influence indirect interactions among native and invading gallwasp species. Many parasitoids attack both native and invading oak gallwasps <xref rid="pone.0053959-Schnrogge1" ref-type="bibr">[9]</xref>, and the invaders may have negative impacts on natives through apparent competition mediated by shared parasitoids <xref rid="pone.0053959-Cronin1" ref-type="bibr">[75]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053959-vanVeen1" ref-type="bibr">[76]</xref>. If birds open galls before parasitoid natural enemies have a chance to emerge, they kill these parasitoids and reduce the potential for apparent competition. However, if feeding on galls has a significant numerical impact on bird populations, then because they also feed on native gallwasps <xref rid="pone.0053959-Betts1" ref-type="bibr">[15]</xref> the birds themselves become agents of apparent competition between the alien gallwasps and other prey outwith gallwasp communities <xref rid="pone.0053959-Holmes2" ref-type="bibr">[74]</xref>. Such an impact may be more likely for the more abundant alien catkin galls on Turkey oak induced by <italic>Andricus grossulariae</italic> and <italic>A. quercuscalicis</italic>, present at densities of up to 1 million/tree during the May nesting season when the link between food availability and bird reproductive success is at its strongest <xref rid="pone.0053959-NaefDaenzer2" ref-type="bibr">[41]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053959-vanNoordwijk1" ref-type="bibr">[62]</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0053959-Visser1" ref-type="bibr">[63]</xref>. To these can be added the resources represented by recently established populations of other oak gallwasps in southern Britain <xref rid="pone.0053959-Schnrogge2" ref-type="bibr">[10]</xref>. These possibilities underline the value of further work on bird exploitation of invading gallwasps and other alien insects.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="s5"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0053959.s001"><label>Figure S1</label><caption><p>
<bold>Patterns in galling and predation rates with latitude through the U.K.</bold> There were no significant geographical trends from the south to the north of the country in A. galling rates (including a squared term for northerliness; F<sub>2,5</sub>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;5.06, p&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.063) or B. predation rates (F<sub>1,6</sub>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.69, p&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.44).</p><p>(TIFF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0053959.s001.tiff"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0053959.s002"><label>Table S1</label><caption><p>
<bold>Average gall densities (as galls per shoot) and predation rates by site and tree.</bold>
</p><p>(DOC)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0053959.s002.doc"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Shelley Hinsley for discussions concerning bird ecology and foraging behaviour.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0053959-Bartomeus1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Bartomeus</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vila</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Steffan-Dewenter</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Combined effects of <italic>Impatiens glandulifera</italic> invasion and landscape structure on native plant pollination</article-title>. <source>J Ecol</source>
<volume>98</volume>: <fpage>440</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>450</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Clavero1"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Clavero</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brotons</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pons</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sol</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name> (<year>2009</year>) <article-title>Prominent role of invasive species in avian biodiversity loss</article-title>. <source>Biol Conserv</source>
<volume>142</volume>: <fpage>2043</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2049</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Skorka1"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Skorka</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lenda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tryjanowski</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Invasive alien goldenrods negatively affect grassland bird communities in Eastern Europe</article-title>. <source>Biol Conserv</source>
<volume>143</volume>: <fpage>856</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>861</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Hails1"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Hails</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Crawley</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Spatial density dependence in populations of a cynipid gall- former <italic>Andricus quercuscalicis</italic>
</article-title>. <source>J Anim Ecol</source>
<volume>61</volume>: <fpage>567</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>584</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Girardoz1"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Girardoz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kenis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Quicke</surname><given-names>DLJ</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Recruitment of native parasitoids by an exotic leaf miner, <italic>Cameraria ohridella</italic>: host-parasitoid synchronization and influence of the environment</article-title>. <source>Agric For Entomol</source>
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>49</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>56</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Girardoz2"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Girardoz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Volter</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tomov</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Quicke</surname><given-names>DLJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kenis</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Variations in parasitism in sympatric populations of three invasive leaf miners</article-title>. <source>J Appl Entomol</source>
<volume>131</volume>: <fpage>603</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>612</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Grabenweger1"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Grabenweger</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kehrli</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zweimuller</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Augustin</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Avtzis</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2010</year>) <article-title>Temporal and spatial variations in the parasitoid complex of the horse chestnut leafminer during its invasion of Europe</article-title>. <source>Biol Invasions</source>
<volume>12</volume>: <fpage>2797</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2813</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Grobler1"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Grobler</surname><given-names>BC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>OT</given-names></name> (<year>2008</year>) <article-title>Response of native parasitoids to a range-expanding host</article-title>. <source>Ecol Entomol</source>
<volume>33</volume>: <fpage>453</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>463</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Schnrogge1"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Sch&#x000f6;nrogge</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Crawley</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Quantitative webs as a means of assessing the impact of alien insects</article-title>. <source>J Anim Ecol</source>
<volume>69</volume>: <fpage>841</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>868</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">29313993</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Schnrogge2"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Sch&#x000f6;nrogge</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Begg</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Melika</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Randle</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>Range expansion and enemy recruitment by eight alien gallwasp species in Britain</article-title>. <source>Ins Conserv Div</source>
<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>298</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>311</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Stone1"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sunnucks</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Genetic consequences of an invasion through a patchy environment - the cynipid gallwasp <italic>Andricus quercuscalicis</italic> (Hymenoptera, Cynipidae)</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol</source>
<volume>2</volume>: <fpage>251</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>268</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Stone2"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Challis</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Atkinson</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cs&#x000f3;ka</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hayward</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>The phylogeographical clade trade: tracing the impact of human-mediated dispersal on the colonization of northern Europe by the oak gallwasp <italic>Andricus kollari</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol</source>
<volume>16</volume>: <fpage>2768</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2781</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17594446</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Hails2"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Hails</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Askew</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Notton</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>The Parasitoids and inquilines of the agamic generation of <italic>Andricus quercuscalicis</italic> (Hym</article-title>. Cynipidae) in Britain. <source>The Entomologist</source>
<volume>109</volume>: <fpage>165</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>172</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Hayward1"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Hayward</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Comparative phylogeography across two trophic levels: the oak gall wasp <italic>Andricus kollari</italic> and its chalcid parasitoid <italic>Megastigmus stigmatizans</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Mol Ecol</source>
<volume>15</volume>: <fpage>479</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>489</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16448414</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Betts1"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Betts</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name> (<year>1955</year>) <article-title>The food of titmice in oak woodland</article-title>. <source>J Anim Ecol</source>
<volume>24</volume>: <fpage>282</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>323</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Schnrogge3"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Sch&#x000f6;nrogge</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Crawley</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Invaders on the move: parasitism in the sexual galls of four alien gall wasps in Britain (Hymenoptera : Cynipidae)</article-title>. <source>Proc Biol Sci</source>
<volume>265</volume>: <fpage>1643</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1650</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Jansson1"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Jansson</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ekman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vonbromssen</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name> (<year>1981</year>) <article-title>Winter mortality and food supply in tits <italic>Parus</italic> spp</article-title>. <source>Oikos</source>
<volume>37</volume>: <fpage>313</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>322</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Schnrogge4"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Sch&#x000f6;nrogge</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Crawley</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Complex life cycles in <italic>Andricus kollari</italic> (Hymenoptera, Cynipidae) and their impact on associated parasitoid and inquiline species</article-title>. <source>Oikos</source>
<volume>84</volume>: <fpage>293</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>301</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Gibb1"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Gibb</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name> (<year>1958</year>) <article-title>The feeding ecology of tits with notes on treecreeper and goldcrest</article-title>. <source>Ibis</source>
<volume>96</volume>: <fpage>513</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>543</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Gibb2"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Gibb</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name> (<year>1966</year>) <article-title>Tit predation and the abundance of <italic>Ernarmonia conicolana</italic> on Weeting Heath, Norfolk 1962&#x02013;63</article-title>. <source>J Anim Ecol</source>
<volume>35</volume>: <fpage>43</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>53</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Krebs1"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Krebs</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Erichsen</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Webber</surname><given-names>MI</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Charnov</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name> (<year>1977</year>) <article-title>Optimal prey selection in great tit (<italic>Parus major</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Anim Behav</source>
<volume>25</volume>: <fpage>30</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>38</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Holmes1"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schultz</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>Food availability for forest birds - effects of prey distribution and abundance of bird foraging</article-title>. <source>Can J Zool</source>
<volume>66</volume>: <fpage>720</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>728</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-NaefDaenzer1"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Naef-Daenzer B (2000) Patch time allocation and patch sampling by foraging great and blue tits. Anim Behav 59, 989&#x02013;999.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Suhonen1"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Suhonen</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Alatalo</surname><given-names>RV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hoglund</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Food resource distribution and the organization of the <italic>Parus</italic> guild in a spruce forest</article-title>. <source>Ornis Scandinavica</source>
<volume>23</volume>: <fpage>467</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>474</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Tscharntke1"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Tscharntke</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name> (<year>1992</year>) <article-title>Cascade effects among four trophic levels: bird predation on galls affects density-dependent parasitism</article-title>. <source>Ecology</source>
<volume>73</volume>: <fpage>1689</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1698</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Lambrechts1"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Lambrechts</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Caro</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Charmantier</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gross</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Galan</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Habitat quality as a predictor of spatial variation in blue tit reproductive performance: a multi-plot analysis in a heterogeneous landscape</article-title>. <source>Oecologia</source>
<volume>141</volume>: <fpage>555</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>561</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15549399</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Heads1"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Heads</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lawton</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name> (<year>1983</year>) <article-title>Tit predation on the holly leaf-miner - the effect of prickly leaves</article-title>. <source>Oikos</source>
<volume>41</volume>: <fpage>161</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>164</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Connor1"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Connor</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yoder</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>May</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>Density-related predation by the Carolina chickadee, <italic>Poecile carolinensis</italic>, on the leaf-mining moth, <italic>Cameraria hamadryadella</italic> at three spatial scales</article-title>. <source>Oikos</source>
<volume>87</volume>: <fpage>105</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>112</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Stewart1"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Stewart AJA, John EA, Hutchings MJ (2000) The world is heterogeneous: ecological consequences of living in a patchy environment. In: Hutchings MJ, John EA, Stewart AJA, editors. The ecological consequences of environmental heterogeneity pp. Oxford: Blackwell Science. 1&#x02013;8.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-McGeoch1"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>McGeoch</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>PW</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Scale-dependent mechanisms in the population dynamics of an insect herbivore</article-title>. <source>Oecologia</source>
<volume>144</volume>: <fpage>278</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>288</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15891834</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Veldtman1"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Veldtman</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McGeoch</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Spatially explicit analyses unveil density dependence</article-title>. <source>Proc Biol Sci</source>
<volume>271</volume>: <fpage>2439</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2444</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15590593</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Connor2"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Connor</surname><given-names>EF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Beck</surname><given-names>MW</given-names></name> (<year>1993</year>) <article-title>Density related mortality in <italic>Cameraria hamadryadella</italic> (Lepidoptera, Gracillariidae) at epidemic and endemic densities</article-title>. <source>Oikos</source>
<volume>66</volume>: <fpage>515</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>525</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Gawlik1"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Gawlik</surname><given-names>DE</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>The effects of prey availability on the numerical response of wading birds</article-title>. <source>Ecol Monogr</source>
<volume>72</volume>: <fpage>329</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>346</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Schnrogge5"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Sch&#x000f6;nrogge</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Crawley</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Parasitoid and inquiline attack in the galls of four alien, cynipid gall wasps: host switches and the effect on parasitoid sex ratios</article-title>. <source>Ecol Entomol</source>
<volume>25</volume>: <fpage>208</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>219</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-R1"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">R Development Core Team (2011) R: A language and environment for statistical computing. Vienna, Austria: R Foundation for Statistical Computing.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Crawley1"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Crawley MJ (2008) The R Book. Chichester, UK: Wiley &#x00026; Sons.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Logan1"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Logan M (2010) Biostatistical Design and Analysis using R. Chichester, UK: Wiley &#x00026; Blackwell.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Nakagawa1"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Nakagawa</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>A farewell to Bonferroni: the problems of low statistical power and publication bias</article-title>. <source>Behav Ecol</source>
<volume>15</volume>: <fpage>1044</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1045</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Quinn1"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Quinn GP, Keough MJ (2002) Experimental Design and Data Analysis for Biologists. Cambridge, UK: Cambridge University Press.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Itamies1"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Itamies</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ojanen</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1977</year>) <article-title>Autumn predation of <italic>Parus major</italic> and <italic>Parus montanus</italic> upon 2 leaf-mining species of <italic>Lithocolletis</italic> (Lepidoptera, Lithocollidae)</article-title>. <source>Ann Zool Fennici</source>
<volume>14</volume>: <fpage>235</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>241</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-NaefDaenzer2"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Naef-Daenzer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name> (<year>1999</year>) <article-title>The foraging performance of great and blue tits (<italic>Parus major</italic> and <italic>P. caerulens</italic>) in relation to caterpillar development, and its consequences for nestling growth and fledging weight</article-title>. <source>J Anim Ecol</source>
<volume>68</volume>: <fpage>708</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>718</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-NaefDaenzer3"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Naef-Daenzer</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nager</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Keller</surname><given-names>LF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Naef-Daenzer</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Are hatching delays a cost or a benefit for great tit <italic>Parus major</italic> parents?</article-title>
<source>Ardea</source>
<volume>92</volume>: <fpage>229</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>237</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Askew1"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Askew</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name> (<year>1962</year>) <article-title>The distribution of galls of <italic>Neuroterus</italic> (Hym</article-title>. Cynipidae) on oak. <source>J Anim Ecol</source>
<volume>31</volume>: <fpage>439</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>455</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Crawley2"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Crawley</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Akhteruzzaman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name> (<year>1988</year>) <article-title>Individual variation in the phenology of oak trees and its consequences for herbivorous insects</article-title>. <source>Funct Ecol</source>
<volume>2</volume>: <fpage>409</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>415</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Egan1"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Egan</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ott</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Host plant quality and local adaptation determine the distribution of a gall-forming herbivore</article-title>. <source>Ecology</source>
<volume>88</volume>: <fpage>2868</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2879</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18051656</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Eliason1"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Eliason</surname><given-names>EA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Potter</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name> (<year>2000</year>) <article-title>Budburst phenology, plant vigor, and host genotype effects on the leaf-galling generation of <italic>Callirhytis cornigera</italic> (Hymenoptera: Cynipidae) on pin oak</article-title>. <source>Environ Entomol</source>
<volume>29</volume>: <fpage>1199</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1207</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Ito1"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Ito</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ozaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Response of a gall wasp community to genetic variation in the host plant <italic>Quercus crispula</italic>: a test using half-sib families</article-title>. <source>Acta Oecol</source>
<volume>27</volume>: <fpage>17</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>24</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Smith1"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bailey</surname><given-names>JK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Shuster</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Whitham</surname><given-names>TG</given-names></name> (<year>2011</year>) <article-title>A geographic mosaic of trophic interactions and selection: trees, aphids and birds</article-title>. <source>J Evol Biol</source>
<volume>24</volume>: <fpage>422</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>429</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21091573</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Walker1"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Leather</surname><given-names>SR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Crawley</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Differential rates of invasion in three related alien oak gall wasps (Cynipidae: Hymenoptera)</article-title>. <source><italic>Diversity and Distributions</italic></source>
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>335</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>349</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Askew2"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Askew</surname><given-names>RR</given-names></name> (<year>1982</year>) <article-title>
<italic>Andricus lignicola</italic> (Hartig) (Hym., Cynipidae), another gall- wasp with an expanding British Distribution</article-title>. <source>Entomologist&#x02019;s Monthly Magazine</source>
<volume>118</volume>: <fpage>116</fpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Keane1"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Keane</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Crawley</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>2002</year>) <article-title>Exotic plant invasions and the enemy release hypothesis</article-title>. <source>Trends Ecol Evol</source>
<volume>17</volume>: <fpage>164</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>170</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Hawkes1"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Hawkes</surname><given-names>CV</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Are invaders moving targets? The generality and persistence of advantages in size, reproduction, and enemy release in invasive plant species with time since introduction</article-title>. <source>Am Nat</source>
<volume>170</volume>: <fpage>832</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>843</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18171166</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Collins1"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Collins</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Crawley</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McGavin</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name> (<year>1983</year>) <article-title>Survivership of the sexual and agamic generations of <italic>Andricus quercuscalicis</italic> on <italic>Quercus cerris</italic> and <italic>Quercus robur</italic>
</article-title>. <source>Ecol Entomol</source>
<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>133</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>138</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Schnrogge6"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Sch&#x000f6;nrogge</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Crawley</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Spatial and temporal variation in guild structure - parasitoids and inquilines of <italic>Andricus quercuscalicis</italic> (Hymenoptera, Cynipidae) in its native and alien ranges</article-title>. <source>Oikos</source>
<volume>72</volume>: <fpage>51</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>60</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Schnrogge7"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Sch&#x000f6;nrogge</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Crawley</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>1996a</year>) <article-title>Abundance patterns and species richness of the parasitoids of inquilines of the gall-former in an alien cynipid gall: <italic>Andricus quercuscalicis</italic> (Hymenoptera: Cynipidae)</article-title>. <source>Oikos</source>
<volume>77</volume>: <fpage>507</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>518</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Schnrogge8"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Sch&#x000f6;nrogge</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Stone</surname><given-names>GN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Crawley</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name> (<year>1996b</year>) <article-title>Alien herbivores and native parasitoids: Rapid development of guild structure in an invading gall wasp <italic>Andricus quercuscalicis</italic> (Hymenoptera: Cynipidae)</article-title>. <source>Ecol Entomol</source>
<volume>21</volume>: <fpage>71</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>80</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Sherry1"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Sherry</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Galef</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name> (<year>1984</year>) <article-title>Cultural transmission without imitation - milk bottle opening by birds</article-title>. <source>Anim Behav</source>
<volume>32</volume>: <fpage>937</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>938</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Sherry2"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Sherry</surname><given-names>DF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Galef</surname><given-names>BG</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Social learning without imitation - more about milk bottle opening by birds</article-title>. <source>Anim Behav</source>
<volume>40</volume>: <fpage>987</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>989</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Gibbons1"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Gibbons DW, Reid JB, Chapman RA (1993) The New Atlas of Breeding Birds in Britain and Ireland. London, U.K.: T and AD Poyser.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Wernhem1"><label>60</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Wernhem C, Toms M, Marchant J, Clarke J, Siriwardena G, <etal>et al</etal>.. (2002) The migration atlas: movements of the birds of Britain and Ireland. London: T and AD Poyser. 900p.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Lefebvre1"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Lefebvre</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>The opening of milk bottles by birds - evidence for accelerating learning rates, but against the wave-of-advance model of cultural transmission</article-title>. <source>Behav Proc</source>
<volume>34</volume>: <fpage>43</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>53</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-vanNoordwijk1"><label>62</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>van Noordwijk</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McCleery</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Perrins</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name> (<year>1995</year>) <article-title>Selection for the timing of Great Tit breeding in relation to caterpillar growth and temperature</article-title>. <source>J Anim Ecol</source>
<volume>64</volume>: <fpage>451</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>458</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Visser1"><label>63</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Visser</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Both</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lambrechts</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Global climate change leads to mistimed avian reproduction</article-title>. <source>Adv Ecol Res</source>
<volume>15</volume>: <fpage>89</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>110</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Tremblay1"><label>64</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Tremblay I, Thomas DW, Lambrechts MM, Blondel J, Perret P (2003) Variation in blue tit breeding performance across gradients in habitat richness. Ecology 84, 3033&#x02013;3043.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Both1"><label>65</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Both</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Artemyev</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Blaauw</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cowie</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dekhuijzen</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2004</year>) <article-title>Large-scale geographical variation confirms that climate change causes birds to lay earlier</article-title>. <source>Proc Biol Sci</source>
<volume>271</volume>: <fpage>1657</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1662</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15306284</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Visser2"><label>66</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Visser</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Holleman</surname><given-names>LJM</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Warmer springs disrupt the synchrony of oak and winter moth phenology</article-title>. <source>Proc Biol Sci</source>
<volume>268</volume>: <fpage>289</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>294</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11217900</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Visser3"><label>67</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Visser</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Holleman</surname><given-names>LJM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gienapp</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Shifts in caterpillar biomass phenology due to climate change and its impact on the breeding biology of an insectivorous bird</article-title>. <source>Oecologia</source>
<volume>147</volume>: <fpage>164</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>172</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16328547</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-McCleery1"><label>68</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>McCleery</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Perrins</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name> (<year>1998</year>) <article-title>Temperature and egg-laying trends</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>391</volume>: <fpage>30</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>31</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Thomas1"><label>69</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Blondel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Perret</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lambrechts</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Speakman</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name> (<year>2001</year>) <article-title>Energetic and fitness costs of mismatching resource supply and demand in seasonally breeding birds</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>291</volume>: <fpage>2598</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2600</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11283370</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Visser4"><label>70</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Visser</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Adriaensen</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>van Balen</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Blondel</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dhondt</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal> (<year>2003</year>) <article-title>Variable responses to large-scale climate change in European <italic>Parus</italic> populations</article-title>. <source>Proc Biol Sci</source>
<volume>270</volume>: <fpage>367</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>372</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12639315</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Nash1"><label>71</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Nash</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Agassiz</surname><given-names>DJL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Godfray</surname><given-names>HCJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lawton</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name> (<year>1995a</year>) <article-title>The pattern of spread of invading species - 2 leaf-mining moths colonizing Great Britain</article-title>. <source>J Anim Ecol</source>
<volume>64</volume>: <fpage>225</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>233</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Jordan1"><label>72</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Jordan</surname><given-names>MJR</given-names></name> (<year>2005</year>) <article-title>Dietary analysis for mammals and birds: a review of field techniques and animal-management applications</article-title>. <source>Ann Acad Reg Sci Upsal</source>
<volume>39</volume>: <fpage>108</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>116</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Hassell1"><label>73</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Hassell</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pacala</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Heterogeneity and the Dynamics of Host Parasitoid Interactions</article-title>. <source>Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci</source>
<volume>330</volume>: <fpage>203</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>220</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Holmes2"><label>74</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Holmes</surname><given-names>RT</given-names></name> (<year>1990</year>) <article-title>Ecological and evolutionary impacts of bird predation on forest insects: an overview</article-title>. <source>Stud Avian Biol</source>
<volume>13</volume>: <fpage>6</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>13</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-Cronin1"><label>75</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>Cronin</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name> (<year>2007</year>) <article-title>Shared parasitoids in a metacommunity: Indirect interactions inhibit herbivore membership in local communities</article-title>. <source>Ecology</source>
<volume>88</volume>: <fpage>2977</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2990</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18229833</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0053959-vanVeen1"><label>76</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
<name><surname>van Veen</surname><given-names>FJF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Godfray</surname><given-names>HCJ</given-names></name> (<year>2006</year>) <article-title>Apparent competition, quantitative food webs, and the structure of phytophagous insect communities</article-title>. <source>Ann Rev Entomol</source>
<volume>51</volume>: <fpage>187</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>208</lpage>.<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16332209</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>