<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par23" class="p">This research builds on national level work on climate change adaptation and health governance (e.g. [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">9</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" class="xref">46</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47" class="xref">47</xref>, 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48" class="xref">48</xref>]), and qualitatively assesses two distinct models of regional support for CCA and health; 1.) the ADB’s project-based model, and 2.) the APRF’s governance model. Initial data collection consisted of 22 in-depth, semi-structured interviews, which were conducted over an 18 month period between September 2015 and February 2017. A 14 question interview guide was approved under the ethics approval for this research, and this was used to structure interviews. Interviews were conducted in English and ranged in length from 25 min to 105 min, with an average length of 52 min. Nineteen interviewees were male, and 3 were female, indicating that regional level governance of climate change and health is a male dominated area. Interviewees represented 11 organisations at national and regional levels, as well as representing three countries in addition to the ROs. Interviewees were given a participant information sheet detailing the research objectives and a number to contact for questions or concerns. Interviewees provided the researcher with either written or recorded consent for the interview to be recorded and used for this research, and were advised that they need only answer questions they were comfortable with. Transcripts were provided to interviewees for their comment and approval. Following this, using FAROCCCA as an analytical tool, interview data was triangulated against an analysis of policy documents, academic publications and grey literature such as annual and financial reports, evaluation documents and strategic plans. Document analysis and interviews focussed on current directions and trends, however it also included reference to charter documents dating back to 1994 and 2007 for the ADB and APRF respectively. The most recent document analysed was published in 2018.
</p>
