<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Collaborations are rarely continued indefinitely; rather they are dependent on current sources of funding and research interests. New authors are continually added to the potential pool of collaborators while others retire or disappear from the academic community. Therefore, the active network is limited to the real or possible collaborations at any given time (Tomassini and Luthi 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" class="xref">2007</xref>). The focus of this study was on how the active network of ongoing collaborations changed over time, capturing the dynamic nature of the interactions. Previous work has suggested that the active network of scientific collaboration has a sliding time frame of 3–4 years, with longer timeframes likely confounded by the inclusion of collaborations which are no longer active (Tomassini and Luthi 
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" class="xref">2007</xref>). A sliding time-window of 3 years was therefore chosen for this analysis. Co-authorship links added to the network for each time step will then represent either the establishment of a new collaboration or the re-establishment of a former collaboration which has lain dormant for a period of time. The first time window was 2008–2010, well before the start of the MACSUR knowledge hub. The final two time windows, 2011–2013 and 2012–2014, encompass the start and first full active phase of MACSUR. For each time window, the database of authors and papers was re-formatted into a co-occurrence matrix, where a co-occurrence in this instance is the co-authorship of a paper. Based on these matrices, network objects were created for further analysis. Within these networks, individual authors are nodes, and the edges between them indicate connection by co-authorship. Each network can be analysed by calculating a number of parameters, including centrality, clustering coefficient, modularity and the size of the largest component. These parameters are defined as follows:
</p>
