<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p content-type="flushleft" class="p">A reduction of forest and expansion of steppe biomes occurred during all stadials (
 <xref rid="r12" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>
 <xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref"/>
 <xref rid="r14" ref-type="bibr" class="xref"/>–
 <xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">21</xref>), but climate records between the Atlantic and the Black Sea show a spatially heterogeneous response to DO cycles (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" class="xref">Fig. 2</xref>). GS13-H5 is apparent in the TC speleothem δ
 <sup class="sup">18</sup>O record but unlike in the Atlantic domain, its amplitude is small compared with subsequent stadials. Southern Black Sea IRDc data (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" class="xref">Fig. 1</xref>) indicate less sea ice than during subsequent stadials despite apparent colder annual sea surface temperature (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" class="xref">Fig. 2</xref>). This suggests a different seasonality with less severe winters. Thus, extreme cold was unlikely in East-Central Europe. The extreme aridity apparent in the Aegean region (
 <xref rid="r13" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">13</xref>) may not have been as severe in the Balkan and Black Sea region (
 <xref rid="r15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r16" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>). GS12, from 43.4–44.3 ka
 <sub class="sub">GICC05</sub> or 43.3–44.0 ka
 <sub class="sub">U-Th</sub> (AC), is a very prominent stadial in Greenland and Central Europe (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" class="xref">Fig. 2</xref>), where permafrost changed the upper Danube lowland cold steppe into a tundra (see above). Malacological data from Willendorf II and the Eifel maar dust record suggests dryer conditions also in Western and Central Europe (
 <xref rid="r22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r24" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">24</xref>) (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" class="xref">Fig. 2</xref>). A cooling step likely occurred over Western Europe, supported by evidence of deep frost in the loess/paleosol record of northern France at ∼43–44 ka cal BP (
 <xref rid="r39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>). However, this stadial is less prominent in the Atlantic record (
 <xref rid="r17" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>). GS11 is present in all continental records, but not as pronounced as GS12. A common cooling trend superimposed over DO cycles 12–9 is apparent in all records (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" class="xref">Fig. 2</xref>). GS10—from 40.1–40.9 ka
 <sub class="sub">GICC05</sub> and 39.7–40.7 ka
 <sub class="sub">U-Th</sub> (TC)—is a very prominent stadial over continental Europe, coeval with another cooling step in Western Europe (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" class="xref">Fig. 2</xref>), but also a reduction in moisture and reduced speleothem growth (
 <xref rid="r25" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">25</xref>). The first occurrence of loess in the Willendorf II profile (C7-2) around that time (
 <xref rid="r22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>) and another strong dust peak in the Eifel maar record suggest stronger aridity than during GS12. Although present in all continental records, this stadial is unremarkable in the Atlantic and in the Black Sea (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" class="xref">Fig. 2</xref>). However, annual sea surface temperature and winter coastal ice abundance in the Black Sea show conflicting results for GS10, which could again indicate a seasonality change. GS9-H4 is a long-lasting stadial that was less prominent in the Central European record but coeval with significant cooling and aridity in Western Europe (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" class="xref">Fig. 2</xref>). Over the Atlantic and the Black Sea, GS9-H4 is a much more significant stadial. Subsequent GI8 is as warm as GI12 in Central Europe and the Black Sea region, with soil formation in the Danube region and East Carpathians (
 <xref rid="r19" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">19</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r22" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">22</xref>), but colder in Western Europe and the Atlantic. Dust deposition in the Eifel maar records was also high during GI8, unlike GI13. The causes to this regionally heterogeneous response to DO climate cycles remain uncertain, but a variable influence of the Siberian high has been suggested (
 <xref rid="r20" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">20</xref>).
</p>
