<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Our analogue-based method only considers climate-induced changes in yield, but increased [CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>] has been found to directly enhance photosynthesis in C3 crops, whilst also promoting greater water use efficiency across all higher plants
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25" class="xref">25</xref>. These [CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>] effects may offset some of the strong negative effects of climate change on attainable yields. A meta-analysis of field experiments suggests a yield enhancement of ca. 8% for non-water-stressed C3 crops for a doubling of [CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>] from pre-industrial levels, although this number disguises huge variability in responses
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b26" class="xref">26</xref>. For an RCP 8.5 scenario this would imply a yield increment due to [CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>] of +6% by 2050, and +18% by 2100, relative to 2000, although the response may be larger in some water-limited regions. Changes of this magnitude only marginally reduce the large vulnerable areas of wheat and rice by mid-century, although by end-of-century they would reduce substantially vulnerable areas of wheat and rice in East Asia (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Supplementary Fig. 15</xref>). Attainable yields of maize, a C4 crop, are not expected to be affected by increased [CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>], although actual yields of all crops may be substantially enhanced in areas where water stress is limiting growth
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b25" class="xref">25</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b27" class="xref">27</xref>. Simulations from the ISI-MIP ensemble show enhancements of wheat and rice yield due to CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> fertilization ranging from 4 to 80% (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Supplementary Table 3</xref>), illustrating the huge uncertainty in projections of CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> fertilization, however, direct comparison is complicated by the differing assumptions on nutrient availability and climate adaptation between the models (see 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Supplementary Note 3</xref> and 
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Supplementary Figs 16 and 17</xref>).
</p>
