<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The analogue method employed here has a number of limitations and uncertainties. The approach assumes that management practices for maximizing yield can be directly transferred between grid-cells. In most cases we expect this to be true, as socio-economic limitations do not apply in the context of attainable yields. However, there may be some circumstances where this concept fails due to specificity of managements to terrain or soil types. In areas with low precipitation, the method will tend towards more positive projections if analogues are drawn from grid cells in which sources of irrigation water are disconnected from local precipitation, that is, regions with large fossil groundwater abstractions or supplied by large rivers. These projected yields remain attainable, but water resources will not allow them to be reached on a large scale unless the grid cell for which yields are being projected also has access to such a water resource. We find no clear evidence of our projections for current cropland area being notably influenced by this effect, but if they were the effect would be to make our conclusions of vulnerability more conservative. It is very relevant, however, for projections of suitable future cropland area. As a result, we have marked such areas in 
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f4" class="xref">Fig. 4</xref>, and excluded them from the other calculations in this analysis (Methods section). Importantly, our projected changes in attainable yields must not be taken as being indicative of changes in rainfed yields in regions where irrigation water is potentially available, but is not utilized on socio-economic grounds; the relation between attainable and rainfed yields is non-linear. Although we mask fundamentally unsuitable soils (Methods section), we do not include variations in soil quality across current cropland area in our analogues. Soil is an important determinant of crop productivity, and thus some of the increases in yields suggested by our method may be limited by poor soil quality. There is a particularly high uncertainty in assessing the importance of soil quality in high northern latitudes, where soil core data are very scarce
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b28" class="xref">28</xref>. Here there is a risk that the analogue method tends to overestimate attainable yields on unimproved soils. We suggest, however, that because properties such as soil nutrient content, organic carbon and pH can be remediated through amendments and management, soil quality is generally a limitation on actual, rather than on attainable, yields. Our conclusions are robust to the choice of analogue variables, with simulations including killing degree days (degree-days above a crop-specific threshold for heat damage) and radiation, excluding precipitation, or limiting to current growing seasons, giving extraordinarily consistent results for yields, despite some variation in the location of the analogue climates (
 <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="S1" class="xref">Supplementary Note 2</xref>).
</p>
