<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Even with the assumption of adaptation within current technology inherent in our approach, climate change is projected to decrease production potential, and therefore likely actual production, from major cereal crops across the tropics and much mid-latitude cropland already by the middle of the 21st century. Our results thus provide an independent line of evidence qualitatively supporting, and thereby increasing confidence in, projections from crop models. In the absence of successfully breeding new crop cultivars to suit warmer climates, attempts to intensify crop production across much of existing cropland are likely to be frustrated by climate change, requiring compensation by other means. We conclude that much more efficient and sustainable production increases are likely to be achieved by altering crop choice and the location of cropland itself, to best take advantage of changes in maximum-attainable yields resulting from climate change. However, we caution that socio-economic constraints, along with any unmanageable aspects of local terrain and soil, will influence whether the climatic potential calculated here can be realised; detailed local-scale assessments will thus be necessary to assess this. Such land-use alterations do not necessarily imply extensification (that is, increasing the area under cultivation). However, changing the distribution of agricultural area might in some regions lead to dramatic changes in land use that will face political, social and cultural impediments if, for instance, some regions need to become net food importers or to change traditional diets. A drastic shift in distribution of cropland would likely also have very serious consequences for other ecosystem services such as carbon storage provided by non-agricultural lands where such a reconfiguration may take place
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b29" class="xref">29</xref>, although these consequences might be mitigated by the regeneration of areas of abandoned cropland in the long-term. Rather than being able to rely principally on continued intensification on existing croplands, as is often a major assumption of economic models
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b13" class="xref">13</xref>
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="b14" class="xref">14</xref>, the need to increase crop production is therefore likely to present a major land-use, trade and economic dilemma over the coming decades. Furthermore, for achieving attainable yields projected by the analogue approach, our results imply the need to transfer technologies and knowledge over large distances, demonstrating that there is yet another important dimension in the agricultural challenge that requires a global perspective; not only trade and markets, but also production knowledge needs to be globalized.
</p>
