<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Correlative distribution models assume that species niches do not change over time or space. This assumption is known to be violated by IAS which have been shown to occupy different niches in their invaded range (Broennimann et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34098-bib-0018" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>; but see also Petitpierre et al., 
 <xref rid="ece34098-bib-0064" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2012</xref>) or to shift their realized niche (Escobar, Qiao, Phelps, Wagner, &amp; Larkin, 
 <xref rid="ece34098-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>) because of altered biotic interactions (e.g., loss of major competitors) or evolutionary changes (Jeschke &amp; Strayer, 
 <xref rid="ece34098-bib-0038" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>; Lavergne, Mouquet, Thuiller, &amp; Ronce, 
 <xref rid="ece34098-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2010</xref>; Moran &amp; Alexander, 
 <xref rid="ece34098-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2014</xref>). This challenge is even more problematic in the case of predicting future IAS distributions, as climate change may create novel conditions (Williams, Jackson, &amp; Kutzbach, 
 <xref rid="ece34098-bib-0088" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2007</xref>) (see below) and lead to novel biotic interactions which have not been encountered by the species in their eco‐evolutionary history (Saul &amp; Jeschke, 
 <xref rid="ece34098-bib-0070" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>). Correlative distribution models alone may be insufficient to overcome this challenge, and more complex models including biotic interactions are necessary (Blois, Zarnetske, Fitzpatrick, &amp; Finnegan, 
 <xref rid="ece34098-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2013</xref>; Jeschke &amp; Strayer, 
 <xref rid="ece34098-bib-0038" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2008</xref>). A promising way forward to reach this objective will be to combine propagule pressure analysis, correlative approaches (Fletcher, Gillingham, Britton, Blanchet, &amp; Gozlan, 
 <xref rid="ece34098-bib-0029" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2016</xref>), and modeling species co‐occurrences of associated species (Morelli &amp; Tryjanowski, 
 <xref rid="ece34098-bib-0060" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2015</xref>; or to constrain the composition of species assemblages, Guisan &amp; Rahbek, 
 <xref rid="ece34098-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" class="xref">2011</xref>) to provide inference about likely interspecific effects in ecosystems.
</p>
