<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">For most climate factors included in the assessment, exposure was estimated from an ensemble of global climate models used in the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change Assessment Report 5 (IPCC AR5). As described above, the choice of climate factors to use in this assessment was impacted by the resolution of the models used for projections. The ocean resolution of these models is too course (0.5–1.0° latitude, 1.0–1.5° longitude) to allow mesoscale eddies, sub-mesoscale eddies, fronts, and regional scale bathymetry and circulation [
 <xref rid="pone.0146756.ref067" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">67</xref>]. The Representative Concentration Pathway 8.5 (RCP 8.5) was used, which represents a “business-as-usual” scenario assuming little to no stabilization of greenhouse gas emissions by 2100 [
 <xref rid="pone.0146756.ref068" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">68</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0146756.ref069" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">69</xref>]. The 2006–2055 period was chosen for projections because this represents the coming decades, which are of more relevance to living marine resource management than the end of the century. The 50 year average focuses the projections on the forced climate change signal, but also includes the multi-decadal variability signal [
 <xref rid="pone.0146756.ref017" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">17</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0146756.ref036" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">36</xref>]. The exposures to ocean surface temperature (upper 10 m), surface air temperature, ocean surface salinity (upper 10 m), and precipitation were estimated from an ensemble of 25–35 global climate models. Exposure to ocean acidification was estimated from an ensemble of 11 earth system models. These ensembles were defined as those models available on the Earth System Grid Federation Portal (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pcmdi9.llnl.gov/esgf-web-fe/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://pcmdi9.llnl.gov/esgf-web-fe/</ext-link>) in autumn 2013 that simulated a given parameter over the time period of interest.
</p>
