<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Background</div>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Improving performance and initiating broad scale changes at the healthcare organisational level often involve multiple or a combination of interventions that may be complex and multi-faceted and will require careful coordination at all levels, including specific contextual adaptations to the implementation [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">1</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2</a>]. In Malaysia, the non-communicable disease (NCD) burden is growing at a very alarming rate, indicating the need for improvements in the healthcare system, especially at the primary healthcare level [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" href="#CR3">3</a>]. The Ministry of Health (MOH) embarked on a complex intervention at the primary healthcare setting, dubbed the Enhanced Primary Healthcare (EnPHC) initiative, which aimed at (1) delivering more effective and efficient healthcare services to NCD patients, and (2) improving patient experience and (3) health outcomes over a period of time [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The proposed EnPHC’s intervention components include establishment of community interventions through fostering population enrolment and population risk profiling for early NCD risk management and case detection, deployment of a two-tiered triaging system in primary healthcare clinics, introduction of the care coordinator role to improve the community engagement mechanisms in facilitating clinic appointments, treatment and medication, improvements in the NCD care management process and improvisations in the communication process for intra-clinic referrals and referrals between clinics and hospitals [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>].
 </p>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Before any new intervention is introduced, addressing organisational readiness and healthcare providers’ (HCPs) receptiveness to change is essential; it is a critical precursor for successful implementation of complex changes in a healthcare setting [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>]. ‘Readiness for change’ (hereafter referred to as readiness) is a state of being both psychologically and behaviourally prepared to take action [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>] to move into a new and different state [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>]. ‘Openness to change’ (hereafter referred to as openness and is terminologically interchangeable with receptiveness) is willingness to accept change and have positive views of changes [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" href="#CR8">8</a>] in which personal resilience, information about changes, self-efficacy for coping with changes and participation in the change decision process were predictive of higher employee openness. The major distinction between readiness and openness is the knowledge about intended change outcome, which acts as a vital component in openness compared to readiness [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">9</a>]. Thus, both organisational readiness and individual employees’ openness are important determinants of implementation success.
 </p>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Consolidated Framework of Implementation Research (CFIR) was selected for this study because it can be used flexibly across a wide range of applications at any implementation phase (pre, during, post) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" href="#CR10">10</a>]. The meta-theoretical CFIR was developed based on a comprehensive review of literatures and models. It integrated multiple frameworks into one consolidated framework and comprised of influential pre-specified factors that are relevant to implementation studies [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>]. The four major domains of CFIR—intervention characteristics, outer setting, inner setting and characteristics of individuals [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">13</a>] were used to practically guide the assessment of organisational readiness and employee openness, including both facilitators and barriers, as well as to facilitate the strategies for development of intervention materials and manage issues related to implementation readiness [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>, 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>]. CFIR can be employed to assess pre-intervention or implementation information such as perceptions of implementers.
 </p>
 <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study aimed to explore receptiveness to change among primary HCPs and other challenges at primary healthcare clinics prior to implementation of EnPHC. Data presented here were collected as part of a larger process evaluation of a complex intervention study. The findings will be used to improve the pre-designed intervention before it is scaled up nationwide.</p>
</sec>
