<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec12" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Individual characteristics</div>
 <p id="Par42" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Under the ‘Individual Characteristics’ domain, all five constructs were found to have a positive presence that could be facilitators. Implementers’ ‘Knowledge and Belief about the Implementation’ is a crucial construct because previous study reported change created uncertainties and fear of the impending unknown [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">7</a>] under individual characteristics. However, in this study, the HCPs expressed their expectation of improved overall health outcomes among patients with the proposed new intervention for NCD management. The ‘Self-efficacy’ construct was another facilitator as HCPs concurred that staff capability to execute tasks for NCD management was crucial since they are the key personnel who will be involved directly with the proposed intervention.
 </p>
 <p id="Par43" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">‘Individual Stage of Change’ depicts the manner in which HCPs embrace and accept new ideas for improvement, which denotes readiness. Ready HCPs are often open to new ideas, which they view as key to improve existing programmes. This type of mental readiness allows acceptance of new or untested methods to be easily implemented versus a non-ready HCP who would openly resist changes. Meanwhile, HCPs identified ‘Individual Identification with Organisation’ as their commitment to implementing MOH-driven programmes. One participant declared that any task assigned is a responsibility that must be executed despite the time needed to figure things out.</p>
 <p id="Par44" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Other personal attributes such as motivation and individual positive attitudes contributed towards acceptance of previously implemented programmes. Some HCPs strongly believed the best care for patients must be provided for their good health outcomes. This reflected their professionalism and value, which could be facilitators for implementing new programmes or interventions.</p>
</sec>
