<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec11" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Inner setting</div>
 <p id="Par32" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This domain consisted of five constructs with nine sub-constructs within the organisational context. Several barriers and facilitators were raised within the primary healthcare clinics’ context that covered all five constructs. Under the construct of Structural ‘Characteristic’, the constraint of clinic physical space was a concern that the HCPs raised. Facility upgrade was deemed crucial, as well as clinic resources, which largely have remained similar to when the clinic was first set up. This would prove challenging especially with the ever-increasing patient attendance that which is due to local population growth around the clinic. Resource issues will be elaborated within the sub-construct of ‘Available Resources’ under the ‘Readiness for Implementation’ construct. Good networking and communication within the clinic facilitates internal information relay regarding clarifications and issues requiring attention. HCPs in clinics that initiated morning briefings felt that the routine communication method boosts their morale and spirit to work.</p>
 <p id="Par33" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">‘Culture’ as a construct within inner setting is an important component in assessing organisational receptiveness and openness to new intervention. HCPs expressed that the culture of teamwork and helping one another had been established within the clinic. HCPs also shared that the sense of belonging to the clinic and professionalism were critical foundations for a strong internal teamwork. However, they were concerned that certain clinics have the culture of working in silos. It does not happen in all clinics, but they think that the concern warrants ministerial-level attention before it gets worse.</p>
 <p id="Par34" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Under the ‘Implementation Climate’ construct, issues on barriers and facilitators were identified under five sub-constructs: ‘Tension to Change’, ‘Compatibility’, ‘Relative Priority’, ‘Organisation Incentives and Rewards’, and ‘Learning Climate’.</p>
 <p id="Par35" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The ‘Tension for Change’ sub-construct assessed the stakeholders’ perception of the current situation as intolerable or needing change [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>]. HCPs reflected on issues that triggered change and the clinics’ current situation. However, certain clinics viewed the patient influx as an opportunity for early detection and screenings, which may be a facilitator for enhancing NCD care management. The increasing clinic attendance also raised concerns among the doctors, who felt less time was spent with patients so as to not cause longer waiting times for patients-in-queue, causing comprehensive assessment and health education to be delivered inadequately. Regarding issues of unstandardised and disorganised workflow, HCPs shared their perception of the issues, their suggestions and attempted solutions in previous programme implementations. However, HCPs identified aspects in the current setting that demanded change, required strengthening or were perceived as intolerable. With regards to documentation strengthening, data entry for routine monthly returns has been done manually instead of computerised, which led to ‘Tension for Change’.
 </p>
 <p id="Par36" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition, the challenges under the ‘Compatibility’ construct were raised. Referrals received from other MOH community screening programmes such as KOSPEN facilitated the clinics’ community screening activity. It was noted that there were no proper patient tracking mechanism in place after patients have been screened for NCD, which hinders efforts to establish person-centred care. Those who have been identified with medium and high risk by the screening activities may default clinic appointments for further management, hence, the lack of tracking mechanism results in the at-risk population to be left untreated until they actually require treatment. Hence, HCPs perceived proper documentation and establishment of a robust tracking mechanism as crucial to achieve person-centred care.</p>
 <p id="Par37" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Under the ‘Relative Priority’ construct, the practice of family doctor concept was found to be a positive asset that could facilitate the proposed EnPHC initiative. This concept established one doctor and a team attending to the same patient to ensure care continuity, allowing them to have a better understanding of their patients’ health status and treatment.</p>
 <p id="Par38" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A conducive ‘Learning Climate’ (a sub-construct under the ‘Implementation Climate’ construct) within the clinic encouraged staff to contribute ideas and opinions for service delivery improvements. Many HCPs expressed this view during the exploration on readiness. Acknowledgement of the ideas and opinions, and establishing avenues for discussion by the leader were seen as factors that create positive clinic environment in problem-solving activities.</p>
 <p id="Par39" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">‘Readiness for Implementation’ is another construct within the ‘Inner Setting’ domain that was defined as immediate indicators of organisational commitment to implement a new intervention. One of its sub-constructs is ‘Leadership Engagement’, which emphasise the leader’s role in an organisation. Approachable and dedicated leaders were viewed as catalysts for a successful intervention in which they are able to comprehend the programmes’ goals and successfully relay information to their staff. In other words, clinic staffs perceived that leadership’s willingness to participate and solve daily clinic issues established a strong support system within the clinic, consequently promoting staffs’ openness and readiness for any challenge.</p>
 <p id="Par40" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">‘Available Resources’ is a sub-construct highlighted during the FGDs. Regardless of the HCP’s enthusiasm towards change, resource availability was critical in determining the level of staffs’ readiness. Resources covered a substantial range of aspects from operational components such as training and funding, to organisational components such as buildings, equipment and staffing. There was a near-consensus among all participants on the need for additional staff and upgraded facilities to implement any new programme or interventions. HCPs shared that logistics was a challenge because most clinics only have one official vehicle, which was always in use. This forced the clinic staff to resort to using their own transportation despite the rare reimbursement from the respective district health offices.</p>
 <p id="Par41" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The sub-construct ‘Access to Knowledge and Information’ or ease of access to information within the primary healthcare clinic was not an issue because the guideline or procedure was always available for reference, especially for NCD care management. However, not all programmes introduced in the clinic came with full implementation guidelines. One clinic shared that the introduction of the family doctor concept in their clinic was not provided with sufficient information or guidelines for implementation.</p>
</sec>
