<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec14" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Strengths and limitations</div>
 <p id="Par52" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Ministry of Health Malaysia plans to implement the EnPHC initiative, a complex intervention package, to improve NCD health service delivery in primary healthcare clinics. Findings from this exploratory study provide the baseline information on the perception of HCPs of various categories about their day-to-day clinic activities and local settings. Insights obtained from the findings will help programme planners and stakeholders plan the intervention deployment strategies. We found that applying the CFIR for formative evaluation provided better understanding of the components of outer and inner settings, as well as individual characteristics. Findings that were explored using the CFIR constructs also established a contextual knowledge platform that can be applied to other primary healthcare settings in the future. The focus group discussions and in-depth interviews allowed for deep understanding of the perceptions and local issues HCPs encountered in the clinic setting.</p>
 <p id="Par53" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There were two limitations in our study. Firstly, the CFIR constructs were only applied later for analysis and were not used during the development of interview guidelines. Nevertheless, comprehensiveness of analysis guided by CFIR facilitates exploration of data from different dimension. Secondly, this study adopted only qualitative approach. Although qualitative data can provide rich information, quantitative measurement for the seriousness and severity of issues raised was not performed in the study. Future study, possibly using mixed method approach of a larger scale for an additional structured questionnaire on an item-scale (Likert for example) assessing the key readiness question in an indirect manner could explore perception as a cross-check measure.</p>
</sec>
