<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Experimental design</div>
 <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In this study, we performed a set of experiments using the stratosphere-resolving Hamburg version of the European Centre Atmospheric General Circulation Model (AGCM): MAECHAM5
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
  </span>. We used the horizontal resolution of T63 (equivalent to ~180 km grid intervals) and 39 vertical levels going up to 0.01 hPa. The lower-boundary condition of the AGCM was taken from the observed climatology of monthly-mean SSTs from 1950 through 2008 (HadISST)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
  </span>. Here we investigate the impact of the Northern Hemisphere OWBCs on the atmospheric circulation that can be simulated with model resolutions currently used to study climate (i.e., as in the IPCC AR6). The OWBCs maintain local maxima in the SST-gradients that we call SST-fronts (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1b</a> and SFig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1c</a>). The OWBCs maintain the SST-fronts through the heat confluence associated with boundary currents of both subtropical and subpolar oceanic gyres. We isolate the impact of the OWBCs by performing AGCM experiments with prescribed SST gradient modified in different ways. Firstly, we produced a Non-Front (NF) SST profile by taking the zonal average of the observed SSTs and smoothing its mid-latitude frontal gradient in both hemispheres. In the NF-Experiment, the observed zonally averaged SST-gradient was relaxed to a constant value northward and southward of the tropical flank of the SST fronts (33.5N and 33.5S). Thereby, a linear poleward SST decrease was assumed, in such a way that the polar SST reaches the freezing temperature (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a</a>; black line in SFig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1c</a>). The effect of sea ice is removed by removing the Arctic and Antarctic sea-ice. This method of smoothing the SST-fronts is similar to the method used in
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>–
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" href="#CR14">14</a>
  </span> for aqua-planet configurations.
 </p>
 <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to isolate the impact of the Northern Hemisphere OWBCs on the large-scale atmospheric circulation, we further performed six sensitivity experiments with realistic climatological SST (ACF, PCF and BCF) and more idealized zonally symmetric (or uniform) SST fronts (ASF, PSF and BSF).</p>
 <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The first experiment (BCF-experiment) is conducted using observed climatological SSTs with realistic climatological extra-tropical SST fronts in both, the Atlantic and the Pacific (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1b</a>); otherwise the experiment is identical to the NF-experiment. The BCF-experiment is compared against the NF-experiment (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1a</a> and SFig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1c</a>) to extract the joint impacts of the Atlantic and Pacific OWBCs on the atmosphere. To identify the individual contributions from the Atlantic and Pacific OWBCs, two additional experiments are compared against the NF-experiment. The ACF-experiment isolates the impact of the Atlantic OWBCs using the observed climatological SST-front only in the Atlantic and smoothed SST conditions in the Pacific; while the converse PCF-experiment isolates the impact of the Pacific OWBCs. The SSTs are identical to the NF-experiments outsides these prescribed SST-fronts regions. Similar simulations were conducted using zonally symmetric (or zonally uniform) instead of climatological SST fronts. In the Atlantic zonally-uniform SST-front experiment (ASF-experiment), the previously described climatological Atlantic SST front is replaced by averaging the observed climatological SST longitudinally across the western Atlantic between 78°W and 32°W; and the SST in the PSF-experiment is similarly obtained by zonally averaging the climatological SST across the Pacific (140°E and 170°E). BSF refers to Both symmetric Fronts with the Atlantic and Pacific zonally-uniform SST fronts are both prescribed. Since the tropical SST also impacts the Northern Hemisphere circulation significantly, we also performed an additional experiment with realistic tropical SST asymmetry and Northern Hemisphere SST-fronts (BCF_Tro-Experiment). The BCF_Tro-Experiment is used in addition to BCF_experiment to test the capability of our model to reproduce the mean large-scale features discussed in this study. The comparison of this experiment with the SST-fronts experiments and reanalysis will give more insight about the role of OWBCs in maintaining the planetary-scale circulation.
 </p>
 <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In all SST front experiments a meridional linear interpolation in the equatorial flank of the imposed frontal area was performed in order to avoid discontinuity in the SST profile between the front and non-front regions. Similar linear interpolations in the polar region were performed but in the zonal direction in ASF, PSF, ACF and PCF experiments, in order to avoid the inter-basin discontinuity. Because of the similarity of the atmospheric response in the realistic and symmetric SST-front experiments (SFig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">10</a>), only the more realistic climatological SST-front experiments will be considered in our main discussions.
 </p>
</sec>
