<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Relevance of the OWBCs for the NAM</div>
 <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The impact of the OWBCs on the Hemisphere-scale atmospheric circulation can result in significant impact of the Ocean on the intrinsic dynamics and the structure of the NAM or NAO. Giving the smaller simulated NAM variability compared to the reanalysis, the observed overall structures of tropospheric and stratospheric NAM
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
  </span> can be reproduced simply by the Northern Hemisphere climatological SST-front prescribed in the presence of continents (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6</a> and SFig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">11</a>). In the absence of the OWBCs and the associated climatological SST-fronts, the NAM (or NAO) influence on Eurasia would become insignificant over large regions (Figs 
  <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6</a> and 
  <a rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig7">7</a>). The NAM-induced fluctuations in tropospheric zonal winds and their eastward extension into the mid-to-high latitude Eurasia are reduced substantially (as much as 50%) in the NF-experiment as compared to the BCF-experiment (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6a,b</a>). The OWBCs also act to enhance the annular structure of the NAM in both stratosphere and troposphere (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6a–d</a>). The differences in the NAM-structure are perceptible in surface climate (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig7">7a,b</a>). In the absence of the sharp SST-gradients, the NAM-induced fluctuations in precipitation and surface temperature would become insignificant over most of the mid-to-high latitude regions including Eurasia, Eastern and Western Atlantic, and Mediterranean areas. The OWBCs can thus considerably enhance the annularity of the NAM and its importance for surface climate variability.
  <div id="Fig6" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 6</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Implications for Northern Annular Mode: (
     <span class="bold">a</span>,
     <span class="bold">b</span>) represent the covariance of the wintertime 250 hPa westerly wind with the wintertime 250 hPa NAMI for (
     <span class="bold">a</span>) BCF-experiment and (
     <span class="bold">b</span>) NF-experiment. (
     <span class="bold">c</span>,
     <span class="bold">d</span>) are the same as (
     <span class="bold">a</span>,
     <span class="bold">b</span>) but for the covariance of 50 hPa westerly wind with the 250 hPa NAMI. Only significant differences at 95%-level according to a covariance test are shaded.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_39392_Fig6_HTML" id="d29e865" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <div id="Fig7" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 7</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Implications for Northern Hemispher climate: (
     <span class="bold">a</span>,
     <span class="bold">b</span>) represent the covariance of wintertime two-meter temperature (contour, in K) and precipitation (shading, in mm/day) with the wintertime 250 hPa NAMI. Only significant differences at the 95%-level according to a covariance test are shaded for the surface temperature and contoured for the precipitation.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_39392_Fig7_HTML" id="d29e880" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
