<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Methods</div>
 <sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Data sources for climate and human stressors</div>
  <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The NOAA (National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration) high resolution (0.25° spatial resolution), optimum interpolation SST (V2; NOAA/OAR/ESRL PSD, Boulder, Colorado, USA; sourced online at 
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.esrl.noaa.gov/psd/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.esrl.noaa.gov/psd/</span>, accessed in July 2017) was used to investigate trends and patterns in ocean warming in the Mediterranean Sea. This product provides daily information on SST for 35 complete years (1982–2016). It is derived from the Advanced Very High Resolution Radiometer (AVHRR) satellite data from the Pathfinder AVHRR SST dataset when available for September 1981 through December 2005, and from the operational Navy AVHRR Multi-Channel SST data for 2006 to 2016. The product also uses 
   <span class="italic">in situ</span> data from ships and buoys, and includes a large-scale adjustment of satellite biases.
  </p>
  <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We also used a reanalysis of the Mediterranean Sea biogeochemistry (0.0625° spatial resolution) for 17 complete years (1999–2016). This is based on the OGSTM-BFM biogeochemical model and data assimilation of surface chlorophyll concentration. OGSTM-BFM was driven by physical forcing fields produced as output by the Med-Currents model. The ESA-CCI database of surface chlorophyll concentration estimated by satellite and delivered within CMEMS-OCTAC was used for data assimilation. This reanalysis provides monthly means of nutrient (phosphate and nitrate) concentrations, net primary production (NPP), dissolved oxygen concentrations (dO
   <sub>2</sub>), ocean pH and CO
   <sub>2</sub> partial pressure (
   <span class="italic">p</span>CO
   <sub>2</sub>).
  </p>
  <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used the fishing effort during the 2012–2017 period as a proxy of local impacts of human fisheries. Data on fishing effort were sourced online at the Global Fishing Watch website (
   <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://globalfishingwatch.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://globalfishingwatch.org/</span>, accessed on August 2017). GFW estimates daily fishing effort by combining scores for all fishing vessels operating in the area. In turn, the fishing score model computes the probability that a vessel is fishing based on its AIS track data. Fishing is defined as the period that a vessel spends away from shore in which it is not transiting to and from the fishing grounds. This fishing effort data source combines information for the fishing activity of trawlers, longliners and purse seiners, and excludes the activity of artisanal fisheries (see
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
   </span>). Artisanal fisheries may contribute substantially to total fishing effort in the Mediterranean Sea, particularly in coastal areas
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46" href="#CR46">46</a>
   </span>. Hence, our approach may not faithfully depict the fine-scale spatial distribution of fishing impacts. However, it is still useful for providing reliable information on the general patterns and distribution of fishing effort for relatively large regions such as the Mediterranean basin.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Estimations of spatio-temporal patterns</div>
  <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Following
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" href="#CR5">5</a>
   </span>, pixel basis, least-square linear regressions for large (SST, pH and 
   <span class="italic">p</span>CO
   <sub>2</sub>) and medium-scale stressors (phosphate and nitrate concentrations, NPP and dO
   <sub>2</sub>) were used for deriving the significance of temporal trends (α-value &lt; 0.05) and their magnitudes (slopes; i.e. annual changes in target features) over recent decades. Temporal trends were calculated for the minimum, maximum and mean annual values of each variable. Although changes in environmental features may not follow linear trends, our simple, intuitive approach allowed us to map spatially-explicit information at the highest spatial resolution to date, on the significance of temporal trends and the magnitudes of observed changes over recent decades.
  </p>
  <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Climate (SST, pH and 
   <span class="italic">p</span>CO
   <sub>2</sub>) and human stressors (phosphate and nitrate concentrations, NPP and dO
   <sub>2</sub>) were grouped and combined to obtain two cumulative, equally-weighted indexes. The slopes (a proxy to the magnitude of environmental changes) for those areas with non-significant trends (α-value &gt; 0.05) were first set to 0. Absolute values for the slopes were then rescaled to the maximum value to make all variables comparable. These relative values (ranging from 0 – no change – to 1 – maximum recorded change –) were subsequently added on a pixel basis and rescaled again to the maximum value. In this way, we obtained two dimensionless indexes ranging from 0 (no change) to 1 (maximum change). Details on trends and slopes for single stressors are provided at Figs 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S1</a> and 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">S2</a>.
  </p>
  <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Spatially-explicit information on fishing effort was provided on a daily basis for 2012–2017. The overall assessment of the spatial distribution of fishing pressure was made by adding all the daily information, thus obtaining a single picture where marine areas particularly impacted by human fisheries over recent years were identified. This parameter was also rescaled to the maximum value to be combined with the two other cumulative indexes, thereby providing information about spatial heterogeneity in the magnitude of cumulative environmental changes, and areas where synergy between negative stressors can be expected.</p>
 </sec>
</sec>
