<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Both hypotheses tested in our study were confirmed. Beech seedlings deriving from populations of N.E. Greece were in general able to survive well under climate change conditions, simulated and applied in the growth chamber. Plants showed adaptive differences that allowed them to avoid high levels of mortality in the growth chamber. Furthermore, beech genotypes demonstrated phenological plastic responses to different environmental conditions and precipitation frequency in particular. Beech seedlings alter the duration of their growing season as a response to environmental signals, avoiding environmental stress and high selection pressure. In our study we were able to describe different adaptation strategies, that relate to the distribution patterns of specific environmental factors, rather than the average annual or monthly values of these measures. Indeed, fluctuations in temperature and precipitation within each year seem to be crucial for survival and growth, as well as the duration of the growing season. For this reason, provenance Evros is considered to be well-adapted to a less temperate climate, due to the low rainfall during summer, despite the high annual precipitation that occurs mainly during the winter in this region. Furthermore, our study proved the adaptive significance of the distribution of precipitation at a small temporal scale, since different adaptive strategies appeared among beech seedlings when the same amount of water was distributed differently within each month. This indicates that the physiological response mechanisms of beech individuals are very complex and depend on several interacting parameters that are difficult to study in total. For this reason, conclusions about the suitability of provenances for translocation and use in afforestation or reforestation projects should consider the small scale ecotypic diversity of the species and view multiple environmental and climatic parameters in connection to each other.</p>
