<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par18" class="p">The past rainfall data for the period (rainfall 1975–2015) were procured from Regional Meteorological Centre (RMC), India Meteorological Department (IMD), Chennai. The occurrence of extreme events were calculated based on IMD norms. The extremely heavy rainfall event (&gt;244.5 mm/day) and very heavy rainfall event (&gt;124.5 mm/day) for the period of 1975–2015 were calculated. Potential anthropogenic climate change scenarios of future and their underlying driving forces are always an important component of any impact assessments. The driving forces are well captured and updated in IPCC’s continuous assessment reports and in Global Climate Models (GCM). The recent IPCC AR5 adopted Representative Concentration Pathways (RCP) to illustrate the concentration of future anthropogenic greenhouse gas (GHG) emissions via., RCP 2.6, RCP 4.5, RCP 6.0 and RCP 8.5. RCP 2.6 is peak scenario and represents very low greenhouse gas concentration levels. RCP 4.5 is balanced mitigation scenario or stabilization scenario where total radiative forcing is stabilized before the year 2100 by the employment of a range of technologies and strategies for reducing greenhouse gas emissions. RCP 6.0 is stabilization scenario where total radiative forcing is stabilized before 2100 without overshoot employment of a range of technologies and strategies for reducing greenhouse gas emissions. RCP 8.5 is business-as-usual scenario leading to high greenhouse gas concentration levels
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">11</xref>
 </sup>. Global Climate Model (GCM) data from CMIP5 (Coupled Model Intercomparison Project Phase 5) dataset of IPCC AR5
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" class="xref">12</xref>
 </sup> for RCP 4.5 scenario were used inthis study to project the future climate change scenario for the period 2015–2085
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">13</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">14</xref>
 </sup>. The GCM models were statistically downloaded from 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://ccafs-climate.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://ccafs-climate.org/</ext-link>. The GCM models cesm1_cam5, mpi_esm_mr, ncar_ccsm4, bnu_esm were used to project future climate scenarios of the study area and to generate the IDF curves. These GCM data were developed by various pioneer institutions in different countries. bnu_esm was developed by Beijing Normal University, China. cesm1_cam5 and ncar_ccsm4 were developed by National Center for Atmospheric Research, USA. Max Planck Institute for Meteorology, Germany developed the model mpi_esm_mr.
</p>
