<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">
 <italic class="italic">Support for adaptive and mitigative responses to climate change</italic> was measured through three items, measured on a 5-point scale ranging from 1 (
 <italic class="italic">strongly disagree</italic>) to 5 (
 <italic class="italic">strongly agree</italic>), gauging the degree to which participants support specific adaptation and mitigation actions. Two items focused on adaptation responses specific to a major predicted impact of climate change on Iowa agriculture: increased incidence of precipitation (
 <xref rid="bibr34-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">ICCIC, 2011</xref>). The first item, “Iowa farmers should take additional steps to protect their land from increased precipitation,” focuses on protection of agricultural land from increases in rainfall. Extreme rain events in 2008 and 2010 resulted in significant, widespread erosion across Iowa (
 <xref rid="bibr16-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Cox, Hug, &amp; Bruzelius, 2011</xref>), raising awareness of the issue and a potential need to act. The second adaptation statement, “Iowa farmers should increase investment in agricultural drainage systems (tile, ditches) to prepare for increased precipitation,” is particularly salient for Iowa farmers given the hydrological history and current profile of Iowa’s most productive agricultural lands. Artificial drainage of Iowa’s humid prairie, the soils of which contain extraordinary amounts of organic matter (
 <xref rid="bibr52-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Mutel, 2007</xref>), facilitated cultivation of these highly fertile soils and made Iowa a leading agricultural state (
 <xref rid="bibr60-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Peterson &amp; Englehorn, 1946</xref>; 
 <xref rid="bibr64-0013916513503832" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Soil Conservation Service [SCS], 1983</xref>). Drainage represents a longstanding engineered solution to the problem of “excess” water in Iowa, and a logical adaptive strategy for maintaining productivity in the face of future increases in precipitation.
</p>
