<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The second issue raised by the use of GCM for assessing climate impacts is that climate models show significant biases in simulating current climate with sometimes insufficient skill for GCM outputs to be used directly as inputs for impact models without prior bias correction (Semenov and Barrow, 
 <xref rid="B174" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1997</xref>). If bias-correction is often included into statistical downscaling, the skill of representing the present-day climate can be very low using regional downscaling (Oettli et al., 
 <xref rid="B133" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>). Since impact models ultimately rely on the accuracy of climate input data (Berg et al., 
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>), the errors inevitably propagated into the combined climate/crop modeling (Oettli et al., 
 <xref rid="B133" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>; Glotter et al., 
 <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>; Ramarohetra et al., 
 <xref rid="B148" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>). For instance, using two RCMs and the DSSAT-CERES-maize crop model over the United States, Glotter et al. (
 <xref rid="B70" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>) showed that although the RCMs correct some GCM biases related to fine-scale geographic features, the use of a RCM cannot compensate for broad-scale systematic errors that dominate the errors for simulated maize yields. Moreover, Ramirez-Villegas et al. (
 <xref rid="B149" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>) suggested that the use of raw GCM outputs can even affect the estimation of the climate change impact on crop yields by significantly under- or overestimate cropping system sensitivity by 2.5–7.5% for precipitation-driven areas and 1.3–23% for temperature-driven areas. Thus, careful evaluation of climate models using regional key drivers of crop yields (Berg et al., 
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>; Ramirez-Villegas et al., 
 <xref rid="B149" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>; Guan et al., 
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>) is needed to make the best use of climate change simulations for impact research. Large errors have been found in the simulation of the WAM rainfall by climate models which usually suffer from too much drizzle and a large bias in rainfall frequency, large errors in simulating seasonal rainfall as well as an underestimation of the interannual variability which can subsequently bias simulated crop yield (Baron et al., 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2005</xref>; Berg et al., 
 <xref rid="B15" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>; Ramirez-Villegas et al., 
 <xref rid="B149" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>; Guan et al., 
 <xref rid="B71" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2015</xref>). Significant biases have also been found CMIP5 simulations for mean temperature and diurnal temperature ranges in West Africa (Ramirez-Villegas et al., 
 <xref rid="B149" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>). To overcome this issue, climate impact studies generally require some level of climate data bias correction. The simplest correction method is the delta method used by Müller et al. (
 <xref rid="B128" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2010</xref>) or Sultan et al. (
 <xref rid="B183" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2013</xref>) which consists to add a computed mean annual anomaly between future and current simulated climates of a given GCM to a current observation-based dataset. Promising results are obtained by Oettli et al. (
 <xref rid="B133" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>) when applying a more complex bias correction technique (Michelangeli et al., 
 <xref rid="B120" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2009</xref>) to climate model outputs. In particular the authors showed that means and standard deviations of simulated yields of sorghum in Senegal are much more realistic with bias corrected climate variables than those using raw climate models outputs.
</p>
