<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece32747-sec-0013" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Early‐life ecological conditions had lifetime consequences for male banded mongooses. More variable early‐life conditions had positive effects on males’ lifespan and lifetime reproductive success, suggesting a relaxation of life‐history trade‐off constraints. In contrast, changes in mean early‐life conditions influenced males’ relative fertility and lifespan in opposite directions resulting in no overall effect on lifetime reproductive success, suggesting a life‐history trade‐off. In Figure 
  <a rid="ece32747-fig-0006" ref-type="fig" href="#ece32747-fig-0006">6</a>, we use a simple graphical model (adapted from Saeki, Tuda, &amp; Crowley, 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0070" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0070">2014</a>) to illustrate these different effects of the variability and mean early‐life conditions. Unlike in males, females’ early‐life ecological conditions had almost no effect on patterns of survival and reproduction.
 </p>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece32747-fig-0006" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 6</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Graphical illustration of the hypothesized effect of changes in the (a) variability and (b) mean of early‐life rainfall on life‐history trade‐off and allocation patterns (after Saeki et al., 
    <a rid="ece32747-bib-0070" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0070">2014</a>). The thin gray lines represent fitness isoclines along which all positions return an equal payoff. The thick dashed line represents the reference trade‐off slope for an individual (here straight lines for simplicity), and the yellow dot represents the reference optimal allocation of resources to survival and reproduction (where the trade‐off slope is tangential to the isocline). In panel (a), the thick red lines and dots show how an (i) increase or (ii) decrease in the variability of early‐life rainfall relaxes or increases the life‐history trade‐off constraints leading to higher or lower fitness payoffs. In panel (b), the thick blue lines and dots represent how an (iii) increase or (iv) decrease in mean early‐life rainfall leads to changes in an individual's trade‐off slope and optimal allocation of resources but no change in their overall fitness payoff
   </p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-13" xlink:href="ECE3-7-1712-g006" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Males who experienced more variable rainfall in early‐life lived longer and had greater lifetime reproductive success. We have shown previously that more variable rainfall is associated with higher adult mortality in mongooses (Marshall et al., 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0047">2016</a>), and our results here also indicate an association with lower food abundance suggesting that years with more variable rainfall are generally unfavorable. These findings, therefore, contrast with previous studies of wild animals showing that favorable early‐life ecological conditions have positive effects on survival and reproduction in later life (e.g., 
  <span class="italic">Haematopus ostralegus</span> Van de Pol et al., 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0077" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0077">2006</a>; 
  <span class="italic">C. elaphus</span> Nussey et al., 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0061">2007</a>; 
  <span class="italic">F. auricularia</span> Wong &amp; Kölliker, 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0081" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0081">2014</a>). Evidence for later‐life fitness advantages of unfavorable early‐life ecological conditions has been shown in two wild bird systems, but this was based on a single measure of fitness (probability of breeding in 
  <span class="italic">L. superbus</span> Rubenstein et al., 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0069" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0069">2016</a>) or was found within an overall positive effect of early‐life ecological conditions on fertility and survival (
  <span class="italic">P. major</span> Wilkin &amp; Sheldon, 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0079" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0079">2009</a>). Increased adult survival was also shown in female roe deer (
  <span class="italic">Capreolus capreolus</span>) that survived periods of high juvenile mortality (Garratt et al., 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0024">2015</a>). Our study uses multiple measures of fitness to directly link later‐life fitness advantages to unfavorable early‐life ecological conditions (rather than measures of early‐life mortality) in a wild mammal system. Moreover, our results show that these later‐life advantages are not explained by the impact of early‐life conditions on offspring survival (i.e., selection), parental investment, or the social environment as suggested previously (Garratt et al., 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0024">2015</a>; Rubenstein et al., 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0069" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0069">2016</a>; Wilkin &amp; Sheldon, 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0079" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0079">2009</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Why might more variable ecological conditions be associated with increased fitness payoffs, without any apparent costs (Figure 
  <a rid="ece32747-fig-0006" ref-type="fig" href="#ece32747-fig-0006">6</a>a)? Previous studies investigating the effect of the variability of early‐life ecological conditions on later‐life performance in a wild animal system are lacking. One possibility is that more varied early‐life conditions might influence individuals’ physiological or cognitive development such that they are able to cope with a greater range of environmental challenges in later‐life. This hypothesis is supported by the fact that, at our study site, years with greater variation in monthly rainfall values were also those with greater maximum and lower minimum monthly rainfalls. Furthermore, comparing the range of monthly rainfall values males experienced during early‐life to the range of monthly values they would experience during a typical male lifespan (42 months, Cant et al., 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0012">2016</a>), those born in highly variable periods (the top third of early‐life 
  <span class="italic">SD</span> rainfall values) experienced 93% ± 7% (mean ± 
  <span class="italic">SD</span>,
  <span class="italic"> n</span> = 50 males) of the typical lifetime range, while those born in low variability periods (the bottom third of early‐life 
  <span class="italic">SD</span> values) experienced 63% ± 8% (
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 55 males). Our results do not support the possibility that a more variable early‐life rainfall conferred advantages through a more diverse diet. However, there are parallels between our hypothesis that early‐life variability may have beneficial impacts on physiological or cognitive development and findings from the medical literature. First, experiencing a wide variety of pathogens during childhood is recognized to be important in the development of the human immune system, with a lack of early‐life immunological challenges leading to inappropriate immune responses in adulthood and allergic diseases (the “hygiene hypothesis”: Strachan, 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0073" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0073">1989</a>, 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0074" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0074">2000</a>; Wills‐Karp et al., 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0080" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0080">2001</a>; Yazdanbakhsh et al., 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0082" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0082">2002</a>). Second, experiencing a variety of childhood psychological stressors is thought to have positive effects on some cognitive abilities in adults under stress (Frankenhuis &amp; de Weerth, 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0021" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0021">2013</a>; Frankenhuis et al., 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0022" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0022">2015</a>). Finally, it may be that reduced early‐life food availability is beneficial. In laboratory models and humans, dietary restriction has repeatedly been shown to increase lifespan (e.g., Colman et al., 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0016" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0016">2009</a>; Fontana et al., 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0019" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0019">2004</a>; Masoro, 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0048" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0048">2006</a>; McCay et al., 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0049" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0049">1935</a>; Zhang et al., 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0084" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0084">2013</a>). In support of this recent ecological studies have shown that restrictions on early‐life diet can have benefits such as reduced oxidative damage in zebra finches, 
  <span class="italic">Taeniopygia guttata</span>, and wild yellow‐legged gulls, 
  <span class="italic">Larus michahellis</span> (Noguera, Lores, Alonso‐Alvarez, &amp; Velando, 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0059" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0059">2011</a>; Noguera, Monaghan, &amp; Metcalfe, 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0060" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0060">2015</a>). The link between our hypothesis and these biomedical findings is speculative at present, but there is clearly much scope for research to elucidate the mechanisms underlying the early‐life effects reported here.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Mean early‐life ecological conditions, rather than having an effect on overall fitness payoffs, appeared to mediate a life‐history trade‐off (Figure 
  <a rid="ece32747-fig-0006" ref-type="fig" href="#ece32747-fig-0006">6</a>b). Depending on mean conditions during development, males apparently adopted a “live‐fast, die‐young” or “live‐slow, die‐old” strategy and achieved similar lifetime fitness as a consequence. These findings are consistent with life‐history theory that individuals trade‐off allocating resources between somatic maintenance and reproduction (Kirkwood &amp; Rose, 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0041" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0041">1991</a>; Reznick &amp; Yang, 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0066" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0066">1993</a>; Zera &amp; Harshman, 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0083" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0083">2001</a>), and support the general hypothesis that conditions during development have an important influence on this life‐history resource allocation across an individuals’ lifetime (Gluckman et al., 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0028">2005</a>; Monaghan, 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0051" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0051">2008</a>; Nettle &amp; Bateson, 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0055">2015</a>; Taborsky, 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0075" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0075">2006</a>). Nonetheless, empirical studies demonstrating the effect of early‐life conditions on life‐history trade‐offs are uncommon (Cartwright et al., 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0014" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0014">2014</a>; Hammers et al., 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0030" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0030">2013</a>), with many more studies showing directly positive (or negative) “silver‐spoon” effects of early‐life conditions on lifetime fitness (Hayward et al., 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0032" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0032">2013</a>; Nussey et al., 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0061" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0061">2007</a>; Rubenstein et al., 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0069" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0069">2016</a>; Van de Pol et al., 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0077" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0077">2006</a>; Wong &amp; Kölliker, 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0081" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0081">2014</a>). Our results provide evidence for both life‐history trade‐off and “silver‐spoon” type effects of early‐life ecological conditions. Poor average early‐life conditions shifted life histories toward the slower end of the survival versus reproduction trade‐off, while more variable early‐life conditions had beneficial effects on both survival and reproduction. This highlights the importance of considering the variability, as well as the average, of early‐life conditions in understanding their consequences for individuals’ lifetime fitness.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Why did early‐life ecological conditions only have consistent effects on males’, and not females’, later‐life fitness? Previous studies have suggested that sex‐differences in the effect of early‐life ecological conditions may be due to sex‐differences in: (1) body size (Ancona &amp; Drummond, 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0002">2013</a>; Kruuk et al., 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0042">1999</a>; Millon et al., 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0050" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0050">2011</a>), (2) the amount of care received during development (Kruuk et al., 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0042" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0042">1999</a>; Rubenstein et al., 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0069" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0069">2016</a>), (3) the effect of early‐life conditions on the development of reproductive organs (Wong &amp; Kölliker, 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0081" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0081">2014</a>) and (4) selection pressures for plasticity to later‐life conditions (Ancona &amp; Drummond, 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0002">2013</a>; Garratt et al., 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0024" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0024">2015</a>; Wilkin &amp; Sheldon, 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0079" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0079">2009</a>). We are able to rule out explanations (1) and (2) here since banded mongooses show little sexual dimorphism and early‐life ecological conditions did not predict the amount of care pups received. We have no direct evidence to rule out explanation (3), but we consider it unlikely since female reproductive organs are more costly to develop and so this would predict later‐life fitness effects in females rather than males (as Wong &amp; Kölliker, 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0081" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0081">2014</a> found), which is the opposite to what we found. There is, however, evidence to support explanation (4) that banded mongoose females are under greater selection to exhibit higher levels of plasticity to ecological conditions experienced in adulthood. Adult females’ mass and survival are more sensitive than males’ to ecological conditions experienced during adulthood (Marshall et al., 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0047">2016</a>). Females in better condition are more fecund and have more competitive offspring (Hodge et al., 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0036">2009</a>; Inzani et al., 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0039">2016</a>), and they reduce their costly helping behavior more than males when food availability is lower (Bell, 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0007" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0007">2010</a>). These effects are all likely to increase selection on females to adapt to the ecological conditions they experience during adulthood, masking any effects of the conditions they experienced in early‐life. In addition, females also start breeding at an earlier age than males (Cant et al., 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0012">2016</a>) and are pregnant for an average of 30% of their adult lives (H. H. Marshall and M. A. Cant, unpublished data). While this last point may impair females’ ability to respond to changes in ecological conditions while they are pregnant (Marshall et al., 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0047">2016</a>), it may increase the pressure to adapt to these changes outside of pregnancy. These results contribute to the growing picture that the effect of early‐life ecological conditions on later‐life fitness is often sex‐specific (Millon et al., 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0050" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0050">2011</a>; Rubenstein et al., 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0069" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0069">2016</a>) and highlights sex‐differences in plasticity to later‐life ecological conditions as a mechanism producing this sex‐specific effect (Ancona &amp; Drummond, 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0002" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0002">2013</a>; Wilkin &amp; Sheldon, 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0079" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0079">2009</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Finally, despite the multiple effects of early‐life ecological conditions in later‐life, we found no immediate effects of early‐life conditions on social care received or offspring survival. There was a trend for males to be heavier at 1 year old after a more variable early‐life; however, this effect was a nonsignificant trend (
  <span class="italic">p</span> = .06) and so needs further investigation. This agrees with other studies showing that early‐life conditions can influence individuals in later‐life without having impacts on early‐life health or survival (Andrews et al., 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0003">2015</a>; Rosa et al., 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0068" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0068">2014</a>). For example, in the European starling, 
  <span class="italic">Sturnis vulgaris</span>, competitive disadvantage during development does not affect chick growth or mass a year later, but disadvantaged birds experience greater telomere attrition as chicks (Nettle, Monaghan, et al., 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0056" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0056">2015</a>) and, as adults, impaired flight performance and altered foraging and cognitive behavior (Andrews et al., 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0003">2015</a>; Bateson, Emmerson, Ergün, Monaghan, &amp; Nettle, 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0006" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0006">2015</a>; Nettle, Andrews, et al., 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0054" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0054">2015</a>; O'Hagan, Andrews, Bedford, Bateson, &amp; Nettle, 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0062" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0062">2015</a>). Such “cryptic” or “carry‐over” effects of early‐life conditions may be mediated by physiological mechanisms that only manifest themselves in later life (Andrews et al., 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0003" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0003">2015</a>; Nettle, Monaghan, et al., 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0056" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0056">2015</a>). A greater understanding of how environmental conditions during development affect individuals’ physiology may be key in understanding why these conditions influence individuals’ health, behavior and fitness in later‐life, with implications for evolutionary and biomedical science (Gluckman et al., 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0028" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0028">2005</a>; Nettle &amp; Bateson, 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0055" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0055">2015</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
