<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece32747-sec-0003" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study system</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We conducted our study between September 1999 and March 2014 on a long‐term study population of banded mongooses on the Mweya Peninsula in Queen Elizabeth National Park, Uganda (0°12′S, 27°54′E). Cant, Vitikainen, and Nichols (
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0013" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0013">2013</a>) and Cant, Nichols, Thompson, and Vitikainen (
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0012">2016</a>), and references therein, provide detailed descriptions of our study site and banded mongoose biology. Here, we provide information about both specific to this study.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Banded mongooses (Figure 
  <a rid="ece32747-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#ece32747-fig-0001">1</a>) are diurnal carnivores (&lt;2 kg) that live in stable, mixed‐sex groups of around 10–30 individuals and whose diet mainly consists of small invertebrates (Rood, 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0067" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0067">1975</a>). Individuals sexually mature around the age of 1 year (Cant et al., 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0012">2016</a>) and all individuals within a group reproduce to some extent, though contributions to reproduction are skewed toward older individuals (Nichols, Amos, Cant, Bell, &amp; Hodge, 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0057" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0057">2010</a>; Nichols, Bell, Hodge, &amp; Cant, 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0058" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0058">2012</a>). Their average lifespan is around 3.5 years (males = 42 months, females = 38 months, max = 149 months, Cant et al., 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0012">2016</a>), and survival rates are constant across all ages (Cant et al., 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0012" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0012">2016</a>; Marshall et al., 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0047">2016</a>). At our equatorial study site reproduction occurs all year round and is not synchronized between groups. Reproduction is, however, highly synchronized within groups: around four times per year, all pregnant females in a group give birth in an underground den to a large communal litter, usually on the same morning (Cant, 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0009" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0009">2000</a>; Hodge, Bell, &amp; Cant, 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0035" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0035">2011</a>). Pups remain in the den for approximately their first 30 days, after which they move with the rest of the group and are cared for by adult “escorts” for around a further 60 days (Gilchrist, 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0025" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0025">2004</a>; Gilchrist &amp; Russell, 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0027" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0027">2007</a>). We are able to individually recognize the mongooses in our study population using unique hair‐shave patterns or colored collars. Radio collars weighing 26–30 g (Sirtrack Ltd, Havelock North, New Zealand) with a 20‐cm whip antenna (Biotrack Ltd, Dorset, UK) are fitted to one to two individuals in each group to allow them to be located. Most individual are trained to step onto an electronic balance in return for a small milk reward. Two groups have access to human refuse (Otali &amp; Gilchrist, 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0063" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0063">2004</a>) and so were excluded from this study (and also a previous complementary study investigating the effects of ecological conditions during adulthood, Marshall et al., 
  <a rid="ece32747-bib-0047" ref-type="ref" href="#ece32747-bib-0047">2016</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
