<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Based on these findings, a guideline for sustainable development should be established. First, a prediction of spatiotemporal change in winter perceived temperature for mitigation is a critical process because it is a key factor that has not been integrated with previous/existing protocols. Second, urban greenery and public open space should be increased across the city. While integrating these two factors, there are items that should be investigated further. For example, previous studies found that wind ventilation is the key to reducing thermal distress [
 <xref rid="B16-ijerph-16-00497" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">16</xref>]. For the design of public open space to reduce the impact of increasing winter perceived temperatures, ventilation should be considered in order to increase the potential air flow across a compact city. In addition, since a compact city is a high-density environment with a large population, there are always limitations to further decreasing building density and road networks to increase the ratio of greenery or public open space. In this case, vertical greenery, green roofs and terrace gardens are important for increasing green coverage. In order for targeted improvement of the urban green environment to take place, two items are necessary: (1) avoid using artificial green roofs in a high-density city, and (2) use an appropriate selection of construction materials for the development of an open space. Unlike urban vegetation, artificial green roofs cannot provide evapotranspiration and thus they cannot reduce urban heat in a high-density environment. A previous study also found that inappropriate selection of construction materials for open spaces cannot passively reduce heat intensity across the space [
 <xref rid="B38-ijerph-16-00497" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>]. Moreover, additional care should be undertaken when selecting appropriate vegetative species for urban greenery. The species should be thoroughly considered keeping in mind their ability to reduce air pollution across the city, since a significant association between air pollution and thermal distress has been widely observed [
 <xref rid="B39-ijerph-16-00497" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>].
</p>
