<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div id="Abs1" class="abstract" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <sec class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Background</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Phasianidae is a family of Galliformes containing 38 genera and approximately 138 species, which is grouped into two tribes based on their morphological features, the Pheasants and Partridges. Several studies have attempted to reconstruct the phylogenetic relationships of the Phasianidae, but many questions still remain unaddressed, such as the taxonomic status and phylogenetic relationships among 
   <span class="italic">Crossoptilon</span> species. The mitochondrial genome (mitogenome) has been extensively used to infer avian genetic diversification with reasonable resolution. Here, we sequenced the entire mitogenomes of three 
   <span class="italic">Crossoptilon</span> species (
   <span class="italic">C. harmani</span>, 
   <span class="italic">C. mantchuricum</span> and 
   <span class="italic">C. crossoptilon</span>) to investigate their evolutionary relationship among 
   <span class="italic">Crossoptilon</span> species.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The complete mitogenomes of 
   <span class="italic">C. harmani</span>, 
   <span class="italic">C. mantchuricum</span> and 
   <span class="italic">C. crossoptilon</span> are 16682 bp, 16690 bp and 16680 bp in length, respectively, encoding a standard set of 13 protein-coding genes, 2 ribosomal RNA genes, 22 transfer RNA genes, and a putative control region. 
   <span class="italic">C. auritum</span> and 
   <span class="italic">C. mantchuricum</span> are more closely related genetically, whereas 
   <span class="italic">C. harmani</span> is more closely related to 
   <span class="italic">C. crossoptilon. Crossoptilon</span> has a closer relationship with 
   <span class="italic">Lophura</span>, and the following phylogenetic relationship was reconstructed: ((
   <span class="italic">Crossoptilon</span> + 
   <span class="italic">Lophura</span>) + (
   <span class="italic">Phasianus</span> + 
   <span class="italic">Chrysolophus</span>)). The divergence time between the clades 
   <span class="italic">C. harmani</span>-
   <span class="italic">C. crossoptilon</span> and 
   <span class="italic">C. mantchuricum</span>-
   <span class="italic">C. auritum</span> is consistent with the uplift of the Tibetan Plateau during the Tertiary Pliocene. The Ka/Ks analysis showed that 
   <span class="italic">atp8</span> gene in the 
   <span class="italic">Crossoptilon</span> likely experienced a strong selective pressure in adaptation to the plateau environment.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusions</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="italic">C. auritum</span> with 
   <span class="italic">C. mantchuricum</span> and 
   <span class="italic">C. harmani</span> with 
   <span class="italic">C. crossoptilon</span> form two pairs of sister groups. The genetic distance between 
   <span class="italic">C. harmani</span> and 
   <span class="italic">C. crossoptilon</span> is far less than the interspecific distance and is close to the intraspecific distance of 
   <span class="italic">Crossoptilon</span>, indicating that 
   <span class="italic">C. harmani</span> is much more closely related to 
   <span class="italic">C. crossoptilon</span>. Our mito-phylogenomic analysis supports the monophyly of 
   <span class="italic">Crossoptilon</span> and its closer relationship with 
   <span class="italic">Lophura</span>. The uplift of Tibetan Plateau is suggested to impact the divergence between 
   <span class="italic">C. harmani</span>-
   <span class="italic">C. crossoptilon</span> clade and 
   <span class="italic">C. mantchuricum</span>-
   <span class="italic">C. auritum</span> clade during the Tertiary Pliocene. 
   <span class="italic">Atp8</span> gene in the 
   <span class="italic">Crossoptilon</span> species might have experienced a strong selective pressure for adaptation to the plateau environment.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec" xmlns="">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Electronic supplementary material</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The online version of this article (doi:10.1186/s12864-015-1234-9) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorized users.</p>
 </sec>
</div>
