<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece33446-sec-0021" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.8</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Changes to relative incubation onset alter the mean, but not the variance, of synchrony between hatch dates and food peak abundance</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Null estimations of hatching synchrony, assuming no changes in relative incubation onset or no changes to incubation duration, and the observed hatching synchrony were compared. This allowed us to tease apart the contributions of different aspects of incubation behavior to the observed hatching synchrony for the 2014 breeding season. The inclusion of alterations to incubation duration altered the variance of synchrony among nests, from 44.8 without duration changes to 37.8 for observed hatching synchrony. The inclusion of changes to the relative onset of incubation also showed a difference in variance, but to a much lower extent (1.1 higher than observed variance). None of these differences in variance were statistically significant. 
  <span class="italic">F</span> test of variances for a baseline with no duration changes compared to observed hatching synchrony showed a ratio of variances of 1.18 (
  <span class="italic">df</span> = 92/92, 
  <span class="italic">p</span> = .21). The 
  <span class="italic">F</span> test for no onset changes compared to observed hatching synchrony showed a ratio of variances of 1.02 (
  <span class="italic">df</span> = 92/92, 
  <span class="italic">p</span> = .44).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A paired 
  <span class="italic">t</span> test testing the difference in mean synchrony with and without incubation onset changes showed a significant difference. Mean synchrony was 4.5 days lower, closer to optimum, for observed compared to null synchrony (difference = −4.5, 
  <span class="italic">T</span> = 13.29, 
  <span class="italic">df</span> = 92, 
  <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; .01).
 </p>
</sec>
