<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece33446-sec-0020" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.7</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Daily intensity of incubation effort increases with higher daily maximum temperatures</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The proportion of the active day spent incubating was significantly positively correlated with time through incubation (~5% increase per day of incubation) and local maximum daily temperature (~2% increase per 1°C), according to the lowest AIC model. There was also a weak but significant negative interaction between temperature and day of incubation (EST = −0.008, 
  <span class="italic">SE</span> = 0.001, 
  <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; .001); with the relationship between temperature and intensity being weaker the further through incubation a bird is. All other candidate model configurations had ΔAIC values of &gt;2. These results show that the further through incubation a female is, and the warmer the daily temperature, the higher the proportion of the day is spent incubating (see Figure 
  <a rid="ece33446-fig-0004" ref-type="fig" href="#ece33446-fig-0004">4</a>).
 </p>
 <div fig-type="Figure" xml:lang="en" id="ece33446-fig-0004" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 4</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>The proportion of the active day spent incubating against maximum daily temperature. The plotted lines are generated from predictions from a binomial GLMM using mean incubation day and one standard deviation above and below the mean incubation day (start of full incubation = incubation day 1). For the purposes of prediction, random effects were ignored. Shaded area represents the 95% confidence interval for the relationship between temperature and intensity when incubation day is 6 only, to improve readability</p>
  </div>
  <div id="nlm-graphic-9" xlink:href="ECE3-7-9415-g004" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Full model selection results and model parameters are given in supporting information 
  <a rid="ece33446-sup-0001" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#ece33446-sup-0001">S6</a>.
 </p>
</sec>
