<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece33446-sec-0007" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Statistical analyses</div>
 <sec id="ece33446-sec-0008" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2.1</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Is reproductive success better explained by timing of hatching relative to the caterpillar peak than timing of clutch initiation relative to the caterpillar peak?</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Whether hatch timing relative to winter moth caterpillar peak abundance (taken as the median date on which caterpillars were observed descending to pupate) is important for reproductive success was tested using a Poisson generalized linear model (GLM) with number of fledglings as the response variable. Fixed effects were hatching synchrony (observed hatch date minus median caterpillar date of that year) and its quadratic. Clutch size, clutch initiation synchrony (observed clutch initiation date minus median caterpillar date of that year), its quadratic, and section of the woodland were also included as explanatory variables to take account of number of eggs laid, individual condition, and local habitat quality.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece33446-sec-0009" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2.2</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Do adjustments to timing of hatching made after clutch initiation improve synchrony between chick hatching and the caterpillar peak?</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to address the overarching question of whether adjustments after clutch initiation improve synchrony between chick hatching and the caterpillar peak, we address two subquestions.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <div list-type="order" id="ece33446-list-0002" class="list">
    <div class="list-item">
     <p>
      <span class="italic">Is annual population‐level variance in hatching timing reduced through incubation adjustments?</span> The annual variance of hatch dates and clutch initiation dates was calculated from 1960 to 2014. To take account of the potential influence of changes in clutch size, we also calculated the variance of clutch completion dates. The variances of clutch initiation date, clutch completion date, and observed hatch date were compared using an ANOVA including a fixed effect of year.
     </p>
    </div>
    <div class="list-item">
     <p>
      <span class="italic">Is synchrony with the food source improved by adjustments made between clutch initiation and hatching?</span> To distinguish whether the observed synchrony between hatch dates and caterpillar peak abundance was a significant improvement to the null expectation of this synchrony, without incubation alterations, a paired 
      <span class="italic">t</span> test was conducted. Observed synchrony was calculated as the difference between each nest's hatch date and the woodland annual caterpillar timing. All synchrony values had 13 added to them as 13 days prior to the caterpillar peak was indicated to be the optimal timing of hatching (see above for the analysis of reproductive success). This gives an index with negative values indicating hatch timing earlier than optimum, positive values indicating hatch dates later, and 0 indicating optimal synchrony. The null expectation assumed no incubation behavior alterations and was calculated as the clutch completion date plus 14 days (to represent duration of incubation) minus annual caterpillar timing. Synchrony index measures were then squared in order to remove negative values.
     </p>
    </div>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece33446-sec-0010" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2.3</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">How much within‐population variation exists in (a) onset of incubation relative to clutch completion, (b) incubation duration, and (c) incubation intensity?</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Using the identified onset of full incubation for the 2014 breeding season, we calculated two primary aspects of incubation behavior: the relative onset (interval between clutch completion and start of daytime incubation) and duration (interval between onset of incubation and observed hatch date). In addition, we also quantified the daily intensity of incubation effort. Incubation effort for each day was determined by calculating the number of 20‐min periods during the active day (7 a.m. to 7 p.m.—the active day) that exceeded the threshold temperature for incubation, as a proportion of the total number of active‐day recordings. The range, mean, and variance of each of these aspects of incubation behavior were calculated.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Relationships between each of the aspects of incubation behavior were also tested. Linear models (LMs) and GLMs were run for each combination of behaviors. Due to sequential timing, relative incubation onset could not be causally influenced by either intensity or duration. However, the onset itself could influence the intensity of incubation effort and consequently impact the duration of daytime incubation. Furthermore, other factors, such as individual condition and clutch size, could also impact incubation effort. These associations were tested in two analyses. The first was a binomial GLM, with mean intensity of incubation as a response variable and relative incubation onset as an explanatory variable, accounting for clutch size and clutch initiation date (a proxy for individual condition (Rowe, Ludwig, &amp; Schluter, 
   <a rid="ece33446-bib-0039" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33446-bib-0039">1994</a>)). The second was a LM with incubation duration as the response variable and mean intensity, relative incubation onset, and clutch size as explanatory variables. The duration of daytime incubation should be a result of the amount of incubation required for an embryo to develop and hatch, scaled by the intensity at which it was incubated. As a result, we would expect incubation duration to show a relationship with mean incubation intensity. However, this relationship could also be modulated by other processes, which influence the amount of incubation required. This could be altered by clutch size (Haftorn, 
   <a rid="ece33446-bib-0017" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33446-bib-0017">1981</a>) and the amount of prior incubation, through relative incubation onset. A nest that began incubation prior to clutch completion could require a greater intensity of incubation effort for the same duration as a nest that began incubation after clutch completion. This occurs due to accumulated hours of incubation during nocturnal incubation reducing the amount required from full incubation for nests which delay onset.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece33446-sec-0011" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2.4</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Can this observed variability be explained by ambient temperature cues, and if so, which temperature measures best capture variation?</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For both relative incubation onset and incubation duration, exploratory analyses were conducted using sliding time window methods in order to identify the temporal temperature window and temperature measure, which best explain variance in different components of incubation behavior. This method does not establish a causal link between the behavior of interest and temperature, but instead attempts to identify the time window in which temperature may be most important for determining the behavior in question.</p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Twelve different length windows were tested for these analyses (Figure 
   <a rid="ece33446-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#ece33446-fig-0001">1</a>). The minimum time window (shown in red) was unique to each nest and spanned from the lay date to the date of onset of full incubation, hereafter termed the “laying period.” The time windows then increase in 1‐day increments spanning backward from the start of laying, up to the maximum window of 10 days prior to laying, up until incubation onset (see Figure 
   <a rid="ece33446-fig-0001" ref-type="fig" href="#ece33446-fig-0001">1</a>). Window 12 is only used in the analysis of incubation duration and spans from the onset of incubation up until hatching.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Candidate models for model selection were LMs and took the form of two configurations of null model (models with no temperature variables included), which were compared with four configurations of temperature model, each containing a single temperature variable (see Table 
   <a rid="ece33446-tbl-0001" ref-type="table-wrap" href="#ece33446-tbl-0001">1</a>a). Four different temperature measures were tested: mean temperature, mean daily minimum temperature (MMin), mean daily maximum temperature (MMax), and mean daily temperature range (Trange). In total, this gave 44 different explanatory temperature variables (four measures across 11 windows). A total of 176 candidate temperature models were compared with relative incubation onset as the response variable, consisting of 44 different temperature variables in each of the four model configurations and the two null models. For models with incubation duration as a response variable, each candidate model also included a fixed effect of relative incubation onset. As incubation occurs at night prior to the onset of full incubation, any delay or advance in full incubation onset will alter the number of accumulated “incubation hours” and therefore will likely influence the final duration of full incubation. An additional four candidate models were also run due to the additional time window for this variable, totaling 180 candidate models.
  </p>
  <div id="ece33446-tbl-0001" xml:lang="en" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
   <span class="label">Table 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Candidate model configurations for the analysis of incubation behavior. (a) Candidate models for the analysis of relative onset of incubation and incubation duration. Models for incubation duration also include the relative onset of incubation as a fixed variable. (b) Candidate models for the analysis of daily incubation intensity</p>
   </div>
   <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
    <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/>
    <col style="border-right:solid 1px #000000" span="1"/>
    <thead valign="top">
     <tr style="border-bottom:solid 1px #000000">
      <th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Model name</th>
      <th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Explanatory fixed variables</th>
     </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">(a)</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Null 1</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clutch initiation date</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Null 2</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clutch initiation date + Clutch size</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Temperature 1</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Temperature variable</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Temperature 2</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Temperature variable + Clutch initiation date</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Temperature 3</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Temperature variable × Clutch initiation date</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Temperature 4</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Temperature variable + Clutch size</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" colspan="2" rowspan="1">(b)</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Null 1</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Clutch initiation date</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Temperature 1</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Incubation day + Temperature variable</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Temperature 2</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Incubation day + Temperature variable + Clutch initiation date</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Temperature 3</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Incubation day + Temperature variable × Clutch initiation date</td>
     </tr>
     <tr>
      <td align="left" style="padding-left:10%" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Temperature 4</td>
      <td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Incubation day + Temperature variable + Clutch size</td>
     </tr>
    </tbody>
   </table>
   <div class="permissions">
    <span class="copyright-holder">John Wiley &amp; Sons, Ltd</span>
   </div>
  </div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For incubation intensity, binomial generalized linear mixed‐effects models (GLMMs) were used with daily incubation effort as the response variable and temperature and stage of incubation (incubation day) as fixed effects. The random effect of individual was also included to take account of individual differences in incubation effort. Incubation days ran from the onset of full incubation (day 1) to the day prior to hatch day. Hatch date itself was excluded as this is when iButtons were removed. Candidate models each included a single temperature variable from daily mean temperature, daily minimum temperature, daily maximum temperature, and daily temperature range. Five different configurations of model were trialed (see Table 
   <a rid="ece33446-tbl-0001" ref-type="table-wrap" href="#ece33446-tbl-0001">1</a>b). Therefore, a total of 20 candidate models were trialed.
  </p>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Candidate models were compared using the ΔAIC. The preferred model was defined as the model with the lowest AIC. Models are considered as not significantly different to the preferred model if the ΔAIC is less than 2. It should be noted that as each model including a temperature variable contains at least a partially overlapping or correlated variable (as all temperature measures and windows are likely to be correlated), we would not expect these analyses to always produce any single clearly preferred model.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="ece33446-sec-0012" class="sec">
  <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.2.5</span>
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To what extent do these three aspects of incubation behavior (relative onset, duration, and intensity) contribute to improving synchrony between timing of chick hatching and the caterpillar peak?</div>
  <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The influence of relative incubation onset and incubation duration on the observed synchrony was tested by comparing the observed hatch date synchrony (hatch date minus caterpillar peak timing) to a null expectation of hatch synchrony, if either aspect of incubation behavior had not varied. This is similar to the technique applied to the long‐term data; however, in this instance we are able to distinguish between different aspects of incubation behavior and quantify their impacts independently. A null expectation was created for both relative incubation onset (calculated as the clutch completion date plus the duration of full incubation minus caterpillar timing) and incubation duration (calculated as the clutch completion date plus the relative incubation onset and the mean duration of full incubation in 2014—12 days minus caterpillar timing). The variance of the observed hatching synchrony was compared to the two null estimations using pairwise 
   <span class="italic">F</span> tests for equality of variance. As there was no logical null estimate for the duration of daytime incubation, isolation of the influence of this element of incubation behavior on mean synchrony was not possible. Therefore, only the influence of relative incubation onset on mean synchrony was tested. This was conducted using a paired 
   <span class="italic">t</span> test between the observed synchrony and a null estimate with no onset changes.
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
