<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="ece33446-sec-0004" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">2.1.1</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Long‐term breeding timing</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The nest box breeding great tit population of Wytham woods has been studied since 1960 using a standardized procedure (Perrins, 
  <a rid="ece33446-bib-0033" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33446-bib-0033">1965</a>; Perrins &amp; McCleery, 
  <a rid="ece33446-bib-0036" ref-type="ref" href="#ece33446-bib-0036">1989</a>). Nest boxes (
  <span class="italic">n</span> = 1,203 with an average of 225 occupied by great tits each year) are visited weekly from early April. During these weekly checks, nest stage and number of eggs are recorded, and the date that a female initiated her clutch is then inferred by assuming a laying rate of one egg per day and counting back from the number of eggs observed on the weekly check. When at least three eggs are present, they are weighed so that species can be assigned (blue tits, coal tits (
  <span class="italic">Periparus ater</span>), and marsh tits (
  <span class="italic">Poecile palustris</span>) also use the Wytham nest boxes). Clutch size is defined as the maximum number of eggs observed in the nest. Date of hatching is established by visiting the nest on the estimated hatch date (date of clutch completion plus 11 days) and then every other day until the eggs hatch. If eggs have hatched prior to the hatch check, the largest chicks are weighed and assigned age based on their weight. Parents are identified at the nest either remotely using RFID (radio‐frequency identification) scanners (all previously trapped birds are fitted with RFID tags) or by catching using spring‐loaded nest box traps. All surviving nestlings are tagged with uniquely identifiable metal leg rings and RFID tags at 2 weeks of age. Nests are then checked postfledging to determine the number of chicks that left the nest.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The timing of caterpillar peak abundance is taken to be the median date on which caterpillars descend to the ground to pupate. These data have been collected as part of a long‐term study in Wytham woods, supplied by Dr L. Cole.</p>
</sec>
