<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Concepts in pediatric thermoregulation have been revisited and challenged over the past 20 years, countering the argument that children possess inferior thermoregulatory capabilities [
 <xref rid="B12-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>], particularly in mild and moderate environmental conditions. However, greater risk of adverse health events compared to healthy adults is widely recognized in more extreme environmental conditions and during physical exertion. Considering the rapidity and magnitude of predicted global climate change and adverse environmental conditions, it is prudent to understand the effects on physiological function resulting from high ambient temperatures, UV radiation [
 <xref rid="B2-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B13-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>,
 <xref rid="B14-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>], and pollution [
 <xref rid="B4-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>,
 <xref rid="B15-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B16-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>,
 <xref rid="B17-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>,
 <xref rid="B18-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. In addition, understanding the interplay between multiple environmental stressors and increasingly common childhood diseases and comorbidities, including obesity and the onset of preventable ‘adult’ diseases in children, is important in accurately predicting thermoregulatory responses and long-term health effects in a rapidly changing environmental landscape. This review is not a comprehensive and exhaustive review of thermoregulation in children, for which the reader is directed to other articles [
 <xref rid="B19-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,
 <xref rid="B20-nutrients-11-02010" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>]. Rather, the focus of the present review will be adult–child differences in thermoregulation, with an emphasis on the adverse impact of projected environmental and climate change on thermoregulation, physiological function, overall health, and precautions for risk reduction.
</p>
