<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="p0045">The study sampled the South Tongu and Zabzugu districts purposively to represent the south and the north of Ghana, respectively. The consideration of these two districts was based on their peculiar characteristics being defined by their ecological zones and also because some climate related projects have been implemented in the past by MoFA and other stakeholders in these two districts. Specific reference was given to Integrated Climate Risk Management Projected which was implemented in the two districts between 2013 and 2019. This project promoted climate adaptation mechanisms as a way of reducing the risks associated with the increasing climate shocks such as floods and droughts. Five communities were selected each from the two districts using simple random sampling procedure. Excel was used in generating random numbers for each community and the first five communities with the highest random numbers in each district were selected. In the final stage of the sampling, simple random sampling procedure was used to select 30 farmers from each selected community. A list of farmers for each selected community was obtained from the office of MoFA in the two districts and entered into Microsoft excel software. A random probability of inclusion was generated for each farmer and the first 30 farmers with the highest probabilities of inclusion were selected in each community. This gave a total sample size of 300 farmers (150 per each district). In order to understand the role of household's power-play in gendered climate adaptation, simple random sampling of the respondents was blind on the status of the respondents. This means that the sampled respondent from a household could either be a household member who operated his or her own farm or a family head who operated their own farm. As such, there was no predetermined number of members within each sampled group. 
 <xref rid="tbl1" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref> shows the distribution of sampled elements at each sampling stage.
</p>
