<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Several studies found sample size had a greater influence on first-flowering estimates than on mean flowering estimates. 
 <xref rid="ref-33" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Miller-Rushing &amp; Primack (2008)</xref> used field data and found that small sample sizes led to biased estimations of first-flowering dates, but mean flowering day was not biased by sample sizes. 
 <xref rid="ref-39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Moussus, Julliard &amp; Jiguet (2010)</xref> investigated sample sizes by simulating 10 known phenological estimators, such as mean flowering day and first-flowering date. After comparing known phenological shifts from simulated sample data with shift estimations from models using the same data, 
 <xref rid="ref-39" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Moussus, Julliard &amp; Jiguet (2010)</xref> concluded that first-flowering dates were inaccurate because they showed much greater differences in comparisons than mean flowering day. Low sample sizes prompted 
 <xref rid="ref-1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bertin (2015)</xref> to provide a detailed analysis of how sample size affected mean, median, range, early flowering and late flowering summary statistics. In random simulations comparing sample sizes, mean flowering day values deviated less than five days for species with as few as four samples (
 <xref rid="ref-1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bertin, 2015</xref>). 
 <xref rid="ref-1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bertin (2015)</xref> concluded that the mean was a more robust measure of phenology than other estimators of early flowering. 
 <xref rid="ref-1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Bertin (2015)</xref> also showed that by increasing the sample size to 20, mean flowering times deviated only one to two days. A recent study by 
 <xref rid="ref-50" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Pearse et al. (2017)</xref> used a Weibull distribution to estimate the start of the process of flowering rather than using only first-flowering observations. 
 <xref rid="ref-50" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Pearse et al. (2017)</xref> showed that by controlling for differences in sampling, first-flowering, peak-flowering (median) and cessation of flowering show similar changes over time in response to climate change. The model used by 
 <xref rid="ref-50" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Pearse et al. (2017)</xref> was also shown to be consistent with changes in mean-flowering from a separate sample using an early time period.
</p>
