<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par2" class="p">The climate and ecosystems usually respond rather linearly to changes in external conditions. However, there are also occasions when at some point a sudden and large shift to a very different state occurs. An important cause of such behavior can be a positive feedback which leads to a self-amplifying change, making the system very sensitive to external conditions. Such feedback-induced threshold behavior is often referred to as a tipping point
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">1</xref>
 </sup>. If the feedback is very strong, alternative stable states can exist under the same external conditions (Fig. 
 <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" class="xref">1a</xref>). In models, the parameter values at which the system’s dynamics suddenly changes are called bifurcation points. For example, when the system is driven over a bifurcation point where a current equilibrium ceases to exist, an abrupt and irreversible shift toward a different equilibrium can occur. Tipping points and alternative states exist in many simple models, for example representing ocean circulation
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" class="xref">2</xref>
 </sup>, global ice coverage
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3" class="xref">3</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" class="xref">4</xref>
 </sup>, Arctic sea ice
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5" class="xref">5</xref>
 </sup>, vegetation-atmosphere interaction
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" class="xref">6</xref>
 </sup>, terrestrial ecosystems
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" class="xref">7</xref>
 </sup>, and the East Asian and Indian monsoons
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8" class="xref">8</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" class="xref">9</xref>
 </sup>. Moreover, there are sometimes also observational indications that multiple states exist in reality
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10" class="xref">10</xref>
 </sup>, and there is evidence that abrupt shifts have occurred in the past
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">11</xref>–
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">13</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
