<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Changes in biophysical process following forest fire</div>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The underlying biophysical mechanisms behind the observed changes in surface temperature can be better understood by looking at the variations in the components of the surface energy balance (see Methods). Consistent with LST, changes in surface fluxes immediately (1 year) after fires also showed distinct latitudinal and seasonal patterns (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>). Changes in surface energy fluxes were more dramatic at high latitudes ( &gt; 45 N/30 S), possibly due to higher fire severity (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1c</a>). At high latitudes, there was an increase in summer (June, July, August (JJA)) SW
  <sub>in</sub> absorption (△SW
  <sub>in</sub> = 2.97 ± 0.85 W m
  <span class="sup">−2</span>) due to a decrease in albedo (△α = −0.0096 ± 0.0031), and a decrease in winter (December, January, February (DJF)) SW
  <sub>in</sub> absorption (△SW
  <sub>in</sub> = −2.05 ± 0.95) due to an increase in α (△α = 0.033 ± 0.0038). The combination of these changes led to a weak increase in net annual SW
  <sub>in</sub> absorption (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>, Supplementary Figs. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">9</a>-
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">11</a>). The upwelling longwave radiation (△LW
  <sub>out</sub>), based on the surface energy balance, is similar to the LST response. Forest fires reduced the annual evaporative cooling (△LE) (primarily during the growing season) due to the consumption of forest canopy and ground vegetation, together with changes in SW
  <sub>in</sub> absorption. These reductions contributed to latitudinal and seasonal changes in sensible and ground heat fluxes (△(HE + G)). In contrast, fire-induced changes in surface energy fluxes were relatively minor and lacked seasonality at low latitudes (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>, Supplementary Figs. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">9</a>-
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">11</a>).
  <div id="Fig4" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Change in energy balance after one year after fire. Immediate (1 year) impacts of fire-induced forest loss on the surface energy flux as a result of changes in 
     <span class="bold">a</span> incoming shortwave radiation (△SW
     <sub>in</sub>), 
     <span class="bold">b</span> upwelling longwave radiation (△LW
     <sub>out</sub>), 
     <span class="bold">c</span> the combination of sensible and ground heat fluxes (△(HE + G)), and 
     <span class="bold">d</span> the latent heat flux (△LE). For the latitudinal summaries of impacts, black lines represent annual impacts, red lines represent summer (June, July, August; JJA) impacts, and blue lines represent winter (December, January, February; DJF) impacts. The shaded areas are the mean ± one standard deviation. Panels 
     <span class="bold">a</span>, 
     <span class="bold">b</span>, 
     <span class="bold">c</span>, 
     <span class="bold">d</span> were created in the R environment for statistical computing and graphics (
     <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.r-project.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">https://www.r-project.org/</span>)
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2018_8237_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e647" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par12" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We also attributed the post-fire trajectory in surface LST to the relative importance between albedo-induced changes in SW (shortwave) radiation (△SW
  <sub>in</sub>) and ET-induced changes in LE (latent heat) fluxes (△LE), within 9 year following fire (see Methods). The strong warming effect immediately ( &lt; 1 year) after fire in boreal forests was due to both a reduction in evaporative cooling and an increase in SW
  <sub>in</sub> absorption (Figs. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3b, c</a>). As the vegetation reestablished, the surface radiative budget becomes dominated by increasing surface albedo thus contributing to a long-term cooling effect. Decreases in ET due to forest canopy loss leveled off after 2 years, possibly because reductions in forest ET (evapotranspiration) were partially offset by increases in grass/shrub ET. As a result, the initial net warming effect caused by decreased LE was slowly outweighed by the cooling effect caused by decreases in absorbed △SW
  <sub>in</sub> causing a cooling trend after 5 years (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a> and Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">12</a>). In contrast, warming effects in tropical savannas were caused primarily by reduced evaporative cooling (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">12</a>). Changes in annual albedo and subsequent effects on SW forcing were very weak, as albedo recovered within several months after fire
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
  </span>, but evapotranspiration required a much longer time to recover.
 </p>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The contrasts between boreal forest and tropical savanna LST responses and surface energy fluxes imply that fire regime characteristics are important for determining surface energy impacts. Therefore, we related △LST to fire severity (% of high severity fire) and BA (% of area burned) within each 2 × 2 degree region in order to explore their impacts on the surface energy budget (see Methods). We found a stronger non-linear relationship between fire severity and summer LST (
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.63) than between BA and summer LST (
  <span class="italic">R</span>
  <span class="sup">2</span> = 0.02), suggesting that fire severity may have a bigger influence on perturbations to the surface radiative budget than BA (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a> and Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">13</a>), which is consistent with previous findings at the regional scale
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>
  </span>. We also related △LST to BA and fire severity at the 0.05˚ scale, which showed a stronger response of △LST to fire severity, especially in tropical regions (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">14</a>). Among biomes, tropical fires are characterized by higher burn frequency but lower fire severity, which partially explains the dampened response of △α, △ET, and △LST within tropical regions. In contrast, boreal forest fires are typically higher in severity but lesser in areal extent, leading to stronger responses in surface biophysical properties (e.g., albedo, forest canopy consumption) and resultant climate feedbacks and energy flux perturbations. The non-linear relationship between △LST and fire severity (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>) suggests that small changes in fire severity in typically low fire severity regions, such as the tropics and Siberian boreal forests, may result in potentially large changes in the post-fire LST response.
  <div id="Fig5" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 5</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Effects of fire severity and burned area on summer (June, July, August; JJA) temperature. Panels show the relationship between land surface temperature change and 
     <span class="bold">a</span> the percentage of high severity fire, and 
     <span class="bold">b</span> the percentage of burned area. Blue points show results from boreal forests, whereas red points show results from the tropical savannas within each 2 × 2 degree region
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2018_8237_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e725" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
