<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Space-for-time approach</div>
 <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We used a space-for-time approach, in which we compared the LST difference (∆LST) between burned pixels (LST
  <sub>fire</sub>) and adjacent unburned pixels (LST
  <sub>control</sub>) to assess the climate effects of fire on local surface temperatures at 0.05° spatial resolution:
  <div id="Equ1" class="disp-formula">
   <span class="label">1</span>
   <div class="alternatives">
    <span id="M1" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$\Delta {\mathrm{LST = LST}}_{{\mathrm{fire}}}{\mathrm{ - LST}}_{{\mathrm{control}}}$$\end{document}</span>
    <div id="M2" display="block" class="math">
     <span class="mi">Δ</span>
     <div class="msub">
      <div class="mrow">
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">LST = LST</span>
      </div>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">fire</span>
      </div>
     </div>
     <div class="msub">
      <div class="mrow">
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">-LST</span>
      </div>
      <div class="mrow">
       <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">control</span>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="41467_2018_8237_Article_Equ1.gif" position="anchor" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Positive (negative) ∆LST indicates a warming (cooling) effect due to fire. Differences in albedo (∆α), ET (∆ET), and energy fluxes (e.g., incoming shortwave radiation (∆SW
  <sub>in</sub>), upwelling longwave radiation (∆LW
  <sub>out</sub>), latent heat fluxes (∆LE), and sensible and ground heat fluxes ∆(HE + G)) are defined similarly
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>
  </span>.
 </p>
 <p id="Par23" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The key goal for this space-for-time approach was to make sure that the change in land surface temperature and energy fluxes was only due to fire, and not due to other factors such as background climate conditions, vegetation type, structure, and dynamics, or the physical environment. To achieve this goal, we employed a three-step procedure (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">4</a>).
 </p>
 <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the first step, for each fire pixel, we overlaid a 9 × 5 pixel search window (longitude × latitude, approximately equal to 50 km × 28 km). Only unburned pixels within the window with the same background climate (defined by Köppen–Geiger climate region map: Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">8</a>) and forest type (defined by MODIS land cover data: Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">15</a>) as the fire pixel were selected as candidate control pixels. This step ensured that the fire and control pixels were within the same background climate and forest type.
 </p>
 <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the second step, time series of spectral indices, including NDVI (Normalized Difference Vegetation Index), LST, and albedo (α), were compared between fire pixels and each candidate control pixel for 2 years before the fire year (
  <span class="italic">t</span> – 2, 
  <span class="italic">t</span> – 1, and 
  <span class="italic">t</span>). If the difference in spectral indices between fire and candidate control pixels was smaller than a threshold (∆NDVI &lt; 0.05, ∆LST &lt; 0.2, ∆α &lt; 0.05), the candidate control pixels were retained. After this procedure, post-fire (
  <span class="italic">t</span> + 1) spectral indices for each candidate control were checked relative to prefire time series (
  <span class="italic">t</span> – 2, 
  <span class="italic">t</span> – 1, and 
  <span class="italic">t</span>) of the same pixel in order to ensure consistency within the control pixels. This step made sure that fire and control pixels were stable and comparable in vegetation characteristics and biophysical parameters.
 </p>
 <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the third step, the difference in physical environment (i.e., elevation, aspect, and slope) between fire and control pixels were also compared. If the physical environment between fire and candidate control pixels were similar (∆elevation &lt; 50 m, ∆slope &lt; 5, ∆aspect &lt; 30), the control pixels were retained. This step ensured that fire and control pixels were topographically similar enough for comparison. Only the control pixel located nearest to the fire pixel was used if more than one candidate control pixel was found following the above-mentioned procedure.</p>
 <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A total of 92,452 paired fire-control samples were identified between 2005 and 2013 with higher numbers in the tropics and lower numbers in boreal regions (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">5</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
