<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Comparison of Resilience and Frailty</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In aging research, resilience has been used in psychology and was related to positive factors determining recovery such as strength, immunity, coping behavior, optimism, and good cognition (
  <a rid="ref37" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref37">Richardson, 2002</a>; 
  <a rid="ref1" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref1">Ahern et al., 2006</a>; 
  <a rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref31">Lavretsky, 2014</a>). This fundamentally distinguishes resilience from frailty, which primarily was defined for physical changes, and was validated only for predicting negative outcomes such as death and hospitalization, and which only takes account of deficits (
  <a rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref11">Clegg et al., 2013</a>). This difference between frailty and resilience is reflected by the six currently available resilience scales, which all use different, positive psychological factors predicting recovery. However, similar to frailty scales, current resilience scales limit their measurements to a single point in time (see 
  <a rid="tab2" ref-type="table" href="#tab2">Table 2</a>; 
  <a rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref31">Lavretsky, 2014</a>).
 </p>
 <div id="tab2" position="float" class="table-wrap" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Table 2</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Comparison of the current state of measurements of frailty and resilience.</p>
  </div>
  <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
   <thead>
    <tr>
     <th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/>
     <th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Measures of resilience</th>
     <th align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Measures of frailty</th>
    </tr>
   </thead>
   <tbody>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
      <span class="bold">Static</span>: list of items questioned or observed
     </td>
     <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Predict positive outcomes (recovery). Currently, 6 psychological resilience scales are in use (e.g., Conner-Davidson resilience questionnaire)</td>
     <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Predict negative outcomes, e.g., mortality. More than 50 static frailty scales are currently available (e.g., Fraily index or Fraily phenotype)</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
     <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">
      <span class="bold">Dynamic</span>: monitoring stimulus-response over time
     </td>
     <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dynamic measures of resilience are not yet available: the hypothesis to develop and validate these is proposed here (e.g., response of blood pressure on orthostatic response over time)</td>
     <td align="left" valign="top" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Dynamic measurements of frailty are not available</td>
    </tr>
   </tbody>
  </table>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While normal aging results in only gradual loss of systemic resilience, this can happen more quickly and unpredictably if aging is accelerated by disease. If the risk for systemic failure is high, young resilient patients usually are transferred to the intensive care. Successful transfer of geriatric patients to an intensive care ward might be improved by the assessment of resilience beforehand, but this assessment is lacking in current practice. Not surprisingly, in medicine, the efforts to understand systemic resilience are most advanced in geriatrics and critical care medicine. In the face of a rapidly aging population and a broad range of public health challenges, there is a widespread and growing interest in assessing resilience and unraveling factors that contribute to it. For instance, geriatricians have shown that gait speed and hand grip strength are good predictors of expected lifespan (
  <a rid="ref49" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref49">Studenski et al., 2011</a>). Qualitative checklists on resilience also allowed a reasonable quantification of overall human health (
  <a rid="ref31" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref31">Lavretsky, 2014</a>). However, these are all indirect and static indicators of resilience.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">An exciting and promising approach to quantify resilience is to measure the rates of recovery following a micro-stressor which causes a safe, micro-change in healthy state (
  <a rid="ref20" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref20">Hadley et al., 2017</a>). Originally, it was thought that this resilience could only be determined by invoking a shift in the biological system and measuring the magnitude of the stressor needed for that. However, it now appears that stochastic changes in the dynamics of biological systems may be used to quantify the chances for recovery after passing a TP, but without pushing the patient over the TP (
  <a rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref16">Gijzel et al., 2017</a>). The most straightforward dynamic indicator of resilience is slowing down of recovery (SDR). Simply put, SDR is the response to micro-changes close to a TP. Increased variance and higher autocorrelation in individual time-series of variables that reflect low system resilience have shown to be highly correlated with SDR (
  <a rid="fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#fig2">Figure 2</a>) and may have similar predictive value (
  <a rid="ref55" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref55">Veraart et al., 2011</a>; 
  <a rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref16">Gijzel et al., 2017</a>).
 </p>
 <div id="fig2" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Graphical illustration of the dynamical resilience indicators. If a person has low systemic resilience, fluctuations of self-rated health over time are hypothesized to show higher variance 
    <span class="bold">(A</span> vs. 
    <span class="bold">B)</span>, higher temporal autocorrelation 
    <span class="bold">(C</span> vs. 
    <span class="bold">D)</span>, and higher cross-correlation between self-rated health domains 
    <span class="bold">(E</span> vs. 
    <span class="bold">F)</span>. In this example of fluctuations of self-rated health (data were randomly induced with a model), the black line may represent physical health and the gray line mental health (
    <a rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref16">Gijzel et al., 2017</a>).
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="fphys-10-00723-g002" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Recently, we showed first proof of concept for the value of SDR while testing the parameters of blood pressure regulation (
  <a rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref28">Lagro et al., 2014</a>). If a person suddenly stands up, orthostatic blood pressure drops due to gravity. Normally, the body quickly corrects this by vasoconstriction and increased cardiac output. This rapid regulation often fails in older adults, leading to a drop in cerebrovascular perfusion, sometimes even resulting in a syncope. Remarkably, a slow rate of blood pressure recovery upon standing up was a significant predictor of recurrent syncope and all-cause mortality (
  <a rid="fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#fig3">Figure 3</a>; 
  <a rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref27">Lagro et al., 2012</a>, 
  <a rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref28">2014</a>). Thus, SDR in blood pressure regulation was a preliminary sign of lower systemic resilience connected to overall death rate and could be accurately measured with hemodynamic parameters. Similarly, time series of self-reported mood revealed that SDR in expressed emotions signaled a lower chance of mood recovery (
  <a rid="ref51" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref51">van de Leemput et al., 2014</a>). It thus appears that human beings are no exception to what may be a general rule in all complex dynamical systems that SDR in physiological key parameters can be a generic indicator of low resilience.
 </p>
 <div id="fig3" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>Slowing down in recovery patterns of systolic blood pressure (SBP) after active standing. Lines show Cox proportional hazards ratios for all-cause mortality, unadjusted and adjusted for age, gender, body mass index, co-morbidity, SBP, diastolic BP (DBP), heart rate, and drug use (
    <span class="italic">N</span> = 238). Mortality is lower in the group with 95% recovery to baseline SBP in less than 1 min after standing (
    <span class="italic">N</span> = 95), compared to the group with 80–95% recovery (
    <span class="italic">N</span> = 98), and the slow (&lt;80%) recovery group (
    <span class="italic">N</span> = 45), (
    <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.05) (
    <a rid="ref27" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref27">Lagro et al., 2012</a>, 
    <a rid="ref28" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref28">2014</a>).
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="fphys-10-00723-g003" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
