<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Frailty</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">According to the official EU statistics, 25.8 million Europeans were age 80 and older in 2015. Of 67.9 million Europeans aged 65–79 years, an estimated 7.5 million (5%) may be frail (
  <a rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref11">Clegg et al., 2013</a>). In the group older than 80 years, 16% is estimated to be frail, and in total, this group is growing rapidly. Frailty is mostly defined epidemiologically as a health state with high risk for negative outcomes following minor illness or trauma (
  <a rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref11">Clegg et al., 2013</a>; 
  <a rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref39">Rockwood and Mitnitski, 2015</a>). Described in the context of this paper, the major problem in these frail adults is that they are highly prone to multiple TP incidents. The incidences of the most important TP incidents within 3 months after hospital discharge are high, but also highly variable: delirium: 20–29%, falls: 11–20%, and acute functional decline: 11–60% (
  <a rid="ref6" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref6">Bakker et al., 2014</a>; 
  <a rid="ref24" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref24">Inouye et al., 2014</a>; 
  <a rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref5">Bakker and Olde Rikkert, 2015</a>). In 25–40% of the subjects, this resulted in sudden and substantial loss of well-being (
  <a rid="ref46" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref46">Steptoe et al., 2015</a>). These high rates indicate that acute changes in health are a major burden for older adults, their families, and society. Improved prediction models are therefore urgently required. Currently, medical practitioners are unable to identify which older patients are close to their TPs, nor whether they have the power to recover from passing these TPs, and benefit from treatment (
  <a rid="ref53" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref53">van Kempen et al., 2015</a>). There are several reasons why identifying resilience in individual patients requires innovation of the current frailty measures, which predominantly have epidemiological aims (
  <a rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref39">Rockwood and Mitnitski, 2015</a>). The frailty measures are mostly based on simply summing up the patients’ static deficits, which can only predict major negative outcomes such as mortality and hospitalizations, and predict only at the group level (between patients), not for individual patients (within patients) (
  <a rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref5">Bakker and Olde Rikkert, 2015</a>; 
  <a rid="ref17" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref17">Gill et al., 2015</a>). The more than 50 measures of frailty that have been developed in the last two decades are all based on a static risk assessment, calculated at a single time point (
  <a rid="ref21" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref21">Hamaker et al., 2012</a>; 
  <a rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref11">Clegg et al., 2013</a>; 
  <a rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref23">Hubbard and Jatoi, 2015</a>; 
  <a rid="ref22" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref22">Hoogendijk, 2016</a>). None of these measures monitors or predicts within patients’ (change in) recovery over time after passing from a healthy to a disease state, i.e., after passing a TP. Moreover, frailty indicators were not validated to predict recovery (
  <a rid="ref5" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref5">Bakker and Olde Rikkert, 2015</a>). Finally, innovation is needed because not only deficits are relevant for recovery potential but also positive capabilities such as coping ability, fitness level, and having goals in life (
  <a rid="ref13" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref13">Crimmins, 2005</a>; 
  <a rid="ref56" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref56">Warnier et al., 2016</a>). Mechanistically, it makes sense that recovery potential is not simply the reverse of physical frailty.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Having to face an increasingly aged population, recognizing frailty has already resulted in major advances in geriatric medicine. Currently, frailty is most precisely measured by the frailty index (FI) based on accumulation of health deficits (
  <a rid="ref39" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref39">Rockwood and Mitnitski, 2015</a>; 
  <a rid="ref53" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref53">van Kempen et al., 2015</a>). This FI quantitatively assesses an individual’s clinical health state, including symptoms, clinical signs, laboratory abnormalities, diseases, and disabilities. However, since frailty criteria are mostly based on the consequences of functional losses, an FI fails to identify individuals at risk before changes are apparent during clinical examination. Recently, Mitnitski et al. called for the development of an earlier measure of frailty and therefore proposed a biomarker-based FI (
  <a rid="ref34" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref34">Mitnitski et al., 2015</a>). Although this advanced FI may indeed contribute to early recognition of frailty, it does not help to enhance understanding of TPs recovery potential in humans. Moreover, the currently used FI’s conceptually do not capture the variable and often non-linear changes in vulnerability over time in a single patient (
  <a rid="ref54" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref54">Varadhan et al., 2008</a>; 
  <a rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref11">Clegg et al., 2013</a>). This is because, so far, it is impossible to measure frailty in a dynamic way.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In agreement with this, Fried’s research group suggested that frail and non-frail adults may be differentiated much better by assessing the dynamics of their physiological systems’ response to stimuli, instead of the current frailty assessment at only a single time point (
  <a rid="ref54" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref54">Varadhan et al., 2008</a>). However, the theoretical, practical, and analytical difficulties associated with such a dynamic approach to frailty so far have limited scientific progress in this direction. This is underlined by a systematic review of frailty studies, in which not a single example of such a dynamic approach to frailty was found (
  <a rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref11">Clegg et al., 2013</a>; 
  <a rid="ref23" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref23">Hubbard and Jatoi, 2015</a>). In the following subsection, the concept of subsystem TPs is linked to frailty and resilience and it is shown how this enables a common design for testing resilience in the equilibrium states of, for example, blood pressure, heart rate, and mood.
 </p>
</sec>
