<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Due to increased life expectancy, the number of persons aged 80 and over in Europe is predicted to rise with 250% within this century
  <a ref-type="fn" rid="fn001" href="#fn001">
   <span class="sup">1</span>
  </a>. One of the hallmarks of this aging trend is the importantly increasing heterogeneity of the population, as aging increases between person variability of most biological and psychological parameters (
  <a rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref36">Olde Rikkert et al., 1997</a>). However, apart from age and demographic variables, we often lack accurate information on the dispersion measures of physiological processes between older adults (
  <a rid="ref36" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref36">Olde Rikkert et al., 1997</a>). In this heterogeneity, “resilience” – in essence, the individual’s recovery potential and restore to its current state – may complement the term “frailty” and improve characterization of the differences in recovery potential between aging individuals. The linked concept of frailty is most often defined as a condition of being more susceptible to a diseased state due to decreased adaptability to stressors (
  <a rid="ref11" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref11">Clegg et al., 2013</a>). Current static frailty prognostics can predict risks for delirium, falls, and other frequently occurring subsystem tipping point (TP) transitions in older adults and ultimately also death. TPs are the points in time that separate a more healthy condition from an acute, but in principle reversible disease condition and malfunction of the human’s subsystems or organ dysfunction (e.g., delirium, a fall or a depressed state). Therefore, TPs are critical challenges to the older human’s equilibrium state (
  <a rid="ref41" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref41">Scheffer et al., 2001</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Improved understanding and forecasting of resilience as recovery potential from these TPs probably requires dynamic measures, reflecting the person’s change over time following a stressor. New dynamic resilience biomarkers (e.g., slowing down in blood pressure, temperature or glucose response after a standardized physiologic stressor) for resilience can enrich clinical prediction for pathophysiological recovery and could test interventions for their effectiveness in improving resilience. Such dynamic measures, i.e., measures with a time scale, should logically be the first to be tested as predictors of recovery, which is also a process over time, to which dynamic resilience measures conceptually can be most closely defined (
  <a rid="ref16" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref16">Gijzel et al., 2017</a>). Dynamic resilience can be quantified by analyzing time series in hemodynamics using indicators such as blood pressure, heart rate, and related variables, but also cerebrovascular responses can be simply and reliably studied over time following clinically relevant micro-stressors, such as changing posture or performing hyperventilation.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ultimately, clinical care might benefit greatly from improved forecasting of resilience regarding the frequently occurring health crises, such as falls and delirium, as it may improve personalization of recovery assisting interventions for older adults (
  <a rid="ref35" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref35">Olde Rikkert et al., 2016</a>). In addition, such forecasting may improve the selection of older patients for obtrusive surgical and oncologic interventions based on sufficiently high chances for recovery, as promoted, for example, for vascular surgery in the oldest old (
  <a rid="ref2" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref2">Ali et al., 2018</a>). Such medical interventions may be reconsidered or even withheld from older adults with insufficient resilience, because such patients face the risk of being pushed over their TPs into an acute and irreversible decline of their health, specifically by delirium, falls, depression, and loss of mobility. To raise a new perspective for quality of care improvement in medicine for the aged, this paper describes the concept of generic resilience for recovery of TPs and presents a new hypothesis of how this generic and subsystem resilience may be measured best.
 </p>
</sec>
