<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p id="Par7" class="p">As suggested by recent studies
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" class="xref">30</xref>
 </sup>, extensive regional and local climate change research is missing in many regions yet, and this is probably the only way to fully understand the response of ecological communities or individual species to climate drivers, including the identification of potential climate refugia
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" class="xref">31</xref>,
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" class="xref">32</xref>
 </sup>. Here we present the most detailed assessment that combines the analyses of seasonal climate change magnitude, direction and the recent velocity of climate change throughout the 20
 <sup class="sup">th</sup> and 21
 <sup class="sup">st</sup> century. In this study we introduce three novel adaptations of the method for climate velocity calculation of Burrows 
 <italic class="italic">et al</italic>.
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" class="xref">24</xref>
 </sup>, as follows: (1) Temporal trends are calculated by a non-parametric Mann-Kendall analysis instead of linear regression; (2) Spatial gradients in long-term median instead of average quantities were used to be consistent with the approach to temporal trends; (3) A novel approach was used to constrain occurrences of near-zero values of spatial gradients. The benefit of these adaptations is an increased robustness in dealing with data distributions potentially skewed by extremes to which an average based approach is more sensitive. In this study we use Germany as an example, because it has excellent availability of long-term weather records, including one of the world’s longest precipitation records. Furthermore, we assess  that the response of species to seasonal climate variability and velocity could be more easily detected, rather than  to coarser metrics such as annual changes in temperature and precipitation, as changes in species distribution are rarely controlled by the mean annual temperatures
 <sup class="sup">
  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" class="xref">27</xref>
 </sup>.
</p>
