<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">To address these issues, the Permafrost Carbon Network (
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.permafrostcarbon.org/" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">www.permafrostcarbon.org/</ext-link>) organized a multimodel assessment with “state-of-the-art” biogeochemical land models that coupled thaw depth with soil C exposure to evaluate (
 <italic class="italic">i</italic>) the contribution of model structural uncertainty and (
 <italic class="italic">ii</italic>) the potential impact of mitigation on the evolution of C storage in the northern permafrost region (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig01" class="xref">Fig. 1</xref>) out to the year 2299. All models were forced with common climate projections (
 <xref rid="r1" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>, 
 <xref rid="r7" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>) for climate change pathways representative of substantive (RCP4.5 stabilization pathway) and little to no (RCP8.5 nonstabilization pathway) mitigation effort (see 
 <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1719903115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">Fig. S1</ext-link> for global and northern high-latitude temperature projections in comparison with other CMIP5 models); RCP4.5 and RCP8.5 are pathways that would result in preindustrial to 2100 radiative forcing being 4.5 W⋅m
 <sup class="sup">−2</sup> (∼650 CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> equivalent) and 8.5 W⋅m
 <sup class="sup">−2</sup> (∼1,370 CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> equivalent), respectively (
 <xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>). To achieve the RCP4.5 pathway would require carbon emissions per energy consumption by global human society to decrease by 75% during this century (
 <xref rid="r8" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>). Our key questions in this analysis are as follows: (
 <italic class="italic">i</italic>) What is the variability in the projected loss of near-surface permafrost across models when forced with a common climate change trajectory (evaluated with eight models; 
 <xref rid="t01" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref>)? (
 <italic class="italic">ii</italic>) What is the variability in projected changes of C stored in the permafrost region (soil and vegetation) for different representative mitigation pathways among model simulations (evaluated with five models; 
 <xref rid="t01" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref>)? (
 <italic class="italic">iii</italic>) What factors explain the variability in the projected dynamics of C among the models (evaluated with three models; 
 <xref rid="t01" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref>)? (
 <italic class="italic">iv</italic>) What are the implications for climate mitigation policies?
</p>
