<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Sea‐level rise may decrease the marsh elevation by reducing their organic accretion (Nyman, Delaune, Roberts, &amp; Patrick, 
 <xref rid="ece35215-bib-0042" ref-type="ref">1993</xref>), promoting decomposition of the marsh substrates (Craft, 
 <xref rid="ece35215-bib-0011" ref-type="ref">2007</xref>; Weston, Vile, Neubauer, &amp; Velinsky, 
 <xref rid="ece35215-bib-0058" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>; Stagg, Schoolmaster, Krauss, Cormier, &amp; Conner, 
 <xref rid="ece35215-bib-0051" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>), and increasing erosion (Smith, Cialone, Wamsley, &amp; McAlpin, 
 <xref rid="ece35215-bib-0050" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>). Hence, the negative correlation between the marsh area and sea‐level can be expected. On contrary, increased air temperature and CO
 <sub>2</sub> concentration can contribute to the marsh stability against sea‐level rise. The elevated air temperature and atmospheric CO
 <sub>2</sub> may promote the marsh plant growth (for both aboveground and belowground) and thus their organic accretion (Langley, McKee, Cahoon, Cherry, &amp; Megonigal, 
 <xref rid="ece35215-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>; Ratliff, Braswell, &amp; Marani, 
 <xref rid="ece35215-bib-0044" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>). Although the enhancement of plant growth from CO
 <sub>2</sub>, as discussed earlier, is mainly for C3 plants, the fertilization of CO
 <sub>2</sub>, based on a modeling study, can increase the marsh elevation for a mixed C3 and C4 plant community (by increasing plant production) in similar magnitude to the effect of increasing inorganic sediment input (Ratliff et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35215-bib-0044" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>). The maintenance of the marsh elevation can further benefit from the increased belowground biomass: the increased shoot density will enhance the trapping of tidally driven sediment and provide stronger protection against erosion (Temmerman, Moonen, Schoelynck, Govers, &amp; Bouma, 
 <xref rid="ece35215-bib-0052" ref-type="ref">2012</xref>; Mudd, D'Alpaos, &amp; Morris, 
 <xref rid="ece35215-bib-0034" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>). It should also be noted that the influence of CO
 <sub>2</sub> fertilization on marsh elevation is likely to depend on many other factors such as the inorganic sedimentation rate (Langley &amp; Megonigal, 
 <xref rid="ece35215-bib-0026" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>; Langley et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35215-bib-0025" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>; Ratliff et al., 
 <xref rid="ece35215-bib-0044" ref-type="ref">2015</xref>) and may be offset by the enhanced decomposition resulted from a rising air temperature (Charles &amp; Dukes, 
 <xref rid="ece35215-bib-0006" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>; Kirwan &amp; Blum, 
 <xref rid="ece35215-bib-0024" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>). The fertilization effects of the increased air temperature and atmospheric CO
 <sub>2</sub> allow the coastal marshes to be more resilient against sea‐level rise, but this study documents a significant decrease in the brackish and saline marsh systems, where the impact of sea‐level is strongest and more likely to overwhelm the fertilization effects of temperature and CO
 <sub>2</sub>.
</p>
