<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">To identify the main sources of uncertainty and establish robust estimates of the aggregate effects of climate change on crop yields, meta-analyses were conducted at the global scale by Challinor et al. (
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>) to contribute to the food security and food production systems chapter of the Fifth Assessment Report (AR5) of the IPCC and at the regional scale, including West Africa (Roudier et al., 
 <xref rid="B162" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>; Knox et al., 
 <xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>). Meta-analyses that combine and compare results from numerous studies are widely used in epidemiology and medicine and can be a useful way of summarizing the range of projected outcomes in the literature and assessing consensus. The meta-analysis conducted by Challinor et al. (
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>) used a data set of more than 1700 published simulations to evaluate yield impacts of climate change and adaptation which is the largest pool of data from diverse modeling studies ever used for a global synthesis of this kind (Rötter, 
 <xref rid="B156" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>). The meta-analyses published by Knox et al. (
 <xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>) and Roudier et al. (
 <xref rid="B162" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>) are based on a smaller data set (1144 and 347 published simulations respectively) but concern specific regions: Asia and Africa in database compiled by Knox et al. (
 <xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>) and only West Africa in the database compiled by Roudier et al. (
 <xref rid="B162" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>). These latter two meta-analyses also include the response of relevant crops in Africa (maize, sorghum, millet, rice, cotton, cassava, groundnut, yam) while the meta-analysis conducted by Challinor et al. (
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>) includes only major crops such as maize, rice and wheat; maize and rice being the only crops of the study grown in West Africa. Interestingly, while there are all based on different approaches and different samples, the three studies came out with similar conclusions on how climate change will affect crop yield in West Africa and how this response varies across the different assumptions and methodological choices. While the magnitude of the response of crop yield to climate warming scenarios varies considerably in the simulations reported by Challinor et al. (
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>), Knox et al. (
 <xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>) and Roudier et al. (
 <xref rid="B162" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2011</xref>), the sign of the change is mostly negative with a mean yield reduction of −8% was identified in all Africa (Knox et al., 
 <xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>) and −11% in West Africa (Roudier et al., 
 <xref rid="B160" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>). Maize was found to be the most affected crop in West Africa and in the Sahel by Knox et al. (
 <xref rid="B92" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2012</xref>). Without adaptation, the mean response of major crops (mostly maize and rice) to climate change depicted by Challinor et al. (
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>) in tropical regions is a yield reduction. This robust yield loss is already significant at moderate levels of local warming (+2°C) but is more consensual and stronger in the second half of the century when the additional radiative forcing is amplified. If this negative impact on crop yield was already depicted in the previous IPCC report, it suggested such yield loss would only occur when exceeding 3–4°C local warming which might be due to an overestimation in previous studies of the yield benefits of enhanced atmospheric CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> (Rötter, 
 <xref rid="B156" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2014</xref>).
</p>
