<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec012" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">First, we showed that future climate changes, as predicted by the IPCC assessment reports [
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref041" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref041">41</a>], should have strong negative impacts on bird population sizes in farmland landscapes. This predicted negative impact of climate change on birds follows the trend of that observed for over the last decades around the world [
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref069" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref069">69</a>] and for European birds [
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref021" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref021">21</a>]. So, our results are in line with current knowledge on the role of climate in shaping bird populations [e.g. 
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref023">23</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref070" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref070">70</a>]. Furthermore, our study is consistent with research on the coupled effect of climate change and land use [
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref028">28</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref030">30</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref071" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref071">71</a>]. We also found evidence that farmland use changes can mitigate the negative effect of climate change for some species or habitat guilds. This result support the hypothesis from Eglington and Pearce-Higgins [
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref035">35</a>] and Dormann et al. [
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref033">33</a>] that there is a potential for countering negative effects of climate change by adaptive landscape management. Our results also emphasize the needs to consider land use/cover when predicting large-scale changes in biodiversity [
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref033">33</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref034">34</a>]. Nevertheless, in our study the climate effect significantly reduces abundance of some bird species in response to likely changes in agriculture. At broad spatial scales it is often possible to identify factors that limit maximum abundance without completely explaining or fully determining abundance in all places [
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref072" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref072">72</a>]. Environmental suitability may predict the upper limit of abundance better than mean abundance, making it particularly difficult to accurately predict local abundance under the influence of climate [
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref072" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref072">72</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref073" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref073">73</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our results predict that bird populations will continue to decline strongly if current observed trends in agriculture persist during the coming decades. This is consistent with other studies on past and potential future effects of agricultural intensification on bird species [
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref009" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref009">9</a>]. In our study, this effect is particularly strong for generalist species that live in farmland, while all specialist species but grassland species seem not to be impacted. This result seems partly conflicting with studies relating agricultural intensification to farmland bird declines [
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref074" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref074">74</a>, e.g. 
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref075" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref075">75</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref076" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref076">76</a>], but is consistent regarding trends in French populations in recent years. During the last decade, the rate of population declines of farmland specialists in France seems to have decreased [
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref047" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref047">47</a>]. Moreover, more than reflecting an intensification of practices—via higher input or mechanization—the 
  <span class="italic">‘status quo’</span> scenario reflects a unification of farmland cover in arable areas and a drastic reduction of permanent grassland throughout the country. Such a scenario is indeed more favorable to open-habitat species described in this study as cropland species such as skylark or corn bunting 
  <span class="italic">Emberiza calandra</span>, which in our results show a strong positive response to this scenario. This effect on open-habitat species pulls upwards the mean changes in abundance of farmland bird population. Meanwhile, it hides the strong negative effects of this scenario on the grassland species. As such, a 
  <span class="italic">‘status quo’</span> scenario may lead to small and species-poor communities by promoting only few very specialized species among farmland birds.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Similarly, we found few positive effects of 
  <span class="italic">‘biofuel’</span> scenarios on bird populations, and negative effects on farmland birds with the 
  <span class="italic">‘global biofuel’</span> scenario. In the latter, the homogenization of crops for rapeseed oil in arable areas and the decrease of grasslands in all agricultural areas are detrimental to farmland birds throughout the study area. As a result, this scenario is predicted to increase the biotic homogenization already observed in farmland by favoring generalist species [
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref077" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref077">77</a>]. In contrast to the global scenario, the 
  <span class="italic">‘regional biofuel’</span> scenario had a small positive impact on farmland and generalist birds. The combination of a regional extensification in livestock areas (i.e. increasing grasslands) and changes of mixed areas into more crop specialized areas seems to be more favorable to farmland birds. This is especially the case for crop specialists (e.g. skylark) and mixed cropland/grassland specialists (e.g. linnet). Although the 
  <span class="italic">‘regional biofuel’</span> scenario partially compensates grassland decrease in arable and mixed-farming areas by increasing their habitats in livestock areas, the strong negative impact of this scenario on grassland species indicates that the regional extensification of grasslands to counterbalance biofuel development and crop intensification may be not effective. As a result, although less favorable for generalists, this scenario may not promote a diversified community of specialists as it favors only those specialized in open cropped habitats.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Extensification scenarios seem to be able to reverse current negative bird population trends in French farmland. Especially, two scenarios—
  <span class="italic">‘regional extensification’</span> and 
  <span class="italic">‘livestock extensification’</span>—have the most positive response by bird abundance. This was mostly driven by a strong effect on farmland specialists. These two scenarios consider an increase of permanent and/or temporary grassland surfaces and an extensive management of these grasslands or crops (e.g. by diversifying rotations) in livestock and mixed-farming areas. These positive results are consistent with several studies that highlight a positive relationship between bird species abundances and semi-natural grasslands [e.g. 
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref078" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref078">78</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref079" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref079">79</a>] and with recommendations that have been made on low-intensive management of grasslands to benefit birds [e.g. 
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref080" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref080">80</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref081" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref081">81</a>]. Our results show that the combination of extensification in livestock areas and diversification of crops in arable areas as developed in the 
  <span class="italic">‘global extensification’</span> scenario have a more positive impact on birds, especially on farmland specialists, than the combination with biofuel crops (tending towards monocultures). This supports conclusions of previous studies that find landscape heterogeneity generally benefits biodiversity [
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref082" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref082">82</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref085" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref085">85</a>], but it could be sometimes at the expense of specialist species or of species of conservation concern [SPECs, 
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref086" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref086">86</a>]. Indeed, here we found that farmland species whose primary habitat is mixed production systems (cropland and grasslands) are negatively impacted by the 
  <span class="italic">‘global extensification’</span> scenario, as well as the 
  <span class="italic">‘livestock extensification’</span> scenario, whereas they benefit more from the regional extensification. These species are the less specialized of the farmland specialists, and they appear to respond like the generalists to the three scenarios of extensification. Finally, in a 
  <span class="italic">‘regional extensification’</span> scenario, agricultural practices such as diversification of crops or extensive management of grasslands seem to benefit both farmland and non-farmland specialists. However, if diversity-enhancing measures benefit non-farmland populations they do not favor some of the farmland specialist species which are more at risk [
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref077" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref077">77</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The regionalization of agricultural trends leads to heterogeneous changes in farmland cover between SARs. In the case of 
  <span class="italic">‘biofuel’</span> scenarios, the impact of biofuel crop cultivation on bird biodiversity depends on a combination of various effects at local or landscape scales [
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref013">13</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref087" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref087">87</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref088" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref088">88</a>], such as the choice of crops, geographical location, scale of implementation and the spatial distribution of the biofuel crops. This is also the case for extensification scenarios, in which the impact of contrasted variations in grassland extensification and crop diversification, either spatially or quantitatively, leads to contrasted responses of bird populations and does not benefit the same species. However, although a regional implementation provides more benefits to bird populations, the chosen crops largely determine the range of farmland specialists that are favored. Directly related to this regionalization policy, one important point is on mixed-farming systems (corresponding to mixed farming and diversification after livestock breeding; 
  <a rid="pone.0117850.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material" href="#pone.0117850.s003">S2 Table</a>). These systems represent a significant part of French farmland (30%). Given the results of the different extensification scenarios, it seems that agricultural extensification measures in these areas, such as increasing proportion of grasslands (permanent or temporary) and increasing diversity of crop rotation, reinforce the positive impact of extensification in livestock areas.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The positive effect of regionalization according to farmland cover scenarios varies between species. For instance, skylark generally responds more negatively to 
  <span class="italic">‘regional extensification’</span> scenarios, especially in arable areas, than to the 
  <span class="italic">‘global extensification’</span> scenario. These results can be explained by the preference of this species (or others such as yellowhammer) for low landscape diversity [
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref089" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref089">89</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref091" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref091">91</a>]. Conversely, regional scenarios, either 
  <span class="italic">‘biofuel’</span> or 
  <span class="italic">‘extensification’</span>, may favour grassland or semi open-species (e.g. whinchat) known to prefer diversified landscape.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">By developing farmland cover scenarios that we combined with available scenarios of global environmental changes (i.e., climate and land use), we projected potential impacts of changes in crop patterns on farmland bird populations. We believe our approach is innovative since no comparable policy impact assessment that integrates both climate and land-use changes at these relatively fine spatial scales has yet to be applied to such a large set of bird species at a national scale. Nevertheless, one should note that these scenarios cannot be interpreted as predictions of future land uses, but rather as sets of coherent and internally consistent simulations based on plausible but necessarily simplified assumptions of how future farms may develop. These kinds of scenarios should always be interpreted in comparison with the reference scenario (here, the 
  <span class="italic">‘status quo’</span> scenario). In addition, since we did not integrate potential effects of future climate changes on crop phenology, crop structure and yields, our results on the ability of land use to balance climatic effects should be interpreted cautiously. Our model relied on simple habitat associations and our projections are based on correlative analysis, which assumes stationarity. As in niche models, we assumed a high degree of niche conservatism between species occurrence-climate and abundance-land use relationships. Thus, it ignores consequences of species adaptations to changing climate and land use [
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref033">33</a>]. The uncertainty attached to violations of these assumptions cannot be estimated and is hence inevitably ignored [
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref092" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref092">92</a>]. Besides, some temporal mismatches between land use and bird data inputs may bias our forecasting results. We believe, however, that land use changes at such large spatial scale happen slower than land cover data. We emphasize the need to develop more land use scenarios at various spatiotemporal scales based on data that can match with the existing biological data sets, in order to make more accurate predictions from this type of scenario-based studies. It is also important to note that the value of our estimates is mainly heuristic, but our results therefore illustrate some possible consequences for biodiversity as a result of adopting various agricultural development pathways in the future.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Nevertheless, there are important conclusions that can be drawn from this scenario-based study. Our results confirm the importance of modeling land cover together with climate change when predicting future biodiversity changes in response to these key drivers, also because in some scenarios land use changes compensated partly the negative impacts predicted from climate change alone. The contrasted responses of bird populations to the different farmland cover scenarios, combined with land use changes, show that agricultural changes can be important drivers of bird diversity. A scenario of more intensive farmland is likely to contribute to further declines of breeding bird abundances in farmland habitats. Additional management efforts counteracting the decrease in landscape heterogeneity are thus needed. Increase or rehabilitation of grassland areas regionally or throughout the country, extensive management of both grasslands and crops areas, and increasing heterogeneity in arable areas might benefit bird populations, or even reverse the current trends, especially those of farmland birds. Such positive impacts justify the introduction or reinforcement of these extensive practices in the common agricultural policy. The extensification of farmland cover seems more appropriate than following with the current agricultural trends or the development of bioenergy crops. However, the effects of extensification on farmland birds differ markedly depending on region and landscape structure, and also depending on species habitat requirements. Consequently, conservation measures need to account for the regional differences in farming practices and landscape structure. These results can contribute to evaluations of public decisions for support in agriculture and biodiversity management. For this purpose, this study might be complemented by other approaches incorporating economic drivers such as agricultural prices and subsidies, which may affect the returns of different land use/cover patterns [see 
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref093" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref093">93</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref094" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref094">94</a>]. Finally, Concepción [
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref095" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref095">95</a>] has recently demonstrated that responses of organisms to agricultural change are strongly non-linear and dependent on landscape configuration. To better predict species responses, we suggest that further development of such farmland cover scenarios should integrate some landscape metrics which have strong effects on the abundance of bird populations, such as metrics of fragmentation (number of patches and edge density) but also topography [
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref034">34</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
