<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="intro" id="sec001" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The modification and management of landscapes to produce food or other agricultural commodities for human consumption represents one of the most severe and widespread threats to global biodiversity [
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref001" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref001">1</a>]. In 2011 in the European Union, 34% of the terrestrial area was used for cropland and 14% for grassland [
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref002" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref002">2</a>]. Numerous studies have highlighted that during the last decades agricultural intensification has already dramatically affected water quality, wildlife habitats and biodiversity [
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref003" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref003">3</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref006" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref006">6</a>], and this is particularly well documented for farmland birds [
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref007" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref007">7</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref010" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref010">10</a>]. In Europe, declines in farmland birds have been severe, and many species have suffered large decreases in abundance since the 1980s, such as skylark 
  <span class="italic">Alauda arvensis</span> (-51%), linnet 
  <span class="italic">Carduelis cannabina</span> (-63%), yellowhammer 
  <span class="italic">Emberiza citrinella</span> (-44%) and whinchat 
  <span class="italic">Saxicola rubetra</span> (-71%) [
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref011" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref011">11</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To respond to increases in major human needs over the next decades (changes in global trade, technology, policies), the structure of agricultural production and spatial patterns in farmland are likely to undergo important transformations [
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref012" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref012">12</a>]. Within agricultural areas, the increasing demand for food production, the introduction and expansion of bio-energy crops, modernization of agriculture techniques, abandonment of grazing areas and crop specialization and intensification, are main factors affecting farmland cover. These land cover changes are characterized by several significant processes such as the transformation of agricultural landscapes into new combinations of crops and semi-natural elements or the management of these crops to increase their productivity [
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref004" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref004">4</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref013" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref013">13</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref014" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref014">14</a>]. Furthermore, the choices in public policies and the spatial scale at which they are implemented (nationally or regionally) can imply differences in spatial patterns of land cover changes. In addition to this, the debate is still open between ‘land sharing’, that aims to integrate goals for food production and biodiversity protection on the same land, and ‘land sparing’, that aims to separate intensive farming from protected ecosystems at the larger scale [e.g. 
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref015" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref015">15</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref016">16</a>]. Thus, in this context, authorities need tools for decision support, to propose public policies to reconcile agricultural production and biodiversity [
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref017" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref017">17</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Anthropogenic climate change is another major driver of current biodiversity changes [
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref018" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref018">18</a>]. Evidence is accumulating that climate change in recent decades [
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref019" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref019">19</a>] has already affected many plants and animals [
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref020" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref020">20</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref022" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref022">22</a>]. A well-documented effect of climate change is a redistribution of species ranges as they track moving climate envelopes [
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref023">23</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref025" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref025">25</a>]. In the future, anthropogenic climatic change is expected to result in warmer global conditions from 2° to 4°C by 2100 [best estimate for RCP2.6 and RCP8.5 scenarios, 
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref026" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref026">26</a>]. The ability of species to survive this climatic transition may depend on the availability of suitable habitats within their future ranges and the ability for species to reach these new areas or adapt [
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref027" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref027">27</a>–
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref029">29</a>]. The availability of these habitats will also depend on changes in future land use and farmland cover.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Only few studies have explored the potential impacts of combined future climate and land use changes on biodiversity at national and continental scales [but see 
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref028">28</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref030">30</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref031" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref031">31</a>], because of the scarcity of relevant non-climatic data projected in the future [
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref032" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref032">32</a>]. However, non-climatic factors such as land-use intensity or landscape structure may be determinant for species richness [
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref033">33</a>] and may also affect large scale species distributions [
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref034">34</a>]. Moreover, Eglington &amp; Pearce-Higgins [
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref035">35</a>] have recently highlighted that the impacts of land-use change can exceed climate change impacts on some species. Thus, climate and land use changes have to be considered together to adequately predict changes in biodiversity [
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref036" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref036">36</a>]. So far, studies that have forecasted the combined potential impacts of future climate and land use changes have often been based on species distributions models (SDMs), applied to presence/absence distribution data [e.g. 
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref028">28</a>, 
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref037" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref037">37</a>]. However, population size and associated trends are the most frequently used data to assess the conservation status of species, to develop biodiversity indicators and determine priorities for action [
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref038" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref038">38</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The objective of this study was to assess the potential impacts of predicted future changes in farmland cover, area of farmland habitats and climate for 2050 on bird populations in French farmland. We focused on breeding birds, a group which is widely used as an indicator of environmental changes at the continental scale [
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref039" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref039">39</a>]. We relied on projections from SDMs and from the IMAGE model [
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref040" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref040">40</a>], based on Special Report on Emission Scenarios SRES [
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref041" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref041">41</a>], respectively, to integrate likely changes in species climatic suitability and changes in proportion of farmland habitats included in the geographical projection of the future suitable climatic areas for the corresponding species. Moreover, as mentioned above, land cover scenarios are rare. To this purpose, we built up farmland cover scenarios to further link bird abundances to cropland/grassland proportions. Data of farmland cover, especially crop patterns, must be analyzed at finer levels than the national level to account for regional disparities [
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref042">42</a>]. To do this, we developed four main scenarios of farmland cover changes at a fine spatial scale (i.e. French Small Agricultural Regions, SAR): a 
  <span class="italic">‘status quo’</span> scenario, a 
  <span class="italic">‘biofuel’</span> scenario, a 
  <span class="italic">‘livestock extensification’</span> scenario and an 
  <span class="italic">‘extensification’</span> scenario, exploring different combinations of agricultural policies and environmental commitments projected for 2050. Two of them were also developed at multiple levels of policy implementation (national or regional). Farmland cover scenarios differed in composition and spatial configuration of croplands and grasslands. Here, scenarios of “extensification” of farmland cover correspond to lowest intensive agriculture, through suitable changes in cropland/grassland to reduce pressure from modern agriculture. We hypothesize that: (1) land cover management could play a role in mitigating climate effect on farmland bird populations [
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref035">35</a>]; (2) a scenario with a regional level of implementation, leading to spatially heterogeneous policies, could benefit more bird populations than a global scenario with policies uniformly implemented at national scale; (3) depending on the ecological requirements of bird species (habitat specialization), their capacity to respond to climate change will be affected by the coverage of agricultural land and the agricultural policies [
  <a rid="pone.0117850.ref043" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0117850.ref043">43</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
