<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>For baleen whales, a number of hypotheses have been posited with regards to how their demography and phenology may respond to climate change. Warming in lower latitudes may cause contractions in migration ranges (similar to the phenotypic plasticity observed in some migratory bird species, e.g. Pulido and Berthold (
 <xref rid="gcb14573-bib-0072" ref-type="ref">2010</xref>), Klaassen et al. (
 <xref rid="gcb14573-bib-0042" ref-type="ref">2014</xref>)), which may directly increase juvenile survival by potentially altering the shape of the fitness surface (Reed, Schindler, &amp; Waples, 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-bib-0080" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>). These benefits, however, would be traded‐off if warming and sea‐ice reduction caused migratory whales to range farther to find prey, increasing energy expenditure and decreasing fitness (Moore &amp; Huntington, 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-bib-0061" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>). As the extent and exact nature of the reliance of ice‐associated species such as blue and minke whales on sea‐ice–mediated ecosystems in the Antarctic remains unclear (Laidre et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-bib-0045" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>), it is not known how changing sea‐ice extent may affect these species in the Southern Hemisphere. In the Northern Hemisphere, there is some evidence to suggest flexible foraging species such as gray whales have begun to adapt to warming and the reduction in winter sea ice by remaining in Arctic areas over winter (Moore, Wynne, Kinney, &amp; Grebmeier, 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-bib-0062" ref-type="ref">2007</xref>). In contrast, warming and associated decreased prey availability are expected to have negative consequences on endangered North Atlantic right whales given recent indications of northward range shifts in their prey (Meyer‐Gutbrod &amp; Greene, 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-bib-0060" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>). Although some populations of ice‐associated species such as bowhead whales have increased despite sea‐ice loss (George, Zeh, Suydam, &amp; Clark, 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-bib-0028" ref-type="ref">2004</xref>), suggesting sea‐ice reduction has not hindered recruitment and may be expanding foraging opportunities (Moore &amp; Huntington, 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-bib-0061" ref-type="ref">2008</xref>), other research suggests increased thermal stress and habitat loss associated with warming may have serious impacts on bowhead whale populations (Chambault et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-bib-0012" ref-type="ref">2018</xref>). With many of the large whales still at depleted levels in the Southern Hemisphere due to massive commercial catches throughout the 20th century (see Tulloch et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14573-bib-0109" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>), an improved understanding of how they may respond to changes in their environment and prey from additional anthropogenic stressors is vitally important from a conservation perspective.
</p>
