<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Relationship Between Vegetation Turnover and Active Fire Feedbacks</div>
 <p content-type="flushleft" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Both 
  <span class="italic">n</span>-alkane δ
  <span class="sup">13</span>C values and PAH abundance records exhibit considerable variability (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1809758115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, 
   <span class="italic">Statistical Analyses</span>
  </span>). High variance is not unexpected, given the inherent heterogeneity of fire processes on nonuniform natural landscapes (
  <a rid="r17" ref-type="bibr" href="#r17">17</a>). To determine whether this scatter confounded larger patterns in the data, we calculated correlation coefficients and their significance between C
  <sub>29</sub>, C
  <sub>31</sub>, and C
  <sub>33</sub>
  <span class="italic">n</span>-alkane δ
  <span class="sup">13</span>C values and log-transformed total PAH/C
  <sub>31</sub> (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1809758115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, 
   <span class="italic">Statistical Analyses</span>
  </span>). Correlations of normalized PAHs to δ
  <span class="sup">13</span>C
  <sub>29</sub>, δ
  <span class="sup">13</span>C
  <sub>31</sub>, and δ
  <span class="sup">13</span>C
  <sub>33</sub> had 
  <span class="italic">r</span> values of 0.70, 0.61, and 0.79, respectively (
  <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.01), and indicate a robust and significant correlation between fire occurrence and C
  <sub>4</sub>-grassland states. Thus, in the following discussion, we use trends in the molecular records to infer relationships between proxies for fire occurrence and vegetation-community change through time (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">Fig. 3</a>).
 </p>
 <div id="fig03" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="label">Fig. 3.</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <p>The relationship between fire and vegetation change in the Siwaliks through time. PAH concentrations normalized to C
    <sub>31</sub>
    <span class="italic">n</span>-alkane (ΣPAH/C
    <sub>31</sub>) plotted on a logarithmic scale against δ
    <span class="sup">13</span>C values from C
    <sub>29</sub>, C
    <sub>31</sub>, C
    <sub>33</sub>, and C
    <sub>35</sub>
    <span class="italic">n</span>-alkanes. Shaded boxes correspond to time slices in the record; symbols correspond to each chain length. Dotted lines represent approximate limits of C
    <sub>3</sub> and C
    <sub>4</sub> values (
    <a rid="r23" ref-type="bibr" href="#r23">23</a>). Respective correlation coefficients and significance levels for log-transformed PAH values vs. n-alkane δ
    <span class="sup">13</span>C are C
    <sub>29</sub>, 
    <span class="italic">r</span> = 0.70 and 
    <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.01; C
    <sub>31</sub>, 
    <span class="italic">r</span> = 0.61 and 
    <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.01; C
    <sub>33</sub>, 
    <span class="italic">r</span> = 0.79 and 
    <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.01; and C
    <sub>35</sub>, 
    <span class="italic">r</span> = 0.57 and 
    <span class="italic">P</span> = nonsignificant. Two samples (R17-B, CFS-4 and R29-1, Psol 2) have both relatively depleted δ
    <span class="sup">13</span>C values and low PAH concentrations relative to other samples of their time slice and fall outside the annotated boxes. However, these samples fit with the statistical relationship between δ
    <span class="sup">13</span>C values and PAH concentrations. We interpret these as C
    <sub>3</sub> patches on the landscape that were subject to less burning.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div id="gra3" xlink:href="pnas.1809758115fig03" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The biomarker data suggest three stages, punctuated by two fire-linked transitions between fire increase and vegetation shifts in time and space, on the Indian subcontinent (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">Figs. 2</a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">3</a>). First, from 10 to 8 Ma, biomarkers indicate that fire increased as conifer inputs declined (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">Figs. 2 
   <span class="italic">C</span> and 
   <span class="italic">D</span>
  </a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">3</a>). Second, between 8 and 6.5 Ma, C
  <sub>4</sub>-grass dominance increased as conifers further declined and, ultimately, were no longer important contributors to the regional ecosystem (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">Figs. 2 
   <span class="italic">B</span> and 
   <span class="italic">D</span>
  </a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">3</a>). Third, after 6.5 Ma, an order of magnitude increase in fire signatures coincided with the rapid onset of a fully C
  <sub>4</sub>-grassland state (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">Figs. 2 
   <span class="italic">B</span> and 
   <span class="italic">C</span>
  </a> and 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig03" href="#fig03">3</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The initial increase in fire at 10 Ma suggests that vegetation transitioned toward increasingly fire-prone communities before C
  <sub>4</sub>-grassland expansion in the Potwar Plateau record. Vegetation type can modify fire occurrence by increasing flammable fuel, independent of changes in climate that promote fire (
  <a rid="r26" ref-type="bibr" href="#r26">26</a>, 
  <a rid="r38" ref-type="bibr" href="#r38">38</a>). In the Nepal section of the Siwaliks, vegetation-community shifts indicated by pollen and plant macrofossils that preceded isotopic evidence for C
  <sub>4</sub>-grassland expansion suggest that mixed conifer and angiosperm evergreen communities were replaced by deciduous angiosperms before the expansion of C
  <sub>4</sub> grasslands (
  <a rid="r39" ref-type="bibr" href="#r39">39</a>, 
  <a rid="r40" ref-type="bibr" href="#r40">40</a>). Additionally, pollen records indicate that grasses were a potentially significant part of the Nepal landscape 2 My before C
  <sub>4</sub> plants expanded (
  <a rid="r40" ref-type="bibr" href="#r40">40</a>, 
  <a rid="r41" ref-type="bibr" href="#r41">41</a>). We suggest that similar changes took place in Pakistan, as indicated by the observed decline in relative retene abundance 2 My before the C
  <sub>4</sub> grassland transition (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">Fig. 2 
   <span class="italic">B</span> and 
   <span class="italic">D</span>
  </a>). Mixed conifer communities were replaced by frequent fire-promoting vegetation, such as a C
  <sub>3</sub> grassland or a dry angiosperm forest.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A transition to a more open landscape at 10 Ma is supported by multiple lines of faunal evidence in Pakistan. Consistent with loss of closed woodland habitats before C
  <sub>4</sub> dominance, frugivorous and browsing mammals in the Potwar faunal record declined between 10.0 and 8.0 Ma (
  <a rid="r18" ref-type="bibr" href="#r18">18</a>). Further, δ
  <span class="sup">13</span>C and δ
  <span class="sup">18</span>O isotopic records of equid enamel indicate that grassland habitats started to expand before 9.4 Ma (
  <a rid="r16" ref-type="bibr" href="#r16">16</a>, 
  <a rid="r18" ref-type="bibr" href="#r18">18</a>, 
  <a rid="r22" ref-type="bibr" href="#r22">22</a>). Microwear analysis of multiple taxa indicates the presence of C
  <sub>3</sub> grass between 10 and 8 Ma, well before C
  <sub>4</sub> vegetation became dominant (
  <a rid="r16" ref-type="bibr" href="#r16">16</a>, 
  <a rid="r42" ref-type="bibr" href="#r42">42</a>). Eventually, mixed feeders and grazers shifted toward more C
  <sub>4</sub> diets between 8.5 and 6.0 Ma, accompanying the rising dominance of C
  <sub>4</sub> vegetation (
  <a rid="r16" ref-type="bibr" href="#r16">16</a>, 
  <a rid="r18" ref-type="bibr" href="#r18">18</a>, 
  <a rid="r22" ref-type="bibr" href="#r22">22</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Today, fire regimes with low frequency (i.e., rare and intermediate return intervals) tend to dominate in tropical conifer (89%), temperate conifer (97%), and mixed conifer (97%) biomes, while frequent fire regimes (with short return intervals) are almost exclusively characteristic of grassland biomes (
  <a rid="r43" ref-type="bibr" href="#r43">43</a>). Lower-frequency fires tend to be litter fueled, whereas high-frequency fires are fueled by the more flammable biomass characteristic of grass biomes (
  <a rid="r43" ref-type="bibr" href="#r43">43</a>). We suggest that the appearance of a more open vegetation state increased fire frequency in the paleofire regime on the Siwalik floodplains and adjacent uplands. An increase in the flammability of biomass is indicated by a fivefold increase in PAHs that preceded isotopic evidence for C
  <sub>4</sub>-grassland expansion and a sharp uptick in seasonal precipitation (
  <a rid="r15" ref-type="bibr" href="#r15">15</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Increased fire occurrence during the C
  <sub>3</sub>-dominated and fire-prone intermediate state likely promoted its own eventual replacement by C
  <sub>4</sub> grasslands. If the intermediate ecosystem was a dry angiosperm forest, an additional increase in flammability would have intensified landscape clearing. The 10× fire marker increase starting at 6 Ma provides evidence for a disturbance trigger that further cleared away woody vegetation and allowed C
  <sub>4</sub> grasslands to dominate (
  <a rid="r8" ref-type="bibr" href="#r8">8</a>). Alternatively, a set of linked fire–seasonality–C
  <sub>4</sub> positive feedbacks could have fostered the transition from a C
  <sub>3</sub>-grassland intermediate state to C
  <sub>4</sub> grassland. Dynamic global vegetation models invoke C
  <sub>4</sub> characteristics based on the quantum yield model for modern C
  <sub>3</sub>/C
  <sub>4</sub> plants (
  <a rid="r44" ref-type="bibr" href="#r44">44</a>, 
  <a rid="r45" ref-type="bibr" href="#r45">45</a>). When used to simulate Miocene C
  <sub>4</sub>-grassland expansion, these models showed that fire favored an intermediate C
  <sub>3</sub>-grassland state when a condition promoting the C
  <sub>4</sub> pathway over the C
  <sub>3</sub> pathway was lacking (i.e., a drop in CO
  <sub>2</sub>, summer growing season, or low mean annual precipitation) (
  <a rid="r44" ref-type="bibr" href="#r44">44</a>). However, when fire was present and one of these climatic or biological conditions was also met, C
  <sub>4</sub> grasslands rapidly replaced C
  <sub>3</sub> grasslands.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The quantum yield model indicates that a wet summer growing season favors the C
  <sub>4</sub> pathway (
  <a rid="r46" ref-type="bibr" href="#r46">46</a>). A seasonality switch in the late Miocene favored summer precipitation over winter precipitation, indicated by the Siwalik oxygen isotope record (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">Fig. 2
   <span class="italic">A</span>
  </a>) (
  <a rid="r17" ref-type="bibr" href="#r17">17</a>), promoting C
  <sub>4</sub> grasses over C
  <sub>3</sub> grasses. Additionally, C
  <sub>4</sub> grasslands are commonly more fire-prone than C
  <sub>3</sub> grasslands due to the evolution of fire-promoting traits (
  <a rid="r44" ref-type="bibr" href="#r44">44</a>, 
  <a rid="r47" ref-type="bibr" href="#r47">47</a>). This advantage, combined with hydrologic conditions that promoted increased fires, is consistent with the large jump in fire compounds observed with the advent of C
  <sub>4</sub> grasslands (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">Fig. 2 
   <span class="italic">A</span> and 
   <span class="italic">C</span>
  </a>) (
  <a rid="r15" ref-type="bibr" href="#r15">15</a>).
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The rapid and simultaneous rise in indicators for fire, C
  <sub>4</sub> grasslands, and seasonal drying provides strong evidence of a fire feedback system that fostered C
  <sub>4</sub>-grassland expansion in South Asia (
  <a rid="r8" ref-type="bibr" href="#r8">8</a>). This does not preclude other factors that could have affected C
  <sub>4</sub> expansion (e.g., a drop in CO
  <sub>2</sub> levels or herbivory), but our results show that fire was important to the development of C
  <sub>4</sub> ecosystems on the Indian subcontinent.
 </p>
</sec>
