<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Because of its shallow root system, potato is considered to be the most drought-sensitive crop species. Drought stress negatively affects physiological processes involved in the tuber formation and growth (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1" class="xref">Figure 1</xref>). Potato growth and tuber yield largely depends on rainfall, consequently, even a short period of water deficit can cause a substantial loss of tuber yield and deterioration of tuber quality (
 <xref rid="B28" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Dalla Costa et al., 1997</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B30" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Deblonde and Ledent, 2001</xref>). The extent of drought induced tuber yield loss, however, largely depends on the duration, severity and plant growth stage (
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Evers et al., 2010</xref>). Early stress is most detrimental to tuberization, bulking and tuber yield due to decreased leaf area, decreased photosynthetic rates and reduced partitioning of assimilates to tubers (
 <xref rid="B37" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Evers et al., 2010</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B96" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Obidiegwu et al., 2015</xref>). If drought occurs at an early growth stage, it will substantially suppress tuber initiation, bulking and tuber yield. Drought during tuberization, causes reduction in the stolon number per stem, reflecting in lower tuber number and yield. If potato plants experience drought during tuber bulking stage, they will produce fewer and smaller sized tuber. Nevertheless, it has been suggested that stolon initiation and tuber formation are the most critical stages to drought stress. Drought-induced reduction in tuber yield is mainly associated with strong inhibition of photosynthesis due to stomatal and non-stomatal limitations (
 <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref>). Drought stress downregulates the expression of genes that code for chlorophyll 
 <italic class="italic">a</italic>-
 <italic class="italic">b</italic> binding proteins, key regulatory photosynthetic enzymes, and sucrose biosynthetic enzymes but upregulate the expression of sucrose breaking enzymes (
 <xref rid="B60" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Hwang et al., 2011</xref>). In addition to its impact on tuber yield, drought also considerably affects numerous tuber quality parameters making them unsuitable for processing and consumption (
 <xref rid="T1" ref-type="table" class="xref">Table 1</xref>). Drought triggers tuber defects such as, tuber cracking, hollow heart, internal brown spot, secondary growth, malformations and considerably increase a-solanine and a-chaconine glycoalkaloid content that may cause several health issues including cancer (reviewed by 
 <xref rid="B137" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Wang-Pruski and Schofield, 2012</xref>). Drought is believed to induce sugar ends, a major quality disorder that causes French fries and potato chips to be dark on one end, which may lead to rejection by consumers (
 <xref rid="B127" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Thompson et al., 2008</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B81" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Liu et al., 2016</xref>). Sugar end tubers are characterized by increased amount of reducing sugars, such as, glucose and fructose, at one end of the tuber. Although the actual losses accounted for by this physiological disorder is still under study, sugar ends can be costly to growers as the crop is rejected by processing industries.
</p>
