<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">To test this hypothesis, we examined the relationships of summer (June to September) air temperature with CESCF and AISMR for both study periods. Since the mid-upper level tropospheric temperature plays a more important role in driving the Indian summer monsoon (
 <xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">44</italic>
 </xref>, 
 <xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">
  <italic class="italic">45</italic>
 </xref>), we used the air temperature at 500 hPa (AT500) to indicate the atmospheric thermal conditions. The regression analyses showed that AT500 over southwestern and northeastern Eurasia has a significant negative association with CESCF during the period 1967–1990 (
 <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig" class="xref">Fig. 3A</xref>), but almost no significant connection occurred after 1990 (
 <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig" class="xref">Fig. 3B</xref>). In contrast, AISMR was positively linked with AT500 over large parts of the Eurasian continent during both periods (
 <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig" class="xref">Fig. 3, C and D</xref>). We further calculated the correlation coefficients of CESCF and AISMR with the area-averaged AT500 over the Iranian Plateau and surroundings (IPS; 55° to 80°E, 25° to 40°N), where the air temperature exerts the strongest influence on the Indian summer monsoon (fig. S5). Our results again showed that CESCF is significantly negatively correlated with AT500 over the IPS during the earlier period (
 <italic class="italic">R</italic> = −0.51, 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic> &lt; 0.01), but the correlation becomes insignificant in the later period (
 <italic class="italic">R</italic> = 0.14, 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic> = 0.50) (
 <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig" class="xref">Fig. 3E</xref>). The observed shift in the snow-air temperature relationship coincides with that in the snow-monsoon relationship (
 <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig" class="xref">Fig. 3F</xref>). However, the AISMR is significantly correlated with AT500 during both earlier (
 <italic class="italic">R</italic> = −0.70, 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic> &lt; 0.01) and later periods (
 <italic class="italic">R</italic> = −0.84, 
 <italic class="italic">P</italic> &lt; 0.01) (
 <xref rid="F3" ref-type="fig" class="xref">Fig. 3G</xref>). This result was also robust to the use of temperature data from the Japanese 55-year Reanalysis (JRA-55) (fig. S6). The analyses presented above support our hypothesis that the failure of the impact of CESCF on AISMR could be attributed to a decoupling between snow cover and atmospheric thermal conditions over the Asian landmass after 1990.
</p>
