<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Design of climate model experiments</div>
 <p id="Par13" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We perform simulations NCAR CESM1.2.1, a fully coupled model with approximately 1° horizontal resolution (f09g16)
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22" href="#CR22">22</a>
  </span>. The atmospheric model is the Community Atmospheric Model version 5 (CAM5) with 30 vertical levels, and the ocean component is the Parallel Ocean Program version 2 (POP2) with 60 vertical levels. The land and sea ice components are the Community Land Model version 4 (CLM4) and the Los Alamos sea ice model version 4 (CICE4), respectively.
 </p>
 <p id="Par14" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To distinguish the climatic responses to sea ice loss and anomalous insolation forcing in the mid-Holocene, we perform three different model simulations. First, we perform a 335-year-long Pre-industrial simulation that has constant year 1850 radiative forcing and greenhouse gas concentrations. Second, the mid-Holocene simulation with 6 ka BP insolation and greenhouse gas concentrations is branched off from year 31 of the Pre-industrial simulation and runs for 315 years. Third, another simulation with mid-Holocene forcing is branched off at year 31 of the Pre-industrial run, except the albedo of sea ice is increased globally, and throughout the year, from 0.73 to 0.91 to reflect more sunlight, while the snow albedo over sea ice is not changed. A recent study
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>
  </span> also used this method (changing sea ice albedo) to isolate the effect of Arctic sea loss on atmospheric circulations.
 </p>
 <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The three different model simulations can be summarized as:</p>
 <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="bold">0</span> 
  <span class="bold">k</span>: Pre-industrial control simulation (335-year duration: from year 1 to 335)
 </p>
 <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="bold">6</span> 
  <span class="bold">ka</span>: Mid-Holocene climate simulation (315-year duration: from year 31 to 345)
 </p>
 <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span class="bold">6</span> 
  <span class="bold">ka with 0</span> 
  <span class="bold">k sea ice</span>: Mid-Holocene climate with sea ice albedo is increased to 0.91 (316-year duration: from year 31 to 346)
 </p>
 <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The contributions of Arctic sea ice loss and direct insolation anomalies to mid-Holocene climate, relative to the preindustrial, can be separated as follows:</p>
 <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The contribution of Arctic sea ice loss: (6 ka)–(6 ka with 0 k sea ice)</p>
 <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The contribution of insolation forcing: (6 ka with 0 k sea ice)–(0 k)</p>
 <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In each simulation, we perform analysis using the last 265 years and discard the first 50 years of the simulations 6 ka and 6 ka with 0 k sea ice. In our CESM1 simulations, the Arctic summer sea ice cover quickly responds to the mid-Holocene insolation forcing, within 10 years (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">5</a>). The wintertime 200-hPa zonal-mean zonal winds averaged from 65°N to 80°N also responds to the Arctic sea ice loss within few years, although large internal variations of wintertime atmospheric circulations are overlaid the signal (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">5</a>). Because of the relatively rapid adjustments of SIC and the associated atmospheric circulations, using the last 150 years of each simulation produces quantitatively similar results. For example, the wintertime SAT and zonal-mean zonal wind anomalies averaged during the last 150 years of model simulations are very similar to those averaged during the last 265 years (compare Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">5</a> and Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>). These results are generally consistent with previous studies showing that the adjustment timescales of atmosphere and the ocean mixed layer to a radiative forcing given as a step function are only a few years
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>
  </span>. Discarding the first 50 years of model integration, therefore, captures the equilibrium response of atmosphere, whereas the deep ocean circulation takes several hundred years to reach an equilibrium
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
  </span> (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5a</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
