<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec2" sec-type="results" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results</div>
 <sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Seasonal changes in surface air temperature</div>
  <p id="Par6" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In our mid-Holocene simulation, Arctic sea ice concentration (SIC) in summer-autumn decreases by 30–35% over wide areas of the Arctic relative to the pre-industrial climate (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>), which is consistent with the multi-model averaged SIC anomalies in the mid-Holocene
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">11</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">12</a>
   </span>. Figure 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2a</a> shows the annual-mean response of mid-Holocene surface air temperature (SAT) to Arctic sea ice loss. The substantial warming over and around Greenland, which also appears in proxy data
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4" href="#CR4">4</a>
   </span>, has previously been reported as a response to Arctic sea ice loss
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24" href="#CR24">24</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25" href="#CR25">25</a>
   </span>. The impact of Arctic sea ice loss is not limited to high latitudes: sea ice loss warms the North Pacific Ocean and North America, but slightly cools the North Atlantic Ocean. The longitude–time Hovmöller plot of SAT averaged between 45°N and 62°N (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2c</a>) shows that the warming over the Pacific and North America persists throughout the season, whereas cooling over Central and East Asia appears in winter, especially in December and January. The amplitudes of these ice melting-induced annual-mean SAT anomalies (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2a</a>) are comparable to those of the direct insolation forcing (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2b</a>). The insolation forcing warms the North Atlantic and Europe, and cools North America. The warming over Europe is usually driven by anomalously strong summer insolation forcing
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26" href="#CR26">26</a>
   </span> and this is supported by multiple pollen records
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27" href="#CR27">27</a>
   </span>. Indeed, the Hovmöller plot (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2d</a>) verifies that the mid-Holocene insolation forcing causes strong summer warming and winter–spring cooling over the entire longitude circle. While the seasonal impact of insolation forcing on SAT in the mid-latitudes is about twice as large as that of sea ice loss (compare Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2c, d</a>), the annual-mean SAT anomalies driven by insolation forcing and sea ice loss are comparable with each other (compare Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2a, b</a>).
   <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 1</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Simulated Arctic sea ice concentration and surface heat flux. Arctic sea ice concentration (%) in Jul–Nov from simulations of 
      <span class="bold">a</span> mid-Holocene climate, 
      <span class="bold">b</span> pre-industrial climate, and 
      <span class="bold">c</span> mid-Holocene climate with pre-industrial sea ice concentration (imposed via increased ice albedo). Jul–Nov averaged sea ice concentration differences 
      <span class="bold">d</span> between the mid-Holocene and pre-industrial simulations, i.e. 
      <span class="bold">a</span>–
      <span class="bold">b</span>, and 
      <span class="bold">e</span> between the mid-Holocene simulation with pre-industrial sea ice and the pre-industrial simulation, i.e. 
      <span class="bold">c</span>–
      <span class="bold">b</span>. The seasonal cycle of 
      <span class="bold">f</span> net surface shortwave flux (
      <span class="italic">F</span>
      <sub>SW</sub>
      <span class="sup">↑</span>−
      <span class="italic">F</span>
      <sub>SW</sub>
      <span class="sup">↓</span>) and 
      <span class="bold">g</span> net surface heat flux (
      <span class="italic">F</span>
      <sub>SW</sub>
      <span class="sup">↑</span>−
      <span class="italic">F</span>
      <sub>SW</sub>
      <span class="sup">↓</span>+
      <span class="italic">F</span>
      <sub>LW</sub>
      <span class="sup">↑</span>−
      <span class="italic">F</span>
      <sub>LW</sub>
      <span class="sup">↓</span>+SHF
      <span class="sup">↑</span>+LHF
      <span class="sup">↑</span>) averaged in the Arctic Ocean. In 
      <span class="bold">f</span> and 
      <span class="bold">g</span>, the red, blue, and black lines denote the mid-Holocene, the mid-Holocene with pre-industrial sea ice, and pre-industrial simulations, respectively
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="41467_2018_7068_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e498" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
   <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 2</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Temperature responses to Arctic sea ice loss and insolation. Surface air temperature response to 
      <span class="bold">a</span>, 
      <span class="bold">c</span> Arctic sea ice loss and 
      <span class="bold">b</span>, 
      <span class="bold">d</span> insolation forcing. 
      <span class="bold">a</span>, 
      <span class="bold">b</span> The annual-mean surface air temperature anomalies (K) and 
      <span class="bold">c</span>, 
      <span class="bold">d</span> meridionally averaged (45°–62°N), longitude–time Hovmöller plots of anomalous surface air temperature (K). The abscissa longitude and the ordinate is time (months). In 
      <span class="bold">a</span> and 
      <span class="bold">b</span>, statistically significant values (
      <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.05) are hatched
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="41467_2018_7068_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e541" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The wintertime SAT</div>
  <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The influence of Arctic sea ice loss on Northern Hemisphere climate is particularly pronounced during winter, from December to March (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3a</a>): SAT over the Eurasian continent, specifically Central and East Asia, decreases by ~0.6 K. This result is comparable to model-simulated eastern Eurasian continent cooling due to the recent sea ice decline
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>
   </span>. This Eurasian continent cooling occurs mostly in early winter (December–January), during which SAT decreases by 0.8 K over wide areas of Central and East Asia (Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2</a>). The decrease in SAT over the Eurasian continent is associated with the development of anomalously high sea level pressure (SLP) in Arctic and sub-Arctic Russia and the deepening of the Aleutian low (Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>), consistent with a recent projection of Arctic sea ice loss
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>
   </span> forced by Representative Concentration Pathway (RCP) 8.5. The development of high pressure in sub-Arctic Russia often causes cold eastern Eurasian winters
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
   </span>. Over Central and East Asia, both sea ice loss and insolation forcing act to decrease temperature (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3a, b</a>), exacerbating the cold continental winter. These model results are supported by proxy records that the East Asian winter monsoon was probably stronger in early- and mid-Holocene than the present
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
   </span>.
   <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Wintertime responses of temperature, westerly winds, and storm tracks. The wintertime (December–March) responses of 
      <span class="bold">a</span>, 
      <span class="bold">b</span> surface air temperature (K), 
      <span class="bold">c</span>, 
      <span class="bold">d</span> zonal-mean zonal winds (m s
      <span class="sup">−1</span>) and 
      <span class="bold">e</span>, 
      <span class="bold">f</span> transient eddy heat flux (10
      <span class="sup">7</span> W m
      <span class="sup">−1</span>) to mid-Holocene Arctic sea ice loss (
      <span class="bold">a</span>, 
      <span class="bold">c</span>, 
      <span class="bold">e</span>) and insolation forcing (
      <span class="bold">b</span>, 
      <span class="bold">d</span>, 
      <span class="bold">f</span>). Purple lines in 
      <span class="bold">c</span> and 
      <span class="bold">d</span> are climatological-mean zonal-mean zonal winds from the mid-Holocene with pre-industrial sea ice simulation. In 
      <span class="bold">e</span> and 
      <span class="bold">f</span>, the transient eddy heat flux at each pressure level is integrated from the surface to 700 hPa. For all the plots, statistically significant values (
      <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.05) are hatched
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="41467_2018_7068_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e656" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Over North America, the anomalous winter insolation decreases SAT by more than 2 K (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3b</a>), which is not surprising given that the winter insolation weakens by 5–10 W m
   <span class="sup">−2</span> and land has a relatively low heat capacity. On the contrary, the sea ice loss increases SAT by 2 K, especially over Alaska and Canada (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3a</a>). This is partly because of the Aleutian low strengthening (Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>), which is followed by the northward transport of warm southern air to Alaska and western Canada
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
   </span>, increasing SAT over these regions. This wintertime surface warming over North America also appears in a climate model simulation of a projected Arctic sea ice loss, forced by RCP 8.5 with a well-resolved stratosphere
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
   </span>. This suggests that without the effect of sea ice loss, the weakening of winter insolation would have led to harsher winters over North America during the mid-Holocene. The summed effects of insolation forcing and sea ice loss on SAT manifest as a warm Arctic and cold continent pattern in winter, consistent with the Paleoclimate Modelling Intercomparison Project phase 3 (PMIP3) multi-model average (Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">3</a>). The wintertime Arctic warming in the PMIP3 multi-model average is generally weaker than that in CESM1, though the 4 warmest of the PMIP3 models simulate Arctic warming that is comparable to CESM1 (Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">3</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The wintertime atmospheric circulations</div>
  <p id="Par9" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">How does Arctic sea ice loss affect the mid-latitude atmospheric circulation pattern during winter? While variability of the atmospheric circulation obscures the mid-latitude climate response to the recent Arctic sea ice loss
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32" href="#CR32">32</a>
   </span>, the zonal-mean circulation response to the recent and the projected Arctic sea ice loss is more robust
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33" href="#CR33">33</a>
   </span>. In particular, Arctic sea ice loss causes a negative AO-like circulation pattern
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>–
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>
   </span>. Consistent with these studies, Arctic sea ice loss in our mid-Holocene simulation substantially weakens the mid-high latitude (57°–82°N) zonal-mean westerlies from the lower troposphere to the stratosphere (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3c</a>). In the upper troposphere and lower stratosphere (around 250–100 hPa), the zonal-mean zonal wind anomalies range from −0.5 to −1.0 m s
   <span class="sup">−1</span>. These westerly wind anomalies are similar to those associated with future projections of Arctic sea ice loss based on RCP 8.5
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>
   </span>. This weakening of the mid-high latitude westerlies induced by sea ice loss is partially offset by insolation forcing in boreal winter, during which the insolation in Northern Hemisphere is weaker than the present by 5–10 W m
   <span class="sup">−2</span>. Figure 
   <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3d</a> shows that the relatively weak insolation forcing in the mid-Holocene strengthens the mid-high latitude westerlies, but this westerly strengthening is confined to the stratosphere, with limited signature in the troposphere. The weakening of mid-high latitude westerlies induced by sea ice loss is accompanied by the weakening of storm tracks over the North Pacific and North Atlantic Oceans (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3e</a>). We quantify the storm track intensity using the transient eddy heat flux in the lower troposphere, 
   <div id="IEq1" class="inline-formula">
    <div class="alternatives">
     <span id="M1" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$\overline {V\prime T\prime }$$\end{document}</span>
     <div id="M2" class="math">
      <div accent="false" class="mover">
       <div class="mrow">
        <span class="mi">V</span>
        <span class="mo">′</span>
        <span class="mi">T</span>
        <span class="mo">′</span>
       </div>
       <span accent="true" class="mo">¯</span>
      </div>
     </div>
     <span xlink:href="41467_2018_7068_Article_IEq1.gif" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    </div>
   </div>. Here, 
   <div id="IEq2" class="inline-formula">
    <div class="alternatives">
     <span id="M3" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$\overline {()}$$\end{document}</span>
     <div id="M4" class="math">
      <div accent="false" class="mover">
       <div class="mrow">
        <div class="mrow">
         <span class="mo">(</span>
         <div class="mrow"/>
         <span class="mo">)</span>
        </div>
       </div>
       <span accent="true" class="mo">¯</span>
      </div>
     </div>
     <span xlink:href="41467_2018_7068_Article_IEq2.gif" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    </div>
   </div> and 
   <div id="IEq3" class="inline-formula">
    <div class="alternatives">
     <span id="M5" class="tex-math">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal} \usepackage{amsmath} \usepackage{wasysym} \usepackage{amsfonts} \usepackage{amssymb} \usepackage{amsbsy} \usepackage{mathrsfs} \usepackage{upgreek} \setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt} \begin{document}$$()\prime$$\end{document}</span>
     <div id="M6" class="math">
      <div class="mrow">
       <span class="mo">(</span>
       <div class="mrow"/>
       <span class="mo">)</span>
      </div>
      <span class="mo">′</span>
     </div>
     <span xlink:href="41467_2018_7068_Article_IEq3.gif" class="inline-graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
    </div>
   </div> denote a time average and a deviation from the time average, respectively, and &lt;&gt; denotes mass-weighted vertical integration from the surface to 700 hPa. This weakening of transient eddy activity is probably because of the reduced baroclinic instability that is dynamically tied to the westerly wind speed
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
   </span>. Meanwhile, the effect of the direct insolation forcing on the storm tracks is weaker than that of the sea ice loss: the insolation forcing slightly weakens the zonal-mean westerly winds and thus the transient eddy activity at lower latitudes, around 30°N–50°N (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3f</a>). These results suggest that mid-Holocene Arctic sea ice loss may have had a stronger influence on wintertime tropospheric westerlies and weather activities than the direct insolation forcing. The Arctic sea ice loss also leads to polar stratospheric warming, especially in late winter (February–March), during which 100-hPa geopotential height increases by 40–50 m (Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2</a>). This is consistent with previous studies indicating that sea ice loss induces Rossby waves that penetrate into the stratosphere and weaken the stratospheric polar vortex
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" href="#CR16">16</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>
   </span>, especially in late winter
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" href="#CR17">17</a>
   </span>.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Sea surface temperature and deep ocean circulations</div>
  <p id="Par10" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">These atmospheric circulation and SAT changes are also associated with sea surface temperature (SST) changes. Figure 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4c</a> shows that the direct insolation forcing increases the annual-mean North Sea and the Mediterranean Sea SSTs by around 0.2–0.3 K. This SST warming likely contributes to the increase in annual-mean SAT over Europe (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2b</a>). The Hovmöller plot of the North Atlantic SSTs averaged between 55°W and 10°W indicates that the SST anomalies increase rapidly in summer because of anomalously strong summer insolation, but quickly subside in autumn and become slightly negative in spring (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4d</a>). In contrast, Arctic sea ice loss produces seasonally persistent SST anomalies in the mid-high latitudes. Arctic sea ice loss increases the annual-mean North Pacific SSTs by around 0.4–0.5 K and produces a localized ~0.5 K decrease in annual-mean SSTs in the central North Atlantic (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4a</a>). The Hovmöller plot of North Atlantic SSTs shows that the sea ice loss decreases (increases) the mid-latitude (subpolar) North Atlantic SSTs throughout the season (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4b</a>), and that these anomalies exhibit far less seasonality than those of the insolation forcing. The summed effects of insolation forcing and sea ice loss exhibit a pattern of North Pacific–subpolar North Atlantic warming and tropical ocean cooling (Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">4</a>). This is qualitatively consistent with the PMIP3 multi-model average (Supplementary Fig. 
   <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">4</a>), with the exception of the North Pacific warming.
   <div id="Fig4" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Sea surface temperature responses to Arctic sea ice loss and insolation. The SST response to mid-Holocene 
      <span class="bold">a</span>, 
      <span class="bold">b</span> Arctic sea ice loss and 
      <span class="bold">c</span>, 
      <span class="bold">d</span> insolation forcing. 
      <span class="bold">a</span>, 
      <span class="bold">c</span> The annual-mean surface air temperature anomalies (K) and 
      <span class="bold">b</span>, 
      <span class="bold">d</span> zonally averaged (55°–10°W; North Atlantic sector), longitude–time Hovmöller plots of anomalous surface air temperature (K). The abscissa is time (months) and the ordinate is latitude. Dotted lines in 
      <span class="bold">a</span> are longitudinal bounds for the Hovmöller plots
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="41467_2018_7068_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e871" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Via what mechanism does Arctic sea ice loss decrease the North Atlantic SSTs? Consistent with recent modeling studies
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36" href="#CR36">36</a>
   </span>, Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5b</a> shows that Arctic sea ice loss weakens the Atlantic meridional overturning circulation (AMOC); the northward mass flux systematically decreases all the way from the subtropics to the subpolar North Atlantic. The decrease in the northward mass flux in the Atlantic Ocean is largest around 35°N–50°N (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5b</a>) and the poleward margin of this region is where the annual-mean SSTs decrease by around 0.5 K (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4a, b</a>). However, the AMOC strength slowly recovers to the control simulation (i.e. mid-Holocene climate with preindustrial sea ice) strength after about 180 years (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5a</a>). After year 200, the AMOC strength anomalies are mostly smaller than 1 Sverdrup (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5a, c</a>), which is consistent with a previous study
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37" href="#CR37">37</a>
   </span> showing that the AMOC weakening is a transient response to the Arctic sea ice loss. Therefore, it is unlikely that the AMOC weakening and the associated North Atlantic cooling persisted throughout the mid-Holocene. While the AMOC weakening signal substantially diminishes after year 200, the North Atlantic cooling still persists (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5g</a>), suggesting that the AMOC weakening is not the only factors causing the North Atlantic cooling. The sea surface height (SSH) anomalies show that Arctic sea ice loss decreases SSH over the mid-North Atlantic (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5d, e</a>), which weakens the Gulf Stream by reducing the meridional gradient of the SSH. The reduced strength of the Gulf Stream is likely to be a factor for the North Atlantic cooling, which is qualitatively consistent with a previous study
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">18</a>
   </span> showing that the Arctic sea ice loss can change the North Atlantic SST pattern by shifting the Gulf Stream southward.
   <div id="Fig5" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 5</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>The response of Atlantic meridional overturning circulation to Arctic sea ice loss. 
      <span class="bold">a</span> The 20-year running averages of AMOC strength, defined as the North Atlantic meridional streamfunction (Sv) averaged between depths of 500 and 2500 m, for the mid-Holocene (red) and the mid-Holocene with pre-industrial sea ice (black) simulations. The gray shadings indicate the range of 1 standard deviation from the mean of the mid-Holocene with pre-industrial sea ice (black) simulations. The responses of 
      <span class="bold">b</span>, 
      <span class="bold">c</span> AMOC (Sv; 1 Sv = 10
      <span class="sup">6</span> m
      <span class="sup">3</span> s
      <span class="sup">−1</span>), 
      <span class="bold">d</span>, 
      <span class="bold">e</span> SSH, and 
      <span class="bold">f</span>, 
      <span class="bold">g</span> SSTs to Arctic sea ice loss averaged over the model years of 
      <span class="bold">b</span>, 
      <span class="bold">d</span>, 
      <span class="bold">f</span> 81– 345 and 
      <span class="bold">c</span>, 
      <span class="bold">e</span>, 
      <span class="bold">g</span> 200–345. Panel 
      <span class="bold">f</span> is identical to Fig. 
      <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4a</a>. In 
      <span class="bold">b</span> and 
      <span class="bold">c</span>, the abscissa is latitude and the ordinate is depth (m). In 
      <span class="bold">b</span> and 
      <span class="bold">c</span>, only statistically significant values (
      <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.05) are shaded
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="41467_2018_7068_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e991" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
