<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec4" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The wintertime SAT</div>
 <p id="Par7" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The influence of Arctic sea ice loss on Northern Hemisphere climate is particularly pronounced during winter, from December to March (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3a</a>): SAT over the Eurasian continent, specifically Central and East Asia, decreases by ~0.6 K. This result is comparable to model-simulated eastern Eurasian continent cooling due to the recent sea ice decline
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20" href="#CR20">20</a>
  </span>. This Eurasian continent cooling occurs mostly in early winter (December–January), during which SAT decreases by 0.8 K over wide areas of Central and East Asia (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">2</a>). The decrease in SAT over the Eurasian continent is associated with the development of anomalously high sea level pressure (SLP) in Arctic and sub-Arctic Russia and the deepening of the Aleutian low (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>), consistent with a recent projection of Arctic sea ice loss
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">21</a>
  </span> forced by Representative Concentration Pathway (RCP) 8.5. The development of high pressure in sub-Arctic Russia often causes cold eastern Eurasian winters
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" href="#CR15">15</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>,
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span>. Over Central and East Asia, both sea ice loss and insolation forcing act to decrease temperature (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3a, b</a>), exacerbating the cold continental winter. These model results are supported by proxy records that the East Asian winter monsoon was probably stronger in early- and mid-Holocene than the present
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
  </span>.
  <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Wintertime responses of temperature, westerly winds, and storm tracks. The wintertime (December–March) responses of 
     <span class="bold">a</span>, 
     <span class="bold">b</span> surface air temperature (K), 
     <span class="bold">c</span>, 
     <span class="bold">d</span> zonal-mean zonal winds (m s
     <span class="sup">−1</span>) and 
     <span class="bold">e</span>, 
     <span class="bold">f</span> transient eddy heat flux (10
     <span class="sup">7</span> W m
     <span class="sup">−1</span>) to mid-Holocene Arctic sea ice loss (
     <span class="bold">a</span>, 
     <span class="bold">c</span>, 
     <span class="bold">e</span>) and insolation forcing (
     <span class="bold">b</span>, 
     <span class="bold">d</span>, 
     <span class="bold">f</span>). Purple lines in 
     <span class="bold">c</span> and 
     <span class="bold">d</span> are climatological-mean zonal-mean zonal winds from the mid-Holocene with pre-industrial sea ice simulation. In 
     <span class="bold">e</span> and 
     <span class="bold">f</span>, the transient eddy heat flux at each pressure level is integrated from the surface to 700 hPa. For all the plots, statistically significant values (
     <span class="italic">p</span> &lt; 0.05) are hatched
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41467_2018_7068_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e656" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par8" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Over North America, the anomalous winter insolation decreases SAT by more than 2 K (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3b</a>), which is not surprising given that the winter insolation weakens by 5–10 W m
  <span class="sup">−2</span> and land has a relatively low heat capacity. On the contrary, the sea ice loss increases SAT by 2 K, especially over Alaska and Canada (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3a</a>). This is partly because of the Aleutian low strengthening (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>), which is followed by the northward transport of warm southern air to Alaska and western Canada
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>
  </span>, increasing SAT over these regions. This wintertime surface warming over North America also appears in a climate model simulation of a projected Arctic sea ice loss, forced by RCP 8.5 with a well-resolved stratosphere
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19" href="#CR19">19</a>
  </span>. This suggests that without the effect of sea ice loss, the weakening of winter insolation would have led to harsher winters over North America during the mid-Holocene. The summed effects of insolation forcing and sea ice loss on SAT manifest as a warm Arctic and cold continent pattern in winter, consistent with the Paleoclimate Modelling Intercomparison Project phase 3 (PMIP3) multi-model average (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">3</a>). The wintertime Arctic warming in the PMIP3 multi-model average is generally weaker than that in CESM1, though the 4 warmest of the PMIP3 models simulate Arctic warming that is comparable to CESM1 (Supplementary Fig. 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">3</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
