<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The ARDL regression indicated that in the long run, the relationship between the average temperature and the winter wheat yield is not significant, which was inconsistent with previous studies exemplified by [
 <xref rid="pone.0184474.ref015" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>] who, used data from agricultural meteorological stations to find that the winter wheat yield was positively correlated with the temperature in Henan Province. However, Zhang and Huang [
 <xref rid="pone.0184474.ref037" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">37</xref>] found that the positive effect of temperature on the wheat yield only existed in the southern part of Henan Province, while in northeast, the effect was negative. In fact, the average temperature during wheat growing season from 1970 to 2014 showed a slightly rising tendency, but it did not appear obviously fluctuation and was around at 11°C (
 <xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0184474.g003" class="xref">Fig 3a</xref>) which was well within the physiological tolerances of the local wheat varieties. Therefore, it was not surprised that there was not clear impact of temperature on wheat yield. In order to ensure winter wheat growing, it needs accumulated temperature of 2100–2400°C during wheat growth period. In a follow-up study, the relationship between wheat yield and accumulated temperature should be tested. In addition, our result also showed that the precipitation has a negative impact on the wheat yield in Henan province, which is consistent with Li et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0184474.ref067" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">67</xref>], who used county-level wheat planting area and production data. This may be related to the fact that Henan province is dominated by non-rain-fed agriculture. Excessive rainfall will be harm to crop growth. Li et al. [
 <xref rid="pone.0184474.ref067" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">67</xref>] argued that precipitation has a higher association with the wheat yield at smaller scales (0.5°, 2°/2.5°) than at larger scales (4°/5°); nevertheless, at all levels of aggregation, the wheat yield has a strong association with temperature. Thus, the correlation between the wheat yield and climate was not consistent. These differences may be due to different spatial scales or geographic location, such that a strong correlation may be found at one scale or in one place, but such a result cannot be assumed to explain other scales or other regions [
 <xref rid="pone.0184474.ref067" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">67</xref>, 
 <xref rid="pone.0184474.ref068" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">68</xref>]. Therefore, in the future study, the relationship between climate factor and crop yield should be examined at different spatial scale.
</p>
