<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec11" sec-type="conclusion" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusions</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We have assessed the risks associated with setting 1.5, 2.0, or 2.5 °C temperature goals and ways to manage them in a systematic manner and discussed their implications. Process-based impact models for multiple sectors were used for future projections of impacts, while multiple IAMs were employed for assessing the portfolios of mitigation options and associated economic impacts for achieving an emission pathway for each goal.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The results suggest the following two major implications for ways to pursue the Paris Agreement goals. First, given the uncertainties in climate sensitivity, “net zero GHG emissions in the second half of this century” is a more actionable goal for society than the 2 or 1.5 °C temperature goals themselves. If the climate sensitivity was relatively high, the temperature goals would not be met even when the net zero emission goal was achieved. If it is proven (through “learning”) to be the case, the options left are: (A) accepting/adapting to a warmer world, (B) boosting mitigation, (C) climate geoengineering, or any combination of these. In this case, the decision should be made based on a deeper discussion of risks associated with each option in society with the latest knowledge on scientific and moral aspects of those risks.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Second, the net zero GHG emission itself is obviously not an easy goal to achieve. We need to consider a wide range of policies: not only climate policies (represented in IAMs by introducing more expensive mitigation options due to higher carbon pricing given a fixed socio-economic scenario), but also broader “sustainability policies” (policies to shift the socio-economic scenario toward a more sustainable one). We need to be aware that IAMs cannot represent innovative changes in technological and socio-economic systems that we are not able to foresee so far. The limitations for net zero emission scenarios (e.g., extremely high cost) would not be absolute. We can envisage more innovative solutions than what IAMs can currently illustrate. At the same time, we need continuous efforts to avoid any possible political failure, which is not represented either in IAMs.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Based on a consideration of social aspects of risk decisions, we also recommend the establishment of a panel of “intermediate layer” experts, who support decision-making by citizens as well as social and ethical thinking by policy makers. Although a global perspective was primarily adopted in our study, diverse subjects such as countries, local governments, enterprises, citizens, etc., need to advance the interpretation of climate risk implications in their own contexts. Conversely, opinions expressed based on their diverse contexts need to be delivered to the global review process. The intermediary experts are expected to facilitate this bi-directional process, but considering the implementation of this layer in society is a future task.</p>
</sec>
