<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Remarks on the achievement of the Paris emission goal</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The above discussion is based on the assumption that we are able to achieve the Paris emission goal, that is, net zero global anthropogenic GHG emissions in the second half of this century. However, it is by no means an easy goal to achieve.</p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One remark regarding the achievement of the Paris emission goal that we can make based on our assessment is that the mitigation action needed to achieve the goal heavily depends on the socio-economic pathways, as has been observed in past assessments (IPCC 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" href="#CR18">2014b</a>), and is smaller for a more sustainable pathway, i.e., the smallest for SSP1, followed by SSP2, and the largest for SSP3, in our assessment. Different socio-economic pathways could be interpreted as representations of the uncertainty range of socio-economic development that we cannot manage. They are certainly external factors when we only think of “climate policy” in a narrow sense, which is represented in IAMs as introducing more expensive mitigation options by setting a higher carbon price. However, when we think of a wider “sustainability policy”, policy interventions should be able to affect SSPs to some extent. Although we did not clarify or identify within the scope of our project what such sustainability policies were, we can suggest that policies to shift the socio-economic condition of the world to a more sustainable one (e.g., from SSP2 toward SSP1) are as important as the climate policy itself to achieve the Paris emission goal, and they should be seriously discussed and implemented.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Another remark is about the limitation of scenarios illustrated by IAMs and the need for a careful interpretation of them. In principle, IAMs cannot represent structural changes (or “transformation”) of socio-economic and technological systems that cannot be foreseen at present, especially when they are applied to illustrate scenarios until the end of this century. Therefore, mitigation scenarios are not something that we have to follow exactly and expected economic damages are not necessarily what we have to accept. Instead, what really is necessary is creating policies to relax constraining conditions that are assumed in models and facilitating transformation of the systems. This point might be obvious in some research communities (Geels et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">2016</a>), but not necessarily in others. It was not drawn directly from our assessment, but was brought up in our inter-disciplinary discussion. At the same time, we should not forget that IAMs cannot represent either possible political failures that might result in insufficient implementation of mitigation actions (Mabey et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23" href="#CR23">2011</a>). Continuous efforts to avoid such a failure are needed.
 </p>
</sec>
