<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Social process of risk decision on global and long-term climate change</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The decision to choose global and long-term goals or options as described in Sect. 
  <a rid="Sec8" ref-type="sec" href="#Sec8">5.3</a> cannot be made based solely on science. It involves uncertainties and value judgments. Thus, social processes play an essential role in such a decision-making, possibly involving citizen participation to democratize the process.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">However, we found in our survey that climate change, as compared with other risk issues, has a characteristic that an average person typically feels that it is difficult to be engaged in, as it is complex, uncertain, long-term, and hard-to-feel self-efficacy (Moser 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">2010</a>; Wolf and Moser 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">2011</a>). Nonetheless, citizens do not necessarily want authorities to make the whole decision. There is a gap between the understanding of climate risk issues by experts and that by citizens. Experts’ understanding should be translated into contexts of citizens’ everyday lives. In addition, citizens may want to know the ethical dimensions and value judgments that are embedded in seemingly objective experts’ arguments.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">To bridge this gap, we propose that an “intermediate layer” of experts be designed to mediate among scientific experts, citizens, and stakeholders to deal with ethical dimensions, value judgments, and translations. This layer will consist of experts from various disciplines particularly including the humanities and social sciences, who can translate scientific results into the contexts of everyday life and can explain how value judgements are embedded in certain scientific statements by revealing the hidden power and knowledge structures of society. The selection process of the members of this layer should be done by the government as well as by the public. The members of this layer should have an open meeting day with concerned people in public. The quality control of this layer will be ensured by continuous discussion. This proposal is discussed in detail by Fujigaki (
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">2018</a>) in this Special Feature.
 </p>
</sec>
