<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study design and sampling</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In June 2011, ten blocks were established in each of the sites (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1" href="#fig-1">Fig. 1</a>). Blocks had at least 90% 
  <span class="italic">E. nigrum</span> cover, a maximum slope of 5 degrees and were placed a minimum of five meters apart to avoid including the same 
  <span class="italic">E. nigrum</span> individual in different blocks, since long-lived, clonally reproducing species can have multiple modular units (
  <a rid="ref-26" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-26">Miller, 2012</a>). Each block consisted of three 50 cm × 50 cm permanently marked plots placed beside each other with a 40-cm separation. Two blocks were unfortunately dropped during the study due to diverse issues (one in Skibotn and one in Gukhesjávri, 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1" href="#fig-1">Fig. 1</a>), hence we had a total of 48 blocks and 144 plots for vegetation analyses.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Each year, all sites were sampled within one or two days from each other at the end of the growing season in late August. 
  <span class="italic">E. nigrum</span> cover and berry production were measured with the use of a wooden frame (50 cm × 50 cm) divided in 16 subplots (0.0125 m
  <span class="sup">2</span> each) by registering presence/absence of live 
  <span class="italic">E. nigrum</span> biomass and 
  <span class="italic">E. nigrum</span> berries in the 16 subplots. Shoot length was measured by selecting five different annual shoots each year (i.e., shoots grown during that summer) in each plot (total of 15 shoots per block). In 2017, 
  <span class="italic">E. nigrum</span> biomass per plot was measured using the point intercept method with 20 pins per plot (
  <a rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-12">Bråthen &amp; Hagberg, 2004</a>) and converting the total number of hits using established calibration functions (
  <a rid="ref-39" ref-type="bibr" href="#ref-39">Ravolainen et al., 2010</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
