<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Post, Forchhammer, et al. (
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0063" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>) pointed out that spatial environmental heterogeneity and scale‐dependent ecological responses are key to understanding and predicting net implications of the various climate change effects reported in Arctic tundra study sites. In caribou and reindeer, some observed population declines have indeed been linked to global environmental change, but the proposed drivers seem to differ locally and include habitat fragmentation (Festa‐Bianchet, Ray, Boutin, Côté, &amp; Gunn, 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0022" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>), Arctic ‘shrubification’ (Fauchald, Park, Tømmervik, Myneni, &amp; Hausner, 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0021" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>), increased insect harassment (Mallory &amp; Boyce, 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0052" ref-type="ref">2017</xref>) and worsening winter‐feeding conditions (Forbes et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0023" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>; Hansen et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0027" ref-type="ref">2011</xref>). Also, the drivers of change may vary in time. For instance, the early population size trajectories on Brøggerhalvøya since the reindeer reintroduction in 1978 followed irruption‐like dynamics (Aanes et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0001" ref-type="ref">2000</xref>), with habitat degradation in the early 1990s (Hansen, Henriksen, Aanes, &amp; Sæther, 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0031" ref-type="ref">2007</xref>) that may have contributed to the 1994 population crash and, thereby, our trend estimates. The more recent negative trends, which appear to be a consequence of negative net effects of climate change, were in sharp contrast to the Adventdalen population increase during the same period. Accordingly, because of the spatial and temporal diversity of factors influencing 
 <italic>Rangifer</italic> population growth rates and ecological carrying capacity, Gunn et al. (
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0026" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>) warned against generalizing observed local abundance trends and impacts of climate change. The concern that there is a ‘global’ decline in 
 <italic>Rangifer</italic> abundance due to increased anthropogenic impact (Vors &amp; Boyce, 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0086" ref-type="ref">2009</xref>) also lacks quantitative support. Most Eurasian reindeer populations show no sign of decline, but rather the opposite (Uboni et al., 
 <xref rid="gcb14761-bib-0081" ref-type="ref">2016</xref>), which also appears to be the case for Svalbard reindeer. Importantly, however, the substantial local variation in abundance trends calls for great caution when extrapolating results from single‐population studies of long‐term climate change effects, even on such small spatial scales (in a 
 <italic>Rangifer</italic> context).
</p>
