<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec7" sec-type="results" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results</div>
 <sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Case Selection: Comparison of Social, Environmental and Financial Settings in Asian Cities</div>
  <p id="Par15" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Asia’s coasts urbanise at a staggering rate. In fact, 11 of the world’s 17 largest cities are coastal Asian cities, such as Bangkok, Jakarta or Manila (Tibbetts 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60" href="#CR60">2002</a>). Economic growth is lifting hundreds of millions of people out of poverty and a rapidly growing urban middle class accounts for about two billion people at present. However, Asian cities also include the world’s largest urban slum populations and the largest population living below the poverty line in areas vulnerable to environmental risks, such as floods, landslides and the effects of pollutions (UN-HABITAT and ESCAP 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64" href="#CR64">2015</a>). The variety in social, environmental and financial contexts of these cities is reflected in the pressures that these cities experience (Table 
   <a rid="Tab3" ref-type="table" href="#Tab3">3</a>).
  </p>
  <p id="Par16" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In general, many cities in Asia, especially those with low average GDP and high inflation, face social pressure, particularly coming from high urbanisation rates, environmental pressure from water scarcity, pollution, flooding and heat risk, as well as financial pressure. During several decades, the expansion of the global market in Asia transformed its large cities into population magnets with relatively high economic and urban growth (Douglass 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7" href="#CR7">2010</a>; Firman 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" href="#CR13">2009</a>). Coastal cities like HCMC, Jakarta and Bangkok are recurrently used as case studies of sinking cities with an average land subsidence rate of 20–100 mm/year (Erkens et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" href="#CR11">2015</a>). Uncontrolled groundwater abstraction in Bandung and Taipei aggravates their land subsidence to 80 mm/year (Abidin et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2" href="#CR2">2013</a>; Hwang et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21" href="#CR21">2016</a>). The two least pressured cities, Seoul and Singapore, face freshwater scarcity. Nevertheless, both cities secure their drinking water supply using advanced technology. Seoul’s water works authority purifies 3.19 million m
   <span class="sup">3</span> drinking water from the Han River, while Singapore is known for its four national taps of imported water, local rainwater harvesting, NEWater (reclaimed water) and desalinated water (SMG 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR55" href="#CR55">2014</a>; PUB 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50" href="#CR50">2017</a>). Many cities in Asia face heat risks. With the most recent heat-wave temperatures of 48 °C in 2016, Ahmedabad’s inhabitants faced an ever-growing heat risk (Aartsen et al. 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">2017</a>). Overall, cities with high social pressures, such as Jakarta and Manila, tend to have high financial pressures. In fact, the city’s overall social, environmental and financial pressures reflected in the TPI has been found to correlate negatively with the IWRM performance reflected in the BCI (Koop and Van Leeuwen 
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">2015b</a>).
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Overview of IWRM Practices in Asian Cities</div>
  <p id="Par17" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figure 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a> shows the results of the City Blueprint analyses in the selected cities according to categorisation shown in Table 
   <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>. The BCI scores span a large range of 2.0 to 8.1. Jakarta, HCMC, Bandung, Bangkok, Manila and Ahmedabad are grouped among cities with low BCIs. According to Table 
   <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>, these six cities can be categorised as 
   <span class="italic">wasteful cities</span> (BCI 2–4), where basic water services are mostly covered but flood risk exists and waste management is poor. Taipei, Tianjin and Hohhot are categorised as 
   <span class="italic">water efficient cities</span> (BCI 4–6) where infrastructure and technologies in addressing basic water services, solid waste and wastewater treatment are more developed. Finally, Seoul and Singapore have implemented measures to be self-sufficient and circular. They categorise as 
   <span class="italic">resource efficient and adaptive cities</span> (BCI 6–8).
  </p>
  <p id="Par18" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figure 
   <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a> shows the City Blueprint’s spider diagrams of Jakarta (BCI 2.0), Tianjin (BCI 4.9) and Singapore (BCI 8.1). Jakarta’s lowest scores are mostly in the category of water quality, solid waste treatment and wastewater treatment. Similarly, HCMC (BCI 2.4), Bandung (BCI 2.6), Bangkok (BCI 2.6), Manila (BCI 2.6) and Ahmedabad (BCI 3.0) have good basic water services, low drinking water consumption, low coverage of secondary WWT systems and combined sewers. These cities have difficulties in meeting their basic water services for marginalised communities. In particular HCMC has low access to sanitation. Moreover, in these cities, wastewater is typically insufficiently collected and treated. Drinking water consumption is low and water leakages are high. Jakarta has the largest water system leakage rate of 48%. Ahmedabad and Manila score higher in solid waste treatment while HCMC has a relatively new sewerage network. Tianjin, Taipei (BCI 3.9) and Hohhot (BCI 5.0) have fully covered basic water services, good solid waste collection systems and high coverage of WWT, but no nutrient and energy recovery yet. Moreover, Taipei has a high drinking water consumption of 342 m
   <span class="sup">3</span>/person/year. Meanwhile, Seoul (BCI 7.3) and Singapore (8.1) have excellent WWT systems with full coverage and efficiency, high percentage of energy recovery from solid waste incineration and implement adaptation plans to improve the city’s climate robustness.
   <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Fig. 3</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Spider diagrams based on 25 performance indicators for Jakarta (top), Tianjin (centre) and Singapore (bottom). The BCI, the geometric means of the 25 indicators, are 2.0, 4.9 and 8.1, respectively</p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="267_2019_1137_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e1150" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec10" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Governance Capacity to Address Flood Risk</div>
  <p id="Par19" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In order to understand the main barriers and enablers that Asian cities experience in their transformation trajectory, we have analysed the water governance capacity of three transforming cities: Ahmedabad, Bandung and Taipei. In this section, we only provide a short overview and mainly limit ourselves to the governance capacity to deal with the risk of flooding. Table 
   <a rid="Tab4" ref-type="table" href="#Tab4">4</a> displays a graphic view of the governance capacity profile in these three cities.
  </p>
  <sec id="Sec11" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Ahmedabad</div>
   <p id="Par20" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In Ahmedabad, visionary agents (ind. 6.3) within the government use their authority (ind. 7.3) to set ambitious goals (ind. 5.1). However, insufficient statutory compliance (ind. 9.2) and poor use of policy instruments (ind. 9.1) limit the implementation of these goals. In particular, insufficient monitoring (ind. 3.1) and policy evaluation (ind. 3.2) hinder learning for better implementation practices. Awareness and financial viability (conditions 1 and 8) are found to encourage governance capacity. On the other hand, continuous learning and implementing capacity (conditions 3 and 9) reduce the governance capacity needed to address flood risks. Interestingly, Ahmedabad’s Governance capacity to address heat risks was found to be rather encouraging (Aartsen et al. 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">2017</a>). This can be seen from the success case of Ahmedabad’s Heat Adaptation Plan. During the 2010 heat wave, an excess of 1,344 additional deaths in Ahmedabad were reported, i.e., an increase of 43.1% compared with the previous years (Shah et al. 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54" href="#CR54">2014</a>). It sets an example for the city to improve its governance capacity to address other challenges of water, waste and climate change.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec12" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Bandung</div>
   <p id="Par21" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Flooding in Bandung has increased in frequency where during the worst seasonal flood, it can be stagnant for 2–4 weeks and causes temporary evacuation. Flooding is the main reason for increased traffic congestion contributing to the city’s air pollution. Inappropriate solid waste collection and treatment causes clogs in drainage channels, which exacerbate flooding events even further (Rahmasary 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">2017</a>). Bandung can improve its smart monitoring and evaluation process (condition 3). The city’s statutory compliance (ind. 9.2) to existing legislation, policies and agreements can be considered a priority for improvement. In addition, sharing knowledge and practice can be improved by endorsing collaboration among engaged stakeholders and multi-level networking (condition 4). Agents of change (condition 6) play a critical role in raising public awareness and realising behavioural change (condition 1) especially in solid waste and wastewater treatment challenges (Rahmasary 
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">2017</a>). Additional support from the regional and national government can be used more effectively to address the city’s strongly interrelated water challenges.
   </p>
  </sec>
  <sec id="Sec13" class="sec">
   <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Taipei</div>
   <p id="Par22" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In Taipei, public awareness of flood risk (ind. 2.1) and smart monitoring (ind. 3.1) is relatively high. Equitable financial support for climate protection (condition 8) is largely provided. Taipei has learned from past disasters. Monitoring systems are further developed and improved, and companies and citizens comply with taxes to further reduce flood risks. However, these measures are merely focussed on short-term flood risks. To further improve the long-term governance capacity for Taipei, the city needs to elaborate detailed long-term urban planning (ind. 5.1) and support visionary agents (6.3). The agents of change, such as the Ministry of Science and Technology, the Taiwan Youth Climate Coalition, private companies and universities, should explore opportunities that go beyond technical solutions and the government and the private sector should provide financial resources to support these entrepreneurial activities. This broader approach may contribute and further improve the city’s preparedness. In particular, capacity development may need to focus on:
    <div list-type="order" class="list">
     <div class="list-item">
      <p id="Par23">Information transparency and comprehensiveness for everyone (ind. 2.2 and 2.3);</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p id="Par24">Awareness raising by applying bottom-up approaches (ind. 1.2);</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p id="Par25">Integration between different levels and different stakeholders (condition 7);</p>
     </div>
     <div class="list-item">
      <p id="Par26">Improving the evaluation process to include long-term risks and climate change (condition 3)</p>
     </div>
    </div>
   </p>
  </sec>
 </sec>
</sec>
