<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Governance Capacity Framework (GCF)</div>
 <p id="Par11" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The GCF analyses the governance capacity of a city to address a specific common water challenge (Koop et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">2017</a>; Watershare 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR77" href="#CR77">2017b</a>). The GCF provides information on how well different organisations can work together and to what extent capacities are institutionalised. In this way, governance capacity is understood as the result of human skills and expertise. In its more recent extension, the GCF has been applied in 15 cities where the publications of Quito (Scheurs et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53" href="#CR53">2018</a>), New York City (Feingold et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12" href="#CR12">2018</a>), Sabadell (Steflova et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57" href="#CR57">2018</a>), Ahmedabad (Aartsen et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">2017</a>), Seoul (Kim et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">2018</a>), Bandung (Rahmasary 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">2017</a>), Cape Town (Madonsela et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR87" href="#CR87">2019</a>) and Amsterdam, Rotterdam, Leicester and Milton Keynes (Koop et al. 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">2018</a>) are available online. The GCF consists of three dimensions and nine conditions (Table 
  <a rid="Tab4" ref-type="table" href="#Tab4">4</a>). Each condition has three indicators that are scored using a Likert scale ranging from very encouraging (++) to very limiting (− −) the overall governance capacity to address a water challenge. A detailed description of the Likert scale for each of the 27 indicators is available (EC 
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9" href="#CR9">2018</a>). Water governance is assessed with respect to five challenges: (1) flood risk, (2) water scarcity, (3) solid waste treatment, (4) wastewater treatment and (5) urban heat islands (UHI). The indicator scoring was done through a triangular approach to validate findings by different sources in three consecutive steps:
  <div list-type="order" class="list">
   <div class="list-item">
    <p id="Par12">Desk study of policy documents, scientific literature and grey literature to provide a preliminary score for each of the 27 indicators based on substantiated argumentation and references to the studied material.</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p id="Par13">Interviews with relevant local stakeholders. Stakeholders in each city were analysed and categorised to ensure the representativeness of interviewees and the diversity of water managers. This paper categorised the stakeholders based on their importance/influence, functionality or power/interest. Multiple interviewees from identified stakeholders were selected for in-depth interviews to collect information, score the indicators and ask follow-up questions for clarification or a better overall understanding. To minimise the risk of bias and assure diversity amongst interviewees, they were selected according to their roles, expertise and responsibilities. Based on the interviews, the preliminary indicator scores were updated.</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p id="Par14">Feedback from interviewees. Interviewees were asked to provide constructive feedback on the updated indicator scores. After including this feedback, the final scores were determined.</p>
   </div>
  </div>
  <div id="Tab4" class="table-wrap">
   <span class="label">Table 4</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Governance Capacity profile of three Asian cities with respect to the integrated challenge of flood risk (Aartsen et al. 
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" href="#CR1">2017</a>; Rahmasary 
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51" href="#CR51">2017</a>; Robert 
     <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52" href="#CR52">2017</a>)
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="267_2019_1137_Tab2_HTML" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
