<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec10" sec-type="conclusion" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusions</div>
 <p id="Par53" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Where data are available in the early 1990s, most sites show evidence of increasing UVI in the earliest part of the record when ozone was declining. However, the short length of the data record prior to 2000, and possible interference from the eruption of Mt Pinatubo, hinder our ability to ascribe changes in UVI to changes in ozone.</p>
 <p id="Par54" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In most cases, we find that calculated and measured trends have been small and are in most cases not significantly different from zero. With the exception of one site (Hoher Sonnblick), they also agree with each other to within their error bars, and with trends calculated with the World Expected model.</p>
 <p id="Par55" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">At clean-air sites in the southern hemisphere, the UVI has followed the World Expected scenario within the limits of the measurement uncertainty. Differences between measurements and the two World Avoided models are already highly significant in the Arctic, and at southern hemisphere sites, especially in Antarctica. The situation is more complex at mid-latitudes in the northern hemisphere, where the effects of changes in aerosol and clouds mask effects of ozone.</p>
 <p id="Par56" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">For winter and autumn, changes observed at mid-latitude sites are mixed. Measurements show a tendency towards decreasing UVI in the southern hemisphere and increasing UVI in the northern hemisphere. However, few of the observed long-term changes since 1996 are statistically significant.</p>
 <p id="Par57" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">A statistically significant decrease in measured summertime UVI has been observed at the Antarctic site Arrival Heights, and the reduction in UVI at Lauder is close to being statistically significant at the 95% level. However, at both sites, trends calculated from ozone remain close to zero, showing that the reductions in UVI must be due to other factors (e.g., changes in cloud, aerosol, or surface albedo). Measurements during the last few years at Lauder also show signs of decreases in UVI, which also cannot be attributed to ozone changes.</p>
 <p id="Par58" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The Montreal Protocol has been effective in curbing increases in harmful UVI. Without the Montreal Protocol, UVI values at northern and southern latitudes &lt;50° would by now be 10 to 20% larger in all seasons compared to UVIs observed during the early 1990s. These changes would have had grave consequences for public health and would have led to increases in skin cancer occurrences
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41" href="#CR41">41</a>
  </span>. For latitudes &gt;50°S, UVI values would have increased over the same period between 25% (Ushuaia in summer and autumn) to more than 100% (South Pole in spring and summer).
 </p>
 <p id="Par59" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">UVI values in the future remain uncertain because of:
  <div list-type="alpha-lower" class="list">
   <div class="list-item">
    <p id="Par60">possible volcanic eruptions, which could temporarily exacerbate ozone depletion as long as chlorine levels remain elevated;</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p id="Par61">interactions with other aspects of climate change, such as changes in clouds and aerosols;</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p id="Par62">slowly varying natural modes of variability
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42" href="#CR42">42</a>
     </span>, such as the Interdecadal Pacific Oscillation
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43" href="#CR43">43</a>
     </span>, which may affect cloud cover but are not included in the study;
    </p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p id="Par63">effects of increasing greenhouse gases, which will lead to stratospheric cooling and changes in dynamics that may subsequently cause ozone to increase above levels observed in 1980 outside polar regions;</p>
   </div>
   <div class="list-item">
    <p id="Par64">non-compliance to the Montreal Protocol, such as found in a recent study
     <span class="sup">
      <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44" href="#CR44">44</a>
     </span>.
    </p>
   </div>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par65" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The reduced number of operational sites measuring UV irradiance is concerning. The value of time series data increases with the length of the record, as shown by the smaller error bars for the longer-term measurement sites in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6</a>. Unfortunately, there are only a few high-quality NDACC sites with data from the early 1990s that are still operational. It is important that they continue to be supported in case of unexpected future changes.
 </p>
</sec>
