<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec5" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Results from Model Simulations</div>
 <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We begin by comparing projected ozone fields from the two World Avoided models (Scenarios (2) and (3)).</p>
 <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Predicted ozone values from these two models are compared for selected latitudes in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a>. The two models are in general agreement in long-term behaviour, but also show significant differences over shorter time scales, especially at low latitudes. Close agreement is not expected at time scales of less than 5 years because there is a random component to the way modes of variability such as the quasi biennial oscillation (QBO) manifest themselves in the model runs. The systematic differences between the two models are within the usual range for chemistry-climate models
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
  </span>.
  <div id="Fig1" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 1</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Comparison between projected ozone values in the GEOS-CCM (blue lines) and NIWA UKCA (red lines) World Avoided models for high (
     <span class="bold">a</span>,
     <span class="bold">d</span>), mid (
     <span class="bold">b</span>,
     <span class="bold">e</span>), and low (
     <span class="bold">c</span>,
     <span class="bold">f</span>) latitudes. Thicker lines are 5-year running means. Green lines indicate the smoothed difference between the two models (i.e., NIWA-UKCA minus GEOS-CCM). Plots for latitude 15° are representative of all equatorial latitudes, while those for 75° are representative for higher polar latitudes.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_48625_Fig1_HTML" id="d29e1292" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par26" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Modelled ozone data for Scenarios (2), (3) and (4) were compared with measured ozone data (Scenario (1)) and results are provided as Supplementary Data. In general, modelled and measured total ozone column amounts (TOCs) agree reasonably well. For the reference period 1978–1987 (i.e., the period between the year when ozone measurements from space became available globally and the year when the Montreal Protocol came into effect), TOCs calculated with the NIWA-UKCA model (both World Expected and World Avoided) for sites between 45°S and 45°N – which represents 71% of the globe –are on average 8 ± 4% (±1σ) higher than the measured TOCs. The maximum bias for this latitude range is 14%. TOCs calculated with the GEOS World Avoided model are slightly smaller. It overestimates the measured TOC by 2 ± 5% on average, with a maximum bias of 12%. Deviations between the modeled and measured TOCs become larger at higher latitudes, especially in the southern hemisphere. In this latitude range, differences can exceed 20% with biases from GEOS model exceeding those from the NIWA-UKCA model. These larger biases are partly a consequence of the low ozone amounts there and partly due to the difficulty to correctly model the destruction of ozone by heterogeneous chemical processes, which strongly depend on the temperature of the lower stratosphere. Furthermore, specific sites are not necessarily well represented by the zonal means used in the model. This is especially true for high-latitude southern hemisphere sites (i.e., Ushuaia and Palmer Station) in spring when the position of the ozone hole is frequently displaced toward the South American quadrant. Some of the discrepancy may also be due to interpolation errors in the ozone assimilation during the polar night, but this is irrelevant for changes in the UVI. Even though some uncertainties remain in the models, the agreement in geographic and seasonal patterns gives confidence that they can be used to project future changes. Finally, we also note that there may be errors in the model projections if factors such as changes in the Brewer-Dobson circulation are not properly parameterised.</p>
 <p id="Par27" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Previous studies have also shown that the CCM models tend to overestimate ozone amounts. For example, the GEOS-CCM used previously
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6" href="#CR6">6</a>
  </span> has a high-ozone bias at mid to high latitudes
  <span class="sup">
   <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>
  </span>, which would lead to UVI estimates that are too low by approximately 10% at latitude 45° S. The green lines in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a> are the mean differences between the two models (smoothed), which shows that they depend on both latitude and time.
 </p>
 <p id="Par28" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the longer-term, projections by the two models are in good agreement. The reasonable level of consistency between these models adds further confidence to those predictions but also illustrates some significant differences.</p>
 <p id="Par29" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">It is interesting to note that by the year 2100, projected ozone declines are largest at high latitudes, and smallest in the tropics. By that time, the lowest mean ozone amounts would be in polar regions, and the highest in the tropics.</p>
 <p id="Par30" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Corresponding changes in UVI from both World Avoided simulations, as well as from the World Expected simulation (Scenario (4)) are shown in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a>. By 2100 the peak UVI at mid-latitudes would have increased a factor of four, and by much larger factors at higher latitudes. Even with the high ozone bias in the model, the calculated peak UVI would have exceeded 40 in over 70% of the area of the globe. Because of the latitudinal redistribution in ozone described above, at the end of the 21
  <span class="sup">st</span> century, the largest clear-sky UVI values projected at mid-latitudes are similar to those in the tropics. This is in contrast to the present situation, where the peak UVI occurs in the tropics.
  <div id="Fig2" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 2</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>UVI calculated from World Avoided and World Expected simulations for the period 1960 to 2100 for high (
     <span class="bold">a</span>,
     <span class="bold">d</span>), mid (
     <span class="bold">b</span>,
     <span class="bold">e</span>), and low (
     <span class="bold">c</span>,
     <span class="bold">f</span>) latitudes. The shaded area shows the seasonal range of predictions calculated from the NIWA-UKCA World Avoided simulation. The upper envelope of the shaded range refers to peak values predicted for the summer and the lower envelope to minimum values predicted for winter. The red and blue lines indicate the 5-year running means for the NIWA-UKCA and GEOS-CCM World Avoided model simulations, respectively. The green line is the 5-year running mean of the NIWA-UKCA World Expected simulation, which assumes full compliance with the Montreal Protocol.
    </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_48625_Fig2_HTML" id="d29e1347" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <sec id="Sec6" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Time series for lauder</div>
  <p id="Par31" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We now compare these UVI projections from the CCM models with observed changes in UVI and with those expected from clear-sky calculations using the assimilated ozone values. Results for Lauder are shown in Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>. Figure 
   <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3a</a> displays the time series of daily ozone derived from the NIWA/BS ozone assimilation for the period since satellite measurements became available. In Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3b</a>, the peak UVI measured within one hour of local noon is compared with the UVI calculated for clear-sky conditions using the NIWA/BS ozone data. There is good agreement in the seasonal range between measured and modelled UVI.
   <div id="Fig3" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Figure 3</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Total ozone column (
      <span class="bold">a</span>) and daily maximum UVI within 1 hour of local noon (
      <span class="bold">b</span>) at Lauder. Panels (
      <span class="bold">c</span>–
      <span class="bold">f</span>) show UVI changes for winter (
      <span class="bold">c</span>), spring (
      <span class="bold">d</span>), summer (
      <span class="bold">e</span>) and autumn (
      <span class="bold">f</span>) determined from measurements of the NDACC instruments (blue), calculated from total ozone column (black), and projected by the two World Avoided (red and magenta) and World Expected (green) CCM model runs. UVI changes were normalized as described in the text and the “UVI ratios” shown in Panels (c–f) are ratios relative to these normalizations. Note that for the season that spans two years (summer at this southern hemisphere site), the year label refers to the year at the start of the season. For example, the summer of Dec 2017 to Feb 2018 is plotted at 2017.
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="41598_2019_48625_Fig3_HTML" id="d29e1395" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p id="Par32" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Because of the large seasonal and day-to-day variability, it is difficult to see any long-term effects (other than in the upper envelope of data) in Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3b</a>. The lower four panels of Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a> redress this by considering seasonal means, with each data point representing the mean over different 3-month periods. Because of the previously discussed biases in calculated and modelled ozone, all data shown in Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3c–f</a> were normalized. The measured UVI values were normalized to the average of all values, while the calculated UVIs were normalized to the average of only those years with measurements. The normalized peak UVI changes derived from measurements (blue lines) are compared with those calculated from the assimilated ozone dataset (black lines). Also shown in these panels are the corresponding UVI changes that would have occurred according to the World Avoided calculations reported by the GEOS-CCM model (broken red lines) and the NIWA-UKCA model (broken magenta lines). UVI values in the World Expected are also shown (broken green lines). The heavier solid lines for each model run include smoothing with an approximating spline. Both World Avoided datasets and the World Expected dataset were normalized to the average of the calculated UVI values of the years 1978 to 1987; the decade that immediately preceded the signing of the Montreal Protocol. Corresponding plots for all other sites are in Supplementary Data.
  </p>
  <p id="Par33" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In the period prior to 2020 shown in Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig3">3</a>, projected changes are generally smaller with the NIWA-UKCA model than with the GEOS-CCM model. However, this is not everywhere the case. At northern mid-latitudes, the two models are in close agreement (see Supplementary Data). They are also similar at high southern latitudes during summer, while the NIWA-UKCA values are larger at high northern latitudes. Reasons for these model differences are outside the scope of the present study.
  </p>
  <p id="Par34" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">As expected, the World Expected line (green) is usually below the World Avoided line (pink). However, for a short period in the late 1990s, which is most pronounced in the winter, it is higher. Differences of this magnitude are within the range of spread between model runs of about 5%.</p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec7" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">UVI in summer</div>
  <p id="Par35" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Possible changes in UV radiation during summer are most relevant from an environmental and health perspective. In Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>, we compare measured, calculated, and projected UVIs for summer at all 17 sites in Table 
   <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>. The figure shows that the World Avoided trends depend greatly on latitude and that differences between the two model runs are also latitude-dependent. For example, at latitude 40°N, there is close agreement between the two models (for other seasons, see Supplementary Data).
   <div id="Fig4" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Figure 4</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Comparison of normalized UVI ratios for summer months at all sites between measurements, calculations for clear skies based on the ozone assimilation, and clear-sky models for the World Avoided and World Expected scenarios. Note that the vertical axis scale varies between panels.</p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="41598_2019_48625_Fig4_HTML" id="d29e1433" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p id="Par36" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">With the exception of Hoher Sonnblick, the measured data from all sites closely match the calculated values and are much closer to the World Expected curves than the World Avoided curves. However, there is a significant divergence between the measured values and World Expected values at higher latitudes: measured and calculated UVI ratios are more or less constant over time while the World Expected curves have a broad maximum during the first decade of the 21
   <span class="sup">st</span> century (last two panels of Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>). This suggests that the impact of the large spring-time ozone depletions persists for too long into the following summer in the model. This is a well-known limitation of CCMs
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>
   </span> for which the causes are not fully understood, and is an area of current research.
  </p>
  <p id="Par37" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The measurements at Hoher Sonnblick (Panel f) show a continuation of the previously reported upward trend in summertime UVI
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>
   </span>, which was attributed to changes in aerosols or cloud cover. This increase is not present in all seasons, so it is not a calibration artefact. However, there are several seasonal gaps in the data, and the year-to-year variability is also much greater at this mountainous site (see Supplementary Data), possibly due to variable snow cover.
  </p>
  <p id="Par38" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">At some other sites, the length of the time series is too short for reliable trend estimates. Only nine of the 17 sites have more than 20 years of data coverage.</p>
  <p id="Par39" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figure 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a> also indicates that UVI ratios calculated from the assimilated ozone data are generally less than unity prior to the 1990s and before the start of UV measurements. The slope in the calculated data is generally consistent with the slope in the datasets of the three CCM models. These model calculations imply that considerable changes in summer UVI occurred between 1978 and 1990 (about 5% at northern mid-latitude sites, up to 10% at southern mid-latitude sites and up to 20% at the three Antarctic sites). However, direct UVI observations needed to confirm these changes do not exist.
  </p>
  <p id="Par40" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">After accounting for differences in elevation between the sites, we note that latitude-for-latitude, the mean summer UVI values tend to be larger at the southern hemisphere (SH) sites compared with the northern hemisphere (NH) sites, as has been predicted and observed previously
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>–
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
   </span>. This NH/SH difference is as expected. For example, Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig2">2</a> shows that at 45°S, the peak UVI value is larger than at 45°N by approximately 13%. Approximately half of this difference is due to ozone differences and half is due to Sun-Earth separation differences. The much larger NH/SH differences reported in the past
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31" href="#CR31">31</a>–
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34" href="#CR34">34</a>
   </span> also include effects of clouds and aerosols, which were not considered in the CCM calculations. The NH/SH asymmetry is projected to be only slightly smaller by year 2100.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">UVI in spring at high latitudes</div>
  <p id="Par41" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>, we compare normalized measured, calculated, World Avoided, and World Expected UVIs in spring for the Arctic and Antarctic sites included in this study, where the largest long-term changes in UVI have been observed. Note the expanded vertical axis scale compared with that in Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>. For these high-latitude sites, the “calculated” and “measured” data sets are in almost perfect agreement, particularly in Antarctica, indicating that ozone variation is the largest contributor to UVI changes. Variability of clouds and albedo is a minor contributor in comparison.
   <div id="Fig5" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Figure 5</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Comparison of UVI in spring at polar sites between measurements, calculations for clear skies based on the ozone assimilation, and clear-sky models for the World Avoided and World Expected scenarios.</p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="41598_2019_48625_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e1497" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p id="Par42" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The “hump” in the World Expected data noted previously for the summer data (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>), which peaks in the early part of the 21
   <span class="sup">st</span> century, is also present in the spring data (Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>). However, in the spring period, there is also a hint of this in the measured and calculated data for the two Antarctic sites and perhaps also at Summit. Data from Barrow show more variability, as one would expect from an Arctic coastal site that is affected by changes in albedo from snow and sea ice.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec id="Sec9" class="sec">
  <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Decadal trends in UVI</div>
  <p id="Par43" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Due to the less complete data coverage early in the period, our statistical analysis is restricted to the period since 1996. This period also excludes effects from the eruption of Mt Pinatubo, which led to significant effects on ozone and UV at some locations
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35" href="#CR35">35</a>–
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38" href="#CR38">38</a>
   </span>. The period since 1996 also includes approximately two complete 11-year solar cycles, which cause variations in ozone of ±2%
   <span class="sup">
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39" href="#CR39">39</a>,
    <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40" href="#CR40">40</a>
   </span> that would lead in turn to a modulation of similar relative magnitude, but of opposite sign, in the UVI.
  </p>
  <p id="Par44" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Even for the period since 1996, measured data are unfortunately incomplete at some sites, and only a small number of sites have full data coverage through to the end of 2018 (see Table 
   <a rid="Tab1" ref-type="table" href="#Tab1">1</a>). For example, due to funding restrictions, measurements were terminated in 2017 at Arctic sites that were initiated by Biospherical Instruments (BSI). Their time series from Ushuaia and San Diego are also restricted to the period before 2010 and 2008 respectively. There was also a gap from 2003 to 2008 in Melbourne data. Of the 17 sites, only three (Lauder, Palmer, and Thessaloniki) have near-complete data coverage for the full period from 1996 to 2018. However, six others (Barrow, Hoher Sonnblick, Boulder, Mauna Loa, Arrival Heights and South Pole) have only a few years of missing data over that period. Greatest confidence should be placed on data from these nine stations.
  </p>
  <p id="Par45" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">There are other possible forcing mechanisms that drive interannual variability in UVI. These include variability due to the QBO or the 
   <span class="italic">El Nino</span> Southern Oscillation (ENSO). However, over time scales as long as 22 years, any such effects are small, and have not been considered in the statistical analysis. In these seasonal averages, where each data point is separated from the previous value by a period of 9 months, any statistical auto-correlation effects should also be small. In the trend analysis, we have assumed that any long-term changes over the period 1996 to 2018 could be represented by a linear change, which is a reasonable assumption (e.g., see Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>). Results of the statistical analysis are shown in Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6</a>. The results are not particularly sensitive to the start year, resulting in a similar picture (not shown) if the start-date for the analysis is changed by 1 or 2 years.
   <div id="Fig6" class="fig">
    <span class="label">Figure 6</span>
    <div class="caption">
     <p>Calculated decadal trends in measured UVI since 1996 (or from the data start year, if later than 1996) as a function of site latitude, compared with those calculated for clear skies from observed ozone, and as calculated by the two World Avoided model runs and the World Expected run for each season (
      <span class="bold">a</span>–
      <span class="bold">d</span>). Sites where the time series spans 20 years or more are denoted by bold text and solid symbols. The number of years of data included in the trend analysis at each site is indicated beside the site name. If data from some seasons are missing, this number can be less than the total number of years. Error bars shown are 2-σ uncertainties of the regression model.
     </p>
    </div>
    <div xlink:href="41598_2019_48625_Fig6_HTML" id="d29e1559" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
   </div>
  </p>
  <p id="Par46" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Note that the error bars shown for the trend estimates in Fig. 
   <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6</a> are 2-σ uncertainties of the regression model, which also include small random uncertainties in the measurements that propagate to the 90-day averages analysed here. However, systematic errors due to potential long-term drifts in the measurements (e.g., due to the transfer of irradiance scales between calibration standards) are not included.
  </p>
  <p id="Par47" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Figure 
   <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6</a> shows the following:
   <div list-type="order" class="list">
    <div class="list-item">
     <p id="Par48">
      <span class="italic">The two World Avoided Simulations give similar trends:</span> With the exception of Palmer Station in winter, there is good agreement between the trends derived from the two World Avoided simulations. (At Palmer Station, the sun is only 2° above the horizon (SZA
      <sub>min</sub> = 88°) at the winter solstice, so peak UVI values during this period are small.) The calculated UVI is also sensitive to small modelling and sampling differences (see Supplementary Data). Also, as shown in Fig. 
      <a rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig1">1</a> (lower left panel), there are significant differences in the seasonal variability between the two model projections in this latitude region and period.
     </p>
    </div>
    <div class="list-item">
     <p id="Par49">
      <span class="italic">UV Trends are large in the World Avoided Simulations:</span> In the World Avoided (without the Montreal Protocol), UVI levels would have increased over the last 22 years by approximately 50% per decade at high southern latitudes in spring, and by 30% per decade in summer. Increases of up to 20% per decade would have been seen at northern high latitudes. At midlatitudes, the increases would have been approximately 5–10% per decade. Such changes would have been clearly detectable in the measurement data.
     </p>
    </div>
    <div class="list-item">
     <p id="Par50">
      <span class="italic">Measurements Differ from the World Avoided Simulations:</span> In the spring and summer, the observed trends for all nine sites with good data coverage (solid symbols in Fig. 
      <a rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig6">6</a>) are significantly different from the World Avoided trends at all mid- and high-latitudes in the southern hemisphere, and at high latitudes in the northern hemisphere. At northern mid-latitudes, differences between measured trends and trends from the World Avoided simulations are significant in summer at all sites except Hoher Sonnblick, but in other seasons the results are more mixed.
     </p>
    </div>
    <div class="list-item">
     <p id="Par51">
      <span class="italic">Measurements follow the World Expected Simulations:</span> For all sites, trends calculated from the measurements are consistent with the World Expected scenario, though uncertainties are large at Hoher Sonnblick, and other sites (e.g., San Diego, Saint Denis and Obs. Haute-Provence), where there are only a few years of observation. While variability in UVI is close to that predicted by changes in ozone at the southern hemisphere sites, the situation is more complex at northern mid-latitude sites, such as Hoher Sonnblick, where the effects of changes in aerosols and clouds are more important in some seasons.
     </p>
    </div>
    <div class="list-item">
     <p id="Par52">
      <span class="italic">Evidence of a Downward Tendency in UVI since 1996 in the Southern Hemisphere:</span> At the three Antarctic sites (South Pole, Arrival Heights, and Palmer Station) the measured UVIs reveal decreases of about 5% per decade during summer, however, only the trend at Arrival Heights is significant at the 95% confidence level. We note that UVIs calculated from changes in ozone show almost no change, suggesting that changes in albedo or cloud cover contribute to the trends in the measured UVIs. We also note that measurements at these three remote sites are potentially affected by long-term drifts of approximately 1% per decade, which are associated with hardware modifications and changes in calibration standards. Even if these drifts were confirmed, the downward trend at Arrival Heights would remain statistically significant. At the South Pole and Arrival Heights, both measured and calculated UVIs appear to have decreased during spring (the period most affected by the ozone hole), however, trends calculated from these changes are not yet statistically significant. At Lauder, small downward trends in measured UVI are observed for summer and autumn, which are on the verge of being statistically significant. These trends are generally consistent with trends derived from the NIWA/BS ozone dataset, although throughout the southern hemisphere, trends are systematically more negative for measurements than for calculations for all seasons.
     </p>
    </div>
   </div>
  </p>
 </sec>
</sec>
