<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec8" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">UVI in spring at high latitudes</div>
 <p id="Par41" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>, we compare normalized measured, calculated, World Avoided, and World Expected UVIs in spring for the Arctic and Antarctic sites included in this study, where the largest long-term changes in UVI have been observed. Note the expanded vertical axis scale compared with that in Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>. For these high-latitude sites, the “calculated” and “measured” data sets are in almost perfect agreement, particularly in Antarctica, indicating that ozone variation is the largest contributor to UVI changes. Variability of clouds and albedo is a minor contributor in comparison.
  <div id="Fig5" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 5</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Comparison of UVI in spring at polar sites between measurements, calculations for clear skies based on the ozone assimilation, and clear-sky models for the World Avoided and World Expected scenarios.</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="41598_2019_48625_Fig5_HTML" id="d29e1497" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p id="Par42" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The “hump” in the World Expected data noted previously for the summer data (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig4">4</a>), which peaks in the early part of the 21
  <span class="sup">st</span> century, is also present in the spring data (Fig. 
  <a rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig" href="#Fig5">5</a>). However, in the spring period, there is also a hint of this in the measured and calculated data for the two Antarctic sites and perhaps also at Summit. Data from Barrow show more variability, as one would expect from an Arctic coastal site that is affected by changes in albedo from snow and sea ice.
 </p>
</sec>
