<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract class="abstract">
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Background</title>
  <p class="p">The medicinal plants of 
   <italic class="italic">Radix et Rhizoma Nardostachyos</italic> include 
   <italic class="italic">Nardostachys jatamansi</italic> and 
   <italic class="italic">N. chinensis</italic>. Traditionally, the two plants have been used to treat many diseases. Because of their special aroma, they are also commonly used in the food and cosmetics industry. Recently, 
   <italic class="italic">N. jatamansi</italic> and 
   <italic class="italic">N. chinensis</italic> have been overexploited due to their economic importance, resulting in a sharp decline in their wild resources. Predicting potential distributions of the genus 
   <italic class="italic">Nardostachys</italic> under different climate scenarios and understanding its preferred habitat are of great significance for their conservation, artificial cultivation, and assessment of their value.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Methods</title>
  <p class="p">The Maxent model was used to predict the potential geographical distributions of the genus 
   <italic class="italic">Nardostachys</italic> under current and future climatic conditions based on two representative concentration pathways (RCP2.6 and RCP8.5) for the 2050s and 2070s. These data were used to study the effects of climate variables.
  </p>
 </sec>
 <sec class="sec">
  <title class="title">Results</title>
  <p class="p">The results show that the potential distribution of the two species will increase, thus more suitable habitats will be present in China. The suitable habitat for 
   <italic class="italic">N. chinensis</italic> presents a relatively stable growth compared to 
   <italic class="italic">N. jatamansi</italic>. In addition, precipitation plays a crucial role in modeling the effects of climate change on the genus 
   <italic class="italic">Nardostachys</italic>. This study provides theoretical guidance for the cultivation of 
   <italic class="italic">N. chinensis</italic>.
  </p>
 </sec>
</abstract>
