<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="Sec3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Study location and health outcomes</div>
 <p id="Par24" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">This study was conducted in Seoul (37.34°N, 126.59°E), which is the capital and largest metropolis of South Korea with a population of approximately 10 million [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28" href="#CR28">28</a>]. Seoul spans a land area of 605.25 km
  <span class="sup">2</span>, which is only 0.6% of the total area of South Korea, but 1/5 of the total population of South Korea live in Seoul (16,492 person/km
  <span class="sup">2</span>). Seoul has a temperate climate with distinct seasons and a wide range of temperatures across the year.
 </p>
 <p id="Par25" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We utilized data on ED visits recorded by the National Emergency Medical Center (NEMC). The NEMC is a government-funded national ED control agency, and one of its roles is to collect data on ED visits to improve the quality of emergency medical service and health care. The collected data included patient’s information such as sex, age, type of insurance, level of consciousness, vital signs, means of transportation, emergency operative procedures, time variables (visit, discharge, and admission), critical care requirement, disposition status after the ED encounter, duration of hospitalization, and final outcomes (information regarding discharge, transfer, and death) [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>]. These data are transferred electronically from the hospitals to the NEMC via a National Emergency Department Information System (NEDIS). The agency maintains an accurate assessment system and annually reports the results to the Ministry of Health and Welfare [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29" href="#CR29">29</a>]. The NEDIS database has been widely used by broad range of epidemiological researchers due to its reliability [
  <a ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30" href="#CR30">30</a>]. ED visit data were obtained from the NEDIS of the NEMC between January 1, 2010 and December 31, 2014 for this study. ED visit data were coded and classified according to the discharge diagnosis using the International Classification of Disease 10th Revision (ICD-10). Patients with ICD-10 code N17 based on the primary and secondary disease codes were considered to have AKI (Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>: Table S2). Because the data were based on ED visit incidence, the onset was regarded as acute even in case of CKD, although it could be regarded as an acute exacerbation of CKD. In this sense, we examined acute renal illness as a whole. In addition, we stratified the patients with both CKD (ICD-10 code N18) and AKI (ICD-10 code N17) in the sensitivity analysis due to the possible discrepancies in the pathophysiological mechanisms of AKI with pre-existing CKD (Additional file 
  <a rid="MOESM1" ref-type="media" href="#MOESM1">1</a>: Figure S1). Patients were also stratified by sex (male and female), age (&lt; 65 years and ≥ 65 years), and season (warm and cool) when they visited the ED. We also analyzed the comorbidities for AKI, namely, hypertension and diabetes.
 </p>
</sec>
