<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s4" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">4.</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Discussion</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We found that larval abundances of the majority of targeted rockfishes increased throughout southern California between 1998 and 2013. The rates of increase, however, were much higher within than outside of the CCAs for most of the targeted but none of the untargeted species (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS170639F5" href="#RSOS170639F5">figure 5</a>; electronic supplementary material, table S4). This indicates that the presence of the CCAs is facilitating the recovery of rockfish species that were historically targeted by fishers.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although it is recognized that augmenting reproductive output is crucially important for MPA success [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C13" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C13">13</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS170639C41" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C41">41</a>], to our knowledge this is the first demonstration that an MPA affected larval production at such large spatial and temporal scales. A handful of studies, however, measured reproductive output in association with MPAs at smaller scales. A study in and around a small (0.9 km
  <span class="sup">2</span>) MPA in the NW Mediterranean in 2003 found high species richness and high abundance of larvae from targeted species in the MPA and suggested that larval export could seed the surrounding fished areas [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C42" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C42">42</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS170639C43" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C43">43</a>]. Another study in the Mediterranean in 2004 also found that commercially targeted fishes were spawning at relatively high rates within an MPA and that the resulting high abundance of larvae were being exported to outside, fished locations [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C44" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C44">44</a>]. Similarly, larval abundance of commercially harvested queen conch, 
  <span class="italic">Strombus gigas</span>, were an order of magnitude higher within than outside of a fished area in the Bahamas and probably seeded fished areas north of the MPA [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C45" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C45">45</a>]. In addition, studies from South Africa [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C46" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C46">46</a>], Spain [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C47" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C47">47</a>] and New Zealand [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C48" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C48">48</a>] indirectly estimated larval production based on female biomass and concluded that fecundity was higher within than outside of MPAs. Our results, in conjunction with these studies, suggest that MPAs often have higher rates of larval output than surrounding regions, with larval movement allowing for recovery of fish populations beyond the boundaries of an MPA.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">While larval rockfish abundances (and larval fish abundances in general) can be driven by multiple factors, it is likely that increased biomass of reproductively active females and favourable environmental conditions contributed to the larval abundance dynamics observed in our study. We found that larval abundances of the majority of both targeted and non-targeted rockfishes increased throughout southern California between 1998 and 2013. Increasing adult rockfish abundances were also documented in stock assessments on 
  <span class="italic">S. levis</span> in the SCB and 
  <span class="italic">S. paucispinis</span> along the western US coast [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C27" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C27">27</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS170639C28" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C28">28</a>]. These trends were probably influenced by exceptionally high recruitment for most species in 1999 when there was a strong La Niña with cold and productive waters [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C49" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C49">49</a>]. Submersible surveys [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C25" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C25">25</a>] also support the idea of high recruitment in 1999 as cowcod were 51–60 cm TL in 2012 which, based on von Bertalanffy growth curves [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C50" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C50">50</a>], places their birth date around 1999. Given that management limited fishing beginning in 2000, it is probable that a relatively large proportion of the 1999 cohort survived long enough to begin becoming reproductively active and contributed to larval production by 2004.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In addition to management actions that allowed more individuals to reach maturity, environmental conditions probably contributed to the proliferation of rockfish larvae. Rockfish spawning output is affected by the environment as female reproduction is reduced when food is scarce and adult energy reserves are low [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C19" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C19">19</a>]. Low spawning years typically occur during El Niños when water temperature is high and primary productivity is low [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C51" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C51">51</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS170639C52" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C52">52</a>]. Our logistic regression models support the idea that reproduction is higher when the water is cool as the presence of most species correlated negatively with temperature. Further, we found that the water was cooler than the 30-year average in most years between 1998 and 2013, and it has been speculated that 1999 marked the beginning of an oceanographic shift from warm conditions that characterized the region between 1977 and 1998 [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C53" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C53">53</a>]. Therefore, environmental conditions appeared to have been generally conducive for high larval production and recruitment throughout much of the study.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Whereas overfishing remains a global concern [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C54" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C54">54</a>], synergistic effects of management and favourable ocean conditions have been identified to augment the recovery of another long-lived, overfished species [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C55" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C55">55</a>]. Striped bass (
  <span class="italic">Morone saxatilis</span>) in the Chesapeake Bay, USA, were severely overfished throughout the 1970s and 1980s. In 1984 a strict fishing moratorium was implemented, and favourable environmental conditions produced strong recruitment in 1989, 1993 and 1996 [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C56" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C56">56</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS170639C57" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C57">57</a>]. By 2000, the stock was rebuilt to pre-exploitation levels [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C57" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C57">57</a>]. Similarly, SCUBA surveys within and outside of no-take MPAs around the Channel Islands in California demonstrated that targeted reef fishes such as cabezon (
  <span class="italic">Scorpaenichthys marmoratus</span>) and kelp rockfish (
  <span class="italic">Sebastes atrovirens</span>) increased both within and outside of reserves between 2003 and 2012 [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C17" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C17">17</a>]. It is possible that targeted rockfishes and other long-lived, targeted species throughout southern California have responded positively to management action and cool, productive ocean environments.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although this was the first study to examine rockfish dynamics in association with the CCAs, short-term studies also suggest that the CCAs benefit rockfish populations. A larval survey in 2005 using the same techniques as the current work but with finer-scale sampling showed that species richness and the abundance of targeted rockfishes was higher within than outside of the CCAs [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C26" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C26">26</a>]. Similarly, submersible surveys in 2012 encountered cowcod with greater frequency within than outside of the CCAs [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C25" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C25">25</a>]. In addition, abundances of recently hatched, but not older, larval bocaccio were concentrated around the relatively shallow banks within the eastern CCA [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C24" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C24">24</a>]. Although we did not detect an interaction between year and CCA for bocaccio, abundances were higher within than outside of paired CCA stations in all but two years. These studies and ours indicate that the CCAs were positioned in locations that are well suited to protect and facilitate the recovery of many rockfishes in southern California.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Relatively large Rockfish Conservation Areas (RCAs) have also been established along the western US coast, as well as further north in Canadian waters with the goal of facilitating recovery of overfished stocks. US RCAs north of southern California appear to be benefitting rockfishes in addition to other demersal species as both bottom trawl [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C58" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C58">58</a>] and hook and line surveys [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C59" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C59">59</a>] detected significant increases in abundances since the beginning of the millennium. However, studies in Canada obtained mixed results. Whereas surveys in the Strait of Georgia indicated that these RCAs positively impacted rockfishes [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C60" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C60">60</a>], a more comprehensive study suggested that Canadian RCAs have not facilitated recovery of demersal fish populations [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C61" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C61">61</a>]. Lack of compliance was a potential explanation for the Canadian MPA ineffectiveness as there was no difference in fishing activity before and after establishment in most of these RCAs [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C62" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C62">62</a>]. Indeed, a recent global survey found that many MPAs were inadequately managed and these performed almost three times worse than equitably governed MPAs [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C63" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C63">63</a>]. It is likely that differences in management efficacy explain performance variation between the US and Canadian RCAs.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Although larval abundances of several targeted rockfishes increased throughout the time-series, targeted larvae were far outnumbered by non-targeted species. Given that the ratio of abundances of a targeted (bocaccio) to non-targeted (shortbelly) species was significantly lower between 1976 and 2001 versus 1951 to 1975 [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C64" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C64">64</a>], that shortbelly were much more common than bocaccio in this study, and that cowcod larval abundances remained low, it seems that targeted rockfish populations have not returned to pre-exploitation levels even within the CCAs. It is possible that not enough time has elapsed for management effects to be fully manifested in some targeted species populations. Theoretical models indicate that it may take decades for targeted rockfish species to reach carrying capacity following MPA establishment because these species experienced high fishing pressure, undergo maturation at older ages, and have low rates of natural mortality [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C65" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C65">65</a>]. Empirical work in the Mediterranean also shows that large fishes that were heavily exploited can take multiple decades to reach equilibrium levels [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C66" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C66">66</a>]. Alternatively, the system could be in an alternative stable state, having transitioned from being dominated by larger targeted rockfish species to smaller, faster-growing, non-targeted species [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C67" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C67">67</a>]. If this is the case, the smaller species may be consuming young targeted species and hence directly impeding recovery. Further monitoring is needed to evaluate whether larval abundances of targeted rockfishes continue to increase relative to non-targeted species after 2013.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Increasing larval rockfish abundances in the CCAs hold the potential to positively affect rockfish populations at a regional scale through larval spillover [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C41" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C41">41</a>]. Recent work off the Great Barrier Reef, Australia, and Hawaii demonstrated through genetic parentage analysis that targeted species that were born within a MPA settled and recruited outside of MPAs in locations open to fishing [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C68" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C68">68</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS170639C69" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C69">69</a>]. Although this type of analysis is beyond the scope of our data, the next step is to use oceanographic models to more precisely estimate the origin and trajectories of the rockfish larvae in our study. Depending on the species, rockfishes spend 1–2 months as pelagic larvae and then up to a year as pelagic juveniles [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C19" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C19">19</a>]. As such, they have the potential to disperse beyond MPA boundaries. In the future we plan to age larvae by counting daily otolith rings and use regional oceanic modelling systems (ROMS) models [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C70" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C70">70</a>] to trace the path each larvae took to arrive at its location of capture and where it probably would have gone had it not been captured. This work should help better establish the degree to which the CCAs are providing a recruitment supplement to fished areas.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our research underscores the value of long-term marine monitoring programmes such as CalCOFI to fisheries management and conservation. Whereas the initial focus of CalCOFI was to determine why the Pacific sardine fishery collapsed in the early 1950s, it has evolved into a comprehensive ecosystem monitoring programme that tracks the dynamics of the physical ocean and hundreds of species of fishes and invertebrates [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C31" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C31">31</a>]. The fact that CalCOFI stations were placed systematically throughout southern California allowed us to quantify MPA effects with samples collected before and after and within and outside of the MPAs. This type of sampling design is rare in MPA studies but is necessary to unambiguously discern MPA effects [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C15" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C15">15</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS170639C71" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C71">71</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS170639C72" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C72">72</a>]. Our work emphasizes the need to maintain programmes such as CalCOFI to help understand how anthropogenic impacts and climate continue to interact and influence fisheries dynamics.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Our work strongly indicates that the CCAs have been effective in facilitating the recovery of multiple targeted rockfish species and supports the effectiveness of establishing and regularly monitoring long-term MPAs. Given that augmenting larval output is the primary mechanism by which MPAs can benefit fisheries, this study provides an example of how larval monitoring can be used to assess MPA efficacy.</p>
</sec>
