<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s1" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">1.</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Introduction</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Negative impacts of fishing on populations and ecosystems have been known for decades [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C1" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C1">1</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS170639C2" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C2">2</a>]. The problem continues to this day, as significant depletions and declining catch-per-unit-effort (CPUE) were found to be a recurring trend worldwide [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C3" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C3">3</a>]. Further, predatory fish biomass is estimated to have declined substantially across the globe from 1880 to 2007, and the rate of decline of top predators is still accelerating while prey abundances are increasing, probably due to predator-release effects [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C4" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C4">4</a>]. Determining how to alleviate overfishing, therefore, is one of the most important issues for both fisheries science and management.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Marine protected areas (MPAs) are ecological refuges that hold the potential to assuage the effects of overfishing, especially for relatively sedentary species, and have been implemented globally over the past two decades [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C5" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C5">5</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS170639C6" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C6">6</a>]. Although it has been shown worldwide that animal abundance, size and species richness often increases within MPA bounds [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C5" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C5">5</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS170639C7" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C7">7</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS170639C8" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C8">8</a>], MPA effects must transcend the local MPA area to benefit fisheries [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C9" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C9">9</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS170639C10" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C10">10</a>]. Movement of adults beyond MPAs (i.e. spillover) is one mechanism by which MPAs can augment fisheries [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C11" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C11">11</a>], but this effect seems to mostly be limited to areas adjacent to MPA boundaries [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C12" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C12">12</a>]. The main way that MPAs can improve fisheries at a large scale is by increasing larval production; larvae can then be transported from the MPA and provide a ‘recruitment subsidy’ [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C13" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C13">13</a>] to surrounding fished regions [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C14" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C14">14</a>]. Despite the importance of larval production to MPA efficacy we are not aware of research that has quantitatively assessed the effects of an MPA on long-term reproductive output. In this study we evaluate rockfish (
  <span class="italic">Sebastes</span> spp.) larval production throughout southern California at both regional and MPA scales.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">One difficulty in evaluating MPA effects has been a lack of robust sampling designs [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C15" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C15">15</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS170639C16" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C16">16</a>]. MPA impacts may be masked or misinterpreted if, for example, samples are collected only within MPA bounds without outside control locations. Furthermore, inside and outside locations should be paired such that habitat conditions are similar inside and outside of MPAs [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C5" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C5">5</a>]. An ideal set-up will monitor both before and after MPA establishment to determine if sample (e.g. fish abundances) trajectories diverge inside and outside following placement of MPAs [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C15" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C15">15</a>]. Finally, data should be collected on species that are and are not targeted by fishing to assess if MPAs are affecting population dynamics of protected species [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C17" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C17">17</a>]. We use a before--after, control-impact paired series design [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C18" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C18">18</a>] to quantify MPA effects on larval abundances of 15 rockfish species that were and were not historically targeted by fishing.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Rockfishes (
  <span class="italic">Sebastes</span> spp.), are a speciose (102 described species as of 2002 [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C19" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C19">19</a>]) group of demersal fishes found mostly (96 species [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C19" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C19">19</a>]) along the west coast of North America and the Gulf of California. Whereas some species are relatively small and short-lived forage fish, others grow to large sizes (more than 90 cm), live for many decades (more than 150 years), and are apex predators [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C19" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C19">19</a>]. Larger rockfish species have been targeted by fisheries since at least the mid-nineteenth century, and technological developments subsequent to the 1940s, and in the 1970s in particular, led to severe population declines due to overfishing by the late 1990s [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C19" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C19">19</a>]. A survey of commercial passenger fishing vessels in the Southern California Bight (SCB) region from 1980 to 1996 revealed drastic declines in CPUE and mean total length of multiple rockfish species such as bocaccio (
  <span class="italic">S. paucispinis</span>), blue (
  <span class="italic">S. mystinus</span>), olive (
  <span class="italic">S. serranoides</span>), chilipepper (
  <span class="italic">S. goodei</span>), swordspine (
  <span class="italic">S. ensifer</span>), yellowtail (
  <span class="italic">S. flavidus</span>) and vermilion rockfishes (
  <span class="italic">S. miniatus</span>) [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C20" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C20">20</a>]. Fishery-independent surveys of larval fishes from 1977 to 1998 also documented declines in abundances of bocaccio and cowcod (
  <span class="italic">S. levis</span>) that were attributed to changing environmental conditions (a shift from cool to warm climate regime in the late 1970s) and fishery exploitation [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C21" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C21">21</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">In response to the decline in populations of rockfishes in southern California, (particularly cowcod, which was formally declared overfished in 1999 [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C22" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C22">22</a>]), the Pacific Fishery Management Council established two Cowcod Conservation Areas (CCAs) in 2001. The CCAs comprise a western and eastern area in the SCB (encompassing 10 878 km
  <span class="sup">2</span> and 260 km
  <span class="sup">2</span>, respectively; 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS170639F1" href="#RSOS170639F1">figure 1</a>) where cowcod were historically caught at high rates [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C22" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C22">22</a>]. Bottom-fishing deeper than 36 m is prohibited within the CCAs as larger, targeted rockfishes typically reside below this depth. These areas are several times larger than most marine MPAs that have been comprehensively studied thus far (but see [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C23" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C23">23</a>]) and are the largest rockfish conservation areas in the world. 
  <div id="RSOS170639F1" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 1.</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Location of stations. Colours designate stations with similar environmental conditions. These stations were used to determine whether rates of change in larval abundance differed inside and outside of the Cowcod Conservation Areas. Boundaries of the fine-scale map are shown in yellow on the large-scale inset map. </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="rsos170639-g1" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Previous research suggests that the CCAs are benefitting targeted rockfishes [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C24" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C24">24</a>–
  <a rid="RSOS170639C26" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C26">26</a>]. However, there have been no studies assessing how the CCAs have impacted rockfishes through time. Both stock assessments [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C27" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C27">27</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS170639C28" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C28">28</a>] and ecological studies [
  <a rid="RSOS170639C29" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C29">29</a>,
  <a rid="RSOS170639C30" ref-type="bibr" href="#RSOS170639C30">30</a>] conducted in and around the CCAs noted that the lack of time-series data hinders our capacity to understand whether the CCAs have influenced the rebuilding of rockfish stocks. We analyse a unique fishery-independent time series of rockfish larvae collected annually from 1998 to 2013 within and outside of the MPAs, before and after MPA establishment. The dataset includes species that are both targeted and untargeted by fishers, as well as oceanographic and habitat conditions at systematically sampled locations. We are thus able to evaluate MPA effects while controlling for oceanographic dynamics and fishing effort. We ask three primary questions: (i) Has there been a systemic change in rockfish production during the 16-year study period throughout southern California? (ii) Does environmental variability explain changes in larval abundances? (iii) Are population trajectories different within versus outside of the CCAs when controlling for environmental effects?
 </p>
</sec>
