<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s3b" class="sec">
 <span class="label" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">3.2.</span>
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Temporal trends</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Six of the eight (excluding cowcod which were quite rare) most abundant targeted species (copper, widow, blue, speckled, bocaccio and olive) showed significant increases in their mean abundances across the entire region over time (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS170639F2" href="#RSOS170639F2">figure 2</a>; electronic supplementary material, table S2). Interestingly, although cowcod abundances were below the threshold for formal analysis, this species did significantly increase during the study (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS170639F2" href="#RSOS170639F2">figure 2</a>). Four of the seven (squarespot, whitespeckled and pygmy) most abundant non-targeted species significantly or nearly significantly (stripetail) increased during the study (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="RSOS170639F3" href="#RSOS170639F3">figure 3</a>; electronic supplementary material, table S2). 
  <div id="RSOS170639F2" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 2.</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Change in mean larval abundances through time for species targeted by fishing. Red line (best linear fit) and shading (95% confidence interval) are shown for species where there was a significant relationship between mean abundance and year. </p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="rsos170639-g2" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
  <div id="RSOS170639F3" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig">
   <span class="label">Figure 3.</span>
   <div class="caption">
    <p>Change in mean larval abundances through time for species not targeted by fishing. Red line (best linear fit) and shading (95% confidence interval) are shown for species where there was a significant relationship between mean abundance and year.</p>
   </div>
   <div xlink:href="rsos170639-g3" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
  </div>
 </p>
</sec>
