<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<abstract class="abstract">
 <p class="p">Pine wilt disease (PWD) constitutes a serious threat to pine forests. Since development depends on temperature and drought, there is a concern that future climate change could lead to the spread of PWD infections. We evaluated the risk of PWD in 21 susceptible 
  <italic class="italic">Pinus</italic> species on a global scale. The MB index, which represents the sum of the difference between the mean monthly temperature and 15 when the mean monthly temperatures exceeds 15°C, was used to determine current and future regions vulnerable to PWD (MB ≥ 22). For future climate conditions, we compared the difference in PWD risks among four different representative concentration pathways (RCPs 2.6, 4.5, 6.0, and 8.5) and two time periods (2050s and 2070s). We also evaluated the impact of climate change on habitat suitability for each 
  <italic class="italic">Pinus</italic> species using species distribution models. The findings were then integrated and the potential risk of PWD spread under climate change was discussed. Within the natural 
  <italic class="italic">Pinus</italic> distribution area, southern parts of North America, Europe, and Asia were categorized as vulnerable regions (MB ≥ 22; 16% of the total 
  <italic class="italic">Pinus</italic> distribution area). Representative provinces in which PWD has been reported at least once overlapped with the vulnerable regions. All RCP scenarios showed expansion of vulnerable regions in northern parts of Europe, Asia, and North America under future climate conditions. By the 2070s, under RCP 8.5, an estimated increase in the area of vulnerable regions to approximately 50% of the total 
  <italic class="italic">Pinus</italic> distribution area was revealed. In addition, the habitat conditions of a large portion of the 
  <italic class="italic">Pinus</italic> distribution areas in Europe and Asia were deemed unsuitable by the 2070s under RCP 8.5. Approximately 40% of these regions overlapped with regions deemed vulnerable to PWD, suggesting that 
  <italic class="italic">Pinus</italic> forests in these areas are at risk of serious damage due to habitat shifts and spread of PWD.
 </p>
</abstract>
