<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1 20151215//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-archivearticle1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.1?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 1?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Sci Adv</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Sci Adv</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">SciAdv</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">advances</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Science Advances</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2375-2548</issn><publisher><publisher-name>American Association for the Advancement of Science</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">6170032</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">aao4719</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/sciadv.aao4719</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="article-type"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Articles</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="legacy-article-type"><subject>SciAdv r-articles</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="field"><subject>Oceanography</subject><subject>Physical Sciences</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="overline"><subject>Atmospheric Science</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Opening the window to the Southern Ocean: The role of jet dynamics</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><contrib-id contrib-id-type="orcid" authenticated="true">http://orcid.org/0000-0002-2038-7922</contrib-id><name><surname>Klocker</surname><given-names>Andreas</given-names></name><xref ref-type="award" rid="award341171"/><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"><sup>2</sup></xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff3"><sup>3</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label>1</label>Institute for Marine and Antarctic Studies, University of Tasmania, Hobart, Tasmania, Australia.</aff><aff id="aff2"><label>2</label>Australian Research Council Centre of Excellence for Climate System Science, University of Tasmania, Hobart, Tasmania, Australia.</aff><aff id="aff3"><label>3</label>Antarctic Climate and Ecosystems Cooperative Research Centre, University of Tasmania, Hobart, Tasmania, Australia.</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Corresponding author. Email: <email xlink:href="andreas.klocker@utas.edu.au">andreas.klocker@utas.edu.au</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><month>10</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>03</day><month>10</month><year>2018</year></pub-date><volume>4</volume><issue>10</issue><elocation-id>eaao4719</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>24</day><month>7</month><year>2017</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>02</day><month>8</month><year>2018</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>Copyright &#x000a9; 2018 The Authors, some rights reserved; exclusive licensee American Association for the Advancement of Science. No claim to original U.S. Government Works. Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution NonCommercial License 4.0 (CC BY-NC).</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2018</copyright-year><copyright-holder>The Authors</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" id="p-2"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial license</ext-link>, which permits use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, so long as the resultant use is <bold>not</bold> for commercial advantage and provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract abstract-type="teaser"><p>Jet dynamics play a crucial role in Southern Ocean ventilation.</p></abstract><abstract><p>The surface waters of the Southern Ocean act as a control valve through which climatically important tracers such as heat, freshwater, and CO<sub>2</sub> are transferred between the atmosphere and the ocean. The process that transports these tracers through the surface mixed layer into the ocean interior is known as ocean ventilation. Changes in ocean ventilation are thought to be important for both rapid transitions of the ocean&#x02019;s global overturning circulation during the last deglaciation and the uptake and storage of excess heat and CO<sub>2</sub> as a consequence of anthropogenic climate change. I show how the interaction between Southern Ocean jets, topographic features, and ocean stratification can lead to rapid changes in Southern Ocean ventilation as a function of wind stress. For increasing winds, this interaction leads from a state in which tracers are confined to the surface mixed layer to a state in which tracers fill the ocean interior. For sufficiently high winds, the jet dynamics abruptly change, allowing the tracer to ventilate a water mass known as Antarctic Intermediate Water in the mid-depth Southern Ocean. Abrupt changes in Antarctic Intermediate Water ventilation have played a major role in rapid climate transitions in Earth&#x02019;s past, and combined with the results presented here, this would suggest that jet dynamics could play a prominent role in contributing to, or even triggering, rapid transitions of the global climate system.</p></abstract><funding-group><award-group id="award341171"><funding-source><institution-wrap><institution-id institution-id-type="doi">http://dx.doi.org/10.13039/501100000923</institution-id><institution>Australian Research Council</institution></institution-wrap></funding-source><award-id>DE140100076</award-id></award-group></funding-group><custom-meta-group><custom-meta><meta-name>Copyeditor</meta-name><meta-value>Sef Rio</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="introduction" disp-level="1"><title>INTRODUCTION</title><p>The ocean is the global climate system&#x02019;s second largest reservoir of heat and carbon dioxide (CO<sub>2</sub>) behind the solid Earth. Because of the correlation between global temperature and atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations over glacial cycles, the time scales involved, and the ocean&#x02019;s capability to store large amounts of CO<sub>2</sub>, it is thought that the ocean is a major player behind these changes (<xref rid="R1" ref-type="bibr"><italic>1</italic></xref>). Most of the ocean below a depth of 1 km interacts with the atmosphere through less than 4% of the ocean&#x02019;s surface area, mostly at high latitudes (<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr"><italic>2</italic></xref>). These high-latitude areas, particularly the Southern Ocean, are therefore crucial in controlling the exchange of CO<sub>2</sub> between the atmosphere and the deep ocean. Numerous proxy data obtained from sediment cores, used to reconstruct past patterns of ocean circulation, confirm the important role of the Southern Ocean (<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr"><italic>3</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr"><italic>4</italic></xref>). In particular, the ventilation of a water mass known as Antarctic Intermediate Water (AAIW) is of global significance. AAIW is formed by fresh Antarctic Surface Waters (AASW) ventilating the mid-depth Southern Ocean (<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr"><italic>5</italic></xref>), leading to the redistribution of heat, freshwater, and nutrients throughout the global ocean (<xref rid="R6" ref-type="bibr"><italic>6</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R7" ref-type="bibr"><italic>7</italic></xref>). AAIW is a significant sink of anthropogenic CO<sub>2</sub> (<xref rid="R8" ref-type="bibr"><italic>8</italic></xref>) and is recognized as being pivotal in explaining rapid transitions observed in Earth&#x02019;s past climate (<xref rid="R9" ref-type="bibr"><italic>9</italic></xref>). Both observational (<xref rid="R10" ref-type="bibr"><italic>10</italic></xref>) and model studies (<xref rid="R11" ref-type="bibr"><italic>11</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R12" ref-type="bibr"><italic>12</italic></xref>) show a possible link between abrupt changes in the ventilation of AAIW and the collapse of North Atlantic Deep Water formation, pointing toward a crucial role of AAIW ventilation in contributing to, or even triggering, abrupt reorganizations of the global meridional overturning circulation (MOC).</p><p>Because of the rotation of Earth, persistent westerly winds over the Southern Ocean push surface waters to the north, leading to the steepening of isopycnals and subsequently the upwelling of carbon and nutrient-rich deep waters as part of the Southern Ocean MOC (<xref rid="R13" ref-type="bibr"><italic>13</italic></xref>). Once these deep waters reach the ocean surface, they are able to exchange properties with the atmosphere before they re-ventilate the ocean interior. The resulting carbon budget is a delicate balance between these ventilation pathways (<xref rid="R14" ref-type="bibr"><italic>14</italic></xref>). From a physical perspective, the balance between the outgassing of CO<sub>2</sub> from the upwelling of natural carbon-rich deep waters and the drawdown of atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> by the ventilation process determines whether the Southern Ocean acts as a sink or source of CO<sub>2</sub> to the atmosphere (<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr"><italic>15</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R16" ref-type="bibr"><italic>16</italic></xref>). If the biological perspective is taken into account, this balance is also responsible for the availability of nutrients at the ocean surface, with consequences for the export of carbon into the ocean interior due to the sinking of biological matter (<xref rid="R17" ref-type="bibr"><italic>17</italic></xref>). The net role of the Southern Ocean as a source or sink of CO<sub>2</sub> is therefore a combination of both physical and biological processes (<xref rid="R3" ref-type="bibr"><italic>3</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R4" ref-type="bibr"><italic>4</italic></xref>).</p><p>Fueled by observation-based evidence of rapid climate transitions in Earth&#x02019;s past, and the uncertainty of the ocean&#x02019;s heat and CO<sub>2</sub> uptake in future climates, substantial effort has gone into understanding how these processes are likely to change under varying wind forcing (<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr"><italic>15</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R18" ref-type="bibr"><italic>18</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R19" ref-type="bibr"><italic>19</italic></xref>), buoyancy forcing (<xref rid="R15" ref-type="bibr"><italic>15</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R20" ref-type="bibr"><italic>20</italic></xref>), and sea ice cover (<xref rid="R21" ref-type="bibr"><italic>21</italic></xref>). Most of this effort has focused on the wind-induced overturning by the Southern Ocean MOC. It has been shown that the upwelling of deep waters, although partially compensated by mesoscale eddies, increases continuously for an increase in wind stress (<xref rid="R22" ref-type="bibr"><italic>22</italic></xref>). With winds predicted to increase under anthropogenic forcing (<xref rid="R23" ref-type="bibr"><italic>23</italic></xref>), this would lead to enhanced outgassing of CO<sub>2</sub> in the future, opposing anthropogenic carbon uptake (<xref rid="R24" ref-type="bibr"><italic>24</italic></xref>), although these results remain controversial (<xref rid="R25" ref-type="bibr"><italic>25</italic></xref>). While substantial progress in understanding this upwelling process has been made, very little is known about the processes that lead to the re-ventilation of these water masses. This is particularly the case for the ventilation of AAIW, for which many processes have been suggested as possible candidates, such as convection driven by air-sea fluxes, Ekman transport, eddy and turbulent mixing, and mixing at the base of the mixed layer, but no conclusion has been reached (<xref rid="R26" ref-type="bibr"><italic>26</italic></xref>).</p><p>This study sheds some light on this problem by using a high-resolution numerical model of the Indian sector of the Southern Ocean to elucidate on the processes relevant to Southern Ocean ventilation. Using the topographically steered jet north of the Kerguelen Plateau (KP) as an example, I show how changes in wind stress affect jet dynamics and their interaction with topographic features and stratification. The sensitivity of jet dynamics to wind stress leads to changes in Southern Ocean ventilation, which are an order of magnitude larger than would be expected from changes in the Southern Ocean MOC alone. Once the wind stress is increased beyond a certain threshold, the jet dynamics abruptly change, allowing for the ventilation of AAIW. Since the jet dynamics discussed here depend on small-scale turbulent processes, it will be a tremendous challenge to represent these jet dynamics, and their effect on Southern Ocean ventilation, in models used for simulations of past and future climates. Nevertheless, it is only once we understand these dynamics that we can confidently predict possible rapid transitions in a future climate.</p></sec><sec sec-type="results" disp-level="1"><title>RESULTS</title><sec disp-level="2"><title>Model simulations show rapid change in ocean ventilation</title><p>The time- and depth-mean circulation in an eddy-resolving ocean model (Materials and Methods) of the Indian sector of the Southern Ocean is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>. The prominent topographic features in this region are the KP and the SEIR, both of which develop strong jets along their northern boundaries due to the interaction of the Southern Ocean&#x02019;s background mean flow with topography. The model experiment shown represents &#x0201c;modern&#x0201d; conditions, with the wind and buoyancy forcing being annually and zonally averaged values from the year 2005. Six perturbation experiments were run in which the zonal component of the wind stress was varied, while all other forcing was kept constant (in the following, modern wind stress is denoted by &#x003c4;, and perturbation experiments range from 0.5*&#x003c4; to 2*&#x003c4;; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B</xref>). In each experiment, a passive tracer, intended to represent a chemical species, such as CO<sub>2</sub>, undergoing atmosphere-ocean exchange processes but ignoring biological and chemical interaction, is introduced homogeneously at the ocean surface for 10 years after model equilibration. This passive tracer is restored with a 2-hour time scale, approximating an infinite tracer reservoir in the surface mixed layer (SML). Results below are shown after 5 years of tracer ventilation since, after this time, the limited domain of this model configuration affects results (Materials and Methods).</p><fig id="F1" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><title>Numerical simulation of the Southern Ocean ventilation.</title><p>(<bold>A</bold>) Time- and depth-mean zonal velocities for the modern wind stress (color) and ocean depth (contours). Both the KP and the South East Indian Ridge (SEIR) are marked. Colored lines show locations of vertical transects shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Figs. 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>. (<bold>B</bold>) Wind stress (N m<sup>&#x02212;2</sup>) of the six perturbation experiments (the red line represents modern conditions). Only the westerly components of the wind stress are changed. (<bold>C</bold>) Changes in Southern Ocean ventilation as a function of changes in wind stress, where zero marks the annual and zonal average winds of 2005. The blue line shows changes in Southern Ocean overturning, the red line shows changes in tracer uptake integrated between water depths of 500 and 1500 m, and the black line shows the 1:1 line, that is, where wind changes equal ventilation changes. Circular markers show the different perturbation experiments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="aao4719-F1"/></fig><p>The first striking result of these model experiments is evident from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1C</xref>, which shows changes of the maximum of the Southern Ocean MOC (blue line; Materials and Methods), and tracer concentrations in the ocean interior (integrated between depths of 500 and 1500 m) after 5 years (red line; Materials and Methods), as a function of changes in wind stress. The black line represents a 1:1 relationship between wind stress and ventilation changes. This figure shows that Southern Ocean ventilation, assuming an infinite tracer reservoir in the SML, is much more sensitive to changes in wind stress than the maximum in Southern Ocean MOC, which is the metric currently used to understand the role of Southern Ocean ventilation in past and future climates. For the perturbation experiments with a wind stress below modern values, changes in tracer ventilation are about twice as large as changes in the maximum of the Southern Ocean MOC, whereas for the perturbation experiments with a wind stress above modern values, changes in tracer ventilation are about one order of magnitude larger than changes in the maximum of the Southern Ocean MOC. As will be shown below, both the high sensitivity of Southern Ocean ventilation to wind stress and the change of behavior at modern wind stress values are closely related to changes in jet dynamics and their interaction with topography and stratification.</p><p>The second striking result is evident from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref>, which shows the geographic location at which the tracer ventilates the ocean interior. Snapshots of tracer concentrations at a depth of 200 m are shown for two perturbation experiments&#x02014;for a wind stress of &#x003c4;, 8 months after the tracer is introduced (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref>), and for a wind stress of 2*&#x003c4;, 4 months after the tracer is first introduced (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B</xref>). These snapshots focus on the time when the tracer first ventilates the ocean interior and before the tracer is advected beyond the ventilation region. Note that because of the differences in ventilation mechanism, both times of snapshots and color scales in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2</xref> (A and B) are different. These examples highlight the two different states of tracer ventilation, closely linked to two different dynamical states of the jet north of the KP (referred to as the Kerguelen jet in the following). For the perturbation experiment with a wind stress of &#x003c4; (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2A</xref>), tracer ventilation predominantly occurs in filaments downstream of the Kerguelen jet in a region commonly referred to as oceanic storm track, with storm tracks being regions of anomalously high eddy kinetic energy (EKE) downstream of topographic features caused by the instability of jets (<xref rid="R27" ref-type="bibr"><italic>27</italic></xref>). On the other hand, for the perturbation experiment with a wind stress of 2*&#x003c4; (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Fig. 2B</xref>), tracer ventilation occurs along the Kerguelen jet. Both states of tracer ventilation have very different consequences for Southern Ocean ventilation.</p><fig id="F2" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><title>Tracer ventilation as a function of jet dynamics.</title><p>Tracer concentration at a depth of 200 m for a wind stress of (<bold>A</bold>) &#x003c4;, 8 months after the tracer is first introduced, and a wind stress of (<bold>B</bold>) 2*&#x003c4;, 4 months after the tracer is introduced. Black contours show time-mean velocities at 200 m to highlight the position of the Kerguelen jet. Note the different color scales.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="aao4719-F2"/></fig><p>The role of the Kerguelen jet in these two states of tracer ventilation becomes even more evident by examining the time-mean tracer forcing at the ocean surface for the perturbation experiments with a wind stress of &#x003c4; (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3A</xref>) and 2*&#x003c4; (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3B</xref>) and the time-mean vertical tracer advection at a depth of 200 m, where the depth is chosen to visualize the tracer being advected across the base of the SML, for the same perturbation experiments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">Fig. 3</xref>, C and D, respectively). The perturbation experiment with a wind stress of 2*&#x003c4; shows enhanced values for the tracer forcing at the ocean surface, which is consistent with an increased tracer ventilation by the Kerguelen jet, reducing the tracer concentration at the ocean surface and subsequently increasing the tracer forcing that restores the tracer concentration at the ocean surface (Materials and Methods). The enhanced values of tracer forcing at the northern boundary are due to currents coming out of the northern sponge layer where the tracer concentration is restored to zero and hence are a numerical artifact. The time-mean vertical tracer advection in the perturbation experiment for a wind stress of 2*&#x003c4; also shows much larger values than the perturbation experiment for a wind stress of &#x003c4;, with changes again occurring along the core of the Kerguelen jet. From this figure, it is also evident that the dominant length scales of upward and downward advection, of the order of 100 km, point toward tracer ventilation being a consequence of the Kerguelen jet interacting with standing mesoscale features. Note though that this long-term mean will remove the footprint of small-scale eddies simply due to the chaotic and short-lived nature of these eddies. These small-scale eddies are crucial for the upper ocean vertical transport and are mostly due to mixed layer instabilities and frontogenesis that can be enhanced in an energetic mesoscale eddy strain field relevant to jets. In the following, the perturbation experiments with wind stresses of 0.5*&#x003c4;, &#x003c4;, and 2*&#x003c4; will be used to further highlight the differences in tracer ventilation and jet dynamics, with the focus being on the Kerguelen jet.</p><fig id="F3" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><title>Location of tracer ventilation.</title><p>Time-mean tracer forcing at the ocean surface for the perturbation experiment with a wind stress of (<bold>A</bold>) &#x003c4; and a wind stress of (<bold>B</bold>) 2*&#x003c4;. Time-mean vertical tracer advection at a depth 200 m for the perturbation experiment with a wind stress of (<bold>C</bold>) &#x003c4; and a wind stress of (<bold>D</bold>) 2*&#x003c4;.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="aao4719-F3"/></fig><p>With tracer concentrations being visualized as colored dye on a log<sub>10</sub> scale, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref> shows the extent to which the passive tracer has ventilated the ocean interior after 5 years. Vertical sections of tracer concentrations are shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref> (A to C) for the cyan transect in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref> and in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref> (D to F) for the purple transect in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>. The cyan transect is chosen to be north of the ventilation region, and the purple transect is chosen to be downstream of the ventilation region, both to highlight tracer concentrations in the ocean interior rather than the ventilation region. Black contours in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref> (A to F) represent salinity, with AAIW being defined by the salinity minimum evident between depths of approximately 500 and 1500 m. For a wind stress of 0.5*&#x003c4;, the tracer is confined to the SML and hence there is no ventilation of the ocean interior (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>, A and D). For a wind stress of &#x003c4;, the tracer is ventilated into the top ~500 m of the water column, with tracer concentrations decreasing monotonically with depth (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>, B and E). For a wind stress of 2*&#x003c4;, the tracer is ventilated across the base of the SML into AAIW, with a vertical separation between elevated tracer concentrations in the SML and AAIW (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>, C and F). These results would suggest that tracer ventilation in storm track leads to deep SMLs, while tracer ventilation along the jet leads to tracer ventilation across the base of the SML into AAIW.</p><fig id="F4" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><title>Tracer ventilation as a function of wind forcing.</title><p>Vertical section along a latitude of 43&#x000b0;S (cyan transect in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>) showing tracer concentration (color; on a log<sub>10</sub> scale) and salinity (psu, practical salinity unit) (contours) for the perturbation experiment with wind stresses of (<bold>A</bold>) 0.5*&#x003c4;, (<bold>B</bold>) &#x003c4;, and (<bold>C</bold>) 2*&#x003c4;. Vertical section along a longitude of 129&#x000b0;E (magenta transect in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>) showing tracer concentration (color; on a log<sub>10</sub> scale) and salinity (contours) for the perturbation experiment with wind stresses of (<bold>D</bold>) 0.5*&#x003c4;, (<bold>E</bold>) &#x003c4;, and (<bold>F</bold>) 2*&#x003c4;.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="aao4719-F4"/></fig></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Tracer ventilation intimately linked to jet dynamics</title><p>The different states of tracer ventilation are intimately linked to changes in jet dynamics, best explained using time-mean hydrographic sections across the Kerguelen jet, as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref> for the green transect in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref>. The time-mean ocean properties in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref> are zonal velocity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>, A to C), stratification (shown as buoyancy frequency; <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>, D to F), and salinity (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>, G to I) for wind stresses of 0.5*&#x003c4; (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>, A, D, and G), &#x003c4; (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>, B, E, and H), and 2*&#x003c4; (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>, C, F, and I). The black feature in these panels is the northern edge of the KP, white contours mark isopycnal surfaces, and the approximate location of the bottom of the SML is shown by the green line. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figure 5</xref> (J to L) shows a horizontal section of stratification at a depth of 120 m (which is approximately the depth of the SML) for the same perturbation experiments. The red patch in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5H</xref> highlights a region of convection. Additional insight is gained from the transient behavior of the jet, shown on a Hovm&#x000f6;ller diagram of zonal velocities at the ocean surface for wind stresses of 0.5*&#x003c4; (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5M</xref>), &#x003c4; (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5N</xref>), and 2*&#x003c4; (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5O</xref>). The abrupt change in jet dynamics occurs at a critical point between wind stresses of &#x003c4; and 2*&#x003c4; (at approximately a wind stress of 1.25*&#x003c4;, which will become evident below). Beyond the critical point, the Kerguelen jet suddenly accelerates, westward jets appear at its flanks (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>, A, D, and G), and, as seen in the Hovm&#x000f6;ller diagram, the Kerguelen jet becomes more steady, locked in latitude, and smaller length scales appear (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>, M to O). While an increase in wind stress from 0.5*&#x003c4; to &#x003c4; leads to a decrease in stratification across the base of the SML across the Kerguelen jet (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>, B and E), it is only when the wind stress increases to 2*&#x003c4; that convection across the base of the SML occurs, resulting in the ventilation of fresh (that is, low salinity) surface waters, known as AASW, into AAIW (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>, C, F, and I), consistent with the ventilation of the passive tracer shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>.</p><fig id="F5" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><title>Hydrographic sections across the Kerguelen jet.</title><p>Colors show vertical sections along the green transect in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1A</xref> of time-mean (<bold>A</bold>, <bold>D</bold>, and <bold>G</bold>) zonal velocity (meters per second), (<bold>B</bold>, <bold>E</bold>, and <bold>H</bold>) buoyancy frequency (per second), and (<bold>C</bold>, <bold>F</bold>, and <bold>I</bold>) salinity (psu), for the perturbation experiments with wind stresses of (A to C) 0.5*&#x003c4;, (D to F) &#x003c4;, and (G to I) 2*&#x003c4;. White contours are time-mean isopycnals, and the green line is the time-mean mixed layer depth. The black feature is the northern slope of the KP. The red patch in (H) marks a region of time-mean convection. Horizontal sections of time-mean buoyancy frequency (per second) on a log<sub>10</sub> scale at a depth of 120 m, chosen to represent the depth of the base of the SML, for the perturbation experiments with wind stresses of (<bold>J</bold>) 0.5*&#x003c4;, (<bold>K</bold>) &#x003c4;, and (<bold>L</bold>) 2*&#x003c4;. Hovm&#x000f6;ller diagrams of zonal surface velocities along the green transect in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1</xref> for (<bold>M</bold>) 0.5*&#x003c4;, (<bold>N</bold>) &#x003c4;, and (<bold>O</bold>) 2*&#x003c4;.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="aao4719-F5"/></fig><p>This change in jet dynamics&#x02014;ignoring their effect on ventilation for a moment&#x02014;can be understood in more detail from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>. Shown are time and zonal means, averaged between 66&#x000b0;E and 70&#x000b0;E, of vertical profiles of zonal velocities in the jet&#x02019;s core (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6A</xref>, solid lines) and its northern flank (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6A</xref>, dashed lines), depth-mean zonal velocities (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6B</xref>), depth-mean EKE (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6C</xref>), and the cross-jet potential vorticity gradient (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6D</xref>). The potential vorticity gradient is a metric that is closely associated with the stability properties of a jet. A zero crossing in the potential vorticity gradient is associated with the necessary condition for the instability of the jet. The potential vorticity gradient used here is defined as &#x003b2;* = &#x003b2; &#x02212; <italic>U</italic><sub><italic>yy</italic></sub> and hence includes a contribution from Earth&#x02019;s rotation (&#x003b2; <italic>= f</italic><sub><italic>y</italic></sub>, where <italic>f</italic> is the Coriolis parameter and <italic>y</italic> is latitude) and the meridional shear of the jet&#x02019;s depth-mean flow (<italic>U</italic><sub><italic>yy</italic></sub>), and is a proxy for the jet&#x02019;s barotropic stability properties (<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr"><italic>28</italic></xref>). In particular, the jet can become barotropically unstable when the stabilizing effect due to Earth&#x02019;s rotation is counteracted by the horizontal shear of the jet. Note that the topographic influence on the potential vorticity gradient is ignored here since it is not clear at which length scales topography affects jet dynamics.</p><fig id="F6" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><title>Dynamics of the Kerguelen jet.</title><p>Jet properties are time- and zonal-mean values calculated between 66&#x000b0;E and 70&#x000b0;E. (<bold>A</bold>) Solid lines represent vertical profiles of zonal velocities in the core [at 45&#x000b0;S; solid gray line in (B) to (D)] of the eastward jet. Dashed lines represent vertical profiles of zonal velocities at the northern flank [at 43&#x000b0;S; dashed gray line in (B) to (D)] of the jet. (<bold>B</bold>) Depth-mean zonal velocities across the jet. (<bold>C</bold>) Depth mean EKE across the jet. (<bold>D</bold>) Smoothed potential vorticity (PV) gradient &#x003b2;* = &#x003b2; &#x02212; <italic>U</italic><sub><italic>yy</italic></sub>, where &#x003b2; is the meridional gradient of the Coriolis force and <italic>U</italic><sub><italic>yy</italic></sub> is the meridional shear of the depth-mean zonal velocity. Colors represent the different wind perturbation experiments shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="aao4719-F6"/></fig><p>The change in jet dynamics shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs. 5</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref> can be interpreted as follows. For a wind stress of 0.5*&#x003c4;, the jet core has near-zero bottom velocities (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6A</xref>, blue line) and its potential vorticity gradient is positive everywhere across the jet (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6C</xref>, blue line). For this state, an increase in wind stress to &#x003c4; leads to an increase in the jet&#x02019;s vertical shear (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6A</xref>) and, consequently, an increase in its baroclinic instability with an associated increase in EKE (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6C</xref>). At the critical point, the potential vorticity gradient approaches zero at its southern flank (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6D</xref>), with a zero crossing of the potential vorticity gradient being the necessary condition for the barotropic instability of the jet (<xref rid="R29" ref-type="bibr"><italic>29</italic></xref>). Once the wind stress further increases, the jet abruptly reorganizes its structure to equilibrate its eddy instabilities through modification of its mean structure by eddy fluxes (<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr"><italic>30</italic></xref>). As a consequence, the eastward jet core significantly accelerates while its flanks develop two westward jets, leading to a large increase in the jet&#x02019;s lateral shear (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Figs. 5</xref>, G and L, and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>, A and B). This jet structure is now associated with a large positive potential vorticity gradient across the jet&#x02019;s core and negative potential vorticity gradients across both of its flanks (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6D</xref>). Beyond the critical point, a further increase in wind stress results in the acceleration of the jet core&#x02019;s depth-mean velocities and, subsequently, a further increase in the jet&#x02019;s lateral shear while keeping its vertical shear near constant (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">Fig. 6</xref>, A and B). At the critical point, the jet dynamics therefore abruptly change from that of a baroclinic jet, in which the jet&#x02019;s vertical shear increases as the jet is accelerated, to that of a barotropic jet, in which the jet&#x02019;s lateral shear increases as the jet is accelerated. This strong lateral shear is known to be able to suppress baroclinic instability, a process known as the barotropic governor (<xref rid="R31" ref-type="bibr"><italic>31</italic></xref>), which explains why this jet can sustain such steep isopycnals without becoming unstable. The effects of jet dynamics on baroclinic instability and, hence, EKE can be used to find the critical point at which jet dynamics abruptly change. From <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5C</xref>, it is apparent that EKE adjacent to the jet increases from a wind stress of 0.5*&#x003c4; to 1.25*&#x003c4;, reaches a maximum of 1.25*&#x003c4;, and then decreases with further increases in wind stress. This is particularly evident in the region where the shear between the eastward jet core and its westward jets at its flanks becomes largest due to the barotropic governor increasingly suppressing baroclinic instability. For the Kerguelen jet, the critical point occurs for a wind stress increase of 25%.</p><p>In the Southern Ocean, strong westerly winds prevail and hence blow into the direction of the jets, a scenario usually referred to as &#x0201c;down-front winds&#x0201d; (<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr"><italic>32</italic></xref>). These down-front winds lead to Ekman advection of buoyancy across the jet. Depending on the lateral gradients of buoyancy and momentum across the jet, the Ekman advection of buoyancy can lead to convection across the base of the SML (<xref rid="R32" ref-type="bibr"><italic>32</italic></xref>). As evident from vertical sections of stratification across the Kerguelen jet (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>, B, E, and H), increasing winds erode the stratification across the base of the SML across all perturbation experiments, but it is only beyond the critical point, where the jet changes from baroclinic to barotropic, that this reduction in stratification is sufficient to lead to convection across the base of the SML [<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref>, B, E, and H; note that the mixed layer depth in the jet (~400 m in the case of 2*&#x003c4;) is much deeper than the boundary layer parameterized by KPP (K-profile parameterization) for the same region (~100 m in the case of 2*&#x003c4;) and hence is not a numerical artifact due to the choice of this parameterization scheme (Materials and Methods)]. This convection allows the passive tracer (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref>, C and F) and AASW (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5I</xref>) to ventilate AAIW along the jet. As evident from <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">Fig. 5</xref> (J to L), which shows a horizontal section of stratification at the base of the mixed layer at a depth of 120 m, convection across the base of the SML is confined to the core of the jet, that is, regions where lateral gradients of buoyancy and momentum are largest. These results therefore point toward the possibility of the abrupt reorganization from a baroclinic to a barotropic jet and the associated increase in the lateral gradients of buoyancy and momentum, which is a prerequisite for the ventilation of AAIW along the jet.</p><p>The role of jet dynamics in Southern Ocean ventilation can be summarized as follows. Because of the interaction of the Southern Ocean&#x02019;s background mean flow with topography, strong jets appear adjacent to this topography, such as the Kerguelen jet discussed here. For the example of the Kerguelen jet, an increase in winds of up to 1.25*&#x003c4; leads to an increase in the jet&#x02019;s vertical shear, which is associated with an increase in EKE due to baroclinic instability in both the jet and the associated storm track. The consequence of this increase in storm track intensity is a change from no tracer ventilation (0.5*&#x003c4;) to the tracer being ventilated into a deep SML (0.75*&#x003c4; to 1.25*&#x003c4;). Once the wind stress increases beyond the critical point at 1.25*&#x003c4;, the jet abruptly changes its structure to a barotropic jet with westward jets at its flanks, increasing its lateral shear and hence suppressing baroclinic instability due to an effect known as the barotropic governor. Because of the emerging barotropic governor, a further increase in winds leads to a decrease in EKE and increasingly steep isopycnal surfaces. This abrupt increase in cross-jet gradients of buoyancy and momentum, combined with down-front winds, leads to convection across the base of the SML. This convection across the base of the mixed layer, combined with the steep isopycnal surfaces across the jet, leads to the ventilation of AAIW along the jet.</p><p>While the model experiments shown here resolve mesoscale turbulence with length scales of the order of 10 to 100 km and Rossby numbers of <italic>R</italic><sub>o</sub> = &#x003b6;<italic>/f</italic> &#x0003c;&#x0003c; 1 (where &#x003b6; <italic>= v</italic><sub><italic>x</italic></sub> &#x02212; <italic>u</italic><sub><italic>y</italic></sub> is the relative vorticity and <italic>f</italic> is the planetary vorticity), these model experiments barely resolve submesoscale turbulence with length scales of the order of 1 to 10 km and Rossby numbers of <italic>R</italic><sub>o</sub> = <italic>O</italic>(1). Nevertheless, it is the submesoscale turbulence, which is associated with strong vertical velocities, that is thought to dominate tracer ventilation (<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr"><italic>33</italic></xref>). An insight into how the dynamics presented here could affect submesoscale turbulence and hence tracer ventilation can be gained from snapshots of Rossby numbers for the different perturbation experiments (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7</xref>). For a wind stress of 0.5*&#x003c4;, the Rossby number <italic>R</italic><sub>o</sub> &#x0003c;&#x0003c; 1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7A</xref>), and no tracer ventilation occurs. For a wind stress of &#x003c4;, the Rossby number <italic>R</italic><sub>o</sub> increases predominantly in the storm track downstream of topography (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7B</xref>), consistent with tracer ventilation occurring in this region. For a wind stress of 2*&#x003c4;, the cross-jet gradients of buoyancy and momentum abruptly increase. This increase in cross-jet buoyancy gradient energizes submesoscale turbulence (<xref rid="R33" ref-type="bibr"><italic>33</italic></xref>), which is consistent with Rossby numbers abruptly increasing to <italic>R</italic><sub>o</sub> = <italic>O</italic>(1) adjacent to the Kerguelen jet (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">Fig. 7C</xref>). If submesoscale turbulence were resolved, then the ventilation of the tracer would very likely substantially increase in regions of <italic>R</italic><sub>o</sub> = <italic>O</italic>(1).</p><fig id="F7" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><title>The dependence of Rossby numbers on wind stress.</title><p>Rossby numbers <italic>R</italic><sub>o</sub> = &#x003b6;<italic>/f</italic>, where &#x003b6; = <italic>v</italic><sub><italic>x</italic></sub> &#x02212; <italic>u</italic><sub><italic>y</italic></sub> is the relative vorticity and <italic>f</italic> is the planetary vorticity, at the ocean surface for (<bold>A</bold>) 0.5*&#x003c4;, (<bold>B</bold>) &#x003c4;, and (<bold>C</bold>) 2*&#x003c4;.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="aao4719-F7"/></fig></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Model results agree with observations of jets and ventilation</title><p>While observations related to the dynamics of Southern Ocean jets and their effect on tracer ventilation are sparse, the few observations that exist are consistent with the dynamics proposed here. Using observational data sets, it has been shown that Southern Ocean ventilation is a very localized process, associated with topographic features (<xref rid="R34" ref-type="bibr"><italic>34</italic></xref>). This has also been confirmed using observationally based estimates of anthropogenic carbon concentrations to show the localized nature of anthropogenic CO<sub>2</sub> ventilation (<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr"><italic>35</italic></xref>). More recent work has used biogeochemical autonomous floats (BGCArgo) to detect intermittent ventilation events in oceanic storm tracks (<xref rid="R36" ref-type="bibr"><italic>36</italic></xref>). All these observational studies agree with the jet dynamics in the case of a baroclinic jet, with ventilation occurring in storm tracks. For the ventilation of AAIW, in the case of a barotropic jet, observations become even more sparse. Most of the AAIW ventilation under current climate forcing occurs in Drake Passage, where the Southern Ocean jet known as the polar front (PF) is pushed through the narrow gap between South America and Antarctica. Observations of the PF in this region show both zero crossings of the cross-jet potential vorticity gradient and bottom velocities of the order of 0.04 to 0.05 m s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> (<xref rid="R37" ref-type="bibr"><italic>37</italic></xref>), similar to the barotropic state of the jet discussed here, that is, the state for which AAIW ventilation occurs. In 1998, an interference between El Nino&#x02013;Southern Oscillation and the Southern Annular Mode led to an anomalous wind forcing with winds in the region of AAIW ventilation being directed in an up-front direction rather than the usual down-front direction. A time series of physical and biogeochemical properties between 1969 and 2005, produced from transects across Drake Passage, shows that in 1998/1999, AAIW suddenly warmed, salinified, and de-oxygenated (<xref rid="R5" ref-type="bibr"><italic>5</italic></xref>). These observations suggest an interruption of AAIW ventilation for 1 to 2 years following this anomalous wind forcing, pointing toward the crucial role of down-front winds in ventilating the ocean interior. Nevertheless, to test whether this anomaly in AAIW ventilation can be explained by the jet dynamics introduced here, it would be necessary to run multiple perturbation experiments of the circulation in Drake Passage. These experiments would be technically very challenging and computationally expensive since the topography of Drake Passage prevents the use of a simple re-entrant model configuration, as done in this study, and hence it would be necessary to simulate the full Southern Ocean.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" disp-level="1"><title>DISCUSSION</title><p>While a plethora of observation-based evidence points toward the existence of rapid climate transitions in Earth&#x02019;s past, and it is generally accepted that these are closely linked to Southern Ocean dynamics, the processes relevant to contributing to, or triggering, these rapid climate transitions have remained elusive. Here, I show, using the jet north of the KP as an example, how the dynamics of Southern Ocean jets and their interaction with topographic features and ocean stratification can lead to rapid changes in Southern Ocean ventilation. For a small increase in wind stress, these jet dynamics lead from a state where the tracer is confined to the SML to a state where the tracer is ventilated into the ocean interior. Once a certain threshold in wind stress is passed, jet dynamics abruptly change, allowing for the ventilation of fresh AASW into AAIW. These dynamics could lead to a rapid change in Southern Ocean surface stratification, the transport of heat, freshwater, and nutrients at intermediate depths into the global ocean, and could potentially have crucial impacts for the Atlantic MOC. On the basis of observation-based evidence of past ocean circulation, all of these changes are thought to have played a crucial role in rapid climate transitions in Earth&#x02019;s past (<xref rid="R28" ref-type="bibr"><italic>28</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr"><italic>38</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R39" ref-type="bibr"><italic>39</italic></xref>). In addition to consequences on the surface and mid-depth ocean, changes in freshwater forcing in the shallow Southern Ocean can lead to changes in the global deep ocean stratification (<xref rid="R40" ref-type="bibr"><italic>40</italic></xref>) and hence modify the efficiency of the deep global ocean as a carbon trap (<xref rid="R41" ref-type="bibr"><italic>41</italic></xref>).</p><p>There are two main reasons why it is only now that the important role of jets in Southern Ocean ventilation has emerged. First, it is only over the past few years that it has become evident that nonzonal dynamics are essential to understand the Southern Ocean&#x02019;s Antarctic Circumpolar Current, such as, for example, its equilibration (<xref rid="R42" ref-type="bibr"><italic>42</italic></xref>) and the localized nature of observed CO<sub>2</sub> ventilation (<xref rid="R35" ref-type="bibr"><italic>35</italic></xref>). Much of the previous literature on ocean ventilation has focused on the role of the Southern Ocean MOC, which is generally assumed to be a residual between the wind-driven Ekman overturning circulation and an eddy overturning circulation driven by eddy buoyancy fluxes, with eddy momentum fluxes (also known as Reynolds stresses) assumed negligible. Nevertheless, to understand the localized jet dynamics presented here, it is necessary to take into account eddy momentum fluxes, which are closely associated with the strong lateral shear in the barotropic jet. Second, it is only over the last few years that computational resources reached a point where numerical models of the Southern Ocean can be run at sufficiently high horizontal resolution, such as the 1/20&#x000b0; horizontal grid spacing used here, to resolve jet dynamics in the Southern Ocean. Nevertheless, for the complete picture of Southern Ocean ventilation, one has to take into account both dynamics of the Southern Ocean MOC and jet dynamics; it is the delicate balance between these two processes that is relevant to understanding carbon and nutrient budgets in the past, current, and future Southern Ocean.</p><p>The model grid spacing used in this work is 1/20&#x000b0; in the horizontal, which resolves the jet dynamics presented here. This horizontal grid spacing needs to be compared to the 1&#x000b0; grid spacing (or coarser) used in studies that model past ocean circulation (due to their need to run over long time periods) and the 1/4&#x000b0; grid spacing of most climate models used by the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) to predict climate for the next centuries. A doubling of horizontal grid spacing, taking into account the necessary adjustments of the model time step, results in approximately an order of magnitude increase in computational resources. Extending this work to the global ocean to understand the impact of rapid changes in Southern Ocean ventilation on global climate would therefore push the current generation of supercomputers to their limits. Nevertheless, with a steady increase in computational resources, it would be of great benefit to extend this work from being restricted to the Indian sector of the Southern Ocean to simulate the circumpolar Southern Ocean. In particular, Drake Passage is of great interest because of its central role in AAIW ventilation in our current climate. It is possible that a change in wind forcing in glacial climates could have resulted in a shutdown of Southern Ocean ventilation in this region, leading to the highly stratified Southern Ocean observed in glacial climates (<xref rid="R38" ref-type="bibr"><italic>38</italic></xref>).</p><p>Reynolds stresses (convergence of eddy momentum fluxes) are crucial for maintaining Southern Ocean jets. Thus, to represent jet dynamics in simulations of past and future climates, it is necessary to either resolve or parameterize these Reynolds stresses. Both conceptual models used to study the role of the global MOC and eddy parameterizations in more realistic models such as those used by the IPCC currently assume Reynolds stresses to be negligible. While regional models, such as the model used in this study, are capable of resolving Reynolds stresses using computational resources available today, it needs to be shown whether global climate simulations, run at lower grid spacing, are able to adequately represent these jet dynamics and associated changes in Southern Ocean ventilation. Until computational resources allow for global ocean models to fully resolve Reynolds stresses, these models rely on parameterizations of these unresolved processes. One approach to achieve this is to build on existing eddy parameterizations, which are limited to eddy buoyancy fluxes and include Reynolds stresses (<xref rid="R43" ref-type="bibr"><italic>43</italic></xref>). Another promising approach is to parameterize Reynolds stresses using stochastic eddy parameterizations that improve jet dynamics in eddy-permitting ocean models, that is, models that partially resolve the relevant dynamics (<xref rid="R44" ref-type="bibr"><italic>44</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R45" ref-type="bibr"><italic>45</italic></xref>). Nevertheless, much work remains until these approaches can be applied in realistic simulations of global climate, with the abrupt change described in this study, at wind stresses predicted for the very near future, pointing toward the urgency to make progress in this field.</p><p>To develop adequate eddy parameterizations, it is first necessary to understand the underlying dynamics of the processes presented here. This study provides a very descriptive approach to show how jet dynamics can abruptly change, with important consequences for Southern Ocean ventilation, but many challenging questions about the detailed dynamics remain. While it has previously been demonstrated that jets can abruptly reorganize their structure as a consequence of small changes in their forcing (<xref rid="R30" ref-type="bibr"><italic>30</italic></xref>), these efforts have been limited to highly idealized model configurations aimed at representing the atmospheres of Earth and giant gas planets, such as Jupiter and Saturn. Nevertheless, the abrupt change in jet dynamics presented here is closely related to the interaction of jets with topography and ocean stratification, both of which are absent in these previous studies. To explore the dynamics behind this abrupt jet reorganization, it is therefore necessary to work from the knowledge gained from these highly idealized model configurations toward the more complex dynamics described in this study.</p><p>The main caveats of this study are the very idealized surface forcing used and the regional, re-entrant domain of this model configuration. Here, the wind forcing is a zonal and annual mean, and it will have to be shown in future work how these results would change under a seasonal cycle or a large amount of stochastic variability on both seasonal and interannual time scales. Seasonal cycles and stochastic variability might also make it harder to detect the processes shown here. The passive tracer is also introduced at the ocean surface with a short time scale, which is equivalent to an infinite tracer reservoir in the SML, and it will have to be shown in future work how this choice affects the percentage change in ventilation presented here. While the processes described here could, to some extent, change in a more realistic model configuration with, for example, a global model domain and an interactive atmosphere, these caveats are also the strength of this particular model configuration. It is only in such an idealized model configuration that it is possible to separate the physical process of interest from many other processes occurring in a more complex model. Taking into account current limitations of supercomputing resources, it is also only possible to run multiple perturbation experiments with sufficient model grid spacing if the model domain is limited in its spatial extent. Several future directions to extend this work become apparent. The abrupt change in jet dynamics presented here leads to an abrupt increase in Rossby number, with consequences for submesoscale processes and hence the ventilation process. Submesoscale processes are barely resolved in this model configuration, and further work is necessary to understand changes in ventilation if these processes were resolved, including the interaction of submesoscale processes with the jet dynamics presented here. It also remains an open question why ventilation does not occur at the SEIR where a similar strong jet is observed. One difference in this region is that topography does not reach close to the surface, and the jet north of the SEIR is close to the boundary of the model domain, which could have effects on ventilation in this region. Another difference is that the jet in the SEIR moves in latitude with changes in wind stress, while the KP jet is pinned to its position by the KP. More idealized experiments would be necessary to understand this discrepancy. More work is also necessary to further understand the adjustment time scales of this abrupt change in jet dynamics and its role in Southern Ocean ventilation. The model results discussed here are based on equilibrated experiments, and hence, it is not known how long the wind has to increase for it to change Southern Ocean ventilation&#x02014;is a storm enough, or an increase of winds during winter, or a long-term increase of winds as predicted by climate models for the coming decades? With more supercomputing resources becoming available in the future, much can be learned from using the idealized experiments used here in conjunction with more complex climate models to understand the consequences of jet dynamics on the global climate system.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" disp-level="1"><title>MATERIALS AND METHODS</title><sec disp-level="2"><title>Ocean model configuration</title><p>The ocean model used was the Massachusetts Institute of Technology general circulation model (MITgcm) (<xref rid="R46" ref-type="bibr"><italic>46</italic></xref>). It uses depth coordinates, partially filled cells for the bathymetry, a quadratic bottom drag coefficient of 0.0025, a nonlinear equation of state (<xref rid="R47" ref-type="bibr"><italic>47</italic></xref>), a seventh-order advection scheme, and the K-profile parameterization (<xref rid="R48" ref-type="bibr"><italic>48</italic></xref>). The model domain ranged from 57&#x000b0; to 129&#x000b0;E in longitude and 70&#x000b0; to 35&#x000b0;S in latitude and hence included the steep topography associated with the KP and the SEIR. The horizontal grid spacing was 1/20&#x000b0;, which converts to a zonal grid spacing of ~4.5 km at the northern boundary and ~1.9 km at the southern boundary, with a meridional grid spacing of ~5.6 km. The vertical resolution was resolved by 150 layers, ranging from 10 m thickness at the surface to 50 m thickness at depth.</p><p>The model topography was taken from the 1-min-resolution Shuttle Radar Topographic Mission (<xref rid="R49" ref-type="bibr"><italic>49</italic></xref>) with a maximum depth of 5000 m. The model domain was made periodic in the east-west direction, and the topography was interpolated over 4&#x000b0; bands at its eastern and western bands to avoid discontinuities. The northern boundary was relaxed over a 1&#x000b0;-wide sponge layer with a relaxation time of 4 days to annually and zonally averaged climatological fields taken from year 2005 of the Southern Ocean State Estimate (<xref rid="R50" ref-type="bibr"><italic>50</italic></xref>). At the ocean surface, the model was forced to the annually and zonally averaged sea-surface temperature (which was restored with a relaxation time of 15 days), freshwater fluxes, and wind forcing from the Southern Ocean State Estimate. The Southern Ocean MOC was calculated using the MITgcm&#x02019;s layer package (<xref rid="R51" ref-type="bibr"><italic>51</italic></xref>), with the maximum value being determined for all regions south of the sponge layer. For this reference experiment, the total zonal transport was equal to 155 Sverdrup (1 Sverdrup = 10<sup>6</sup> m<sup>3</sup> s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>), which was close to the observed value of the transport estimated in Drake Passage of 173.3 Sverdrup (<xref rid="R52" ref-type="bibr"><italic>52</italic></xref>). A more detailed comparison of this model configuration with observations can be found elsewhere (<xref rid="R53" ref-type="bibr"><italic>53</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R54" ref-type="bibr"><italic>54</italic></xref>).</p></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Perturbation experiments</title><p>In the perturbation experiments, the westerly component of the wind stress was changed to multiples of the annually and zonally averaged wind stress of the year 2005 taken from the Southern Ocean State Estimate (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B</xref>). With the 2005 winds used as the reference case, and denoted by &#x003c4;, five perturbation experiments were run where the westerly component of the wind stress was perturbed to 0.5*&#x003c4;, 0.75*&#x003c4;, 1.25*&#x003c4;, 1.5*&#x003c4;, and 2*&#x003c4;. In all perturbation experiments, forcing at the northern boundary and the surface remained the same as in the reference experiment. All perturbation experiments were run for 30 years starting from the equilibrated reference experiment, with results shown here being mean values over the last 10 years. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Figure 8</xref> shows EKE, baroclinic transports (<italic>T</italic><sub>bci</sub>), barotropic transports (<italic>T</italic><sub>btp</sub>), and maximum Southern Ocean MOC (&#x003a8;<sub>max</sub>) for all perturbation experiments. Similar to EKE derived from satellite observations and modeling studies, EKE increases with increasing wind forcing (<xref rid="R55" ref-type="bibr"><italic>55</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R56" ref-type="bibr"><italic>56</italic></xref>). Because of the complex topography in the model, baroclinic and barotropic transports were calculated using a two-layer model approximation (<xref rid="R57" ref-type="bibr"><italic>57</italic></xref>) at the most eastern longitude of the model domain. The barotropic transport (<italic>T</italic><sub>btp</sub>) was defined as the average velocity in the bottom layer multiplied by the ocean depth, and the baroclinic transport (<italic>T</italic><sub>bci</sub>) was defined as the difference in transport between the upper and lower layers. The boundary between the two layers was chosen to be 1600 m, with the transport anomalies in the perturbation experiments being insensitive to this choice (<xref rid="R57" ref-type="bibr"><italic>57</italic></xref>). As shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F8">Fig. 8</xref>, the baroclinic transport changed very little with wind stress, an effect known as &#x0201c;eddy saturation&#x0201d; (<xref rid="R56" ref-type="bibr"><italic>56</italic></xref>, <xref rid="R58" ref-type="bibr"><italic>58</italic></xref>), whereas the barotropic transport increased with wind stress. The insensitivity of the baroclinic transport is the reason why ocean observations show little change in isopycnal slopes over recent decades during which wind speeds increased (<xref rid="R59" ref-type="bibr"><italic>59</italic></xref>). The Southern Ocean MOC increases less than linearly with wind stress owing to a partial compensation of the wind stress by mesoscale eddies, an effect known as &#x0201c;eddy compensation&#x0201d; (<xref rid="R2" ref-type="bibr"><italic>2</italic></xref>). All of these metrics agree with previous work.</p><fig id="F8" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><title>Properties of equilibrated perturbation experiments.</title><p>Equilibrated mean EKE (blue line), baroclinic transport (<italic>T</italic><sub>bci</sub>; green line), barotropic transport (<italic>T</italic><sub>btp</sub>; red line), and maximum MOC (&#x003a8;; cyan line) are shown for all the perturbation experiments. Transports are given in units of Sverdrup, where 1 Sverdrup = 10<sup>6</sup> m<sup>3</sup> s<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="aao4719-F8"/></fig></sec><sec disp-level="2"><title>Tracer ventilation</title><p>A passive tracer has been introduced at the ocean surface over the last 10 years of model integration. This is done by relaxing the tracer concentration to a value of 1, with a relaxation time scale of 2 hours, homogeneously everywhere south of 37.6&#x000b0;S. North of this latitude, no tracer is introduced because of the numerics of the sponge layer, leading to unphysical vertical motion of the tracer. At the northern boundary of the model domain, the tracer concentration is relaxed to zero to simulate the tracer leaving the domain. The transient increase in tracer concentration in the mid-depth Southern Ocean, integrated between depths of 500 and 1500 m, is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F9">Fig. 9</xref>. Tracer concentrations increase over approximately 5 years before leveling off due to the tracer being relaxed to zero once reaching the northern sponge layer. Tracer concentrations shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">Fig. 4</xref> are a 2-month mean after 5 years of tracer input at the ocean surface.</p><fig id="F9" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float"><label>Fig. 9</label><caption><title>Transients of tracer ventilation.</title><p>Changes of tracer concentration integrated between depths of 500 and 1500 m with time. Colors represent the different wind perturbation experiments shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Fig. 1B</xref>.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="aao4719-F9"/></fig></sec></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgments</title><p>I want to thank L. Zanna, D. R. Munday, D. P. Marshall, and C. Langlais for useful discussions that helped to improve this manuscript. I also want to thank the three anonymous reviewers for very constructive comments that helped to substantially improve this manuscript. <bold>Funding:</bold> A.K. was supported by an Australian Research Council Discovery Early Career Researcher Award (DE140100076). This research was undertaken with the assistance of resources from the National Computational Infrastructure, which is supported by the Australian Government. <bold>Author contributions:</bold> A.K. developed the model configuration, concept, and wrote the manuscript. <bold>Competing interests:</bold> The author declares that he has no competing interests. <bold>Data and materials availability:</bold> All data needed to evaluate the conclusions in the paper are present in the paper. The numerical ocean model is available at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mitgcm.org/">http://mitgcm.org/</ext-link>. Additional data related to this paper may be requested from the author.</p></ack><ref-list><title>REFERENCES AND NOTES</title><ref id="R1"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Broecker</surname><given-names>W. S.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Glacial to interglacial changes in ocean chemistry</article-title>. <source>Prog. Oceanogr.</source>
<volume>11</volume>, 
<fpage>151</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>197</lpage> (<year>1982</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R2"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sarmiento</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Toggweiler</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>A new model for the role of the oceans in determining atmospheric <italic>P</italic>CO<sub>2</sub></article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>308</volume>, 
<fpage>621</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>624</lpage> (<year>1984</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R3"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sigman</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hain</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haug</surname><given-names>G. H.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>The polar ocean and glacial cycles in atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> concentration</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>466</volume>, 
<fpage>47</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>55</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20596012</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R4"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Gottschalk</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Skinner</surname><given-names>L. C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lippold</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jaccard</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Waelbroeck</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Biological and physical controls in the Southern Ocean on past millennial-scale atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> changes</article-title>. <source>Nat. Commun.</source>
<volume>7</volume>, 
<fpage>11539</fpage> (<year>2016</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">27187527</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R5"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Naveira Garabato</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jullion</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stevens</surname><given-names>D. P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heywood</surname><given-names>K. J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>King</surname><given-names>B. A.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Variability of Subantarctic Mode Water and Antarctic Intermediate Water in the Drake Passage during the late-twentieth and early-twenty-first centuries</article-title>. <source>J. Climate</source>
<volume>22</volume>, 
<fpage>3661</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3688</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R6"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Schmitz</surname><given-names>W. J.</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>On the interbasin-scale thermohaline circulation</article-title>. <source>Rev. Geophys.</source>
<volume>33</volume>, 
<fpage>151</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>173</lpage> (<year>1995</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R7"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Talley</surname><given-names>L. D.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Freshwater transport estimates and the global overturning circulation: Shallow, deep and throughflow components</article-title>. <source>Prog. Oceanogr.</source>
<volume>78</volume>, 
<fpage>257</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>303</lpage> (<year>2008</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R8"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sabine</surname><given-names>C. L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Feely</surname><given-names>R. A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gruber</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Key</surname><given-names>R. M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bullister</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wanninkhof</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>C. S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wallace</surname><given-names>D. W. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tilbrook</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Millero</surname><given-names>F. J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>T.-H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kozyr</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ono</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rios</surname><given-names>A. F.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>The oceanic sink for anthropogenic CO<sub>2</sub></article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>305</volume>, 
<fpage>367</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>371</lpage> (<year>2004</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15256665</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R9"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pahnke</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Goldstein</surname><given-names>S. L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hemming</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Abrupt changes in Antarctic intermediate water circulation over the past 25,000 years</article-title>. <source>Nat. Geosci.</source>
<volume>1</volume>, 
<fpage>870</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>874</lpage> (<year>2008</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R10"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Pahnke</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zahn</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Southern Hemisphere water mass conversion linked with North Atlantic Climate variability</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>307</volume>, 
<fpage>1741</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1746</lpage> (<year>2005</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15774752</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R11"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Saenko</surname><given-names>O. A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gregory</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>On the link between the two modes of the ocean thermohaline circulation and the formation of global-scale water masses</article-title>. <source>J. Climate</source>
<volume>16</volume>, 
<fpage>2797</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2801</lpage> (<year>2003</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R12"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Stouffer</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Seidov</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Haupt</surname><given-names>B. J.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Climate response to external sources of freshwater: North Atlantic versus the Southern Ocean</article-title>. <source>J. Climate</source>
<volume>20</volume>, 
<fpage>436</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>448</lpage> (<year>2007</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R13"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Speer</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Closure of the meridional overturning circulation through Southern Ocean upwelling</article-title>. <source>Nat. Geosci.</source>
<volume>5</volume>, 
<fpage>171</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>180</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R14"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>A. K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fr&#x000f6;licher</surname><given-names>T. L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sarmiento</surname><given-names>J. L.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Upwelling in the Southern Ocean</article-title>. <source>Phys. Today</source>
<volume>68</volume>, 
<fpage>27</fpage> (<year>2015</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R15"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Lauderdale</surname><given-names>J. M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>R. G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Munday</surname><given-names>D. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>D. P.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>The impact of Southern Ocean residual upwelling on atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> on centennial and millennial timescales</article-title>. <source>Clim. Dyn.</source>
<volume>48</volume>, 
<fpage>1611</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1631</lpage> (<year>2017</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R16"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>DeVries</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Holzer</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Primeau</surname><given-names>F.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Recent increase in oceanic carbon uptake driven by weaker upper-ocean overturning</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>542</volume>, 
<fpage>215</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>218</lpage> (<year>2017</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">28179663</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R17"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Siegenthaler</surname><given-names>U.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wenk</surname><given-names>Th.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Rapid atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> variations and ocean circulation</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>308</volume>, 
<fpage>624</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>626</lpage> (<year>1984</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R18"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Viehbahn</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eden</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Towards the impact of eddies on the response of the Southern Ocean to climate change</article-title>. <source>Ocean Model.</source>
<volume>34</volume>, 
<fpage>150</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>165</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R19"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>R. F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ali</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bradtmiller</surname><given-names>L. I.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>S. H. H.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fleisher</surname><given-names>M. Q.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Anderson</surname><given-names>B. E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burckle</surname><given-names>L. H.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Wind-driven upwelling in the southern ocean and the deglacial rise in atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub></article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>323</volume>, 
<fpage>1443</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1448</lpage> (<year>2009</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19286547</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R20"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Watson</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Vallis</surname><given-names>G. K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nikurashin</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Southern Ocean buoyancy forcing of ocean ventilation and glacial atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub></article-title>. <source>Nat. Geosci.</source>
<volume>8</volume>, 
<fpage>861</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>864</lpage> (<year>2015</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R21"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrari</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Jansen</surname><given-names>M. F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adkins</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Burke</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>A. F.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Antarctic sea ice control on ocean circulation in present and glacial climates</article-title>. <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A.</source>
<volume>111</volume>, 
<fpage>8753</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8758</lpage> (<year>2014</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24889624</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R22"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Viebahn</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eden</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Towards the impact of eddies on the response of the Southern Ocean to climate change</article-title>. <source>Ocean Model.</source>
<volume>34</volume>, 
<fpage>150</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>165</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R23"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Swart</surname><given-names>N. C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fyfe</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Observed and simulated changes in the Southern Hemisphere surface westerly wind-stress</article-title>. <source>Geophys. Res. Lett.</source>
<volume>39</volume>, 
<fpage>L16711</fpage> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R24"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Le Qu&#x000e9;r&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>R&#x000f6;denbeck</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Buitenhuis</surname><given-names>E. T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Conway</surname><given-names>T. J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Langenfelds</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gomez</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Labuschagne</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ramonet</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Nakazawa</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Metzl</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gillett</surname><given-names>N.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heimann</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Saturation of the Southern Ocean CO<sub>2</sub> sink due to recent climate change</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>316</volume>, 
<fpage>1735</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1738</lpage> (<year>2007</year>).<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17510327</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R25"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zickfeld</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Fyfe</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eby</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Weaver</surname><given-names>A. J.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Comment on &#x0201c;Saturation of the Southern Ocean CO<sub>2</sub> sink due to recent climate change&#x0201d;</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>319</volume>, 
<fpage>570</fpage> (<year>2008</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R26"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Bostock</surname><given-names>H. C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sutton</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>M. J. M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Opdyke</surname><given-names>B. N.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Reviewing the circulation and mixing of Antarctic Intermediate Water in the South Pacific using evidence from geochemical tracers and Argo float trajectories</article-title>. <source>Deep Sea Res. I</source>
<volume>73</volume>, 
<fpage>84</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>98</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R27"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>R. G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>C. W.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Ocean and atmosphere storm tracks: The role of eddy vorticity forcing</article-title>. <source>J. Phys. Oceanogr.</source>
<volume>37</volume>, 
<fpage>2267</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2289</lpage> (<year>2007</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R28"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hendry</surname><given-names>K. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Robinson</surname><given-names>L. F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meredith</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Mulitza</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chiessi</surname><given-names>C. M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Arz</surname><given-names>H.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Abrupt changes in high-latitude nutrient supply to the Atlantic during the last glacial cycle</article-title>. <source>Geology</source>
<volume>40</volume>, 
<fpage>123</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>126</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R29"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Kuo</surname><given-names>H.-I.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Dynamic instability of two-dimensional nondivergent flow in a barotropic atmosphere</article-title>. <source>J. Meteor.</source>
<volume>6</volume>, 
<fpage>105</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>122</lpage> (<year>1949</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R30"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Farrell</surname><given-names>B. F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ioannou</surname><given-names>P. J.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Formation of jets by baroclinic turbulence</article-title>. <source>J. Atmos. Sci.</source>
<volume>65</volume>, 
<fpage>3353</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3375</lpage> (<year>2008</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R31"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>James</surname><given-names>I. N.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Suppression of baroclinic instability in horizontally sheared flows</article-title>. <source>J. Atmos. Sci.</source>
<volume>44</volume>, 
<fpage>3710</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3720</lpage> (<year>1987</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R32"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>L. N.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferrari</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Friction, frontogenesis, and the stratification of the surface mixed layer</article-title>. <source>J. Phys. Oceanogr.</source>
<volume>38</volume>, 
<fpage>2501</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2518</lpage> (<year>2008</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R33"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mahadevan</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>The impact of submesoscale physics on primary productivity of plankton</article-title>. <source>Ann. Rev. Mar. Sci.</source>
<volume>8</volume>, 
<fpage>161</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>184</lpage> (<year>2016</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R34"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sall&#x000e9;e</surname><given-names>J.-B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Speer</surname><given-names>K.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rintoul</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wijffels</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Southern ocean thermocline ventilation</article-title>. <source>J. Phys. Oceanogr.</source>
<volume>40</volume>, 
<fpage>509</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>529</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R35"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sall&#x000e9;e</surname><given-names>J.-B.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matear</surname><given-names>R. J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rintoul</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lenton</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Localized subduction of anthropogenic carbon dioxide in the Southern Hemisphere oceans</article-title>. <source>Nat. Geosci.</source>
<volume>5</volume>, 
<fpage>579</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>584</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R36"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Llort</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Langlais</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matear</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Moreau</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Lenton</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Strutton</surname><given-names>P. G.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Evaluating southern ocean carbon eddy-pump from biogeochemical-argo floats</article-title>. <source>J. Geophys. Res. Oceans</source>
<volume>123</volume>, 
<fpage>971</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>984</lpage> (<year>2018</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R37"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Foppert</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Donohue</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Watts</surname><given-names>D. R.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>The polar front in Drake passage: A composite-mean stream-coordinate view</article-title>. <source>J. Geophys. Res. Oceans</source>
<volume>121</volume>, 
<fpage>1771</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1788</lpage> (<year>2016</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R38"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Franois</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Altabet</surname><given-names>M. A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Yu</surname><given-names>E.-F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sigman</surname><given-names>D. M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bacon</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bohrmann</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bareille</surname><given-names>G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Labeyrie</surname><given-names>L. D.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Contribution of Southern Ocean surface-water stratification to low atmospheric CO<sub>2</sub> concentrations during the last glacial period</article-title>. <source>Nature</source>
<volume>389</volume>, 
<fpage>929</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>935</lpage> (<year>1997</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R39"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>K.-F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Oppo</surname><given-names>D. W.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Curry</surname><given-names>W. B.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Decreased influence of Antarctic intermediate water in the tropical Atlantic during North Atlantic cold events</article-title>. <source>Earth Planet. Sci. Lett.</source>
<volume>389</volume>, 
<fpage>200</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>208</lpage> (<year>2014</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R40"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Sun</surname><given-names>S.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Eisenman</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Stewart</surname><given-names>A. L.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>The influence of Southern Ocean surface buoyancy forcing on glacial-interglacial changes in the global deep ocean stratification</article-title>. <source>Geophys. Res. Lett.</source>
<volume>43</volume>, 
<fpage>8124</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8132</lpage> (<year>2016</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R41"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Adkins</surname><given-names>J. F.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>The role of deep ocean circulation in setting glacial climates</article-title>. <source>Paleoceanography</source>
<volume>28</volume>, 
<fpage>539</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>561</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R42"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>A. F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Naveira Garabato</surname><given-names>A. C.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Equilibration of the Antarctic Circumpolar Current by standing meanders</article-title>. <source>J. Phys. Oceanogr.</source>
<volume>44</volume>, 
<fpage>1811</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1828</lpage> (<year>2014</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R43"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>D. P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Maddison</surname><given-names>J. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Berloff</surname><given-names>P. S.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>A framework for parameterizing eddy potential vorticity fluxes</article-title>. <source>J. Phys. Oceanogr.</source>
<volume>42</volume>, 
<fpage>539</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>557</lpage> (<year>2012</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R44"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Zanna</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Porta Mana</surname><given-names>P. G. L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Anstey</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>David</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Bolton</surname><given-names>T.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Scale-aware deterministic and stochastic parameterizations of eddy-mean flow interaction</article-title>. <source>Ocean Model.</source>
<volume>111</volume>, 
<fpage>66</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>80</lpage> (<year>2017</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R45"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Anstey</surname><given-names>J. A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zanna</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>A deformation-based parameterization of ocean mesoscale eddy Reynolds stresses</article-title>. <source>Ocean Modell.</source>
<volume>112</volume>, 
<fpage>99</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>111</lpage> (<year>2017</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R46"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Adcroft</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hill</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Perelman</surname><given-names>L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heisey</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>A finite-volume, incompressible Navier Stokes model for studies of the ocean on parallel computers</article-title>. <source>J. Geophys. Res.</source>
<volume>102</volume>, 
<fpage>5753</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>5766</lpage> (<year>1997</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R47"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Jackett</surname><given-names>D. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McDougall</surname><given-names>T. J.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Minimal adjustment of hydrographic profiles to achieve static stability</article-title>. <source>J. Atmos. Oceanic Tech.</source>
<volume>12</volume>, 
<fpage>381</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>389</lpage> (<year>1995</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R48"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Large</surname><given-names>W. G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>McWilliams</surname><given-names>J. C.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Doney</surname><given-names>S. C.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Oceanic vertical mixing: A review and a model with nonlocal boundary layer parameterization</article-title>. <source>Rev. Geophys.</source>
<volume>32</volume>, 
<fpage>363</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>403</lpage> (<year>1994</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R49"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>W. H. F.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Sandwell</surname><given-names>D. T.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Global sea floor topography from satellite altimetry and ship depth soundings</article-title>. <source>Science</source>
<volume>277</volume>, 
<fpage>1956</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1962</lpage> (<year>1997</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R50"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Mazloff</surname><given-names>M. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Heimbach</surname><given-names>P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Wunsch</surname><given-names>C.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>An eddy-permitting Southern Ocean state estimate</article-title>. <source>J. Phys. Oceanogr.</source>
<volume>40</volume>, 
<fpage>880</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>899</lpage> (<year>2010</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R51"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Abernathey</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>J.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>D.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>The dependence of Southern Ocean meridional overturning on wind stress</article-title>. <source>J. Phys. Oceanogr.</source>
<volume>41</volume>, 
<fpage>2261</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>2278</lpage> (<year>2011</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R52"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Donohue</surname><given-names>K. A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Tracey</surname><given-names>K. L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Watts</surname><given-names>D. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chidichimo</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chereskin</surname><given-names>T. K.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Mean Antarctic Circumpolar Current transport measured in Drake Passage</article-title>. <source>Geophys. Res. Lett.</source>
<volume>43</volume>, 
<fpage>11760</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>11767</lpage> (<year>2016</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R53"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosso</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hogg</surname><given-names>A. McC.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Strutton</surname><given-names>P. G.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kiss</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Matear</surname><given-names>R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Klocker</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>van Sebille</surname><given-names>E.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Vertical transport in the ocean due to sub-mesoscale structures: Impacts in the Kerguelen region</article-title>. <source>Ocean Model.</source>
<volume>80</volume>, 
<fpage>10</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>23</lpage> (<year>2014</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R54"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Rosso</surname><given-names>I.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hogg</surname><given-names>A. McC.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Kiss</surname><given-names>A. E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Gayen</surname><given-names>B.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Topographic influence on submesoscale dynamics in the Southern Ocean</article-title>. <source>Geophys. Res. Lett.</source>
<volume>42</volume>, 
<fpage>1139</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1147</lpage> (<year>2015</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R55"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Hogg</surname><given-names>A. McC.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Meredith</surname><given-names>M. P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Chambers</surname><given-names>D. P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Abrahamsen</surname><given-names>E. P.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>C. W.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Morrison</surname><given-names>A. K.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Recent trends in the Southern Ocean eddy field</article-title>. <source>J. Geophys. Res.</source>
<volume>120</volume>, 
<fpage>257</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>267</lpage> (<year>2015</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R56"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Munday</surname><given-names>D. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>H. L.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>D. P.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Eddy saturation of equilibrated circumpolar currents</article-title>. <source>J. Phys. Oceanogr.</source>
<volume>43</volume>, 
<fpage>507</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>532</lpage> (<year>2013</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R57"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Langlais</surname><given-names>C. E.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rintoul</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Zika</surname><given-names>J. D.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>Sensitivity of Antarctic circumpolar current transport and eddy activity to wind patterns in the Southern Ocean</article-title>. <source>J. Phys. Oceanogr.</source>
<volume>45</volume>, 
<fpage>1051</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1067</lpage> (<year>2015</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R58"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>Straub</surname><given-names>D. N.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>On the transport and angular momentum balance of channel models of the Antarctic Circumpolar Current</article-title>. <source>J. Phys. Oceanogr.</source>
<volume>23</volume>, 
<fpage>776</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>782</lpage> (<year>1993</year>).</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="R59"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name name-style="western"><surname>B&#x000f6;ning</surname><given-names>C. W.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Dispert</surname><given-names>A.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Visbeck</surname><given-names>M.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Rintoul</surname><given-names>S. R.</given-names></name>, <name name-style="western"><surname>Schwarzkopf</surname><given-names>F. U.</given-names></name></person-group>, 
<article-title>The response of the Antarctic Circumpolar Current to recent climate change</article-title>. <source>Nat. Geosci.</source>
<volume>1</volume>, 
<fpage>864</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>869</lpage> (<year>2008</year>).</mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>