<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2a1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Box 1. Effects of temperature on timing of breeding in great tits</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The great tit (
  <span class="italic">Parus major</span>) is one of the most commonly studied songbird species. In the Netherlands, monitoring of the ecology of this species started at the beginning of the twentieth century, and an extensive amount of data has been accumulated on its breeding phenology. This includes studies on the correlational relationship between temperature and timing of breeding in the wild: in warmer years, Dutch great tits breed earlier 
  <a rid="pbio.1001517-Kluijver1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1001517-Kluijver1">[76]</a>; and studies show that great tits advance their breeding phenology in response to global warming 
  <a rid="pbio.1001517-Husby1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1001517-Husby1">[77]</a>,
  <a rid="pbio.1001517-Nussey1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1001517-Nussey1">[78]</a>. In 1999, a series of experiments aimed at deciphering the possible causal relationship between temperature and breeding phenology were started. This research program made use of up to 36 climate-controlled aviaries in which single pairs of great tits were housed. During the first 6 years, birds were exposed to temperature patterns mimicking a particularly cold and a particularly warm spring (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001517-g002" href="#pbio-1001517-g002">Figure IA</a>) 
  <a rid="pbio.1001517-Visser4" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1001517-Visser4">[79]</a>. The average temperature difference between the treatments was only 4°C. Although year-to-year variation in the average laying dates was large despite the use of the same temperature patterns across years, a direct effect of temperature was demonstrated. In 5 out of 6 years, birds exposed to the warm treatment laid early compared to birds exposed to the cold treatment 
  <a rid="pbio.1001517-Visser4" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1001517-Visser4">[79]</a>. Once the causal relationship between temperature and laying dates was demonstrated, a second set of experiments aimed at identifying the characteristics of temperature that these birds use to time their breeding period was initiated. For this, artificial profiles of temperature were used. They varied either (i) continuously by 4°C over the spring, (ii) in the timing of a cold period, or (iii) in the onset and rate of increase during spring (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001517-g002" href="#pbio-1001517-g002">Figure IB–D</a>) 
  <a rid="pbio.1001517-Visser3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1001517-Visser3">[54]</a>,
  <a rid="pbio.1001517-Schaper2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1001517-Schaper2">[80]</a>. According to these experiments, it is essentially the periods during which temperature increases that play a role in the proximate determination of reproduction in the Dutch great tits; the absolute temperature value has no effect 
  <a rid="pbio.1001517-Schaper2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1001517-Schaper2">[80]</a>. For example, birds exposed to temperatures increasing progressively during spring but constantly differing by 4°C (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001517-g002" href="#pbio-1001517-g002">Figure IB</a>) start breeding at the same time. However, a late spring increase in temperature will influence laying dates more than an early increase or a constant temperature (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001517-g002" href="#pbio-1001517-g002">Figure IC–D</a>) 
  <a rid="pbio.1001517-Schaper2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1001517-Schaper2">[80]</a>. 
 </p>
 <div id="pbio-1001517-g002" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pbio.1001517.g002</span>
  <span class="label">Figure I</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Temperature profiles used during experiments conducted in climate-controlled aviaries.</div>
   <p>A: Natural patterns of variation of temperature. B?D: Artificial patterns of temperature variation. B: Progressive increase of temperature with a constant 4uC difference. C: Variation in the onset and termination of a cold period. D: Variation in the onset and the rate of increase of temperature. Adapted from 
    <a rid="pbio.1001517-Visser3" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1001517-Visser3">[54]</a>,
    <a rid="pbio.1001517-Visser4" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1001517-Visser4">[79]</a>,
    <a rid="pbio.1001517-Schaper2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1001517-Schaper2">[80]</a>.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pbio.1001517.g002" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
