<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s2b1" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Box 2. Effects of temperature on timing of hibernation in ground squirrels and other rodents</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Terrestrial mammals often rely on body reserves or food storages combined with metabolic suppression to overcome the harsh winter conditions. Several mammal species can be characterized as deep hibernators. In these animals, extreme metabolic suppression is found, with metabolic rates that can be reduced down to about 1% of normal euthermic resting metabolism 
  <a rid="pbio.1001517-Geiser1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1001517-Geiser1">[81]</a> for about 5–9 months per year. Body temperature drops dramatically during that life-cycle stage, sometimes below freezing temperatures (as low as −2.9°C in the Arctic ground squirrel 
  <a rid="pbio.1001517-Barnes1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1001517-Barnes1">[82]</a>). Hibernation is however generally not continuous and most hibernating species show intermittent interruptions of their low-temperature torpid states by short arousal phases that are modulated both by endogenous circannual cycles and by ambient temperatures 
  <a rid="pbio.1001517-Hut2" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1001517-Hut2">[83]</a>,
  <a rid="pbio.1001517-Pengelley1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1001517-Pengelley1">[84]</a>. Due to this temperature dependency of arousal frequency, energy expenditure during hibernation is minimized at ambient temperatures around 0°C 
  <a rid="pbio.1001517-Humphries1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1001517-Humphries1">[85]</a>. For most hibernators in temperate zones this means that increased winter temperatures will lead to increased energy expenditure, stronger decline in energy reserves, reduced winter survival, and possibly altered behavior and phenology. Indeed, hibernation energetics modeling in bats led to the prediction that the location of overwintering caves will be at higher latitudes as a response to global warming 
  <a rid="pbio.1001517-Humphries1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1001517-Humphries1">[85]</a>. Hibernating species that do not migrate, such as squirrels, marmots, or hamsters, would rather have to adapt their hibernating phenology under global warming. Indeed, earlier snow melt and/or higher spring temperatures correlate with advanced hibernation end in ground squirrels 
  <a rid="pbio.1001517-Fagerstone1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1001517-Fagerstone1">[86]</a>,
  <a rid="pbio.1001517-Lane1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1001517-Lane1">[87]</a> and marmots 
  <a rid="pbio.1001517-Inouye1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1001517-Inouye1">[6]</a>. Although this is expected to have detrimental effects on parental quality, the concomitant advancement in reproduction seems to be beneficial for juveniles that have more time to develop in preparation of the next winter 
  <a rid="pbio.1001517-Ozgul1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1001517-Ozgul1">[21]</a>. The causality of these temperature effects on hibernation phenology was demonstrated in laboratory manipulations of ambient temperature during hibernation. In an experiment conducted in climate-controlled rooms, Nemeth et al. 
  <a rid="pbio.1001517-Nmeth1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1001517-Nmeth1">[88]</a> showed that European ground squirrels maintained at 5°C and 9°C during their hibernation emerged significantly earlier in spring than squirrels maintained at 0°C (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001517-g003" href="#pbio-1001517-g003">Figure IIA</a>). In addition, squirrels exposed to the high temperature treatments did arouse more often and for longer periods of time, causing body mass to decrease more quickly than in the cold treatment 
  <a rid="pbio.1001517-Nmeth1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1001517-Nmeth1">[88]</a>. In an earlier set of experiments with golden-mantled ground squirrels, it was shown that maintaining animals at 0°C advanced the onset of hibernation by about 40 days compared to animals kept at 21°C, even though food and water were constantly provided ad libitum 
  <a rid="pbio.1001517-Pengelley1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1001517-Pengelley1">[84]</a> (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pbio-1001517-g003" href="#pbio-1001517-g003">Figure IIB</a>). It was even shown that by dropping temperature to 0°C after a prolonged period of high temperature at 35°C–38°C, it was possible to induce hibernation in the middle of the summer phase of the endogenous clock 
  <a rid="pbio.1001517-Pengelley1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1001517-Pengelley1">[84]</a>. 
 </p>
 <div id="pbio-1001517-g003" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <span pub-id-type="doi" class="object-id">10.1371/journal.pbio.1001517.g003</span>
  <span class="label">Figure II</span>
  <div class="caption">
   <div class="title">Effect of ambient temperature on hibernation phenology in squirrels.</div>
   <p>(A) Timing of spring emergence from hibernation in European ground squirrels (
    <span class="italic">Spermophilus citellus</span>) and (B) timing of autumn onset of hibernation in golden-mantled ground squirrels (
    <span class="italic">Citellus lateralis tescorum</span>) maintained under different temperatures. Drawn from (A) Nemeth et al 
    <a rid="pbio.1001517-Nmeth1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1001517-Nmeth1">[88]</a> and (B) Pengelley and Fisher 
    <a rid="pbio.1001517-Pengelley1" ref-type="bibr" href="#pbio.1001517-Pengelley1">[84]</a>, error bars in A indicate standard deviation, and in B, data range.
   </p>
  </div>
  <div xlink:href="pbio.1001517.g003" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
 </div>
</sec>
