<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec003" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Biological data</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Recruitment (REC3; number of 3-year olds) and total stock biomass (TSB; age 3 and older) for Barents Sea cod between 1950 and 2017 are taken from the latest report of ICES AFWG [
  <a rid="pone.0206319.ref030" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0206319.ref030">30</a>]. TSB is calculated using virtual population analysis (VPA), which means that the stock biomass is back-calculated based on the knowledge of death rates including fisheries and natural mortality sources. The TSB provided by ICES AFWG will be referred to as observations. It should be noted that when using VPA, adding another year of data also leads to a revision of the stock size some years back in time. For an illustration of the recent uncertainties in the stock estimates see the latest ICES advice for this stock (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ices.dk" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.ices.dk</span>). To obtain a relative measure of fishing efforts, the harvest rate of Barents Sea cod was calculated by dividing the annual catches (provided by ICES) by the total stock biomass.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">ICES predictions are taken from the annual ICES AFWG reports since 1981, and are those which are the basis for the quota advice. Before 1981 such predictions were generally not provided. The length of predictions given in the reports vary from 2 to 6 years. Here we consider predictions 1–3 years ahead. In most years, predictions are given for several different exploitation rates. For each year, we have chosen the predictions which correspond to catch in tonnes (i.e., human impact) closest to the actual catches for the first three years in the prediction. Note that the 1987 assessment and advice was revised in mid-year (spring 1988), but that the figures from that revision are not shown. To evaluate the ICES predictions we construct a time series for each lead time and correlate it with the observation-based time series. Associated uncertainty estimates were calculated by sub-sampling 80% of the time series 1000 times.</p>
</sec>
