<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec004" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Oceanographic data</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We use the Nordic Seas Atlas (NSA) [
  <a rid="pone.0206319.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0206319.ref029">29</a>] to obtain annual time series of observed temperature and salinity from the Atlantic inflow to the Nordic Seas between 1950 and 2012. The NSA contains data on a 0.25° grid at 29 vertical levels, which allows for a good representation of Atlantic water properties. The NSA is designed specifically for the region of interest and utilizes the extensive observations from the Nordic Seas and Barents Sea [
  <a rid="pone.0206319.ref029" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0206319.ref029">29</a>]. Time series of annual temperature and salinity are obtained along the Atlantic water pathways (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0206319.g001" href="#pone.0206319.g001">Fig 1a</a>); Faroe–Shetland Channel (FSC; 60.5–61°N, 2.5–5°W), Iceland–Faroe ridge (IFR; 62.5–63.5°N, 6°W) and the Fugløya-Bear Island section (Barents Sea Opening: BSO; 70–74°N, 20°E). The time series are constructed by averaging over the different areas and between 50–200 m depth, the latter commonly used to define the depth of Atlantic water [
  <a rid="pone.0206319.ref031" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0206319.ref031">31</a>]. The time series from FSC and IFR are also sometimes combined to create an average temperature and salinity of the Atlantic inflow across the Greenland-Scotland ridge, denoted 
  <span class="italic">TS</span>
  <sub>gsr</sub>. As the NSA only provides data up to 2012, the hydrography from Nordic Seas Atlas is supplemented by observations from the ICES report on ocean climate (IROC), where observations of the northward flowing Atlantic water in the FSC are available for the time period 1950–2017 [
  <a rid="pone.0206319.ref032" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0206319.ref032">32</a>].
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">We also use North Atlantic climate indexes as potential predictors for Barents Sea cod stock. The Atlantic Multidecadal Oscillation (AMO) index [
  <a rid="pone.0206319.ref033" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0206319.ref033">33</a>] is defined as the annual (unfiltered) sea surface temperature (SST) between 0–70°N and was obtained from NOAA at 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.esrl.noaa.gov/psd/data/timeseries/AMO" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.esrl.noaa.gov/psd/data/timeseries/AMO</span>, whereas the subpolar gyre index (SPGi) is defined as the annual mean SST (from HadISST [
  <a rid="pone.0206319.ref028" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0206319.ref028">28</a>]) between 52.5–62.5°N, 27.5-12.5°W [
  <a rid="pone.0206319.ref034" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0206319.ref034">34</a>]. Although the AMO index by definition reflects basin scale ocean temperature variations in the North Atlantic, the primary center of action is found in the subpolar North Atlantic [
  <a rid="pone.0206319.ref035" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0206319.ref035">35</a>]. The SPGi and AMO thus display similar variability (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0206319.g001" href="#pone.0206319.g001">Fig 1b</a>).
 </p>
</sec>
