<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Overall, long-term climate observations in a traditional grape-wine growing area highlighted important weather modifications over time. In particular, warming, variations in precipitation patterns, and a progressive increase in extreme summer events were the main changes observed during 1995–2015. The study area, classified as ‘hot-warm’ climate in 1995–2015, according to GST values [
 <xref rid="B30-plants-08-00121" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>], exhibited an increasingly linear trend in the GST (1.4 °C in the last 15 years). Estimated warming of the grapevine vegetative period is in accordance with what was observed in other traditional wine growing areas [
 <xref rid="B1-plants-08-00121" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>,
 <xref rid="B2-plants-08-00121" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>,
 <xref rid="B38-plants-08-00121" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">38</xref>], or predicted by climate models [
 <xref rid="B7-plants-08-00121" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">7</xref>,
 <xref rid="B12-plants-08-00121" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">12</xref>]. The WI and HI indices, that provide information about temperatures necessary for vine growth, grape ripening, and grape oenological potential [
 <xref rid="B39-plants-08-00121" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">39</xref>], also increased over time like in other Mediterranean areas [
 <xref rid="B40-plants-08-00121" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>,
 <xref rid="B41-plants-08-00121" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>]. This process may lead to a local rearrangement of crop varieties. Contrary to what was observed elsewhere [
 <xref rid="B15-plants-08-00121" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">15</xref>,
 <xref rid="B42-plants-08-00121" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">42</xref>], the increase in temperature was not coupled with an extension of the drought period, usually leading to increased irrigation needs in the vineyard [
 <xref rid="B43-plants-08-00121" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">43</xref>], and consequently to the necessity to adjust vineyard management practices for semi-arid regions. Indeed, an increase in total precipitation and numbers of rainy days (rain &gt; 1mm) was recorded in this grape-wine growing area, in line with earlier results provided by Ramos et al. [
 <xref rid="B40-plants-08-00121" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">40</xref>]. More specifically, precipitation frequency and amount did not show any significant trend against time as observed in Jones et al. [
 <xref rid="B1-plants-08-00121" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">1</xref>] and Tomasi et al. [
 <xref rid="B41-plants-08-00121" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">41</xref>]. This evidence was proved by analysis of the HTC calculated for the two sub-areas. The occurrence of a high amount of precipitation out of season (hydrological winter), given the high soil organic matter typical of both sub-areas [
 <xref rid="B44-plants-08-00121" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">44</xref>], can indicate the replenishment of soil water content. A relatively high amount of soil organic matter, together with the values of HTC prove the effectiveness of precipitation in the growing season, preventing the need of vineyard systematic irrigation, and with a consistent increase of pest and diseases risk. Given this fact, while a more sustainable use of water resources may indicate the occurrence of sustainability condition in the agro-ecosystem, the increase of agrochemical need endangers this objective. Therefore, ombrothermic graphs are a key tool to profile micro-climate regimes in the vineyard and to plan adaptation strategies at soil or canopy level [
 <xref rid="B30-plants-08-00121" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">30</xref>].
</p>
