<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">Our investigation proved the influence of climate variability on ripening phenology and consequently harvest date, and also on berry ripening indices, like TSS and TA. The response was highly genotype-specific, differing among international and native grapevine varieties and between white grape and red grape varieties. In the last years, there is an increasing interest by winegrowers in adopting autochthones genotypes, being landraces known to optimize genotype–environment interaction [
 <xref rid="B52-plants-08-00121" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>,
 <xref rid="B53-plants-08-00121" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">53</xref>] and to exhibits greater phenotypic plasticity to climate conditions [
 <xref rid="B54-plants-08-00121" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">54</xref>,
 <xref rid="B55-plants-08-00121" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">55</xref>]. Local genetic resources have a role in sustainable viticulture, allowing rich high quality grape and oenological products with minimal outside-farm input requirements [
 <xref rid="B53-plants-08-00121" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">53</xref>]. Concerning the ripening phase, the two tested autochthonous varieties, the white grape cv Grechetto and the red grape cv Aleatico, showed annual fluctuations in the harvest date, irrespective of warming. In general, the international varieties exhibited adaptive traits, resulting in a strict correlation of ripening phenology (occurrence of technological ripening) with climate change, although with a different pattern among the genotypes. In fact, genotype response was reflected in both advanced and delayed harvest dates. For example, a different behavior was exhibited within the tested red grape varieties, all classified as mid to late season varieties [
 <xref rid="B56-plants-08-00121" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">56</xref>]. Grapevine varieties clustered into climate-maturity groupings, according to Jones [
 <xref rid="B2-plants-08-00121" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">2</xref>]. In particular, cv C. Sauvignon and cv Sangiovese, classified as suitable for ‘warm climate maturity’ ranges (GST, 17–19°C), while cv C. franc and cv Merlot classified for ‘intermediate’ to ‘warm climate maturity’ ranges (GST, 15–17 °C and 17–19 °C, respectively). Our study proved that climate maturity grouping may change over time. This genotype-specific response in ripening phenology implies that the precision management of harvest has to deal with the genotype different response to climate change.
</p>
