<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The predicted rise in atmospheric CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> level is expected to increase crop yield and biomass through stimulation of photosynthesis and suppression of photorespiration albeit the enhancement is crop species dependent (
 <xref rid="B84" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Long et al., 2006</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B21" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Dahal et al., 2012</xref>). However, an important concern with increase in atmospheric CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> is concomitant increase in heat stress and associated water deficit and biotic stress. Thus, although the projected rise in the atmospheric CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub> is expected to increase yield potential in certain crop species, the yield deterioration due to climate change associated heat stress, drought stress and biotic stress can outpace the benefit achieved by any increase in atmospheric CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>. It is one of the challenges for plant breeders and agriculturists to maintain yield stability through improved tolerance to climate change associated stresses such as drought, low and high temperature in future (
 <xref rid="B103" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">Powell et al., 2012</xref>). Potato crop, like most other crop species, is highly prone to abiotic stress particularly, high temperature, drought and soil salinity. In order to maintain a sustainable potato production under climate change, we must identify best cultivation practices and develop heat, drought, insect and pathogen tolerant cultivars that can best adapt to the changing environment. It is one of the challenges for crop scientists to pinpoint means of improving crop yield and quality at high CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>, high temperature and drought stress as well as biotic stress. One important approach is to understand stress-related molecular, biochemical and physiological markers that can be used to develop screening procedures for selection of crop cultivars that can better adapt to sub-optimal growth conditions. The mechanism by which potato plants initially sense the changes in their surrounding CO
 <sub class="sub">2</sub>, temperature, water status, soil salinity and biotic stress and consequently respond to these changes at the molecular, biochemical and physiological levels is still under infancy. Future research needs be concentrated on the identification of signaling molecules, target genes and their networks that govern plant phenotypic and metabolic plasticity in response to elevated CO
 <sub class="sub">2,</sub>high temperature and water deficit. Elucidation of such mechanism may provide new insights into the identification of specific characteristics that may be useful in breeding programs aimed at (1) developing new potato cultivars with enhanced yield potential and (ii) developing potato germplasm with adaptation to climate change. This will help in sustaining or even enhancing potato productivity under predicted climate change.
</p>
