<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<contrib-group class="contrib-group">
 <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes" class="contrib">
  <name class="name">
   <surname class="surname">Ravera</surname>
   <given-names class="given-names">Federica</given-names>
  </name>
  <address class="address">
   <email class="email">Federica.ravera@gmail.com</email>
  </address>
  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1" class="xref">1</xref>
  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2" class="xref">2</xref>
  <bio class="bio">
   <sec id="FPar1" class="sec">
    <title class="title">Federica Ravera</title>
    <p class="p">is a Postdoctoral researcher at the Universidade de Évora—
     <italic class="italic">Instituto de Ciências Agrárias e Ambientais Mediterrânicas</italic>. She is an ecological economist. Her research interests focus on evaluating factors, practices, institutions which influence vulnerability and/or support processes of adaptation to change and transformations of socio-ecological systems towards sustainability in mountain and semi-arid regions around the world. Recently, on her work she has put emphasis on the gender perspective in vulnerability, resilience and adaptation studies.
    </p>
   </sec>
  </bio>
 </contrib>
 <contrib contrib-type="author" class="contrib">
  <name class="name">
   <surname class="surname">Martín-López</surname>
   <given-names class="given-names">Berta</given-names>
  </name>
  <address class="address">
   <email class="email">martinlo@leuphana.de</email>
  </address>
  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3" class="xref">3</xref>
  <bio class="bio">
   <sec id="FPar2" class="sec">
    <title class="title">Berta Martín-López</title>
    <p class="p">is a Professor of Sustainability Science at Leuphana University Lueneburg. She is also a member of the scientific committees of PECS (
     <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://pecs-science.org/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://pecs-science.org/</ext-link>) and ecoSERVICES (
     <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.futureearth.org/ecoservices/" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">http://www.futureearth.org/ecoservices/</ext-link>). Her research interests focus on analysing the dynamics of social–ecological systems, including the assessment of ecosystem services and the institutional analysis of biodiversity and ecosystem services.
    </p>
   </sec>
  </bio>
 </contrib>
 <contrib contrib-type="author" class="contrib">
  <name class="name">
   <surname class="surname">Pascual</surname>
   <given-names class="given-names">Unai</given-names>
  </name>
  <address class="address">
   <email class="email">unai.pascual@bc3research.org</email>
  </address>
  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4" class="xref">4</xref>
  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5" class="xref">5</xref>
  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6" class="xref">6</xref>
  <bio class="bio">
   <sec id="FPar3" class="sec">
    <title class="title">Unai Pascual</title>
    <p class="p">is Ikerbasque Research Professor at the Basque Centre for Climate Change (BC3) and Senior Lecturer at the University of Cambridge. He is an ecological economist with 20 years’ experience bridging the social and natural sciences for understanding complex social–ecological systems. His main research focuses on the interconnectedness between global environmental change and economic development paying special attention to the evolutionary role of institutions, markets and environmental governance across scales. He has conducted research projects in many countries around the world, including Europe and the USA and in developing countries such as Mexico, Peru, Bolivia, Colombia, India, Ethiopia and Malawi.</p>
   </sec>
  </bio>
 </contrib>
 <contrib contrib-type="author" class="contrib">
  <name class="name">
   <surname class="surname">Drucker</surname>
   <given-names class="given-names">Adam</given-names>
  </name>
  <address class="address">
   <email class="email">A.Drucker@cgiar.org</email>
  </address>
  <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff7" class="xref">7</xref>
  <bio class="bio">
   <sec id="FPar4" class="sec">
    <title class="title">Adam G. Drucker</title>
    <p class="p">is a Senior Economist at Biodiversity International (CGIAR). His background is in Ecological Economics and his current research is focussed on the Economics of Agrobiodiversity Conservation and Use. Additional interests/expertise covers a wide range of natural resource management issues including sustainable agriculture and rural development, deforestation, biodiversity conservation, climate change, environmental policy development and the use of market-based instruments.</p>
   </sec>
  </bio>
 </contrib>
 <aff id="Aff1" class="aff">
  <label class="label">1</label>ICAAM - Instituto de Ciências Agrárias e Ambientais Mediterrânicas, LDSP - Landscape Dynamics and Social Process Research Group, Universidade de Évora, Pólo da Mitra, Ap. 94, 7002-554 Évora, Portugal 
 </aff>
 <aff id="Aff2" class="aff">
  <label class="label">2</label>CREAF, Cerdanyola del Vallès, 08193 Catalonia, Spain 
 </aff>
 <aff id="Aff3" class="aff">
  <label class="label">3</label>Faculty of Sustainability, Institute of Ethics and Transdisciplinary Sustainability Research, Leuphana University, Scharnhorststr. 1, 21335 Lüneburg, Germany 
 </aff>
 <aff id="Aff4" class="aff">
  <label class="label">4</label>Basque Centre for Climate Change (BC3), Edificio Sede Nº 1, Planta 1ª, Parque Científico de UPV/EHU, Barrio Sarriena, 48940 Leioa, Spain 
 </aff>
 <aff id="Aff5" class="aff">
  <label class="label">5</label>IKERBASQUE, Basque Foundation for Science, Maria Diaz de Haro 3, 6 floor, 48013 Bilbao, Spain 
 </aff>
 <aff id="Aff6" class="aff">
  <label class="label">6</label>Department of Land Economy, University of Cambridge, 19 Silver St., Cambridge, CB3 9EP UK 
 </aff>
 <aff id="Aff7" class="aff">
  <label class="label">7</label>Bioversity International, Via dei Tre Denari 472/a, 00057 Maccarese, Rome, Italy 
 </aff>
</contrib-group>
