<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div id="F4" fig-type="figure" orientation="portrait" position="float" class="fig" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
 <span class="label">Fig. 4</span>
 <div class="caption">
  <div class="title">Model-proxy agreement.</div>
  <p>Maximum Cohen’s κ (left) and pattern correlation coefficient (right) for each climate response simulated by CESM1. Cohen’s κ quantifies agreement between simulated patterns of rainfall change and a multiproxy synthesis of hydroclimate change at the LGM. The maximum κ value obtained from the threshold sensitivity analysis is reported. The correlation coefficient (
   <span class="italic">r</span>) quantifies agreement between simulated patterns of SST change and our reconstruction of LGM temperature changes derived from Mg/Ca and 
   <div class="inline-formula">
    <div id="m2" class="math">
     <div class="mrow">
      <div class="mrow">
       <div class="msubsup">
        <span mathvariant="normal" class="mi">U</span>
        <span class="mn">37</span>
        <div class="mrow">
         <span mathvariant="italic" class="mi">K</span>
         <span class="mo">′</span>
        </div>
       </div>
      </div>
     </div>
    </div>
   </div> records. A κ or 
   <span class="italic">r</span> value of one indicates perfect model-proxy agreement. A value of zero indicates lack of agreement. Solid circles indicate statistically significant (
   <span class="italic">P</span> &lt; 0.05) κ and 
   <span class="italic">r</span> values. Error bars indicate the 95% confidence intervals for the κ values. Uncertainty due to calibration of SST proxies is reported as the minimum-maximum range of the 
   <span class="italic">r</span> values computed using each reconstruction in our ensemble (blue error bars). The 95% confidence interval of the 
   <span class="italic">r</span> values computed using the ensemble mean reconstruction is also shown (gray error bars). Further details on the computation of these proxy-model agreement estimators, as well as the definition of the climate responses, are provided in the Supplementary Materials.
  </p>
 </div>
 <div xlink:href="aat9658-F4" class="graphic" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"/>
</div>
