<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The increasing frequency and intensity of extreme weather events due to climate change pose growing risks to human health. Heat-waves were the deadliest extreme climate event in Europe between 1991 and 2015, particularly in southern and western Europe. Several extreme heat-waves have occurred since 2000 (in 2003, 2006, 2007, 2010, 2014, 2015 and 2016) [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1" class="xref">1</xref>]. Exceptionally persistent and high July temperatures in 2018 baked countries across the WHO European Region, including northern Europe and even above the Arctic circle in Lapland, setting the stage for catastrophic forest fires in Greece, for example [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13" class="xref">13</xref>]. Sweden experienced a large number of wildfires due to a prolonged heatwave in summer 2018, which the Swedish Civil Contingencies Agency considered the most serious in the modern history of the country [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14" class="xref">14</xref>]. In the summer of 2017, Portugal was severely affected by wildfires, which occurred during a concurrent heatwave and severe drought, killing 65 people [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15" class="xref">15</xref>]. In Greece, Italy and France, severe alert warning messages were also issued in 2017, indicating that even healthy and active people could suffer from possible negative effects. In Italy, hospital admissions went up by 15% during the heatwave [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16" class="xref">16</xref>]. The heatwave during the summer of 2003 claimed more than 70,000 lives across mostly western European countries [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17" class="xref">17</xref>], and in 2010 many eastern European cities recorded extremely high temperatures, particularly in the Russian Federation, where the deaths attributable to these high temperatures were estimated at around 55,000 [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18" class="xref">18</xref>]. Urban populations are at risk of multiple exposures; for example air pollution also increases the health risks associated with high temperatures [
 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11" class="xref">11</xref>].
</p>
