<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="s3" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Spatial Pattern of Threats and Their Overlap.</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The overall area where species richness is projected to become impacted by either of the threats or any of their combinations does not differ between the low- and the high-emission scenario, except for amphibians, where the area is higher under the low-emission scenario (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">Fig. 2</a> and 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1807745115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Table S1
  </span>). Under RCP2.6, vertebrate species richness may become impacted by high-intensity climate and land-use change in about 36% of the world’s terrestrial area [amphibians: 35.9 ± 3.94 (SD); birds: 36.2 ± 4.45, mammals: 36.8 ± 4.97]; under RCP6.0, this figure is also projected to be about 36% (amphibians: 33.6 ± 3.05; birds: 37.4 ± 7.92, mammals: 38.1 ± 7.68) (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">Fig. 2</a> and 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1807745115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Table S1
  </span>). The main differences between the RCP2.6 and RCP6.0 emission scenario lies in the individual extent of climate and land-use change threat. Whereas climate change threat is projected to become more extensive under the high-emission scenario, threat from land-use change may become more extensive under the low-emission scenario. This high level of land-use change threat under the low-emission scenario is mainly due to the large projected increase in bioenergy cropland. Focusing on the overlap between projected impacts from climate change and cropland change (both bioenergy and nonbioenergy), RCP2.6 shows a larger area of potential impact: for these threat combinations, about 5.2% [amphibians: 5.9 ± 0.63 (SD); birds: 4.6 ± 0.84; mammals: 5.0 ± 0.86] of the global land area is projected to become impacted under RCP2.6, but only 3.2% (amphibians: 3.1 ± 0.36; birds: 3.3 ± 0.65; mammals: 3.3 ± 0.69) under RCP 6.0 (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1807745115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Table S1
  </span>). All of these values decline slightly when a basic dispersal of species is incorporated, but the differences remain consistent (
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1807745115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Fig. S8 and Table S1
  </span>). Areas where nonbioenergy cropland change is projected to overlap with direct climate change impacts are larger under RCP6.0, as are areas where projected changes to pastures overlap with climate change impacts (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">Fig. 2</a> and 
  <span ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="https://www.pnas.org/lookup/suppl/doi:10.1073/pnas.1807745115/-/DCSupplemental" xlink:show="new" class="ext-link" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
   <span class="italic">SI Appendix</span>, Table S1
  </span>). The patterns of threat overlap also vary across space, depending on the taxonomic group, the emission scenario, and the land-use type (see 
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="fig02" href="#fig02">Fig. 2</a> for details). Overall, most areas with high levels of projected climate and land-use change impacts coincide in the tropics. Southwestern South America (mainly the Pampas, Atlantic Forest, and Cerrado regions), Central America, large parts of tropical Africa, and also of south and southeast Asia, including Indonesia and New Guinea, are projected to become highly impacted from different threat combinations, independent of the taxon or the emission scenario.
 </p>
</sec>
