<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>Our analyses of leaf traits, including the SLA, 
 <italic>N</italic>
 <sub>area</sub>, and LAI, could be treated as two important dimensions of trait covariation (
 <xref rid="B47" ref-type="bibr">Yang et al., 2019</xref>). The three plant traits used in this study have important ecological and modeling significance. SLA and 
 <italic>N</italic>
 <sub>area</sub> are included in the universal leaf economic spectrum. SLA is an essential variable in vegetation models because it determines the relationship between the LA available for light interception and photosynthesis and the amount of photosynthate required for leaf construction (
 <xref rid="B23" ref-type="bibr">Niklas et al., 2007</xref>). Compared with the leaf N concentration per unit mass (
 <italic>N</italic>
 <sub>mass</sub>), 
 <italic>N
  <sub>area</sub>
 </italic> can be expressed more accurately as the sum of a metabolic component proportional to photosynthetic capacity and a structural component proportional to the leaf mass per area (LMA, LMA = 1/SLA) (
 <xref rid="B7" ref-type="bibr">Dong et al., 2017</xref>). 
 <italic>N
  <sub>area</sub>
 </italic> is a key variable for modeling because it determines the N demand of leaf construction. This variable is represented in many recent vegetation models that include an interactive N cycle (
 <xref rid="B50" ref-type="bibr">Zaehle et al., 2014</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B33" ref-type="bibr">Stocker et al., 2016</xref>). The LES reflects the linkage between high construction costs and long payback times of leaves with low SLA (
 <xref rid="B18" ref-type="bibr">McMurtrie and Dewar, 2011</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B8" ref-type="bibr">Funk and Cornwell, 2013</xref>). More broadly, the LES is a universal feature of functional diversity within communities (see e.g., 
 <xref rid="B11" ref-type="bibr">Hallik et al., 2009</xref>; 
 <xref rid="B25" ref-type="bibr">Pierce et al., 2013</xref>) and as such, should be represented in models.
</p>
