<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p>The scale of our experiment did not capture population-level differences that would be useful to exploit for restoration strategies for two of the three species included. Overall, seedlings from mesic-wet forest and subalpine shrubland environments did not demonstrate short-term differences in growth and survival. Although seed sources for 
 <italic>C</italic>. 
 <italic>oahuense</italic> and 
 <italic>S</italic>. 
 <italic>chrysophylla</italic> differed by 500 m in elevation and varied &gt; 1,000 mm of annual rainfall, they were ≤4 km apart in distance. Perhaps the scale at which seeds were sourced encompassed a ‘local’ provenance. While plots spaced ~60 m apart in altitude was a small interval, there is evidence for climatic conditions affecting montane plant vigor across similarly-spaced plots. Inouye [
 <xref rid="pone.0218516.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>] documented flower bud death caused by frost differed &gt;20% between neighboring plots 12 m apart in elevation, and more dramatic differences across 90 m elevation. Although not explicitly tested, sufficient gene flow may be retained in the common species of 
 <italic>C</italic>. 
 <italic>oahuense</italic> and 
 <italic>S</italic>. 
 <italic>chrysophylla</italic> given the relatively small distance separating populations, and further studies examining the genotypic variation within seed sources would yield complementary insights. In contrast, 
 <italic>D</italic>. 
 <italic>viscosa</italic> had significantly greater survival in seedlings from high-elevation origin than those from low-elevation origin, and the source of these low-elevation seedlings was approximately 30 km from KBC on the southwestern slope of Mauna Kea. Furthermore, furthest-sourced 
 <italic>D</italic>. 
 <italic>viscosa</italic> seedlings had the lowest survival in our experiment. It is possible that population-level variation exists across this broader 30 km distance, an order of magnitude greater than that of seeds sourced for 
 <italic>C</italic>. 
 <italic>oahuense</italic> and 
 <italic>S</italic>. 
 <italic>chrysophylla</italic>.
</p>
