<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec015" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Conclusions</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">Recovery is occurring for representative populations of most marine mammal and sea turtle species listed under the ESA and analyzed in our study. Representative populations from species listed for over 20 years were more likely to have populations that significantly increased in numbers. In contrast, relatively recently listed species were more likely to have populations with non-significant change or declines. These findings provide critical information to set real-world expectations for recovery of marine mammal and sea turtle populations. Targeted conservation efforts triggered by ESA listing and other national and international conservation efforts have been largely successful in promoting population recovery leading to the delisting of some species and to significant increases in most others. The recovery of listed species depends ultimately on the adequate implementation of the ESA’s tools and other conservation measures. Studies have demonstrated that the government’s failure to fully implement the ESA’s protections and adequately fund conservation actions have been major impediments to species recovery [
  <a rid="pone.0210164.ref019" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210164.ref019">19</a>]. In general, listed species with designated critical habitat, sufficient conservation funding, and well-implemented species-specific recovery plans tend to recover relatively faster [
  <a rid="pone.0210164.ref016" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210164.ref016">16</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0210164.ref023" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210164.ref023">23</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0210164.ref024" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210164.ref024">24</a>]. Our analysis not only underscores the capacity of marine mammal and sea turtle populations to rebound after decades of exploitation and habitat degradation, but also highlights the success of marine species conservation through a combination of ESA protection and other conservation efforts.
 </p>
</sec>
