<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<sec id="sec014" class="sec">
 <div class="title" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">North Atlantic DPS of green sea turtle</div>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">The North Atlantic DPS of the green sea turtle within U.S. jurisdiction mostly nests across Florida beaches and is an ESA conservation success. The species has been increasing exponentially and has become one of the largest nesting aggregations in the western Atlantic in recent years [
  <a rid="pone.0210164.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210164.ref042">42</a>]. Historically exploited across the Caribbean [
  <a rid="pone.0210164.ref054" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210164.ref054">54</a>], this species has shown a high recovery potential when nesting areas are strictly protected from human disturbance and development, and fishery bycatch is substantially reduced [
  <a rid="pone.0210164.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210164.ref042">42</a>]. The nesting population of green turtles across Florida showed high records of nest numbers in 2013 (36,169 nests) and 2015 (37,341 nests) compared with only 62 nests estimated in 1979 (
  <a ref-type="fig" rid="pone.0210164.g004" href="#pone.0210164.g004">Fig 4</a>). These record numbers have occurred despite large annual fluctuations in nesting numbers that have been linked to changes in food supply (seagrass and macroalgae production) due to environmental changes [
  <a rid="pone.0210164.ref126" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210164.ref126">126</a>]. In 2016, NMFS and USFWS reclassified green sea turtles into 11 DPSs of which the Florida nesting population was downlisted from endangered to threatened due to strong population growth and record numbers of nests in nesting beaches throughout the peninsula [
  <a rid="pone.0210164.ref127" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210164.ref127">127</a>]. However, these population numbers are based on assessing the female component of the population and do not account for males and recruitment of juveniles.
 </p>
 <p xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">ESA protections and several local and international conservation efforts have been important for the recovery of green sea turtles in the North Atlantic and other regions. ESA regulations have led to fishing gear modifications, major changes in fishing practices, time and area closures, and the establishment of turtle excluder devices for shrimp trawlers [
  <a rid="pone.0210164.ref087" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210164.ref087">87</a>,
  <a rid="pone.0210164.ref128" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210164.ref128">128</a>]. In particular, fishery regulations instituted because of ESA protection have been largely successful in reducing green sea turtle bycatch from Atlantic pelagic longlines and gillnets, the Chesapeake Bay pound net fishery, and the Gulf of Mexico’s shrimp and flounder trawl fisheries [
  <a rid="pone.0210164.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210164.ref042">42</a>]. The ESA and other state-level laws prohibited direct harvesting of adult turtles and turtle eggs, preventing removal of mature and reproductive adults [
  <a rid="pone.0210164.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210164.ref042">42</a>]. In addition, several national wildlife refuges were dedicated to protecting nesting areas on the Atlantic coast and Gulf of Mexico, with nest watchers and patrols during nesting seasons [
  <a rid="pone.0210164.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210164.ref042">42</a>]. The Florida Statewide Nesting Beach Survey program, initiated in 1979 (one year after listing) as a cooperative agreement between USFWS and the Florida Fish and Wildlife Conservation Commission, now monitors ~215 nesting beaches (~825 miles) across Florida, involving federal, state, and regional institutions as well as several conservation organizations, university scientists, and private citizens [
  <a rid="pone.0210164.ref129" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210164.ref129">129</a>]. Federal agencies (NMFS and USFWS) along with state agencies and other institutions have worked together in implementing the management actions in the 1991 recovery plan, eliminating or reducing threats in nesting and foraging areas [
  <a rid="pone.0210164.ref042" ref-type="bibr" href="#pone.0210164.ref042">42</a>].
 </p>
</sec>
