<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">In this study, we used multiple GCMs and RCP scenarios and one hydrological model to discuss the possible variation in extreme floods. Although we have assessed the performance of multiple climate models and selected the most suitable climate models for this research before analyzing the future variation of flood, uncertainty caused by future climate conditions still exist in future flood projection. Similar research was carried out by Bell et al. and Kay et al. [
 <xref rid="B46-ijerph-15-02491" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">46</xref>,
 <xref rid="B47-ijerph-15-02491" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">47</xref>]. Another uncertainty source is the structure and parameters of the hydrological models. Since the impact of this kind of uncertainty is much less than that in GCMs [
 <xref rid="B8-ijerph-15-02491" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">8</xref>,
 <xref rid="B48-ijerph-15-02491" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">48</xref>], this research did not take the uncertainties from hydrological models into consideration. Still, this does not mean that this kind of uncertainty should be totally ignored. Taking the XAJ model used in this study as an example, the potential evapotranspiration (PET) can be estimated by the Penman-Monteith method or Hargreaves method. More meteorological data, such as solar radiation, is needed when using Penman-Monteith method, while Hargreaves method only needs temperature data. Since the data used by the XAJ model in this research is the gridded dataset provided by National Meteorological Information Center, which only involves precipitation and temperature, Hargreaves method was utilized to calculate PET. As a result, the projection of future flood did not take variation of solar radiation, wind speed or relative humidity into consideration. Furthermore, we assumed that the hydrological model parameters calibrated from observation are still valid when they are used in future climate simulations. It is on this basis that the impact of climate change could be evaluated by a hydrological model [
 <xref rid="B49-ijerph-15-02491" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">49</xref>]. Actually, as pointed by Merz et al., hydrological model parameters may potentially change if calibrated to different periods [
 <xref rid="B50-ijerph-15-02491" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">50</xref>]. Therefore, this study will do further research on the uncertainty produced by model structure and its parameters. Different hydrological models and PET computation methods shall be used to compare differences of response to climate change in the JRB.
</p>
