<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<p class="p">The data of climate change scenarios used in this study is provided by Inter-Sectoral Impact Model Intercomparison Project, which has been bias-corrected and resampled with 0.5° × 0.5° resolution, which also means that the original GCMs data has been statistically downscaled. Compared with the dynamical downscaling method based on Regional Climate Model (RCM), statistical downscaling method lacks solid mathematical and physics foundation. Thus, projected flood variation using the data in this research may have difference in the flood projection using RCMs’ output data. In the further research, RCMs such as PRECIS could be used to analyze the impact of climate change on extreme precipitation and flood in JRB and the result of two studies could be compared. Due to the daily precipitation provided by GCM, research on hourly flood peak is hard to carried out using this data set to analyze the impact of climate change on flood. Thus, annual maximum 
 <italic class="italic">n</italic>-day discharge on hydrologic station was chosen to characterize the impact of climate change on flood. In the meantime, the hydrological model (the XAJ model), which can describe the relationship between rainfall and runoff well, was selected. However, the impact of climate change on designed flood hydrograph was the most concerned issue in flood risk management. In the following research, time set method can be utilized to obtain precipitation data with shorter temporal scale (such as hourly scale) based on the GCMs’ output. Based on this, the storm event watershed model, e.g. the FLOW-R2D model, can be used to do hydrodynamic simulation, so as to assess the impact of climate change on future typical flood propagation [
 <xref rid="B51-ijerph-15-02491" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">51</xref>,
 <xref rid="B52-ijerph-15-02491" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">52</xref>,
 <xref rid="B53-ijerph-15-02491" ref-type="bibr" class="xref">53</xref>].
</p>
